<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>1.1.hoover</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Blake’s engravings for Captain John Steadman’s 
Narrative, of a five years’ expedition</title>
				<author n="Hoover">Suzanne R. Hoover</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>June 15, 1967</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1967</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">01.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1967"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_01">
        <body>
            <pb id="p01-7" n="7"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-01-1-0003">
                <byline>From <docAuthor>Mrs. Suzanne R. <name>Hoover</name></docAuthor>, Wellesley College,
Wellesley, Mass.:</byline>
                <p>References to Blake in print in the 1790’s are so rare that virtually any item, however
slight, is of interest to us today. It should therefore be noted that the <hi rend="u">British Critic</hi> for
November 1796 (VIII, 536-540) reviewed a work with engravings by Blake: Captain John Steadman’s 
<hi rend="u">Narrative, of a five years’ expedition, against the Revolted Negroes of Surinam.</hi> (Another
review, of an Englished edition of Burger’s <hi rend="u">Leonore</hi> with three plates by Blake, appeared
in the <hi rend="u">British Critic</hi> two months earlier and is listed in the Bentley and Nurmi 
<hi rend="u">Blake Bibliography</hi>, pp. 5, 230).</p>
                <p>Blake had engraved at least thirteen, and possibly sixteen, of Steadman’s eighty-six
designs for his book. (For the attribution of three unsigned plates to Blake, see Bentley and Nurmi, p. 159).
The reviewer for the November, 1796, <hi rend="u">British Critic</hi> was on the whole pleased with the text,
but thought the plates “very unequal; some would do honour to the most elegant, whilst others would disgrace
the meanest, performance.” As in
<pb id="p01-8" n="8"/>
the September review, Blake’s work was specifically criticised, although his name was never mentioned. For
example, the reviewer thought that
<q>
the representations of the negroes suffering under various kinds of torture, might well have been omitted,
both in the narrative, and as engravings, for we will not call them embellishments to the work.
</q>
                </p>
                <p>Blake could have taken this criticism as being in part directed against him. Among the
plates bearing his name were “A Negro hung alive by the Ribs to a Gallows,” and “Flagellation of a Female
Samboe Slave.” He did not sign, but probably did engrave, the plate entitled “The Execution of Breaking on the
Rack.”</p>
                <p>Further along in his article on Stedman the reviewer pronounced upon the quality of the
plates. He noted five of them, by title, for their bad drawing or faulty execution. Among them was Blake’s
witty engraving of “The skinning of the Aboma Snake, shot by Cap. Stedman,” surely one of the best plates in
the book. “The snake in the plate,” observed the reviewer,
<q>
must be greatly out of proportion with respect to the man. In the narrative it is expressly affirmed to be
about the thickness of the boy Quaco; but in the plate it far exceeds that of the man David . . .
</q>
(Elsewhere, one is pleased to find, the quality of the plate did not go unrecognized; Bentley and Nurmi [p.
160] note that an article on Stedman in the <hi rend="u">London Review</hi> singled out the same plate as “a
very good print.”)</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="u">British Critic</hi>, founded in 1793, was from the first devoted to High
Church religion and Tory politics; it regularly failed to take quite seriously contemporary experiments in
literature and art. We would not expect it to have championed Blake. And yet, the magazine’s very
conventionality and inability to comprehend change led to some curious “happenings”: for example, an
approving, if rather bored, review of <hi rend="u">Lyrical Ballads</hi>, simply because the reviewer was not
able to find in the volume “any offensive mixture of enmity to present institutions, except in one or two
instances, which are so unobtrusive as hardly to deserve notice.” The same affection for “present
institutions” led to a violent attack by the same magazine on George Cumberland’s outspokenly anti-Academic
<hi rend="u">Thoughts on Outline</hi> — once again, with engravings by Blake. But more of this another
time.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>