<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>1.1.publications</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">Publications and exhibitions</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>June 15, 1967</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1967</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">01.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1967"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_01">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-01-1-0002">
                <div2>
                    <pb id="p01-4" n="4"/>
                    <p>Professor Michael Tolley of The University of Adelaide is the author of a note on “The
Auckland Blakes” (“an interesting copy of <hi rend="u">America</hi> bound with <hi rend="u">Europe</hi> held
in the Auckland Public Library”) in the January issue of <hi rend="u">Biblionews</hi> (Australia).</p>
                    <p>Mr. Martin Butlin, Assistant Keeper of The Tate Gallery (London, S.W. 1), writes on the
progress of his catalogue raisonné: “It is to include all Blake’s paintings, watercolours, drawings and
hand coloured engravings. The format and treatment are to be on the lines of my 1957 catalogue of the Tate’s
Blakes. It is difficult to say how many totally new discoveries it will include as, though no complete
catalogue has been published before, a very full skeleton of one was prepared by Sir Geoffrey Keynes and
Ruthven Todd. This has proved invaluable to me and although I have found a few extra items most of my work has
been concerned with completing the history of each item, which has in fact often reduced two or more entries
to a single one. As for a completion date, this always seems, like a mirage, to be about two years ahead. It
would be a great help to me if any readers who come across Blakes with whose owners I have not been in touch
could let me know.”</p>
                    <pb id="p01-5" n="5"/>
                    <p>The Blake Trust facsimile of <hi rend="u">Milton</hi> has been published by The Trianon
Press. The Rosenwald copy was used for the facsimile, with the “Jerusalem” page added from the British Museum
copy. Pure rag paper was specially manufactured to match that of Blake, with his monogram added as a watermark
in each leaf. Reproduction is by the collotype and hand-stencil process, in up to twenty colors. There is a
description and bibliographical statement by Sir Geoffrey Keynes. The edition is limited to 400 numbered
copies for sale. Price 48 gns.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Arnold Fawcus, publisher of the Trianon facsimiles, writes that “since our Blake
Trust facsimile of the <hi rend="u">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> is out of print, The Trianon
Press is preparing a new edition in high quality 6-8 colour offset which should be within the means of all
Blake lovers — about $16.50 until December 25 and $20 after that. It will contain reproductions of the
illuminated poems, with their text in letter-press on the opposite page, a commentary on each poem and a
splendid introduction by Sir Geoffrey Keynes. It will be published in the States by the Orion Press,
distributors Grossman Publishers, and in England by McGibbon &amp; Kee.”</p>
                    <p>There was an exhibition of Blake’s illuminated books at the Metropolitan Museum of
Art, New York, from April 5 until May 30. The Mellon copy of <hi rend="u">Jerusalem</hi> was among the works
displayed. The exhibition, “William Blake: Poet, Printer, and <corr type="emend">Prophet,” also</corr>
included some original sketches, biographical memorabilia, and the only surviving fragment of a copper plate
made by Blake in the relief-etched process. It was organized by Mr. Arnold Fawcus for the Blake Trust; it was
previously shown at the Tate Gallery and at the National Gallery in Washington. A commemorative handbook with
26 colored plates, a study of Blake’s life and work by Sir Geoffrey Keynes, and a foreword by Mr. Lessing J.
Rosenwald, is available from the Metropolitan Museum for $3.00.</p>
                    <p>Professor Hazard Adams (University of California, Irvine) is going to edit the Rinehart
paperback edition of Blake. He invited suggestions from Blake scholars as to what should be included in it.
Professor Adams is also going to do a commentary on <hi rend="u">Jerusalem</hi> as an appendix to the
book.</p>
                    <pb id="p01-6" n="6"/>
                    <p>Mr. William Wells, Keeper of the Burrell Collection (Glasgow Art Gallery and Museum),
has written a monograph on Blake’s “Heads of the Poets.” “It will comprise an introductory essay, followed
by a catalogue of the Heads, discussing them in relation to the contents of Hayley’s library and the very
different artistic and literary view points of the patron and artist involved in their production. In addition
to the Heads themselves, the reproductions will include their engraved sources and other comparative
material.” The monograph will be published by the Manchester City Art Gallery, the present owner of the
eighteen canvasses. Mr. Wells is a former member of the Gallery’s staff.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Kerrison Preston writes that his Blake Library is now open to the public at
Westminster Public Library, 35 St. Martin’s Street, London W.C.2. “It is just off Leicester Square, and not
very far from the site of Blake’s birthplace in Soho, where the Westminster City Council has recently
erected a lofty building with a sculptured memorial to Blake in the entrance. The new building is called 
<hi rend="u">William Blake House.</hi>”</p>
                    <p>Mr. Michael Curtis Phillips (71 Fore Street, Topsham, Devon) is working on a fully
annotated text of <hi rend="u">Poetical Sketches</hi>, together with a detailed critical exposition and
photographic reproduction in facsimile of a copy of the poems corrected in Blake’s hand. He welcomes
suggestions.</p>
                    <p>A New edition of <hi rend="u">Tracks in the Snow</hi> by Ruthven Todd will appear
shortly. It will include a chapter on Blake’s techniques of etching which did not appear in the first
edition.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>