<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>1.2.bentley</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Blake Apocrypha</title>
				<author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>October 1, 1967</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1967</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">01.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1967"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_01">
        <body>
            <pb id="p01-4" n="4"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-01-2-0003">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="u">NOTES</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Blake Apocrypha</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>So ill-known was Blake among his contemporaries that few had even heard that he was a
poet. Of those who had heard of his poetry, most probably agreed with <hi rend="u">The Antijacobin
Review</hi>, which wrote in 1808:
<q>
Should he again essay to climb the Parnassian heights, his friends would do well to restrain his wanderings by
the strait waistcoat. Whatever license we may allow him as a painter, to tolerate him as a poet would be
insufferable.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref>
                            <note id="n1">
                                <hi rend="s">1</hi> Anon., “<hi rend="u">The Grave</hi> . . . illustrated . .
. [by] William Blake,” <hi rend="u">The Antijacobin Review and Magazine</hi>, XXXI (1808), 225-234; see 
<hi rend="u">Blake Records</hi>, 1967, p. 206.</note>
						</q>
As a consequence of this antipathy and obscurity, there is rarely any question of Blake’s authorship of a
given work, since almost all that survive are either in his own hand or printed by his own unique method of
Illuminated Printing. Blake’s works have often been suppressed, distorted, “improved,” and misunderstood,
but heretofore we have not been troubled with the problem which arises among more popular authors, of having
the works of other men attributed to him. His obscurity has had at least this advantage from the scholar’s
point of view.</p>
                    <p>However, an apocryphal Blake poem has recently been noticed in a review published just
over a century ago. In his 1863 biography of Blake, Alexander Gilchrist had quoted a number of Blake’s
doggerel poems from his Notebook expressing his resentment against his erstwhile patron William Hayley:
<q>
ON H[AYLEY] THE PICK THANK<lb/>
                            <lb/>
I write the Rascal Thanks till he &amp; I<lb/>
With Thanks &amp; Compliments are quite drawn dry.<lb/>
. . . . .<lb/>
Thy Friendship oft has made my heart to ake:<lb/>
Do be my Enemy for Friendship’s sake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref>
                            <note id="n2">
                                <hi rend="s">2</hi> A. Gilchrist, <hi rend="u">Life of William Blake</hi>, ed.
R. Todd, London &amp; New York, 1942, pp. 196, 197.</note>
						</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>One of Gilchrist’s anonymous reviewers was W. M. Tartt, who claimed that he had “met
Cromek in 1808, as the guest of [<hi rend="u">Fuseli’s patron</hi>] Mr. Roscoe at Allerton, and knew him
afterwards.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> Tartt is generally highly
unsympathetic—“To enter upon a minute criticism of his [Blake’s] poetry would be a mere waste of
time”—but he does present one point of interest. In reference to “the trashy doggerel” which Gilchrist
printed, such as that about Hayley quoted above, Tartt said:
<q>
The best specimen, in this way, was circulated (and attributed to Blake) in the first decade of the present
century; but it is not republished by Mr. Gilchrist.<lb/>
                            <pb id="p01-5" n="5"/>
“‘Tickle me,’ said Mr. Hayley,<lb/>
‘Tickle me, Miss Seward, do;<lb/>
And be sure I will not fail ye,<lb/>
But in my turn will tickle you.’<lb/>
So to it they fell a-tickling.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
‘Britain’s honour! Britain’s glory!<lb/>
Mr. Hayley that is you.’<lb/>
‘The nine muses bow before ye!<lb/>
Trust me, Lichfield’s swan, they do.’<lb/>
                            <lb/>
Thus these feeble bardlings squand’ring<lb/>
Each on each their lavish rhymes,<lb/>
Set the foolish reader wond’ring<lb/>
                            <hi rend="u">At the genius of the times</hi>!”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref>
						</q>
Though the reciprocated admiration between Hayley, the hermit of Felpham, and Anna Seward, the Swan of
Lichfield, must have been known and amusing to Blake, no verses remotely like these have been attributed to
him by anyone else, and the verse style seems quite alien to him. 
                        <note id="n3">
                            <hi rend="s">3</hi> Anon., “‘Pictor Ignotus,’ A Biography,” <hi rend="u">New
Monthly Magazine</hi>, CXXX (1864), 309-319, revised in Tartt’s <hi rend="u">Essays on some Modern
Works</hi>, London, 1876, Vol. II, pp. 192-215.</note>
                        <note id="n4">
                            <hi rend="s">4</hi> When the article was collected in book form, the introductory
paragraph was retained but the verse itself was omitted.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Fortunately, however, we have something more to go on in defending Blake from the
allegation of authorship of these verses than mere stylistic disparities. The central quatrain of the poem has
also been attributed to William Lort Mansel (1753-1820), the epigrammatical Bishop of Bristol. Mansel’s poem
is a series of couplets:
<q>
“Prince of poets, England’s glory,<lb/>
Mr. Hayley, that is you.”<lb/>
                            <lb/>
“Ma’am, you carry all before you,<lb/>
Lichfield Swan, indeed you do.”<lb/>
                            <lb/>
“In epic, elegy, or sonnet,<lb/>
Mr. Hayley, you’re divine.”<lb/>
                            <lb/>
“Madam, take my word upon it,<lb/>
You yourself are all the Nine.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref>
                            <note id="n5">
                                <hi rend="s">5</hi>
                                <hi rend="u"> The Private Letter-Books of Sir Walter Scott</hi>, ed. Wilfred
Partington, London, 1930, p. 215; in deference to the necessities of scansion and rhyme, I have taken the
liberty of altering the penultimate line from “word for it.”</note>
						</q>
Unfortunately the scholar who quoted these lines did not indicate their date or derivation, and I have been
unable to discover a contemporary source for them. Probably they were current before Miss Seward died in
1809.</p>
                    <p>The light-hearted merit of the lines, combined with contemporary topicality, explains
easily enough their currency about 1808. Their misattribution to William Blake may perhaps have occurred
during his lifetime, but it seems more likely that it is a trick of an old man’s memory writing fifty-six
years after the events he recalls. Whether the lines are most interesting for what they tell us of William
Blake, William Hayley, William Mansel, W. M. Tartt, or the Swan of Lichfield, Tartt was surely right in
thinking that they deserved no more than a footnote. Their interest for Blake lies not so much in the
plausibility with which they may be attributed to him as in the fact that a contemporary thought it worth
fathering such by-blows upon him.</p>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Gerald E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor>, University of
Toronto</byline>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>