<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>1.2.grant</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="discussion">Recognizing Fathers</title>
				<author n="Grant">John E. Grant</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>October 1, 1967</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1967</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">01.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1967"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_01">
        <body>
            <pb id="p01-7" n="7"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-01-2-0005">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="u">DISCUSSION</hi></title>
                </head>
                <head>
                    <title type="section-subtitle">
                        “With intellectual spears, &amp; long winged arrows of thought.”</title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Recognizing Fathers</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Re. Thomas E. Connolly and George R. Levine, “Pictorial and Poetic Design in Two Songs
of Innocence,” <hi rend="u">PMLA</hi>, LXXXII (May, 1967), 257-264, and the query by David V. Erdman in 
<hi rend="u">Blake Newsletter</hi> I.</p>
                    <p>There are so many marks of weakness and unfamiliarity with the basic facts of Blake
scholarship in this article by Connolly and Levine that it would take many pages to identify and correct them
all. One must, however, share the exasperation of Erdman at the contention of these authors that the guiding
figure depicted in “The Little Boy Found” is the boy’s mother. To be sure, they hedge their identification
by conceding that “there are traces of the Blakean version of Christ’s face in the face of the female
figure. Perhaps Blake, by interfusing the face of Christ with that of the earthly mother, attempted to suggest
the interpenetration of the human with the divine . . .” (p. 263). But they return to their assertion that the
guide is the mother and it is this identification which is sure to be referred to in all subsequent
discussions of the design. The methodological as well as interpretational problems raised by this article make
it particularly apposite for readers of the <hi rend="u">Blake Newsletter.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>That the reader cannot be depended on simply to look at the picture and then make up
his mind as to whether the guide is a man or a woman must immediately be conceded. The basic reason that this
is not possible, of course, is that it is not self-evident what we are referring to when we speak of the
“picture.” Because Connolly and Levine don’t know how to identify the picture, as it exists for systematic
scholarship, it is not surprising that they don’t know how to interpret the few versions of it that they
claim to have seen. In their “Appendix” (p. 264), where they give almost all their detailed data, they mention
having examined “all the British Museum copies of <hi rend="u">Innocence and Expendence</hi>”—“subsequent to
this paper’s being sent to the printers”[!]—and they also mention the copy “that Blake gave [sic] to Henry
Crabb Robinson in 1826,” though it is not perfectly clear that they have actually seen the original of this
copy. They also show no awareness of the Keynes-Wolf <hi rend="u">William Blake’s Illuminated Books: A
Census</hi> (1953), which changes the letter designations of Keynes’s <hi rend="u">Bibliography</hi> (1921)
that they employ to identify the four copies they seem to have seen.</p>
                    <p>I suppose all Blake scholars would agree that such carelessness and evasiveness is
avoidable, but it remains possible that Connolly and Levine may be right about other more important things.
What there is likely to be less unanimity about is how many copies of the <hi rend="u">Songs</hi> a scholar
ought to study before he is competent to pronounce on niceties of color or iconography. Probably four copies
taken at random are not enough;
<pb id="p01-8" n="8"/>
certainly four are not enough if the would-be scholar has not read the <hi rend="u">Census</hi> and shows no
awareness of the Blake Trust facsimiles, as Connolly and Levine do not. It seems inevitable that the Blake
Trust facsimiles should be the first source cited for evidence of what the pictures look like since the
facsimiles are widely available and since everything averred by true scholarship should aspire to be
verifiable. The facsimiles are not perfectly reliable (as I imply on p. 6 of <hi rend="u">Newsletter</hi> I)
but none of the pages of <hi rend="u">Songs</hi> should mislead anyone who has seen enough original copies to
know how to interpret the stencil colored pages.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">1</ref>
                        <note id="n6">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi> I too was happy to see the announcement in 
<hi rend="u">Newsletter</hi> I, 5, that the Trianon Press is about to issue a photographic reproduction of the
facsimile edition. But the quality of the plates in Keynes’s <hi rend="u">Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet</hi>
(1964) was often quite poor. The new edition of <hi rend="u">Songs</hi> is likely to cause trouble. See also
fn. 2.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Because Connolly and Levine refer to Keynes “Z,” the Crabb Robinson-Rosenwald copy of
<hi rend="u">Innocence and of Experience</hi>, they might seem to have covered themselves with regards to the
Blake Trust facsimiles, but they do not even hint that they have seen the Blake Trust facsimile of 
<hi rend="u">Innocence</hi>, Census “B,” (also Rosenwald) of the uncombined anthology. If they had done so they
would have seen a version of the guide who has nothing that can be called a halo, though in their lengthy
discussions they assume that this figure always possesses one.</p>
                    <p>On the other hand, Erdman seems to imply in his query that if the figure (usually)
possesses a halo it couldn’t be the mother who is depicted as the guide. This objection is not sustained if
we look—properly, it seems to me—at the facsimile of copy Z and also at the Micro Methods color microfilm
of copy AA.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">2</ref> In both copies the figure
in the right margin, with outstretched arms, has a halo. Connolly and Levine refer to her as an “angel,”
though she has no wings (like the four indubitable angels in LBL) but she must be the mother about to take
over, just as the poem says she does. 
                        <note id="n7">
                            <hi rend="s">2</hi> These microfilms, which in the case of the 
<hi rend="u">Songs</hi> are of copies B and AA, ought to have authority comparable to that of the Blake Trust
facsimiles and thus should also be cited in all real scholarly work. Until somebody carefully reviews both the
microfilms and the facsimiles, opinions as to which is more reliable will not be worth much. “Reliability”
may, indeed, not be what is at issue: perhaps we should be concerned with “proper uses and proper
purposes.”</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>It must be admitted, however, that the guide (“the nightgowned adult,” Erdman) does not
always look very masculine. In copy Z the somewhat indistinct features are almost as feminine, though quite
different, as those in copy T. which Connolly and Levine reproduce. The fact that the guide is generally busty
will not persuade Blakeists who have seen many of Blake’s pictures of Christ in Empire nightgowns that the
figure in question is a woman. An especially well-known representation of Christ in this costume and in almost
the same position will be found in the first picture of <hi rend="u">Blake’s Grave</hi>, entitled, “Christ
<pb id="p01-9" n="9"/>
Descending Into the Grave.” This figure is almost as busty, even though Schiavonetti’s engraving stands
between Blake’s conception and the reader. The only significant difference is that the guide in LBF has no
beard, as do almost all Blake’s representations of the mature Christ, including the one on the second page
of “The Little Black Boy” (pl. 10). If Connolly and Levine had bothered to present this evidence to
substantiate their claim that the guide is female they would at least have made an impressive case.</p>
                    <p>But the evidence that the guide is supposed to be either a woman or Christ per se
cannot be found in either the poem or the picture. Where Blake wanted an indubitable Christ, as in the
aforementioned plate 10, he depicted one; where he wanted an unmistakable God the Father, as in “The Little
Vagabond,” (p. 45), he also depicted one; likewise, where he wanted to depict women he did so with
unquestionably female figures. There is one figure<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">3</ref> depicted in <hi rend="u">Songs</hi>, however, who is clearly related to the beardless
guide of LBF. I refer to the nude and beardless male supported by two females and being given water by a
bearded man in “To Tirzah” (pl. 52). This figure undoubtedly suggests Christ after the deposition, though His
notable lack of beard is remarkable in view of Blake’s iconography elsewhere. The fact that this picture was
probably made after 1805, much later than the rest of the anthology, probably has no bearing on this
iconographic detail. Even if fashions in facial hair were changing, Blake’s indubitable Christs continued to
be bearded. 
                        <note id="n8">
                            <hi rend="s">3</hi> I am reminded by E. J. Rose that other kinds of connections
can also be made to such a figure as that mysterious adult on plate 28, the frontispiece to Experience, who
carries a winged child on his head.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The probable explanation for the lack of beard on the man in “To Tirzah” is that the
reader is being invited to see that he too is in a plight similar to that of the male victim, who is in the
condition of the crucified Christ but is not dignified, remote, and therefore irrelevant. This, at least, is
what the refrain of the odd poem that was oddly added to the anthology much later seems to imply. Every man
needs to say, Woman, “what have I to do with thee?” In a somewhat similar way the reader of LBF is shown a
guide who, though he is God, appears like the boy’s father, not like the Savior who is depicted in Church.
Every reader should be able to penetrate this clean-shaven disguise but it will not help the innocent little
boy to think he has no earthly father. Presumably he does not have to envision this father as a rough, tough,
two-hundred percent male in order to believe in his existence.</p>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>John E. <name>Grant</name>
                        </docAuthor> University of Iowa</byline>
                </div2>
				<div2>
                    <p>A reply by Professors Connolly and Levine will appear in Newsletter No. 3.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>