<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>1.2.news</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">Publications and exhibitions</title>
				<author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>October 1, 1967</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1967</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">01.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1967"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_01">
        <body>
            <pb id="p01-2" n="2"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-01-2-0002">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="u">NEWS</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <p>SIR GEOFFREY KEYNES informs us that a revised and augmented edition of 
<hi rend="u">Blake’s Letters</hi> will be published later this year by Rupert Hart-Davis. It will include “all
that have turned up to be added in recent years, with corrections and some revision of notes. There isn’t a
great deal but it will bring us up to date.” For the same publisher, Sir Geoffrey is preparing an enlarged
edition of his <hi rend="u">Blake Studies</hi> for next year. Also, “The Kraus Reprint Corporation are making
a reprint of my <hi rend="u">Bibliography of Blake</hi> (1921) and of the <hi rend="u">Census of the
Illuminated Books.</hi> These will not be revised, but will be reproduced as they stand. The Oxford University
Press is reprinting the Oxford Standard Authors Blake with some corrections and additions.”</p>
                <p>From Mr. KERRISON PRESTON: “All ten letters from Blake at Felpham to Butts at Westminster
are now in the Preston Blake Library in London. Also <hi rend="u">Poetical Sketches</hi> marked by Blake (the
Graham Robertson copy).<supplied type="emend">”</supplied></p>
                <p>From Professor G. E. BENTLEY, Jr: “I am now about mid-way through revised page proofs of a
volume to be called <hi rend="u">Blake Records</hi>, which is designed to embrace all the contemporary
references to the poet and his family which I can locate. The systematic chronological limits are 1737 to
1831, with selected comments from surviving friends of Blake such as Linnell, Palmer, and Tatham. It
comprehends the early biographies (J. T. Smith, Cunningham, Malkin, Tatham, H. C. Robinson), reviews, excerpts
from letters, records in rate books, wills, voting records, and church records. It includes a good deal from
Gilchrist, of course. A few score new references have turned up, but the vast majority of them have long been
known. It contains evidence purporting to trace Blake’s family to Rotherhithe, to associate his father with
the Baptist church, to show Blake having a patron arrested for not paying for pictures, and so on. The book is
designed as a reference tool, where biographical facts about Blake are collected.”</p>
                <p>“British Water Colors, 1750-1850,” an exhibition of 100 paintings from the Victoria and
Albert Museum, was shown at the California Palace of the Legion of Honor in July. It will subsequently appear
at the City Art Museum of St. Louis (Aug. 15 - Sept. 15) and at the Cleveland Museum of Art (Oct. 3 - Nov. 5).
Included are two paintings by Blake: “The Compassion of the Pharoah’s Daughter” (otherwise known as “The
Finding of Moses”) and “Moses and the Burning Bush.” There are also several pictures by friends of Blake’s:
“Piling Straw” by Linnell, “Papigno on the Nar” by Palmer, “Sketch of a Lady” by Fuseli, “A Village Church
Among Trees” by Palmer, and “View in the Pass of Llanberis” and “Fragnal, Hampstead” by John Varley. I found
the Varley “View” (dated 1803) especially interesting, with the blue sky divided into planes of light oddly
suggestive of the paintings of Lionel Feininger. The Palmer is in his richest style; also worth mentioning is
a crucifixion by John Martin, with the vastness of perspective that gives such a strange quality to his
work.</p>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>MDP</docAuthor>
                </byline>
                <pb id="p01-3" n="3"/>
                <p>In June we noted a forthcoming new edition of <hi rend="u">Tracks in the Snow</hi> by
RUTHVEN TODD. Mr. Todd writes: “Dover is to do it, with the addition of my essay on the printing techniques,
which I worked on with Bill Hayter and Joan Miro in New York in 1947, and which appeared in 
<hi rend="u">Print</hi> in the following year. The new issue is to be called <hi rend="u">Some Aspects of Blake
and Others</hi> and, in addition to the extra essay (which is now hard to come by), will have an introduction
by Kathleen Raine, and a new index by Anne Collins McGuire.” Mr. Todd also mentions that he has given the
first copy of his Blake catalogue to the Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection of the Library of Congress.</p>
                <p>The BBC has made a television program on the subject of “The Tyger.” Its producer, Mr.
CHRISTOPHER BURSTALL, writes: “The film I have made is called ‘Tyger, Tyger’ and I hope that the subtitle
‘An enquiry into the power of a familiar poem’ will give you some idea of what it is all about. It will
run for fifty minutes and includes some views by Kathleen Raine, Robert Graves, Richard Hoggart, Stuart Hall,
George Goyder, The Rev. Gordon Davies, as well as the opinions of a lot of private and inexpert people, old
and young, who find the poem memorable. I made the film - it’s a sort of ‘Workshop’ really I suppose, to
try and show some of the qualities which make the Tyger so potent, so generally. It is not in any way an
expert elucidation. We shall be transmitting it some time this winter, and I certainly hope that it will prove
of interest to NET.”</p>
                <p>Professor S. FOSTER DAMON notes that in Kenneth Patchen’s latest book, 
<hi rend="u">Hallelujah Anyway</hi> (New Directions Paperbook #219, price $1.25), there’s a prose poem with
reference to Blake’s Lamb and Tyger. “Patchen was an early lover of Blake—one of his first books was 
<hi rend="u">Journal of Albion Moonlight</hi>—and his ‘picture-poems’ were inspired by, but not an imitation
of, Blake’s combination of pictures and poems. I think that <hi rend="u">Hallelujah Anyway</hi> is one of
his best books.” [Kenneth Patchen has again been hospitalized with a recurring spine ailment, and collections
have been taken up in the Bay Area to help him meet medical expenses. Should readers of the 
<hi rend="u">Newsletter</hi> want to contribute, his address is 2340 Sierra Court, Palo Alto, California
94303.]</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>