<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>1.3.erdman</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Errata Emendata: Second Printing, Erdman-Bloom Poetry &amp; Prose of
William Blake</title>
				<author n="Erdman">David V. Erdman</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>December 15, 1967</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1967</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">01.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>S. Foster Damon</name>
                            <name>Alvin H. Rosenfeld</name>
                            <name>Laurence Goldstein</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_01">
        <body>
	<pb id="p01-11" n="11"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-01-3-0005">
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">3. Errata Emendata: Second Printing: Erdman-Bloom P&amp;P of
WB</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>David V. <name>Erdman</name>
                        </docAuthor> State University of New York at Stony Brook</byline>
                    <p>P 14 <hi rend="u">Night</hi> line 44 Graze <hi rend="u">shd be</hi> Grase (The 
<hi rend="u">s</hi> is angular but not a <hi rend="u">z</hi>).</p>
                    <p>P 51 line 10 Hands deprest <hi rend="u">shd read</hi> Heads deprest (Depressing!)</p>
                    <p>P 61 line 5 Human <hi rend="u">shd be lower case</hi> human</p>
                    <p>P 62 line 26 enclos’d <hi rend="u">sh<hi rend="s">d</hi> read</hi> inclos’d</p>
                    <p>P 146 line 27 rovolve <hi rend="u">shd be</hi> revolve</p>
                    <p>P 181 line 29 tragic <hi rend="u">shd be spelled</hi> trajic</p>
                    <p>P 202 line 20 Universal Concave <hi rend="u">can be emended to</hi> Universal Conclave
(as the context pretty much demands)</p>
                    <p>P. 270 Several persons have collated the Hebrew of the Laocoön inscriptions with the
engraved plate and kindly noted that the printers misspelled Lilith and King Jehovah, although Blake had them
both right. In Lilith a Heh appears instead of the final Thav. In Melekh Iehovah three incorrect letters
appear, Deleth instead of Khaph sophith, Kheth instead of Heh, and Resh instead of Vav.</p>
                    <p>(P 277 TIRIEL: The substantive variants in the new edition by Bentley, “were” for “was”
in 4: 2 and “vales” for “dales” in 4: 27, are simply misprints, as one can see from the facsimile).</p>
                    <p>P 287 line 101 loud (since it is an emendation) <hi rend="u">shd be</hi> [loud]</p>
                    <p>Pp 287-8 William F. Halloran (who is writing about this in <hi rend="u">BNYPL</hi>)
makes a convincing case for emending the dialogue by moving lines 105-9 to come after line 120.</p>
                    <p>P 493 From Cratelos <hi rend="u">shd be spelled</hi> from Cratetos (clear enough in 
<hi rend="u">N</hi>; now first observed by W. H. Stevenson)</p>
                    <p>REYNOLDS ANNOTATIONS. Marcia Allentuck, going through my xerox and elaborate
transcript, noted the following slips in the Doubleday simplified report:</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="u">Angle brackets shd enclose</hi> “Here . . . Circumstances” (P 639: p 87),
“Broken . . . Sublime” (P 641: p 102), “The . . . Operations” (P 643: p 131), “To . . . Science” (P644: p
135), “How . . . Species” (P 645: p 149), “Demonstration . . . Intuition” (P 648: p200), and “These . . .
Colour” (P 651: p 279). On P 645: p 152, no brackets shd be around the second “Never!”</p>
                    <pb id="p01-12" n="12"/>
                    <p>P 669 On design pg 101, add this inadvertently omitted paragraph at the end of the
inscription:</p>
                    <p>Whatever Book is for Vengeance for Sin &amp; whatever Book is Against the Forgiveness
of Sins is not of the Father but of Satan the Accuser &amp; Father of Hell</p>
                    <p>*** The following should be added as a separate entry: On drawing LB 32 in the British
Museum Print Room — a design for a title page. (The title sketched in begins with “The” but consists, in two
further lines, of strokes not perhaps meant to form actual words).</p>
					<q>
Angels to be very small as small<lb/>
as the letters<lb/>
that they may not<lb/>
interfere with the<lb/>
subject at bottom<lb/>
which is to be in a<lb/>
stormy sky &amp; rain<lb/>
seperated from the angels<lb/>
by Clouds
</q>
                    <p>P 729 note on 32: 15 Kerabim. The lemma is right as transcript of what Blake actually
wrote, Khaph the first letter. But to spell Kerabim it should be Kaph. The “correction” gets the second letter
wrong, however, following Keynes (Daleth instead of Resh) and does not correct the first. (PS: The new Keynes
is corrected). ** But wait! What first letter Blake meant to write is not all that certain. The plate shows a
strong dot just left of the top bar of the letter. Kaph would have the dot within its curve, but Khaph would
have no dot. Take your choice. It really looks as though Blake wrote and meant Kerabim, not Cherubim, and all
this “error” is among us editors and printers.</p>
                    <p>P 732 insert this for 49: 35: Void] ground <hi rend="u">rdg on plate</hi>, scribal
error influenced by line 33; correct reading supplied from <hi rend="u">Milton</hi> 5: 22, which Blake was
rather absently copying</p>
                    <p>P 732 52: 20 bloody pain <hi rend="u">shd be</hi> bloody plain</p>
                    <p>P 733 add 55:20 Conclave] <hi rend="u">emendation of textual</hi> Concave</p>
                    <p>69: 1 combined] <hi rend="u">mended by pen from</hi> conjoined (in the Mellon copy)
This is true, but too simple; Blake etched “combined”, mended it by cutting the plate to form “conjoined”, and
only in the Mellon copy restored “combined” by pen and link.</p>
                    <p>P 734 add: 98:45 the Covenant of] <hi rend="u">mended from</hi> thy Covenant 
<hi rend="u">to</hi> the Coventof <hi rend="u">which we emend to</hi> the Covenant of (But restored by pen in the
Mellon copy to <hi rend="u">thy covenant</hi> — I argue nevertheless for the emended reading: all this is in
“Suppressed and Altered Passages . . . ” <hi rend="u">SB</hi> XVII (1964) 38-39).</p>
                    <p>P 736 Deleted matter noted in Bentley’s <hi rend="u">Tiriel</hi> — or in my own
notes, and now perhaps called for:</p>
                    <p>4: 79 The secret] The gloom <hi rend="u">1st rdg</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>4: 74 like] torn like <hi rend="u">1st rdg del</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>5: 22 sun] slee[p] <hi rend="u">1st rdg</hi>: but Bentley may be right:
?plea[sure?]</p>
                    <p>6: 40 art] ? child art <hi rend="u">1st rdg</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>6: 49 fail] <hi rend="u">mended from</hi> fall</p>
                    <p>8: 21 drone] foolish crawling drone <hi rend="u">1st rdg</hi>
                    </p>
                    <pb id="p01-13" n="13"/>
                    <p>P 748 30: 16 ? halls of <hi rend="u">1st rdg erased</hi> (<hi rend="u">I doubt; could
be</hi> centr f[orm])</p>
                    <p>P 750 40: 11 I] We xxxxx (Delete the X’s — printer’s mistake)</p>
                    <p>P 752 56: 11-16 sixth erased line: I doubt most of this conjectured reading: “from” may
be “with”; “woe” probably “war”.</p>
                    <p>P 757 99: 4-9 Note citing <hi rend="u">Jerusalem</hi> 38 twice should cite 34 [38].</p>
                    <p>P 758 Second line shd read <hi rend="u">J</hi> 34.</p>
                    <p>P 768 Three poems written in . . . a copy of <hi rend="u">Poetical Sketches</hi>: said
copy is now in the Alexander Turnbull Library in Wellington, New Zealand.</p>
                    <p>P 770 [To go] on 1 Plate. gouped <hi rend="u">shd be</hi> grouped</p>
                    <p>P 772 The wild flowers song: 3 wild] <hi rend="u">shd read</hi> 3 flower</p>
                    <p>P 773 Several Questions . . . Line 17, 1st and 2nd rdgs shd be p 107, not p 99</p>
                    <p>P 776 Asterisks should be above the bracketed headings, not below them.</p>
                    <p>P 790 New mistake: “Her whole Life . . . ” <hi rend="u">N</hi> 101 rev <hi rend="u">shd
read N</hi> 100 rev</p>
                    <p>P 896 From Cratelos <hi rend="u">shd read</hi> From Cratetos</p>
                    <p>P 897 “I love Theotormon” shd read “I loved Theotormon”</p>
                    <p>“I saw a chapel . . . ” shd cite t 768</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>