<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>1.3.princeton</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">Blake at Princeton</title>
				<author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>December 15, 1967</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1967</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">01.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>S. Foster Damon</name>
                            <name>Alvin H. Rosenfeld</name>
                            <name>Laurence Goldstein</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_01">
        <body>
            <pb id="p01-6" n="6"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-01-3-0004">
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">2. BLAKE AT PRINCETON</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>The keen eye of Virginia Erdman detected the following item in Princeton 
<hi rend="u">Town Topics</hi> for November 9, 1967:</p>
					<q>
                        <head>
                            <title>BLAKE BOOK HERE</title>
                        </head>
                        <p>Gift to Princeton. A rare copy of William Blake’s book, “Songs of Innocence and
of Experience” has been given to Princeton University and is now on exhibition in Firestone Library.</p>
                        <p>Hours are 9 a.m. to 6 p.m., Monday through Saturday, and 2 p.m. to 5 p.m.
Sundays.</p>
                        <p>The volume was probably printed in 1815 according to Charles A. Ryskamp, curator of
English and American literature for the library. It was printed in red-brown ink, and contains 54
copper-engraved plates, elaborately and brilliantly colored with watercolors and gold.</p>
                        <p>“Blake’s book is considered by many to be the most beautiful book in the history
of English art and poetry and this is certainly one of the finest copies,” says Professor Ryskamp. The volume
was the gift of Miss Caroline Newton of Berwyn, Pennsylvania. It was included in the Grolier Club exhibition
of Blake’s works in 1905 in New York and at the Philadelphia Museum of Art exhibit in 1939.</p>
                        <p>The history of the Princeton book can be traced to 1824, when it was sold to the
publisher, Edwards. It was subsequently bought by William Beckford the novelist, who assembled the first
important Blake collection, and then by Quaritch, the British booksellers, who used it for a
						<pb id="p01-7" n="7"/>
						facsimile edition in the 1890’s. Shortly after, it was acquired by William A. White, one of the
greatest Blake collectors.</p>
                        <p>Professor Ryskamp points out that Princeton’s copy is complete, with 54 leaves;
other existing volumes are incomplete. It is identified as copy “U” in the census of Blake’s illuminated
books compiled by Sir Geoffrey Keynes and Edwin Wolf II.</p>
					</q>
					<p>We went to see this copy and found that the Firestone Library was also exhibiting a number of other
works, most of them on loan from Miss Newton. The following items were included:</p>
                    <p>Illuminated books: In addition to copy U, copy j of the <hi rend="u">Songs of Innocence
and of Experience</hi> (posthumous); copy D of <hi rend="u">America</hi>; copy L of <hi rend="u">Visions of
the Daughters of Albion</hi> (probably colored by Mrs. Blake).</p>
                    <p>Engraved sets: <hi rend="u">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> (large-paper page
proofs); <hi rend="u">For the Sexes: the Gates of Paradise</hi> (title page, frontispiece, plates 1, 7-13,
18-19).</p>
                    <p>Engravings from books: 4 plates after Fuseli from <hi rend="u">A New and Improved Roman
History</hi> by Charles Allen (1798); Wilson Lowry (proof copy of fourth state, engraved with Lowry for
Rees’ Cyclopedia); “Tornado”, after Fuseli, from the third edition (1795) of Erasmus Darwin’s 
<hi rend="u">Botanic Garden</hi>, Part II.</p>
                    <p>Engraving: Canterbury Pilgrims, fourth state.</p>
                    <p>Books: <hi rend="u">Poetical Sketches</hi>, Blair’s <hi rend="u">Grave</hi>
illustrated by Blake, Botanic Garden Part I (five engravings by Blake after Fuseli), and Hayley’s 
<hi rend="u">Ballads</hi> and <hi rend="u">Little Tom the Sailor</hi>, both with illustrations designed and
engraved by Blake.</p>
                    <p>Drawings: Watercolor of Hayley’s design for the Cowper monument (one of three copies
made by Blake); wash drawing “Job and His Family Restored to Prosperity”; and four pencil drawings. One of
these showing a male and a female figure, is identified as “for a rejected illustration for 
<hi rend="u">Comus.</hi>” One of the others is a sketch of what seems to be a theatrical production, with a male
figure wearing a plumed hat or helmet. Another shows several horses, one of which wears a plumed headdress of
some kind and is harnessed to something (a chariot?) unshown. Another horse appears to be reading a book
opened on the ground while a woman wearing a bandana milks her; a third is unmistakably horselaughing.</p>
                    <p>Manuscript: Fair copy in Blake’s hand of “I asked a thief to steal me a peach.”</p>
                    <p>Color prints: From <hi rend="u">A Small Book of Designs</hi> (copy B)—plate 9 of 
<hi rend="u">The First Book of Urizen</hi>, inscribed “Eternally I labour on”; and plate 11 of <hi rend="u">The
Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, inscribed “Death &amp; Hell”/<corr type="emend">“Teem</corr> with Life”. [In
both inscriptions, the quotation marks are in the original.]</p>
                    <p>Also: Rivington and Cochrane’s catalog for 1824, advertising the 
<hi rend="u">Songs</hi> (copy U) at 8 guineas and <hi rend="u">The Grave</hi> at £1 16s.</p>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>MDP</docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>