<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>1.3.miscellaneous</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">Miscellaneous</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>December 15, 1967</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1967</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">01.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>S. Foster Damon</name>
                            <name>Alvin H. Rosenfeld</name>
                            <name>Laurence Goldstein</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_01">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-01-3-0004">
                <pb id="p01-8" n="8"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">4. MISCELLANEOUS</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>An expanded version of Kathleen Raine’s A. W. Mellon Lectures in the Fine Arts, 
<hi rend="u">Blake and Tradition</hi>, is scheduled for June publication in the Bollingen Series by the Princeton
University Press. The two-volume work includes 194 illustrations, 11 in color. Also of interest to Blake
scholars will be <hi rend="u">Thomas Taylor the Platonist: Selected Writings</hi>, edited by Miss Raine and
George Mills Harper, and scheduled for summer publication in the Bollingen Series. And Miss Raine informs us
that her collection of essays <hi rend="u">Defending Ancient Springs</hi>, just published by Oxford University
Press, includes “Yeats’s Debt to William Blake.”</p>
                    <p>An unaltered reprint of Swinburne’s <hi rend="u">William Blake: A Critical Study</hi>
(1869) has been issued by Benjamin Blom, Inc. (4 West Mt. Eden Avenue, Bronx, N.Y. 10452. Price $12.50).</p>
                    <p>A second edition of <hi rend="u">A Blake Dictionary</hi>, with some additions, is in
the press; also a second printing of <hi rend="u">Blake’s Job.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>More Blake courses: Foster Damon will give a graduate seminar on Blake at Brown in the
spring ’68 semester. Edward Rose teaches a full-year graduate seminar on Blake at the University of Alberta
(Edmonton, Ontario) every other year. Morton Paley will give a graduate seminar on Blake’s longer poems in
fall ’68, at Berkeley.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>