<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>1.3.europe</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Europe iii: 18</title>
				<author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>December 15, 1967</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1967</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">01.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>S. Foster Damon</name>
                            <name>Alvin H. Rosenfeld</name>
                            <name>Laurence Goldstein</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_01">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-01-3-0005">
				<pb id="p01-16" n="16"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">5. <hi rend="u">Europe</hi> iii: 18</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>In examining copy H of <hi rend="u">Europe</hi> at the Houghton Library, I found that
line 18 of the prefatory poem reads “The world, when every particle of dust breathes forth its joy.” The third
word is usually printed as “where,” but there is only one other copy of <hi rend="u">Europe</hi> with this
plate extant (K, in the Fitzwilliam Museum), and David Erdman informs me that he has examined his slide of the
Fitzwilliam plate iii and found the reading to be “when.” The line makes perfect sense as Blake etched it; in
fact, “when” ties in more closely with the theme of the prefatory poem.</p>
                    <p>At the beginning of the poem, Blake hears the Fairy singing about the senses: “Five
windows light the cavern’d Man” etc. The fifth sense, touch, could admit man to the joys of Eternity if his
hypocritical morality did not restrain him:
					<q>
					Thro’ one, himself pass out what time he please, but he will not;<lb/>
					For stolen joys are sweet, &amp; bread eaten in secret pleasant.
					</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>After the Fairy is caught by the poet, he promises to write a Blakean illuminated book
(“on leaves of flowers”) and to
					<q>
					shew you all alive<lb/>
					The world, when every particle of dust breathes forth its joy.
					</q>
					</p>
                    <p>Thus the line as Blake etched it continues the theme of erotic mysticism introduced
earlier in the poem, “when” referring to the ecstatic moment at which the life of the universe is
perceived.<gap type="emend"/></p>
					<pb id="p01-18" n="18"/>
                    <p>How “when” came to be printed for “where” in editions of Blake is not clear. Perhaps
Ellis and Yeats started the tradition. Sampson (1905) printed “when,” but Sloss and Wallis (1926) reverted to
“where.” Keynes printed “when” in 1925, but afterwards substituted “where”; the Erdman-Bloom edition has
“where.” There appears to be no textual authority for any reading but “when.”</p>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>MDP</docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>