<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>1.3.rose</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">The Meaning of Los</title>
				<author n="Rose">E. J. Rose</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>December 15, 1967</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1967</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">01.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>S. Foster Damon</name>
                            <name>Alvin H. Rosenfeld</name>
                            <name>Laurence Goldstein</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_01">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-01-3-0005">
				<pb id="p01-10" n="10"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">2. The Meaning of Los</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>E. J. <name>Rose</name>
                        </docAuthor> University of Alberta Edmonton, Canada</byline>
                    <p>The traditional reading of ‘Los’ as an anagram for ‘sol’ has been long
established, though other sources have been suggested. Frye, for instance, cites ‘<hi rend="u">los</hi> or
<hi rend="u">loos</hi>’ from Chaucer’s <hi rend="u">House of Fame</hi> as a possible analogue.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> Though I do not discount the possibility that
Blake may have had several sources in mind at once, as with the names of many of his major figures, like Orc
and Vala, I think ‘los’ means literally and metaphorically something more than ‘sol.’ I do not intend
or even suggest that ‘sol’ be abandoned because Los is too often associated with the sun in both the verse
and the illustrations for ‘sol’ to be ignored. Los is, of course, the ‘more bright Sun of Imagination’
in the <hi rend="u">L’Allegro</hi> designs and not the fiery guinea-disk of economics and nature. What I
think ‘los’ means is ‘look’ or ‘behold’ in the traditionally shortened form of the interjection,
‘lo,’ only in the third person singular of the verb — perhaps, with all the same implications as
Ferlinghetti’s very Blakean <corr type="emend">‘fourth</corr> person singular.’<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> Los is aware, he watches, looks, sees, and beholds. His 
<hi rend="u">is</hi> vision. He <hi rend="u">los</hi> all the time and all Time. Los is the word within the word,
a visionary verbal wheel within a wheeling verbal universe, a moving vision or visionary (a seer) within the
vision. Los is a perennial proclamation in the present tense, the ever-present tense, a seeing word in an
iconographical drama. He is his own ejaculation, an infinite ‘lo.’ The <hi rend="u">s</hi> in Los should
be pronounced as a voiced sibilant in contrast with the voiceless sound uttered by the serpent. ‘The Song’
or ‘The Book’ of Los, like all of Blake’s work, is a song or a book of <hi rend="u">los.</hi> We see
through Los, not with him. Before this suggested interpretation of the meaning of Los is dismissed as
fanciful, I only ask that several of Blake’s works be re-read with the ear attuned to the metaphorical sound
of Los pronounced as <hi rend="u">lo</hi> with a voiced sibilant. Such phrases as the ‘Gate of Los’ or
‘head of Los’ which appear repeatedly and other phrases, such as ‘Scribe of Los’, or building of Los,
or power of Los, or ‘they gave their power to Los, Naming him the Spirit of Prophecy,’ take on a new and
important dimension, which once entertained, is not easily ignored. No serious critic of Blake or of the Bible
can afford to ignore the aural metaphors or what Buber calls ‘A bold visual metaphor for an acoustical
event’ when he discusses the ‘voice of thin silence’ from I Kings 19:21, which he says ‘is a silence,
but not a thick and solid one, rather one that is of such veil-like thinness that the Word shines through
it.’<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> ‘Lo is the recurrent
ejaculation of God and his
<pb id="p01-11" n="11"/>
prophets throughout man’s history. It is the sound of the visual herald when he reveals truth and an
interjection which appears repeatedly in Blake’s work. ‘Lo’ is a word which proclaims that men see with
their minds, travel mentally, and wage ‘Mental War.’ <note id="n1">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi> “Notes for a Commentary on <hi rend="u">Milton</hi>,” 
<hi rend="u">The Divine Vision</hi> (London, 1957). pp. 100-101; of <hi rend="u">Fearful Symmetry</hi> (Princeton,
1947), p.445 n.2 and p. 417.</note>
                        <note id="n2">
                            <hi rend="s">2</hi> The phrase appears repeatedly in <hi rend="u">Her.</hi> Los
is, of course, the <hi rend="u">fourth</hi> Zoa — he says so in <hi rend="u">J</hi> 42: 11, 23-24.</note>
                        <note id="n3">
                            <hi rend="s">3</hi> “On the Suspension of the Ethical,” in <hi rend="u">Eclipse of
God</hi> (New York, 1957), p. 119.</note>
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>