<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>1.4.toc</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="toc">Contents</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>March 15, 1968</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1968</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">01.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>W.H. Stevenson</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1968"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_01">
        <front id="issue_04">
                <pb id="p01-1" n="1"/>
                <div1 id="cover">
                    <figure n="cover.001.04.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="334">
                        <figTranscr>Blake Newsletter<lb/>
                            Number 4<lb/>
                            March 15, 1968<lb/>
                            With this issue, the <hi rend="u">Blake</hi> <hi rend="u">Newsletter</hi>
concludes its first year<lb/>
                            of publication.  The response from Blake scholars has been generous and<lb/>
                            enthusiastic, and we thank our many contributors and correspondents for<lb/>
                            their support, something it has been impossible to do adequately in<lb/>
                            individual correspondence.<lb/>
                            Our only serious problem at the moment is, paradoxically, the success<lb/>
                            of the <hi rend="u">Newsletter</hi>.  We produced 120 copies of #3 and found that
this was<lb/>
                            about the limit that our resources of time, energy and assistance will allow.<lb/>
                            If most of our original subscribers re-subscribe, and if new subscriptions<lb/>
                            continue to come in at the present rate, we will soon reach a point where<lb/>
                            we can no longer fill new orders.  The alternative to this would be to find<lb/>
                            some institutional support which would allow us to have the physical pro-<lb/>
                            duction of the <hi rend="u">Newsletter</hi> done professionally, along with
perhaps the mailing<lb/>
                            and addressing of copies.  The point to be emphasized is that we 
<hi rend="u">can</hi> continue<lb/>
                            as at present for an indefinite time, but we cannot continue to grow without<lb/>
                            changing our present arrangements for publication and distribution.  We do<lb/>
                            not in any event plan to alter the informal nature of the 
<hi rend="u">Newsletter</hi>.
                            Most subscriptions to the <hi rend="u">Newsletter</hi> expire with this issue.  If
you<lb/>
                            have received Numbers 1-4 and wish to receive Numbers 5-8, please remember<lb/>
                            to resubscribe.  Extensive tally-keeping and reminder-sending would<lb/>
                            seriously interfere with work on our June issue, which is scheduled for<lb/>
                            June 15.  We once more welcome contributions of news, notes, queries, and<lb/>
                            discussion items.  The deadline for submissions is June 1.<lb/>
                            The June issue will include a checklist of recent articles on Blake,<lb/>
                            including reviews.  If you know of any that are likely to escape us, please<lb/>
                            let us know.<lb/>
                            The BLAKE NEWSLETTER is edited by Morton D. Paley, Dept. of English, Univer-<lb/>
                            sity of California, Berkeley Calif. 94720.  Subscription price: two dollars<lb/>
                            for one year (four issues.  Please make checks payable to Morton D. Paley.<lb/>
                            British subscribers may remit Postal Money Orders for 16/8.  Such money<lb/>
                            orders must be <hi rend="u">open</hi> and 
<hi rend="u">uncrossed</hi>.</figTranscr>
                    </figure>
                </div1>
				<div1 id="BQ-01-4-0000">
					<supplied type="emend" rend="plain">
						<table id="contents" rows="13" cols="2">
						  <row>
							<cell><head><title><supplied type="emend">Contents</supplied></title></head></cell>
							<cell/>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><hi rend="b">News</hi></cell>
							<cell/>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><ref type="article" issue="1.4.damoniana">Further Damoniana</ref><lb/>
							<hi rend="i">Alvin Rosenfeld, Foster Damon</hi></cell>
							<cell>2</cell>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><ref type="article" issue="1.4.news">Miscellaneous News</ref></cell>
							<cell>3</cell>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><hi rend="b">Notes</hi></cell>
							<cell/>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><ref type="article" issue="1.4.stevenson">1. Two Problems in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
(continued)</ref><lb/>
							<hi rend="i">W. H. Stevenson</hi></cell>
							<cell>6</cell>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><ref type="article" issue="1.4.erdman">2. Blake’s Terrible Ease!</ref><lb/>
							<hi rend="i">David V. Erdman</hi></cell>
							<cell>8</cell>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><ref type="article" issue="1.4.tolley">3. Some Analogues or Sources</ref><lb/>
							<hi rend="i">Michael J. Tolley</hi></cell>
							<cell>9</cell>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><hi rend="b">Queries</hi></cell>
							<cell/>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><ref type="article" issue="1.4.howell">1. An Early, Hand-made Facsimile of the <hi rend="i">Songs
of Innocence and of Experience</hi></ref><lb/>
							<hi rend="i">John Howell</hi></cell>
							<cell>10</cell>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><ref type="article" issue="1.4.todd">2. A Projected New Edition of the Gilchrist-Todd 
<hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi></ref><lb/>
							<hi rend="i">Ruthven Todd</hi></cell>
							<cell>11</cell>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><hi rend="b">Discussion</hi><lb/>
							<hi rend="b">“With intellectual spears, &amp; long winged arrows of thought”</hi></cell>
							<cell/>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><ref type="article" issue="1.4.letter">On the Newly Rediscovered Blake Letter</ref><lb/>
							<hi rend="i">David V. Erdman</hi></cell>
							<cell>12</cell>
						  </row>
						</table>
					</supplied>
				</div1>
                <div1 id="BQ-01-4-0001">
                    <p>With this issue, the <hi rend="u">Blake Newsletter</hi> concludes its first year of
publication. The response from Blake scholars has been generous and enthusiastic, and we thank our many
contributors and correspondents for their support, something it has been impossible to do adequately in
individual correspondence.</p>
                    <p>Our only serious problem at the moment is, paradoxically, the success of the 
<hi rend="u">Newsletter.</hi> We produced 120 copies of #3 and found that this was about the limit that our
resources of time, energy and assistance will allow. If most of our original subscribers re-subscribe, and if
new subscriptions continue to come in at the present rate, we will soon reach a point where we can no longer
fill new orders. The alternative to this would be to find some institutional support which would allow us to
have the physical production of the <hi rend="u">Newsletter</hi> done professionally, along with perhaps the
mailing and addressing of copies. The point to be emphasized is that we <hi rend="u">can</hi> continue as at
present for an indefinite time, but we cannot continue to grow without changing our present arrangements for
publication and distribution. We do not in any event plan to alter the informal nature of the 
<hi rend="u">Newsletter.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>Most subscriptions to the <hi rend="u">Newsletter</hi> expire with this issue. If you
have received Numbers 1-4 and wish to receive Numbers 5-8, please remember to resubscribe. Extensive
tally-keeping and reminder-sending would seriously interfere with work on our June issue, which is scheduled
for June 15. We once more welcome contributions of news, notes, queries, and discussion items. The deadline
for submissions is June 1.</p>
                    <p>The June issue will include a checklist of recent articles on Blake, including reviews.
If you know of any that are likely to escape us, please let us know. 
<note type="unreferenced" place="footer">The BLAKE NEWSLETTER is edited by Morton D. Paley, Dept. of English, University of California,
Berkeley Calif. 94720. Subscription price: two dollars for one year (four issues. Please make checks payable
to Morton D. Paley. British subscribers may remit Postal Money Orders for 16/8. Such money orders must be 
<hi rend="u">open</hi> and <hi rend="u">uncrossed.</hi>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                </div1>
        </front>
        <body>
                <pb id="p01-12" n="12"/>
                <div1 id="BQ-01-4-0005">
                    <p>The BLAKE NEWSLETTER is copyright 1968 by Morton D. Paley and its contents may not be
reproduced without written permission. This is in order to protect our contributors, who are of course welcome
to reprint their own material.</p>
                </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>