<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>1.4.todd</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="query">A Projected New Edition of the Gilchrist-Todd Life of Blake</title>
				<author n="Todd">Ruthven Todd</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>March 15, 1968</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1968</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">01.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>W.H. Stevenson</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1968"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_01">
            <body>
                <div1 id="BQ-01-4-0004">
                    <pb id="p01-11" n="11"/>
                    <div2>
                        <head>
                            <title type="main">2. A PROJECTED NEW EDITION OF THE GILCHRIST-TODD 
<hi rend="u">LIFE OF BLAKE</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>Mr. Ruthven Todd writes that he is planning to revise and augment his edition of
Gilchrist’s <hi rend="u">Life</hi>, originally published by Everyman’s Library in 1942. The extensive
notes to this edition are, even after 25 years, invaluable, and now Mr. Todd proposes to bring them
up-to-date. He writes:
<q>
What I would like to do is produce, at first, a hard cover edition which could then be reproduced for cheaper
sale. I have also come to an agreement with J.M. Dent so that I can buy the electrotypes of the Virgil
woodcuts which, by a private wangle between myself and the Linnell family, were made directly from the blocks
in the BM, so that they are <hi rend="u">not</hi> reproductions, but as near to the originals as one can get.
Then, too, only Keynes and myself have the right to ask for electrotypes of the <hi rend="u">Songs</hi> which
I rediscovered and which are in the BM. I think that these, printed on decent paper, should almost in
themselves attract a hard-cover public.<lb/>
                                <lb/>
I quite realize that I, unaided, cannot hope to make the book as good as it should be, but I am quite sure
that there must be many scholars who have thought of extra notes and corrections, and who, in return for being
given full credit, would be willing to help me produce a book which would not again need revising for many
years. I would welcome all notes, corrections, and so on, and in every case the donor would receive full
credit for his/ her help. I would like, for instance, not only to acknowledge all corrections, but also, in
the case of new notes, to sign them by the names of the contributors.
</q>
Mr. Todd’s address is: Ca’n Bielo, Galilea, Mallorca, Spain.</p>
                    </div2>
                </div1>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>