<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>1.4.damoniana</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">Further Damoniana</title>
				<author n="Rosenfeld">Alvin Rosenfeld</author>
				<author n="Damon">S. Foster Damon</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>March 15, 1968</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1968</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">01.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>W.H. Stevenson</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1968"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_01">
            <body>
                <pb id="p01-2" n="2"/>
                <div1 id="BQ-01-4-0002">
                    <head>
                        <title type="section">
                            <hi rend="u">NEWS</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <div2>
                        <head>
                            <title type="main">Further Damoniana</title>
                        </head>
                        <p>ALVIN ROSENFELD kindly sends us the following report on the S. Foster Damon
Festival, held at Brown University on February 22 and 23 in celebration of Professor Damon’s seventy-fifth
birthday: The Festival opened on Thursday afternoon, February 22, with S. Foster Damon offering a reading from
his own poetry; there followed a presentation of a scene from his prize-winning play, “Witch of Dogtown”; and
a piano recital of some of S. Foster Damon’s musical compositions, including the song “The Garden of Love,”
after Blake.</p>
                        <p>On Friday, February 23, the festival continued with a Blake seminar and film. An
audience of some 350 people gathered to hear Professors Damon, Harold Bloom, Geoffrey Hartman, and Robert
Langbaum discuss “Blake in the Twentieth Century.” The discussion centered chiefly on the critical discovery
of Blake in our time and emphasized Professor Damon’s pioneering work in the field. Professor Bloom pointed
out the absence of any received tradition of commentary on Blake before Damon and paid tribute to the
latter’s landmark study, William Blake, His Philosophy and Symbols (1924), a work that he called “almost
outrageously magnificent.”</p>
                        <p>Professor Damon spoke of how he came to discover Blake and related some of the
problems he encountered in trying to read and understand Blake’s poetry before a proper text was established
and without the benefit of reliable scholarship and criticism.</p>
                        <p>Geoffrey Hartman and Robert Langbaum each spoke about contemporary problems in
reading Blake, and both stressed the need for a critical approach that would emphasize the fundamentally human
aspects of Blake’s poetry as they are relevant today.</p>
                        <p>Following the seminar there was a showing of the B.B.C. television film on Blake,
“Tyger, Tyger.” Most people who watched the film didn’t like it, and from the comments heard—“puerile,
silly, long-winded, a bore”—it cannot be highly recommended. Most agreed that the earlier British film on
Blake (1957) was far superior.</p>
                        <p>The festival concluded with a large dinner on Friday evening, which included brief
speeches by Virgil Thomson, the composer, and Willard Maas, the poet and film-maker, among others. “A Birthday
Garland for S. Foster Damon,” a commemorative booklet of reminiscences and tributes collected for the
occasion, was distributed to invited guests.</p>
                        <p>An exhibit of Damoniana with special Blake items, currently featured at the
Rockefeller Library at Brown University, provided a fitting backdrop to the S. Foster Damon Festival. Included
in the exhibit and of particular interest to Blake scholars are the following: J.G. Stedman’s two-volume 
<hi rend="u">Narrative of a Five Years’ Expedition</hi> (1796), including eight plates engraved by Blake (and
possibly colored by Blake himself); the 1805 reissue of Hayley’s <hi rend="u">Ballads</hi>, with five plates
re-engraved (the copy on exhibit, from
						<pb id="p01-3" n="3"/>
						Professor Damon’s personal library, is the only known copy of this book in which Blake colored his own
plates); and The Trianon Press facsimile volumes of <hi rend="u">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>
(1959), <hi rend="u">Jerusalem</hi> (1963), <hi rend="u">America</hi> (1963), <hi rend="u">Songs of Innocence
and Experience</hi> (1967), and <hi rend="u">Milton</hi> (1967).</p>
                        <p>The “Birthday Garland,” edited by Mr. Rosenfeld and Barton Levi St. Armand, is a
beautiful booklet of poems, prose, and illustrations. Among the contributors are Edwin Honig, Lincoln
Kirstein, Marianne Moore, Winfield Townley Scott, Hyatt Howe Waggoner, and Colin Wilson.</p>
                        <p>FOSTER DAMON himself writes to say that his <hi rend="u">Blake Dictionary</hi> has
been re-issued in what is in effect a second edition, with a number of alterations and some new short
articles.</p>
                        <p>Malcolm Cowley’s article, “The Self-Obliterated Author: S. Foster Damon,” appears
in the January ’68 <hi rend="u">Southern Review.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </div2>
                </div1>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>