<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>1.4.howell</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="query">An Early, Hand-made Facsimile of the Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</title>
				<author n="Howell">John Howell</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>March 15, 1968</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1968</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">01.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>W.H. Stevenson</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1968"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_01">
            <body>
                <pb id="p01-10" n="10"/>
                <div1 id="BQ-01-4-0004">
                    <head>
                        <title type="section">
                            <hi rend="u">QUERIES</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">1. AN EARLY, HAND-MADE FACSIMILE OF THE <hi rend="u">SONGS OF
INNOCENCE AND OF EXPERIENCE</hi></title>
                    </head>
					<p>(The following description and query comes to us from a leading rare book dealer, Mr. John Howell [434
Post Street, San Francisco].</p>
                    <p>An album containing 54 water-colour drawings of very high quality (each about 122 by 78
mm). These drawings tally exactly with those reproduced in William Muir’s two volumes of facsimiles; i.e.
<hi rend="u">Songs of Innocence</hi> 28 drawings; <hi rend="u">Songs of Experience</hi> 22 from the
Beaconsfield copy in the B.M., plus 4 more from the other B.M. copy. There are separate title-pages to each
work and another title-page for the joint volume. The additional plate reproduced by Muir in his Appendix - “A
Divine Image” - not included in either book, nor known in any coloured copy, is not present here.</p>
                    <p>The drawings are lightly mounted onto large sheets of Whatman paper watermarked 1821;
the front end-paper is watermarked 1813. The album (13 ⅜ by <corr type="emend"><supplied type="emend"
rend="plain">9</supplied> ¼</corr> ins.) is bound in early 19th century red straight-grained morocco, the
sides filled with gilt and blind tooling surrounding a central panel; the spine is divided into compartments
by five raised bands and decorated with gilt and blind tooling. Two panels of the spine are lettered in gilt:
SONGS OF INNOCENCE AND EXPERIENCE—BY W. BLAKE. Edges gilt. The style of this binding is contemporary with
the date in the watermarks; 1821.</p>
                    <p>The text varies in minute details from the printed version: e.g. a happy song - my
happy song, ‘&amp;’ in place of ‘and’, cheer for chear, etc. But the differences in the drawing and
colouring are considerable. In ‘Piping Down the Valleys Wild’ the piper wears a pink coat, in the printed
version this is brown. In other pages some figures are depicted in a far more finished style; while border
patterns sometimes differ considerably in both layout and colour from the printed version.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Martin Butlin, who specialises in Blake at the Tate Gallery examined the album
containing contemporary copies of Blake’s Songs of Innocence and Experience. He did not think that the
drawings are by Blake himself. For one thing, Blake was little interested in drawing his figures in the round,
his characters having an <corr type="emend">almost</corr> flat surface; while the artist who made these
drawings endeavoured to give them both roundness and depth. The drawing is by some person who, although not
academy trained, had very considerable <corr type="emend">ability</corr> and technique. The colouring, on the
other hand, is <corr type="emend">extraordinarily</corr> Blakean, and this makes it certain not only that
these drawings <corr type="emend">were</corr> made early in the nineteenth century, but that they are by
someone in the circle of Blake himself. It is known, for example, that Linnell himself made copies of
Blake’s drawings and set his family to do the same. Thomas Butts, the other of Blake’s major patrons, did
a certain amount of amateur engraving, while Blake gave drawing lessons to Butts’ son.</p>
                    <pb id="p01-11" n="11"/>
                    <p>It is probable that the person who did the drawings also mounted them in the album, or
at least that this was done at much the same time. Evidence for this lies in the second drawing for 
<hi rend="u">The Little Black Boy</hi> which has been cut rather close (bottom left) and extended in matching
water-colour on the mount itself. Incidentally Thomas Butts commissioned Blake to make water-colour Biblical
illustrations and someone in the Butts family mounted these, wrote appropriate texts underneath, drew frames
around the pictures, and in some cases extended the painted surface to touch the frames.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Butlin gave it as his opinion that this album is ‘absolutely fascinating’ and
calls for a considerable amount of research. He suggested, as a line to follow, that the various copies of the
twin edition of <hi rend="u">Songs of Innocence and Experience</hi> are bound up in different orders and the
colouring varies. Is it possible to locate an original copy which interlocks with the order and colouring of
the drawings in this album, and if so, does it, perhaps, stem from the Linnell or Butts families?</p>
                </div1>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>