<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>1.4.erdman</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Blake’s Terrible Ease!</title>
				<author n="Erdman">David V. Erdman</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>March 15, 1968</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1968</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">01.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>W.H. Stevenson</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1968"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_01">
            <body>
                <div1 id="BQ-01-4-0003">
                	<pb id="p01-8" n="8"/>
                    <div2>
                        <head>
                            <title type="main">2. Blake’s Terrible Ease!</title>
                        </head>
                        <byline>
                            <docAuthor>David V. <name>Erdman</name>
                            </docAuthor>
                        </byline>
                        <p>Through an accident of photographic ordering, a second infra-red print of Notebook
page 5 has come from the B.M. (in connection with preparations for a new facsimile edition, still some years
off); and on this page the bottom lines are surprisingly darker and more legible than had seemed possible from
earlier infra and other photographs. One can, in fact, <hi rend="u">see</hi> everything, i.e. complete lines
of squiggle for words; the writing is Blake at his unsteadiest (he was probably writing on one knee); and it
is now possible to be well nigh definitive in the reading of these deathless lines. (Doubleday pp. 491-2;
781)</p>
                        <p>I can see now that the apparently random pair of scratches at the bottom of the
page are intended to cancel lines 31-32, to be replaced by lines 33-34—with what can be now read as the same
rhyme words. Page 492 in a new printing will thus be emended to conclude:
<q>From pity then he redend round<lb/>
And the Spell removed unwound<lb/>
If Blake could do this when he rose up from shite<lb/>
What might he not do if he sat down to write
</q>
The textual notes on p. 781 will read:</p>
                        <p>29 From pity then] Then after <hi rend="u">1st rdg del</hi> “Then” was mended to
“From”, “after” was <corr type="emend">canceled,</corr> “pity then” was written above the line; in a faint
photograph of this very rubbed pencil page, at one time the outside page of the Notebook, the “pi” looks like
a “B”, and “then” combining with the ascending stroke of “he” looks like “thing” or “shing” (thus “Blushing”
in my earlier reading). In a better photograph this and the following lines are distinctly legible.</p>
                        <p>30 removed] <hi rend="u">inserted above the line</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>31 rose up from] sat down to <hi rend="u">1st rdg del</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>31-32 written in margin to replace the following two lines, cancelled with two
slanting strokes:
<q>
If thus Blake could Shite<lb/>
What Klopstock did write
</q>
                        </p>
                    </div2>
                </div1>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>