<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>1.4.stevenson</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Two Problems in The Four Zoas (continued)</title>
				<author n="Stevenson">W. H. Stevenson</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>March 15, 1968</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1968</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">01.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>W.H. Stevenson</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1968"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_01">
            <body>
                <pb id="p01-6" n="6"/>
                <div1 id="BQ-01-4-0003">
                    <head>
                        <title type="section">
                            <hi rend="u">NOTES</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <div2>
                        <head>
                            <title type="main">1. TWO PROBLEMS IN <hi rend="u">THE FOUR ZOAS</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <byline>
                            <docAuthor>W. H. <name>Stevenson</name></docAuthor><lb/>
                            University of Ibadan, Nigeria<supplied type="emend" rend="plain"><ref target="nE"
type="note">*</ref></supplied></byline>
                        <note id="nE"><supplied type="emend"><hi rend="s">*</hi> 
<ref type="article" issue="1.3.stevenson">Continued from previous issue</ref>.</supplied></note>
                        <p>My second problem is the place of VIIb, if any. The argument here is well known; is
VIIb earlier than VIIa, contemporary, or later? More important; was it rejected or not? On the first question,
my conclusions tie in with Margoliouth’s - that VIIb is of the same period as the first, early part of VIIa,
and consecutive upon it; and that the later part of VIIa, from the middle of p. 85, is an insertion, or a
series of insertions, between p. 85: 25 and VIIb. The famous stitch-marks, which end at p. 85 (not counting
the tailpiece design, now p. 112) fit this theory, though they do not confirm it. Margoliouth says 
(<hi rend="u">Vala</hi>, p. xiii) “But when the accretions have been removed and VIIb<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="p6u1" type="note">*</ref> printed in Blake’s original order (i.e. as on the MS,
beginning on p. 91, <corr type="emend">‘Thus</corr> in the Caverns of the Grave . . . ’<supplied
type="emend">)</supplied> . . . it appears that VIIb follows straight on VIIa”. That is to say: VIIa ended
when (85: 6-7) “Enitharmon’s Shadow pregnant in the deeps beneath/Brought forth a wonder horrible”, a
“nameless shadowy” female - Vala, in fact (p. 91: 14) - who is given “Charge over the howling Orc” (85: 22).
Night VIIb continues this scene - “The Shadow reard her dismal head over the flaming youth” (p. 91: 3). (It
may be noted that Blake here follows his usual technique of changing a scene, not as the Night begins, but
soon afterwards. Nights IV to VIIa all begin with the scene of the previous Night, though sometimes this is
obscured by the ending of a Night with a lament, so that the actual setting is to be found some little way
back.) <note id="p6u1">* I have altered H.M.M’s <hi rend="u">VII</hi> and <hi rend="u">VIIbis</hi> to
conform with the now accepted labelling.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>The real question, however, is: Did Blake reject VIIb when he enlarged VIIa? The
new VIIa ends with the reconciled Los and Enitharmon working together to redeem the dead; VIII now begins with
this (after a few lines, not entirely detached, about the Council of God); and my argument in the last
paragraph may be taken to apply here also. On the other hand, there is the simple fact that, although large
parts of I are clearly cancelled, Blake left VIIb in the MS, and still unmarked. If he had wished to reject
VIIb <corr type="emend">nothing</corr> would have been easier than to remove the four sheets and either throw
them away (as presumably the very first drafts of the poem were thrown away) or put them somewhere separate.
That they are still with the MS suggests that, though they might have been an embarrassment, he had not
determined to reject them. At any rate, we must be very sure of our ground before we reject them on his
behalf.</p>
                        <pb id="p01-7" n="7"/>
                        <p>I suspect that the beginning of VIII, as it now is, forms an attempt to reconcile
the new narrative of the end of VIIa and the old of VIIb. The old narrative was simple; the “nameless shadowy
female” - named as Vala - produces Orc’s release, and a war ensues which covers the rest of VIIb and most of
VIII, resulting in the collapse of all the warring powers in a stupor and the triumph of Vala, whose subtlety
has undermined the vast structure of Urizen’s power. But Blake’s interest has been taken by other matters,
as the additions show. In VIII these are various and complex, developing the theme of the Council of God and
its guidance of the catastrophic situation though the confrontation of the forces of evil by Jesus. In VIIa,
which more closely concerns us, the new interest is the study of Los and Enitharmon. They have quarrelled ever
since I, although half-reconciled in V: but in the new VIIa, helped by the benevolent Spectre of Urthona,
their reconciliation is complete and therefore manifests itself in new and wonderful powers. They are
privileged together to take part in the redemption of the dead, a work which is going on even when the war of
Urizen and Orc - for which Los and Enitharmon have no little responsibility - is coming to its tragic
climax.</p>
                        <p>The present beginning of VIII shows what seem to me deliberate attempts to
introduce both the old and new elements. VIIb now ends with twelve lines about the Daughters of Beulah. (It is
interesting but irrelevant to this question, to note that these lines, though apparently of the same date as
the <hi rend="u">added</hi> lines at IV, p. 55:10 to 56:27, are an original part of this MS. This should stand
as a warning, to those inclined to presuppose a “non-Christian” MS with “Christian” additions, and those
inclined to assume that similar themes mean passages of similar date, that the matter is not as simple as it
may seem.) The beginning of VIII contains the following references specifically to VIIb: line 3, “Upon the
Limit of Contraction” (ref. VIIb 95:13, “Limit of Translucence”; Blake is naming both Limits, as he usually
does, together). Line 4, “The Fallen Man stretchd like a Corse” is of course part of Blake’s whole later
myth, but is also relevant to the “Promise Divine” of <corr type="emend">the</corr> Lazarus story 
(<hi rend="u">John</hi> 11:23) referred to in VIIb, 95:4-8. Line 20: the “Shadowy female” barely appears in VIIa
and is not so named <corr type="emend">until</corr> VIIb. Line 21, “the Daughters of Beulah” are not mentioned
in VIIa or, indeed, anywhere between IV and the end of VIIb. The descent of the dead “away from” them is
derived from the end of VIIb, 95:10-11. Line 22: “Urizens temple” was erected in VIIb, 95:31ff. Finally,
100:1, “the War of Urizen &amp; Tharmas” broke out in VIIb. It is indeed mentioned in the last lines of VIIa
(90:29, 44, 59); yet this can only be a slip of memory on Blake’s part, since he had not started the war in
VIIa - the threat at the end of VI evaporated.</p>
                        <p>Thus VIII in its late form is clearly connected to VIIb. It is equally clearly
connected to the new end of VIIa, which makes me think that Blake was deliberately trying to reconcile the two
states of the narrative. VIII, 99:15 brings back the scene at the end of VIIIa where Los and Enitharmon are
working together to redeem and remake “the spectrous dead”. 99:19-20, already referred to, brings together
VIIb (as shown above) and the work of Los and Enitharmon with the dead. 99:24 refers to “The broken heart Gate
of Enitharmon<supplied type="emend">”</supplied> from VIIa 85:13 and 87:41-2; this is an essential part of the
story
<pb id="p01-8" n="8"/>
since the shattering of the “obdurate gates” made Enitharmon capable of love and sympathy so that she could
join <corr type="emend">Los’s</corr> work (VIIa 87: 40-45, 90:6, VIII, 99:22-27). In p.100 the material of the end of VIIa and the
end of VIIb - Enitharmon and the Daughters of Beulah - is mixed and intertwined. As the Night goes on into p.
101 the mixture extends to include material from the whole of Nights VIIa and VIIb.</p>
                        <p>Thus I conclude that Blake had decided to keep VIIb somehow; but had not solved the
problem of the quart of inspiration and the pint pot of nine Nights. The numbering of the Nights was, after
all, the least of his problems.</p>
                    </div2>
                </div1>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>