<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>10.1.bogan</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Vampire Bats &amp; Blake’s Spectre</title>
        <author n="Bogan">James Bogan</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1976</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1976</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">10.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <name>Brad Hayden</name>
              <name>Jean Stalker</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Debra Sackett</name>
              <resp>Design &amp; layout for this issue</resp>
              <name>Brad Hayden</name>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>James Bogan</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>J. Walter Nelson</name>
              <name>Michael Tolley</name>
              <resp>Photo credits</resp>
              <name>Aethelred and Alexandra Eldridge</name>
              <name>Leonard and Marjorie Gayton</name>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1976"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_10">
    <body>
	<pb id="p10-32" n="32"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-10-1-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">JAMES</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">BOGAN</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">Vampire Bats &amp; Blake’s Spectre</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>“The Spectre is, in Giant Man, insane and most deform’d” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 37:4). This
aspect of the divided man is a vicious aggregate of shame, doubt, despair, deceit, compulsion, brooding
melancholy, negation, vengeance, selfishness, fear, cruelty, cannibalism, mindless rage, blind hunger,
self-righteousness, pride, insanity, etc. The Spectre has all the energy of hysteria and does his powerful
worst to devour any and all that stand between him and the objects of his insatiable lust, born of the craving
for the lost emanation. The Spectre is the rational power divorced from the heart, “but he is anything but
reasonable; rather, he is a machine which has lost its controls and is running 
wild.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">1</ref> 
The blood-sucking Spectre tries to drain the life out of the
living man by all manner of deceit, treachery, and temptation. Once he has debilitated the healthy soul, then
he usurps the place of “humanity” and goes on a bootless rampage once again to capture life. 
<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">1</hi> S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary</hi> (New York: Dutton, 1971), p.
381.</note></p>
          <p>In Blake’s day, the standard definitions of “spectre” included ghost, phantasm, horrid sight,
apparition of dread and terror, all of which can justly be applied to the Spectre. There is another dimension
to the Spectre that should not be overlooked. He is usually pictured as dark and batwinged; indeed he is a
spectre-bat, a true vampire, a literal blood-sucker. The image of this winged cannibal came to Blake’s
attention before he started to work on the major prophecies. Blake was hired by Joseph Johnson in 1792 to help
with the engravings to John Stedman’s <hi rend="i">Narrative of a five year’s expedition against the
Revolted Negroes of Surinam.</hi> Stedman recounts the following episode:
<q>
I cannot here forbear relating a singular circumstance respecting myself, <hi rend="i">viz.</hi> that on
waking about four o’clock this morning in my hammock, I was extremely alarmed at finding myself weltering in
congealed blood, and without feeling any pain whatever. Having started up, and run for a surgeon, with a
firebrand in one hand, and all over besmeared with gore: to which if added my pale face, short hair, and
tattered apparel, he might well ask the question,<lb/>
<lb/>
‘Be thou spirit of health or goblin damn’d, Bring with thee airs of Heav’n or blasts from Hell!’<lb/>
<lb/>
The mystery however, was that I had been bitten by the <hi rend="i">vampire</hi> or <hi rend="i">spectre</hi>
of Guiana, which is also called the <hi rend="i">flying-dog</hi> of New Spain. . . . This is no other than a
bat of monstrous size, that sucks blood from men and cattle when they are fast asleep, even sometimes till
they die; and as the manner in which they proceed is truly wonderful, I shall endeavour to give a distinct
account of it. —Knowing by instinct that the person they intend to attack is in a sound slumber, they
generally light near the feet, where, while the creature continues fanning with his enormous wings, which
keeps one cool, he bites a piece out of the tip of the great toe, so very small indeed that the head of a pin
could scarcely be received into the wound, which is consequently not painful; yet through
<pb id="p10-33" n="33"/>
<figure n="jerusalem.I.P37" rend="file" width="718" height="1000">
	<head><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 33</head>
</figure>
this orifice he continues to suck the blood, until he is obliged to disgorge. He then begins again, and thus
continues sucking and disgorging till he is scarcely able to fly, and the sufferer has often been known to
sleep from time into eternity. . . . Having applied tobacco-ashes as the best remedy, and washed the gore from
myself and from my hammock, I observed several small heaps of congealed blood all round the place where I had
lain, upon the ground: upon examining which, the surgeon judged that I had lost at least twelve or fourteen
ounces during the night. . . .<lb/>
<lb/>
Having measured this creature I found it to be between the tips of the wings thirty-two inches and a half; it
is said that some are above three feet. . . . the colour was a dark brown, nearly black, but lighter under the
belly. Its aspect was truly hideous upon the whole, but particularly the head, which has an erect shining
membrane above the nose, terminating in a shrivelled point: the ears are long, rounded, and transparent: the
cutting teeth are four above and six below.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">2</hi> London, 1796, pp. 142-143.</note></q>
Stedman’s spectre-bat has the qualities of gluttony, ugliness, and murderous intent associated with the
spectres in the prophetic poems. Blake even draws the Spectre with a dark body and enormous bat-wings that are
spread over Los to occlude a vision of higher realms (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 6).</p>
          <p>The Spectre also haunts the reposed body of Jerusalem. With his page-wide wingspread, he
separates her from the dying Albion (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 33). So, an image that had seized Blake’s fancy
while at work on a hired job eventually became transmuted into a baleful and portentous element of his
epics.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
