<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>10.2.minnick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="checklist">A Checklist of Recent Blake Scholarship</title>
        <author n="Minnick">Thomas L. Minnick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1976</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1976</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">10.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
              <name>Michael Hays</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Jane Welford</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Mary Baine</name>
              <name>Rodney Baine</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <name>Judith Ott</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1976"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_10">
    <body>
	<pb id="p10-59" n="59"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-10-2-0004">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">NOTES</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">A Checklist of Recent Blake Scholarship</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">BY</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">THOMAS</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">MINNICK</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Bibliographies and Bibliographical Essays</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Curran, Stuart. “Recent Studies in the Nineteenth Century.” Studies in English Literature
1500-1900, 14 (1974), 637-638.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V., comp., with the assistance of Robert R. Mollenauer and James S. Patty. “The
Romantic Movement: A Selective and Critical Bibliography for 1974.” English Language Notes, 13 (1975),
supplement to no. 1.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N. “Corrections of the BMPR Handlist.” Blake Newsletter, 8 (Winter 1974-75),
90-91. [Corrects and adds to Bentley’s Handlist, Blake Newsletter, 5 (Spring 1972), whole no. 20.]</p>
            <p>Frost, Everett, comp. “A Checklist of Blake Slides.” Blake Newsletter, 9 (Summer 1975),
4-28.</p>
            <p>Lehrer, Ruth Fine. “A Checklist of Blake Material in The Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection,
Alverthorpe Gallery, Jenkintown, Pennsylvania.” Blake Newsletter, 9 (Winter 1975-76), 58-85.</p>
            <p>Oliver, Barbara and K. E. Robinson, “The Eighteenth Century” in James Redmond, ed., The
Year’s Work in English Studies, 54 (1973), 276-300.</p>
            <p>Taylor, Ron. “A Checklist of Recent Blake Scholarship.” Blake Newsletter, 8 (Spring 1975),
146-158.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Editions, Facsimiles, Reproductions</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Blake, William. America. Bushey Heath, Herts.: Taurus Press of Willow Dene, 1975. £50. [Illus.
with modern woodcuts; edition limited to 100 copies.]</p>
            <p>Blake, William. America, A Prophecy. Albuquerque, N.M.: Blake Newsletter, 1975. $2.50. [Black
and white reproduction of copy E, 2 plates from a*, and the 4 cancelled plates, all from the Rosenwald
Collection; designed for classroom use.]</p>
            <p>Blake, William. William Blake: Selected Engravings. London: Academy Editions, 1975. $16.95
hardbound; $9.95 paper.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V. The Illuminated Blake: All of William Blake’s Illuminated Works with a
Plate-by-Plate Commentary. 1974; slightly revised in the second printing, 1975 (New York: Doubleday) and in
the Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1975 printing. $7.95.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert and Jenijoy La Belle, eds. Night Thoughts or The Complaint and The Consolation.
Illustrations by William Blake. Text by Edward Young. New York: Dover, 1975. $4.00. [Reprints the 1797 edition
at 65% of original size. 43 engravings by Blake.]</p>
            <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. Auguries of Innocence. Burford,
<pb id="p10-60" n="60"/>
                            Oxfordshire: The Cygnet Press, 1975. £2.80. [Edition limited to 375 copies.]</p>
            <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. Jerusalem: The Emanation of the Giant Albion. [Chapter 1.] London:
Bernard Quaritch for The William Blake Trust, 1974. £130.00. [Reproduces copy B, the Cunliffe copy, and, as
an appendix, the four cropped pages from the Preston collection.]</p>
            <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. The Marriage of Heaven and Hell. London and New York: Oxford Univ. Press,
1975. Cloth edition, $16.95; paper, $7.95. [A reproduction in original size of one of the Fitzwilliam copies;
the title page and enlargements of interlinear decorations are from copy E.]</p>
            <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. The Song of Los. London: Bernard Quaritch for The William Blake Trust,
1975. £95.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Critical Studies</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Adams, Hazard. “Blake, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, and Symbolic Form.” Blake Studies, 7
(1975), 143-166.</p>
            <p>Allentuck, Marcia. “Henry Fuseli and J. G. Herder’s <hi rend="i">Ideen Zur Philosophie Der
Geschichte Der Menschheit</hi> in Britain: An Unrecorded Connection.” Journal of the History of Ideas,
35(1974), 113-120.</p>
            <p>Allentuck, Marcia. “Henry Fuseli on Engravings of His Milton Paintings: An Unpublished Letter.”
Burlington Magazine, 116 (1974), 214.</p>
            <p>Ault, Donald. “Report: 1974 MLA Blake Seminar.” Blake Newsletter, 8 (Spring 1975), 105-106.</p>
            <p>Baine, Mary R. and Rodney M. Baine. “Blake’s Other Tigers and ‘The Tyger’.” Studies in
English Literature 1500-1900, 15 (Autumn 1975), 563-578.</p>
            <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr. “The Accuracy of the Blake Reproductions.” Blake Newsletter, 8 (Winter
1974-75), 88-89.</p>
            <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr., ed. William Blake: The Critical Heritage. London: Routledge &amp;
Kegan Paul, 1975. $24.00.</p>
            <p>Bloom, Harold. Poetry and Repression: Revisionism from Blake to Stevens. New Haven and London:
Yale Univ. Press, 1976. [Chapter 2, “Blake and Revisionism,” is pp. 28-51.]</p>
            <p>Brown, Robert E. See Grant, John E. and Robert E. Brown.</p>
            <p>Butlin, Martin. “The Catalogue of Blake’s Designs Completed &amp; A Last-Minute Inclusion.”
Blake Newsletter, 9 (Fall 1975), 48-49.</p>
            <p>Butlin, Martin. “A New Portrait of William Blake.” Blake Studies, 7 (1975), 101-103.</p>
            <p>Chard, Leslie F., II. “Two ‘New’ Blake Engravings: Blake, James Earle, and the Surgeon’s
Art.” Blake Studies, 6 (1975), 153-165. [6 illus.]</p>
            <p>Clarke, John H. From Copernicus to William Blake. 1928; rpt. Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library
Editions, 1974.</p>
            <p>Connolly, Thomas E. “The Real ‘Holy Thursday’ of William Blake.” Blake Studies, 6 (1975),
179-187.</p>
            <p>Curtis, Francis B. “Blake and the Booksellers.” Blake Studies, 6 (1975), 167-178.</p>
            <p>Duerksen, Roland A. “Bromion’s Usurped Power—Its Source, Essence, and Effect: A
Replication.” Blake Newsletter, 8 (Winter 1974-75), 95-96.</p>
            <p>Eaves, Morris. “Reproducing <hi rend="i">The Characters of Spenser’s Faerie Queene.</hi>”
Blake Newsletter, 8 (Winter 1974-75), 86-87.</p>
            <p>Ebanks, Milena D. Laocoon in Art and Literature: Its Contribution to Eighteenth-Century
Aesthetics. Diss. New York Univ., 1975. Dissertation Abstracts International, 36, no. 6 (December 1975),
3648-A.</p>
            <p>Efron, Arthur. See Wooster, Margaret and Arthur Efron.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V. “Errors in the 1973 Third Edition of <hi rend="i">The Notebook of William
Blake</hi> &amp; in the First Printing of <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake.</hi>” Blake Newsletter, 9
(1975), 39-40.</p>
            <p>Evans, James C. “Blake, Locke, &amp; The Concept of Generation.” Blake Newsletter, 9 (Fall
1975), 47-48.</p>
            <p>Fairchild, B. H., Jr. “<hi rend="i">Melos</hi> and Meaning in Blake’s Lyric Art.” Blake
Studies, 7 (1975), 125-141.</p>
            <p>Fawcus, Arnold. “William Blake, républicain et antiimpérialiste.” Nouvelles de 1 ’Estampe,
no. 9 (1973), 11-13. [4 illus.]</p>
            <p>Ferber, Michael. “A Possible Source for ‘Thel’s Motto’.” Blake Newsletter, 9 (Fall 1975),
43-44.</p>
            <p>Fiske, Irving. Bernard Shaw’s Debt to William Blake. 1951; rpt. Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft
Library Editions, 1974.</p>
            <p>Flemming, H. T. “Johann Heinrich Fussli Retrospektive.” Weltkunst, 45 (1975), 14-15.</p>
            <p>Folsom, L. Edwin. “Nobodaddy: Through the Bottomless Pit, Darkly.” Blake Newsletter, 9 (Fall
1975), 45-46.</p>
            <p>Fox, Susan. Poetic Form in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> Princeton, N.J.: Princeton Univ.
Press, 1976. [Forthcoming.]</p>
            <p>Frye, Northrop. “Expanding Eyes.” Critical Inquiry, 2 (1975), 199-216. [Includes occasional
remarks on Blake.]</p>
            <p>Gillow, N. J. “Some Flaxman Drawings at York.” Preview, 26 (1973), 915-919.</p>
            <p>Gleckner, Robert F. “Most Holy Forms of Thought: Some Observations on Blake and Language.” ELH,
41 (1974), 555-577.</p>
            <p>Grant, John E. “The Fate of Blake’s Sun-Flower: A Forecast and Some Conclusions.” Blake
Studies, 5 (1974), 7-49. [Illus.]</p>
            <p>Grant, John E. and Robert E. Brown. “Blake’s Vision of Spenser’s <hi rend="i">Faerie
Queene</hi>: A Report and an Anatomy.” Blake Newsletter, 8 (Winter 1974-75), 56-85. [Includes a 4-color
reproduction of Blake’s tempera painting, <hi rend="i">The Characters of Spenser’s Faerie Queene</hi>,
with many monochrome details throughout.]</p>
            <p>Green, Richard G. “Blake and Dante on Paradise.” Comparative Literature, 26 (1974), 51-61.</p>
            <p>Harper, George Mills. “The Odyssey of the Soul in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” Blake
Studies, 5 (1974), 65-80.</p>
            <p>Hassler, Donald M. Erasmus Darwin. (Twayne’s English Author Series, 160.) New York: Twayne,
1973. [Avoids Blake.]</p>
            <p>Herrstrom, David S. Mythopoeia and Blake’s Major Prophecies. Diss. New York Univ., 1975.
Dissertation Abstracts International, 36, no. 6 (December 1975), 3652-A.</p>
            <p>Heygate, William E. William Blake. New York: Garland Publishing Co., 1975.</p>
            <p>Hinkel, Howard H. “From Pivotal Idea to Poetic Ideal: Blake’s Theory of Contraries and ‘The
Little Black Boy’.” Papers on Language &amp; Literature, 11 (Winter 1975), 39-45.</p>
            <p>Hirst, Désirée. “Once More Continuing ‘The Tyger’.” Blake Studies, 7 (1975), 177-179.</p>
            <p>Jackson, Mary V. “Additional Lines in <hi rend="i">VDA.</hi>” Blake Newsletter, 8 (Winter
1974-75), 91-93.</p>
            <p>Jenkins, Herbert George. William Blake: Studies of His Life and Personality. 1925; rpt.
Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1974.</p>
            <p>Johnson, Mary Lynn. “Emblem and Symbol in Blake.” Huntington Library Quarterly, 37 (1974),
151-170. [Illus.]</p>
            <p>Kalman, H. “Un Fuseli à Vancouver.” Vie Arts, 71 (1973), 38-41. [Notes <hi rend="i">Le rève
de Belinda</hi>, 1781-82, in the Vancouver Art Gallery.]</p>
            <p>Kaplan, Justin. “‘The emphasis is on the individual, the handful of shepherds, the pair of
lovers’: A Conversation with Northrop Frye.” Harvard Magazine, 77 (July-August 1975), 52-56. [Reproduces one
of Blake’s engraved designs (p. 30) to <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> on p. 55.]</p>
            <p>Kaplan, Nancy A. William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: The Rhetoric of Vision.
Diss. Cornell Univ., 1975. Dissertation Abstracts International, 36, no. 5 (November 1975), 2846-A.</p>
            <p>Keynes, Geoffrey. “Blake in the Provinces.” Blake Newsletter, 9 (Fall 1975), 41-42.</p>
            <p>Lefcowitz, Barbara. “Blake and the Natural World.” PMLA, 89 (1974), 121-131.</p>
            <p>Lister, Raymond. Infernal Methods: A Study of William Blake’s Art Techniques. London: Bell,
1975.</p>
            <p>Lowry, Mark D. Relationship of Design, Color, and Text in the Stirling-Keir Copy of William
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Diss. Univ. of Texas at Austin, 1975. Dissertation Abstracts
International, 36, no. 5 (November 1975), 2850-A.</p>
            <p>Mandle, R. “A Preparatory Drawing for Henry Fuseli’s Painting ‘The Shepherd’s Dream’.”
Master Drawings, 11 (1973), 272-276. [Illus.]</p>
            <p>Marks, Mollyanne. “Structure and Irony in Blake’s ‘The Book of Urizen’.” Studies in
English Literature 1500-1900, 15 (Autumn 1975), 578-590.</p>
            <p>Metcalf, Francis W. “<hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>: Two Corrected First Readings.” Blake Newsletter,
9 (Fall 1975), 40-41.</p>
            <p>Mitchell, W. J. Thomas. “Blake’s Visions of the Last Judgment: Some Problems in
Interpretation.” Blake Newsletter, extra number, 1975. [Published for the MLA Blake Seminar, 28 December 1975;
6 illustrations, including “all of Blake’s pictures of the Last Judgment that are accessible in public
collections.”]</p>
            <p>Morton, Arthur L. The Everlasting Gospel: A Study in the Sources of William Blake. 1958; rpt.
Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1974.</p>
            <p>Murray, E. B. “‘Bound Back to Back in Bromion’s Cave’.” Blake Newsletter, B (Winter
1974-75), 94.</p>
            <p>Near, P. L. “William Blake’s Illustrations of the Book of
<pb id="p10-61" n="61"/>
Job.” Arts in Virginia, 15 (1974-75), 1-24. [Some recent acquisitions.by Virginia museums.]</p>
            <p>Nelms, Ben F. “Exemplars of Memory and of Intellect: <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Plates
96-100.” Blake Studies, 5 (1974), 81-90. [Illus.]</p>
            <p>Nelson, J. Walter. “Blake’s Diction—An Emendatory Note.” Blake Studies, 7 (1975),
167-175.</p>
            <p>Ober, Warren U. “‘Poor Robin’ &amp; Blake’s ‘The Blossom’.” Blake Newsletter, 9 (Fall
1975), 42-43.</p>
            <p>Paley, Morton and Morris Eaves, eds. Blake Newsletter, nos. 1-13, 1967-1970: rpt. Part I, nos.
1-8 (1967-1969), $5.00; Part II, nos. 9-13 (1969-1970), $5.00. Albuquerque: Blake Newsletter, 1975.</p>
            <p>Peterfreund, Stuart S. A Program Toward Prophecy: Eighteenth-Century Influences on the Poetry
of William Blake. Diss. Univ. of Washington, 1974. Dissertation Abstracts International, 36, no. 6 (December
1975), 3700-A.</p>
            <p>Peterson, Jane E. Metric and Syntactic Experimentation in Blake’s Prophecies of 1788-1795.
Diss. Univ. of Arkansas, 1975. Dissertation Abstracts International, 36, no. 6 (December 1975), 3661-A.</p>
            <p>Phillips, Michael. “The Reputation of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> 1783-1863.”
The Review of English Studies, 36 (1975), 19-33.</p>
            <p>Powell, N. “Fuseli at Hamburg, the Tate and Paris.” Burlington Magazine, 117 (1975), 123-124.
[Reviews a traveling Fuseli exhibition.]</p>
            <p>Powell, N. “Recent Fussli Studies.” Burlington Magazine, 116 (1974), 334-336.</p>
            <p>Powys, John Cowper. William Blake. 1916; rpt. London: Village Press, 1974. [Reprints Bentley
and Nurmi item 1778.]</p>
            <p>Reiman, Donald H. “A Significant New Blakean Fragment.” Blake Newsletter, 9 (Fall 1975), 44-45.
[Identifies a possible source for Blake’s influence on C. L. Dodgson.]</p>
            <p>Reisner, Thomas A. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">To Tirzah.</hi>” Explicator, 33 (1974), 3.</p>
            <p>Rollins, Mark E. The Necessity of Art: A Study of William Blake. Diss. Univ. of Massachusetts,
1974. Dissertation Abstracts International, 35, no. 9 (March 1975), 6156-A.</p>
            <p>Rosenblum, Robert. “German Romantic Painting in International Perspective.” Yale University Art
Gallery Bulletin, 33 (1971-72), 23-36. [Examines the works of Carstens, <corr type="emend">Runge</corr> and Friedrich in relationship
to English painting, especially Blake.]</p>
            <p>Salter, Thomas N. Toward a Symbology of Form in the Illuminations of Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience.</hi> Diss. Univ. of Massachusetts, 1975. Dissertation Abstracts
International, 36, no. 6 (December 1975), 3737-A.</p>
            <p>Sanzo, Eileen. “Blake’s Beulah &amp; Beulah Hill, Surrey.” Blake Newsletter, 9 (Fall 1975),
46.</p>
            <p>Schiff, Gert. <hi rend="i">Johann Heinrich Fussli 1741-1825.</hi> I: Text und Oeuvre Katalog,
II: Tafelband. Zurich: Verlag Berichthaus, and München: Prestil-Verlag, 1973.</p>
            <p>Schlieper, Reinhold. William Blake, Philosopher: An Analysis of the Metaphysical System
Underlying His Poetry. Diss. Ball State Univ., 1974. Dissertation Abstracts International, 35, no. 9 (March
1975), 6158-A.</p>
            <p>Schuchard, Marsha K. Freemasonry, Secret Societies, and the Continuity of the Occult Traditions
in English Literature. Diss. Univ. of Texas at Austin, 1975. Dissertation Abstracts International, 36, no. 5
(November 1975), 2792-A. [Includes discussion of Blake, John Varley, Lavater, Rossetti, Yeats.]</p>
            <p>Stahl, Harvey. William Blake: The Apocalyptic Vision. Preface and Catalogue by Harvey Stahl;
Introduction by Bruce D. Barone. Purchase, N.Y.: Manhattanville College, 1974. [28 illus.]</p>
            <p>Starobinski, Jean. 1789: Les emblèmes de la raison. Paris: Flammarion, 1974. [Discusses Blake,
Goya, David, Fuseli, et al.]</p>
            <p>Starobinski, Jean. <corr type="emend">Trois Fureurs.</corr> Paris: Gallimard, 1974. [One of the essays discusses
Fuseli’s <hi rend="i">The Nightmare.</hi>]</p>
            <p>Symmons, S. “French Copies after Flaxman’s Outlines.” Burlington Magazine, 115 (1973),
591-599. [Examines the influence of Flaxman’s Homer and Aeschylus illustrations.]</p>
            <p>Symmons, S. “Géricault, Flaxman and ‘Ugolino’.” Burlington Magazine, 115 (1973),
669-672.</p>
            <p>Todd, Ruthven. “The Identity of ‘Hereford’ in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> with Observations
on Welsh Matters.” Blake Studies, 6 (1975), 139-151. [4 illus.]</p>
            <p>Tully, Velma A. Innocence and Experience as Structural Comic Values in Selected Plays of the
Restoration and Eighteenth Century. Diss. Univ. of Arkansas, 1975. Dissertation Abstracts International, 36,
no. 6 (December 1975), 3666-A.</p>
            <p>Tvson, G. P. “An Early Allusion to Blake.” Blake Newsletter, 9 (Fall 1975), 43.</p>
            <p>Viscoli, Lois K. The Promethean Archetype. Diss. Univ. of New Mexico, 1974. Dissertation
Abstracts <corr type="emend">International,</corr> 39, no. 9 (March 1975), 6114-A. [Culminates in a study of
Blake and Shelley.]</p>
            <p>Volpi-Orlandini, M. “La Figura Ammantata.” Qui, 13 (1974), 8-14. [Work by Blake is among the 12
illus.]</p>
            <p>Wardle, Judith. “The Influence of Wynne’s <hi rend="i">Emblems</hi> on Blake.” Blake
Newsletter, 9 (Fall 1975), 46-47.</p>
            <p>Wehrli, R. “Johann Heinrich Fussli.” Arti, 23 (1973), 18-23. [11 illus.]</p>
            <p>Wilkie, Brian. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Innocence and Experience</hi>: An Approach.” Blake
Studies, 6 (1975), 119-137.</p>
            <p>Wilkinson, Andrew M. William Blake and the Great Sin. Exeter: Univ. of Exeter Press, 1974.
£0.30.</p>
            <p>Winter, David B. “Girtin’s Sketching Club.” Huntington Library Quarterly, 37 (1974), 123-149.
[An essay on the interrelationships between some major and minor Romantic painters, emphasizing paintings
inspired by poetry.]</p>
            <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr. Angel of Apocalypse: Blake’s Idea of Milton. Madison: Univ. of
Wisconsin Press, 1975. $15.00.</p>
            <p>Wooster, Margaret, and Arthur Efron. “On Blake’s ‘Streams of Gore’: An Exchange.” Paunch,
nos. 40-41 (April 1975), 152-165.</p>
            <p>Wooster, Margaret, and Arthur Efron. “Another Round on Blake’s ‘Streams of Gore’.”
Paunch, nos. 42-43 (December 1975), 141-148.</p>
            <p>Wyatt, David M. “The Woman Jerusalem: <hi rend="i">Pictura</hi> versus 
<hi rend="i">Poesis.</hi>” Blake Studies, 7 (1975), 105-124.</p>
            <p><corr type="emend">Yasuda, Masayoshi.</corr> William Blake Kenkyu. Tokyo: Sogensha, 1973.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Reviews</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Adlard, John. The Sports of Cruelty. Reviewed by Mary Lynn Johnson, Blake Studies, 7 (1975),
186-188.</p>
            <p>Antal, Frederick. Füssli-Studien. Reviewed in Bildende Kunst, 22 (1974), 203-204.</p>
            <p>Ault, Donald D. Visionary Physics: Blake’s Response to Newton. Reviewed by David V. Erdman,
Blake Newsletter, 8 (Spring 1975), 128-130.</p>
            <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr. Blake Records. Reviewed by Freda E. Holtgen, Anglia, 93 (1975),
268-270.</p>
            <p>Blondel, Jacques. William Blake, émerveillement et profanation. Reviewed by Simone Pignard,
Blake Newsletter, 8 (Spring 1975), 120.</p>
            <p>Bloom, Harold. The Anxiety of Influence. Reviewed by Alvin H. Rosenfeld, Southern Review, 11
(1975), 444-451.</p>
            <p>Brisman, Leslie. Milton’s Poetry of Choice and Its Romantic Heirs. Reviewed by Florence
Sandler, Blake Newsletter, 8 (Spring 1975), 127-128.</p>
            <p>Clark, Kenneth. Blake and Visionary Art. Reviewed by Jean H. Hagstrum, Blake Newsletter, 8
(Spring 1975), 143-144.</p>
            <p>Clark, Kenneth. The Romantic Rebellion: Romantic versus Classic Art. Reviewed by Jean H.
Hagstrum, Blake Newsletter, 8 (Spring 1975), 143-144.</p>
            <p>Curran, Stuart and Joseph A. Wittreich, Jr., eds. Blake’s Sublime Allegory. Reviewed by W. H.
Stevenson, Blake Studies, 6 (1974), 188-192.</p>
            <p>Donoghue, Denis. Thieves of Fire. Reviewed by Howard Nemerov, Sewanee Review, 83 (1975),
161.</p>
            <p>Downey, James and Ben Jones, eds. Fearful Joy: Papers from The Thomas Gray Bicentenary
Conference at Carleton University. Reviewed by Joseph A. Wittreich, Jr., Blake Newsletter, 8 (Spring 1975),
141-142.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V. The Illuminated Blake. Reviewed by Gerald E. Bentley, Jr., University of
Toronto Quarterly, 44 (1975), 251-258; Lawrence Lipking, Princeton Alumni Weekly, 19 Nov 74; Edward J. Rose,
Blake Newsletter, 9 (Fall 1975), 50-54; Harvey Stahl, Print Collector’s Newsletter, 6 (1975), 48-49; W. H.
Stevenson, Studies in Romanticism, 14 (Spring 1975), 201-205.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V. and Donald K. Moore, eds. The Notebook of William Blake. Reviewed By Robert N.
Essick, Blake Newsletter, 8 (Spring 1975), 132-136; Harvey Stahl, Print Collector’s Newsletter, 6 (1975),
48-49; W. H. Stevenson, Studies in Romanticism, 14 (Spring 1975), 201-205.</p>
            <p>Essick, Robert N. The Visionary Hand: Essays for the Study
<pb id="p10-62" n="62"/>
              of William Blake’s Art and Aesthetics. Reviewed by <corr type="emend">Thomas</corr> L. Minnick, Blake Newsletter, 8 (Spring 1975),
130-132; Harvey Stahl, Print Collector’s Newsletter, 6 (1975), 48-49; Brian Wilkie, Blake Studies, 6(1975),
204-208.</p>
            <p>Frosch, Thomas R. The Awakening of Albion: The Renovation of the Body in the Poetry of William
Blake. Reviewed by Irene H. Chayes, Blake Newsletter, 8 (Spring 1975), 114-115; Thomas L. Minnick, Blake
Studies, 6 (1975), 192-194.</p>
            <p>Gillham, D. G. William Blake. Reviewed by Alicia Ostriker, Blake Newsletter, 8 (Spring 1975),
136-137.</p>
            <p>Grimes, Ronald L. The Divine Imagination: William Blake’s Major Prophetic Visions. Reviewed
by James Rieger, Blake Studies, 6 (1975), 194-196.</p>
            <p>Hughes, Catherine, ed. The Clouded Hills: Selections from William Blake. Reviewed by Morris
Eaves, Blake Newsletter, 8 (Spring 1975), 139-140.</p>
            <p>John, Brian. Supreme Fictions: Studies in the Work of William Blake, Thomas Carlyle, W. B.
Yeats, and D. H. Lawrence. Reviewed by David Wagenknecht, Blake Newsletter, 9 (Fall 1975), 55.</p>
            <p>Keynes, Geoffrey. Blake Studies, 2nd ed. Reviewed by Paul Miner, Blake Newsletter, 8 (Spring
1975), 122-125.</p>
            <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. William Blake’s Watercolours Illustrating the Poems of Thomas Gray.
Reviewed by Janet Warner, Blake Studies, 6 (1975), 203-204.</p>
            <p>Leavis, F. R. and Q. D. Leavis. Dickens the Novelist. Reviewed by J. R. Harvey, The Cambridge
Quarterly, 6 (1972), 77-93. [Pp. 89, 93 concern the chapter “Dickens and Blake.”]</p>
            <p>Leyris, Pierre, ed. and trans. William Blake, Works. Vol. 1. Reviewed by Claude Jannoud, Blake
Newsletter, 8 (Spring 1975), 121. [Rpt. from Le Figaro, 29 June 1974, p. 8; trans. Katharyn R. Gabriella.]</p>
            <p>Lindberg, Bo. William Blake’s Illustrations to the Book of Job. Reviewed by Gerald E.
Bentley, Jr., Blake Newsletter, 8 (Spring 1975), 125-126; Jeffry B. Spencer, Blake Studies, 6 (1975),
197-200.</p>
            <p>Lister, Raymond. British Romantic Art. Reviewed by Jean H. Hagstrum, Blake Newsletter, 8
(Spring 1975), 143-144.</p>
            <p>Mellor, Anne K. Blake’s Human Form Divine. Reviewed by W. J. Thomas Mitchell, Blake
Newsletter, 8 (Spring 1975), 117-119; Harvey Stahl, Print Collector’s Newsletter, 6 (1975), 48-49; Brian
Wilkie, Journal of English and Germanic Philology, 74 (January 1975), 134-137.</p>
            <p>Nelson, Cary. The Incarnate Word: Literature as Verbal Space. Reviewed by Thomas A. Vogler,
Blake Newsletter, 8 (Spring 1975), 108-113.</p>
            <p>Nurmi, Martin K. William Blake. Reviewed by Paul M. Zall, Blake Newsletter, 9 (Fall 1975),
54-55.</p>
            <p>Paley, Morton D. and Michael Phillips, eds. William Blake: Essays in Honour of Sir Geoffrey
Keynes. Reviewed by Paul Miner, Blake Newsletter, 8 (Spring 1975), 122-125.</p>
            <p>Reardon, John, producer. On Reflection: Adrian Mitchell on William Blake [Film]. Reviewed by
Morris Eaves, Blake Newsletter, 8 (Spring 1975), 139-140.</p>
            <p>Sabri-Tabrizi, G. R. The “Heaven” and “Hell” of William Blake. Reviewed by Michael J. Tolley,
Blake Newsletter, 8 (Spring 1975), 138; James T. Wills, Blake Studies, 6 (1975), 201-202.</p>
            <p>Stevenson, Warren. Divine Analogy: A Study of the Creation Motif in Blake and Coleridge.
Reviewed by Stuart Curran, Blake Studies, 7 (1975), 180-182.</p>
            <p>Taylor, Irene C. Blake’s Illustrations to the Poems of Gray. Reviewed by Alan Watson, Art
Bulletin, 55 (1973), 464-465.</p>
            <p>Wagenknecht, David. Blake’s Night: William Blake and the Idea of Pastoral. Reviewed by Hazard
Adams, Modern Philology, 73 (November 1975), 200-203.</p>
            <p>Wright, Andrew. Blake’s Job. A Commentary. Reviewed by Karl Kiralis, Blake Studies, 7 (1975),
182-186.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
