<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>10.2.ott</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="note">The Bird-Man of William Blake’s Jerusalem</title>
        <author n="Ott">Judith Ott</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1976</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1976</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">10.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
              <name>Michael Hays</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Jane Welford</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Mary Baine</name>
              <name>Rodney Baine</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <name>Judith Ott</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1976"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_10">
    <body>
      <pb id="p10-48" n="48"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-10-2-0004">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">NOTES</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <figure n="Jerusalem.D.P78.10.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="789" height="1000">
          <head>1 <hi rend="i">Jerusalem 78</hi></head>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p10-49" n="49"/>
        <figure n="Jerusalem78Detail.10.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="247">
          <head>2 <hi rend="i">Jerusalem 78</hi>, detail</head>
        </figure>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">The Bird-Man of William Blake’s Jerusalem</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">BY</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">JUDITH</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">OTT</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The illuminations of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> are as complex as the actual
text and as fascinating. One of the more puzzling of these illuminations is found on plate 78 (illus. 1), the
title page of Chapter 4. It is a half-page illustration of a man with a bird’s head, seated upon a rock, his
head resting upon the clenched fist of his left hand. The text of the page is written upon the murky waters
which surround him, a quarter-sun appears upon his left, and dark clouds billow in an arch above his head.</p>
          <p>This odd figure has already been identified as representing Los, Blake’s Time-Spirit “in a mood
of conflicting emotions.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> This
interpretation is probably correct, as far as it goes. However, there is more meaning in this Bird-Man image
(illus. 2), unique among Blake’s illuminations, than an identification as Los can provide. Blake has
incorporated several visual allusions within this image and, once recognized, they add dimension to his
character Los. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Joseph Wicksteed, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Jerusalem</hi> (London: The Trianon Press, n.d.), p. 226. Mr. Wicksteed’s further identification of the
figure, however, I feel is incorrect. The bird’s head shown is not that of a cock. This is made obvious
through a comparison with the bird’s head in Blake’s illustration of <hi rend="i">Comus with the Lady
Spellbound</hi>, which does show a cock’s head. John Beer, in <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Universe</hi>
(New York: Barnes and Noble, Inc., 1969) also identifies the Bird-Man as an “Eagleheaded guardian visionary,”
pl. 43.</note></p>
          <p>The motif of a figure resting his head on his hand is part of a visual tradition traceable to
ancient Egyptian sarcophagi reliefs.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref>
Connected with Egyptian mourners, it signifies grief. This gesture was also used to show sleep, fatigue and
creative thought. That Blake was familiar with this ancient device and used it in several of its meanings can
be seen in his illuminations. In his watercolor, <hi rend="i">Queen Katherine’s Dream</hi>, he uses it to
show dream-filled sleep. In <hi rend="i">My Son! My Son!</hi>, from the <hi rend="i">Gates of Paradise</hi>
(pl. 8), he uses the pose to represent despair and grief. And in his illuminations for <hi rend="i">Poems by
Mr. Gray</hi> (p. 82) Blake repeats the convention again, this time to imply creative thought. Which, if any
of these meanings, apply to the figure in plate 78? A look at his artistic sources is helpful here. 
<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> <corr type="emend">Raymond Klibansky,</corr> Erwin Panofsky and Fritz Saxl, <hi rend="i">Saturn and
Melancholy</hi> (London: Thomas Nelson and Sons, Ltd., 1964), pp. 286-87; see also Erwin Panofsky, 
<hi rend="i">Albrecht Dürer</hi>, 2 v., (Princeton, N. J.: Princeton University, n.d.), v. I, p. 162.</note></p>
          <p>As a boy, Blake bought engravings and drawings from several of London’s auction rooms.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> Dürer, in particular, was one of Blake’s
heroes and it is known that a copy of Durer’s <hi rend="i">Melancholia I</hi> (illus. 3) hung for a great
part of Blake’s life on his workroom wall.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
type="note">4</ref> It is doubtful that the similarity between the poses of Dürer’s melancholy angel and
Blake’s Bird-Man is merely coincidental. What is puzzling is why Blake chose to make such an obvious and
singular allusion to <hi rend="i">Melancholia I</hi> in this illumination. The answer may lie in the
Neoplatonic philosophy in which Dürer’s print is steeped and about which Blake may well have known. 
<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: The Clarendon Press,
Press, 1969), pp. 421-22.</note>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Bentley, p. 565, fn. 3.</note></p>
          <figure n="DurerMelancholia.10.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="499">
            <figTranscr>MELENCOLIA I<lb/>
            <lb/>
            VIIII X XI XII I II III IIII V<lb/>
            <lb/>
            16   3   2   13<lb/>
             5  10  11    8<lb/>
             9   6   7   12<lb/>
             4  15  14    1<lb/>
             <lb/>
             15[14]<lb/>
             AD</figTranscr>
            <head>3 Albrecht Dürer, <hi rend="i">Melancholia I</hi></head>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p10-50" n="50"/>
          <p>Of the major works of Dürer in 1514, <hi rend="i">Melancholia I</hi> is the most involved
iconographically.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> It symbolizes one of
the four humors, or temperaments, popular in the Middle Ages—specifically, the dreaded melancholy humor. The
Florentine Neoplatonists, in particular Marsilio Ficino, gave the melancholic a much more favored position
than previously assigned him.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> By
transposing the idea that all geniuses are melancholics into the statement that all melancholics are geniuses,
this humor became associated with high thought. This kind of melancholic is the one that Dürer represents.
His engraving is, in Neoplatonic terms, of a “melancholia artificialis,” or artist’s melancholy. For Durer,
and possibly for Blake as well, <hi rend="i">Melancholia I</hi> was a visionary image of the melancholy artist
he was himself. <note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> I have relied heavily upon Panofsky’s analysis here, 
<hi rend="i">Albrecht Dürer</hi>, v. I, pp. 156-71.</note>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> See <corr type="emend">R. Klibansky,</corr> <hi rend="i">et al., Saturn and Melancholy</hi> for a
discussion of the evolution of melancholy in the 16th century’s Neoplatonic thought.</note></p>
          <p>Plate 78 therefore has an implicit connection with the melancholy artist. In Blake’s system Los
is the “creative imagination,” the deepest Zoa and the center of each individual.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> Durer’s angel, lapsed into a state of gloomy inaction,
represents Theoretical Insight, for she thinks but cannot act—so Los broods in inactivity. Melancholia,
representing architecture and carpentry, has about her elements which are of Los’ trade. They are both
seated near water as murky as the black gall which afflicts melancholics and both have the characteristic
“earthlike” complexion of melancholics.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">8</ref> As Durer’s angel is the embodiment of the tragic unrest of human creation, Los—the
creative imagination—is the origin of that restless creation, and his son Orc is the revolutionary spirit
itself. <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary</hi> (Providence,
R. I.: Brown University Press, 1965), p. 246.</note>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Erwin Panofsky, <hi rend="i">Albrecht Dürer</hi>, vol. 1, p.
163.</note></p>
          <p>Another element in plate 78, traced to its artistic source, provides the next level of meaning in
Blake’s image. That is the figure of a man with a bird’s head. Again this is a commonly used, ancient
motif traceable to representations of the Egyptian sun god Horus, shown with the head of a hawk. As both Los
and Horus are associated with the sun, Los probably being an anagram of “Sol,” there is a connection even
here.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> Yet the head of Blake’s
Bird-Man is not a hawk and his artistic source may well be not from his early work for the Society of
Antiquaries, but from his knowledge of early medieval Christian motifs. <note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi>
Damon, p. 246.</note></p>
          <p>That Blake chose an eagle’s head for his Bird-Man can be seen through a comparison with the
eagle-head of the griffin in his illumination to Dante, <hi rend="i">Beatrice Addressing Dante from the
Car.</hi> Blake was familiar with the Christian tradition that associated the four evangelists with the four
beasts of the Apocalypse (in Blake’s system, the Four Zoas). In this tradition St. John was represented by
the eagle. Medieval illuminators chose to depict St. John in one of three ways: with an eagle, as an eagle, or
as a man with an eagle’s head (illus. 4).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> F. Edward Hulme, <hi rend="i">Symbolism in Christian Art</hi> (New York:
Macmillan &amp; Co., 1891), p. 132.</note></p>
          <p>Aside from the fact that an eagle-man is St. John’s traditional symbol, he is also often shown,
as in plate 78, alone on the island of Patmos writing the Book of Revelation. Thus Blake’s figure is not
only a direct reference to the evangelist, but to the event of divine inspiration for which he was known.
Again, it seems pertinent to ask why Blake chose this allusion.</p>
          <p>According to Blake’s system, Los is “the ‘Prophet of Eternity,’ who reveals the basic
truths . . . He directly inspires Blake himself . . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">11</ref> Thus St. John, who wrote the Apocalypse—a book exclusively meant to reveal future
truths—proves an appropriate parallel figure. St. John’s visions, especially of the Last Judgment, were
also a great inspiration in Blake’s writings. As Blake identified with Los, so too he must have identified
with the great visionary evangelist. With Blake as the common link, Los and St. John became fused, in plate
78, into one image. <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Damon, p. 247.</note></p>
          <p>Traditionally, the eagle was the one bird who could soar on high and look directly at the
sun.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> A symbol of genius, he was an
appropriate symbol for St. John, who wrote of the highest mysteries of faith. As Blake said, “When thou seest
an eagle, thou seest a portion of Genius; lift up thy head!”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n13" type="note">13</ref> Thus the symbolism surrounding St. John, the sun and the eagle are linked.
In plate 78, the sun is not only the link with Los as his “golden orb,” but with St. John as his source of
Divine Inspiration. <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Damon, p. 112.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi><hi rend="i"> Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, 9:15.</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s quarter-sun is divine because he shows it on the left side of his Bird-Man plate. In
Renaissance tradition, the sun shown on the left, or sunlight from the left in a picture, was a northern
sun.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> Northern light, as an unnatural
phenomenon, was considered divine—a well-known artistic convention even in Blake’s time. Los and the
eagle, both in Blake’s northern quarternary, further identify the region as northern.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> Thus the sun is not only a symbol for Los,
and of St. John’s inspiration, but an equation of the two. Blake, the visionary, saw his inspiration and
that of St. John as originating in the same way—from imagination. <note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Erwin
Panofsky, <hi rend="i">Early Netherlandish Paintings: Its Origins and Character</hi> (Cambridge, Mass.:
Harvard University Press, 1953), pp. 147-48; for a discussion of the symbolism of lighting conventions and
their meanings in Renaissance art.</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Damon, p. 246.</note></p>
          <p>But do the motifs of St. John and Melancholia have a common linkage? The four evangelists were
equated with the four humors in medieval literature.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16"
type="note">16</ref> Durer himself made this connection and, using age as the key, showed St. John—according
to northern custom—as a young man and therefore the sanguine. But, as Panofsky implies, this does not
necessarily reflect a fixed association. St. John was often represented as an old man with a white beard in
the Eastern tradition and could have been also associated with the melancholic humor. Certainly some
representations of St. John suggest just such an association.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n17" type="note">17</ref> The melancholic’s inclination for
<figure n="ManEagle.10.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="241">
	<head>4 Man with an eagle’s head</head>
</figure>
<pb id="p10-51" n="51"/>
solitude and study, plus the Neoplatonic equation with genius, make the connection a strong possibility.
Perhaps Blake, knowing of the medieval associations, made his own link. <note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi>
Erwin Panofsky, <hi rend="i">Albrecht Dürer</hi>, included in his discussion of Durer’s <hi rend="i">Four
Apostles</hi>, p. 235.</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> A representation such as <hi rend="i">St. John</hi> sculpted by <corr type="emend">Jacobello
e Pierpaolo Dalle Masegne</corr> in the Basilica di S. Marco, which shows the apostle characteristically with his
hand to his cheek, in a melancholic pose.</note></p>
          <p>Thus the illumination of plate 78 is multilayered in its meaning. It is the figure Los, the
creative imagination, surrounded by the sea of time and space, enveloped in Urizen’s “clouds of reason”
which obscure the mind, accompanied by his sun symbol, in a mood of sullen contemplation. The figure is also
the melancholy artist, surrounded by the waters of Saturn or waves of black gall, gazing at the inspirational
sun, but unable to use his genius as he broods on the lonely shore. He is St. John as well, but without (or
before) inspiration, exiled to Patmos, lethargically looking upon God’s sun with his eagle eyes, unable to
act. Together, plate 78 represents all of these elements in one image, as they were in Blake’s mind—not to
be differentiated, but ultimately perceived as one unit infinitely meaningful.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
