<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>10.2.baine</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="note">Blake’s Inflammable Gass</title>
        <author n="Baine">Rodney M. Baine</author>
        <author n="Baine">Mary R. Baine</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1976</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1976</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">10.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
              <name>Michael Hays</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Jane Welford</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Mary Baine</name>
              <name>Rodney Baine</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <name>Judith Ott</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1976"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_10">
    <body>
	<pb id="p10-51" n="51"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-10-2-0004">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">NOTES</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">Blake’s Inflammable Gass</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">BY</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">RODNEY</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">M.</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">AND</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">MARY R.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">BAINE</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Although he may well be a type as well as a caricature,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n18" type="note">1</ref> one of the characters in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Island in the
Moon</hi> whose original has so far defied satisfactory identification is Inflammable Gass the Wind-finder.
The various scientists so far proposed for this friend of the Philosophers have been too far from Blake’s
scene, too elderly, too eminent, or too conventional. Probably the most popular identification is that
proposed by S. Foster Damon—Joseph Priestley (1733-1804).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n19" type="note">2</ref> This suggestion has been accepted by a number of Blake scholars. Serious
questioning of the identification by Nancy Bogen, however, led David Erdman to change his mind,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">3</ref> and with reason: since Priestley was
twenty-four years older than Blake, was eminent in his profession, and lived in Birmingham from 1780 to 1791,
he does not fit into the picture at all. Other identifications have been no more satisfying. In 1951 Palmer
Brown suggested Gustavus Katterfelto (d. 1799). Although Erdman seems to accept this identification in part,
the Philosophers would surely have been repelled by this conjuror and quack doctor, who was ultimately
committed to prison in Shrewsbury as an impostor and who for decades lingered in popular memory among “the
most celebrated professors in natural magic.” In his own opinion the greatest philosopher in Great Britain
since Newton, Katterfelto was about the time of <hi rend="i">An Island</hi> moving in eminent circles, in 1784
attracting even the Royal Family to his exhibit. Not a bumbling amateur like Inflammable, he was a smoothly
operating professional exhibitor.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">4</ref> In
1968 Stanley Gardner proposed Dr. George Fordyce (1736-1802) or Henry Cavendish (1731-1810),<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">5</ref> but each was at least twenty years older than
Blake and eminent in his profession. Fordyce was a physician; Inflammable is not so characterized. Cavendish
was an unsociable millionaire. <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See Martha W. England, “The Satiric Blake:
Apprenticeship at the Haymarket?” <hi rend="i">BNYPL</hi> 73 (1969), 440-64, 531-50, and in 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman and John E. Grant (Princeton: Princeton
Univ. Press, 1970), pp. 3-29.</note>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">2</hi> S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Philosophy and
Symbols</hi> (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1924; rpt. New York: Peter Smith, 1947), p. 33, and <hi rend="i">A
Blake Dictionary</hi> (Providence: Brown Univ. Press, 1965), p. 197.</note>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Nancy Bogen, “William Blake’s ‘Island in the Moon’ Revisited,” 
<hi rend="i">Satire Newsletter</hi> 5 (1968), 110; David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet against
Empire</hi>, revised ed. (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1969), pp. 93-94, n. 13.</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Erdman, pp. 93-94, n. 13. Giuseppe Pinetti, <hi rend="i">The Conjuror’s
Repository</hi> (London: T. and R. Hughes, [1795?]); <hi rend="i">The Whole Art of Legerdemain, or the Black
Art Laid Open and Explained, by Katterfelto</hi> . . . (London: T. Hughes, [1826?]); Robert Chambers, 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Days</hi> (London, [1864]) 1, 511-12; W.C., “Who was Katerfelto,” in <hi rend="i">The
Mirror</hi>, XVII, 69.</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Stanley Gardner, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1968; rpt. New York: Arco,
1969), pp. 63, 65.</note></p>
          <p>The portrait of Inflammable Gass as presented in <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi> seems to
us to suggest most strongly William Nicholson (1753-1815), who was only four years older than Blake, lived
nearby, shared his political and religious views, and could have met Blake through either John Flaxman or
Thomas Holcroft. Blake is almost certain to have known Nicholson in the 1800’s<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">6</ref>; but he could have met him in the late 1770’s or early
’80’s. In 1776 Nicholson was serving as an agent for the Wedgwoods, and Flaxman was already designing for
<pb id="p10-52" n="52"/>
that firm. If Blake did not meet Nicholson through Flaxman, he may have done so later through Thomas Holcroft.
In 1784 Blake was contributing monthly a featured engraving to Holcroft’s <hi rend="i">Wit’s
Magazine</hi>, and he probably knew Holcroft before then. If he visited Holcroft in the early 1780’s at the
Southhampton Buildings he would probably have met Nicholson there, for Nicholson had rooms with Holcorft at
the time and collaborated with him in his first complete novel, <hi rend="i">Alwyn</hi> (1780).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">7</ref> Later in the 1780’s Nicholson lived even
closer to Blake, at Red Lion Square. Or Blake may have met Nicholson through Joseph Johnson, the liberal
publisher who planned to publish <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi>; indeed Blake engraved for Johnson
this same year (1782) the plate for a mathematical volume of Bonnycastle. He may have also engraved during
this same year some of the twenty-five unsigned plates for Nicholson’s <hi rend="i">Introduction to Natural
Philosophy</hi>, published, again, by Johnson. <note id="n23"><hi rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake,
Records</hi>, ed. G. E. Bentley, Jr. (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969), p. 188.</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Rodney M. Baine, <hi rend="i">Thomas Holcroft and the Revolutionary
Novel</hi> (Athens, Ga.: Univ. of Georgia Press, 1965), pp. 12, 115.</note></p>
          <p>The internal evidence from these two volumes suggests that Nicholson may well have been the
original of Inflammable. A dedicated scientist like Nicholson, Inflammable cannot conceive that any man can be
a fool if he is “desirous of enquiring into the works of nature” (E 441). Blake’s name for him is surely apt
for Nicholson. In his <hi rend="i">Introduction</hi> Nicholson included an extended discussion of inflammable
gas and specifically noted the inflammable nature of the air found in privies: “Putrescent animal matters emit
this fluid [inflammable gas], as has been observed in church-yards, houses of office, and such 
. . . ”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">8</ref> 
Inflammable boasts, “Heres a bottle
of wind that I took up in the bog house [privy]” (E 452). As wind-finder (probably not so much wind-measurer
as wind-locator) Nicholson not only described and illustrated instruments which he perfected for measuring the
“elasticity” and weight of air (II, 42-44; figs. 105, 106), but he also included a chapter “Of Winds, and
their Causes,” locating many winds (II, 63-76). Here is a typical example: “Between the parallels of 28 and 40
south latitude, in that tract which extends from 30° West to 100° East longitude from the meridian of
London, the wind is variable, but by far the greater part between the N.W. and S.W. so that the outward bound
East India ships generally run down their easting on the parallel of 36° south” (II, 64-65). Not only does
Inflammable’s name fit Nicholson, but so do Inflammable’s actions, except that the biological
demonstrations using microscope and slides do not appear in the <hi rend="i">Introduction.</hi> Here, however,
are Inflammable’s air pump, his camera obscura, and “Flogiston.” In Chapter 10 of <hi rend="i">An
Island</hi> the air pump which Tilly Lally and Little Scopprell break must have been fitted with a glass
receiver, for “Smack went the glass” (E 453). “The most useful of all philosophical instruments, whose actions
depend on the properties of the air” (II, 110), Nicholson’s model is equipped with a “glass-receiver, out of
which the air is to be exhausted” (II, 111). “By the help of this machine,” Nicholson remarked, “all that has
been shewn concerning the weight and elasticity of the air, is demonstrated in the most simple and elegant
manner” (II, 110). When Inflammable remarks suddenly, “I have got a camera obscura at home” (E 443) and later
has “magic pictures” (E 452) to exhibit to his guests, Blake may again have had Nicholson in mind. Nicholson
described and illustrated both the darkened room, the literal camera obscura, and the “Magic Lanthorn” (I,
359, 368; figs. 83, 87). Moreover, in an episode which he had just written for Thomas Holcroft’s 
<hi rend="i">Alwyn</hi> he had one of the young heroes frighten a Methodist minister up the chimney (Ch. XIV) by
using a magic lanthorn to show a picture of the Devil. Again, Inflammable boasts, “I have got a bottle of air
that would spread a Plague” (E 442), and he later warns his guests when some of the bottles are broken, “our
lungs are destroyed with the Flogiston” (E 453). In his detailed study of phlogiston, Nicholson noted, “With
regard to the effect of phlogisticated air . . . an animal plunged in a vessel of noxious air dies much more
suddenly and irrecoverably than in the vacuum of an air-pump” (II, 335-36). He then cited the fatal effects of
the long exposure of miners to “phlogistic emanations” (II, 339). <note id="n25"><hi rend="s">8</hi> William
Nicholson, <hi rend="i">An Introduction to Natural Philosophy</hi> (London: Johnson, 1782), II, 351-59; II,
351. Subsequent citations, incorporated in the text, cite this first edition.</note></p>
          <p>A final suggestion of Nicholson may lie in Inflammable’s defense of Voltaire, whom he praises
as “the Glory of France” who had “found out a Number of Queries in Philosophy” (E 442, 441) and in
Inflammable’s desire to “see the parsons all hangd a parcel of lying—” (E 443). This anti-ecclesiasticism
sounds very like the militant deism of <hi rend="i">The Doubts of the Infidels</hi> (1781), in which Nicholson
anonymously attacked Biblical inconsistencies and contradictions, continuing Voltaire’s Biblical attacks in
the <hi rend="i">Dictionnaire Philosophique.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26"
type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">9</hi> This work, unattributed to Nicholson in his brief biographies and in the
BM catalog, was reprinted in the first volume of Richard Carlile’s periodical <hi rend="i">The
Deist.</hi></note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
