<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>10.3.boyette</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr., Angel of Apocalypse: Blake’s Idea of
Milton</title>
        <author n="Boyette">Purvis E. Boyette</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1976-77</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1976-77</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">10.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
              <name>Michael Hays</name>
              <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Jane Welford</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Irene Tayler</name>
              <name>Elaine M. Kauver</name>
              <name>Philip B. Grant</name>
              <name>Purvis E. Boyette</name>
              <name>Suzanne Hoover</name>
              <name>Myra Glazer Schotz</name>
              <name>Gerda Norvig</name>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1976"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_10">
    <body>
      <pb id="p10-88" n="88"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-10-3-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">Reviews</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr. <hi rend="b">Angel of Apocalypse: Blake’s Idea
of Milton.</hi> Madison: Univ. of Wisconsin Press, 1975. xxii + 322 pp. $15.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Purvis E. <name>Boyette</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Wittreich has written a wonderfully old-fashioned book, although students who have gone to school
with Bloom and Bush may think they are reading a book more revolutionary than it is. Blake’s idea of Milton,
according to Wittreich, is that the great poet was an apocalyptic visionary whose deepest insight was depicted
in the spiritual illumination of the Jesus of <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained.</hi> This transcendental
experience of redemption allowed Milton to burst through the patterns of tradition, art, and constricting
personal moralities to achieve the divine vision of revolutionary and transforming prophecy—and thus become,
in a figure less metaphorical than one might suppose, an angel of apocalypse. Blake’s original perception of
this initiatory and liberating experience revealed Milton’s revolutionary attitudes toward “all” artistic
and intellectual traditions, and as an inspired, lifting purity of imagination, Blake’s perception of Milton
“freed Blake from tyrannies of art and of history” (p. 231) and made Milton far otherwise than the Great
Inhibitor. With that thesis, Wittreich’s book, somewhat unexpectedly, explores Blake’s achievement within
the context of tradition, seeking to show not “how a recalcitrant poet withdrew from his cultural heritage but
how a revolutionary artist [Blake] learned to use his heritage both creatively and subversively” (p. 69).</p>
          <p>The most provocative chapter in the book, to my mind, is on “Milton as a Revolutionary,”
following two chapters of exemplary analysis and criticism of “Blake’s Portrait and Portrayals of Milton”
and “Blake’s Milton Illustrations.” Blake’s idea of Milton merits our attention, Wittreich says, because
the comprehension of an entire age is summarized therein and because Blake embodies “truths about Milton
repressed during the eighteenth century and still lost in the orthodoxies of modern criticism” (p. 148). Most
generally, the proponents of these orthodoxies appear to be Eliot and Leavis, though closer to home, Wittreich
cites the Victorian villainy of one of Robert West’s essays in which Milton is proclaimed “a superbly gifted
confirmer of what his audience already believed and user of ways of thinking already established.” Opposed to
that is a sentence by Marcuse arguing that an “artist’s invocation of orthodoxies” may well allow a poet to
assume subversive attitudes toward them, followed by a telling point that on “virtually every occasion when he
speaks of tradition and custom, [Milton] associates both with tyranny and error” (p. 149). Thus, the battle is
joined, and what follows is a carefully argued and thoroughly researched discussion of how the “forms of
poetry . . . may be used against the very systems that have disfigured them” (p. 155).</p>
          <p>Wittreich’s apparent intellectual and emotional identification with Blake’s perception of
Milton is a remarkable feat of imaginative criticism, stimulated by the admirable care of a serious scholar.
But I, for one, would have preferred to read Plato on the <hi rend="i">Forms</hi> of things instead of
Marcuse, who learned his metaphysics from Plato too. There is something trendy, not quite gratuitous, in such
citations of our contemporary philosophers, but one finds support where one can, and Wittreich knows too
much—much of it displayed—to be chastized for lack of classical reading. Marcuse, however, leads Wittreich
into an oddity of thought that ought to be remarked: theology keeps turning into ideology (pp. 85, 190, 213,
241), a metamorphosis slippery at best, misleading at worst, and in any case a suspicious bit of rhetoric,
leading Wittreich to say that Spenser, Milton’s celebrated teacher, “was locked into the orthodoxies from
which Milton wished to liberate poetry” (p. 157); that the audience to whom the epic was addressed shifted
from a social to a spiritual elite; and that Blake/Milton’s preference for the daughters of inspiration over
the daughters of memory shifted epic theory from a theory of imitation to a theory of inspiration; and
finally, that “in terms of ideology, <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> expresses the poet’s radicalism . . .
in its rejection of epic structure” (p. 170). Now, all of this is effectively argued, often persuasive, but
the old boys who still like their Plato (especially the <hi rend="i">Timaeus, Ion</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">Symposium</hi>), the orphic theories of Chapman and Reynolds, the mystical theology of William
Alabaster, and even Dryden have not yet been done to death. That Wittreich/Blake has made an important
difference in the way one must think about Milton from now on is, however, certain.</p>
          <p>Milton is of the devil’s party because he is “both a political radical and a religious
dissenter” (p. 214) and because the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> embraces the double perspective of the
prophetic poem, which means that what the Devil says “may be true from the perspective of history, but . . .
not true from the perspective of eternity that the poet enjoys” (p. 215). This artistic strategy engages an
ironic play between speakers and shifting perspectives, whereby “the Devil is to Blake what Milton’s
Beelzebub is to Satan and what Satan sometimes is to Milton—a spokesman who never exhibits the same
largeness of mind as the figure with whom he is identified” (p. 215). Milton, in short, knew what he was doing
when he invested his Satan with those qualities of sublimity, majesty, and energy which Blake and Milton could
admire in a moral character, like the Jesus of <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> but not the Satan of 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi> If Wittreich/Blake’s reading of Milton is true to Milton’s poems, then Blake
is indeed Milton’s first “fit” reader, unlike Dryden and those others who have thought the Devil was
Milton’s hero instead of Adam.</p>
          <p>Wittreich’s book, as I have tried to indicate, is closely argued, making a lot of sense out of
<pb id="p10-89" n="89"/>
the foam and rolling weed of Blake’s sea of words, as well as casting light on the pictorial language and
meaning of Blake’s illustrations, forty-five of them reproduced in black and white on glossy paper. There is
much in the book that I have not mentioned, the final chapter being richly suggestive, of Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> as an attempt to mythologize “the decisive turning point of Milton’s life, which . . .
comes with the writing of <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>” and to related “that moment of redemption to
the renewal of the entire human race” (p. 243), and more, that “prophecy is a sublime allegory, . . . its
reference points [being] . . . not history but the inner life of man” (p. 245). In fact, the final chapter is
not so much epilogue as prologue to yet another book, that one being a promised full-scale commentary on 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>; and one may look forward to it as work that will be characterized, like 
<hi rend="i">Angel of Apocalypse</hi>, by rigor, strong points of view, dense documentation, and significance.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
