<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>10.3.hoover</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">G. E. Bentley, Jr.’s William Blake: The Critical Heritage</title>
        <author n="Hoover">Suzanne R. Hoover</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1976-77</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1976-77</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">10.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
              <name>Michael Hays</name>
              <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Jane Welford</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Irene Tayler</name>
              <name>Elaine M. Kauver</name>
              <name>Philip B. Grant</name>
              <name>Purvis E. Boyette</name>
              <name>Suzanne Hoover</name>
              <name>Myra Glazer Schotz</name>
              <name>Gerda Norvig</name>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1976"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_10">
    <body>
	<pb id="p10-89" n="89"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-10-3-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">Reviews</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">G. E. Bentley, Jr. <hi rend="b">William Blake: The Critical Heritage.</hi>
London and Boston: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1975. xix + 294 pp. $25.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Suzanne R. <name>Hoover</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Though the Mortal &amp; Perishing part of the present book be inelegant, expensive, and small,
the Real Book, a documentary survey of the reaction to Blake and his works before the publication of
Gilchrist’s biography in 1863, will hold a large interest for readers who may wonder what it was like in the
old days to encounter Blake without a trot. The details of this survey may at times baffle us, suggesting a
playing-out of tidal under-rhythms of attraction and repulsion that have little to do with sophisticated
appreciation, but the overall curve seems explicable enough. The brief “high” of Blake’s reputation in the
early 1800’s turned to a long, largely ebbing phase as a consequence of the fact that the character of the
man was increasingly out of harmony with the character of the times: as Samuel Palmer wrote to Gilchrist in
1855 (part of a long reminiscence about Blake for Gilchrist’s book), “materialism was his abhorrence.” The
importance of the profound dyspathy between Blake and the culture of the first half of the nineteenth century
cannot be overstressed, for there is no artist of whom it is truer to say that his character is his art—and
therefore, his destiny. Some of the pain of looking closely at that destiny is mitigated for us by the
enjoyments of Regency and Victorian genius; reactions to Blake during the pre-Gilchrist period come most
copiously from persons who hold considerable, in some cases great, interest for us in their own right—as
poets, essayists, critics, artists, mountebanks, etc.—a circumstance which compounds the interest of what we
are reading and helps to put the whole question of early responses to Blake in a suitably spacious
setting.</p>
          <p>Further to help us to that end Professor Bentley begins his book with a useful twenty-six-page
Introduction that sets forth the history of Blake criticism and Blake studies. The present compilation
resembles earlier ones in the Critical Heritage Series in its mixture of general essays on Blake with
commentary on specific works. It differs from the other volumes in being about a writer who was also a
professional artist, and in that it is necessarily composed more of private statements than of published
reviews. A selection of comment on Blake and his work during his lifetime has been made from the fuller
materials in <hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13"
type="note">1</ref> This includes some long pieces, such as the essays by Malkin and Crabb Robinson, and the
now famous reviews in the <hi rend="i">Examiner</hi> (1808) and <hi rend="i">Antijacobin</hi> (1808), as well
as numerous brief, even fragmentary, references, in many cases excerpted from longer items in 
<hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi> The biographical essays of 1827-31 by Smith, Cunningham, and Tatham are given in
full, along with early post-obit articles on Blake in <hi rend="i">Fraser’s</hi> and the <hi rend="i">London
University Magazine</hi> (all in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>). A spare, running commentary like that in
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> introduces and connects the items. <note id="n13"><hi rend="s">1</hi> G. E.
Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969).</note></p>
          <p>The new feature of this book is its chronologically ordered final section on the years 1831-63,
which cites every commentary on Blake in that period, and even every comment that is now known, some for the
first time: 300 items in all. This is a valuable drawing in of the nets, notwithstanding that, with netting so
very fine, whitebait are brought up with tuna. The question one might raise about this chapter concerns its
title, “The Forgotten Years.” It is my belief, stated already in these pages and elsewhere, that “forgotten”
is a misnomer in that it places an emphasis on the number of comments rather than on a consideration of their
significance. Many of the (comparatively few) notices of Blake’s work that <hi rend="i">were</hi> taken were
important, coming as they did from Emerson, Ruskin, Palgrave, Henry James, Sr., the Pre-Raphaelites, and
others of interest to us now. An edition of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> was published for Wilkinson in
1839; pictures by Blake were exhibited with works of other English artists to a mass audience in 1857 and
1862, and commented on in the press. “Forgotten” really does not describe this state of affairs. Nor is it
quite accurate to place the turn of the Blake tide at 1863, as Professor Bentley does in a paragraph
introductory to this chapter. From the late ‘forties through the early ‘sixties there was a definite
increase in interest in Blake, which was marked by (among numerous other indices) the acquisition of many of
his works by the British Museum. The immediate burst of attention to Blake supposedly aroused from nil by
Gilchrist in fact occurred in at atmosphere in which Blake was <hi rend="i">somewhat</hi> known. Of course, it
is proper to emphasize the huge limitations of the mid-Victorians’ knowledge of Blake, with regard both to
the number of works available and the number of persons familiar with them, but that should not entitle us to
write off as inconsequential the knowledge that did exist. I am conscious of the fineness of this point, and
yet, if there is a purpose in retrieving and citing the small documents along with the large, it can only be
to refine our picture of the way things actually happened.</p>
          <pb id="p10-90" n="90"/>
          <p>There is a small misunderstanding in the final section that I am happily able to set right. On
page 263 Professor Bentley notes that he has been unable to find “Palgrave’s Official Catalogue” of the 1862
Exhibition, which he states was cited by me in my essay on Blake’s reputation in the 
<hi rend="i">Festschrift</hi> for Sir Geoffrey Keynes.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">2</ref> The form of my citation makes it clear that I was referring to an article by Palgrave
which constitutes a part of the one and only <hi rend="i">Official Catalogue</hi>: it is a three-page essay
introducing the watercolor listings entitled, “The British School of Water Colour Painting.” What is
remarkable about this short piece by Palgrave is that nearly one page of it is taken up with a comparison of
Stothard and Blake. Along with other notices of the Exhibition Blakes it was described in detail and quoted
from in my earlier essay, “Pictures at the Exhibitions.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15"
type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">2</hi> “William Blake in the Wilderness: A Closer Look at his Reputation,
1827-63,” in Morton D. Paley and Michael Phillips, eds., <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays in Honour of Sir
Geoffrey Keynes</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1973), pp. 310-49.</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">3</hi> “Pictures at the Exhibitions,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter 21</hi>,
1973, pp. 6-12.</note></p>
          <p>With the <hi rend="i">Blake Bibliography</hi> (produced jointly with Martin K. Nurmi) in 1964,
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> in 1969, the present book on the critical heritage, and the forthcoming
revised bibliography to be entitled <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, Professor Bentley has made a most solid and
impressive contribution to our knowledge of Blake’s fortunes during his life and after. When distant, these
separate books appear as One Book; and even if we look more closely, we may note a certain amount of
overlapping, or duplication. Roughly three-quarters of the materials of <hi rend="i">William Blake: The
Critical Heritage</hi> have already been published by Bentley in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>; in addition,
three-fifths of the Introduction to the present volume are, in its author’s words, “largely adapted from the
essay on ‘Blake’s Reputation and Interpreters’ in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (forthcoming)”; and
finally, all—or almost all—of the items in the present book will be cited in <hi rend="i">Blake
Books.</hi> To be sure, each of these source books is different and has its own special purpose, that of the
volume in hand being to provide an overview for the general student, of early reactions to Blake. But in the
light of the considerable duplications mentioned above, one wonders whether this interesting volume on the
critical heritage might not have been more indispensible, and at the same time more broadly and accurately
reflective of its subject, had its final section on the years 1831-63 been followed by selections from the
post-Gilchrist criticism, taking us, perhaps, to the end of the century? It is rather too bad that a book of
Blake criticism should end just when things are about to get really lively: it was, after all, in response to
the critical challenge posed by Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi> that informed public discussion of
Blake’s thought and work suddenly picked up speed and took off.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
