<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>10.3.kauvar</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="note">Los’s Messenger to Eden: Blake’s Wild Thyme</title>
        <author n="Kauvar">Elaine Kauvar</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1976-77</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1976-77</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">10.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
              <name>Michael Hays</name>
              <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Jane Welford</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Irene Tayler</name>
              <name>Elaine M. Kauver</name>
              <name>Philip B. Grant</name>
              <name>Purvis E. Boyette</name>
              <name>Suzanne Hoover</name>
              <name>Myra Glazer Schotz</name>
              <name>Gerda Norvig</name>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1976"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_10">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-10-3-0004">
        <pb id="p10-82" n="82"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">Los’s Messenger to Eden: Blake’s Wild Thyme</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Elaine</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Kauvar</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> the poet’s consciousness and the inward struggles it involves
command our attention. Book II of the poem focuses on the poet’s and Ololon’s decision to undergo the
purgation of their self-hoods, demonstrates that their actions result in the recovery of Innocence, and ends
with presages of the Apocalypse. Ololon’s descent to Beulah incorporates Blake’s fullest description of
Beulah, a description which exhibits the opulent natural growth of Organized Innocence. In the catalogue of
the individual flowers in Beulah, the Wild Thyme is prominent, and it remains prominent throughout the
remainder of the poem.</p>
          <p>The Wild Thyme is mentioned three times in Book II of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, and twice Blake
designates it as “first.” Its initial appearance is in the flower passage; the second time Blake writes about
it is in conjunction with the renovating moments of each day where it becomes “Los’s Messenger to Eden,” and
it reappears at the end of the poem after Blake falls in his own garden only to witness the imminent signs of
the Apocalypse. The occurrence of the flower three times in Book II compels us to recognize the importance
Blake attaches to it in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>; in fact, discovery of its symbolic meaning reveals why Blake
stresses its role in the poem. The significations of the Wild Thyme accrue with each new presence of it, first
as the foremost flower in Beulah, then as the messenger of Los, and finally as Blake’s vision of it helps us
to see that it signals the approaching Apocalypse—not attained but at least forecast in 
<hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> It becomes associated with Ololon when she descends to Beulah, with Los when it becomes
his Messenger to Eden, and with Blake when he sees it mounting with the Lark before the “Great Harvest &amp;
Vintage of the Nations.” Knowledge of the sources Blake might have drawn upon demonstrates why the Wild Thyme
is an apt emblem in a poem so concerned with the necessary negation of selfhood, and in Ololon’s case, with
the institutional virginity that stands in the way of her union with Milton.</p>
          <p>We should not be surprised that Blake attaches such a heavy freight of meaning to a flower in 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, for it is now widely acknowledged that he assigned great importance to his flowers.
Critics have explored the symbolism of his roses and his lilies;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n6" type="note">1</ref> and most recently, in an edition of Blake’s illuminated works, David V.
Erdman calls attention to the purposeful occurrence of flowers, vines, tendrils, and all manner of flora which
appear everywhere in the texts and the designs.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
type="note">2</ref> However, while commentators have recognized and discussed the presence of Blake’s Wild
Thyme, no one has yet attempted to discover its possible sources.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n8" type="note">3</ref> Blake’s use of his background to enrich the symbolism of the Wild Thyme not
only provides a means to understand the poet’s method elsewhere, it illuminates Book II of 
<hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> The various traits attributed to this flowering herb emphasize that its strategic
appearance three times in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> is symbolic in itself, and suggest that Blake may have
explored several sources in order to endow this plant with various significances in the poem. 
<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See, for example, John E. Grant, “Two Flowers in the Garden of Experience,” in 
<hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays for S. Foster Damon</hi>, ed. Alvin H. Rosenfeld (Providence, R.I.: Brown Univ.
Press, 1969), pp. 353-68.</note>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i"> The Illuminated Blake</hi>, annotated by David V. Erdman (New
York: Doubleday, 1974).</note>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">3</hi> See, for example, Harold Bloom <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse: A Study
in Poetic Argument</hi> (1963; rpt. N.Y.: Anchor, 1965), pp. 380-82, and Kathleen Raine, <hi rend="i">Blake
and Tradition</hi> (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1968), II, 159-61. Both Bloom and Raine agree, in the
main, with these observations; but neither attempts to discover the source of this flowering herb. Raine
suggests that Blake chooses the herb because of a pun involved in the name.</note></p>
          <p>Blake could have found information about the Wild Thyme in two places, so his awareness of it
seems undeniable. In his famous rejection of Swedenborg in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>,
Blake cites Paracelsus or Jacob Behmen as superior. And his familiarity with the writings of Erasmus Darwin
would have lead him to Robert John Thornton’s full plate illustrations of the plant species and to his
Herbal where he describes the properties and the lore of herbs. Paracelsus calls the Wild Thyme the “Mother of
Thyme” and lists it under “Those things which come forth from the earth and have a warm nature.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">4</ref> Thornton places it under the name 
<hi rend="i">Hypericum Perforatum</hi>, or Perforated St. John’s Wort, in his collection of plates, and it is
included as Mother of Thyme in his Herbal. The variety of names ascribed to this plant indicates that it was
well-known and that it was thought to possess more than one characteristic. 
<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">4</hi><hi rend="i"> Paracelsus</hi>, ed. A. E. Waite (London: James Elliott and Co., 1894), II,
181.</note></p>
          <p>Paracelsus calls the herb “Mother of Thyme” because he claimed it as a uterine herb—“Mother” in
the sense of the womb. But its other name, St. John’s Wort or <hi rend="i">Hypericum Perforatum</hi>, makes
it one of John the Baptist’s herbs. Associated with St. John, the plant assumes magical qualities, for the
herb was burned on St. John’s Eve as a strengthening and purifying plant. Blake’s designation of this herb
as “a mighty Demon” suggests that he may have known of the English legends and ballads that mention it. In
these the herb possesses the ability to rid a woman of her demon lover and to keep her house free of evil
spirits. Some have called it “Christ’s Ladder,” a name which reflects its manner of growing along the ground
and climbing towards heaven on mountains.</p>
          <pb id="p10-83" n="83"/>
          <p>Blake first mentions the Wild Thyme after Ololon’s descent to Beulah:
<q>
Thou percievest the Flowers put forth their precious Odours!<lb/>
And none can tell how from so small a center comes such sweets<lb/>
Forgetting that within that Center Eternity expands<lb/>
Its ever during doors, that Og &amp; Anak fiercely guard[.]<lb/>
First eer the morning breaks joy opens in the flowery bosoms<lb/>
Joy even to tears, which the Sun rising dries; first the Wild Thyme<lb/>
And Meadow-sweet downy &amp; soft waving among the reeds.<lb/>
Light springing on the air lead the sweet Dance<lb/>
(E 130, 11. 46-53)
</q>
The passage extols the beauty and the sensuousness of Beulah, and it names the Wild Thyme as the leader of
“the sweet Dance.” The passage also suggests the relationship between time and eternity as Blake makes the
connection between the opening flowers and eternity: the opening flowers’ response to the sun or the light
of heaven implies their link to eternity. The passage also places the Wild Thyme within an erotic context, for
“joy opens in the flowery bosoms.” The lines emphasize the fusion of flowers, sexuality, and joy. Northrop
Frye and Harold Bloom’s observation that the passage is a Song of Spring that resembles the Song of Solomon
intensifies the already explicit connection Blake makes between flowers and sensuality.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Northrop Frye, <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry: A Study of William
Blake</hi> (Princeton Univ. Press, 1948), p. 355, and Bloom, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse</hi>, p.
377.</note></p>
          <p>The passage is a striking description of the fecundity of Beulah—a place surrounding Eden and
offering repose from it. The soft and moony Beulah is maternal in nature.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">6</ref> That the Wild Thyme leads the other flowers lends vigor and
concrete power to its role in Beulah as well as in the poem. But the Wild Thyme’s other name, Mother of
Thyme, and the belief that it was a uterine herb serve to vitalize and reinforce its importance in Beulah, a
maternal and married land. More significantly, Blake’s later naming of it as Los’s Messenger marks its
appearance here as well as there with a sign that the efforts of creativity will be called into being. 
<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">6</hi> For this interpretation of Beulah, I am indebted to Bloom and Frye.</note></p>
          <p>Therefore, the connection made between Ololon and the Wild Thyme in Beulah is a crucial one, for
Ololon descends to Beulah, and it is there that she sees the Wild Thyme, and it is from there that she opens
up a “wide road” to eternity (E 134, 1.35). The virgin Ololon must cast off the Not Human—her holy
chastity—in order to complete the purgation of her selfhood that will enable her to unite with Milton. To
accomplish this, she must reject Natural Religion and the Female Will, thereby ridding herself of “dark secret
love” and embracing instead open human love. Later in the poem, she confesses to Milton in horror that her
selfish chastity and holiness have separated her from him. When she does this, Rahab Babylon is exposed and
Ololon descends to Felpham as “a Moony Ark” who heralds the appearance of the redemptive Christ. It is in the
context of Ololon’s selfish chastity that the Wild Thyme must be considered, for Blake proclaims that the
fourfold city of Golgonooza cannot be seen without passing the Polypus, “Or till you become Mortal &amp;
Vegetable in Sexuality” (E 134, 1.24). Like Oothoon, Ololon must rejoice in “lovely Copulation.” Because the
Wild Thyme is called Mother of Thyme, is known as a procreative uterine herb with “a warm nature,” and is
believed to be a purifying and strengthening herb, it is a singularly appropriate flower for Ololon to
encounter in Beulah. Its presence in Beulah, where Ololon first descends, proclaims its status as an emblem of
the human sexuality Ololon must learn to accept. Its association with strengthening and purifying rites
symbolizes what Ololon undertakes as she descends to the world of generation to cast off the Not Human. The
union of flowers, sexuality, and eternity is symbolized here by the Wild Thyme and is suggested as the means
of attaining paradise.</p>
          <p>This suggestion becomes an actuality when the Wild Thyme next appears in the passage associating
it with the renovating moments of each day and hailing it as Los’s Messenger. In these lines, Blake records
his central beliefs about the renewing moments of each day, those moments which neither Satan nor his Watch
Fiends can find; only the Industrious can discover these moments and can renovate every other moment of the
day. During this moment, Ololon descends to Los and Enitharmon. Immediately after the description of
Ololon’s descent, Blake invokes the Wild Thyme: “Just in this Moment when the morning odours ride abroad/And
first from the Wild Thyme” (E 135, 11.48-49). The lines locate the Wild Thyme as first in the moment of
renovation just as it is first on the list of flowers in Beulah, and its associations with purification,
strength, and procreation befit its function as an emblem of renewal. But it becomes specifically associated
here with the creative energies of the poet Los, in addition to the procreative energies of the virgin Ololon.
Blake now makes the Wild Thyme “Los’s Messenger to Eden” (E 135, 1.54). In that role it is
<q>
. . . a mighty Demon<lb/>
Terrible deadly &amp; poisonous his presence in Ulro dark<lb/>
Therefore he appears only a small Root creeping in grass<lb/>
Covering over the Rock of Odours his bright purple mantle<lb/>
Beside the Fount above the Larks nest in Golgonooza<lb/>
Luvah slept here in death &amp; here is Luvahs empty tomb<lb/>
Ololon sat beside this Fountain on the Rock of Odours.<lb/>
(E 135, 11.54-60)
</q></p>
          <p>Because the Wild Thyme is Los’s Messenger to Eden and because it is also the first of the
morning odors which arise in the renovating moments of each day, it joints the renovating moments to the
poet’s creation. In Ulro, however, the thyme, “only a small Root creeping in grass,” appears deadly and
poisonous. Blake implies that only those who dwell in Ulro, the land of limited
<pb id="p10-84" n="84"/>
vision, see the thyme as a poisonous, destructive demon; for Luvah’s empty tomb, filled with the fragrance
of the thyme, presages eternity in Christ’s ascension.</p>
          <p>The connection the Wild Thyme has with the empty tomb and Christ affirms it as an emblem of
eternity. That association along with those from the purifying and strengthening rites of St. John’s Eve
enhance its value as a symbol of poetic inspiration. By grouping the thyme, Beulah, and Ololon together and
then by using the plant in conjunction with Los, poetic inspiration, and eternity, Blake emphasizes the
inescapable fusion of healthy sexual desire, poetic inspiration, and the fourfold vision offered by Eden.</p>
          <p>The final occurrence of the Wild Thyme gathers these meanings together. After Ololon’s descent
as a Moony Ark to Felpham’s Vale and the sound of the four trumpets, Blake shifts the subject of the poem to
himself. He falls “outstretched upon the path” in his garden where his soul returns to its mortal state, “To
Resurrection &amp; Judgment in the Vegetable Body,” and where “Immediately the Lark mounted with a loud trill
from Felpham’s Vale / And the Wild Thyme from Wimbletons green &amp; impurpled Hills” appears (E 142, 11.27,
29-30). After that appear the human harvest, the open winepresses and barns; and then the Apocalypse is
imminent.</p>
          <p>As Los’s Messenger to Eden, the Wild Thyme heralds the Apocalypse. The reference to
Wimbleton’s “impurpled Hills” undoubtedly is another sign of its approach, for the Wild Thyme, a plant with
purple blossoms that grows close to the ground and on mountains, is called “Christ’s Ladder.” The name adds
naturalistic force to the plant’s symbolic meanings. The reference to it as impurpling Wimbleton’s hills,
together with the specific alliance with Christ’s ascension, and the designation as Los’s Messenger to
Eden make it a symbolic Christ’s ladder, which joins heaven and earth, or Beulah and Eden.</p>
          <p>Blake’s choice of Wild Thyme as a symbol in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> is surely not accidental,
for in the poem Milton struggles to purge everything within himself that is not fully human. Book II declares
that love which exists apart from the imagination—what Blake maintains is human existence itself—is a
state, and states change and cease, unlike individual identities. Blake must have selected the Wild Thyme for
its natural trait of growing along the ground in addition to its potential for symbolism; for as a creeping
vine, it is firmly rooted in the earth—the human—which it must also cover. Unlike Blake’s sunflower, it
does not merely aspire to heaven. Instead, it impurples the hills of Wimbleton, exhibiting its closeness to
earth as well as its ability to climb towards heaven. Blake’s use of it as Los’s Messenger to Eden
symbolizes Milton’s decision to cast away whatever is not human and to become entirely a man. At the end of
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, Blake consolidates all of the Wild Thyme’s associations when he identifies the
plant with sexuality and poetic inspiration, adding yet another dimension to them—eternity. This yields an
emblem which by relating human being, imagination, and eternity embodies the entire struggle in Book II of 
<hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> The Wild Thyme, an emblem of sex, creation, and eternity, underscores Blake’s
insistence that human sexuality must triumph over the hypocrisy of holy chastity for man to reside in
paradise.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
