<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>10.3.norvig</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Carolyn Keay, William Blake Selected Engravings</title>
        <author n="Norvig">Gerda Norvig</author>
        <author n="Schotz">Myra Glazer Schotz</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1976-77</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1976-77</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">10.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
              <name>Michael Hays</name>
              <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Jane Welford</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Irene Tayler</name>
              <name>Elaine M. Kauver</name>
              <name>Philip B. Grant</name>
              <name>Purvis E. Boyette</name>
              <name>Suzanne Hoover</name>
              <name>Myra Glazer Schotz</name>
              <name>Gerda Norvig</name>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1976"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_10">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-10-3-0005">
		<pb id="p10-90" n="90"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Carolyn Keay. <hi rend="b">William Blake Selected Engravings.</hi> London:
Academy Editions. New York: St. Martin’s Press, 1975. 84 pp., 4 colorplates. $16.95 hardbound, $9.95
paper.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Gerda <name>Norvig</name></docAuthor> and <docAuthor>Myra Glazer
<name>Schotz</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The blurb on the back cover of <hi rend="i">William Blake Selected Engravings</hi> suggests we
are in for a treat. In addition to a sampling “from almost all the artist’s major projects”—from most of
the poems and prophecies and from the illustrations for Stedman, Hayley, Blair, Thornton’s Virgil and the
Book of Job—this volume, we are told, contains “a small number of engravings by contemporary craftsmen after
original designs by Blake.”</p>
          <p>What a letdown when you open the book! Practically every selection from the illuminated canon has
been retouched, redrawn, or re-engraved in so crude and careless a manner one needn’t wonder at the
anonymity of the “craftsmen.” Furthermore, the renderings, as it turns out, are contemporary neither to Blake
nor to us, for the bulk of them to have been photographed from a stash of awkward, nineteenth-century
facsimiles now in the Victoria and Albert Museum. Robert Essick, our informant on sources, claims the most
shockingly altered designs are from an 1876 lithographic adaptation, the authorship of which has never been
acknowledged or determined. Occasionally a composition from that collection is a successful cartoon in its own
right, as is the case with some of the radical simplifications of plates from <hi rend="i">Urizen.</hi> But to
omit proper identification of both the medium and the source, which is Keay’s wont, and to pass such work
off as Blake’s, is at best a gross disservice to the newcomer seeking acquaintance with Blake’s authentic
vision. Only Schiavonetti’s 1808 engravings for <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> are duly captioned as “after
original designs by Blake”—an admission which might well have the adverse effect of convincing a beginner
everything else is unadulterated.</p>
          <p>Unconscionable editorial flaws of this kind are matched by others of a technical and scholarly
nature. An abridged group of the Job engravings, haphazardly arranged, appear in murky reproductions that
convey little of the special characteristics of line for which they are justly famous. And why, in a book
called “Selected Engravings,” do renditions of watercolor drawings so frequently show up? Blake’s Gray is
here, along with a color illustration—not an engraving—for Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi>
More puzzling still is the substitution of watercolor studies for three of Blake’s finest engravings in the
closing section of the book where a run of Dante drawings is featured. This total neglect of Blake’s last
and possibly greatest achievement in the very medium with which Keay is supposedly concerned, epitomizes the
problems of the entire collection.</p>
          <p>Even with four color plates, the book is outrageously priced at $16.95 in hardcover, $9.95
paper.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
