<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>10.3.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1976-77</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1976-77</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">10.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
              <name>Michael Hays</name>
              <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Jane Welford</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Irene Tayler</name>
              <name>Elaine M. Kauver</name>
              <name>Philip B. Grant</name>
              <name>Purvis E. Boyette</name>
              <name>Suzanne Hoover</name>
              <name>Myra Glazer Schotz</name>
              <name>Gerda Norvig</name>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1976"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_10">
    <front>
      <pb id="p10-65-66" n="65-66"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.010.03.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="334">
          <figTranscr>Blake<lb/>
            NEWSLETTER 39<lb/>
            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
            WINTER 1976-77, VOLUME 10, NUMBER 3</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-10-3-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="13" cols="2">
          <row>
          	<cell>
        	  <head>
          		<title>
            	  <hi rend="b">CONTENTS</hi>
          		</title>
        	  </head>
          	</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">News</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <ref type="article" issue="10.3.news">Newsletter Publications</ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="10.3.wanted">News Always Wanted</ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="10.3.request">Our Bibliographer’s Request</ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="10.3.seminar">Romantic &amp; Modern Literature: Seminar</ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="10.3.moderns">Blake and the Moderns</ref>,<gap type="emend"
rend="plain"/> 
              <supplied type="emend"><ref type="article" issue="10.3.mla">MLA Seminar:
Laocoön</ref>,</supplied> 
              <ref type="article" issue="10.3.palmer">Samuel Palmer in the Market</ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="10.3.forthcoming">Forthcoming Publications</ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="10.3.correction">A Correction</ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="10.3.art">Scripting a City of Art</ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="10.3.announcement">An Announcement</ref>
            </cell>
            <cell>68</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Notes</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="10.3.tayler">Blake’s Laocoön</ref> by Irene Tayler</cell>
            <cell>72</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="10.3.kauvar">Los’s Messenger to Eden: Blake’s Wild
Thyme</ref><lb/>
by Elaine Kauvar</cell>
            <cell>82</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="10.3.grant">A Possible Source for a Blake Sketch and
Drawing</ref> by Philip B. Grant</cell>
            <cell>85</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">Reviews</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><corr type="emend"><ref type="article" issue="10.3.boyette">Joseph Anthony Wittreich,
Jr.’s ANGEL OF<gap type="emend" rend="plain"/> APOCALYPSE: BLAKE’S IDEA OF MILTON</ref></corr> reviewed by
Purvis E. Boyette</cell>
            <cell>88</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="10.3.hoover">G. E. Bentley, Jr.’s WILLIAM BLAKE: THE CRITICAL
HERITAGE</ref> reviewed by Suzanne R. Hoover</cell>
            <cell>89</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="10.3.norvig">Carolyn Keay’s WILLIAM BLAKE SELECTED
ENGRAVINGS</ref> reviewed by Gerda Norvig and Myra Glazer Schotz</cell>
            <cell>90</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><corr type="emend"><ref type="article" issue="10.3.behrendt"><corr type="emend"
rend="plain">Eleanor</corr> Wilner’s GATHERING THE WINDS: VISIONARY IMAGINATION AND RADICAL TRANSFORMATION
OF SELF AND SOCIETY</ref></corr> reviewed by Stephen C. Behrendt</cell>
            <cell>91</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="10.3.fischer">Thomas Weiskel’s THE ROMANTIC SUBLIME: STUDIES IN
THE STRUCTURE AND PSYCHOLOGY OF TRANSCENDENCE</ref> reviewed by Michael Fischer</cell>
            <cell>93</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-10-3-0002">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">CONTRIBUTORS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p>Irene Tayler is an Associate Professor of Humanities at M.I.T. and author of a number of articles
and BLAKE’S ILLUSTRATIONS TO THE POEMS OF GREY (Princeton, 1971).</p>
        <p>Elaine M. Kauver teaches English at Baruch College of the City University of New York. Currently,
she is working with Jean H. Hagstrum and Jeffry B. Spencer on a dictionary of Blake’s visual symbols.</p>
        <p>Philip B. Grant is currently writing a dissertation, “William Blake’s THE EVERLASTING GOSPEL: An
Edition and Study,” at the University of Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>Purvis E. Boyette is the Head of English in the College of Arts and Sciences at Tulane University.
He is author of a monograph “Milton and the Sacred Fire: Sex Symbolism in PARADISE LOST” and is now coediting
THE MILTON ENCYCLOPEDIA (forthcoming in eight volumes).</p>
        <p>A frequent contributor to the NEWSLETTER, Suzanne Hoover has been unable to get a teaching job and
is therefore about to embark on a wholly new career of self-enjoyment and self-employment.</p>
        <p>Myra Glazer Schotz, Chairwoman of the English Department at Ben-Gurion University of the Negev,
Israel, has written on the FOUR ZOAS and, with Gerda Norvig, on the SONGS. Her latest paper, a study of the
figure of the hermaphrodite in Blake and Lawrence, was presented at the MLA seminar on Blake and the Moderns
in December.</p>
        <p>Gerda Norvig wrote her dissertation on Blake and Bunyan at Brandeis University. She is currently a
visiting lecturer at Ben-Gurion University of the Negev where she is collaborating with Myra Schotz on a
series of articles concerning variant colorings 
                    <pb id="p10-67" n="67"/>
of several copies of the SONGS. In addition, she and Professor Schotz are preparing a do-it-yourself Blake
coloringbook, for children of all ages, to be published in the fall.</p>
        <p>Stephen C. Behrendt is a visiting Assistant Professor of English at the University of Minnesota,
and is the author of several articles on Blake’s illustrations.</p>
        <p>Michael Fischer teaches courses at the University of New Mexico on literary theory and
Romanticism.</p>
        <p>Photographic credits: pg. 70, Aethelred and Alexandra Eldridge (Golgonooza); pp. 73,77,78, Sir
Geoffrey Keynes collection; pp. 79,85, (col. 2), British Museum; pg. 85 (col. 1), Fogg Art Museum; pp. 86,87,
Huntington Library. Cover and inside cover: Fertilization of Egypt and detail, Huntington Library.</p>
        <p>The Blake Newsletter, An Illustrated Quarterly, is published four times a year under the
sponsorship of the Department of English of the University of New Mexico.</p>
        <p>Editors: Morris Eaves, University of New Mexico, and Morton D. Paley, Boston University.</p>
        <p>Bibliographer: Thomas Minnick, Ohio State University.</p>
        <p>Associate Editor for Great Britain: Francis A. Carey, Assistant Curator, Department of Prints &amp;
Drawings, British Museum.</p>
        <p>Editorial Assistant: Michael Hays, University of New Mexico.</p>
        <p>Design Consultant: Virginia Masi Circulation Manager: Jane Welford, University of New Mexico.</p>
        <p>Manuscripts are welcome. Send two copies, typed and documented according to the forms suggested in
the MLA Style Sheet, 2nd ed., to either of the editors: Morris Eaves, Dept. of English, Univ. of New Mexico,
Albuquerque NM 87131; Morton D. Paley, Dept. of English, Boston Univ., Boston Mass. 02215.</p>
        <p>Subscriptions are $5 for one year, one volume, four issues. Special rate for individuals, $4 for
one year, surface mail. For subscribers overseas who want to receive their issues by air mail, $8. U.S.
currency or international money order if possible. Make checks payable to the Blake Newsletter. Address all
subscription orders and related communications to Jane Welford, Blake Newsletter, Univ. of New Mexico,
Albuquerque NM 87131.</p>
        <p>Some back issues are available. Address Jane Welford. Prices: whole numbers 1-8, bound together,
whole numbers 9-13, bound together, $5 each (special rate for individuals, $4). Whole numbers 22, 23, 24, 25,
26, 27, 28, 32, 33, 34, 36, 37, 38, $2 each. Whole number 20 (A Handlist of Works by William Blake in the
Department of Prints &amp; Drawings of the British Museum, ed. G. E. Bentley, Jr.) and whole number 35 (A
Checklist of the Blake Material in the Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Alverthorpe Gallery, ed. Ruth Lehrer),
$3 each. Whole numbers 14-19 are out of print. The International Standard Serial Number of the Blake
Newsletter is 0006-453X.</p>
        <p>Design and layout for this issue: Brad Hayden, University of New Mexico; for Irene Tayler’s essay
on Laocoön, Corinne Henning, UCLA.
	<note type="unreferenced" place="footer">Copyright © 1976 by Morris Eaves &amp; Morton D. Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
