<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>10.4.publications</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">Publications</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1977</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1977</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">10.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
              <name>Brad Hayden</name>
              <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Jane Welford</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Tom Dargan</name>
              <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
              <name>George Goyder</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson-Grant</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Edward Terry Jones</name>
              <name>Martin K. Nurmi</name>
              <name>Mary Ellen Reisner</name>
              <name>Myra Glazer Schotz</name>
              <name>Harry White</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1977"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_10">
    <body>
	<pb id="p10-136" n="136"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-10-4-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">NEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">PUBLICATIONS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Oxford has announced the publication of G. E. Bentley, Jr.’s two-volume text of 
<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings.</hi> Volume I: Engraved and Etched Writings. Volume II: Writings in
Conventional Typography and in Manuscript. Oxford English Texts. Volume I, 694 pages; II, 1370 pages. The set,
$83.60.</p>
          <p>The British Museum will publish a new printing of Blake’s illustrations to Thornton’s Virgil,
made directly from Blake’s original woodblocks, on 28 February 1977. The price is to be £300, plus (in the
U.K. only) 8% VAT. A prospectus is enclosed in this issue.</p>
          <figure n="Virgil.10.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="265"/>
          <p>Longman has announced a paper cover edition of <hi rend="i">The Poems of William Blake</hi>,
edited by W. H. Stevenson in its Annotated English Poets series. $8.75.</p>
          <p>David Erdman’s edition of <hi rend="i">The Notebook of William Blake</hi> will be published in
a paper bound version, smyth sewn and of the same size as the original published by Oxford, by Readex Books
this spring. The new edition will correct the errors listed in <hi rend="i">Newsletter 34</hi> and include
some further revisions. The retail price will be $16.50.</p>
          <p>The University of California, Santa Barbara, has announced the publication of the catalogue of
the
<pb id="p10-137" n="137"/>
Blake exhibition held last spring during the conference on Blake in the Art of His Time. The catalogue may be
ordered for $7.50 + .50 handling and postage (make checks payable to The Regents, University of California)
from the University Art Galleries, University of California, Santa Barbara 93106.</p>
          <figure n="Catalogue.10.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="235"/>
          <p>The Manchester City Art Gallery still has available its booklet on Blake’s Heads of the Poets
for 35p. Their Concise Catalogue, Volume 1, has illustrations of all the Heads, works by Linnell, etc.; price
£2.50 + 35p postage and packing (Volume 1 covers oil paintings by British artists born before 1850). (One
work not listed in the catalogue because it has been acquired since publication is Samuel Palmer’s “The
Bright Cloud.” A watercolor by Blake of “The Withering of King Jeroboam’s Arm” will be in an exhibition of
the Gallery’s watercolors at Agnews, London, next fall, and will probably be illustrated in the catalogue of
that exhibition.)</p>
          <figure n="Loehrich.10.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="249"/>
          <p>Rolf Loehrich, the author of <hi rend="i">Oneirics and Psychosomatics, The Secret of “Ulysses,”
Modus Operandi</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Systematic Oneirics</hi>, and whose work “was acknowledged as original
by Schlick, Carnap, Jung, Lichtenberger, and Monsieur de Monbrison,” has now finished a work of six volumes
entitled <hi rend="i">Exercitium Cogitandi.</hi> Volume 6, “The Personal Equation—Dancing with Death: A
Diagnostic Impertinence,” is a “satirical dramatization” that is “far from the joke under which it
masquerades.” It “expresses my hostilities directed against Kant, Luther, Blake, Jaspers . . . with due
tolerance of the existential limitations we all suffer jointly.” Blake is included in a section titled “Menage
a Trois / Blake at a seminar, with the menage present among others.” The price of the six volumes is £46;
volume 6 alone, £8.50. Make checks payable to Exercitia Publications, 12 Penzance Place, London W.11,
England. (Thanks to Robert Gleckner for this item.)</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
