<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>10.4.schotz</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">On the Frontispiece of The Four Zoas</title>
        <author n="Schotz">Myra Glazer Schotz</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1977</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1977</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">10.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
              <name>Brad Hayden</name>
              <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Jane Welford</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Tom Dargan</name>
              <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
              <name>George Goyder</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson-Grant</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Edward Terry Jones</name>
              <name>Martin K. Nurmi</name>
              <name>Mary Ellen Reisner</name>
              <name>Myra Glazer Schotz</name>
              <name>Harry White</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1977"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_10">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-10-4-0004">
        <pb id="p10-126" n="126"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">ON THE FRONTISPIECE OF <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi></hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline><docAuthor>MYRA GLAZER <name>SCHOTZ</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The frontispiece to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, a male figure sketched above the words “Rest
before Labour” on ms. page 2, is as problematic as the poem itself.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="p126u1" type="note">*</ref> While Geoffrey Keynes, W. H. Stevenson, and G. E. Bentley, Jr., all
describe the figure as recumbent, Bentley notes that it may alternatively be seen as soaring upward.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65" type="note">1</ref> Recently, John Grant, assuming that his
predecessors based their description on the manuscript held sideways, asserts that when it is held upright, as
the “inscription and the binding indicate” that it should be, “what one <hi rend="i">sees</hi> is that the man
is rising, no doubt to or in his ‘labour,’ after his ‘rest.’”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n66" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n65"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See Geoffrey Keynes, ed., <hi rend="i">Blake: Complete Writings with
variant readings</hi> (London: Oxford University Press, 1969), p. 897 (hereafter K); W. H. Stevenson, ed., 
<hi rend="i">The Poems of William Blake</hi> (London: Longman’s, 1971), p. 292; G. E. Bentley, Jr., 
<hi rend="i">William Blake: Vala or The Four Zoas : A Facsimile of the Manuscript, A Transcript of the Poem, and a
Study of its Growth and Significance</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1963), p.2.</note>
	<note id="n66"><hi rend="s">2</hi> “Visions in <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>,” in Stuart Curran and Joseph Anthony
Wittreich, Jr., eds., <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory: Essays on The Four Zoas, Milton &amp;
Jerusalem</hi> (Madison: University of Wisconsin, 1973), p. 146n.</note>
	<note id="p126u1"><hi rend="s">*</hi> I am grateful for a research grant from Ben Gurion University enabling
me to study the illustrations in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> manuscript.</note></p>
          <p>But even when the manuscript is held upright, the figure remains ambiguous. That ambiguity is
due, in part, to the unfinished state of the drawing and the absence of a background for reference, but it is
also due to complexities inherent in his posture. Those complexities, I believe, are worthy of critical
attention.</p>
          <figure n="BB209.1.2.MS" rend="file" width="782" height="1000">
            <head>1 From <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: the frontispiece.</head>
          </figure>
          <p>One point needs to be made at the outset. Whether Blake’s figure is reclining, or rising, or
both, he certainly is not <hi rend="i">resting.</hi> He veers in several directions at once and is engaged in
at least three simultaneous actions. His upper and lower torsos are contradictions of one another. As a
result, his stance as a whole suggests not rest, but inner conflict and physical tension.</p>
          <p>From the waist up, the figure bends sharply to the left in a manner reminiscent of Michael’s
posture in “Michael Binding Satan.” He pillows his head in his extended left arm and, unless Blake intended
him to be markedly exophthalmic, his eyes are closed. He thus appears to be sleeping. But if the upper torso
suggests sleep, the lower torso suggests movement. From knee to foot the right leg suggests a soaring movement
by veering leftward, literally echoing the upper torso yet, by its movement, contradicting it. It is also
contrasted to the left leg which, indeed, is like a Zoa seeking separation from his fellows and attempting to
exist independently of them. In an anatomically impossible position, the left leg is drastically
foreshortened, with toes splayed as if the foot is pushing against a counterforce in order to heave itself
upward.</p>
          <p>The tension inherent first in the contrast between the upper and lower torsos and, second, in the
effort needed to rise, is intensified by the
<pb id="p10-127" n="127"/>
presence of the chain. The chain dangles from his right hand, falling straight down in a manner reminiscent of
the chain in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> 21. It serves as a counterforce against his soaring. Lightly sketched
loops on the figure’s left, below his shoulder, make feasible the hypothesis that the chain continues from
his right hand to the back of his body and is grasped in his left hand, from which it falls downward again.
The effect of his posture as a whole is reminiscent of Bo Lindberg’s remark on plate 17 of the Job series: 
“ . . . you cannot twist a model to assume the position of Job’s friends,” Lindberg comments, “without killing
him.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n67"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Bo Lindberg, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Book of
Job</hi> (ACTA, Academiae Aboensis, series A: Humaniora, vol. 46, Abo: Abo Akademi, 1973), p. 119.</note></p>
          <p>A body tense with exertion, certainly not resting yet sleeping and rising at once; the
frontispiece to a work that locates itself on no objectively definable landscape and embodies the
metamorphoses, displacements, and incongruities of dreams:<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n68" type="note">4</ref> it is surprising that viewers of the drawing have not recognized the figure
as a dreamer and his ambiguous position as emblematic of the dream world. The drawing shows a dreamer rising
as he dreams or perhaps even dreaming that he rises. Neither resting nor laboring, he embodies the state of
“rest-before-labor,” the period of engagement with the psyche preluding the creation of a work of art. “What
is Above is Within,” writes Blake (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 71:6, K 709): in rising, the figure is engaging himself
with the images of the inner world which the poem will explore, including the “Torments of Love &amp;
Jealousy” suggested both by the chain and by the tensions inherent in his pose. On the final page of the
manuscript, a female figure faces inward in a position at once reversing and echoing his; his counter-image,
she is, appropriately, drawn under the words “End of the Dream.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n69" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n68"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See Mary Lynn Johnson and Brian Wilkie, “On Reading <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>,” Curran and Wittreich, p. 205.</note>
	<note id="n69"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Grant identifies this figure as Enitharmon; see “Visions in 
<hi rend="i">Vala</hi>,” pp. 200-02.</note></p>
          <figure n="BB209.1.139.MS" rend="file" width="857" height="1000">
            <head>2 From <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: ms. p. 70<hi rend="s">r</hi>.</head>
          </figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
