<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>10.4.johnsongrant</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="note">Mapping Blake’s London</title>
        <author n="Johnson-Grant">Mary Lynn Johnson-Grant</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1977</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1977</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">10.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
              <name>Brad Hayden</name>
              <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Jane Welford</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Tom Dargan</name>
              <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
              <name>George Goyder</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson-Grant</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Edward Terry Jones</name>
              <name>Martin K. Nurmi</name>
              <name>Mary Ellen Reisner</name>
              <name>Myra Glazer Schotz</name>
              <name>Harry White</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1977"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_10">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-10-4-0003">
        <pb id="p10-117" n="117"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">MAPPING BLAKE’S LONDON</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">MARY LYNN</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">JOHNSON-GRANT</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>When Karen McHaney and I began working on maps for the Norton Critical Edition of Blake in
February 1976, neither of us knew what we were getting into. Karen, a professional cartographer who happens to
be a close friend of mine, expected to do precision work; I had in mind a visionary map making use of the
northern and southern “gates” in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 28 [K 26] and the miniature skylines of York and
London in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 57, perhaps outlining Albion’s sleeping body against the cliffs of
Dover. I thought we could distort the scale along the lines of “A New Yorker’s View of the U.S.A.,” which
shows the Hudson River about where the Mississippi should be and the rest of the country a shrunken blur,
except for San Francisco, Los Angeles, and Miami Beach. The only example I had on hand to give Karen was a
non-scale tourist map of London which contains blow-ups of the main attractions. It turned out, however, that
Karen’s insistence on true scale forced me to a better understanding of the physical spaces in Blake’s
visionary universe which I believe will make certain geographical relationships clearer to others than can be
determined from previously existing maps.</p>
          <p>We worked first on the Holy Land and Britain, thinking it would be a cinch to put together the
maps in the backs of our Bibles with Stevenson’s map in the Longman-Norton Blake and to check both against
Blake’s biblical allusions. But Bible maps show political boundaries at particular points in history, and
the map in Stevenson’s edition (p. 575, drawn by K. C. Jordan) doesn’t make a typographical distinction
between tribal names and other territories such as Bashan and Moab; also the tribal territory of Simeon has
been omitted. We combined place-names from all historical periods to represent Blake’s overlaying a
Christian outlook upon this ancient land. When the authorities were uncertain or in conflict about the
location of a city, we placed it where it seemed best to fit Blake’s references. To keep the map
uncluttered, we left out all places important in the Bible but unimportant in Blake. We followed the same
practice for the map of Britain, adding to Damon’s <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> map of the cathedral cities
the locations of the 52 counties (a meaningless catalogue of names to American students) and the major rivers
and mountains mentioned by Blake, as well as Felpham and the landmarks in the southern “gate,” Lizard Point
and Land’s End. We settled for an arrow pointing to Caithness along the northern “gate”; if we had extended
the area to the north of Scotland we would have had no space for the names of the counties, after reduction to
fit the map on the Norton page. Our effort to draw something resembling both the coastline of Britain and the
Giant Form of Albion came to nothing; perhaps some one person knowledgeable in Blake and skilled in
cartography, calligraphy, and drawing could do better. We left Albion and Jerusalem to the viewer’s
imagination and suggested the visionary dimensions of Britain and Palestine by Stonehenge-like trilithon
markers for places associated with human sacrifice, including Golgotha and Tyburn.</p>
          <p>Making the London map was the hardest, yet most rewarding, of our jobs. Our chief innovation has
been to represent all places important to Blake, in both his life and his work, during all periods of his
career. Thus we could not base our map on any single historical map. Stevenson’s “Map of London ca. 1810”
requires an explanatory note: “The site of Regent St. is approximately that of Swallow St. on this map” (p.
621), and in any case it takes in so much territory that it had to be reduced beyond the point of legibility
to fit on the page. Nor could we depend upon the portion of Cary’s “Plan of London and Westminster” (1820)
reproduced in Damon’s <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi>—helpful though it was to us—because the Blake
locations don’t stand out among all the other features; also it doesn’t extend far enough east into The
City to show St. Paul’s and London Stone or far enough north to show Regent’s Park. Until the last stages
of our project, I somehow forgot about Bentley’s reproduction of portions of Horwood’s “Plan of the Cities
of London and Westminster” (1792-99), which points out all Blake’s residences; without Bentley’s guidance
I would have misplaced Fountain Court near the Temple, on the basis of an erroneous guidebook description.
Because of the combined effects of photographic blurring and reduction, the name of Fountain Court in
Bentley’s reproduction is illegible; this street is not shown at all in Damon’s clear reproduction of
Cary’s Plan (it should be about where the “46” is, west of Waterloo Bridge).</p>
          <p>Because we were not confined to a London map of any one year, we were able to represent
“eternally building eternally falling” London: John Nash’s renovations (1812-20) and Waterloo Bridge
(originally planned as Strand Bridge). Here I began to understand what the Golden Builders were doing. We had
already found Willan’s Farm and the Jew’s-Harp House on early maps of London before Blake’s time; in
<pb id="p10-118" n="118"/>
<figure n="BlakesBritain.10.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="521">
	<figTranscr>BLAKE’S BRITAIN<lb/>
	MAJOR CATHEDRAL CITIES<lb/>
	Minor Cathedral Cities<lb/>
	0 30 60<lb/>
	miles<lb/>
	<lb/>
	Caithness<lb/>
	EDINBURGH<lb/>
	Tweed R.<lb/>
	NORTHUMBERLAND<lb/>
	Carlisle<lb/>
	CUMBERLAND		Durham<lb/>
	Skiddaw Mt.			DURHAM<lb/>
	WESTMORLAND<lb/>
	Sodor		ISLE OF MAN		YORKSHIRE<lb/>
	YORK<lb/>
	LANCASHIRE<lb/>
	ANGLESEY<lb/>
	Mam-Tor<lb/>
	Asaph		FLINT		CHESHIRE		Lincoln<lb/>
	Bangor		Chester		DERBY			LINCOLN<lb/>
	Mt. Penmaenmawr<lb/>
	DENBIGH		NOTTINGHAM<lb/>
	CAERNARVON		Mt. Snowdon<lb/>
	MERIONETH<lb/>
	STAFFORD		NORFOLK<lb/>
	LICHFIELD		RUTLAND<lb/>
	SHROPSHIRE		LEICESTER		Norwich<lb/>
	MONTGOMERY		Peterborough<lb/>
	Mt. Plinlimmon<lb/>
	HUNTINGDON &amp; PETERBOROUGH		Ely<lb/>
	WARWICK		NORTHAMPTON<lb/>
	RADNOR		WORCESTER<lb/>
	CARDIGAN		Worcester		CAMBRIDGESHIRE &amp; ELY		SUFFOLK<lb/>
	HEREFORD<lb/>
	BRECONSHIRE		Hereford		Severn R.		BEDFORD<lb/>
	PEMBROKE		HERTFORD		ESSEX<lb/>
	St. David’s		CARMARTHEN<lb/>
	Gloucester		OXFORD		BUCKINGHAM		VERULAM<lb/>
	MONMOUTH		GLOUCESTER		Oxford<lb/>
	GLAMORGAN		Cotswold Hills		Thames R.<lb/>
	Llandaff		Bristol		Bath		Avebury		LONDON<lb/>
	Avon R.		BERKSHIRE		Rochester<lb/>
	SURREY		Medway R.		Canterbury<lb/>
	Stonehenge		Dover<lb/>
	SOMERSET		HAMPSHIRE		KENT<lb/>
	Salisbury		Winchester		SUSSEX<lb/>
	WILTSHIRE<lb/>
	Chichester<lb/>
	DEVON		DORSET		Felpham<lb/>
	Exeter		Kelsey<lb/>
	CORNWALL<lb/>
	Land’s End<lb/>
	Lizard Point<lb/>
	<lb/>
	© KAREN McHANEY &amp; MARY LYNN JOHNSON 1977<lb/>
	CARTOGRAPHY BY KAREN McHANEY</figTranscr>
</figure>
<pb id="p10-119" n="119"/>
<figure n="HolyLand.10.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="612">
	<figTranscr>	Gethsemane		Mount of Olives<lb/>
	Golgotha		Temple<lb/>
	Herod’s Palace<lb/>
	JERUSALEM<lb/>
	0 miles .5<lb/>
	<lb/>
	Sidon		Mt. Lebanon		Damascus<lb/>
	LEBANON		Mt. Hermon		ARAM (SYRIA)<lb/>
	Tyre<lb/>
	OG<lb/>
	Hazor<lb/>
	ASHER		BASHAN<lb/>
	NAPHTALI		Sea of Galilee<lb/>
	[Land of Cabul]<lb/>
	ZEBULON		Ashteroth<lb/>
	MEDITERRANEAN SEA<lb/>
	Mt. Carmel		Kishon Richer		Nazareth		Manasseh<lb/>
	ISSACHAR<lb/>
	MANASSEH		GAD<lb/>
	NORTHERN KINGDOM<lb/>
	Tirzah		Jordan River<lb/>
	Mt. Ebal		Mahanaim<lb/>
	Shechem		Succoth		Jabbok River		GILEAD<lb/>
	Kanah River		Mt. Gerizim<lb/>
	Adam		AMMON<lb/>
	Shiloh<lb/>
	EPHRAIM		Zaretan		Rabbath<lb/>
	DAN<lb/>
	SIHON<lb/>
	Jericho<lb/>
	BENJAMIN		Gilgal<lb/>
	CANAAN		Mt. Peor		Heshbon<lb/>
	Jerusalem		Mt. Pisgah<lb/>
	Bethlehem<lb/>
	PHILISTIA		Gath<lb/>
	JUDAH		REUBEN<lb/>
	SOUTHERN KINGDOM<lb/>
	Hebron		DEAD SEA		Arabian Mts.		Arnon River<lb/>
	Gaza<lb/>
	SIMEON<lb/>
	Beersheba<lb/>
	AMALEK<lb/>
	MOAB<lb/>
	EDOM<lb/>
	[IDUMEA]<lb/>
	SINAI		Deserts of MIDIAN and Mt. Horeb<lb/>
	<lb/>
	THE HOLY LAND<lb/>
	Tribal names . . . . . . . . JUDAH<lb/>
	0 15 30<lb/>
	miles<lb/>
	<lb/>
	© KAREN McHANEY &amp; MARY LYNN JOHNSON 1977<lb/>
	CARTOGRAPHY BY KAREN McHANEY</figTranscr>
</figure>
<pb id="p10-120-121" n="120-121"/>
<figure n="BlakesLondon.10.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="570">
	<figTranscr>BLAKE’S LONDON<lb/>
	1757-1827<lb/>
	0 ¼ ½<lb/>
	miles<lb/>
	<lb/>
	to HAMPSTEAD		to HIGHGATE<lb/>
	Primrose Hill		Pancras Work House<lb/>
	ST. JOHN’S WOOD		[REGENT’S PARK]		GREEN LANE		PANCRAS<lb/>
	New Small[p]ox Hospital<lb/>
	Willan’s Farm		Jew’s-Harp House<lb/>
	NEW ROAD FROM PADDINGTON TO ISLINGTON<lb/>
	PADDINGTON		MARYLEBONE<lb/>
	Work House		Green Men		FITZROY SQ.		Foundling Hospit[a]l<lb/>
	Thomas Butts’ House after 1808<lb/>
	EDGWARE ROAD		MARYLEBONE LANE		PORTLAND PL. [REGENT ST.]		TOTTENHAM CT. RD.<lb/>
	Tyburn		STRATFORD PL.		Butts’ House in Gt. Marlborough St.<lb/>
	TYBURN ROAD		OXFORD STREET		BROAD ST.<lb/>
	S. MOLTON ST.		POLAND		SOHO SQ.		Basire’s Hou[s]e<lb/>
	GROSVENOR SQUARE		NEW BOND ST.		Carnaby Mkt.		BROAD<lb/>
	School of Industry		GOLDEN SQ.		LEICESTER SQ.		ST. MARTIN’S LANE		DRURY LANE<lb/>
	HYDE PARK		Tyburn Brook		Pars’ Drawing School		Fountain Court<lb/>
	KENSINGTON GARDENS		PICCADILLY		PALL MALL		GOLGONOOZA<lb/>
	KENSINGTON RD.		KNIGHTSBRIDGE		GREEN PARK		THE MALL		WHITEHALL<lb/>
	to HOUNSLOW<lb/>
	Buckingham Palace		ST. JAMES PARK<lb/>
	BIRD CAGE WALK		GT. GEORGE ST.		WESTMINSTER BRIDGE<lb/>
	JAMES ST.		Westminster Abbey		Parliament<lb/>
	Dacres Alms House<lb/>
	Green Coat School		Lambet[h] Charity School<lb/>
	KINGS ROAD		ROCHESTER ROW		Grey Coat School		HORSEFERRY RD.		Lambeth Palace<lb/>
	Royal Military Asylum<lb/>
	RANELAGH GARDENS<lb/>
	Chelsea Hospital		VAUX[H]ALL GAR[D]ENS<lb/>
	CHELSEA		[VAUXHALL BRIDGE]<lb/>
	RIVER THAMES<lb/>
	BATTERSEA ROAD<lb/>
	CHELSEA BRIDGE<lb/>
	BATTERSEA<lb/>
	<lb/>
	UPPER STREET		LOWER STREET<lb/>
	ISLINGTON<lb/>
	CITY ROAD		HACKNEY ROAD<lb/>
	GRAY’S INN ROAD		OLD STREET RD.<lb/>
	RED LION ST.		[Sutton’s] Charterhouse School		Bunhill Fields<lb/>
	ALDERSGATE ST.		FINSBURY PL.		BISHOPSGATE ST.<lb/>
	HOLBORN		Christ’s Hospital [Blue Coat School]<lb/>
	[L]INCOLN’S INN FIELDS		Bethlehem Hospital [Bedlam]<lb/>
	Newgate Prison<lb/>
	[T]HE STRAND		FLEET ST.		CHEAPSIDE		WHITECHAPEL ST.		MILE-END and “OLD BOW”<lb/>
	St. Paul’s<lb/>
	Somerset Hs.	Royal Acad.		WATLING ST.<lb/>
	Joseph Johnson’s Bookshop		London Stone<lb/>
	WATERLOO BRIDGE		BLACKFRIARS BRIDGE<lb/>
	LONDON BRIDGE		The Tower<lb/>
	BLACK FRIARS ROAD		St. Thomas Hospital		TOOLY STREET		POPLAR<lb/>
	A[stl]ey’s Royal Amphitheatre		Guy’s Hospital<lb/>
	He[rc]ules Bldg.		BOROUGH ROAD		LONG LANE		[I]SLE OF DOGS<lb/>
	Asylum for Female Orphans		BLACKMAN STREET<lb/>
	LAMBETH ROAD<lb/>
	New Bethlehem Hospital<lb/>
	CAMBERWELL ROAD		OLD KENT ROAD<lb/>
	BLACKHEATH and SHOOTER’S HILL<lb/>
	CLAPHAM ROAD<lb/>
	CAMBERWELL		PECKHAM RYE<lb/>
	<lb/>
	© KAREN McHANEY &amp; MARY LYNN JOHNSON 1977<lb/>
	CARTOGRAPHY BY KAREN McHANEY</figTranscr>
</figure>
<pb id="p10-122" n="122"/>
aligning these with post-1820 maps showing the results of Nash’s project, I was finally able to grasp the
point that the farm and the tavern were actually within the royal preserve which Nash redesigned as Regent’s
Park—not further out in the country as I had imagined them. Even after going through piles of reference
books, however, we were never entirely sure of the exact course of Tyburn Brook. It rises at Shepherd’s Well
in Hampstead and since the sixteenth century has flowed in a conduit surfacing at Stratford Place and Oxford
Street; it formerly separated into three swampy branches emptying into the Thames near Westminster Abbey, but
it was diverted into ornamental streams in Green Park and St. James Park. It was originally the boundary
between Kensington and Westminster. Blake seems to place it <hi rend="i">within</hi> Kensington Gardens 
(<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 6:9); Hogarth pictures it just at Tyburn Gallows in <hi rend="i">The Idle</hi> ’<hi
rend="i">Prentice Executed at Tyburn</hi> (1747). According to Damon’s <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi>, “It
crossed Oxford Street a little to the east of the present Marble Arch [i.e., at Tyburn], and flowed through
St. James’ Park, then plunged underground at the intersection of Stratford Place and South Molton Street”;
this would mean that it flowed south and then back north, crossing Oxford Street twice. It was apparently so
scarcely a river and so nearly a sewer that maps of Blake’s time do not record it. Karen and I followed
Stevenson in representing only the surface section which wound from Stratford Place past Grosvenor Square and
entered Green Park at Halfmoon Street (the latter street not named on our map). I would like to know its full
course and what it looked like in Blake’s time.</p>
          <p>A few other features are noteworthy: Blake’s patron Thomas Butts, usually thought of as
residing in Fitzroy Square, did not move there until 1808; we have marked also his house in Great Marlborough
Street, to which Blake addressed his correspondence. By leaving out streets and landmarks inessential to
Blake’s London, we were able to show places associated with his training and career as an artist-engraver:
Pars’ Drawing School, James Basire’s house and engraving shop in Great Queen Street, the Royal Academy in
Somerset House, Joseph Johnson’s bookshop in St. Paul’s Churchyard; if I had thought of it we might have
put in Langford’s sale-rooms in Covent Garden. We included prominent orphanages, hospitals, and workhouses
which must have been important in Blake’s vision of London whether or not he names them. One of these is the
Charterhouse School, the institution for “aged men and youth” in Obtuse Angle’s song “To be or not to be”
from <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi>; this and other charity schools on our map can be imagined as
those from which children in red and blue (Christ’s Hospital) and green (Green Coat School) marched to St.
Paul’s, and perhaps Dacre’s Alms House is where little Tom Dacre lived before he was sold to the master
chimney sweeper. An idle query of no scholarly significance: as there is no North Molton Street, was South
Molton Street named after the Devonshire village of South Molton? Books on the origin of London street-names
don’t answer the question.</p>
          <p>Working on these maps has helped me visualize the building of Golgonooza amid the soot and clamor
of London. Place-names associated with Blake are easier to spot than they are on other readily available maps
of late eighteenth-century and early nineteenth-century London. I hope all three maps will be useful to
readers of the <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, as well as to the students who will read 
<hi rend="i">William Blake: Selected Poems and Designs</hi>, a Norton Critical Edition edited by John E. Grant and
Mary Lynn Johnson, scheduled for publication in the winter of 1978.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
