<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>10.4.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1977</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1977</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">10.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
              <name>Brad Hayden</name>
              <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Jane Welford</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Tom Dargan</name>
              <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
              <name>George Goyder</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson-Grant</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Edward Terry Jones</name>
              <name>Martin K. Nurmi</name>
              <name>Mary Ellen Reisner</name>
              <name>Myra Glazer Schotz</name>
              <name>Harry White</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1977"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_10">
    <front>
      <pb id="p10-97-98" n="97-98"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.010.04.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="319">
          <figTranscr>Blake<lb/>
            NEWSLETTER 40<lb/>
            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
            SPRING 1977, VOLUME 10, NUMBER 4</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-10-4-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="19" cols="2">
          <row>
          	<cell>
        	  <head>
          		<title>
            	  <hi rend="b">CONTENTS</hi>
          		</title>
        	  </head>
          	</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">NOTES</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="10.4.heppner">Notes on some items in the Blake Collection at
McGill, with a few speculations around William Roscoe</ref> by Christopher Heppner</cell>
            <cell>100</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="10.4.white">Blake and the Mills of Induction</ref> by Harry
White</cell>
            <cell>109</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="10.4.bentley">The Vicissitudes of Vision, The First Account of
William Blake in Russian (1834)</ref> by G.E. Bentley, Jr.</cell>
            <cell>112</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="10.4.jones">Another Look at the Structure of <hi rend="i">The
Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi></ref> by Edward Terry Jones</cell>
            <cell>115</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="10.4.johnsongrant">Mapping Blake’s London</ref> by Mary Lynn
Johnson-Grant</cell>
            <cell>117</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="10.4.butlin">The Rediscovery of an Artist: James Jefferys,
1751-1784</ref> by Martin Butlin</cell>
            <cell>123</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="10.4.deck">Unnoticed Printings of Blake’s Poems,
1825-1851</ref> by Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</cell>
            <cell>125</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="10.4.goyder">An Unpublished Poem about Blake by William Bell
Scott</ref> by George Goyder</cell>
            <cell>125</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="10.4.schotz">On the Frontispiece of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi></ref> by Myra Glazer Schotz</cell>
            <cell>126</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">REVIEW</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="10.4.nurmi">Blake Music at the Santa Barbara Conference and
Everett Frost’s production of <hi rend="i">Island in the Moon</hi></ref> reviewed by Martin K. Nurmi</cell>
            <cell>128</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">DISCUSSION</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="10.4.reisner">Folcroft Facsimile of the 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi></ref> by Mary Ellen Reisner</cell>
            <cell>130</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="10.4.dargan">Blake and Hayley in Wittreich’s <hi rend="i">Angel
of Apocalypse</hi></ref> by Tom Dargan</cell>
            <cell>130</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">NEWS</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <ref type="article" issue="10.4.mla">MLA Seminar 1977</ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="10.4.adelphi">Blake Exhibition and Festival at Adelphi</ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="10.4.prints">Books and Prints for Sale</ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="10.4.aloud">This Man Reads Blake Aloud</ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="10.4.publications">Publications</ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="10.4.turner">Turner Society Journal</ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="10.4.thel"><hi rend="i">Thel</hi> Copy A</ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="10.4.glasgow">Blake Greetings from Glasgow</ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="10.4.faerie">Blake’s Faerie Queene Painting</ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="10.4.news">News Last Instead of First</ref>, 
              <supplied type="emend"><ref type="article" issue="10.4.vision">A Vision for
1977</ref>.</supplied>
            </cell>
            <cell>136</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">Copyright © 1977 by Morris Eaves &amp; Morton D.
Paley</note>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p10-99" n="99"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-10-4-0002">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">CONTRIBUTORS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr. (University of Toronto) is editor of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> (1964),
<hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> (1967), and <hi rend="i">Writings</hi> (2 vols., Clarendon Press, ?1977); author of
<hi rend="i">A Blake Bibliography</hi> (with M. K. Nurmi, 1964), <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (1969), 
<hi rend="i">William Blake: The Critical Heritage</hi> (1975), and <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (a revised
edition of <hi rend="i">A Blake Bibliography</hi>, Clarendon Press, ?1977).</p>
        <p>Martin Butlin is Keeper of the British Collection at the Tate Gallery, London, and a specialist in
the work of Blake and Turner. He has recently completed a detailed catalogue of Blake’s paintings, drawings,
and color prints for the William Blake Trust.</p>
        <p>Tom Dargan is a graduate student and a job hunter from the English Department at Stony Brook. His
dissertation (for a June 1975 Ph.D.) shows how Stonehenge is the foundation for Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></p>
        <p>Raymond H. Deck, Jr. is finishing at Brandeis University a dissertation on Blake and Swedenborg and
will spend next year making a book on that topic. He has developed lists of Blake’s Swedenborgian
associates, including the one hundred other enthusiasts attending the First General Conference in 1789, and
would like to correspond (in the epistolary, not Swedenborgian, sense) with researchers who may have
discovered other connections between Blake and these individuals.</p>
        <p>George Goyder is the co-founder with Sir Geoffrey Keynes of the William Blake Trust, and is well
known as a Blake lover and collector.</p>
        <p>Mary Lynn Johnson-Grant of Georgia State University has published articles and reviews on Blake,
Wordsworth, Coleridge, and Keats. With her husband, John Grant, she is editing a Norton Critical Edition of
Blake, to be published in 1977.</p>
        <p>Christopher Heppner is an Assistant Professor of English at McGill, and has an essay on 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> forthcoming in the <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly.</hi></p>
        <p>Edward Terry Jones, a Teaching Fellow at the University of Pennsylvania, is knee-deep in a
dissertation on prose fiction of the Romantic Period.</p>
        <p>Martin K. Nurmi, Professor of English at Kent State University, is the author of numerous articles
and books about Blake, most recently the volume on Blake in the Hutchinson University Library series. He wrote
the brief essay on musical settings for Blake’s poetry in <hi rend="i">A Blake Bibliography.</hi></p>
        <p>Mary Ellen Reisner teaches in the literature department at the Université Laval, Québec.</p>
        <p>Myra Glazer Schotz lectures at Ben Gurion University, Israel. Her most recent articles include
“Blake’s Book of Changes: On Viewing Three Copies of the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi>” (with Gerda Norvig), and studies of sexuality in Blake and D.H. Lawrence. She is currently
editing an anthology of contemporary Israeli poetry by women (in English translation).</p>
        <p>Harry White is an Associate Professor of English at Northeastern Illinois University whose work on
Shelley remains unpublished and therefore, with the exception of his students, unrecognized.</p>
        <p>Photographic credits: pp. 100-108 by permission of McLennan Library of McGill University; pp.
118-121 by permission of Karen McHaney and Mary Lynn Johnson; pp. 123 &amp; 124, cover &amp; inside cover by
permission of Maidstone Museum and Art Gallery; pp. 126 &amp; 128 by permission of the Trustees of the British
Library; p. 130 by permission of the Harvard Library.</p>
        <p>The Blake Newsletter, An Illustrated Quarterly, is published four times a year under the
sponsorship of the Department of English of the University of New Mexico.</p>
        <p>Editors: Morris Eaves, University of New Mexico, and Morton D. Paley, Boston University.</p>
        <p>Bibliographer: Thomas Minnick, Ohio State University.</p>
        <p>Associate Editor for Great <corr type="emend">Britain:</corr> Frances A. Carey, Assistant Curator,
Department of Prints &amp; Drawings, British Museum.</p>
        <p>Editorial Assistant: Brad Hayden, University of New Mexico.</p>
        <p>Design Consultant: Virginia Masi</p>
        <p>Circulation Manager: Jane Welford, University of New Mexico.</p>
        <p>Manuscripts are welcome. Send two copies, typed and documented according to the forms suggested in
the MLA Style Sheet, 2nd ed., to either of the editors: Morris Eaves, Dept. of English, Univ. of New Mexico,
Albuquerque, NM 87131; Morton D. Paley, Dept. of English, Boston Univ., Boston Mass. 02215.</p>
        <p>Subscriptions are $5 for one year, one volume, four issues. Special rate for individuals, $4 for
one year, surface mail. For subscribers overseas who want to receive their issues by air mail, $8. U.S.
currency or international money order if possible. Make checks payable to the Blake Newsletter. Address all
subscription orders and related communications to Jane Welford, Blake Newsletter, Univ. of New Mexico,
Albuquerque NM 87131.</p>
        <p>Some back issues are available. Address Jane Welford. Prices: whole numbers 1-8, bound together,
whole numbers 9-13, bound together, $5 each (special rate for individuals, $4). Whole numbers 22, 23, 24, 25,
26, 27, 28, 32, 33, 34, 36, 37, 38, 39, $2 each. Whole number 20 (A Handlist of Works by William Blake in the
Department of Prints &amp; Drawings of the British Museum, ed. G. E. Bentley, Jr.) and whole number 35 (A
Checklist of the Blake Material in the Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Alverthorpe Gallery, ed. Ruth Lehrer),
$3 each. Whole numbers 14-19 are out of print. The International Standard Serial Number of the Blake
Newsletter is 0006-453X.</p>
        <p>Design and layout for this issue: Brad Hayden and Michael Hays, University of New Mexico.</p>
      </div1>
    </front>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
