<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>10.4.nurmi</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Blake Music at the Santa Barbara Conference and Everett Frost, production of
Island in the Moon</title>
        <author n="Nurmi">Martin K. Nurmi</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1977</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1977</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">10.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
              <name>Brad Hayden</name>
              <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Jane Welford</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Tom Dargan</name>
              <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
              <name>George Goyder</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson-Grant</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Edward Terry Jones</name>
              <name>Martin K. Nurmi</name>
              <name>Mary Ellen Reisner</name>
              <name>Myra Glazer Schotz</name>
              <name>Harry White</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1977"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_10">
    <body>
      <pb id="p10-128" n="128"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-10-4-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEW</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main"><hi rend="i">Songs of William Blake and Music of Blake’s Time.</hi> A concert
at the University of California, Santa Barbara, 3 March 1976, for the conference on Blake in the Art of His
Time.; William Blake. <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon.</hi> Audio tape of a production for KPFK Pacifica,
Pasadena, CA. Produced by Everett C. Frost. Music by Edward Cansino. 2 reels, 7 ½″ ips; also cassettes. Los
Angeles, CA.: Pacifica (Los Angeles 90038).</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Martin K. <name>Nurmi</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>According to Burton R. Pollin’s bibliography, <hi rend="i">Music for Shelley’s Poetry</hi>
(1974), over 800 composers have set Shelley. The number may not be quite that high for Blake, because Shelley
was better known earlier. But Blake has been extremely attractive to composers to set, partly because of the
surface simplicity of his lyrics but also partly because of his strong musical rhythms, which must result from
his evidently having composed melodies for many of his songs himself. (Shelley, who loved music very much, was
apparently almost tone-deaf but had a marvelous ear for poetic-musical rhythms.) Words alone, however
musically rhythmic, do not imply specific pitch intervals of melodies, but some of Blake’s lyrics come about
as close to doing that as seems possible, because their rhythms are so insistently musical, their grammatical
sense often suggests musical phrases, and pitch patterns of words sometimes even suggest the direction of
voice leading.</p>
          <p>The concert, “Songs of William Blake and Music of Blake’s Time,” given in connection with the
Blake conference in Santa Barbara in March of 1976, gives a sample of some recent settings, mostly choral,
with also <hi rend="i">Ten Blake Songs for Voice and Oboe</hi> by Ralph Vaughan Williams, a selection of two
pieces by the glee composer, Samuel Webbe, and two songs from the theatre by Charles Dibdin and Thomas Linley.
Ending the concert was a performance of Hubert Parry’s familiar setting of the preface to 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, titled “Jerusalem.” The program of the concert gives no information on the works or
performance besides their names and dates for the songs by Dibdin and Linley. Vocal groups are The Dorians and
The Schubertians from the University of California—Santa Barbara and the University of
California—Riverside Choral Society. There are various soloists.</p>
          <p>Daniel Pinkham’s choral settings of “The Sick Rose,” “The Blossom,” and “Spring” follow closely
the rhythms of Blake’s text but heighten them in musical declamation. The very short lines of “Spring” are
properly grouped into musical phrases at a tempo faster than that of speech in a way that should suggest how
the poem should be read, as well as sung. Blake probably sang it.</p>
          <p>“The Lamb” in Arthur Farwell’s set of four songs almost completely follows the rhythms of the
words, even a bit literally—which is almost inevitable because the words clearly indicate musical rhythms.
“Cradle Song” is suitably gentle until an unaccountable dynamic climax near the end that would surely wake up
anyone it was being sung to. “The Tyger,” with its terrible intensity and incantatory trochees is probably
impossible to set in a vocal line that effectively and adequately combines with the words in what Thomas Moore
called the “compound creation” of a song. Farwell does about the only thing a composer can do: he puts the
energy of the tiger into the piano part and lets the singer give the text without any real attempt to evoke
the fearful symmetry vocally. The result is quite effective, as a keyboard composition with intoned vocal
part. Benjamin Britten’s treatment of “The Tyger” in his fine song cycle, <hi rend="i">The Poems and
Proverbs of William Blake</hi> (1964) does something similar, but his setting, written for Dietrich
Fischer-Dieskau and recorded by him with the composer at the piano (London OS 26099), relies more on the vocal
part, in which Blake’s rhythms are altered by being strongly dotted, sometimes syncopated and even jazzy,
while the piano, mostly in a pulsating accented bass, evokes a tiger of controlled but incredible energy. In
this group of songs by Farwell, Jill Feldman’s clear, steady soprano negotiates the tritones and other
demanding intervals cleanly and musically, and Stephen Kelly’s piano accompaniments are solid, impressive in
“The Tyger.”</p>
          <p>Vaughan Williams’ approach to Blake’s lyrics is a very different one in <hi rend="i">Ten
Blake Songs for Voice and Oboe</hi>, written in 1957 for the film, “The Vision of William Blake.” As the title
suggests, the only “accompaniment” is a solo oboe (three songs are for voice alone). “The Tyger” is not
included in this set, probably because the voice needs more help than an oboe can provide. Nevertheless,
though one would expect a voice-oboe setting to concentrate on pastoral songs, this set is not restricted to
them but includes some very difficult ones, like “London,” “A Poison Tree,” and “Cruelty has a Human Heart.”
Blake, who equated melody in music with line in art, and harmony with coloristic effects, would have been
delighted with these settings. They show what melody alone can do in realizing the musical implications of the
words. And the oboe playing its own melodies with the tenor voice—it is not an accompaniment in the usual
sense of the term—interweaves with the voice, now commenting on thematic material from the vocal line, now
introducing motifs to be expressed by the voice, now realizing contrapuntal and harmonic implications of the
vocal intervals. A version with everything worked out in conventional harmonic accompaniments would be as
disappointing as the various harmonic realizations of the Chaconne from Bach’s Partita No. 2 for
unaccompanied violin.</p>
          <p>The performance of <hi rend="i">Ten Songs</hi> by Ian Partridge, tenor, and Janet Craxton, oboe,
as recorded by EMI (HQS 1236) is a hard act to follow. Peter Roberts, a robust but lyrical tenor, gives a very
good performance, but John Beckner’s oboe part leaves much to be desired in rhythmic suppleness,
articulation, and phrasing. He plays the notes.</p>
          <p>The song character of Blake’s lyrics rather gets lost in Roger Nixon’s setting of “Love’s
Secret” and in John Crawford’s “Nurse’s Song” and “The Little Black Boy,” which strike me as being more
choral compositions that use words as a starting point than as musical settings of the text in which text and
music work together; for they all but overwhelm the
		  <pb id="p10-129" n="129"/>
		  poems, especially Crawford’s “The Little Black Boy,” where the irony of the tenderness of the Black Boy
toward the English Boy is completely lost in the striving for impressive choral effects with piano
accompaniment—which even at one point introduces some irrelevantly gauche jazzy figures. Crawford’s
setting of “Spring,” however, is thoroughly delightful, merrily rhythmic and straightforward.</p>
          <p>The glees and songs of Webbe, Dibdin, and Linley are pleasant and well performed by the
Schubertians, Carl Zytowski, tenor and “Concertmaster” for the occasion, and Michael Ingham, baritone and
director of the Dorians (who is a little shy of some of his high notes). The anthem, “Jerusalem,” by
Parry—who should also be known for his 1880 setting of <hi rend="i">Prometheus Unbound</hi>—may have been
embraced by religious orthodoxy and even used as a hymn without full awareness of its doctrine, but it is a
strong piece anyway, either as a solo song (Paul Robeson used to sing it) or as a choral composition. (It is
available through G. Schirmer in New York.) This piece, with organ and combined choral forces, ended the
concert.</p>
          <p>Most of the new music in this concert consisted of choral settings of Blake’s songs. Blake’s
song texts do make good texts for choral pieces, but it seems to me that they work better for the solo voice.
Blake wrote words for choruses galore, especially in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, and it would be
interesting to have some of these turned into the musical form he had in mind.</p>
          <p>Frost’s dramatized production of <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi>, with music, for radio
was originally played at the Santa Barbara Blake <corr type="emend">Conference</corr> and is now available for
<corr type="emend">rental.</corr> It is well worth having.</p>
          <p>The production does everything it can to translate Blake’s text into a dramatic-musical form
with complete fidelity. With the exception of a very few added words to help the procedings make sense, and an
occasional modification of a word here and there in the song-text of a kind which does not violate the sense
or spirit of the original, the words spoken by the singer-actors and sung by them are all Blake’s and
include the whole of the <hi rend="i">Island.</hi> One can follow the production completely with the text and
not have to skip around through cuts or rearrangements. It would be an excellent—and thoroughly
enjoyable—teaching aid. Technically, it is professionally produced, with stereophonic spatial separation of
the speakers effectively employed.</p>
          <p>Since almost all of the speakers are also singers and represent different ranges of the voice,
differentiation of the large cast of characters comes through quite clearly, and the narrator helps the
listener out in identifying them whenever things get confusing. If the production were played for an audience
thoroughly familiar with the text—or had the advantage of visual identification of the characters—the pace
of some of it might be picked up a bit to communicate more of the rollicking spirit of this (mostly) genial
satire. But the boisterous parts come across well, and it keeps moving, especially with the delightful
music.</p>
          <p>Edward Cansino’s score for the production is also directed toward evoking the original but
without attempting a literal archeological recreation of the music Blake would have heard in his ears as he
wrote. The instrumental introduction first suggests space-travel by means of electronic instruments, or
electrically modified ordinary instruments, and lands us in a musical scene on an 18th century moon (which
resembles England) where we hear a harpsichord and a few strings, which will be the basic instrumentation for
most of the music, aided on occasion by flute, piano, and once by tympani. Cansino’s selection of a
Handelian model for many of the songs is right, it seems to me, with his adaptation of the Baroque arias for
harpsichord and voice, using recitatives and floridly embellished arioso passages, sometimes in the parody of
which the English were so fond. Blake might well have known Samuel Foote’s parody of an air by Gemmiani, to
which he wrote words on “The Tragical History of Billy Pringle’s Pig.” We hear echoes in the music also of
Haydn, the English ballad, and of Purcell—especially in Miss Gittipin’s “Leave O leave [me] to my
sorrows,” which rather suggests in its repeated bass the <hi rend="i">basso ostinato</hi> of Dido’s “When I
am laid in earth.” The music is always delightful and, when appropriate, moving. Cansino properly resists the
inevitable temptation to milk the two songs of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> by writing really lyrical melodies
for them, which I think would have violated the spirit of the piece. His settings are sensitive and moving but
of a kind in which the words of the poems retain prominence. Blake might have sung tunes like these. An
effective device musically in some of the songs is that of suddenly moving from floridly embellished singing
to <hi rend="i">Sprechstimme</hi>, to bring us back from musical satire to a more verbal one.</p>
          <p>Transitions between chapters are marked by music, usually atonal; and what must have happened in
the missing leaf of the MS is suggested by an extended musical interlude with crowd sounds.</p>
          <p>I couldn’t help but be a little curious as to why none of Handel’s 
<hi rend="i">Watermusic</hi> was used at the point where Steelyard says, “lets have handels waterpiece.” Instead,
Cancino writes a recitative that is mostly chanted and then works in an imitation of the Hallelujah chorus
from <hi rend="i">Messiah</hi>, though I must admit that the rhythms of the last three lines work with the
dotted rhythms of parts of the chorus.</p>
          <p>The musical performance is very good on everyone’s part, and so is the acting.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
