<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>10.4.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="note">The Vicissitudes of Vision, The First Account of William Blake in Russian
(1834)</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1977</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1977</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">10.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
              <name>Brad Hayden</name>
              <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Jane Welford</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Tom Dargan</name>
              <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
              <name>George Goyder</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson-Grant</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Edward Terry Jones</name>
              <name>Martin K. Nurmi</name>
              <name>Mary Ellen Reisner</name>
              <name>Myra Glazer Schotz</name>
              <name>Harry White</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1977"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_10">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-10-4-0003">
        <pb id="p10-112" n="112"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">THE VICISSITUDES OF VISION<lb/>
			  THE FIRST ACCOUNT OF WILLIAM BLAKE IN RUSSIAN</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">G. E. </hi><name><hi rend="b">BENTLEY</hi></name>, 
<hi rend="b">JR.</hi></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>William Blake is essentially an English phenomenon, strange and bewildering to his
contemporaries, barely of interest beyond the English-speaking world until more than a century after his birth
in 1757. Even today, no contemporary copy of Blake’s writings is known to be outside the Anglophone world of
Britain, the United States, New Zealand, Australia, and Canada, and, though there are hundreds of articles and
books on Blake in other languages, chiefly Japanese, they are mostly derivative and introductory. The poet
called himself “English Blake,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">1</ref> and
so he is. <note id="n44"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi rend="i"> Notebook</hi> p. 5.</note></p>
          <p>Interest in and information about Blake spread beyond the English Channel only very slowly. Aside
from incidental references in bibliographies and directories,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n45" type="note">2</ref> the first account of Blake in German was in 1811, the first in the United
States in 1830, the first in French in 1833, and even these were essentially English. Anon., “William Blake,
Künstler, Dichter, und religiöser Schwärmer” in <hi rend="i">Vaterländisches Museum</hi>, 1 (January
1811), 107-31, was written by an Englishman, Henry Crabb Robinson,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n46" type="note">3</ref> and Anon., “Hôpital des fous à Londres” in <hi rend="i">Revue
Britannique</hi>, 3<hi rend="s">e</hi> Série, 4 (July 1833), 179-87, is manifestly based on, and confused
from, Anon., “Bits of Biography. No. I. Blake, the Vision Seer, and Martin the York Minster Incendiary,” 
<hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi>, 15 (March 1833), 244-49.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47"
type="note">4</ref> The early accounts of Blake in the United States are all simply extracts from or reprints
of Allan Cunningham’s life of Blake (1830).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48"
type="note">5</ref> And there are apparently no accounts of Blake at all, not even incidental references to
him, in Italy, Spain, or Holland or in other Romance or Germanic languages until well after 1863, when 
<corr type="emend">Alexander</corr> Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake, “Pictor 
<corr type="emend">Ignotus”</corr></hi> made him sensationally well known. <note id="n45"><hi rend="s">2</hi> e.g.,
F. A. Ebert, <hi rend="i">Allegemeines Bibliographisches Lexikon</hi>, Vol. I (1821), Vol. II (1830), and P.
F. &amp; A. L. Basan, <hi rend="i">Dictionnaire des Graveurs Anciens et Modernes</hi> (1809), I, 70—see 
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (1969), 270, 375-76, 623.</note>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">3</hi> See <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (1969), 432-55. Robinson’s essay was
translated into German by Dr. N. K. Julius. The account of Blake in <hi rend="i">Zeitgenossen</hi>, 3 (1830),
170-78, is a translation from Cunningham’s biography of Blake—see <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, 377, n.
2.</note>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">4</hi> The <hi rend="i">Revue Britannique</hi> piece was also the basis for the
account of Blake in Brierre de Boismont, <hi rend="i">Des Hallucinations</hi> (1845 ff).</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Anon., “Visions of Blake the Artist,” <hi rend="i">The Casket</hi>, 5
([Philadelphia] May 1830), 231-32 (reprinting Cunningham Paragraphs 36-39, 41), partly reprinted in 
<hi rend="i">The New-England Weekly Review</hi> [Hartford], 3 May 1830, p. 1; Anon., “Model of a Painter’s
Wife,” <hi rend="i">Literary Port Folio</hi>, 1 ([Philadelphia] 13 May 1830), 150 (reprinting the London 
<hi rend="i">Athenaeum</hi> review of Cunningham, 6 February 1830, pp. 66-68); <hi rend="i">American Monthly
Magazine</hi>, 3 (June 1831), 164-71 (a review of Cunningham consisting largely of extracts)—see 
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, 377-78, 398, 400, 410. The first edition of Cunningham (but not the second, 1830)
was reprinted in the U. S. in 1831, 1837, 1842, 1844, and 1846.</note></p>
          <p>In these circumstances, it is astonishing to find an article on Blake in Russian as early as
1834, an article, moreover, which does not appear in any Blake bibliography and which is quite unknown to
Blake scholars. What it says and how it got there are mysteries well worth pursuing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n85" type="note">*</ref>
	<note id="n85">* The translation of the Russian account itself will appear in the journal of The University
of Poona [India].</note></p>
          <p>When I was in Leningrad in 1973, I visited the great Saltykov-Shchedrin Library where Lenin had
worked, to discover what they have on Blake, and found in due time that their surprisingly extensive Blake
holdings included an article on the poet in <hi rend="i">Teleskop</hi> for 1834.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">6</ref> When I first saw the <hi rend="i">Teleskop</hi> entry in the
Saltykov-Shchedrin Blake list, I assumed that it must be misdated; indeed, I was 
                        <pb id="p10-113" n="113"/>
moderately confident that this must be the case until many months later, when I saw a microfilm copy of the
journal itself. Then, persuaded of the importance of the article, I of course had to secure a translation, for
I have no Russian at all. I was fortunate in securing the assistance of Mrs. Christine Moisan, a graduate
student in Russian at The University of Toronto, who made a careful translation of the article and gave me
information about <hi rend="i">Teleskop</hi> itself. <note id="n49"><hi rend="s">6</hi> See “Blake Among the
Slavs: A Checklist,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> (1977).</note></p>
          <p>The anonymous article is entitled “Artist-Poet-Sumassheshii: zhizn Vil’yama Bleka
[Artist-Poet-Madman: Life of William Blake],” <hi rend="i">Teleskop</hi> [<hi rend="i">Telescope</hi>: A
Journal of Contemporary Enlightenment], Vol.22 (Moscow: Printed by P. Stepanov, Published by <corr type="emend">Nikolai
Nadezhdin,</corr> 1834), 69-97. <hi rend="i">Teleskop</hi> was evidently an energetic though short-lived attempt to
give Russian intellectuals a window on the European cultural world, and it regularly printed articles on the
literature of France and England. The Russian writer of the 1834 essay had not known Blake but was depending
on second-hand information. The substance of the <hi rend="i">Teleskop</hi> Blake essay is an adaptation of
Cunningham’s life of Blake which appeared in his <hi rend="i">The Lives of the Most Eminent British
Painters, Sculptors, and Architects</hi> (1830), Vol. II, pp. 143-88, in a series published by John Murray
called The Family Library. Indeed, references in the essay make it clear that it was the second edition of
Cunningham (also of 1830) which was used, for the letter from Charles Lamb and “Holy Thursday” from 
<corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi></corr> given in <hi rend="i">Teleskop</hi> were first
printed in Cunningham’s second edition.</p>
          <p>The adaptor gives no indication that he has sources of biographical information beyond
Cunningham’s account. The reference to “Biographers,” plural, in Paragraph 11, seems to refer to Cunningham
and to J. T. Smith’s account of Blake in <hi rend="i">Nollekens and his Times</hi> (1828) which is
explicitly quoted by Cunningham. He says that he has seen “a few” of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> prints
(Para. 47), and he may be naming those he has seen in his abbreviated list of them, but such knowledge is not
improbable, since we know that the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> designs were circulating in France and Germany in the
early 1830s.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">7</ref> When the adaptor says
that he “could present them [the readers] with a full catalogue” of Blake’s literary “works” (Para. 49), we
may be confident that he could have done no better than make a further digest of Cunningham’s information;
certainly he gives no facts about Blake which are not also in Cunningham’s life of Blake. 
<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">7</hi> See <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (1969), 602, n. 3, and <hi rend="i">William Blake:</hi>
The Critical Heritage (1975), 229-30.</note></p>
          <p>Though the adaptor has derived all his Blake information from Cunningham, he does not go through
Cunningham’s account systematically at all. This is just as well, as a matter of fact, for Cunningham’s
story is highly anecdotal and chronologically racketty. For example, Cunningham discusses “The Chimney
Sweeper” and “Holy Thursday” from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> in his Paragraphs 13 and 53,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">8</ref> while the adaptation much more satisfactorily
discusses the two poems sequentially, in Paragraphs 20-27. <note id="n51"><hi rend="s">8</hi> All information
about Cunningham here derives from <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (1969), 476-507, where his life is
reprinted and annotated.</note></p>
          <p>Of course, the adaptor has added a great deal to Cunningham’s account, both in new material
(usually opinions and comparisons) and in new emphases and interpretations. While Paragraphs 2-9, 11-12,
20-25, 27, 29-30, 35-36, 38, 41-43, 44 (mostly), and 46 are little more than translations of Cunningham, the
Russian Paragraphs 1, 10, 15, 31, 33 (the first half), 47 (the first three sentences), 48 (the first two
sentences), 49, and 52 (the last sentence), for example, are entirely new. In general, where Cunningham was
usually faithful to Blake in his fashion, the adaptor is merely often faithful to Cunningham. Normally, the
adaptor takes Cunningham’s materials and goes beyond them, as when he says that “The Chimney Sweeper” “can
give some idea of Blake’s lack of sophistication, and perhaps even of his too child-like spiritualism”
(Paragraph 19), when Cunningham had only said that it is “rude enough, truly, but yet not without pathos”
(Paragraph 13). Even the biographical “facts” are altered at the whim of the adaptor, particularly with
dialogue. A good deal of the dialogue is simply invented by the adaptor, turning into dramatic form what
Cunningham had left as mere expository narrative. For instance, the dialogue in Paragraphs 2, 3, 16 (most of
it), 37 (the last quotation), and 44 (at the end) does not appear in Cunningham at all. There is, however,
some poetic justice in this dramatization of Cunningham’s prose, for Cunningham had been similarly
high-handed with <hi rend="i">his</hi> source, J. T. Smith, in making dialogue out of mere narration.</p>
          <p>Occasionally, the changes the adaptor makes are so remarkable that one wonders at his grasp of
English (or of his own language). For example, where Blake and Cunningham wrote of “books and pictures of old,
which I wrote in ages of eternity, before my mortal life” (Paragraph 22), the adaptor gives “books and
pictures of old, which I will revive in eternity when I have finished my mortal life” (Paragraph 36). (A yet
more striking example is in Paragraph 16.) Either the adaptor’s English was pretty poor, or his belief that
Blake was deranged made him feel it to be unnecessary to give Blake’s words with even approximate accuracy.
The differences of past, present, and future, confused here by the adaptor, are substantial.</p>
          <p>One effect of the adaptation is to put Blake in a much wider cultural and literary context than
Cunningham provides. The adaptor compares Blake with Wordsworth and the Lake School (Paragraph 19), wishes
Blake had illustrated Bunyan (Paragraph 33), and discusses him in connection with the great young French
Romantics Victor Hugo (1802-85), Alexandre Guiraud (1788-1847), and Lamartine (1790-1869) (Paragraphs 26, 31).
Another change is the emphasis upon Blake’s madness. Cunningham usually speaks of Blake as “wild . . .
overflowing with . . . oddities and dreams” (Paragraph 30), and where he does call him in some respects
“utterly wild and mad” he says he “was at the same time perfectly sensible” in other respects (Paragraph 32);
he sees Blake as a kind of schizophrenic, a sane <corr type="emend">artisan</corr> by day and a mad visionary
by night. His adaptor, however, will scarcely allow the daytime sanity and stresses insistently Blake’s
“derangement,” often with evidence that is virtually invented (e.g., Paragraphs 14-16).</p>
          <p>In fact, there can be no doubt that the adaptor was unscrupulously making journalistic capital
out of the sensational aspects of Blake’s life, and the whole performance is somewhat disreputable. Blake
<pb id="p10-114" n="114"/>
really did have visions, and the anonymous adaptor seems to have felt that this eccentricity absolved his
critics of responsibility to precise truth. It is unfortunate that it was through articles such as this one
that Blake’s reputation, or notoriety, was spread on the Continent.</p>
          <p>It is striking that there are no references to Russian authors in the <hi rend="i">Teleskop</hi>
article, while the comparisons with Blake added to Cunningham’s account are chiefly either French or
English. As a matter of fact, the author of the <hi rend="i">Teleskop</hi> article is identifiable, and he is
not Russian but French. The same article was originally published anonymously as “Artiste, Poete et Fou. (La
Vie de Blake)” in <hi rend="i">Revue de Paris</hi>, 56 (November 1833), 164-82, and <hi rend="i">Teleskop</hi>
apparently merely translated it entire, and without acknowledgement. (Indeed, the reference at the end of the
<hi rend="i">Teleskop</hi> version to “Lives of British Artists” is disingenuous, for the Russian translator
apparently never saw Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives.</hi>) The French adaptor of Cunningham was Amédée
Pichot, who reprinted his 1833 article in “Le Visionnaire Blake” in <hi rend="i">Revue Britannique</hi>, 5
(1862), 25-47, where he acknowledged that Cunningham’s life “m’avait presque seul fourni les documents
anecdotique.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">9</hi> C. H. Moore, “Amedee Pichot’s Discovery of Blake,” <hi rend="i">Etudes
Anglaises</hi>, 16 (1963), 54-58, cites L. A. Bisson, <hi rend="i">Amédée Pichot:</hi> A Romantic Prometheus
(n.d.), who described Pichot as the chief liaison officer between French and English literature.</note></p>
          <p>The <hi rend="i">Teleskop</hi> essay is, then, a translation into Russian (1834) of a rough
adaptation into French (1833) of Cunningham’s biography in English (1830) which was in turn largely derived
from J. T. Smith’s biography of Blake (1828). It is a process which makes for lively reading and a
degeneration of truth.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
