<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>10.4.dargan</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">Blake and Hayley in Wittreich’s Angel of Apocalypse</title>
        <author n="Dargan">Tom Dargan</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1977</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1977</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">10.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
              <name>Brad Hayden</name>
              <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Jane Welford</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Tom Dargan</name>
              <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
              <name>George Goyder</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson-Grant</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Edward Terry Jones</name>
              <name>Martin K. Nurmi</name>
              <name>Mary Ellen Reisner</name>
              <name>Myra Glazer Schotz</name>
              <name>Harry White</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1977"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_10">
    <body>
	<pb id="p10-130" n="130"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-10-4-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">DISCUSSION</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <head>
          <title type="section-subtitle">
            <hi rend="b">WITH INTELLECTUAL SPEARS &amp; LONG WINGED ARROWS OF THOUGHT</hi>
          </title>        
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">BLAKE AND HAYLEY IN WITTREICH’S <hi rend="i">Angel of Apocalypse</hi></hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">TOM</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">DARGAN</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Richly illustrated and densely documented, this book on “Blake’s idea of Milton” by a Milton
scholar has the appearance of an admirable and exciting performance. So it was reviewed by Purvis E. Boyette
(<hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 39), and so it first appeared to me. In fact, I took it for a guide to new
territory, and navigating by its footnotes and bibliography I steered back through Wittreich’s previous
books and articles to the obscure and sometimes rare works of William Hayley (1745-1820), the sometimes
Miltonist and sometimes patron of William Blake. And my wages were exasperation.</p>
          <p>A close reading of <hi rend="i">Angel of Apocalypse</hi> reveals double disaster: the evidence is
not evidence, and the arguments won’t stand to a position. The two faults feed each other, at the expense of
the reader, so when he leaves the text to trace a reference he finds only a tenuous or illusory connection
where he expected solid evidence, and when he returns to the text he soon finds himself robbed of his
scrupulousness—for the emphatic position of page 248 becomes abandoned territory by page 251. This book is a
shell game.</p>
          <p>The trick of the shell game is to make a move before the observer starts counting, so you are
always a jump ahead of him. Wittreich gets the jump on his reader with the fallacy of the dubious assumption.
A central point—persistently referred to, repeatedly elaborated—is never argued in its own right, but
instead is passed off in the footnotes as if it were an established fact. An instance is the idea that Hayley
was an important influence on Blake. Wittreich cites Frederick Pierce as evidence, in a
<pb id="p10-131" n="131"/>
sleight-of-hand where a question of degree is passed off as a matter of fact:
<q>
Pierce’s conclusion is that Blake, profoundly influenced by Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi> [of Milton]
took imaginative hints from it. (p. 231)
</q>
We are referred to Pierce’s article of 1929.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70"
type="note">1</ref> In that article, we find Pierce citing lines from Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Life of
Milton</hi> (1797) that seem to provide the plot for Blake’s brief epic <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (begun
1804). Says Pierce, “it is possible that the central theme of Blake’s poem was suggested by two passages in
Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Life.</hi>” In one Hayley imagines that Milton might come back from the other world to
give the lie to his misinterpreters. In the other passage Hayley imagines Milton coming back specifically to
revenge Dr. Johnson’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi> of him by writing a worse account of Johnson. Pierce points out
that Blake had every opportunity to read Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi>, since Blake moved to Hayley’s
village, Felpham, to work with Hayley, in 1800. Pierce concludes that Blake took “imaginative hints”
(Pierce’s term) from such passages. <note id="n70"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Frederick Pierce, “The Genesis and
General Meaning of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi>, 25 (1927),
165-78.</note></p>
          <p>Whether Hayley’s influence is here “profound” (as Wittreich says) is another matter. This is
not Pierce’s conclusion. Plot, of course, is profound only in an architectural sense: it is the basis of the
shape and structure of a work. Thought and skill enter after the plot has been fixed: in the elaboration and
development of the work. There is no profound thinking in Hayley’s plot for <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> A
giant, maligned by his inferiors, returns. This is a formula for hundreds of stories and myths, an idea
re-invented, probably, by every child who has muttered at a parent. That Hayley is the source of the idea is
interesting, perhaps, for the same reason that it is interesting that Lady Hesketh suggested the Sofa for the
theme of Cowper’s <hi rend="i">Task.</hi> No particular originality, thoughtfulness, or active participation
is assigned to the source; the source is distinguished only by his or her proximity to the artist. Pierce
himself is careful not to inflate Hayley’s influence here, and careful not to inflate Hayley’s capacity as
a thinker. During Blake’s stay st Felpham, from 1800 to 1803, Hayley was “posing as a Miltonist,” says
Pierce. The materials Hayley had assembled for an edition of Milton’s works were the important influence on
Blake; from these (Pierce continues) we can infer a broad reading of Milton for Blake. Pierce certainly does
<hi rend="i">not</hi> conclude that Hayley’s thinking or writing was a “profound influence” on Blake, as
Wittreich’s reference might lead a reader to believe.</p>
          <p>Efforts to further press Hayley into an original, thinking, active influence are not successful.
Another note on the Hayley-influence issue refers readers to Wittreich’s 1972 article, “Domes of Mental
Pleasure.” Here Wittreich has proposed that Hayley taught Blake a new theory of poetry. Statements of Hayley
and Blake are juxtaposed:
<q>
The epic poem, in Hayley’s words, is a “dome of mental pleasure” that combines at its “different portals”
the various arts . . . ; it is the “prime enobler of th’ aspiring mind” and the great “arbiter of space and
time,” capable of penetrating and embodying the unknown. . . . Blake’s epic practice mirrors Hayley’s
theory. He uses the epic form to transcend the time-world in whose center he finds the heavens of eternity;
within the epic mode, he presents “Visionary Forms Dramatic . . . In Visions / In new Expanses, creating
exemplars of Memory and of Intellect, / Creating Space, Creating Time according to the wonders Divine / Of
Human Imagination.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n71"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Joseph Anthony Wittreich, “Domes of Mental Pleasure: Blake’s Epics and
Hayley’s Epic Theory,” <hi rend="i">Studies in Philology</hi>, 59 (1972), 112.</note></q>
But when Hayley’s lines are seen in their context they have nothing to do with Blake’s unique ideas about
time in narrative structure. In the immediate context of the phrases quoted by Wittreich, Hayley is simply
comparing painting with poetry. In his view, a painting can only portray in instant in the visible world,
whereas poetry can proceed through time, or makes jumps in it, or describe things of the invisible world.
Painting “catches, with observance keen, / Her single moment of the changeful scene”; whereas poetry, the
“Unquestion’d arbiter of space and time! / Can join the distant, the unknown create. . . .”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72" type="note">3</ref> This praise of poetry over painting is
contained in a broader context where Hayley encourages poetry to catch up with the successes of her sister
art. I see no connection whatsoever between this and Blake’s “Visionary Forms Dramatic,” or any uniquely
Blakean use of “the epic form to transcend the time world.” Yet, for Wittreich, “Blake’s sympathy with these
precepts is so obvious as to preclude the necessity for lengthy discussion.” 
<note id="n72"><hi rend="s">3</hi> William Hayley, <hi rend="i">An Essay on Epic Poetry</hi>, 1782, reprinted Gainsville,
Florida, 1968, p. 7.</note></p>
          <p>Nonetheless, Wittreich does press the discussion a little further. The article continues to the
effect that this is where Blake learned to eliminate sequential narrative time in <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>
That poem, of course, does eliminate conventional sequence. The text, says Frye, proceeds through a “series of
lifting backdrops”;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73" type="note">4</ref> the pictures,
says Erdman, “converge upon the center” of a moment of revelation.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n74" type="note">5</ref> <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>’s organization is more a concentric pattern than a
narrative line connecting beginning and end. But to argue that Blake derived his non-sequential narrative from
Hayley is not only to over-read Hayley out of context, it is to invert Hayley’s categories. What could be
more conventional than Hayley’s idea of narrative time—unless it is his static theory of painting? It
might have been better to look for the origin of Blake’s unconventional narrative time in painting, and the
ways a painting can present multiple perspectives on a single moment. <note id="n73"><hi rend="s">4</hi>
Northrop Frye, <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi> (Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press, 1947), p.
332.</note>
	<note id="n74"><hi rend="s">5</hi> David V. Erdman, “The Steps (of Dance and Stone) that Order Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 6 (Fall 1973), p. 73.</note></p>
          <p>So, even though the Hayley-influence idea is central to <hi rend="i">Angel of Apocalypse</hi>,
the reader will have to turn to the earlier article, “Domes of Mental Pleasure,” to see that idea argued in
its own right. The article concludes, “Hayley’s theory of epic as a revolutionary form—and the precepts
related to that theory—are related, then, with meticulous clarity, to Blake’s epic achievements.” 
<hi rend="i">Angel of Apocalypse</hi> begins (logically speaking) at this point.</p>
          <p>It should be remembered that Wittreich has been challenged before on this point, and on the habit
of over-reading Hayley and quoting him out of context. This is the point of Judith Wardle’s 1974 article
“Satan not having the Science of Wrath . . . ” in <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism.</hi> And the challenge
is not fairly answered by Wittreich’s attempt to dismiss it
<pb id="p10-132" n="132"/>
as a “difference in point of view,” or as a confusion on Wardle’s part of Hayley’s epic theory and
Hayley’s epic practice. Nor is Wardle’s challenge given the attention it deserves when Wittreich buries
his response to her in a footnote (p. 314). Wardle faults Wittreich for just the sort of errors I have found:
for teasing tidbits of Hayley off the bone to make a thin soup. “By careful selection of quotations [Wittreich
makes] it seem that Hayley’s attitudes were very close to Blake’s,” says Wardle; “Wittreich summarizes
Hayley’s recommendations in the <hi rend="i">Essay</hi> in such a way that it appears valid to claim that
Hayley provided theoretical support [for Blake].” And on Wittreich’s contention that Hayley presented Blake
with an idea of “epic as a revolutionary form,” celebrating an idea of freedom, she finds, “when one examines
more closely what this means to Hayley, the similarities are not so close.” In addition to this too-careful
picking out of evidence, Wardle faults Wittreich for misreading Hayley: “He is deceived into believing” that
Hayley condemns epic machinery, while in fact Hayley “vacillates” on this point (Hayley vacillates on most
points: this is why he can seem to support almost any point one likes). Again, Wittreich “miss[es] the shift
of tone” when Hayley makes a close pass at praise for Spenser, and so misreads Hayley’s negative reference
to allegory for a positive one.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n75"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Judith Wardle, “Satan not having the Science of Wrath but only of Pity,”
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 13 (1974), 147-54.</note></p>
          <p>I turn back now to the book proper, to consider closely some interpretations of Blake’s text
and designs. Wittreich infers from a line in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (15:52) that Blake saw in Milton some
change of heart, some shift from political to religious hopes, and some model for himself to console worldly
disappointment with otherworldly hope:
<q>
The poet who lost God in his childhood returned to him in old age . . . this observation . . . is implicit in
Blake’s reference to Milton’s “bright pilgrimage of sixty years.” (p. 40)
</q></p>
          <p>Milton lived 66 years; the idea is to account for the six years Blake drops here. The last six
years must be when Milton returned to God, according to this reading of Blake. But if we turn to the line in
Blake, the context supports precisely the opposite view. Here Milton descends to Blake’s “tarsus,” then
“redounds” as a cloud over Europe. “Then Milton knew that the THree Heavens of Beulah were beheld / By him on
earth in his bright pilgrimage of sixty years.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76"
type="note">7</ref> That is, Milton’s revelation comes in Milton’s afterlife, when he entered into William
Blake. The “bright pilgrimage” is Blake’s way of referring to Milton’s lifetime, when he was “on earth.”
In <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> Blake seems to think of a person’s allotted time on earth as “sixty winters”; in
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (published when he had passed that mark), he seems to prefer a “pilgrimage of
seventy years.” Blake has only rounded off the number here. <note id="n76"><hi rend="s">7</hi><hi rend="i">
The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1965), p.
109.</note></p>
          <p>Still, this reading of the “sixty years” is the textual basis in Blake for Wittreich’s idea
that <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> celebrates a change of heart in Milton’s lifetime:
<q>
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> pursues a double purpose: one is to locate the decisive turning point in
Milton’s life, which, we have already said, comes with the writing of <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>
and then to mythologize it; the other is to relate that moment of redemption to the renewal of the entire
human race which comes with “the great Harvest and Vintage of the Nations” promised in the poem’s final
plate. (p. 243)
</q>
The assertion persists: Blake brings Milton back, not to have him correct errors he made in his lifetime, not
to correct errors made by his interpreters, not to assert political leadership once again in an England torn
between republicanism and royal tyranny; but rather to dramatize a revelation Milton had during his lifetime.
I am not taking issue with any tradition in Milton criticism that Milton may have experienced some religious
conversion or re-conversion late in life, nor with any interpretation of <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>
that takes such a conversion experience into account. The issue is whether, in Wittreich’s terms, such a
“decisive turning point” is “located” in Milton’s lifetime in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> By
Wittreich’s own evidence, it is not.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77"
type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n77"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Edward J. Rose arrived at the same theory from different evidence. See
“Blake’s Illustrations for <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost, L’Allegro</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi>:
A Thematic Reading,” <hi rend="i">Hartford Studies in Literature</hi>, 2 (1970), pp. 40-67.</note></p>
          <p>Nonetheless Wittreich uses this idea of Milton’s conversion to account for differences between
designs in different copies of <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> Both Plate 1 and Plate 16 of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
give full page pictures of Milton. The engraving on the copper plate, of course, is fixed and permanent, but
one print can and does vary from the next because the inking and coloring of the print vary. Here is a good
place to look for changes of emphasis, even changes of mind in Blake’s mental picture of Milton. In copies C
and D of Plate 1 the cross-hatching over Milton’s body is not so obvious as in A and B, because these lines,
printed from the copper plate, are colored over with a more opaque pigment. Wittreich sees in this difference
an indication that Milton has escaped from what Wittreich terms a “net of selfhood.” He says the
cross-hatching has been “lifted”:
<q>
The alterations of this plate as we move from Copy A to Copy D, turn us from a darkened into a transfigured
Milton. . . . Blake’s implication is clear: the journey Milton makes through the wilderness of self enables
him to transcend the law and to embrace the spirit of prophecy. (pp. 26-27)
</q></p>
          <p>Now there is no way of knowing from this if Wittreich is saying that Milton changed his mind, or
Blake. Remember, we are collating one plate from four copies. And note the implicit assumption about the
relationship of these copies: that they constitute a complete series, A through D, separated by more or less
equal periods of time, or at least equal portions of mental space, to correspond to an evolution in Blake’s
thinking, or in Milton’s, whichever it is. In fact not much is known about when these copies were printed,
beyond the watermark on the paper, which is dated 1808 on copies A, B, and C, and 1815 on D—which only means
these copies were not printed before these respective dates. And to call cross-hatching a “net of selfhood”
implies that cross-hatching has a special and negative meaning in Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78" type="note">9</ref> In fact, Blake would have been very foolish to adopt such a
symbolism: cross-hatching is the engraver’s usual
<pb id="p10-133" n="133"/>
method of giving body to an outlined figure. Blake would have to draw only benighted figures, or stick to
simple line engravings. But most important, this interpretation overlooks the picture as a whole. Here Milton
is stepping forth, pushing through his name, just as he steps through his literal “self / hood” in Plate 18.
Wittreich is “quoting” the cross-hatching out of context, out of the context of the picture. We don’t need
to collate A, B, C, and D to see that Milton escapes from his selfhood. He is doing it in every copy, by main
strength of his left hand (traditionally his political hand) at that. Has Wittreich missed this because of his
peculiar idea that Milton here “walks naked, Blake exhibiting Milton’s shame, exposing his faults?” (p.
36)— an unBlakean reading for a naked hero! <note id="n78"><hi rend="s">9</hi> For a discussion of how to
read Blake’s pictures emblematically see W. J. T. Mitchell, “Blake’s Composite Art,” in Erdman and Grant,
eds., <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic</hi> (Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press,
1970), pp. 57-81. Mitchell is a sensible, undogmatic guide; “The image of evil in Blake’s designs . . . is
not an arbitrary emblem, or simply a devil with horns, but the sight of the human body surrendering its unique
form and dissolving into a nonhuman landscape, as in many designs in the Lambeth books and the later
prophecies where bodies take root in the ground or sprout bestial appendages.” (p. 71).</note></p>
          <p>Wittreich applies the same interpretation, and the same method, to Plate 16. All copies show the
hero standing naked, with a garment in his left hand and a belt in his right; both hands are held away from
the body and the stance is broad. Wittreich maintains that in A and B Milton is taking off his clothes (a
“garment of selfhood”), and in C and D he is putting them on (a “robe of righteousness”). His primary evidence
is the pink-brown shading on the white garment of Copy D. He understands this to depict a bloody garment,
which he associates with the bloody robes of Ololon. So Milton is putting on a “robe of righteousness” like
Ololon’s, whereas in the other copies he is (or was) taking off some pristine, hypocritical covering. But in
fact, the pink-brown shading is used generally in Plate 16 D, and not only on the garment; so there is no
reason to assign the color any special meaning when it comes to the garment. Once again Wittreich is quoting
out of context; the picture as a whole clearly shows the hero with naked beauty displayed. And with all this
worrying about whether the clothes are coming off or going on, Wittreich has missed an alteration of some
substance: in D the garment is extended so the end of it is now under Milton’s left foot. In Wittreich’s
reading, Milton would be standing on the clothes he is about to put on!</p>
          <p>Clearly Wittreich’s habits do not improve as he moves from Hayley to Blake. General rules,
however arbitrary, come before any particular evidence; and any shred or flicker of text or design that might
serve as an instance is pulled from its context to so serve, even if the whole context is tugging mightily in
just the opposite direction. One more instance of this habit of holding evidence hostage to a formula may be
instructive.</p>
          <p>The formula will be familiar: different copies of a design reverse in meaning. The instance is
prints of the engraving <hi rend="i">Albion Rose</hi> (the print Gilchrist called <hi rend="i">Glad Day</hi>).
The interpretation: that the uncolored print of the engraving (the one with the caption from which we get the
title) depicts a sinister, “selfish” Albion:
<q>
the line engraving portrays Albion in his fallen aspect; the color print depicts him as a redeemed man. (p.
54)
</q></p>
          <p>Readers will recall the design as Blake’s exuberant application of the traditional
drawing-textbook picture of a man inscribed in a circle. Traditionally the design demonstrates the “exempeda”
method of measuring a man’s proportions where his height is six times the length of his foot. Blake’s
version is pleasing, and essentially Blakean, for the way the passive anatomy-lesson model is made active:
human proportion, it seems to say, is found when a man measures the steps of the “dance of death.” The term is
found in the caption; it means willing self-sacrifice:
<q>
Albion rose from where he labour’d at the Mill with Slaves / Giving himself for the Nations he danc’d the
dance of Eternal Death
</q>
“Eternal Death” in this sense of self-sacrifice is used in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: when Milton sacrifices
his place in Heaven to return to earth, he says, “I go to Eternal Death,” because “The Nations still / Follow
after the detestable Gods of Priam” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 14:13-14).</p>
          <p>How Wittreich can read this print as sinister and selfish is a troublesome problem. He confuses
the dates of the engraving and the prints made from it until, at one point, he seems to date the color print
earlier than the engraving from which it was printed; no matter, the Keynes book of 
<hi rend="i">Engravings</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79" type="note">10</ref> assures us
that the two color prints and the two monochromes are from the same plate, because the lines that print on the
monochrome have also printed on the color print, even if coloring has mostly hidden them. It shouldn’t
matter; but Wittreich’s formula seems to demand some sequence of printing, over a period of time in which
Blake had second thoughts about his republicanism. In the caption, it has been pointed out, “dance of Eternal
Death” looks like an ironic inversion of Burke’s characterization of democratic revolution as a “death
dance.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80" type="note">11</ref> Somehow Wittreich gets his
signs reversed, and reads all of the caption ironically, except for the “dance of Eternal Death,” which, he
says, shows that Blake agreed with Burke. In the picture itself Wittreich finds the expression on Albion’s
face to be “selfish.” which is probably not worth arguing about. And he finds the moth flying between
Albion’s legs, which he calls “bat winged,” some symbol of universal pollution (this moth is not evident in
the color prints). But we need only leaf through the reproductions in Wittreich’s own book to see worse
monsters who do not signal a negative reading for the pictures they are in. <hi rend="i">Paradise
Regained</hi> watercolors nos. 8 and 9, for example (plates 41 and 42 in <hi rend="i">Angel of
Apocalypse</hi>), have monsters and creatures of the night, but certainly they have not made Jesus sinister or
selfish. They seem to have troubled Jesus like bad dreams, but as he wakes and rises they flee offstage,
rather like Albion’s moth. <note id="n79"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">Engravings by
William Blake: The Separate Plates</hi>, (Dublin: Emery Walker, 1956), pp. 6-7.</note>
	<note id="n80"><hi rend="s">11</hi> David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire</hi> (Garden
City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1969), p. 11.</note></p>
          <p>This interpretation of <hi rend="i">Albion Rose</hi> as sinister and selfish is only one—the
worst perhaps—of the troublesome interpretations to be found in <hi rend="i">Angel of Apocalypse.</hi>
Clearly they do not begin with evidence and build toward a general formula—they work the wrong way around,
by beginning with a formula and then finding instances wihch, taken out of context, might seem to fit it. How
else explain the persistence of this conversion or reversal formula, when each instance Wittreich himself
cites turns out to be testimony against it? Wittreich has put himself
<pb id="p10-134" n="134"/>
in the position of a trial lawyer with a poor case, who knows in advance the position he must argue, who can
offer only circumstantial evidence, and who can only hope to carry the jury by stubborn persistence.</p>
          <p>I have already noted the theory, central to <hi rend="i">Angel of Apocalypse</hi>, that Hayley
profoundly influenced Blake. This theory is constantly invoked in the book to support arguments to this or
that point, but it is never presented and proved in its own right. I have shown important instances where it
does not hold up, instances where Wittreich argues that Hayley’s thinking about Milton, and Hayley’s
thinking about epic, were the sources of Blake’s ideas on the same matters. Now I want to consider
Wittreich’s contention that Hayley perceived an important conversion or reversal of thinking in Milton,
which occurred between <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>, and that
Hayley perceived <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> in a new and original way, and that Hayley strongly
influenced Blake in this regard. The formula, that Hayley mediated an idea Blake held about an important
change of heart Milton experienced in old age, is familiar. I want to show that this formula—which is at the
core of the theory that Hayley was a profound influence on Blake—is unfounded, if remarkably persistent. It
seems to give <hi rend="i">Angel of Apocalypse</hi> coherence, but it does so by mere persistence, and not by
any evidence that holds up in this book, nor by any certain proof in Wittreich’s work before the book. I
will trace the argument for Hayley’s perception of Milton’s change of heart to Wittreich’s earlier
articles and sources, through his own citation of them, and demonstrate that this aspect of the
Milton-Hayley-Blake theory is, literally, built on nothing.</p>
          <p>To open the question of Hayley’s influence on Blake in <hi rend="i">Angel of Apocalypse</hi>,
Wittreich confronts the tradition that Blake remembered Hayley as a nuisance. He cites what he calls Stuart
Curran’s “proof” that Hyle—the character Blake cast as a damned nuisance in the inferno of his poetry—is
<hi rend="i">not</hi> Hayley. Curran begins with the fact that “hyle” can be a Greek term for matter, and that
there is a Gnostic tradition of personifying materialism as Hyle.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n81" type="note">12</ref> Curran’s point here is well taken: there in more to Hyle than the
historical Hayley; Blake has appropriated part of a Gnostic tradition to mold a symbolic character. But Curran
is not reasonable when he declares that since Hyle is more than Hayley, he is no longer Hayley in any part.
There are just too many instances in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> where Hyle is
grouped with other characters whose names are thin disguises for the real-life principals of Blake’s
well-known sedition case, principals like his accuser, judge, and the prosecutor. In that case Hayley stood
bail for Blake—Hayley being the “great man” of the village Felpham where the trouble took place. Perhaps
Blake was not properly grateful for Hayley’s help, but in that role, and in his role of patron (where Blake
assumed Hayley would come up with some profitable project for him), it is probable that Blake saw Hayley as an
emblem of materialism of some sort—company in which a poet can come to worldly distress. To conclude from
Curran’s article that the development and expansion of the character Hyle eliminates the historical Hayley
as the basic material for Hyle is surely incorrect. But Wittreich does just that. 
<note id="n81"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Stuart Curran, “Blake and the Gnostic Hyle,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 4 (1972), pp.
117-33.</note></p>
          <p>Next, he asserts that Blake follows Hayley in a new understanding of Milton:
<q>
Like Hayley, Blake found in Milton’s <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> a poem of “pure religion”
accompanied by “greater force of imagination” than had been presented in <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi> (p.
128)
</q>
Wittreich is quoting Hayley here, not Blake, and he cites a previous article of his to substantiate the idea:
<q>
In the final estimate of both Hayley and Blake Milton’s distinguishing characteristic was his religious
enthusiasm. It was the “prime director of his genius” as exhibited in <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and 
  <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>, the latter poem representing “the truest heroism, and the <corr type="emend">triumph</corr> of
Christianity.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82" type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n82"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Joseph Anthony Wittreich, “William Blake, Illustrator-Interpreter of 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>,” in Wittreich, ed., <hi rend="i">Calm of Mind . . . Essays for John S.
Diekoff</hi> (Cleveland: Case-Western Reserve, 1971), pp. 93-133.</note></q>
Again the quotations are all from Hayley, not Blake. At this point in the <hi rend="i">Festschrift</hi>
article Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Life of Milton</hi> is cited. But the reader who turns to the 
<hi rend="i">Life</hi> will find that Hayley is not promoting <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> as any advance
of Miltonic genius beyond <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi> Nor does Hayley mention any conversion or change of
heart that might have provided extra energy to write <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>, as Wittreich
implies.</p>
          <p>On the contrary, Hayley is defending <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> against the familiar,
specious charge that it is less brilliant than <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, by asserting its own virtues.
Hayley points out that it is plainly moralistic instead of mightily imagistic like its big sister: “The
splendor of the poet does not blaze, indeed, so intensely as in his larger production.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83" type="note">14</ref> Wittreich implies that Hayley finds a
“triumph of Christianity” in the theme of <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>, an expression of a new-found
religious enthusiasm in Milton. But Hayley only says that the poem’s plain style represents a “spirit of
self-command” in Milton: the mighty poet demonstrated modesty when he constructed a plain poem. Hayley
everywhere is full of enthusiasm for the rhetoric of elaborate compliments; here he is only saying that such
“self-command” might serve to teach modesty and plainess to “ingenuous youth”: in Hayleyan rhetoric such
modesty is “the triumph of Christianity.” When the reader sees the context of these mighty-sounding quotations
that Wittreich culls from Hayley, they prove to be no more than a rhetorical inflation of some dull
prescription for modest oaks from mighty acorns. <note id="n83"><hi rend="s">14</hi> William Hayley, 
<hi rend="i">The Life of Milton</hi>, 1976, reprinted by Folcroft Press (no city), 1970, p. 220.</note></p>
          <p>Since there is nothing in Hayley that explicitly treats <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> as
evidence of an important change in Milton’s thinking, and since Hayley says nothing at all of this supposed
conversion or recantation of politics on Milton’s part, and certainly nothing of Milton achieving a more
“pure religion” in any context that would make the phrase mean anything significant, what, at bottom, is the
basis of Wittreich’s persistent assertion that Hayley perceived a new Milton which he passed along to Blake?
Wittreich’s evidence, finally, is only a negative kind of evidence, which makes much of nothing. He says
that Hayley did not treat <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> as if it were dependent on, or a sequel to, 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>:
<pb id="p10-135" n="135"/>
	<q>
Hayley asserts the integrity of Milton’s brief epic, which is to say that he regards the poem as neither
companion nor sequel to <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84"
type="note">15</ref>
	<note id="n84"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Wittreich, “Illustrator-Interpreter,” p. 107.</note></q>
Wittreich means only that, as an editor of Milton, Hayley did not arrange the poems so it would be inferred
that <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> together make up an epic in
sixteen books. For that matter, so didn’t editor Thomas Newton before Hayley.</p>
          <p>It is not difficult to cite Hayley as evidence for an arbitrary formula, because Hayley, as Blake
remembered him, and as Judith Wardle reminds us, was a great vacillator. And besides, no one much cares what
Hayley said. It is a different matter with Blake, whose views were extreme and definite. To imagine Blake that
“fleshed out” Hayley’s epic theories is to put Blake to school to the man he immortalized as a fool not to
be endured. And it is to set Blake’s motto, “Particulars before Generals,” around backwards, to make Blake a
willing producer of evidence <hi rend="i">post facto</hi> for Hayley’s theories, in defiance of Blake’s
fierce originiality and jealous independence.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
