<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>10.4.heppner</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="note">Notes on some items in the Blake Collection at McGill, with a few speculations
around William Roscoe</title>
        <author n="Heppner">Christopher Heppner</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1977</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1977</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake Newsletter/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">10.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
              <name>Brad Hayden</name>
              <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
              <name>Virginia Masi</name>
              <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
              <name>Jane Welford</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Tom Dargan</name>
              <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
              <name>George Goyder</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson-Grant</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Edward Terry Jones</name>
              <name>Martin K. Nurmi</name>
              <name>Mary Ellen Reisner</name>
              <name>Myra Glazer Schotz</name>
              <name>Harry White</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1977"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_10">
    <body>
      <pb id="p10-100" n="100"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-10-4-0003">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">NOTES</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">NOTES ON SOME ITEMS IN THE BLAKE COLLECTION AT McGILL WITH A FEW SPECULATIONS
AROUND WILLIAM ROSCOE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">CHRISTOPHER</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">HEPPNER</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <figure n="FamilyMeeting.10.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="564">
            <head>1 Engraving based on “The meeting of a Family in Heaven” for Blair’s <hi rend="i">The
Grave.</hi></head>
          </figure>
          <p><hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> readers may not know that there is an interesting Blake
collection in the Rare Book Room of the McLennan Library at McGill University.<ref target="n0" type="note">*</ref> 
It is a good collection, except
for the lack of any original copies of Blake’s own poems or paintings. But it has a few original drawings,
sets of the Job and Dante engravings, one of the four or five known impressions of the engraving of Edmund
Pitts,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> the Linnell portrait of Wilson
Lowry that served as the original design for Blake’s engraving,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n2" type="note">2</ref> many of the books illustrated by Blake, and a good collection of facsimiles,
critical works, and related items. The core of the collection was donated in 1953 by Mr. Lawrence Lande, and
the Rare Book Room librarians and I have tried to fill gaps and keep the collection up to date, aided by
further donations from Mr. Lande. In the course of working with the collection, I have come across several
interesting items that I would like to describe, by way of both sharing and requesting information.
	<note id="n0">The preparation of this essay was aided by a grant from the Faculty of Graduate Studies and 
Research at McGill. Diane Mayor brought the <hi rend="i">Grandison</hi> edition to my attention.</note>
	<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See Keynes, <hi rend="i">Engravings by William Blake: The Separate Plates</hi>
(Dublin: Emery Walker, 1956), p. 78, and also his “William Blake and Bart’s” in <hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter</hi> 25 (Summer 1973). 9-10.</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> See Keynes, <hi rend="i">Engravings by William Blake: The Separate
Plates</hi>, pp. 86-87, and pl. 45. Lowry was the inventor of a ruling machine used for engraving, which Blake
apparently used in his Dante engravings; see Ruthven Todd, “Blake’s Dante Plates,” <hi rend="i">TLS</hi>, 29
August 1968, p. 928.</note></p>
          <p>The first two are apparently plagiarisms. One is a much reduced—in all senses—and unsigned
version of Blake’s “The meeting of a Family in Heaven” design for Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>,
with a new text which is not from that poem (illus. 1). The dimensions of the frame line are 142 × 90 mm.,
and the plate has been bound in as frontispiece to a copy of Hayley’s <hi rend="i">The Triumphs of
Temper</hi>, the twelfth edition with Blake’s engravings. The volume also contains two other prints glued
onto the inside of the covers, one being Plate IX (one of Blake’s plates) for Vol. VIII of <hi rend="i">The
Novelist’s Magazine</hi>, containing <hi rend="i">Don Quixote.</hi> The book has been signed “Ann Shipman”
in what looks like an approximately contemporary, and very shaky, hand.</p>
          <p>The “appearance of libidinousness” to which Robert Hunt objected in the original<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> has been removed; in this version the
husband’s hand remains decorously at his wife’s waist rather than openly enjoying the fullness of her
buttock. One version of the philistine unwilling to give the artist in form and line his due? The angels’
wings have also had their free, erect Gothic curves cut down into a flaccid droop. The dynamism of the son
entering from the right has been negated by placing him behind the group of children on the left. The three
pairs of figures on the ground retain their general positions, but
<pb id="p10-101" n="101"/>
each pair has been reversed. Perhaps the changes were enough to protect the publisher; they were certainly
enough to emasculate the design. Does any reader know anything of the book which this presumably once
illustrated? <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> See G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>
(Oxford: Clarendon, 1969), pp. 195-97.</note></p>
          <p>The second apparent plagiarism is a two volume edition of <hi rend="i">The History of Sir Charles
Grandison.</hi> Both title-pages read “Formerly Published in Seven Volumes; the Whole now Comprised in Two.
Cooke’s Edition. Embellished with Fifteen Superb Engravings.” The first volume then reads “London;
Stereotyped and Printed for T. Kelly. 17, Paternoster-Row,” and is dated 1818; the second volume reads
“London; Stereotyped and Printed for C. Cooke. 17, Paternoster Row; by D. Cock, and Co. Dean Street, Soho,”
and is undated. At the end of both volumes is a colophon attributing the stereotyping and printing to D. Cock
and Co. at 75 Dean Street, Soho. The edition is unrecorded as far as I have been able to check.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See the bibliography in Jocelyn Harris, ed., <hi rend="i">The History of
Sir Charles Grandison</hi> (London: Oxford Univ. Press, 1972), I, xl. It is admitted that the list is
“probably not complete” (I, xxxix). The British Museum Catalogue lists a “Cooke’s edition. Embellished with
. . . engravings. 7 vol. <hi rend="i">London</hi>, 1817. 24°,” which I have not seen, but the date, number of
volumes, and format (the McGill copy is 8°) seem clearly to mark this as a different edition. The layout of
the text is not identical with that of <hi rend="i">The Novelist’s Magazine</hi> edition.</note></p>
          <p>The date of 1818 on the first volume presents some difficulties, and the evidence suggests that
there was an interval of several years between the printing and the publishing of this edition, or
alternatively between the making of the stereotypes and the actual printing. The engraved illustrations are
all dated between 19 May and 21 November 1811; D. Cock appears to have moved from Dean Street in
1815,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> and Charles Cooke died in
1816.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> The title-page of the first
volume thus seems anomalous, and possibly replaces a previous one, either actual or planned. 
<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> See under D. Cock and Co. in William B. Todd, <hi rend="i">A Directory of Printers and Others
in Allied Trades: London and Vicinity 1800-1840</hi> (London: Printing Historical Society, 1972).</note>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> DNB.</hi></note></p>
          <p>In any case, the “Fifteen Superb Engravings” are copied—or altered—from those in 
<hi rend="i">The Novelist’s Magazine</hi> edition, with plates designed by Stothard, of which three were
engraved by Blake. The plates are in most respects very close to the originals, though there are substantial
changes in the figures, especially in the women’s clothing, which has been updated to represent the
high-waisted Grecian style of the Regency period.</p>
          <p>The first plate, “Miss Byron paying a visit to Emily in her Chamber,” is dated 6 July 1811, and
like all the plates is described as “Printed for C. Cooke, Paternoster Row.” The women’s costumes have been
altered, and Stothard’s name replaced by “Scatchard.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
type="note">7</ref> But many details, such as the irregular marks under the period after “sculp.,” are
identical with those visible on the original illustration, suggesting that the same plate was used for both,
or that the later plate was made from a stereotype of the original (see illus. 2).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> The second plate, “Sir Charles Grandison, disarming Captain
Salmonet,” is dated 8 June or July (only the “Ju” is visible) 1811. Again Stothard’s name becomes
“Scatchard,” but the changes are extensive enough to make it clear that a new plate has been used (see illus.
3). The third plate, “Charlotte and Caroline’s affecting interview with their Brother Sir Charles
Grandison,” is dated 1 June 1811, but just after that one can barely make out the imperfectly erased original
date, “Jan. 18, 1783,” making it quite clear that this is printed from the original plate reworked (see illus.
4). On this plate Stothard’s name remains, brought up to date with an “R.A.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> I have not found any trace of this name in any of the standard dictionaries
of artists and engravers, and assume it to be a fiction.</note>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> The repetition of irregular marks which are not part of the engraving
proper suggests that the later plate is not copied from the first by any method involving tracing. For helpful
information on copying methods—and ethics—in the period, see G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">The Early
Engravings of Flaxman’s Classical Designs: A Bibliographical Study</hi>, With a Note on the Duplicating of
Engravings by Richard J. Wolfe (New York: New York Public Library, 1964). The methods discussed by Wolfe’s
note both involve tracing.</note>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Stothard became an academician in 1794, according to the 
<hi rend="i">DNB.</hi></note></p>
          <p>In the edition as a whole, Stothard’s name has been changed to Scatchard on eight of the
plates, remains unchanged on two, and is updated with an “R.A.” on five. In no case has an engraver’s name
been changed, though Heath is advanced to J. Heath A.R.A.. The respect with which Stothard and Heath’s names
have been treated in at least some instances clashes oddly with the changes of Stothard to Scatchard, 
<corr type="emend">which</corr> would seem to imply conscious deception. I do not know whether Blake 
had a hand in the reworking of his plates or not; it seems very unlikely, though it is worth remembering 
that Blake felt decidedly hostile to Stothard by 1811, and he had previously done work for John Cooke, 
Charles’s father and predecessor.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> See G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford:
Clarendon Press, 1969), p. 609.</note></p>
          <p>The next group of items consists of original drawings, some of which raise questions of
attribution and identification. One is almost certainly the original drawing for Thomas Butts’ engraving of
“Venus Anadyomene,” reproduced most accessibly on Plate IX of <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> by G. E.
Bentley, Jr..<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> The drawing, which
measures 114 × 76 mm., is attributed to Blake in a pencil note on the mat reading “by William Blake / From
the Collection of Thomas Butts, the artist’s friend and patron.” The notation is not recent, but the hand is
not Tatham’s, and Martin Butlin in a letter agrees that the drawing is most probably by Butts rather than
Blake. <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> See also Ada E. Briggs, “Mr. Butts, the Friend and Patron of
Blake,” <hi rend="i">The Connoissuer</hi>, 19 (October 1907), 90-92, and G. E. Bentley, Jr., “Thomas Butts,
White Collar Maecenas,” <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi>, 71 (1956), 1052-66.</note></p>
          <pb id="p10-102" n="102"/>
          <p>The next drawing (illus. 5), measuring 130 × 100 mm., is more puzzling. It obviously depicts the
creation of Eve, and has been attributed to Blake in a pencil note on the reverse of the drawing itself, in
the same hand as the previously described note, and in exactly the same words. David Erdman and Martin Butlin
have both commented, on the basis of a good photograph, that the drawing is not by Blake, and that seems
clearly right. But the drawing has life and charm, and I should be glad to hear from any reader who has any
ideas about the identity of the artist.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12"
type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> To my eye there is some analogy with the floating Eve and relaxed Adam of
Fuseli’s painting of “The Creation of Eve,” though the drawing is clearly not by Fuseli.</note></p>
          <p>The collection also has two pairs of drawings which are certainly by Blake. One (illus. 6), 158
× 121 mm., is of a woman’s head, and was formerly described as a portrait of Blake’s wife. However,
Geoffrey Keynes in a recent letter has stated that it does not resemble any of the known portraits, and may be
a kind of visionary head. The drawing does show some resemblance in manner to the visionary head reproduced on
the cover of <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 5:1 (1972). The reverse is a very sketchy and faint drawing of a
woman’s torso (illus. 7).</p>
          <p>The other pair, measuring 275 × 213 mm., has as its recto (illus. 8) the drawing listed as No.
130 by W. M. Rossetti in his catalogue in the 1880 edition of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi>, and
reproduced there through the intermediary of an engraving by J. Hellawell.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> Rossetti gives it the tentative title of “Young burying
Narcissa (?),” referring to an episode in Night Three of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, though
adding
<figure n="BB487.1.1.COM" rend="file" width="644" height="1000"/>
<figure n="LadiesForgery.10.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="502">
	<head>2 The original 1783 plate of Miss Byron visiting Emily engraved by Blake for <hi rend="i">Sir Charles
Grandison</hi> in <hi rend="i">The Novelist’s Magazine</hi> (a) compared with the 1811 version (b).</head>
</figure>
<figure n="BB487.1.2.COM" rend="file" width="638" height="1000"/>
<pb id="p10-103" n="103"/>
<figure n="FencingForgery.10.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="552">
	<head>3 The original 1783 plate of Sir C. Grandison disarming Captain Salmonet (a) compared with the 1811
version (b).</head>
</figure>
<figure n="BB487.1.3.COM" rend="file" width="621" height="1000"/>
<figure n="WeepingForgery.10.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="536">
	<head>4 The original 1783 plate of Charlotte and Caroline with Sir C. Grandison (a) compared with the 1811
version (b)</head>
</figure>
<pb id="p10-104" n="104"/>
that “If the subject is the one surmised from Young, the introduction of these two children seems to be
Blake’s own addition to the narrative.” Martin Butlin in a letter agrees with me in being dubious about
this; he dates both this and the verso in the earlier 1780’s on stylistic grounds. The design is very
closely related to the illustration of “The Garden of Love” in <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, though
the atmosphere of the drawing is very far from the garden setting of the poem.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> See Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, 2nd ed.
(London: Macmillan, 1880), I, 132 and II, 268.</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> The design suggests to me the following lines from Blair’s 
<hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>:
<q>
The sickly Taper<lb/>
By glimmering thro’ thy low-brow’d misty Vaults,<lb/>
(Furr’d round with mouldy Damps, and ropy Slime,)<lb/>
Lets fall a supernumerary Horror,<lb/>
And only serves to make thy Night more irksome
</q>
(<hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> [London, 1743], p. 4, 11. 16-20), though the drawing is much earlier than
Blake’s designs for Cromek’s edition of 1808.
                        </note></p>
          <p>The verso drawing (illus. 9) is clearly a sickbed scene; the drawing is sketchy, but the sick
man’s face is strong. The number visible on the drawing identifies it as having once belonged to Joseph
Hogarth, a nineteenth-century print seller who acquired his Blakes from Tatham.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> See Martin Butlin, “Five Blakes from a Nineteenth-Century Scottish
Collection,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 25 (Summer 1973), p. 8.</note></p>
          <p>Finally, I shall describe a few items in the collection which in one way or another are
associated with William Roscoe, however indirectly. There are in the collection a number of woodblocks
attributed to Blake, usually in conjunction with another name. They come from a large collection of blocks,
many of which illustrated ballads, chapbooks, and children’s books of the late eighteenth and nineteenth
centuries. The blocks attributed to Blake have pencilled notations written on paper labels glued to the
blocks; the labels would appear at a guess to be early twentieth century, and are certainly not contemporary
with the blocks themselves. The information is puzzlingly specific but, so far, untraceable; for instance, one
block is said to belong to Thornton’s <hi rend="i">Virgil</hi>, but it does not illustrate the well-known
edition. Several of the others, which clearly form a series, are identified as “Trimmers Bible,” “Mrs.
Trimmer,” or “Historical.” The subjects would make it appear very possible that the blocks did illustrate
editions of Sarah Trimmer’s various works, but I have so far been unable to find any edition with these
illustrations.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> Photographs of the
blocks—made by filling them with talcum powder—have been sent to David Erdman and Robert Essick, who agree
that they are not by Blake, and they certainly do not look at all like his work as either designer or
engraver. <note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> It is possible that the attributions are in part simply
optimistic reflections of entry No. 132 in A. G. B. Russell, <hi rend="i">The Engravings of William Blake</hi>
(London: Grant Richards, 1912), though the information on the labels is quite specific.</note></p>
          <p>Perhaps the most interesting of these blocks are two (illus. 10) identified as illustrating a
Harris edition of <hi rend="i">The Butterfly’s Ball</hi>, the larger one attributed to “W. Blake &amp;
Flaxman” and the other to “W. Blake &amp; Craig.” The attributions seem highly unlikely; the blocks did not
illustrate the 1807 or 1808 Harris editions of Roscoe’s poem, nor is there anything in that poem that really
fits the scene depicted on the larger of the two blocks. But the information, though in part at least
certainly mistaken, is very specific, and the connection with Flaxman seems to make it certain that it was our
Blake who was intended. The annotations on other blocks, though sometimes misleading and mistaken,
<pb id="p10-105" n="105"/>
<figure n="ForestScene.10.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="381">
	<head>5 (far left) The Creation of Eve; by an unidentified artist.</head>
	<figDesc>Pencil drawing, McGill University.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="WomansHead.10.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="481">
	<head>6 (above left) Blake, a woman’s head.</head>
	<figDesc>Pencil drawing, McGill University.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="WomansTorso.10.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="426">
	<head>7 (above) Verso of illus. 6; pencil sketch of a woman’s torso by Blake.</head>
</figure>
have often proved helpful in tracing those blocks to the works that they originally illustrated. To my eye
there is a Blakean quality to the outlined clouds on the larger block, and these two factors make me a little
hesitant to reject the attribution outright.</p>
          <p>The blocks, however, sent me to William Roscoe’s poem, and my impression now is that Roscoe
knew Blake’s “A Dream” from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> The conjunction of emmet, beetle, and
glow-worm as watchman seems beyond coincidence. The poem was written about 1802,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> but first published in November 1806 in <hi rend="i">The
Gentleman’s Magazine.</hi> I quote the most relevant lines from the Harris chapbook edition of 1808:
<q>
And there came the <hi rend="i">Beetle</hi>, so blind and so black,<lb/>
Who carried the <hi rend="i">Emmet</hi>, his friend, on his Back.<lb/>
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
Then, as Evening gave Way to the Shadows of Night,<lb/>
Their Watchman, the <hi rend="i">Glow-worm</hi>, came out with a <hi rend="i">Light.</hi><lb/>
Then Home let us hasten, while yet we can see,<lb/>
For no Watchman is waiting for you and for me.<lb/>
So said little Robert, and pacing along,<lb/>
His merry Companions returned in a Throng.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">18</ref>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> The MS of the poem is dated January 1802; see George Chandler, 
<hi rend="i">William Roscoe of Liverpool</hi> (London: Batsford, 1953), p. 114.</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> The lines are quoted from <hi rend="i">The Butterfly’s Ball and the
Grasshopper’s Feast</hi>, A Facsimile Reproduction of the Edition of 1808, ed. Charles Welsh (London:
Griffith and Farran, 1883); see pp. iii-v, 5, and 7. Some later versions with the same title have a different
text. “A Dream” from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> is not one of the poems published by Malkin in 1806,
which is in any case too late; see <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, pp. 421-31.</note></q>
The last lines quoted are reminiscent of the design as well as mood of the second plate of “The Ecchoing
Green.” The poem moralizes just a little at the end, but is infinitely more playful that Watts’ poem about
emmets—in the generalizing plural, not the specific singular as in Blake and Roscoe.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref> The poem was enormously popular, and gave rise to many
sequels and imitations. Perhaps, in one way and another, Blake had more effect upon his contemporary world
than we usually realize. 
                        <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> See V. de Sola Pinto, “William Blake, Isaac Watts,
and Mrs. Barbauld,” in V. de Sola Pinto, ed., <hi rend="i">The Divine Vision</hi> (1957; rpt. New York:
Haskell House, 1968), pp. 76-78.</note></p>
          <p>Arnold Goldman has already written an article associating Blake with the Roscoes, suggesting that
W. Roscoe may very well have owned a copy of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> which influenced a poem
written by his son William Stanley Roscoe.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20"
type="note">20</ref> Both subscribed to Cromek’s edition of <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, presumably in
response to Cromek’s direct solicitation, since he arrived in Liverpool in 1806 armed with a letter of
introduction from Fuseli.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref> Roscoe was
building a library, and is known to have owned also Hayley’s <hi rend="i">The Life, and Posthumous Writings
of William Cowper</hi>, published in 1803 with six plates engraved by Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref> He not only collected books, but wrote an unpublished poem
on “The Origin of Engraving,” in addition to quite well-known poems attacking the slave-trade and
<pb id="p10-106" n="106"/>
<figure n="GilchristWash.10.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="378">
	<head>8 Pen and wash drawing by Blake, No. 130 in Rossetti’s catalogue in the 1880 edition of
Gilchrist.</head>
	<figDesc>McGill University.</figDesc>
</figure>
welcoming the French Revolution.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref> He
knew Johnson, Hayley, Cromek, and Fuseli—Fuseli very well. Fuseli wrote to him mentioning Blake at least
twice, once in 1792 telling Roscoe about two of his Milton paintings that were “intended for Blake,” and again
in 1798, this time commending Blake for the excellence of his handling of drapery in the engraving of
Fuseli’s “Fertilization of Egypt” for Darwin’s <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden.</hi><supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref> The letter clearly implies that Roscoe would
recognize Blake’s name. Cromek has a comment that links the two together in a letter to James Montgomery: “I
am certain—and it is the opinion of M. Roscoe &amp; M<hi rend="s">r</hi>. Blake as well as myself—that
your volume will <hi rend="i">command</hi> the applause &amp; admiration of all good Men, &amp; of all Lovers
of the Higher kinds of Poetry.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref>
Given Roscoe’s interests, and his contacts in Blake’s circle, it would be almost surprising if the two had
had no contact. There is no record of his owning a copy of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, but there is no
difficulty in believing that he might have seen one, and there is good evidence for his interest in
illuminated manuscripts of an earlier era.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26"
type="note">26</ref>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Arnold Goldman, “Blake and the Roscoes,” <hi rend="i">N&amp;Q</hi>, 210
[N.S. 12] (1965), 178-82.</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> See Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 179.</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Goldman, “Blake and the Roscoes,” pp. 179-80.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> For the poem on engraving, see Henry Roscoe, 
	<hi rend="i">The Life of William Roscoe</hi> (London: Cadell, and Edinburgh: 
	Blackwood, 1833), 1, 67; for Roscoe on the slave-trade and the French 
	Revolution, see Chandler, <hi rend="i">William Roscoe</hi>, pp. 60-70. Roscoe’s 
	“The Song for the Anniversary of the French Revolution, Liverpool, 
	14<hi rend="s">th</hi> July, 1791” was a great success, and though the 
	<hi rend="i">Song</hi> was published anonymously, Priestley knew of Roscoe’s 
	authorship (Chandler, p. 70). Chandler also cites evidence (p. 83) that Roscoe sent 
	Fuseli a copy of his unsigned ballad attacking Burke. Roscoe’s poems clearly 
	circulated among Blake’s friends and acquaintances.</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> For Roscoe’s friendship with Fuseli, see Hugh Macandrew, “Henry Fuseli
and William Roscoe,” <hi rend="i">Walker Art Gallery Bulletin</hi>, 8 (1959-1960), 5-32. For Fuseli’s
letters to Roscoe about Blake, see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, pp. 46-47, and Hugh Macandrew,
“Selected Letters from the Correspondence of Henry Fuseli and William Roscoe of Liverpool,” 
<hi rend="i">Gazette des Beaux-Arts</hi>, 62 (July-December 1963), 218. Bentley appears to have missed this second
letter, which constitutes another contemporary reference to Blake.</note>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi> The letter is quoted by G. E. Bentley, Jr., “Blake and Cromek: The Wheat
and the Tares,” <hi rend="i">MP</hi>, 71 (1974), 373.</note>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> See Chandler, <hi rend="i">William Roscoe</hi>, pp. 16, 107.</note></p>
          <p>The collection has one more item related to Roscoe, a copy of <hi rend="i">Religious Emblems,
Being a series of Engravings on Wood</hi>, published in 1809 with designs by Thurston and descriptions written
by Joseph Thomas, a major patron of Blake. As Leslie Parris has pointed out, the presence of such names as
Cromek, Flaxman, and Fuseli in the list of subscribers make it very probable that the “William Blake, Esq.”
also listed is our poet.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref> The present
copy has been inscribed to Roscoe by the authors, and was doubtless the immediate cause of the fulsome
testimonial from Roscoe that Parris records as present in a copy of the work in his possession which had
probably belonged to either Thomas or Thurston. The inscription to Roscoe reads thus: “M<hi rend="s">r</hi>..
Thomas and M<hi rend="s">r</hi>.. Thurston request M<hi rend="s">r</hi>.. Roscoes’ acceptance of this work,
in testimony, of the high sense they entertain of his distinguished talents and likewise as a mark of their
ESTEEM. While [White?] Grove, Epsom Sept<hi rend="s">r</hi>.. 1<hi rend="s">st</hi>.. 1809.” The volume also
contains a bookplate <corr type="emend">identifying</corr> it as being <hi rend="i">ex libris</hi> William
Malin Roscoe, Roscoe’s great-grandson, dated 1897. Roscoe’s library was dispersed by auction after his
bankruptcy in 1816, but Roscoe specifically stated that he was withholding from the auction books given him by
their authors, and this volume was doubtless among those which thus remained in the family.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">28</ref> The language of the inscription is rather
formal, but certainly is one more piece of evidence, however minor, linking Roscoe with Blake’s circle of
friends and patrons. <note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> Leslie Parris, “William Blake’s Mr. Thomas,” 
<hi rend="i">TLS</hi>, 5 December 1968, p. 1390. See also <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, 165-66.</note>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">28</hi> Henry Roscoe, <hi rend="i">Life of William Roscoe</hi>, p.
118.</note></p>
          <p>The connections made here between Blake and William Roscoe are all indirect, but I hope that they
are suggestive. The work of piecing together a fuller picture of Blake’s relationship with the society of
his time is a continuing process, and the kinds of information that can be found in collections such as that
at McGill can help to fill in the details of that growing picture.</p>
          <pb id="p10-107" n="107"/>
          <figure n="PencilandWash.10.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="382">
            <head>9 Verso of illus. 8; pen, pencil and wash drawing by Blake, McGill University.</head>
          </figure>
        </div2>
        <pb id="p10-108" n="108"/>
        <figure n="ButterflyWoodblock.10.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="87"/>
        <figure n="ButterflyBall.10.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="218">
          <head>10 Photographs (reversed) of two woodblocks described as illustrating a Harris edition of 
<hi rend="i">The Butterfly’s Ball</hi>, the larger (61 × 57 mm.)</head>
          <figDesc>attributed to “W. Blake &amp; Flaxman,” the smaller (76 × 21 mm.) attributed to “W. Blake
and Craig.”</figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
