<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>11.1.mulhallen</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Robert Essick and Jenijoy La Belle, eds., Night Thoughts on the Complaint
and Consolation</title>
                <author n="Mulhallen">Karen Mulhallen</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1977</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1977</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">11.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Brad Hayden</name>
                            <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
                            <name>Michael Hays</name>
                            <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
                            <name>Jane Welford</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>John Beer</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Raymond Deck</name>
                            <name>Thomas Dilworth</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
                            <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
                            <name>Donald L. Kent</name>
                            <name>Vivian Mercier</name>
                            <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
                            <name>Dennis Read</name>
                            <name>Grant C. Roti</name>
                            <name>Richard J. Schroyer</name>
                            <name>Ruthven Todd</name>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1977"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_11">
        <body>
            <pb id="p11-41" n="41"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-11-1-0010">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">Reviews</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <figure n="NightThoughts.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="100" height="127"/>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Robert Essick and Jenijoy La Belle, editors. <hi rend="i">Night
                                Thoughts</hi> or <hi rend="i">the Complaint and the
                                Consolation.</hi> Illustrated by William Blake. Text by Edward
                            Young. New York: Dover, 1975. pp. xxx + 95. $4.00 paper.</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Karen <name>Mulhallen</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>This publication consists of the complete text of Richard Edwards’
                        1797 edition of Edward Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>,
                        accompanied by reproductions, reduced 35% from the originals, of
                        Blake’s forty three engravings, as well as editorial
                        material—a two-page introduction, a thirteen page critical
                        commentary, and a two-page annotated bibliography. Though the 1797 <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> isn’t scarce—copies
                        appear each season at auction and in booksellers’
                        catalogues—it has become increasingly costly, and its importance
                        for any study of Blake’s art, as well as its intrinsic beauty,
                        have made a facsimile desirable. There is still such a need, but the present
                        edition, along with the descriptive bibliographic notes in Easson and
                        Essick’s <hi rend="i">William Blake: Book Illustrator</hi>, is a
                        useful substitute for the original.</p>
                    <p>Let’s consider the quality of the reproductions in the present
                        edition before turning to the usefulness of the supplementary material and
                        commentary. Something of the compelling beauty of Blake’s
                        original engravings was conveyed in the <hi rend="i">Library Companion</hi>
                        (1824) by Thomas Frognall Dibdin who recounted how “amidst the wild
                        uproar of the wintry elements—when piping winds are howling for
                        entrance round every corner of the turretted chamber” he loved to
                        read “the text of Young which has been embellished by the pencil of
                        Blake.” Scale was an arresting feature of Blake’s
                        originals—especially when viewed next to Stothard’s or
                        even Westall’s designs. The reduction in the present edition
                        makes the overall page appear busy, gray and even claustrophobic. The airy
                        personification of Night on page 1, for example, has no room to soar. The
                        figure of the sleepless shepherd-poet becomes more decorative than engaging.
                        And when Death, with his emblems, appears to the sleepless poet, on page 7,
                        the urgency conveyed by the original scene is absent. Airy supernaturalish,
                        dynamic confrontations, the recognition of giant forms who inhabit at once
                        several dimensions—these aspects, ineffables perhaps, are
                        distorted by reduction. Of course, to claim that on page [17]
                        Time’s scythe—in the original as long as this
                        reader’s forearm—is decoratively tame rather than
                        menacing is rather subjective. But when, as on page 37, in the ambiguous
                        depiction of Christ as a good Samaritan, the mood of a scene is conveyed by
                        hanging that scene on a vast tree, which expresses the oppressiveness of the
                        vegetable world, then diminution becomes a critical element of
                        interpretation.</p>
                    <p>Two last niggling points about the printing of this Dover edition. Because of
                        the complex and remarkable way the 1797 <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> was
                        printed, there are numerous variations in the copies of the first edition,
                        and my <corr type="emend">comparison</corr> of this reproduction with the 1797 edition
in the Toronto
                        Public Library turned up an anticipated number of variations, such as the
                        presence of inscriptions on different pages. An unexpected 
<corr type="emend">difference,</corr>
                        however, was found in the use of borders in the reproduction. We can see
                        this clearly on page 24, where the word “Pub<hi rend="s">d</hi>.” is cut off in
Essick’s original inscription,
                        which should, therefore, begin “June” at the exact
                        lefthand edge of the page. Instead, there’s a border of
                        approximately 7/16 of an inch. Such borders—appearing along the
                        bottom and the top, as well as, more irregularly, along the inner and outer
                        edges—make Blake’s designs, which no longer occupy the
                        whole space, rather picturesque, as borders and frames tend to do. Christ
                        triumphant, page [65], who leaps up in the original design, is now tamed.
                        Finally, although the tonal quality is generally not problematic, on page 80
                        the feeling of reflected light on the man who prays by the seashore, and the
                        delicate gradations in tone in the whole engraving, have disappeared, so
                        that the man, who looks awestruck in the original, appears fearful in the
                        reproduction.</p>
                    <p>The editorial material—introduction, commentary, and
                        bibliography—is excellent, concise, and sensitive to
                        Blake’s iconography. And it also acknowledges Young’s
                        importance for Blake. The plate-by-plate commentary is non-partisan and
                        stimulating. In discussing, for example, the hunter Nimrod on page 70,
                        Essick and Labelle point to both the Genesis reference and iconographic
                        resemblences in Blake’s later and earlier work. Similarly, they
                        present several translations for the Hebrew letters on the scroll of the
                        King of Terrors, page 63. Yet, partly as a result of brevity, and partly
                        because of problems in their critical stance, a few “little
                        monsters” of caution appear.</p>
                    <p>Even had we not Blake’s enormous output of <hi rend="i">Night
                            Thought</hi> designs as evidence, we need to assume that Blake respected
                        the poet whose work he agreed to illustrate. And the poem enjoyed a
                        considerable contemporary reputation. The <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
                        was an international best-seller <hi rend="i">and</hi> a major artistic
                        force—influencing Goethe’s <hi rend="i">Werther</hi>
                        and Klopstock’s <hi rend="i">Messiah.</hi> Burns quoted the poem
                        in his letters; Coleridge and Wordsworth echoed it in verse. I think that
                        Essick and La Belle overstress the illustrations where Blake criticizes
                        Young. And when Blake does criticize, it is quite legitimate in his task as
                        an illustrator. To criticize is not to disparage. On page 72, for example,
                        there is a moving hymn by Young in which he would “drink the spirit
                        of the golden day.” Surely here the poet has not, as the editors
                        contend, “forgot the visionary themes of salvation and
                        resurrection.” And the editors might allow that on page 80 the poet
                        is rejecting the “nameless HE” for Christ, a position
                        Blake would commend.</p>
                    <p>Let’s leave the question of attitude and look briefly at tactical
                        issues. First a caveat against explaining any of Blake’ designs
                        with quotations from his poetry of a later period. Essick and Labelle
                        unnecessarily quote <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> plate 26, to 
<pb id="p11-42" n="42"/>
explicate the title page to the first Night; also against
                        assuming Blake’s “iconographic consistency” (p.
                        xiii). How would the editors explain the cup held by the child about to be
                        cut down by Time, on page 26? Such a cup is often associated in Blake with
                        bacchic figures and with the Scarlet Whore. Hence, it is ordinarily a
                        sinister icon. Odd that it appears in the hands of a child. It is true that
                        the editors express a mild reservation about iconographic consistency (p.
                        viii), but the assumption should be that Blake adapted his images to his
                        context.</p>
                    <p>The editors’ commendable compression of iconographic material has
                        led to small omissions and overstatements. The <corr type="emend">design,</corr> on
page 90, of Christ
                        touching an “afflicted” man is said to be “almost
                        identical” to the frontispiece for Blake’s <hi rend="i">There Is No Natural
Religion</hi>, second series, and to those two
                        figures in the lower right corner of “The Divine Image” in
                            <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> The “same basic
                        motif” is pointed out in “The Chimney Sweeper” in
                            <hi rend="i">Innocence.</hi> Yet, among these designs the editors should
                        have drawn an important distinction. In “The Chimney
                        Sweeper” and the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs the two
                        figures touch; in “The Divine Image” and <hi rend="i">There Is No Natural
Religion</hi> they do not. Hence, while all four
                        designs share the theme of resurrection, in only two is there a touch which
                        humanizes the action.</p>
                    <p>The process of iconographic selection is always complex. Very rarely in this
                        edition does that selection appear indelicate. It does seem significant,
                        however, that the “spiritual presences,”
                        “Angels,” on page 93, are wingless. In the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> Blake
often uses winged creatures for ascension,
                        and wingless beings for visitations.</p>
                    <p>I think that it is more often in the designs with clear Biblical referents
                        (particularly pages [43], 72, 80, 88) that the editors’
                        interpretations seem to demand the reader’s critical attention.
                        On the title page for the third Night, the woman clothed in the sun is
                        pregnant. Through her pregnancy she may escape the endless revolutions of
                        time, turn time to eternity. (Nonetheless, the verso in the water colors
                        shows her even more a prisoner.) On page 88, where Jacob wrestles with an
                        “angel,” it is the equality of man and God that Blake
                        seems to stress, an equality quite consistent with the Biblical account and
                        with Blake’s emphasis throughout the <hi rend="i">Night
                            Thoughts.</hi> (It’s an emphasis which also shows
                        Blake’s preparedness for the Bible illustrations done for
                        Butts.)</p>
                    <p>Can we offer an overall interpretation for the <hi rend="i">Night
                            Thoughts</hi> engravings? The editors don’t suggest one,
                        though many of their comments are interpretative. The repetition of images
                        and of the figures of Death, Time, and Christ do unify the designs and
                        suggest, as Fuseli wrote of Blake’s designs for
                        Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>, that they “form of
                        themselves a most interesting Poem.” With one exception all of the
                        Christ images appear in the fourth Night. Thus, the grouping of the figures
                        suggests a progression from the world of Time and Death to a world informed
                        by Christ—a progression in keeping with the movement of the
                        poem.</p>
                    <p>Since the Dover edition is for the general reader, its annotated bibliography
                        is quite properly short. It is short as well because there’s been
                        little work done on the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi> The major studies
                        are listed, though some interesting brief mentions of the <hi rend="i">Night
                            Thoughts</hi>, such as John Grant’s in <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Newsletter</hi> 13, pp. 23-24, are omitted. The first entry in the
                        chronological bibliography is out of order. If the editors wish to consider
                        Thomas Edwards as their first entry, his name should be listed, along with
                        the titles of his catalogues. I must quarrel as well with the fifth entry,
                        which dismisses Adeline Butterworth’s <hi rend="i">William Blake,
                            Mystic.</hi> Butterworth was, after all, the first to reproduce both the
                        engravings and the full text of the first two Nights. Her reproductions of
                        the engravings are by no means “poor-quality”; the paper
                        stock on which they are printed is superior to that of the Dover
                        edition.</p>
                    <p>Despite its minor failings, many of them deriving, as I have suggested, from
                        compression and the exeqencies of commercial printing, Essick and La Belle
                        have performed a service for students of Blake. Like Robespierre, we can all
                        go to the guillotine with the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, now
                        “embellished by the pencil of Blake,” in our pockets.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>