<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>11.1.m</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="minute">Holy Thursday</title>
                <author n="M">M.</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1977</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1977</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">11.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Brad Hayden</name>
                            <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
                            <name>Michael Hays</name>
                            <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
                            <name>Jane Welford</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>John Beer</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Raymond Deck</name>
                            <name>Thomas Dilworth</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
                            <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
                            <name>Donald L. Kent</name>
                            <name>Vivian Mercier</name>
                            <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
                            <name>Dennis Read</name>
                            <name>Grant C. Roti</name>
                            <name>Richard J. Schroyer</name>
                            <name>Ruthven Todd</name>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1977"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_11">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-11-1-0009">
				<pb id="p11-38" n="38"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">Holy Thursday</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <hi rend="b">By</hi>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">M.</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>Sir Geoffrey Keynes recently called our attention to the following letter,
                        which appeared in the <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi>, 23 (1 July 1807),
                        554-56. 
						<q>
                            <hi rend="i">To the Editor of the Monthly Magazine.</hi>
                            <lb/>
 SIR,<lb/>
                            HAVING attended the annual meeting of the charity-children at St.
                            Paul’s, on the 28th of last month, I can hardly find words to
                            express how highly I was gratified, as well with the spectacle of
                            upwards of six thousand poor children clothed, maintained and educated
                            at the public expence, as with the astonishing effect produced by the
                            union of sounds from so many voices, chanting the praises of their great
                            Creator.<lb/>
 I should not, however, have troubled you with this, were
                            it not at the same time to transmit some observations I made whilst
                            there, in the hope, that by communicating them to the public through
                            your widely-extended miscellany, they 
<pb id="p11-39" n="39"/>
may be
                            attended to by those concerned, and the effect of the whole improved to
                            the greatest degree possible.<lb/>
 As I was there pretty early, and
                            before many of the children had taken their places, the first
                            observation I made was that, notwithstanding the immense theatre erected
                            and provision made, there was yet hardly sufficient room to accommodate
                            the whole of the different schools; many of the children finding a
                            difficulty in seating themselves, and, when settled, were much crowded.
                            Owing to this probably it was, that some few were occasionally had down
                            to the schoolmistresses below, to be plied with smelling-bottles to be
                            kept from fainting. And this would perhaps have happened to a much
                            greater degree, had not the day been as favourable as possibly could
                            have been for the purpose, without either rain or extreme heat.<lb/>
 As
                            each school must doubtless be made acquainted with the number of seats
                            allotted to it, this inconvenience might certainly be remedied, by
                            leaving as many of the younger children behind, (whose voices can hardly
                            be expected to add much to the general effect,) as may enable the
                            remainder to be well accommodated.<lb/>
 My next observation was upon the
                            choir of St. Paul’s, which sang alone in the Te Deum and
                            Jubilate, and in the greater part of the Coronation-Anthem and
                            Hallelujah from the Messiah, and which appeared to me to be much too
                            weak for that occasion, especially after the charity-children had added
                            their voices in the two latter; contrasted to the immense force of which
                            the choir seemed as it were annihilated; scarcely any thing but the
                            organ (at least where I sat) being to be heard. Surely upon so great an
                            occasion as this may justly be reckoned, the choirs of the Chapel Royal
                            and Westminster Abbey might be requested to lend their assistance, as at
                            the Festival for the Sons of the Clergy, with which aid the contrast
                            would not be carried to such an extreme, as must be the case with a
                            single choir opposed to such a force.<lb/>
 My third observation was upon
                            the performance of the charity-children themselves, whose extreme
                            steadiness and accuracy was astonishing, and did the highest credit as
                            well to themselves, as to the persons that had instructed them. In,
                            however, the beginning of the 100th psalm, with which the service
                            commenced, the effect was not so great as I had expected, owing probably
                            to a want of courage in many of the children, which might prevent their
                            putting out their voices so much as they did in the latter verses. But
                            in the 118th Psalm, before the Sermon, they made ample amends, as
                            nothing, I think, could exceed the wonderful and striking effect
                            occasioned by the transition from the full chorus, to the voices of the
                            girls alone on one side, and thence again to the full chorus, as was
                            also the ease in the Hallelujah succeeding it. The cathedral responses
                            and amens too were very accurately performed by them, and well in time.
                            I cannot, however, help thinking, but that, in the Coronation-Anthem,
                            and Hallelujah chorus from the Messiah, a considerable improvement in
                            the effect may yet be made, by a different arrangement of the air, or
                            tune, in the parts where the children join, by not merely taking the
                            treble notes, to which the melody is by no means confined. For when the
                            composer thus formed his score, he naturally supposed that the different
                            voices would in general be pretty equally arranged, and that therefore
                            it would be of little consequence whether the principal air was in the
                            treble or any other part. Could he however have foreseen that, upon some
                            future occasions, there would be about two thousand trebles, (supposing
                            only a third part of the children to sing in these chorusses,) to about
                            three or four tenors and basses, or had the present annual meeting and
                            performance been instituted in his time, he would undoubtedly in the
                            full chorus have thrown the air as much as possible into that 
<pb id="p11-40" n="40"/>
part, which cannot so justly be said to
                            predominate over the others, as to drown and annihilate them. My
                            principal allusion is to the first three bars of the last movement of
                            the Coronation-Anthem, “God save the King,”
                            &amp;c, and the same as repeated towards the end, which as a loyal
                                <hi rend="i">exclamation</hi> in unison, appears striking enough,
                            but can hardly be called singing, being nearly all upon one note. As,
                            therefore, the air is here evidently sung by the counter-tenors and
                            tenors, supported by the violins in the octave above, I should propose
                            in these three bars, the boys taking the counter-tenor part, and the
                            girls the tenor in the octave above, or in unison with the second violin
                            part. And this, being in fact but one bar three times repeated, need not
                            startle those who with great reason object to the children being taught
                            to sing in parts, to which I would make this the sole exception. In like
                            manner, as at the repetition of the same words in the key of A at the
                            17th bar, the principal air is in the tenor part; I would have the
                            children taught to sing that part in the octave above, instead of the
                            proper treble part, as being likely to produce a more striking
                            effect.<lb/>
 In other parts of the Coronation-Anthem, and in the
                            Hallelujah chorus, similar improvements may be made, by selecting such
                            parts from the score, as have most air or time in them, for the children
                            to sing, either in unison or in the octave above, as may best suit their
                            voices.<lb/>
 I have yet a fourth observation to mention which I made,
                            viz, the want of an organ of more power in the bass to qualify the
                            prodigious strength of treble; although Mr. Attwood, by his full and
                            judicious accompaniment, made the most that he could of that, (upon all
                            other occasions as it may be reckoned,) compleat and noble instrument.
                            Indeed, since these annual meetings have been established, one cannot
                            but lament that the proposal of Mr. Renatus Harris, mentioned in the
                            552d number of the Spectator, of erecting an organ of the greatest
                            powers and dimensions over the great west door of the cathedral, has not
                            since been carried into execution. The present organ, however, might be
                            enlarged for this occasion, by the exchange of the trumpet stop for one
                            of more power than the present, and addition of a double trumpet bass,
                            with likewise (if room should be found,) a clarion, or octave trumpet.
                            With these powerful reed stops, and additional voices proposed, there
                            would be something considerable left when the childrens’
                            voices cease in the Coronation Anthem, &amp;c. and in the full
                            chorus the great force of the trebles would be qualified and contrasted
                            by a bass bearing some proportion to it, and a grandeur would be given
                            to the whole, which would wonderfully improve the general effect. Should
                            however the additions to the organ here proposed, be not found
                            practicable or expedient, then perhaps one or two bass trombones, used
                            merely when all the children sing, might answer the purpose.<lb/>
 I
                            cannot conclude without paying my small tribute of approbation to Mr.
                            Page, as well for the very great pains he must have taken, and time he
                            must have bestowed, in preparing the children at the different schools
                            so as to enable them to perform by ear, and without the least knowledge
                            of the science, with such great accuracy and precision; as for his
                            clear, distinct, and animated manner of conducting so large an
                            assemblage of voices, actuated as it were by one mind; thereby producing
                            an effect that is probably not equalled in Europe.<lb/>
                            Your’s, &amp;c. M. </q>
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>