<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>11.1.beer</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Geoffrey Keynes, The Marriage of Heaven and Hell: A reproduction, with introduction and
commentary</title>
                <author n="Beer">John Beer</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1977</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1977</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">11.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Brad Hayden</name>
                            <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
                            <name>Michael Hays</name>
                            <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
                            <name>Jane Welford</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>John Beer</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Raymond Deck</name>
                            <name>Thomas Dilworth</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
                            <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
                            <name>Donald L. Kent</name>
                            <name>Vivian Mercier</name>
                            <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
                            <name>Dennis Read</name>
                            <name>Grant C. Roti</name>
                            <name>Richard J. Schroyer</name>
                            <name>Ruthven Todd</name>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1977"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_11">
        <body>
	<pb id="p11-42" n="42"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-11-1-0010">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">Reviews</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <figure n="Marriage.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="100" height="74"/>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> by William Blake. A
                            reproduction, with introduction and commentary by Geoffrey Keynes.
                            Oxford University Press, London &amp; New York, in association with
                            The Trianon Press, Paris. $16.95 cloth; $7.95 paper.</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>John <name>Beer</name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>This new edition of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, issued
                        as it is at a reasonable price, marks an important step in making
                        Blake’s work available to the ordinary reader in the form in
                        which he meant it to be seen. For the Blake specialist who already has
                        access to existing facsimiles through a good library it will serve a further
                        important purpose. In recent years it has become clear that a new dimension
                        of Blake’s work opens when one looks at the various copies which
                        he executed throughout his life, since almost all of them show interesting
                        variations from one another. It is in some ways a subsidiary enterprise,
                        since there is no evidence that these various executions betray any
                        fundamental change of mind about a book, once constructed, but they can
                        still give evidence of the continuing processes of his mind: the themes
                        which he may now wish to emphasize by rearrangement, by the insertion of an
                        additional plate or plates, or by the different perspectives on a text which
                        can be given through the choice of different colors or the emphasis on
                        particular visual motifs.</p>
                    <p>The pioneers in this enterprise have been David Erdman and his associates,
                        who have described such variations in detail, but there is a limit to what
                        an individual scholar can do, particularly when, as must often happen, he is
                        forced to carry some differences in his head from one copy to another. It is
                        even more difficult to convey them to other readers 
<pb id="p11-43" n="43"/>
                        through the printed description. The slide lecture (as David Erdman has
                        found) is often the best way of communicating such discoveries.</p>
                    <p>The publication of this edition marks an important step in remedying this
                        situation, since the copy it reproduces, copy I (Keynes-Wolf) in the
                        Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge, often thought to be the finest of all, is one
                        that has not so far been available. (It could not be produced as the
                        original Trianon Press facsimile, since the Fitzwilliam, for understandable
                        reasons, has been unwilling to send its copies to Paris for the dismantling
                        which would be inevitable under that process.) As a result of this
                        initiative, a scholar anywhere in the world now has the chance of comparing
                        three versions: this one; copy H (Keynes-Wolf) in the Fitzwilliam
                        (reproduced in Max Plowman’s 1927 facsimile); and the Rosenwald
                        copy, reproduced in the Trianon Press facsimile. No printed description can
                        reproduce the experience of comparing say, the slightly sombre effect of
                        copy H, with its cavernous enclosures here and there, and the brighter,
                        rainbow effect of copy I.</p>
                    <p>The new edition is reproduced with an introduction, a reading text and an
                        arrangement of the reproduction so that two pages of reproduction are
                        regularly interspersed with two of commentary, allowing the plates to appear
                        facing one another as in the original. This is the most satisfactory way of
                        reproducing within the traditional book format, though it might be
                        worthwhile to experiment with an arrangement which would make it possible
                        for pages of interpretation to be pulled out <hi rend="i">beyond</hi> the
                        plates and so to be read side by side with the open text.</p>
                    <p>The commentary, as we have come to expect from Sir Geoffrey Keynes, is
                        uncluttered, clear and very much to the point. He wastes little time over
                        previous interpretations, with the important exception of David
                        Erdman’s 1973 essay on the interlinear drawings. He is, indeed,
                        brisk to the point of being almost cavalier with his predecessors: of the
                        two books he does mention, Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet
                            against Empire</hi> is given only the second part of its title, together
                        with a date which is that of the second, revised edition, no mention being
                        made of the first, while Sabri-Tabrizi is turned into Fabri-Tabrizi.</p>
                    <p>The problem with any running commentary on Blake is that it cannot give the
                        reader the initial bearings that he needs before entering the world of the
                        prophetic books. Simple identifications of Blake’s personages
                        with human qualities or physical functions will not normally do unless the
                        reader has some grasp of the larger pattern of what is going on. I do not
                        think there is a simple answer to this problem: each reader has to match
                        readings of the larger interpretations against scrutiny of the text itself
                        until he finds a reading that works for him. So far as running commentary
                            <hi rend="i">is</hi> possible, however, this one is good. Some important
                        points are missed out: the reader will not learn anywhere that the Memorable
                        Fancies are satirical versions of Swedenborg’s Memorable
                        Relations, for example. Some of the identifications strike one as
                        over-simplistic: to see Rintrah simply as “Wrath,” for
                        instance, is to suggest a kind of crude animism which is not characteristic
                        of Blake’s work. I am also unhappy with references to
                        “materialism” and “the spiritual” in
                        commentaries on Blake, for when run together they suggest adherence to a
                        dichotomy between the material and the spiritual which was foreign to his
                        purposes. When, for example, the illustration at the head of plate 11,
                        showing various figures of land and sea, is described as “nature in
                        its spiritual forms,” I find it more natural to refer to the text
                        immediately beneath (“The Ancient Poets animated all sensible
                        objects with Gods or Geniuses,” etc.) which it seems to be
                        illustrating very closely. Blake’s spirits interpenetrate the
                        material to an extraordinary and unaccustomed degree, drastically changing
                        the meaning of the word “spiritual” from conventional
                        usage.</p>
                    <p>One or two other disagreements may be briefly noted. Keynes interprets
                        “Now is the dominion of Edom and the return of Adam into
                        Paradise” as meaning that Adam has already returned into Paradise;
                        I would read it more in the Biblical form which would suggest “Now
                        is the time for . . . ”: that is, as an announcement of
                        potentiality and anticipation rather than a statement of achieved fact. On
                        plate 11 he remarks that “a serpent was not infrequently
                        Blake’s symbol for the priest of organized religion.”
                        Although the Prester Serpent of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> might
                        support such an identification, I cannot offhand think of other instances
                        where it is explicit. The serpent is always, primarily, Blake’s
                        figure for energy (this is one of the few instances where a straightforward
                        identification does work); only a fallen, sneaking serpent would do for the
                        organized priesthood. Similarly I would not agree that the male figure
                        shackled in flames on page 4 “can only be Blake’s
                        devil”: he can also, for example, be the male shackled under the
                        Law. In such cases, Keynes’s own <hi rend="i">caveat</hi> on
                        interpretations of the interlinear decorations—that they are
                        “not always easy and must be regarded as sometimes
                        conjectural”—may profitably be extended to
                        interpretations of the text as well.</p>
                    <p>The interpretations of the interlinear figures just referred to are, on the
                        other hand, one of the most valuable features of the new edition. The main
                        problem is to know whether in some cases they are straightforward
                        illustrations of the neighboring texts, or counterpointing images of energy
                        (as sometimes seems to be the case in the Song of Liberty). Cautious as one
                        has to be with Blake’s left/right symbolism, something of the
                        sort seems to be at work here, since figures on the right are often under
                        the dominion of reason, with a greater emphasis on energy as one looks along
                        to the left.</p>
                    <p>What of the reproduction? Arnold Fawcus, of the Trianon Press, states in his
                        foreword—“The result, we feel, is as close to the
                        original as can be obtained by a photo-mechanical
                        process”—which is fair. The blurb on the dust-jacket,
                        however, claims that the reproduced plates are “of an accuracy and
                        delicacy which Blake himself would have admired”—which
                        is at the very least questionable—and speaks of their
                        “excellence”—which is certainly too strong a
                        word. The editor, likewise, claims that the reproduction is “in all
                        respects . . . most satisfactory”—which again is
                        somewhat misleading—and is at pains to dispel doubts about the
                        accuracy of register in the lettering which are in fact well
                        founded—at least on the highest standards.</p>
                    <pb id="p11-44" n="44"/>
                    <p>For the plain fact (which will no doubt come as a surprise to many readers)
                        is that the facsimile reproduction which H. John Dent made of the other
                        Fitzwilliam copy of the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> fifty years ago, though
                        by no means perfect, is a good deal closer to its original than is this one.
                        In Dent’s facsimile, colors are sometimes darker than the
                        original, Blake’s brown is a little too orange and occasionally a
                        background tint is out; but in other respects the rendering is extremely
                        faithful. This is less so in the present case. The most glaring difference
                        is that Blake used gilt on many of the plates, which both added a touch of
                        subtle brilliance and pointed the imagery of energy. It was no doubt
                        impossible to manage this with a reproduction based on photography (though,
                        again, Dent managed it for his facsimile in 1927), but the omission should
                        at least have been noted somewhere in the edition; I can find no mention of
                        it. I have also noted a number of further differences, primarily in
                        coloring, from the original: this is not intended in any way to be an
                        exhaustive list, simply a note of those differences which have struck me
                        most forcibly in comparing the plates.</p>
                    <table rows="11" cols="2">
                        <row>
                            <cell>Plate 2</cell>
                            <cell>The colors rendered as yellow and orange-brown in the trees and
                                foliage are green and green-brown in the original.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>The “line effect” on the flames is not as
                                defined as, and the colors are more purple than, the original, which
                                is more orange-brown.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>4-5</cell>
                            <cell>In the original, colors are lighter and more delicate, giving
                                better definition to the faces, in particular.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8</cell>
                            <cell>There is a strong orange effect throughout here, as against the
                                dominant yellow-green effect of the original.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>9</cell>
                            <cell>A light brown appears, similarly—as against the
                                dominant yellows and blues of the original.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>10</cell>
                            <cell>The blues are much stronger, throughout, than in the
                                original.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>12</cell>
                            <cell>The head title is mauve, as against the orange-red of the
                                original.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>14 &amp; 16</cell>
                            <cell>(and elsewhere). The lettering gives a fuzzier and lighter effect
                                than in the original.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>18-19</cell>
                            <cell>The lettering in the blue-green passages is much darker than in
                                the originals, giving a false effect of strong contrast between
                                these and other sections of the text.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>21</cell>
                            <cell>In the head design the purple is very much exaggerated; in the
                                darker sections of the first five lines there is a red effect which
                                is absent from the original.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>24</cell>
                            <cell>The effect is much bolder than in the original.</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>In many cases of course the effect is surprisingly good, and it is obviously
                        necessary to preserve a sense of proportion in making such criticisms. This
                        copy is on any terms a beautiful book, reasonable value at the price and one
                        which most people, including myself, will be glad to have on their shelves.
                        For many purposes, and especially that of comparison with other reproduced
                        versions, mentioned earlier, it will be invaluable. The point at issue is
                        simply that the imprint of the Trianon Press, along with the superlatives
                        used in descriptions of the reproductions, may give many readers the
                        impression that this book is of the same quality as that of the limited
                        editions. An extra qualifying word here or there would have been enough to
                        guard against such a false impression. This reservation aside, Arnold
                        Fawcus, Sir Geoffrey Keynes and the Oxford University Press are to be
                        congratulated (— can hardly, indeed, be sufficiently praised) for
                        bringing this book within the grasp of the ordinary reader.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>