<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>11.1.quarterly</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">Blake An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                <author n="Eaves">Morris Eaves</author>
                <author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1977</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1977</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">11.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Brad Hayden</name>
                            <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
                            <name>Michael Hays</name>
                            <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
                            <name>Jane Welford</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>John Beer</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Raymond Deck</name>
                            <name>Thomas Dilworth</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
                            <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
                            <name>Donald L. Kent</name>
                            <name>Vivian Mercier</name>
                            <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
                            <name>Dennis Read</name>
                            <name>Grant C. Roti</name>
                            <name>Richard J. Schroyer</name>
                            <name>Ruthven Todd</name>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1977"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_11">
        <body>
            <pb id="p11-60" n="60"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-11-1-0012">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">Newsletter</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">Blake An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>With this issue the <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> celebrates its tenth
                        anniversary. The first issue was edited and published by Morton Paley from
                        the University of California at Berkeley in the summer of 1967. In 1970
                        Paley divided the editorial responsibilities with Morris Eaves, and the
                        production office of the <hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> was moved to the
                        University of New Mexico in Albuquerque. With the sponsorship of the English
                        Department there, the <hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> was able to change its
                        format: first from multilith to photo-offset, which allowed us to reproduce
                        pictures, and then from photo-offset in single columns to a double-column
                        format that allowed the pictures to be integrated more flexibly with the
                        text. We published our first color illustration in 1974-75, and another last
                        year. Bibliographical work gradually became a sort of sub-specialty,
                        beginning with the supplement to the Bentley-Nurmi <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Bibliography</hi> that appeared in one of the very early issues, which
                        was followed by Robert Essick’s handlist of reproductions,
                        Bentley’s checklist of the Blake <figure n="Quarterly.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="695" height="1000"/>
collection at the
                        British Museum, Ruth Lehrer’s checklist of the Rosenwald
                        collections, Everett Frost’s checklist of Blake slides, and a
                        host of others. Finally, in 1976 Thomas Minnick was added to the editorial
                        staff as Bibliographer, to handle all our bibliographical projects,
                        including the annual checklist of Blake scholarship, which was joined a
                        couple of years ago by Robert Essick’s annual checklist of sales,
                        “Blake in the Market-place.” We published our first
                        special thematic issue, on Blake among Victorians, in 1974, and another, on
                        The Textbook Blake, with a long bibliographical essay with checklist by Mary
                        Lynn Johnson, in 1976. We contributed resources for discussion to the annual
                        MLA Blake seminar for the first time in 1975, with a supplemental booklet by
                        W. J. T. Mitchell on Blake’s pictures of the Last Judgment, and
                        again in 1976, with an essay by Irene Tayler on Blake’s
                        Laocoön. In 1975 we went outside the confines of the journal
                        itself to publish an inexpensive classroom facsimile of <hi rend="i">America</hi>, a
feat we hope to duplicate with other works in
                        illuminated printing before too long.</p>
                    <p>Now, in 1977, with issue number 41, the first in our eleventh volume, we are
                        changing our name to bring it in line with what we think is the
                        truth—dropping “Newsletter” from the title to
                        become simply <hi rend="i">Blake An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, and
                        reminding ourselves of our origins by making our “News”
                        section the “Newsletter.” We have already grown, we
                        believe, to be the quarterly that our new name asserts we are, and therefore
                        we plan no special changes in format or extent, except that we shall now
                        welcome from contributors some of the longer and more
                        “interpretive” articles that we have never solicited in
                        the past.</p>
                    <p>The change in the price of a subscription that also goes into effect with
                        this volume is an anniversary present that we did not want to give to our
                        subscribers. We want to assure you that the raise in price has nothing to do
                        with the change in our name—only with the steady change in the
                        costs of goods and services. If history consoles, a subscription in 1967
                        cost $2; in 1970, $3 and $4; in 1971, $3 and $5; and by early 1972, $4 and
                        $5—the present rate, which has held steady for more than half a
                        decade (to put it as strongly as possible). The new rate is $6 for
                        individuals, $7 for institutions. 
                        <byline><docAuthor>MORRIS <name>EAVES</name></docAuthor> AND 
                        <docAuthor>MORTON D. <name>PALEY</name>,</docAuthor>
                        CO-EDITORS, BLAKE AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY.</byline></p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>