<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>11.1.schroyer</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">The 1788 Publication of Lavater’s Aphorisms on Man</title>
                <author n="Schroyer">Richard J. Schroyer</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1977</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1977</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">11.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Brad Hayden</name>
                            <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
                            <name>Michael Hays</name>
                            <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
                            <name>Jane Welford</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>John Beer</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Raymond Deck</name>
                            <name>Thomas Dilworth</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
                            <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
                            <name>Donald L. Kent</name>
                            <name>Vivian Mercier</name>
                            <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
                            <name>Dennis Read</name>
                            <name>Grant C. Roti</name>
                            <name>Richard J. Schroyer</name>
                            <name>Ruthven Todd</name>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1977"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_11">
        <body>
	<pb id="p11-23" n="23"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-11-1-0006">
                <head>
                    <title type="main">
                        <hi rend="b">The 1788 Publication Date of Lavater’s Aphorisms on
                            Man</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <byline>
                    <hi rend="b">by</hi>
                    <docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="b">Richard J.</hi>
                        <name>
                            <hi rend="b">Schroyer</hi>
                        </name>
                    </docAuthor>
                </byline>
                <p>William Blake’s annotated copy of the first English edition of J. C.
                    Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man</hi> (tr. H. Fuseli, pub. J.
                        Johnson)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">1</ref> is
usually dated 1788 on the
                    apparently firm evidence of the title page dated 1788 and the unsigned
                    “Advertisement” (pp. v-vi) dated “May,
                        1788.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">2</ref> This
date may be
                    especially important for the chronology of Blake’s earliest
                    illuminated books, if, as S. Foster Damon first observed, <hi rend="i">All
                        Religions are One</hi> and the two series of <hi rend="i">There is No
                        Natural Religion</hi> are formally and materially indebted to
                    Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Aphorisms.</hi>
                    <ref target="n34" type="note">3</ref> In light of this, it is unsettling to find that
David Erdman, in
                    two very influential studies of Blake,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n35" type="note">4</ref>
                    re-dates <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> 1789—and thereby pushes the <hi rend="i">terminus a
quo</hi> of Blake’s annotations forward by at
                    least six months—on the authority of the following statement in John
                    Knowles’ <hi rend="i">Life and Writings of Henry Fuseli</hi> (1831):
						<q> In the beginning of the year (1789), Fuseli published, in a small
                        duodecimo [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>, for octavo] volume, a translation of
                        Lavater’s “Aphorisms on Man;” which work,
                        written in German, was dedicated to him by this early and esteemed friend.
                        The dedication is dated October, 1787.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n36" type="note">5</ref>
					</q>
					Knowles’ generally valuable biography is, I would suggest,
                    almost certainly wrong on this particular point, the victim perhaps of a
                    printer’s slip.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">6</ref>
Although there
                    is some reason to believe that the first edition of <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi>
                    was not widely circulated until the spring of 1789, when Christopher Moody wrote
                    that the volume was “now before us,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38"
type="note">7</ref> other evidence indicates that the book was in print, and
                    therefore available to Blake, as early as perhaps May (the date of the
                    “Advertisement”), and very probably by June or July 1788. The
                    July 1788 issue of Joseph Johnson’s recently founded <hi rend="i">Analytical Review</hi>
carried two notices of the book. <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> is listed as one of the “Books and Pamphlets
                    Published during the first six months [i.e., by June] of 1788,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">8</ref> and a critic identified as
                    “N” gives a fairly extensive account of the book, with a
                    generous selection of aphorisms: 
					<q> ART. III. APHORISMS ON MAN: <hi rend="i">Translated
from the original German</hi> MS. <hi rend="i">of</hi> John
                        Caspar Lavater, <hi rend="i">Citizen of Zuric.</hi> With a frontispiece.
                        Pot. 8vo. P. 232. Price 3s. sewed. Johnson.<lb/>
                        <lb/>
 The author of these
                        Aphorisms seems to have proceeded from the head to the heart, or rather the
                        study of one enabled him to trace the different forms the passions wear, and
                        to discriminate many of their almost endless combinations. We with pleasure
                        read the only maxims extant written by a benevolent man; and perhaps it is
                        necessary 
<pb id="p11-24" n="24"/>
                        <figure n="LavaterAphorismsTitle.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="750" height="565"/> to love the
human race, and to be one of its ornaments, before the
                        virtues and vices which adorn and debase it can be discerned and unfolded.
                        He must have genius who can point out its characteristics, and display the
                        sublime he describes. [Following an accurate transcript of the
                        “Dedication” and “Advertisement,” the
                        reviewer continues.]<lb/>
                        <lb/>
 Many of the aphorisms are so well expressed
                        in the translation, that they have all the merit of an original thought
                        almost intuitively struck off. . . . The blemishes . . . are trifling; and
                        the work, taken collectively, we think the most interesting and original
                        production we have for a long time perused, and that it does equal honour to
                        the goodness, discernment, and sensibility of the author.<lb/>
                        <lb/>
 The
                        number of the aphorisms is 643.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
type="note">9</ref>
					</q>
                    <note id="n32">
                        <hi rend="s">1</hi> I wish to express my thanks to the
                        authorities of the Huntington Library, San Marino, California, for supplying
                        me with a microfilm of Blake’s copy of Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi>
(shelf-mark RB 57431).</note>
                    <note id="n33">
                        <hi rend="s">2</hi> On the conventional date of the Lavater
                        marginalia, see G. E. Bentley, Jr. and Martin K. Nurmi, <hi rend="i">A Blake
                            Bibliography</hi> (Minneapolis: Univ. of Minnesota Press, 1964), pp. 36,
                        37, 137, 207-08. Hereafter cited as Bentley &amp; Nurmi.</note>
                    <note id="n34">
                        <hi rend="s">3</hi> S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">William Blake:
                            His Philosophy and Symbols</hi> (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1924), p.
                        37n. Admitting the real differences between Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi>
and Blake’s principles in the Natural
                        Religion tractates, one may nevertheless agree with Damon that
                        Lavater’s first two aphorisms (which Blake in his note called
                        “true Christian philosophy far above all abstraction”)
                        bear a striking resemblance to <hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi>,
                        principles 1, 2, and 7. Although none of the extant copies of the Natural
                        Religion tractates can be shown to have been printed as early as 1788, the
                        scholarly consensus is that the plates were probably etched at about that
                        time. Briefly, the evidence for this conjecture is that the size and
                        technical imperfections in the lettering and designs suggest that Blake was
                        experimenting with a new medium, and that the colophon to the <hi rend="i">Ghost of
Abel</hi> (“1822: W Blake’s Original
                        <corr type="emend">Stereotype</corr> was 1788”), a work addressed to “Lord Byron in
                        the wilderness” probably refers to <hi rend="i">All Religions are
                            One</hi>, the frontispiece of which is inscribed “The Voice of
                        One Crying in the Wilderness.” If Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> is
considered to be a positive influence upon the
                        Natural Religion tractates, then, as Martin K. Nurmi plausibly argues in 
<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (London: Hutchinson Univ. Library, 1975),
                        pp. 52-54, Bacon’s maxims may be considered a negative
                        influence.</note>
                    <note id="n35">
                        <hi rend="s">4</hi>
                        <hi rend="i"> Blake: Prophet Against Empire</hi>, 2nd ed., rev. (Princeton,
                        N.J.: Princeton Univ. Press, 1969), p. 139n. and <hi rend="i">The Poetry and
                            Prose of William Blake</hi>, with a commentary by Harold Bloom, 4th
                            printing, rev. (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1970), pp. 572, 799.</note>
                    <note id="n36">
                        <hi rend="s">5</hi> I, 159. Those who date <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> 1789 include:
E. D. Hirsch, Jr., <hi rend="i">Innocence and Experience: An Introduction to Blake</hi> (New Haven
                        and London: Yale Univ. Press, 1964), p. 326; Marcia Allentuck,
                        <corr type="emend">“Fuseli and Lavater: Physiognomical Theory and the
                        Enlightenment,”</corr> in <hi rend="i">Studies on Voltaire and the
                            Eighteenth Century</hi>, ed. Theodore Besterman, 55 (Geneva:
                        Institut et Musée Voltaire, 1967), 97; Anne Kostelanetz
                        Mellor, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Human Form Divine</hi>
                        (Berkeley: Univ. of California Press, 1974), p. 4n; Morton D. Paley, 
<hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination: A Study of the Development of
                            Blake’s Thought</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1970), p.
                        10n. Paley is alone in identifying and trying to resolve the discrepancy
                        between the 1789 date of <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> and the traditional
                        chronology of Blake’s other works: “As Blake, having
                        engraved the frontispiece for Johnson, obtained an unbound copy, he
                        probably read the book before its publication in 1789.”</note>
                    <note id="n37">
                        <hi rend="s">6</hi> As occurs elsewhere in the <hi rend="i">Life</hi>, e.g., I,
287-88, where Knowles’ first meeting
                        with Fuseli in 1805 is dated 1825, the year of Fuseli’s
                        death.</note>
                    <note id="n38">
                        <hi rend="s">7</hi> [Christopher] Moo[d]y, review of
                        Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi>, in <hi rend="i">The
                            Monthly Review</hi>, 80 (June 1789), 526-28. When Moody writes that the
                        “little book of aphorisms” is “now before
                        us” (p. 526), he may simply mean that the work is now under review.
                        Moody’s review first noted by Allentuck, p. 97.</note>
                    <note id="n39">
                        <hi rend="s">8</hi>
                        <hi rend="i"> Analytical Review</hi>, 1 (July 1788), 377. <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi>
is described here, as in Knowles above, as a duodecimo
                        rather than an octavo volume, though I suspect that these terms were used
                        rather loosely to indicate relative size rather than exact
                        format.</note>
                    <note id="n40">
                        <hi rend="s">9</hi>
                        <hi rend="i"> Analytical Review</hi>, 1 (July 1788), 286-89. In fact, the
                        volume contains only 633 aphorisms, numbered 1-189, 200-643; this
                        misnumbering was corrected in the second edition of 1789. It is of
                        course possible that the July number of <hi rend="i">Analytical
                            Review</hi> came out after July (the combined title page for volume
                        1 reads “From May to August, Inclusive, 1788.”),
                        though I have no solid evidence that this in fact happened.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The existence of this dated review, together with the facts and inferences
                    already available, permit us to construct a fairly detailed outline of the
                    history of <hi rend="i">Aphorisms.</hi> During the autumn of 1787, when, as
                    Blake later recalled, “Flaxman was taken to Italy” and
                    “Fuseli was given to me for a season,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n41" type="note">10</ref> Fuseli’s friend Lavater was rapidly
                    composing his “verdicts of wisdom on the reports of
                        experience,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">11</ref>
a task he
                    evidently completed by 13 October, when the dedication to Fuseli was written. By
                    the end of the year, part of the collection was published in German as 
<hi rend="i">Vermischte unphysiognomische Regeln zur Selbst- und
                        Menschenkenntniss</hi>, but without the dedication. The part of the
                    collection not published in 1787 was apparently reserved for a second volume of
                        1788.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">12</ref>
Between October 1787 and May
                    1788, Fuseli translated Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Regeln</hi> into
                    English aphorisms which, as far as I can determine, fairly reflect the spirit of
                    the originals. And it was probably during the same period that either Fuseli or
                    Johnson employed Blake—who may have begun to experiment with
                    illuminated printing—to engrave the frontispiece after Fuseli.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">13</ref> By May 1788, when Blake’s first
                    plate for Lavater’s major work, <hi rend="i">Essays on
                        Physiognomy</hi>, was issued,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45"
type="note">14</ref>
                    <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> was very probably ready for the press. By July 1788,
                    as we have seen, the first edition was in print and was being discussed openly,
                    at least in Johnson’s house journal. <note id="n41">
                        <hi rend="s">10</hi> Letter from Blake to Flaxman of 12 September 1800; E 680. The
                        Flaxmans evidently left England in August 1787 and made their way slowly to
                        Rome by way of France. See Eliza Meteyard, <hi rend="i">The Life of Josiah
                            Wedgwood</hi> (London: Hurst &amp; Blackett, 1865), II,
                        503-06.</note>
                    <note id="n42">
                        <hi rend="s">11</hi> J. C. Lavater, <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on
                            Man</hi> (1788), “Advertisement,” p. v (perhaps by
                        Fuseli).</note>
                    <note id="n43">
                        <hi rend="s">12</hi> The colophon of the first volume in German
                        reads: “Zurich Freytags den 30. Nov. 1787.” I have not
                        seen the second volume of 1788, though Miss Hilde Siegl of the Deutsche
                        Bibliothek, Frankfurt, reports that the title page reads: <hi rend="i">Vermischte
unphysiognomische Regeln zur Menschen- und Selbstkenntniss
                            Von</hi> Johann Kaspar Lavater. Zum Bessten der Armen [the last seven
                        words handwritten, perhaps by the author]. 1788. Presumably, the aphorisms
                        found in Fuseli’s translation, but not in the <hi rend="i">Regeln</hi> of 1787, were
included in the <hi rend="i">Regeln</hi> of
                        1788. For Lavater’s habit of dedicating his works to friends, see
                        Franz Muncker, “Lavater,” in <hi rend="i">Allgemeine
                            Deutsche Biographie</hi>, 18 (1883; rpt. Berlin: Duncker &amp;
                        Humbolt, 1969), 783-94.</note>
                    <note id="n44">
                        <hi rend="s">13</hi> On the frontispiece, see Ruthven Todd,
                            “Two Blake Prints and Two Fuseli Drawings <hi rend="i">with
                                some possibly pertinent speculations</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter</hi>, 5 (Winter, 1971-72), 173-81. According to
                            Bentley &amp; Nurmi, p. 137, “There were no plates in the
                            ‘Third Edition’ of Dublin, 1790, or the
                            ‘Fifth Edition’ of Newburyport, 1793.”
                            The copy of the Dublin edition of <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> in the
                            University of Western Ontario Library, however, contains a frontispiece
                            copied from Blake’s and is inscribed “P. Maguire
                            Sculpt.” (Illus. 2.)
                        <p>“P. Maguire” is very probably Patrick Maguire, an Irish
                            engraver about whom I know very little except that he was
                            “admitted as a student in the Dublin Society’s
                            School in 1783, and afterwards worked in Dublin for many years [c.
                            1790-1820], as an engraver in Trinity Place and Anglesea
                            Street” according to Walter G. Strickland, <hi rend="i">A
                                Dictionary of Irish Artists</hi> (Dublin: Maunsel, 1913; reprint
                            ed., Shannon: Irish Univ. Press, 1969), II, 86-87.</p>
                    </note>
                    <note id="n45">
                        <hi rend="s">14</hi> Bentley &amp; Nurmi, pp.
                    137-38.</note>
                </p>
                <p>That Blake did in fact obtain his copy of the book in May-July 1788 is probable
                    but not certain. <pb id="p11-25" n="25"/>
                    <figure n="LavaterAphorismsThird.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="750" height="645"/> As the engraver of
the frontispiece and as a friend of the translator,
                    Blake seems to have had both opportunity and motive to acquire and begin to
                    annotate his copy of <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> as soon as it became available.
                    Further, nothing in Blake’s annotations would contradict a date of
                    composition as early as spring or summer 1788, and the evidence of offsets
                    gathered by G. E. Bentley, Jr. may indicate that Blake received an
                    unbound—and therefore possibly a pre-publication—copy of
                    the book, perhaps in partial payment for engraving the frontispiece.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">15</ref> In sum, although several problems in
                    Blake’s chronology await better solutions (or at least more precise
                    definitions) than are now available, the 1788 publication date of
                    Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> would seem to be fairly secure,
                    and the traditional chronology of Blake’s annotations and Natural
                    Religion tractates, as a consequence, intact. <note id="n46">
                        <hi rend="s">15</hi> Bentley &amp; Nurmi, pp. 207-08. Since Blake apparently
                        kept his copy of <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> by him until his death in 1827,
                        it is not impossible that some of his annotations were made long after 1788.
                        See G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon
                        Press, 1969), pp. 288-89, 355-56.</note>
                </p>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="b">Postscript</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>In his <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, Alexander Gilchrist tells a
                        story about Blake, Fuseli, and Blake’s copy of
                        Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> which has always seemed to
                        me to have the ring of truth. “Blake,” Gilchrist reports,
                        “showed his notes to Fuseli; who said one could assuredly read
                        their writer’s character in <hi rend="i">them.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">16</ref> I had hoped to find that
                        Fuseli’s revisions for the second edition of <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> (1789)
would show that he read and incorporated into his
                        revised text some of the suggestions found in Blake’s
                        annotations. Alas, a careful comparison of the two editions against
                        Blake’s comments does not confirm or deny Gilchrist’s
                        story, and it must therefore remain in the limbo of unsubstantiated
                        anecdote. <note id="n47">
                            <hi rend="s">16</hi> Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>,
ed. Ruthven Todd, rev. ed.
                            (London: Dent, and New York: Dutton, 1945), p. 54.</note>
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
	<pb id="p11-26" n="26" rend="hidden"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>