<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>11.1.todd</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">A Tentative Note on the Economics of The Canterbury Pilgrims</title>
                <author n="Todd">Ruthven Todd</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1977</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1977</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">11.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Brad Hayden</name>
                            <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
                            <name>Michael Hays</name>
                            <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
                            <name>Jane Welford</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>John Beer</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Raymond Deck</name>
                            <name>Thomas Dilworth</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
                            <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
                            <name>Donald L. Kent</name>
                            <name>Vivian Mercier</name>
                            <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
                            <name>Dennis Read</name>
                            <name>Grant C. Roti</name>
                            <name>Richard J. Schroyer</name>
                            <name>Ruthven Todd</name>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1977"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_11">
        <body>
            <pb id="p11-30" n="30"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-11-1-0008">
                <head>
                    <title type="main">
                        <hi rend="b">A Tentative Note on the Economics of The Canterbury
                            Pilgrims</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <byline>
                    <hi rend="b">by</hi>
                    <docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="b">Ruthven</hi>
                        <name>
                            <hi rend="b">Todd</hi>
                        </name>
                    </docAuthor>
                </byline>
                <p>The printing of intaglio plates was never a driving impulse with William Blake,
                    despite <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of
                        Los.</hi> During the years of his apprenticeship to James Basire, 1772-1779,
                    he undoubtedly learned how to pull a proof of any plate upon which he happened
                    to be working, in order to see what further work was needed upon the plate, but
                    such a proof did not have to be more than competent. He was trained as an
                    engraver, not as a printer.</p>
                <p>The copperplate-printer served an apprenticeship of at least five years and, like
                    all indentured and trained craftsmen, was naturally most protective of his trade
                    and his skills. It is, perhaps, noteworthy that the only two published works for
                    which William and Catherine Blake actually printed the plates, <hi rend="i">Designs to a
Series of Ballads</hi>, 1802, by William Hayley and the first
                    two volumes of the same author’s <hi rend="i">The Life and Posthumous
                        Writings of William Cowper</hi>, 1803, were provincial productions.</p>
                <p>Although William protested otherwise, in his letter of 30 January 1803 to James
                    Blake, anyone who has had the opportunity of examining several copies of either
                    work alongside one another will at once see that the prints do not exhibit the
                    mechanical, and often deadly, production-line perfection of those pulled by a
                    professional plate-printer.</p>
                <p>“The London section of Pendred’s <hi rend="i">Vade Mecum</hi>
                    of 1785 lists thirteen plate printers, fourteen engraver-printers, and one
                        rolling-press-maker.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55"
type="note">1</ref> Such a
                    listing, from a generalized work, can only be taken as a sampling of the actual
                    total. London being a comparatively small city at that date, however, it can be
                    accepted that it shows that there was always a plate-printer near at hand for
                    Blake, except when he lived in Lambeth and at Felpham. The natural thing for him
                    to do would be to take any plate upon which he was working round to the nearest
                    plate-printer and have a proof or two pulled. The cost was little and was far
                    outweighed by the trouble of setting up the press and all the paraphernalia to
                    do such a tiny job at home. <note id="n55">
                        <hi rend="s">1</hi> Iain Bain,
                        “ Thomas Ross &amp; Son: Copper- and Steel- plate Printers
                        since 1833,” <hi rend="i">Journal of the Printing Historical
                            Society</hi>, 2(1966), p. 4.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Longman accounts referring to Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Dante</hi>,
                    1807, and <hi rend="i">Hesiod</hi>, 1817, show that the plate-printers Cox
                    &amp; Barnett received 3d. a pull for proofs and 5s. per hundred prints, in
                    a run, in 1807, and 6d. a proof and 6s. a hundred in 1817.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">2</ref>
                    <note id="n56">
                        <hi rend="s">2</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">The Early
                            Engravings of Flaxman’s Classical Designs</hi> (New York
                        Public Library), 1964.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Paper for the various classical designs by Flaxman, between April 1805 and 1817,
                    all of it “medium plate,” varied from as much as £6.10s.
                    to as little as £4 a ream. As a ream consists of five hundred sheets, this
                    breaks down to as little as about 1½d. to about 2½d. a
                    sheet. Of course, these sheets would be smaller than those required to print
                    “The Canterbury Pilgrims,” but an estimate of 1s. a sheet for
                    paper of the requisite size does not seem out of order.</p>
                <p>The firm of Dixon &amp; Ross, c.1835, charged 1s. 1d. an impression or
                    £8 per hundred in a run in Double Elephant folio, i.e. 20 × 27
                        in.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">3</ref> The
smallest paper upon which
                    “The Canterbury Pilgrims” could have been printed is about 19
                    × 42 in. I know that paper was made which was about 40 ×
                    54 in., although I cannot recollect what it was called in the trade. Such a
                    sheet would provide for two prints. <note id="n57">
                        <hi rend="s">3</hi> Iain
                        Bain, p. 9.</note>
                </p>
                <p>There was no difference for a shorter run than that of a hundred, and, allowing
                    for a general increase in prices between 1810 and 1835, it seems likely that a
                    proportion of £8 per hundred would still apply.</p>
                <p>Copper has always fluctuated in value, so it is difficult to decide what the
                    plate would have cost. The plates for the <hi rend="i">Hesiod</hi>, bought
                    through Blake, averaged just over 7s. each. But it seems likely that Blake
                    brought down the price by buying secondhand plates of which he would use the
                    back or plane off the previous design with a snake-stone.</p>
                <p>The top price for any of the plates for <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of
                        Job</hi> was 3s.10d. I think that the price of copper, as always during
                    wartime, was high around 1810, and it is likely that the <hi rend="i">Job</hi>
                    plates might have cost 4s. at that time.</p>
                <p>As the plate of “The Canterbury Pilgrims” measures 35.5
                    × 97.5 cm., which is roughly seven 
<pb id="p11-31" n="31"/>
times
                    that of the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> plates, 22 × 17 cm., it may be
                    assumed that the large plate would have cost about £1.8s., or, even if Blake
                    had used a thicker gauge of copper in view of the size of the plate (I am trying
                    to find out the gauges of the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and “The Canterbury
                    Pilgrims”), as much as £1.10s.</p>
                <p>Although I doubt whether Blake produced a printing of the first state of
                    “The Canterbury Pilgrims” of as many copies as 25, I have made
                    an estimate based upon that number: <table rows="4" cols="2">
                        <row>
                            <cell>Cost of copperplate . . . . . . . . . .</cell>
                            <cell>£1.10s.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Cost of paper (1 sheet, 2 prints) . . .</cell>
                            <cell>£0.12s.6d.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Cost of printing 25 copies . . . . . .</cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="u">£2.00s.</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>total</cell>
                            <cell>£4.02s.6d.</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table> Allowing for extras, including perhaps a pint of porter for the
                    pressman, the price might well be leveled off at £4.4s., which was the price
                    of one subscription, paid in advance, and it seems more than likely that Thomas
                    Butts, who bought the tempera painting of “The Canterbury
                    Pilgrims,” would have provided this.</p>
                <p>(I have never seen a copy, and no such copy is mentioned in Sir Geoffrey
                    Keynes’s <hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi>, but it would seem from the Linnell 
                    accounts<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n87" type="note">4</ref><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">5</ref> 
                    that some proofs,
                    presumably of the fourth state, were printed on India paper, since John Linnell,
                    on behalf of Catherine Blake, sold one, so described, to a Mr. Flowers of
                    Islington for £2.12s.6d. on 29 September 1827.) 
                    <note id="n87">
                        <hi rend="s">4</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Records</hi> (Oxford: The Clarendon Press), 1969, <hi rend="i">passim.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <note id="n58">
                        <hi rend="s">5</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p.
                        594.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The above <hi rend="i">jeu d’esprit</hi>, of course, takes no account
                    of the immense amount of work which went 
                    into turning 30s. worth of copper into a most impressive work of art.
                    An impression of the final state, given to me by Charles Sessler in Philadelphia
                    in 1947, faces me across my room as I write and makes me feel rather ashamed at
                    having pointed out that the material base of the work cost so little. But the
                    same can be said of the materials with which any artist works, and the costs are
                    the same for the bad artist as for the great one. The limbo of forgotten
                    engravings of the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries contains many larger and
                    more pretentious plates which cost about the same to fabricate. It is the work
                    of art upon the plate which makes it memorable.</p>
                <p>I hope that these notes will be of some interest in giving a part of the economic
                    background of a poor artist during a difficult time, and also hope that anyone
                    who has any information about the costs of commercial plate-printers during
                    Blake’s lifetime will pass it on to me. 
                </p>
                <figure n="ESXVI.1.3I.SP" rend="file" width="958" height="356">
                     <head>Blake, “The Canterbury Pilgrims”</head>
                </figure>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>