<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>11.1.deck</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">An American Original: Mrs. Colman’s Illustrated Printings of Blake’s
Poems, 1843-44</title>
                <author n="Deck">Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1977</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1977</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">11.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Brad Hayden</name>
                            <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
                            <name>Michael Hays</name>
                            <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
                            <name>Jane Welford</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>John Beer</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Raymond Deck</name>
                            <name>Thomas Dilworth</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
                            <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
                            <name>Donald L. Kent</name>
                            <name>Vivian Mercier</name>
                            <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
                            <name>Dennis Read</name>
                            <name>Grant C. Roti</name>
                            <name>Richard J. Schroyer</name>
                            <name>Ruthven Todd</name>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1977"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_11">
        <body>
            <pb id="p11-4" n="4"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-11-1-0003">
                <head>
                    <title type="main">
                        <hi rend="b">An American Original: Mrs. Colman’s Illustrated
                            Printings of Blake’s Poems, 1843-44</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <byline><hi rend="b">By</hi> <docAuthor><hi rend="b">Raymond H. </hi><name><hi
rend="b">Deck</hi></name>, <hi rend="b">Jr.</hi></docAuthor></byline>
                <figure n="ColemanProspectus.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="632">
                	<figTranscr>PROSPECTUS.<lb/>
                	THE BOYS’ AND GIRLS’ MAGAZINE.<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	UNDER the above title, we shall commence, this month, the publication of a new<lb/>
                	MAGAZINE. Having been engaged a long time in preparing books for their young<lb/>
                	friends, the publishers have frequently thought of, and intended to make, a Monthly<lb/>
                	Visitor, for all the Girls and Boys of America; and now, finding their facilities sufficient,<lb/>
                	and their hearts still warm on the subject, they propose to furnish, Monthly, a<lb/>
                	BOYS’ AND GIRLS’ MAGAZINE.<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	The Editor of the work will be MRS. S. COLMAN, heretofore favorably known as the<lb/>
                	editor of the Mother’s Library, Aunt Mary’s Library, The Dahlia, Child’s Gem, &amp;c.<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	The following persons are also engaged as regular contributors to every number, viz.:<lb/>
                	Rev. JACOB ABBOTT, author of the Rollo, Lucy, and Jonas Books; T. S. ARTHUR,<lb/>
                	author of Stories for Children, Six Nights with the Washingtonians, and as many other<lb/>
                	popular tales; and also several ladies, well known and much approved writers for<lb/>
                	young people.<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	THE BOYS’ AND GIRLS’ MAGAZINE will be issued in beautiful style, embellished<lb/>
                	with extra Engravings, executed in a superior manner, under the particular care and<lb/>
                	supervision of S. Colman, and will contain such kind and variety of reading and<lb/>
                	amusement as every parent, desirous of promoting the happiness of his children, may<lb/>
                	approve. The yearly volume will contain Four Hundred and Thirty-Two pages,<lb/>
                	including the extra engravings, and will be sold for One Dollar and Twenty-Five Cents<lb/>
                	a year, in advance. Five copies for Five Dollars. Ten copies, to one address, for<lb/>
                	Ten Dollars; or in Monthly Parks, for Twelve and a half Cents.<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	EMBELLISHMENTS OF NUMBER III.<lb/>
                	PRINTED ON EXTRA PAPER, IN BEAUTIFUL STYLE, BY MEAD &amp; BEAL.<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	THREE very beautiful extra Engravings, by Messrs. J. G. CHANDLER &amp; Co.,<lb/>
                	Artists, together with the Initial Letters, &amp;c., in the body of the work; and a colored<lb/>
                	plate of a Moss ROSE, richly executed under the supervision of a lady of much<lb/>
                	taste and experience.<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	☞ Postmasters and Teachers are respectfully requested to take an interest in<lb/>
                	this work. A number, for examination, will be sent free to those who may desire it.<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	Subscriptions received by the publishers, T. H. CARTER &amp; CO., 118½ Washington<lb/>
                	Street, Boston, by the following and by the publishers named on the title-page.<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	☞ Newspapers, in any part of the country, inserting the above, and occasionally<lb/>
                	noticing the work editorially, will be entitled to the yearly volume.<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	AGENTS.<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	GEORGE COLMAN, Portland.<lb/>
                	W. &amp; S. B. IVES, Salem.<lb/>
                	W. TAYLOR, Baltimore.<lb/>
                	R. FARNHAM,<lb/>
                	ZIEBER &amp; Co.,<lb/>
                	} Washington, D.C.<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	R. Y. BERFORD, Pittsburg, Pa.<lb/>
                	A. M. WILDER, Brooklyn, N. Y.<lb/>
                	W. C. LITTLE, Albany, N. Y.<lb/>
                	C. MORSE, Rochester, N. Y.<lb/>
                	J. H. TEBBETTS, Montreal, Can.</figTranscr>
                    <head>Illus. 1</head>
                </figure>
                <p>Between 1843 and 1845, Pamela Chandler Colman, an American Swedenborgian active
                    in the production of children’s books, was responsible for printing
                    in four separate publications nine different poems from Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence.</hi>
                    <ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> Taken
                    together, these printings constitute a remarkable “edition” of
                    Blake’s poems, both for their text and for their accompanying
                    illustrations. As we will see, Mrs. Colman did not simply reprint a selection
                    from Wilkinson’s 1839 edition of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> or from
                    Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives</hi> as we might expect at this time
                    in America; she apparently used an original copy of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>
                    and chose texts which she thought most appropriate for her young readers; she
                    even took the liberty of attributing to Blake a rather saccharine piece entitled
                    “Evening Hymn.” Perhaps more remarkable, most of these poems,
                    taken from Blake’s illuminated pages, are accompanied by
                    illustrations, at least one or two of which seem to have been inspired by
                    Blake’s etched design and which constitute a graphic interpretation
                    of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Innocence.</hi> After presenting the
                    illustrated text of Mrs. Colman’s “edition” of
                    Blake’s poems, I will consider the question of her source text and
                    finally suggest two contexts in which to view her work: the genre of American
                    children’s books in the 1840s and the continuing interest in Blake
                    manifested by American Swedenborgians. <note id="n1">
                        <hi rend="s">1</hi> My
                        discoveries of six of Mrs. Colman’s insertions and of several
                        other early printings of Blake’s poems have been noted in my
                        “Unnoticed Printings of Blake’s Poems,
                        1825-51,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 40 (Spring 1977); with
                        the exception of her insertions of “A Dream,”
                        “The Little Boy lost,” and “The Little Boy
                        Found,” Mrs. Colman’s printings of Blake’s
                        poems have not been noticed previously in Blake scholarship. For other early
                        printings and mentions of Blake helpfully arranged in chronological order,
                        see G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Critical
                            Heritage</hi> (London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1975), pp.
                        220-69.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Mrs. Colman’s editorial career began in the 1830s, when her husband,
                    Samuel, established himself as a successful bookseller and publisher in New York
                    City. In addition to his adult publications and his sale of works by other
                    publishers, Samuel Colman began by 1839 to produce children’s books
                    edited, and sometimes written, by his wife. Their most extensive effort to
                    achieve some prominence in the field of children’s literature did not
                    begin until 1843, when the Colmans (who continued to reside and to publish other
                    works in New York) began to publish a number of children’s books in
                    Boston. Some of these productions, especially the original inventions of Mrs.
                    Colman, were published by “S[amuel]. Colman” of Boston, but
                    others, including all those with Blake poems, give on their title pages only
                    “T. H. <pb id="p11-5" n="5"/>
Carter &amp; Co.” of
                    Boston, although they were the joint enterprise of Carter and Samuel Colman.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref>
                    <note id="n2">
                        <hi rend="s">2</hi> Samuel and Pamela Colman are considered
                        briefly in both the <hi rend="i">Dictionary of American Biography</hi> and
                            <hi rend="i">Appleton’s Cyclopedia of American Biography</hi>
                        as the parents of the American landscape painter Samuel Colman. My chief
                        source of information about their publishing activities is the <hi rend="i">National
Union Catalogue.</hi> Relevant to their New York activities
                        during 1843 and 1844 are J. C. Palmer, <hi rend="i">Thulia: A Tale of the
                            <corr type="emend">Antarctic</corr></hi> (New York: Samuel Colman, 1843), and a
New York edition of
                            <hi rend="i">The Little Keepsake for 1844</hi> (see my note 5, below).
                        For Samuel Colman’s early publishing activities in New York see
                        “S. Colman’s List of Publications,” appended to
                        Anon., <hi rend="i">Sunday Morning Reflections</hi> (New York: S. Colman,
                        1839), and his “List of Birthday and Holiday Presents Published by
                        Samuel Colman” appended to Jane Marcet, <hi rend="i">Willy’s Stories for Young
Children</hi> (New York: S.
                        Colman, 1839), pp. 143-44. About the New York-Boston connection, one
                        possibility is that the “G. Colman” of Boston listed as
                        publisher of some of Mrs. Colman’s works was a relative who, in
                        some sort of business relationship with Samuel Colman, represented the New
                        York publisher’s interests in Boston.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Clearly the showpiece of the Colman’s juvenile
                    productions—and the one upon which must have depended their greatest
                    hopes for success—was the first of their Boston publications, the <hi rend="i">Boys’
and Girls’ Magazine</hi>
                    <ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> (illus. 1). The magazine featured
                    contributions by the genre’s leading authors, and the publishers went
                    to the special expense of having many illustrations especially designed and
                    engraved to accompany particular texts. Unfortunately, the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and
Girls’ Magazine</hi> seems to have proved a
                    less successful venture than had been hoped, for no numbers were published after
                    the twelve for 1843. As an indication of the public’s disappointing
                    response during that year, we find, in the prefatory notice integral to the
                    third bound volume, the announcement that the next year’s edition,
                    which in fact never appeared, would be reduced in price to $1.00,
                    “trusting thereby to meet the wishes of a much larger number throughout
                    the whole country.” <note id="n3">
                        <hi rend="s">3</hi> In addition to
                        the monthly and annual states described in the
                        “Prospectus” (illus. 1), the <hi rend="i">Boys’
                            and Girls’ Magazine</hi> was issued in tri-annual volumes,
                        which I have seen at the Wellesley College Library and at the New Church
                        Theological School, Newton, Massachusetts. The magazine is concurrently
                        paginated for the tri-annual and annual volumes, e.g., Blake’s
                        “The Blossom” appears on page 142 of Volume II of the
                        tri-annual volumes, which is also page 286 of the annual volume; my volume
                        and page references are to the tri-annual volumes.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">July 1843</hi> Mrs. Colman seems first to have encountered
                    Blake’s poems in the middle of 1843—probably, as argued in
                    a later section of this essay, in an original but uncolored copy of 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> alone. She displays Blake’s
                    “Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> very prominently
                    as the leading piece of the July number (II, No. 3, 73-74), and she appends to
                    the poem a short biography of the author in which she promises future selections
                    from Blake’s “charming, illuminated volume” (illus.
                    2).</p>
                <p>For all Mrs. Colman’s Blake texts we can make here the general
                    observation that they vary from Blake’s original in accidentals of
                    capitalization and punctuation and in the normalizing of many of
                    Blake’s contracted forms, for example
                    “vanish’d” and
                    “pluck’d” in his “Introduction”
                    and “wandring” and “thro’” in
                    “The Little Boy Found.” In Blake’s
                    “Introduction,” our Victorian editor also has altered the
                    “chear” of Blake’s lines 6 and 10 to
                    “cheer” and has added Roman numerals as stanza numbers.</p>
                <p>That the Victorian illustration accompanying this printing resembles
                    Blake’s design of his frontispiece to <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> may
                    result from Mrs. Colman’s access to an original copy of
                    Blake’s work and her deliberate copying of his design (illus. 3). In
                    considering that we may have in 1843 a graphic reinterpretation of
                    Blake’s design, it is important to establish that the editor or
                    publisher has not simply chosen an extant engraving which seemed generally
                    appropriate to the subject matter, as would be the usual procedure in
                    children’s books of the period. In fact, the engraving accompanying
                    Blake’s “Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> was used at least once in later
years, as the cover of Miss
                    [Mary Russell] Mitford’s <hi rend="i">The Rustic Wreath</hi> (Boston,
                    1849), published by W. J. Reynolds, who also republished several of Mrs.
                    Colman’s original works (illus. 4). But an examination of many of the
                    works Mrs. Colman edited or wrote and of publications by likely firms,
                    especially T. H. Carter &amp; Co., has not revealed an earlier use of the
                        engraving.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref>
Neither have I found any
                    other engraving related closely enough in design so as to suggest that someone
                    in the Carter-Colman business circle was likely to have conceived of this 
                    <figure n="ColemanIntro.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="858">
                    	<figTranscr>BOYS’ &amp; GIRLS’ MAG.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	INTRODUCTION<lb/>
                    	TO<lb/>
                    	SONGS OF INNOCENCE.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	BY WILLIAM BLAKE.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	I.<lb/>
                    	PIPING down the valleys wild,<lb/>
                    	Piping songs of pleasant glee,<lb/>
                    	On a cloud I saw a child,<lb/>
                    	And he, laughing, said to me:<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	II.<lb/>
                    	“Pipe a song about a lamb;”<lb/>
                    	So I piped with merry cheer.<lb/>
                    	“Piper, pipe that song again;”<lb/>
                    	So I piped,—he wept to hear.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	VOL. II.   JULY, 1843.   G<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	73<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	218<lb/>
                    	CHARLES AND WILLIAM.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	III.<lb/>
                    	“Drop thy pipe,—thy happy pipe,<lb/>
                    	Sing thy songs of happy cheer;”<lb/>
                    	So I sung the same again,<lb/>
                    	While he wept with joy to hear.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	IV.<lb/>
                    	“Piper, sit thee down and write<lb/>
                    	In a book, that all may read;”<lb/>
                    	So he vanished from my sight,<lb/>
                    	And I plucked a hollow reed,—<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	V.<lb/>
                    	And I made a rural pen,<lb/>
                    	And I stain’d the water clear,<lb/>
                    	And I wrote my happy songs,<lb/>
                    	Every child may joy to hear.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	NOTE.—William Blake was a poet of the <lb/>
                    	last century, contemporary with Flaxman.<lb/>
                    	This article is taken from a charming, illuminated<lb/>
                    	volume, printed in 1789, from which<lb/>
                    	some of the most beautiful songs will be<lb/>
                    	given in future numbers of the Magazine.</figTranscr>
                        <head>Illus. 2</head>
                    </figure>
                    <figure n="s-inn.u.p2" id="s-inn.u.illbk.02" work-copy="s-inn.u" rend="db" width="651" height="1000">
	<figTranscr/>
                        <head>Illus. 3 from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (U)</head>
                    </figure>
                    <pb id="p11-6" n="6"/>
                    <figure n="MitfordRusticWreath.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="733">
                    	<figTranscr>FOR<lb/>
                    	BOYS’ &amp; GIRLS’<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	THE<lb/>
                    	RUSTIC WREATH.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	BY MISS MITFORD.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	WITH OTHER<lb/>
                    	AMUSTING AND INSTRUCTIVE<lb/>
                    	STORIES.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	BOSTON:<lb/>
                    	W. J. REYNOLDS AND COMPANY.<lb/>
                    	1849.</figTranscr>
                        <head>Illus. 4</head>
                    </figure>
                    <figure n="Blossom.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="230">
                    	<figTranscr>THE BLOSSOM.<lb/>
                    	BY WILLIAM BLAKE.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	MERRY, merry sparrow,<lb/>
                    	Under leaves so green,<lb/>
                    	A happy blossom<lb/>
                    	Sees you, swift as arrow,<lb/>
                    	Seek your cradle narrow,<lb/>
                    	In the greenwood tree.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Pretty, pretty robin,<lb/>
                    	Under leaves so green,<lb/>
                    	A happy blossom hears your<lb/>
                    	Sobbing, sobbing—<lb/>
                    	Pretty robin,<lb/>
                    	In the greenwood tree.</figTranscr>
                        <head>Illus. 5</head>
                    </figure> design without reference to Blake’s original. To be sure,
                    some of the engravings in the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and
                        Girls’ Magazine</hi> antedated that publication by several years,
                    perhaps the oldest being the ornamental design bordering the dedication page,
                    which had been used as early as 1838 in <hi rend="i">The Metamorphoscope</hi>
                    (Boston: T. H. Carter). Nevertheless, my survey of the productions of Mrs.
                    Colman and her publishers makes clear that a great majority of the engravings in
                    the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and Girls’ Magazine</hi> were not
                    used earlier, although they were then frequently reused in later publications.
                    The unusually close correlation between texts and accompanying designs supports
                    the conclusion that new engravings usually were prepared to accompany specific
                    texts in the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and Girls’ Magazine.</hi>
                    <note id="n4">
                        <hi rend="s">4</hi> I have seen many publications by T. H. Carter
                        and related firms in a unique collection at the John Greene Chandler
                        Memorial at South Lancaster, Mass. Other collections which I have examined
                        include those at the Boston Atheneum, the American Antiquarian Society, the
                        Boston Public Library, Wellesley, and Harvard.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">August 1843</hi> “The Blossom” from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> appeared at
the end of the next number of the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and Girls’ Magazine</hi> (II, No. 4, 142)
                    (illus. 5). Mrs. Colman has made a drastic emendation of Blake’s
                    lines 6 and 12, which should read “Near my Bosom.” Also, the
                    words “hears you” belong to line 10. That this poem is the
                    last feature in Volume II of the magazine suggests that Mrs. Colman was
                    deliberately beginning one number and ending the next number, and the second
                    tri-annual volume, with Blake’s poems.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">September 1843</hi> A version of “Nurse’s
                    Song” from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> appeared in the subsequent issue
                    of the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and Girls’ Magazine</hi> (III,
                    No. 1, 9) (illus. 6). In none of Blake’s texts is Mrs.
                    Colman’s brazen ear, which so handicaps her as an editor of poetry,
                    more obvious than in her multitude of substantive emendations to this poem, most
                    of which seem to have no special purpose and which serve to destroy
                    Blake’s meter and even his rhyme scheme. We begin with the addition
                    of the indefinite article to the poem’s title, and proceed to the
                    syntactical inversion of the first sentence, which should begin, “When
                    the voices of children are heard” and which should not include
                    “When” at line 3. In the next stanza (Mrs. Colman might be
                    excused for ignoring the stanza divisions which are somewhat unclear on
                    Blake’s illuminated page), we should have “Then” in
                    place of “Now” and “gone down” rather than
                    simply “down” in line 5. In the next line, Blake tells us that
                    the dews “arise,” but Mrs. Colman, not content merely to have
                    them “fall,” tells us that they “fall fast.”
                    To complete the mutilation of this stanza, Mrs. Colman has omitted the
                    repetition of “come” at the beginning of line 7 and has the
                    morning appear in the “east” rather than in the
                    “skies,” which fortunately does nothing further to disturb the
                    rhyme scheme because she has already emended the preceding rhyme word from
                    “arise” to “fast.” This trend of unfortunate
                    emendation, which could only improve, does improve. In the last half of the
                    poem, our editor is content to destroy the final rhymes by changing
                    “bed” to “rest” at the end of line 12 and
                    then by adding “for joy” after a regularized spelling of
                    Blake’s “ecchoed.”</p>
                <p>Although Mrs. Colman has not been very careful in attending to the texts of
                    Blake’s “Nurse’s Song,” she has produced
                    an accompanying engraving similar to Blake’s designs for that poem
                    and for the title page of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (illus. 7, 8). I have
                    found neither an earlier nor a later use of the Victorian engraving. In the May
                    issue of the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and Girls’</hi>
                    <pb id="p11-7" n="7"/>
                    <figure n="NursesSong.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="418">
                    	<figTranscr>A NURSE’S SONG.<lb/>
                    	BY WILLIAM BLAKE.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	THE voice of children is heard on the green,<lb/>
                    	And laughing is heard on the hill;<lb/>
                    	When my heart is at rest within my breast,<lb/>
                    	And everything else is still.<lb/>
                    	“Now come home, my children, the sun is down,<lb/>
                    	And the dews of night fall fast;<lb/>
                    	Come, leave off play, and let us away,<lb/>
                    	Till the morning appears in the east.”<lb/>
                    	No, no, let us play, for it is yet day—<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	And we cannot go to sleep;<lb/>
                    	Besides, in the sky the little birds fly,<lb/>
                    	And the hills are all covered with sheep.<lb/>
                    	“Well, well, go and play till the light fades away,<lb/>
                    	And then go home to rest.”<lb/>
                    	The little ones leaped, and shouted, and laughed,<lb/>
                    	And all the hills echoed for joy.</figTranscr>
                        <head>Illus. 6</head>
                    </figure>
                    <figure n="s-inn.u.p9-24" id="s-inn.u.illbk.09" work-copy="s-inn.u" rend="db" width="689" height="1000">
                    	<figTranscr>Nurse’s Song<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	When the voices of children are heard on the green<lb/>
                    	And laughing is heard on the hill,<lb/>
                    	My heart is at rest within my breast<lb/>
                    	And every thing else is still<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Then come home my children, the sun is gone down<lb/>
                    	And the dews of night arise<lb/>
                    	Come come leave off play, and let us away<lb/>
                    	Till the morning appears in the skies<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	No no let us play, for it is yet day<lb/>
                    	And we cannot go to sleep<lb/>
                    	Besides in the sky, the little birds fly<lb/>
                    	And the hills are all coverd with sheep<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Well well go &amp; play till the light fades away<lb/>
                    	And then go home to bed<lb/>
                    	The little ones leaped &amp; shouted &amp; laugh’d<lb/>
                    	And all the hills ecchoed</figTranscr>
                        <head>Illus. 7, from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (U)</head>
                    </figure>
                    <figure n="s-inn.u.p1-3" id="s-inn.u.illbk.01" work-copy="s-inn.u" rend="db" width="633" height="1000">
                    	<figTranscr>SONGS<lb/>
                    	of<lb/>
                    	Innocence<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	1789<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	The Author &amp; Printer. WBlake</figTranscr>
                        <head>Illus. 8, from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (U)</head>
                    </figure>
                    <pb id="p11-8" n="8"/>
                    <figure n="TwoNurses.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="562">
                        <head>Illus. 9</head>
                    </figure>
                    <figure n="LaughingSkipping.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="416">
                    	<figTranscr>LAUGHING SONG.<lb/>
                    	BY WILLIAM BLAKE.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	WHEN the green woods laugh with the voice of joy,<lb/>
                    	And the dimpling stream runs laughing by,<lb/>
                    	When the air does laugh with our merry wit,<lb/>
                    	And the green hills laugh with the noise of it;<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	When the meadows laugh with lively green,<lb/>
                    	And the grasshopper laughs in the merry scene,<lb/>
                    	When Mary and Susan and Emily,<lb/>
                    	With their sweet round mouths sing, Ha, ha, ha;<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	When the painted birds laugh in the shade,<lb/>
                    	Where our table with cherries and nuts is spread;<lb/>
                    	Come live and be merry and join with me,<lb/>
                    	To sing the sweet chorus of Ha, ha, ha.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	THE SKIPPING-ROPE.<lb/>
                    	BY ALFRED TENNYSON.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	SURE never yet was antelope<lb/>
                    	Could skip so lightly by.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Stand off, or else my skipping-rope<lb/>
                    	With hit you in the eye.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	How lightly whirls the skipping-rope!<lb/>
                    	How fairy-like you fly!<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Go, get you gone, you muse and mope,<lb/>
                    	I hate that silly sigh.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Nay, dearest, teach me how to hope,<lb/>
                    	Or tell me how to die.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	There, take it, take my skipping-rope,<lb/>
                    	And hang yourself thereby.</figTranscr>
                        <head>Illus. 10</head>
                    </figure>
                    <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi>, however, there is an illustration which includes the
                    nurse and which is probably by the same designer (illus. 9). This illustration
                    also may have been produced with reference to Blake’s designs. Even
                    if it was not, the designer may have combined his preconceived iconography of
                    the nurse with some inspiration from Blake to produce the Victorian design
                    accompanying “Nurse’s Song.” Here the repeated use
                    of the rather Georgian chair with its high, rounded back both on
                    Blake’s title page and in the Victorian design for
                    “Nurse’s Song” is particularly important, for we
                    should expect our later designer, if indeed he had no knowledge of
                    Blake’s design, to situate his nurse on a Victorian chair as had been
                    done in the designs prepared a few months earlier.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">October 1843</hi> Blake’s “Laughing
                    Song” from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, with an interesting choice for
                    a companion piece, was the fourth of his poems to appear in successive monthly
                    numbers of the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and Girls’ Magazine</hi>
                    (III, No. 2, 66) (illus. 10). Besides emending “hill laughs”
                    to “hills laugh” at line 4, Mrs. Colman has given, instead of
                    the “He” which is quite clear on Blake’s
                    illuminated page, yet a third “ha” at the ends of he second
                    and third stanzas.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">1843</hi> It was probably during the latter part of this year that
                    “Mrs. Colman” edited—and her husband and his
                    co-publisher, T. H. Carter offered for sale—<hi rend="i">The Little
                        Keepsake for 1844</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5"
type="note">5</ref> which, we learn
                    from their advertisements, was intended primarily as a Christmas and New
                    Year’s gift. Included in this small volume are Blake’s
                    “A Dream” and “A Cradle Song” (illus. 11).
                    In “A Dream,” Mrs. Colman has emended the first words of
                    several lines: “Where” to “When” at line 4,
                    “All” to “Quite” at line 8, and
                    “Do” to “And” at line 10. She has also given
                    “do” for “how” at line 9, and
                    “beetle” for “beetles” at line 19. I have
                    found no other uses of this particular engraving, but it is very similar in
                    style to many illustrations of animals and foliage in the Colman and Carter
                    publications. <note id="n5">
                        <hi rend="s">5</hi>
                        <hi rend="i"> The Little Keepsake for 1844</hi>, ed. Mrs. S. Colman (Boston:
                        T. H. Carter and Co. [copyright 1843]). The <hi rend="i">NUC</hi> (NC
                        0555861) lists what seems to be another copy of this same work, but which
                        gives “Colman” of “New York” as
                        publisher; this copy, reported by the Boston Public Library, unfortunately
                        has disappeared from that library.</note>
                </p>
                <p>“A Cradle Song” is included in a story, “The
                    Baby,” which apparently was written by Mrs. Colman specifically to
                    display Blake’s poem and which reflects her continued enthusiasm for
                    his poems as works which should be known to her young readers (illus. 12). The
                    most substantial emendation is of line 4, which should read “By happy
                    silent moony beams.” Mrs. Colman has also given
                    “weeps” for Blake’s verb “weep”
                    at line 20 and “Thus” for “Thou” at line 27.
                    This engraving, which is not in any event notably similar to Blake’s
                    original illuminations, also appeared with Miss A. A. Gray’s story
                    “Little Charlie” in the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and
                        Girls’ Library</hi> (II, 62). This issue (June 1844) follows the
                    preparation of <hi rend="i">The Little Keepsake for 1844</hi> by several months
                    and is a good example of the reuse of a design which could fit several
                    narratives; here the design seems less appropriate to Blake’s poem
                    than to Miss Gray’s story, which begins: “‘The
                    Babe will not eat his breakfast; will he, mother?’ said little Laura.
                    ‘No; he will eat nothing. Poor little Charlie! He is very
                    ill.’”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">June 1844</hi> During 1844, Mrs. Colman edited the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and
Girls’ Library</hi> (Boston: T. H. Carter
                    and Co. [copyright 1844]), which was almost identical 
<pb id="p11-9" n="9"/>
                    <figure n="Emmet.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="398">
                    	<figTranscr>“But I saw a glow-worm near.”<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	STORY OF THE EMMET.<lb/>
                    	(A DREAM.)<lb/>
                    	BY WILLIAM BLAKE.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	ONCE a dream did weave a shade,<lb/>
                    	O’er my angel guarded bed,<lb/>
                    	That an Emmet lost its way —<lb/>
                    	Where on grass methought I lay.<lb/>
                    	Troubled, wildered, and forlorn,<lb/>
                    	Dark, benighted, travel-worn<lb/>
                    	Over many a tangled spray,<lb/>
                    	Quite heart-broke I heard her say,<lb/>
                    	Oh my children! how they cry;<lb/>
                    	And they hear their father sigh.<lb/>
                    	Now they look abroad to see,<lb/>
                    	Now return and weep for me.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Pitying, I drop’d a tear;<lb/>
                    	But I saw a glow-worm near,<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	STORY OF THE EMMET.   37<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Who replied, - What wailing wight<lb/>
                    	Calls the watchman of the night.<lb/>
                    	I am set to light the ground,<lb/>
                    	While the beetle goes his round;<lb/>
                    	Follow now the beetle hum -<lb/>
                    	Little wanderer, hie thee home.</figTranscr>
                        <head>Illus. 11</head>
                    </figure>
                    <figure n="Baby.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="754">
                    	<figTranscr>THE BABY.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	“OH, what a lovely little babe! Is it<lb/>
                    	really my sister, and may I sometimes<lb/>
                    	hold it, mamma?”<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	“Yes, my darling, and when it is larger<lb/>
                    	and stronger, you shall hold it a<lb/>
                    	much as you please.”<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	“Oh, dear, I am afraid she is going to<lb/>
                    	cry; may I sing that little song to her<lb/>
                    	that I learnt in William Blake’s “Songs<lb/>
                    	of Innocence,” mamma?”<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	“Yes, Helen, you may, if it is not<lb/>
                    	very long.”<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	“No, mamma, it is not, — and it is all<lb/>
                    	about a little baby.”<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	94   THE BABY.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	“Sweet dreams form a shade<lb/>
                    	O’er my lovely infant’s head,<lb/>
                    	Sweet dreams of pleasant streams<lb/>
                    	Under happy, silver moonbeams.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Sweet sleep, with soft down,<lb/>
                    	Weave thy brows an infant crown,<lb/>
                    	Sweet sleep, angel mild,<lb/>
                    	Hover o’er my happy child.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Sweet smiles in the night,<lb/>
                    	Hover over my delight,<lb/>
                    	Sweet smiles, mother’s smiles,<lb/>
                    	All the livelong night beguiles.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Sweet means, dove-like sighs,<lb/>
                    	Chase not slumber from thine eyes,<lb/>
                    	Sweet moans, sweeter smiles,<lb/>
                    	All the dove-like moans, beguiles.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	THE BABY.   95<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Sleep, sleep, happy child,<lb/>
                    	All creation slept and smiled:<lb/>
                    	Sleep, sleep, happy sleep,<lb/>
                    	While o’er thee thy mother weeps.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Sweet babe, in thy face,<lb/>
                    	Holy image I can trace,<lb/>
                    	Sweet babe, once like thee,<lb/>
                    	Thy Maker lay and wept for me.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Wept for me, for thee, for all,<lb/>
                    	When he was an infant small,<lb/>
                    	Thus His image ever see,<lb/>
                    	Heavenly face that smiles on thee.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Smiles on thee, on me, on all,<lb/>
                    	Who became an infant small —<lb/>
                    	Infant smiles are his own smiles,<lb/>
                    	Heaven and earth to peace beguiles.”<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	96   THE BABY.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	“Mamma, she is fast asleep; how<lb/>
                    	sweet she looks with her eyes shut! But<lb/>
                    	don’t you think that is a beautiful song?”<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	“Yes, indeed, my daughter; but now<lb/>
                    	little sister is sleeping, you had better go<lb/>
                    	out to play.”<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	“Well, good-by, darling sister, I will<lb/>
                    	come to see you again when you wake.<lb/>
                    	Let me first kiss your precious little hand.<lb/>
                    	There, now I’m gone.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	“Sleep, sleep, happy child,<lb/>
                    	All creation slept and smiled.”</figTranscr>
                        <head>Illus. 12</head>
                    </figure>
                    <pb id="p11-10" n="10"/>
                    <figure n="EveningHymn.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="734">
                    	<figTranscr>EVENING HYMN.<lb/>
                    	BY WILLIAM BLAKE.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	I KNOW, when I lie down to sleep,<lb/>
                    	The Lord is near my bed;<lb/>
                    	That angels watch, by his command,<lb/>
                    	Around my infant head.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	I know, when I kneel down to pray,<lb/>
                    	That still the Lord is there;<lb/>
                    	He hears my words, he sees my thoughts,<lb/>
                    	And listens to my prayer.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	I know, when I go forth to play,<lb/>
                    	The Lord is by my side;<lb/>
                    	Through every hour, at every step,<lb/>
                    	He is my guard and guide.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	I know his eye sees everything<lb/>
                    	In earth and sea and air;<lb/>
                    	The he in darkness, as in light,<lb/>
                    	Can see me everywhere.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Then let me guard each thought, each word,<lb/>
                    	Lest he should chance to find<lb/>
                    	Evil within a heart that should<lb/>
                    	Be gentle, meek, and kind.</figTranscr>
                        <head>Illus. 13</head>
                    </figure>
                    <figure n="ChildandLamb.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="721">
                    	<figTranscr>87<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	THE CHILD AND LAMB.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	BY W. BLAKE.<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	LITTLE lamb, who made thee?<lb/>
                    	Does thou know who made thee?<lb/>
                    	Gave thee life and bid thee feed<lb/>
                    	By the stream and o’er the mead;<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Gave thee clothing of delight—<lb/>
                    	Softest clothing woolly bright;<lb/>
                    	Gave thee such a tender voice—<lb/>
                    	Making all the vales rejoice:<lb/>
                    	Little lamb, who made thee?<lb/>
                    	Dost thou know who made thee?</figTranscr>
                        <head>Illus. 14, part 1</head>
                    </figure> to the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and Girls’
                        Magazine</hi> in subject matter and format, and which was issued in twelve
                    monthly numbers later bound in three successive volumes. In the issue for June
                    1844 (II, 47) she incorrectly attributes the poem “Evening
                    Hymn” to Blake (illus. 13). I have been unable to discover the correct
                    attribution of this sentimental piece; the prominence which she has given
                    Blake’s other poems and the absence of any other likely poet named
                    William Blake indicate that she did indeed consider “Evening
                    Hymn” and “The Lamb” works by the same poet. Mrs.
                    Colman’s error in attribution suggests that she no longer had
                    Blake’s original printing at hand, that she was now working with a
                    transcription of Blake’s poems which she had apparently confused with
                    a transcription of some other poet’s work.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">July 1844</hi> Mrs. Colman printed “The Lamb” in
                    the next monthly number of the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and
                        Girls’ Library</hi> (II, 87-88) (illus. 14). Instead of small
                    mistakes which might be attributed to careless transcription, we have the
                    substantive emendation of three important lines. Mrs. Colman has altered line
                    14, which should read “For he calls himself a Lamb,” and the
                    final two lines, both of which should read “Little Lamb God bless
                    thee.”</p>
                <figure n="USBank.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="833">
                	<figTranscr>88   LATE UNITED STATES BANK.<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	Little lamb, I’ll tell thee,<lb/>
                	Little lamb, I’ll tell thee.<lb/>
                	He is called by thy name,<lb/>
                	He is called himself a Lamb.<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	He is meek and he is mild,<lb/>
                	He became a little child;<lb/>
                	I a child and thou a lamb,<lb/>
                	We are called by his name.<lb/>
                	Little lamb, the Lord bless thee,<lb/>
                	Little lamb, God bless.<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	Songs of Innocence.<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	LATE UNITED STATES BANK. — Philadelphia.<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	THIS picture represents a very elegant edifice of white<lb/>
                	marble, and in its design and proportions are displayed<lb/>
                	the leading features of the Parthenon at Athens.<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	<lb/>
                	CONUNDRUM. — Why are poets like toys?</figTranscr>
                    <head>Illus. 14, part 2</head>
                </figure>
                <pb id="p11-11" n="11"/>
                <p>One difference between the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and Girls’
                        Magazine</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and Girls’
                        Library</hi> is that, apparently as an economy measure, the Colmans
                    frequently used engravings which were at hand from their earlier publications
                    and from other sources rather than going to the expense of regularly producing
                    engravings especially for particular texts. In fact, the cherub from the
                    engraving for Blake’s “Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> in the 
<hi rend="i">Boys’ and
                        Girls’ Magazine</hi> for July 1843 is used in the successor
                    publication to illustrate a piece about the aeolian harp (III, 48) (illus. 15).
                    The availability of the engraving with which Mrs. Colman accompanies
                    Blake’s “The Lamb” might explain why the lamb is
                    attended in the illustration by a woman rather than by a
                    “child” as in the text of Blake’s poem and in his
                    design. Originally, this engraving may have been prepared as an illustration of
                    Wordsworth’s “The Pet-Lamb” in <hi rend="i">Poems
                        for the Little Folks</hi> (New York: Samuel Colman), p. 38, which is similar
                    in typography and format to Samuel Colman’s New York publications of
                    about 1839. The engraving was later put to at least one less glorious use, as an
                    illustration for the story, “The Dwarf in Search of a
                    Lodging,” in Miss A. A. Gray’s <hi rend="i">John’s Adventures, or the Little Knight
Errant</hi> (Boston: S.
                    Colman [copyright 1846 by Mrs. P. Colman]), p. 62.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">1844</hi> As in the previous year, Mrs. Colman compiled a small
                    Christmas and New Year’s gift book, the <hi rend="i">Child’s Gem for 1845</hi>
(Boston: T. H. Carter &amp; Co.),
                    in which she included Blake’s “The Little Boy lost”
                    and “The Little Boy Found” from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>
                    (illus. 16). In the former poem, Mrs. Colman has added the word
                    “dear” to the first line, and she has made a quite significant
                    alteration in the sense of the poem by substituting “thick”
                    for “away” at line 8. For “The Little Boy
                    Found,” our Victorian editor’s text agrees with
                    Blake’s except for the addition of “he” to line
                    6.</p>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>The Source Text</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>A case establishing that Mrs. Colman has taken an original copy of
                        Blake’s <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> as her source text would be
                        substantial support of speculation about Mrs. Colman’s designs as
                        a graphic Victorian reinterpretation of Blake’s art and would add
                        to our interest in her various emendations and in her enthusiastic response
                        to Blake’s illuminated work. Similarities between the Victorian
                        designs and Blake’s originals suggest Mrs. Colman’s
                        use of an original copy; further, we can establish that she had access to
                        Copy U of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> in New York in 1843, and we can
                        discount the possibility that she has used earlier letterpress versions of
                        the poems as her source. 
						<q> Keynes gives a short history of 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (U):<lb/>
                            <lb/>
 Formerly in the possession of Robert
                            Balmanno, an English journalist, who emigrated to New York. He had been
                            friendly with Stothard and Fuseli and other artists who knew Blake, and
                            may have had the books directly from him. Afterwards in the collection
                            of E. W. Hooper, of Boston.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref>
                            <note id="n6">
                                <hi rend="s">6</hi> Sir Geoffrey Keynes and Edwin Wolf II,
                                    <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illuminated Books, A
                                    Census</hi> (New York: Grolier Club, 1953), p. 17. This copy is
                                described in detail by Thomas E. Connally in “<hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence</hi>, Keynes (1921) Copy U, Keynes-Wolf
                                (1953) Copy U,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 28
                                (Spring 1974), 88-89.</note>
						</q>
						On the flyleaf now found with Copy U, which is in the Houghton Library,
                        Harvard University, is Hooper’s 
                        <figure n="Cherub.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="400">
                            <head>Illus. 15</head>
                        </figure>
                        <figure n="LittleBoy.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="620">
                        	<figTranscr>THE LITTLE BOY LOST.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	Father, dear father, where are you going,<lb/>
                        	Oh do not walk so fast.<lb/>
                        	Speak father. speak to your little boy,<lb/>
                        	Or else I shall be lost.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	The night was dark, no father was there,<lb/>
                        	The child was wet with dew.<lb/>
                        	The swamp was deep, the child did weep,<lb/>
                        	And thick the vapor flew.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	THE LITTLE BOY FOUND.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	The little boy lost in the lonely fen,<lb/>
                        	Led by the wandering light,<lb/>
                        	Began to cry, but God ever nigh,<lb/>
                        	Appeared like his father in white.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	He kissed the child, and by the hand led,<lb/>
                        	And to his mother he brought,<lb/>
                        	Who in sorrow pale through the lonely dale,<lb/>
                        	Her little boy weeping sought.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	W. BLAKE.</figTranscr>
                        	<head>Illus. 16</head>
                        </figure>
                        <pb id="p11-12" n="12"/>
                        <figure n="Publications.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="604" height="1000">
                        	<figTranscr>S. COLMAN’S LIST OF PUBLICATIONS.   I<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	S. COLMAN<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	ANDERSON<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	SAMUEL COLMAN,<lb/>
                        	PUBLISHER AND BOOKSELLER.<lb/>
                        	No. VIII Aster House, Broadway, New-York.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	Complete in 1 vol. 8vo. law binding.<lb/>
                        	THE LAW OF PATENTS. BY W. PHILLIPS.<lb/>
                        	My Williard Phillips of Boston, is well known as the author of several valuable<lb/>
                        	law books. The present work is the only one on this subject in this <lb/>
                        	country.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	In 1 vol. 12mo. well bound.<lb/>
                        	THE INVENTOR’S GUIDE. BY W. PHILLIPS.<lb/>
                        	Author of “The Law of Patents.”<lb/>
                        	It comprises the Rules, Forms, and Proceedings for securing Patent Rights,<lb/>
                        	and embraces all that is considered of practical importance to Inventors and <lb/>
                        	Patentees.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	The following letter from the Commissioner of patents at Washington, respecting<lb/>
                        	the above valuable works, will fully establish their reputations.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	Patent Office, Washington.<lb/>
                        	WILLIARD PHILLIPS, ESQ.—Dear Sir, I have intended a long time to embrace<lb/>
                        	a leisure moment to assure you with how much pleasure I have perused<lb/>
                        	two works published by yourself, the Law of Patents, and the Inventor’s<lb/>
                        	Guide. Both of these are admirably calculated for the objects in view.<lb/>
                        	Much that is valuable is condensed in a small compass, and I trust you will</figTranscr>
                            <head>Illus. 17, part 1</head>
                        </figure> 
                        note which has supplied most of Keynes’ information and
                        which adds that Balmanno “died in Brooklyn N. Y. about 1865 (He was
                        formerly a Secty of Antiqu[ari]es of London?) E.W.H.”</p>
                    <p>Although an investigation of the entire history of Copy U is not called for
                        here, we should like to know enough about Balmanno’s situation in
                        New York to estimate the likelihood of his association with Mrs. Colman. I
                        have been able to piece together some idea of his American career from such
                        secondary sources as the <hi rend="i">NUC</hi>, Allibone’s 
<hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi>, which includes articles on Robert and Mary
                        Balmanno written in 1858, and the New York Historical Society’s
                            <hi rend="i">Dictionary of Artists in America</hi> (1957), which relies
                        upon a search of records at the National Academy of Design and the American
                            Institute.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref>
First, we can be certain
                        that Robert Balmanno (1780-1861, dates given in the <hi rend="i">NUC</hi>)
                        had emigrated to New York by 1843, the first year of Mrs.
                        Colman’s Blake publications. A date before 1835 is suggested by
                        Mrs. Balmanno’s “three poems written for special
                        occasions (July 3-4, 1835) at Geneva, N.Y.” which were added to a
                        copy of her <hi rend="i">Poems</hi> (London, 1830; <hi rend="i">NUC</hi>
                        NB0074878), and we know that in 1843 she was exhibiting her works at the
                        National Academy (NYHS <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi>). Although Robert
                        Balmanno actually made his living in New York as “a clerk at the
                        customhouse” (NYHS <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi>), by the later
                        years of the 1840s and into the next decade both of the Balmannos occupied
                        places of at least some small note in artistic and literary circles. Mary
                        Balmanno published various short poems, continued to exhibit her still life
                        paintings, produced “the beautiful drawing of all the flowers
                        mentioned by Shakespeare, which excited so much attention at the New York
                        Crystal Palace in 1853-54” (Allibone), and in 1858 published <hi rend="i">Pen and
Pencil</hi> (<hi rend="i">NUC</hi> NB0074877)
                        “illustrated with cuts, a majority of which were drawn on the block
                        by her own hand” (Allibone). This last work was published by D.
                        Appleton &amp; Co. as was her earlier edition of Thomas
                        Moore’s poems (1850, <hi rend="i">NUC</hi> NM0751581), a fact
                        which suggests a specific connection with Mrs. Colman, whose <hi rend="i">Innocence of
Childhood</hi> was also published by Appleton in 1850 (<hi rend="i">NUC</hi> NC0555851). Robert Balmanno’s
literary
                        career was quite similar. His first American work was published in 1846 
(<hi rend="i">NUC</hi> NB0074881), and two years later his <hi rend="i">Stoke
                            Church and Park</hi> (<hi rend="i">NUC</hi> NB0074882) was printed with
                        illustrations engraved after his own designs. In addition to his few short
                        works in the <hi rend="i">NUC</hi>, we are told by Allibone that he
                        “contributed many articles to the London periodicals and to the New
                        York Knickerbocker, Evening Post, and Graham’s (Phila.)
                        Magazine.” <note id="n7">
                            <hi rend="s">7</hi> S[amuel] Austin
                            Allibone, <hi rend="i">Dictionary of English Literature</hi>
                            (Philadelphia: Lippincott, 1886); the writer of the article on Balmanno
                            states that his account was written in 1858. George C. Groce and David
                            H. Wallace, <hi rend="i">The New-York Historical Society’s
                                Dictionary of Artists in America, 1564-1860</hi> (New Haven: Yale,
                            1957).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Although the preceding evidence documents the Balmannos’ literary
                        activities only after 1843, it seem reasonable to assume that their
                        association with literary circles probably began soon after their arrival in
                        New York. It would then seem quite possible that by 1843 the Balmannos may
                        have found their way to Samuel Colman’s successful publishing
                        house on Broadway which was “one of the first in this country to
                        publish illustrated books in color; and which became a gathering place for
                        literary men and artists” (<hi rend="i">Appleton’s
                            Cyclopedia of American Biography</hi>, III, 546), probably including
                        Longfellow and the dramatist Willis, whom Colman published (<hi rend="i">Dictionary of
American Biography</hi>) (illus. 17). There they may have
                        loaned Blake’s illustrated volume to the publisher’s
                            <pb id="p11-13" n="13"/>
wife, who was then editing an illustrated
                        children’s magazine. Of course <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (U)
                        may have come to Mrs. Colman in a multitude of other ways; it is even
                        possible that Balmanno had sold Copy U by 1843 and that she had it on loan
                        from someone else, possibly her brother-in-law, William, a publisher of
                        prints who was then preparing to open “the first gallery in the
                        city for the sale of pictures” (<hi rend="i">ACAB</hi>). It is the
                        combination of Mrs. Colman’s access to Copy U of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>
together with her production of designs similar to
                        Blake’s originals which most strongly supports the case that her
                        source was this original copy of <hi rend="i">Innocence.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>The remainder of the case for Mrs. Colman’s use of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (U)
depends upon our exclusion of other possible
                        sources. We can first discount the possibility that Mrs. Colman has used
                        earlier letterpress versions of the poems. Wilkinson’s (1839) and
                        Tulk’s (1843 or later) complete editions of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> were the
only letterpress sources to include all or even
                        most of the poems which Mrs. Colman prints. Tulk’s edition of
                        only twelve copies was printed on paper watermarked 1843 and may well have
                        been produced after Mrs. Colman’s first printing of a Blake poem,
                        in July 1843; neither do we have any evidence that a copy was available in
                            America.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref>
We do know that at least
                        one copy of Wilkinson’s edition had made its way across the
                        Atlantic by 1843, for at a time almost exactly contemporaneous with Mrs.
                        Colman’s first printings, we find in the <hi rend="i">New Church
                            Magazine for Children</hi> (Boston: August-December 1843) five of
                        Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> given in a text following
                        Wilkinson’s almost exactly;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">9</ref>
                        copies belonging to Emerson and T. W. Higginson may also have been available
                        at this early date.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
type="note">10</ref> Mrs.
                        Colman’s texts have no recognizable pattern of similarity to the
                        punctuation, capitalization, stanza divisions and other emendations by which
                        Wilkinson’s texts differ from Blake’s originals. It is
                        true that Mrs. Colman was not particularly careful with many of her texts:
                        for example, in Tennyson’s “The May Queen” (<hi rend="i">Boys’ and Girls’
Magazine</hi>, II, No.
                        1, 12-13) she gives only one “black” in line 5 and
                        contracts his “woven” to
                        “wov’n” at line 25, both of which emendations
                        adversely affect the meter. Yet the text in substance and accidentals
                        clearly shows that she was cognizant, if not particularly respectful, of
                        Tennyson’s printed text,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">11</ref>
                        and I think it reasonable to suppose that even someone who has treated
                        Blake’s “Nurse’s Song” as she has
                        would betray some familiarity with Wilkinson’s version if that
                        were her source. <note id="n8">
                            <hi rend="s">8</hi> Sir Geoffrey Keynes
                            describes the two known surviving copies of Tulk’s edition
                            (now at the British Museum and Liverpool University) in “Blake,
                            Tulk and Garth Wilkinson,” <hi rend="i">The Library</hi>, 4th
                            ser. 26 (1945), 190-92.</note>
                        <note id="n9">
                            <hi rend="s">9</hi> Cited in my “Unnoticed
                            Printings.” The copy of Wilkinson’s edition used by
                            the Swedenborgians in 1843 was probably available to them a year
                            earlier, when another Boston Swedenborgian publication, the <hi rend="i">New
Jerusalem Magazine</hi>, reprinted Wilkinson’s text
                            of “The Lamb” (16 (September, 1842), 40).</note>
                        <note id="n10">
                            <hi rend="s">10</hi> In “The 1839 Wilkinson Edition
                            of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> in Transcendental
                            America,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 16 (Winter,
                            1970-71), Edward J. Rose discusses two copies, those of Emerson and T.
                            W. Higginson, which may have been in America by 1843.</note>
                        <note id="n11">
                            <hi rend="s">11</hi> I have compared Mrs. Colman’s
                            text to the American edition published by W. D. Ticknor (Boston,
                            1842).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Another possibility is that Mrs. Colman may have seen a manuscript
                        transcription by a third party, who would then be held responsible for the
                        various emendations. A third party could even have been responsible for
                        sketching Blake’s designs and thus for providing Mrs. Colman with
                        a semblance of Blake’s original. Although it is possible that
                        Mrs. Colman may have seen a manuscript which has not been traced in Blake
                        scholarship, I know of only one transcription—this one complete
                        with detailed copies of Blake’s designs—which
                        eventually found its way to America, but its text differs in particulars
                        from that given by Mrs. Colman.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12"
type="note">12</ref> A
                        final possibility is that Mrs. Colman had seen an original copy of 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> or of the complete <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> but
                        not Copy U. No other copies are reported by Keynes (<hi rend="i">Census</hi>) as
                        <figure n="PublicationsDetail.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="465">
                        	<figTranscr>S. COLMAN</figTranscr>
                            <head>Illus. 17, detail</head>
                        </figure>
                        <pb id="p11-14" n="14"/>
                        <figure n="MagazineTitlePage.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="732">
                        	<figTranscr>BOYS’ AND GIRLS’<lb/>
                        	MAGAZINE.<lb/>
                        	EDITED BY MRS. S. COLMAN.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	CONTRIBUTORS.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	REV. JACOB ABBOTT,<lb/>
                        	T. S. ARTHUR,<lb/>
                        	MRS. L. H. SIGOURNEY,<lb/>
                        	MRS. F. S. OSGOOD,<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	MRS. A. J. GRAVES,<lb/>
                        	MRS. SUSAN JEWETT,<lb/>
                        	WILLIAM CUTTER, ESQ.,<lb/>
                        	EDITOR OF THE YOUTH’S KEEPSAKE,<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	MISS H. F. GOULD,<lb/>
                        	MRS. E. GOODWIN,<lb/>
                        	MISS C. M. SEDGWICK.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	BOSTON.<lb/>
                        	PUBLISHED BY T. H. CARTER &amp; CO.</figTranscr>
                            <head>Illus. 18</head>
                        </figure> having been available in America at such an early date, but for
                        our purposes, new evidence about the availability of another copy would only
                        strengthen our most important argument: that Mrs. Colman has seen an
                        original copy of Blake’s illuminated work. Of course we should
                        like to know exactly which copy she used as a source text, but it is more
                        important that her texts, her enthusiastic reaction to Blake’s
                        works, and some of her illustrations may have been in response to the
                        original form of Blake’s art. <note id="n12">
                            <hi rend="s">12</hi>
                            G. E. Bentley, Jr., “The Contemporary Facsimiles of <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence and of Experience</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Papers of the Bibliographical Society of America</hi>, 64
                            (1970), 450-63. Copy “Alpha” (c. 1805) remained in
                            England until 1958. The history of copy “Beta” (c.
                            1821), which was made from copy “Alpha,” is not known
                            before its sale in San Francisco in 1965.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>We must consider briefly some of the obvious problems and questions which
                        remain in connection with the hypothesis that the designs in Mrs.
                        Colman’s publications derive from Blake’s original
                        illuminations. How might the design have been transmitted from Mrs. Colman
                        in New York to T. H. Carter in Boston? Can we know who might have done the
                        designing and engraving? A study of the signed engravings in the
                        “Boys’ and Girls’” series of 1843
                        and 1844 shows the services both of Boston engravers (John Greene Chandler,
                        George T. Devereux, Fernando E. Worcester) and of New York engravers
                        (Alexander Anderson, Joline J. Butler, Marx M. Hart, and William
                            Howland).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13"
type="note">13</ref> These facts put us no
                        closer to knowing who actually designed or engraved the illustrations to the
                        Blake poems; none of these engravers seems to have been very active as a
                        designer, and none of the signed engravings bears a particular technical
                        resemblance to the Victorian illustrations of Blake’s
                        poems—but they do indicate that at least some of the designs and
                        engravings issued from New York. If the engravings illustrating
                        Blake’s “Introduction” and
                        “Nurse’s Song” were prepared in New York, we
                        can suppose, given her prominent and deliberate display of
                        Blake’s poems and the special production of the accompanying
                        engraving, that Mrs. Colman may have shown the designer Blake’s
                        original with instructions about how she would like text and illustration
                        arranged on the page. <note id="n13">
                            <hi rend="s">13</hi> For information on
                            these engravers see the <hi rend="i">NYHS Dictionary</hi> and Sinclair
                            Hamilton, <hi rend="i">Early American Book Illustrators and Wood
                                Engravers, 1670-1870</hi>, 2 vols. (Princeton Univ. Press,
                            1968).</note>
                    </p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>American Children’s Books at Mid-Century</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>We should also consider the immediate context in which Mrs.
                        Colman’s readers encountered Blake’s poems. The <hi rend="i">Boys’ and Girls’
Magazine</hi> is
                        generally representative of all four publications considered here. Although
                        the Blake printings have previously gone unnoticed, the work has a place in
                        the bibliography of American literature for the first printing of a
                        Hawthorne story. In the August 1843 issue, also containing the bowdlerized
                        version of “The Blossom,” we find Hawthorne’s
                        “Little Daffydowndilly” (II, No. 4, 264-69), the story of
                        a boy by this name who, through various encounters with a rather irksome
                        character named Mr. Toil, learns that “diligence is not a whit more
                        toilsome than sport or idleness” (269). Even more important for its
                        contemporary reputation, the magazine had as contributors some of the most
                        popular writers of juvenile stories and verse (illus. 18). Jacob Abbott
                        (1803-79) was a prolific writer of moral works (48 pages in the 
<hi rend="i">NUC</hi>), most notably <hi rend="i">The Young Christian</hi> (1832 and
                        numerous editions thereafter) and of the extended juvenile series, the 
<hi rend="i">Rollo</hi> and <hi rend="i">Lucy</hi> books. Abbott had moved
                        to New York in 1843, and his contributions may well have resulted from his
                        personal association with the Colmans (<hi rend="i">DAB</hi>). T. S. Arthur
                        (1809-85) was another prolific writer of children’s books (36
                        pages in the 
<pb id="p11-15" n="15"/>
                        <hi rend="i">NUC</hi>), although his greatest fame came from <hi rend="i">Ten Nights
in a Barroom and What I Saw There</hi> (1854), a volume
                        which enjoyed sales in the 1850s second only to those of <hi rend="i">Uncle
                            Tom’s Cabin</hi> (<hi rend="i">DAB</hi>). We should note that
                        Arthur manifested an interest in Blake after his involvement with Mrs.
                        Colman’s publications; his <hi rend="i">The Brilliant: A Gift
                            Book for 1850</hi> (New York: 1850) included the text of “The
                        Tyger” and a lengthy account of Blake’s life taken from
                        Cunningham (120-26). Later, Arthur repeated an anecdote from Cunningham in
                        “Death of Blake, the Painter,” <hi rend="i">Arthur’s Home Magazine</hi>, 3 (March
1854), 220. The
                        publications of Lydia Howard Sigourney (1791-1865) may have exceeded those
                        of Abbott and Arthur combined, in number if not in length (<hi rend="i">ACAB</hi>,
Vol. I, 154). In the <hi rend="i">Dictionary of American
                            Biography</hi> we read that “it is almost impossible to find a
                        number of one of the popular magazines of the thirties or forties that does
                        not contain a poem or an article by her”; indeed, “the
                        inevitable regularity with which her poetic tribute followed the demise of
                        any prominent person led a wag to declare that she had added a new terror to
                        death.” Catherine Maria Sedgwick (1789-1867) was on one occasion
                        praised by her co-contributor, Hawthorne, as “our most truthful
                        novelist” (<hi rend="i">DAB</hi>). A series of novels published
                        from 1825-35 and marked by “extravagent and imitative
                        romanticism” (<hi rend="i">DAB</hi>) had established her as perhaps
                        the most popular woman author in the country, and she continued with
                        increasingly moral works until 1857. The only other contributors to the
                        magazine noted in American biography (<hi rend="i">DAB</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">ACAB</hi>) are Hannah Flagg Gould (1789-1865), and Frances Sargent
                        Osgood (1811-50), poets whose chief works were short, innocuous
                        contributions to magazines and annuals. In addition, Miss Gould edited
                        several juvenile works in this genre; Mrs. Osgood did some similar editorial
                        work and published several volumes of verse on floral topics.</p>
                    <p>Although Mrs. Colman apparently had managed to assemble for her magazines and
                        annuals the work of many well known writers, their contributions might seem
                        strikingly undifferentiated to the modern reader. What we might see as an
                        oppressive lack of innovation is not really so very surprising, for the
                        surge of juvenile literature in the thirties and forties had actually begun
                        with a formal code set for authors and editors by the American Sunday School
                        Union, which published 6,000,000 volumes between 1824 and 1830.
                        Contributions were to be adapted to the children’s level, to
                        adhere to high standards of style and content, to have an American
                        character, and to be morally and religiously impeccable, although
                            non-denominational<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">14</ref> (illus. 19).
                            <note id="n14">
                            <hi rend="s">14</hi> John Tebbell, <hi rend="i">A History
                                of Book Publishing in the United States</hi>, 2 vols. (New York: R.
                            R. Bowker, 1972), I, 531.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>This code and the strict traditions which flowed from it may help us to
                        understand Mrs. Colman’s treatment of Blake’s poems.
                        On one level, some of her emendations may be understandable attempts to
                        present Blake’s poems as correct and instructive models of the
                        English language—as any work in her collection might have been
                        expected to serve. This requirement certainly explains her addition of heavy
                        punctuation as well as many of her alterations of capitalization and
                        spelling, for example her regularization of “chear”
                        (“Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>) to the
                        standard Victorian American spelling, “cheer.” Especially
                        in the case of Blake, whose text was difficult to read and whose works were 
                        <figure n="MagazineIntro.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="610">
                        	<figTranscr>INTRODUCTION<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	It is with feelings of pleasure, my dear young friends, that the editor<lb/>
                        	of the “GIRL’S AND BOY’S MAGAZINE” enters upon the duties of preparing<lb/>
                        	a monthly repast for your moral and intellectual nature, because<lb/>
                        	she anticipates being able, with the kind and generous assistance<lb/>
                        	of several Ladies and Gentlemen, who have already done much for your<lb/>
                        	happiness, in preparing for you good books, to place before you, in<lb/>
                        	the pages of this Magazine, such Pictures, Tales, Anecdotes, Travels,<lb/>
                        	Biography, and Amusement, as may, if rightly improved, cultivate<lb/>
                        	your taste, improve your judgment, awaken a desire for rational inquiry,<lb/>
                        	and teach, confirm, and strengthen the moral principles and best<lb/>
                        	affections of the heart.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	Without making any further engagements of what shall be done,<lb/>
                        	allow me to wish you a “Happy New-Year,” and to invite you to read,<lb/>
                        	and judge for yourselves, the monthly numbers of the MAGAZINE FOR<lb/>
                        	GIRLS AND BOYS.</figTranscr>
                            <head>Illus. 19</head>
                        </figure>
                        <pb id="p11-16" n="16"/>
almost unknown, Mrs. Colman—in the best
                        tradition of nearly all of Blake’s nineteenth century
                        editors—apparently felt an almost complete freedom in bringing
                        his works into conformity with the established code. An innocent but
                        substantial example is the final line of “Nurse’s
                        Song”; Blake’s “And all the hills
                        ecchoed” may have been intended to leave the echo pointedly
                        unexplained, but Mrs. Colman apparently felt it necessary to make explicit
                        for her young readers that the hills echo “for joy,” lest
                        they think otherwise. Similarly, the “dews of night” in
                        the same poem might be said to “fall fast” rather than to
                        “arise” because Mrs. Colman has in mind some scientific
                        explanation which she believes accurate for the phenomenon of dew (her
                        explanation seems no closer than Blake’s to the scientific fact
                        that dew condenses). Attention to the facts of Scripture may explain the
                        emendation of Blake’s “For he calls himself a
                        Lamb:” (“The Lamb,” line 14) to “<hi rend="i">He</hi> is called 
<hi rend="i">himself</hi> a Lamb.”
                        Mrs. Colman is correct in that Jesus never calls himself a lamb, although he
                        is often so named, e.g. John 1: 29. As for the illustrations, the piper and
                        cherub of Blake’s frontispiece are draped according to popular
                        stereotypes, while the angel is given a small harp and the shepherd a
                        faithful dog, because they serve, as does Blake’s poem, as proper
                        introductions to a series of moral poems and tales. About the emendation to
                        “A Blossom,” we can easily understand Mrs.
                        Colman’s categorical exclusion of the word
                        “bosom”; this emendation also suggests her idea of a
                        Victorian order for the natural world as she would have the blossom wish the
                        sparrow and robin to be “In the greenwood tree” rather
                        than “Near my bosom.”</p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="b">Swedenborgian Interest in Blake</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Mrs. Colman’s unique “edition” of
                        Blake’s poems should also be understood in the context of
                        American Swedenborgianism. “Samuel Colman” and
                        “Mrs. Pamela C. Colman” of New York had joined the Boston
                        Society of the New Jerusalem in 1833, and in succeeding years Colman
                        advertised and sold many of Swedenborg’s works and such
                        Swedenborgian collaterals as the <hi rend="i">New Jerusalem
                            Magazine.</hi>
                        <ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> That Mrs.
                        Colman’s Swedenborgian interests continued after 1839 is clear
                        from her <hi rend="i">Innocence of Childhood</hi> (New York: Appleton,
                        1850), which was reviewed and advertised in Swedenborgian periodicals and
                        which includes fairly direct references to Swedenborg’s teachings
                        although the master’s name is not mentioned.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n16" type="note">16</ref> Indeed it may well have been through the
                        Swedenborgian connection that Colman and T. H. Carter came together to
                        publish the volumes which are the objects of our study. Carter had joined
                        the Boston Society in 1821 and continued as an important member in
                        subsequent years.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">17</ref> The fact of the
                        Colmans’, and the Carters’, Swedenborgianism might
                        itself seem a circumstance unrelated to their printing of Blake’s
                        poems except for the remarkable coincidence that almost every other printing
                        of Blake’s poems in America before the time of Gilchrist seems to
                        have depended upon various Swedenborgians.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n18" type="note">18</ref> All these coincidences may have resulted from the fact that so
                        many Swedenborgians were involved in publishing, but I think that the
                        evidence of specific Swedenborgian statements about Blake, especially the
                        American view expressed in articles about Blake and Flaxman in the <hi rend="i">New
Jerusalem Magazine</hi> (1831),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref>
suggests that their Swedenborgianism gave these
                        individuals a special interest in sustaining the memory of Blake. <note id="n15">
                            <hi rend="s">15</hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> A Sketch of the History of the Boston Society of the New
                                Jerusalem, with a list of its members</hi> (Boston: John C. Regan,
                            1873), p. 84. “S. Colman’s List of
                            Publications,” op. cit., p. 9.</note>
                        <note id="n16">
                            <hi rend="s">16</hi> See especially pp. 11-24 for Mrs.
                            Colman’s Swedenborgian interpretation of
                            “Innocence.” A short review praising Mrs. Colman for
                            having “managed to interweave some of the choicest truths and
                            lessons of the New Church” into “a pleasant vein of
                            fiction” appeared in the <hi rend="i">New Church
                                Repository</hi>, 1 (New York, 1850), p. 50. Advertisements listing
                            the work appeared on the paper cover of another New York Swedenborgian
                            Journal, <hi rend="i">The Herald of Light</hi>, e. g., the back cover of
                            2, No. 1 (May 1858).</note>
                        <note id="n17">
                            <hi rend="s">17</hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> History of the Boston Society</hi>, pp. 82, 15, 27-28,
                            73.</note>
                        <note id="n18">
                            <hi rend="s">18</hi> All of the American reprintings included
                            in my “Unnoticed Printings” are of Swedenborgian
                            origin. T. S. Arthur, whose works I have mentioned in my text, was a
                            Swedenborgian, as was Mrs. D. L. Child, the author of the popular 
<hi rend="i">Good Wives</hi>, which included sketches of Blake and
                            Flaxman. Longfellow’s printings in <hi rend="i">The
                                Estray</hi> (1847) may have had a source with Samuel Colman, who was
                            one of his New York publishers before 1845. Henry James, Sr., had the
                            poems which he reprinted in <hi rend="i">The Harbinger</hi> (1848) from
                            Garth Wilkinson.</note>
                        <note id="n19">
                            <hi rend="s">19</hi> “Memoir of Flaxman the
                            Sculptor” and “Memoirs of William Blake,” <hi rend="i">New Jerusalem
Magazine</hi>, 5 (1831-32), pp. 153-60,
                            192-99.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Unlike more conventional rationalists of the nineteenth century, the
                        Swedenborgians had no quarrel with what the editor of the <hi rend="i">New
                            Jerusalem Magazine</hi> called Blake’s “continual
                        intercourse with spirits” (p. 193). Swedenborg himself had
                        conversed frequently with spirits and had been privileged to visit their
                        heavens and hells on many occasions. The very fact that Blake had spiritual
                        visions argued for the existence of a spiritual world, the basic tenet of
                        the Swedenborgian world view. Blake’s error, they believed, was
                        “the strange use he made of this intercourse,” and it was
                        seen in contrast to Flaxman’s rational, Swedenborgian
                        interpretation of his spiritual vision: 
						<q> But while Flaxman believed in
                            the reality of a spiritual world, and in the actual and personal
                            existence of spirits, as fully as Blake, in him this belief had nothing
                            in it or with it of unregulated enthusiasm or of wild phantasy; he
                            believed, and he knew why and what he believed, . . . But it was not so
                            with Blake. He was gifted with perhaps an equal talent, and he appears
                            to have embraced some of the peculiar opinions of Flaxman, but not
                            understandingly; and these truths were, in his case, little more than
                            broken parts of a system of which he knew not the unity and coherence;
                            and they were mingled with falsities and made to minister to his
                            self-conceit, and grievously distorted by the false medium through which
                            he saw them. (p. 193) </q>
Although Blake’s interpretation of
                        his visions was misguided, the editor believed that the worth of the visions
                        themselves was to be acknowledged: 
						<q> We do not say that their [the
                            visions’] influence was destroyed or entirely perverted, for
                            there was enough in his character to justify the hope that this was not
                            the case; nevertheless, our readers will find in the following account
                            of him frequent occasions for pity and regret. (p. 193) </q>
                    </p>
                    <p>We should add that this same magazine was, some ten years later, the first
                        American publication (with the exception of American editions of
                        Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives</hi>) to reprint one of
                        Blake’s poems, “The Lamb,” in September 1842
                        (p. 40). Further, in 1843 and 1844 the <hi rend="i">New Church Magazine for
                            Children</hi> reprinted several of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi> Despite
their criticism of Blake’s excesses in
                        interpreting his spiritual vision, the American Swedenborgians may well have
                        agreed with J. J. Garth Wilkinson’s argument, in the preface to
                        his edition of 1839, that at least Blake’s <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> represented a
vision of the eternal state of childhood
                        in accord with Swedenborg’s teachings.</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Colman had joined the Boston Society of the New Jerusalem on 7 April
                        1833, only a little more than a year after the articles about Flaxman and
                        Blake appeared in the Society’s publication, the <hi rend="i">New
                            Jerusalem Magazine</hi>, and that her husband was later a New York
                        distributor of that periodical also suggests 
                    <pb id="p11-17" n="17"/> 
                    	that she may have known the articles. Mrs. Colman may be sharing the special
                        interest of the other Boston Swedenborgians in sustaining Blake’s
                        memory when she chooses to introduce so prominently to her nineteenth
                        century readers the poems of Blake, whom, in accord with the editors of the
                            <hi rend="i">New Jerusalem Magazine</hi>, she associates with Flaxman in
                        her brief biographical sketch.</p>
                    <p>Mrs. Colman’s Swedenborgianism also offers one explanation of her
                        emendations to Blake’s poems and illustrations. That she gives
                        “the Lord” instead of Blake’s
                        “God” in the penultimate line of “The
                        Lamb” may possibly reflect a habit of Swedenborgian expression,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> but otherwise there is little evidence
                        of Swedenborgian influence in her emendations. Although many of her small
                        emendations are certainly due more to carelessness and to her insensitivity
                        to rhyme and meter than to a deliberate, philosophical interpretation, a
                        critical predisposition against Blake’s “unregulated
                        enthusiasm” and “wild phantasy” may have
                        increased her disregard for the authority of Blake’s given text.
                        As for the designs, Mrs. Colman may have agreed with Blake that his
                        arrangement of the piper and the angel were an appropriate illustration of
                        his “Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, but
                        instead of the naked and energetic figures which Blake may have seen in the
                        excesses of his “unregulated enthusiasm,” Mrs. Colman has
                        seen fit to present his design in a much more conventional and rationally
                        acceptable manner. We should add that however strongly Mrs. Colman may have
                        felt about the supposed Swedenborgian content of Blake’s vision
                        of innocence, she probably would not in any event have made overtly
                        Swedenborgian references in her emendations or in her short biographical
                        sketch of Blake, for such reference would have violated the requirements of
                        non-denominationalism. The reader familiar with Swedenborg’s
                        writings can recognize as Swedenborgian the references in her publications
                        to “Use” or to “Divine Providence,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n21" type="note">21</ref> but these are presented in such a way
                        as to be consistent with the standard nineteenth-century Protestant view of
                        the world. The point is that just because she makes no overt connection
                        between Blake and Swedenborg, we should not discount the extent to which
                        Mrs. Colman may have shared in Swedenborgian interest in Blake’s
                        life and work and the possible significance of this interest in her decision
                        to display prominently a number of Blake’s poems. <note id="n20">
                            <hi rend="s">20</hi> See Swedenborg’s <hi rend="i">True
                                Christian Religion</hi>, Section 81.</note>
                        <note id="n21">
                            <hi rend="s">21</hi> E.g., T. S. Arthur’s
                                little story “The Delight of Use,” <hi rend="i">Boys’ and Girls’
Magazine</hi>, I, No. 3,
                                90-94, and a Swedenborgian analysis of the “use”
                                of conundrums and riddles according to the concept of
                                “Divine Providence” by “W,” <hi rend="i">Boys’ and Girls’ Library</hi>, I,
                                No. 1, 31-32. Mrs. Colman’s contributions seem free of
                                Swedenborgian coloration.
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p>In Mrs. Colman we have a person who, in the years of relative public neglect
                        which preceded the Blake revival of the 1860s, found the illuminated poems
                        of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> so interesting that she displayed them
                        prominently in her publications and possibly had some of Blake’s
                        original illustrations redesigned and engraved, thus providing us with a
                        unique graphic interpretation of Blake’s art. The context of her
                        little “edition” is important because it indicates some of
                        the various channels by which Blake’s reputation survived. We see
                        the fortuitous coming together of a copy of Blake’s poems,
                        probably <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (U), with a publisher, and we see that
                        Blake’s poems were of interest chiefly because of their openness
                        to interpretation as lyrics intended for the delight and edification of
                        children. Finally, Mrs. Colman’s printings reflect the special
                        Swedenborgian interest in Blake’s life and works which helped to
                        sustain Blake’s reputation during the years before Gilchrist.</p>
                    <pb id="p11-18" n="18"/> 
					<note type="unreferenced">
						<p>
							<hi rend="i">Additional notes on the
								illustrations.</hi> The “Prospectus” (illus.
							1) is printed on the back of the paper cover in which the April 1843
							monthly issue of the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and
								Girls’ Magazine</hi> was bound; identical covers,
							with the exception of the printed date and volume number, seem to
							have been used for all twelve issues of the publication. The
							original page size of the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and
								Girls’ Magazine</hi>, the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and Girls’ Library</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The
Rustic Wreath</hi> is 6 ¾″ by 5
							¼″. The three illustrations from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (illus. 3, 7, 8) are produced from Copy
U, the
							same copy which was probably available to Mrs. Colman and which is
							now at the Houghton Library, Harvard University. The two designs of
							the old woman (illus. 9) appear on successive pages of the May 1843
							issue of the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and Girls’
								Magazine</hi> (II, No. 1, 24-25) and illustrate a narrative
							poem, “Julia Clifford.” “A
							Dream” (illus. 11) appears on pages 35-37 and “The
							Baby” (illus. 12), including Blake’s
							“Cradle Song,” on pages 92-96 of the <hi rend="i">Little Keepsake for 1844</hi>; the original page size
is 3
							¾″ by 2 ¾″. “The
							Little Boy lost” and “The Little Boy
							Found” (illus. 16) appear on page 69 of the <hi rend="i">Child’s Gem for 1845</hi>; the original page
size is
							4 ½″ by 7 ¼″. The title page
							of the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and Girls’
								Magazine</hi> reproduced here (illus. 18) is that of the second
							tri-annual volume. Mrs. Colman’s
							“Introduction” (illus. 19) is printed on the third
							page of the first issue of the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and
								Girls’ Magazine.</hi>
						</p>
						<p>Illustrations are reproduced with the generous permission of the
							following institutions: the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and
								Girls’ Magazine</hi> courtesy of the Swedenborg
							School of Religion, Newton, Massachusetts; the <hi rend="i">Boys’ and Girls’ Library</hi> courtesy
of
							The Boston Athenaeum; the <hi rend="i">Little Keepsake for 1844</hi>
							courtesy of the Houghton Library, Harvard University; <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (U) courtesy of the
Houghton Library, Department
							of Printing and Graphic Arts, Harvard University; the <hi rend="i">Child’s Gem for 1845</hi> courtesy
of the Boston
							Public Library; <hi rend="i">The Rustic Wreath</hi> courtesy of the
							John Greene Chandler Memorial, South Lancaster, Massachusetts. For
							assistance with the complex bibliographical problems presented by
							the material in this article, I am indebted to the staff of the
							above institutions and of the American Antiquarian Society, of the
							Margaret Clapp Library, Wellesley College, and of the Goldfarb
							Library, Brandeis University, particularly: Victor Burch, Special
							Collections Librarian, and Barton Lessin, Assistant Reference
							Librarian, Goldfarb Library, Brandeis University; Marian Kirven,
							Librarian, Swedenborg School of Religion; Herbert H. Hosmer,
							Curator, John Greene Chandler Memorial; Miss Eleanor Garvey,
							Curator, and David Becker, <corr type="emend">Assistant</corr> Curator, Department of Printing
							and Graphic Arts, Houghton Library, Harvard University; Jack
							Jackson, Art Department, and Ann Wadsworth, Rachel Stuhlman, and
							Kathleen S. Boyd, Reference Department, The Boston Athenaeum; and
							Miss Eleanor Nicholes, Special Collections Librarian, Margaret Clapp
							Library, Wellesley College.</p>
					</note>
                    <figure n="Fence.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="350"/>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>