<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>11.1.erdman</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Preface to the Revised Edition of Blake’s Notebook</title>
                <author n="Erdman">David V. Erdman</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1977</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1977</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">11.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Brad Hayden</name>
                            <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
                            <name>Michael Hays</name>
                            <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
                            <name>Jane Welford</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>John Beer</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Raymond Deck</name>
                            <name>Thomas Dilworth</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
                            <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
                            <name>Donald L. Kent</name>
                            <name>Vivian Mercier</name>
                            <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
                            <name>Dennis Read</name>
                            <name>Grant C. Roti</name>
                            <name>Richard J. Schroyer</name>
                            <name>Ruthven Todd</name>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1977"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_11">
        <body>
            <pb id="p11-21" n="21"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-11-1-0005">
                <head>
                    <title type="main">
                        <hi rend="b">Preface to the Revised Edition of Blake’s
                            Notebook</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <byline>
                    <hi rend="b">by</hi>
                    <docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="b">David V.</hi>
                        <name>
                            <hi rend="b">Erdman</hi>
                        </name>
                    </docAuthor>
                </byline>
                <p>Reviewers were generous in their praise of the first edition; their welcoming of
                    this facsimile as “an essential
                    guide”—“both stimulating and useful” and
                    even “something of a landmark”—lulled my critical
                    faculties, so that when the opportunity of a reissue arose my first inclination
                    was merely to correct the manifest errors and occasional misprints, to put a
                    proper note of identification near the finely sketched portrait of
                    Blake’s wife Catherine on Notebook page 82 (Geoffrey Keynes having
                    pointed out that the sketch had been copied by Frederick Shields for the 1880
                    Gilchrist <hi rend="i">Life</hi> and there identified), and, with the necessary
                    rearrangement of adjacent items, to correct my mistaken dating of Poem 78 in the
                    Table on pages 56-58 and in the explanation on page 71. I intended also to cite
                    briefly, in the note to page 27, a clear solution to the puzzle of Emblem 10
                    which was proposed by Robert N. Essick in his review in <hi rend="i">Blake
                        Newsletter</hi> 32 (Spring 1975) pp. 132-36.</p>
                <p>When I sat down to check through the reviews for specific criticisms and
                    suggestions, however, I was gradually drawn into a sober reappraisal of my
                    “readings” of two of the emblem designs, one being that of the
                    figure resting on a cloud in a star-studded sky used by Blake in his strategic
                    “Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi>
                    “On pages 73 and N57, the figure in Emblem 36 must surely be identified
                    not as the future Bard but as the future Earth,” declared Jean H.
                    Hagstrum in his review in <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi>, 53 (Fall
                    1974) 643-45. “Her position resembles that of a clear but unmistakable
                    Blakean icon . . . the position of Earth, of the Clod of Clay or Nature in 
<hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, of the sleeping girl in <hi rend="i">America</hi>, and
                    of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Long
                    uncertain about this figure, I had defined it as “the alerted Soul on
                    her cloud” as late as the galley-proof stage of the first edition, then
                    persuaded myself that it was, after all, “the Bard on his
                    scroll.” Sir Geoffrey Keynes had once agreed that it was the Bard but
                    in his recent facsimile edition of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (1967) had come
                    round to seeing it as “Earth . . . a female figure reclining on a couch
                    borne on a cloud among a night of stars.” What finally convinced me
                    were two pages of close 
<pb id="p11-22" n="22"/>
argument for the Earth/Soul
                    interpretation in a copy John E. Grant sent me of his review scheduled for
                    publication in the Autumn 1977 issue of <hi rend="i">Modern Philology.</hi> It
                    is with relief and pleasure that I now belatedly join such a
                    “strong” company of scholars as Keynes, Grant, and
                    Hagstrum.</p>
                <p>John Grant’s review also questions my reading of Emblem 13, page 31,
                    as did Robert Essick’s. Where I saw a gowned
                    “Saviour” descending through a doorway, they see a gowned
                    woman ascending. The sketch is quite vague; what convinces me in this case is
                    the early wash drawing, kindly supplied by Essick, of what is clearly a variant
                    of the same scene (Fig. 43). William Rossetti had been substantially correct
                    with his caption, “The Soul entering Eternity. Exhibits a maiden
                    entering a door, guarded by two spiritual women” (Gilchrist <hi rend="i">Life</hi>, 1863,
II, 248 no. 92). Another variant is
                    Blake’s design for Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
                        Thoughts</hi> (<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 510), in which the woman entering
                    “at the door of Heaven” is welcomed by a bearded man who
                    pushes the door open and represents “humble Love.” (Another
                    version, emblem size, is a slight sketch of a figure entering a door, inscribed
                    “Frontispiece” above the drawing and “It is Deep
                    Midnight” below it. Since this sketch is drawn on the verso of
                    Blake’s title page “For Children The Gates of
                    HELL,” the probability is, Martin Butlin suggests, that this and some
                    of the other unpublished Notebook emblems were at one time intended for a
                    separate, unpublished <hi rend="i">Gates of Hell.</hi>) As for Emblem 10, which
                    I can now see as a variant of <hi rend="i">A Breach in a City the Morning after
                        the Battle</hi> (1784) or <hi rend="i">War</hi> (1805), Essick has kindly
                    sent me an annotated tracing which helps to identify the edges of the broken
                    wall, the three corpses before and within the break, a small figure seen in the
                    distance through the break and walking to the left, and an eagle perched on the
                    wall. I would hardly say that “the eagle’s beak and left
                    wing are particularly clear in the emblem,” since I see only the neck,
                    not the beak, but I do agree that “this arrangement at least seems more
                    likely than Erdman’s ‘lightning strikes the neck of a
                    woman whose slippered leg is extended at left.’” As
                    comparison with the variant versions makes evident, what I saw as cloud and
                    lightning are a clump of trees and the outlines of the eagle. What looks like a
                    giant leg proves to be the space between the edge of the broken wall and a
                    fallen body.</p>
                <p>Revising the account of Emblem 10, which I had called “War,”
                    required little more than a refining of connotations. But my erroneous accounts
                    of Emblems 13 and 36 had far-reaching effects. While I was wrestling with the
                    necessary revisions <hi rend="i">passim</hi>, and discussing them on the
                    telephone with John Grant, he gently urged me to examine and reconsider the sex
                    of the figure I had identified as Satan in the picture on pages 110-11. The
                    prominent rounded breasts ought perhaps to suggest Eve—or
                    Satan’s daughter and paramour, Sin. (But then Christ in the same
                    picture looks rather like that Bard—I mean “lapsed
                    Soul”— in Emblem 36, hair and gown: some suggestion of an
                    androgynous Human Form Divine?)</p>
                <p>Three females I had mistaken for males! I could take some comfort from recalling
                    the first part of Blake’s letter to the <hi rend="i">Monthly
                        Magazine</hi> in 1806 in which he protested the criticism of a painting by
                    Fuseli. The critic had mistaken a boy in Count Ugolino’s arms for a
                    girl. “Whether a boy or girl,” Blake wrote,
                    “signifies not.” Then he added: “but the critic must
                    be a fool . . . who does not know a boy from a girl.” Small comfort. I
                    have omitted the first “who”: “a fool who has not
                    read Dante”: Blake <hi rend="i">knew</hi>, from reading Dante, that the
                    child was a boy. I had thought I <hi rend="i">knew</hi>, from reading Blake,
                    that those figures were male. By this time a simple patching here and there and
                    a note of errors would not do. I have now revised the descriptions of these
                    three Emblems completely, put in a query about Eve or Sin, and revised my
                    accounts of the sequences of emblems in Blake’s various numberings.
                    The changed readings of the three emblem pictures fortunately make no drastic
                    change in the sequences of variation between images of fear and images of hope
                    which constitute the dynamics of the series. Emblem 10 comes into sharper focus
                    as death and mourning after battle, with permissable allusions to the English
                    Civil War and the American War, while “the drift of hollow
                    states” suggests contemporary prophecy. Emblem 13, whether representing
                    Christ coming through a doorway toward us or a Soul going toward heaven, is an
                    emblem of hope. And Emblem 36, whether the Bard watching for Earth to respond to
                    “the Word” or the Earth awake to “the Word”
                    but not yet arising, is critically ambivalent. It can make a positive thrust in
                    the thematic series of the Notebook emblems; in the context of the
                    “Introduction” poem and its sequel
                    “Earth’s Answer” it may lead the viewer and reader
                    into a lapsed condition that puts the dawn of a future age far off. The fit of
                    text to picture, however, is a compelling reality: it is the Earth <hi rend="i">as
globe</hi> to whom “the starry floor,” prominent in
                    the picture, is given; the “watry shore” is given as boundary
                    to the earth <hi rend="i">as land</hi> (the “slumberous
                    mass”), and it is from that prison that her chained spirit answers in
                    the second poem (“Earth’s Answer”).</p>
                <p>Four emblem pictures which I have added at John Grant’s suggestion, on
                    pages 98-99, afford further possibilities—which I leave others to
                    explore—for the reconstruction of Blake’s numbered series
                    of emblems. Figures 44 and 45 are sketches on a small sheet of paper which Grant
                    calls to my attention as bearing alongside their captions revised and thrice
                    revised numbers that seem to fit gaps in Table V (p. 64) of emblems in numbered
                    series. In Fig. 45 a bee-winged girl hovers with folded arms under an archway,
                    or possibly the branch of a tree. These drawings are not much like those in the
                    Notebook, but the possibility that they may have been considered for the
                    Notebook series cannot be ruled out. They <hi rend="i">are</hi> like the
                    drawings of Figs. 46-47.</p>
                <p>Figures 46 and 47 are less ambiguous and in a different category. Both were added
                    to blank verso pages, within the areas framed by the plate printed on the
                    rectos, in copy C of <hi rend="i">For Children: The Gates of Paradise</hi>, a
                    copy which Blake’s old friend George Cumberland apparently purchased
                    after his death. These added emblems, a flower-woman to match the fire-man of
                    the emblem it faces, and a printer at work following
                    “Death’s Door,” show Blake still the relentless
                    emblem-maker. Perhaps they are restorations of earlier rejected designs; the
                    first Fig. 46, bears a kind of sibling relation to Fig. 45. 
                    <pb id="p11-23" n="23"/> 
                    But I have no ingenious speculations ready, nor has John Grant, who
                    led me to these surprises.</p>
                <p>Thanks, then, to Professors Essick, Grant, and Hagstrum, this new edition
                    contains significant improvements that have involved minor revisions throughout,
                    even in the index. And although I have found no way to make direct use of
                    <corr type="emend">“Blake’s ‘Gothicised Imagination’ and the History of England,”</corr> 
                    David Bindman’s essay in <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, 1973 (the Keynes 
                    <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">Festschrift</hi></corr> edited by Morton
                    Paley and Michael Phillips), my brief discussion of the historical sketches and
                    of the list of topics from English history on page 116 would benefit from the
                    wider context supplied by Bindman’s survey “of
                    Blake’s interpretation of the whole panorama of English history from
                    its mythological origins to the apocalyptic future.”</p>
                <p>Jean H. Hagstrum is to be thanked for a most interesting textual correction of
                    “Public Address” sections 63 and 29 (N 20 and N 62). What has
                    always been read as “Poco Pen” and “Poco
                    Pend,” but never made sense of, can now be confidently given as
                    “Poco Piu” and “Poco Piud.” Hagstrum
                    observed that <hi rend="i">n</hi> was a misreading of <hi rend="i">u</hi>, and
                    Geoffrey Keynes noted that what looks like <hi rend="i">e</hi> (though loopless)
                    is indistinguishable from an undotted <hi rend="i">i</hi> (of which the text
                    affords frequent examples) and that Blake is attacking the slang of the
                    “Cunning Sures” (N 40); compare his scorn of their
                    “je ne sais quoi” in Poem 124 (N 41). The only other error of
                    transcription noted, and corrected, is “Accusation” corrected
                    to “Accusations” in Appendix page 95.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>