<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>11.1.roti</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">The Last Stanza of Blake’s London</title>
                <author n="Roti">Grant C. Roti</author>
                <author n="Kent">Donald L. Kent</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1977</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1977</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">11.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Brad Hayden</name>
                            <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
                            <name>Michael Hays</name>
                            <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
                            <name>Jane Welford</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>John Beer</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Raymond Deck</name>
                            <name>Thomas Dilworth</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
                            <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
                            <name>Donald L. Kent</name>
                            <name>Vivian Mercier</name>
                            <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
                            <name>Dennis Read</name>
                            <name>Grant C. Roti</name>
                            <name>Richard J. Schroyer</name>
                            <name>Ruthven Todd</name>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1977"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_11">
        <body>
            <pb id="p11-19" n="19"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-11-1-0004">
                <head>
                    <title type="main">
                        <hi rend="b">The Last Stanza of Blake’s London</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <byline>
                    <hi rend="b">by</hi>
                    <docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="b">Grant C.</hi>
                        <name>
                            <hi rend="b">Roti</hi>
                        </name>
                    </docAuthor>
                    <hi rend="b">and</hi>
                    <docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="b">Donald L.</hi>
                        <name>
                            <hi rend="b">Kent</hi>
                        </name>
                    </docAuthor>
                </byline>
                <p>Blake’s “London” is a bitter lament for the moral
                    and political conditions of London, ending with these four lines: 
					<q> But most
                        thro’ midnight streets I hear<lb/>
 How the youthful Harlots
                        curse<lb/>
 Blasts the new-born Infants tear<lb/>
 And blights with plagues
                        the Marriage hearse.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
type="note">1</ref>
                        <note id="n22">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V.
                            Erdman (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1968), pp. 26-27.</note>
					</q>
					“London” may very well be the least controversial of
                    Blake’s poems, but this last stanza has been a problem for critics
                    and is in need of very close explication. The purpose of this article is not
                    only to clarify the meaning of these lines but to show Blake’s
                    precise and detailed awareness of the social conditions of his time, and thereby
                    to emphasize the caution expressed by some critics against moving too rapidly
                    from fact to symbol in the interpretation of Blake’s poetry.</p>
                <p>In <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse: A Study in Poetic Argument</hi>,
                    Harold Bloom recognized “two possible readings” for this last
                    stanza, readings which “may reinforce one another”: 
					<q> One is
                        that the blasting of the tear refers to prenatal blindness due to venereal
                        disease, the “plagues” of the poem’s last line.
                        A closer reading gives what is at first more surprising and yet finally more
                        characteristic of Blake’s individual thinking. Most of <hi rend="i">London</hi> is
sounds: after the first stanza, Blake talks
                        about what he hears as he walks the streets of his city. In the midnight
                        streets of the city, he hears a harlot’s curse against the
                        morality of the Bromions, who speak of her with the authority of reason and
                        society and, as they would suppose, of nature. But it is her cry, from
                        street to street that weaves their fate, the winding sheet of their England.
                        They have mistaken her, for she is nature, and her plagues are subtler than
                        those of venereal disease. A shouted curse can <hi rend="i">blast</hi> a 
<hi rend="i">tear</hi> in a quite literal way: the released breath can
                        scatter the small body of moisture out of existence. Blake knows his natural
                        facts; he distrusted nature too much not to know them. The tear ducts of a
                        new born infant are closed; its eyes need to be moistened before it can
                        begin to weep. Blake ascribes a natural fact to the Harlot’s
                        curse, and so the Harlot is not just an exploited Londoner but nature
                        herself, the Tirzah of the last Song of Experience. In this reading, 
<hi rend="i">London</hi>’s concluding lines take a very different
                        and greater emphasis. The curse of nature that blights the marriage coach
                        and turns it into a hearse is venereal infection in the first reading. But
                        Blake is talking about <hi rend="i">every</hi> marriage, and he means
                        literally that each rides in a hearse. The plagues are the enormous plagues
                        that come from identifying reason, society, and nature, and the greatest of
                        these plagues is the Jealousy of Experience, and dark secret love of the
                        natural heart.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23"
type="note">2</ref>
                        <note id="n23">
                            <hi rend="s">2</hi> (Ithaca, N.Y.: Cornell Univ. Press,
                            1963), pp. 141-42.</note>
					</q>
                </p>
                <p>There are a number of reasons for questioning Bloom’s literal
                    “closer reading.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">3</ref>
First
                    of all, although most of “London” is sounds, what the speaker
                    of the poem hears is not the curse itself but <hi rend="i">how</hi>
                    “the youthful Harlots curse / Blasts the new-born Infants tear, / And
                    blights with plagues the Marriage hearse.” The object of
                    “hear” is not the curse but the indirect question, the
                    how-clause. “Hear” in this sense means “understand
                    the manner in which . . . ”: it does not refer to a literal hearing.
                    The speaker, walking through the midnight streets, becomes aware of the
                    conditions and effects of the “Harlots curse,” how it ruins
                    (“blasts”) and blights. Secondly, it has been suggested by
                    Erdman that the “Harlots curse” is parallel to the
                    “Soldiers sigh” of the third stanza, and that Blake may have
                    been thinking about a curse written on the palace walls, not shouted in the
                        streets.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">4</ref>
Third, Bloom’s
                    “closer reading” destroys the parallel metaphorical meaning of
                    “blast” (ruin or destroy vegetation) and
                    “blight.” In his reading the reader’s attention
                    must move rapidly from the literal blasting (the harlot’s breath
                    moistening the baby’s eyes) to the more gradual onset of blight, in
                    spite of the alliteration. Fourth, it will be shown later in our argument that
                    Blake also 
<pb id="p11-20" n="20"/>
wants to link the parallel ideas of the
                    “Infants tear” (the infant’s venereal disease) and
                    the “Marriage hearse” (the mother’s venereal
                    disease). Fifth, and last, Bloom (apparently) rejects the interpretation that
                    the harlot’s blast of breath can literally scatter the
                    child’s tear out of existence, since a newborn baby has no tear<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">5</ref>; and his point seems to be that the harlot
                    causes the tear to come into existence by moistening the child’s eyes
                    with the breath of her cursing. But, in this case, the harlot is, logically
                    speaking, blasting the child’s <hi rend="i">eye</hi>, not the tear,
                    unless <hi rend="i">blast</hi> is reinterpreted to mean “cause to come
                    into existence,” which considerably distorts the traditional meanings.
                    The “Harlots curse” must refer predominantly to venereal
                    disease, and this is what we intend to show in this article. <note id="n24">
                        <hi rend="s">3</hi> Bloom’s “closer reading” is
                        actually two readings: (1) a literal reading which takes the curse to be an
                        oral imprecation moistening the baby’s eyes, and (2) a symbolic
                        reading dependent on this literal reading. In this paper we are directly
                        questioning only the first.</note>
                    <note id="n25">
                        <hi rend="s">4</hi> David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake, Prophet
                            Against Empire</hi>, rev. ed. (Princeton, N.J.: Princeton Univ. Press,
                        1969), p. 278.</note>
                    <note id="n26">
                        <hi rend="s">5</hi>
                        This interpretation is something of a straw man anyway; that the
                            harlot’s breath can literally scatter the baby’s
                            tear out of existence is contrary to ordinary language and the facts of
                            experience.
                        <p>A more common interpretation would reply that Bloom is demanding too
                            technical a knowledge of his reader and of Blake when he points out that
                            a newborn baby has no tear (at any rate, a “newborn”
                            baby could be two days old, and have tears). Such a reading would also
                            take “Infants tear” as a <corr type="emend">synecdoche</corr> meaning
                            “infant’s crying.” This, however, leaves
                            the reader suspecting that Blake used “tear” largely
                            because it rhymed with “hear”; it shows a faulty
                            craftsmanship in Blake which we do not feel is necessarily in the
                            poem.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>The main problem in interpreting these second and third lines of the stanza lies,
                    we suspect, in knowing what it means to <hi rend="i">blast</hi> a <hi rend="i">tear.</hi>
Bloom also is aware of this and is to be commended for wrestling
                    with the problem; no other critic has dealt with it in such detail. We take
                    “blast” to mean predominantly “to ruin,
                    destroy” (OED, II, 8), especially to ruin or destroy the bud, flower,
                    or fruit of a plant. (It should be noted here that “blast” in
                    the sense of “ruin” may ultimately derive from the idea of a
                    “malignant wind” (OED, II, 7) which destroys vegetation; but
                    it destroys the vegetation by bringing disease, not by blowing the plant to
                    pieces. So, the “Harlots curse” may figuratively operate as a
                    “malignant wind” but only in the sense that it brings disease,
                    not in the sense that it blows away or apart.) But what does it mean to ruin or
                    destroy a tear? Blake could very well have in mind the effects of a particular
                    venereal disease, <hi rend="i">gonococcal conjunctivitis</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">6</ref> a form of gonorrhea which was certainly widespread at
                    Blake’s time and which shortly after birth produces an ugly, pussy
                    discharge from the eyes. The disease itself is an infection “contracted
                    from the birth canal during delivery.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n28" type="note">7</ref> Shortly after birth the newborn baby’s eyelids are
                    marked by a puffy, reddened appearance and are swollen shut; a green pussy
                    discharge oozes through the closed lids. In the days before penicillin, this
                    untreated disease progressed over a period of six weeks to involve the cornea
                    (an important protector of the eye), resulting in a perforated cornea with loss
                    of the eye. Thus, the child’s “tears” appear to be
                    quite literally “blasted”: they have been changed to pus. The
                    child’s eyesight may also be “blasted” in that he
                    may lose his sight. <note id="n27">
                        <hi rend="s">6</hi> For a complete
                        description and a photograph of an infected child see <hi rend="i">Adler’s Textbook
of <corr type="emend">Ophthalmology</corr></hi>, 8th ed., ed. Harold
                        G. Scheie and Daniel M. Albert (Philadelphia: W. B. Sanders, 1969), p. 147.
                        Dr. Kent is responsible for the medical information given at this point in
                        the article; we are also partly indebted to Virginia Burpos of Bridgeport,
                        Connecticut, for this reading of the poem.</note>
                    <note id="n28">
                        <hi rend="s">7</hi>
                        <hi rend="i"> Adler’s Textbook of Ophthalmology</hi>, p. 147.
                        Since <hi rend="i">gonoccal conjunctivitis</hi> is a form of gonorrhea, it
                        is not prenatal or congenital. A number of commentators have referred to the
                        “curse” as “prenatal,” thinking, no
                        doubt, of the blindness resulting from congenital syphilis: see Bloom, p.
                        141; M. H. Abrams’ comments in <hi rend="i">The Norton Anthology
                            of English Literature</hi>, ed. M. H. Abrams <hi rend="i">et al.</hi>,
                        rev. ed. (New York: W. W. Norton, 1968), II, 59; and Bloom’s
                        comments in <hi rend="i">The Oxford Anthology of English Literature</hi>,
                        ed. Frank Kermode and John Hollander, <hi rend="i">et al.</hi> (New York:
                        Oxford Univ. Press, 1973), II, 27. Since venereal diseases were not
                        differentiated until late in the nineteenth century, Blake and others could
                        easily have thought of any form of gonorrhea as congenital and so a
                        “curse” passed on in the blood. See Charles Clayton
                        Dennie, <hi rend="i">History of Syphilis</hi> (Springfield, Ill.: Charles C.
                        Thomas, 1962), esp. p. 92f.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Through this new reading, we can better appreciate the skillful parallelism of
                    the last two lines of the poem. Blake is moving from the immediate effects of
                    the youthful harlot on the newborn baby to her more pervasive effects on
                    marriage in general; he is moving from the more concrete, more nearly literal
                    blasting of the “Infants tear” to the more abstract, more
                    symbolic blighting of the “Marriage hearse,” and this shift is
                    carefully reflected in his diction. Blasting and blighting in general destroy
                    vegetation and the two actions are linked with the “bl-”
                    alliteration; but <hi rend="i">blast</hi> refers particularly to the destruction
                    of the bud, fruit, or flower of a plant, and so Blake uses it to refer to the
                    actions of the harlot on the infant (the bud of the marriage plant). 
<hi rend="i">Blight</hi>, as a verb, refers to destruction of the plant in
                    general; and <hi rend="i">blight</hi>, as a noun, refers to the
                    “baleful influence” that destroys plants or “prevents
                    their blossom from ‘setting’” (OED, 1.); and so
                    Blake uses it to refer to the destruction of marriage (the plant which produces
                    the bud). Also, venereal disease would prevent the “blossom from
                    ‘setting’” properly.</p>
                <p>Just as the harlot infects the child with venereal disease (the “Infants
                    tear”) so, in the last line of the poem, she more pervasively
                    (“with plagues”) destroys marriage in general through venereal
                    disease (“Marriage hearse”). “Marriage
                    hearse” now becomes a dynamic symbol which fuses a number of suggestive
                    meanings. In the context of the poem it can be read grammatically as an
                    adjective modifying a noun and as a compound noun, each form having harmonious
                    overtones. In the first case, “hearse” is a description which
                    interprets Blake’s culture. It refers in general to the deadly
                    condition of marriage, in that marriage, for Blake, is a restrictive institution
                    (deadly, in a spiritual sense) which actually fosters prostitution;<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">8</ref> and individual marriages are literally and
                    physically deadly, since the venereal disease is transferred to the wife and
                    children. “Marriage hearse” also calls to mind the marriage
                    coach (marriage is again spiritually dead) and the marriage bed<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">9</ref> (marriage is again physically deadly). (An early meaning
                    of hearse is “bier,” “the movable stand on which a
                    corpse, whether in a coffin or not, is placed before burial; that on which it is
                    carried to the grave” OED, 2.) <note id="n29">
                        <hi rend="s">8</hi> E. D.
                        Hirsch, Jr., <hi rend="i">Innocence and Experience: An Introduction to
                            Blake</hi> (New Haven, Conn.: Yale Univ. Press, 1964), pp. 94 and
                        265.</note>
                    <note id="n30">
                        <hi rend="s">9</hi> See Abrams’ comments in <hi rend="i">The Norton Anthology of
English Literature</hi>, II, 59; and
                        Bloom, p. 142.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In the second case, “Marriage hearse” can be taken as a
                    compound noun; here the emphasis shifts from “hearse” to
                    “Marriage,” and “hearse” virtually becomes
                    an appositive adjective (“marriage, which is a hearse”) since
                    “Marriage” is the object of “blights.” The
                    meaning is essentially the same, “marriage, which is a deadly
                    condition, spiritually and physically”; but the awareness of this
                    alternate grammatical form helps to account for the ability of the two words to
                    resonate, so to speak, to become musically dynamic. Not only are there multiple
                    meanings which harmonize, but there are also two conforming grammatical
                    structures by which the meanings are expressed.</p>
                <p>Mark Schorer, years ago, remarked that although Blake could “see
                    spiritual realities within natural objects and . . . could impose spiritual
                    realities upon nature,” in his early poems he tends to
                    “illuminate facts by vision.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
type="note">10</ref> The last stanza of “London” shows this tendency
                    well. The speaker is walking the streets of London, listening; but he is also a
                    kind of prophet, the midnight also a moral and political darkness, and he hears
                    the facts and conditions of his city and passes judgment on them. He is aware of
                    the details of venereal disease, but he is also aware that it is a
                    “curse,” inherited in the blood, which
                    “blasts” the child and his crying and “blights with
                    plagues” the institution of marriage and the mothers who must carry and
                    give birth to the diseased children. <note id="n31">
                        <hi rend="s">10</hi> Mark
                        Schorer, <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Politics of Vision</hi>, Vintage
                        Books (New York: Random House, 1959), p. 378.</note>
                </p>
            </div1>
	<pb id="p11-21" n="21" rend="hidden"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>