<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>11.1.mercier</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="minute">Blake Echoes in Victorian Dublin</title>
                <author n="Mercier">Vivian Mercier</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1977</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1977</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">11.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Brad Hayden</name>
                            <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
                            <name>Michael Hays</name>
                            <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
                            <name>Jane Welford</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>John Beer</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Raymond Deck</name>
                            <name>Thomas Dilworth</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
                            <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
                            <name>Donald L. Kent</name>
                            <name>Vivian Mercier</name>
                            <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
                            <name>Dennis Read</name>
                            <name>Grant C. Roti</name>
                            <name>Richard J. Schroyer</name>
                            <name>Ruthven Todd</name>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1977"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_11">
        <body>
            <pb id="p11-32" n="32"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-11-1-0009">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">Minute Particulars</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">Blake Echoes in Victorian Dublin</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <hi rend="b">by</hi>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="b">Vivian</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">Mercier</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>At Morton Paley’s request, I went through the file of <hi rend="i">Kottabos</hi> in
the library of Trinity College, Dublin: it consists of
                        three volumes in the original series and two in the new series, running from
                        1869 to 1895, with a pause between the series in the 1880’s.
                        Edited by the distinguished classical scholar Robert Yelverton Tyrrell, 
<hi rend="i">Kottabos</hi> normally appeared three times a year. Each issue,
                        looking like a bound set of examination papers in spite of its pink paper
                        cover, was dated according to the term in which it
                        appeared—Michaelmas, Hilary, or Trinity. Apart from an occasional
                        prose parody tucked in at the end of an issue, it consisted entirely of
                        original verse and translations (usually verse) into and out of various
                        classical and modern languages, but chiefly from English into Latin and
                        Greek.</p>
                    <p>Most of the so-called original verse was extremely derivative; often the
                        author made it perfectly clear that he was attempting only parody or
                        pastiche. The series of “Poems Written in Discipleship” to
                        which John Todhunter contributed his two imitations of Blake was usually
                        accompanied by a footnote: “These poems are in no sense parodies,
                        but intend to be affectionate studies or sketches in the manner of some of
                        the masters of song.” In other words, they are exercises in
                        pastiche. No doubt a parallel could be found in <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Innocence</hi> or <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> for virtually
                        every line of Todhunter’s “Paradise Lost” and
                        “Paradise Found.” The most interesting aspect of these
                        poems “Of the School of William Blake” may well be their
                        date, since they appeared in the issue for Michaelmas Term (i.e. Fall
                        Quarter), 1871. Another point worth noting, though it may be the result of
                        pure chance, is Blake’s apparent high position in the batting
                        order of the masters of song. Only Browning and Tennyson, in that order, had
                        preceded him, both imitated by Edward Dowden, Professor of English
                        Literature at Trinity, still remembered for his books on Shakespeare and
                        Shelley. After Blake in the series came Longfellow (imitated by the
                        otherwise unknown Percy S. Payne), Wordsworth (by Todhunter), “The
                        Earlier Style of Euripides” (by R. Y. Tyrrell, in Greek), and
                        Whitman (by Todhunter again). One might ask why Swinburne did not appear;
                        the obvious answer is that practically all the “original”
                        poetry showed his influence, especially that written by Oscar Wilde and his
                        brother William. One might have expected Oscar to be aware of Blake, but his
                        work for <hi rend="i">Kottabos</hi> offers no proof of this.</p>
                    <p>In the scholarly world of the time—and to a large extent in the
                        literary world, too—<hi rend="i">Kottabos</hi> owed its
                        reputation primarily to its contributors’ felicity in turning
                        English poetry into Latin and Greek verse, a Renaissance accomplishment
                        still highly prized among the Victorians. Shakespeare naturally offered the
                        greatest challenge and was probably the most frequently translated author:
                        classicists could not resist trying to turn Hamlet’s soliloquies
                        into the rhetoric of the Greek tragedians. Milton and Pope, steeped as they
                        were in the classics, went easily enough into Latin, though Dryden, perhaps
                        because of his Catholicism, was neglected by the staunch Protestants of
                        Trinity (Pope of course was Catholic, too; it was Dryden’s well
                        publicized <hi rend="i">conversion</hi> to Catholicism in the reign of James
                        II that caused Protestant resentment). Swinburne, as the author of 
<hi rend="i">Atlanta in Calydon</hi>, provoked attempts to translate him
                        into Greek as well as Latin. On the other hand, those who cared more for
                        grammar and meter than for <hi rend="i">belles lettres</hi> often turned to
                        translating humorous stage-Irish ballads or mediocre album verse. R. Y.
                        Tyrrell, over a number of years, hammered out a complete Latin version of
                        Thomas Hood’s “The Bridge of Sighs” in the
                        meter of the original—itself derived from medieval Latin verse.
                        Given the above facts, you can imagine my surprise and delight at finding a
                        Latin rendering of a Blake poem in the issue for Trinity Term, 1876.
                        Blake’s “The Fly” is translated into eleven
                        lines of Catullan hendecasyllabics under the hackneyed but appropriate title
                        “Carpe Diem.” The Latin is signed “W. G.
                        T.”—the initials of William Gerald Tyrrell, as we learn
                        elsewhere in the issue. No doubt he was a relative of the editor.</p>
                    <p>It was shrewd of the translator to see how neatly Blake’s poem
                        would fit into a classical subgenre. Too often we glibly categorize Blake as
                        Romantic and ignore the “Augustan” element in his earlier
                        work. By the way, Catullus, whom W. G. 
                        <figure n="Todhunter.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="624">
                            <head>Portrait of Dr. John Todhunter, by H. M. Paget (posthumous
                                portrait from Elliott &amp; Dry, photographed 1899).</head>
                        </figure>
                        <pb id="p11-33" n="33"/>
                        <figure n="Discipleship.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="825"/>
                        <figure n="ParadiseFound.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="830"/>
                        <figure n="Fly.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="889">
                        	<figTranscr>266<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	Then raising her voice to a strain<lb/>
                        	The sweetest that ear ever heard,<lb/>
                        	She sung of the slave’s broken chain<lb/>
                        	Wherever her glory appeared.<lb/>
                        	Some clouds, which had over us hung,<lb/>
                        	Fled, chased by her melody clear,<lb/>
                        	And methought while she liberty sung,<lb/>
                        	’Twas liberty only to hear.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	COWPER.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	The Fly.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	LITTLE fly,<lb/>
                        	Thy summer’s play<lb/>
                        	My thoughtless hand<lb/>
                        	Has brush’d away.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	Am not I<lb/>
                        	A fly like thee?<lb/>
                        	Or art not thou<lb/>
                        	A man like me?<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	For I dance,<lb/>
                        	And drink, and sing,<lb/>
                        	Till some blind hand<lb/>
                        	Shall brush my wing.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	If thought is life,<lb/>
                        	And strength, and breath,<lb/>
                        	And the want<lb/>
                        	Of thought is death,<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	Then am I<lb/>
                        	A happy fly,<lb/>
                        	If I live,<lb/>
                        	Or if I die.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	BLAKE.</figTranscr>
                        </figure>
                        <figure n="CarpeDiem.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="751">
                        	<figTranscr>267<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	Tum liquida teneros intendit voce canores<lb/>
                        	Queis equidem excepi dulcius aure nihil;<lb/>
                        	Vincula enim cecinit servis casura soluta<lb/>
                        	Undique qua, visu splendida, ferret iter.<lb/>
                        	Nubila, quae cymbae rara imminuere per auras,<lb/>
                        	Fugerunt magicis exsuperata modis;<lb/>
                        	Et rebar mecum, dum iura aequanda canebat,<lb/>
                        	Audiat haec quisquis carmina, liber, erit.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	L. W. K.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	Carpe Diem.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	AH nuper volitans, misella musca,<lb/>
                        	Per solem, temeraria peristi<lb/>
                        	Nostra rapta manu, nec hoc putavi<lb/>
                        	Nostri vivere more te modoque,<lb/>
                        	Me vestri simul impedire fatum.<lb/>
                        	Sic convivia cum choris frequento,<lb/>
                        	Donec caeca manus recidat alas.<lb/>
                        	At si mens anima est vigorque vivi,<lb/>
                        	Hac autem pereunte deperimus,<lb/>
                        	Carpam quod spatium supersit aevi,<lb/>
                        	Mortemque impavidus morabor atram.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	W[illiam] G[erald] T[yrrell]</figTranscr>
                        </figure>
                        <pb id="p11-34" n="34"/>
                        Tyrrell seems to be imitating, was not himself an
                        Augustan in the Roman sense: he died nearly thirty years before Octavian
                        took the title of Augustus. Tyrrell’s version is surprisingly
                        faithful to Blake, if we allow for the vast difference in philosophic and
                        stylistic assumptions between Rome of the first century B.C. and late
                        eighteenth-century England. After being in contact with so much translation
                        and imitation, I could not resist giving my own line-by-line version of
                        Tyrrell’s Latin: it is much more literal than it may appear at
                        first sight.</p>
					<q>
                        <hi rend="b">Pluck the Day</hi>
                        <lb/>
                        Unlucky little fly, just lately fluttering<lb/>
                        brashly in the sun, you perished<lb/>
                        caught in my hand, and I never thought of this till now:<lb/>
                        you and I have the same life style<lb/>
                        and are involved in each other’s fate.<lb/>
                        I too dance and sing often at parties<lb/>
                        till a blind hand clip my wings.<lb/>
                        But if mind be the soul and strength of the living creature<lb/>
                        and when it’s dead we’re gone for good,<lb/>
                        then I’m going to enjoy the rest of life<lb/>
                        and wait for gloomy death without a qualm.
                    </q>
					<note type="unreferenced">
						<hi rend="i">Note</hi>: The Todhunter
						imitations are in <hi rend="i">Kottabos</hi>, 1 (1869-73), 228-29.
						“The Fly” and “Carpe Diem” appear on
						facing pages: <hi rend="i">Kottabos</hi>, 2(1873-77), 266-67.</note>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>