<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>11.1.gleckner</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">Blake’s Miltonizing of Chatterton</title>
                <author n="Gleckner">Robert F. Gleckner</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1977</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1977</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">11.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Brad Hayden</name>
                            <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
                            <name>Michael Hays</name>
                            <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
                            <name>Jane Welford</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>John Beer</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Raymond Deck</name>
                            <name>Thomas Dilworth</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
                            <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
                            <name>Donald L. Kent</name>
                            <name>Vivian Mercier</name>
                            <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
                            <name>Dennis Read</name>
                            <name>Grant C. Roti</name>
                            <name>Richard J. Schroyer</name>
                            <name>Ruthven Todd</name>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1977"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_11">
        <body>
            <pb id="p11-27" n="27"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-11-1-0007">
                <head>
                    <title type="main">
                        <hi rend="b">Blake’s Miltonizing of <corr type="emend">Chatterton</corr></hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <byline>
                    <hi rend="b">by</hi>
                    <docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="b">Robert F.</hi>
                        <name>
                            <hi rend="b">Gleckner</hi>
                        </name>
                    </docAuthor>
                </byline>
                <p>While there is little doubt that Blake read, absorbed, and stole from Chatterton,
                    especially early in his career, the standard assumption has been, stemming
                    largely from Margaret Lowery’s <hi rend="i">Windows of the
                        Morning</hi>, that Blake’s borrowings from his near contemporary
                    merely signal his indebtedness to the eighteenth century, particularly to the
                    minor poets of the latter half of that century.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n48" type="note">1</ref> Trying to deal adequately and fairly with verbal echoes is, of
                    course, extremely risky, as the recent counterpoint between Michael Tolley and
                    Michael Ferber over Thel’s Motto newly demonstrates (<hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>,
Summer 1976). So much of the verbal poetic tradition
                    impinges upon a poet’s unconscious memory that it is more often than
                    not impossible to assign a phrase’s ultimate origin.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">2</ref> And, especially with a poet like Blake, such assignment
                    is all the more difficult because of his habit of wrenching, upsetting, or even
                    perverting the sense of the original to fit his own purposes—which
                    include frequently a turning of the echo (or quotation or near-quotation)
                    against itself. <note id="n48">
                        <hi rend="s">1</hi> (New Haven: Yale Univ. Press,
                        1940). See especially pp. 131-93, and also my note 9 below. Cf. T. S.
                        Eliot’s similar position in <hi rend="i">The Sacred Wood</hi>
                        (London: Methuen &amp; Co., 1920).</note>
                    <note id="n49">
                        <hi rend="s">2</hi> For some of these difficulties see such
                        studies as R. D. Havens, <hi rend="i">The Influence of Milton on English
                            Poetry</hi> (Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard Univ. Press, 1922); C. V. Deane,
                            <hi rend="i">Aspects of Eighteenth-Century Nature Poetry</hi> (Oxford:
                        Basil Blackwell, 1935); John Arthos, <hi rend="i">The Language of Natural
                            Description in Eighteenth Century Poetry</hi> (Ann Arbor: Univ. of
                        Michigan Press, 1949); Bernard Groom, <hi rend="i">The Diction of Poetry
                            from Spenser to Bridges</hi> (Toronto: Univ. of Toronto Press, 1955);
                        Geoffrey Tillotson, <hi rend="i">Augustan Poetic Diction</hi> (London: The
                        Athlone Press, 1964); and most recently Arthur Sherbo, <hi rend="i">English
                            Poetic Diction from Chaucer to Wordsworth</hi> (East Lansing: Michigan
                        State Univ. Press, 1975).</note>
                </p>
                <p>One of the means Blake uses to accomplish such reversals or self-destructions is
                    the introduction into the verbal context of a contrary (or at least
                    superficially unrelated) allusion which, in its thematic import and usually
                    clear Blakean affinities, dominates the total verbal and imagistic context to
                    the point where assumptions about Blake’s indebtedness of the first
                    “source” are affectively short-circuited by the second.</p>
                <p>Let me take a simple and characteristic case in point. At the close of the
                    Memorable Fancy preceding the Proverbs of Hell Blake’s Devil
                    “folded in black clouds” writes “with corroding
                    fires” the following: 
					<q> How do you know but ev’ry Bird
                        that cuts the airy way,<lb/>
 Is an immense world of delight,
                        clos’d by your senses five? </q>
As has been pointed out by
                        others,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">3</ref> the
immediate source of the
                    first line, at least, seems to be Chatterton’s <hi rend="i">Bristowe
                        Tragedie</hi>: 
						<q> Howe dydd I knowe thatt ev’ry darte,<lb/>
                        Thatt cutte the airie waie,<lb/>
 Myghte nott fynde passage toe my
                        harte,<lb/>
 And close myne eyes for aie? (11. 133-36) </q>
The speaker is
                    “Syr Charles Bawdin,” who is about to be executed, the
                    particular context his memory of escapes from death in battle and the consequent
                    irony of his present predicament. The sharpness of the contrast with
                    Blake’s context needs no comment. Indeed so obviously irrelevant to
                    Blake’s purposes are both Chatterton’s context and the
                    “darte,” even if somehow manipulated to
                    “fit,” that one wonders whether there is any point to
                    Blake’s making the allusion at all. It seems merely an unconsious (or
                    perhaps even conscious) borrowing of a felicitious phrase. <note id="n50">
                        <hi rend="s">3</hi> E.g. Harold Bloom, <hi rend="i">Blake’s
                            Apocalypse</hi> (Garden City: Doubleday &amp; Co., 1963), p. 83,
                        and most recently Geoffrey Keynes, ed., <hi rend="i">William Blake: The
                            Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> (London and New York: Oxford Univ.
                        Press, 1975), commentary on plates 6-7 (no page numbers
                    supplied).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Even early, however, such borrowing of felicities is not Blake’s
                    habit. And that is not the case here either. The trope of “cutting the
                    air” (or the water) has a long history in literature, extending
                    certainly as far back as Homer, Virgil, and Ovid<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n51" type="note">4</ref>—and appearing prominently at least twice in Spenser
                    (whose influence on Blake’s <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> is
                    demonstrably substantial). For example, in <hi rend="i">The Faerie Queene</hi>
                    the angel attending Guyon, who is “laid in swowne,” is
                    described, in part, by Spenser thus: 
					<q> two sharpe winged sheares [i.e.
                        wings]<lb/>
 Decked with diuerse plumes, like painted Iayes,<lb/>
 Were fixed
                        at his backe, to cut his ayerie wayes.<lb/>
 (II, viii, 5) </q>
Further,
                    Canto VIII is introduced by an account of the “care” of
                    “heavenly spirits” who 
					<q> with golden pineons, cleave<lb/>
                        The flitting skyes, like flying Pursuivant,<lb/>
 Against foule feends to
                        aide us millitant.<lb/>
 (stanza 2) </q>
And this is followed by a comparison
                    of Guyon’s protector with 
					<q> Cupido on Idaean hill,<lb/>
 When having
                        laid his cruell bow away,<lb/>
 And mortall arrowes, wherewith he doth
                        fill<lb/>
 The world with murdrous spoiles and bloudie pray.<lb/>
 (stanza 6) </q>
                    <pb id="p11-28" n="28"/>
Here, then, is the likely “source”
                    for Chatterton’s passage, wherein he translates Spenser’s
                    heavenly spirits into the warrior martyr who, though obviously no longer
                    protected from harm, reasserts throughout the latter half of the poem the
                    righteousness of his life and career, his readiness to die, and his faith in a
                    future life in “the land of bliss” with “God in
                    Heaven.” <note id="n51">
                        <hi rend="s">4</hi> Sherbo, e.g., cites
                        Dryden’s <hi rend="i">Aeneid</hi>, Pope’s <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> (in the former of which we
                        find “airy way” as well), Sandys’ <hi rend="i">Ovid’s Metamorphoses</hi>,
Godolphin’s <hi rend="i">The Passion of Dido for Aeneas</hi>, and Evelyn’s
                            <hi rend="i">Lucretius</hi> among others (<hi rend="i">English Poetic
                            Diction</hi>, pp. 62-65), while Arthos lists Virgil’s <hi rend="i">Aeneid</hi>
and the <hi rend="i">Georgics</hi>, as well as Du
                        Bartas, Sylvester, Chapman, Drayton, and Cowley (<hi rend="i">The Language
                            of Natural Description</hi>, pp. 134-35).</note>
                </p>
                <p>That Blake knew these lines from Spenser is, of course, a matter of speculation;
                    but in view of his apparently wide and careful early reading of Spenser it is
                        likely.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">5</ref>
Further, in <hi rend="i">An
                        Hymne of Heavenly Love</hi> the nine orders of angels are presented
                    “with nimble wings to cut the skies, / When he [God] them on his
                    messages doth send” (11. 66-67), a passage that may have suggested to
                    Blake his characteristic perversion of angel-messengers into the Devil who
                    conveys his wisdom to “the minds of men” by corrosive writing.
                        <note id="n52">
                        <hi rend="s">5</hi> We might also note, from <hi rend="i">Muiopotmos</hi>, the phrase
“air-cutting wings” (1.
                        154).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Be that as it may, the most important point about Blake’s context is
                    that it is even more Miltonic than it may be Spenserian. In <hi rend="i">Paradise
Regained</hi> “the Adversary” 
<q> with envy
                        fraught and rage<lb/>
 Flies to his place, nor rests, but in mid air<lb/>
 To
                        Council summons all his mighty Peers,<lb/>
 Within thick Clouds and dark
                        tenfold involv’d.<lb/>
 (I, 38-41) </q>
Similarly,
                    “folded in black clouds” Blake’s Devil hovers
                    “on the sides of the rock” “on the abyss of the five
                    senses, where a flat sided steep frowns over the present world.”
                    Milton’s Satan must 
					<q> tempt with wand’ring feet<lb/>
 The
                        dark unbottom’d infinite Abyss<lb/>
 And through the palpable
                        obscure find out<lb/>
 His uncouth way. . . . (II, 404-07) </q>
And: 
	<q> Into
                        this wild Abyss the wary friend<lb/>
 Stood on the brink of Hell and
                        look’d a while<lb/>
 Pondering his Voyage. . . . (II, 917-19) </q>
                    Blake thus draws directly on Milton’s abyss to help him define his
                    own “abyss of the five senses” and “the present
                    world.” At the same time Blake surely recalled that Satan faced another
                    “steep” when he reached the borders of Eden, “a steep
                    wilderness” which to him “Access deni’d”
                    (IV, 132-37). If so, then his Devil represents both the imaginative man, the
                    artist, whose perception will not be restrained by the senses, as well as the
                    Miltonic Satan who longingly connives to enter the “delicious
                    Paradise” where, through those very senses (among other things, of
                    course), Eve is tempted. Perhaps this duality explains why the Devil is
                    unimaginatively “folded in black clouds” while at the same
                    time his corrosives can melt “apparent surfaces away, and [display] the
                    infinite which was hid” (<hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>,
                    pl. 14).</p>
                <p>Although by virtue of these allusions alone the apparent allusion to Chatterton
                    is effectively swallowed up by the thoroughly Miltonic framework, Blake may have
                    recalled as well Eve’s dream in Book V of <hi rend="i">Paradise
                        Lost</hi>: 
						<q> Forthwith up to the Clouds<lb/>
 With him I flew, and
                        underneath beheld<lb/>
 The Earth outstretcht immense. . . . (V, 86-88) </q>
                    Adam’s subsequent interpretation of the dream interestingly involves,
                    in familiar faculty-psychology terms, the senses: 
					<q> of all external
                        things,<lb/>
 Which the five watchful Senses represent,<lb/>
 She forms
                        Imaginations, Aery shapes,<lb/>
 Which Reason joining or disjoining,
                        frames<lb/>
 All what we affirm or what deny, and call<lb/>
 Our knowledge or
                        opinion. . . . (V, 103-08) </q>
Thus, if Blake indeed had this sequence in
                    mind, he artfully transforms Eve’s tempting prospect of the earth
                    (engineered by Satan) from far above into the speaker’s and the
                    Devil’s perspective, also from high above the earth, hovering
                    “over the present world.” But for them, of course, there is no
                    temptation but rather the terror of the abyss of the five senses over which they
                    may triumph not by resisting temptation but by imaginatively overleaping the
                    constrictions of a sense-bound universe—by, in other words,
                    perceiving (and hence creating) their own “immense world of
                    delight” otherwise “clos’d by [their] senses
                        five.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53" type="note">6</ref>
                    <note id="n53">
                        <hi rend="s">6</hi> We should recall that part of
                            Satan’s temptation (in the dream as well as later in reality)
                            is the achieving of godhood: 
<q> Forbidd’n here, it seems, as
                                only fit<lb/>
 For Gods, yet able to make Gods of Men. (V, 69-70)
                            </q>
The difference between Blake’s idea of
                            “godhood” and Satan’s (as well as
                            Milton’s) is a measure of both Blake’s distance
                            from the seventeenth century and the care with which he adapts
                            Milton’s Satan for his own prophetic purposes.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Finally, we should note that the word “delight” itself, a
                    favorite of both Spenser and Milton, is steadily associated by the latter
                    especially with Eden, with God, with man as God’s creation, with
                    Adam’s relationship to Eve, and the like. While Blake was surely
                    aware of these associations, transforming them into his own conception of
                    imaginative bliss in a Blakean Eden, he may also have had in mind passages such
                    as the following dealing with God’s creation of a sublunary world of
                    delight: 
					<q> Beneath him with new wonder now he views<lb/>
 To all delight of
                        human sense expos’d<lb/>
 In narrow room Nature’s whole
                        wealth, yea more,<lb/>
 A Heaven on Earth. . . . (IV, 205-08) </q>
                </p>
                <p>In one sense, then, the entire Memorable Fancy is a dramatic enactment of or
                    gloss on the first part of Plate 5 of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
                        Hell.</hi> Adam’s interpretation of Eve’s dream
                    includes a discussion of Reason as the restraint of desire: 
					<q> . . . what in
                        sleep thou didst abhor to dream,<lb/>
 Waking thou never wilt consent to do.
                        (V, 121-22) </q>
Thus Eve’s temptations, in the dream and in
                    actuality, are clearly the models for Thel’s failure in <hi rend="i">The Book of
Thel</hi> and Oothoon’s ill-starred triumph in <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi> And the
transformation of
                    Milton’s Satan into the imaginative perceivercreator-artist, whose
                    worlds of delight are neither of the senses nor of the Miltonic God’s
                    Eden, is neatly prefigurative of Blake’s later efforts in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> to
release the seventeenth-century poet from his
                    “fetters.”</p>
                <p>We are obviously a long way from Chatterton, from the eighteenth century, and
                    from the “influence” of both. The <hi rend="i">Bristowe
                        Tragedie</hi> passage must be seen then as merely the vehicle for
                    Blake’s manipulation 
<pb id="p11-29" n="29"/>
of Milton to his own,
                    and ultimately to Milton’s, benefit. If Chatterton’s
                    “darte” (a word which Blake uses only once in
                    Chatterton’s sense—in <hi rend="i">King Edward the
                        Third</hi>, III, 176<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54"
type="note">7</ref>) and its warlike
                    associations remained in Blake’s mind at all, they too become
                    transmogrified into “Arrows of desire,” “long winged
                    arrows of thought,” “Arrows of Love,” and
                    “Arrows of Intellect”—that is, the weapons of
                    “Mental Fight” whereby even “Bacon &amp; Newton
                    &amp; Locke” as well as “Milton &amp; Shakspear
                    &amp; Chaucer” may “appear in Heaven.” And
                    perhaps Chatterton as well.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n85"
type="note">8</ref><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86" type="note">9</ref> 
                    <note id="n54">
                        <hi rend="s">7</hi> Both Spenser and
                        Milton make heavy use of the word.</note>
                    <note id="n85">
                        <hi rend="s">8</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, pl. 1; <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, pls. 33, 97,
                        98.</note>
                    <note id="n86">
                        <hi rend="s">9</hi> Another similar
                        reversal of Chatterton, but without the assistance of Spenser or Milton,
                        represents a more rudimentary form of Blake’s absorption of his
                        sources— and thus may suggest one way that we can conjecturally
                        date individual poems in the <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (or at
                        least determine whether they are early or late). In the second stanza of 
<hi rend="i">Gwin, King of Norway</hi> Blake virtually takes over whole
                        Chatterton’s stanza xli of the <hi rend="i">Bristowe
                            Tragedie.</hi> But whereas Bawdin’s speech extols the virtue
                        of his noble father who taught him “To feed the hungry poor/ Nor
                        let my servants drive away/ The hungry from my door,”
                        Blake’s tyrants are those very nobles who “did feed/
                        Upon the hungry poor” and “drive/ The needy from my
                        door.” A more elaborate transformation, though still without the
                        conversion factors of a Milton or a Spenser, is Blake’s rewrite
                        of Chatterton’s stanza lxii in “The Chimney
                        Sweeper” of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, where
                        Chatterton’s ballad stanza is elongated into fourteeners and the
                        “councilmen” escorting Bawdin to his beheading become the
                        “Grey headed beadles” leading the children into St.
                        Paul’s cathedral. Since Lowery concentrated on apparent
                        similarities in wording, form, and tone, she ignores passages such as these
                        which involve major transmutations by Blake.</note>
                </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>