<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>11.1.worrall</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="minute">Blake’s Derbyshire: A Visionary Locale in Jerusalem</title>
                <author n="Worrall">David Worrall</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1977</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1977</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">11.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
                            <name>Brad Hayden</name>
                            <resp>Design Consultant</resp>
                            <name>Michael Hays</name>
                            <resp>Circulation Manager</resp>
                            <name>Jane Welford</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>John Beer</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Raymond Deck</name>
                            <name>Thomas Dilworth</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
                            <name>Corinne M. Henning</name>
                            <name>Donald L. Kent</name>
                            <name>Vivian Mercier</name>
                            <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
                            <name>Dennis Read</name>
                            <name>Grant C. Roti</name>
                            <name>Richard J. Schroyer</name>
                            <name>Ruthven Todd</name>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1977"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_11">
        <body>
	<pb id="p11-34" n="34"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-11-1-0009">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">Minute Particulars</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">Blake’s Derbyshire: A Visionary Locale in
                                Jerusalem</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <hi rend="b">by</hi>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="b">David</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">Worrall</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>In the design to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 23 where Albion utters
                        “his last words, relapsing! / Hoarse from his rocks, from caverns
                        of Derbyshire &amp; Wales / And Scotland” (<hi rend="i">J</hi>
                        23:26-28, E 167), Blake shows a series of separate, enclosed human forms who
                        are apparently the inhabitants of these caverns. If Blake is making a
                        specific reference here it is probably to the Devil’s Arse cavern
                        in Derbyshire (see Damon, <hi rend="i">Blake Dictionary</hi>) which was
                        inhabited by the poor during Blake’s lifetime.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">1</ref> Charles Leigh’s <hi rend="i">The Natural
                            History Of Lancashire, Cheshire, And The Peak, in Derbyshire</hi>,
                        Oxford, 1700, has a large, unsigned engraving of the Devil’s Arse
                        showing “the Area where the Persons and the Houses are, where a
                        great many of the poor Inhabitants live” (Bk. 1, p. 192).
                        Blake’s knowledge is accurate then, but what of the
                        “fables” of the “caverns in Cornwall, Wales,
                        Derbyshire, and Scotland” which had been the subject of his
                        “visionary contemplations” in <hi rend="i">A Descriptive
                            Catalogue</hi> (40; E 533)? <note id="n59">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi> See James
                            Pilkington, <hi rend="i">A View Of The Present State Of Derbyshire</hi>,
                            (Derby 1789), I, 63-68. J. Johnson is given on the titlepage as one of a
                            pair of London Booksellers.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The absorption of the Peak, East Moor and the caverns and mines of Derbyshire
                        (see <hi rend="i">Blake Concordance</hi>) into Blake’s myth in
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> may stem from his imaginative reading or
                        recollection of another of Leigh’s plates which illustrated the
                        interior of Pooles Hole in the same county. This plate shows a guide and a
                        pair of tourists undergoing 
<figure n="DevilsArse.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="619">
                            <head>Illus. 1, “The Devil’s Arse,” from
                                Charles Leigh’s <hi rend="i">The Natural History of
                                    Lancashire, Cheshire, And The Peak, in Derbyshire</hi>, Oxford,
                                1700.</head>
                        </figure>
                        <figure n="PoolesHole.11.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="591">
                            <head>Illus. 2, “Poole’s Hole,” from
                                Leigh.</head>
                        </figure>
                        <pb id="p11-35" n="35"/> “the Diversion of beholding various
                        Representations produced by the petrifying Water continually dropping from
                        the Roof and Sides of the Rock” (Bk. 3, p. 43). The shapes produced
                        are stalactites and stalagmites plus the strong visual fancy of the
                        beholder. Leigh explains their popular interpretations as (E) a lion; (F)
                        the “Queen of Scots Pillar”; (H) and (I) as globes of
                        “Alabaster Sparr” called “the Font” and
                        “Mr. Cotton’s Haycocks”; (K) “the
                        Flitch of Bacon” and (L) “the Chairs” (Bk. i, pp.
                        189-90).</p>
                    <p>The most interesting figure from the Blakean point of view, however, is that
                        of (G) “the Figure of a Human Corps, formed likewise by the
                        Dropping of the Water from the Top of the Arch and the Sides.” It
                        is probable that B. knew of this figure in Leigh’s plate<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">2</ref> and associated its identification by
                        the local people as a memorial or “fable” of Albion who,
                        in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, is also “petrified” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 34[38]:1, 7,
E 177-78: <hi rend="i">J</hi> 46[32]:5, E
                        193) but awaiting revival: “Albion mov’d . . . / His
                        stony members” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 95:2-4, E 252). With this
                        interpretation the solitary pillar now standing beside the human figure can
                        be recognized as a remnant of the sixteen pillars erected when: 
						<q> the
                            merciful Saviour in his arms<lb/>
 Receiv’d him, in the arms
                            of tender mercy and repos’d<lb/>
 The pale limbs of his
                            Eternal Individuality<lb/>
 Upon the Rock of Ages. Then, surrounded with
                            a Cloud:<lb/>
 In silence the Divine Lord builded with immortal
                            labour,<lb/>
 Of gold &amp; jewels a sublime Ornament, a Couch of
                            repose,<lb/>
 With Sixteen pillars: canopied with emblems &amp;
                            written verse. (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 48:1-7, E 194) </q>
                        <note id="n60">
                            <hi rend="s">2</hi> Another oddly Blakean part of
                            Leigh’s plate is (B) “The Child that was born of a
                            Lancashire Gentlewoman with the Representation of a Flame upon its Body,
                            the Mother being affrighted with that terrible Flame when the City of
                            London was burned” (Bk. 1, p. 188).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>These crucial differences between vision and mere degenerate fancy make it
                        clear why the eighteenth century visitor to Pooles Hole saw a similarity
                        between the cave’s interior and the interior of a church. Instead
                        of the “Spiritual Verse” of the Decalogue, Joshua, Judges,
                        Samuel, Kings, Psalms, Prophets, Gospels and Revelation (<hi rend="i">J</hi>
                        48:8-11, E 194) which surrounds Albion’s sleeping form, they only
                        saw the rock shapes as an “Organ and Choir-work” and Font
                        (Bk. 3, p. 43).</p>
                    <p>Albion’s movements in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> imply that his
                        resting place is a variant of Pooles Hole. After a temporary manifestation
                        of rebellion when his “Great Voice of the Atlantic howled over
                        Druid Altars” and “Round the Rocky Peak of Derbyshire
                        London Stone &amp; Rosamonds Bower” (<hi rend="i">J</hi>
                        57:5,7, E 205), Albion “fled beneath the Plow / Till he came to the
                        Rock of Ages. &amp; he took his Seat upon the Rock” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 57:15-16, E
205). The Peak’s prophetic
                        elevation (but capable of druid cruelty if reason usurps, <hi rend="i">J</hi> 21:34, E
165) has as its contrary the “horrid
                        Chasm” beneath (“the most terrible Chasm that I ever yet
                        beheld” Leigh on Pooles Hole, Bk. 1, p. 187), where a more deadly
                        liquid drips: 
						<q> Derby Peak yawnd a horrid Chasm at the Cries of Gwendolen,
                            &amp; at<lb/>
 The stamping feet of Ragan upon the flaming Treddles
                            of her Loom<lb/>
 That drop with crimson gore with the Loves of Albion
                            &amp; Canaan<lb/>
 Opening along the Valley of Rephaim, weaving over
                            the Caves of Machpelah. (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 64:35-38, E 213) </q>
                    </p>
                    <p>An intermediate, earthly plain of existence is indicated as East Moor in
                        Derbyshire, a level state with the potential for either reasoning slavery or
                        prophetic independence: 
						<q> Hyle on East Moor in rocky Derbyshire,
                            rav’d to the Moon<lb/>
 For Gwendolen: she took up in bitter
                            tears his anguished heart<lb/>
 That apparent to all in Eternity, glows
                            like the Sun in the breast:<lb/>
 She hid it in his ribs &amp; back
                            . . . . . . raving he ran among the rocks,<lb/>
 Compelld into a shape of
                            Moral Virtue against the Lamb. (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 80:66-69, 76-77, E
                            235)<lb/>
                            <lb/>
 The Mothers love of obedience is forgotten &amp; you
                            seek a Love<lb/>
 Of the pride of dominion, that will Divorce Ocalythron
                            &amp; Elynittria<lb/>
 Upon the East Moor in Derbyshire &amp;
                            along the Valleys of Cheviot. (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 93:4-6, E 251) </q>
                        Enitharmon’s words in the latter passage unconsciously reflect
                        how the moor of the surface of the physical land of Albion is the level on
                        which the battle for vision is fought.</p>
                    <p>Blake’s use of the three levels of Derbyshire, peak, moor and
                        cavern, illustrates how neatly geographical locale can be adapted for an
                        imaginative purpose.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>