<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>11.2.ott</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Clark Stewart, illus., The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</title>
        <author n="Ott">Judith Ott</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1977</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1977</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">11.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>[Contributors]</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <name>Raymond Deck</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Brice Farwell</name>
              <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
              <name>Katharyn R. Gabriella</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Mary V. Jackson</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Judith Ott</name>
              <name>Claude Marie Senninger</name>
              <name>Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1977"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_11">
    <body>
	<pb id="p11-117" n="117"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-11-2-0005">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell. William Blake. Drawings by Clark Stewart:
Knoxville, TN: Darkpool Press, 1972. 35 pp., 13 pls. $55. Order from F. Clark Stewart, Art Department,
University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN 37916. Edition of 100 copies, numbered and signed by the
author.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Judith</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Ott</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Clark Stewart’s drawings for <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> will cause mixed reactions in many
a Blake enthusiast. Intended as a personal response to Blake’s visionary cosmology, Stewart’s designs
incorporate familiar Blakean motifs (mundane shell, batwinged spectre, and flocks of
<figure n="StewartDrawing.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="658" height="1000"/>
sheep) with some wildly disparate ones (World War I and II planes and tanks, top hats and a jack-o-lantern).
As a result, the combined images in these drawings create a simultaneous sensation of déjà vu and culture
shock in the viewer. This kind of liberal play within the hallowed territory of Blake’s own illustrations
may well be frowned upon by the Blake purist. However, seen as an extension of—rather than an intrusion
upon—Blake’s designs, these drawings present a fresh <corr type="emend">interpretation</corr> of the artist-poet’s well-thumbed
iconographical system.</p>
          <p>In style, Stewart’s drawings are of a gorgeously detailed, linear character not unlike the
graphic works of Dürer. They display the variety of texture, depth of space, crinkled drapery patterns and
tightly packed compositions that characterize works of the Northern Renaissance. Although Blake often borrowed
from such engravings, he inevitably simplified the figures and flattened the spatial representations in his
own work. Thus, with their Northern Renaissance flavor, Stewart’s illustrations resemble Blakean, sources
more closely than Blake designs. Both Blake and Dürer were skilled at combining many different symbolic
elements into a cohesive whole. Unfortunately, Stewart’s compositions lack this quality and too often appear
overworked, disjointed or contrived e.g., pls. 7, 11, 13). The unifying device of a frame is only successful
in some of the designs
<pb id="p11-118" n="118"/>
<figure n="StewartEagle.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="593" height="1000"/>
<pb id="p11-119" n="119"/>
<figure n="StewartSerpent.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="648" height="1000"/>
(pls. 1, 3, 8, 10)—generally the compositions suffer from a non-integrated eclecticism.</p>
          <p>Iconographically, Stewart borrows much from Yeats and the Christian mystical-magical symbolism of
the Rosicrucians (pls. 1, 4, 7, 9). The rose and other emblems like the stag and horned goat have a prominence
in these drawings that is foreign to Blake. But Blake is certainly the main source of Stewart’s imagery and
some of his drawings follow the text of <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> closely. Plate 8 is clearly the
“Printing House in Hell,” complete with Dragon-Man, viper, eagle, lion (shown as a cat) and books “arranged in
libraries” (Blake and Stewart’s books among them). Many of the other illustrations can be convincingly
linked with a line from the text: plate 6 with the poet “sitting on a pleasant bank beside a river by
moonlight”; plate 5 with “man [who] has closed himself up, till he sees all things thro’ narrow chinks of
his cavern”<gap type="emend"/> and plate 4 with “ a mighty Devil folded in black clouds, 
hovering on the sides of a rock.”</p>
          <p>There are other drawings by Stewart that owe more to Blake’s images than to his text. Plates 1
and 2 compare in theme with Blake’s title-page for <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> and plate 3 seems to
elaborate on the image of “The Sick Rose” from <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi> Although there is much
of Blake in these drawings, Stewart has not attempted to illustrate <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> literally.
Each of his plates contain fresh and intriguing combinations of old and new motifs and this is their greatest
strength. Significantly, Stewart is most successful in the few designs in which he goes beyond the text. For
example, plate 12 represents the “cherub with flaming sword” with an intense visionary grandeur comparable to
Blake’s own.</p>
          <p>In a well-bound, signed and limited edition, Clark Stewart’s illustrations for <hi rend="i">The
Marriage</hi> should be of interest to any Blake admirer who has struggled with the poet-artist’s complex
visions in the past, knows the joys born of careful thought and close observation, and is willing to apply
these techniques to the work of another. As with Blake’s illustrations to the works of other poets,
Stewart’s drawings inevitably reveal more about the illustrator than about the subject being illustrated.
Those who would seek only an echo of Blake’s imagery should look elsewhere.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
