<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>11.2.gleckner</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake’s Illustration of the Third Temptation in Paradise Regained</title>
        <author n="Gleckner">Robert F. Gleckner</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1977</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1977</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">11.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>[Contributors]</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <name>Raymond Deck</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Brice Farwell</name>
              <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
              <name>Katharyn R. Gabriella</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Mary V. Jackson</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Judith Ott</name>
              <name>Claude Marie Senninger</name>
              <name>Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1977"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_11">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-11-2-0006">
        <pb id="p11-126" n="126"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">BLAKE’S ILLUSTRATION OF THE THIRD TEMPTATION IN <hi rend="i">PARADISE
REGAINED</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>Robert F. <name>Gleckner</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In a recent note in the <hi rend="i">Milton Quarterly</hi> (10 [1976], 48-53) J. Karl Franson
compares a number of the illustrations by various artists to the temple spire scene in <hi rend="i">Paradise
Regained</hi>, concluding that “only one—William Blake—interprets the scene in close accord with the text
of the entire poem.” Further, his illustration “presents a perceptive and convincing interpretation of the
crisis, and indeed of the whole work, that resolves much of the apparent ambiguity” in the episode that has
made it one of the most perplexing cruxes in the poem (p. 48). More particularly, in contrast to the other
Milton illustrators and to his commentators, Blake’s rendition “suggests neither a human balancing feat nor
a miraculous intervention” (i.e. support for Christ by the angels), but rather “provocative evidence that
Blake is proposing a third alternative, that Christ alone performs the miraculous 
stand,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">1</ref> 
that, as Wittreich pointed out earlier,
“Christ’s words [on the pinnacle] indicate his own coming to awareness; he now comprehends that which he did
not know before.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Franson, p. 51. He cites other passages in <hi rend="i">Paradise
Regained</hi> (e.g. I, 11; IV, 535-36, 598, 601-03) and <hi rend="i">The Christian Doctrine</hi> as evidence
of Milton’s intent. Blake’s illustrations to <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> are available in a
variety of publications: Darrell Figgis, <hi rend="i">The Paintings of William Blake</hi> (London: E. Benn,
1925); Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">Milton’s Poems in English</hi> (London: Nonesuch Press, 1926); David
Bindman, <hi rend="i">Catalogue of the Blake Collection of the Fitzwilliam Museum</hi> (Cambridge: Heffer,
1970); and J. A. Wittreich, <hi rend="i">Calm of Mind</hi> (Cleveland: Case Western Reserve, 1971). The issue
of the <hi rend="i">Milton Quarterly</hi> in which Franson’s note appears features the pinnacle
illustration, in color, on its cover.</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">2</hi> “William Blake: Illustrator-Interpreter of <hi rend="i">Paradise
Regained</hi>,” in <hi rend="i">Calm of Mind: Tercentenary Essays on Paradise Regained and Samson
Agonistes</hi>, ed. Wittreich (Cleveland and London: Case Western Reserve University Press, 1971), p.
121.</note></p>
          <p>While there is little to quarrel with in this general view, there are some additional details
that both strengthen Franson’s (and Wittreich’s) case and at the same time reveal a greater complexity in
Blake’s illustration than he seems to see. For example, Psalm 91, which Satan refers to 
(<hi rend="i">PR</hi>, IV, 556-59), speaks of God’s angels being given “charge over” Christ, including the
responsibility to “bear thee up in their hands, lest thou dash thy foot against a stone.” Milton’s version,
in Satan’s words, is: “in thir hands / They shall up lift thee” (IV, 557-58). But in fact it is Satan who
lifts him up and bears him in his hands (“caught him up” and “There on the highest Pinnacle he set / The Son
of God”—IV, 541, 549-50). Beyond this textual reinterpretation by Milton of the Biblical passage and
Satan’s version of it,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">3</ref> Blake
positions one of his three angels at Christ’s feet somewhat ambiguously. Is he indicating appropriate
obeisance, or offering physical support as if in anticipation of a loss of balance, or calling attention to
the lack of physical and divine aid, or gesturing to earth in invitation to the “flow’ry valley” in which
they finally “set him down” for the feast of “Celestial Food, Divine, / Ambrosial” and “Ambrosial drink” (IV,
586-90) before Christ returns refreshed “to his Mother’s house” (639)? The answer seems to me a combination
of all four, the second and third possibilities reiterating visually Franson’s point that neither physical
support nor divine intervention is necessary to steady Christ no matter how “uneasy” his “station” (IV, 584),
the “undoubtable ‘proof’ of his divine nature” (Franson, 51). <note id="n36"><hi rend="s">3</hi> It should
also be noted that Satan’s setting Christ “on the highest Pinnacle” (“highest plac’t” as he himself puts
it—IV, 553) is parodic of Psalm 91.14: “Because he hath set his love upon me, therefore will I deliver him:
I will set him on high . . . ”).</note></p>
          <p>Blake further enhances this view by the positioning of his angels both in relation to each other
and to Christ, and to the plummeting, defeated Satan. Our eye movement over the angels’ configuration seems
to me to proceed both downward and upward, each angel being, as it were, a kind of still portrait, the three
together constituting a cinematographic sequence. The downward movement, from upright posture to kneeling
upright to the gesture of obeisance, is implicitly rejected by the self-sustained Christ. The upward movement
from the lowered arms of the bottom angel up through the wings of the other two (echoed in the prayerful hands
of the middle angel) reasserts that self-containedness. Contrariwise, Satan to the right of Christ falls
heavily, the encompassing mass of flame ironically repeating the angelic configuration, and his divided beard
and struggling legs grotesquely parodying the angels’ wings. Thus just as Milton has Satan enact his own
challenge to Christ (“if not to stand, / Cast thyself down”—IV, 554-55), so Blake dramatizes the inadequacy
of physical strength or balance in his muscular Satan to paralle the superfluousness of aid from the
angels.</p>
          <p>Finally, Blake’s Christ thus stands between both angelic and physical natures, between youth
and age, between heaven and earth (as well as heaven and hell), comprising, yet triumphing over, both in the
cruciform position set against the penumbral background of cloud and sky:
<q>
Whether thron’d<lb/>
In the bosom of bliss, and light of light<lb/>
Conceiving, or remote from Heaven, enshrin’d<lb/>
In fleshly Tabernacle, and human form. . . .<lb/>
(IV, 596-99)
</q>
Franson’s conclusion is sound, then: Blake reveals and illustrates “Milton’s fundamental concern in the
work,” that is “to dramatize his conception of Christ’s unique nature” (51). But Blake also, via the
positional dynamics and spatial movement of his entire illustration, enacts the several complexities and
implicit contrasts in Milton’s poem that even more fully than Franson shows illuminate the precise nature of
that uniqueness.</p>
<pb id="p11-127" n="127"/>
<figure n="but544.1.10.wc" id="but544.1.wc.10" work-copy="but544.1" rend="db" width="825" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>WBlake inv<lb/>
	10</figTranscr>
</figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
