<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>11.2.fine</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">William Blake: The Painter as Poet, An Exhibition at Adelphi University</title>
        <author n="Fine">Ruth E. Fine</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1977</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1977</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">11.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>[Contributors]</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <name>Raymond Deck</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Brice Farwell</name>
              <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
              <name>Katharyn R. Gabriella</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Mary V. Jackson</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Judith Ott</name>
              <name>Claude Marie Senninger</name>
              <name>Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1977"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_11">
    <body>
      <pb id="p11-110" n="110"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-11-2-0005">
        <figure n="Exhibition.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="750" height="618"/>
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Blake: The Painter as Poet. An Exhibition Commemorating the 150th
Anniversary of the Artist’s Death. March 19-May 29, 1977. Catalog by Donald A. Wolf, Tom Dargan, &amp; Erica
Doctorow. Garden City, NY: Library Gallery, Adelphi University, 1977. 24 pp., 9 pls. (1 in color).
$1.50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Ruth</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Fine</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>As part of a University Blake Festival commemorating the 150th anniversary of the artist’s
death, the exhibition <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Painter as Poet</hi> was held at the Swirbul Library
Gallery, Adelphi University, Garden City, NY, from 19 March to 29 May. Donald A. Wolf, Chairman of Adelphi’s
Department of English, Erica Doctorow, Head of the Fine Arts Library, and Tom Dargan, consultant from State
University of New York, Stony Brook, organized the exhibition and wrote the accompanying illustrated
catalogue. The catalogue is essentially a word-for-word record of the exhibition labels and other posted
explanatory material, and I shall refer below either to labels or to catalogue entries depending upon the
context. Either of the two designations may be assumed to describe both. The exhibition consisted of 41
objects—15 original Blake works borrowed from various collections as listed below, supplemented by facsimile
items mainly drawn from the Swirbul Library’s Leipniker Blake Collection with loans from the Hofstra
University Library and Lessing J. Rosenwald.</p>
          <p>The exhibition was housed in an entrance gallery space with standing cases along ore wall and
table cases along a second. It was directed to the broad university audience, possibly serving as an
introductory Blake experience for many. The cases were
<pb id="p11-111" n="111"/>
<figure n="ExhibitionVisitor.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="799"/>
tightly filled but the installation was handsome; the works were placed upon felt and velvet of a brown-orange
color similar to that used by Blake in surface printing, for example <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi>, Copy V or <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, Copy F.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">1</ref> Magnifying lenses permitted a clearer view of
particular objects and the volumes rested on plexiglas cradles. Unfortunately, labels occasionally were placed
so that a novice viewer might easily have been confused about which labels referred to which objects. 
<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">1</hi> This color was used for the catalogue cover-stock, text, and illustrations as
well as for printed material related to the other Blake Festival events—clearly an effort to visually
emphasize for the public the relationship among the several activities. For the catalogue illustrations, the
color is sympathetic to reproduction of Blake’s relief printed works, but the engravings and the drawing do
suffer.</note></p>
          <p>According to the catalogue introduction, the exhibition (which was inclusive enough to indicate
the rich texture of Blake’s <hi rend="i">oeuvre</hi> and the complexity of his mythology) “focuses on the
ways in which art and poetry contribute to the totality of his vision; and in doing so it explores a central
theme, the contraries of innocence and experience in his work.” The introduction then provides Northrop
Frye’s explanation of Blake’s contrary states of innocence and experience.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">2</ref> Lacking in both the catalogue introduction and the
accumulated catalogue entries was a broad statement explaining the relationships between the particular
exhibited works in the context of Blake’s contraries of innocence and experience. Also, given that the
exhibition was directed to a non-specialist audience, it would have been helpful if some explanation of
Blake’s total system (of which this pair of contraries was a part) had been offered in the descriptive
material. For the books, a paragraph summarizing the essential bibliographical information and more
importantly the content or themes of volumes, followed by brief explanatory labels for each plate, would have
helped make the exhibition easier to grasp than the repetitive (especially with the bibliographical material),
somewhat fragmented labels that were provided.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">3</ref> As this review is to be of both the exhibition and the catalogue (unpublished labels are
not the same as a published catalogue, even if the material is identical), I feel obligated to make one
initial distinction—the selection of objects (the exhibition) was much richer than the explanatory material
(the catalogue), which was more spirited than informative. <note id="n16"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Northrop Frye,
ed., <hi rend="i">Selected Poetry and Prose of</hi> [<hi rend="i">William</hi>] <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (New
York: Random House, 1953), pp. xxv-xxvii.</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Summaries and explanatory material were inconsistent in quantity and
quality. For example, no overall picture was presented for <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, or 
<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, while for <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, one was. In this
regard, it is difficult to accept as explanation that “<hi rend="i">Visions</hi> is a feminist tragedy and
something of a puzzle” (cat. 20). Interpretive entries at times lacked clarity. In some instances this results
from the fragmentary presentation. For example, cat. 25 by implication refers back to cat. 24 in contrasting
two “perspective(s)” on Urizen. Some entries are internally confusing, as in cat. 30, where in a description
of plate 2 from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem, Milton</hi> is quoted without indicating the source. The entry is
further unclear as to what a “labor hymn” is and whether the phrase refers to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, the
work being described, or <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, the work being quoted. Facts, too, sometimes require
clarification. In cat. 38, while the inscription on plate 1 of <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of
Job</hi> may indeed be read as “1828,” one presumes this is an error for 1825.</note></p>
          <p>Along with one copy of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (Trianon facsimile) and one of 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> (Muir facsimile) were two copies of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi> (both Trianon); <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> presented in two copies (Trianon and Brown
University Press facsimiles); <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> in three copies (two Trianon
and one Hotten facsimile). <hi rend="i">America, A Prophecy</hi> was presented both in facsimile and
<pb id="p11-112" n="112"/>
the original; the facsimiles were two copies of the Trianon edition, and the electrotype made from the
copperplate fragment of cancelled plate “a” (in copy a* not A* as in cat. 19) in the National Gallery of Art,
Rosenwald Collection. Importantly, the exhibition included the hand colored <hi rend="i">America</hi>
frontispiece from the Philip H. and A. S. W. Rosenbach Foundation. Also on loan from the Rosenbach Foundation
were the title page and frontispiece from <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (Copy H) and
the title page from <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">4</ref> <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> was further presented in two facsimiles (Muir and Trianon), 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> in one (Trianon). <hi rend="i">Europe, A Prophecy</hi> was represented by the hand
colored frontispiece “The Ancient of Days” from the Rosenbach Foundation and plate 11 (uncolored) on loan from
the Philadelphia Museum of Art. <hi rend="i">The Song of Los, Milton, A Poem</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> were all shown in Trianon Press facsimiles. An impression of <hi rend="i">Little Tom
the Sailor</hi>, on loan from the Philadelphia Museum of Art, further demonstrated Blake’s work in relief
printing. <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Editorial inconsistencies which affect the quality of the
information occur throughout the catalogue. To cite one example, the Rosenbach <hi rend="i">America</hi>
frontispiece (cat. 17) is described as “Relief etching printed in blue painted with tan and blue watercolors”
while the Rosenbach <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> title page and frontispiece (cat. 20 and 22) are described as
“Relief etching painted with watercolors.” One might also note such editorial problems as the fact that both
of Northrop Frye’s names are misspelled in the footnote to the Introduction.</note></p>
          <p>Blake as an engraver was seen in <hi rend="i">The Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> on loan from Maxine S.
Cronbach, <hi rend="i">Christ Trampling Urizen</hi> and <hi rend="i">George Cumberland’s Card</hi>, the
latter two lent by R. John Blackley, and from The Art Museum, Princeton University, four plates from 
<hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>, and restrikes from two of the seven (not six as stated in cat.
39) <hi rend="i">Illustrations of Dante</hi>, printed in 1968 from the engraved plates in the National Gallery
of Art, Rosenwald Collection. The one drawing in the exhibition was one of the wash drawings from the 
<hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> series, “Tiriel Dead Before Hela” (lent anonymously).</p>
          <p>Because the exhibition in several instances included more than one facsimile of a given book, one
was able to see several plates from one book, or, when different facsimile editions (from various copies) were
used, to focus on the variations Blake made on one plate. While this aspect of Blake’s investigative spirit
was both implied and demonstrated by the exhibition, it was not pointed out or discussed; neither were the
very real differences between facsimiles and originals. Adelphi was fortunate in obtaining several significant
originals which made these differences clear but they might not have been noted by the novice viewer. A most
cogent demonstration of the differences in the tactile life of printed surfaces and their effects on one’s
responses to works of art might have been made by comparing the Trianon copy of <hi rend="i">The Gates of
Paradise</hi> with any of the original engravings on exhibition. Attention might well have been brought to
this difference, as well as to the variations in the quality and character of the different facsimile
editions. I don’t mean to suggest that this ought to have been a major concentration but, rather, that
within the context of an exhibition these points are important if the viewer is to see the significance of the
nuances in Blake’s visual art.</p>
          <p>The focus of the Adelphi exhibition was not one of art historical or bibliographical analysis or
explication. The catalogue was undoubtedly published within a limited timespan and budget. It seems desirable,
however, that certain basic information be included. To cite a few desiderata: one would like to have page or
entry numbers throughout for references cited; would like to know that the impression of <hi rend="i">The
Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> was in the fourth state (cat. 1); that the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> drawing is one of
9 extant of a presumed series of 12, and something about the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> poem other than that it
“is about an old man who was really dead before his day, a despairing wanderer who cursed his children” (cat.
11); that the 1868 (J. C., not T. C.) Hotten facsimile of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>
was the first published facsimile of a Blake illuminated book (cat. 9); be assured that inscriptions are
accurately quoted, as, for example, the ones from <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi> (cat. 34) and 
<hi rend="i">George Cumberland’s Card</hi> (cat. 41) which are not;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n19" type="note">5</ref> “Experts” and “pupil” are best mentioned by name (because Keynes’ 
<hi rend="i">Engravings by William Blake: The Separate Plates</hi> is cited, one assumes that reference is being
made to Sir Geoffrey Keynes and Thomas Butts, Jr. or Sr., cat.26); and finally, I have reservations about the
words and phrases quoted throughout without citation. <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">5</hi> “printed &amp; sold
by the Widow Spicer of Folkstone for the benefit of her orphans.” should read “Printed for &amp; Sold by the
Widow Spicer of Folkstone / for the Benefit of her Orphans / October 5, 1800” and “W Blake inv &amp; sc: A AE
1827.” should read “W Blake inv &amp; sc: / A Æ 70 1827.”</note></p>
          <p>Unfortunately, the catalogue perpetuates some fallacies. For example, to describe Blake in the
introduction as having “found a way through his contemporary wasteland of indifference, ignorance and
dullness” does a disservice to late 18th and early 19th century England.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">6</ref> To say that “Blake should be read with imagination. The
reasoning intellect can tag along if it can keep up . . . ” (cat. 1) does a disservice to Blake’s contraries
of reason and imagination. While Blake’s process for applying his texts to metal plates and his relief
printing techniques may remain “Blake’s secret(s)” (cat. 19), not mentioning some of the recent experiments
and theories related to these methods does a disservice to contemporary artists and scholars.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">7</ref> Furthermore, it seems shortsighted to state
(in the introduction) that Blake was “neglected, regarded as an eccentric or a madman” by his
contemporaries.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">6</hi> As a recent and convincing denial of this premise, one might note Corlette
Rossiter Walker’s <hi rend="i">William Blake in the Art of His Time</hi>, the catalogue for an exhibition
held at the University Art Galleries, University of California at Santa Barbara, 24 February to 28 March
1976.</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">7</hi> See Robert N. Essick, ed., <hi rend="i">The Visionary Hand: Essays for the
Study of William Blake’s Art and Aesthetics</hi> (Los Angeles: Hennessey &amp; Ingalls, 1973), Part I:
“Blake’s Techniques of Relief Etching: Sources and Experiments,” pp. 7-44 (includes Ruthven Todd’s essay
“The Techniques of William Blake’s Illuminated Printing” originally published in <hi rend="i">The Print
Collector’s Quarterly</hi>, 29 (Nov. 1948), here published with Todd’s revisions of the notes and new
illustrations and (p. 44) the editor’s list of sources for other brief descriptions of the relief etching
process); John W. Wright, “Blake’s Relief-Etching Method,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 36(Spring
1976), pp. 94-114; Robert N. Essick, “William Blake as an Engraver and Etcher,” pp. 16-17 in Walker, 
<hi rend="i">William Blake in the Art of His Time</hi>, op. cit.</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">8</hi> A less negative possibility is presented by Suzanne R. Hoover in her essay
“William Blake in the Wilderness: A Closer Look at his Reputation, 1827-1863,” published in Morton D. Paley
and Michael Phillips, eds., <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays in Honour of Sir Geoffrey Keynes</hi> (Oxford:
Clarendon Press, 1973), pp. 310-48. While the essay attends to the period after Blake’s death, on p. 312
Hoover notes that “Of the seven obituaries that are known, one is derisive, but the others are
appreciative.”</note></p>
          <p>The Adelphi Swirbul Library exhibition brings into focus some problems facing Blake studies and
also presents possibilities for future Blake exhibitions. While one laments the extensive use of facsimile
objects (especially without adequate explanatory material), it has become clear that important unique Blake
works (and one generally considers each copy of his books as unique) will be more and more difficult to obtain
for other than major exhibitions (i.e., those that will both attract large audiences and make scholarly
contributions via well-researched and imaginative catalogues). The organizers of the Adelphi exhibition
indicated that institutions which in the past have been most generous in lending their other holdings for
exhibitions were hesitant to release the Blake items. It is admirable that they organized their exhibition in
spite of this obstacle. It seems that in the near future organizing an exhibition like <hi rend="i">William
Blake: The Apocalyptic Vision</hi> held at Manhattanville College in Purchase, NY in 1974<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">9</ref> will be difficult except in special
circumstances. <note id="n23"><hi rend="s">9</hi> This exhibition, also held at a small, not centrally located
educational institution, included several very important Blake watercolors and drawings as well as superb
plates from the illuminated books. It was accompanied by an illustrated catalogue.</note></p>
          <p>Since 1974 the number of requests to borrow Blake material for exhibitions has increased
dramatically. Various factors make repeated lending a problem. The primary one is concern for the care and
preservation of the objects; increasing knowledge in the field of paper conservation has made many of us alter
<pb id="p11-113" n="113"/>
<figure n="PainterasPoet.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="637">
	<head>Frontispiece and Titlepage, <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Painter as Poet</hi>, catalogue of the
Adelphi exhibition.</head>
</figure>
our long-range views about exhibitions. Also, Blake material is so extensively studied at home institutions
(in itself a danger to the preservation of the objects) that one feels an obligation to try to have it
available for persons who travel great distances and at great expense in anticipation of viewing particular
works. From the standpoint of borrowing institutions, insurance costs have become prohibitive. One suspects,
therefore, that many institutions may have to make use of facsimile material in organizing small instructional
exhibitions such as this, which was reviewed at length by the press<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n24" type="note">10</ref> and enthusiastically received by the University community. 
<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Garden City, N.Y., <hi rend="i">Newsday</hi>, 13 May 1977, p. 11a, and 
<hi rend="i">The New York Times</hi>, Long Island Supplement, 15 May 1977, p. 24.</note></p>
          <p>Adelphi’s Blake festival included several <corr type="emend">inter-disciplinary</corr> programs
which took place concurrently with the exhibition—Tom Dargan’s illustrated talk, “Engraving Lessons from a
Favorite Angel: William Blake’s Secret Printing Process;” “Eternity in an Hour” including “The Spoken Word,”
readings arranged and directed by Nancy Miller and read by the University’s Story Players, and “The Visual
Image,” a modern dance piece inspired by Blake’s poetry (with choreography by Norman Walker, music by
Britten, lighting by Randy Klein, and costumes by Linda Cliggett) which was performed by the senior dance
majors; and the world premiere of a structuralist opera, commissioned especially for the Blake Festival,
“Willy” or “Auguries of Innocence.” The opera was written and directed by Jacques Burdick and Thomas Vuozzo
and performed by students in the Theatre Program. According to Mr. Burdick, Director of the Department of
Performing Arts Theatre Program, the opera based on Blake’s life, times, visions, and works began as a class
project in a Radical Theatre course concerned with the structuralist tenets of the French linguist Jacques
Lacan. The particular problem was how to translate Blake’s vision to sound. When it became apparent that the
project as envisioned would become a five or six hour trilogy, the group determined to concern itself, for the
time, with only the first part, “Willy” (Blake’s use of his powers of sight in infancy and youth). The
remaining two sections are conceived as “Will Blake” (youth and maturity) and “Mr. William Blake” (Blake’s
prophetic powers in old age). Mr. Burdick noted in the program that the group was hoping for financial
assistance to “stir up ‘Willy’ and allow him to spring, like the phoenix, into the triple flight of a
complete realization of our project.”</p>
          <p>A lighter facet of the Blake Festival was the production of Blake tee-shirts. Available from the
same address as the catalogue, the tee-shirts bear Blake’s autograph (Berg Collection, New York Public
Library), and come in sizes S, M, L, XL, in yellow, red, blue, white, royal and brown. The cost is $5 + .50
shipping. The University requests prepayment for the exhibition catalogue and the tee-shirts.</p>
          <pb id="p11-114" n="114"/>
          <p>The exhibition catalogue is available from the Fine Arts Library, Adelphi University, Garden
City, NY 11530, for $1 + .50 shipping.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
