<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>11.2.jackson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake and Zoroastrianism</title>
        <author n="Jackson">Mary Jackson</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1977</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1977</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">11.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>[Contributors]</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <name>Raymond Deck</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Brice Farwell</name>
              <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
              <name>Katharyn R. Gabriella</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Mary V. Jackson</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Judith Ott</name>
              <name>Claude Marie Senninger</name>
              <name>Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1977"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_11">
    <body>
    <pb id="p11-72" n="72"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-11-2-0002">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">BLAKE AND ZOROASTRIANISM</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>MARY <name>JACKSON</name></docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>There is considerable evidence that Blake was influenced by Zoroastrian and Mithraic iconography in
several illuminations for his and other’s poetry. When one compares the figures of god and 
<hi rend="i">daeva</hi> with Blake’s drawings and engravings, the sheer number of parallels argues convincingly
for some form of influence. Were there no other data than this to prove that Blake may have incorporated
elements of representations of the bull-slaying ritual, of Arimanes or Ahriman, god of dark, and Ormazd, god
of light, into his visual art, the evidence would seem persuasive. Fortunately, there is a good deal of
external evidence to substantiate the case for direct sources. To begin with, we have Blake’s own testimony
in <hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalogue</hi> of 1809. In his discussion of the spiritual form of Pitt guiding
Behemoth, Blake asserts:
<q>
These two pictures of Nelson and Pitt are compositions of a mythological cast, similar to those Apotheoses of
Persian, Hindoo and Egyptian antiquity which are still preserved on rude monuments, being copies from some
stupendous originals now lost or perhaps buried till some happier age. The artist having been taken in vision
to those wonderful republics . . . has seen those wonderful Originals . . . some of them were one hundred feet
in height; some were painted as pictures, and some carved as basso relievos, and some as groupes of statues,
all containing mythological and recondite meaning, where more is meant than meets the eye. (Keynes, 565-66;
Erdman, 521-22.)
</q>
Several things are suggested: first, that Blake actually saw representations of ancient Persian and other
compositions, for he asserts that they <hi rend="i">are</hi> preserved on rude monuments and are but copies of
the originals; second, that Blake’s imagination was keenly touched by what he saw, as his visionary journey
to view the originals attests; third, that he obviously considered his two paintings to resemble Persian
design, the most likely element being the snake enfolding portions of creation. Blake’s words and the often
stunning similarity of his illuminations and “copies” of Ahriman and Ormazd require careful consideration of
these analogues and possible direct sources of the Persian or so-called Zoroastrian.</p>
        <p>The evidence is corroborated by the existence of a large and diverse body of literature on
Zoroaster, which was often accompanied by drawings and engravings, and some of which we know Blake saw. That
this material usually contained information on and designs of the cult of Mithras—the religion popular among
Roman legions and thus spread even to Britain—is of no real importance, for writers frequently confused the
two. Religious and secular commentators contributed volume after volume on the subject. Travelers’ accounts
of voyages to the East were popular and numerous after mid-seventeenth century and continued to interest
philosophers and mythologists in the eighteenth century. These books only occasionally added any really fresh
information to what was already known from ancient Greek and Roman sources and from medieval writers, but they
sometimes contained line engravings of ruins, temples, rituals, and the like.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> (Although many travelers were themselves clergymen, they by no
means unanimously approved of Persian religion and culture.) To some, the praise of Zoroastrian monotheism and
spiritual enlightenment smacked of a heretical failure to appreciate the uniqueness of Christianity’s
divinely revealed truth. This priestly perception fueled many a dispute, eventually involving
<pb id="p11-73" n="73"/>
<figure n="BB450.6.COM" rend="file" width="705" height="1000">
	<head>3 “Tornado,” published state, from Darwin’s <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>Robert N. Essick Collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p11-74" n="74"/>
even the philosophes, notably Diderot and Voltaire, who wished to discredit the idea that Christianity was the
sole possessor of Truth, which could be discovered, they argued, by man in a natural and reasonable fashion,
unaided by the “light of Revelation.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref>
Both groups of partisans entertained hopes that the explorations of a young Frenchman in India would settle
the battle in their favor; both were rather disappointed, for the scrupulously non-partisan researcher
declined to enter the lists. Interest in Zoroastrianism was greatly stimulated, nonetheless, in 1771 upon the
publication of his work, <hi rend="i">Zend Avesta, Ouvrages du Zoroastre.</hi>
	<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Mandelslo, du Mans, Le Bruyn, Wheeler, Hanaway and Kaempfer, for example,
are among those traveler-journalists cited, with some engravings reproduced, in Jacob Bryant, <hi rend="i">A
New System</hi> (1774-76). See also J. Bidez and F. Cumont, <hi rend="i">Les Mages Hellénisés</hi> (Paris,
1938); F. Cumont, <hi rend="i">Textes et monuments figurés relatif aux mystères de Mithra</hi> (Paris,
1902); J. Duchesne-Guillemin, <hi rend="i">The Western Response to Zoroaster</hi> (Oxford, 1958); and A. V. W.
Jackson, <hi rend="i">Zoroaster, the Prophet of Ancient Iran</hi> (New York, 1898, 1928).</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Duchesne-Guillemin, pp. 2-10, 12-15.</note></p>
        <p>Anquetil du Perron had spent eight years in India in Pahlavi or Parsee communities learning ancient
and modern Persian, Arabic and Sanskrit. During these years he also meticulously copied and collated numerous
volumes of sacred works, and collected many texts and sorely needed dictionaries in these languages. His
two-volume translation, with a lengthy account of his voyage and a seventy page “Vie de Zoroastre,” was
received with much excitement in Germany and France, where scholars agreed that it superseded all other works.
Although English academics knew of du Perron’s finds before they were published, for he had visited London
and Oxford University before returning to France (<hi rend="i">Tome</hi> I, cccclviij-ccccxviij), they were
slower to accept the Continental judgment. Indeed, du Perron’s splendid achievement had little if any effect
on English mythologists before 1830: studies continued to pour out and most, like John Bell’s 
<hi rend="i">New Pantheon, or Historical Dictionary of the Gods</hi> (1790), rehearsed the established errors and
clichés. In addition to such “new” efforts, earlier popular works were readily available. Pierre Bayle’s
<hi rend="i">Dictionnaire historique et critique</hi>, for example, went through four editions in England
between 1710 and 1826.</p>
        <p>Two volumes contain crucial evidence about Blake’s possible sources. The first is familiar to
Blake critics. Jacob Bryant’s <hi rend="i">A New System, an Analysis of Ancient Mythology</hi> (1774-1776)
contains several fine line engravings of Ormazd, the god of light, and Mithraic devices. The plates were
engraved in Basire’s shop while Blake was an apprentice there, as is well known. Almost certainly, they are
a direct source for one of Blake’s most important illuminations. The second work may have been seen by
Blake, though it is impossible to be certain. Prior to 1771 (and long after in England) the treatise on the
Persian religion most widely known and influential was by the English scholar Thomas Hyde, whose 
<hi rend="i">Historica Religionis Veterum Persarum</hi> [sic] was first published in 1700 and reissued in a second
edition, which I have used, in 1760. On the continent it had been the subject of heated debate and controversy
because of the English cleric’s high esteem for the Zoroastrian religion. In England it remained a major
source for “speculative mythologists,” like Jacob Bryant, as his numerous references to it in <hi rend="i">A
New System</hi> reveal.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Historica Persarum</hi> contains several reproductions, including a four-panelled
tauroctone (illus. 1), which is from the 1760 edition. The progress of the panels is from the lower left,
where the stage is set for the sacrifice; to the upper left, where the key characters are positioned (Mithra,
the bull, Cautes, Cautopates, dog, sun, moon, snake and scorpion); to the upper right, in which the arrows,
whip and stylized thunderbolts indicate the world turbulence the sacrifice will rectify; to the lower right
panel, where the bull’s blood and semen are shed, and, though they try, neither scorpion nor snake will
steal the precious life-renewing fluids. Located between the two right panels is a minute particular which, if
Blake saw this book, he might not have overlooked. Illustration 2 is an enlargement of the center right scene.
Between the Apollo-like figure guiding four horses (which resembles the upper left hand figure in 
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, plate 11) and the chariot of seven fire altars drawn by two horses, there are two
figures of special interest. The main, winged one is serpent entwined and holds a sceptre in his left hand.
This small engraving of Ahriman, taken from a gem-stone carving, is accompanied by another, less frequently
seen version of the god or <hi rend="i">daeva</hi>, one which depicts him without lion features and wings, as
an entirely human form which is serpent encoiled.</p>
        <p>In this illustration from the 1760 work much alluded to by Bryant we find two major elements which
are paralleled in Blake drawings and engravings: first, those in the tauroctone in which Mithra sacrifices the
sacred bull; second, the winged, serpent-bound god, Ahriman, ruler of the corporeal world and guardian of the
means of ingress and egress. There is little difficulty tracing sources for the bull-slaying scene, which was
frequently described and illustrated. Examples of the Mithraic ritual, identical in the main to its
Zoroastrian counterpart, are housed in museums throughout Britain. Some were imported, like the magnificent
marble statue of the sacrifice in the British Museum (#1720), taken to England from Rome in 1815 by one C.
Standish, Esq. But in reality that was a case of coals-to-Newcastle, for the country was dotted by
archaeological sites containing tauroctones and a number of these were reported in “Transactions of the
Philosophical Society,” starting as early as 1743.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3"
type="note">3</ref> The representation of Ahriman, however, is rarer. These two figures in Hyde are the only
possible direct links I have yet discovered between Blake and images of the Mithraic god who is the
Zoroastrian devil, except for Fuseli’s drawing of Tornado, which we know only through Blake’s engraving
(illus. 3). While it cannot be stated unequivocally that the figures in <hi rend="i">Historica</hi> constitute
a direct influence, it can justly be said that Blake at least could have known through Bryant of this widely
influential work. I suggest that these minute particulars are very possible sources and that such close
analogues may in fact indicate direct influence, especially in the light of Blake’s own comments in 
<hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalogue.</hi>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Leroy A. Campbell, <hi rend="i">Mithraic Iconography and Ideology</hi>
(London, 1968). Prof. and Mrs. T. J. King verified data on the holdings in the British Museum.</note></p>
        <p>The figure of Ahriman in Hyde contains all the vital components commonly found in representations
of the god except one, the lion’s head. Curiously, Blake’s engraving of “Tornado” after Fuseli, depicting
<pb id="p11-75" n="75"/>
<figure n="Tauroctone.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="670">
	<head>1 Tauroctone.</head>
	<figDesc>Hyde’s <hi rend="i">Historica.</hi></figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="TauroctonePanel.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="282">
	<head>2 Enlargement of right center panel.</head>
</figure>
<pb id="p11-76" n="76"/>
<figure n="MithraicGod190.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="456" height="1000">
	<head>4 Mithraic God (190 AD), Vatican Museum.</head>
	<figDesc>Alinari 35666.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="MithraicGodC2.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="547" height="1000">
	<head>5 Mithraic God (c. 2nd C.), Vatican Museum.</head>
	<figDesc>Alinari 35667.</figDesc>
</figure>
a lion-headed, winged demon, is both an analogue to the tradition and evidence of a direct source. We do not
have the original drawing and cannot guess how Blake may have treated its contents. But his engraving for the
third edition of Erasmus Darwin’s <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi> (1795) bears a great mechanical
resemblance to more often seen versions of the god, the human face being a late development. Both forms were
accessible in Europe during the eighteenth century. Though strikingly alike, the engraving does not precisely
reproduce the symbolic features of the Mithraic god. For one thing, Tornado is encircled by a dragon with
bat-like wings and a snaky body and tail; the wings are not his own. However, the leonine head is notable as
are the flashes of lightning which recall the Mithraic tradition in which Ahriman’s two keys frame a
thunderbolt, an emblem associated with Jupiter. Perhaps the interesting parallels in the plate raise questions
less about Blake than about what Fuseli might have seen, or about what he actually drew, for that matter. For
we do not know what details, if any, Blake added or altered. The most we can say is that the engraving is
significant because it points to a now lost source which, in some respects was like the more widely available
representations of the lion-headed, winged god holding his sceptre.</p>
        <p>I have included examples of statues and bas-reliefs of the two main Mithraic traditions without
intending to suggest, naturally, that they are to be used for anything other than comparisons. As striking as
some of the correspondences are, there is no reason to believe they are more than coincidence. To facilitate
the discussion, I offer a brief account of the major Ahrimanic visual traits and their symbolism.</p>
        <p>In the statues, “basso-relievos,” and gem-stone engravings, Ahriman is most frequently depicted as
having the body of a man, the head of a lion, and one or two sets of wings (illus. 4, 5, and 6). His body is
entwined by a serpent—usually in two to three or five to seven coils—whose head rests on the crown of the
god’s head. In Mithraism, the serpent represents the world serpent believed to have been coiled around the
body of the cosmos. The four wings attached at the shoulders and hips (broken in illus. 4 but clearly visible
in 6) represent the
<pb id="p11-77" n="77"/>
<figure n="Eone.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="519" height="1000">
	<head>6 Eone, Villa Albani, Rome.</head>
	<figDesc>Alinari 27619.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="DeusArimanius.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="474" height="1000">
	<head>7 Deus Arimanius (c. 2nd C.), Florence.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of E.J. Brill, Leiden.</figDesc>
</figure>
winds of the four seasons and are “symbols of Pneuma, the hot breath that rules the seasons of life.” In his
aspect as <hi rend="i">Deus aeternus</hi>, Ahriman holds two keys (illus. 4 and 5), or less frequently one
(illus. 6), emblems of his cosmic powers in his role as demi-urge or creator of the natural world and lord of
men’s fortunes. He is not merely prince of <hi rend="i">this</hi> world, for the keys unlock one of the
seven doors barring the soul’s path to heaven. His rod or sceptre usually held in the left hand (illus. 4
and 6) is another emblem of his sovereignty over this world, as is the globe on which his feet rest. The
zodiacal and planetary signs on the body of the god (illus. 5) or surrounding him (illus. 10) became
increasingly popular and had important implications. Whether in his role as <hi rend="i">daeva</hi> or 
<hi rend="i">Deus aeternus</hi>, Ahriman is thus shown to have control over the cycle of the months as well as the
movements of planets and other heavenly bodies.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Campbell, pp. 211, 300-03, 348, 353. Cumont <hi rend="i">Les Mages</hi>, I,
12, 59, 67; II, 145. R. C. Zaehner, <hi rend="i">The Dawn and Twilight of Zoroastrianism</hi> (London, 1961),
pp. 129-30.</note></p>
        <p>Although there is a good deal of variety in the representations of the god, most of them contain
the symbolic elements described, with two noteworthy exceptions. There is a not very common tradition in which
Ahriman is depicted solely as a serpent encircled human figure, with none of the features usually given him.
Second, many of the standard traits appear in illus. 7, as well as another unusual, intriguing detail. To the
lower left, attached to the lowest two coils of the serpent, is what appears to be a cocoon-like structure
with the head and shoulders of a tiny human form breaking through its top. The cocoon is similar to the design
in the center of the god’s chest in illus. 4. Its progress down the snake’s body toward its tail suggests
the movement of the soul toward material or bodily existence. This appears to be a symbol of creation
specifically as a fall into the mortal world.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5"
type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Campbell, p. 350. Note that the cocoon-like encasing of the human form is
analogous to the Frontispiece, “What is Man?”, <hi rend="i">For the Sexes</hi> and to the ambiguously
infantile worm, Plate III, <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel.</hi></note></p>
        <p>There are numerous Blake illuminations which closely parallel these versions of Ahriman’s form
and meaning in Mithraism and Zoroastrianism. Perhaps the most well known are the variants of plate 6 of 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.</hi> In copy D in the Fitzwilliam, a single serpent entwined human figure is
shown falling, head downwards, arms in a cruciform position. The more frequently published version of that
detail contains two additional snake-coiled figures on either
<pb id="p11-78" n="78"/>
<figure n="but289.1.1.cpd" id="but289.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="765">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	1795 WB</figTranscr>
	<head>8 Elohim Creating Adam.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy Tate Gallery.</figDesc>
</figure>
side.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> Blake has clearly incorporated
his own recondite mythological meaning. The cruciform male with his falling companions simultaneously
fore-shadows and parodies Christ’s crucifixion, an inevitable though distant consequence of Urizen’s
error, which leads to fallenness or creation. But also the falling, serpent-bound bodies are symbolic forms
being thrown headlong toward the abyss or, more mercifully, toward the fixed forms that will limit their
fallen condition, which may then be temporary. Although the cruciform position of the figure is unique, I
think, to <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, the motive is certainly utilized increasingly in Blake’s visual art
after 1795, paralleling perhaps his growing view of the peril and horror of corporeality, despite its merciful
quality or even its beauty. Examples abound, from the detail in plate 13 of the early prophetic book, 
<hi rend="i">America</hi>, to major individual creations such as “The Spiritual Form of Nelson Guiding 
Leviathan,<supplied type="emend">”</supplied> “Laocoön,” or “A Vision of the Last Judgment.” 
<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Where it is feasible, I refer
readers to published plates, as in this case; see the Micromethods filmstrips for the Fitzwilliam variant. See
also David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> (Garden City, N. Y., 1974), p. 188.</note></p>
        <p>Blake’s “Elohim Creating Adam” (1795) is a richly imaginative analogue to the icons of Ahriman,
despite, or perhaps because of, the fact that the critical elements—wings, lion’s head, man’s naked
body, and serpent—are dispersed, so to speak, divided between the two figures (illus. 8). God or the Elohim
is given the wings (which closely resemble those of Ahriman in illus. 4) and a lion-like face with flowing,
mane-like hair. Adam’s body, serpent encoiled, is being created, given fixed form. The
<pb id="p11-79" n="79"/>
<figure n="but536.1.4.wc" id="but536.1.wc.04" work-copy="but536.1" rend="db" width="757" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>WBlake 1808<lb/>
	WBlake 1808</figTranscr>
	<head>9 Satan Watching the Caresses of Adam and Eve.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p11-80" n="80"/>
<figure n="DeusArimaniusModena.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="673" height="1000">
	<head>10 Deus Arimanius (c. 3rd C.), Modena.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy E.J. Brill, Leiden.</figDesc>
</figure>
snake encircles the lower half of his body, as God’s hands reach out to touch or gesture over Adam’s head;
and Adam’s feet (less completely articulated or metamorphosed than his head and torso?) seem to blend or
bend into the last two coils of the snake’s body. Blake may have intended to suggest in vision that Adam was
created out of the serpent’s body—the serpent symbolizing the senses, corporeality, and nature. The wings
no less than the serpent suggest to me the ambiguity of this scene, for wings recall the immortal psyche, but
also angels who are often representatives of mistaken or fallen vision (and at least one important devil, as
we shall see). The four parallel forms, the wings, God’s and Adam’s and the snake’s bodies, emphasize
the paradox, as do the mirrorings in the plate. The curling of the serpent’s tail above Adam’s lower legs
mirrors the swirling robe of God, and the facial expressions, particularly the somberness and the open mouths,
are deliberate visual echoes designed to shadow forth the truth that Creator and created are inescapably bound
together in this paradoxical moment: the momentous beginning is an end to eternal life; creation is fall. The
senses are vital in corporeal existence but simultaneously signal the closing off of the soul from
immortality. The vision records the moment and the shape of the process that are both profoundly sad and
merciful. Blake’s illumination calls to mind the statue (illus. 6) in which the tiny human form in the
cocoon progresses down the snake’s body toward existence in this world.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Blake’s “With Dreams upon my bed thou scarest me,” Plate XI of 
<hi rend="i">Job</hi>, is indeed a horrific and intensely ironic analogue to his “Elohim Creating Adam.” See S.
Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Job</hi> (New York, 1969).</note></p>
        <p>Ahriman was an ambiguous figure partly because of his innately paradoxical attributes and partly
because of the early confusion of two discrete traditions. In Mithraism he was a <hi rend="i">deus</hi> whose
awesome powers necessitated supplicating him for release from earthly existence and safe passage to heaven; in
Zoroastrianism he was a <hi rend="i">daeva</hi> (diabolical spirit) with a ferocity, cruelty, and fondness for
wantonly destroying men’s fortunes and spiritual hopes. This latter tradition predominated in Western
culture, where he was identified with Baal, Pluto, the anti-Christ and Satan.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> Blake’s watercolor, “Satan Watching the Caresses of Adam and
Eve” (1808) for <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> (illus. 9), is part of that tradition, to the extent that we
can allow that he was influenced by representations of Ahriman. It is also an analogue to a late Roman visual
development. The transformation in the bas-relief (illus. 10) represents a late trend in which Ahriman has
fully human features, though the symbolic lion is retained, appearing on his chest. As in the other icons, he
is serpent entwined and bears the sceptre of sovereignty in his left hand. Signs of the zodiac adorn the
ovular frame of the relief, and that structure is echoed by the egg—note its flaming halves at his feet and
above his head—from which the god is born.
<figure n="but529.1.4.wc" id="but529.1.wc.04" work-copy="but529.1" rend="db" width="815" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>WBlake 1807</figTranscr>
	<head>11 Satan’s and Raphael’s Entries into Paradise.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy the Huntington Library, San Marino, Calif.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p11-81" n="81"/>
Blake’s Satan, winged and serpent bound like the god, also has fully human features. In the foliage just
left of and slightly above Eve’s right wrist, however, one may see a shape created by the configuration of
the leaves, flame-like leaves, which suggests perhaps the head of a lion. It is coincidence undoubtedly that
there is so great a similarity between the drawing and bas-relief so removed from each other in time and
place. Yet the resemblance is even more striking in “Satan’s and Raphael’s Entries into Paradise” (1807)
for <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> (illus. 11). One can only marvel at what appears to be one of those
fortuitous similarities whose exactness is suggestive of the powerful, universal appeal of certain visual
symbols. <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> F. Cumont, <hi rend="i">The Oriental Religions in Roman
Paganism</hi> (New York, 1956), pp. 153-54; and <hi rend="i">Les Mages</hi>, I, 12, 59. Campbell, p.
353.</note></p>
        <p>Examples abound of Blake’s incorporation of two Ahrimanic details, perhaps from Hyde and
certainly from Fuseli, into his own visual symbolism, bat-like wings and serpent-encoiled forms. Any one even
a little familiar with his illuminations and paintings can call to mind an impressive number of serpent-bound
bodies, emblematic of Blake’s vision of the paradox of corporeal existence. Though essential to life and
often the portals of joy, the senses, especially touch, are perilous and can easily become a bog in which
mortals flounder and are lost. They are simultaneously the tangible, outward bound of the process by which the
spirit is benighted and the mode in this life of experiencing potentially redemptive bliss. Touch
(particularly sexuality), the most threatening of all, is appropriately symbolized by the serpent. And, though
the condition of being either female or male bespeaks to Blake the spirit’s descent and diminution, sexual
delight is a reflection, if only a pale one, of the imagination’s delight which is Eternity. As such it lies
at the heart of the dilemma of mortality—the unavoidable need to surrender to that which in Eternity is
horrific because in corporeality it is a staff of life to the soul.</p>
        <p>In few instances indeed does Blake’s pictorial imagery more succinctly delineate this quandary
than in “Comus with the Lady Spellbound” for <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> (illus. 12). The patterns on the chair to
which the enchanted Lady is riveted are unique adaptations of the serpent-bound Ahriman, with and without
wings. The two wingless figures decorating the legs of the chair and the winged one on its back are women, not
girls, as their full breasts indicate. Unlike the Lady, whose hands fold protectively across her breasts, the
winged, serpent-coiled female’s arms are raised, perhaps suggesting her openness to experience, as in plate
99 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> The sinuous coils of the serpents are rigidly circumscribed by the moldings
of the chair, a potently compressed metaphor of the Lady’s condition as she confronts the problem of
successfully negotiating her way from childhood to a womanhood which includes wholesome sexuality. The
nightmare enchantment, the phallic threatening Comus, and the serpent-dominated females who are further
imprisoned in the frame represent the Lady’s own spiritual state as she approaches and resists adult
sexuality. The
<figure n="but527.1.5.wc" id="but527.1.wc.05" work-copy="but527.1" rend="db" width="821" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
	<head>12 Comus with the Lady Spellbound at the Banquet.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy the Huntington Library, San Marino, Calif.</figDesc>
</figure>
tension between living, flowing line and the inanimate, geometric one underscores the virgin’s perplexity:
budding desire hemmed in, repressed, and thus distorted by her mingled fear and shame. The bestialized serpent
coils belong within the rigid, wooden frame, for together they symbolize obverse sides of a fundamental
process, the impulse-repression mechanism of her mind. Once the Lady can forgive and accept her own
sensuality, she will transcend the entrapping process and no longer see sex as bestial. The wings and uplifted
arms of one of the females suggest that she shall succeed.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> And she does, as Irene Tayler so cogently argues in “Say First! What
Mov’d Blake? Blake’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> Designs and <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>,” [S. Curran and J. A.
Wittreich, Jr., eds., <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory</hi> (Madison, Wisconsin, 1973), pp.
233-581.</note></p>
        <p>We have examined at some length the ambiguities of the serpent, but wings too have their
paradoxical emblematic value. They may be those of the eagle who is strong enough to fly near the sun, emblem
of the life of the imagination which is Eternity; or those of the bat, symbol of the long night of the soul
and dormancy of the imagination. But both are after all wings, where withal for passage from one point or
state to another, image of the capability during the season of mortal existence of transforming consciousness
into either the divinely human state of Man that approaches eternal bliss or the sub-human, visionless state
of misery that Blake called Satan. So consistently did Blake use the bat-like dragon wings of his Tornado
engraving that they constitute a visual code for destructive fallenness or demonic vision. With a few
exceptions (like the early, ironic use of the emblem in some copies of <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, plate 10,
where a devil-liberator attempts
<pb id="p11-82" n="82"/>
to instruct the human from the bible of Hell) the bat wings signify vision so narrow as to constitute evil,
the hindrance of life. In plate 11 of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>; plate 19 of <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The
Gates of Paradise</hi>, added after 1815, when <hi rend="i">For the Children</hi> was enlarged and renamed,
according to Erdman (<hi rend="i">Poetry and Prose</hi>, p. 734); in several illustrations for the 
<hi rend="i">Divine Comedy; Job</hi> engravings and paintings, and “Sullen Moloch” for <hi rend="i">On the Morning
of Christ’s Nativity</hi>, we have instances of the adaptation from Fuseli of Ahriman’s demon wings to
Blake’s own symbolic cosmos.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi><hi rend="i"> The Illuminated Blake</hi>, pp. 169, 279; Albert S. Roe, 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations to the Divine Comedy</hi> (Princeton, 1953); Damon, <hi rend="i">Blake’s
Job.</hi> “Sullen Moloch” is reproduced in Ruthven Todd’s <hi rend="i">William Blake The Artist</hi>
(London, 1971).</note></p>
        <p>I wish to call attention briefly to three last motives from Zoroastrian and Mithraic statuary and
bas-reliefs which may have influenced Blake’s illuminations of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> The first we
have already examined in the reproduction from Hyde’s <hi rend="i">Historica</hi> (illus. 1), but as I
pointed out, tauroctones were frequently unearthed in, and even brought to, England during the eighteenth and
nineteenth centuries. The bull slaying, sacred to Zoroaster and Mithras, is analogous to plates 25, 69, and 85
of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> Of
course, Blake’s symbolism stresses the cruelty and dubious value of the living sacrifice. The second
feature, noticed originally by Anthony Blunt, is the near mirroring in what he calls Blake’s “human-headed
bulls” in plate 41 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> of an engraving
<figure n="OrmazdandPriest.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="520">
	<head>13 Ormazd and the priest, engraving for <hi rend="i">A New System.</hi></head>
</figure>
from <hi rend="i">Ouseley’s Travels.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12"
type="note">12</ref> I think Erdman’s idea that they are “ox-hooved, lion-maned, man-headed unicorns” is
convincing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> Although I have not
found any source to which Blake may have had access, I have recently come across examples from Susa of the
winged bull figure, single-horned like the fabulous unicorn. In some cases such figures have even been called
sphinxes, perhaps in acknowledgement of their likeness to the human-headed offspring of Chimaera, herself part
serpent and lion. In any event, the similarity between Blake’s beasts in harness and the Persepolis reliefs
is so great that it hardly seems accidental, especially since the figure in <hi rend="i">Ouseley</hi> is also
reproduced in <hi rend="i">A New System</hi>, source for the final device in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> that
I wish to discuss. <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi><hi rend="i"> The Illuminated Blake</hi>, pp. 304, 348,
364. <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 22, Vol. 6, no. 2 (Fall, 1972) note by Deirdre Toomey on the states
of Plate 25.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Anthony Blunt, “Blake’s Pictorial Imagination,” <hi rend="i">Journal of
the Warburg and Courtauld Institutes</hi>, 6 (1943), 205; and <hi rend="i">The Art of William Blake</hi> (New
York, [1959]), p. 38, Plates 50a, b.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi><hi rend="i"> The Illuminated Blake</hi>, p. 320.</note></p>
        <p>The Zoroastrian god of light, Ormazd, was frequently represented on temples and state buildings in
“basso relievos,” and copies of them were available in travel accounts and books on mythology. Illustration 13
is taken from an 1807 edition of the second volume of <hi rend="i">A New System.</hi> Because of Blake’s
relationship to Bryant, it is one quite important example of the readily accessible reproductions of Ormazd.
In addition to the staple elements, such as the sun and fire altar, we see here the priest and Ormazd looking
amazingly like in features and
<pb id="p11-83" n="83"/>
<figure n="Ormazd.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="431" height="400">
	<head>14 Enlarged engravings of Ormazd, <hi rend="i">A New System.</hi></head>
</figure>
<figure n="PalaceDoorway.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="485" height="1000">
	<head>15 The Palace Doorway of Darius the Great, Persepolis.</head>
	<figDesc>Alinari MW207.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p11-84" n="84"/>
clothing (Bryant, II, plate XI). The god floats above his priest in clouds which fan out to either side; he
holds a circlet or ring which is symbolic of the sun, the universe, and his eternal realm beyond this life.
Scroll- or ribbon-like streamers unfold beneath the clouds to either side of the rather ragged skirt of the
god’s gown. There are more accurate engravings of this motive in the same volume. A stylized drawing of the
god’s wings (left, illus. 14) also contains the traditional curving, serpentine appendages below (Bryant,
II, plate VIII). The line engraving to the right is a fine reproduction of a portion of the ruins at
Persepolis, taken from a travel account as is its fellow. Eagle-like wings, the god’s perched hat, the
symbolic ring, and—most notably—the circle or cincture, which encloses the god’s waist, with its curving
lower arms or appendages, are faithfully copied as we can see by comparing the engravings to two photographs
of the ruins. The first is the palace doorway of Darius the Great (illus. 15); the second is an earlier,
better preserved example from the same ruin (enlarged detail, illus. 16).</p>
        <p>I particularly wish to call attention, again, to the cincture about the waist of Ormazd and its two
swirling appendages, for there is a precise analogue to this structure in plate 100 of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> I believe Ruthven Todd was the first to notice that the serpent temple, in front of
which we see Los or Urthone, his Spectre and Emanation (illus. 17), is quite similar to a drawing of a Druid
temple at Averbury, reproduced (or “reconstructed”) in Stukeley’s <hi rend="i">Abury, A British Druid
Temple</hi> (1743).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> Surely it is
also clear that we have here another direct influence, for Blake’s serpent temple is exactly like Ormazd’s
serpentine girdle, as it is shown in Bryant and in the photographs of the ruins of Persepolis. 
<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Ruthven Todd, <hi rend="i">Tracks in the Snow</hi> (London, 1946), pp. 31
ff.</note></p>
        <p>Analogues can be vexing, for once they have been produced they sometimes seem little more than
curiosities. With Blake, however, it is usually true that they are integral both to his aesthetics and to the
practice of his own art, because of his interpretations of the artist, be he poet or painter, and of human
nature, which he believed to be a miracle of infinite variety founded on primal, universal patterns and
processes. Thus, as we know, it was his conviction that the truth and beauty the artist creates are in a very
real sense “discovered.” For they represent that rare state of grace in which the artist is in touch with the
source of his own being, which is itself a reflection of the soul of the Eternal Man who is the cosmos. And
thus whatever an <corr type="emend">artist</corr> produces can be and almost always has been discovered by
others before him, with a greater or lesser accuracy and fullness depending upon the freedom from fetters of
individual poetic genius and the sureness of individual craft. The existence, for example, of the coincidences
we have discussed would only prove to Blake that his beliefs about art, vision and human nature are right. It
is accurate though tautological to observe that for him the abundance of correspondences of ideas and visual
forms in art and architecture <hi rend="i">demands</hi> his theory of poetic genius as a guide to Truth 
(<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, plate 11), which in turn sensitizes one to perceive still more of these fortunate
affinities: Ahriman’s and Tornado’s wings and those of the Elohim and Raphael, of Satan and Moloch;
Ahriman’s serpent coiling, awesome symbol of the power and terror of corporeality and touch, and the falling
soul’s taking on a body or Adam and the Lady emerging; the mistaken attempts at a <hi rend="i">natural</hi>
renovation of the world through the bull slaying, the Druids’ human sacrifices, and the sacrifice of Albion
in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 25; Ahura Mazda’s fiery serpentine girdle, Abury’s Druid temple, and
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s serpent temple—these must have been to Blake a wondrous concordance, proof
of the sublime unity and universality of genuine myth or vision, the golden string threaded mercifully through
the labyrinth.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p11-85" n="85"/>
      <figure n="Persepolis.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="609">
        <head>16 Enlargment of Ormazd, Persepolis.</head>
      </figure>
      <figure n="jerusalem.e.p100" id="jerusalem.e.illbk.100" work-copy="jerusalem.e" rend="db" width="958" height="653">
	<figTranscr>100</figTranscr>
        <head>17 <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 100.</head>
        <figDesc>From the collection of Mr. and Mrs. Paul Mellon.</figDesc>
      </figure>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
