<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>11.2.farwell</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">More Than Music Composed After Blake by Arthur Farwell</title>
        <author n="Farwell">Brice Farwell</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1977</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1977</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">11.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>[Contributors]</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <name>Raymond Deck</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Brice Farwell</name>
              <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
              <name>Katharyn R. Gabriella</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Mary V. Jackson</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Judith Ott</name>
              <name>Claude Marie Senninger</name>
              <name>Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr.</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1977"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_11">
    <body>
      <pb id="p11-86" n="86"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-11-2-0003">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">MORE THAN MUSIC COMPOSED AFTER BLAKE BY ARTHUR FARWELL</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>BRICE <name>FARWELL</name></docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>“Blake is right, ‘One thought fills immensity,’” wrote composer Arthur Farwell in the 1940s
about the power of Blake’s imagery and intuitive quest for “unlimited mental expansion.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n0" type="note">*</ref>
Farwell is another composer who
contributed to the music on Blake’s verse, but he did not stop there. He was influenced not only by the
lyrical and beautiful (the strong symbolic and philosophical inventiveness of Blake’s expression) but was
also intensely interested in Blake’s creative processes and in what Blake told about them. Like Blake,
Farwell recorded an inner consciousness of his own that was possessed with vivid intuitive images, not only of
musical ideas but also of both spontaneous and consciously-induced flashes of pictorial or visionary insight,
which he was able to illustrate in a somewhat Blakean fashion decades later.</p>
		<note id="n0">* Acknowledgement is due my sister Beatrice Farwell for originally suggesting the form 
of this communication and for a critical editorial review of later drafts.
<p><corr type="emend">For further information about Farwell’s music or writings, <hi rend="i">a Guide to the Music
of Arthur Farwell and to the Microfilm Collection of His Work,</hi> 1972, is available at music libraries or
from the publisher, Brice Farwell, 5 Deer Trail, Briarcliff Manor, New York 10510. In the present essay,
numbers in parentheses following opus numbers refer to their arrangement in the <hi rend="i">Guide.</hi> In
1975 the entire lifework archive was micropublished. Several major music libraries have acquired the
collection; for information, address Brice Farwell as above.</corr></p></note>
        <p>The intuitive process, in Blake, in others and in his own experience, became an object of lifelong
study by the composer, my father (trained in electrical engineering, B.S.E.E., M.I.T., 1893) before he
embarked on his musical <corr type="emend">career.</corr> In his investigations he sought to objectify the
role of intuitive phenomena in his own life and to understand the psychological principles in the general
operation of intuition. He developed his work into a practical discipline whereby one might achieve
purposeful, directed expansion of consciousness for artistic creation.</p>
        <p>In his record of the results of these studies, entitled in manuscript <hi rend="i">Intuition in the
World-Making</hi>, Farwell explores the insights of numerous creative giants in the history of art, science
and thought. Of Blake he concludes, “In the history and on the stage of intuition in art, Blake is surely the
protagonist”; the thrust of this interpretation of Blake is presented in excerpts following this article.</p>
        <p>We may presume Arthur Farwell’s musical treatment of Blake’s verse to be among many unpublished
or unsung Blake settings which no doubt exist. It is not surprising that they did not appear in the article on
and checklist of musical settings of Blake’s poetry by Peter Roberts (<hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> 28,
Spring 1974). There is no more reason for Peter Roberts, or anyone, to know Farwell’s Blake music today than
for anyone beyond a small circle to have known of Blake the artist before Gilchrist’s 
<corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">Pictor-Ignotus</hi></corr> in 1863. Upon Roberts’ invitation for assistance from readers, we
introduce below five Blake poems Arthur Farwell set into song.</p>
        <p>Farwell, 1872-1952, was a composer better known for his music on American Indian themes than for
his Blake settings, and for his efforts on behalf of his colleagues in the early part of this century (see the
recent re-issue in 5 volumes of his music and writings from the Wa-Wan Press, edited by Vera B. Lawrence and
published by Arno Press in 1970). In order of their composition, his Blake works are settings of 
<hi rend="i">Love’s Secret, The Wild Flower’s Song, The Lamb</hi>, a version of <hi rend="i">A Cradle
Song</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Tyger</hi>, the first of which was published by the Wa-Wan Press in 1903. The
next Blake poem was not set until after World War I.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">The Lamb, The Tyger</hi>, and <hi rend="i">A Cradle Song</hi> were done in the early
1930s, when Farwell was beginning to draft his notes for the text on intuition. <hi rend="i">The Tyger</hi>
exists only in manuscript, but the other two were published in a curiously Blakean fashion by the composer
himself, who learned offset lithography for the purpose, drew the music and title designs on tracing paper,
hand coated and exposed the zinc
<pb id="p11-87" n="87"/>
<figure n="Farwell.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="771" height="1000">
	<head>Blake songs in hand-made editions announced by the composer.</head>
	<figDesc>In explaining the venture, Farwell said (on verso), “The present is, generally, a time of
mass-thought and mass-action. However desirable or necessary this may be in certain fields, it is nevertheless
directly against the spirit of art, which must remain a matter peculiarly individual.”</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p11-88" n="88"/>
plates and operated the press himself. (A photo of him engaged in this activity, shown here, is reproduced in
Percy Scholes’ <hi rend="i">Oxford Companion to Music.</hi>) Editions and distribution of the settings were
naturally quite limited. Proper bibliographic references are as follows:
<q>
Op. 14 (25): No. 2.—(1) <hi rend="i">Love’s Secret</hi>, 1903, published by Wa-Wan Press, Newton Center,
Mass., 1903.<lb/>
<lb/>
Op. 54 (74): <hi rend="i">Three Songs for Medium Voice</hi>: No. 2. <hi rend="i">The Wild Flower’s
Song</hi>, 1919, published by John Church, New York, 1920.<lb/>
<lb/>
Op. 88 (114): Two Songs on Poems by William Blake, for medium voice and piano: No. 1. <hi rend="i">The
Lamb</hi>, 1930, published privately, East Lansing, Mich., 1935.<lb/>
No. 2. <hi rend="i">A Cradle Song</hi>, 1930, published privately, East Lansing, Mich., 1935.<lb/>
<lb/>
Op. 98 (128): <hi rend="i">The Tyger</hi>, for medium voice and piano, 1934, ms. only.
</q></p>
        <p>From the earliest setting the music is sensitive to the color, form, mood and meaning of Blake’s
poetry: <hi rend="i">The Lamb</hi> is simple and lyrical, <hi rend="i">The Tyger</hi> is quite stormy, and 
<hi rend="i">A Cradle Song</hi> has characteristics of both. The harmonic characteristics of all three are
romantic and somewhat “modern” but not avant-garde for the 1930s. These and the early <hi rend="i">Love’s
Secret</hi> were heard on 3 March 1976 in a musical program at the conference on “Blake in the Art of His
Time,” sponsored by the Departments of Art and English at the University of California at Santa Barbara. Local
reviewer Richard Ames considered the Farwell songs the “most subtle settings of the evening.” Another piece,
without text, composed at about the same time, also printed at Farwell’s hand press at East Lansing, was
inspired by Blake’s visionary mythology: Op. 91 (116), <hi rend="i">Vale of Enitharmon</hi>, piano, 1930,
published 1935.</p>
        <p>Like Blake, Farwell was practically as well as philosophically anti-establishment, which is seen as
one motif in his hand-crafted do-it-yourself publishing venture. His choice and treatment of these selections
was styled more to seek a working response from devoted amateurs than to serve a virtuoso elite. And, like the
poet, he also sought symbolic meanings. He introduced these publications with examples from <hi rend="i">Songs
of Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">Experience.</hi> In his own way, Farwell may have borrowed an aspect of
Blake’s symbolic concepts to subtly represent his own sense of an eternal and revolutionary rejuvenation
(akin to what he had found deeply in Boehme) in Blake’s mythology and prophecy. Something vital, human and
universal governed the function of music for Farwell and colored his musical expression of his inner
vision.</p>
        <p>He had been driven in this quest since his early student days when he began to experience visionary
phenomena, later recorded in drawings (the Blakean influence of which is suggested in the accompanying
illustrations). He had also been a very public man in the first half of his musical career and quite a fighter
for the independence of American music. As a music student he immersed himself in the romantic, bohemian ideas
of his day, having spent two years in Europe under Humperdinck, Pfitzner and Guilmant. In the Wa-Wan venture
he travelled the country, lecturing with the aid of a piano, and energetically organizing music clubs. Coming
to New York in 1909, he joined the editorial staff of <hi rend="i">Musical America</hi> and became Supervisor
of Municipal Concerts. He wrote numerous civic pageants and masques, including “Caliban” for the Shakespeare
Tercentenary, with Percy MacKaye. During World War I he was a leader in the community singing movement.</p>
        <p>When he went west in 1918 with the beginnings of a family, he left behind much of his public life.
He turned to formal teaching, at Berkeley and at Pasadena, and later at East Lansing, where he taught
composition at Michigan State until his retirement in 1939. Although he continued with further interpretations
of Indian themes into the 1940s, by the California years he had turned substantially toward his own musical
ideas, trying to create an identifiably American music. He remained deliberately and constitutionally opposed
to the zeitgeist of his day. Some of his work received public performance, such as the orchestral 
<hi rend="i">Symbolistic Study No. 3</hi> Op. 18 (68), on Walt Whitman’s “Once I passed through a populous city”
and the <hi rend="i">Gods of the Mountain</hi> suite, Op. 52 (68). His <hi rend="i">Symbolistic Study No. 6,
Mountain Vision</hi>, Op. 37 (52), earned a national broadcast in a 1939 competition, the year he retired to
New York City. During the 1940s his most advanced American Indian works were heard in the concert repertoire
of pianist John Kirkpatrick and the <hi rend="i">a capella</hi> choral tours of the Westminster Choir
School.</p>
        <p>Musicians today, beginning to examine the compositions of Farwell’s later years, are finding of
interest works which are said to show inventive musical experimentation and growth. Though these works are
still only in manuscript (except for the few works of his hand-press venture) several posthumous premieres in
the last three years have introduced his <hi rend="i">Piano Sonata</hi>, Op. 113 (161), <hi rend="i">Sonata
for ‘Cello and Piano</hi>, Op. 116 (163), <hi rend="i">Quintet in E</hi>
        <pb id="p11-89" n="89"/>
        <figure n="CoverDesign.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="802" height="1000">
        	<head>Cover design, in red and black, for two Blake songs, the first issue of Arthur Farwell’s hand
press.</head>
        	<figDesc>The cover for his Blake-inspired piano work <hi rend="i">Vale of Enitharmon</hi> (see ff.
pp.) was illustrated with an angelic figure, vignetted in radiant color, reproduced from an original drawing
by Irish poet George Russell (A.E.), given to Farwell at an earlier time.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p11-90-91" n="90-91"/>
        <figure n="SpiritSketch.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="715" height="1000">
        	<head>Page 91<gap type="emend" rend="plain"/>: sketch in pencil and crayon of “Spirit refusing to
reincarnate in such a body,” given to Arthur Farwell about 1903.</head>
        	<figDesc>According to a note in Farwell’s hand on the back of the drawing, it was given to him by
Charles Johnston, who told him it was by the poet A.E. But when A.E. paid a visit to Farwell in 1938, “He
couldn’t remember, said it could be either by him or Jack Yeats.”</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p11-92" n="92"/>
        <figure n="EnitharmonCover.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="766" height="1000">
        	<head>Page 92: cover for <hi rend="i">Vale of Enitharmon</hi>, using the sketch.</head>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p11-93" n="93"/>
        <figure n="EnitharmonPage1.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="763" height="1000">
        	<head>Page 93: first page of <hi rend="i">Vale of Enitharmon</hi>, 1935.</head>
        	<figDesc>On the back of this page is the following explanation:</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <figure n="EnitharmonNote.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="496">
        	<figTranscr>“Vale of Enitharmon” is the fourth of <lb/>
        	my works to be lithographed by me <lb/>
        	on my own press at East Lansing, <lb/>
        	Michigan. The music pages and title <lb/>
        	lettering have been hand-drawn by <lb/>
        	myself. The figure on the title is from <lb/>
        	a sketch by “A. E.” (George Russell) in <lb/>
        	my possession. <lb/>
        	<lb/>
        	Enitharmon, in the unique mythology <lb/>
        	of William Blake, has been interpreted, <lb/>
        	in one phase, as Spiritual Beauty. <lb/>
        	<lb/>
        	Arthur Farwell</figTranscr>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p11-94" n="94"/>
        <figure n="TheLamb.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="773" height="1000">
        	<head>Pages 94-95: <hi rend="i">The Lamb</hi>, first publication of Arthur Farwell’s hand
press.</head>
        	<figDesc>For uniformity he hand-whittled a cherrywood stamp for the note heads, which he applied on
tracing paper using an india-ink stamp pad. Note stems were made with a draftsman’s ruling pen.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p11-95" n="95"/>
        <figure n="TheLamb2.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="779" height="1000"/>
        <pb id="p11-96" n="96"/>
        <figure n="CradleSong.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="761" height="1000"/>
        <pb id="p11-97" n="97"/>
        <figure n="TheTyger.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="741" height="1000">
        	<head>Pages 96-97: Farwell’s music hand, as shown on a manuscript page of <hi rend="i">The
Tyger</hi>, compared with his hand-copied opening page of the published version of <hi rend="i">A Cradle
Song.</hi></head>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p11-98" n="98"/>
        <hi rend="i">Minor</hi>, piano and strings, Op. 103 (136) and <hi rend="i">What’s In an Octave?</hi>
Op. 84 (111) for piano. Perhaps his most characteristic works have been his many settings of poems by Emily
Dickinson, another individualist and spirited American mystic. These were written from the time of the later
Blake settings on through the 1940s and until the end of his life. Farwell worked at the manuscript of his
study of intuition and the illustrations of his visionary experience throughout this period. He published
several articles on his views of intuition and gave lectures illustrated with slides of his drawings (like
those here reproduced) along with some done in water colors.</p>
        <p>Farwell asserts that any individual can bring the infinite resources of his own intuitive faculty
to bear on any problem, if he will learn meditatively to let the force of universal principles flow and work.
From fleeting hunches to visions of “cosmic import,” a whole spectrum of inner experience lies along the axis
from the particular to the universal. In art, Farwell perceived Blake’s visionary experiences to fully
embody this process in which Blake “set forth his symbolic dreams in their entirety, just as they came to
him.” Farwell held that in this portion of Blake’s work the direct recording of visionary symbolism
accounted for much of what he termed the “unique and problematic place Blake has so long held in the world of
art.” Farwell was of course unaware of the recent scholarship that has shown Blake’s graphic work to be
readily understandable in the context of other work in his time. But at any rate Farwell was more interested
in the working of Blake’s creative mind and its influence on the larger meaning of the work than in
particulars per se.</p>
        <p>The captioned illustrations in these pages suggest a Blakean influence on several levels in
Farwell’s work, which exemplify an awareness of craft, a naive artistic style and some analogue of universal
intuition furnished in part by his exposure to the inspiration of Blake. Arthur Farwell’s contributions have
not as yet found a Gilchrist; they may never. Though his name is listed in the musical encyclopedias, most of
his works lay undisturbed until his seven children<gap type="emend"/>
were able to find ways to make them accessible beginning in 1972, his centennial year.</p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">ARTHUR FARWELL ON BLAKE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Excerpted from his book manuscript <hi rend="i">Intuition in the World-Making</hi>, drafted over
the years from about 1933 through 1948 and illustrated by the author with his sketches of symbolic images from
his inner experiences, Arthur Farwell dwells on the meaning of Blake’s inner experiences for Blake’s
art.</p>
          <p>Each chapter, broadly titled as shown in these pages, is given an analytical list of contents.
For Chapter Six, containing Farwell’s principal examination of Blake and entitled <hi rend="i">Artistic
Inspiration as Intuition</hi>, these topics are:
<q>
Relation of the artistic to the spiritual. Example of musical intuition. Richard Strauss’ testimony.
Schubert’s phenomenal intuition. Composition in hypontic state. Composition in semi-trance. Unconscious
practice of “consciously induced” intuition. Asking the “infinite” for musical themes. Application of Criteria
and Law. Wagner’s striking testimony. Transference of artistic intuitive power to life-problems. Artists’
lack of understanding of intuition. Testimony of writers. Identity of principle of intuition in all fields,
including the spiritual. Testimony of painters. Blake’s singular position. Vision as abstract art. Vision
vs. dream in painting. Relation of conscious and subconscious minds to imagination. Artistic functioning as
field for psychological study. Man’s four basic faculties. Intuition and “inspiration.” Genius.
Despiritualization of art. A new artistic teaching. Potential height of subconscious response.
</q>
Farwell’s development of Blake’s “singular position” is excerpted below, slightly condensed, following
these brief opening words in his Introduction, given here to set the author’s tone and perspective.
<q>
This book, on its first level, is a direct and unqualified account of the experience of myself and others with
intuition, and, on my own part, with its conscious control and use. As such, it is a recital of adventure and
observation in a region of perception beyond that of reason, though not without a recognition of the organic
relation of that region to the total human consciousness, in which reason plays its proper part.<lb/>
<lb/>
On its second level it presents a formulation of certain principles and laws of intuition and its use, and a
record of thoughts, conclusions and outlooks born of this adventure and observation. On its third level it
pictures the result upon human life, the larger meanings for the individual and the race, of the full
development and use of the intuitive faculty.<lb/>
<lb/>
The present work in no way seeks to alter or oppose the current general idea of what
<pb id="p11-99" n="99"/>
<figure n="FarwellTOC.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="848">
	<head>Title and Table of Contents of Arthur Farwell’s discourse on his investigation of intuition.</head>
	<figDesc>Farwell went on to examine this process, tame it, reduce it to practice and study its context and
range of meaning in human experience. Farwell illustrated his treatise with his hand sketches from memory of
both his spontaneous visionary experiences and also with some of those he consciously induced. He turned to
Blake as a key example of intuition and vision in art; he concluded the study by picturing, narrating and
interpreting a vision-like experience which he likens to Blake’s visions. Two of his sketches for this
example are shown here.</figDesc>
</figure>
intuition is. But this idea is so . . . narrow and limited . . . that it has become outworn as an aid to the
further development of this faculty, with its limitless latent powers of illumination . . . and of creative
inspiration. . . . This popular attitude is further devoid of any sense of the spiritual and cosmic
implications of the intuitive faculty, and of its immense significance for the future, in human evolution. . .
.<lb/>
<lb/>
Intuition, then, will embrace the commonly understood idea of intuition (inclusive of what is popularly known
as the “hunch”), the artistic, scientific, philosophical or spiritual inspiration, in fact all creative
revelation in any sphere, the symbolic dream, the vision, and other related subconscious phenomena of a
revelatory nature, and all of these reason-transcending illuminations as experienced both in their
spontaneous, unexpected manner, and also as the result of the conscious and purposeful inducing of them. The
name of none of these so different appearing phenomena, other than “intuition” itself, may suitably be used to
include them all.<lb/>
<lb/>
The present work aims to make progress in laying the foundations of a Science of Intuition.
</q></p>
          <p>Leaping from here into the framework of his Chapter Six, as given above, we read of Blake in
Arthur Farwell’s thought thus:
<q>
William Blake’s is the name most usually brought forward in connection with the idea of artistic inspiration
as intuition, but without the bearing which I shall indicate. His pictorial work, along the line of cleavage
which I am considering, divides itself into two classes: one being the work in which he exercised his creative
capacities in the usual manner of artist, whether or not intuition played a part; the other being that in
which he set forth his symbolic dreams and vision in their entirety, exactly as they came to him, with nothing
added from his conscious mind. . . .<lb/>
<lb/>
In the extensive portion of Blake’s art which is a direct and exclusive presentation of that which the
subconscious mind puts forth, he was more completely a medium of intuitive revelations than were the other
artists mentioned
<pb id="p11-100" n="100"/>
here. Pure intuition is pure truth, clearly revealing itself and readily graspable as such, when not sullied
or distorted by . . . the darkness and error to which the objective mind is all too susceptible. Its immediate
expression in artistic terms, with no such interferences . . . introduced, will reflect that truth in equal
purity. The result of this cosmically involved act of the direct revelation of truth [is] a picture of most
decisive outline, authoritative, absolutely irrefutable, and commanding acceptance. And it is precisely these
qualities that mark the character of Blake’s genuine vision pictures. Blake, quite naturally, is not always
at this height.<lb/>
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
<lb/>
It is this giving straight out of his intuitive visions as they came to him, instead of merely availing
himself of the aid of occasional intuitions in the execution of a consciously conceived picture, that accounts
for the unique and problematical place which Blake has so long held, and still holds [1948], in the world of
art. The many works in which he has followed this course do not appear to reveal a man’s conscious devising
faculties at play, but rather a superhuman power, as from without, working through the artist’s hand. Of
these Blake writes, “And though I call them mine, I know they are not mine.”<lb/>
<lb/>
Two of the six somewhat Blake-inspired drawings by the composer illustrating his narration, recorded and drawn
in the 1930s from his memory of an experience in the night of 28 December 1905, which he interpreted at length
in the final chapter of his book ms. on intuition; “‘The Vision of The Great City,’ in its most general
sense, is a picture of regeneration and reconstruction in its widest human bearings. It is revealed in a
five-fold cycle—the end of a certain phase of consciousness with its attendant human order, cataclysm and
change, ascent to a higher level, passage through darkness leading to mystical experience, and establishment
of a new human order on a higher ground. With the momentary exclusion [1948 writing] of the more obscure
fourth phase, it will, I believe, be generally admitted that these are, or contain, issues of first importance
to the world today. They are certainly vastly more to the fore now than they were at the time the vision
occured.” Farwell’s use and illustrations of this experience are a personal example of the sort of occurence
he ascribes to Blake in regard to Blake’s more visionary art.
<pb id="p11-101" n="101"/>
<figure n="HumanityStandstill.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="740">
	<head><hi rend="i">Humanity at a Standstill</hi>—Opening scene in Farwell’s 1905 “Vision of the Great
City.”</head>
	<figDesc>“ . . . stood an immense multitude of people, waiting, with dread . . . An age had ended,
civilisation collapsed—everything had stopped. Mankind, with its dream—at last—thwarted—beaten.
Something must happen, and happen quickly, or the race itself would be at an end.”</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p11-102" n="102"/>
          <figure n="Cataclysm.11.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="742">
            <head><hi rend="i">Cataclysm</hi>—The second vista in Farwell’s “Vision of The Great
City.”</head>
            <figDesc>In the picture the figures in the foreground he said were himself and “one who was my
mother.” “It was a period of upheaval and dire events. Occupations had been swept away, and the people
thronged the hills. . . . Suddenly there came a great earthquake . . . I and those around me were hurled
helplessly about.” After a quiet, “Again a mighty earthquake shook and split the earth . . . until in the
midst of the convulsions the hills gave way and sank, and mountains rose up from the low 
places.<supplied type="emend">”</supplied></figDesc>
          </figure>
<pb id="p11-103" n="103"/>
This is to me the <hi rend="i">real</hi> abstract art, as conveying human and cosmic meanings which seldom
appear in the art of the day bearing that designation. While we shall probably never do without pictorial art
produced in the usual manner, . . . [yet] “without a vision the people perish” is a truth for tomorrow as well
as for yesterday. A function hitherto observed chiefly in spiritual seers may very possibly appear and find
increasing activity in the sphere of pictorial art. So much did his visions mean to Blake, that when they
failed to appear he went to his knees and prayed for them, a quite sufficient testimony to the spiritual
character of the man. . . .<lb/>
In the exercise of imagination without the intuitive possibility, I would merely be fishing around for images
in a mind of which I ought to be thoroughly tired. But in the request for intuitive revelations I would be
offering myself as a candidate for unlimited mental expansion. Blake was evidently continually tired of what
he knew his conscious mind to contain, and so was frequently praying for more visions. The continuous
revelation of continually new images of truth is undoubtedly what he justifiably thought of and so greatly
exalted as “imagination,” and not the former limited and wearying procedure. Hence the amazing divergence and
variety of his designs. . . . Blake is right, “One thought fills immensity.” . . .<lb/>
<lb/>
. . . Certain . . . famous painters . . . have had virtually only one pictorial idea or image in their heads.
. . . They appear to have spent the best part of their lives seeking to paint this image continually better .
. . . We doubtless have some of our most perfect specimens of art from such. . . . Blake’s mind, on the
other hand, was in this respect a <hi rend="i">tabula rasa</hi>, ready for the impress of any sort of image
whatsoever, of any aspect of the universal diversity. . . . The major attitude and trend, indeed the prayerful
urge, of his mind was . . . toward universal imagination—necessarily something beyond his conscious
conceptive power. Images from such a super-personal sphere can be communicated to the individual in no other
way than through intuition. What comes through intuition <hi rend="i">lives.</hi> Thus Blake’s art has
remained vital, in essential respects “modern,” and even prophetic, for a century and a half. In the history,
and on the stage, of intuition in art, Blake is surely the protagonist.
</q></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
