<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>11.3.walker</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Raymond Lister, Infernal Methods: A Study of William Blake’s Art
Technique</title>
        <author n="Walker">Corlette Walker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1977-1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1977-1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">11.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Michael Hays</name>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>W. J. T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>Edward J. Rose</name>
              <name>Corlette Walker</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_11">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-11-3-0006">
        <pb id="p11-203" n="203"/>
        <div2>
          <figure n="ListerCover.11.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="441"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Raymond Lister. <hi rend="b">Infernal Methods:</hi> A Study of
                            William Blake’s Art Techniques. London: G. Bell &amp;
                            Sons, Ltd., 1975. Pp. 102, illus. £8 (+ postage,
                            U.S.).</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Corlette</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Walker</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>An important development in Blake scholarship in recent years has been the
                        attention paid to the influence of Blake’s techniques as an
                        engraver and as a painter on his art. Raymond Lister’s <hi rend="i">Infernal
Methods: A Study of William Blake’s Art
                            Techniques</hi> comes at the right moment to supply the necessary
                        synthesis of these studies. Mr. Lister is a British art historian who has
                        specialized in the Romantic period in Britain with particular emphasis on
                        engraving and etching. In the introduction to this book he states that he is
                        concentrating on Blake’s craftsmanship and avoiding discussion of
                        “subjects such as the symbolism of Blake’s colors . . .
                        the gestures and stances of his figures, of the relevance of his designs to
                        his ideas of contraries, and so on, deeming it of greater importance in the
                        present context to dwell on <hi rend="i">how</hi> rather than on 
<hi rend="i">why.</hi>” Mr. Lister’s motives in making
                        this statement become more obvious as he describes many of
                        Blake’s techniques and admits that there is no general agreement
                        on exactly how they were done. Some of the controversies are relatively
                        minor, such as the problem of whether Blake varnished his watercolors or
                        not, but some others, for example his creation of relief etching, are
                        crucial to the <hi rend="i">why</hi> of his art. Indeed Mr. Lister does not
                        avoid analyzing the effect of the techniques which Blake chose on his
                        style—such as the influence of the firm wiry kind of engraving he
                        learned from Basire on his conception of the “bounding
                        line.” By and large, however, with his admirable British clarity of
                        expression, Lister does restrict himself to factual discussions of
                        Blake’s engraving and painting. And in truth it is exactly this
                        kind of dispassionate analysis that is needed more than ever in the present
                        climate of Blake scholarship. His discussion of Blake’s engraving
                        describes not only the techniques themselves but also their use from the
                        seventeenth century onward. He compares Blake’s techniques to
                        those of his contemporaries, Flaxman and Fuseli, and analyzes the effects of
                        the new engraving techniques of the late eighteenth century.</p>
          <p>Since engraving was Blake’s profession, Lister, like most other
                        writers on Blake’s techniques, assumes that Blake was more than
                        just conversant with the different techniques of wood engraving, aquatint
                        and so on, even if he did not use them very often. Lister acknowledges that
                        the same cannot be said for Blake’s painting techniques, and he
                        quotes Gilchrist’s remarks that “ . . . In an era of
                        academies, associations and combined efforts we have in him a solitary
                        self-taught and as an artist semi-taught dreamer. . . . ” Lister
                        does, however, quarrel with Gilchrist’s use of the word
                        “dreamer,” again emphasizing that a craftsman even in
                        another medium would be more of a realist in his use of different techniques
                        than the word might imply. Blake’s use of so-called
                        “fresco painting,” for example, cannot be equated with any
                        known practice exactly and can only be labeled experimental. Yet in its way,
                        as Lister points out, it is totally competent and realized.</p>
          <p>He suggests much the same conclusion in his chapter on Blake’s
                        relief etching. My only quarrel with Lister, in this respect, is that he
                        sides with Ruthven Todd, Stanley William Hayter and Joan Miro in their
                        solution to the problem of how Blake’s relief etching was really
                        achieved. He states his agreement with them without referring to other and
                        more current solutions. Even though his book was published in 1975, he does
                        not mention the ideas put forth in many of the essays in Robert
                        Essick’s collection <hi rend="i">The Visionary Hand</hi> of 1973
                        nor in the essay in the 1973 <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> by John
                        Wright, nor does he suggest that it is an area of scholarly 
                        controversy.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">1</ref>
				<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Robert Essick “Blake and the
						Traditions of Reproductive Engraving” in <hi rend="i">The
						Visionary Hand: Essays for the Study of William Blake’s
						Art and Aesthetics</hi>, edited by Robert Essick (Los Angeles:
						Hennessey &amp; Ingalls, 1973); John Wright,
						“Blake’s Relief Etching Method,<supplied type="emend">”</supplied> 
						<hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 36 (Spring 1976), pp. 94-115.</note></p>
          <p>Lister does not, in fact, digress very often from his straightforward
                        accounting of the often extremely 
                        <pb id="p11-204" n="204"/> 
                        complicated techniques of painting and printmaking of this period. Therein, in my
                        opinion, is one of the great virtues of this book. I see its almost
                        recipe-like simplicity as an antidote to the intense and subjective approach
                        of the literary scholar to Blake’s imagery. As the German art
                        historian Detlef Dörrbecker suggests in the 1977 summer issue of
                        <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> in his review of the David Bindman catalogue of
                        the Blake exhibition in Hamburg in 1975, art historians have only very
                        recently decided to deal to any great degree with the problem of form in
                        Blake. In the past with the exception of Sir Anthony Blunt and a few others,
                        literary scholars, as Dörrbecker notes, “ . . . <hi rend="i">used</hi> Blake’s
                        illuminations and paintings
                        because of their explanatory value as a kind of visual commentary or
                        complementary code for understanding his poetic creation. . . .”
                        Now he is confident that the idea that Blake’s work as an
                        engraver and painter is much more than a literal translation of his writing
                        must finally be taken seriously, and that more attention should and will be
                        paid the special visual qualities of Blake’s art. As a result the
                        new attention to form will have a salutary influence on our knowledge of the
                        iconographical content of Blake’s designs.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n36" type="note">2</ref> I am not quite so confident that the unique
                        character of Blake’s formes as separate in some respects from his
                        ideas is as generally accepted as Dörrbecker would like.
                        Certainly the recent interest in Blake’s relief etchings as a
                        problem which has many different kinds of implications is a symptom of this
                        interest. Even here, however, in the mechanical descriptions of the
                        process—where one would think that the literary scholar would be
                        held to the physical facts of the process—there are still many
                        areas of misunderstanding and ignorance. These in turn often result in
                        tortured and arcane interpretations which are fully as obscure as the most
                        complicated iconographical studies. Over and over reviewers and scholars
                        stumble on the most elementary problems without realizing the implications
                        of the use of this or that technique. Recently, in the 1977 spring issue of
                        the <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> Tom Dargan criticized J. Wittreich
                        for calling crosshatching “a net of self-hood” and for
                        implying that Blake had used it for subjective interpretive reasons and not
                        as Mr. Dargan points out “because crosshatching is the
                        engraver’s usual method of giving body to the outlined
                        figure.” At the same time, neither writer notes, in this regard,
                        Blake’s preoccupation with nets <hi rend="i">per se.</hi> Robert
                        Essick in his article “The Traditions of Reproductive
                        Engraving” of 1972<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37"
type="note">3</ref>
                        demonstrates quite plainly that the new net-like conventions of engraving
                        resulted not only in images of webs and nets in Blake’s poetry
                        but, in his designs themselves, human forms covered with nets.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">4</ref> More often Blake’s
                        experiments with techniques are treated as individual and unique
                        expressions. Because there is very little understanding of the conventions
                        and <hi rend="i">schemata</hi> which the artist used unselfconsciously,
                        Blake’s techniques are often freighted with a meaning which is
                        controversial as well as all but incomprehensible except to the initiate.
                        For example, John Wright’s conclusion on the impulses which
                        caused Blake to use relief engraving—as being “ . . .
                        the stages of process and cosmography of his sculptural plates, an analogue
                        or emblem of the layered structure of the hierarchic allegorical systems of
                        the cultural world he sought to anatomize and to represent by
                        transfiguration” is an extreme example. Could it not have been just
                        as much, as Lister, Robert Essick and others have pointed out, a part of the
                        general tendency to experiment with techniques of all kinds in the late
                        eighteenth century in England rather than a deliberately conscious synthesis
                        with poetic hierarchies? <note id="n36"><hi rend="s">2</hi> It is a curious
                            fact but literary scholars appear to find iconography more attractive
                            than the study of technique. One wonders why this is so. It may be that
                            it generally resembles literary history. Unfortunately art historical
                            methodology is as various as literary criticism, and while a literary
                            scholar would never use structuralist and Marxist methodology in the
                            same work, he often does not see that the same differences operate in
                            art history. In other words, until now, no one has as yet mastered both
                            disciplines well enough to use them both with ease.</note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Robert Essick’s article was
                            first published in <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 5 (Fall 1972),
                            59-103, and Lister does list it in his bibliography. He does not,
                            however, deal with its point of view.</note>
	<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Reproduced in <hi rend="i">The Visionary
                                Hand</hi>, p. 512, Plate 161 (<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> plate 12
                            detail of lower right corner, copy L, Huntington Library). It depicts a
                            figure caught in a net.</note></p>
          <p>Mr. Lister’s reasoned clarity, rather than intuition and
                        interpretation—no matter how brilliant—should be the
                        basis for further discussion of Blake’s technique and the
                        influence of this technique on his visual imagery. It is more important at
                        this stage to know what Blake did, how he did it, how his techniques fit
                        into the general artistic situation, than to view his formal experiments
                        solely in connection with his poetry. This may seem like heresy to some and
                        yet the best art historical work of recent years, Bo Lindberg’s
                            <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Book of
                            Job</hi>, includes a whole chapter on the techniques used and their
                        effect on the imagery of this one work alone. After all, Blake, no matter
                        how experimental and eccentric, must have assumed that his works would be
                        viewed in a certain way. His craftsmanship by itself would have had control
                        over many of the effects he attempted; they could not have been the result
                        of sudden inspiration. Lister, for example, indicates that the difference in
                        the time taken for hand coloring those plates colored by Blake and his wife
                        Catharine together and those colored by Blake alone, which took more time
                        and were done with more detail, resulted in appreciable visual
                        differences.</p>
          <p>Furthermore, rather than being the result of some poetic idea, the very
                        notion of hand coloring—of “fresco” painting,
                        of recreating tempera effects—is part and parcel of the
                        experimental British taste of the time, a taste which was often deliberately
                            anachronistic.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39"
type="note">5</ref> One can compare Sir
                        Joshua Reynolds (whom Blake despised) and his use of asphaltum to achieve
                        “Rembrandtian” effects with Blake’s techniques
                        of painting and engraving in which he wished to recreate
                        “Gothic” effects. In fact, as Thomas Hess remarked in his
                        recent review of the newly opened Yale Center for British Art,
                        “English painting is apt to be technically corrupt. The artists
                        liked eclectic mixtures of texture and illumination.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">6</ref> British artists tended also, unlike
                        their peers on the continent (whose long indoctrination into the hierarchy
                        of <hi rend="i">genres</hi> more or less restricted experimentation to the
                        separate medium), to wander from one technique to another. The English
                        desire to achieve the brightness and clarity of illumination or fresco,
                        while part of the early nineteenth century longing for the
                        “simplicity” and “purity” of the <hi rend="i">Quattrocento</hi>, took forms as
different as Samuel
                        Palmer’s use of body-color and later the “wet
                        white” ground of the Pre-Raphaelites.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n41" type="note">7</ref> In this connection Blake, rather than being outside the stream
                        of tradition as he is so often depicted in histories of painting, is at the
                        very center of what was to become the overriding preoccupation of the
                        nineteenth century artist—the concentration on
                        process—on how the work of art was made and the relationship of
                        this process to the content of the work. <note id="n39"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Duncan
MacMillan in his review of David
                                Erdman’s <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> and
                                Raymond Lister’s <hi rend="i">Infernal Methods</hi> in
                                the <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, August, 1976, points out that there
                                was another engraver, Joseph Strutt, who was interested in
                                illuminated manuscripts and “Gothic” effects at
                                the same period that Blake was also interested in these things. He
                                states: 
<q> The world of the London engraver was small, but even if
                                    no direct link can be established between Strutt and Blake, his
                                    example is important. By showing that Blake was not isolated in
                                    his enthusiasm for illuminated manuscripts does not make his use
                                    of them any less original but by making it seem less
                                    unprecedented it makes the logic of his choice of art forms
                                    apparent. </q></note>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Thomas Hess, “English Artists,
                            Warts and Halos,” <hi rend="i">New York Magazine</hi>, 29 Aug.
                            1977, p. 35.</note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Martin Hardie in his <hi rend="i">Water-colour Painting in Britain</hi>,
Vol. I., p. 15, notes
                                that “Samuel Palmer in his last period underpainted with
                                solid white producing great brilliance by the use of transparent
                                water-colours over this white surface when quite dry.”
                                Linda Nochlin in <hi rend="i">Realism and Tradition in Art
                                    1848-1900</hi> p. 106, excerpts a passage from William Holman
                                Hunt where he describes this process: 
<q> 
                                	. . . Select a prepared
                                    ground originally for its brightness and renovate it, if
                                    necessary, with fresh white when first it comes into the studio,
                                    white to be mixed with a very little amber or copal varnish. Let
                                    this last coat become of a thoroughly stone-like hardness. Upon
                                    this surface, complete with exactness the outline of the part in
                                    hand. On the morning for the painting, with fresh white (from
                                    which all superfluous oil has been extracted by means of
                                    absorbent paper and to which again a small drop of varnish has
                                    been added) spread a further coat very evenly with a palette
                                    knife over the part for the day’s work. . . .<gap type="emend"/> 
                                </q>
                                In both cases the artists are using techniques
                                usually associated with one medium in another—Palmer
                                tempera techniques with water color, Hunt fresco procedure with oil
                                paint.
                        </note></p>
          <pb id="p11-205" n="205"/> 
          <p>While it is probable that art historians and literary scholars will never
                        view Blake’s dual creative processes in exactly the same way, it
                        seems logical that such studies as Lister’s <hi rend="i">Infernal
                            Methods</hi> should be read as the first step in understanding
                        Blake’s visual imagery. It is, as I mentioned before, especially
                        useful because it does not try to be interpretive in a literary or
                        philosophical way. As literary scholars such as Robert Essick and others
                        have already realized, iconography, which is just as dense and impenetrable
                        in its way as textual analysis, may not be as useful as an initial response
                        to Blake’s imagery as the study of technique and its relationship
                        to form. To understand the medium, its norms and the experiments that Blake
                        made with these norms might enable us to take the first step toward the
                        “ . . . more than meets the eye.” It might even be the
                        essential bridge between the two areas of Blake scholarship.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
