<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>11.3.mitchell</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Robert Rosenblum, Modern Painting and the Northern Tradition: Friedrich to
Rothko</title>
        <author n="Mitchell">W. J. T. Mitchell</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1977-1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1977-1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">11.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Michael Hays</name>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>W. J. T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>Edward J. Rose</name>
              <name>Corlette Walker</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_11">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-11-3-0006">
        <pb id="p11-200" n="200"/>
        <div2>
          <figure n="RosenblumCover.11.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="403"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Robert Rosenblum. <hi rend="b">Modern Painting and the Northern
                                Romantic Tradition:</hi> Friedrich to Rothko. New York: Harper
                            &amp; Row, 1975. Pp. 240, illus. $17.50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">W. J. T.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Mitchell</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Friends and foes of Romanticism have always agreed on at least one thing: the
                        importance of a displaced, sublimated, or (to use T. E. Hulme’s
                        word) “spilt” religious sensibility as a quality of
                        Romantic art. Shelley may start out as an atheist, Blake as an iconoclast,
                        Turner as a godless naturalist, but we still feel that the work of all these
                        artists is inseparable from some form of religious quest, some attempt to
                        probe ultimate mysteries. One of the most difficult problems in the
                        interpretation of Romantic art has been to clarify the precise relation
                        between secular and sacred, supernatural and natural, the infinite and
                        finite which informs the work of particular artists. An easy way out of this
                        dilemma is to divide nineteenth century art into two antithetical columns
                        labelled “sacred” and “secular,” give
                        them geographical locations (“Northern” and
                        “Southern”), and announce that you have revealed a
                        “new structure of the history of modern art”: 
						<q> The gist
                            of my ambitious argument is this: that there is an important alternate
                            reading of the history of modern art which might well supplement the
                            orthodox one that has as its almost exclusive locus Paris, from David
                            and Delacroix to Matisse and Picasso. My own reading is based . . . on
                            the impact of certain problems of modern cultural history, and most
                            particularly the religious dilemmas posed in the Romantic movement, upon
                            the combination of subject, feeling and structure shared by a long
                            tradition of artists working mainly in Northern Europe and the United
                            States. (Rosenblum, p. 7) </q>
Robert Rosenblum is too sophisticated,
                        however, to think that this claim will pass unchallenged, and he carries the
                        art of the defensive preface to new heights, anticipating all the objections
                        a reviewer might make. He apologizes for “the many subtle and
                        perhaps unsubtle historical distortions I have had to make for the sake of
                        internal logic. Perhaps the most incautious of these is my far too
                        simple-minded polarization between French and non-French art, as if all
                        French painters were concerned primarily, if not exclusively, with
                        art-for-art’s sake, and all Northern European painters with its
                        opposite extremes” (8). Rosenblum even warns us against the
                        beguiling effect of his own prestige as an art historian, and of the Slade
                        Lectures out of which this book developed, by confessing that he will be
                        “deeply distressed . . . if my own structure of what I now see as a
                        cohesive tradition in modern art were to be codified by innocent readers
                        into a fixed historical truth” (8).</p>
          <p>These caveats should be taken very seriously by all readers, innocent or not,
                        and especially by unwary Blake scholars who will be delighted to see the
                        crucial position given to Blake in Rosenblum’s “cohesive
                        tradition.” The fact is that it is neither cohesive nor a tradition
                        in any recognizably historical sense. The continuity of Northern Romantic
                        art which Rosenblum constructs is riddled with adventitious associations and
                        what Erwin Panofsky called
                        “pseudomorphoses”—“the accidental
                        appearance at different moments in the history of art of works whose close
                        formal analogies falsify the fact that their meaning is totally
                        different” (10). The Southern or “Parisian” or
                        “orthodox” tradition which provides Rosenblum with a handy
                        straw-man throughout is almost equally mysterious. <corr type="emend">Rosenblum</corr> tells us in his
                        preface that he has left the “secure foothills of facts”
                        for the “precarious summits of ideas” (7), and so he
                        evidently feels 
<pb id="p11-201" n="201"/>
no obligation to show that the
                        alleged orthodox tradition actually exists; at least we are not graced with
                        a single footnote, a passing allusion to an author or title, or any other
                        mundane fact which might tell us where to find the case for this orthodox
                        tradition presented.</p>
          <p>Our confidence in the cohesiveness of the Paris-based
                        “secular” tradition is hardly reinforced when we turn back
                        to Rosenblum’s earlier (and better) <hi rend="i">Transformations
                            in Late Eighteenth Century Art</hi> to check his assessment of the
                        founding father of this tradition, Jacques-Louis David.
                        Rosenblum’s reading of the <hi rend="i">Death of Marat</hi> is
                        filled with the purple prose which, in his newest book, is transferred to
                        the Northern Romantics: 
						<q> The somber and resonant void above the martyred
                            figure creates a supernatural aura that demands a religious silence; it
                            is the post-medieval painter’s equivalent of a gold
                            background. Similarly the Caravaggesque light emanating from a high and
                            invisible source, saturates the bloody scene with an immateriality that
						  <corr type="emend">metamorphoses</corr> the victim of a sordid bathtub murder into an icon of a new
                            religion. (<hi rend="i">Transformations</hi>, 83) </q>
How are we to
                        reconcile this reading of David with the supposedly secular, aesthetic,
                        realistic tradition that stems from him?</p>
          <p>Faced with this inconsistency, Rosenblum falls back on a secondary
                        distinction, arguing that, while a religious aura can be found in 
<hi rend="i">both</hi> Southern and Northern painting, “yet in the
                        Protestant North, far more than in the Catholic South, another kind of
                        translation from the sacred to the secular took place, one in which we feel
                        that the powers of the deity have somehow left the flesh-and-blood dramas of
                        Christian art and have penetrated, instead, the domain of
                        landscape” (17). The antithesis drawn here between Christian art
                        and landscape is both exaggerated (landscape had long been part of Christian
                        art) and beside the point. <hi rend="i">The Death of Marat</hi>,
                        Goya’s <hi rend="i">Third of May</hi> and Ingres’ <hi rend="i">Napoleon I on his
Imperial
                        Throne</hi>—Rosenblum’s main examples of Southern
                        religious art—are not examples of the “flesh-and-blood
                        drama of Christian art”; they may echo Christian imagery but they
                        are not pieces of Christian art. If we assume that Rosenblum is claiming
                        less than he says here, and simply arguing that the distinction is between
                        Northern religious landscape and Southern religious <hi rend="i">figure</hi>
                        painting (“flesh-and-blood dramas,” Christian or
                        otherwise), the problem is not eliminated. First, he will later argue that
                        the “powers of the deity,” far from having “left
                        the flesh and blood dramas of Christian art” in Northern painting,
                        are renewed in precisely that format in the work of Blake and Runge. Second,
                        the implication that all Southern landscape tends to be secular, northern
                        religious, will be undermined countless times as the book develops.
                        Constable’s views of Salisbury Cathedral will be declared
                        “far too sunny in mood, far too picturesque in vantage point to
                        convey any transcendental message” (30), an assertion which
                        conflicts both with Rosenblum’s thesis about Northern religious
                        sentiment, and with all that we know about the actual intentions behind
                        Constable’s painting. (Constable’s religious attitudes
                        may be consulted in Basil Taylor’s <hi rend="i">Constable:
                            Paintings, Drawings, and Watercolors</hi>, London, 1973, pp. 26, 228,
                        and 221.) Certain landscapes by the southern-based Corot will be allowed to
                        have religious overtones, but they are “at the most . . . only
                        implicit,” whereas the religious dimensions of
                        Friedrich’s landscapes will be pronounced
                        “explicit” (31). Yet elsewhere Rosenblum, borrowing from
                        M. H. Abrams, will argue that the ability to implicitly present sacred
                        feelings in the apparently secular domain is a crucial feature of the
                        “natural supernaturalism” he finds in Northern
                        Romanticism, and that the abandonment of explicit and traditional Christian
                        imagery (those “flesh and blood dramas” again) is
                        precisely what his new tradition is all about.</p>
          <p>The problem, it should be evident, is that Rosenblum’s simple
                        polarities cannot hold the full range or complexity of Romantic and
                        post-Romantic painting in any clear focus, and that he is forced repeatedly
                        to shift the grounds of his distinctions in the face of overwhelming
                        counter-evidence. Turner, for instance, is continually linked with Friedrich
                        as a fellow “Northern Protestant artist,” though all the
                        evidence suggests that Turner was quite uninterested in the Friedrichian
                        brand of natural Christianity which grew up in eighteenth century Germany.
                        Contemporary accounts of Turner make it clear that he had, as Jack Lindsay
                        points out, a “total lack of interest in religion, as if it were
                        something so unimportant that he need not even indicate his blank
                        unconcern” (<hi rend="i">J. M. W. Turner—His Life and
                            Work</hi>, London, 1966, p. 35). Constable, whose “picturesque,
                        sunny” landscapes are pronounced incompatible with religious
                        feeling on one page, is restored to the Northern side of the equation on
                        another, when his treatment of nature is compared with
                        Gericault’s. The <hi rend="i">Raft of Medusa</hi> is seen as an
                        “anthropocentric” document, showing man dominating nature
                        (35), in contrast to Northern Romantics like Constable who depict the
                        “pathetic fallacy” in which human feelings are attributed
                        to nature. Laying aside the obvious objection that the pathetic fallacy is
                        an example of anthropocentrism, not an antithesis of it, we have to be a
                        little uneasy when Constable is employed as a secular contrast to the
                        religious Friedrich on page 30, and then is allied with him against the
                        secular French painters on page 37.</p>
          <p>Like most of the “great traditions” which have been foisted
                        on the arts, Rosenblum’s Northern Romantic tradition is
                        essentially a rhetorical device used to bolster a series of value
                        judgments—in this case a preference for any art that has
                        pretensions to the mystical, symbolic, mysterious, or portentous, and thus
                        provides an occasion for the metaphysical fireworks of critical profundity.
                        A brief tour of Rosenblum’s distinctions between southern and
                        northern art quickly reveals the thread of invidious comparisons. Southern
                        landscapes show us “nothing more than a cheerful prospect”
                        (66), a “casually observed experience” like that of a
                        “tourist holiday” (77). Northern landscapes, on the other
                        hand, are always full of “deep” implications of one kind
                        or another (except, of 
<pb id="p11-202" n="202"/>
course, when the Northern
                        artist is working in a picturesque mode, which is probably about half the
                        time). There is “no temptation to read beyond” the surface
                        of Southern painting, unless, Rosenblum admits, it is for “some
                        statement about perception” (73)—presumably a lower kind
                        of message than the deep religious meanings of the Northerners. Northern
                        paintings of children reveal “primal forces” while
                        Southern examples of this genre are “sentimental and
                        prettified” (87-88). Southern art is described throughout as
                        “purely decorative, artificial, prosaic, earthbound, egotistical,
                        concerned only with particulars” (an assertion that is undermined
                        when Rosenblum contrasts the particularity of Van Gogh’s flower
                        paintings to the generality of the Impressionists). At its best, Southern
                        art is concerned with close observation and empirical fidelity (a claim
                        which could surely apply to Turner and Constable as well). Northern art, by
                        contrast, is never characterized as “merely” this or that;
                        it is an art which always gives us more than meets the eye, evoking floods
                        of glittering abstractions which, as Rosenblum admits in a refreshingly
                        humorous aside, always sound more convincing in German than English.</p>
          <p>Art history has always advanced, it seems, by grand syntheses or dialectical
                        schemes which are then eroded away after years of careful scholarly
                        investigation. Wölfflin’s distinctions between
                        painterly and linear in <hi rend="i">Principles of Art History</hi> are
                        perhaps the most famous example, and despite universal skepticism about his
                        distinctions, they survive everywhere in the practical criticism and
                        teaching of art. The question is, are Rosenblum’s categories of
                        Northern and Southern Romanticism useful as critical fictions in the same
                        measure as were Wölfflin’s? I think the answer must be
                        a resounding no. Rosenblum’s categories, unlike
                        Wölfflin’s, are never subjected to any criticism or
                        analysis, but are thrown out as if they were self-evident. They are not
                        firmly grounded in the concrete properties of the works of art under
                        scrutiny, or in the intentions of the artists, but proceed through a series
                        of “subtle and perhaps unsubtle historical distortions . . . for
                        the sake of internal logic” (8). Substitute the word
                        “rhetoric” for “logic” here and you get
                        the picture. Most important, Rosenblum’s distinctions do not
                        serve to differentiate two equally valid and often intermingling currents in
                        nineteenth century art, the complex dialectic between sacred and secular;
                        they emerge rather as thinly veiled attempts to elevate Northern art by
                        depreciating Southern. Perhaps this was inevitable in a book which set out
                        to change the balance of power in art history, and to assert the value of a
                        rival tradition. But neither the value or nature of that tradition is
                        well-served by invidious comparisons masquerading as reasoned
                        distinctions.</p>
          <p>It will be important for Blake scholars in particular to be wary of the
                        beguiling over-simplifications of Rosenblum’s thesis. Blake
                        emerges from isolation in this book (as he did on much surer grounds in
                        Rosenblum’s earlier book, <hi rend="i">Transformations in Late
                            Eighteenth Century Art</hi>), to take his place as a key figure in the
                        continuity of Romantic and Modern painting. This is heady wine for Blakeans
                        who are used to seeing their man on the sidelines of art history, but it
                        should be sipped with caution. Rosenblum’s understanding of Blake
                        is based on criticism which is anything but fresh (the only footnoted
                        scholarship is Anthony Blunt’s article on the <hi rend="i">Ancient of Days</hi> from
1938), and does little more than repeat the
                        standard half-truths about Blake being against reason, materialism,
                        mathematics, and in favor of imagination, spirit, and emotion. It is very
                        intriguing to suppose that Blake belongs to a tradition that goes through
                        Samuel Palmer to Van Gogh, but in the absence of any demonstration of
                        historical links (Rosenblum says not a word about the Pre-Raphaelites, an
                        astonishing omission) one must rest content with being intrigued, but
                        unconvinced. When Rosenblum does get down to specifics with Blake he
                        presents a far-fetched comparison with Barnett Newman on the grounds that
                        both of them “rebelled against geometry” (209). We are
                        told that “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Ancient of Days</hi>,
                        like his <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> of 1795, is in effect, an evil force,
                        imposing trivial clarity in a sublime universe” (210). Surely our
                        understanding of Blake has gotten beyond the naive allegorizing which sees
                        Newton and Urizen as either trivial or evil forces in Blake’s
                        universe. “Heroic folly” or “Sublime
                        Error” seem to be much more accurate descriptions of
                        Blake’s attitude toward the activities of these characters, and
                        the images of them which he created.</p>
          <p>It would be pleasant to conclude that Rosenblum is, like Urizen, a Heroic
                        Fool trying to reduce the world to two principles, and that he has conducted
                        what Harold Bloom would call a “strong misreading” of
                        Romantic and Modern art, killing off his symbolic father (the orthodox
                        tradition of Paris-based art history) in order to assert a new vision.
                        Unfortunately this is not the case. The father is never named or confronted
                        in any concrete way, and the misreadings are consistently weak. The main
                        value of this book is that is does provide an encyclopedic survey of a great
                        many artists, some of whom <hi rend="i">might</hi> belong to a continuous
                        tradition. In particular, it demonstrates that Friedrich’s
                        contribution to modern art is probably much greater than has been realized.
                        If Rosenblum had contented himself with documenting Friedrich’s
                        influence in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries he probably would have
                        produced a much sounder, if more cautious book. As a contribution to our
                        understanding of English Romantic art (and Blake in particular) in relation
                        to the modern tradition, it has much less to recommend it. The task of
                        clarifying the interaction of sacred and secular themes in Romantic and
                        Modern art remains to be done.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
