<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
     <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
             <idno>11.3.essick</idno>
             <fileDesc>
                     <titleStmt>
                       <title type="review">G. E. Bentley, Jr., Blake Books</title>
                       <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
                     </titleStmt>
                     <editionStmt>
                       <edition>Winter 1977-1978</edition>
                     </editionStmt>
                     <publicationStmt>
                       <date>1977-1978</date>
                     </publicationStmt>
                     <sourceDesc>
                       <biblFull>
                       <titleStmt>
                       <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                       <biblScope unit="volIss">11.3</biblScope>
                       <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
                       <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                       <respStmt>
                       <resp>Editors</resp>
                       <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                       <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                       <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                       <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                       <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                       <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                       <resp>Production Office</resp>
                       <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                       <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                       <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
                       <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                       <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                       <name>Michael Hays</name>
                       <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                       <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
                       <resp>Contributors</resp>
                       <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                       <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                       <name>W. J. T. Mitchell</name>
                       <name>Edward J. Rose</name>
                       <name>Corlette Walker</name>
                       </respStmt>
                       </titleStmt>
                       <publicationStmt>
                       <publisher>Department of English, University of
                       New Mexico</publisher>
                       <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                       <date when="1978"/>
                       <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                       </publicationStmt>
                       </biblFull>
                     </sourceDesc>
             </fileDesc>
             <profileDesc>
                     <langUsage>
                       <language id="eng">English</language>
                     </langUsage>
                     <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                       <constitution type="composite"/>
                       <domain type="education"/>
                     </textDesc>
             </profileDesc>
     </teiHeader>
     <text id="volume_11">
             <body>
                     <pb id="p11-178" n="178"/>
                     <div1 id="BQ-11-3-0006">
                       <head>
                       <title type="section">
                       <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
                       </title>
                       </head>
                       <div2>
                       <head>
                       <title type="main">G. E. Bentley, Jr. 
                       <hi rend="b">Blake Books.</hi> Annotated Catalogues of William
                       Blake’s Writings in Illuminated Printing, in
                       Conventional Typography and in Manuscript and
                       Reprints thereof, Reproductions of his Designs,
                       Books with his Engravings, Catalogues, Books he
                       owned, and Scholarly and Critical Works about him.
                       Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977. Pp. xii + 1079. £40
                       U.K., $88 U.S.</title>
                       </head>
                       <byline>
                       <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
                       <docAuthor>
                       <hi rend="b">Robert N.</hi>
                       <name>
                       <hi rend="b">Essick</hi>
                       </name>
                       </docAuthor>
                       </byline>
                       <p>The first impression is one of sheer
                       overwhelming size and of the Herculean effort that
                       must have gone into this book’s production. Have
                       we really churned out enough Blake criticism since
                       1964 to increase the enchiridion dimensions of the
                       Bentley &amp; Nurmi <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi>
                       to over one thousand pages? Not quite. 
                       <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> is far more than an
                       updating of its predecessor, for it supplies vast
                       amounts of information in areas not even touched
                       upon in its prototype. Most significantly, Bentley
                       has written a new census of the illuminated books.
                       There may be some initial resistance to replacing
                       the familiar and more elegantly printed pages of
                       the Keynes &amp; Wolf <hi rend="i">Census</hi>
                       with this bulky new bibliography. Some may grumble
                       over the format, particularly the use of densely
                       packed charts, but the amount and diversity of
                       material require complex packaging. In the long
                       run, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> will be
                       accepted as the standard bibliography in its field
                       and will remain so for many years.</p>
                       <p>When reviewing a work of this magnitude, one
                       serves little purpose by setting down general
                       evaluations based on a casual overview or the spot
                       checking of a few entries. The slower and less
                       showy work of correction and augmentation is far
                       more important. My intention is to deal with each
                       of the six sections of <hi rend="i">Blake
                       Books</hi> in turn, plunging as quickly and deeply
                       as possible into those minute particulars which
                       form the heart of any bibliography.</p>
                       <div3>
                       <head>
                       <title>
                       <hi rend="b">“INTRODUCTION” &amp; “BLAKE’S
                       REPUTATION &amp; INTERPRETERS”</hi>
                       </title>
                       </head>
                       <p>Bentley explains the organization and coverage
                       of the volume in the eleven page Introduction. He
                       has “examined every original copy of Blake’s works
                       which could be located, in some ninety collections
                       ranging from Edinburgh to Auckland” (p. 9). Thus
                       Bentley has no doubt inspected more copies of
                       Blake’s writings than anyone else—save for their
                       author. He has replaced the “perfunctory
                       descriptions” of Blake’s writings in Bentley &amp;
                       Nurmi with “the results of work on the originals”
                       (p. 11). A final “Postscript” (p. 14) notes that
                       “the body of the text” includes entries to the end
                       of 1970, but that “most important works published
                       by June 1974” have been either added to the main
                       sequence of entries or gathered in the fifty-page
                       “Addenda.”</p>
                       <p>The thirty-six page survey of Blake’s
                       reputation and interpreters takes the same broad,
                       long-range perspective provided by the earlier
                       version in Bentley &amp; Nurmi. The emphasis is on
                       objective summarizing and pointing out the
                       acknowledged high-points, but Bentley sometimes
                       reveals his own wry evaluations: “In Blake
                       studies, at least, there is an unfortunate
                       connection between an inclination to make
                       psychological interpretations and scholarly
                       incompetence” (p. 48). Two points need correction.
                       The monochrome facsimile of <hi rend="i">The
                       Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> edited by Clark
                       Emery (Miami, 1963) does not reproduce the Blake
                       Trust facsimile of copy D (as Bentley states, p.
                       38 n. 3), but the Dent facsimile (1927) of copy I
                       (I warned you I was going to get minute). As far
                       as I understand the genesis of the 
                       <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> and <hi rend="i">Blake
                       Studies</hi>, it is not in fact true that the
                       latter was established “in imitation” (p. 49) of
                       the former. The founding editors of 
                       <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> tell me that they had already
                       announced their first issue before they learned of
                       the existence of the <hi rend="i">Newsletter.</hi></p>
                       <pb id="p11-179" n="179"/>
                       <figure n="PsycheRepents.11.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="750" height="419">
						   <head>1 Plate 13, “Psyche Repents,” in George
						   Cumberland, <hi rend="i">Thoughts On Outline</hi>,
						   1796.</head>
						   <figDesc>Blake after Cumberland. Plate-mark 12.4 ×
						   16.1 cm. Author’s Collection.</figDesc>
                       </figure>
                       </div3>
                       <div3>
                       <head>
                       <title>
                       <hi rend="b">PART I</hi>
                       <lb/>
                       <hi rend="b">EDITIONS OF BLAKE’S WRITINGS</hi>
                       </title>
                       </head>
                       <p>In the most important, and longest, section of
                       his book, Bentley gives us complete bibliographic
                       descriptions of all of Blake’s writings, including
                       the letters and those prints bearing inscriptions
                       that are more than just titles. A considerable
                       amount of information on the illuminated books,
                       either ignored or treated summarily in Keynes
                       &amp; Wolf, is now available, including individual
                       plate sizes,
                       <figure n="BB447.1.2.COM" rend="file" width="958" height="748">
						   <head>2 Plate 6 in Cumberland, 
						   <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi>, 1796.</head>
						   <figDesc>Designed and engraved by Cumberland,
						   inscriptions probably engraved by Blake.
						   Plate-mark 11.9 × 22.7 cm. Note the similarity of
						   the letters of the imprint to those in Illus. 1
						   and the left-pointing serif on the 
						   <hi rend="i">g</hi> of <hi rend="i">Design’d.</hi> Author’s
						   Collection.</figDesc>
                       </figure> 
                       watermarks plate by plate, leaf sizes
                       (width followed by height—the reverse of the
                       conventional order in print catalogues), binding
                       history, offsets, original numeration, and
                       stab-hole measurements. Bentley has traced and
                       described a good many copies and fragments of
                       copies not in Keynes &amp; Wolf, and eliminated a
                       few conjectural copies by identifying them with
                       known ones. This last improvement was made
                       possible by more thorough recordings of
                       provenances. Valuable information is also provided
                       on pairs of designs with identical plate-mark
                       dimensions, thus indicating that Blake used both
                       sides of his copperplates in most cases. The
                       printing dates of many copies have been revised in
                       light of a more thorough consideration of the
                       sequence of variants than that provided by keynes
                       &amp; Wolf. Although this considerably alters the
                       printing sequence for many titles, and some past
                       assumptions about Blake’s development as a
                       colorist, the old, familiar letter designations
                       are retained, for which we should all be thankful.
                       Plate numbering is different for many titles since
                       Bentley has numbered all copies continuously,
                       whereas Keynes &amp; Wolf sometimes use roman
                       numerals for front-matter. In the plate numbering
                       <pb id="p11-180" n="180"/>
                       of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, Bentley and Keynes &amp; Wolf are
                       the same, but Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Illuminated
                       Blake</hi> uses a different sequence, and Erdman’s
                       <hi rend="i">Poetry &amp; Prose</hi> and Keynes’
                       <hi rend="i">Writings</hi> yet another. For 
                       <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Bentley, Keynes, and
                       Keynes &amp; Wolf are all in accord, following
                       copy E; but Erdman follows copies A, C, and F. All
                       this can cause a good deal of confusion, and we
                       should take pains to make clear which system we
                       are using in each case. The best long-term
                       solution will be to take <hi rend="i">Blake
                       Books</hi> as the standard.</p>
                       <p>A similar set of problems confronts us in line
                       numbering. The usual practice has been to number
                       each plate individually, but for most illuminated
                       books Bentley numbers the lines in one sequence
                       for the whole work, excluding preludia. For “The
                       Song of Liberty,” the “line” references (for
                       example, in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> pp. 290,
                       297) are not to lines at all, but to Blake’s
                       numbered sentences, all but three of which take up
                       more than one line. Happily this clumsy method,
                       requiring one to count through a whole poem to
                       find one of Bentley’s references, is suspended for
                       <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 
                       <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, and of course each poem in 
                       <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>
                       is separately numbered. I suspect that Bentley
                       will use the same, albeit inconsistent, system in
                       his forthcoming edition of Blake’s writings, and
                       this should make it easier to look up a line
                       reference in <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi></p>
                       <p>For each plate, Bentley gives a part-line
                       incipit followed by a brief description of the
                       design. These should be used only as identifying
                       notes on major design elements; Bentley makes no
                       attempt to number every streak on every tulip.
                       Comparisons between Erdman’s descriptions in 
                       <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> and
                       Bentley’s—a game I will not play here at any
                       length—show once again that there is no such thing
                       as a completely objective description of a
                       picture. We are also given a good deal of
                       information on coloring, particularly of people
                       and their dress. These notes offer both
                       nourishment and correction to those interested in
                       the pursuit of color symbolism.</p>
                       <p>Bentley also deals with variants between copies
                       of the same illuminated book—a problem which, as
                       he reminds us in the Introduction (p. 9), is
                       extremely tricky. Let me set down a few of my own
                       conclusions about this important issue, based on
                       examinations of Blake’s prints and on my own
                       etching and printing of relief plates. Traditional
                       bibliography, based on the study of typographic
                       printing, is incapable of dealing with many
                       elements of printing from relief blocks. The
                       bibliographer must give way to the chalcographer,
                       and the first great truth he must utter is that
                       <hi rend="i">no two impressions from Blake’s
                       copperplates printed in relief are identical.</hi>
                       In relief printing, unlike intaglio, the ink
                       spreads over large areas relative to the total
                       size of the image. The larger the area, the
                       greater the chance for accidental, uncontrollable,
                       and <hi rend="i">visible</hi> variations in
                       texture and color. Such factors as ink viscosity,
                       humidity, and air pressure can affect the
                       appearance of each impression. Far more than with
                       modern inking rollers, Blake’s inking balls made
                       it easy to under-ink, or completely miss, small
                       relief plateaus, over-ink others, and foul bitten
                       areas. Because of these inevitable and
                       uncontrollable differences between all
                       impressions, it is important to keep in mind the
                       following five distinct types of variants, listed
                       in descending order of chalcographic significance:
                       <list type="ordered">
                       <item><p><label>1.</label> Changes made in the
                       plate. These have great significance since they
                       take conscious effort to execute and have a high
                       degree of permanence. Erasing black lines (i.e.,
                       increasing bitten areas) is easy; adding black
                       lines is difficult, although not impossible.
                       Alterations of this type are the 
                       <hi rend="i">only</hi> ones which affect the “state” of the
                       plate.</p></item>
                       <item><p><label>2.</label> Conscious alterations
                       in inking or color printing the plate. These can
                       take two basic forms: (a) Deletion of words or
                       design elements by masking (as with the last four
                       lines on <hi rend="i">America</hi> pl. 4 in copies
                       B-F, H-M, R, a), by wiping the ink off (as with
                       the plate edges in almost all of Blake’s
                       eighteenth-century impressions), or by failure to
                       ink certain areas. With simple failure to ink it
                       is sometimes difficult to determine whether the
                       change was purposeful or not. If the area is
                       completely uninked (not just smudged) and is
                       discrete—that is, limited to particular motifs and
                       words surrounded by well inked areas—then the
                       failure to ink probably took conscious effort. (b)
                       Alterations in inking color, texture, or
                       directional wiping (as in 
                       <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> copy F).</p></item>
                       <item><p><label>3.</label> Conscious addition or
                       elimination of design elements or text with ink or
                       watercolors on individual impressions after
                       printing.</p></item>
                       <item><p><label>4.</label> Pen &amp; ink work or
                       coloring on individual impressions after printing
                       which does not add new lines not on the
                       copperplate, or subtract them, but only
                       underscores or tints what is already
                       there.</p></item>
                       <item><p><label>5.</label> Accidental variants in
                       inking or coloring, including foul inking of
                       whites, incomplete wiping of ink from whites, the
                       running of watercolor washes beyond bounding
                       lines, and other countless minor variations of all
                       sorts.</p></item>
                       </list> Bentley properly deals almost exclusively
                       with categories 1-3 in his lists of variants. It
                       is important to indicate, however, which type of
                       variant one is describing in each case, and 
                       <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> sometimes fails to do
                       this. Individual problems are dealt with
                       below.</p>
                       <p>Bentley brings us to similar difficulties with
                       categories in his notes on drawings related to
                       designs in the illuminated books and, in Part III,
                       in commercial book illustrations. There is a
                       considerable difference between a true preliminary
                       drawing and an analogue. It is often important to
                       make a further distinction between analogues
                       produced prior to the design in question and those
                       produced later, particularly when tracing the
                       development of a motif through Blake’s career. It
                       is frequently difficult to make these distinctions
                       in each individual case, but the
                       bibliographer-chalcographer should seek the aid of
                       the art historian and give it a try if he is going
                       to delve into the matter at all. Bentley’s notes
                       hover between a list of preliminaries and a list
                       of analogues, the latter sometimes masquerading as
                       the former. For example, on p. 86 we find that
                       “there are sketches on <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>
                       pp. 75 (top right), 77 
<pb id="p11-181" n="181"/>
                       (bottom), and 17 [should read “71”] related to
                       designs on [<hi rend="i">America</hi>] pl. 7, 11,
                       14.” Here, “related to” must mean different things
                       for each plate, for the sketch on 
                       <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> p. 71 is a preliminary for 
                       <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi> pl. 17 and no
                       more “related to” <hi rend="i">America</hi> pl. 14
                       (to use Bentley’s new numbers) than the engraving;
                       the sketch on p. 75 and the man and snake on 
                       <hi rend="i">America</hi> pl. 7 are variations on the
                       same motifs but pictorially quite different; and
                       the prone infant on p. 77 is much closer to the
                       one in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, p. 23 of
                       the engravings, than to <hi rend="i">America</hi>
                       pl. 11. In his notes on <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
                       pl. 10 (p. 153), Bentley states that the “sketch
                       for the three bottom figures appears on 
                       <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> p. 25.” But this sketch is
                       no doubt a rejected preliminary (numbered 32 
                       <hi rend="i">del.</hi>, 23) for a series of emblems
                       that finally emerged as <hi rend="i">The Gates of
                       Paradise.</hi> Bentley’s “for” could lead to a
                       false impression about the development of these
                       important motifs which make their first appearance
                       in a water color of c.1779, usually called
                       “Pestilence” or “Plague,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
                       type="note">1</ref> and then again in a slightly
                       later water color of the same subject.<ref
                       target="n18" type="note">2</ref> Bentley mentions
                       only the first water color. His wording is
                       misleading when he notes (p. 254) that the verso
                       sketch on the drawing of “Albion Rose” (Victoria
                       &amp; Albert Museum)<ref target="n19" type="note">3</ref> is “for” 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> pl.
                       76, and again when he states that the wash
                       drawing<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">4</ref> of a
                       battlefield scene in the collection of the Earl of
                       Crawford &amp; Balcarres is “for” “The Counsellor,
                       King, Warrior, Mother &amp; Child in the Tomb”
                       among the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> illustrations.
                       In each case, the design referred to is an early
                       appearance of the motifs in question, but is in no
                       sense a preliminary “for” the later work. In light
                       of these art-historical complexities that can take
                       many sentences to explain fully, the best recourse
                       for the bibliographer may be to avoid preliminary
                       and analogue lists altogether. 
                       <note id="n17"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Repro. <hi rend="i">Blake
                       Newsletter</hi>, 7 (1973), 4; collection of Donald
                       Davidson.</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">2</hi>
                       Repro. Christie’s sale catalogue, 2 March 1976,
                       no. 97; now Essick collection.</note>
                       <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Repro. Keynes, 
                       <hi rend="i">Drawings by Blake</hi> (1927), pl.
                       2.</note>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Repro.
                       Keynes, <hi rend="i">A Bibliography of Blake</hi>
                       (1921), facing p. 220. Keynes also presents this
                       as a preliminary for <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>,
                       and my “finding list of reproductions of blake’s
                       art,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 5
                       (1971), is also guilty of the misleading
                       “for.”</note></p>
                       <p>What follows is a list of additions and
                       corrections to Part I, intermixed with a few
                       longer discussions or queries about particular
                       points. I have not added material outside the
                       scope of Bentley’s coverage, nor fussed over minor
                       and subjective disagreements on color or
                       descriptions of designs. Except where I question a
                       point or simply indicate an area where more work
                       must be done, I have a good deal of confidence in
                       my corrections to all parts of <hi rend="i">Blake
                       Books.</hi> They are based on examinations of the
                       original materials involved or high quality
                       reproductions when these are sufficient. Many of
                       these corrections are minor, to say the least, but
                       the importance of Bentley’s book warrants a
                       microscopic perspective. Unless indicated
                       otherwise, all page- and entry-number references
                       and quotations are from <hi rend="i">Blake
                       Books.</hi> Those interested only in a general
                       overview of <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> can
                       precede directly to the last paragraph of this
                       review. “And after this warning,” as Fielding puts
                       it, if the reader “shall be of opinion that he can
                       find enough of Serious in other parts of this
                       history, he may pass over these, in which we
                       profess to be laboriously dull.”</p>
                       <p>“The Accusers,” no. 1, p. 76. Bentley gets the
                       order of the first two states backwards. The first
                       state in the Bodleian (Bentley’s copy B) is
                       followed by the untraced second state (copy I in
                       Bentley’s list at the top of the page, but called
                       “A” in footnote 1) known through its description
                       in the Boston Museum of Fine Arts 1891 catalogue.
                       This sequence is confirmed by the presence of
                       fragments of the second state inscriptions on the
                       third state but not on Bentley’s second state,
                       which therefore must be the true 
                       first.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">5</ref> The
second state
                       (not the third, as Bentley has it) resides beneath
                       the Rosenwald color printed impression, and
                       presumably beneath the more thickly printed
                       British Museum copy as well. 
                       <note id="n21"><hi rend="s">5</hi> The proper sequence was first
                       pointed out by Erdman in “The Dating of William
                       Blake’s Engravings,” <hi rend="i">PQ</hi>, 31
                       (1952), 337-43; rpt. in <hi rend="i">The Visionary
                       Hand</hi>, ed. Essick, pp. 161-69. In the first
                       printing of Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Poetry &amp;
                       Prose</hi> (1965), p. 660, the states are
                       reversed, but by the fourth printing (1970) this
                       has been corrected. Keynes, <hi rend="i">Separate
                       Plates</hi> (1956), also gets it backwards. In
                       “Dating Blake’s Script,” <hi rend="i">Blake
                       Newsletter</hi>, 3 (1969), 8-13, Erdman proposes a
                       date of 1803 or earlier for the final state, but
                       like Bentley I would put it considerably
                       later.</note></p>
                       <p>According to <hi rend="i">William Blake: The
                       Painter as Poet</hi>, catalogue of an exhibition
                       at the Swirbul Library, Adelphi University (1977),
                       entry 15, a copy (previously unrecorded) of the
                       third state is in the Philadelphia Museum of
                       Art.</p>
                       <p>P. 77, copy G. Reference to Small Book of
                       Designs should be to p. 356, not 236.</p>
                       <p>“Albion Rose,” no. 2, p. 78. The dating and
                       sequence of states is wrong. The engraving beneath
                       the Huntington color printed copy, and no doubt
                       beneath the more thickly printed British Museum
                       copy, is a first state lacking the inscription.
                       There is no known impression of this state printed
                       in intaglio. The “Albion” inscription was added
                       c.1804 when the extensive burnishing and the worm
                       and bat-winged moth were also added to the plate.
                       In footnote 3, Bentley states that “Erdman, p.
                       804, guesses 1790-1 on the basis of the rightward,
                       conventional terminal ‘g’ in ‘Giving’” as the date
                       of the inscription. The only work by Erdman I can
                       find with a reference to “<corr type="emend">Albion</corr> Rose” on p. 804
                       is his edition of the <hi rend="i">Poetry &amp;
                       Prose</hi>, where he dates the inscription “1790
                       or early 1791” in his first printing of 1965, but
                       changes this “to the late 1790s (or later)” by the
                       fourth printing of 1970.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
type="note">6</ref> 
                       The images in the inscription
                       (compare to Blake’s letter to Hayley of 23 Oct.
                       1804), the lettering style, and the development of
                       Blake’s burnishing techniques all point to an 1804
                       date for the second state bearing the “Albion”
                       inscription. <note id="n22"><hi rend="s">6</hi>
                       Erdman, “Dating Blake’s Script,” argues for c.
                       1800-1803 for the “Albion” inscription.</note></p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi>,
                       no. 3, pp. 80-81. Bentley indicates that all
                       copies are color printed. With such small plates
                       it is difficult to tell the difference between
                       true color printing and the reticulated surface of
                       thick watercolors that have dried quickly, and as
                       Bentley notes (p. 84), “the colour printing in
                       both works [<hi rend="i">All Religions are
                       One</hi> and <hi rend="i">No Natural
                       Religion</hi>] is very tentative.” But if he is
                       right, then either all recorded copies were
                       printed c.1795—a remarkable situation—or the usual
                       dating of Blake’s color printing must be changed.
                       Perhaps some of these small prints were made with
                       colored inks or blotted hand coloring, and thus
                       represent an early stage in Blake’s development of
                       color printing techniques.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi>, no. 3,
                       p. 85. The incipit recorded for pl. 2 is actually
                       inscribed at the bottom of pl. 1. Bentley’s note
                       that the angel on pl. 2 has “his right hand on the
                       stone and his left on the old man’s shoulder”
                       corrects Erdman’s “a winged angel, with arms
                       around stone tablets” (<hi rend="i">The
                       Illuminated Blake</hi>, p. 24).</p>
                       <p>P. 85, pl. 5. The man leans on his 
                       <hi rend="i">left</hi> hand.</p>
                       <p>P. 86, pls. 2-10. The Huntington copy includes
                       <pb id="p11-182" n="182"/> 
                       pl. a2 (not a1) of 
                       <hi rend="i">No Natural Religion.</hi> This error also
                       appears in the Table of Collections, p. 60.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">America</hi>, no. 6, p. 86. Title:
                       period follows 1793. P. 86, footnote 2. “The fact
                       that the top lines of text on pl. 7 are curtailed
                       by the design suggests that here at least the
                       design was etched before the text.” I very much
                       doubt that Blake “etched” text and design at
                       different times, for this would require several
                       extra steps of stopping-out and cleaning and would
                       create many unnecessary problems in text-design
                       coordination. He may, however, have painted the
                       resist on the copper at different times. At any
                       time prior to etching, any curtailment of text
                       lines could be altered easily (by changing the
                       design, or rewriting the text, or adjusting the
                       left margin) if Blake had wanted to. Since the
                       text had to be written or transferred onto the
                       plate in reverse, the line breaks on the right
                       margin had to be worked out well before etching.
                       There is no way I can think of for telling which
                       Blake painted on the plate first—design or
                       text—from the evidence of line breaks or other
                       spatial relationships between text and design. But
                       it does tell us that Blake was willing to alter
                       his text lines in order to make room for his
                       designs, and I suspect that the reverse may also
                       be true in many cases. Bentley makes this point in
                       regard to <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> on p. 144,
                       footonte 1, but his suggestion that “some of the
                       design preceded the text” is not necessarily
                       true.</p>
                       <p>P. 91, pl. 2 variants. “The printed cloud-line
                       in copies A-M is absent in copies N-Q.” The cloud
                       does appear in N, where it has been drawn in ink
                       as Bentley notes, p. 93, and in O and Q the entire
                       upper left corner is colored in so that the cloud
                       line is still present as a bounding line. I have
                       not been able to check copy P. We need more
                       information here on whether these variants are in
                       printing or in subsequent hand coloring.</p>
                       <p>P. 92, pl. 14 variants and p. 97, pl. 14.
                       “There seems to be a coiled serpent inside the
                       door in copy O.” This “serpent” is actually a
                       partially rolled woven mat of the sort pictured in
                       Blake’s white line etching of “Death’s Door” and
                       in Schiavonetti’s copy engraving.</p>
                       <p>P. 92, pl. 1. There is no “plant at bottom
                       right,” only a plant-like relief decoration in the
                       stone.</p>
                       <p>P. 93, pl. 3 incipit. First letter of
                       “daughter” is lower case.</p>
                       <p>P. 94, pl. 5. Which “P” in “PROPHECY” is the
                       terminus for a cloud line, and which for flames,
                       in copy A?</p>
                       <p>P. 94, pl. 6. The leaf of <hi rend="i">America</hi> 
                       sketches in the BMPR has a hesitant
                       line that suggests a copy and makes the
                       attribution to Blake questionable.</p>
                       <p>P. 95, pl. 7. The figure holding a sword is
                       probably a man, not a “long-haired woman.” His
                       hair is hardly longer than that of the “flying man
                       [holding] a balance.”</p>
                       <p>P. 96, pl. 10 incipit. First letter of “terror”
                       is lower case.</p>
                       <p>P. 96, pl. 11. There is no corn-field “left of
                       the text”—only swirls of crosshatching quite
                       distinct from the wheat below the text.</p>
                       <p>P. 96, pl. 12. The flames reach up the left
                       (not right) margin.</p>
                       <p>P. 97, pl. 14. Reference should be to 
                       <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> p. 71.</p>
                       <p>P. 98, pl. 16. It is clear from copy I that
                       only one line of text was deleted on the
                       plate.</p>
                       <p>Pp. 98-99, pl. a. “ . . . there are no birds
                       above or below the ‘Y’ of ‘PROPHECY’.” There is
                       one below “Y,” and two above and to the left of
                       the first “P.” “The only surviving copperplate
                       from Blake’s works in Illuminated Printing is a
                       fragment from the top right corner of this
                       rejected plate from <hi rend="i">America.</hi>”
                       The fragment is from the right margin extending
                       from the lower part of the “Y” of “PROPHECY” to
                       mid-way in line 6. In the quoted text on this
                       fragment there is a comma or period at the end of
                       the third line. The deletion marks noted by
                       Bentley are of two types. The two horizontal
                       scratches through part of the first line may well
                       be part of a purposeful deletion; but the vertical
                       gouges, too haphazard and deep to be text
                       deletions, through the right side of lines 4-5
                       were probably created after the plate was cut up
                       and at least this one piece given to young
                       Butts.</p>
                       <p>P. 99, pl. d. “If it was intended for 
                       <hi rend="i">America</hi>, there must have been text
                       or design cut off at the bottom.” It seems far
                       more likely that it was cut off at the top where
                       the fragmentary text appears.</p>
                       <p>“Ancient of Days,” no. 10, pp. 108-10. Even
                       though this plate bears no “writings,” the colored
                       impressions are listed in a separate section here.
                       Uncolored impressions not bound in copies of 
                       <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> are listed on p. 161. On p.
                       148, Bentley suggests that the “Ancient of Days”
                       was printed from a different plate than the 
                       <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> frontispiece—hence the
                       separate entry for it. There are indeed two plates
                       of this design, but not quite in the way Bentley
                       has it. One colored impression in Keynes’
                       collection (Bentley’s copy C, 
                       p. 107)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">7</ref> has
rather
                       different cloud outlines, larger crosshatching
                       patterns in the clouds on both sides of the
                       figure’s extended arm and in the upper right
                       corner, fewer but bolder lines of radiance below
                       the clouds, a shorter beard on the figure, and a
                       central disc measuring 10.3 cm. in diameter—a full
                       6 mm. greater than in all other versions I have
                       measured. The differences among all other
                       impressions can be accounted for by differences in
                       inking and coloring. The fractional differences in
                       plate-mark, given by Bentley, can be accounted for
                       by paper shrinkage (a phenomenon Bentley takes
                       note of on p. 67) and are no greater than
                       variances (1 to 2 mm.) between separate colored
                       impressions themselves. All the separate colored
                       impressions of the “Ancient of Days” were printed
                       from the same plate as the <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> 
                       frontispiece—with the single
                       exception of the Keynes copy described above.
                       <note id="n23"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Repro. Keynes,
                       <hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi>, pl.
                       16.</note></p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, no. 14,
                       p. 113, pl. 1. The man does not have “his head on
                       his knees.” The woman looks up, but not “at
                       him.”</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, no. 18, p.
                       123, pl. 4 variants. The tree is not “extended up
                       the right margin in copy O.” A second tree trunk
                       is added to the right margin but it extends no
                       higher than its companion.</p>
                       <pb id="p11-183" n="183"/>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, no.
                       32, p. 135, title-page. “by” follows “Printed” and
                       “J. Blake” is in roman letters.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, no. 33, p. 141,
                       title-page. Copies a, C-E, H-I, and L have a colon
                       after “<hi rend="i">Blake.</hi>” P. 149, pl. 1
                       variants. “In the proofs, the clouds by the god’s
                       right knee are not hatched (a), there is no
                       division between clouds at the top middle (a), . .
                       . and the top cloud impinges on the sun at the
                       left (Keynes pull).” In copy a, the clouds have
                       considerable hatching, but it does not extend as
                       far towards the left margin as in the finished
                       state, and the division between clouds is present
                       although not clearly printed. The top cloud does
                       not impinge “on the sun at the left” in the Keynes
                       uncolored impression, which is not a proof.</p>
                       <p>P. 149, pl. 2 variants. There is now a further
                       proof with sketches in the Pierpont Morgan
                       Library.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">8</ref>
                       <note id="n24"><hi rend="s">8</hi> See Charles Ryskamp
                       [and Thomas V. Lange], “A Blake Discovery,” 
                       <hi rend="i">TLS</hi> (14 Jan. 1977), 40.</note></p>
                       <p>P. 150, pl. 3. “The only trace of decoration is
                       a little foliage at the foot.” There is also a fly
                       left of the vegetation.</p>
                       <p>P. 151, pl. 6. The sphere with a crouching man
                       is not invariably yellow.</p>
                       <p>P. 153, pl. 9 state 2. There are also
                       additional white lines added to the smoke.</p>
                       <p>P. 153, pl. 11. A proof in copy a lacks the
                       white line hatching in the area just below the
                       leg, from upper thigh to calf, of the woman
                       closest to the viewer.</p>
                       <p>P. 154, pl. 14. The man’s ears are not “long”
                       or “pointed” on the plate, but in copies B and C
                       the inner sides of the pointed vaults on either
                       side of the man’s head have been transformed into
                       giant ears through tinting with flesh-tones. I can
                       discern no difference in the sex of the two
                       angels. P. 156, pl. 18 variants. In copy a, there
                       <hi rend="i">are</hi> white lines “on the right
                       ankle of the man.”</p>
                       <p>“Exhibition of Paintings,” p. 164, title-page.
                       The “<hi rend="smallcaps">y</hi>” in “<hi rend="smallcaps">By</hi>” 
                       (fifth line) is a small capital.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi>, no.
                       38, p. 166, title-page. There is a period after
                       “1794” (colored out in copy G). “The logical,
                       consecutive nature of the narrative is emphasized
                       by chapter- and section-numbers and by running
                       heads.” It seems to me that Blake has set up a
                       tension between these mechanical, Bible-like
                       divisions and his non-consecutive narrative as a
                       formal embodiment of the conflict between Urizen
                       and the Eternals. P. 167. Pl. 15 would also “seem
                       to be etched over other designs, as the odd swirls
                       in copy D suggest,” but I am not certain about pl.
                       20. In copy D the coloring does not correspond to
                       relief surfaces, but this does not necessarily
                       mean that fragments of an earlier etching lie
                       beneath pl. 20.</p>
                       <p>P. 176, pl. 13 incipit. First letter of
                       “Nostrils” is a capital.</p>
                       <p>P. 177, pl. 17. “The whole page is a design of
                       a (?female) figure with long hair and a Red skirt
                       (but no top) who holds her ears as she bends
                       towards us over a flaming sphere.” In the note on
                       “Colouring,” the figure is called “Enitharmon.”
                       Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi>,
                       p. 199, claims (rightly, I think) that the figure
                       is Los and that the globe is not “flaming” but
                       pendant on veins of blood. The disagreement here
                       calls into question Bentley’s contention that this
                       is one of “many . . . designs” in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> 
                       which “illustrate the text more
                       literally than was often Blake’s custom” (p.
                       166).</p>
                       <p>P. 178, pl. 21 variants. “Enitharmon has her
                       right hand in the small of Orc’s back” in copy B
                       as well as A. The cloth she holds is absent from
                       A.</p>
                       <p>P. 178, pl. 22 variants. In copy G, the tears
                       are on his cheeks, not “in his eyes.”</p>
                       <p>P. 179, pl. 24. “ . . . across the middle of
                       the page floats a man with his hands raised to
                       shoulder level and a Red swirl coming from his
                       chest.” The swirl is not visible in copies B, D,
                       G, and is probably just a highlighted cloud-line
                       elsewhere.</p>
                       <p>Variants: the top-most figure’s arms are not
                       visible in copy B. The reference to “Fuzon” and
                       “Grodna” are somewhat mysterious since these
                       figures are not located by name in the design
                       description. According to Erdman, <hi rend="i">The
                       Illuminated Blake</hi>, p. 206, they are the
                       figures at top and lower right.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">For Children: The Gates of
                       Paradise</hi>, no. 43, p. 185, title-page. No
                       apostrophe after “Pauls.” p. 187, pl. 1 variants.
                       There <hi rend="i">is</hi> “shading above the
                       chrysalis” in the first state.</p>
                       <p>P. 191, pl. 18. “ . . . on the ground to the
                       right are the profiles of two or more men the same
                       colour as the earth.” In reference to a monochrome
                       intaglio print, “colour” traditionally means the
                       linear patterns that create tone, but on this
                       plate these patterns are not the same on the faces
                       and the ground.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of
                       Paradise</hi>, no. 45, p. 199, pls. 5 &amp; 7.
                       There are intermediate states between Bentley’s
                       first and second in copy D. On pl. 5, copy D has
                       most of the work on the figure and the hatching
                       lower left of the final state, but lacks the
                       additional hatching on the rocks lower right and a
                       few strokes on the man’s arms. On pl. 7, there are
                       more scales on the figure’s loins than in the
                       first state, but they do not extend as far up his
                       belly as in the final state. This intermediate
                       state also lacks many fine lines on the figure.
                       Blake seems to have tinkered with <hi rend="i">For
                       the Sexes</hi> to the end of his life.</p>
                       <p>P. 205, no. 48. The limited edition of the
                       Blake Trust Facsimile includes five extra plates
                       from copies G and L.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi>, no.
                       48, p. 205, title-page. Period after “FIRST.”</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi>, no. 51, p.
                       207. A previously unrecorded copy of pl. 1 only,
                       now in my collection, is printed in black on a
                       sheet of unwatermarked wove paper measuring 24.5 ×
                       34.5 cm. P. 208, pl. 1 incipit. “THE” is in what
                       might be called small capitals, “GHOST” is in
                       larger letters, and “ABEL” is still larger. The
                       problem here is a good example of the frequently
                       encountered difficulty in reducing Blake’s etched
                       texts to typographic forms and the conventions of
                       <pb id="p11-184" n="184"/>
descriptive
                       bibliography based on them. This, I suspect, is
                       just what Blake wanted.</p>
                       <p>P. 209, pl. 2. The “horizontal figure in a fur
                       skirt” does not lean “on the ground” but rests on
                       the chest of another figure prone on the
                       ground.</p>
                       <p>Inscription on a title-page design for Blair’s
                       <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>, no. 58, p. 213. A colon
                       follows “<hi rend="i">Designs.</hi>” All words and
                       numbers are italic except “Grave,” which is
                       followed by a period.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi>, no.
                       74, p. 223. “There is no context for p. A, and the
                       immediately preceding pages may have been removed
                       because they reveal too directly or too
                       inaccurately Blake’s secret method of Illuminated
                       Printing.” This seems unlikely because the
                       surviving fragment says nothing about relief
                       etching and is probably just a gentle parody of
                       Cumberland’s notions about engraved writing in
                       intaglio.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, no. 75, p. 224,
                       title-page. Period after “W” visible in copy
                       C.</p>
                       <p>P. 224, footnote 2. “Forty-two of the 52 (or
                       more) copperplates needed for 
                       <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> could have been formed from the
                       centres of Blake’s engravings for Young’s 
                       <hi rend="i">Night thoughts</hi> [sic] (1797) left
                       blank (except for p. 65) for the typeset text.”
                       This is very unlikely. The standard
                       eighteenth-century practice was for the publisher
                       to purchase the coppers in which he retained all
                       rights after engraving. If Blake did acquire the
                       plates, he could not have made use of the
                       unengraved centers without cutting through the
                       surrounding areas. This would have produced a pile
                       of odd pieces of copper and would have been far
                       less economical than scraping and burnishing the
                       engraved areas to make use of the whole
                       plates.</p>
                       <p>P. 231. “Of these designs [in 
                       <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>], those on pl. 1-2, 11, 26, 35,
                       37, 51, 53 and 76 are in White line; that is, they
                       are engraved in the ordinary manner, but with
                       Blake’s method of intaglio printing. . . .” Pl. 46
                       should be added to this list, and pl. 28 is
                       largely white line. They are basically etchings,
                       not engravings, and printed in relief, not
                       “intaglio.”</p>
                       <p>P. 232, footnote 9. Bentley states that the
                       catchword on the BMPR proof of pl. 53 was “altered
                       ineffectively to ‘In’ in all other copies.” I
                       cannot find this catchword in reproductions of
                       copies C, D, or E, and on p. 250 Bentley states
                       that the “catchword is gone in all” but the BMPR
                       proof.</p>
                       <p>P. 238, pl. 1 variants. “The traveller’s
                       fingers [in the second state] extend through the
                       central cone of light in B, not just through its
                       rays as elsewhere.” The fingers 
                       <hi rend="i">can</hi> be seen within the disc in copies A,
                       C-F, and I (I have not checked H). In B the entire
                       hand can be seen within the disc (perhaps a
                       sphere—but why a “cone”?).</p>
                       <p>P. 239. The states listed 4-5 lines from the
                       bottom of the page are of pl. 4, not pl. 5 as a
                       <corr type="emend">printer’s</corr> error makes it seem.</p>
                       <p>P. 244, pl. 25. The plate exists in three
                       states. The first (copies A-C, and the Preston
                       proof now in the National Gallery of Art,
                       Canberra) lacks the black squiggle lines on the
                       rocks (below and on each side of the central
                       figure) and around the head and arm upper right,
                       and also lacks the contour lines on the legs and
                       torso of the woman on the right, all added to the
                       second state (copies D, E). In the third state
                       (copies F, H, I, and no doubt posthumous copy J)
                       there is further black line shading on the rocks
                       and in the upper right corner, plus additional
                       white line work in the hair of the top and right
                       women. Bentley mentions none of these interesting
                       white and black line additions, some probably made
                       by engraving white lines and printing in relief
                       from the burr.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">9</ref>
                       <note id="n25"><hi rend="s">9</hi>
                       Alterations in this plate were first discussed,
                       although without due regard for mere printing
                       differences, in Deirdre Toomey, “The States of
                       Plates 25 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,” 
                       <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 6 (1972),
                       46-48.</note></p>
                       <p>P. 244, pl. 26. Line break after “ME” in quoted
                       text.</p>
                       <p>P. 246, pl. 36 incipit. Apostrophe in
                       “return’d.”</p>
                       <p>P. 246, pl. 37, note on line 1. “The first six
                       words are engraved (not etched) in intaglio . . . ” 
                       The words are in relief, for if they were in
                       intaglio they would print white like the last
                       three lines and the ampersand. Whether engraved or
                       etched is hard to tell, but Bentley may be right
                       since the letters appear to be relief plateaus
                       remaining after surrounding areas were scraped or
                       gouged away with a tool.</p>
                       <p>P. 247, pl. 40 incipit. Apostrophe in
                       “shudder’d.”</p>
                       <p>P. 248, pl. 46. The Tonner copy of “God Judging
                       Adam” is now in the Philadelphia Museum of
                       Art.</p>
                       <p>P. 248, pl. 47. The quoted incipit is 
                       <hi rend="i">not</hi> “deleted” (but there is a
                       deleted line above it) and it does not begin with
                       an ampersand but with the first word quoted by
                       Bentley, “From.”</p>
                       <p>P. 249, pl. 51. The sketch previously in the
                       collection of David J. Black has been sold through
                       Colnaghi’s to the Hamburg Kunsthalle.</p>
                       <p>P. 252, pl. 64. The “low, Regency chair” is
                       probably a large scroll.</p>
                       <p>P. 252, pl. 69. If the text was “altered in the
                       copper” then at least two states should be listed.
                       In which copies do these appear?</p>
                       <p>P. 253, pl. 72. Capital “D” in “Decaying,”
                       “Tormenters” not “Tormentors,” in the quoted
                       lines.</p>
                       <p>P. 253, pl. 75. Why is the figure on the left a
                       “man” rather than another long-haired, crowned
                       woman?</p>
                       <p>P. 254, pl. 78 incipit. Period after
                       “Jerusalem.”</p>
                       <p>P. 255, pl. 81. The last two lines are 
                       <hi rend="i">not</hi> “written in a solid Black part
                       of the margin” but in a white peninsula etched
                       into the surrounding relief area.</p>
                       <p>P. 256, pl. 92. The “Note” should be appended
                       to pl. 94.</p>
                       <p>P. 257, pl. 97 variants. “The light to the left
                       and below the globe is gone in C.” Its
                       disappearance is caused by (accidental?) fouling
                       of whites. This impression bears other evidence of
                       fouling and smudging in the whites on the figure
                       and globe. P. 258, copy A. The “colour microfilm
                       by Micro Methods Ltd.” is of the Blake Trust
                       facsimile of copy E, not of the uncolored copy
                       A.</p>
                       <p>P. 263, history of pl. 47. This print was
                       listed for sale in Colnaghi’s May 1977
                       catalogue.</p>
                       <p>“Joseph of Arimathea,” no. 83, p. 266, table of
                       copies. Neither copy B nor E is 
                       “<hi rend="i">colour-printed.</hi>” Keynes, 
                       <hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi>, p. 4, and in 
                       <hi rend="i">Bibliotheca Bibliographici</hi>, p. 61, reports
                       that his copy E is watermarked 1828, not 1825.
                       There are two copies not on Bentley’s list: one
                       with added washes (as in copy H) recently acquired
                       by the Pierpont Morgan Library, and one on late
                       paper (1830-50?) in my 
<pb id="p11-185" n="185"/>
                       collection (Bentley’s untraced copy G?).</p>
                       <p>“Laocoon,” no. 84, p. 268. The leaf-size of
                       copy B indicates that it must be cropped
                       considerably at top, bottom, or both.</p>
                       <p>P. 269. “The original and the engraving for
                       Rees are faithful copies of the cast, showing it
                       without the hands, arms, and serpent heads.” All
                       of Blake’s versions have all hands, arms, and
                       heads, as does the Royal Academy cast at present.
                       I do not know if the cast was ever incomplete, but
                       I doubt it.</p>
                       <p>Malkin’s <hi rend="i">Father’s Memoirs</hi>,
                       no. 97, p. 285, title-page. All but first letter
                       of “<hi rend="smallcaps">Astrophel</hi>” are small capitals.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
                       Hell</hi>, no. 98, p. 290, variants. It is
                       difficult to understand how all but the second of
                       the “changes on pl. 24-25, 27 [in copies K-M] were
                       made . . . on the copperplate.” On p. 297, Bentley
                       notes that pl. 24 “was masked in printing, so that
                       nothing shows of the design in K”—which makes more
                       sense than removal from the copper. If pl. 27 of
                       untraced copy M is indeed “<hi rend="i">without</hi> 
                       the 8-line Chorus at the end” (as
                       the Linnell sale catalogue of 15 March 1918
                       states), it was probably masked in printing or
                       simply cut out of the leaf. Auction catalogues are
                       more likely to record defects for the vendor’s
                       protection against returns than to note details
                       for their own sakes.</p>
                       <p>P. 291, pl. 3 variants. “The bottom woman is on
                       a cloud in A.” The “cloud” would seem not to be a
                       variant, for it appears in copies A-E, H, I, and
                       is partly colored out only in F. It is etched in
                       the copper, as uncolored copy B shows.</p>
                       <p>P. 293, pl. 6. “Below the text there appear to
                       be non-functional lines including the letters ‘WOH...’ 
                       in mirror-writing.” Erdman’s reading (“HOW” in 
                       <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi>, p. 104) 
                       makes the letters functional,
                       but the leftward slant of the letters does suggest
                       mirror-image writing.</p>
                       <p>P. 293, pl. 10 incipit. Line break after
                       “Hell.”</p>
                       <p>P. 294, pl. 11 variants. The “stump” is
                       extended and colored like water in copy I, and the
                       “island is not <corr type="emend">distinguishable</corr> from the water” as
                       in D and both the BMPR and Newton color prints of
                       the design.</p>
                       <p>P. 295, pl. 16. The figures sit on the floor of
                       their cell, not on the “grass.”</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, no. 118, p. 312, pl.
                       8. Is one of the figures on the left a “woman”
                       (Bentley) or a man (Erdman, <hi rend="i">The
                       Illuminated Blake</hi>, p. 226)?</p>
                       <p>P. 317, pl. 38 variants. “In copy D, the man’s
                       left thumb on the woman’s left leg has been
                       extended to place it on her vagina.” The left
                       thumb has been painted in, and perhaps extended a
                       bit, but it is below her vagina and extends
                       downward along her inner thigh. Bentley does not
                       mention the man’s erect penis, visible in the
                       Harvey loose pull and copy A, obscured in B and C,
                       and painted out in D.</p>
                       <p>P. 318, p. 40 incipit. First letters are
                       capitals in “All” and “Things.”</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>, no. 122, p. 323. I
                       doubt that the “writing . . . , especially that in
                       pencil” has “faded noticeably since the facsimile
                       of 1935 was made.” The darker lines in the
                       facsimile are probably the result of the
                       photographic processes used, for the paper looks
                       darker and dirtier in this facimile than in the
                       original.</p>
                       <p>Pp. 324-32, Designs in the <hi rend="i">Notebook.</hi> 
                       Bentley follows the sequence of
                       pages as they are now bound, not the
                       reconstruction of the original order in Erdman’s
                       1973 facsimile, and gives many, but not all, of
                       the deleted emblem numbers recorded by Erdman. My
                       corrections noted here are based on a study of the
                       original manuscript.</p>
                       <p>P. 326, p. 17 of the <hi rend="i">Notebook.</hi> 
                       Line break after “find,” not
                       “can.”</p>
                       <p>P. 326, p. 19. Bentley’s transcription of the
                       lines from <hi rend="i">The Faerie Queene</hi> are
                       true to both Spenser and Blake, correcting the
                       Erdman facsimile’s “That” for “Full” and “now” for
                       “thou.”</p>
                       <p>P. 327, p. 27. The “two (?) smudged figures”
                       are part of an early version of “A Breach in a
                       City, the Morning after Battle” (two versions, one
                       formerly Robertson, the other formerly Rosenbloom,
                       collections) and “War” (Fogg Museum). It is
                       numbered 53 <hi rend="i">del</hi>, not “33.”</p>
                       <p>P. 327, p. 33. Design is numbered 11.</p>
                       <p>P. 328, p. 41. First deleted number is 37, not
                       “32.”</p>
                       <p>P. 328, p. 45. Erdman facsimile records “2” for
                       the second deleted number, not “7.” It looks like
                       9 to me.</p>
                       <p>P. 328, p. 47. Erdman facsimile records “25”
                       for the first number, not “2”; it is hard to tell
                       which is right.</p>
                       <p>P. 328, p. 49. First deleted number is 11, not
                       “4.”</p>
                       <p>P. 329, p. 55. Design is numbered 50, not
                       “5.”</p>
                       <p>P. 329, p. 58. I doubt that the design upper
                       right is “for pl. 11” of <hi rend="i">For
                       Children</hi> because it shows a figure holding on
                       to a tree. The third “undecipherable” sketch
                       (upper left) clearly shows a figure sitting
                       beneath a tree.</p>
                       <p>P. 329, p. 60. Following the deleted number
                       Blake has added “44” according to Erdman’s
                       facsimile. Could be 41.</p>
                       <p>P. 329, p. 61. The first deleted number is 29.
                       Erdman’s facsimile accurately transcribes “we,”
                       not “to,” in the quoted inscription.</p>
                       <p>P. 329, p. 63. Erdman’s facsimile records “43
                       <hi rend="i">del</hi> 45,” not “[10 del] 15.” The
                       4s are fairly clear.</p>
                       <p>P. 329, p. 64. Bentley overlooks the sketch of
                       two figures on this page.</p>
                       <p>P. 329, p. 65. Deleted number is 47.</p>
                       <p>P. 329, p. 66. Besides the profile, there is a
                       reclining figure near the center of the page.</p>
                       <p>P. 329, p. 67. Erdman’s facsimile records “41”
                       for the deleted number, not “48.” I can’t make out
                       the second digit at all.</p>
                       <p>P. 329, p. 68. No “e” in both “shouldst” in
                       quoted inscription.</p>
                       <p>P. 329, p. 69. Following the deleted number
                       Blake has added 7.</p>
                       <p>P. 330, p. 71. After 35 <hi rend="i">del</hi>
                       Erdman’s facsimile records “14.” There are two
                       numbers, but 14 may be the deleted one.</p>
                       <p>P. 330, p. 73. The deleted number is 15, not
                       “18.” In the inscription, the word is “perswade,”
                       not “persuade.”</p>
                       <p>P. 330, p. 74. The sketch for the woman “etched
                       reversed in <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (1794) pl. 33”
                       is accompanied by 
                       <pb id="p11-186" n="186"/> 
                       the (dead?) child. Bentley’s “fourth” sketch looks
                       like one figure, not two, and looks nothing like
                       “<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> . . . pl. 21” to me.</p>
                       <p>P. 330, p. 77. Erdman’s facsimile records the
                       design numbers as 9 <hi rend="i">del</hi>, 10.</p>
                       <p>P. 330, p. 79. Bentley overlooks the partially
                       erased sketch numbered 18 <hi rend="i">del</hi>,
                       12.</p>
                       <p>P. 330, p. 81. Erdman’s facsimile gives the
                       deleted number as “19,” not “14.” I can’t tell
                       which is right.</p>
                       <p>P. 330, p. 83. The design is numbered 49 
                       <hi rend="i">del</hi>, 37.</p>
                       <p>P. 331, p. 89. Bentley overlooks the faint
                       sketch numbered 21.</p>
                       <p>P. 331, p. 91. Above the other numbers is 22
                       <hi rend="i">del.</hi></p>
                       <p>P. 331, p. 94. Line break after “the,” not
                       “as.”</p>
                       <p>P. 332, p. 97. The first deleted number is
                       25.</p>
                       <p>P. 332, p. 98. I can’t find the “5” Bentley
                       records.</p>
                       <p>P. 332, p. 101. No line break in the
                       inscription.</p>
                       <p>P. 332, p. 114. Bentley overlooks the swirls on
                       this page, perhaps representing figures.</p>
                       <p>“Small Book of Designs,” no. 136, pp. 356-57.
                       The three color printed designs from 
                       <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> sold Sotheby’s London, 5
                       April 1977, lots 207, 209, 210, may have once been
                       part of one of the design books.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>, no. 137, p.
                       359. “The first five lines of text, the prelude,
                       are etched in italic, the rest in roman
                       characters.” This is backwards—the first five
                       lines are in roman, the rest in italic.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                       Experience</hi>, no. 139, p. 380, general
                       title-page. Last three letters of 
                       “<hi rend="i">Soul</hi>” are lower case italic.</p>
                       <p>P. 381, footnote 1. “The <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> 
                       plates appear to be both etched
                       and engraved but the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>
                       plates only etched.” I take this to mean that
                       there is some white line work (whether etched or
                       engraved is hard to tell in each case) on some 
                       <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> plates but none in 
                       <hi rend="i">Experience.</hi> However, there is crude
                       white line work on a number of plates in 
                       <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, most apparent on the old
                       man in “London” and the lower trunk of the tree in
                       “Human Abstract.”</p>
                       <p>P. 388, pl. 1. Leaves are around the “nude”
                       woman’s loins as well as the man’s.</p>
                       <p>P. 389, pl. 4. The vignette upper right (as
                       etched) shows a bird, not “a standing man.” In
                       copies Y and Z a standing figure is painted in the
                       lower right vignette.</p>
                       <p>P. 393, pl. 18. How can we tell that the
                       floating figure upper left is a “man” and the
                       figure lower right partly beneath the plant is a
                       “woman”? The first wears a flowing gown like the
                       “walking woman” beside her/him, and the second
                       looks no more feminine than the rising figure just
                       above.</p>
                       <p>P. 394, pl. 19. The adult leading the girls is
                       very likely a female matron, not a “man.”</p>
                       <p>P. 396, pl. 26. The lantern is in the
                       watchman’s left hand, not “fastened at the top” of
                       his staff.</p>
                       <p>P. 398, pl. 37. The <hi rend="i">falling</hi>
                       snow is “Black”—that is, the color in which the
                       plate is printed—but on the ground it is
                       white.</p>
                       <p>P. 399, pl. 39. The figure is not “wrapped
                       round” by the worm in all copies (for example, not
                       in A, B, I, K, N, Z, AA).</p>
                       <p>P. 400, pl. 42 variants. The pen &amp; ink
                       addition in copy P is “Formd,” not “Formed.” This
                       misspelling also appears on p. 388, line 5. The
                       question mark after “hand” in line 12 was also
                       erased along with “&amp; what.”</p>
                       <p>P. 401, pl. 46. How can we tell that the old
                       man is “blind”?</p>
                       <p>P. 421, copy T. A previously untraced copy of
                       “The Clod &amp; the Pebble” now in my collection
                       may have originally been part of copy T.<ref
                       target="n26" type="note">10</ref> The print now in
                       T is one of the color printed plates inserted to
                       complete the copy. Like the other hand tinted
                       prints in T, my impression is printed in
                       terra-cotta orange with an orange pen &amp; ink
                       framing line (6-7 mm. outside the plate) and
                       number (32) upper right within the frame. The
                       number indicates that this is not a separate
                       impression, and Bentley lists no other copy of the
                       book with similar frames and numbers lacking pl.
                       32. <note id="n26"><hi rend="s">10</hi> This
                       possibility was kindly suggested to me by Prof.
                       Bentley.</note></p>
                       <p>P. 429. “The electrotypes seem to be identical
                       in form with Blake’s plates except for pl. 29.”
                       There are several minor differences visible in all
                       impressions from the electrotypes I have seen:</p>
                       <p>“A Cradle Song,” line 3, “dreams”: “d”
                       missing.</p>
                       <p>“Holy Thursday,” in <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, 
                       line 4: dot of question mark
                       missing. Line 14, “rain”: “n” missing.</p>
                       <p>“Ah! Sun-Flower”: hyphen in title missing.</p>
                       <p>“London,” line 9, “Chimney-sweepers”: hyphen
                       missing.</p>
                       <p>“Infant Sorrow,” line 1: vertical of
                       exclamation mark after “groand” missing. Period at
                       end of line 4 missing.</p>
                       <p>“The School Boy,” line 29, “bless”: “e” partly
                       missing.</p>
                       <p>P. 432, no. 143. The Benn 1927 facsimile is
                       indeed of copy A, except that “To Tirzah,” “A
                       Little Boy Lost,” and “A Little Girl Lost” are
                       from copy T.</p>
                       <p>P. 437, no. 178. The colored copies of this
                       1923 facsimile follow copy T.</p>
                       <p>P. 438, no. A191. There is a revised edition of
                       1973 with a new “Publisher’s Foreword.”</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi>,
                       no. 200, p. 443, pl. b10. The engraving of a man
                       holding a compass pointed out by Michael Phillips
                       as the design from which Blake “adapted” his
                       etching is only one of many analogues.</p>
                       <p>P. 445, copies G and I. The Pierpont Morgan
                       Library sold six plates from these copies, Sotheby
                       Parke Bernet New York, 24 May 1977, lot 153. Pls.
                       a4, a6, and b12 are now in an anonymous American
                       collection; pls. a3, a9, and b12 are in my
                       collection.</p>
                       <p>P. 447. Bentley overlooks the following color
                       facsimile, apparently of copy C: <hi rend="i">There 
                       is No Natural Religion</hi> by W. Blake.
                       Privately Printed. London, Pickering &amp; Co.,
                       1886. This is clearly distinct from the Muir
                       facsimile of the same year.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>, no. 203, p. 448. The
                       twelfth drawing, formerly in the Hanley
                       collection, is now in the private collection of a
                       New York art dealer.</p>
                       <p>“To the Queen,” no. 207, p. 451, engraved title
                       to Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi> “<hi rend="i">THE</hi>,” 
                       “<hi rend="i">Illustrated by twelve
                       Etchings</hi>,” “<hi rend="i">From the
                       Original</hi>,” “<hi rend="i">OF</hi>,” and
                       “William Blake.” are all in italic. 
                       “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">A Poem</hi></hi></hi>” is in gothic
                       letters, and all but the first letters of “<hi rend="smallcaps">Grave</hi>”
                       <pb id="p11-187" n="187"/>
                       and 
                       “<hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="i">William Blake</hi></hi>” are small capitals. 
                       “<hi rend="i">BY</hi>” is in italic capitals and is on
                       a separate line.</p>
                       <p>P. 452, footnote 1. Last date should be
                       1870.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
                       Albion</hi>, no. 213, p. 469, pl. 2. Four, not
                       “five,” figures “are sporting” in the rainbow.</p>
                       <p>P. 470, pl. 4 incipit. Comma after
                       “Enslav’d.”</p>
                       <p>P. 486, no. 236. The Introduction and Notes are
                       in the same place in both editions.</p>
                       <p>P. 488, no. 249c, Muir facsimile of 
                       <hi rend="i">Visions.</hi> At least one copy (in my
                       collection) is colored after copy G (bound with
                       <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> copy J used by Muir for his
                       1884 facsimile) rather than A.</p>
                       <p>P. 490, no. 259. Also published N.Y.</p>
                       <p>P. 493, no. 287. Also printed London &amp;
                       N.Y., 1965.</p>
                       <p>P. 495, no. 303. Also printed 1935 &amp;
                       1946.</p>
                       </div3>
                       <div3>
                       <head>
                       <title>
                       <hi rend="b">PART II REPRODUCTIONS OF DRAWINGS
                       &amp; PAINTINGS</hi>
                       </title>
                       </head>
                       <p>This Part updates the similar section in
                       Bentley &amp; Nurmi. A few corrections and
                       additions (not beyond Bentley’s terminal date)
                       follow.</p>
                       <p>P. 506, no. 390. The illustrations were also
                       issued loose in a portfolio with a different
                       title-page.</p>
                       <p>P. 507, no. 398. Also printed London, 1961.</p>
                       <p>P. 508, no. 408. The illustrations were also
                       issued loose in portfolio.</p>
                       <p>Addition: <hi rend="i">William Blake. The
                       Masters 6.</hi> Ed. Geoffrey Keynes. London,
                       1965.</p>
                       </div3>
                       <div3>
                       <head>
                       <title>
                       <hi rend="b">PART III</hi>
                       <lb/>
                       <hi rend="b">COMMERCIAL BOOK ENGRAVINGS</hi>
                       </title>
                       </head>
                       <p>This is a thorough revision of the similar
                       section in Bentley &amp; Nurmi, with several new
                       titles, now all transcribed, giving much more
                       information on publication history, plate-size,
                       plate inscriptions, proofs, and other pertinent
                       matters. Some of the books with plates engraved by
                       others after Blake’s designs are simply hand-made
                       reproductions of earlier engravings and thus
                       should be categorized somewhere between the first
                       generation graphics, made from Blake’s drawings,
                       and modern photographic reproductions. For
                       example, the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
                       design in <hi rend="i">The Seraph</hi> (no. 512)
                       and the two <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> designs in
                       Hamilton’s <hi rend="i">English School</hi> (no.
                       463) are no doubt copies of the plates engraved by
                       Blake and Schiavonetti, not of the drawings.
                       Bentley has been selective in his choice of this
                       type of material, apparently including only
                       metal-plate reproductions made shortly after
                       Blake’s death and excluding various
                       nineteenth-century wood engravings after Blake’s
                       designs, such as those in Gilchrist’s 
                       <hi rend="i">Life</hi>, vol. 20 of <hi rend="i">Scribner’s
                       Monthly</hi>, or Chatto’s <hi rend="i">Treatise on
                       Wood Engraving</hi>, which are just as close to
                       the originals in the number of reproductive steps.
                       On the other hand, the Virgil illustrations in
                       Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi> and the 1843
                       <hi rend="i">Athenaeum</hi> are mentioned only in
                       passing (p. 630) even though they were printed
                       from Blake’s original blocks. There is some minor
                       inconsistency in the way modern reprints are
                       listed. For example, reproductions of the complete
                       Job series are given individual entry numbers, but
                       twentieth-century reproductions of Blair’s 
                       <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> (including two lacking the
                       text) are listed as editions under the single 
                       <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> entry number.</p>
                       <p>Corrections and additions follow. Some of the
                       latter is previously unrecorded information on
                       Blake’s plates contained in vols. II-III of 
                       <hi rend="i">William Blake: Book Illustrator</hi>, the
                       publication of which has been long delayed. One or
                       two of the many corrections I propose in Bentley’s
                       transcriptions of title-pages and plate
                       inscriptions may be due to our inspection of
                       copies that do in fact differ. In most cases,
                       however, I have checked multiple copies, including
                       some of those Bentley lists, and I doubt that I am
                       simply recording a host of variants. I have not
                       been able to compare Bentley’s information
                       directly against the following works, listed by
                       Bentley’s entry numbers: 419, 436B-D, 452B, 453D,
                       E, 454, 455, 456C, 457B-E, 462, 463, 464B, 475A,
                       C-D, 477A-D, 478, 481B, 485B, 486B, 487C, D, 492D,
                       494C, 495, 496, 497B, 498D, E, 499D, E, 511,
                       512A-B, 514B.</p>
                       <p>Allen, <hi rend="i">History of England</hi>,
                       no. 415, p. 512. Title: “parti-/ cular,” double
                       rule after “period,” and the title-page is dated
                       1798 not “1797.”</p>
                       <p>Ariosto, <hi rend="i">Orlando Furioso</hi>, no.
                       417C, p. 513. Title: comma after “Hoole,” line
                       break and rule after volume number. The design in
                       D (1799) is considerably reworked into a
                       high-finish plate.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Bellamy’s Picturesque
                       Magazine</hi>, no. 418, p. 514. Title: Line break
                       after first “AND,” all but first letters of
                       “<hi rend="smallcaps">Literary Museum</hi>” and 
                       “<hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi>” are small capitals.
                       The correct position of the plate is facing p.
                       [37] (Huntington copy) where the essay illustrated
                       begins, not “between pp. 48 and 49” (Harvard
                       copy).</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Royal Universal Family Bible</hi>,
                       no. 420, pp. 515-16. Title: “difference” in
                       thirtieth line, “Trans-/|lation” in forty-first
                       line. An impression of pl 1 in my collection, on
                       paper watermarked 1803, is in a later state. The
                       plate is cut down from 28.5 × 18.6 cm. to 25.1 ×
                       18 cm. and the inscriptions removed, probably in
                       preparation for use in another book.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Job</hi>, no. 424, p. 524. I can
                       confirm Keynes’ remark, quoted by Bentley, “that
                       the reduced-size plates were also issued
                       separately in a portfolio.” Isn’t no. 425 just the
                       N.Y. issue of no. 424? No. 431, p. 525. There is
                       also a N.Y. issue.</p>
                       <p>Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, no. 435,
                       pp. 526-31. Title of F: Period, not comma, after
                       “POEM.”</p>
                       <p>Period, not comma, after “POEM.”</p>
                       <p>No. 435K, title: “Prophetic” not “Prophet.” The
                       1808 folio is not “marked ‘Proof Copy’ on the
                       plates,” but only on the engraved title-page.
                       Engraved title-page: all but first letter of
                       “<hi rend="smallcaps">Grave</hi>” are small capitals, 
                       “<hi rend="smallcaps"><hi rend="i">William Blake</hi></hi>” is in
                       italic small capitals except for the first letters
                       in each word, and all but the first letter of
                       “Executed” are lower case.</p>
                       <p>Label in Subscribers’ copies: “<hi rend="gothic">BLAIR’S</hi>” is in
                       gothic letters, “<hi rend="i">ENGRAVED BY
                       SCHIAVONETTI</hi>” in italic capitals, dash before
                       (not after) “Price.” Phillips portrait: there are
                       other versions in the collection of Philip Hofer
                       and another in a 
<pb id="p11-188" n="188"/>
                       private British collection (Sir Geoffrey Keynes
                       tells me).</p>
                       <p>Pl. 1. The inscriptions recorded for this and
                       all other <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> plates are those
                       of the second states appearing in the 1808
                       quarto.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 3. The sketch in the Robertson catalogue,
                       no. 82, is not related to pl. 3 but may be a
                       rejected alternate design for pl. 2.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 4 inscription. “<hi rend="i">Counseller</hi>,” 
                       not “<hi rend="i">Counsellor.</hi>”</p>
                       <p>Pl. 6 inscription. “<hi rend="i">her’s</hi>,”
                       not “<hi rend="i">hers.</hi>” I have never been
                       able to locate a sketch for this plate “in the
                       Rosenwald Collection.” The Rosenwald does have,
                       however, a separate color print of the design on
                       pl. 14 of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
                       Hell</hi> which was entitled “The Soul Hovering
                       Over the Body” in the Philadelphia exhibition
                       catalogue (1939), no. 188.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 7. I have not been able to locate any
                       sketch for this plate “in the Rosenwald
                       Collection.” Ruth Fine Lehrer’s “Blake Materials
                       in the Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection,” 
                       <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 9 (Winter
                       1975-76), does not list any sketches for this or
                       the previous plate.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 8. There is a proof before inscriptions
                       except for the signatures in the Achenbach Print
                       Collection, San Francisco.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 11. I have never been able to locate a
                       “proof before the verses were added” in Keynes’
                       collection, but Sir Geoffrey does own a loose
                       impression of the first published state from the
                       1808 folio (which lacks the verses).</p>
                       <p>P. 531. “The Gambols of Ghosts” was for some
                       years on deposit at the Fitzwilliam Museum, where
                       I saw it, but is now (June 1977) for sale by a New
                       York dealer. The Princeton and Harvard copies with
                       the transcribed label are <hi rend="i">1813</hi>
                       large folios.</p>
                       <p>P. 534, F-G. The “biography of ‘William Blake’”
                       does not appear in the N.Y. edition of 1847. The
                       plates are not signed in the 1847 edition.</p>
                       <p>Bonnycastle, <hi rend="i">Introduction to
                       Mensuration</hi>, no. 436, p. 535. The lettering
                       on the BMPR proof is in the plate, not hand
                       written on the print as Bentley implies. The plate
                       was cut down for the 1787 (not first in the 1791)
                       edition. I can find no differences between second
                       edition (1787) and third edition (1791)
                       impressions that cannot be accounted for by
                       differences in inking, printing, and wear.</p>
                       <p>Boydell’s <hi rend="i">Shakespeare</hi>, no.
                       437, pp. 535-36. Title: “SERIES OF PRINTS” is in
                       roman capitals, line break after 
                       “<hi rend="i">Works</hi>,” “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">Engraved
                       from</hi></hi></hi>” in gothic letters, second letter
                       of “<hi rend="smallcaps">Co.</hi>” is a small capital, line break, rule, and
                       no period after “<hi rend="i">Cheapside</hi>,”
                       comma after “<hi rend="i">Halliwell.</hi>”</p>
                       <p>Brown, <hi rend="i">Elements of Medicine</hi>,
                       no. 438, pp. 536-37. Title: No hyphen after
                       “deduc” in first volume, periods after 
                       “<hi rend="smallcaps">Darwin</hi>” and 
                       “<hi rend="smallcaps">Zoonomia.</hi>” 
                       Plate inscription: all but the
                       first letters in names are small capitals in 
                       “<hi rend="smallcaps">John Brown, m.d.,</hi>” 
                       period after “<hi rend="i">May 1.</hi>”</p>
                       <p>Bryant, <hi rend="i">New System of
                       Mythology</hi>, no. 439, p. 537. The transcribed
                       title-page is of the second (1775) edition, not
                       the 1774 first edition as indicated. There are
                       differences in lineation, as Bentley notes, and
                       “INDOSCYTHAE” is not hyphenated in the first
                       edition. In both editions there is a comma after
                       “OR,” “LELEGES” has but two Ls, and there is a
                       line break after “Charing-cross.” In the second
                       edition, the plate at the end of vol. II has the
                       outer frame removed.</p>
                       <p>Burger, <hi rend="i">Leonora</hi>, no. 440, p.
                       537. Title: single rule after “BURGER.”</p>
                       <p>Catullus, <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, no. 441, p.
                       539. Title: colon after “NEPOS” in vol. I, period
                       in vol. II. “<hi rend="i">March 19</hi>” in plate
                       imprint.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Prologue and Characters of
                       Chaucer’s Pilgrims</hi>, no. 443, p. 540. Title:
                       “<hi rend="i">PRICE TWO SHILLINGS AND
                       SIXPENCE</hi>” is in italic capitals, date has
                       three periods—“M.DCCC.XII.”</p>
                       <p>Commins, <hi rend="i">Elegy</hi>, no. 444, p.
                       540. Title: colon after “<hi rend="i">Tho</hi>”
                       below “<hi rend="i">s.</hi>” No period at end of
                       quoted verse, “<hi rend="i">Street, Strand.</hi>”
                       at end of plate imprint.</p>
                       <p>Cumberland, <hi rend="i">An Attempt to Describe
                       Hafod</hi>, no. 445, pp. 540-41. Title: Last
                       letter in “<hi rend="smallcaps">DEVIL’s</hi>” 
                       is a small capital. Bentley
                       comments that, “since pl. 2-3, 5-11, 22 signed
                       with some variant of ‘Engraved by G:C:’ in
                       Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi>
                       (1796) exhibit [like the <hi rend="i">Hafod</hi>]
                       this eccentric, sinister ‘g,’ it seems likely that
                       Cumberland too used this ‘g.’ (Otherwise, we must
                       assume that Blake lettered the plates signed
                       ‘Engraved by G:C:’).” I think it is very likely
                       that Blake did indeed do all the lettering for
                       Cumberland on the <hi rend="i">Thoughts on
                       Outline</hi> plates. The inscriptions on the
                       “G:C:” plates not only have the leftward serif on
                       the “g,” but all the letters are formed the same
                       as on Blake’s signed plates in 
                       <hi rend="i">Thoughts</hi> [compare illus. 1 &amp; 2]. 
                       I doubt that Cumberland had any skill at writing
                       backwards—witness his difficulties with his “New
                       Mode of Printing”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27"
type="note">11</ref>—and 
                       thus had to have Blake do all the
                       lettering for him. It is of course possible that
                       Blake engraved the lettering on the 
                       <hi rend="i">Hafod</hi> map but not the map itself. 
                       <note id="n27"><hi rend="s">11</hi> See <hi rend="i">A
                       New Review</hi> . . . <hi rend="i">for the year
                       1784</hi>, ed. Henry Maty, 6 (1784), 318-19, and
                       Cumberland’s letter to his brother suggesting a
                       counterproofing method to reverse his backwards
                       printing, both rpt. in <hi rend="i">The Visionary
                       Hand</hi>, pp. 11-14.</note></p>
                       <p>Cumberland, <hi rend="i">Outlines of the
                       Antients</hi>, no. 446, pp. 541-42. Title of A: no
                       comma after “CUMBERLAND.” The “variant titles” in
                       B are in the table of contents; the plates are the
                       same as in A.</p>
                       <p>Cumberland, <hi rend="i">Thoughts on
                       Outline</hi>, no. 447, pp. 542-43. Title: line
                       break after “DESIGNS OF,” semicolon after
                       “COMMONS.” The quoted “legend” is all in italic.
                       Bentley reports that the BMPR has “proofs of pl.
                       2-24.” In a thorough search I have been able to
                       find only the following related to Blake’s plates,
                       other than loose impressions of the published
                       plates: pl. 16, a tinted drawing of the design,
                       with inscriptions by Cumberland; pl. 18, tinted
                       drawing; pl. 19, tinted impression, state
                       undetermined; pl. 23, tinted drawing.</p>
                       <p>Dante, <hi rend="i">Illustrations of</hi>, no.
                       448, pp. 544-46. Title: double quotation marks
                       around “<hi rend="i">Illustrations of / the Book
                       of Job</hi>,” line break after “sat,” all but the
                       first letters of “<hi rend="smallcaps">Cary’s Dante</hi>” 
                       are small capitals. In the quoted letter to Linnell of 30
                       Dec. 1856, J. H. Chance mentions “Two proofs of
                       Emmaus.” This is no doubt Linnell’s mezzotint, 
                       <pb id="p11-189" n="189"/> 
                       “The Journey to Emmaus,”
                       the published state of which bears an imprint
                       dated 17 June 1839. “Proof” in Chance’s letter may
                       mean no more than “impression.”</p>
                       <p>Pl. 1. The inscription is scratched on the
                       plate in mirror-image writing, and no doubt was
                       intended for re-engraving right way round (i.e.,
                       reversed in the copper) before publication.
                       Bentley states that “there are proofs of each
                       [Dante plate] in the BMPR,” but I have found
                       proofs of only three plates, the other four being
                       published states. None of the plates were
                       completed before Blake’s death.</p>
                       <p>Darwin, <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden</hi>, no.
                       450, pp. 546-47. General title of A-B: single rule
                       after “CHURCHYARD,” “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b">Entered at
                       Stationers Hall</hi></hi>” in gothic letters.</p>
                       <p>General title of C: rule and line break before
                       “MDCCXCV.”</p>
                       <p>Pl. 1. The rain-god <hi rend="i">does</hi>
                       appear in Fuseli’s original sketch, but he is
                       smaller than in Blake’s rendering and his arms are
                       at a 45° angle.</p>
                       <p>Pls. 2-5. There are imprints reading 
                       “<hi rend="i">1</hi> [<hi rend="i">2, 3, 4</hi>]. 
                       <hi rend="i">London, Published Dec<hi rend="s">r</hi>.
                       1<hi rend="s">st</hi>. 1791, by J. Johnson, 
                       S<hi rend="s">t</hi>. Paul’s Church Yard.</hi>” This is
                       trimmed off in all copies of pl. 2 I have seen
                       except one at Princeton in which the binder folded
                       the lower quarter of the plate before trimming
                       text pages. In B, there <hi rend="i">is</hi> a
                       date on pl. 1 (same as in A).</p>
                       <p>Pl. 6. Another proof is in the collection of
                       Raymond Lister. These five proofs, all lacking the
                       same considerable amount of finishing lines in the
                       design, have various amounts of lettering from
                       signatures only to full inscriptions as published.
                       In D, Bentley believes that the plates (except for
                       one additional illustration) “were evidently
                       commissioned and executed at the same time as
                       those for the first edition,” presumably because
                       the same dates appear on these reduced plates.
                       However, it seems to have been a common practice
                       in the eighteenth century to retain original
                       imprint dates when reissuing the same
                       illustrations, even if they are printed from new
                       copperplates. And I doubt that even Joseph Johnson
                       was prescient enough in 1791 to know that he would
                       be publishing an octavo edition of Darwin eight
                       years later.</p>
                       <p>Donne, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi>, no.
                       A450, pp. 548-49. Title: “<hi rend="i">Anno</hi>”
                       is in italic letters. That the previously
                       unidentified proof in the BMPR [illus. 3] was
                       intended for Bell’s Poets is certain because of
                       the border design; that it was to illustrate the
                       Donne volume is somewhat less certain. Another
                       possibility is that it was meant for the first
                       Milton volume in the series; for the published
                       plate therein, after Mortimer’s design, has the
                       same subject as this proof [illus. 4].</p>
                       <p>Emlyn, <hi rend="i">Proposition</hi>, no. 452,
                       pp. 550-51. Title of A: line break after “FOR,”
                       semi-colon after “CHARING CROSS,” period after
                       date. Bentley rejects Gibson &amp; Minnick’s
                       contention that the plate Blake signed in 1781 was
                       “reworked, rather than re-engraved entirely” for
                       the 1797 edition. I tend to agree with Gibson
                       &amp; Minnick. The differences in the feathers
                       cited by Bentley can be explained as the common
                       practice of reworking areas that printed weakly in
                       earlier editions. Two bits of evidence suggest
                       that Blake’s plate was indeed reworked and cut
                       down. A fragment of a semi-circular measurement
                       line (upper left) still appears on the plate even
                       though it no longer has any function. This can be
                       most easily exlained as an oversight in reworking
                       the plate; it would be odd to retain an
                       unnecessary line on a new plate. More convincing
                       evidence is provided by five tiny dots. In the
                       1781 impressions, dots are clearly visible in the
                       exact centers of the four half-circles that
                       terminate two pad-like elements of the column’s
                       base. These were no doubt made by the fixed foot
                       of the compass used to mechanically draw the
                       half-circles (yes, Blake <hi rend="i">did</hi> use
                       compasses). On the left end of the lower pad are
                       two dots, probably made by the need to replace the
                       compass foot in a second position in order to get
                       the semi-circle right. All these dots—including
                       the extra one lower left in exactly the same
                       place—also appear in the 1797 plate. An
                       “accidental” (to borrow a bibliographic term) of
                       this sort is a far better indication that two
                       impressions are from the same copperplate than the
                       “substantive” elements of design which receive
                       careful attention in reworking a plate.</p>
                       <p>Enfield, <hi rend="i">The Speaker</hi>, no.
                       453, pp. 551-52. Title of A: the lineation follows
                       the Bodleian copy. The BM and American Blake
                       Foundation copies differ in lineation. There is
                       also an unillustrated edition of 1786.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 1. The BMPR has a proof before letters,
                       with the face of the winged figure visible rather
                       than covered with hair, but I have never been able
                       to find “a sketch.” There is a drawing by Stothard
                       illustrating <hi rend="i">Richard III</hi>, but it
                       shows Richard tossing on his bed in his tent and
                       is totally unlike Blake’s plate. In the W. E. Moss
                       sale, Sotheby’s, 2 March 1937, lot 232, were the
                       “Original Sketches by Stothard, for the re-working
                       of the 3rd state” (?), and in his 1921 
                       <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi>, p. 226, Keynes records
                       that “Stothard’s original sketch for the design”
                       was then in Moss’s collection, but I have not been
                       able to locate any of these. Bentley notes that
                       the plate was “touched up” in the 1795 edition,
                       but I believe wear and printing differences can
                       account for the variations.</p>
                       <p>Euler, <hi rend="i">Elements of Algebra</hi>,
                       no. 454, p. 553, pl. 1 inscription. Double comma
                       under “<hi rend="i">r</hi>” in 
                       “<hi rend="i">Esq<hi rend="s">r</hi>,,.</hi>”</p>
                       <p>Fenning &amp; Collyer, <hi rend="i">New System
                       of Geography</hi>, no. 455, p. 554, pl. 2 imprint.
                       “<hi rend="i">Pauls Church Yard</hi>” is in
                       italic. The “reference beside the proof” of pl. 1
                       is in pencil.</p>
                       <p>Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Hesiod</hi>, no. 456, pp.
                       556-60. Title of A: 
                       <pb id="p11-190" n="190"/>
                       <figure n="BlakeAfterStothard.11.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="862">
						   <head>3 Proof of an engraving intended for 
						   <hi rend="i">Bell’s Edition</hi> [of] <hi rend="i">The
						   Poets of Great Britain</hi>, 1778-84.</head>
						   <figDesc>Blake after Thomas Stothard, 20 × 14.5
						   cm. British Museum.</figDesc>
                       </figure>
                       <pb id="p11-191" n="191"/>
                       <figure n="HallAfterMortimer.11.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="845">
						   <head>4 Engraved title-page to <hi rend="i">The
						   Poetical Works of John Milton</hi>, Vol. I, 1779,
						   in <hi rend="i">Bell’s Edition</hi> [of] 
						   <hi rend="i">The Poets of Great Britain.</hi></head>
						   <figDesc>John Hall after John Hamilton Mortimer.
						   10.5 × 6.1 cm. Author’s Collection.</figDesc>
                       </figure>
                       <pb id="p11-192" n="192"/> 
                       the double rule after “BLAKE” is actually the frame
                       surrounding the title. The 24 
                       <hi rend="i">Hesiod</hi> drawings in “Grey wash” (Metropolitan
                       Museum) are very likely copies after the
                       engravings. A drawing in the BMPR may be an
                       alternate for pl. 6. I have never been able to
                       locate the proofs in the Bodleian, although
                       several people (including Bentley) tell me they
                       have seen them there in the past.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 3. The two drawings formerly in the Powney
                       collection, both alternates very different from
                       the published version, were offered for sale by
                       the Heim Gallery, London, spring 1976, catalogue
                       nos. 18, 19.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 6. There is a drawing in the
                       Fitzwilliam.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 7. One of the Powney drawings was offered
                       for sale by the Heim Gallery, spring 1976,
                       catalogue no. 20.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 12. There are three related sheets of
                       studies in the BMPR.</p>
                       <p>Pls. 18, 22. The Princeton sketches are very
                       likely copies after the engravings.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 32. The Powney drawing (not “draft”) was
                       offered for sale by the Heim Gallery, spring 1976,
                       catalogue no. 22.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 33. A variant drawing from the Powney
                       collection was offered for sale by the Heim
                       Gallery, spring 1976, catalogue no. 23.</p>
                       <p>An unpublished design showing Rhea consulting
                       with Uranus and Terra was in the Heim sale,
                       catalogue no. 21. I do not know the present
                       whereabouts of any of these Powney-Heim
                       drawings.</p>
                       <p>In the Bell edition (B), the original imprints
                       have been removed from the plates.</p>
                       <p>Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi>, no. 457, pp.
                       560-63. Title of A: ampersand, not “AND,” after
                       “REES.”</p>
                       <p>1879 edition (C): there is an edition of 1885
                       by Seely &amp; Co. containing the 
                       <hi rend="i">Hesiod</hi> as well as the 
                       <hi rend="i">Iliad.</hi> The title suggests that the 
                       <hi rend="i">Hesiod</hi> also appeared in the 1879
                       edition.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 2 inscription. Period after “B.1.” The
                       Chicago Art Institute sketch is probably a copy
                       after the engraving; the sketch formerly in the
                       Powney collection is now in my possession.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 3. I have not been able to find any “proof”
                       in the BMPR. A variant sketch is in University
                       College, London.</p>
                       <p>Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Naval Pillar</hi>, no.
                       458, p. 564. There are six related sketches in the
                       Rosenwald collection, two of which are close to
                       pl. 1.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">12</ref>
                       <note id="n28"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Repro. 
                       <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 9 (Winter 1975-76),
                       82.</note></p>
                       <p>Fuseli, <hi rend="i">Lectures on Painting</hi>,
                       no. 459, p. 564, pl. 1 inscription. 
                       “<hi rend="i">Ancora.</hi>” A proof before letters except
                       signatures is in Keynes’ collection.</p>
                       <p>Gay, <hi rend="i">Fables</hi>, no. 460, pp.
                       564-65. Title: “<hi rend="i">Printed for John
                       Stockdale, Piccadilly</hi>” (not all capitals).
                       There is a proof of pl. 2 in the BMPR, but the
                       other loose impressions are in the published
                       state.</p>
                       <p>Gough, <hi rend="i">Sepulchral Monuments</hi>,
                       no. 461, pp. 566-68. There is a variant title to
                       “PART I,” lacking the volume designation, in my
                       collection.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 10. Proof before letters in the collection
                       of Raymond Lister.</p>
                       <p>For some plates there is only one proof
                       impression (not “three to five”) in the
                       Bodleian.</p>
                       <p>Greco, <hi rend="i">Mrs. Q</hi>, no. 462, p.
                       568, pl. 1. All inscriptions are in italic. Comma
                       after “<hi rend="i">1820</hi>,” period after 
                       “<hi rend="i">Pancras.</hi>” The prints in Greco’s book
                       are in the second state with some reworking of the
                       aquatint in the woman’s hair.</p>
                       <p>Hartley, <hi rend="i">Observations on Man</hi>,
                       no. 464, p. 570. Title of A: “<hi rend="smallcaps">y</hi>” 
                       in “<hi rend="smallcaps">By</hi> DAVID” is
                       a small capital, no line division after “Rev.” or
                       “<hi rend="smallcaps">Pistorius,</hi>” 
                       all but the first letter of “Rector
                       of” lower case, all but “I” of “Island” lower case
                       in “in the Island of.” Issue A is a quarto, B an
                       octavo.</p>
                       <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>, no. 465, p.
                       571. Title: all but first letter of 
                       “<hi rend="i"><hi rend="smallcaps">Esq.</hi></hi>” 
                       are small capitals. There are two
                       states of pls. 1-3. The second states appear in
                       some copies with the regular title-page as well as
                       the Princeton variant noted by Bentley.</p>
                       <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of
                       Ballads</hi>, no. 466, pp. 572-73. Title: all but
                       the first letter of “<hi rend="smallcaps">Esq.</hi>” 
                       are small capitals,
                       “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b">Chichester</hi></hi>” in gothic
                       letters.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 1. I have not been able to find “a proof
                       before imprint . . . in the BMPR,” although there
                       is a loose impression of the published state.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 4. Sketches appear on pp. 6 &amp; 92 of the
                       <hi rend="i">Notebook.</hi></p>
                       <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>,
                       no. 467, p. 575, pl. 1. A sketch by Flaxman is in
                       the Rosenwald Collection.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28"
type="note" n="12b">12</ref> 
                       The reason for
                       Flaxman sketching a design attributed on the plate
                       to Thomas Hayley is explained by W. Hayley’s
                       letter to Flaxman of 21 Dec. 1799: “You I know
                       will have the Goodness to retouch for Him [Tom]
                       his Demosthenes in such a manner, that it may form
                       an engrav’d outline, &amp; yet still remain very
                       fairly his own design” (<hi rend="i">Blake
                       Records</hi>, p. 62).</p>
                       <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Life of Cowper</hi>, no.
                       468, pp. 576-77. Title of A: no comma after
                       “LETTER,” single rule after the 5-line motto, 
                       “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b">Chichester</hi></hi>” in gothic letters. Title
                       of B: “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b">Chichester</hi></hi>” in gothic
                       letters, “<hi rend="i">PRINTED BY J.
                       SEAGRAVE</hi>” in italic.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 4. A second state appears in the second
                       edition, and a proof of an intermediate state (on
                       a sheet with the typography of the first edition)
                       is in Keynes’ collection.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 6. There are drawings at Princeton (by
                       Blake of Hayley’s own version),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29"
type="note">13</ref> 
                       Harvard (one by Blake after
                       Flaxman’s design, and another by Blake of Hayley’s
                       version), and the Berg Collection of the New York
                       Public Library (an alternate version by Flaxman).
                       According to Charles Ryskamp,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30"
type="note">14</ref> 
                       there is yet another drawing
                       of Cowper’s monument (perhaps by Blake) in the
                       collection of James Osborne. The weak sketch of
                       Cowper (perhaps by Blake) in the Widener
                       Collection, Harvard, is probably after Romney’s
                       portrait, not Lawrence’s. Keynes, <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi> 
                       (1921), reports proofs in his
                       collection of pls. 3 &amp; 4 (the intermediate
                       state noted above), not pl. 6. 
                       <note id="n29"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Repro. <hi rend="i">Princeton
                       University Library Chronicle</hi>, 24 (1962),
                       facing p. 3.</note>
                       <note id="n30"><hi rend="s">14</hi> “Blake’s 
                       Drawings of Cowper’s Monument,”
                       <hi rend="i">Princeton University Library
                       Chronicle</hi>, 24 (1962), 27-31.</note></p>
                       <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Life of Romney</hi>, no.
                       469, p. 577. Title: line break before “GEORGE,”
                       comma after “ROMNEY,” double rule and line break
                       after 10-line motto, double rule before 
                       “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b">Chichester.</hi></hi>”</p>
                       <pb id="p11-193" n="193"/>
                       <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Little Tom the
                       Sailor</hi>, no. 470, pp. 577-78. Title and
                       imprint: the periods after 
                       “<hi rend="i">Sailor</hi>” and “<hi rend="i">1800</hi>” appear
                       in the Walker-Muir facsimile, but not in the
                       original.</p>
                       <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Triumphs of Temper</hi>,
                       no. 471, p. 578. Title of A: no line breaks after
                       “TRIUMPHS” or before “TEMPER,” “<hi rend="smallcaps">of</hi>” 
                       between the two in small capitals, comma after “HAYLEY.” Title
                       of B: corrections to A given above, plus “y” in
                       “By WILLIAM” is lower case, “Esqr.” after
                       “HAYLEY,” “Mitate” (“Mirate” in A), 
                       “<hi rend="i">Dante, Inferno, Canto</hi>” in italic, comma
                       after “CORRECTED.” I suspect that there is no true
                       “large paper” issue. All were probably issued on
                       the same tall sheets and small paper copies have
                       simply been cut down.</p>
                       <p>Henry, <hi rend="i">Memoirs of Albert de
                       Haller</hi>, no. 472, p. 579, pl. 1 inscription.
                       No period after “<hi rend="i">d.</hi>”</p>
                       <p>Hoare, <hi rend="i">Academic
                       Correspondence</hi>, no. 473, p. 580. Title: 
                       “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b">London</hi></hi>” is in gothic letters.</p>
                       <p>Hoare, <hi rend="i">Inquiry</hi>, no. 474, p.
                       581, pl. 1 inscriptions. Period after 
                       “<hi rend="i">sc</hi>,” comma after “<hi rend="i">Street.</hi>”</p>
                       <p>Hogarth, <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, no. 475, pp.
                       581-84. Title of B: all quotation marks are
                       double, no line break after “Virtue,” comma after
                       “JAMES’S.” The open letter state of Blake’s plate
                       appears in the Metropolitan Museum of Art and
                       Princeton copies of the 1790 edition and is thus
                       the first state published in a book. I have been
                       able to find only two later states: filled letters
                       in most copies of the 1790 (A) edition and all
                       copies examined (about 15) of the undated Boydell
                       edition (B); the “restored” (perhaps “ruined”
                       would be more accurate) plate in Heath’s edition
                       of 1822 (C). All subsequent changes in this plate,
                       probably printed more often than any other
                       engraving by Blake, can be attributed to excessive
                       wear. The impression in the 1965 portfolio (I) is
                       a mere ghost of what began as one of Blake’s
                       finest reproductive prints.</p>
                       <p>Hunter, <hi rend="i">Historical Journal</hi>,
                       no. 476, pp. 584-85. Title of A: line break and
                       rule after “1792,” rule and line break before
                       “LONDON.” Title of B: middle word in “PHILLIP 
                       <hi rend="smallcaps">and</hi> KING” is in small capitals, 
                       as are all letters in
                       “<hi rend="i"><hi rend="smallcaps">by Iohn Hunter , Esq<hi rend="s">r</hi>.</hi></hi>” 
                       except first letters of second,
                       third, and fourth words.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 1 inscription. “<hi rend="smallcaps">of</hi>” is in small capitals,
                       colon under “<hi rend="i">r</hi>” in 
                       “<hi rend="i">Nov<hi rend="s">r</hi>:</hi>,” comma after 
                       “<hi rend="i">15.</hi>” In the octavo edition (B), the
                       plate is in a second state, with smaller letters
                       in the title inscription, now 9 mm. closer to the
                       design than in the quarto (A).</p>
                       <p>Josephus, <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, no. 477, pp.
                       587-88. Title of E: comma after “Philo.”</p>
                       <p>Pl. 2. There are two states of the published
                       plate. The second, appearing in the third and
                       subsequent issues, has new finishing work in the
                       design.</p>
                       <p>Kimpton, <hi rend="i">History of the
                       Bible</hi>, no. 478, pp. 590-91, pls. 1-3
                       inscriptions. The words and numbers Bentley
                       records as capitals are small capitals except for
                       the first letter in each word and “XIII” on pl. 1.
                       On all three published plates the ornamental
                       frames and inscriptions were changed for
                       publication in the <hi rend="i">Josephus.</hi></p>
                       <p>Pl. 4. “<hi rend="i">Grinke</hi>” not 
                       “<hi rend="i">Grinka.</hi>”</p>
                       <p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi>, no. 480,
                       pp. 592-93. Title of B: period after
                       “CHURCH-YARD.” Title of C: double rule after
                       “EDITION.” The second state of the plate, with
                       <corr type="emend">additional</corr> hatching on the seated figure’s arms and
                       legs and on the floor, appears in some copies of
                       the 1794 edition (Bodleian, British Library,
                       Preston Blake Library, and the Bentley, Keynes,
                       and Essick collections). The “proofs” in the
                       Rosenwald Collection are all first states with
                       variations in inking and wear.</p>
                       <p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on
                       Physiognomy</hi>, no. 481, pp. 593-94. Title of A:
                       colon after “LONDON.”</p>
                       <p>Pl. 2 inscription. All but first letter of
                       “<hi rend="smallcaps">Democritus</hi>” are small capitals.</p>
                       <p>Malkin, <hi rend="i">Father’s Memoirs</hi>, no.
                       482, pp. 595-96. Title: line break after
                       “ROW.”</p>
                       <p>Pl. 1 inscription. Periods after initials in
                       “<hi rend="i">R. H. Cromek.</hi>” Above the design
                       and to the right is “<hi rend="i">Page</hi>”
                       (visible in the Princeton and Essick copies in
                       boards). I believe that only one of the two loose
                       impressions in BMPR is a proof before letters.
                       There are related drawings in the BMPR (two women
                       and a child) and in the collection of Donald
                       Davidson (child’s face).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
type="note">15</ref>
                       <note id="n31"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Repro. <hi rend="i">Blake
                       Newsletter</hi>, 7 (Summer, 1973), 6.</note></p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi>, no. 483, p.
                       596, pl. 1 inscription. Small capital 
                       “<hi rend="smallcaps">r</hi>” in 
                       “M<hi rend="s"><hi rend="smallcaps">r</hi></hi>.”</p>
                       <p>Mora, <hi rend="i">Meditaciones Poeticas</hi>,
                       no. 484, p. 596. The imprint and Blake’s signature
                       also appear on pl. 1 (visible in the Gordon N. Ray
                       copy on deposit in the Pierpont Morgan
                       Library).</p>
                       <p>Pl. 1 inscription. “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b">por</hi></hi>” is
                       in gothic letters.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine</hi>, nos.
                       485-87, pp. 597-603.</p>
                       <p>There are two states of all plates.</p>
                       <p>No. 485, A, title: all but first letter of 
                       <corr type="emend">“<hi rend="i"><hi rend="smallcaps">London</hi></hi>” are</corr>  in
small capitals.</p>
                       <p>Pls. 1, 2. There are proofs before letters in
                       the BMPR.</p>
                       <p>No. 486, iv.A, title: period after
                       “SMOLLETT.”</p>
                       <p>There is a title-page for Smollett’s 
                       <hi rend="i">Launcelot Greaves</hi> dated 1792 (this
                       should be No. 486 iv.C in Bentley’s
                       reckoning).</p>
                       <p>Pl. 1. There are two proofs before letters in
                       the BMPR.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 3. There is a proof before letters in the
                       BMPR.</p>
                       <p>No. 487, A, title: line break after “Third,” no
                       comma or line break after “Fourth.”</p>
                       <p>Pls. 1, 2. There are proofs before letters in
                       the BMPR.</p>
                       <p>Olivier, <hi rend="i">Fencing
                       Familiarized</hi>, no. 488, pp. 602-03. Title:
                       “OLIVIER” (not “OLIVER”), two periods after 
                       “<hi rend="i">Delectatione.</hi>”</p>
                       <p>Pl. 1 inscription. Two commas beneath 
                       “<hi rend="i">e</hi>” in 
                       “<hi rend="i">4<hi rend="s">e</hi></hi>,,”,“<hi rend="i">quarte</hi>” 
                       (not “<hi rend="i">quatre</hi>”).</p>
                       <p>Rees, <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia</hi>, no. 489,
                       pp. 603-05. Title: “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b">Arts. Sciences,
                       and Literature</hi></hi>” is in gothic 
                       <pb id="p11-194" n="194"/>
                       <figure n="CyclopaediaSketch.11.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="538">
						   <head>5 Blake’s pencil sketch, vouched for by
						   Frederick Tatham, of designs in Abraham Rees, 
						   <hi rend="i">The Cyclopaedia</hi>, Plates Vol. II,
						   1820, section on “Brasso Relievo.”</head>
						   <figDesc>Sketch lower left is for pl. IV (engraved
						   by Blake); top for pl. I (unsigned); lower right
						   for pl. II (engraved by William Bond). 31.8 × 28.3
						   cm. Untraced.</figDesc>
                       </figure> 
                       letters, period after “VOL. I.” Bentley
                       has not transcribed the following after “BROWN”:
                       Paternoster-Row, / F. C. AND J. RIVINGTON, A.
                       STRAHAN, PAYNE AND FOSS.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 2. An untraced drawing [illus. 5] for the
                       three figures lower left was in the Robertson
                       sale, Sotheby’s 22 July 1949, lot 68A. This
                       drawing also contains sketches of figures on pls.
                       I (unsigned) and II (signed <hi rend="i">Bond
                       sculp.</hi>) of “BASSO RELIEVO.” Perhaps William
                       Blake had something to do with the execution of
                       these plates as well.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 3. A proof of the lower portion of the
                       design, reportedly from a different plate, is in
                       the Pierpont Morgan Library.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">16</ref>
                       <note id="n32"><hi rend="s">16</hi> According to Ryskamp [and Lange]—see
                       footnote 8.</note></p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Remember Me!</hi>, no. 490, pp.
                       605-06. Title: “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b">OR</hi></hi>” and 
                       “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b">London</hi></hi>” are in gothic letters, as is
                       “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b">Presented by</hi></hi>” 
                       in the frontispiece inscription.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 1. A proof before letters is in the
                       BMPR.</p>
                       <p>Ritson, <hi rend="i">Select Collection of
                       English Songs</hi>, no. 491, pp. 606-07. The
                       signatures on the BMPR proofs are in the plate,
                       not “inscribed in ink.”</p>
                       <p>Salzmann, <hi rend="i">Elements of
                       Morality</hi>, no. 492, pp. 607-08. There are at
                       least two, and in most cases three, states of the
                       plates: first, 1791 edition; second, 1792; third,
                       1799 and subsequent editions. Title of A: line
                       break before “VOL.” Title of E: comma after
                       “MORALITY.” The designer is Daniel Nicolas
                       Chodowiecki (1726-1801), not “David
                       Chodowiecki.”</p>
                       <p>Salzmann, <hi rend="i">Gymnastics for
                       Youth</hi>, no. 493, p. 610. Title: 
                       “<hi rend="smallcaps">and</hi>” is in
                       small capitals, rule and line break before 
                       “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b">London</hi></hi>” which is in gothic letters.
                       The proofs in the BMPR are of pls. 2, 3, 5, 6,
                       8-10. Only the last is “reversed.”</p>
                       <p>Pl. 10 inscription. No period after 
                       “<hi rend="i">Swimming.</hi>”</p>
                       <p>Scott, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi>, no.
                       494, p. 611. Title: period after “ESQ.” There are
                       proofs before letters in the BMPR (pls. 1-3) as
                       well as those in the Rosenwald Collection (pls. 2,
                       3 only).</p>
                       <p>Seally &amp; Lyons, <hi rend="i">Complete
                       Geographical Dictionary</hi>, no. 495, p. 612.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 1 inscription. “<hi rend="i">23</hi>” not
                       “<hi rend="i">3.</hi>”</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Seaman’s Recorder</hi>, no. 496,
                       p. 614, pl. 2 inscription Period after
                       “NELSON.”</p>
                       <p>Bentley records Keynes’ objections to the
                       attribution of these plates to Blake. Erdman has
                       also questioned it,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33"
type="note">17</ref> and one can only hope that Blake did not
                       do such miserable work late in his career—in spite
                       of the prima facie evidence of his name on each
                       plate. The problem is not simply that the
                       engravings are bad, but that they are bad in a way
                       not at all characteristic of Blake in the last
                       years of his life when he brought his own very
                       recognizable style even to small plates for
                       ephemeral publications like <hi rend="i">Remember
                       Me!</hi> and a calling card for Cumberland. 
                       <note id="n33"><hi rend="s">17</hi><hi rend="i"> English
                       Language Notes</hi>, 9 (1971), supplement 1, pp.
                       27-28.</note></p>
                       <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Dramatic Works</hi>,
                       no. 497, p. 614. Title of A: line break after
                       “REVISED,” double rule and line break before
                       “PRINTED.”</p>
                       <p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Plays of</hi>, no.
                       498, p. 619, pl. 1. Blake’s squared drawing of
                       Fuseli’s design is in the Rosenwald
                       Collection.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 2. A proof before letters except for
                       signatures is bound in an extra-illustrated copy
                       of the 1805 ten-volume edition in the Huntington
                       Library.</p>
                       <p>Stedman, <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi>, no. 499,
                       pp. 621-23. Title of A: “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b">Revolted
                       Negroes</hi></hi>”, “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b">Surinam</hi></hi>”, 
                       “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b">By</hi></hi>” (before 
                       “CAPT<hi rend="s">N</hi>.”), and “London” are in gothic letters, 
                       “ <hi rend="i">WILD COAST of</hi>” in italic, period
                       after “<hi rend="i">Guinea.</hi>” Title of B: 
                       “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b">London</hi></hi>” is in gothic letters.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 1 inscription. Lower case 
                       “<hi rend="i">a</hi>” in “<hi rend="i">armed.</hi>”</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Vetusta Monumenta</hi>, no. 503,
                       pp. 626-27. Title: comma after “NICHOLS.”</p>
                       <p>Pls. 5, 6 inscriptions. No periods at end of
                       each. There are two drawings each for pls. 3 and 5
                       in the Royal Society of Antiquaries, but they are
                       not “duplicates.” One drawing for pl. 3 is of
                       figs. A-C, the other for fig. D; one for pl. 5 is
                       of King Sebert, the other of King Henry III. The
                       drawings for pl. 5 in the Bodleian are similarly
                       divided between the two kings.</p>
                       <p>Virgil, <hi rend="i">Pastorals</hi>, no. 504,
                       pp. 627-30. Title: semi-colon and no line break
                       after “Whittaker and 
<pb id="p11-195" n="195"/>
                       Co.” For the brief biographies inscribed on pls.
                       1-4 Bentley does not give the lineation.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 1 inscription. Comma after 
                       “<hi rend="i">Poet.</hi>”</p>
                       <p>Pl. 2. A proof lacking letters and some work in
                       the design is in the BMPR.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 3 inscription. 
                       “<hi rend="i">Cleopatria</hi>” [sic] not 
                       “<hi rend="i">Cleopatra.</hi>”</p>
                       <p>Pl. 4 inscription. Period after 
                       “<hi rend="i">Tyrannically.</hi>”</p>
                       <p>Pl. 5 inscription. Line break before
                       “FRONTISPIECE.”</p>
                       <p>Pl. 25 inscription. Line break after
                       “INTRODUCTORY.”</p>
                       <p>Pl. 26 inscription. Period after 
                       “<hi rend="i">Æra</hi>” and at end.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 27 inscription. Double quotation marks
                       around “<hi rend="i">De Rerum Naturâ</hi>,” “B.C.”
                       are capitals (not small capitals) in both
                       cases.</p>
                       <p>There are proofs of Blake’s untrimmed wood
                       engravings in the Rosenwald Collection (nos. 2-5,
                       6-9) and the Pierpont Morgan Library (nos. 6-9).
                       Fine impressions from the original blocks of the
                       wood engravings were issued loose in portfolio in
                       1977 by British Museum Publications, Ltd.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Wedgwood’s Catalogue</hi>, no.
                       511, p. 631. Besides those noted by Bentley, pls.
                       8 and 16 in the BMPR are also proofs.</p>
                       <p>Whitaker, <hi rend="i">The Seraph</hi>, no.
                       512, p. 633. Title of C: quoted lines are in roman
                       letters.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">The Wit’s Magazine</hi>, no. 513,
                       pp. 634-35. Title: the “s” of “WIT’s” is not
                       raised in some copies (Essick [Illus. 6] and
                       Princeton), “COMPLEAT” not “COMPLETE” and line
                       break before “Printed” in all copies examined,
                       period under “o” of “N<hi rend="s">O</hi>.” in
                       some copies (Essick) [Illus. 6].</p>
                       <p>Pl. 1. Unfortunately, there is no proof “in the
                       collection of Mr. Robert N. Essick.” The error is
                       mine; I thought I had a proof before realizing
                       that there are two plates of the design, as
                       Bentley explains [see illus. 6 &amp; 7].</p>
                       <p>Pl. 2. A proof before signatures, with other
                       inscriptions cropped, is in the Rosenwald
                       Collection.</p>
                       <p>The back of the original wrapper for the Nov.
                       1784 issue in my collection advertises separate
                       colored copies of Blake’s prints and issues of the
                       magazine with two impressions, one plain and one
                       colored. I have never seen a colored copy.</p>
                       <p>Wollstonecraft, <hi rend="i">Original
                       Stories</hi>, no. 514, pp. 635-36. Title of A:
                       Bentley does not transcribe the following line
                       after “GOODNESS”: BY MARY WOLLSTONECRAFT. Title of
                       C: no period at end. Pl. 1 inscription. Period
                       after “<hi rend="i">Frontispiece.</hi>” There are
                       three states of pls. 1-2, as described in Easson
                       and Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake: Book
                       Illustrator</hi>, vol. I.</p>
                       <p>Young, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, no.
                       515, pp. 636-40. Title: comma after “NOBLE,”
                       spaces after the “M” and second “C” in the date.
                       Blake’s monogram originally appeared on pl. 34,
                       but was eliminated in the published state except
                       for a small fragment.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 1 inscription. “<hi rend="i">NIGHT the
                       FIRST</hi>” is in italic letters.</p>
                       <p>Pls. 5, 25. A copy of the book in my collection
                       contains impressions before imprints.</p>
                       <p>Pl. 11. A few copies of the book contain an
                       early state<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">18</ref>
                       with many differences from the more common final
                       state. <note id="n34"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Repro.
                       Sotheby’s (Hodgson’s Rooms) catalogue, 29 June
                       1977, facing p. 26.</note></p>
                       </div3>
                       <div3>
                       <head>
						   <title>
							   <hi rend="b">PART IV<lb/>
 CATALOGUES &amp;
							   BIBLIOGRAPHIES</hi>
						   </title>
                       </head>
                       <p>The corresponding section in Bentley &amp;
                       Nurmi has been deepened and extended. The emphasis
                       is naturally on catalogues of Blake’s writings,
                       but Bentley has included most of the important
                       exhibition and sale catalogues devoted to Blake’s
                       pictorial art. One addition in this category would
                       be the sale of Lady Melchett’s collection,
                       Christie’s, 9 Nov. 1971, lots 71-79—the last
                       auction catalogue to contain a significant number
                       of Blakes, including two <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>
                       drawings. Bentley includes the Hoe sale catalogue
                       of 1911 (Part II, nos. 452-55, and Part III, nos.
                       376-88, should also be referred to) but overlooks
                       the privately printed <hi rend="i">Catalogue of
                       Books in English Later than 1700, forming a
                       portion of the Library of Robert Hoe New York
                       1905.</hi></p>
                       </div3>
                       <div3>
                       <head>
						   <title>
							   <hi rend="b">PART V<lb/>
 BOOKS OWNED BY BLAKE</hi>
						   </title>
                       </head>
                       <p>This Part is divided into three lists: six
                       titles “Blake is known to have owned” (edition
                       unidentified), forty-four copies of books owned by
                       Blake, and ten “Books Owned by the Wrong William
                       Blake.” The second list is appropriately
                       conservative, including only works with Blake’s
                       name in the subscribers’ list, or for which we
                       have a copy inscribed by him, or which we know
                       that he owned (and which edition) from Blake’s own
                       writings. These principles of selection exclude
                       from all three lists a number of works that we
                       know, from indirect evidence, that Blake had read.
                       His reference to Bryant in the 
                       <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> and his own methods in
                       comparative mythology show familiarity with 
                       <hi rend="i">A New System, or, an Analysis of Ancient
                       Mythology.</hi> Apparently this is not included in
                       Bentley’s first list because there is no direct
                       evidence that Blake <hi rend="i">owned</hi> it.
                       Law’s edition of <hi rend="i">The Works of Jacob
                       Behmen</hi> and Byron’s <hi rend="i">Cain</hi>,
                       both in Bentley &amp; Nurmi, also go unmentioned
                       here, presumably for similar reasons. It would be
                       interesting to have a full list of books (the
                       Bible, Chaucer, Shakespeare, Milton, Ossian—to
                       name some of the more obvious entries) that we can
                       be reasonably sure Blake knew from the evidence of
                       his writings and the subjects of his designs.</p>
                       <p>Bentley gives title-page transcriptions of most
                       of the works in his main list. Some corrections to
                       these follow. I have not been able to check nos.
                       712, 734, 738, 742, 743.</p>
                       <p>Aeschylus, <hi rend="i">Tragedies</hi>, no.
                       711. Period after “TRANSLATED,” line break after
                       “NOTES.”</p>
                       <p>Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, no. 716.
                       “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b">Twelve Etchings</hi></hi>” is in gothic
                       letters.</p>
                       <p>Cennini, <hi rend="i">Trattato</hi>, no. 717.
                       “ANNOTAZIONI,” “SOCIO,” lower case first letter in
                       “<hi rend="i">approvazione.</hi>”</p>
                       <p>Chatterton, <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, no. 718.
                       “POEMS” is in roman letters.</p>
                       <p>Cumberland, <hi rend="i">Thoughts on
                       Outline</hi>, no. 720. Line 
                       <pb id="p11-196" n="196"/> 
                       break before “CLASSICAL,” semi-colon
                       after “DOCTORS’-COMMONS.”</p>
                       <p>Dante, <hi rend="i">Inferno</hi>, no. 721. This
                       is a two volume work, although Blake’s annotations
                       appear only in the first.</p>
                       <p>Gay, <hi rend="i">Fables</hi>, no. 724. 
                       “<hi rend="i">AND</hi>” is in italic capitals, 
                       “<hi rend="i">Printed for John Stockdale,
                       Piccadilly</hi>” (not all capitals).</p>
                       <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Life of Cowper</hi>, no.
                       727. No comma after “LETTER,” single rule after
                       5-line motto, “<hi rend="b"><hi rend="gothic">Chichester</hi></hi>” in
                       gothic letters.</p>
                       <p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Triumphs of Temper</hi>,
                       no. 730. “<hi rend="smallcaps">of</hi>” 
                       is in small capitals on the same
                       line with “TRIUMPHS” and “TEMPER.”</p>
                       <p>Homer, <hi rend="i">Iliad and Odyssey</hi>, no.
                       732. Comma after “72.”</p>
                       <p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi>, no. 735.
                       “<hi rend="smallcaps">on</hi>” 
                       is in small capitals, colon after “MAN.”</p>
                       <p>Percy, <hi rend="i">Reliques</hi>, no. 736.
                       Period after date.</p>
                       <p>Spurzheim, <hi rend="i">Observations</hi>, no.
                       739. All quotation marks are double.</p>
                       <p>Stedman, <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi>, no. 740.
                       See corrections to no. 499, Part III above.</p>
                       <p>Swedenborg, <hi rend="i">Heaven and Hell</hi>,
                       no. 741. “<hi rend="smallcaps">and</hi>” 
                       (after “HEAVEN,” after “HEARD,” and
                       after “HONOURABLE”), the “<hi rend="smallcaps">y</hi>” in 
                       “<hi rend="smallcaps">By</hi>” and “<hi rend="smallcaps">the</hi>”
                       (both before “HONOURABLE”) are in small capitals,
                       line breaks after “Kingdom” and 
                       “<hi rend="i">LONDON</hi>” (the latter in italic capitals), and
                       no “the” before “other Booksellers.”</p>
                       <figure n="WitsFrontispieceFirstVersion.11.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="750" height="419">
						   <head>6 General title-page and frontispiece of 
						   <hi rend="i">The Wit’s Magazine</hi>, Jan. 1784
						   issue.</head>
						   <figDesc>Bentley’s first version of the
						   frontispiece, Blake after Thomas Stothard. 17.4 ×
						   22.6 cm. Author’s Collection.</figDesc>
                       </figure>
                       <p>Tatham, <hi rend="i">Etchings</hi>, no. 744.
                       All letters are roman, line break and double rule
                       after “1796” and “BOLOGNA,” “<hi rend="smallcaps">y</hi>” 
                       in “<hi rend="smallcaps">By</hi>” (before
                       “CHARLES”) and all but first letter of 
                       “<hi rend="smallcaps">Architect</hi>”
                       are small capitals, “OF” before “THE
                       INSTITUTE.”</p>
                       <p>Tatham, <hi rend="i">Three Designs</hi>, no.
                       745. All letters are roman, except that 
                       “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b">London</hi></hi>” is in gothic letters.</p>
                       <p>Thomas, <hi rend="i">Religious Emblems</hi>,
                       no. 746. Line break before “1809.”</p>
                       <p>Thornton, <hi rend="i">Lord’s Prayer</hi>, no.
                       747. Capital “<hi rend="i">P</hi>” in 
                       “<hi rend="i">Printed</hi>,” “PRICE” after
                       “BOOKSELLERS.”</p>
                       <p>Watson, <hi rend="i">Apology</hi>, no. 749.
                       “<hi rend="i">R. WATSON</hi>” is in italic
                       capitals, “UNI-/ VERSITY.”</p>
                       <p>Wordsworth, <hi rend="i">Excursion</hi>, no.
                       752. Line break after “LONDON.”</p>
                       </div3>
                       <div3>
                       <head>
						   <title>
							   <hi rend="b">PART VI<lb/>
 BIOGRAPHY &amp; CRITICISM</hi>
						   </title>
                       </head>
                       <p>A great many items have been added to the 1964
                       list in Bentley &amp; Nurmi, and all authors are
                       now included in the index. But there have also
                       been some eliminations. As Bentley explains in the
                       general Introduction, he has “omitted scores of
                       entries which appear in <hi rend="i">A Blake
                       Bibliography</hi> (1964), normally because closer
                       inspection proved them either to be reviews [all
                       excluded] or to be substantially irrelevant to
                       Blake” (p. 11). Some of these 
                       <pb id="p11-197" n="197"/> 
                       omissions deserve listing because of
                       their importance, in spite of brevity, and these
                       have been included in the following list of
                       corrections and additions. Bentley does include
                       some important books with only passing references
                       to Blake, like Ellmann’s <hi rend="i">Yeats: The
                       Man and the Masks</hi>, but does not list others
                       if they contain less than a chapter on Blake. A
                       few significant works of this sort which I have
                       encountered are included below. I have not listed
                       any items published since Bentley’s terminal date
                       of June 1974. I know of some of the newspaper
                       articles only through clippings without page
                       numbers.</p>
                       <p>Aldington, Richard. “Everyman’s Poets.” 
                       <hi rend="i">Everyman</hi>, 15 April 1933, p. 462.</p>
                       <p>Anon. “An Allegory.” <hi rend="i">Bibby’s
                       Annual</hi>, 1922. P. 43. On the “Epitome of
                       Hervey’s Meditations.”</p>
                       <p>— “Blake as Artist-Printer.” <hi rend="i">The
                       Times</hi>, 15 July 1964.</p>
                       <p>— “Blake in Poet’s Corner.” 
                       <hi rend="i">Manchester Guardian</hi>, 25 Nov. 1957.</p>
                       <p>— “Blake Moulded in Song.” <hi rend="i">The
                       Times</hi>, 7 Dec. 1965.</p>
                       <p>— “Blake’s Home to be Betting Shop.” 
                       <hi rend="i">Evening Standard</hi>, 24 Jan. 1968.</p>
                       <p>— “Bitter Cycle of Song by Britten.” 
                       <hi rend="i">The Times</hi>, 25 June 1965.</p>
                       <p>— “Epstein Bust of Blake.” <hi rend="i">The
                       Times</hi>, 25 Nov. 1957.</p>
                       <figure n="WitsFrontispieceSecondVersion.11.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="441">
						   <head>7 Frontispiece of <hi rend="i">The Wit’s
						   Magazine</hi>, Jan. 1784 issue.</head>
						   <figDesc>Bentley’s second version, Blake after
						   Thomas Stothard. 17.1 × 22.6 cm. Author’s
						   Collection.</figDesc>
                       </figure>
                       <p>— “William Blake.” <hi rend="i">The Times</hi>,
                       12 Sept. 1927. B., W. H. “Blake and Dante.” 
                       <hi rend="i">Bibby’s Annual</hi>, 1922. Pp. 42-43.</p>
                       <p>Baker, C. H. Collins, and Montague R. James.
                       “Barry, Fuseli and Blake.” Pp. 166-70 of 
                       <hi rend="i">British Painting.</hi> London, 1933.</p>
                       <p>Bland, <hi rend="i">History of Book
                       Illustration</hi>, no. 1221. There is a second
                       ed., Berkeley, Calif., 1969.</p>
                       <p>Brooks, Cleanth and Robert Penn Warren. 
                       <hi rend="i">Understanding Poetry.</hi> New York,
                       1938. Third ed., 1960. Pp. 95-96, 147, 380-83.</p>
                       <p>Bronowski, Jacob. “Artist in Revolt.” 
                       <hi rend="i">Books and Art</hi>, I (Dec. 1957),
                       20-22.</p>
                       <p>— “The Modern Mr. Blake.” <hi rend="i">Radio
                       Times</hi>, 3 Jan. 1969.</p>
                       <p>Brower, Reuben Arthur. <hi rend="i">The Fields
                       of Light: An Experiment in Critical Reading.</hi>
                       London, 1951. New York, 1962. Pp. 6-13.</p>
                       <p>On “The Sick Rose.”</p>
                       <pb id="p11-198" n="198"/>
                       <p>Bury, Adrian. “The Astrologer.” Pp. 49-61 in
                       <hi rend="i">John Varley of the “Old
                       Society.”</hi> Leigh-on-Sea, 1946.</p>
                       <p>Carter, Peter. <hi rend="i">The Gates of
                       Paradise.</hi> London, 1974. A fictionalized
                       account of Blake for younger readers.</p>
                       <p>Carey, <hi rend="i">Critical Description of . .
                       . Chaucer’s Pilgrims</hi>, no. 1338A.</p>
                       <p>Line breaks before “PROCESSION,” “JOHN,” and
                       “1808,” “<hi rend="i">CANTERBURY</hi>” is in
                       italic capitals, double quotation marks
                       throughout.</p>
                       <p>Choremi, Argine. “William Blake: Visions of
                       Eternity.” <hi rend="i">International History
                       Magazine</hi>, no. 11, Nov. 1973. Pp. 56-65 (with
                       10 illus., 6 in color).</p>
                       <p>Cunningham, <hi rend="i">Cabinet Gallery</hi>,
                       no. 1431. There is also an edition of London,
                       1836, in 2 vols. published by George and William
                       Nicol and Hodgson and Graves. Blake account in
                       vol. I, pp. 11-13.</p>
                       <p>Damon, <hi rend="i">Blake Dictionary</hi>, no.
                       1445. There is a third printing, 1973.</p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Note on . . . a New Page</hi>, no.
                       1450. Rpt. Folcroft, Pa., 1972.</p>
                       <p>Davie, Donald. <hi rend="i">Articulate Energy:
                       An Inquiry into the Syntax of English Poetry.</hi>
                       London, 1955. Pp. 80-85.</p>
                       <p>Dibdin, <hi rend="i">Library Companion</hi>,
                       no. 1484A. “<hi rend="gothic"><hi rend="b">Library Companion</hi></hi>”
                       is in gothic letters, no rule before “LONDON,” no
                       line break before “FINSBURY-SQUARE.” I have a copy
                       in boards with (original?) labels which is 
                       <hi rend="i">not</hi> “separately paginated.”</p>
                       <p>Eppink, Norman R. <hi rend="i">101 Prints: The
                       History and Techniques of Printmaking.</hi>
                       Norman, Oklahoma, 1967, 1971. Pp. 52, 54, 124.</p>
                       <p>On Blake’s method of relief etching.</p>
                       <p>Freeman, Rosemary. <hi rend="i">English Emblem
                       Books.</hi> London, 1948. Rpt. New York, 1966. Pp.
                       27-32.</p>
                       <p>Frye. “Yeats and the Language of Symbolism,”
                       no. 1652. Rpt. in Frye, <hi rend="i">Fables of
                       Identity.</hi> New York, 1963.</p>
                       <p>Gahlin, Sven. “Blake for Sale.” 
                       <hi rend="i">Books and Art</hi>, Dec. 1957, p. 22.</p>
                       <p>Grant, John E. “Apocalypse in Blake’s ‘Auguries
                       of Innocence’.” <hi rend="i">Texas Studies in
                       Literature and Language</hi>, V (1964),
                       489-508.</p>
                       <p>Grigson, Geoffrey. “The Upas Tree.” Pp. 56-65
                       in <hi rend="i">The Harp of Aeolus.</hi> London,
                       1947.</p>
                       <p>Hardie, <hi rend="i">English Coloured
                       Books</hi>, no. 1785. Rpt. Bath, 1973.</p>
                       <p>Hayter, <hi rend="i">New Ways of Gravure</hi>,
                       no. 1815. Second ed., London, 1966.</p>
                       <p>Hudson, Derek. “Reynolds and Blake.” 
                       <hi rend="i">Listener.</hi> 27 Feb. 1969.</p>
                       <p>No. 1920, <hi rend="i">English Neoclassical
                       Art.</hi> The author is David Irwin, not Robin
                       Ironside.</p>
                       <p>Johnstone, <hi rend="i">Creative Art in
                       England</hi>, no. 1964. There is a revised
                       edition, London, 1950, with the new title, 
                       <hi rend="i">Creative Art in Britain.</hi> The Blake
                       section is pp. 144-49.</p>
                       <p>Kitson, Michael and Alexandra Wedgwood.
                       “William Blake: The Spiritual Form of Nelson
                       guiding Leviathan.” 2 pp. (unnumbered) and large
                       color repro. in <hi rend="i">Art of the Western
                       World: English Painting.</hi> New York, 1964.</p>
                       <p>Lande, Lawrence. “McGill’s Blake Collection.”
                       <hi rend="i">McGill Reporter</hi>, 3 April
                       1969.</p>
                       <p>Lang, <hi rend="i">The Library</hi>, no. 2097C.
                       The 1892 edition was also published in London.</p>
                       <p>Langbaum, Robert. <hi rend="i">The Poetry of
                       Experience.</hi> New York, 1957. 
                       <hi rend="i">Passim.</hi></p>
                       <p>Las Vergnas, Raymond. “William Blake.” 
                       <hi rend="i">Les Lettres</hi>, vol. II, 1946, Cahier
                       Special 5-6. Pp. 59-73.</p>
                       <p>Locker, Frederick. “The Illustrations in Mrs.
                       Godwin’s ‘Elements of Morality’.” 
                       <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>, I, 6th S. (19 June 1880),
                       493-94.</p>
                       <p>MacDonald, <hi rend="i">Sanity of Blake</hi>,
                       no. 2168. There is a “New Issue” of 1920.</p>
                       <p>McLuhan, Marshall and Harley Parker. “The
                       Tyger.” Pp. 138-41 in <hi rend="i">Through the
                       Vanishing Point.</hi> New York, 1969.</p>
                       <p>Mullaly, Terence. “Drawing by Blake Sold for
                       4,000 gns.” <hi rend="i">Daily Telegraph</hi>, 11
                       Feb. 1958.</p>
                       <p>Palmer, <hi rend="i">Life and Letters of Samuel
                       Palmer</hi>, no. 2353. Rpt. London, 1972, with a
                       new “Introductory Essay” by Raymond Lister and a
                       new “Preface” by Kathleen Raine.</p>
                       <p>Paris, H. J. “Rowlandson and Blake.” Pp. 33-36
                       in <hi rend="i">English Water Colour
                       Painters.</hi> London, 1945.</p>
                       <p>Pearson, <hi rend="i">Banbury Chap Books</hi>,
                       no. 2371. In spite of the mention of Blake on the
                       title-page, the wood engraving reproduced from
                       Thornton’s <hi rend="i">Virgil</hi> has nothing to
                       do with Blake. It is a cut printed on the 
                       <hi rend="i">verso</hi> of the scene painted by
                       Poussin, drawn by Blake, and cut by Byfield.</p>
                       <p>Pevsner, <hi rend="i">Englishness of English
                       Art</hi>, no. 2388. Rpt. London, 1964.</p>
                       <p>Piper, John. “Vision and Imagination.” Pp.
                       24-32 in <hi rend="i">British Romantic
                       Artists.</hi> London, 1946.</p>
                       <p>Quayle, Thomas. “William Blake.” 
                       <hi rend="i">Bibby’s Annual</hi>, 1921. Pp. 53-54.</p>
                       <p>Raine, Kathleen. “Thomas Taylor in England.” In
                       <hi rend="i">Thomas Taylor the Platonist: Selected
                       Writings</hi>, ed. Kathleen Raine and George Mills
                       Harper. Princeton, 1969. <hi rend="i">Passim.</hi></p>
                       <p>Redgrave, Samuel. “William Blake.” In 
                       <hi rend="i">A Dictionary of Artists of the English
                       School.</hi> London, 1873. Second ed., London,
                       1878; rpt. London, 1970. Pp. 44-45.</p>
                       <p>Reti, Ladislao. “Leonardo da Vinci and the
                       Graphic Arts: The Early Invention of
                       Relief-Etching.” <hi rend="i">Burlington
                       Magazine</hi>, CXIII (April 1971), 189-95.</p>
                       <p>Leonardo’s methods are compared to Blake’s.</p>
                       <p>Rosenblum, Robert. <hi rend="i">Transformations
                       in Late Eighteenth-Century Art.</hi> Princeton,
                       1967. Second printing, with revisions, 1969. Third
                       printing, with revisions, 1970. <hi rend="i">Passim.</hi></p>
                       <p><hi rend="i">The Rossetti-Macmillan
                       Letters.</hi> Ed. Lona Mosk Packer. Berkeley and
                       Cambridge, 1963. Minor Blake references in letters
                       of 1863-64.</p>
                       <p>Shipp, Horace. “William Blake Makes a Minority
                       Report.” Pp. 96-107 in <hi rend="i">The British
                       Masters: A Survey and Guide.</hi> London,
                       [1943?].</p>
                       <p>Story, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, no. 2772A. The
                       first edition was issued in both large and small
                       paper formats, the former with four plates not in
                       the latter.</p>
                       <p>Todd, Ruthven. “<hi rend="i">Miro in New York:
                       A Reminiscence.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Malahat
                       Review</hi>, no. 1 (1967), 77-92. Rpt. as a 15 pp.
                       booklet, Brookville, New York, 1967. Contains some
                       details about Todd’s experiments with relief
                       etching not recorded elsewhere.</p>
                       <p>Vaizey, Marina. “Blake,” <hi rend="i">Arts
                       Review</hi>, 18 Dec. 1971. On the exhibition of
                       Gray designs at the Tate.</p>
                       <p>Wallis, Nevile. “Blake’s Vision.” 
                       <hi rend="i">The Spectator</hi>, 14 Aug. 1964.</p>
                       <p>White, Gleeson. <hi rend="i">The Master
                       Painters of Britain.</hi> Birmingham, 1910. Pp.
                       56-59.</p>
                       <p>On the “Canterbury Pilgrims” and “Death’s
                       Door.”</p>
                       <p>Whitley, William T. <hi rend="i">Artists and
                       Their Friends in England, 1700-1799.</hi> London
                       and Boston, 1928. Vol. I, pp. 277, 311, 375; vol.
                       II, 336.</p>
                       <pb id="p11-199" n="199"/>
                       <p><hi rend="i">Art in England 1800-1820.</hi>
                       Cambridge, 1928. Pp. 10. 105, 127-28, 155.</p>
                       <p>Williams, Iolo A. <hi rend="i">Early English
                       Watercolours.</hi> London, 1952; Bath, 1970. Pp.
                       117-21.</p>
                       <p>I fear that the fit audience, though few, who
                       have followed the entire course of this review may
                       come to two conclusions: (1) Essick’s mind is
                       pickled in trivia; (2) Bentley’s book is seriously
                       flawed. I hope I can disabuse you of the latter. A
                       book that lists over 3,000 items is bound to
                       include some mistakes. The ones that I have listed
                       here are at worst simple errors in fact, limited
                       to individual entries, and in no way indicate
                       flaws in Bentley’s bibliographic principles or
                       logic. My perspective, as usual, has been that of
                       the collector and chalcographer, interested in
                       minor bibliographic “points,” rather than that of
                       the literary critic. I could fill even more pages
                       than I have here with a recitation of Bentley’s
                       discoveries, corrections to previously published
                       bibliographies, and sound deductions about such
                       complexities as the printing sequence of the
                       illuminated books. Sir Geoffrey remains, in his
                       ninetieth year, the King of Blake bibliographers
                       (and long may he reign!), but surely the author of
                       <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> is the heir
                       apparent.</p>
                       </div3>
                         <figure n="Bird.11.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="121"/>
                       </div2>
                     </div1>
             </body>
     </text>
</TEI.2>
