<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>11.3.rose</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Victor N. Paananen, William Blake</title>
        <author n="Rose">Edward J. Rose</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1977-1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1977-1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">11.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Michael Hays</name>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>W. J. T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>Edward J. Rose</name>
              <name>Corlette Walker</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_11">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-11-3-0006">
        <pb id="p11-205" n="205"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Victor N. Paananen. <hi rend="b">William Blake.</hi> Boston: Twayne
                            Publishers/G. K. Hall &amp; Co., 1977. Pp. 171. $7.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Edward J.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Rose</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>A reviewer must pity the author of a Twayne volume—the
                        restrictions of which apparently make the writing of an intelligent and
                        meaningful book on Blake difficult. I must assume that Victor Paananen has
                        done his best, having accepted willingly the limitations of the Twayne
                        format. Unfortunately, however, the final result is a near disaster that is
                        redeemed from absolute failure only by Paananen’s understanding
                        that he is not writing about a mythological poet but a prophet who tried to
                        dramatize mental strife and not to create another rattletrap pantheon of
                        bloated gods and goddesses. The Twayne <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, however,
                        cannot be taken seriously as a contribution to the study of Blake. It is, in
                        fact, not even a good introduction and fares poorly when compared to Max
                        Plowman’s fifty-year old critique, which, by the way, is not
                        listed in the selected bibliography; nor are Swinburne, Yeats, Symons,
                        Wicksteed, or Percival. The usual Twayne restriction on the number of
                        entries in selected bibliographies will not explain Paananen’s
                        astounding omissions, especially considering some of the items included. But
                        “we” (Paananen’s favorite personal pronoun,
                        which makes him sound repeatedly like Charles Lindbergh in Paris), does not
                        compliment the dead, since, “we” may suppose, they have no
                        influence on the careers of the living. <pb id="p11-206" n="206"/>
It would
                        be possible to list at random fifty articles of more worth than the Twayne
                            <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, half of which might well have been included
                        either in the bibliography <hi rend="i">or</hi> in the notes. But with
                        Yeats, Wicksteed, and Percival missing (from the notes, too), what else can
                        be said.</p>
          <p>In his preface Paananen suggests that serious Blake scholarship makes it
                        possible for “a book like this one [to be] written with fewer
                        trepidations.” Fewer trepidations than what? (Aside from regretting
                        the incomplete comparison, I still wonder why. I should imagine it would be
                        the other way around, that is, since it was decided to publish the book at
                        all.) He assures the reader that “Specialized work can now be
                        carried forward confidently” because of that serious scholarship
                        about which he speaks. Very nice, very nice, but Twayne and Paananen should
                        have helped. Needless to say, they did not. The reader is also informed that
                        “Because of Blake’s reputation for obscurity,”
                        Paananen will make “extensive use of quotation [he overdoes it]
                        both to explicate the lines [there is very little true explication] and to
                        demonstrate that Blake can speak very well for himself.” Believe it
                        or not, Paananen actually does write that “Blake can speak very
                        well for himself.” Aside from the silliness of such a remark, which
                        even a Twayne book ought to avoid, Paananen calls attention to one of the
                        book’s greatest weaknesses. Not serious scholarship itself, the
                        Twayne <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> does a poor job of introducing Blake,
                        especially to the neophyte reader, the only kind of reader for whom a Twayne
                        book has any value. The author must explain and illuminate, not just quote.
                        His description of Blake’s method of illuminated printing, for
                        example, is incomplete, incorrect, and unclear. It is certainly of no use to
                        anyone as an explanation. The reader gets the impression that Blake and
                        Blake’s ideas have literally sprung from nowhere. He is given
                        some names, but no relations are established. The discussion of
                        “outline” is a case in point. There is no mention of
                        Michelangelo or Raphael. In fact, they are nowhere mentioned in the book.
                        Neither are a host of others who contributed to Blake’s
                        intellectual milieu.</p>
          <p>The Twayne <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> begins with a skimpy and wholly inadequate
                        biographical survey. This is followed by a chapter on <hi rend="i">There is
                            No Natural Religion, All Religions are One</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The
                            Book of Urizen.</hi> The discussion of the three <hi rend="i">Religion</hi> plates
could easily have been omitted, since Paananen
                        does not really explain them. The rest of the chapter is pedestrian at best
                        and fundamentally out of place. The third chapter on the <hi rend="i">Poetical
Sketches</hi> is a shallow pastiche of quotations and
                        superficial comments, but chapters four and five on <hi rend="i">The
                            Marriage of Heaven and Hell, The French Revolution</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> are even worse. <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> is
                        ignored as are Blake’s illustrations for his own work as well as
                        that of others.</p>
          <p>Paananen’s commentary interlaced by inexcusable gobs of quotation
                        is distantly descriptive at best. The reader gets little or no insight into
                        Blake’s work or how his mind works. The book’s four
                        pages (a chapter!) on the <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
                            Albion</hi> are superficial and chapter seven on <hi rend="i">The Songs
                            of Innocence and of Experience, Thel</hi> and <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>
                        fails in every respect to illuminate these poems. In trying unsuccessfully
                        to cover as much as he can, Paananen covers little. The book is poorly
                        organized and disjointed. The reader is never permitted to get hold of
                        anything on which to build even the foundations of an understanding of what
                        Blake is about. The piecemeal chronology, which Paananen violates at just
                        those times when he should not, is carried over to the chapter on <hi rend="i">The
Four Zoas.</hi> Instead of giving his reader a coherent
                        introduction to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> as a whole, he resorts to
                        snippets (most of his chapters are snippets) on each of the nine nights.
                        Like the following chapter on the “Manuscript Poems”
                        (another pastiche of quotation), the chapter on <hi rend="i">The Four
                            Zoas</hi> is a superficial narrative concerned in turn with
                        Blake’s narrative, which Paananen tells us rightly and early in
                        the book is not the fundamental structure of a Blake
                        “epic.” Would to God he had organized his book with this
                        understanding in the forefront of his mind. The chapters on <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> are not worthy of serious
                        discussion, and the “Conclusion” might have served as the
                        beginning of a truly well oriented introductory chapter, which the book
                        sorely needs.</p>
          <p>In his preface, Paananen somewhat pompously suggests that “Blake
                        scholars will no doubt dispute many of my [sic] readings of individual poems
                        and passages—many of the readings are indeed new—but
                        they will recognize that I am writing about the same William Blake that the
                        scholarship of the last fifty years has identified for us.” Not
                        only is there nothing new to dispute (absolutely nothing),
                        “we” wonder why <hi rend="i">only</hi> fifty years and
                        where is the evidence that even that has been adequately researched by the
                        author. The absurdity of Paananen’s opinion of his book is
                        underscored by the book itself. The errors in interpretation and
                        over-simplifications that abound in it do not require a scholar’s
                        refutation.</p>
          <p>Paananen’s heart is, I suppose, in the right place. He likes Blake
                        and he appreciates the integrity of Blake’s work as a whole.
                        Furthermore, he says he understands that both the individual poem and the
                        individual plate each have an independent as well as an interdependent
                        being, although he seems not to have organized his material with this idea
                        in mind. Also, he stresses rightly Blake’s radical politics and
                        biblical evangelicalism, at least in general. But the book does not
                        particularize. It does not go deep. It is not well-written, well-organized,
                        or truly helpful as an introduction to Blake. And, finally, it is certainly
                        not a contribution to Blake studies. It will, I believe, serve no purpose at
                        all.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
