<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>11.4.paulson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Joan Dolmetsch, Rebellion and Reconciliation; Gary Kelly, The English
Jacobin Novel 1780-1805</title>
        <author n="Paulson">Ronald Paulson</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">11.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Susan Fox</name>
              <name>Laurence Goldstein</name>
              <name>Janice Lyle</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Ronald Paulson</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_11">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-11-4-0008">
        <pb id="p11-291" n="291"/>
        <div2>
          <figure n="Jacobin.11.4.bqscan" rend="file" type="reviewed-cover" width="300" height="477"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Joan D. Dolmetsch. <hi rend="b">Rebellion and Reconciliation: Satirical Prints
on the Revolution at Williamsburg.</hi> Williamsburg: The Colonial Williamsburg Foundation, 1976. Pp. vii +
221. 101 black-on-white plates. $12.95.</title>
            <title type="main">Gary Kelly. <hi rend="b">The English Jacobin Novel 1780-1805.</hi> Oxford:
Clarendon Press, 1976. Pp. xi + 291. $21.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Ronald</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Paulson</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
		<q>
I think of sailing for America, where I may aid the struggles of liberty, may freely publish all which the
efforts of reason can teach me, and at the same time may form a society of savages, who seem in consequence of
their very ignorance to have a less quantity of error, and therefore to be less liable to repel truth than
those whose information is more multifarious.
</q>
          <p>Frank Henley’s project for fleeing the England depicted in Holcroft’s <hi rend="i">Anna St.
Ives</hi> (1792) sums up what America meant to defenders of the French Revolution. America was the successful
revolutionary society; the open society in which censorship and suspension of habeas corpus were unknown; the
locus of innocence and noble savages, free of all the forms (primogeniture and the rest) that curb and
corrupt. Robert Bage, in <hi rend="i">Hermsprong, or Man As He Is Not</hi> (1796), invented a Frank Henley who
had been brought up in America, sent him to France during the Revolution, and then dropped him down like
Voltaire’s Huron in England of the Pittite repression. Hermsprong is like Blake’s allegories of the
American Revolution in that he can also act energetically when action is called for. He has soon discomfited
and defeated the flabby aristocrats, and for good measure (being among other things a descendent of Tom Jones)
shown them to be usurpers of his own rightful patrimony in England.</p>
          <p>What continues to surprise me is the fact that this image of the American Revolution as fiery Orc
was primary an English one, promulgated by sympathetic English propagandists in the 1770s and in the 1790s.
Even Burke, who was to find these qualities noxious in the French revolutionaries, praised the Americans’
active, energetic, youthful course of action, which he contrasted with “the listlessness that has fallen upon
almost all” Englishmen. The Americans are “savage . . . uncouth,” but “animated with the first glow and
activity of juvenile heart.” But of course Burke was also defending America’s loss of ancient traditional
rights against the innovative commercial policies of the English government.</p>
          <p>In 1975 M. W. Jones’ <hi rend="i">Cartoon History of the American Revolution</hi> appeared, and
in the year of the centennial Joan Dolmetsch published a selection of the American Revolution cartoons (or to
be historically accurate, satiric prints) from the Colonial Williamsburg collection. This is a more elegant,
better produced (and reproduced) volume than Jones’, which had the format and general appearance of
newsprint. Jones supplied a racy running text with chronological lists and suggestive juxtapositions of prints
(three or four to a page) of the sort one associates with a <hi rend="i">Time-Life</hi> educational series.
Dolmetsch supplies catalogue entries with complete bibliographical information, description, and citations
from the <hi rend="i">British Museum Catalogue of Satiric Prints and Drawings.</hi> Yet for cartoons whose
artistic quality is almost nil but whose context is of great interest, Jones’ tabloid format may have been
more appropriate as well as more informative.</p>
          <pb id="p11-292" n="292"/>
          <p>The satiric prints were almost entirely English and continental. America seems to have produced
very few other than copies of the English ones: a fact which may help to explain the dearth of fiery
Orc-fiqures. The two powerful images produced on the American side are omitted from Dolmetsch’s collection,
probably because technically they are not satiric prints. One is <hi rend="i">The Boston Massacre</hi> of
1770, the essential image as the American propagandists wanted it seen: helpless Bostonians being shot down by
British soldiers lined up to resemble a firing squad. This was the image that stimulated the colonists to
revolt and secured sympathy from the English Opposition (and was later adapted by Goya for his 
<hi rend="i">Third of May</hi>). The other image was a representation of the overturning of George III’s statue
in New York City on 4 July 1776 (the newspaper blockprint of the scene followed within days; the elaborate
engraving some years later). Here are the Orc overtones so noticeably missing in earlier American propaganda.
Indians are even present in the crowd, as a sort of reference to one sturdy aspect of the Americans (as Frank
Henley’s remarks show, “American” meant equally Indian and “savage” to eighteenth-century Englishmen), and
perhaps also to the Boston Tea Party, where Bostonians disguised as Indians to carry out an un-English act.
There is even present that ubiquitous eighteenth-century symbol of dissent and natural subversion, a dog.</p>
          <p>But aside from that one blockprint in a New York newspaper none of the ritual crowd action (from
Baltimore to Boston) following the Declaration of Independence was recorded in graphic imagery; any more than
the active image of the Boston Tea Party of two years earlier was exploited by the Americans. The colonists
did in fact react by casting tea in Boston Harbor, by tarring and feathering Tories, and by forcing customs
officers to drink large quantities of tea (in one case in toasts to a large variety of subversive subjects,
reminiscent of the Wilkite crowd action of the 1770s). But these scenes were portrayed for propaganda purposes
only by English sympathizers of the colonists in London.</p>
          <p>It is possible to trace the origin of the graphic image. In April 1774 there was <hi rend="i">The
Whitehall Pump</hi> (Dolmetsch, no. 23), a satiric print showing Lord North pumping water over and into the
mouth of a prone Britannia to revive her. She has collapsed on top of the prone Indian brave who represents
America. In <hi rend="i">The Able Doctor or America swallowing the Bitter Draught</hi> (p. 7), published in
the May <hi rend="i">London Magazine</hi>, the female figure has been turned into an American. Lord North is
forcing the Boston tea down the throat of this bare-breasted Indian maiden, held by Lord Mansfield, with Lord
Sandwich (notorious womanizer that he was) securing her legs and peering up her skirt. Britannia, standing by,
covers her eyes in shame. Even here, however, America is shown gallantly spitting the tea back in Lord
North’s face. By June this image of America in the role of patient corresponding to the Americans of 
<hi rend="i">The Boston Massacre</hi> was copied by Paul Revere for <hi rend="i">The Royal American Magazine.</hi>
In October the roles were reversed in a series of English mezzotint prints (nos. 25-27): the active American
colonists are now forcing tea down the throat of, and tarring and feathering, English customs officers. Then,
not reproduced by Dolmetsch (reproduced by Jones, p. 49), is the atrocity print, <hi rend="i">Hancock’s
Warehouse for Tarring &amp; Feathering</hi>, where the party being mishandled by the patriots has become a
pretty semi-nude English woman.</p>
          <p>There is no indication that the prints in which the Americans are the aggressors were copied in
America, though they were probably imported. Another in the English mezzotint series is <hi rend="i">The
Patriotic Barber of New York</hi> (no. 32), which shows the barber chasing a Tory out of his shop, razor at
the ready. Especially interesting is the rearing horse of <hi rend="i">A Political Lesson</hi> (no. 25) in
which the vigorous American horse is casting off his English master. These show precisely the graphic image
the Americans repressed.</p>
          <p>The difference between the internal and external images is, I suppose, that the Americans
initially saw themselves as the underdog and oppressed victim. They did not want to associate themselves
officially with the kind of Wilkite insubordination upon which in many ways they actually modelled their
actions. Accordingly the paradigm that stirred souls was the Boston Massacre until the Declaration of
Independence, when the really mythic image appeared in the destruction of the statue of George III, with its
echoes of the primal horde dismembering the Father/King, which Paine had already adumbrated—in effect had
called for—in <hi rend="i">Common Sense</hi> a few months before.</p>
          <p>It was at this time that the “Don’t Tread on Me” flag, showing the coiled rattlesnake, came
into temporary use. (The image of the divided snake of the disunited colonies—“Join or Die”—goes back to
the French-Indian War but reemerged as a patriotic image in the Stamp Act Crisis.) By the 1780s the
rattlesnake of the flag had become the property of English cartoonists (Dolmetsch, nos. 79, 84; Jones, pp.
158, 177). The image is shunned by American artists, and appears to have been quickly swept under the carpet.
But it is possible to conclude that in pre-revolutionary times when the colonists felt oppressed the figure
invoked was passive or female; in the revolutionary moment when they were the aggressor, the figure
represented a male principle. The aggressive maleness of the statue-breakers and of the snake was the aspect
developed by Blake in his serpentine Orc.</p>
          <p>But by that time the official American image (with a Federalist government in power) had been
painted by John Trumbull, who on the eve of the Revolution in France was representing the successful American
Revolution in terms of the Boston Massacre. Only faintly does he reflect the youth-age conflict, so powerful
in Paine and Blake. In <hi rend="i">Bunker Hill</hi> the British tend to be fairly elderly and jowled, while
the central American figures are young. Something like the British Oak appears in the battle scenes that
follow, decaying from painting to painting until it has fallen to the ground in <hi rend="i">The Surrender of
General Burgoyne</hi>, where a luxuriantly leafy tree first appears, a Liberty Tree of the sort seen in the
background of the prints in which Americans tar and feather British customs officers. These are
<pb id="p11-293" n="293"/>
perpheral details. Trumbull’s central imagery is of passivity in the hands of a benign providence. His
paintings alternate scenes of defeat or dying generals with images of such covenants as an enemy general’s
surrender, the Declaration of Independence, and Washington resigning his commission as general of the
army.</p>
          <p>What we see are two different responses, competing by the 1790s, but by then one of them
advocated most strongly by Americans, the other by the Englishmen Paine and Blake. The images summed up by
Trumbull probably represent the fact that Americans considered their relationship with the king as contractual
and indeed believed all political authority to be based on compact. But they also reflect the position of John
Adams and the Boston Presbyterians who still drew on a belief in election for an elite and government by
covenant, its model ultimately the covenant of the Chosen People with God. Naturally Trumbull used images of
providential suffering and martyrdom as preparation for the victory he knew was to follow. Paine and Blake
shared the same roots and traditions of English working-class radicalism, which kept alive the heresies of the
Ranters and Levellers. They believed not in election for an elite but in election for all, not in government
by covenant and passivity in the hands of God but in active energetic attack—indeed attack on the Father
Himself and on all figures of authority. It is understandable that Trumbull represented the covenant as the
essence of the American Revolution; it was Paine’s purpose to destroy this idea, and he exploited the
subliminal feelings of the colonists for the paternal relationship, which they as earnestly repressed. It
should have surprised no one that Paine went on to demystify the Father in Heaven Himself in his 
<hi rend="i">Age of Reason</hi>, or that the American government was in no hurry to acknowledge him as one of
themselves by seeking his release from prison during the Terror.</p>
          <p>One view of English literary history in the 1790s is expressed by Howard Mumford Jones in 
<hi rend="i">Revolution and Romanticism</hi>: a shift in epistemology, from empiricism to Kantian idealism,
explains the difference between the behavior of a Washington or Jefferson and a Danton or Robespierre—and, I
suppose we could add, between a Diderot and David, Wilkes and Cobbett, or Gray and Blake. Melvin J. Lasky in
<hi rend="i">Utopia and Revolution</hi> argues that the uninterrupted continuation of the empiricist tradition
in England (characteristically English, he implies) saved England from the rationalist excesses of the French
Revolution. Carl Woodring in <hi rend="i">Politics and English Romantic Poetry</hi> argues that the
rationalist emphasis on natural law <hi rend="i">and</hi> the empirical concern with individual experience
explain the whole phenomenon of the French Revolution, and also the early sympathy of the Romantic poets, as
well as the later conflict that developed between their liberal tenets and their growing faith in imaginative
perception and organic wholeness. In effect, the conjunction of the empirical-liberal tradition 
<hi rend="i">and</hi> the French Revolution created Romanticism. Woodring avoids Jones’ determinism (the rise of
Kantian idealism produced a state of mind that conditioned Robespierre or allowed him to do the outrageous
things he did) along with Lasky’s confident anglophilia, and explains the human conflict lacking in the
pre-Romantic writers and artists, which sets off the poems of Blake, Wordsworth, and Coleridge.</p>
          <p>Gary Kelly’s subject is the Jacobin novel—also sometimes called the radical or reform novel,
since “Jacobin” was a term applied by the unsympathetic to writing that had been largely shaped before the
French Revolution began by writers some of whom were sometimes Jacobins. The paradox of Kelly’s thesis
concerning these novels is how little they were affected by the events of 1789 and following. The best of
them, however, do seem to have required that injection of historical violence on the scale and at the distance
of the French Revolution. The Revolution, in other words, may account for the difference between Charlotte
Smith’s <hi rend="i">Emmeline</hi> (1788) and Holcroft’s <hi rend="i">Anna St. Ives</hi> (1792), and above
all between these and Godwin’s <hi rend="i">Caleb Williams</hi>, the one undeniably major work of the
Jacobin novel genre. Anna St. Ives, a granddaughter of Clarissa, is still the object of genteel attempted
rape, but Godwin’s hero is locked in a master-slave relationship which involves broader forms of social
violence and destroys both parties (as happened in <hi rend="i">Clarissa</hi> but not in <hi rend="i">Anna St.
Ives</hi>).</p>
          <p>Kelly’s study of the Jacobin novelists is welcome. The available books on the French Revolution
and the English poets, novelists, and playwrights are uniformly antiquated and limited to biography and plot
summary. Kelly offers the first serious attempt to define radical fiction of the 1780s and 90s and assess its
importance. He carries with him some traces of the earlier approach and of the doctoral dissertation. So few
of these novels are now read that an extreme circumstantiality of treatment is required for the general reader
(which includes Kelly’s <hi rend="i">TLS</hi> reviewer, who seems to have read only <hi rend="i">Caleb
Williams</hi>). A reader becomes a little impatient with the equally emphatic coverage of one item after
another, and annoyed to find words, phrases, and sentences repeated verbatim sometimes only a few pages apart.
Nevertheless, Kelly’s treatment of the subject is both intelligent and sensitive, often stimulating, and
here and there adventurous (as in his treatment of names as historical allegory). Given its scope, the book is
extremely informative. Its limits are Inchbald, Bage, Holcroft, and Godwin. The chapter on Godwin is easily
the most impressive thing in the book. Kelly has written his equally good Wollstonecraft chapter as
introduction to his edition of <hi rend="i">Mary</hi> and <hi rend="i">Maria</hi> in the Oxford English Novel
series.</p>
          <p>I will try to place Kelly’s findings in context. One’s first literary referent in any
revolutionary period is the drama—the danger spot most closely scrutinized by politicians; witness
Walpole’s Licensing Act and Corbyn Morris’ supporting opinion that it is far more difficult
<pb id="p11-294" n="294"/>
to efface the impression of what is seen and heard than what is merely read. It is therefore no surprise to
find the dramatic response to the French Revolution in operatic entertainments. The plays that went seriously,
though clumsily, at the real issues and took sides were prohibited and never performed. Even so, the surviving
texts show that they generally took the allegorical way out, through parallels in earlier English history or
in Roman or Swiss history (just as the French were doing across the Channel). A few attempted to dramatize the
current events in Paris, with Charlotte Corday or Robespierre as protagonist.</p>
          <p>Scholars examining this material tend to look for specific references to France or liberty or
rebellion, and have overlooked the area of greatest literary interest: the analogical plots developed by
writers who could not, or did not wish to, express their feelings directly. We are told that Holcroft’s play
<hi rend="i">Love’s Frailties</hi> (1794) was hissed off the stage for the line “I was bred to the most
useless, and often the most worthless of all professions; that of a gentleman.” Such a sentence was one sign
of Jacobin sentiment. But what distinguishes <hi rend="i">Love’s Frailties</hi> is its modification of the
<hi rend="i">Marriage of Figaro</hi> plot, brought into the revolutionary period (Holcroft also made an
expurgated translation of Beaumarchais’ play). The English version of the <hi rend="i">droit de
seigneur</hi> is an uncle who controls the marriages of his charges—siblings, each of whom is in love with
an unsuitable person, a soldier for her and a painter’s daughter for him. The old guardian who prohibits
these matches pursues young girls himself, and the plot is an animated version of a Rowlandson situation with
the old guardian, the young girl he pursues, and her young lover (who, of course, turns out to be the old
man’s charge). On the one hand the young folk rebel and marry as they please, and on the other the old man
is thwarted in his personal designs on the young girl. Love, it is made clear, is both the great leveller and
the great catalyst for rebellious action, and the battle is between generations (whether the participants are
called father-son-daughter or guardian-brother-sister).</p>
          <p>As Kelly’s examples document, the situation of domestic tyranny was already present in novels
of the 1780s as a paradigm of repression and rebellion. As early as <hi rend="i">Mount Heneth</hi> (1782) Bage
was using his characters’ speeches to make the analogy between domestic and national tyranny; and what is
implicit in the 80s becomes explicit in the 90s in references to the situation with Hastings in India and the
lost colonies of America (<hi rend="i">Man As He Is</hi>, 1792). Bage is the least representative of these
novelists, because he remains fairly well confined within the comic tradition of Fielding and Smollett. Kelly
thinks, with good reason, that his covert and overt domestic analogies fit politically into the rationalist
and empirical opposition to Filmer’s patriarchal monarchy. But the question of continuum or interruption
haunts Kelly’s book. There is a chasm between the emphasis domestic tyranny receives in the 1780s, let alone
the 90s, and in <hi rend="i">Tom Jones</hi> and <hi rend="i">Marriage à la Mode</hi>, where it is also an
integral part. Intervening—though Kelly does not mention the fact—are the intensifying phenomena of Wilkes
and the Gordon Riots, as well as the American Revolution and Burke’s attack on Hastings. There is the
question whether, as Kelly says, “events had turned one of Bage’s favourite themes into a piece of
provocative radicalism” or whether as a result of the possibilities loosed by the Wilkite propaganda and the
American Revolution, some literature itself was turning in this more radical and provocative direction.</p>
          <p>Some questions remain. Why does Bage—admittedly an imitator of Fielding—have to go to
Montesquieu (as Kelly has him do) for his stress on “virtuous living rather than the mere outward forms of
religion”? The theme was an old one in England, present in the works of Bishop Hoadly as well as Fielding,
long before Bage began to write. How do we distinguish the image of the villainous titled aristocrat as a
phenomenon of the 1780s (the dividing line, Kelly notes, seems to have been baronet/baron)? Richardson’s
Lovelace was <hi rend="i">not</hi> an aristocrat in the later sense. When and why does the break occur with
the older and more conservative convention of attacking not higher orders but “fashion” and the middleclass
“desire to ape a higher level of society”? “Luxury” too was essentially a topos used by the upperclass to
criticize the lower orders. Why then in the 1780s does it become attached, as Kelly shows it does, to the
titled aristocrat?</p>
          <p>The convention that could probably bear most investigation is the arranged/forced marriage,
already present in Hogarth’s <hi rend="i">Marriage à la Mode</hi> and Richardson’s 
<hi rend="i">Clarissa.</hi> Here the question is less the rape of an innocent than the forced marriage from which
Clarissa escapes into rape. A story can often be dated by its solution to the problem of how to overthrow this
tyranny. In <hi rend="i">Marriage à la Mode</hi> overthrow is effected by natural forces after the marriage;
in <hi rend="i">Clarissa</hi> by the daughter’s willful action before the marriage takes place, but with
equally terrible consequences for all. In the Gothic novels out of Walpole’s <hi rend="i">Castle of
Otranto</hi> the defiance precedes marriage—as in the old romances—by mere flight. The literary aspect of
the change in the 1780s turns on the conventions of the Gothic, which transform the situation of domestic
tyranny into a more extreme situation with ruined castles serving as implicit trappings of royal tyranny (on
the decline). One other factor only glancingly mentioned by Kelly is the women novelists of the Gothic who
preceded Inchbald, in particular Charlotte Smith. The Gothic charge was picked up by a novelist like Smith,
who found therein a vehicle for expressing her own feelings in the figure of a Gothic heroine—feelings the
male novelist simply did not share, did not even have much reason to feel or notice in her novels.</p>
          <p>The woman’s experience, like that of the black slave, was a model standing ready for use when
the Revolution erupted in 1789. The experience of the female chattel, of oppression with no recourse to law,
of sexual pursuit and assault upon body and mind, all provided the woman novelist (who had also read 
<hi rend="i">Clarissa</hi> and <hi rend="i">Otranto</hi>) with the experience
<pb id="p11-295" n="295"/>
and the point for a revolutionary novel—or an anticipation of one—which could be adapted by Holcroft and
Godwin when the moment was ripe. The emphasis might be on the wife’s feelings of guilt, but at its best in
Inchbald’s <hi rend="i">Simple Story</hi> (1791) the scenario ends in the increasingly censorious and
dictatorial husband against whom his wife can only rebel in adultery. Wollstonecraft’s 
<hi rend="i">Vindication of the Rights of Woman</hi> and <hi rend="i">Maria</hi> are only the discursive and
melodramatic extremes of this plot.</p>
          <p>In the 1780s and into the 90s Charlotte Smith’s women remain peripheral, the marital horrors
and the adultery taking place off stage, and usually to secondary characters. The emphasis is on the virtue of
the heroine who remains faithful to her worthless husband, but the strength of the novel lies in its portrayal
of the husband. Then in <hi rend="i">Desmond</hi> (1792) the characters talk about the Revolution in France,
underline the parallel between the French and English situations, and shift our admiration from the wife’s
virtue to her brave behavior in a situation of tyranny.</p>
          <p>What sets apart Kelly’s main protagonists, Inchbald, Holcroft, and Godwin, is their adherence
to the rational strain of literary-political-philosophical theorizing. This is present not only in the
dialogues on philosophical issues in their novels but in the theoretical basis for the formal structure that
sets their best novels above other English fiction of the 1790s. This was the search for “unity of design”
which Holcroft was advocating in the preface to <hi rend="i">Alwyn</hi> as early as 1780—and so “the
simplicity which is requisite” (taken up in the title of Inchbald’s <hi rend="i">Simple Story</hi>). Unity
and simplicity also derived from the integration of plot and character through the “doctrine of necessity,”
the belief that “The characters of men originate in their external circumstances.” The formal result at its
best was a remarkable union of character and incident.</p>
          <p>The special kind of novel that was produced had as its object, in Holcroft’s words, to “develop
the emotions that preceded and the causes that produced the passion, and, afterward, trace it through all its
consequences.” The action was, in short, a passion—a relationship or entanglement, with its emotions and
causes as well as its consequences analyzed in some depth; and the form the passion took was one involving
love and compulsion, rape of one sort or another, and mastery, based on the model of 
<hi rend="i">Clarissa.</hi> The line of transmission was from the Clarissa-Lovelace symplegma which ends in mutual
destruction, a consequence of his need to subjugate and hers to maintain her freedom; to Rousseau’s 
<hi rend="i">Julie</hi> and Mackenzie’s <hi rend="i">Julia de Roubigné</hi>, where the situation becomes a
triangle involving an impossible love for a younger man and a marriage with an older (in Julia’s case the
husband’s jealousy leads to her murder). Thus we arrive at Inchbald’s <hi rend="i">Simple Story.</hi> On
one level its two parts, contrasting Miss Milner with the wrong education and Matilda with the right one,
merely correspond to the two protagonists of her later novel <hi rend="i">Nature and Art</hi> (1796). This is
not, however, the simple <hi rend="i">Industry and Idleness</hi> or <hi rend="i">Sanford and Merton</hi> plot
that surfaces in Inchbald’s less inspired work. For on another level the two parts correspond to two
versions, in two generations, of the power struggle between an older father-lover and the young girl. (She
also uses the January-May theme, with its personal as well as political motivations, in her play 
<hi rend="i">The Child of Nature</hi>, 1788.) Dorriforth is guardian, Catholic priest, moralist, Miss Milner’s
dead father’s substitute, eventually (ennobled as Lord Elmwood) a titled aristocrat, and Matilda’s actual
but invisible father. Inchbald manages to get in all the oppressive relationships that materialize in the
imagery of Burke and Paine after the outbreak of the Revolution. Against this authority figure appears
natural, untutored, giddy, freedom-loving Miss Milner. She loves Dorriforth and he her, but the love includes
subjugation (and self-subjugation) and is tested by her rebellion and his subsequent tyranny, with its effects
on the next generation and its finally ameliorist solution (a corrective to Miss Milner’s revolutionary
one). Inchbald projects a world of Dorriforth’s house which is strangely like the Garden of Eden with its
tempter God in Blake’s “Poison Tree,” suggesting as it does the repetition of the struggle for each new
generation.</p>
          <p>What makes <hi rend="i">A Simple Story</hi> so attractive is that the situation it dramatizes is
remarkably appropriate to the time, without being in any way allegorically or analogically related to what was
happening (or even was about to happen, since it was largely written before 1789) in France. Kelly has it
exactly right when he sums up the strength of the novel as Inchbald’s portrayal of “the repression and the
force of powerful but natural feelings.” His remarks are illuminating on the subject: “Dorriforth, Miss
Milner, Sandford [the clergyman friend of Dorriforth], are all locked in a moral and psychological bastille
built by reason and pride, and since words are the language of this super-ego, only gestures can elude the
censorship of conscience to tell the story of the heart’s imprisonment.” Although “bastille” is his own
metaphor, Kelly is uncovering the strand connecting <hi rend="i">A Simple Story</hi> to Sterne’s 
<hi rend="i">Sentimental Journey</hi>, and even to <hi rend="i">Joseph Andrews.</hi> It is still part of the
sentimental tradition, where the inauthenticity of words was an essential ingredient. (“But how unimportant,
how weak, how ineffectual are <hi rend="i">words</hi> in conversation,” we read in <hi rend="i">A Simple
Story</hi>, “—looks and manners alone express—”.) But <hi rend="i">A Simple Story</hi> also shows how
these assumptions can become Jacobin, either by placing Sterne’s caged starling, or even Rousseau’s, in a
context of the fall of the Bastille, or by intensifying the feeling and the symbolism of the situation by
adding, however implicitly, a political dimension.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">A Simple Story</hi> is the work without which <hi rend="i">Anna St. Ives</hi> and
<hi rend="i">Caleb Williams</hi> would have been inconceivable. If one theme, as Holcroft states his aim in
<hi rend="i">Anna St. Ives</hi>, is “teaching fortitude to females,” and this fortitude is in the face of a
guardian or husband, another that follows is the conflict of the generations. Here it is the old Sir Arthur
St. Ives and Abimilech Henley against young Anna and Frank, and the relationship of the oppressive or foolish
parents and the rebellious
<pb id="p11-296" n="296"/>
children joins the Jacobin thesis that education and changing circumstances affect character (“the virtuous
children can make reparation for the errors of their parents,” in Kelly’s words). There is also, carried
over from <hi rend="i">A Simple Story</hi>, “the conflict between [Anna’s] rational intentions and her
unconscious yearnings and fears” (cf. Inchbald’s “showing the force of feeling by the force necessary to
suppress it”). In <hi rend="i">her</hi> terms, her love for Frank conflicts with her duty to Sir Arthur as
passion conflicts with reason: “Indeed indeed, Frank, it is not my heart that refuses you; it is my
understanding; it is principle; it is a determination not to do that which my reason cannot justify. . . .”
But of the real problem, she says: “I cannot encounter the malediction of a father!—What! Behold him in an
agony of cursing his child?—I cannot!—I cannot!—It must not be!” “ . . . because,” says Frank, “this
wise world has decreed that to abhor, reprove, and avoid vice in a father, instead of being the performance of
a duty, is offensive to all moral feeling.”</p>
          <p>The lesson of these rather fine though minor novels is that the important percursors of 
<hi rend="i">Caleb Williams</hi> (or <hi rend="i">Things as They Are, or the Adventures of Caleb Williams</hi>,
Godwin’s first, Jacobin title) are not the overt radical novels but some granddaughters of 
<hi rend="i">Clarissa.</hi> What Godwin does is to change the sex, making it man against man, father against son,
instead of the father (husband) against the daughter (wife) of Inchbald and Holcroft. He does not omit the
sexual nexus of the Caleb-Falkland relationship, but now it introduces the Oedipal dimension which had been
displaced heretofore to the daughter. And he ruthlessly carries out in both of his endings the implications
elided by his fellow Jacobin novelists. His revised ending is not very satisfactorily explained by Kelly as
Godwin’s wanting an optimistic ending which mitigates Caleb’s triumph with remorse. Rather the fact that
Caleb has in effect <hi rend="i">become</hi> the murderer Falkland, the slave and master changing roles,
reflects the central problem, which Godwin shared with his contemporary Blake, of whether history is a closed
structure as the MS. ending suggests; one involving irreversible change; or merely cyclic and repetitive.</p>
          <p>If we put aside the Godwin model for a “Jacobin novel” embodied in this succession of novels, we
are left with a number of more traditional models. These are masked by the tendency to call Jacobin fiction
(plays as well as novels) <hi rend="i">Such Things Are</hi> or <hi rend="i">Wives as They Were and Maids as
They Are</hi> (Inchbald, 1787 and 1797), <hi rend="i">Man as He Is, Things as They Are, Elinor, or The World
As It Is</hi> (Mary J. Hanaway, 1798), and <hi rend="i">What Has Been</hi> (Mrs. Mathews, 1803). These titles,
usually disingenuous, do express the attempt to get out from behind the conventions of fiction and show
conditions as they were. The greatest and most successful case was Goya’s <hi rend="i">Desastres</hi> with
the inscriptions “Can such things be?” or “Such things are,” or “I saw this myself.” But in England these
titles expressed an ideal rather than an accomplishment.</p>
          <p>We can imagine a writer asking himself: how <hi rend="i">does</hi> one write a revolutionary
novel (overt or covert) in the 1790s in England? The novelistic alternatives seem to have been to portray a
hero who goes out into the world and learns how corruptly society operates, and is disillusioned; or to
portray a hero who, once he has learned this, goes around setting things straight. The first was Holcroft’s
strategy in <hi rend="i">Hugh Trevor</hi> (1794-97), which is hardly an advance on <hi rend="i">Roderick
Random.</hi> The second solution was followed by Bage in <hi rend="i">Hermsprong, or Man as He Is Not</hi>
(1796). An American, an echo of the Huron in Voltaire’s <hi rend="i">L’Ingenu</hi>, with no clear past,
enters and disrupts the remote, over-conventionalized society of Grondale. He talks about the French
Revolution and the clamp-down of Freedom of speech and thought in England, seeing from the vantage of an
American who has come to England by way of France.</p>
          <p>It is no surprise to find a great many children either disowned or cut off by their fathers.
(Hugh Trevor has the same sort of relationship with his grandfather.) In <hi rend="i">Hermsprong</hi> Glen’s
father will not acknowledge him; Miss Campinet’s will barely acknowledge her, sending her off to live with
an aunt; Miss Fluart’s father has died, turning her over to a lawyer-guardian. Bage takes up Burke’s
panegyric on primogeniture and aristocratic chivalry and gives us appalling examples in Lord Grondale and Sir
Philip Chestrum, with Dr. Blick their today clergyman. A sprightly dialogue between Miss Campinet and Miss
Fluart replays the argument between Anna and Frank Henley on the loyalty to a father, concluding that a tie of
blood is not sufficient sanction for tyranny. Hermsprong is lucky enough to have no such ties. Asked where the
“price” of custom “is <hi rend="i">not</hi> paid,” he answers Miss Campinet: “Amongst the aborigines of
America, Miss Campinet. There . . . I was born a savage.” “I am a young American, without father or mother;
but with a fortune that sets me above the necessity of employment.” Thus he operates as an Orc figure who
shatters the image of the decadent, self-indulgent aristocracy (Bage’s image of leading-strings recalls
Goya’s <hi rend="i">Capricho</hi> No. 4). Having assumed their inherited role as protector in emergencies
when they are absent or unable to act, he proceeds to defeat their strategies to discredit him, and at the end
reveals himself to be the rightful heir to the land and title which Lord Grondale has usurped.</p>
          <p>His being himself an aristocrat is a convention which keeps the novel safe. Another is Bage’s
denouement. After preparing for an uprising of Lord Grondale’s miners, with his fiefdom collapsing around
his ears and this English Louis XVI even planning a “flight to Varennes,” Bage has the revolt fail to
materialize when Hermsprong dissuades the miners, using arguments of an almost Pittite hue.</p>
          <p>Kelly sees these novelists as somewhat more original than I do. He argues for various kinds of
revision, or what he calls Jacobinizing, of the conventional forms, both social and fictional. The
Jacobinization of the Smollettian picaresque in <hi rend="i">Hugh Trevor</hi> involves making the
“impetuosity” of
<pb id="p11-297" n="297"/>
the picaro reflect the French, supposedly regarded by the English as impetuous, and <corr type="emend">more so</corr> in their
catastrophically over-zealous revolution. Richardson’s Sir Charles Grandison, the perfect Christian hero, is
Jacobinized by Godwin into Ferdinando Falkland. It emerges that Jacobinization means allegorizing, or
re-allegorizing, conventional forms or topoi. Kelly’s chief contribution, I believe, lies in his drawing
attention to these revolutionary reformulations, though (as in the case of “impetuosity”) I do not always find
myself convinced in particular cases.</p>
          <p>Coke Clifton, the potential Lovelace of <hi rend="i">Anna St. Ives</hi>, undoubtedly carries with
him Burkean overtones of chivalry, to be seen in their “true colors.” The Chateau of Villebrun appears to be a
translation of Brunswick and the count who has read the <corr type="emend">Provençal</corr> poets and romanciers “till he has made
himself a kind of Don Quixote” evokes, of course, Paine’s name for Burke. One thinks of Erdman’s
interpretation of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, with its allusions to Gillray caricatures of Burke and
Pitt, when Kelly argues that Sir Barnard Bray and Falkland (and to some extent St. Leon) are all portraits of
Burke; as Dr. Blick, the fat Bishop in <hi rend="i">Hugh Trevor</hi>, and other bad clergymen are portraits of
Bishop Horsley; Lord Idford alludes to the Duke of Portland; and <hi rend="i">Bryan Perdue</hi> contains
references to the “English Pit” and to pitfalls. All of these—most of them probable—at the very least
provide annotation not to be found in the volumes of the Oxford English Novel series.</p>
          <p>Kelly is also right to detect allegorical formulations in <hi rend="i">Anna St. Ives.</hi> A
general allegory of class is set up in Sir Arthur’s mania for improvement and his factotum Abimelech
Henley’s exploitation of this mania, and the central triangle of Coke Clifton, Anna, and Frank represents
values of chivalry, reform, and perhaps nature—“a paradigm of the political situation of the 1790s,” says
Kelly. Kelly’s most interesting point is that allegorical resonance is achieved by the play on names. He
gives us elaborate sources for Coke Clifton and other Holcroft names, but settles down to business with 
<hi rend="i">Caleb Williams.</hi> Falkland’s name is meant to recall the Lord Falkland of the Civil War (down to
the fact that he fought a celebrated duel) and Ferdinando is a particular reference to the “heroic and
chivalric King of Spain.” We can at least accept Ferdinando as a generally chivalric name, and certainly
Godwin, like many of his contemporaries, brought the present conflict into the context of the English Civil
War.</p>
          <p>I become less easy when I read that Falkland therefore equals <hi rend="i">ancien-régime</hi>
France, and Caleb equals the early moderate reformers of the Revolution—Lafayette and the Girondists, and in
particular General Dumouriez, who was “faced with the agonizing decision of having to join France’s enemies
and seek her downfall, or leaving the national distemper to run its course.” Kelly’s argument gains
plausibility from the existence of Dumouriez’ <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi>, translated by a friend of
Godwin’s in 1794. “By attempting to root out the evil of the old feudal regime,” writes Kelly, “Caleb
Williams, and the French moderates, found they had helped to destroy the whole fabric.” This may or may not
be; but Kelly’s main points about topicality are convincing, especially as regards the agencies of Pittite
oppression finding their reflection in “the kind of social and semi-legal persecution Caleb Williams had to
endure for daring to question the integrity of Falkland his employer.”</p>
          <p>There is only confirmation in the fact that Goodwin’s fictions after <hi rend="i">Caleb
Williams</hi> become ever more allegorical, or that even Inchbald retreats into fable in that “Satire upon the
Times” which became <hi rend="i">Nature and Art</hi>, where she translates Pope’s “And wretches hang that
jurymen may dine” into the literal scene of William passing sentence of death on his ex-mistress Agnes, who
swoons “while he adjourned court to go to dinner.” The circumstances that produced <hi rend="i">A Simple
Story</hi> and <hi rend="i">Caleb Williams</hi> were unrepeatable, and both writers returned to easier and
more conventional ways of dealing with political issues, which themselves became increasingly fuzzy. It is the
accomplishment of Kelly’s <hi rend="i">English Jacobin Novel</hi> that we can now see these high points in a
clearer relation to contemporary run-of-the-mill novels and plays, to their predecessors, and to the various
alternative ways of dealing with the Jacobin experience in fiction.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
