<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>11.4.job</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">Job in Frankfurt Schauspielhaus</title>
        <author n="Dörrbecker">Detlef W. Dörrbecker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">11.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Susan Fox</name>
              <name>Laurence Goldstein</name>
              <name>Janice Lyle</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Ronald Paulson</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_11">
    <body>
      <pb id="p11-298" n="298"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-11-4-0009">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">NEWSLETTER</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">JOB IN FRANKFURT SCHAUSPIELHAUS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>In Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi> we find the record of a conversation between Samuel
Palmer and William Blake concerning the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> illustrations. Palmer recollects that he “asked
him [Blake] how he would like to paint on glass, for the great west window [of Westminster Abbey], his ‘Sons
of God shouting for Joy,’ from his designs in the <hi rend="i">Job.</hi> He said, after a pause, ‘I could
do it’ kindling at the thought.” (Gilchrist, 1863, I, 303). Almost 150 years after Blake’s death this
idea—mutatis mutandis—was finally put into practice, not in Westminster Abbey and not by Blake himself, of
course, but on stage at the Frankfurt Schauspielhaus by the scenic designer Erich Wonder. On 5 June 1977 I
went to see the first performance of Tankred Dorst and Horst Laube’s new play, <hi rend="i">Goncourt oder:
Die Abschaffung des Todes</hi>—itself, I thought, rather disappointing. The stage directions for scene 16,
however, demanded the interior of a small Gothic chapel where members of the 1871 Paris Commune were to be
seen during one of their last meetings prior to their final defeat, which was inflicted upon them by the
<corr type="emend">troops</corr> of the reactionary Thiers. The design for the one “stained glass window” shown in the scenery was taken
from Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> watercolors. A giant transparency enlargement of the Butts version of
“When the Morning Stars Sang Together” had been cut into the shape of a slightly pointed twelfth-century
Gothic window, thus spreading some spiritual comfort and hope on the representation of that otherwise 
<corr type="emend">desperate</corr> moment in history. Whether Erich Wonder in his stage design did so with or
without knowledge of the Blakean context I cannot say. For me—and I hope some others in the audience
too—the appearance of that reproduction both meant that the sufferings of the Commune members were related
to the sufferings of the Biblical patriarch, and that at the same time there was a promise for their final
redemption (which will be ours too). <byline><docAuthor>DETLEF W. 
<corr type="emend"><name>DÖRRBECKER</name>,</corr></docAuthor> FRANKFURT.</byline></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
