<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>11.4.jefferys</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">James Jefferys Update</title>
        <author n="Butlin">Martin Butlin</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">11.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Susan Fox</name>
              <name>Laurence Goldstein</name>
              <name>Janice Lyle</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Ronald Paulson</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_11">
    <body>
	<pb id="p11-298" n="298"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-11-4-0009">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">NEWSLETTER</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">JAMES JEFFERYS UPDATE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> for spring 1977 it was hinted that two further developments were
imminent in the rediscovery of James Jefferys.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39"
type="note">1</ref> Both have now appeared in the April 1977 issue of <hi rend="i">The Burlington
Magazine.</hi> The first article, by John Sunderland, reports the discovery by Timothy Clifford at the close
of the Jefferys exhibition that the drawing formerly accepted as a self-portrait from behind by John Hamilton
Mortimer in fact shows a figure holding a drawing by Jefferys included in the exhibition.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">2</ref> It was also clear that the drawing was
inscribed in Jefferys’ hand, including the address “To Mr. Benchley,” Jefferys’ early patron at Maidstone.
The conclusion is that both this drawing, now in the Mellon Collection at Yale, and the companion
self-portrait seen from the front, in the National Portrait Gallery, London, are by Jefferys. It is
interesting that Sunderland had already suspected that other so-called Mortimers from the same source as these
two drawings were not by him; one can now look for a strongly Mortimeresque phase in the development of
Jefferys’ very eclectic style. <note id="n39"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Martin Butlin, “The Rediscovery of an
Artist: James Jeffreys 1751-1784” in <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 40 (Spring 1977), pp. 123-24, two
drawings repr.</note>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">2</hi> John Sunderland, “Two Self-Portraits by James Jefferys?” in 
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 119 (April 1977), 279-80, the two drawings repr. p. 281, figs. 76 and
77.</note></p>
          <p>This may be still more eclectic than has been supposed. The other article was by Nancy L.
Pressly, identifying Jefferys with the mysterious “Master of the Giants.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">3</ref> Various attributions to such artists as Prince Hoare have
proved untenable and, although Mrs. Pressly’s identification has not yet been whole-heartedly accepted in
all quarters, it seems convincing to me. The sketchy treatment of the background figures of the “Master of the
Giants” drawings, perhaps more than the more consciously finished foreground figures, seems particularly close
to Jefferys’ style; a distinctive manner of drawing kneecaps is a characteristic feature of both groups of
drawings! It is good news that Mrs.
<pb id="p11-299" n="299"/>
Pressly is continuing her study of the activity at Rome in the 1770s of such artists as Fuseli, Sergel,
Alexander Runciman, John Brown, Romney and Mauritius Lowe: the <hi rend="i">teribilità</hi>, forceful rather
than accomplished, of much of Blake’s work in the 1780s seems to owe as much to these artists’ revival of
Mannerism as it does to the more orthodox tenets of Neo-Classicism. 
<byline><docAuthor>MARTIN <name>BUTLIN</name>,</docAuthor> KEEPER OF THE BRITISH COLLECTION, TATE GALLERY, 
LONDON.</byline>
<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Nancy L. Pressly, “James Jefferys and the
‘Master of the Giants,’” <hi rend="i">ibid.</hi>, pp. 280-84, drawings by Jefferys, including some
formerly attributed to the Master of the Giants, repr. pp. 282 and 285, figs. 80-86.</note></p>
<figure n="FallenWarrior.11.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="750" height="464">
	<head>James Jefferys, “Fallen Warrior lying against a Dead Horse.”</head>
	<figDesc>Pen and grey wash over pencil 19-¾ × 30-¼ (50.1 × 76.8) Maidstone Museum and Art
Gallery.</figDesc>
</figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
