<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>11.4.worrall</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Joan Evans, A History of the Society of Antiquaries</title>
        <author n="Worrall">David Worrall</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">11.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Susan Fox</name>
              <name>Laurence Goldstein</name>
              <name>Janice Lyle</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Ronald Paulson</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_11">
    <body>
      <pb id="p11-287" n="287"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-11-4-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure n="Antiquaries.11.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="347"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Joan Evans. <hi rend="b">A History of The Society of Antiquaries.</hi> Oxford:
Society of Antiquaries, 1956. Published rebound, London: Thames &amp; Hudson, 1977. Pp. xv + 487. 44
black-and-white plates.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">David</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Worrall</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p><corr type="emend">“The</corr> British Antiquities are now in the Artist’s hands” wrote Blake in <hi rend="i">A
Descriptive Catalogue.</hi> This rebound issue of Joan Evans’s book, distributed by Thames &amp; Hudson, and
dealing with the Society’s history from its Renaissance precursors up to the early 1950’s, provides a
timely opportunity for examining the intellectual context of Blake’s “visionary contemplations” concerning
his own country.</p>
          <p>Professor England has shown us how Samuel Foote’s parody of an Antiquaries meeting in 
<hi rend="i">The Nabob</hi> led the way to Etruscan Column’s lecture on “virtuous cats” in “An Island in the
Moon.” Reading through the eighteenth-century part of this history one can see how nearly Foote held the
mirror up to life. This production of the summer of 1772 must have virtually coincided with the beginning of
Blake’s apprenticeship to James Basire, who had been the Society’s engraver since March 1759. Foote’s
joke about Antiquaries and cats had been sparked off by a paper read by Samuel Pegge in December 1771 in which
he conjectured that Dick Whittington’s “cat” had been the name of a type of ship. The ridicule prompted by
<hi rend="i">The Nabob</hi> brought Horace Walpole’s resignation from the Society in 1773 but he had earlier
confided his intention in a letter to William Cole written on 28 July 1772, only a few days before Blake’s
exchange of indentures with Basire. Despite nineteen years of membership, Walpole’s involvement with the
Society had been indifferent and recently embittered by criticism, so that this episode of “their council on
Whittington and his cat, and the ridicule that Foote has thrown on them” (to Cole) provided a convenient but
honorable occasion for departure.</p>
          <p>The Basire family held their position well into the nineteenth century, and Joan Evans has made
the forgiveable error of attributing William as the apprentice of James Basire the Younger who was elected a
Fellow in 1823. Fortunately for Blake’s training, both master and apprentice had only the very highest
standards to seek to emulate since, until his death, almost all previous engraving for the Society had been
under the management and general surveillance of George Vertue. Vertue had not only been one of the
Society’s founder members, but both benevolent and indefatigably active on its behalf for nearly half a
century, and it was largely through his influence that the early parts of <hi rend="i">Vestuta Monumenta</hi>
contained as much medieval material as they did. It was for this irregularly issued record of the Society’s
activities and interests that Blake’s Westminster Abbey sketches were intended, probably following the
immediate initiative of Richard Gough, who had become their enthusiastic Director the year before Blake’s
entry into apprenticeship.</p>
          <p>In his <hi rend="i">Topographical Antiquities</hi> (1768), Gough had bemoaned the lack of an
antiquarian periodical
<pb id="p11-288" n="288"/>
miscellany, and during the period of Blake’s apprenticeship he put much energy into insuring the continued
publication of the Society’s <hi rend="i">Archaeologia</hi>, which had begun in 1770 in order to fulfill
this role. Such were Gough’s efforts in this direction that Blake’s Westminster Abbey sketches remained
unpublished until 1780, but the <hi rend="i">Archaeologia</hi>, while adding a new dimension to the
Society’s pursuits, radically increased the amount of engraving undertaken by Basire for the Society. During
Blake’s apprenticeship, issues were published in 1773, 1775, 1777 and 1779. Most of the papers are
illustrated with engravings signed by Basire, and it is a source of harmless speculation to wonder how many of
them Blake had a hand in.</p>
          <p>After his resignation Horace Walpole greeted most of the Society’s enthusiasms with amused
incredulity, and there were certainly enough <hi rend="i">Archaeologia</hi> papers on such topics as
cockfighting, horseshoes and buried bird bones to validate his reactions. Their interests were not narrowly in
archaeological “hardware,” however, and a similar impulse to that which prompted the publication of papers on
the origin of the word “Romance” and on “The Wisdom of the Ancient Egyptians” must have led the President,
Jeremiah Milles, to sponsor the second edition of Chatterton’s Rowley poems in 1782 despite the cordially
tepid response from the rest of the Society, who appear to have sensed the presence of forgery.</p>
          <p>It is difficult to escape the conclusion that at this period the Society was intellectually
second-rate: certainly their ranks in the second half of the century can muster no mind approaching that of
William Stukeley, whose varied researches had been without parallel during the Society’s early years.
Inevitably, this “antique” company of aged and conscious exclusiveness became the fair and easy victim of
caricaturists from both within, such as Francis Grose, and without, such as Thomas Rowlandson. Joan Evans
reproduces an interesting Rowlandson cartoon dating from c. 1795 which appears to be based on the opening of
the tomb of Edward I in 1772, when Blake was probably present. Entitled “Death and the Antiquaries,” a group
of antiquaries gather round an opened royal tomb, one stealing a ring from the corpse, while a skeletal Death
stands outraged above. This episode was remarkable in the Society’s history because it was just about the
first time they had been taken seriously enough to be allowed to interfere with a relic of national
importance. The late date of Rowlandson’s plate is silent testimony enough to the uneventful obscurity to
which they subsequently returned.</p>
          <p>Although such figures in Blake’s world as Benjamin Heath Malkin and Henry Crabb Robinson found
admittance to the Society at some point in their lives, the Antiquaries and their pursuits had little effect
on Blake’s imagination or intellectual development. To return to his remarks in <hi rend="i">A Descriptive
Catalogue</hi>, it is clear that the “British Antiquities” have already become transformed into a part of the
Blake Pantheon. Blake recognized antiquity as witness to the loss of imagination and the ascendancy of memory.
The sublime truth represented diagramatically in the well-known illustration of the Mundane Shell and
Universes of the Four Zoas in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> became distorted and petrified into the serpent temples
of Britain. Milton’s journey from Eternity, seen in Time by Milton’s vision of Satan’s fall through the
Serpentarius constellation in <corr type="emend">Ophiuchus</corr> (<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> Bk. II), was distorted by the Druids
into the serpent and mundane shell configuration of the serpent temples. The transfiguring re-emergence from
the mundane shell, which Blake characterizes as being without dimension, became further distorted by Druidic
vision into the other half of the serpent ascending out of the circle of stones in unconscious repetition of
the original fall. This portrayal of the cosmological through the antique probably had its beginnings in the
eighteenth century’s association of stone circles with sun worship, but the development is so extensive as
to leave these theories far behind. In similar fashion, Blake’s reference to the “pavement of
Watling-street” in <hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalogue</hi> comprehends not only the ancient Roman road but
the traditional English (and Chaucerian) name for the Milky Way.</p>
          <p>Unfortunately, the antiquarian writers Blake most obviously seems to have admired, such as Jacob
Bryant and Edward Davies, figured little if at all in the Society’s affairs and neither finds
acknowledgement in Joan Evans’s book. The congenial literary and mythological emphasis of these writers was
declining in importance as more scientific methods of inquiry began to assert their worth (to the Society’s
benefit, it has to be said). Outside the Society, isolated enthusiasts continued their researches relatively
untroubled by the consensus of informed development, and it was from these quarters that some of the most
imaginative studies stemmed. In the final years of the eighteenth century, the antiquarian writer who most
obviously exemplified the virtues Blake admired was Thomas Maurice, whose <hi rend="i">Indian Antiquities</hi>
ranges over the cultures of the major Mediterranean, Northern and Eastern civilizations before returning to an
extended account of Stonehenge and ancient Britain during the course of proving his thesis that all nations
have spontaneously recognized a divine trinity. For the student of the backgrounds of Romanticism in
comparative mythology and antiquity, Maurice’s work provides a clear and well-documented guide to the state
of research as it existed in these fields and may be used in conjunction with the broad outlines offered by
Joan Evans, but the Blakeophile will inevitably need to consult <hi rend="i">A History of The Society of
Antiquaries</hi> for knowledge of the Society’s interests and personalities during the period of his
apprenticeship.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
