<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.1.hagstrum</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">David Bindman, Blake as an Artist</title>
                <author n="Hagstrum">Jean H. Hagstrum</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1978</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Shelley Grieve</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Mary Clarke</name>
                            <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
                            <name>Frank Graziano</name>
                            <name>Jean H. Hagstrum</name>
                            <name>Gunnar Harding</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Joe Napora</name>
                            <name>Martin K. Numri</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>R. W. Peattie</name>
                            <name>Marcia Tillotson</name>
                            <name>Gunnel Tottie</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1978"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-1-0011">
            	<pb id="p12-64" n="64"/> 
                <div2>
                    <figure n="BindmanBlakeasanArtist.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="429"/>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">David Bindman. Blake as an Artist. Oxford: Phaidon. New York: E. P.
                            Dutton, 1977. Pp. 256, 182 illus. in black and white; 4 pls. in color.
                            $18.95</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="b">Jean H.</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">Hagstrum</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>This book grew out of David Bindman’s 1971 doctoral dissertation at
                        the Courtauld Institute. Its aim is to take “an analytical view of
                        Blake’s art with particular emphasis upon its relationship to English
                        art of his own time” (p. 9). Blake’s achievement is broadly
                        enough conceived to include all the illuminated books as well as
                        Blake’s paintings and engravings in all media, including the
                        illustrations of the Bible, Milton, <corr type="emend">Bunyan,</corr> Gray, Young, and
others. The
                        “seemingly more conventional designs” (p. 9)—that is, those
                        that do not accompany Blake’s own words—Bindman properly sees
                        as an end in themselves to which the decorated poetry contributes meanings
                        and motifs. Most literary scholars have it the other way round, making what
                        Frye once called the canonical works the center of their attention; but
                        Bindman does not see these as “self-contained” (p. 9). Following
                        in the footsteps of his teachers, Blunt and Butlin, he uses, for the most
                        part, the methods of an art historian, analyzing the visual elements of
                        Blake’s <hi rend="i">oeuvre</hi> and their relation to contemporary
                        and antecedent art. He defines his 
                    <pb id="p12-65" n="65"/> 
                    	task in such a
                        way as to require more attention to Blake’s artistic friends and
                        contemporaries than to the grand examples of Dürer, Raphael,
                        Michelangelo, and the Mannerists. Even so, Bindman does not give a
                        sufficiently detailed account of Blake’s relations to Fuseli,
                        Flaxman, Banks, Romney, West, Barry, Mortimer, all of whom are mentioned and
                        some of whom are discussed with penetration. One would have to say that the
                        iconographical and stylistic relations of Blake to English art need still to
                        be studied, since Bindman subordinates this important scholarly task to his
                        chronological plan of analyzing each important work of Blake as it appeared,
                        concentrating on its meaning and value. The author has thus given us not so
                        much a new work of intellectual synthesis or of scholarship as another
                        introduction to Blake’s chief works with incidental comments on their
                        personal and traditional contexts.</p>
                    <p>What point of view about Blake’s ultimate place in art history
                        prevails? Boldly but disarmingly, Bindman derives his perspective from none
                        other than Reynolds, whose characterization of the “original or
                        characteristical style” he applies to Blake (pp. 9-10). That style the
                        president of the Royal Academy had regarded as inferior to the grand style
                        though it was produced by men “of lively and vigorous
                        imagination,” but he found it valuable because it reveals internal
                        coherence and harmony even when irregular, wild, and incorrect. It can be
                        admired as the faithful picture of a mind, and it commands attention for its
                        consistency even though it does not rise to elevation. This use of Reynolds
                        at the very beginning of the book is, in its way, refreshing; it seems to
                        give Bindman his perspective, leading him into commentary that is central
                        and commonsensical. He honors his subject and is capable of enthusiastic
                        appreciation, but one never has the feeling that Bindman confuses Blake with
                        Michelangelo or Rembrandt.</p>
                    <p>Since this book confronts all of Blake’s visual and visual-verbal
                        works, the literary scholar will be curious to know how well the
                        “readings” come off. Very well indeed, in my view. The mastery of
                        modern scholarship is impressive, the knowledge of Blake’s visual and
                        literary contexts exemplary. The criticism of particular works is the more
                        effective for being organized and for being related to developing topics
                        that run all through the study. Sometimes, to be sure, Bindman, like so many
                        of us, runs to mere description; but it is gratifying to notice that more
                        often than not the elements treated are properly subordinated in an analysis
                        and that a real effort has been made to arrive at interpretation. The
                        readings are “prophetic”—that is, Bindman knows and uses
                        Blake’s myth and is therefore not content with surface meanings or
                        traditional iconographic interpretation. In discussing, for example, the
                        colorprint of 1795 entitled <hi rend="i">Pity</hi>, Bindman sees it, along
                        with its companion <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi>, as an expression of the Female
                        Will. The child is Orc, the son of Enitharmon, who lies prone on the ground.
                        In the same series, the <hi rend="i">Good and Evil Angels</hi> is seen as a
                        continuation of the story of Orc in which a jealous Los (and here there is a
                        recollection of his role in <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>) reaches
                        out to restrain the revolutionary boy (p. 99).</p>
                    <p>Most “readings” are similarly “prophetic,” and Bindman is
                        a good guide to the essential meanings of both word and figure. But one does
                        have reservations, and some of these are important enough to divulge.
                        Although the description of the Vales of Har in <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>
                        (pp. 44-46)—and that particular spot of Blakean spiritual geography I
                        myself find to be of the highest importance—is very good, one is
                        tempted to ask, Where is the horror? The horror, that is, of a mature woman
                        and a white-bearded man sleeping together like infants and, awake, panting
                        out puerilities. Bindman’s description of these Vales as being
                        “lyrical” or as being a prefiguration of Beulah obscures their
                        qualities of regression and arrested development. Other commentary reveals
                        the same critical fault: it is sound and central but not sufficiently
                        emphatic and so, through excessive caution, dissipates some of
                        Blake’s power of expression and blunts his often dismaying
                        originality. The analysis of <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> contains one
                        serious confusion. Can Thel be said to confront Experience when she
                        encounters the Lily, the Cloud, the Worm, and the Clod of Clay, all of whom
                        are surely denizens of Blake’s Innocence, enjoying its uninhibited
                        freedom and displaying its love and charity with unselfconscious ease? The
                        world of Experience seems to me to be confined to the last plate; it is from
                        that vision of social and psychological perversion which Thel flees at the
                        end, not from the joyous portrayal of natural life.</p>
                    <p>Rather than pausing to note such qualifications as these all the way through
                        the book, perhaps it would be wise to concentrate on the interpretation of
                        one important illuminated work. In commenting on <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
                        (pp. 79 ff), that beautiful, resonant, and complex Lambeth prophecy, Bindman
                        perceives why the incarnation of Christ is so important at this historical
                        moment, why Urizen appears on the frontispiece, why the title-page serpent
                        is so energetic (though something should have been said on how it is related
                        to the similar serpent on plate 10 and to the whole matter of revolutionary
                        versus counter-revolutionary serpents), why the inquiring man is
                        Blake’s Mental Traveller, why Enitharmon holds the veil over the
                        sleeping youth (she is covering and not unveiling him), and why the
                        spiderweb is the net of religion (is it not, however, woven primarily by
                        Urizen and not by Albion’s Angels?). And yet, good though it is, the
                        commentary does not confront the truly difficult cruxes. What is the meaning
                        of the nameless shadowy female, who brandishes her snaky hair? Why does
                        Newton blow the trumpet? Blake evidently perceived that when revolutionary
                        forces are unleashed a fecund nature will utter uninhibited and chaotic
                        cries against all order, even the artistic. He also saw that the possessor
                        of a great genius that had been perverted to mischievous cultural and
                        intellectual ends might well fill the cup of iniquity to overflowing and so
                        precipitate both revolution and counter-revolution.</p>
                    <p>The analyses of the purely visual works are usually excellent. Bindman sees
                        the prophetic potential in Blake’s early “neo-classical”
                        works (observe his perceptive comment on the significance of Joseph in
                        Egypt, pp. 34-35). Very often he adduces original materials which help
                        interpret the works in question; and he alerts us to what is 
<pb id="p12-66" n="66"/>
often neglected or may surprise us, Blake’s admiration
                        of Claude (p. 203) or a possible recollection of Rembrandt (p. 126). But
                        even in the area of the purely visual, where Bindman is more thoroughly
                        trained than most Blake commentators, we find that his plan of covering
                        everything forces him to be excessively brief and general at crucial
                        moments. For example, although he is fully aware of the superiority of the
                        Boston <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> illustrations to those in the
                        Huntington, he misses an opportunity to show in precise detail the
                        superiority of one version of Adam, Eve, and Raphael over the other (pp.
                        190-191 and plates 152, 153). In the Huntington version the profiles of Adam
                        and Eve are simply drawn and as expressions are undifferentiated. In the
                        Boston version the facial lineaments of our first parents are subtly drawn
                        and express profound meaning: Adam seems to be confused and disturbed by
                        what he hears and Eve responds delicately, wonderingly and submissively to
                        his confusion. The bodies of the first pair are also more powerfully
                        modeled, and the angel looks less like a worried human being and more like a
                        royal, though slightly surprised, heavenly monitor. The centrality of
                        Eve’s standing position in a later version not only provides the
                        beautiful female form at the focus of our attention, not only shows her
                        separated from Adam, but may also point to her central role in the Fall and
                        perhaps even ultimately in the redemption of man. Blake was certainly not
                        the master of facial expression that the very greatest portrait artists
                        were; but faces and particularly eyes are extremely important, as the
                        superiority of the Boston version of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> over the
                        Huntington also expresses. Bindman is extremely good in showing the 
<hi rend="i">formal</hi> superiority of the later version of <hi rend="i">Comus and his Revellers</hi>, for
example (p. 186 and plates 146, 147),
                        but he says nothing of the greater richness and humanity of the Boston lady
                        over the rather flat, simple, one-dimensional San Marino virgin. Similarly,
                        on page 115, in an otherwise excellent analysis of a watercolor entitled 
<hi rend="i">Malevolence</hi>, Bindman seems to miss the importance of the
                        youthful father’s gaze, which is directed at Malevolence (plate 96),
                        showing that the hideous psychological states portrayed can be seen as being
                            <hi rend="i">caused</hi> by merit (“He hath a daily beauty in his
                        life that makes mine ugly”). In the same painting the father’s
                        calm gaze is returned by the two fiends, each staring back in his own malign
                        way while the wife and child fix their gazes upon the father. In fact, one
                        of the most striking features of this powerful work are the lines of force
                        and meaning that are generated by the eye-contacts of five people.
                        Surprisingly, such matters are usually met with silence by Bindman, who
                        apparently is not often impressed with the importance in Blake of eyes and
                        glances.</p>
                    <p>To turn to an important matter involving Blake’s artistic background,
                        one wishes that Bindman had been a little bit fuller on the influence of
                        Raphael. It is not that he neglects the prince of painters or that he would
                        not acknowledge that Raphael is one of Blake’s culture heores. It is
                        rather that his several references are not pulled together into a coherent
                        whole, and we are therefore not allowed to see what is one of the most
                        powerful, consistent, and uninterrupted influences upon Blake by any
                        antecedent painter. I shall not repeat the case I made for Raphael’s
                        influence in <hi rend="i">William Blake Poet and Painter</hi> (pp. 41-43 and
                        plates XIXA, XIXB, XX, XXI). Here I would only like to disagree with
                        Bindman’s finding that in <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> it is
                        Michelangelo’s God the Father in the Sistine Chapel who chiefly
                        presides over Blake’s imagination (pp. 89-95). I find, instead, that
                        it is the God of Raphael’s Bible, as engraved by some of his
                        followers, whose body, hand-positions, and activities are precise
                        anticipations of Blake’s creator-god. I do not wish to deny that
                        Michelangelo and the Sistine Chapel may indeed be present in Blake’s
                        imagination (they almost always are), but I wish to suggest that, in terms
                        of context, the Genesis of Blake’s Bible of Hell is a direct and
                        forceful inversion of Raphael.</p>
                    <p>I have praised the centrality and soundness of Bindman’s commentary.
                        That praise is meant to embrace his perception of what is revolutionary and
                        revisionist in Blake’s religion. More than once Bindman reveals that
                        he is aware that his subject possessed a radical, inquiring, restless mind,
                        not content to dwell comfortably in the house of conventional platitude,
                        however beautiful. Nevertheless, all the way through the book the author
                        displays a tendency to use Christian and Neoplatonic truisms to describe
                        Blake’s essential vision, often omitting the specific details, the
                        alterations of convention, even the subversions of meaning that give it
                        originality, force, and revolutionary energy. A few examples will show the
                        “piety” that tends to prevail and that appears in language which
                        is too close to Blake’s own phrasing to be illuminating and which can
                        obscure Blake’s radical originality. Thus the designs and texts of
                            <hi rend="i">The Songs of Innocence</hi> are said to pertain primarily
                        to the idea of man’s salvation (p. 62). The caves that entrap Oothoon
                        are “materialistic” (p. 74). The cage that imprisons the soul is
                        the body in the lovely early poem, “How Sweet I Roam’d” (p.
                        86). Albion’s dance is a paradigm of “regeneration,” which
                        is here called “the true religious ecstasy” (p. 97). A lonely
                        woman in the moonlight of one of the Young illustrations (p. 112) is
                        “the soul seeking the aid of truth”—an “ineffable
                        resonance” (p. 112). And Paul’s posture in <hi rend="i">St. Paul
                            Preaching at Athens</hi> suggests the “timeless operation of the
                        spirit” (p. 138). But if we look more closely at these
                        examples—and several others might have been chosen—we see that
                        Bindman has caught Blake’s meaning in a conventional net and that the
                        complex, troubled emotion of the original has been rendered somewhat
                        complacent by the commentary. The rigidity of Paul’s form and
                        position, the excessive symmetry of the composition, the expression on his
                        face, and his relation to the light make the Apostle at best an ambiguous
                        figure. One wonders if the young female asking the way of two nightwatchmen
                        by moonlight may not be a young woman like Lyca of <hi rend="i">Innocence
                            and Experience</hi>, encountering a young man and an old man in the
                        deserts of sexuality, rather than the soul ineffably seeking the truth.
                        Albion’s dance, by Blake’s own word, is the “dance of
                        Eternal Death”: can it therefore be called a “key image of
                        Regeneration” (p. 97)? The cage is more often that of love and marriage
                        in Blake than of the body, and the lovely words of “How Sweet I
                        Roam’d” are more erotic than Neoplatonic. Oothoon’s 
<pb id="p12-67" n="67"/>
cave
is rather marital and sexual than
                        materialistic. And Christ is present in <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> more as
                        a sanctioner of sexual joy and uninhibited play than of other-worldly
                        salvation. Bindman may be a little too determined to see divine light in
                        Blake, a light which he usually interprets as supernatural. But, as Blake
                        said in concluding <hi rend="i">The Auguries of Innocence</hi>, God is light
                        primarily to those who dwell in unvisionary night but displays a human form
                        to those who live in realms of prophetic daylight.</p>
                    <p>It should perhaps be noted that something has rather frequently gone wrong
                        with references to the plates. I have noted the following mistakes: plate 39
                        on page 55, pl. 60 on p. 78, pl. 85 on p. 99, pl. 124 on p. 164, pl. 140 on
                        p. 178, pl. 165 on p. 204, pl. 169 on p. 210. In each of these instances,
                        the number refers to a work other than the one that appears on the
                        designated plate. In some cases the proper work appears elsewhere in this
                        volume, on another plate; occasionally it does not appear at all.</p>
                    <p>I do not wish to end negatively. Bindman’s book is an example of good
                        scholarship and trained, intelligent perceptions.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>