<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.1.gebentley</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="minute">The Selling of Blake’s Night Thoughts Designs in the 1870s</title>
                <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1978</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Shelley Grieve</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Mary Clarke</name>
                            <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
                            <name>Frank Graziano</name>
                            <name>Jean H. Hagstrum</name>
                            <name>Gunnar Harding</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Joe Napora</name>
                            <name>Martin K. Numri</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>R. W. Peattie</name>
                            <name>Marcia Tillotson</name>
                            <name>Gunnel Tottie</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1978"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
	<pb id="p12-70" n="70"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-1-0012">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">THE SELLING OF BLAKE’S <hi rend="i">NIGHT
                                    THOUGHTS</hi> DESIGNS IN THE 1870s</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor><hi rend="b">G. E. </hi><name><hi rend="b">Bentley</hi></name>, 
<hi rend="b">Jr.</hi>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>The most extensive series of illustrations Blake is known to have made was
                        for Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>—537 large water
                        colors preparatory for the Richard Edwards edition of 1797. When that
                        publication proved to be an incubator baby, requiring peace and seclusion
                        from the world for over a century before reaching full growth in public
                        esteem and commercial price, the drawings too were largely forgotten. They
                        passed from Richard Edwards to his brother Thomas, who offered them at
                        £52.10.0 in 1826 and 1828,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76"
type="note">1</ref> but even
                        praise comparing them favorably with the work of Michael Angelo could not
                        lure a collector to venture so large a sum.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n76" type="note" n="1b">1</ref> They therefore retreated into the bosom of the Edwards family,
                        and their whereabouts was almost completely unknown for some fifty years. In
                        his <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake, “Pictor Ignotus”</hi>
                        (1863) which revived Blake’s flickering fame, Alexander Gilchrist
                        supposed erroneously that the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> drawings had
                        gone to “one of the royal collections” (Vol. I, p. 140). A few new
                        facts have recently turned up which throw light on the history of the
                        drawings in the 1870s. <note id="n76">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (1969), 330-31, 368.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>About a decade later, the interest in Blake which Gilchrist’s book had
                        aroused fostered the emergence of the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
                        drawings again, and by the above passage in Gilchrist one reader wrote: 
						<q>
                            No, I saw these drawings, over 500 in number, at [<hi rend="i">the
                                bookdealer</hi>] Rimell’s in Oxford Street, in May 1874. They
                            were then the property of the Edwards family, and for sale.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77" type="note">2</ref>
                            <note id="n77">
                                <hi rend="s">2</hi> Quoted from the exta-illustrated copy
                                of Gilchrist recently acquired (1976) by the McGill University
                                Library. The annotator may have been the Laurence Aurrin [?] whose
                                bookplate is in the volumes.</note>
						</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>Something of the background of the re-emergence of the <hi rend="i">Night
                            Thoughts</hi> drawings is given in the diary of Louisa Bain, whose uncle
                        James was one of the chief antiquarian booksellers of the time. On 18 June
                        1874 she wrote that she went 
						<q> To the Haymarket [<hi rend="i">where the
                                Bain shop was located</hi>] and looked at the two volumes of
                            Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> with original
                            illustrations by William Blake, which James has lately met with [<hi rend="i">?at
Rimell’s</hi>], and thinks himself extremely
                            fortunate to have secured at the price of £425. He considers it a
                            perfect treasure, and people who are considered judges flock to see it,
                            and speak highly of it. I do not like it, but then I am no judge of its
                                merits.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78"
type="note">3</ref>
                            <note id="n78">
                                <hi rend="s">3</hi> James S. Bain, <hi rend="i">A
                                    Bookseller Looks Back:</hi> The Story of the Bains (London:
                                Macmillan, 1940), pp. 72-73.</note>
						</q>
						A year later, on 13 June 1875, she wrote again: 
						<q> James has spoke of
                            his <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> to Mr. Disraeli who advises his writing to
                            the British Museum authorities, and allows him to use his name, which we
                            hope will have great weight, both as Prime Minister and also as a member
                            of the British Museum Committee. James has written accordingly and they
                            have sent for the book, which is there now to be inspected. [<hi rend="i">P.
75</hi>] </q>
They had another reason to think that
                        Disraeli’s opinion might bear some weight, for he had inherited from
                        his father one of the most notable early collections of Blake’s books
                        and therefore was in a good position to judge Blake’s merits.
                        However, what Disraeli did was fairly minimal. The bookseller wrote to the
                        British Museum: 
						<q> James Bain<lb/>
 1 Haymarket<lb/>
 London (SW)<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            7th June 1875<lb/>
 Sir<lb/>
 I am desired by Mr. Disraeli to bring under
                            your notice some original drawings by William Blake now in my
                            possession.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
 The designs illustrate Young’s Night
                            Thoughts and are drawn upon the enlarged margins of the original quarto
                            text.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
 They form the most extensive series of designs done by
                            this Artist and tho’ unknown to his later biographers may be
                            regarded as the ‘great work’ of his life. As such it seems
                            desirable that they should find an appropriate place in the National
                            Collections. My price is £2,000. (Two Thousand Pounds)<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            Your obedient servant<lb/>
 (signed) James Bain.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79" type="note">4</ref>
                            <note id="n79">
                                <hi rend="s">4</hi> Quoted from the British Museum Print
                                Room’s “Original Letters and Papers,” June 1875,
                                Reg. no. 2720.</note>
						</q>
						The sponsorship of Disraeli was given through his Parliamentary
                        Secretary as follows: 
						<q> 10 Downing Street<lb/>
 Whitehall<lb/>
                            <lb/>
 June 9
                            1875<lb/>
 Dear Sir,<lb/>
                            <lb/>
 Mr. Disraeli desires me to send you the
                            enclosed letter left here today by Mr. Reid [<hi rend="i">Keeper of the
                                Department of Prints and Drawings in the British Museum</hi>], and
                            to tell you that on being asked by Mr. Bain in what way he could bring
                            the drawings referred to to the notice of the authorities of the British
                            Museum Mr. Disraeli advised him that the best course would be to write
                            to you on the subject and gave him authority to make use of his name in
                            the matter.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
 Yours faithfully,<lb/>
 (signed) James F.
                            Daly.<lb/>
 J. Winter Jones Esq.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80" type="note">5</ref>
                            <note id="n80">
                                <hi rend="s">5</hi> Ibid. Reg. no. 2821, quoted by
                                courtesy of H. M. Stationary Office.</note>
						</q>
                        <pb id="p12-71" n="71"/>
The discrepancy between James Bain’s
                        expectations and Disraeli’s performance is striking, and one does not
                        know whether to admire more the slipperiness of the politician or the
                        discretion of the statesman, struggling to avoid appearing as both advocate
                        and judge in the same cause.</p>
                    <p>On receipt of this letter, the Museum authorities sought the opinion of
                        George William Reid, the Keeper of the Print Room (1866-83), and he replied
                        on the same day: 
						<q> Department of Prints and Drawings<lb/>
 June 9th.
                            1875<lb/>
                            <lb/>
 Mr. Reid has the honour to report to the Trustees he has
                            carefully examined the 2 volumes of Blake’s designs offered to
                            the Trustees for the sum of £2,000 [<hi rend="i">or about £3.
                                15. 0 each</hi>], and finds the series very interesting but somewhat
                            dear.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
 The 2 volumes offered by Mr. Bain, if the purchase were
                            entertained, could only be acquired by the aid of a special grant, which
                            Mr. Reid has ascertained by Mr. Montagu Corry [<hi rend="i">a treasury
                                official</hi>] to be quite out of the question at the present
                            moment.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
 G. W. Reid<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81" type="note">6</ref>
                            <note id="n81">
                                <hi rend="s">6</hi> Quoted from “Original Letters
                                and Papers,” June 1875, Reg. no. 2822. The grant would
                                presumably have come, at least indirectly, from the First Lord of
                                the Treasury.</note>
						</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>This reply was of course decisive, and the Minutes of the British Museum
                        Standing Committee for 12 June 1875 (pp. 13292-93) record: 
						<q> Read a letter
                            from Mr. James Bain, dated the 7th of June, offering, for £2,000,
                            William Blake’s original drawings, in two volumes, in
                            illustration of Young’s Night Thoughts; also a letter from one of
                            the Secretaries of the First Lord of the Treasury, and a report from Mr.
                            Reid, both dated the 9th of June.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
 Resolved, that Mr.
                            Bain’s offer be declined. </q>
The conclusion was forwarded to
                        James Bain, whose niece wrote in her Journal for 17 June: “The British
                        Museum declines to take the <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>; I am so sorry” (p.
                        75).</p>
                    <p>Scholars of Blake and lovers of art had cause to be sorry too, for the
                        drawings remained in private hands for another fifty years. In the Bain
                        family, “the book was looked upon as a white elephant for twenty years
                        or more” until it was sold for £1,500 to Marsden J. Parry (p. 187),
                        from whom it passed to W. A. White a few years later, and the first partial
                        publication and exhibition of the drawings were in 1927. Somewhat
                        ironically, they returned to The British Museum Print Room by the munificent
                        gift of W. A. White’s daughter Frances White Emerson in 1929. Had
                        they entered The British Museum Print Room in 1875, they might not still be
                        largely unreproduced<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82"
type="note">7</ref> and little known.
                            <note id="n82">
                            <hi rend="s">7</hi> The Clarendon Press is apparently
                            about to publish a black-and-white set of reproductions of the whole,
                            with extensive commentaries by Michael Tolley, John E. Grant, Edward J.
                            Rose, and D. V. Erdman.</note>
                    </p>
                    <figure n="bb515.1.15.com" id="bb515.1.comb.15" work-copy="bb515.1" rend="db" width="806" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>inv &amp; sc<lb/>
	WB<lb/>
	Pubd. June 27. 1796, by R. Edwards, No. 142 New Bond Street.</figTranscr>
</figure>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>