<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.1.heppner</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="article">Blake and the Seaman’s Recorder: The
                            Letter and the Spirit in a Problem of Attribution</title>
                <author n="Heppner">Christopher Heppner</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1978</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Shelley Grieve</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Mary Clarke</name>
                            <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
                            <name>Frank Graziano</name>
                            <name>Jean H. Hagstrum</name>
                            <name>Gunnar Harding</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Joe Napora</name>
                            <name>Martin K. Numri</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>R. W. Peattie</name>
                            <name>Marcia Tillotson</name>
                            <name>Gunnel Tottie</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1978"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
            <pb id="p12-15" n="15"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-1-0007">
                <head>
                    <title type="main">
                        <hi rend="b">BLAKE AND <hi rend="i">THE SEAMAN’S RECORDER:</hi> THE
                            LETTER AND THE SPIRIT IN A PROBLEM OF ATTRIBUTION</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="b">CHRISTOPHER</hi>
                        <name>
                            <hi rend="b">HEPPNER</hi>
                        </name>
                    </docAuthor>
                </byline>
                <p>The attribution of engravings is often a very difficult matter in the absence of
                    definitive biographical evidence. It is especially difficult in an area such as
                    that represented by Blake’s commercial engravings, in which the engraver
                    is often following another man’s designs, and in which a personal style
                    tends to be submerged in conventions that are not particular to any one
                    individual. An experienced eye and mind may be able to look at a print and
                    arrive at a correct attribution, but such an intuitive solution may be difficult
                    to support in debate without the evidence of some identifiable minute
                    particulars. This brief essay is an attempt to provide a few such particulars in
                    support of a conclusion arrived at, it would seem, by an intuitive process honed
                    by long and committed experience.</p>
                <p>Some years ago the six plates signed “Blake” in the three volumes of
                        <hi rend="i">The Seaman’s Recorder</hi> were claimed for William
                    Blake in an article written by G. E. Bentley, Jr., though with an
                    acknowledgement that they were “the merest journeyman work.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">1</ref> This drew a reply from Geoffrey Keynes, who
                    argued that the “plain incompetence” of the etchings made it
                    impossible to attribute them to William Blake, the signatures
                        notwithstanding.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52"
type="note">2</ref> Bentley, in his recent
                        <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, still regards the plates as William
                    Blake’s, but adds the comment that Keynes’s case “will be
                    stronger when there is clear evidence that another engraver named Blake was
                    signing plates in the 1820s.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53"
type="note">3</ref>
                    <note id="n51">
                        <hi rend="s">1</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., “Byron, Shelley,
                        Wordsworth, Blake, and <hi rend="i">The Seaman’s Recorder</hi>,”
                            <hi rend="i">SiR</hi>, 9 (1970), 21-36. Bentley gives full
                        bibliographical details of the volumes, together with reproductions of all
                        of the plates in question.</note>
                    <note id="n52">
                        <hi rend="s">2</hi> Geoffrey Keynes, “Blake’s
                        Engravings for Gay’s Fables,” <hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi>,
                        21 (1972), 59-64.</note>
                    <note id="n53">
                        <hi rend="s">3</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1977), pp. 613-14.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Such evidence exists, and not too surprisingly is to be found in the Print Room
                    of the British Museum. There, the only item in a folder marked, and catalogued,
                    “E. Blake?” is a proof (<hi rend="i">BM</hi> 1920-9-30-1) of the plate
                    “Lord Byron in a Storm” from <hi rend="i">The Seaman’s
                        Recorder.</hi> The cataloguer has obviously not identified the print as
                    deriving from this work, but has added a note (referring to A. G. B.
                    Russell’s <hi rend="i">The Engravings of William Blake</hi>) which
                    associates the print, quite correctly in my view, with the E. Blake who etched
                    some of the plates for W. West’s Theatrical Characters, of which the
                    British Museum Print Room has a large collection.</p>
                <p>A comparison of the signature of the Lord Byron plate (illus. 1) with the
                    signature of the E. Blake who etched some of the Theatrical Characters plates
                    shows a close resemblance in style and form. Two of these signatures are
                    reproduced here, one reading “Blake fect” (illus. 2)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">4</ref> and the other “E. Blake fc [Sc?]” (illus.
                        3);<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">5</ref> the
signatures resemble each other
                    quite closely, and there is another plate signed “E. Blake fect” to
                    act as a mediator between the two forms illustrated.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">6</ref> It is apparent that these two signatures are very close
                    indeed to the signature on the Lord Byron plate. The dates are also entirely
                    compatible; the <hi rend="i">Seaman’s Recorder</hi> volumes are dated
                    1824-1825, while the Theatrical Characters plates from which illustrations 2 and
                    3 are taken are both dated 1825. I think it is clear that the same E. Blake was
                    responsible for all of these plates. <note id="n54">
                        <hi rend="s">4</hi> This
                        signature is taken from Vol. 2, No. 166, “Mr. H. Kemble, as
                        Massaniello, In the Fisherman of Naples. London, Published March 17, 1825,
                        by W. West, at his Theatrical Print Warehouse, 57, Wych Street. Opposite
                        Olympic Theatre Strand.”</note>
                    <note id="n55">
                        <hi rend="s">5</hi> This is from Vol. 2, No. 136, “Mr.
                        Huntley, as Bagzed. London, Published March 6, 1825, by W. West,
                        etc.”</note>
                    <note id="n56">
                        <hi rend="s">6</hi> Vol. 2, No. 208, “Mr. O Smith—as
                        Malvolex. London, Published May 18, 1827, by W. West, etc.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>The standard dictionaries of artists and engravers do not mention an E. Blake,
                    and neither does Keynes or Bentley, who have both written about Blakes other
                    than the William Blake who was both poet and painter.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">7</ref> He was mentioned very briefly a few times late in the
                    nineteenth century,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58"
type="note">8</ref> but A. G. B. Russell
                    seems to be the last writer on Blake to refer to him, in dismissing the
                    Theatrical Characters prints from the canon of William Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">9</ref>
                    <note id="n57">
                        <hi rend="s">7</hi> Geoffrey Keynes, “Engravers Called
                        Blake,” in <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 2nd ed. (Oxford: Clarendon
                        Press, 1971), pp. 46-49; and G. E. Bentley, Jr., “A Collection of
                        Prosaic William Blakes,” <hi rend="i">N &amp; Q</hi>, 210 [N. S. 12]
                        (1965), 172-78. As the title indicates, E. Blake is not relevant to this
                        latter essay.</note>
                    <note id="n58">
                        <hi rend="s">8</hi> William Archer has a sensible note which
                        casts doubt on previous enthusiastic claims for William Blake’s hand
                        in the Theatrical Characters prints, “The Drama in Pasteboard,”
                            <hi rend="i">The Art Journal</hi>, N. S. 7 (1887), 105-08,
                        141-44.</note>
                    <note id="n59">
                        <hi rend="s">9</hi> A. G. B. Russell, <hi rend="i">The Engravings
                            of William Blake</hi> (London: Grant Richards, 1912), p. 199.</note>
                </p>
                <p>It will be noticed that all of the signatures which I am here attributing to E.
                    Blake have a closed upper loop in the “k.” This is true both of the
                    rapidly etched signatures already illustrated, <pb id="p12-16" n="16"/>
                    <figure n="SeamanSignature.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="303">
                        <head>1 Signature on plate of “Lord Byron in a Storm,” <hi rend="i">The Seaman’s
Recorder</hi>, Vol. II, p. 1.</head>
                    </figure> and of the more formal signatures on the other plates signed
                    “Blake” from <hi rend="i">The Seaman’s Recorder</hi>, which all
                    follow the pattern of the signature (illus. 4) to the plate representing
                    Flaxman’s monument to Nelson, which is the frontispiece to Vol. II,
                    Bentley’s Plate No. 2.</p>
                <p>These engraved signatures look rather like some of William Blake’s, but in
                    fact William Blake never closed the loop of a “k” in this period,
                    though he did do this sometimes in earlier signatures, as on the vignette on p.
                    21 of <hi rend="i">The Poetical Works of John Scott Esq.</hi> (1782), <hi rend="i">The
Idle Laundress</hi> (1788), and Plate 21 for Vol. 3 of <hi rend="i">The Antiquities of Athens</hi> (1791), the
last of which is
                    reproduced here (illus. 5). But apart from the plate for Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Life of
George Romney</hi> (published 1809), on which I think that
                    the imprint and signature are most probably not actually cut by Blake
                        himself,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">10</ref> I
have been unable to find
                    any engraved or etched signature known to be by William Blake and later than
                    1800 with a closed loop on the “k.” <note id="n60">
                        <hi rend="s">10</hi> This is an opinion based partly on the style of the lettering
                        and partly on the long period of time between Blake’s work on the
                        plate (his letter of 11 December 1805 refers to it as very nearly finished)
                        and the actual date of publication; I would assume that the plate had long
                        been out of Blake’s hands when the publication date of 14 April 1809
                        was cut on all the plates in the volume, not only Blake’s. It is
                        worth remembering Bentley’s warning that inscriptions are not always
                        the work of the original engraver; see David V. Erdman, “Dating
                        Blake’s Script: a postscript,” <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Newsletter</hi> 10 (September 1969), p. 42.</note>
                </p>
                <figure n="TheatricalCharactersSignature.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="270">
                    <head>2 Signature on plate of “M<hi rend="s">r</hi>.. H. Kemble, as
                        Massaniello,” <hi rend="i">West’s Theatrical
                        Characters.</hi>
                    </head>
                </figure>
                <figure n="TheatricalBagzedSignature.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="750" height="350">
                    <head>3 Signature on plate of “M<hi rend="s">r</hi>.. Huntley, as
                        Bagzed,” <hi rend="i">West’s Theatrical Characters.</hi>
                    </head>
                </figure>
                <p>A perhaps less significant difference is that the signatures in <hi rend="i">The
                        Seaman’s Recorder</hi> have a rather more pronounced backwards
                    sweeping head on the “l” and “k” than do the corresponding
                    strokes on William Blake’s signatures.</p>
                <p>Writers on Blake’s commercial engravings have usually been wary of using
                    stylistic evidence as the basis for making attributions, in the absence of
                    supporting forms of documentation. I think this caution is usually justified,
                    but on the other hand Blake scholars have grown accustomed to accepting the
                    evidence of changes in the formation of the serif at the top of a “g”
                    in determining the date of some of Blake’s works,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">11</ref> and even in the attribution of the map of Hafod in
                    Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">An Attempt to Describe Hafod.</hi>
                    <ref target="n62" type="note">12</ref> Though I have looked only at engraved or
                    etched signatures for this essay, I think that the evidence presented here is
                    specific enough to settle the question of the disputed attribution of the plates
                    signed “Blake” in <hi rend="i">The Seaman’s Recorder</hi>, and
                    to outline a 
<pb id="p12-17" n="17"/>
                    <figure n="MonumentSignature.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="290">
                        <head>4 Signature on plate of Nelson’s monument, frontispiece to <hi rend="i">The
Seaman’s Recorder</hi>, Vol. II.</head>
                    </figure> small-scale bibliographic tool which may possibly have further uses.
                    In this instance, a technique—developed by Erdman with the assistance of
                    Bentley—of using the evidence provided by Blake’s script can be
                    used to confirm the intuition of Keynes. Here, at least, the letter and the
                    spirit are in concord. <note id="n61">
                        <hi rend="s">11</hi> See David V. Erdman,
                        “Dating Blake’s Script: the ‘g’ hypothesis,”
                            <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 9 (June 1969), pp. 8-13; Erdman,
                        “Dating Blake’s Script: a postscript,” <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Newsletter</hi> 10 (September 1969), p. 42; and G. E. Bentley, Jr.,
                        “Blake’s Sinister ‘g,’ from 1789-93 to
                        ?1803,” <hi rend="i">ibid.</hi>, pp. 43-45.</note>
                    <note id="n62">
                        <hi rend="s">12</hi> See Keynes, “George Cumberland and
                        William Blake” in <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, pp. 236-37. The
                        attribution is credited to Erdman. But see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Books</hi>, p. 541, which points out that Cumberland also seems to have
                        used an eccentric, “sinister g,” so that the Hafod map may very
                        well not be Blake after all. Attribution on purely stylistic grounds remains
                        risky, and the present essay is obviously not exempt from the
                        dangers.</note>
                </p>
                <figure n="AthensSignature.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="303">
                    <head>5 Signature on plate 21 of Vol. III of <hi rend="i">The Anti-quities of
                            Athens</hi>, 1791.</head>
                    <figDesc>Bottom of page 16.</figDesc>
                </figure>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>