<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.1.tillotson</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Recent Wollstonecraft</title>
                <author n="Tillotson">Marcia Tillotson</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1978</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Shelley Grieve</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Mary Clarke</name>
                            <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
                            <name>Frank Graziano</name>
                            <name>Jean H. Hagstrum</name>
                            <name>Gunnar Harding</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Joe Napora</name>
                            <name>Martin K. Numri</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>R. W. Peattie</name>
                            <name>Marcia Tillotson</name>
                            <name>Gunnel Tottie</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1978"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-1-0011">
                <pb id="p12-58" n="58"/>
                <div2>
                    <figure n="RecentWollstonecraft.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="432"/>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main" rend="main">RECENT WOLLSTONECRAFT</title>
                    </head>
                    <head>
                    	<title type="main">Mary
                        Wollstonecraft. <hi rend="b">Mary, A Fiction, and The Wrongs of
                            Woman.</hi> Edited, with an introduction, by Gary Kelly. London:
                        Oxford University Press, 1976. Pp. xxxii + 231. $12.00.</title>
                        <title type="main">Mary Wollstonecraft. <hi rend="b">Letters Written 
                        during a Short Residence in Sweden, Norway, and
                            Denmark.</hi> Edited, with an introduction, by Carol H. Poston.
                        Lincoln, NB, and London: University of Nebraska Press, 1976. Pp. xxiv +
                        201. $11.50 cloth, $4.95 paper.</title>
                    	<title type="main">Ralph M. Wardle, editor. <hi rend="b">Godwin &amp; 
                    	Mary: Letters of William Godwin and
						Mary Wollstonecraft.</hi> Lincoln, NB, and London: University of Nebraska
                        Press, 1977. Pp. x + 125. $2.65 paper.</title>
                        <title type="main">Mary Wollstonecraft. <hi rend="b">A
                            Vindication of the Rights of Woman.</hi> Edited, with an
                            introduction, by Miriam Brody Kramnick. Harmondsworth, England: Penguin
                            Books, 1975. Pp. 319. $3.95 paper.</title>
                        <title type="main">Claire Tomalin. <hi rend="b">The
                            Life and Death of Mary Wollstonecraft.</hi> New York and London:
                            Harcourt, Brace, Jovanovich, 1974. Pp. xii + 316. $8.95.</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="b">Marcia</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">Tillotson</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>The Romantic Period was less an age of feeling than the reaction against an
                        age of feeling. By 1790 the case for sensibility had been made all too well.
                        The Romantics may have talked about poetry as “the spontaneous overflow
                        of powerful feeling” and “the lava of the imagination whose
                        eruption prevents an earth-quake,” and they may have dreamt of “a
                        Life of Sensations rather than Thoughts,” but what they did was turn
                        back from the heart to the mind. The masterpieces of the first quarter of
                        the nineteenth century—<hi rend="i">The Prelude</hi> and <hi rend="i">Don Juan,
                        Pride and Prejudice</hi> and <hi rend="i">Waverley</hi>—speak to people who 
                        think as deeply as they feel.
                        Perhaps the Imagination itself appealed to the Romantics because with it
                        they could close up the rift that had opened in the eighteenth century
                        between intellect and emotion: the Imagination was preeminently a faculty of
                        the active, creative mind.</p>
                    <p>In the last decades of the eighteenth century, already dissatisfied or just
                        bored with the cult of feeling, writers of differing intentions and
                        sympathies struggled with the problem that the Romantics later solved
                        triumphantly. The sentimental had reached a kind of apogee in Fanny
                        Burney’s <hi rend="i">Evelina</hi> (1778): reunited with the father
                        who had deserted her and her mother when she was an infant, Evelina falls
                        weeping to her knees five times in a single conversation, and her repentant
                        father, also in tears, kneels three times and stays down longer. A few
                        minutes of crying can atone for sixteen years of neglect. In <hi rend="i">Northanger
                        Abbey</hi> and <hi rend="i">Sense and Sensibility</hi> Jane
                        Austen attacks this kind of absurd sentimentalism, and in <hi rend="i">The
                            Prelude</hi> Wordsworth acknowledges the temporary attraction of a
                        system of values that resembles Austen’s at its simplest: “the
                        philosophy / That promised to abstract the hopes of man / Out of his
                        feelings” (1805 text, X.807-09) appealed because it substituted reason
                        for emotion. The writers of Gothic fiction—“Monk” Lewis and
                        Ann Radcliffe, in particular—found a different escape from
                        sensibility; they gave their readers the horrors of Catholicism and
                        superstition, but created characters with enlightened Protestant
                        intelligences to experience, analyze, and often even explain the terrors.
                        Another group of novelists, the English Jacobins, wrote fiction with
                        sensational plots in order to reach their readers’ heads through
                        their hearts.</p>
                    <p>We must see Mary Wollstonecraft in this context, as a writer and thinker
                        trying to patch up the split between mind and heart, and succeeding, like
                        most of her contemporaries, only partially. Neither her character nor her
                        background did as much to shape her ideas and her work as the intellectual
                        climate she lived in. It is not a criticism to say that she was a creature
                        of her age; so were Fanny Burney and Ann Radcliffe, William Godwin and
                        William Blake. Like them, Wollstonecraft was challenged by the artificial
                        separation of thought and feeling. The new editions of her work reveal both
                        what she achieved and what she struggled against. The confusions of her less
                        successful efforts make them interesting even in failure.</p>
                    <pb id="p12-59" n="59"/>
                    <figure n="Vindication.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="477"/>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Mary, A Fiction</hi> (1788)—actually a glamorized
                        autobiography—was Wollstonecraft’s second publication. (The
                        first was <hi rend="i">Thoughts on the Education of Daughters</hi>,
                        published in 1787.) With no real interest in characterization or setting,
                        dialogue or action, she pushes her story along in short chapters of flat,
                        undeveloped narration. The heroine is supposed to have “thinking
                        powers” (p. xxxi), but after every effort to act according to
                        considered principles of virtue and humanity, she collapses into
                        self-pitying grief. Separated from a despised husband, deprived by death of
                        the woman and man she most loves, Mary settles in the country to practice
                        “benevolence and religion,” and to take comfort in the knowledge
                        that “[h]er delicate state of health did not promise long life”
                        (p. 68). Having inherited the values of her age, Wollstonecraft may have
                        feared that Mary would lose the reader’s sympathy if she thought a
                        little more and felt a little less.</p>
                    <p>The same weakness damages <hi rend="i">The Wrongs of Woman: or, Maria</hi>,
                        the novel that Wollstonecraft was working on when she died and that her
                        husband William Godwin published in her <hi rend="i">Posthumous Works</hi>
                        (1798). <hi rend="i">Mary</hi> had been written just before she lost her
                        position as a governess and began to support herself by writing; <hi rend="i">The
                        Wrongs of Woman</hi> was written nine years later, at the
                        end of her career. Maria is stronger, braver, and wiser than the miserable
                        Mary. The writing is more skillful, too, with a group of first-person
                        narratives giving some life to the single-minded pursuit of didactic points.
                        And the novel’s scheme is far more ambitious: drawing not only on her
                        own experiences and her family’s but also on a wide range of reading,
                        Wollstonecraft shows how men legally rob women, tyrannize over them, force
                        them into prostitution, take away their children. She tries to shock her
                        audience, and to a certain extent she succeeds. The heroine defends her
                        lover when he is tried for having seduced her; she argues that no adultery
                        took place because her husband by his cruelty, degeneracy, and greed had
                        forfeited his right to her loyalty. But there are suggestions that
                        Maria’s passion for her lover is not the virtuous impulse of a
                        generous heart but only sentimental self-delusion: “ . . . pity,
                        sorrow, and solitude all conspired to soften her mind, and nourish romantic
                        wishes, and, from a natural progress, romantic expectations” (p. 98).
                        One version of the notes for completing this unfinished work reads:
                        “Divorced by her husband—Her lover
                        unfaithful—Pregnancy—Miscarriage—Suicide” (p.
                        202). But a conclusion along these lines would have made Maria entirely the
                        victim of men’s deceit. Wollstonecraft was too much a product of the
                        Age of Sensibility to create a heroine who was blameable for letting her
                        heart control her head. Maria’s emotional susceptibility was, like
                        Mary’s, an essential part of her virtue. In her fiction
                        Wollstonecraft could not find a substitute for the 
<pb id="p12-60" n="60"/>
                        sentimental belief in the value of feeling for its own sake. <hi rend="i">Mary</hi>
                        and <hi rend="i">The Wrongs of Woman</hi> thus have less
                        interest for readers of fiction than for students of the social and
                        intellectual history of the late eighteenth century. What is striking about
                        both works is the way in which Wollstonecraft willingly sinks her heroines
                        in a morass of feeling.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Letters Written during a Short Residence in Sweden, Norway, and
                            Denmark</hi> (1796) is similarly interesting for what it is not. The
                        most impressive thing about the volume is probably its origin in the journey
                        to Scandinavia that Wollstonecraft made, accompanied only by her
                        one-year-old daughter and a French nursemaid. She went on business for her
                        American lover, Gilbert Imlay, the baby’s father. His infidelity had
                        driven her to attempt suicide in the spring of 1795, and he sent her to
                        Scandinavia that summer as a distraction. His plan didn’t work, for
                        soon after her return she made a second attempt and very nearly
                        succeeded.</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="i">Letters from Sweden</hi> were addressed to Imlay but written
                        for publication. The book reveals Wollstonecraft at her worst, trying to
                        impress two different audiences—her lover and the book’s
                        buyers—with two different things, her sensibility and her
                        intelligence. She struggles to show how seriously she thinks and how
                        tenderly she feels: “Amongst the peasantry, there is . . . so much of
                        the simplicity of the golden age in this land of flint—so much
                        overflowing of heart, and fellow-feeling, that only benevolence, and the
                        honest sympathy of nature, diffused smiles over my countenance when they
                        kept me standing, regardless of my fatigue, whilst they dropped courtesy
                        after courtesy” (p. 12). This letter, written the day after her
                        landing, shows her straining to utter universal truths about the
                        “peasantry”; at the same time she expresses the warmth of her
                        disposition, thus letting Imlay know what a loving heart he is throwing
                        away. At one point she announces, “I am persuaded that I have formed a
                        very just opinion of the character of the Norwegians, without being able to
                        hold converse with them” (p. 78), and she smugly consoles herself for
                        not knowing the language: “As their minds were totally uncultivated, I
                        did not lose much, perhaps gained, by not being able to understand
                        them” (p. 79). She seems to be a combination of Marianne Dashwood and
                        Elizabeth Bennet’s priggish piano-playing sister Mary. On the
                        occasions when she forgets to be at once an unusual woman, who reasons
                        vigorously, and an ideal woman, who feels strongly, she writes better:
                        “A mistaken tenderness . . . for their children, makes them, even in
                        summer, load them with flannels; and, having a sort of natural antipathy to
                        cold water, the squalid appearance of the poor babes, not to speak of the
                        noxious smell which flannel and rugs retain, seems a reply to a question I
                        had often asked—Why I did not see more children in the villages I
                        passed through” (p. 33). But the letters do not often give us what they
                        give us here, a vivid impression either of what she saw in Scandinavia or of
                        the person who saw it.</p>
                    <p>A more interesting woman emerges from the private and unpretentious
                        correspondence published in <hi rend="i">Godwin &amp; Mary</hi> Of the 151
                        letters—106 published whole or in part for the first time in this
                        edition, <figure n="LettersfromNorway.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="651" height="1000"/>
                        <pb id="p12-61" n="61"/>
                        a reprint of the 1966 original—only 42 are
                        Godwin’s. The correspondence is largely an exchange of invitations
                        before meetings and of explanations after them. (There are a great many
                        explanations here.) Since Godwin and Wollstonecraft maintained separate
                        lives even after their marriage, the correspondence takes them from the
                        beginning of their love affair, in July 1796, right up to the birth of their
                        daughter on 30 August 1797, ten days before Wollstonecraft’s death.
                        While few of the letters are interesting by themselves, the whole sequence
                        lets us watch an unusual understanding develop between the
                        thirty-seven-year-old Wollstonecraft, who had been rejected by her lover,
                        and the forty-year-old Godwin, who had just been turned down by another
                        woman. Even the circumstantial details of life that are missing in
                        Wollstonecraft’s fiction appear here: “I was splashed up to my
                        knees yesterday, and to sit several hours in that state is intolerable. . .
                        . [I]t snows, so incessantly, that I do not know how I shall be able to keep
                        my appointment this evening. What say you? But you have no petticoats to
                        dangle in the snow” (pp. 60, 62). Easily offended and depressed,
                        subject to feelings of neglect and fits of jealousy, Wollstonecraft was
                        capable of undemanding affection: “I wish you, from my soul, to be
                        rivetted in my heart; but I do not desire to have you always at my
                        elbow—though at this moment [Godwin had left London three days
                        earlier] I did not care if you were” (p. 83). She manages to explain
                        her excessive sensitivity: “One reason, I believe, why I wish you to
                        have a good opinion of me is a conviction 
                        <figure n="GodwinMemoirsTitle.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="770">
                            <head>Title page of Godwin’s <hi rend="i">Memoirs of
                                    the Author of a Vindication of the Rights of Woman</hi>,
                                1798.</head>
                            <figDesc>Collection of Claire Tomalin (illus. 19 in <hi rend="i">The
                                    Life and Death of Mary Wollstonecraft</hi>).</figDesc>
                        </figure> 
                        that the strongest affection is the most involuntary” (p.
                        40). In these letters we can see the intelligent woman she must have been.
                        Godwin’s criticism of her writing at first hurts her into
                        defensiveness: “I am compelled to think that there is some thing in my
                        writings more valuable, than in the productions of some people on whom you
                        bestow warm eulogiums—I mean more mind . . . ” (p. 28). Eleven
                        days later she gives in: “ . . . yet now you have led me to discover
                        that I write worse, than I thought I did, there is no stopping
                        short—I must improve, or be dissatisfied with myself—”
                        (p. 35). Energy, independence, professionalism, come through in these
                        letters, for Wollstonecraft was sure of her own voice and of her audience;
                        she felt no compulsion to parade either her intelligence or her
                        sensibility.</p>
                    <p>And that, finally, is the reason for the success of her masterpiece, <hi rend="i">A
                    	Vindication of the Rights of Woman</hi> (1792): she had a
                        clear sense of herself and of her audience. Repetitious and unsystematic the
                        work may be, but it is also compelling. The very evidence that she wrote it
                        rapidly is proof of the strength of her mind as well as of her feelings; as
                        she said in the <hi rend="i">Letters from Sweden</hi>, “we reason
                        deeply, when we forcibly feel” (p. 160). Her rhetorical ploy works:
                        “ . . . frankly acknowledging the inferiority of women” in their
                        oppressed condition, she argues “that men have increased that
                        inferiority” (p. 119), making them unnecessarily weak, stupid, and
                        frivolous. After attacking Rousseau and others who theorized about
                        women’s education, she sets forth her own notions: that 
<pb id="p12-62" n="62"/>
                        <figure n="OpiePortrai.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="783" height="1000">
                            <head>Portrait of Mary by John Opie.</head>
                            <figDesc>National Gallery. (Illus. 20 in Tomalin, <hi rend="i">Life and
                                    Death</hi>).</figDesc>
                        </figure> 
                        women should exercise their minds and bodies in youth as boys do,
                        and should share responsibility for the management of their homes in
                        adulthood. The latter argument is not unliberated, for she believed domestic
                        occupations offered men as well as women the best chance to be happy and
                        virtuous. She tried not “to leave the line of mediocrity” (p. 138)
                        and therefore talked about the lives of ordinary people, believing that the
                        talented of both sexes would seek other kinds of achievement if they were
                        free to do so. In <hi rend="i">The Rights of Woman</hi> she does not
                        over-simplify as she does in <hi rend="i">The Wrongs of Woman</hi>: if women
                        are the victims of men, whose bad laws, bad education, and bad religion
                        stifle them, women are also more or less willing collaborators in their own
                        degradation.</p>
                    <p>Only near the end of the work does Wollstone-craft mention political
                        equality: “I may excite laughter, by dropping a hint, which I mean to
                        pursue, some future time, for I really think that women ought to have
                        representatives, instead of being arbitrarily governed without any direct
                        share allowed them in the deliberation of government” (pp. 259-60).
                        Energetic and confident in developing the arguments that interest her, she
                        sounds uncharacteristically weak, hesitant, and apologetic here. In fact,
                        she was more concerned that women should learn than that they should vote,
                        and she was more eager to see them increase their power in the family than
                        in the state. She was wiser than she could have known, for the equality she
                        cared about turns out to be the equality that matters, and the right to vote
                        has not been the answer that women hoped it would be. 
                        <figure n="EtchingafterOpie.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="785" height="1000">
                            <head>Etching of Mary after Opie’s
                                portrait.</head>
                            <figDesc>British Museum. (Illus. 21 in Tomalin.)</figDesc>
                        </figure> 
                        The <hi rend="i">Vindication</hi> remains readable because
                        Wollstone-craft saw the problem so clearly; she recognized that political
                        inequality oppressed women less than the belief in what she called
                        “sexual virtues” (p. 139)—qualities, like delicacy or
                        courage, that are considered merits in one sex but faults in the other.
                        Virginia Woolf’s opinion of the Vindication—that its
                        “originality has become our commonplace” (The Second Common
                        Reader, pp. 143-44)—is probably wrong. The work retains the freshness
                        of an active mind’s enthusiastic encounter with a brand-new idea; the
                        chance to say something truly original freed Wollstonecraft from
                        sensibility, at least temporarily.</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="i">Vindication</hi> is worth reading, and this new edition is
                        welcome. Miriam Brody Kramnick provides a helpful introduction that places
                        Wollstonecraft’s achievement in its various historical contexts; the
                        notes, by contrast, are only adequate. Gary Kelly, editing the two pieces of
                        fiction for the Oxford English Novels, supplies the full and enlightening
                        notes we have come to expect from that series, and his introduction makes
                        the best possible case for both works. Without minimizing their limitations,
                        he sees what Wollstonecraft’s intentions probably were and suggests
                        that the stories have a coherency of purpose, whatever they lack in
                        execution. The editor of <hi rend="i">Godwin &amp; Mary</hi>, Ralph M.
                        Wardle, published a biography of Wollstonecraft in 1951. His beautifully
                        meticulous handling of the letters transforms these fragmentary materials
                        into a satisfying, readable whole; there is an excellent, brief introductory
                        essay as well as full and enlightening notes and even a fine index. The
                        Scandinavian 
<pb id="p12-63" n="63"/>
						letters are not so well edited. Carol
                        H. Poston’s introduction exaggerates the merits of the letters
                        themselves, and her notes are more often gratuitous than useful. She
                        includes a map of the itinerary but makes no further effort to sort out the
                        jumble that Wollstonecraft’s topographical and chronological
                        vagueness creates. While the book is nicely illustrated with engravings that
                        were not in the original edition, these are not identified.</p>
                    <p>Wollstonecraft’s life was eventful enough to be interesting if she had
                        written nothing. She rescued—or kidnapped—her sister from the
                        sister’s husband, leaving behind a five-month-old baby that died
                        within the year. She traveled alone across winter seas to Lisbon to be with
                        her friend Fanny Blood at the childbed that turned into a deathbed, then
                        sailed back to London in worse weather, compelling the captain to rescue the
                        crew from a foundering French ship. She fell in love with the painter Henry
                        Fuseli but was turned down when she tried to persuade his wife to let her
                        live with them, so she went to France in December 1792, in time for the
                        King’s trial and execution, and stayed on through the Terror, an
                        enemy alien but Imlay’s mistress finally returning to London in April
                        1795. She struggled from the age of eighteen on to support, at different
                        times, her two sisters, her younger brothers, Fanny Blood, and
                        Fanny’s family; her eldest brother, a lawyer who had inherited
                        property from their grandfather, did almost nothing for any of them. At
                        twenty-five she started a girls’ school in which she, her sisters.
                        and Fanny worked, and when it failed, she went to Ireland as a governess in
                        an aristocratic Anglo-Irish family, before she fianlly settled in London,
                        writing, reviewing, and translating. She did not always live by the
                        principles of sense, discipline, and duty that she laid down in the 
                        <hi rend="i">Vindication</hi>; her two attempts to kill herself when she had
                        a baby who was dependent on her violated the rules that she said women
                        should live by if they were to act like rational creatures.</p>
                    <p>Claire Tomalin had a good story to tell, and she tells it sympathetically but
                        critically in <hi rend="i">The Life and Death of Mary Wollstonecraft.</hi>
                        It has been told before—several times quite recently—but this
                        life is the most comprehensive. Tomalin tells us a great deal about the
                        people who surrounded Wollstonecraft in England and France, fills in the
                        political and social background fully and vividly, and discusses
                        Wollstonecraft’s influence after her death. This breadth allows
                        Tomalin to give convincing factual explanations of Wollstonecraft’s
                        actions and feelings, and to avoid psychologizing. Tomalin seems to tell all
                        that can be known about Wollstonecraft’s life. There is one issue
                        that Tomalin does not discuss, however: the suggestion made by Robert R.
                        Hare that Wollstonecraft and not Imlay wrote the two books published as
                        his.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64" type="note">1</ref> 
                        If the works were actually
                        hers or collaborations between her and Imlay, that would not only affect the
                        chronology of their relation but also alter our view of both of them, making
                        him a still less significant character and her the author of a third novel
                        and a successful travel book. Hare’s arguments deserve to be
                        answered, and Tomalin’s opinion would be worth having. 
                        <note id="n64">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi> Hare presented his case at length in “The
                            Base Indian: A Vindication of the Rights of Mary Wollstonecraft”
                            (M.A. theses Univ. of Delaware 1957), and later summarized his arguments
                            in the introduction to his facsimile edition of the novel, <hi rend="i">The
                            Emigrants</hi>, which he published with both
                            Wollstonecraft’s and Imlay’s names on the title page
                            (Gainesville, Fla.: Scholars’ Facsimiles &amp; Reprints,
                            1964).</note>
                    </p>
                    <figure n="UnknownWollstonecraftPortrait.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="815" height="1000">
                        <head>Portrait of Mary, artist unknown.</head>
                        <figDesc>Collection of Claire Tomalin (illus. 6 in <hi rend="i">Life and
                                Death</hi>).</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <figure n="JohnsonPortrait.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="773" height="1000">
                        <head>Portrait of Joseph Johnson the printer.</head>
                        <figDesc>British Museum. (Illus. 7 in Tomalin.)</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <pb id="p12-64" n="64"/>
                    <p>Wollstonecraft was thirty-eight when she died. Tomalin makes us feel the loss
                        of this woman who was important not simply as the mother of feminism or of
                        Mary Shelley but also as a writer, thinker, and observer. She was, after
                        all, the friend as well as the wife of William Godwin; she had been
                        encouraged and helped by Dr. Richard Price, the Dissenting minister whose
                        sermon on the French Revolution provoked Burke to begin his 
                        <hi rend="i">Reflections</hi>; she was the protegée of Joseph Johnson, the
                        Radical publisher, who got Blake to illustrate two of her works; she was
                        read by Blake and Southey, and her conversation impressed Coleridge and
                        Lamb. She achieved a great deal in a working life that was shortened at one
                        end by poverty and lack of education as well as at the other by early death.
                        She was prevented from achieving more by her sex, which limited her activity
                        to writing although her real talents were probably for some other
                        field—politics, education, medicine—then closed to her. Yet
                        she managed to write a book that was nearly two hundred years ahead of its
                        time; not many men or women without her weaknesses or disadvantages have
                        done that much. 
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>