<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.1.deck</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="minute">“Blake, William” in the New American Cyclopedia</title>
                <author n="Deck">Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1978</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Shelley Grieve</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Mary Clarke</name>
                            <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
                            <name>Frank Graziano</name>
                            <name>Jean H. Hagstrum</name>
                            <name>Gunnar Harding</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Joe Napora</name>
                            <name>Martin K. Numri</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>R. W. Peattie</name>
                            <name>Marcia Tillotson</name>
                            <name>Gunnel Tottie</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1978"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
            <pb id="p12-68" n="68"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-1-0012">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">“BLAKE, WILLIAM” IN THE <hi rend="i">NEW AMERICAN
                                    CYCLOPEDIA</hi> (1861)</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor><hi rend="b">Raymond H. </hi><name><hi rend="b">Deck</hi></name>, 
<hi rend="b">Jr.</hi>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>An article about William Blake which was one of the most widely circulated
                        American accounts of his life and works in the later pre-Gilchrist years and
                        for at least a decade thereafter should be added to the extensive
                        pre-Gilchrist bibliographies of G. E. Bentley, Jr.’s <hi rend="i">Critical
Heritage</hi> and <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi>
                        <ref target="n65" type="note">1</ref> The sketch appears in volume III of the
                            <hi rend="i">New American Cyclopedia</hi>, published in 1861 but
                        copyrighted in 1858; the discrepancy between the dates of publication and
                        copyright is explained by the editorial preface to volume I (publ. 1860,
                        copyright 1857), which notes that the actual publication of the first volume
                        was undertaken only when the entire project was in “an advanced state
                        of preparation for the press.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66"
type="note">2</ref>
                        <note id="n65">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">William
                                Blake: The Critical Heritage</hi> (London: Routledge, 1975); 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977).</note>
                        <note id="n66">
                            <hi rend="s">2</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">New American Cyclopedia: A Popular Dictionary of General
                                Knowledge</hi>, ed. George Ripley and Charles A. Dana (New York: D.
                            Appleton and Co., 1858-63); in the revised edition of 1872 and in later
                            reprintings the name was changed to simply <hi rend="i">American
                                Cyclopedia: A Popular Dictionary of General
                        Knowledge.</hi>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The article, about 550 words long, seems to depend almost entirely upon
                        Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives</hi> for biographical and
                        bibliographical information as well as for a judgment of Blake and his
                        works; in fact, numerous parallels (for example, 1828 as the date of
                        Blake’s death) make it plain that Cunningham is quoted silently,
                        repeatedly, and often pretty carelessly. Several of Blake’s works are
                        mentioned specifically, and, after Cunningham, the “inventions for the
                        Book of Job” are judged “his best production.” Likewise,
                        Blake’s visionary qualities are emphasized: 
						<q> He wrote songs,
                            composed music, and painted at the same time; but in the excitement of
                            his labors, he began to conceive that he was under spiritual influences;
                            and as external prosperity was wanting, he grew more and more abstracted
                            and retired, until the visionary tendencies of his nature dominated his
                            life. Among his friends he gave out that the works on which he was
                            engaged were copied from great works revealed to him, and that his
                            lessons in art were given him by celestial tongues. An original and
                            beautiful method of engraving and tinting his plates he ascribed to the
                            dead brother of his wife, Robert. </q>
The error in the last sentence
                        suggests a careless reading of Cunningham, as do the statements that 
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> contains a “drama” (Cunningham
                        says “a dramatic poem”) and that Blake made “12
                        ‘Inventions’” for the “Canterbury Pilgrims.”
                        Curiously, however, the article states correctly a few details not included
                        in Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives</hi>: 1789 is given as the date of
                        the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, and the “Canterbury Pilgrims”
                        (correctly named in contrast to Cunningham’s “Canterbury
                        Pilgrimage”) is described as a “water-color painting” whereas
                        Cunningham simply mentions that it was painted. Possibly the article-writer
                        was familiar with Robert Balmanno’s copy of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, which gives
“1789” clearly on the title page;
                        that this same copy, <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (U), had bound with it a
                        print from Blake’s engraving of the “Canterbury Pilgrims”
                        may also explain why the article-writer gives a correct version of
                        Blake’s title, although the accurate observation that Blake’s
                        larger version was a “water-color painting,” or at least not an
                        oil, remains of mysterious origin.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n67" type="note">3</ref>
                        <note id="n67">
                            <hi rend="s">3</hi> See my “An American Original: Mrs.
                            Colman’s Illustrated Printings of Blake’s Poems,
                            1843-44,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, 11, (Summer 1977),
                        4-18.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="i">New American Cyclopedia</hi> article probably was written by
                        Charles Dana, the city editor of the New York <hi rend="i">Tribune.</hi>
                        Dana and George Ripley, the newspaper’s literary critic, were the two
                        editors of the <hi rend="i">New American Cyclopedia</hi> (whose list of
                        contributors does not include anyone else known to have had an early
                        interest in Blake), and in 1857 Dana had edited the <hi rend="i">Household
                            Book of Poetry</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68"
type="note">4</ref> in which he
                        included four of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and “My
                        Silks” from <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches.</hi>
                        <note id="n68">
                            <hi rend="s">4</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Household Book of Poetry</hi>, ed. Charles A. Dana (New
                            York: D. Appleton and Co., 1857).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Although Dana’s contribution to Blake’s fame occurred late in
                        the pre-Gilchrist years, his two publications mentioned here are especially
                        important to Blake’s American reputation because they were widely
                        read and respected. Dana judged the <hi rend="i">Household Book of
                            Poetry</hi> to include “within the bounds of a single volume
                        whatever is truly beautiful and admirable among the minor poems of the
                        English language,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69"
type="note">5</ref> and the
                        American public seems to have enthusiastically supported his critical
                        judgments, for the anthology (with the addition of yet another of
                        Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> in the 1858 and subsequent
                            editions<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70" type="note">6</ref>)
went through dozens of
                        printings in the nineteenth century and four more in the twentieth.
                        Dana’s biographer seems correct in describing the <hi rend="i">New
                            American Cyclopedia</hi> as “the <corr type="emend">principal</corr> American work of its
                            time”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71" type="note">7</ref>; in
sixteen volumes the
                        most extensive nineteenth-century American reference work (the only
                        competition was the even earlier but slightly smaller <hi rend="i">Encyclopedia
Americana</hi>), the <hi rend="i">New American
                            Cyclopedia</hi> passed through more than a dozen printings in fifteen
                        years and included extensive annual supplements issued from 1876 to 1887.
                            <note id="n69">
                            <hi rend="s">5</hi> Ibid., p. v.</note>
                        <note id="n70">
                            <hi rend="s">6</hi> Noted by Suzanne R. Hoover in
                            “William Blake in the Wilderness: A Closer Look at his Reputation
                            1827-63,” <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays in Honour of Sir
                                Geoffrey Keynes</hi>, ed. Morton D. Paley and Michael Phillips
                            (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1973), p. 322.</note>
                        <note id="n71">
                            <hi rend="s">7</hi> James H. Wilson, <hi rend="i">Life of
                                Charles A. Dana</hi> (New York: Harper, 1908), p. 159.</note>
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
	<pb id="p12-69" n="69" rend="hidden"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>