<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.1.clarke</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="article">The Job Ballet</title>
                <author n="Clarke">Mary Clarke</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1978</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Shelley Grieve</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Mary Clarke</name>
                            <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
                            <name>Frank Graziano</name>
                            <name>Jean H. Hagstrum</name>
                            <name>Gunnar Harding</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Joe Napora</name>
                            <name>Martin K. Numri</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>R. W. Peattie</name>
                            <name>Marcia Tillotson</name>
                            <name>Gunnel Tottie</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1978"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
            <pb id="p12-18" n="18"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-1-0008">
                <head>
                    <title type="main">
                        <hi rend="b">THE JOB BALLET</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="b">MARY</hi>
                        <name>
                            <hi rend="b">CLARKE</hi>
                        </name>
                    </docAuthor>
                </byline>
                <p>The 1931-32 season opened at the Old Vic on 22nd September and this first full
                    season was fittingly introduced by a performance of <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, which
                    the Camargo Society lent to the company and for which Vaughan Williams asked
                    only a nominal fee.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n0"
type="note">*</ref>
                    <note id="n0">Reprinted from
                        Mary Clarke, <hi rend="i">The Sadler’s Wells Ballet/A History and an
                            Appreciation</hi> (Adam and Charles Black, London), 1955.</note> Dolin repeated
his magnificent performance as Satan and the
                    impact of the ballet was instantaneous. The first slight programmes may not have
                    seemed very important, but a work like <hi rend="i">Job</hi> at once revealed
                    the power and the creative force of de Valois as a choreographer and the
                    possibilities for serious English ballet.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Job</hi> was not only a <hi rend="i">succès
                        d’estime</hi> but a popular success as well, and the Vic and Wells
                    were crowded whenever it was given. It has remained in the repertoire of the
                    Sadler’s Wells Ballet ever since and now occupies a very special place in
                    the traditions of the company and in the affections of everyone who has been
                    associated with Sadler’s Wells.</p>
                <p>This “Masque for Dancing” had been invented by Dr. Geoffrey Keynes some
                    years previously. An ardent balletomane and a great authority on the work of
                    William Blake, he had felt that Blake’s <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the
                        Book of Job</hi>, first published as a series of twenty-one engravings in
                    1825, unconsciously provided settings which could easily be translated on the
                    stage, while there were “innumerable suggestions in his figures for
                    attitudes and groupings, which cried out for their conversion by a choreographer
                    into actuality and movement.” He prepared a detailed scenario for a stage
                    production and persuaded his sister-in-law Gwendolen Raverat (<hi rend="i">née</hi>
Darwin) to design backcloths based on Blake’s
                    drawings and to colour small cut-out figures to represent the leading characters
                    in the main scenes and groupings. These designs were prepared for a toy theatre,
                    and when the cardboard figures were assembled they illustrated very exactly the
                    main climaxes of the action as they were eventually to appear in the ballet. Dr.
                    Keynes had completed his scheme for the ballet by 1927 and had persuaded Ralph
                    Vaughan Williams (a cousin of the Darwins) to compose the music. He sent a
                    French translation of 
                    <pb id="p12-19" n="19"/>
                     <figure n="ToyTheater.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="938">
                    <head>1 Toy theater model for <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, Gwendolen Raverat
                        design.</head>
                    <figDesc>Victoria and Albert Museum.</figDesc>
                	</figure>
                    <figure n="ValoisSketches.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="644" height="1000">
                        <head>2 Notebook sketches, Ninette de Valois.</head>
                        <figDesc>Victoria and Albert Museum.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <figure n="JobTVProduction.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="587">
                        <head>3 <hi rend="i">Job</hi> television production, Harold Turner as
                            Satan.</head>
                        <figDesc>Victoria and Albert Museum.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <pb id="p12-20" n="20"/>
                    <figure n="JobProgramme.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="658" height="1000"/>
                    <pb id="p12-21" n="21"/>
                    <figure n="JobPlaybill.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="631" height="1000">
                        <head>4 &amp; 5 Original production, 5 July 1931.</head>
                        <figDesc>Victoria and Albert Museum.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <pb id="p12-22" n="22"/>
                    <figure n="Job1931Production.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="629">
                        <head>6 Michael Somes as Job, later production.</head>
                        <figDesc>Victoria and Albert Museum.</figDesc>
                    </figure> the scenario to Diaghileff, who was at that time the only person in a
                    position to produce such a ballet, but the subject did not appeal to Diaghileff
                    and he rejected it as too English and too old-fashioned. Dr. Keynes can probably
                    take credit, however, for having sown a seed in the great man’s mind
                    which was later to bear fruit in the production of <hi rend="i">Le Fils
                        Prodigue.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>With the formation of the Camargo Society, Dr. Keynes saw another chance of
                    having <hi rend="i">Job</hi> produced, and he invited Lilian Baylis and Ninette
                    de Valois to come and see the models and the toy theatre. They were at once
                    interested and it was agreed that de Valois should undertake the production,
                    following the scenario of Dr. Keynes and using Mrs. Raverat’s designs.
                    Dr. Vaughan Williams had stipulated that there should be no <hi rend="i">pointe</hi> work
(which he detested) and that <hi rend="i">Job</hi> should
                    not be described as a ballet, so the description “a Masque for
                    Dancing” was adopted. De Valois made a very careful study of the Blake
                    engravings and began to plan her production, while Mrs. Raverat set to work
                    painting scenery at the Old Vic. The production was to be presented by the
                    Camargo Society at its fourth programme and Geoffrey Keynes undertook to finance
                    it, being assisted by several friends, in particular by his brother Maynard and
                    Sir Thomas Dunhill.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63"
type="note">1</ref> Constant Lambert
                    rescored the music for a much smaller orchestra and <hi rend="i">Job</hi> was
                    produced for the first time at the Cambridge Theatre on 5th and 6th July 1931.
                        <note id="n63">
                        <hi rend="s">1</hi> One benefactor was later taken to a
                        performance by Geoffrey Keynes and his wife. The eminent man sat solemnly
                        through the opening ballet, which happened to be <hi rend="i">The Jackdaw
                            and the Pigeons</hi>, and at the end said politely to Keynes, “Yes,
                        old boy, very interesting. But tell me, which one was Job?”</note>
                </p>
                <figure n="AntonDolin.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="834" height="1000">
                    <head>7 Studio picture of Anton Dolin for a later Raverat production.</head>
                    <figDesc>Victoria and Albert Museum.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <pb id="p12-23" n="23"/>
                <figure n="JoyNewtonJob.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="785" height="1000">
                    <head>8 Joy Newton, original production.</head>
                    <figDesc>Victoria and Albert Museum.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <pb id="p12-24" n="24"/>
                <figure n="JobOriginalProduction.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="735">
                    <head>9 Original production.</head>
                    <figDesc>Victoria and Albert Museum.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Job</hi> won much esteem for both the Camargo Society and the
                    Vic-Wells Ballet. With <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, Edwin Evans used to say, Camargo
                    stepped on the map of Europe. Karsavina said, “The dignity of the greatest
                    tragedy of all ages is nowhere impaired by a mere dance for the dance’s
                    sake, and yet this production fully answers the qualification of ballet. The
                    quality of mime in <hi rend="i">Job</hi> is that of the flowing pattern of a
                    well-conceived dance.” Perhaps Lydia Lopokova, at first not very
                    enthusiastic but greatly impressed after seeing it performed at Oxford during
                    the Ninth Annual Festival of the International Society for Contemporary Music,
                    put her finger on the most important achievement when she wrote to Geoffrey
                    Keynes: “My chief pleasure was that it differed from the Russian ballet
                    tradition, the most important merit of <hi rend="i">Job.</hi>” Ashley
                    Dukes, writing in the American <hi rend="i">Theatre Arts Monthly</hi> about the
                    English theatre in general, said <hi rend="i">Job</hi> was by far the most
                    satisfying achievement of the English theatre that season, representing
                    “the impressive silence in the midst of unimpressive talk.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Job</hi> owed no small part of its success to the performance of
                    Anton Dolin as Satan, Blakish and devilish, yet superbly arrogant and physically
                    magnificent in a way that none of his successors have been able to equal,
                    although all of them (and Robert Helpman in particular) have given striking and
                    valid interpretations. At the time of the first Vic-Wells performances Dolin was
                    still appearing in <hi rend="i">Stand Up and Sing</hi>, but Jack Buchanan (to
                    whom all honour) gave him permission to dance at the Vic, and his performance
                    was a major feature of the success of the ballet—although the timing was
                    so close that he had to take his last curtain half-dressed in evening clothes,
                    with a taxi waiting at the stage door to whisk him back to the Hippodrome.
                    Lilian Baylis wrote him her thanks: “Ellen Terry was one of the first great
                    players who gave such practical help to the Old Vic, and you are the first great
                    dancer, and I shall pray and remember you always with very great
                    affection.” <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">Photo behind title:
                        backdrop design for <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, Gwendolen Raverat. On deposit at
                        the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge; reproduced by permission of the
                        owner.</note>
                </p>
                <pb id="p12-25" n="25"/>
                <figure n="RobertHelpmann.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="830">
                    <head>10 Robert Helpmann as Satan, later production.</head>
                    <figDesc>Victoria and Albert Museum.</figDesc>
                </figure>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>