<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.1.peattie</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="article">William Rossetti’s Aldine Edition of Blake</title>
                <author n="Peattie">R. W. Peattie</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1978</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Shelley Grieve</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Mary Clarke</name>
                            <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
                            <name>Frank Graziano</name>
                            <name>Jean H. Hagstrum</name>
                            <name>Gunnar Harding</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Joe Napora</name>
                            <name>Martin K. Numri</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>R. W. Peattie</name>
                            <name>Marcia Tillotson</name>
                            <name>Gunnel Tottie</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1978"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
        <pb id="p12-4" n="4"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-1-0005">
                <head>
                    <title type="main">
                        <hi rend="b">WILLIAM MICHAEL ROSSETTI’S ALDINE EDITION OF BLAKE</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="b">R. W.</hi>
                        <name>
                            <hi rend="b">PEATTIE</hi>
                        </name>
                    </docAuthor>
                </byline>
                <p>Although William Michael Rossetti has been given his due as a major contributor
                    to Victorian writings on Blake, a number of unpublished or unremarked details
                    relating to the preparation, publication and reception of his edition of the 
                    <hi rend="i">Poetical Works of William Blake</hi> (1874) make his concern with
                    Blake’s reputation worth returning 
                    to.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> 
                    As early as 1864, in a letter to Horace Scudder, Rossetti lamented
                    the public response to Gilchrist in a way which suggests how much more he
                    considered needed to be done to secure Blake’s fame. Scudder had recently
                    reviewed Gilchrist in the <hi rend="i">North American Review</hi>, and Rossetti
                    was acknowledging a copy of the review. 
                    <note id="n1">
                        <hi rend="s">1</hi>
                        Rossetti’s part in the 1863 and 1880 editions of Gilchrist, his
                        Aldine edition, and his miscellaneous writings on Blake are discussed in the
                        bibliographies by Keynes, and Bentley and Nurmi, and in Deborah Dorfman, 
                        <hi rend="i">Blake in the Nineteenth Century</hi> (New Haven, 1969).
                        Dorfman’s account of the Aldine edition is the fullest (pp. 112-14,
                        165-67), but it needs supplementing as provided here. Our knowledge of the
                        preparation of Rossetti’s <hi rend="i">catalogue raisonné</hi>
                        for Gilchrist is sketchy, but it should be possible to fill in the details
                        as more of Rossetti’s correspondence becomes available. Of
                        Rossetti’s miscellaneous writings on Blake, the following do not
                        appear in the standard lists: (1) “Gilchrist’s Life of
                        Blake,” <hi rend="i">Reader</hi>, 2 (November 1863), 544. (Corrects a
                        statement in the <hi rend="i">Reader</hi> about his part in completing
                        Gilchrist.) (2) Review of <hi rend="i">Selections from the Writings of
                        Blake</hi>, with an Introductory Essay by Laurence Housman, 
                        <hi rend="i">Athenaeum</hi>, 3 June 1893, p. 700. (Identified from Rossetti’s
                        file of the <hi rend="i">Athenaeum</hi> in the Library of the Courtauld
                        Institute.) (3) “The William Blake Revival,” <hi rend="i">Daily
                        Graphic</hi>, 2 November 1904, Supplement, p. 1. (Review of
                        Russell’s <hi rend="i">Letters of Blake</hi>, Ellis’ <hi rend="i">Poetical Works
                        of Blake</hi>, and G. Robertson’s edition
                        of Gilchrist.)</note>
                </p>
				<q> 
                	27 November 1864<lb/>
                	My dear Sir,<lb/>
                	I have to thank you very sincerely for
                    your note, &amp; the accompanying review of Blake from the North American
                    Review. However I had already read the article; having seen it advertized &amp;
                    strongly suspecting—from my knowledge of what has taken place on former
                    occasions where a little openness to new impressions was needed, &amp; a little
                    boldness of opinion—that the book would be better estimated in America
                    than in England. I found my anticipation more than confirmed, &amp; derived
                    much pleasure from a perusal of the article. It is (if I may say so to you
                    without impertinence) far the best I have seen; &amp; I am sorry to say that it
                    is not necessarily so much a compliment as I mean it to be, for the English
                    notices, with one or two exceptions amounting to tolerable, have been silly,
                    poor stuff which an Englishman winces &amp; blushes at—or ought to do
                    so, at least.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> 
                    My brother, who saw your
                    article here yesterday, joins me in rating that very differently—as being
                    positively not less than comparatively a worthy tribute to that very wonderful
                    genius, the “mad-man” of his discerning countrymen, 
                    Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref>
				</q>
                    <note id="n2">
                        <hi rend="s">2</hi> Suzanne R. Hoover, “The Public Reception
                        of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>,
                        8 (1974), 26-31, points out that there were at
                        least half a dozen favorable reviews in British periodicals up to this
                        date.</note>
                    <note id="n3">
                        <hi rend="s">3</hi> Houghton Library MS., Harvard University. All
                        quotations from manuscripts are, to the best of my knowledge, published for
                        the first time. I am indebted to Mrs. Imogen Dennis for permission to quote
                        from the letters and diaries of her grandfather William Michael Rossetti,
                        and to Prof. W. E. Fredeman and the University of British Columbia for
                        permission to publish the extracts from Rossetti’s diaries (from the
                        Angeli Papers). Permission to publish manuscripts in their Collections has
                        also been given by the following libraries: the British Library, the
                        Bodleian, and the Houghton.</note>
                <p>It was almost another decade, however, before Rossetti was offered the chance to
                    write comprehensively on Blake. Two entries in his Diary, the first for 8 May
                    1872 and the second for 6 August 1873, give a reasonably full account of the
                    origin of his edition: 
					<q> Daldy the Publisher called on me, thinking of
                        including Blake in his Aldine series of Poets;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n4" type="note">4</ref> &amp; he asked me whether I wd. undertake the
                        editing—including a Memoir of some 30 to 100 pages. He does not wish
                        to insert the Prophetic Books, but only a complete set of the poems of an
                        ordinary cast. I replied that I wd. undertake the work for £50, on the
                        understanding 
<pb id="p12-5" n="5"/>
                        <figure n="BlakePoeticalWorks1874.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="710"/> that I am not to be
controlled in anything I may see fit to say;
                        also that I might not find it convenient to commence the work for some 6
                        mos. or so to come. Daldy took leave, saying he wd. consult with his partner
                        Bell. He had in the first instance proposed for either Gabriel or me as
                        editor; but, as I told him, it is practically certain that G. wd.
                        decline.<lb/>
                        <lb/>
 Mr. Bell,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> of the
                        publishing firm, called on me at Som. Ho., &amp; agreed to the terms set
                        forth under 8 May 1872 regarding an edition of Blake’s poems in his
                        Aldine series. He wd. like the introductory notice to be only about 32 to 48
                            pp.,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> &amp;
the arrangement of the
                        poems mainly chronological. The Prophetic Books wd. not be included: I think
                        however an exception must be made in favour at any rate of the Marriage of
                        Heaven &amp; Hell, if only for the sake of making the vol. of a moderately
                        substantial thickness.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
type="note">7</ref>
                        <note id="n4">
                            <hi rend="s">4</hi> On “The Aldine Poets,” an
                            established series then being reissued with new names at a popular
                            price, see Edward Bell, <hi rend="i">George Bell, Publisher</hi>
                            (London, 1924), p. 51.</note>
                        <note id="n5">
                            <hi rend="s">5</hi> The <hi rend="i">Athenaeum</hi> reported
                            on 5 July 1873, p. 17, that “The term of partnership existing
                            between Messrs. Bell &amp; Daldy having expired, Mr. Daldy has retired
                            from that firm.”</note>
                        <note id="n6">
                            <hi rend="s">6</hi> As published the Memoir ran to 125
                            pp.</note>
                        <note id="n7">
                            <hi rend="s">7</hi> MS. Diary. Angeli Papers, Special
                            Collections, University of British Columbia.</note>
					</q>
					Unfortunately a considerable gap in Rossetti’s Diary between the
                    second entry and late 1876 makes it impossible to chart the preparation of the
                    volume as thoroughly as we can document his earlier editions of Whitman and
                    Shelley, though a number of his letters to Swinburne and Mrs. Gilchrist offer
                    additional information. We can assume that he worked with his usual steadiness,
                    for on 4 March 1874 he informed Swinburne that “Yesterday I received the
                    first proofs, both of the poems &amp; of my Prefatory Memoir.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> A copy of the edition (presumably an advance
                    copy) was in Swinburne’s hands by late October 1874,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> and it was listed in “Publications of the
                    Week” in the <hi rend="i">Spectator</hi> of 14 November 1874.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref>
                    <note id="n8">
                        <hi rend="s">8</hi> B. L. Ashley MS. A1444, fol. 109v.</note>
                    <note id="n9">
                        <hi rend="s">9</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">Swinburne Letters</hi>, ed. C. Y. Lang (New Haven, 1959-1962),
                        II, 348.</note>
                    <note id="n10">
                        <hi rend="s">10</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">Spectator</hi>, p. 1439. Also noted in “List of New
                        Books,” <hi rend="i">Athenaeum</hi>, 14 November 1874, p. 642. Both
                        lists give the price as 5/-.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In his correspondence with Mrs. Gilchrist and Swinburne between August 1873 and
                    March 1874, Rossetti discussed mainly copyright matters and the inclusion of
                    representative Prophetic Books. Initially he anticipated no difficulty over the
                    ten poems from the manuscript book later known as the Pickering MS., nine of
                    which D. G. Rossetti had printed in Volume II of Gilchrist. On 25 August 1873 he
                    wrote to Mrs. Gilchrist that “B[ell] wd. probably succeed in effecting some
                    arrangement with M[acmillan] &amp; P[ickering] enabling B. to reproduce the
                    poems,” though four days later he admitted that “the matter appears to
                    be a little complicated.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">11</ref> By 27
                    February 1874 he had reason to complain to Swinburne about “a provoking
                    claim of copyright,” and his fear that he might have to “miss
                    out” the poems, “thus spoiling the edition.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n12" type="note">12</ref> In another letter to Swinburne of 4 March 1874 he
                    reported as follows: 
					<q> The copyright difficulty—of wh. I foresaw
                        something from the first—is this. You 
<pb id="p12-6" n="6"/>
                        <figure n="PrefatoryMemoir.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="671" height="1000">
                        	<figTranscr>PREFATORY MEMOIR.<lb/>
							1.—PRELIMINARY.<lb/>
							IN writing a Memoir of William Blake,<lb/>
							little or no difficulty can now arise<lb/>
							as to the external facts—the dates,<lb/>
							personages, and incidents. The truly<lb/>
							valuable and so far exhaustive book<lb/>
							of Mr. Alexander Gilchrist has settled all these<lb/>
							points for us substantially; it barely requires to<lb/>
							be here and there rectified or supplemented in<lb/>
							some minor particular. Its tone moreover is as<lb/>
							earnest and elevated as its research is true and<lb/>
							thorough. I need hardly say that I am indebted<lb/>
							to this book for the vast majority of my facts:<lb/>
							any one who undertakes to write about Blake<lb/>
							cannot be otherwise. Thus far, therefore, everything<lb/>
							is plain: one has openly to acknowledge a<lb/>
							genuine debt of gratitude to Mr. Gilchrist, and<lb/>
							to run up the account freely.<lb/>
							The difficulty of Blake’s biographers, subsequent<lb/>
							to 1863, the date of Mr. Gilchrist’s book, is of a<lb/>
							different kind altogether. It is the difficulty of<lb/>
							stating sufficiently high the extraordinary claims<lb/>
							b</figTranscr>
                        </figure> 
                        remember that certain poems by Blake were for the first time
                        published in Gilchrist’s book—viz.: those wh. came from the
                        manuscript belonging to Gabriel &amp; me, &amp; also certain others
                        (Auguries of Innocence, Mental Traveller, &amp;c) wh. came from a small MS.
                        then in the hands of Mrs. Gilchrist. The poems from this small MS. are 
                        <hi rend="i">someone’s</hi> copyright for 42 years from date of first
                        publication (1863), just as the poems from Gabriel’s &amp; my
                        manuscript are <hi rend="i">our</hi> copyright. It turns out that the small
                        book was claimed by and returned to Tatham, who sold it to Harvey
                        (bookseller), who sold it to Pickering;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n13" type="note">13</ref> &amp; the latter republished these poems in or about 1865,
                        along with the Innocence &amp; Experience. Thus Pickering is the present
                        owner of this copyright; &amp; he, not liking Bell, nor relishing a further
                        republication of the poems, declines to authorize reissue. This is very
                        annoying. Bell did tell me a fortnight or so ago that he understands Dr.
                        Wilkinson is in possession of a certain Blake MS. containing perhaps these
                        same poems, or most of them, &amp; that Wilkinson would allow their
                        republication from this other MS. Of this I have as yet heard no more,
                        &amp; fear it will prove fallacious.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n14" type="note">14</ref>
                        <note id="n13">
                            <hi rend="s">13</hi> Cf. the account of provenance given by
                            G. E. Bentley, Jr., in <hi rend="i">The Blake Collection of Mrs. Landon
                                K. Thorne</hi> (New York, 1971), pp. 42-43.</note>
                        <note id="n14">
                            <hi rend="s">14</hi> B. L. Ashley MS. A1444, foll.
                            109v-110v.</note>
					</q>
					Wilkinson’s manuscript did not materialize,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n15" type="note">15</ref> but Rossetti was able to confide to Swinburne on 9
                    March 1874 that further probing by Bell had established an interpretation of the
                    ownership of copyright favorable to his edition: 
					<q> Bell told me the other day
                        . . . that the only poem to wh. Pickering’s copyright really applies
                        is Long John Brown.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16"
type="note">16</ref> This is indeed a
                        great satisfaction: for whether L. J. B. is in or out matters hardly at all.
                        I don’t however understand <hi rend="i">why</hi> Pickering’s
                        copyright is limited to that particular poem. My view of the matter was
                        this: —copyright attached to that whole series of poems for 42 years
                        following date of first publication, 1863: Pickering, at a later date,
                        became the legal owner of the poems, and therefore of the unexpired residue
                        of their copyright. <hi rend="i">Macmillan</hi> . . . was never the owner of
                        the copyright. Mrs. Gilchrist was the owner, as regards the Life generally:
                        &amp; it seems each proprietor of <hi rend="i">poems previously
                            unpublished</hi> was owner of the copyright in those same poems. Hence
                        Tatham was in 1863 owner of the copyright in the Pickering poems. I am
                        surprised to learn that he is still the owner; but Bell’s letter
                        seems to imply as much. Tatham gave me carte blanche some while ago, in case
                        he had any rights in the matter.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">17</ref>
                        <note id="n16">
                            <hi rend="s">16</hi> It applied also to “Song by a
                            Shepherd” and “Song by an Old Shepherd,” published for
                            the first time in R. H. Shepherd’s 1874 edition. Rossetti
                            excluded both from his edition.</note>
                        <note id="n17">
                            <hi rend="s">17</hi> B. L. Ashley MS. 1446, foll.
                            93-94.</note>
					</q>
                    <note id="n11">
                        <hi rend="s">11</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">Letters of William Michael Rossetti to Anne Gilchrist</hi>, ed.
                        C. Gohdes and P. F. Baum (Durham, N. C., 1934), pp. 87, 89.</note>
                    <note id="n12">
                        <hi rend="s">12</hi> B. L. Ashley MS. 1446, fol. 91.</note>
                    <note id="n15">
                        <hi rend="s">15</hi> “It seems Wilkinson has <hi rend="i">not</hi> got those rumoured
Blake poems: but he has referred Bell to a
                        lady who is supposed to possess something of the kind.” Rossetti to
                        Swinburne, 9 March [1874]. B. L. Ashley MS. 1446, foll. 93-93v.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Although Rossetti obviously had doubts about Bell’s understanding of the
                    matter, he finally added the Pickering poems to his edition, excluding
                    “Long John Brown” as D. G. Rossetti had done in 1863. In the
                    circumstances one would expect him to have reproduced his brother’s
                        versions,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref>
but his practice was
                    sometimes to follow the edition prepared for Pickering by R. H. Shepherd in 1866
                    and reissued in 1874, at other times to follow his brother, while at the same
                    time introducing emendations of his own.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n19" type="note">19</ref>
                    For example, as Sampson pointed out in 1905, Rossetti’s text of “The
                    Grey Monk” adopts four of D. G. Rossetti’s emendations, but
                    “follows Shepherd <figure n="Tiriel.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="623" height="1000"/>
                    <pb id="p12-7" n="7"/>
in the number and arrangement of verses, and generally as
                    to text, adopting two out of the three important changes from the MS. Book
                        version.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> On
the other hand, in
                    “The Crystal Cabinet” he adopts freely from both Shepherd and D. G.
                    Rossetti, and introduces substantial punctuation of his own devising. But on the
                    whole he was cautious about offering new readings. Fresh from his editing of
                    Shelley, he had no wish to encounter again the many reviewers who had taken
                    exception to his numerous conjectural emendations of Shelley’s poems.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref>
                    <note id="n18">
                        <hi rend="s">18</hi> In early October 1874 he was still
                        discussing the matter of text with D. G. Rossetti, who suggested:
                        “About the <hi rend="i">Auguries of Innocence</hi> etc., it strikes me
                        that a verbatim version of the former, at any rate, appeared in
                        Swinburne’s <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>—did it not? and might in
                        that case be reprinted by Bell &amp; Daldy if you wish.” (<hi rend="i">Letters of
Dante Gabriel Rossetti</hi>, ed. O. Doughty and J. R. Wahl
                        (Oxford, 1965-1967), III, 1314.) William’s review of
                        Shepherd’s 1874 edition, Pickering’s fly-sheet attacking the
                        editing of the poems in Gilchrist, and Rossetti’s reply in the 
<hi rend="i">Academy</hi> (see Dorfman, pp. 112-13), all of which appeared
                        between 5 September and 10 October 1874, undoubtedly delayed
                        Rossetti’s decision about adopting readings from Shepherd’s
                        text.</note>
                    <note id="n19">
                        <hi rend="s">19</hi> Cf. G. Keynes’ statement (<hi rend="i">A Blake
Bibliography</hi> (New York, 1921), p. 271) that in the
                        poems from the Pickering MS. Rossetti “generally” followed D. G.
                        Rossetti. Keynes correctly notes that Rossetti’s text of the <hi rend="i">Poetical
Sketches</hi> “is derived from Shepherd’s
                        edition of 1868 . . . and is very accurate,” whereas in the case of the
                            <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> and of the poems
                        from the Rossetti MS. he “followed the very inaccurate version given by
                        D. G. Rossetti in Gilchrist.”</note>
                    <note id="n20">
                        <hi rend="s">20</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">The Poetical Works of William Blake</hi>, ed. J. Sampson
                        (Oxford, 1905), p. 284.</note>
                    <note id="n21">
                        <hi rend="s">21</hi> Chief among them was Robert Buchanan in the
                            <hi rend="i">Athenaeum</hi> for 29 January 1870, pp. 154-56.</note>
                </p>
                <p>As for the Prophetic Books, Rossetti was not sufficiently enthusiastic to
                    champion them against Bell’s dismissal beyond arguing for the inclusion
                    of a sampling.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref>
In his Diary for 6 August
                    1873 (quoted above) he mentions <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
                        Hell</hi>, but by 23 August he had decided on <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref> choosing it, he answered Swinburne who had
                    urged on him the claims of <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>,
						<q> not because it is the best of the Prophetic Books (of course it is far
                        from being such), but because it is short, lyrical in tone &amp;
                        approximately in form, &amp; easily accesible—being printed in
                        Gilchrist’s book. The Visions of the Daughters of Albion wd. have had
                        to be hunted up: probably transcribed bodily from some copy in the British
                        Museum. I don’t <hi rend="i">remember</hi> it very exactly, but am
                        quite prepared to think it is a finer poem than Thel: I <hi rend="i">do</hi>
                        remember that it is one of the more startling of Blake’s moral
                        dithyrambics, &amp; that wd. weight the scale agst. it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref>
                        <note id="n24">
                            <hi rend="s">24</hi> 7 March [1874]. B. L. Ashley MS. 1446,
                            foll. 92-92v.</note>
					</q>
					“The prospective publisher is not a known emanation of the giant
                    Albion,” he reminded Swinburne later in the letter. Why he included 
<hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> as well is not clear, though the unexpected
                    reappearance of the manuscript was the most likely reason.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref> When Swinburne, in acknowledging Rossetti’s
                    edition, regretted its “public appearance,” Rossetti merely replied
                    that he was “Sorry you are so adverse to Tiriel—wh. I for my part
                    think fully entitled to its place in the book.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n26" type="note">26</ref>
                    <note id="n22">
                        <hi rend="s">22</hi> During the 1860’s Rossetti’s
                        attitude towards the Prophetic Books, if not overly sympathetic, was at
                        least open. On 22 May 1862 Mrs. Gilchrist requested from him “brief
                        general” descriptions of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell,
                            The Book of Ahania, The Song of Los, Asia</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Africa.</hi> 
(<hi rend="i">Rossetti Papers</hi>, ed. W. M. Rossetti
                        (London, 1903), p. 6.) Perhaps it is to these that Rossetti refers in an
                        unpublished passage of his <hi rend="i">Reminiscences</hi> (Bodley MS. Eng.
                        Misc. d. 332, fol. 213) where he records that remarks by him of a critical
                        bearing were embodied in Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life.</hi> That
                        Mrs. Gilchrist’s list was extended is suggested by a surviving note
                        on <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, which Mrs.
                        Gilchrist “reduced,” certain that Macmillan would reject it,
                        though she considered it “most vigorous and admirable.” (H. H.
                        Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Anne Gilchrist, Her Life and Writings</hi> (London,
                        1887), pp. 127-28, where the original note is printed. She in fact rewrote
                        it, replacing Rossetti’s direct exposition with the statement that
                        “Formidable moral questions are opened up through the medium of this
                        allegory. . . . But we will not enter on them here.” (<hi rend="i">Life
                            of Blake</hi> (London, 1863), p. 108.) Even this statement was omitted
                        from the second edition of 1880.) It is worth mentioning as well
                        Rossetti’s lengthy exposition of “The Mental Traveller,”
                        printed in Gilchrist, as evidence of his willingness to tackle a difficult
                        text; and his constant support for Swinburne’s <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, of which he
wrote to the poet on 2 January [1866] after
                        reading the manuscript: “I should consider its publication the greatest
                        service at present possible to Blake, &amp; hardly inferior to a full
                        critical edition of his writings.” (B. L. Ashley MS. 1446, fol.
                        2v.)</note>
                    <note id="n23">
                        <hi rend="s">23</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">Letters to Anne Gilchrist</hi>, p. 85.</note>
                    <note id="n25">
                        <hi rend="s">25</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">Poetical Works of William Blake</hi>, ed. W. M. Rossetti
                        (London, 1874), p. cxxiii.</note>
                    <note id="n26">
                        <hi rend="s">26</hi> 4 November [1874]. B. L. Ashley MS. 1446,
                        fol. 96.</note>
                </p>
                <p>At the same time, it should be noted that however ambivalent Rossetti’s
                    attitude towards the Prophetic Books was, he favored publication of a
                    letterpress edition. Their exclusion from the Aldine edition, he insisted to
                    Swinburne, “wd. not have been my voluntary choice,” and he again
                    excused that “it was obviously the only course likely to be adopted by a
                        Publisher.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref>
In the Memoir
                    prefixed to the edition he explicitly called for publication, arguing that
                    “Blake will be but imperfectly known even to his enthusiasts until this is
                        done.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">28</ref> Four
years later, in a
                    review in the <hi rend="i">Academy</hi> of the facsimile edition of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> published by Pearson in 1877, he pleaded at length:
<q> We
                        cannot omit the present opportunity of saying that the publication in
                        ordinary book-form, without designs, and without any attempt at facsimile of
                        text, of the <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and other Prophetic Books, is
                        highly to be desired. Difficult under any circumstances, it would be a good
                        deal <hi rend="i">less</hi> difficult to read these works in an edition of
                        that kind, with clear print, <figure n="BookofThel.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="675" height="1000"/>
reasonable division of lines, and the
                        like aids to business-like perusal. An index of the mythologic personages of
                        Blake’s strangely-named pantheon or pandemonium, with an account of
                        their various and semi-intelligible performances throughout the successive
                        Prophetic Books, would also be a powerful aid to such understanding of the
                        subject as is, in the nature of things, possible. No doubt the compilation
                        of such an index would be rather like attempting to draw a nightmare to
                        scale: but something or other in that direction could undoubtedly be
                        accomplished, with patience and goodwill for the work.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">29</ref>
                        <note id="n29">
                            <hi rend="s">29</hi>
                            <hi rend="i">Academy</hi>, 13 (1878), 174.</note>
					</q>
					About the possibility of approaching total explication he remained
                    skeptical. In an unpublished passage of his autobiography, written between 1901
                    and 1903, he observed: 
					<q> I know most of what has been written about Blake, but
                        have not investigated the elaborate study of his works by Messrs. Ellis
                        &amp; Yeats in their edition of a few years ago. I had a little speech with
                        them on this subject, &amp; learned that they regarded Blake’s
                        religious or quasi-religious utterances, usually counted to be chaotic, as
                        cosmical in essence, &amp; in detail interpretable. I presume that this
                        view is to some valid extent justified by their commentary; yet cannot bring
                        myself to think that Blake was in these matters a constructive thinker or an
                        orderly expositor. My impression continues as heretofore—that, while
                        he was a great genius in two arts, there was also a maniacal side to his
                        intellect. Needless to 
<pb id="p12-8" n="8"/>
                        <figure n="PoeticalWorksBinding.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="700"/> say that he was not a
madman pure &amp; simple: but he was a
                        creative inventor whose ideas &amp; utterances struggled beyond the limits
                        of sanity. This view may be erroneous: it is the one to which my studies of
                        Blake’s works have led me.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30"
type="note">30</ref>
                        <note id="n30">
                            <hi rend="s">30</hi> “Some Reminiscences.”
                                Bodley MS. Eng. Misc. d. 331, fol. 214. Two visits, one from Yeats
                                and one from Yeats and Ellis, are recorded in Rossetti’s
                                Diary (Special Collections, University of British Columbia): 11
                                September 1890, “Yeats the young Irish Poet (to whom I was
                                introduced some while ago at a Shelley meeting) left a card the
                                other day noting that he wd. like to speak to me on some Blake
                                matters, as he is now writing on that subject. I explained that we
                                are in the confusion of moving, &amp; suggested that he might
                                perhaps as well call at Somer. Ho. He did so today, &amp; we had a
                                longish talk. He is certainly a very acute &amp; bright-minded
                                young man. He &amp; one of the Ellis (Philological) family are
                                engaged in producing a complete edition of B’s Prophetical
                                Books &amp;c., with comment expounding his philosophical or
                                speculative system—wh. Y. regards as being founded very
                                mainly on Boehme. This matter was glanced at in an article by York
                                Powell (I was reading it the other evg.), introductory to the
                                “Book of Los” lately discovered. Tho’ I have not as
                                yet been disposed to regard B’s Jerusalem &amp;c. as capable
                                of more than a moderate amount of reasoned explanation, I see, from
                                what Y. says, that there is a good deal to be adduced &amp;
                                expounded from his point of view. What he more particuly. wanted
                                from me was to trace out the Book of Ahania, &amp; The French
                                Revolution. He says they are not in the British Museum. My
                                impression is that that is where I read them (in 1862): I shall
                                probably, as I look into the matter, be able to give Y. some little
                                further informn. as to details. I referred Y. to that passage in my
                                Memoir of B. in wh. I indicate the affiliation of his theology to
                                that of Marcion: Y. seems as yet not to have fixed his attention on
                                this passage, but he will now give some practical study to the
                                question.”
                            <p>13 April 1891, “Yeats, &amp; his colleague in the project of
                                reediting Blake . . . called on me at Somers. Ho. Their undertaking
                                has now reached an advanced stage. They showed me one of the
                                Prophetic Books reprinted in a quasi-facsimile. I
                                think—&amp; told them so—that I regard this as a
                                decided mistake. One cannot read with any comfort a book in any such
                                sort of fancy-type: besides the cost of the edition, both to
                                projectors and to purchasers must thus become beyond all bounds of
                                reason.”</p>
                            <p>Yeats later wrote of Rossetti, <hi rend="i">apropos</hi> of his
                                opinion of the Prophetic Books, that he was “a man of
                                exceptional ability and high literary standing, who happens not to
                                be in sympathy with Blake’s method of writing.” <hi rend="i">The Works of
William Blake</hi>, ed. E. J. Ellis and W.
                                B. Yeats (London, 1893), I, 54-55.</p>
                        </note>
					</q>
					That Rossetti deleted this passage when he prepared his autobiography for
                    publication in 1906 could, of course, be interpreted as suggesting a waning of
                    confidence in his judgment. <note id="n27">
                        <hi rend="s">27</hi> 4 March [1874].
                        B. L. Ashley MS. A1444, fol. 109v.</note>
                    <note id="n28">
                        <hi rend="s">28</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi>, p. cxxix.</note>
                </p>
                <p>To the reviewers of the Aldine edition in 1874-1875, Rossetti’s kind of
                    cautious assessment was (in a word applied to the Memoir by most of them)
                    “sound.” Edmund Gosse’s two-part review in the <hi rend="i">Examiner</hi>
                    <ref target="n31" type="note">31</ref> offers the most
                    pronounced indication of critical opinion of Blake in the 1870s. Gosse, a friend
                    both of the Rossettis and of Swinburne, declared that there was a danger
                    “that, after so long a time of disgrace and oblivion, the reaction may be
                    too violent, and the enthusiasm over the newfound wonder be blind and altogether
                    excessive.” He confessed that “some such fear as this was in our mind
                    when we began Mr. Rossetti’s long, learned, and most interesting memoir;
                    and, though we are of the opinion that in one or two cases his admiration for
                    his subject has led him beyond what the canons of pure criticism permit, we are
                    bound in justice to say that, as a whole, his memoir is as remarkable for clear
                    judgment and good sense as it is for enthusiasm.” At the same time Gosse
                    was sharply critical of Rossetti’s urging of the publication of the
                    Prophetic Books: “He seems to us to propose one of the most hopeless and
                    ill-advised experiments that the publishing world has ever seen.” A similar
                    criticism came from John Dennis in the <hi rend="i">Spectator.</hi>
                    <ref target="n32" type="note">32</ref> Dennis expressed surprise that,
                    considering Rossetti’s opinion that the Prophetic Books “are neither
                    readable nor even entirely sane” (Dennis’ words), he should consider
                    it desirable that they be published: “We disagree with him altogether.
                    Blake wrote a great deal of what, had it been the work of a smaller man, would
                    be accounted trash, and the sooner it is forgotten the better for his fame. We
                    venture indeed to think that Mr. Rossetti would have done wisely to omit a good
                    deal contained in this small volume, since there are passages here as free
                    almost from mind and meaning as any combination of words could well be.”
                    Only George Saintsbury in the <hi rend="i">Academy</hi>
                    <ref target="n33" type="note">33</ref> supported publication: “The sooner it is done the
                    better.” Yet even Saintsbury was of the opinion that on Blake’s
                    madness Rossetti’s “conclusions might have been safely stated with
                    much less qualification, that Blake was most undoubtedly mad, unless the meaning
                    of words is to be strangely perverted.” Much the same point was made, less
                    sympathetically, by Coventry Patmore in the <hi rend="i">St. James’s
                        Gazette</hi>: “Mr. W. Rossetti . . . goes a great way further in his
                    admiration of Blake than reason can be shown for.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n34" type="note">34</ref> What these reviews amply demonstrate (and other reviews
                    in such papers as the <hi rend="i">Daily News</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Sunday
                        Times</hi> closely echo them)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35"
type="note">35</ref> is that
                    the publishers were clearly right in thinking that the Prophetic Books did not
                    yet have a place in a “popular” edition of Blake’s poems, and
                    just as clearly, that Rossetti’s qualified assessment of Blake’s
                    genius, however tame and wrong-headed it would in time appear, was in 1874
                    somewhat in advance of the times. The real value of Rossetti’s edition,
                    as Saintsbury remarked, consisted in the “increased facilities” it
                    offered for studying a significant portion of Blake’s poetry, and of
                    assessing its “certain excellences.” This value it retained until its
                    place was taken by the Yeats-Ellis edition of 1893, and, more effectively, by
                    Sampson’s one-volume edition of 1905.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n36" type="note">36</ref>
                    <note id="n31">
                        <hi rend="s">31</hi> 14, 21 November 1874, pp. 1243-44,
                        1270-71.</note>
                    <note id="n32">
                        <hi rend="s">32</hi> 2 January 1875, pp. 14-16. I am indebted to
                        my colleague, Dr. R. H. Tener, for identifying the reviewer from his
                        transcript of the <hi rend="i">Spectator</hi> records.</note>
                    <note id="n33">
                        <hi rend="s">33</hi> 6 (5 December 1874), 599-601.</note>
                    <note id="n34">
                        <hi rend="s">34</hi> Reprinted in <hi rend="i">Principles in
                            Art</hi> (London, 1907), p. 94.</note>
                    <note id="n35">
                        <hi rend="s">35</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">Daily News</hi>, 5 December 1874, p. 2; <hi rend="i">Sunday
                            Times</hi>, 22 November 1874, p. 7. A neglected four-part review by G.
                        W. Foote, the atheist who was tried for blasphemy in 1883, appeared in the
                            <hi rend="i">National Reformer</hi>, N.S. 25 (14, 21, 28 February, 21
                        March 1875), 100-01, 115-16, 131-32, 181-82. Foote observed that after his
                        “generous vindication of the rising genius of Swinburne” and his
                        edition of Whitman, Rossetti had turned appropriately to Blake, a poet
                        “as audacious even as Whitman.”</note>
                    <note id="n36">
                        <hi rend="s">36</hi> Since the records of G. Bell &amp; Sons are
                        unavailable, it is impossible to know how often the volume was reprinted. I
                        have examined the following reprints: 1875, 1879, 1882, 1883, 1885, 1888,
                        May 1890, October 1890, 1891, 1893, 1913, 1914 (“Bohn’s Popular
                        Library,” with the addition of the three Pickering copyright pieces
                        mentioned above). Bentley and Nurmi note reprints of 1890 and
                    1911.</note>
                </p>
            </div1>
	<pb id="p12-9" n="9" rend="hidden"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>