<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.1.discussion</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="discussion">Ruth Fine’s review of the Blake exhibition at Adelphi University</title>
                <author n="Doctorow">Erica Doctorow</author>
                <author n="Wolf">Donald Wolf</author>
                <author n="Fine">Ruth E. Fine</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1978</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Shelley Grieve</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Mary Clarke</name>
                            <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
                            <name>Frank Graziano</name>
                            <name>Jean H. Hagstrum</name>
                            <name>Gunnar Harding</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Joe Napora</name>
                            <name>Martin K. Numri</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>R. W. Peattie</name>
                            <name>Marcia Tillotson</name>
                            <name>Gunnel Tottie</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1978"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
	<pb id="p12-72" n="72"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-1-0013">
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="section">
                            <hi rend="b">DISCUSSION</hi>
                        </title>
                        <title type="section-subtitle">
                            (with intellectual spears &amp; long winged arrows of thought)
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>We received the following letter from Erica Doctorow and Donald Wolf and
                        solicited the reply from Ruth E. Fine that follows it in turn:</p>
                    <p>To the Editors: 1 June 1978<lb/>
 This may seem like a tardy reply to Ruth
                        Fine’s review (<hi rend="i">Blake 42</hi>, fall 1977) of the Blake
                        exhibition at Adelphi University, but the review itself appeared six months
                        after the exhibition closed, and it raises some interesting questions.</p>
                    <p>To begin with, Miss Fine writes that it is a “disservice to late
                        18th-early 19th century England” to suggest that Blake confronted
                        neglect and indifference. Isn’t it an even greater disservice to
                        Blake to imply that he may actually have received the recognition he
                        deserved?</p>
                    <p>Miss Fine’s review also does a disservice to the catalog, a reading of
                        which can hardly justify her remark that it is “more spirited than
                        informative,” especially if one keeps in mind that it was intended 
<pb id="p12-73" n="73"/>
to be an introduction to Blake. Miss Fine notes
                        this purpose but recalls it only fitfully.</p>
                    <p>“The crow wish’d every thing was black, the owl that every thing
                        was white.” Miss Fine wishes that the exhibition had made a major point
                        of the fact that original prints and drawings are superior to reproductions.
                        At least, that seems to be what she means when she says that it should have
                        demonstrated “the differences in the tactile life of printed surfaces
                        and their effects on one’s responses to works of art.” (Her
                        style is definitely not spirited.) Adelphi focused on the content of
                        Blake’s art. Would it not have been a disservice to our students to
                        teach them that they were doomed to inferior esthetic experiences by the
                        unavailability of the original prints, which, as Miss Fine puts it, must
                        remain in repositories like the Alverthorpe Gallery for the sake of
                        “persons”—she seems to mean scholars—“who
                        travel great distances and at great expense in anticipation of viewing
                        particular works”? Apparently she is as content for Blake to belong to
                        the few, not the many, in the present as in the past. As it happens, the
                        exhibition itself contradicted her premise, thanks to the generosity of
                        other institutions and private collectors who lent Adelphi many original
                        works.</p>
                    <p>It is also a disservice to readers of <hi rend="i">Blake, An Illustrated
                            Quarterly</hi> to permit the implication to stand, as Miss Fine does,
                        that she attended any of the events related to the exhibition—in
                        particular, the opera, “Auguries of Innocence,” and the dance,
                        “Eternity in an Hour.” Since she did not, it does not much matter
                        that she seems to find them praiseworthy. On the other hand, she does not
                        mention that the exhibition opened with a talk on Blake’s methods of
                        printing; but she does criticize Adelphi for giving no attention to the
                        matter.</p>
                    <p>Given a different tone, Miss Fine’s criticisms might be understood as
                        the opposition of true friendship. As it is, our reaction is better
                        suggested by another of Blake’s proverbs: “He whose face gives
                        no light shall never become a star.”</p>
                    <table rows="3" cols="2">
                        <row>
                            <cell>Erica Doctorow</cell>
                            <cell>Donald Wolf</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Fine Arts Librarian</cell>
                            <cell>Professor of English</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Adelphi University</cell>
                            <cell>Adelphi University</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>Ruth E. Fine replies: 27 June 1978<lb/>
 Ms. Doctorow and Professor Wolf were
                        sent a copy of the Blake exhibition review manuscript, published in the fall
                        1977 issue of <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, well in advance of its publication, a
                        gesture to which they never responded; the elliptical implication of the
                        sorrows of time passed with which they open their letter thus leaves a
                        mysterious question as to motivation in writing now.</p>
                    <p>It remains extremely disturbing that the difference between reproductions and
                        original works is a matter of such casual inconsequence to the organizers of
                        a Blake exhibition. This, however, may account for the lack or
                        superficiality of the descriptive material regarding such differences.</p>
                    <p>So far as viewing original material is concerned, Alverthorpe Gallery, as the
                        review accurately stated, is open to “persons”—any person
                        who will write or call and who shows genuine interest in examining the
                        collection. Hundreds do. The inference drawn by Ms. Doctorow and Professor
                        Wolf that access to the collection is restricted to “scholars”
                        (with no suggestion of what standards they would assign to that category) is
                        inaccurate; it is also unscholarly since the truth of the matter could
                        easily have been determined before it was committed to paper.</p>
                    <p>This is only one inaccuracy of several in their defensive response to my
                        review, but it would be tedious beyond decent patience to refute them
                        further.</p>
                    <p>Ruth E. Fine</p>
                    <p>Curator</p>
                    <p>Alverthorpe Gallery</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>