<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.1.bentley</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="minute">The First Printed Reference to the Publication of Job: Disraeli(?) in The
Star Chamber (1826)</title>
                <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1978</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Shelley Grieve</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Mary Clarke</name>
                            <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
                            <name>Frank Graziano</name>
                            <name>Jean H. Hagstrum</name>
                            <name>Gunnar Harding</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Joe Napora</name>
                            <name>Martin K. Numri</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>R. W. Peattie</name>
                            <name>Marcia Tillotson</name>
                            <name>Gunnel Tottie</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1978"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
	<pb id="p12-69" n="69"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-1-0012">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">THE FIRST PRINTED REFERENCE TO THE PUBLICATION OF 
<hi rend="i">JOB:</hi> DISRAELI (?) IN <hi rend="i">THE STAR
                                    CHAMBER</hi> (1826)</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor><hi rend="b">G. E. </hi><name><hi rend="b">Bentley</hi></name>, 
<hi rend="b">Jr.</hi>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>Professor William S. Ward has generously drawn my attention to a previously
                        unrecorded reference to Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> in the obscure
                        and short-lived satirical political weekly <hi rend="i">The Star
                            Chamber</hi> for Wednesday 3 May 1826: 
<q> Mr. William Blake, whose
                            illustrations in outline of Young, Gray, and other poets have long been
                            before the public, has completed his designs for the Book of Job. Some
                            of the etchings are full of that remarkable wildness and singularity of
                            conception, for which Blake is so well known. The embodying of the
                            plagues inflicted on Job by the Almighty; the personification of a
                            Night-mare, and the figures of the creation,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72" type="note">1</ref> are wonderful, although we do not think them
                            equal either in point of originality or skilful execution to some of the
                            earlier productions of this extraordinary artist.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73" type="note">2</ref>
                            <note id="n72">
                                <hi rend="s">1</hi> The three <hi rend="i">Job</hi>
                                plates referred to are presumably pl. 6, “And smote Job with
                                sore boils”; pl. 11, “With Dreams upon my bed thou scarest
                                me”; and pl. 15, “Behold now Behemoth which I made with
                                thee.”</note>
                            <note id="n73">
                                <hi rend="s">2</hi>
                                <hi rend="i">The Star Chamber</hi>, No. 4 (3 May 1826), 73.</note>
						</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>The account is interesting for a number of reasons. For one thing, it
                        displays a surprising knowledge of Blake’s works. The
                        “illustrations in outline of Young” refer of course to
                        Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797) with forty-three
                        plates designed and engraved by Blake. The “Gray” outlines can
                        scarcely refer to the series of watercolors Blake made in 1797-98 for
                        Flaxman in illustration of Gray’s poems, for these were not
                        “before the public” in 1826 (they were first published in 1922);
                        “Gray” is probably a mistake for <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> by
                        Robert Blair with twelve designs by Blake etched by Schiavonetti published
                        in 1808 and 1813, for this was Blake’s best-known work. The
                        “earlier productions of this extraordinary artist” seems to refer
                        to Blake’s works in Illuminated Printing, and since very few copies
                        were printed they were known only to few. The <hi rend="i">Star Chamber</hi>
                        author seems to have been surprisingly well informed about Blake’s
                        works.</p>
                    <p>He is also strikingly up-to-date in his information about the publication of
                            <hi rend="i">Job.</hi> Subscriptions for it had been taken since 1823
                            (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> [1969], 598), but the label is dated
                        “March 1826,” and the first completed copies were distributed at
                        the end of that month (<hi rend="i">ibid</hi>, p. 327). It was not, however,
                        published in the ordinary way, apparently no review-copies were sent to
                        journals, and no review of it is known. Indeed, not only is the <hi rend="i">Star
Chamber</hi> paragraph the first known published reference to the
                        publication of <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, but it seems to be the only such
                        reference during Blake’s lifetime. Even the obituaries of Blake
                        failed to mention <hi rend="i">Job</hi> except for that in <hi rend="i">The
                            Literary Gazette</hi> (1 November 1827), and the only other account
                        before 1830 was in J. T. Smith’s life of Blake (1828). The <hi rend="i">Star
Chamber</hi> account is important, therefore, as the only
                        printed reference during Blake’s lifetime to the publication of his
                        greatest finished series of line-engravings.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">The Star Chamber</hi> is a jocular sixteen-page weekly published
                        by W. Marsh which began on 19 April 1826 and ended with No. 9 on Wednesday 7
                        June 1826. It includes reviews, attacks on politicians, “The Dunciad of
                        To-day,” and news of the arts, particularly exhibitions; it is in the
                        untitled art section that the Blake reference comes. The periodical seems to
                        have been founded by Peter Hall (who gave a copy to Bodley) with various
                        assistants. Benjamin Disraeli was accused of having been the first editor,
                        but he expressly denied this in <hi rend="i">The Times</hi> for 3 November
                        1871 and <hi rend="i">Leisure Hours</hi> for 4 November 1871.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">3</ref> However, his authorized biographer
                        concedes that Disraeli did contribute some fables called “The Modern
                        AEsop,” a review, “and perhaps other matter,”<hi rend="s">3</hi> and it is not
unlikely that he was responsible directly or
                        indirectly for the notice of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job.</hi> At any
                        rate, he was peculiarly well situated to know of Blake’s more
                        “original” and “skilful” “earlier
                        productions,” for his father Isaac (d. 1848) owned <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> (F), 
<hi rend="i">Visions</hi> (F), <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> (D), <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> (B), 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (A), <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (A), and <hi rend="i">Song of
                            Los</hi>, and these works of course later came into Benjamin
                        Disraeli’s hands. And we know that Benjamin himself was interested in
                        Blake, for he tried to get The British Museum to buy Blake’s 537
                        watercolor designs to Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> in
                            1875,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75" type="note">4</ref>
over fifty years before they
                        eventually reached the Museum. It is at least a plausible guess that
                        Benjamin Disraeli is the 
<pb id="p12-70" n="70"/>
author of the only
                        contemporary printed reference to the publication of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job.</hi>
                        <note id="n74">
                            <hi rend="s">3</hi> William Flavelle Monypenny, <hi rend="i">The Life of Benjamin
Disraeli Earl of Beaconsfield</hi>, I (1910),
                            84n. Robert Blake, <hi rend="i">Disraeli</hi> (1966), p. 44, finds it
                            “difficult to avoid the conclusion that Disraeli was the moving
                            spirit.”</note>
                        <note id="n75">
                            <hi rend="s">4</hi> James S. Bain, <hi rend="i">A Bookseller
                                Looks Back</hi> (1940), p. 75.</note>
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>