<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.1.nurmi</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">John Howard, Blake’s Milton; John Karl Franson, ed., Milton
Reconsidered</title>
                <author n="Nurmi">Martin K. Nurmi</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1978</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Shelley Grieve</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Mary Clarke</name>
                            <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
                            <name>Frank Graziano</name>
                            <name>Jean H. Hagstrum</name>
                            <name>Gunnar Harding</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Joe Napora</name>
                            <name>Martin K. Numri</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>R. W. Peattie</name>
                            <name>Marcia Tillotson</name>
                            <name>Gunnel Tottie</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1978"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-1-0011">
                <pb id="p12-56" n="56"/>
                <div2>
                    <figure n="HowardBlakesMilton.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="431"/>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">John Howard. <hi rend="b">Blake’s Milton: A Study in
                                Selfhood.</hi> Rutherford, N.J.: Fairleigh Dickinson University
                            Press, 1976. Pp. 300. $15.00.</title>
                        <title type="main">John Karl Franson, ed. <hi rend="b">Milton Reconsidered: Essays in
Honor of Arthur E. Barker.</hi>
                            Salzburg: Institut für Sprache und Literatur, Salzburg Studies in
                            English Literature, No. 49, 1976. $17.50.</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="b">Martin K.</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">Nurmi</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>The essential argument of John Howard’s monograph on <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> is
given on p. 13: 
<q> It is with Blake’s view of
                            the process of [the psychic fall and redemption characteristic of long
                            Romantic poems] that we are concerned here. Blake’s vision of the
                            fall and redemption offers a way of talking about the
                            individual’s “spiritual” makeup, a way of mapping out
                            the architecture and landscape of the personality. Blake describes how
                            the personality permits its own instincts of fear to imprison its
                            creativity in delusion, an imprisonment that lasts until its creativity
                            reasserts itself in a defiant act of self-annihilation. This
                            imprisonment and subsequent freedom are embodied in his vision of the
                            fall and redemption in <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> . . . . The imprisoning
                            instincts he called the selfhood, which is a false covering over the
                            immortal spirit. Blake saw the selfhood as survival-oriented,
                            manifesting itself as a hold-fast defense mechanism toward exterior
                            reality as well as repressive enchainments of the creativity within. But
                            Blake’s view of the selfhood encompassed even more. Because he
                            believed that the exterior world is an emanation of the immortal,
                            creative part of personality, his concept of the selfhood also
                            encompassed all the defensive structures of society and man’s
                            history. </q>
                    </p>
                    <p>The psychological orientation of Howard’s study produces some fresh
                        insights into some of the individual passages he comments on, but I think on
                        the whole it is limited by an assumption that comes perilously close to
                        saying that Romantic poetry, which wanted to express the conflict between
                        the imprisoning selfhood and the impulse toward free creativity and full
                        realization of the integrated personality, might not have been written at
                        all—or at least would not have taken the form it did—if the
                        age had developed a psychological language adequate to express this
                        conflict: “The psychological language necessary to express the conflict
                        between these two forces of personality had not yet been created, and only
                        in the imaginative analogies of poetry could a successful vehicle be found.
                        But the age certainly had a need for such language. Without it, the writer
                        could only project his undelineated feelings onto exterior phenomena, and
                        describe those phenomena in a way that relfected his but semi-conscious
                        feelings” (pp. 13-14). Specifically concerning Blake in this context,
                        Howard adds: “Though Blake had no readymade language to reveal how
                        these objective symbols [that projected the semi-conscious feelings] were
                        reflections of interior states of mind, he had certainly become aware of the
                        phenomenon, and his task was to put together a language and poetic structure
                        that could express what he saw. He called it <hi rend="i">sublime
                            allegory</hi>” (p. 14). Poetry in 
<pb id="p12-57" n="57"/>
                        Howard’s esthetic is very much in the service of “concept”
                        or idea, which could be expressed more directly if only an adequate language
                        had been developed for it. And Blake’s “tool” for
                        expressing his “concept of reality” was the symbol (p. 15).</p>
                    <p>Howard’s conception of Blake’s myth as expressing the conflicts
                        within an individual personality I find disturbingly limiting and
                        misleading, and this is not really compensated for by his effort to expand
                        the idea of selfhood to society and its institutions in his notion of the
                        “exterior” selfhood. To be sure, the idea can be supported by
                        selection from among the most condensed utterances from Blake’s text.
                        But it seems to me that the things that crystalize and institutionalize the
                        selfhood are not identical with the selfhood but extensions of it, results
                        of its operation. And the opposite of the selfhood is not, as Howard
                        suggests, creativity but an opening out of the self into relationship and
                        full identification with humanity and divinity, which may be brought about
                        by the creativity of apocalyptic and visionary art like Blake’s and
                        which would create the conditions for the continued production of art that
                        expresses the whole life of man. But I think in this context that the much
                        abused term “creativity” is not very useful or accurate. Though by
                        the time he wrote and designed <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> Blake had greatly
                        expanded his earlier idea of the selfhood, it still seems to me that it is
                        consistent with its appearance in poems like “The Clod and the
                        Pebble” and the opening chapters of <hi rend="i">The Book of
                            Urizen.</hi> As elaborated, I’m not sure Howard’s always
                        is. After many years of acquaintance with Blake, I still find afresh, in
                        various personal difficulties, psychological illuminations that are simply
                        amazing. But I think it is wrong to posit that the whole of Blake’s
                        myth expresses a “landscape and architecture of the
                        personality.”</p>
                    <p>Fortunately, when Howard works with specific passages in the text, the power
                        of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> usually overwhelms his esthetic, and he talks
                        about the poetry in a way that doesn’t reflect the limitations in his
                        theory. But he does talk about the poetry only, and in the general context
                        of its ideas.</p>
                    <p>This is a book which might have been written two or three decades ago, before
                        Blake criticism began fully to direct attention to the illuminated books as
                        composite art. It is still possible to focus critically on Blake’s
                        text alone, especially in the lyrics, without at every point in the
                        discussion bringing in the designs, especially when they do little more than
                        illustrate. Or on the designs alone. But in 1976 a full scale critical study
                        of a gorgeous and pregnantly illuminated work of composite art like 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, even one giving special attention to a theme as
                        this one does, must not ignore the total form in which Blake developed his
                        theme. A reader of this book who knew nothing else about Blake would be
                        quite astonished to discover what kind of work <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
                        really is.</p>
                    <p>Though Howard’s study in general follows the pattern of the fall and
                        redemption and hence the overall pattern of the narrative of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
(with chapters on “The Spiritual World,”
                        “Fall into Selfhood,” “The Blossoming of the Selfhood,”
                        “Regeneration,” “The Journey: Background,” and finally
                        “The Journey”), it is not a <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">seriatim</hi></corr>
reading or
                        critical commentary on it. It is really a study for someone who already
                        knows the work pretty well and would, I think, be quite confusing to the
                        uninitiated.</p>
                    <p>A pair of characteristically vigorous articles by Karl Kiralis and John E.
                        Grant, both deriving from papers at the 1975 MLA meeting, consider,
                        respectively, Blake’s illustrations for Milton’s <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and
<hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi> and plates 42,
                        48, 49, and 50 of <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> The articles are included in a
                        Festschrift for Arthur E. Barker. Kiralis, in “Blake’s Criticism
                        of Milton’s <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il
                            Penseroso</hi> and of Its Author” (pp. 46-77 of the volume, with
                        twelve plates), disagrees with other critics in arguing that in these
                        illustrations Blake shows that Milton was still “too indoctrinated by
                        society’s rational forces to the false ideals of the Female Will,
                        especially Deism, and too sexually repressed to search for true experience .
                        . . for Blake yet to hope for Milton’s salvation and consequent
                        prophetic writing” (p. 77). Buttressing the discursive argument is a
                        commentary that reads the meaning of the illustrations—plausibly, I
                        think.</p>
                    <p>Grant, in “The Female Awakening at the End of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: A
Picture Story with Questions” (pp. 78-99,
                        with three plates), first raises some theoretical “alignments” in
                        relationships between “a poet and a visual artist,” “the
                        writer Milton and the writer and visual artist Blake,” “of Blake
                        as designer of <hi rend="i">Milton: A Poem</hi> and as illustrator of John
                        Milton’s poems,” and “the writer Blake and the visual
                        artist Blake in a poem entitled <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>,” and then
                        goes on to ask a number of suggestive questions about the plates intended to
                        evoke a reading of the sequence of plates that makes coherent sense, as he
                        thinks Blake’s plates do if responsibly examined. The article ends
                        with some briefly suggested answers.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>