<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.1.essick</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="article">The Figure in the Carpet</title>
                <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1978</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Shelley Grieve</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Mary Clarke</name>
                            <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
                            <name>Frank Graziano</name>
                            <name>Jean H. Hagstrum</name>
                            <name>Gunnar Harding</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Joe Napora</name>
                            <name>Martin K. Numri</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>R. W. Peattie</name>
                            <name>Marcia Tillotson</name>
                            <name>Gunnel Tottie</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1978"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
            <pb id="p12-10" n="10"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-1-0006">
                <head>
                    <title type="main">
                        <hi rend="b">THE FIGURE IN THE CARPET: BLAKE’S ENGRAVINGS IN SALZMANN’S 
                                <hi rend="i">ELEMENTS OF MORALITY</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="b">ROBERT N.</hi>
                        <name>
                            <hi rend="b">ESSICK</hi>
                        </name>
                    </docAuthor>
                </byline>
                <p>The attribution of the unsigned plates in the English translation of C. G.
                    Salzmann’s <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality</hi>
                    <ref target="n37" type="note">1</ref> has had a checkered career. In the first
                    edition of his <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, Alexander Gilchrist
                    wrote that Blake “illustrated” Salzmann’s “pinafore precepts,” leaving it
                    unclear as to whether Blake simply engraved the plates, designed them, or
                        both.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">2</ref> The
ambiguity was corrected for
                    the second edition (1880, I, 91), where the German artist Daniel Nicolaus
                    Chodowiecki (1726-1801) was named as the designer and Blake as the engraver. The
                    change may have been prompted by a brief note by Frederick Locker on “The
                    Illustrations in Mrs. Godwin’s ‘Elements of Morality,’”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39"
                        type="note">3</ref> which points out that the plates were designed by
                    Chodowiecki with the exception of those numbered 27 and 28. These two plates
                    were exhibited at the Grolier Club in 1905 and described in the catalogue as
                    being of Blake’s “own designing.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
type="note">4</ref> This
                    attribution of pl. 27, at least to Blake as the engraver, can be rejected with a
                    fair degree of confidence because, like the frontispiece to vol. I and pls. 1,
                    7, 10 (signed <hi rend="i">W. P: C fect 1790</hi>), and 11, it was clearly
                    executed by someone other than the engraver of the remaining forty-five plates
                    and looks not in the least like Blake’s hand. In his catalogue of 1912, A. G. B.
                    Russell, exercising his usual skepticism about Gilchrist’s casual attributions,
                    lists only fourteen plates as Blake’s copy work, including eight “possibly, but
                    not certainly, by Blake.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41"
type="note">5</ref> In his great 
                        <hi rend="i">Bibliography of William Blake</hi> of 1921, Geoffrey Keynes
                    ascribes sixteen plates to Blake,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42"
type="note">6</ref> only ten
                    of which are the same as those listed by Russell. Keynes takes note of the
                    Grolier catalogue attribution of pls. 27 and 28 and comments that “the treatment
                    of the trees and vines in the second of these (pl. 28) certainly suggests
                    Blake’s work,” but then rejects this idea because both “plates were obviously
                    not engraved by him.” Bentley and Nurmi are a bit more generous, crediting Blake
                    with seventeen plates but expressing judicious uneasiness over the whole
                    business of attribution on stylistic grounds.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n43" type="note">7</ref> Bentley repeats the same list in <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi>
                    <ref target="n44" type="note">8</ref> None of these authorities indicates how he
                    made his selections; to my eye, all but the six (listed above) by another hand,
                    and possibly pl. 48, are by the same engraver, or at least by a group following
                    a “house style” as in the <hi rend="i">Novelist’s Magazine.</hi> A comparison of
                    the English plates illustrating Salzmann with their German prototypes provides
                    new evidence for Blake’s involvement. More surprisingly, it suggests that the
                    Grolier catalogue may be right about pl. 28. <note id="n37">
                        <hi rend="s">1</hi> First published by Joseph Johnson in 3 vols., 1791. The
                        plates also appear in editions of 1792 (second state), 1799 (third state of
                        most plates), 1805, and the undated “Juvenile Library” edition
                        (1815?).</note>
                    <note id="n38">
                        <hi rend="s">2</hi> London and Cambridge: Macmillan, 1863, I, 91-92.</note>
                    <note id="n39">
                        <hi rend="s">3</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>, I, 6th S. (19 June 1880), 493-94.
                        Locker concludes with the comment that “I trouble you with this as I
                        understand that Mrs. Gilchrist is now engaged on the pious work of
                        re-editing her late husband’s book.”</note>
                    <note id="n40">
                        <hi rend="s">4</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">Catalogue of Books, Engravings Water-Colors &amp; Sketches by
                            William Blake</hi> ([New York]: Grolier Club, 1905), no. 67 p.
                        102.</note>
                    <note id="n41">
                        <hi rend="s">5</hi>
                        <hi rend="i">The Engravings of William Blake</hi> (Boston and New York:
                        Houghton Mifflin, 1912), pp. 156-58.</note>
                    <note id="n42">
                        <hi rend="s">6</hi> New York: Grolier Club, pp. 235-37.</note>
                    <note id="n43">
                        <hi rend="s">7</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., and Martin K. Nurmi, <hi rend="i">A
                            Blake Bibliography</hi> (Minneapolis: Univ. of Minnesota Press, 1964),
                        pp. 149-50.</note>
                    <note id="n44">
                        <hi rend="s">8</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977, pp. 607-09. As in Bentley
                        and Nurmi, the name of the designer is incorrectly given as “David
                        Chodowiecki.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>Chodowiecki’s seventy designs were first published in <hi rend="i">Kupfer zu
                        Herrn <corr type="emend">Professor</corr> Salzmanns Elementarwerk nach den zeichnungen Herrn Dan.
                        Chodowiecki, von Herrn Nussbiegel Herrn Penzel und Herrn Crusius Sen.
                        gestocken.</hi>
                    <ref target="n45" type="note">9</ref> Among the forty-five plates not by the
                    “other hand” in the English edition, all but pl. 28 are based closely on
                    Chodowiecki’s designs, and were probably copied directly from the German plates.
                    There are, however, some minor but substantive differences between fourteen of
                    the prints. These variations are not significant enough to suggest that another
                    artist was hired to adapt Chodowiecki’s designs—they are still very much his—and
                    were no doubt made by the English engraver(s). These changes are listed below,
                    along with speculations on why some were made. <note id="n45">
                        <hi rend="s">9</hi> Leipzig, 1784. Locker—and following him the 1905 Grolier
                        catalogue, p. 102, Russell, p. 156, and Keynes, p. 236—point out that the
                        illustrations are in the Leipzig, 1785, edition of the 
                            <hi rend="i">Moralisches Elementarbuch</hi> and do not note the earlier appearance
                        of the plates alone.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Pl. 3.</hi> The rather elegant floor divided into large squares in
                    the German plate is replaced by a carpet in the English. Both seem equally
                    appropriate since the design shows the drawing room in Sir William’s “grand
                    house” (I, 16 in the 1791 edition). I have not been able to find out if English
                    drawing rooms were more frequently carpeted than the Continental variety.</p>
                <pb id="p12-11" n="11"/>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Pl. 20.</hi> The place setting on the table in the German print has
                    been eliminated in the English, and two children added on the left. The first
                    change follows the text, for the scene takes place “after the cloth was taken
                    away” (II, 48). The text does not specifically place the children in the scene,
                    but they are mentioned (II, 49) in the conversation between the husband and wife
                    pictured in both plates.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Pl. 26.</hi> The curtain covering part of the back wall in the
                    German plate has been replaced with what looks like patterned wallpaper in the
                    English. There seems to be no textual reason for this, unless wallpaper is more
                    appropriate for the breakfast room setting.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Pl. 34</hi> (illus. 1). The German squared floor is replaced in the
                    English copy by a carpet, and the back of the chair has been shortened so as not
                    to cover as much of the boy’s legs.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Pl. 37.</hi> The round knobs on the chest of drawers in the German
                    plate have been replaced in the English copy by handles of the sort more
                    commonly found on eighteenth-century English furniture.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Pl. 38</hi> (illus. 2). The German squared floor has been replaced
                    by rough boards and a carpet in the English copy. At least the boards seem more
                    appropriate than the squared floor, for this is the room of a poor and
                    desperately sick family. The wicker basket on the left does not appear in the
                    German plate. It is probably the cradle of the infant at his mother’s breast and
                    is reminiscent of the basket-cradles in Blake’s “A Cradle Song” (second plate)
                    and “Infant Sorrow.”</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Pl. 41.</hi> The German squared floor has been replaced in the
                    English plate by a crosshatching pattern apparently representing boards.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Pl. 42.</hi> The desk and man’s legs visible through the railing in
                    the German plate have been obscured with crosshatching in the English.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Pl. 44.</hi> The sleigh in the German plate has been replaced by a
                    cart, and the second sleigh on the far right replaced by a horse and rider. Both
                    changes follow the English text, for the family is specifically placed in a
                    “cart” three times (III, 116, 117, 123) and there is no reference to a second
                    cart or sleigh. “The boy who rode on the first horse” (III, 123) probably refers
                    to a servant riding on the lead horse hitched to the cart, but may have prompted
                    the addition far right.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Pl. 45.</hi> The German squared floor has been replaced by a carpet
                    in the English copy. As in pl. 26, the setting is a breakfast room. (Salzmann
                    was a forerunner of Oliver Wendell Holmes in the pedagogic uses of the breakfast
                    table).</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Pl. 46.</hi> The back wall, divided into large panels in the German
                    plate, has been made plain in the English copy, and carpet replaces the German
                    squared floor.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Pl. 47.</hi> The floor and back wall are smooth and even in the
                    German plate; but in the English copy the floor looks rough and uneven, and the
                    wall is cracked 
                    <figure n="BB492.1.29.COM" rend="file" width="525" height="1000">
                        <head>1 Plate 34 in C. G. Salzmann, <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality</hi>
                            (1791), III, facing p. 23.</head>
                        <figDesc>First state, 12.2 × 7 cm., Blake after Chodowiecki. Author’s
                            collection.</figDesc>
                    </figure> 
                    with holes in the plaster. The setting is a sick old man’s “miserable
                    garret” (III, 161), and thus the changes are most appropriate. The dilapidated
                    wall looks very much like the one in Blake’s sixth illustration to Mary
                    Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi> (J. Johnson, 1791). Both are
                    delineated with etched worm lines that twist and break to picture the holes. The
                    general boldness of etched 
<pb id="p12-12" n="12"/>
                    <figure n="BB492.1.33.COM" rend="file" width="550" height="1000">
                        <head>2 Plate 38 in Salzmann, <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality</hi> (1791),
                            III, facing p. 68.</head>
                        <figDesc>First state, 12.5 × 6.7 cm., Blake after Chodowiecki. Author’s
                            collection.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <figure n="BB475.1.1.COM" rend="file" width="958" height="771">
                        <head>3 “Beggar’s Opera, Act III,” Blake after Hogarth,
                            1788.</head>
                        <figDesc>Detail, 19.3 × 11.3 cm., of the fourth state (1790).
                            Author’s collection.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <figure n="MooreAdDetail.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="511" height="1000">
                        <head>4 “Moore and Co’s Advertisement,” designed and engraved by Blake c.
                            1797.</head>
                        <figDesc>Detail, 12.8 × 6.8 cm. British Museum.</figDesc>
                    </figure> 
                    patterns in this and other Salzmann plates is similar to those in 
                        <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi>, to which they have been compared by
                        others.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">10</ref>
                    <note id="n46">
                        <hi rend="s">10</hi> See the 1905 Grolier catalogue, p. 102, Bentley and
                        Nurmi, p. 149, and Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 608.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="i">Pl. 50.</hi> The German squared floor has been replaced in the
                    English copy by smooth boards, and a few decorative swirls have been added to
                    the curtain behind the bed.</p>
                <p>The alterations in pls. 20, 38, 44, and 47 show a careful responsiveness to the
                    text which is most unusual for simple copy engravings in a children’s book. This
                    fact alone suggests the habits of mind of the engraver of the <hi rend="i">Night
                        Thoughts</hi> and <hi rend="i">Job</hi> illustrations, but it is a seemingly
                    insignificant addition to the English plates that points more directly to
                    Blake.</p>
                <p>The carpets added to pls. 3, 34, 38, 41, 45, and 46 bear the same bold swirls,
                    arabesques, and vegetative motifs (see illus. 1, 2). On pls. 26, 29, and 43, the
                    engraver has modified Chodowiecki’s original carpets to picture this pattern.
                    The same sort of carpet appears in three plates unquestionably by Blake. In 1788
                    Blake etched and engraved his fine plate of Hogarth’s “Beggar’s Opera.” The
                    carpet (illus. 3) beneath Macheath’s left foot is a larger version of those in
                    the Salzmann illustrations. Except for the swirls in the lower left corner, the
                    pattern is only vaguely suggested in Hogarth’s oil painting (Mellon collection).
                    Its specific deliniation in the print is as much the engraver’s as the
                    designer’s. That this particular carpet became part of Blake’s decorative
                    repertoire is confirmed by its reappearance in two later original graphics: the
                    “Moore and Co’s Advertisement” of c. 1797 (illus. 4)<ref target="n47"
                        type="note">11</ref> and the final plate in <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series
                        of Ballads</hi> of 1802. <note id="n47">
                        <hi rend="s">11</hi> Keynes, <hi rend="i">Engravings by William Blake: The
                            Separate Plates</hi> (Dublin: Emery Walker, 1956), p. 15, dates the
                        plate c. 1790 because of its similarity to the Wollstonecraft illustrations,
                        but David. V. Erdman, “The Suppressed and Altered Passages in Blake’s 
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi>, 17
                        (1964), 36 n. 34, points out that Moore &amp; Co. is listed only in the
                        London directories of 1797 and 1798 and that the firm apparently had no
                        other names in earlier years.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The appearance of the carpet pattern—as it were, a Blakean signature—in some of
                    the Salzmann plates lends new credence to the contention that Blake was their
                    engraver. And if we attribute the carpet plates to him, I find it impossible to
                    go through the other forty-five candidates and weed out definite non-Blakes,
                    with the possible exception of pl. 48. There is of course a natural resistance
                    to attributing to Blake’s hand all this undistinguished hack-work. That,
                    however, should not stand in our way. By 1790 Blake was a very skilled
                    etcher-engraver (witness the Hogarth plate), but he inevitably modified his
                    style according to the genre in which he was working—and no doubt according to
                        <pb id="p12-13" n="13"/>
the fee as well. For example, in 1784 Blake
                    engraved two sophisticated “fancy” stipple prints after Stothard, “Zephyrus and
                    Flora” and “Calisto,” and in the same year produced six crude plates for 
                        <hi rend="i">The Wit’s Magazine.</hi> In each case, the style is appropriate for
                    the subject, and the latter group perfectly suited to the rough humor of their
                    literary context.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48"
type="note">12</ref> This Blakean version of
                    eighteenth-century rules of decorum is a persistent feature of Blake’s entire
                    career as a graphic artist. For a children’s book like the <hi rend="i">Elements
                        of Morality</hi>, the simple mixed-method plates are appropriate for the
                    simple moralistic tales they accompany. The same may be said for Blake’s relief
                    etchings in <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi>, for which the artist
                    himself pointed out the principle of decorum: “they are rough like rough
                        sailors.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">13</ref>
When compared with other
                    prints of the period intended for a youthful audience, such as the Carver &amp;
                    Bowles “catchpenny prints” or those in Banbury chap books,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50"
                        type="note">14</ref> the Salzmann plates seem almost elegant. That they are
                    less accomplished than the Wollstonecraft illustrations, begun in the same year
                    as the last of those for Salzmann, can be attributed at least in part to the
                    fact that in one case Blake was executing signed plates after his own designs,
                    and in the other rapidly producing a good many unsigned copy prints. 
                        <note id="n48">
                        <hi rend="s">12</hi> Keynes makes much the same point about the 
                            <hi rend="i">Wit’s Magasine</hi> plates in “Blake’s Engravings for Gay’s
Fables,”
                            <hi rend="i">The Book Collector</hi>, 21 (1972), 60.</note>
                    <note id="n49">
                        <hi rend="s">13</hi> Letter to William Hayley, 26 Nov. 1800. 
                            <hi rend="i">The Letters of William Blake</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes, 2nd ed.
                        (London: Rupert Hart-Davis, 1968), p. 49.</note>
                    <note id="n50">
                        <hi rend="s">14</hi> For some examples, see <hi rend="i">Catchpenny Prints:
                            163 Popular Engravings from the Eighteenth Century</hi> (New York:
                        Dover, 1970) and Edwin Pearson, <hi rend="i">Banbury Chap Books and Nursery
                            Toy Book Literature</hi> (London, 1890; rpt. New York: Burt Franklin, n.
                        d.).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Plate 28 (illus. 5) offers the greatest challenge to the chalcographer. At first
                    glance it would seem to be one of the prints executed by the “other hand.” But
                    this is only because the smallness of the figure relative to the size of the
                    whole design is similar to the frontispiece to vol. I and pl. 27; in graphic
                    style pl. 28 is strikingly different. Most of the prints throughout 
                        <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality</hi> suffer from the <hi rend="i">horror vacui</hi>
                    endemic among eighteenth-century engravers, although those plates most
                    frequently attributed to Blake in the past are less cluttered than the others.
                    Plate 28 is the most open of them all, with the worm lines so much a part of
                    Blake’s early style but remarkably little crosshatching. Blake used a similarly
                    open, etched style, deriving from Salvator Rosa, in two plates after Fuseli,
                    “Timon and Alcibiades” and “Falsa ad Coelum” of 1790, and attempted to combine
                    it with more conventional patterns in the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
                    engravings (1796-97) and the illustrations, also after Fuseli, for Charles
                    Allen’s <hi rend="i">New and Improved History of England</hi> and 
                        <hi rend="i">New and Improved Roman History</hi>, both of 1798. Almost every motif in
                    pl. 28 also has its parallel in Blake’s work. The slender tree with arching
                    branches recalls those in “The Lamb,” “Night” (first plate), “The Little Girl
                    Lost” (first plate), the title-page of <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, and
                        <hi rend="i">America</hi> pl. 7. A much stronger parallel is between the
                    vine on the right margin of pl. 28 and that on the right in the frontispiece to
                    Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi> (illus. 6), also climbing up
                    a wall next to a portal. The delineation of the leaves is almost identical. The
                    general subject—a child or children before a large doorway—can also be compared
                    to the Wollstonecraft frontispiece, “Nurse’s Song” in <hi rend="i">Songs of
                        Experience</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> pl. 26. This last
                    example also contains a heavy wooden door as in the Salzmann plate, but the
                    closest parallel for the setting is the water color illustration to Young’s 
                        <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, Night II, p. 7, where Blake also pictures a
                    gigantic door in a curiously free-standing wall. Salzmann’s text indicates that
                    William, pictured in pl. 28, is locked 
                    <figure n="BB492.1.23.COM" rend="file" width="479" height="1000">
                        <head>5 Plate 28 in Salzmann, <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality</hi> (1791),
                            II, facing p. 104.</head>
                        <figDesc>First state, 12.5 × 6.8 cm., tentatively attributed to Blake as
                            designer and engraver. Author’s collection.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <pb id="p12-14" n="14"/>
                    <hi rend="i">inside</hi> a garden, but it seems as though anyone not so caught
                    up by “impatience” could simply walk around the end of the wall, just as in the
                        <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> design. William’s clothes are generally
                    like those of other children in the Salzmann plates, including the unattributed
                    pl. 27, but are more closely fitting and with less distinction between breeches
                    and blouse than the other outfits, and without the usual jacket. In these
                    respects William’s clothing is similar to that worn by the boys in 
                        <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, particularly one in “Nurse’s
                    Song” in <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, and by the shepherd in the 
                        <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> frontispiece. Lastly, William’s arm and hand gesture is
                    very close to the young woman’s in the illustration to Thomas Commins’ 
                        <hi rend="i">Elegy Set to Music</hi>, designed and engraved by Blake in 1786.
                    Each of these parallels is in itself inconclusive, but taken together they form
                    a remarkably consistent pattern of Blakean styles and motifs. Perhaps Johnson
                    allowed each of his two engravers to contribute one new design to the book, and
                    thus pl. 27 is the other copyist’s effort. My tentative attribution of pl. 28 to
                    Blake as both designer and engraver is certainly open to question, but the
                    evidence suggests that, even when hired as a journeyman copyist, Blake found an
                    opportunity to create one small work of original graphic art.</p>
                <figure n="bb514.2.1.com" id="bb514.2.comb.01" work-copy="bb514.2" rend="db" width="518" height="1000">
					<figTranscr>Frontispiece.<lb/>
					Blake. inv. &amp; sc.<lb/>
					Look what a fine morning it is. __ Insects,<lb/>
					Birds, &amp; Animals, are all enjoying existence.<lb/>
					Published by J.Johnson, Septr. 1.st 1791.</figTranscr>
                    <head>6 Frontispiece in Mary Wollstonecraft, <hi rend="i">Original Stories from
                            Real Life</hi>, 1791.</head>
                    <figDesc>Second state, 11.7 × 6.5 cm., designed and engraved by Blake. Author’s
                        collection.</figDesc>
                </figure>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
