<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.1.fine</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Martin Butlin, William Blake (Tate Gallery)</title>
                <author n="Fine">Ruth E. Fine</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1978</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Shelley Grieve</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Mary Clarke</name>
                            <name>Raymond H. Deck, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
                            <name>Frank Graziano</name>
                            <name>Jean H. Hagstrum</name>
                            <name>Gunnar Harding</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Joe Napora</name>
                            <name>Martin K. Numri</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>R. W. Peattie</name>
                            <name>Marcia Tillotson</name>
                            <name>Gunnel Tottie</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1978"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
            <pb id="p12-42" n="42"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-1-0011">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <figure n="ButlinWilliamBlake.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="615">
                    	<figTranscr>TATE GALLERY 9 March - 21 May 1978<lb/>
                    	William<lb/>
                    	Blake<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Admission 50p<lb/>
                    	(students and old-age pensioners 25p)<lb/>
                    	Mon. Tue. Wed. Fri 10-6<lb/>
                    	Thur 10-8 Sun 2-6<lb/>
                    	Closed Good Friday<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	1795 WB<lb/>
						<lb/>                    	
                    	Presented in association with the William Blake Trust</figTranscr>
                    </figure>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main" rend="main"><hi rend="b">BLAKE AT THE TATE</hi></title>
                        <title type="main">Martin Butlin. <hi rend="b">William Blake.</hi> London: Tate
Gallery, 1978. Pp. 164. 339
                            monochrome illus. + 16 color pls. £ 1.80 softcover, £ 3.00
                            hardcover.</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="b">Ruth E.</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">Fine</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
					<q> There is a contradictory quality in the middle classes which makes them
                        suddenly produce artists, where nothing in the tastes, manners, or
                        aspirations of such well-ordered families might warrant the spontaneous
                        generation of personalities in no way deducible from the characters of
                        parents or kindred. It is as if the moderation, the fear of risk, the
                        clear-cut and well-tried beliefs, the cult of security and solidity in all
                        its forms, were suddenly defied—and mystified—by the daemon of
                        painting or poetry, risen among the abruptly blazed-up flames of a gentle
                        and sleepy hearth. Beings of a singular sensibility, troubled with a
                        restless will to expression, appear in the midst of a tranquil little world,
                        to astonish, sometimes to annoy, and sometimes to win it over. Perhaps this
                        should be seen as the workings of a natural law: an artist is a reaction;
                        responding to the usual with the unheard-of, detecting what is strange in
                        what is common, distilling purity from impurity by a mysterious process
                        which can take place only in the presence of all that is worn out, habitual,
                        conventional, and commonplace. Our daemon’s task is to cheat the law
                        by which habit debases all sensation.<lb/>
                        <lb/>
 Paul Valéry </q>
                    <p>Laurence Binyon’s introduction to the Burlington Fine Arts
                        Club’s 1927 William Blake Centenary Exhibition suggested that Blake
                        was at that time respected more as a poet than as a painter. To some extent
                        that situation prevails today, and in his introduction to the catalogue for
                        the exhibition of Blake’s work that he recently organized for the
                        Tate Gallery (9 March-21 May), Martin Butlin indicates that a primary
                        purpose of the exhibition was to focus on Blake’s achievements as a
                        visual artist as distinct from his literary achievements. To do this Butlin
                        assembled Blake’s very best work from forty-five public and private
                        collections plus several anonymous lenders. For the most part, lesser pieces
                        of an essentially historical or curious nature were not included.
                        Butlin’s long years of studying Blake served him well when he was
                        selecting the exhibition. It was extraordinarily beautiful. The clarity
                        which Blake emphasized as the aim of his art in his own 1809 <hi rend="i">Descriptive
Catalogue</hi> was apparent throughout. The exhibition
                        demonstrated clearly that Blake’s pictorial achievements may be
                        appreciated even by those who have not yet memorized <hi rend="i">A Blake
                            Dictionary</hi> (“Does he have political overtones, this William
                        Blake?” was a query overheard from one enthusiastic viewer). In fact,
                        Blake’s rich and complex range as an image maker is probably best
                        communicated by the direct and comprehensive visual contact facilitated by
                        an exhibition such as this one. Consisting of 338 works, including one by
                        Blake’s brother Robert and two by John Linnell, the exhibition was
                        hung in 
<pb id="p12-43" n="43"/>
                        <figure n="FawcusKeynesRosenwald.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="844" height="1000">
                            <head>Arnold Fawcus pauses to speak with Sir Geoffrey Keynes and Edith
                                G. Rosenwald at the opening dinner.</head>
                        </figure> seventeen sub-sections and arranged to make evident the many
                        facets of Blake’s oeuvre.</p>
                    <p>Given the large number of pieces exhibited, the many subdivisions, and the
                        visual mix of techniques, the exhibition flowed very well. Paintings,
                        drawings, watercolors, prints and book pages were hung in an integrated
                        fashion with subjects, concepts, stylistic considerations, chronology, and
                        technical distinctions all working together to reveal Blake’s truly
                        organic development as an artist. One could walk through the show and be
                        carried along strictly by the visual images before going back to probe the
                        works through their many layers, attend to scholarly considerations, make
                        comparisons, etc. The exhibition, installed under the direction of Ruth
                        Rattenbury (also of the Tate Gallery staff), was organized in seventeen
                        sections as follows: Apprenticeship and Early Work, c. 1775-85; Blake the
                        Neo-Classicist, c. 1780-90; The Early Illuminated Books and Contemporary
                        Book Illustrations, 1789-91; The Prophetic Books, 1793-96; The Large Colour
                        Prints of 1795; The Great Book Illustrations, c. 1795-98; Blake’s
                        First Works for Thomas Butts: Tempera Paintings of Biblical Subjects, c.
                        1799-1800; The Hazards of Patronage: William Hayley and “The
                        Grave,” c. 1799-1806; Watercolour Illustrations to the Bible for Thomas
                        Butts, c. 1800-08; Illustrations to the Book of Job, c. 1805-25;
                        Blake’s Exhibition, “The Last Judgment” and other works, c.
                        1800-10; Illustrations to Milton and other Writers, c. 1807-20;
                        “Jerusalem,” c. 1804-20; John Linnell, John Varley and the
                        Visionary Heads, c. 1819-25; Illustrations to Thornton’s Virgil,
                        1820-21; Late Tempera Paintings and Other Works, 1921-27; and Illustrations
                        to Dante, 1824-27. The hanging of the exhibition did not rigidly conform to
                        the dates of these sub-sections, however, and works of a particular theme
                        from various periods were often shown side by side. For example, the five
                        versions of <hi rend="i">Pestilence: The Great Plague of London</hi>, of
                        which the earliest dates from c. 1779-80 and the latest from c. 1805, were
                        all grouped within “Blake the Neo-Classicist, c. 1780-90.”</p>
                    <p>As Blake’s stylistic development was made clear by instances of
                        thematic hanging, his proclivity for working within a serial narrative
                        framework was also to be seen, for example, in the reunion of the twelve
                        watercolors in the 1808 set to Milton’s <hi rend="i">Paradise
                            Lost</hi> (“Satan, Sin, and Death, Satan Comes to the Gates of
                        Hell” was represented by a photograph). Blake’s poetic dialogue
                        reveals his personal mythology and is paralleled in his graphic work by a
                        dialogue of formal images. The exhibition format encouraged walking back and
                        forth from section to section, comparing a composition, a figure, or a
                        setting 
<pb id="p12-44" n="44"/>
in one work with its counterpart in
                        another. Often great shifts in emotional response were elicited; for
                        example, it is one thing to cite a relationship between the figures of Abias
                        (in the c. 1780-85 drawing after a Ghisi engraving from a Michelangelo
                        fresco) and Newton (in the color print of 1795); it is another to look at
                        the rather uninspired, somewhat flaccid figure in the early study and then
                        encounter the densely formed, powerful Newton, whose reverberations of
                        meaning within Blake’s written mythology are as important as his
                        pictorial reverberations within Blake’s art.</p>
                    <p>What one wants to do in writing a review of an exhibition of this stature is
                        to share, as much as possible, the experience of seeing it—of seeing,
                        for example, <hi rend="i">The Magdalene at the Sepulchre</hi> from the Yale
                        Center for British Art, the Petworth House <hi rend="i">Last Judgment</hi>,
                        and <hi rend="i">The Arlington Court Picture</hi> all together under one
                        roof. It is an experience of particular and unique intellectual,
                        imaginative, and sensual luxury, not easily or directly translatable into
                        words. An indirect approach aimed at accomplishing that elusive end has to
                        suffice; therefore, the following attempts an overview of the exhibition
                        within the framework of observations stimulated while seeing it.</p>
                    <p>Drawings comprised much of the early-apprenticeship section, including
                        several, drawn from Westminster Abbey monuments, not heretofore exhibited as
                        part of Blake’s oeuvre. Apart from 
<figure n="RosenwaldExhibit.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="741" height="1000">
                            <head>Lessing J. Rosenwald views the exhibit.</head>
                        </figure> these earliest studies, among the drawings, the broadly conceived,
                        rapidly done, freely worked drawing, <hi rend="i">Young Woman Reclining on a
                            Couch</hi>, and the more incisive <hi rend="i">Fall of Fair
                            Rosamund</hi>, could be seen in contrast to such highly developed works
                        as the exquisitely delicate <hi rend="i">Resurrection of the Dead</hi>, or
                        the rather meticulous visionary heads of Blake’s late years. Of
                        particular interest were the pencil sketches for <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> and
                            <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> which, although broadly drawn, have many of the
                        qualities of expressive totality and tautness of structure that characterize
                        the large color prints developed from them. Perhaps the most powerful
                        drawing was the <hi rend="i">Free Version of the Laocoön</hi>, which
                        acted both as an accumulation and as a culmination of features of the other
                        drawings—the very sparsely described serpents, and the more fully
                        formed figures of Adam and Satan, building up to the most explicit and
                        highly worked figure of Urizen/Jehovah whose sensuous robes flow around his
                        strongly modelled form. The three figures become a unit with icon-like
                        power.</p>
                    <p>Among the early prints was Blake’s relief etching based on his brother
                        Robert’s compelling, if almost humorously naive, drawing known as <hi rend="i">The
Approach of Doom</hi> which hung near <hi rend="i">The
                            Complaint of Job</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Death of Ezekiel’s
                            Wife.</hi> These two Biblical subjects, engraved in the conventional dot
                        and lozenge technique of the period, are composed of carefully modelled
                        figures, with gestures and gazes of utmost importance to their powerful
                        expressive qualities. The figure compositions are relief-like and placed
                        within an explicit space of Neo-Classical origin. <hi rend="i">The Approach
                            of Doom</hi> print is also a highly charged image but its drama is
                        expressed mainly through the totality of the composition. With its more
                        generalized form and implied spatial infinity, the relief etching stood in
                        startling contrast to the <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi> and <hi rend="i">Job</hi>
engravings.</p>
                    <p>The subject of Job became the focus of a later section of the exhibition that
                        included six of the twenty-one engraved <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the
                            Book of Job</hi>, 1823-26, and eight related watercolors of various
                        dates, among them two versions of <hi rend="i">Job and His Family Restored
                            to Prosperity.</hi> Three of the engravings corresponded to watercolors
                        on exhibition while others did not, thus presenting ten of the twenty-one
                        subjects, as well as an idea of the close relationship between the
                        watercolor series and the engravings. The <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engravings
                        represent the heights of Blake’s work in this medium. With Durer as
                        his measure, Blake wielded his burin with a sureness of hand and clarity of
                        mind yielding solidly formed images, bathed in luminosity. The narrative
                        series ranks among the most important sequences in the history of
                        engraving.</p>
                    <p>In addition to splendid engravings like the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> series,
                        Blake’s output as a commercial engraver was voluminous, a part of his
                        oeuvre which was rarely considered in the exhibition. His own 
<pb id="p12-45" n="45"/>
designs for conventional book illustration were
                        seen in the four pen and wash drawings for Mary Wollstonecraft’s 
<hi rend="i">Original Stories.</hi> The stipple engravings after Watteau,
                            <hi rend="i">Morning Amusement</hi> and <hi rend="i">Evening
                            Amusement</hi>, indicate his skill as a reproductive engraver within the
                        confines of that tradition, as do three engravings from his own designs for
                        the second, 1805, edition of Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads.</hi>
                        These were placed among the “Hazards of Patronage” along with Mrs.
                        Butt’s charming needlework, <hi rend="i">Hares</hi>, the design of
                        which is attributed to Blake. Caprices of patronage were also responsible
                        for Schiavonetti’s engravings after Blake’s designs for <hi rend="i">The
Grave.</hi> In a comparison of the unique impression of
                        Blake’s interpretation of his design for the “Death’s
                        Door” plate and the published one by Schiavonetti, what became most
                        apparent was Blake’s belief in the strength of his image.
                        Blake’s heroic sense of form and the gestures of his personal
                        handwriting (the descriptive marks that were peculiarly his) developed the
                        large figural tensions on which the impact of his own version is dependent.
                        The drama is heightened by the rich black areas produced by relief printing
                        a plate that had broad areas of unengraved surface. “Drama” and
                        “impact” are not really appropriate terms to use in describing
                        Schiavonetti’s interpretation. In contrast it is a rather schematic
                        and conventional engraving of an intriguing image, but one with few dramatic
                        formal properties.</p>
                    <p>Historically prints have offered particularly rich possibilities for
                        comparative study, a point repeatedly demonstrated by the prints on
                        exhibition. Some were seen in more than one state (<hi rend="i">The
                            Complaint of Job</hi>); some were seen as studies on which Blake worked
                        to develop, rethink, and extend his ideas (three of the four known and
                        greatly differing touched proofs of the <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> title page,
                        which were hung adjacent to the published version); some were seen as the
                        pages of illuminated books, used as a base to which watercolor and color
                        printing were applied with great variety of approach (pages from <hi rend="i">The Book
of Urizen</hi> and the same images from <hi rend="i">The Small Book of Designs</hi>). Progressions like these,
along with
                        the sketches and drawings related to more finished prints and paintings (two
                        preliminary drawings, a trial print, and one of two known finished versions
                        of <hi rend="i">Pity</hi>), and the instances of works in more than one
                        version (<hi rend="i">The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins</hi>),
                        added up to an exhibition that was didactic almost in spite of itself. The
                        mind of the artist at work is always best studied through this kind of
                        material.</p>
                    <p>While patronage did have its hazards, the positive importance of both Thomas
                        Butts and John Linnell is evidenced by Blake’s prodigious output
                        during the years of their support. The Tate exhibition included seven
                        temperas painted for Butts during the 1799-1800 period. Mainly of Biblical
                        subjects, many of them, unfortunately, are irretrievably darkened because of
                        Blake’s peculiar use of carpenter’s glue as a binder for his
                        pigment. Still quite bright, however, is the very gentle <hi rend="i">Our
                            Lady with the Infant Jesus Riding on a Lamb.</hi> Like many of
                        Blake’s paintings of the period, it is 
<figure n="ExhibitEntrance12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="662">
                            <head>The entrance to the exhibit.</head>
                        </figure> characterized by a planar, frieze-like grouping of figures set
                        before a deep landscape space.</p>
                    <p>There was only one true landscape in the exhibition, the lovely watercolor,
                            <hi rend="i">Landscape near Felpham</hi> (with sunlight, the light of
                        poetic inspiration, to be sure, shining down on Blake’s cottage), but
                        Blake’s response to the landscape could be repeatedly observed,
                        notably in <hi rend="i">Ruth, the Dutiful Daughter-in-law</hi> and the
                        striking, moonlit night scene of <hi rend="i">Malevolence.</hi>
                        Blake’s landscapes were far closer to the pastoral tradition of
                        Claude, whom he admired, than that of the heroic or sublime landscape of,
                        for example, his contemporary De Loutherbourg. Often, as in the freely
                        laid-in setting for the Ruth subject, the landscapes appeared to be
                        generalized descriptions of particular places with a focus on mood; in other
                        instances, perhaps most pointedly in the abundant landscape elements in the
                        Milton <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> watercolors, Blake made
                        particularized depictions of generalized natural forms.</p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of
                            Urizen</hi> preceded Blake’s large color prints of c. 1795. With
                            <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>, which contained several full-page
                        images, designs gained importance in relation to text, and Blake became
                        immersed in his color-printing technique. The reticulated textures of
                        Blake’s color printing imply weight and density, pictorial qualities
                        that are indeed sympathetic to Blake’s growing pessimism. These
                        qualities were reduced or amplified depending upon the luminosity of
                        particular colors, the thickness of the color layer (in this
                        monoprint-related technique the earliest of several impressions of an image
                        would have the thickest layer of pigment), and the number of layers of
                        colors. Of additional importance was the way colors were placed in proximity
                        to one another. For instance, in <hi rend="i">Elohim Creating Adam</hi> the
                        forcefulness of the image is heightened by the rich blues which describe the
                        background space and press the figure grouping forward. All of the color
                        prints have additional work in watercolor and pen and ink. How much work 
<pb id="p12-46" n="46"/>
                        <figure n="BUT662.1.1.PT" rend="file" width="773" height="1000">
                            <head>1 <hi rend="i">Satan Calling up his Legions.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <figDesc>c. 1805. H. M. Treasury and the National Trust, Petworth House,
                                Sussex.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <pb id="p12-47" n="47"/>
                        <figure n="BUT661.1.1.PT" rend="file" width="784" height="1000">
                            <head>2 <hi rend="i">Satan Calling up his Legions.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <figDesc>c. 1800-09. Victoria and Albert Museum, London.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <pb id="p12-48" n="48"/>
                        <figure n="but387.1.1.pt" id="but387.1.pt.01" work-copy="biblicaltemperas" rend="db" width="707" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
                            <head>3 <hi rend="i">Moses Indignant at the Golden Calf.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <figDesc>c. 1799-1800. Butts and W. Graham Robertson
                                collections.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <pb id="p12-49" n="49"/>
                        <figure n="but411.1.1.pt" id="but411.1.pt.01" work-copy="biblicaltemperas" rend="db" width="958" height="682">
	<figTranscr/>
                            <head>4 <hi rend="i">The Christ Child Asleep on the Cross.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <figDesc>c. 1799-1800. Victoria and Albert Museum, London.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <figure n="but404.1.1.pt" id="but404.1.pt.01" work-copy="biblicaltemperas" rend="db" width="958" height="671">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB 179</figTranscr>
                            <head>5 <hi rend="i">The Flight into Egypt.</hi>
                            </head>
                            <figDesc>1799. Butts and W. Graham Robertson collections.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <pb id="p12-50" n="50"/>
                        <figure n="BlakeExhibition.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="537"/> is added varies from image to
image and within the different
                        versions of an image. The variables were clearly to be seen in the three
                        impressions of <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam.</hi> The watercolor washes,
                        sometimes transparent, but often made translucent or opaque by the use of
                        body color, were used for various purposes, such as adding solidity to large
                        sale forms by gently modelling them, and to soften distinctions between
                        areas of the image. For instance, watercolor was used in <hi rend="i">Elohim
                            Creating Adam</hi> to give greater unity to Adam’s leg and the
                        worm that entwines it. Lines in watercolor and pen and ink were used in
                        finishing the color prints to refine and enhance form in much the same way
                        that Blake used the pen to further define aspects of his watercolors. To use
                        the same work as an example, linear elements particularized forms and made
                        them more incisive, as with Elohim’s hands, facial features, beard,
                        hair, etc. As a group, the large color prints are intensely dramatic, the
                        power of the images consistently reinforced by eerie qualities of light.</p>
                    <p>At least one version of each of the twelve subjects was included in the
                        exhibition, and in them the intense pessimism expressed in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> is
given full visual form. They repay lengthy and careful
                        scrutiny: color printing thickly and thinly applied; numerous layers of
                        color reworked with transparent or opaque watercolors; accents of painted
                        and/or drawn lines; textures which vary in density; highly modelled forms
                        placed next to flat areas of color; pictorial space implied and denied;
                        generalities of a Neo-Classical nature juxtaposed with very personalized
                        conceptions; layered compositions layered with meaning. This rich visual
                        world becomes hideously diluted when discussed in terms of technical
                        analysis; and, in fact, Blake was certainly to reach equally expressive
                        heights with far less technical complexity in the Dante watercolors of his
                        last years.</p>
                    <p>Two major watercolor projects closely followed the large color prints. Seven
                        of Blake’s 116 illustrations to Gray’s <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>
                        were on view, with the satirical, humorous third illustration to “Ode
                        on the Death of a Favorite Cat” a high point. This set was commissioned
                        by John Flaxman for his wife, both apparently admirers of Blake’s
                        illustrations to Edward Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi>
                        Twenty-one of the 537 watercolors (about one-fourth of Blake’s known
                        oeuvre) for that aborted project (only forty-three were actually engraved by
                        Blake) were on view. The range of Young’s subject and mood was
                        extended to express Blake’s own world view, one which was far more
                        interesting and expansive than Young’s. One <hi rend="i">Night
                            Thoughts</hi> illustration refers back to the drawing <hi rend="i">Warring Angels:
Michael Contending with Satan</hi> of the
                        1780’s, and another, the title page to “Night the Eighth,”
                        foretells the <hi rend="i">Apocalypse</hi> watercolor of 1809, or “The
                        Harlot and the Giant” in the “Purgatorio” illustrations for
                        Dante. Death mowing down an assembled throng, rebirth symbolized by the
                        butterfly and the cocoon, Christianity symbolized by the vine, and the
                        serpent of materialism, were all to be found as well. The transparency of
                        watercolor at its most fluid and luminous was seen in “The Queen of
                        Heaven walking in brightness,” in contrast to the watercolor layers of
                        darker-hued, more dryly applied paint that added up to form “The Whore
                        of Babylon astride the Seven Headed Beast.” Fanciful in the context of
                        Blake’s art, these illustrations give clues to his witty and
                        satirical nature. They also show his developing powers as a
                        watercolorist.</p>
                    <p>One was able to see individual figures and entire compositions developed,
                        revised, and refined throughout the exhibition, an exhibition being the best
                        vehicle for making such things apparent. Blake’s all-encompassing
                        themes repeatedly 
<pb id="p12-51" n="51"/>
reappeared—The Creation,
                        The Fall, Judgment, Salvation, War, Death, to name just a few. His
                        vocabulary, his signs and symbols, were encountered again and
                        again—the flames of eternal fury or of inspiration, the Egyptian
                        pyramids of materialism, the worm of mortality, the musical instruments of
                        creative activity. Compositional structures repeatedly
                        recur—icon-like, emblematic, vertically symmetrical formats; layered
                        horizontal bands; compartmentalized compositions which become mosaics of
                        images; or schemata that depend on an open swirling gesture. The figure of
                        the Bard, himself, reappears in many guises.</p>
                    <p>Blake made illustrations for Miltonic and Biblical themes throughout his
                        career. Comparison of early and late versions of <hi rend="i">Paradise
                            Lost</hi> subjects, or <hi rend="i">The Parable of the Wise and Foolish
                            Virgins</hi>, made clear some of the changes that took place in his
                        style. In later versions less emphasis was placed on overly dramatic and
                        schematized facial expressions; compositions focused less on particular
                        figures or groupings; color harmonies tended to be less delicate and/or
                        monochromatic. Rather, the power of many of the later images comes from
                        their more integrated compositions, organized by means of a flickering
                        quality of light that fractures and activates forms modelled 
<figure n="PicturesfromParadise.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="711" height="1000"/> with
                        rich, densely painted areas of color. Generally Blake’s later drawing
                        style is freer and more open.</p>
                    <p>Also shown were pages from both the unique complete colored Copy E and Copy B
                        of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Blake’s last and longest illuminated
                        book. The unique impression of the frontispiece before he deleted the
                        inscriptions, and the published state of this plate, as well as two
                        impressions of the title page, encouraged comparisons. Blake’s
                        illuminated books were colored throughout his lifetime. Those colored in his
                        later years (regardless of when the plates were actually made) are far more
                        elaborate than the earlier ones. In late versions, as in his late
                        watercolors, he used more complex color relationships, usually composed of
                        small patches of rich color, as distinct from the broadly applied, delicate
                        washes of the earlier work. Colors within the areas of text more fully
                        integrated the text with the illustrations, and gold was sometimes employed
                        for increased sumptuousness. This could be vividly seen in the title page of
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> Copy E.</p>
                    <p>The exhibition closed with nineteen of Blake’s 102 watercolors to
                        Dante, as well as two of the seven engravings from them. The ten watercolors
                        for the “Inferno” were generally the most highly finished and
                        dramatic; seven for “Purgatorio” were shown, and four for
                        “Paradiso,” which as a group were the most freely sketch-like,
                        with pronounced broad linear structures, at times like a kind of suggestive
                        shorthand. The freedom with which Blake used color in these watercolors was
                        <figure n="GentleSeer.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="703" height="1000"/> heightened by his use of line. In
earlier works, such as the 1808
                            <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> series, line essentially functioned to
                        confine color. In these late pieces, its role became increasingly complex,
                        creating pathways on many levels through the compositions. Blake’s
                        Dante watercolors which illustrate, parallel, and comment on <hi rend="i">The Divine
Comedy</hi> are also 
<pb id="p12-52" n="52"/>
                        <figure n="ExhibitExamples.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="482"/> a summation of his own visual
dialogue, the summation of his
                        “cycle of spiritual experience,” to use a phrase of Albert S.
                        Roe’s. Contraries, so important to Blake, abound: stasis and
                        activity, tenderness and terror, implication and finish. The ecstasy of an
                        imagination fully liberated after years of trying to give it definition is
                        apparent throughout the series. Sweeping lines define compositions and then
                        accumulate to become form; patches of color, freely washed in, behave
                        similarly. In some of the more finished examples, a stipple technique builds
                        to a density similar in effect to the reticulated surfaces of the earlier
                        large color prints. The settings, the situations, and then the details work
                        together to evoke various expressive moods. These watercolors must have been
                        a culmination for Blake just as, 150 years later, Matisse’s late
                        cutouts were a culmination of his own work. In both instances, ideas of a
                        lifetime were summarized and reflected upon, and new ones were introduced.
                        Descriptions of each of these two masters spiritedly at work in his sick-bed
                        have marked similarities.</p>
                    <p>An obvious advantage of having this Blake exhibition at the Tate Gallery was
                        that in the permanent collection one could study paintings by Fuseli,
                        Stothard, Flaxman and Mortimer, and also additional works by Blake and his
                        followers. Directly outside of the Blake exhibition itself was a display of
                        works by his contemporaries, including Stothard’s version of 
<hi rend="i">Chaucer’s Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>, and works by the
                        younger circle of Blake’s admirers, as well as later 
<figure n="ExhibitPanorama.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="291"/>
                        English painters and printmakers, some of whom, such as Paul Nash and Cecil
                        Collins, at least in the examples presented, seemed to be out of place.</p>
                    <p>Every exhibition reflects to some extent the taste and biases of the person
                        who selected it; everyone else who sees the exhibition probably draws a
                        desiderata list of what they’d have included. One can be rather
                        certain in this instance, however, that many works one missed were missing
                        because of institutional lending policies, as in the case of works from the
                        Huntington Library, or restrictions attached to certain collections such as
                        works from the Grenville Winthrop Collection at the Fogg Museum. Other loan
                        requests would have been turned down for any number of reasons. For example,
                        many <figure n="TateGalleryMap.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="896" height="416"/> of the tempera paintings are
too fragile to travel,
                        presumably the reason for a particularly sad lacuna, the tempera of 
<hi rend="i">Chaucer’s Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> in Pollok House,
                        Glasgow. This subject was included in a unique hand-colored first state
                        impression of Blake’s engraving from it. The Tate actually was
                        extremely fortunate to assemble eleven temperas in addition to the nine
                        shown from their own collection. Several of the latter were cleaned
                        especially for the exhibition (late ones like <hi rend="i">The Body of Abel
                            Found by Adam and Eve</hi> were brilliant in their luminosity but
                        earlier ones like <hi rend="i">The Spiritual Form of Pitt Guiding
                            Behemoth</hi> were cleaned with far less success because of
                        Blake’s use of fugitive materials).</p>
                    <p>Given what Martin Butlin aptly refers to as the flood of Blake literature,
                        one can sympathize with his decision to avoid crowding the entries of an
                        exhibition catalogue directed to the general 
<pb id="p12-53" n="53"/>
public
                        with specialized scholarly information available elsewhere (exhibition
                        history, listings of all related works, full provenance, etc.). His well
                        organized bibliography was selected with an acute awareness of the most
                        useful literature, including his own comprehensive catalogue of
                        Blake’s paintings, drawings, and separate color prints which is to be
                        published by Trianon Press for the William Blake Trust (which co-sponsored
                        the Tate exhibition) later this year. This publication will undoubtedly
                        provide a new standard of reference to these aspects of Blake’s
                        oeuvre. In his cogent introductory essay, in the overviews that precede each
                        section of catalogue entries, and in the entries themselves Butlin gives a
                        splendidly complete picture of Blake’s art. The entries were brief
                        and clear enough to be read by scholar and non-scholar alike while viewing
                        the exhibition, as well as re-read and mulled over afterwards. Most of the
                        longer <figure n="Crest.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="377" height="309"/> entries contain relevant quotations
from Blake’s own
                        descriptive writings or from his poetry. Butlin was able to weave together a
                        wealth of information of endless variety—bibliographical data, the
                        social history of England, Biblical and literary synopsis, Blake’s
                        life, his mythology, the complex relationships between his writing and his
                        visual art, technical information, stylistic analysis, reasons for dating,
                        especially interesting provenances, the history of collecting in England and
                        America, issues of scholarly disagreement, and so forth, developing as he
                        went along a rich body of references between works of art, just as the
                        exhibition itself did.</p>
                    <p>The catalogue reproduces everything in the exhibition as well as twenty-one
                        illustrations of other works of art which supplement the text and 
<figure n="ExhibitCorner.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="294"/>
                        <figure n="FriendsandFollowers.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="584"/> help to demonstrate
Blake’s relationships with
                        contemporaries (e.g. Romney, Hamilton, West), as well as to some degree, the
                        range of Blake’s art-historical connections (e.g. Poussin, Raphael,
                        Dürer). Given the small scale of the reproductions (about 2 ×
                        2 ½″), they are for the most part quite clear, and one can
                        assume that the variation in quality depended on the variation in
                        photographs available for reproduction from lending institutions. There are
                        also sixteen full-page color plates, and it is especially pleasant to note
                        sensitivity to the scale of the works of art—the color plates of
                        Blake’s book pages are not blown up to fill the catalogue pages, a
                        recent practice which destroys the delicacy and clarity of such small
                        images. Reproductions of verso images would have been a splendid addition to
                        the catalogue (especially as the forthcoming William Blake Trust catalogue
                        will not be comprehensively illustrated), but presumably there were just too
                        many of them for this to have been given serious consideration. Although the
                        price inevitably is to go up after the close of the exhibition, the
                        catalogue is, and will probably remain, the book bargain of the year. At the
                        exhibition it sold for £1.80, softcover, and £3.00, hardcover.</p>
                    <p>There was one printing mix-up; the catalogue entry for #67 was repeated for
                        #68. The latter should read: <pb id="p12-54" n="54"/>
                        <figure n="TateGalleryBlake.12.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="834" height="1000"/>
                        <pb id="p12-55" n="55"/>
						<q> 68 <hi rend="i">God Creating the Universe (‘The Ancient of
                                Days’)</hi> c.1794/1824 or 7 (?)<lb/>
 Relief etching finished
                            in gold, gouache and watercolour. 93/16 × 65/3 (23.4 ×
                            16.8).<lb/>
 Signed ‘Blake 1824’ [?, or a clumsy
                            ‘inv’: the end of the inscription is smudged]<lb/>
                            <hi rend="i">Whitworth Art Gallery, University of Manchester</hi>
                            <lb/>
                            This copy of the print is generally identified as that which, according
                            to J. T. Smith and Frederick Tatham, Blake coloured for Tatham on his
                            deathbed. It is however exceedingly difficult to read the last digit of
                            the date, if indeed it is a date, as a seven. The print is nevertheless
                            typical of Blake’s late rich elaborate colouring, including the
                            use of gold. It seems to be from the later state of the engraving, that
                            actually used in copies of <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi>
						</q>
                    </p>
                    <p>Needless to say, all of the old questions about Blake’s art are not
                        answered with the exhibition, and new ones are raised. For example, the
                        three versions of <hi rend="i">God Creating The Universe, The Ancient of
                            Days</hi> do indeed make one wonder if they all could have been printed
                        from the same plate, the relief-printed lines of the clouds so differed from
                        impression to impression; and one does have to be curious about the rather
                        meticulous watercolor study of a serpent which, as Mr. Butlin indicates,
                        corresponds to none of Blake’s serpents. Neither does it seem to
                        correspond in style to any of Blake’s other studies.</p>
                    <p>For the most part, Blake’s works are small in scale. He not only
                        hovers between the worlds of literature and art, but, within the world of
                        art, suffers because so many of his best, or best known, works are printed.
                        This fact often eliminates an artist from standard art-history surveys, to
                        be included only in studies of the history of prints—at one time
                        considered by some to be second-string art history. The catalogue for the
                        1939 Philadelphia Museum of Art’s Blake exhibition introduced the
                        paintings section as follows: “Blake was not a painter in the accepted
                        sense of the term since he never really mastered the technique of oil
                        painting.” “Accepted,” of course, is the operative word.</p>
                    <p>Developments within the contemporary art world have made Blake more palatable
                        and perhaps more accessible. Boundaries are by necessity being broken down
                        between <corr type="emend">categories,</corr> making color-printed drawings more
easily
                        “acceptable” to an art public. None of this alters Blake’s
                        work, but rather presents the possibility that a Blake exhibition in the
                        year 2027 won’t have to be introduced again with the propostion that
                        it aims to demonstrate Blake’s importance as a visual artist. To use
                        the last sentence of Martin Butlin’s introduction, “Of his
                        [Blake’s] greatness as a complete man there can be no doubt; nor, it
                        is here claimed, should there be any doubt about his greatness as an
                        artist.”</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>