<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>12.2.alincoln</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The Revision of the Seventh and Eighth Nights of The Four Zoas</title>
        <author n="Lincoln">Andrew Lincoln</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">12.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Special Design and Pasteup for this issue</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Everett Frost</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Terrence Hoagwood</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John Kilgore</name>
              <name>Mark Lefebvre</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Cettina Magno</name>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <name>Jeffry Spencer</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_12">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-12-2-0011">
    	<pb id="p12-115" n="115"/>
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">THE REVISION OF THE SEVENTH AND EIGHTH NIGHTS OF THE FOUR
                            ZOAS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">ANDREW</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">LINCOLN</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>The presence of two Nights headed “Night the Seventh” in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> forces
        			editorial choice of an uncomfortable kind. If we
                    decide to exclude one we will exclude material which seems necessary for a full
                    understanding of the poem. If both are included, how should we read them? We
                    seem to be left with a narrative which is hopelessly confused. In this article I
                    want first to analyze in detail some of the stages in the poem’s
                    development, and then to suggest a textual arrangement which will allow the two
                    Nights to be read as a single and reasonably coherent 
                    narrative.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n62"><hi rend="s">1</hi> All references to <hi rend="i">The Four
                                Zoas</hi> follow the line-numbering in the facsimile edited by
                            Gerald E. Bentley, Jr.: <hi rend="i">Vala, or The Four Zoas</hi>
                            (Oxford: Clarendon, 1963), hereafter referred to in the notes as
                            “Bentley.” In quotations, <hi rend="i">italics</hi> indicate
                            an erasure or deletion; additions to the basic text are bracketed
                            &lt; &gt;.
                        <p>In the text of my essay, the following abbreviations are used: 
						<table rows="7" cols="3"><row>
							<cell>Night</cell>
							<cell>VIIa1</cell>
							<cell>ms pages 77-85 (to line 85:22)</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell/>
							<cell>VIIa2</cell>
							<cell>85-90 (85:23-98:68)</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell/>
							<cell>VIIIa</cell>
							<cell>hypothetical lost draft</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell/>
							<cell>VIIIb</cell>
							<cell>a second hypothetical draft, very similar to VIII*</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell/>
							<cell>VIII*</cell>
							<cell>ms pages 99-110 before additions</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell/>
							<cell>VIII</cell>
							<cell>final ms version</cell>
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell/>
							<cell>IX*</cell>
							<cell>ms pages 119-39 (from line 119:24)</cell>
						</row></table></p></note></p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">NIGHTS VIIa AND VIIb</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>By considering VIIa (pages 77-90) as a single homogeneous narrative, Sloss
                        and Wallis helped to establish the critical tradition which has regarded
                        this Night as later than VIIb (pages 91-98). They asserted that
                        “Enitharmon’s fear of punishment and utter extinction . . . and
                        Los’s creation of Bodies from the Spectres” were described
                        “in the main body of the 
                        text,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63" type="note">2</ref> 
                        whereas they are clearly described in a subsequent addition to
                        the main body of the Night, introduced after two previous Night endings (at
                        85:22 and 85:31). In order to have a meaningful basis for the discussion of
                        relative dates, we must first try to distinguish the original form of VIIa
                        from the subsequent additions. <note id="n63"><hi rend="s">2</hi> D. J.
                        Sloss and J. P. R. Wallis, eds., <hi rend="i">The Prophetic Writings of
                        William Blake</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1926), I, 138.</note></p>
          <p>The first four leaves of VIIa, pages 77-84, have stitch marks which indicate
                        that they were once bound together with pages 43-76 and 111-12. The presence
                        of stitch marks on pages 111-12 suggests that this leaf was not originally
                        designed for its present context in VIII (the rest of which was never bound)
                        but had some other place in the manuscript. Bentley suggests<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64" type="note">3</ref> that the leaf, which has a full-page
                        sketch on page 112, was bound at the end of IV when Blake added the
                        pencilled instruction “Bring in here the Globe of Blood as in the B of
                        Urizen” between lines 17 and 18 on page 55. Bentley argues that the
                        drawing (showing a male looking anxiously at a female howling in horror, the
                        female trying to break away from the male’s embrace) was intended to
                        illustrate the lines which follow the Globe of Blood passage in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>:
						<q>
							But Los saw the Female &amp; pitied<lb/>
							He embrac’d her, she wept, she refus’d<lb/>
							In perverse and cruel delight<lb/>
							She fled from his arms, yet he followd.<lb/>
							<lb/>
							(<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> VI, 1)
						</q>
	<note id="n64"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Bentley, p. 200.</note></p>
          <p>Bentley concludes that the leaf was added after Blake had covered page 56
                        (originally left blank) with additions; but the two sets of additions which
                        cover the page contain Christian symbolism of a fairly developed kind, and
                        so Bentley’s suggestion implies that the binding which once held
                        pages 43-84 and 111-12 was made after Blake had begun to introduce Christian
                        material into the poem. As no other page containing Christian symbolism in
                        the basic text shows any sign of stitch marks, this seems unlikely.</p>
          <p>As there is no apparent connection between the drawing on page 112 and
                        anything else at the end of IV, the leaf may have been designed for some
                        other context within the binding that once held pages 43-84. Although only
                        the first four leaves of VIIa were bound (pages 77-84), there is no Night
                        ending on page 84, and the first ending now occurs after line 21 on the
                        unbound page 85. Bentley comments: “Assuming that the Night was
                        complete when bound, [Blake] later found it necessary to alter the last 
<pb id="p12-114" n="114"/>
		<figure n="BB209.1.112.MS" rend="file" width="772" height="1000">
			<head><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 112.</head>
	    </figure>
<pb id="p12-116" n="116"/>
						leaf so much that the whole leaf had to be removed and a new one 
                        substituted.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65" type="note">4</ref> 
                        This rests on the assumption that the Night was complete when
                        bound, which is open to question. The first Night ending on page 85 comes
                        after the description of Vala’s rebirth; and page 86 has a full-page
                        drawing of a female figure who is probably Vala, which may have been
                        intended to illustrate the Night ending. With this leaf VIIa would have nine
                        pages of text plus a full-page drawing, in line with the pattern Blake had
                        established in III, V, and VI, and which he probably intended for IV. As we
                        have seen, it is unlikely that the leaf containing pages 111-12 was bound at
                        the end of IV. It seems more likely, in view of the drawing on page 112,
                        that the leaf was originally designed for the end of VIIa. The relationship
                        between the Spectre of Urthona and the Spirit of Enitharmon described on
                        pages 82-84 follows the pattern typical of Los and Enitharmon, the male
                        tortured by jealousy, the female scornful and elusive: 
						<q>
							He turned from side to side in tears he wept &amp; he embracd<lb/>
							The fleeting image &amp; in whispers mild wood the faint shade.<lb/>
							<lb/>
							(82:26-27)
						</q>
	<note id="n65"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Bentley, p. 162.</note></p>
          <p>The drawing on page 112 would have been very suitable for VIIa if the Night
                        had ended with the tension between the Spectre and Shadow still unresolved.
                        When Blake bound the leaf with pages 43-84, that may have been his
                        intention; but in transcribing VIIa he may have begun to feel that
                        Vala’s birth would make a better climax (deciding, perhaps, to
                        transfer it from the beginning of the eighth Night?). In that case he would
                        naturally unbind his manuscript to remove pages 111-12; and he would also
                        prepare a new sheet which would be exactly like pages 85-86 before the
                        additions. When it was unbound page 111 was almost certainly still blank,
                        and it was only written on when Blake decided to use it in VIII. In this
                        case, then, Blake seems to have bound a leaf and prepared it with a drawing
                            <hi rend="i">before</hi> anything had been written on it: a surprising
                        instance which calls into question the assumption that the stitch marks were
                        made after Blake had completed, or partially completed, a draft of the poem.
                        This also suggests that the basic text of page 85 may have been the first
                        ending of VIIa to be transcribed on proof pages, and that it may be regarded
                        as the original end of VIIa. I shall subsequently refer to the basic text of
                        pages 77-85 (ending with 85:22) as “VIIa1,” and to the added
                        material (85:23-90:68) as “VIIa2.”</p>
          <p>Night VIIa1 contains little that could be regarded as “late” in
                        relation to pages 43-76. The Shadow of Enitharmon is a new figure, but she
                        enters the poem through the same kind of division that produced the Spectre,
                        and her appearance is a natural development in the disintegration of Urthona
                        rather than a late development in Blake’s symbolism. There are
                        references to Beulah in the Shadow’s account of the fall on page 83,
                        but Beulah is also mentioned in the Spectre’s account of the fall on
                        page 50 in IV. Night VIIa1 has strong narrative links with pages 43-76, as
                        it describes the confrontation between Urizen and Orc (anticipated at the
                        end of VI), and the rebirth of Vala (anticipated in V). Taken together, the
                        narrative of pages 43-85 follows the narrative sequence of 
                        <hi rend="i">Urizen-Ahania</hi> (the active confrontation between Urizen and Fuzon
                        becomes a verbal confrontation between Urizen and Orc, but at the end of
                        both the defeated energy principle is forced to ascend the tree of
                        Mystery).</p>
          <p>As Erdman points out in his review of Bentley’s edition of the
                        facsimile, stitch marks alone are of little help in questions of relative
                        date.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66" type="note">5</ref>
                        Leaves without stitch marks
                        could have been superseded and removed before Blake bound the manuscript, or
                        they could have been added afterwards. Nor can we be sure at what stage in
                        the process of composition the manuscript was bound. So we must rely on
                        internal evidence: the coherence of the narrative may be indicative, and the
                        date of transcription will be suggested by the latest reference in the basic
                        text. <note id="n66"><hi rend="s">5</hi> David V. Erdman, “The Binding
                        (<hi rend="i">et cetera</hi>) of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>,” <hi rend="i">The
                        Library</hi>, 5th Ser., XIX (1964), 121-22.</note></p>
          <p>In VIIb there is material which clearly seems to be later than anything in
                        the basic text of pages 43-76 or VIIa1, namely lines 4-14 on page 95, which
                        describe the Daughters of Beulah “Waiting with Patience for the
                        fulfilment of the Promise Divine,” and which conclude with the
                        appearance of Satan. Once again, the relevance of these lines was obscured
                        by Sloss and Wallis, who reported that they were “written over a previous draft,
                        deleted,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">6</ref> 
                        whereas they are clearly part of the basic text. The “Promise” of these
                        lines is a reference to the story of Lazarus in John 11. Similar references
                        occur only in recognizably late additions to the poem, on the added page 21
                        (lines 9-10) and in an added passage on page 56 (line 1). Satan also appears
                        only in late passages, as on the added page 22 (line 4), in the added
                        passage on page 56 (line 19), and in the manifestly late eighth Night. 
<note id="n67"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Sloss and Wallis, I, 337.</note></p>
          <p>This evidence alone suggests that VIIb is later than VIIa1, but there is also
                        the fact that VIIb has stronger narrative links with VIIa1 than it has with
                        VI. The growth of the tree of Mystery, Orc climbing the tree, and
                        Vala’s birth are all described in VIIa1, and yet all are assumed in
                        VIIb; and the original beginning of VIIb (on page 91 before the narrative
                        was rearranged) seems to follow from the end of VIIa1. Bentley suggests that
                        Blake revised and expanded the eighth Night, rewriting it as two Nights, one
                        of which was 
                        VIIb;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68" type="note">7</ref> 
                        this suggestion
                        merits further consideration, for if VIIb does contain material which was
                        displaced from the eighth Night we would expect to find some evidence of
                        this displacement. I believe such evidence does exist. 
<note id="n68"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Bentley, pp. 162-63.</note></p>
          <p>In the Lambeth books Blake had developed two different images for the
                        corruption of Orc: in <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi> crucifixion, and in the
                        Preludium of <hi rend="i">America</hi> the embrace with the Shadowy female,
                        whose possessive reaction suggests that she may simply absorb Orc’s
                        energies. In VIIa1 Blake reconciles the two images. The Spectre draws Vala
                        to embrace Orc who is stretched on the Tree of Mystery. An elaborate
                        parallel to the Preludium of <hi rend="i">America</hi> begins with the 
<pb id="p12-117" n="117"/>
<figure n="BB209.1.86.MS" rend="file" width="783" height="1000">
	<head><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 86.</head>
</figure>
<pb id="p12-118" n="118"/>
						daughters of Urizen feeding Orc (79:26-28).
                        Orc’s transformation into a jewelled serpent recalls not only
                        Fuzon’s corruption on the tree, but also Orc’s growth into
                        maturity. Vala is born as a spreading cloud at the end of VIIal, and in the
                        first lines of VIIb she stands before Orc (91:1-2). Directly after these
                        lines in VIIb, Orc breaks free from his bondage and is embraced by Vala
                        “that he might lose his rage” (91:4). The embrace completes the
                        transformation of Orc: “his human form consumd in his own fires”
                        (93:21) until “No more remaind of Orc but the Serpent round the tree of
                        Mystery” (93:24). Vala herself is strewn on the abyss. The
                        confrontation of Vala and Orc is resolved, then, near the beginning of VIIb.
                        However, there is a passage in VIII (101:10-25) which should, logically,
                        precede this embrace. In this passage Orc is still in bondage, and his
                        transformation into a jewelled serpent is still not complete—he is
                        still “raging,” his form is still partially “human.” The
                        passage brings us to a point equivalent to the third line of the 
                        <hi rend="i">America</hi> Preludium, and it is at this point that we might
                        expect a description of the embrace in which Orc breaks from bondage and
                        loses his human form completely.</p>
          <p>There is evidence of similar displacements elsewhere in VIIb. Urizen’s
                        triumphant proclamation at 95:15-24 was addressed to the Shadowy female in
                        the basic text, and followed by a line which was immediately deleted:
                        “The shadowy voice answerd O Urizen Prince of Light.” The speech
                        that was to have followed here was omitted, but perhaps it is worth pointing
                        out that Vala addresses Urizen only twice in the rest of the poem, once at
                        31:4-16 and once in VIII (102:28-103:20) in a speech which begins, as above,
                        “O Urizen Prince of Light.” It seems possible that the speech in
                        VIII was once intended as a reply to Urizen’s proclamation. Blake
                        must have been editing the text from which he was copying when he
                        transcribed VIIb. After 96:18 half a line was deleted: “Urizen namd it
                        Pande,” which suggests that Blake was cutting short a longer passage
                        here. He introduced instead, rather abruptly, the passage 96:20-98:31, which
                        may have originally had a different context.</p>
          <p>Urizen’s proclamation is followed by a description of his
                        preparations—the construction of a slave-based economy and the
                        erection of a temple of secret religion. More of these preparations are
                        described in passages which now appear in VIII, and these passages seem to
                        be leading up to an apocalyptic confrontation like the one described in
                        96:20-98:31. In the passage 100:27-32 Urizen begins to manufacture the
                        machinery of warfare, the object of this work being “To undermine the
                        World of Los &amp; tear bright Enitharmon / To the four winds”
                        (100:35-101:1). The work is continued in 102:14-22, where Urizen gives
                        “life &amp; sense . . . To all his Engines of deceit.” The four
                        lines 101:29-32 apparently describe the culmination of this activity: 
						<q>
                            Thus Urizen in self deceit his warlike preparations fabricated<lb/>
                            And when all things were finishd sudden wavd &lt;among the Stars&gt;<lb/>
                            &lt;His hurtling&gt; hand gave the dire signal thunderous Clarions blow<lb/>
                            And all the hollow deep rebellowd with the wondrous war.
                        </q>
                        In their present context these lines simply
                        herald an intensification of the conflict which is seen to be an inherent
                        feature of the fallen world over which Urizen presides; but the lines
                        themselves seem to describe a more decisive event. All of Urizen’s
                        preparations, now described variously in VIIb and VIII, seem to be leading
                        up to such a moment. The sudden, apocalyptic battle-signal should herald the
                        eruption of warfare. We might expect the passage 96:20-98:31, describing the
                        furious response of Los and Tharmas to the outbreak of war, to follow such a
                        signal. The passage apparently has a climactic significance. The
                        relationship between Los and Enitharmon is at its lowest ebb. Los, as in 
                        <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, rises eagerly to the prospect of war; his
                        appearance is more wrathful here than at any other point in <hi rend="i">The
                            Four Zoas</hi>, and his speech, 96:25-28, emphasizes the apocalyptic
                        dimension of the conflict, closely following Revelation 19:17-18. The last
                        line of the passage hints at the consequences of the spreading confusion,
                        for “Urizen’s web vibrated torment on torment.”</p>
          <p>The collapse of Urizen’s web is described in VIII in a sequence which
                        now begins with the Shadowy female’s speech. The collapse occurs at
                        103:21-31, and the description of Urizen’s final degeneration is
                        continued in 106:17-107:36. In 107:32-35, Tharmas and the Spectre of Urthona
                        give their strength to Los: 
						<q>
							And Tharmas gave his Power to Los Urthona gave his strength<lb/>
							Into the youthful prophet for the Love of Enitharmon<lb/>
							And of the nameless Shadowy female in the nether deep<lb/>
							And for the dread of the dark terrors of Orc &amp; Urizen.
						</q>
						These lines seem to anticipate some decisive action by Los, and it is
                        possible that they were followed originally by the description of Los
                        rending the heavens, now found in the beginning of IX. Several factors
                        suggest that this description formed the conclusion of an eighth Night
                        designed to follow VIIal. Night IX originally began on page 119 with the
                        words “Without this Universal Confusion . . . ” (119:24). In the
                        poem as it now stands these words clearly apply to the chaos described in
                        the new beginning of the Night; but when they were first transcribed they
                        must have applied to the end of the eighth Night. There is a reference to
                        Los destroying the heavens in the main body of IX, on page 121: 
						<q>
							Let Orc consume let Tharmas rage let dark Urthona give<lb/>
							All strength to Los &amp; Enitharmon &amp; let Los self cursd<lb/>
							Rend down this fabric as a wall ruind &amp; family extinct.<lb/>
							<lb/>
							(121:23-25)
						</q>
                        Here the destruction of the heavens is seen as a direct result of the Spectre of
                        Urthona’s attempt to give up his strength to Los. When these lines
                        were transcribed they cannot have referred to the new beginning of IX unless
                        Blake added the new beginning before he had transcribed three pages of 
                        <pb id="p12-119" n="119"/> 
						the Night (the lines occur three pages after the
                        original beginning). This seems to confirm that when Blake transcribed the
                        main body of IX, the “Universal Confusion” was described at the
                        end of the eighth Night, after the description of Urthona giving his
                        strength to Los.</p>
          <p>In the new beginning as it now stands, Los’s destructive gesture is
                        described in a passage of thirteen lines (117:1-13) added over an erasure.
                        In the added passage Los is watched over by Jesus, so the action appears to
                        be part of the divine scheme of redemption, and the passage is clearly
                        related to a late addition near the end of VIII (110:38-41). Without the
                        Christian framework the significance of Los’s action would be
                        different. The crucial lines on page 117, in which Los rends “the
                        heavens across from immense to immense” recall his gesture in <hi rend="i">The Book of
                        Los</hi>, Chapter II, where he stands “frozen
                        amidst / The vast rock of eternity”; “The Prophetic wrath,
                        strug’ling for vent” rends the rock “from immense to
                        immense,” and he falls into the abyss. This is an example of the
                        destructive nature of prophetic impatience, marking a further stage in the
                        fall. As originally transcribed, the corresponding action in <hi rend="i">The Four
                        Zoas</hi> may have been ironically redemptive, taking the
                        confusion of Urizen’s empire to its ultimate limit, a collapse
                        <corr type="emend">analogous</corr> to the destruction of the ego necessary for
                        Man’s awakening.</p>
          <p>In lines 117:24-25, 118:1-6 there is an account of the destruction of the
                        Spectres of Urthona and Enitharmon: 
						<q>
							The Spectre of Enitharmon let loose on the troubled deep<lb/>
							Waild Shrill in the confusion &amp; the Spectre of Urthona<lb/>
							Recievd her in the darkning South their bodies lost they stood<lb/>
							Trembling &amp; weak a faint embrace a fierce desire as when<lb/>
							Two shadows mingle on a wall they wail &amp; shadowy tears<lb/>
							Fell down &amp; shadowy forms of joy mixd with despair &amp; grief<lb/>
							Their bodies buried in the ruins of the Universe<lb/>
							Mingled with the confusion. Who shall call them from the Grave.
						</q>
						The “Spectre of Enitharmon” here is clearly an
                        alternative term for the “Shadow” that appears in VIIal as a
                        result of a further division of Urthona. The passage seems to be an attempt
                        to resolve the problem of Urthona’s disintegration. No solution is
                        offered in VIIal. The added endings of VIIa do not completely resolve this
                        division, but they do introduce a principle by which unity may be achieved:
                        the principle of self-annihilation. Compared with the new endings of VIIa,
                        the solution offered in the passage above seems crudely mechanical. The
                        outcome would seem to be a separation from Los, rather than integration with
                        him, as their bodies lie “buried in the ruins of the
                        Universe.”</p>
          <p>The additions at the end of VIIal (i.e. in VIIa2) almost seem to take the
                        situation described above as their starting point. In the additions, the
                        Spectre speaks to astound Los’s ear with “irresistable
                        conviction” 
						<q>
							Of thy fierce Soul Unbar the Gates of Memory look upon me<lb/>
							Not as another but as thy real Self I am thy Spectre<lb/>
							Tho horrible &amp; Ghastly to thine Eyes tho buried beneath<lb/>
							The ruins of the Universe.<lb/>
							<lb/>
							(85:37-40) 
 						</q>
						It seems that the account of
                        the Spectre of Urthona’s union with the Spirit of Enitharmon now
                        contained in the new beginning of IX was composed before the additions at
                        the end of VIIa were conceived. In fact the account may be Blake’s
                        original solution to the problem of Urthona’s disintegration, a
                        problem which is prominent in VIIal. Other manifestations of error
                        introduced in VIIal—Urizen’s books and the Tree of
                        Mystery—are consumed in the new beginning of IX, so the narrative as
                        a whole would have formed an appropriate conclusion to an eighth Night
                        designed to follow on from VIIal.</p>
          <p>There does seem to be evidence, then, to support Bentley’s suggestion
                        that in the process of revising the eighth Night, Blake rewrote it as two
                        Nights, the first of which was VIIb. There are traces of a narrative
                        sequence which may have been dislocated in the process of revision. This
                        sequence probably began with the embrace of Vala and Orc, may have described
                        how Urizen’s empire-building culminated in an apocalyptic
                        confrontation with Tharmas and Los and in the collapse of Urizen’s
                        web and the stupefaction of all of Man’s faculties except
                        Los—who pulled down the heavens. Such a narrative would have formed
                        an appropriate sequel to VIIal, and I shall subsequently refer to this
                        (lost) version of the eighth Night as “VIIIa.”</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">NIGHT IX</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>At this stage, a consideration of the ninth Night may prove helpful, and
                        Bentley’s comments on this Night make a convenient starting point for
                        discussion. He suggests that early drafts of the eighth and ninth Nights may
                        have been bound together with pages 43-84, and “may have described a
                        titanic war among the Zoas (Night VIIb seems to be a prelude to such a war).
                        This war would have resulted in ‘Universal Confusion’ (with
                        which Night IX begins, page 119), and have been resolved perhaps, in the
                        reunion of the four Zoas in the Eternal Man.” He suggests that as VIII
                        and IX contain overt Christian references, they are probably later than
                        VIIb: “They were probably recopied when VIIb was, but Blake’s
                        rapidly changing ideas may have forced him to transcribe Nights VIII and IX
                        yet once or twice again.” He suggests that IX is earlier than the
                        existing VIII, and concludes: “Presumably Blake’s major
                        alteration from the previous draft of Night IX was in his composition or
                        rewriting of the great harvest of the vintage which concludes the
                            Night.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n69"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Bentley, p. 163.</note></p>
          <p>For convenience I shall refer to the main body of the ninth Night, without
                        the new beginning (i.e. 119:24-139:10) as “IX*.” It seems that the
                        absence of stitch marks in IX* leads Bentley to conclude that this Night
                        must have replaced an earlier copy; it follows from this that IX* must have
                        evolved 
<pb id="p12-120" n="120"/>
						through a major revision of the
                        “earlier version,” as only such a major revision would justify the
                        complete retranscription of a Night. But as we have noted, internal evidence
                        is likely to provide a surer indication of relative date than the absence or
                        presence of stitch marks. Curiously, Bentley’s hypothesis for the
                        “original” ninth Night seems quite appropriate to IX*, which does
                        resolve the Universal Confusion “with the reunion of the four Zoas in
                        the Eternal Man.” How much of IX*, then, if any, is the product of
                        subsequent revision?</p>
          <p>The harvest and vintage sequence begins at 124:6 and continues to the end of
                        the poem, forming the greater part of the Night. There are obvious
                        precedents for such a sequence in Revelation 14:14-20, and in 
                        <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi>, where Urizen is introduced as the eternal sower. The
                        detail in which the sequence of ploughing, sowing, and harvesting is
                        described in IX* suggests that Blake was drawing on his observation of the
                        rural life around Felpham, and the sequence contains none of the Christian
                        references that might be regarded as conclusive evidence of revision,
                        although some elements could be regarded as late relative to pages 43-85.
                        First, there is a development in the presentation of Beulah: Urizen and his
                        sons, wearied after the sowing, receive visions on the “Couches of
                        Beulah” (131:21). Their vision is the long pastoral interlude in which
                        Luvah and Vala, and Tharmas and Enion, are reunited in innocence. However,
                        this development is anticipated in the Shadow of Enitharmon’s account
                        of the fall in VIIal, where Beulah is <corr type="emend">identified</corr> as a region of dreams, a
                        pastoral retreat from Eternity, an enticing world where Man’s fall
                        began: “he forgot Eternity delighted in his sweet joy / Among his
                        family his flocks &amp; herds &amp; tents &amp; pastures”
                        (83:21-22).</p>
          <p>The denunciation of Mystery on page 134 is clearly a direct allusion to the
                        archetypal female of Revelation 17 and 18, but it is not certain that when
                        IX* was transcribed the name Mystery had the specific meaning that it has in
                        VIII, where it is the name of the most degenerate form of Vala, Rahab. In VI
                        one of Urizen’s daughters is identified with the female of Revelation
                        by the writing on her forehead, and the female in IX* may have been
                        introduced similarly, as a simple personification of Urizenic mystery,
                        appropriate to the apocalyptic context. The names “Satan,”
                        “Rahab”, and “Mystery the Harlot” appear only in an
                        addition to IX* (120: 47,49), suggesting that the specific symbolic meanings
                        they have in the poem were developed after the Night had been
                        transcribed.</p>
          <p>The introduction of the Eternals on page 133 indicates Blake’s growing
                        sense of the existence of an unfallen reality, a development which
                        culminated in the introduction of “the Council of God;” and the
                        reference to the “Mercy Divine” at 125:39 suggests an unequivocal
                        faith in divine providence. However, there are references to “The ever
                        pitying one who seeth all things” and to “Providence divine”
                        in VI (71:25-26, 74:31-32); and the Eternals are to some extent anticipated
                        in the Shadow of Enitharmon’s account of the fall in VIIal:
                        “Wonder siezd / All heaven they saw him dark. they built a golden wall
                        / Round Beulah” (83:9-11). If the Eternals in IX* do indicate a new
                        concern with divine intervention, they are clearly closer to the Eternals of
                            <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> than to the providential Council of God. (As in
                            <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, the intervention of the Eternals described in
                        133:15-21 contributes to man’s fall.)</p>
          <p>Finally, the reference to the “crown of thorns” which falls from
                        Luvah’s head (135:23) as he rises from the Eternal feast may be an
                        example of the identification of Christ and Luvah which becomes important in
                        the Christian additions to the poem, although there are no other examples of
                        this identification in IX*, and as a passing reference the line may simply
                        describe the risen Orc relinquishing the trappings of the Tree of
                        Mystery.</p>
          <p>There seems to be little in the harvest and vintage sequence which can be
                        identified as the product of a major revision. In fact, the only parts of
                        IX* which contain symbolism for which there is no precedent in the basic
                        text of 43-85 are those passages near the beginning of the Night which refer
                        directly to Christ and Jerusalem.</p>
          <p>Man’s awakening, as it is described at the beginning of IX*, involves
                        the gradual reassertion of his will. Responding to the Universal Confusion
                        he reasons with himself until he recovers first a sense of determination,
                        and then feelings of wrath (120:27). This active struggle is the natural
                        sequel to the resignation of will described in the copperplate text
                        (23:3,5,6). However, after a description of the regeneration of Urizen,
                        there is a passage in which Man describes his awakening in terms of a divine
                        intervention. The passage begins: 
						<q>
							Behold Jerusalem in whose bosom the Lamb of God<lb/>
							Is seen tho slain before her Gates he self renewd remains<lb/>
							Eternal &amp; I thro him awake to life from deaths dark vale.<lb/>
							<lb/>
							(122:1-3)
						</q>
						These lines introduce a description of
                        the seasonal revival of Ahania in a harmonious relationship with Urizen,
                        followed by five lines in which Jerusalem is hailed as the bride of Christ,
                        “Mother of myriads redeemd &amp; born in her spiritual palaces / By a
                        New Spiritual birth Regenerated from Death” (122:19-20). This allusion
                        to Revelation 21 shows a new readiness to use Christian symbolism in a
                        direct way, but the providential awakening mentioned here seems quite
                        irrelevant to the awakening actually described, and seems to deny the
                        importance of Man’s struggle to reassert his will. This suggests that
                        the eight lines referring to the Lamb of God were not originally an integral
                        part of the passage in which they now appear, although they must have been
                        introduced before page 122 was transcribed as they are in the basic text. In
                        IX* there is no mention of the Council of God, and there is nothing to
                        connect Jerusalem with Golgonooza, nor with Los (who is mentioned only four
                        times in the Night), nor with Enitharmon (who is mentioned only twice). The
                        immediate connection between St. John’s vision and the basic myth of
                        IX* (apart from the obvious fact that both describe an apocalypse) is the
                        fact that St. John’s vision involves the ordering of a creative
                        sexual relationship, a principle of vital importance 
<pb id="p12-121" n="121"/>
						in the reintegration of Man’s faculties in
                        Blake’s poem. The passage framed by the Christian lines on page 122
                        describes the relationship between Ahania and Urizen in its ideal form.
                        Blake seems to have introduced the Christian symbolism in a context which
                        emphasizes the correspondence between the sexual harmony required in his own
                        myth and that which forms the climax of Revelation.</p>
          <p>The other example of this kind of Christiann symbolism occurs at the end of a
                        passage describing how the dead gather, waiting to be delivered. Again,
                        Blake seems to have introduced references to Revelation in a context which
                        enables a general analogy to be made: Jerusalem appears as “the
                        innocent accused before the Judges” (123:22) and, like the crucified
                        Christ, is identified with the oppressed who now rise to be delivered from
                        their oppressors. The vision of the Cloud of Blood is seen as the climax of
                        the violent destruction of the universe, and identifies the destruction with
                        the Judgment of Christ’s second coming. The vision includes 
						<q> 
                        	four Wonders of the Almighty<lb/>
                        	Incomprehensible. pervading all amidst &amp; round about<lb/>
                        	Fourfold each in the other reflected they are named Life’s in Eternity.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	(123:36-38) 
						</q>
                        Margoliouth, commenting on the word “Life’s” in the last line, writes:
                        “in spite of the apostrophe I think this is a plural and is a
                        translation of ζῶα Zoa, the ‘beasts’ or living creatures of
                        Revelation 4. . . . The four ‘Life’s’ have not here
                        been identified with Urthona, Luvah, Urizen and Tharmas, so providing a new
                        title for 
                        <hi rend="i">Vala.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70" type="note">9</ref>
                        As Margoliouth suggests, the symbolism of this passage has not really been
                        assimilated into the symbolic structure of the Night. The references to
                        divine intervention are registered as interpolations which remain ultimately
                        separate from the rest of the Night. This is the fundamental difference
                        between the Christian references in IX* and those in VIII. In any Night that
                        had been retranscribed at least once to <corr type="emend">accommodate</corr> material
                        which would
                        radically modify the conceptual basis of the poem, we might expect the new
                        ideas to revise the existing ideas satisfactorily; we might expect their
                        modifying effect to be dominant, if not complete. This is largely their
                        effect in VIII. If the first fourteen lines or so of VIII are compared with
                        the awakening described in IX*, the formalizing effect that the Christian
                        framework was to have is evident. In the lines at the beginning of VIII the
                        machinery of divine intervention has been fully developed, but at the
                        expense of the will: Man responds passively to a regulated scheme of
                        redemption in which his own will plays no part. In IX* the Christian
                        references have no such controlling effect, but are subordinate in a
                        narrative which is otherwise conceptually compatible with the basic text of
                        pages 43-85. The limited importance of these references suggests that they
                        were not introduced as part of a carefully planned revision; they seem to
                        have been introduced more as an immediate response to the major model for
                        the Last Judgment, the Book of Revelation, and Blake may even have decided
                        to introduce them while he was actually transcribing the Night. Their extent
                        is so limited that their inclusion would hardly seem to have justified the
                        complete retranscription of the Night, or even of the individual leaves on
                        which they occur. As there seems to be little evidence of major revision
                        elsewhere in the Night, it seems likely that the Christian references were
                        included in Blake’s first transcription of his “Last
                        Judgment,” which survives as the basic text of IX*. <note id="n70"><hi rend="s">9</hi>
                        H. M. Margoliouth, ed., <hi rend="i">Vala,
                        Blake’s Numbered Text</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1956), p.
                        148.</note></p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">NEW DEVELOPMENTS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>This study of the ninth Night implies that IX*, like VIIa1, was part of a
                        single draft of the poem which included the basic text of pages 43-76 and a
                        copy of the eight Night similar to the sequence I have called
                        “VIIIa”. Within this draft the lengths of the Nights had tended to
                        increase towards the end of the poem, and there had obviously been some
                        development in the symbolism. For example, Beulah had become more important
                        towards the end of the poem, and Christian symbolism had been introduced in
                        the ninth Night. It has long been recognized that much of the text on the
                        proof pages may have been composed while Blake was staying with Hayley at
                        Felpham. Commenting on the proof text, Margoliouth pointed out that
                        “Some of the Tharmas passages, especially in Nights III and IV, point
                        to a personal knowledge of the sea which we have no reason to suppose Blake
                        had before he went to 
                        Felpham.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71" type="note">10</ref>
                        As we have noted, Blake may have been influenced by his observation of the
                        rural countryside around Felpham in his treatment of eternal harvest in the
                        ninth Night. Blake’s letters from Felpham help to illuminate some of
                        the developments in the poem. <note id="n71"><hi rend="s">10</hi>
                        Margoliouth, pp. xxiii-xxiv.</note></p>
          <p>After the depressing final years at Lambeth, the removal to the peaceful
                        environment of Felpham and the security of Hayley’s patronage seem to
                        have given Blake a profound sense of spiritual release. His enthusiasm is
                        evident in his first letters from Felpham, and a fortnight after his arrival
                        he sent a poem to Butts which describes his “First Vision of
                    	Light.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72" type="note">11</ref>
						The poem relates how,
                        on the beach at Felpham, he has a vision in which his limbs are infolded in
                        beams of gold by “One Man.” This is a regeneration visualized in
                        terms far removed from the fierce, revolutionary apocalypse of the Lambeth
                        books. The tone and imagery of the poem are mild, the poet is passive, there
                        is little sense of a determined imaginative effort. This implies an
                        awareness of divine providence which had largely been absent from
                        Blake’s work since <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, and the poem
                        also suggests a new readiness to use direct (as opposed to satirical)
                        Christian parallels. The “One Man” may be identified readily with
                        the New Testament “Good Shepherd.” Man’s vision of
                        Jerusalem on page 122, derived from Revelation 21, has obvious similarities
                        with the “Vision of Light” that Blake described to Butts: just as
                        Blake was reborn in a renewed environment at “Female” Felpham, so
                        Man is awakened by Christ to be reborn in Jerusalem’s “spiritual
                        palaces.” Blake’s adoption of Christian symbolism in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
						may have begun with his tentative attempt to
                        reinterpret the resurrection described in the ninth Night in the light of
                        his growing awareness of a 
<pb id="p12-122" n="122"/>
						divine providence. The
                        willingness to adopt symbols from both Testaments of the bible, a
                        willingness apparent in additions to the poem, was undoubtedly stimulated
                        further by his study first of Greek, and then of Hebrew, begun under
                        Hayley’s supervision at Felpham. By January 1803 Blake felt confident
                        of his mastery of Greek, and was looking forward to reading “The Hebrew
                            bible.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73" type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n72"><hi rend="s">11</hi> See the letter to Butts of 2 Oct. 1800:
                            Geoffrey Keynes, ed., <hi rend="i">Blake: Complete Writings</hi>, rev.
                            edn. (Oxford: Clarendon, 1969), p. 804-06.</note>
	<note id="n73"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Keynes, p. 821.</note></p>
          <p>In a letter to Butts dated 22 November 
          				1802,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">13</ref> 
          				Blake included a poem “composed above a twelve month
                        ago” which, after dramatizing some of the doubts and uncertainties he
                        suffered at Felpham, ends triumphantly: 
						<q> Now I a fourfold vision see<lb/>
                            And a fourfold vision is given to me.</q>
                        Whether the word
                        “Now” in the first line refers to the date of the rest of the
                        verses, which were composed “above a twelve month ago” (i.e. in
                        1801), or to the date of the letter (November 1802) is open to question. But
                        it seems unlikely that Blake could have delayed by a year the announcement
                        of the gift of fourfold vision, and these last lines may have been added to
                        the rest of the poem when the letter was written (i.e., Blake was writing of
                        past difficulties which had now, in November 1802, been resolved). Another
                        letter to Butts of the same day seems to confirm this, for Blake declared
                        “I am again Emerged into the light of day; I still &amp; shall to
                        Eternity Embrace Christianity and Adore him who is the express image of God
                        . . . My Enthusiasm is still what it was, only Enlarged and
                        confirm’d.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75" type="note">14</ref> 
						I think the tone of this letter expresses more than the need to keep in favor with a
                        more orthodox patron; it suggests that as Blake progressed into fourfold
                        vision, Christianity assumed a new meaning for him. 
	<note id="n74"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Keynes, pp. 816-19.</note>
	<note id="n75"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Keynes, pp. 815-16.</note></p>
          <p>In the basic text of pages 43-76 the term “Beulah” occurs only
                        twice, in IV, where the Spectre tells Tharmas “thou Drewst all the Sons
                        of Beulah into thy dread vortex following / Thy Eddying spirit down the
                        hills of Beulah” (50:5-6). This reference to the “Sons of
                        Beulah” is unique: Blake normally refers to the “Sons of
                        Eden” and the “Daughters of Beulah,” and the reference in IV
                        may have survived from a time when Blake regarded Beulah as Man’s,
                        eternal dwelling place, the highest attainable ideal. When he received the
                        gift of fourfold vision Beulah would naturally come to be seen as a lower
                        paradise, and the need to distinguish the different degrees of vision in a
                        coherent symbolic structure must have become apparent. A passage in the
                        Shadow of Enitharmon’s account of the fall in VIIa1 seems to be an
                        early attempt to make such a distinction: 
						<q>
							Wonder siezd<lb/>
							All heaven they saw him dark. they built a golden wall<lb/>
							Round Beulah There he reveld in delight among the Flowers.<lb/>
							<lb/>
							(83:9-11)
						</q>
						Here Beulah is clearly identified as a lower paradise, distinguished from a
                        higher ideal identified vaguely as “All heaven.” In IX* there is a
                        further development, for Beulah is identified as a resting place from
                        Eternity where Man reposes, entertained by dreams before his
                        resurrection.</p>
          <p>There are two descriptions of cyclical relationships in IX*. In the long
                        pastoral passage Tharmas complains: 
						<q>
							the sweet smelling fruit<lb/>
                            Revives me to new deaths I fade even like a water lilly<lb/>
                            In the suns heat till in the night on the couch of Enion<lb/>
                            I drink new life.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            (131:2-5)
                        </q>
                        The recurring cycle described here is
                        comparable to the cycle which Blake developed more fully in “The Mental
                        Traveller.” In introducing this myth showing history as a series of
                        recurring cycles, Blake was beginning to go beyond the original structure of
                            <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, which was concerned with a single cycle
                        from fall to redemption. As a counterpart to the relationship of Tharmas and
                        Enion there is a description of an ideal cyclical relationship between males
                        and females, in which the obedient female sacrifices herself so that the
                        male remains “Immortal”: 
						<q> 
							Then bright Ahania shall awake from death<lb/>
							A glorious Vision to thine Eyes a Self renewing Vision<lb/>
                            The spring. the summer to be thine then sleep the wintry days<lb/>
                            In silken garments spun by her own hands against her funeral.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            (122:6-9)
                        </q>
                        This harmonious relationship is the converse of the
                        time-bound cycle, and both cycles suggest that when Blake transcribed IX* he
                        was already beginning to devise a structure in which the different levels of
                        vision would be characterized by distinct and antithetical modes of
                        existence.</p>
          <p>The new developments visible in VIIa1 and IX* are on a small scale and do not
                        seriously threaten the general coherence of the narrative in which they
                        occur. Bentley has discovered that page 48 of the manuscript was used as a
                        backing sheet when Blake was printing engravings for Hayley’s ballads
                        at Felpham. Engravings for the first ballad are dated 1 June 1802, and, as
                        it is very unlikely that Blake would temporarily remove a page of his
                        manuscript to use it as a backing sheet, it is reasonable to conclude, as
                        Bentley does, <ref target="n76" type="note">15</ref> that the page was not
                        transcribed until after the end of May 1802. Pages 43-84 may have been bound
                        together some time after this date; and as we have seen, at least one leaf
                        (pages 111-12) seems to have been bound before any thing was written on it.
                        Early in 1803, two months after Blake had written to Butts about
                        “fourfold vision,” his letters began to refer to the completion of
                        a major work, and on 6 July he mentioned 
						<q> a Sublime Allegory, which is
                            now perfectly completed into a Grand Poem. . . . This poem 
<pb id="p12-123" n="123"/>
						shall by Divine Assistance be progressively Printed and Ornamented with 
						Prints &amp; given to the 
						Public.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77" type="note">16</ref></q>
						Frye thinks that this “does not literally apply to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, 
						which was never completed into 
						anything.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78" type="note">17</ref> 
						But although the poem was never
                        “progressively Printed and Ornamented with Prints” there is no
                        reason to suppose that it was never completed into anything. The poem as it
                        stands contains revisions almost certainly made after 1803; but Blake could
                        have been referring to an intermediate stage of composition in which nine
                        Nights had been completed into a unified and symbolically homogeneous whole.
                        It is possible that Blake was referring to a single draft of <hi rend="i">The Four
                        Zoas</hi> which included a revised copperplate text, pages
                        43-85 and IX*. Blake’s symbolism may have begun to develop in new
                        directions when his Grand Poem was almost complete. This would explain the
                        new developments apparent in VIIal and IX*; and it would also explain why
                        Blake subsequently began to revise the poem, to integrate the new ideas more
                        fully. <note id="n76"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Bentley, p. 161.</note>
	<note id="n77"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Keynes, p. 825.</note>
	<note id="n78"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Northrop Frye, <hi rend="i">Fearful
                                Symmetry</hi> (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1947), p.
                            314.</note></p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">THE FIRST REVISION OF THE EIGHTH NIGHT</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>If VIIb <hi rend="i">was</hi> composed during a revision of
                        “VIIIa,” what kind of changes were made to the eighth Night at
                        this stage? The text of VIIb and of the present eighth Night should provide
                        useful clues. The existence of VIIb suggests that Blake was extremely
                        reluciant to discard material once it had been used in the poem, and so it
                        may be possible to find traces in VIII of material introduced in any
                        previous revision (even if it has been subsequently modified). Night VIII is
                        manifestly composite, and consists of: (i) six leaves which contain a
                        continuous narrative running from the title-page (page 99) to page 110, on
                        which “End of the eighth Night” was twice written and twice
                        erased; and (ii) three leaves (pages 111-16) which contain material to be
                        interpolated in or added to pages 99-110. For convenience I shall refer to
                        the basic text of pages 99-110 as “VIII*.” This text ends at
                        110:28, “And all his Sorrows till he reassumes his ancient
                        bliss.”</p>
          <p>Broadly speaking, VIII* falls into three sections, as the Night is divided by
                        a sequence describing the descent, judgment, and crucifixion of Christ, the
                        sequence occuring almost exactly in the middle of the Night (104:5 to
                        106:6). The last part of the Night begins “Darkness &amp; sorrow
                        coverd all flesh Eternity was darkend,” and from this point to the end
                        of VIII* there is nothing in the basic text necessarily later than the basic
                        text of pages 43-85. Although the rest of VIII* contains highly developed
                        Christian symbolism, the reference to the Divine Lamb at 107:37-39 and
                        110:1-2 are both subsequent additions; and there is no mention of the
                        redemptive labors of Los and Enitharmon in this part of the narrative,
                        although they are prominent in the rest of the Night. This suggests that the
                        last section may have been composed before the development of Blake’s
                        Christian symbolism was advanced, and before Los had begun to assume an
                        actively redemptive role in the poem. The section ends, after Tharmas and
                        the Spectre give up their strength to Los, with the final lamentation of
                        Ahania and Enion’s comforting answer. One of Blake’s first
                        revisions to VIIIa may have been the addition of the lament with
                        Enion’s reply, which would have displaced the original ending (Los
                        rending the heavens), which would then have to be added at the beginning of
                        the ninth Night. Such a revision, while changing the ending of the eighth
                        Night from an explosive climax to a passage of elegiac expectation, would
                        help to re-establish the presence of Enion and Ahania (who are largely
                        absent from the central Nights of the poem) before their resurrection in the
                        last Night.</p>
          <p>The material in the basic text of VIIb which seems manifestly late indicates
                        that when the Night was composed, Blake was beginning to define the
                        different degrees of vision in a coherent structure. In VIIal and IX* Beulah
                        had been distinguished from Eternity; in VIIb two more levels are
                        distinguished, although they are not named. The Shadowy female extends
                        through one: 
						<q>
							far &amp; wide she stretchd thro all the worlds of Urizens journey<lb/>
							And was Adjoind to Beulah as the Polypus to the Rock.<lb/>
							<lb/>
							(95:1-2)
						</q>
						This world has been the scene of most of
                        the events described in the poem, but now Blake distinguished a lower world
                        “Beyond the Limit of Translucence,” the world of single vision and
                        opacity which was subsequently called “Ulro.” As the dead descend
                        into this world to form Satan, the daughters of Beulah sing songs of
                        comfort, “Waiting with Patience for the fulfilment of the Promise
                        Divine.” This passage suggests that when Blake composed VIIb he
                        envisaged a comprehensive scheme of divine intervention which would control
                        the events of the fallen world.</p>
          <p>At the end of IV Blake made two additions, the first of which was twenty-two
                        lines long, transcribed over the original (erased) Night ending, at the foot
                        of page 55 and at the top of page 56. It was marked for insertion after 55:9
                        (i.e., it was designed to follow the description of Los binding Urizen). In
                        this addition the daughters of Beulah observe the fallen world from
                        “Beulahs mild moon coverd regions,” and take comfort in the Divine
                        Vision embodied in the Council of God. The last six lines of the passage,
                        which were subsequently erased, may have described a measure of divine
                        intervention by the Council, and, if Erdman’s conjecture for the
                        fourth line is correct, the founding of the limit of 
                        Contraction.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79" type="note">18</ref> 
                        The founding of this limit is
                        described in the passage which replaced these six lines, and also the
                        founding of the “Limit of Opacity” or Translucence, which suggests
                        that the erased lines may also have described the founding of the limit of
                        Translucence. This means that the first addition at the end of IV may have
                        been designed to prepare for the related passage in VIIb, where the dead
                        descend below the limit of Translucence to become Satan. (In the first
                        addition the daughters of Beulah quote Martha’s rebuke to Jesus:
                        “Lord if thou had’st been here, my brother had not died,”
                        John 11:21; in VIIb the daughters are comforted by Christ’s reply to
                        Martha, “Thy brother shall rise again,” v. 23.) <note id="n79"><hi rend="s">18</hi>
						David V. Erdman, ed., and Harold Bloom, <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of 
						William Blake</hi>, rev. edn. (New York: Doubleday, 1970), p. 752.</note></p>
          <pb id="p12-124" n="124"/>
                      <figure n="BB209.1.55.MS" rend="file" width="820" height="1000">
            <head><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 55.</head>
          </figure>
          <p>The passage at the beginning of the eighth Night, in which the Council,
                        described as a “Vision of all Beulah,” meets to create the fallen
                        man, brings the scheme initiated at the end of IV to fruition.
                        Christ’s descent and the final epiphany of Satan in the eighth Night
                        are seen as the culmination of a divine scheme which has been observed in
                        all its stages by the daughters of Beulah. The description of the Council of
                        God in the eighth Night, then, is closely related to the first addition at
                        the end of IV and to the passage in VIIb describing the formation of Satan,
                        and it was probably introduced during the revision which produced VIIb. The
                        passage may have been modified subsequently when Blake composed VIII*, for
                        it contains Old Testament references and the term “Eden,” for
                        which there is no precedent in VIIb. Similarly, it seems unlikely that the
                        second addition at the end of IV, or the reference to the story of Lazarus
                        on page 21 (lines 9-10) were added at this time; both passages contain
                        terms, such as “Emanation,” which seem later than anything in the
                        basic text of either VIIb or VIII*.</p>
          <p>It seems clear that when Blake composed VIIb he must have planned to include
                        in the eight Night some kind of sequence describing the epiphany of Satan,
                        and the incarnation and crucifixion of Christ. The late passage in VIIb
                        clearly prepares for Satan’s epiphany, and the crucifixion would form
                        the prelude to the triumphant second coming which had already been described
                        in the ninth Night. There is little in the account of Satan’s
                        epiphany described on page 104 in VIII* that is not anticipated in VIIb or
                        compatible with the Christian passages in IX*, except perhaps the
                        introduction of the “Sons of Eden.” The last lines on page 104
                        originally stated that the Lamb of God would “rend the Veil of Mystery
                        / And the Call Urizen &amp; Luvah &amp; Tharmas &amp; Urthona,”
                        which prescribes a more directly active role for Christ than he actually has
                        in the rest of VIII*: they suggest that he will become a kind of divine
                        caretaker who will assume responsibility for reintegrating the faculties on
                        Man’s behalf. In VIII* Man’s regeneration depends on the
                        creative labors of an enlightened Los who is inspired by Christ. The
                        pencilled addition at 104:31, “Los said to Enitharmon Pitying I
                        saw,” may be an attempt to maintain the presence of Los in a passage
                        which was conceived before Los had been seen as an enlightened redeemer.
                        There may also have been an early version of the judgment and crucifixion
                        which was subsequently revised to produce the fragment p. 145, and the final
                        version 105:1 to 106:6.</p>
          <p>Each of these additions to the eighth Night—the description of the
                        Council of God, the Christian sequence, the lament of Ahania and
                        Enion’s answer—would have increased the length of the eighth
                        Night. This increase in size, together with the fact that the introduction
                        of a scheme of divine intervention would have a far-reaching effect on the
                        poem as a whole, may have prompted Blake to undertake a major reorganization
                        of the narrative sequence of the Night. It was probably at this stage that
                        Blake decided to add the new beginning to the ninth Night and to compose an
                        entirely new Night, VIIb, taking from VIIIa the description of the Vala-Orc
                        embrace, the construction of Urizen’s empire, and the passage
                        describing how Tharmas, Los, and Enitharmon react to the warfare.</p>
          <p>In composing VIIb, Blake would have to change the sequence and the
                        significance of events originally described in the eighth Night. The warfare
                        was now seen to begin not with Urizen’s apocalyptic battle-signal but
                        with the Vala-Orc embrace; and the conflict became an inherent feature of
                        Urizen’s empire, rather than the culmination of his elaborate
                        preparations. Orc no longer loses his rage completely at the moment of the
                        embrace with Vala, for although the embrace is now described in VIIb, the
                        description of Orc’s transformation on the Tree of Mystery is
                        retained in the eighth Night, the swelling Orc symbolizing enslaved energy
                        bound in the widening conflict of Urizen’s empire. Orc is thus seen
                        as an active force in Urizen’s empire. Orc and Urizen are now seen to
                        be “Communing” (100:33).</p>
          <p>Night VIIb seems to have been composed before Blake had reassessed the role
                        of Los, for he appears in the Night as a wrathful figure rather than a
                        patient, enlightened redeemer. The major difference between the version of
                        the eighth Night produced at this stage and the present VIII* (apart from
                        local revisions) would be the absence of the three passages which in VIII*
                        describe the redemptive labors of Los and Enitharmon (99:20 to 100:26,
                        101:35-37, 103:32 to 104:4). In other respects the outline of the eighth
                        Night—beginning with a description of the Council of God, continuing
                        with chaotic warfare, a central sequence describing the crucifixion, and
                        concluding with a passage possibly identical to 
<pb id="p12-125" n="125"/>
                        106:17 to 110:28—would have been very similar to VIII*. I shall
                        subsequently refer to this second version of the eighth Night, contemporary
                        with VIIb, as “VIIIb.”</p>
          <p>When he transcribed VIIb Blake probably did not intend to exclude VIIal from
                        the poem, as both Nights contain elements essential to the coherence of the
                        poem’s narrative, and VIIb seems to have been designed to follow on
                        from the end of VIIal. As Bentley 
                        suggests,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80" type="note">19</ref> 
                        it seems likely that Blake intended to conflate the first
                        seven Nights into six; but whatever revision he had in mind, he
                        doesn’t seem to have carried it out at this time, and he probably
                        deferred the problem of reconciling the two seventh Nights. 
<note id="n80"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Bentley, p. 163.</note></p>
          <p>Although VIIb had just under 300 lines as originally transcribed (comparable
                        to VI and VIIal), it was transcribed on four leaves instead of the usual
                        five, and no room was left for a full-page drawing on the final page. This
                        suggests that when he transcribed VIIb Blake had used up most of the 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> proof-leaves, and had started to use them
                        more sparingly. The new beginning of the ninth Night was probably
                        transcribed at about the same time. An addition at 118:7 refers to Rahab and
                        Tirzah, who are mentioned nowhere else in the new beginning, although they
                        occur in the basic text of VIII*. This suggests that the new beginning was
                        probably transcribed before VIII* was composed. However, it seems unlikely
                        that the revised eighth Night (“VIIIb”) was transcribed at this
                        stage. The last part of VIII* (106:17 to the end), as we have seen, contains
                        no late symbolism in the basic text, and was probably identical to the last
                        section of VIIIb. It seems unlikely that Blake would copy out this section
                            <hi rend="i">twice</hi>, once in VIIIb and again in VIII*, without
                        making any changes. Before it was transcribed the eighth Night probably
                        underwent further revision.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">THE SECOND REVISION OF THE EIGHTH NIGHT</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>In a letter to Hayley of 23 October 1804, Blake suddenly made an unusually
                        enthusiastic announcement: 
						<q> I have entirely reduced that spectrous Fiend
                            to his station, whose annoyance has been the ruin of my labours for the
                            last passed twenty years of my life. He is the enemy of conjugal love
                            and is the Jupiter of the Greeks, an iron-hearted tyrant, the ruiner of
                            ancient Greece. . . . Suddenly, on the day after visiting the
                            Truchsessian Gallery of pictures, I was again enlightened with the light
                            I enjoyed in my youth, and which has for exactly twenty years been
                            closed from me as by a door and by window-shutters. . . . he is become
                            my servant who domineered over me, he is even a brother who was my
                            enemy.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81" type="note">20</ref>
	<note id="n81"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Keynes, p. 935.</note></q></p>
          <p>As John Sutherland has observed, this enlightenment seems similar to the one
                        experienced by Los in some of the additions to <hi rend="i">The Four
                            Zoas</hi>: “After 1804, Blake seems more concerned with
                        communicating a method he had discovered by which men may win free from
                        individual, internal tyranny—a method by which an individual may free
                        himself from the domination of one distorted aspect of his own psyche
                        (either from Urizen, or from the Spectre of his dominant Zoa—in
                        Blake’s case, from the Spectre of 
                        Urthona).”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82" type="note">21</ref> 
                        Throughout much of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
                        Los appears as a spectral figure. In the main body of the ninth Night, for
                        example, he is mentioned only a few times, once near the very end of the
                        poem, where he is not clearly distinguished from the Spectre of Urthona: 
						<q>
                            Urthona is arisen in his strength no longer now<lb/>
                            Divided from Enitharmon no longer the Spectre Los<lb/>
                            Where is the Spectre of Prophecy the delusive phantom.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            (139:4-6)
                        </q>
						The apparent
                        lack of distinction between Los and the Spectre in parts of the poem
                        possibly reflects Blake’s own difficulties in freeing his prophetic
                        voice from its attendant Spectre. In additions at the end of VIIa the
                        relationship between Los and the Spectre is brought into focus. The original
                        Night-ending on page 85 [after line 18] was erased to make room for an
                        addition of six lines in which 
						<q>
							Los Embracd the Spectre first as a brother<lb/>
							Then as another Self; astonishd humanizing &amp; in tears<lb/>
							In Self abasement Giving up his Domineering lust. 
 						</q>
                        There are echoes in these lines of the extract from the letter quoted above; and
                        in another letter to Hayley (4 December 1804) Blake writes in similar terms
                        that he has lived a 
                        “Divided Existence”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83" type="note">22</ref> 
                        but is no longer at war with himself. The passages
                        in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> in which Los unites with his Spectre to
                        assume the role of enlightened redeemer were probably suggested by the
                        dramatic enlightenment that followed Blake’s visit to the
                        Truchsessian Gallery in the Autumn of 1804. <note id="n82"><hi rend="s">21</hi> John
Sutherland, “Blake and Urizen,” <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman
                            and John E. Grant (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1970) pp.
                            250-51.</note>
	<note id="n83"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Keynes, p. 935.</note></p>
          <p>The new enlightenment seems to have come after VIIb was transcribed, and
                        after the Christianization of the poem had begun, but before the second
                        version of the eighth Night (VIIIb) had been copied out. It was a
                        development which would cause a peculiar problem of organization. When VIIb
                        was composed, it seems probable that Christ’s descent in the eighth
                        Night was to have been the major turning point in the poem, because at this
                        stage in the poem’s development none of Man’s faculties would
                        have been capable of enlightened action (Los’s final rending of the
                        heavens would have been an act of desperation rather than an enlightened
                        gesture). When Los became an enlightened redeemer, Christ’s descent
                        would appear as a culmination rather than a turning point. The redemptive
                        labors of Los would be described most appropriately in the prelude to
                        Man’s awakening, the eighth Night. But as Los’s reconciliation
                        with the Spectre provides a partial solution to the problem of
                        Urthona’s disintegration, a problem which is discussed in some detail
                        by the Spectre and the Shadow of Enitharmon at the end of VIIal, the
                        reinterpretation of Los would inevitably strengthen the narrative links
                        between the end of VIIal and the eighth Night—despite the fact that
                        the two Nights were now separated by the new Night, VIIb.</p>
          <pb id="p12-126" n="126"/>
          <p>The exact nature of this problem will become clear if we examine some of the
                        elements of the VIIb narrative. At the end of VIIal the rebirth of Vala is
                        described thus: “a Cloud she grew &amp; grew / Till many of the dead
                        burst forth from the bottoms of their tombs” (85:17-18). Before later
                        additions were made to this page, the last line would seem to have had only
                        a general significance, identifying Vala’s rebirth as an event of
                        apocalyptic importance. A variant of the same line occurs in VIIb, where the
                        dead descend beyong the limit of Translucence to form Satan (95:11-14).
                        There “the Dead” begin to take on a specific importance in the
                        developing mythology. When Los had been reassessed, the identification of
                        the Dead as victims of Urizen’s war became important to
                        Blake’s conception of Los’s redemptive activities. In VIII*,
                        for example, Los strives to assimilate the chaotic warfare: 
						<q>
							Los builds the walls of Golgonooza against the stirring battle<lb/>
							That only thro the Gates of Death they can enter to Enitharmon.<lb/>
							<lb/>
							(101:35-36)
						</q>
						The pronoun “they” refers to “the Dead” who are
                        rescued by Los and Enitharmon as they descend towards the lowest level of
                        existence “tempted by the Shadowy females sweet / Delusive
                        cruelty.” The descent described in VIIb thus became an integral part of
                        the process of redemption.</p>
          <p>However, in VIIb there is tension rather than cooperation between Los and
                        Enitharmon. Los responds enthusiastically to the violence, and Golgonooza
                        seems threatened by his neglect rather than strengthened by his efforts:
                        Enitharmon cries “O Los unless thou keep my tower the Watchman will be
                        slain” (98:6). In short, in VIIb the misguided Los contributes eagerly
                        to the chaos which, as an agent of redemption, he should be striving to
                        assimilate. When Los had been reassessed, then, part of VIIb became useful
                        to the developing scheme of salvation, while part became manifestly
                        inappropriate to that scheme. As long as the narrative of VIIb remained
                        unchanged between VIIal and the eighth Night, Blake would have difficulty in
                        introducing an account of Los’s enlightening reconciliation with the
                        Spectre and Enitharmon where it would be most appropriate—at the end
                        of VIIal.</p>
          <p>Another problem in introducing new material to the poem would be the
                        inevitable strain imposed on the general structure. The basic text of VIII*
                        had over 400 lines—about 100 more than any other Night except the
                        ninth; it had six leaves instead of five; and the text continued on the
                        verso of the sixth leaf, leaving no room for a full.-page drawing. In these
                        respects the Night was “irregular.” Blake was being forced by the
                        quantity of his material to abandon some of the formal patterning which had
                        shaped his earlier Nights. However, the Night was transcribed on <hi rend="i">Night
                        Thoughts</hi> proof pages in the normal way, and had
                        approximately the same number of lines per page as the earlier Nights on the
                        proof pages, which suggests that Blake still maintained some concern for the
                        general appearance of his manuscript, and was hoping to resolve the problem
                        of his two seventh Nights within a nine-Night structure. The desire to
                        preserve the formal structure of the poem obviously conflicted with the
                        desire to include growing quantities of new material, but Blake may have
                        maintained a fairly selective attitude towards new material at this
                        stage.</p>
          <p>The regularity of VIII* will be appreciated if it is compared with the two
                        leaves added at the end of VIIal, in which the reuinion of Los with the
                        Spectre and Enitharmon is described. These leaves, pages 87-90, were formed
                        by cutting in two a print (of <hi rend="i">Edward &amp; Elenor</hi>, 1793);
                        the text is written on one side of each leaf (with the print on the other
                        side), and the number of lines per page is considerably larger than the
                        average for the rest of the proof-text. The fact that the leaves were made
                        by destroying a large print would suggest that they were among the very last
                        to be added to the poem, used when Blake was having difficulty finding paper
                        of an appropriate size, and when the overall appearance of the manuscript
                        was less important to him than the inclusion of all relevant material.
                        However, with one or two local exceptions, the basic text of pages 87 and 90
                        seems to be contemporary in date of composition with those passages in VIII*
                        which describe the redemptive labors of Los and Enitharmon. Much of the
                        material added at the end of VIIal, then, may have been composed before, but
                        transcribed some time after, VIII* was transcribed.</p>
          <p>On page 85 Blake erased the original Night ending (of VIIal), adding nine
                        lines in which Los embraces the Spectre and gives up his “Domineering
                        Lust,” and a new Night ending which was erased when the Night was
                        extended further. The final result of the later additions was a continuous
                        narrative from 85:32 to 90:68. Although as the poem now stands this
                        narrative <hi rend="i">is</hi> continuous, there is evidence to suggest that
                        it was originally composed and transcribed as two distinct sections designed
                        for separate contexts within the poem. The first section runs from 85:32 to
                        the foot of page 87 (line 59 in the basic text). The text from 85:32 to
                        86:14 is really a more elaborate version of the previous nine-line addition,
                        except that it describes Los’s reunion with the Spectre in terms
                        quite new to the poem, for Los now responds to the Spectre’s doctrine
                        of “Self annihilation.” Golgonooza, previously featured in IV
                        (49:18-21), V (59:28; 60:1-3), and VIIb (97:31-32), now becomes prominent,
                        opening a way to “new heavens &amp; a new Earth” (87:9). In
                        87:30-35 the Spectre explains that Los’s task will be to ransom the
                        “Spectres of the Dead,” a phrase which here refers to the dead who
                        burst from their tombs when Vala is reborn at the end of VIIal. But Los can
                        find no way to redeem the Spectres until he has been reconciled with
                        Enitharmon, an event which will complete the second stage of his
                        enlightenment. In 87:13-29 Enitharmon tempts Los with the fruit of
                        Urizen’s tree, and Los eats the fruit, sitting down “in
                        Despair.” This passage ties the narrative firmly to that of VIIal, as
                        it continues the tension between Los and Enitharmon described on pages 81 to
                        85. The text of page 87 concludes with Enitharmon still possessed by jealous
                        fears, still refusing the entreaties of Los and misinterpreting the descent
                        <pb id="p12-127" n="127"/>
                        of Christ: “I . . . fear that he / Will
                        give us to Eternal Death.” At this point Los’s restoration is
                        incomplete, as he has yet to be reconciled with Enitharmon.</p>
          <p>Whereas the passage from 85:32 to 87:59 was clearly designed as a
                        continuation of VIIal, the basic text of page 90 may have been designed
                        originally for a different context. In 90:5-7 Los pleads once more with
                        Enitharmon: 
						<q>
							Lovely delight of Men Enitharmon shady refuge from furious war<lb/>
							Thy bosom translucent is a soft repose for the weeping souls<lb/>
							Of those piteous victims of battle . . .
						</q>
						The references
                        to “war” and the “victims of battle” are explained when
                        Enitharmon is finally reassured by Los and they are reconciled: Los draws
                        flames “From out the ranks of Urizens war” (90:30). “Urizens
                        war” is the chaotic conflict which is described in VIIb and the eighth
                        Night. On page 90 the identification of the Spectres of the dead as victims
                        of this battle suggests that this passage may have been designed originally
                        for some context after the embrace of Vala and Orc, which in VIIb initiates
                        the conflict.</p>
          <p>On page 100 in VIII a marginal note “Los stood &amp;c” indicates
                        that a passage was to be inserted between lines 1 and 2. Erdman suggests
                        that this refers to 90:2, originally the first line on page 90, which
                        originally read “Los stood in Golgonooza in the Gate of Luban.”
                        Erdman observes that “The thematic material of 90, amplified with
                        marginal additions, seems all an amplification backward from the
                        ‘Looms in Luban’s Gate’ in 100:2.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n84" type="note">23</ref> The suggestion of an
                        “amplification backward” follows from the observation that page 90
                        is “unquestionably a late addition.” The physical evidence, we
                        have seen, would certainly suggest that pages 87 to 90 were among the last
                        additions to the poem, but this does not necessarily apply to the original
                        date of composition. From the internal evidence the material in VIII*
                        describing the labors of Los and Enitharmon seems to be a continuation of
                        the text of page 90. Los’s reunion with the Spectre and with
                        Enitharmon, and his discovery of a way to redeem the victims of
                        Urizen’s war, are assumed in VIII*, where there is no mention of the
                        Spectre, and where Los and Enitharmon start to rescue the Spectres of the
                        dead at the beginning of the Night. In fact, shortly after Los and
                        Enitharmon are introduced the focus of attention moves away from Los to the
                        building and working of Enitharmon’s looms. The shift in emphasis
                        seems quite natural if VIII* is read as a continuation of page 90, where
                        full attention is paid to Los’s role and Enitharmon, finally
                        reassured, begins to assume importance in the scheme of salvation. It seems
                        more likely that Blake worked out the details of Los’s reunion with
                        the Spectre and Enitharmon before VIII* was copied out, rather than
                        composing it afterwards as an “amplification backward.” Old
                        Testament references occur in the three leaves added to VIII* (pages 113,
                        115, and 111) and in the added leaves pages 19-20, all of which also seem to
                        be unquestionably late additions, but there are no comparable references in
                        pages 87 and 90, which again suggests that the texts of the later pages may
                        have been composed before Blake had begun to adopt Old Testament references.
                            <note id="n84"><hi rend="s">23</hi> Erdman, <hi rend="i">Poetry and
                                Prose</hi>, p. 758.</note></p>
          <p>When Blake first reassessed the role of Los, he may have composed two related
                        but distinct passages: (i) a new ending to VIIa, describing the conversion
                        of Los by the new doctrine of “Self annihilation,” which included
                        his reunion with the Spectre but did not resolve the tension between Los and
                        Enitharmon; (ii) a narrative designed to come after VIIb (i.e., to be
                        included in the eighth Night) which described Los’s reconciliation
                        with Enitharmon <hi rend="i">and</hi> the construction of
                        Enitharmon’s looms. By leaving the tension between Los and Enitharmon
                        unresolved in the new ending of VIIa, Blake may have hoped to explain the
                        strained relationship in VIIb, although the Spectre-like Los of VIIb is hard
                        to equate with the humanized Los of page 87, who has already begun his
                        inspired construction of Golgonooza. When Blake first composed this passage
                        he was possibly more concerned with developing the myth to his own
                        satisfaction than with the problem of containing it within the existing
                        structure of the poem.</p>
          <p>I have suggested that in his attempts to preserve the formal outline of the
                        poem Blake probably maintained a fairly selective attitude to new material.
                        In view of the fact that the new passages were developing beyond the
                        original scheme of the poem—could provide, in fact, the basis of a
                        separate poem—Blake may even have considered dropping VIIal from the
                        poem at this stage. A note on page 91 of VIIb reads, “This Night begins
                        at line 153 the following comes in at the End”; on page 95 after line
                        14 a note indicates the “Beginning of the <hi rend="i">Book</hi>
                        Seventh Night”; and at the foot of page 98 Blake wrote, “Then
                        follows Thus in the Caverns of the Grave &amp;c as it stands now in the
                        beginning of Night the Seventh.” When he added these instructions he
                        clearly intended the seventh Night to begin at 95:15. The sixth Night ends
                        on page 75 with Urizen’s confrontation with Tharmas and the Spectre,
                        who impede his progress down the vale of Urthona. In the final lines of the
                        Night Urizen breaks down their resistance, as his “massy Globes . . .
                        slow oerwheel / The dismal squadrons of Urthona.” Line 15 on page 95
                        would follow on quite well from this point as the beginning of the seventh
                        Night: 
						<q> 
						But in the Deeps beneath the <hi rend="i">tree</hi>
						&lt;Roots&gt; of Mystery in darkest night<lb/>
						When Urizen sat on his rock the Shadow brooded I <hi rend="i">dismal</hi><lb/>
						Urizen saw &amp; triumphd &amp; he cried to <hi rend="i">the Shadowy female</hi> &lt;his warriors&gt;<lb/>
						The time of Prophecy is now revolvd &amp; all<lb/>
						This Universal Ornament is mine . . .<lb/>
						<lb/>
						(95:15-19)
                        </q>
                        The “Shadow” in line 16 was the
                        Shadowy female in the original context. If these lines followed from the end
                        of VI, however, “Shadow” would refer to the Spectre of Urthona,
                        who is called the “Shadow of Urthona” in 75:6, where the term was
                        altered from 
<pb id="p12-128" n="128"/> 
						“Shade of Urthona,”
                        possibly to emphasize this identification. It may have been at this stage
                        that Blake deleted the last surviving reference to the Shadowy female, in
                        line 17, and substituted “his warriors.” Urizen’s triumph
                        in lines 18 and 19 would thus be seen as the consequence of his victory over
                        Tharmas and the Spectre, and the chaotic warfare that follows would be seen
                        as a consequence of the confrontation at the end of VI. This may have been
                        the kind of transition Blake intended when he indicated that the seventh
                        Night began at 95:15.</p>
          <p>Blake’s instruction at the original beginning of VIIb clearly states
                        that “the following [i.e., 91:1 to 95:14] comes in at the end.”
                        This portion continues the description of the chaotic conflict (but without
                        featuring Los or Enitharmon) and shows how the Shadowy female, stretching
                        through the fallen world, creates the conditions necessary for Los’s
                        redemptive activity in the eighth Night, as the dead descend on her clouds
                        to form Satan. The portion ends with the description of the descent of the
                        dead, which would lead appropriately into VIII*, on the first page of which
                        there is a similar passage (99:24-26).</p>
          <p>The transposed halves of VIIb, then, would link effectively with both the end
                        of VI and the beginning of the eight Night, and when he added the
                        instructions to indicate the transposition, he may have intended to exclude
                        VIIa1 from the poem. This, however, was probably only a temporary measure,
                        for the lengthy revisions in VIIa (i.e. the addition of VIIa2) show that
                        Blake decided to keep the Night after all.</p>
          <figure n="BB209.1.98.MS.detail" rend="file" width="958" height="627">
            <head><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 98 (detail).</head>
          </figure>
          <p>Rather than abandon VIIa1, or further unbalance the poem by introducing the
                        two new long passages describing the enlightenment of Los and Enitharmon, he
                        may have decided to edit the new passages in a drastic way. The nine lines
                        which formed the first new ending to VIIa may have been designed as an
                        alternative to the longer ending. The lines give a brief summary of
                        Los’s union with the Spectre without introducing any new terminology:
                        Los does not respond to the doctrine of Self annihilation, but simply to the
                        Shadow of Enitharmon’s “tale of Urthona.” After the new
                        ending Blake wrote “The End of the Seventh Night” indicating that
                        he still thought of this as the seventh Night. The addition would therefore
                        supersede the instructions in VIIb, and might even imply that Blake had
                        decided to drop VIIb from the poem. The new ending would certainly introduce
                        an anomaly, as the Los of VIIb is almost an epitome of the “Domineering
                        Lust” which, in the new ending, he gives up. Perhaps he regarded the
                        new ending as a provisional measure, a concession to the new material he had
                        decided to exclude at this stage, written at a time when he had found no way
                        to reconcile the two seventh Nights.</p>
          <p>Of the second passage, designed for inclusion in the eighth Night, Blake
                        seems to have decided to introduce only a part at this stage—namely
                        the three passages describing the labors of Los and Enitharmon and the
                        weaving of a “Universal female form” identified as Jerusalem
                        (99:20 to 100:26, 101:35-36 and 103:32-39, 104:1-4). This is the culmination
                        of their redemptive labors, and relates their activity to the descent of
                        Christ, already described in the eighth Night. Lines 99:20-23, 
<pb id="p12-129" n="129"/>
						which as the manuscript now stands represent the
                        final stage in a gradual process of enlightenment, would have represented
                        the moment of enlightenment itself in the absence of the long additional
                        passages at the end of VIIa. All the references to “Ulro” in VIII*
                        are contained in the three passages describing the enlightened Los and
                        Enitharmon; Blake probably adopted the term at this stage. He also further
                        revised the central Christian sequence at this time, introducing first the
                        figure of Rahab (as the fragment page 145 shows), and then the song of the
                        females of Amalek which features Tirzah. At this stage, then, Blake’s
                        reading of the Old Testament began to influence the poem’s symbolism
                        more directly. Having introduced this song to the revised Christian
                        sequence, Blake transcribed VIII* on the proof-pages.</p>
          <p>The revision which in two stages transformed the original eighth Night into
                        VIII* reveals a growing tension between the wish to incorporate large
                        quantities of new material and the wish to preserve the poem’s
                        original structure; and there is evidence to suggest that Blake’s
                        symbolism was still developing rapidly when VIII* was composed. The song
                        which features Tirzah and the passage which introduces Rahab suggest that
                        Blake was trying to contain as concisely as possible a mythology which was
                        rapidly developing beyond the original myth of the poem. VIII* was not the
                        final product of this development, but represents an intermediate stage.</p>
          <p>Blake made two kinds of revisions to VIII*: (i) local modifications within
                        the original six leaves of the Night; (ii) additions contained on three
                        extra proof-leaves, pp. 111-12, 113-14 and 115-16. The three extra leaves
                        radically change the structure of the Night, but the first revisions to
                        VIII* were probably the local revisions designed to integrate more
                        satisfactorily the older and newer elements of the existing mythology,
                        without introducing any more new ideas. Three Christian additions in the
                        last section of VIII* have this function, updating part of the narrative
                        which contained no Christian references when it was copied out. At the
                        beginning of the Night an addition of twelve lines on page 99 describes the
                        double female form of the daughters of Beulah, mentioned in the first
                        addition at the end of IV. The narrative sequence was altered on pages 100
                        and 101, the passage 100:27-101:3 having a new context between lines 32 and
                        33 on page 101; and two additions on page 101 were probably made at this
                        time: a passage of five lines describing the appearance of Satan (written in
                        the margin without a guideline, but placed by Keynes and Erdman after
                        101:3), and five lines describing the labors of Los. The description of
                        Orc’s transformation into a jewelled serpent would now be followed by
                        the description of Urizen’s instruments of war, in which Urizen is
                        seen “Communing with the Serpent of Orc.” The rearrangement
                        restores to Urizen’s battle-signal something of its original
                        significance, for it is now seen to have special consequences, intensifying
                        the conflict which begins to take the form of Satan. The new sequence also
                        suggests that the epiphany of Satan is the culmination of Orc’s
                        transformation and of the sinister communion between Urizen and Orc. The
                        added lines describing Los’s redemptive labors, by which the dead are
                        humanized, emphasize the opposition between Los’s effort and
                        Urizen’s military campaign which causes the dead to degenerate into
                        the form of Satan.</p>
          <p>These revisions make better or wider use of ideas which were already present
                        in VIII*. However, Blake undertook another series of revisions designed to
                        integrate the figure of Rahab more successfully into the Night, which led
                        eventually to major alterations. In the description of the crucifixion in
                        VIII* the daughters of Amalek, Canaan, and Moab were identified as different
                        forms of Rahab, and Rahab herself was identified as Mystery (who had been
                        introduced as a simple personification in the ninth Night). An addition at
                        105:11-24 attempts to account for the appearance of Rahab in the poem:
                        “The Synagogue Created her from Fruit of Urizens tree”; and the
                        addition was subsequently extended by three-and-a-half lines which explain
                        that she was “hidden within / The bosom of Satan,” and that her
                        daughters are called Tirzah. Tirzah, who in VIII* had been introduced within
                        the song of the daughters of Amalek, now entered the main narrative, and her
                        relationship with Rahab was clarified. Other revisions probably made at
                        about the same time are the added line 105:13, which describes Vala hidden
                        in Satan’s bosom “as in an ark &amp; Curtains”; and, at
                        the foot of page 104, the last one-and-a-half lines, which were deleted and
                        replaced by a new account of the purpose of Christ’s incarnation:
                        “to Give his vegetated body / To be cut off &amp; separated that the
                        Spiritual body may be Reveald.” With these revisions Blake was
                        apparently preparing to introduce the description of Rahab’s epiphany
                        after the revelation of Christ’s spiritual body, which had been
                        included in the fragment page 145, but excluded from VIII*. It was probably
                        after he had made these additions that he erased the original Night ending
                        of VIII* and added a new passage (110:30-37) in which he seems to have been
                        working towards a climactic conclusion describing the final epiphany of
                        Rahab before the revealed Christ. The passage was not finished, but was
                        deleted and replaced by a shorter passage (110:38-41) in which Los takes
                        Christ’s body from the cross and places it “in a Sepulcher which
                        Los had hewn / For himself.” This action is repeated at the end of a
                        marginal addition on page 106 (7-16); and the new passage of thirteen lines
                        introduced on page 117, in the new beginning of the ninth Night, describes
                        how “Los &amp; Enitharmon builded Jerusalem weeping / Over the
                        Sepulcher &amp; over the Crucified body.” Both of these revisions were
                        probably made when Blake revised the ending of VIII*.</p>
          <p>Clearly, Rahab was becoming increasingly important in this series of local
                        additions. The new passages show how she managed to absorb the crucifixion
                        in a religion of mystery. Los, Enitharmon, and Jerusalem weep over the
                        sepulchre, and their misunderstanding of Christ’s death is
                        Rahab’s triumph. When Blake added the new ending on page 110 he had
                        still not introduced a description of Rahab’s epiphany, although
                        Jerusalem weeps 
<pb id="p12-130" n="130"/>
						over the sepulchre “two
                        thousand years,” suggesting a relationship between Rahab’s
                        triumph and contemporary history. This relationship is brought into focus in
                        the text of the added page 111. After explaining that St. John understood
                        the immediate absorption of Christ’s death into a religion of
                        mystery, the passage describes the rise of Natural Religion after the
                        Synagogue of Satan had resolved to burn Mystery: 
						<q>
							The Ashes of Mystery began to animate they calld it Deism<lb/>
                            And Natural Religion as of old so now anew began<lb/>
                            Babylon again in Infancy Calld Natural Religion.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            (111:22-24)
                        </q>
						This satanic second coming provides
                        the logical conclusion to the series of local additions made to VIII*, for
                        it is the final consolidation of error, the final epiphany of Rahab, and the
                        passage may have been added shortly after Blake made the final additions on
                        pages 110 and 117. The references to “Ahania weeping on the Void”
                        and to Enion speaking “from the Caverns of the Grave” indicate
                        that this text was designed for the end of the eighth Night, and when he
                        composed it Blake may have intended to add it at the foot of page 110 after
                        the second Night ending. He chose instead to transcribe it on a separate
                        leaf, the leaf which may originally have been intended for the end of VIIa
                        (the engraving of the sorrowful, pierced Christ on the recto of the leaf
                        would make an appropriate illustration for a text which describes how
                        Christ’s death was mis-interpreted). The text was first
                        pencilled—possibly Blake was hesitant about using up a near-exhausted
                        stock of proof-leaves for revisions of this kind-then it was inked, but
                        without a new Night ending at the foot of the page. By this time he had
                        added almost eighty new lines to VIII*, and the night now had seven leaves.
                        There would be little reason now not to include material which had
                        previously been exluded on grounds of economy in deference to the
                        poem’s structure. When page 111 was written he may have omitted a new
                        night ending because he intended, or felt that he might need, to add more
                        new material at the end of the Night. For some time the pressure of new
                        material had been gradually eroding the poem’s structure. At this
                        point it seems that Blake opened the flood-gates, and the original structure
                        was overwhelmed.</p>
          <p>In the manuscript as it now stands, the texts of pages 113-116 have been
                        interpolated into the eighth Night at two points: 113:1-39 is inserted on
                        page 104, in the song of the Sons of Eden; and 113:40-116:6 is inserted on
                        page 106 after the description of the crucifixion. Both passages have been
                        modified to suit their present contexts. The text on page 113 originally
                        began with an invocation to Blake’s muse, “Daughter of Beulah
                        describe . . . ,” but this was subsequently changed to “We behold
                        with wonder” so that the narrative could become part of the song of the
                        Sons of Eden. The added line 24 beginning “We look down into Ulro . . . ”
                        and the alteration in line 33 have the same effect. An ink line was
                        drawn after line 39, and the passage below the line was modified to
                        introduce Rahab, while on page 115 the third-person description in the basic
                        text was altered to become part of Los’s speech to Rahab. Before
                        these changes were made pages 113 and 115 may have formed a single
                        narrative, but it would have been a passage unlike the narrative of the rest
                        of the poem: it would have been a digression amplifying the main narrative
                        by providing an historical perspective. The description of the geography of
                        Golgonooza and Udan Adan, and the myth of Rintrah, Palamabron, and Satan
                        seem to be the result of independent experiments rather than developments
                        designed for a specific context in the poem. The pages have more lines of
                        text than any of the other proof-leaves used in the manuscript, which again
                        suggests that Blake’s stock of proofleaves was dwindling. Page 114
                        has a full-page engraving of the risen Christ, and page 116 has a full-page
                        drawing which may represent the risen Man. The illustrations may indicate
                        that the narrative was originally intended for the end of the eighth Night,
                        but as there is no Night ending on page 115, the pages may have been
                        interpolated in the rest of the Night shortly after they were
                        transcribed.</p>
          <p>Blake interpolated the pages by modifying the passages as we have said; by
                        adding a marginal direction after 104:10, “We behold with wonder
                        &amp;c,” to indicate where 113:1-39 should be inserted; by adding a
                        note after the six lines at the top of page 116, “Darkness &amp;
                        sorrow &amp;c turn over leaf”; and by adding after 106:16 the
                        instruction, “But when Rahab &amp;c turn back 3 leaves.” This
                        marked another departure from the regularity of the manuscript. Not only was
                        the length of the eighth Night further increased, but the leaves of the
                        manuscript were no longer in a strictly sequential order. In other words, at
                        this stage the manuscript was beginning to look more like a rough draft than
                        a fair copy. There would be little reason now not to make any other major
                        alterations that seemed necessary by annotating existing leaves instead of
                        recopying the revised text; and there would be little reason not to include
                        material previously excluded to preserve the shape of the poem. In short,
                        there would be little reason to exclude the full account of Los’s
                        enlightenment, and Blake probably decided to introduce this material after
                        he had added pages 113-16.</p>
          <p>He seems to have used up his last <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> proofs in
                        pages 113-16, for to accommodate the new material about Los he had to cut a
                        large print of <hi rend="i">Edward &amp; Elenor</hi> in two. When he used
                        these sheets he may still have intended to introduce the account of
                        Los’s enlightenment as two separate passages. Erdman notes that
                        “90:1 is probably an addition, the text originally starting within the
                        platemark”—and it is this line that now links the narratives of
                        pages 87 and 90. Line 90:2 originally began “Los stood in Golgonooza 
                        . . . ” and between lines 1 and 2 on page 100 in the eighth Night a
                        marginal note, “Los stood &amp;c,” calls for an insertion which,
                        as Erdman notes, “probably refer[s] to 90:2 before revision.”
                        Erdman concludes that “Blake wrote the 
<pb id="p12-131" n="131"/>
<figure n="BB209.1.116.MS" rend="file" width="772" height="1000">
	<head><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 116.</head>
</figure>
<pb id="p12-132" n="132"/>
<figure n="BB209.1.111.MS" rend="file" width="786" height="1000">
	<head><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 115.</head>
</figure> 
						two pages 87 and 90 as a sequence, considered using the second
                        page as a second page for Night VIII (i.e. inserting it on p 100), but then
                        chose to tighten the sequence (with additions at the bottom of 87 and top of
                        90) and insert it (unquestionably a late addition) at the end of
                        VII.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n85" type="note">24</ref>
                        However, when Blake
                        added 90:1 he may have been creating rather than tightening a sequence, and
                        as originally transcribed page 90 may have been intended as an addition to
                        the eighth Night, to be interpolated like pp. 113, 115, and 116. (The
                        reference to Rintrah and Palamabron in 90:45-58 may have been introduced as
                        the page was transcribed to account for the appearance of these characters
                        in the myth described on page 115.) <note id="n85"><hi rend="s">24</hi>
                            Erdman, <hi rend="i">Poetry and Prose</hi>, p. 758.</note></p>
          <p>We have seen that although VIIb seems to follow logically from the end of
                        VIIal, the scenes describing the tension between Los and Enitharmon would
                        seem completely out of place if made to follow an account of their
                        enlightened reunion. This may be why the description of the reunion on page
                        90 was originally designed for inclusion in the eighth Night. When Blake
                        moved page 90 from VIII to the end of VIIa, he must have felt that he had
                        overcome this problem. Presumably, when he moved the page, he had decided to
                        drop VIIb from the poem, thus removing the anomaly.</p>
          <p>As we have seen, he may have considered removing VIIb earlier, when he added
                        the first new ending of nine lines to VIIa. But the fact that VIIb has
                        survived in the manuscript suggests that Blake was never finally committed
                        to excluding it, although he left no indication of how the Night should be
                        fitted into the poem. However, as VIIb had been rearranged so that the
                        second half (95:15-98:31) would follow on directly from VI, and the first
                        half (91:1-95:14) would lead into the eighth Night, it is possible to
                        conflate the two versions of the seventh Night simply by inserting the whole
                        of VIIa between the transposed halves of VIIb. The scenes describing the
                        tension between Los and Enitharmon would thus be placed in a context which
                        would allow a relatively coherent narrative sequence to develop, describing
                        a steady progress in the relationship of Los and Enitharmon, from disharmony
                        to unity.</p>
          <p>We have already seen how the transition from VI to 95:15 would work. The new
                        beginning of the seventh Night would describe Urizen’s initial
                        triumph over Tharmas and the Spectre (following their confrontation at the
                        end of VI), the preparations for Urizen’s Universal Empire, Los and
                        Tharmas rallying to the battle, the consequent degeneration of Los’s
                        relationship with Enitharmon, and the universal conflict of the natural
                        world: 
						<q>
							sullen the wooly sheep<lb/>
							Walks thro the battle Dark &amp; fierce the Bull his rage<lb/>
							Propagates thro the warring Earth the Lion raging in flames<lb/>
							The Tyger in redounding smoke.<lb/>
							<lb/>
                            (98:17-20)
                        </q>
                        The transition from this part of VIIb to the beginning
                        of VIIa would be assisted by the similarities between the lines above and
                        77:6-9. Urizen, having conducted his preparations while sitting on a rock
                        (95:16) now rises, causing Tharmas and the Spectre to flee once more.
                        Leaving the battle, Urizen descends to the caves of Orc. After the
                        confrontation with Orc, the narrative focuses on the disordered relationship
                        of Los and Enitharmon. Vala is reborn, and is given charge over the howling
                        Orc, an event which underlines the urgency of the problem of
                        Urthona’s divided personality. On page 87 the narrative continues
                        with an account of Los’s reunion first with the Spectre and then with
                        Enitharmon. After the reconciliation (on page 90), which sets another part
                        of the scheme of redemption in motion, the narrative would return to the
                        confrontation between Vala and Orc, prepared for in 85:22. VIIb pages 91-95
                        would follow effectively from the end of VIIa2. On page 90 Tharmas is
                        heartened by the first signs of recovery: 
						<q>
							But Tharmas most rejoicd in hope of Enions return<lb/>
							For he beheld new Female forms born forth upon the air<lb/>
							<lb/>
							(90:55-56)
						</q>
						But in pages 91-95, after Vala
                        has embraced Orc she mocks this hope and attempts to deceive Tharmas
                        (94:12-23), while the Dead descend upon her clouds and begin to take up the
                        form of Satan, thus preparing for the epiphany of Satan in the eighth
                        Night.</p>
          <pb id="p12-133" n="133"/>
          <p>This arrangement produces a seventh Night of about 790 lines, compared with
                        about 620 in the eighth Night and about 850 in the ninth Night. The total
                        sequence is inevitably rather disjointed, but Blake had used a comparable
                        patchwork method when composing VIIb and VIII. Furthermore, the arrangement
                        tends to reduce serious anomalies in the text rather than create them.</p>
          <p>It seems that here, as elsewhere in the poem, Blake did not finally complete
                        his revisions. We have no authority for this textual arrangement, but
                        neither do we have authority to exclude VIIb from the poem. As I said at the
                        beginning of this article, the problem compels editorial choice of an
                        uncomfortable kind. I suggest we adopt an arrangement which includes all the
                        available material necessary for a full understanding of the poem, and which
                        introduces order to the narrative.</p>
			  <figure n="BB209.1.82.MS.detail" rend="file" width="958" height="423">
				<head><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 82 (detail).</head>
			  </figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
