<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>12.2.kilgore</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The Order of Nights VIIa and VIIb in Blake’s The Four Zoas</title>
        <author n="Kilgore">John Kilgore</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">12.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Special Design and Pasteup for this issue</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Everett Frost</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Terrence Hoagwood</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John Kilgore</name>
              <name>Mark Lefebvre</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Cettina Magno</name>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <name>Jeffry Spencer</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_12">
    <body>
      <pb id="p12-107" n="107"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-12-2-0010">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">THE ORDER OF NIGHTS VIIa AND VIIb IN BLAKE’S <hi rend="i">THE FOUR ZOAS</hi></hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">JOHN</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">KILGORE</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>The presence of two seventh Nights in the perplexing manuscript of Blake’s
                        <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is a scholarly puzzle which has two
                    theoretically distinguishable aspects. First there is the editorial problem of
                    finding the least imperfect arrangement of the two Nights within the text of the
                    poem; then there is the interpretive problem of deciding what imaginative place
                    each Night has in the poem as a whole. The two problems really overlap, of
                    course, for critical issues arise in editorial debate as “internal
                    evidence,” and responsible interpretation must be consistent with a factual
                    understanding of the manuscript. Even from a primarily interpretive standpoint,
                    moreover, it is occasionally more illuminating to sift through the hectic
                    evidence of Blake’s deletions, additions, and revisions in <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi> than to treat the present text as if it were a fully
                    intentional work. The study of the manuscript can itself become a kind of
                    interpretation, for part of the significance of the poem resides in the story of
                    artistic growth and struggle which the manuscript obliquely reveals.</p>
        <p>Yet there has been a certain tendency to divorce textual scholarship from
                    critical interpretation in the study of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, and in
                    the debate over the VIIa-VIIb problem in particular.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">1</ref> In its commitment to a synoptic overview of
                    Blake’s entire canon, its preoccupation with the basic structural
                    principles of his symbolic system, what one may call the main critical tradition
                    in modern Blake studies has had very little to say about the manuscript of 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> Prior to David Wagenknecht’s fairly
                    recent discussion of the two Nights seven in <hi rend="i">Blake’s Night:
                        William Blake and the Idea of Pastoral</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n44" type="note">2</ref> there had been to my knowledge no really detailed critical
                    examination of internal evidence bearing on the problem. On the other side,
                    Blake’s editors have been equally reluctant to become “readers”
                    in the Damon-Frye tradition, preferring either to remain within the precincts of
                    textual scholarship, or to employ such alternative critical methods as
                    Erdman’s “historical approach.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45"
type="note">3</ref> In some ways, no doubt, this division of perspectives is desirable;
                    yet it has probably lent some obscurity to the problem of the Nights seven, and
                    to the poem as a whole, which is not purely Blake’s own. In what follows
                    I try to give a systematic account of the critical and editorial alternatives
                    associated with the VIIa-VIIb problem, synthesizing previous arguments and
                    adding a number of observations based on my own reading of the poem. 
                    <note id="n43"><hi rend="s">1</hi> An exception to this general tendency is
                            Morton Paley’s <hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination: the
                                Development of Blake’s Thought</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon,
                            1970), chapter 6. See pp. 160-61 and 263 for vary succinct discussions
                            of the ambiguity of the two Nights seven. A similar approach is taken by
                            E. D. Hirsch, Jr., in <hi rend="i">Innocence and Experience: An
                                Introduction to Blake</hi> (New Haven: Yale Univ. Press, 1964),
                            chapter 7. In emphasizing the changes and inconsistencies involved in
                            Blake’s “development,” however, both studies tend to
                            exclude any sense of final coherence in the structure of the poem.
                        <p>All references to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> are from David V.
                            Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>,
                            4th ed., rev. (Garden City: Doubleday, 1956).</p></note>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Cambridge, Mass.: The Belknap Press of the
                        Harvard Univ. Press, 1973. See pp. 225-26, 298-302, and for a critical
                        reading which takes textual problems into account, pp. 210-50, 
<hi rend="i">passim.</hi> In much of what follows I am indebted to
                        Wagenknecht.</note>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">3</hi> David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet
                            Against Empire</hi>, 2nd ed. (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1969).
                        See pp. 293-96 for Erdman’s description of his method as applied to
                            <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></note></p>
        <p>Both Nights are headed “Vala / Night the Seventh” and VIIb contains in
                    addition a marginal note, “Beginning of Night VII,” and an interlinear
                    note, “Beginning of the Seventh Night,” both inserted at line 153
                    after Blake decided to change the internal order of the Night. “End of the
                    Seventh Night” is written at the end of VIIb, and the same phrase occurred
                    after the last line of VIIa at two or possibly three different stages of
                    revision, but Blake erased it each time to add new material, and after his
                    latest additions he did not replace it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n46" type="note">4</ref> All
                    the leaves of VIIa except the last three bear stitch-marks which indicate that
                    at one time the Night was bound up in a grouping which included most of the
                    present Night III and all of IV, V, and VI; the unstitched leaves were
                    presumably added after Blake had unbound the others. The fact that VIIb bears no
                    stitch-marks indicates that it, like Nights VIII and IX and the added leaves of
                    VIIa, was never bound. <note id="n46"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See G. E. Bentley,
                        Jr., <hi rend="i">William Blake: Vala or The Four Zoas: A Facsimile of the
                            Manuscript, a Transcript of the Poem, and a Study of Its Growth and
                            Significance</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1963), p. 162 col. 2. I am, of
                        course, indebted to Bentley throughout.</note></p>
        <p>The traditional explanation of the rival Nights is that Blake wrote VIIb first,
                    later grew dissatisfied and wrote VIIa to replace it, and then simply failed to
                    decide what should be done with VIIb. Thus in Erdman’s text VIIa is
                    printed in sequence, on the supposition that it represents Blake’s later
                    and more definitive thoughts on what should happen at this point in the poem,
                    while 
<pb id="p12-108" n="108"/>
VIIb is printed as an appendix after Night IX.
                    The critical tradition which has grown up around the assumption that VIIa is a
                    later “version” of VIIb interprets Blake’s need to rewrite the
                    earlier Night as the symptom of an imaginative crisis, and thus looks to one or
                    both Nights for some definitive turning point in the growth of the poem and the
                    development of Blake’s vision. Frye, for instance, associates the textual
                    problem with Blake’s invention of the Spectre of Urthona: “The
                    conception of the Spectre of Urthona seems to have broken on Blake quite
                    suddenly when he was proceeding to a simpler climax, and occasioned the
                    rewriting of Night VII . . . . Eventually it burst the whole Zoa scheme
                    altogether, and was one of the chief reasons for abandoning the poem.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Northrop Frye, <hi rend="i">Fearful
                            Symmetry</hi> (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1947), p.
                    298.</note></p>
        <p>This account of the poem’s growth sounds persuasive, but more recent
                    scholarship has severely questioned the assumption on which it is based, namely
                    that VIIb preceded VIIa. Wagenknecht describes the emergence of the alternative
                    view of the problem: 
					<q> In 1956 . . . H. M. Margoliouth, in his edition of 
<hi rend="i">Vala</hi> . . . reminded scholars that, except for obviously
                        late additions, the narrative of VIIa flows continuously into VIIb. This
                        fact of course hinted that the long-held assumption that VIIb was composed
                        prior to VIIa needed to be reexamined, as did the idea fostered by received
                        opinion that the two versions were somehow thematically opposed to each
                        other. . . . Margoliouth’s hint was developed into a death knell for
                        received opinion by G. E. Bentley’s facsimile edition of the poem,
                        which demonstrated conclusively on the basis of stitch marks on the
                        manuscript that VIIb—as VIII and IX—had to be considered later
                        than VIIa.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Wagenknecht, p. 226.</note></q>
The implication here is that the two
Nights were never alternate
                    “versions” at all, but simply two Nights written in sequence, with
                    VIIa coming first; and that Blake gave both of them the number seven because,
                    when he came to transcribe VIIb, he realized that he needed more than three
                    Nights to finish his poem, and so must fit I-VIIa into six Nights.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">7</ref> In other words, VIIb was originally
                    intended as part or all of a Night VIII, but had to be changed into a Night VII;
                    the original Night VII, i.e. VIIa, had to be squeezed back into the preceding
                    Nights. <note id="n49"><hi rend="s">7</hi> See H. M. Margoliouth, ed., 
<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Vala: Blake’s Numbered Text</hi>
                        (Oxford: Clarendon, 1956), p. xiii. Cf. Bentley, p. 163, cols.
                    1-2.</note></p>
        <p>It should be noted, however, that Erdman does not find Bentley’s dating of
                    VIIb conclusive at all,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50"
type="note">8</ref> but argues that
                    Blake may have omitted it from the stitched grouping of Nights III-VIIa, not
                    because it was later (i.e., as yet unwritten), but because Blake had already
                    replaced it by the time he bound up the other Nights. This is not impossible,
                    but the hypothesis by itself is not more convincing than Bentley’s
                    simpler assumption that all of the unstitched Nights (VIIb, VIII, and IX) are
                    later than VIIa, and it fails to account either for the narrative continuity of
                    VIIa-VIIb, or for the use in VIIb of symbolic names which crept into the poem
                    only at a late stage of revision (Bentley, 171 col. 2). <note id="n50"><hi rend="s">8</hi>
Nor, apparently, does W. H. Stevenson, editor of the
                            Longman’s Annotated Edition of <hi rend="i">The Poems of William
                                Blake</hi> (London, 1971). On p. 371 Stevenson asserts that VIIb
                            “as a whole was undoubtedly written earlier . . . [and] rejected by
                            Blake.” But I find Stevenson’s overall position rather
                            confusing and equivocal. If he believes that VIIb was
                            “undoubtedly” written earlier and rejected, why does he print
                            the text VIIa-VIIb, and indicate in his notes (371) that “a
                            continuity in the narrative” justifies this order? This treatment
                            of the text corresponds to the view that VIIb is neither earlier nor
                            rejected; and Stevenson hardly clarifies matters by remarking that
                            “the first part of VIIa . . . appears to belong to the same date as
                            VIIb” (371). My suspicion is that Stevenson really subscribes to
                            essentially the view I give—that the Nights were originally
                            written VIIa-VIIb, with the present ending of VIIa coming
                            later—but has preferred to avoid controversy by not saying so in
                            unmistakably clear terms.
                        <p>Alicia Ostriker sides with Erdman in <hi rend="i">William Blake: The
                                Complete Poems</hi> (New York: Penguin, 1977), p.
                    945.</p></note></p>
        <p>In short, though no really definitive evidence is available, it seems fairly
                    clear that VIIa was composed before VIIb. Composed, that is, <hi rend="i">in
                        some form</hi>: for the conclusion does not apply to the last three leaves
                    of VIIa, which are unstitched and contain “obviously late additions”
                    to the original Night (we will consider the significance of this fact in a
                    moment). Margoliouth’s demonstration of the original narrative continuity
                    of VIIa-VIIb remains the most important piece of evidence supporting the newer
                    theory of the Nights seven, so it is worth glancing at this juncture in the text
                    of his <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>:
<q> . . . the immortal shadow shuddering<lb/>
                        Brought forth this wonder horrible [Vala] a Cloud she grew &amp; grew<lb/>
                        Till many of the dead burst forth from the bottoms of their tombs<lb/>
 The
                        Spectre smild &amp; gave her Charge over the howling Orc<lb/>
<lb/>
 End of
                        the Seventh Night<lb/>
 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
<lb/>
                        VALA<lb/>
<lb/>
 Night the Seventh<lb/>
<lb/>
 Now in the Caverns of the Grave
                        and Places of human seed<lb/>
 The nameless shadowy Vortex stood before the
                        face of Orc<lb/>
 The shadow reard her dismal head over the flaming
                        youth<lb/>
 With sighs &amp; howling &amp; deep sobs that he might lose his
                        rage<lb/>
 And with it lose himself in meekness she embracd his
                        fire<lb/>
<lb/>
 (Margoliouth, 45-46) </q>
In the original ending of VIIa, the
                    Shadow of Enitharmon, having coupled with the Spectre of Urthona, gives birth to
                    Vala, whom the Spectre then sets as a guard over Orc. At the original beginning
                    of VIIb, Vala obediently stands on guard duty, and then embraces Orc, much as in
                    the <hi rend="i">Preludium</hi> to America. In default of more conclusive
                    evidence, the continuity of the narrative is a persuasive demonstration that at
                    an early stage of the poem’s development VIIa came first and VIIb second.
                    The argument can be reinforced by other, similar observations. In VIIa Urizen,
                    arriving in the Caves of Orc after his journey through chaos, “took his
                    seat upon a rock” (77:18); in VIIb we find him still seated there (95:16).
                    In VIIa Urizen proceeds to create the precondition of war by enslaving Orc (for
                    “War is Energy enslav’d”); in VIIb there is war. In VIIa
                    Enitharmon tells the Spectre of her fear that Orc may rend her “to the
                    winds of heaven” (82:38) and her hope that he will rend Vala instead
                    (83:34); in VIIb Orc does rend Vala (93:21), and Enitharmon’s fear for
                    herself reaches a climax in her “Watchman” speech (97:28ff.).
                    Likewise, early in VIIa (78:4), Blake describes the Tree of Mystery in a way
                    which strongly suggests that he is using the symbol for the first time; there
                    have been no previous references in Nights I-VI, and the more cryptic allusions
                    to 
<pb id="p12-109" n="109"/>
the Tree in VIIb seem to presuppose the passage in
                    VIIa.</p>
        <p>This evidence of an original VIIa-VIIb order is further strengthened by the fact
                    that Night VI is continuous with VIIa but not VIIb. Placed at the end of VI,
                    either the original or the revised version of VIIb would produce a bewildering
                    non sequitur. By contrast, VI-VIIa is a clear sequence. Night VI ends with a
                    confrontation between Urizen, Tharmas, and the Spectre of Urthona; VIIa begins,
                    “Then Urizen arose the Spectre fled &amp; Tharmas fled.” It is rather
                    hard to doubt that Blake conceived and wrote this transition all at once.</p>
        <p>Again, the attempt to think of VIIa as a “replacement” for VIIb becomes
                    very difficult when one notices how greatly the two differ in content. There is
                    virtually nothing in either the original or the added passages of VIIb to
                    indicate that the Night was an early model of VIIa. Given Blake’s usual
                    habits of composition, the traditional account of the two Nights would lead us
                    to expect an exceedingly complex entanglement of VIIa and VIIb, or perhaps a
                    single palimpsest. Instead, we have two clearly separate Nights, involving
                    largely different events and characters.</p>
        <p>Clearly, then, we ought to abandon the idea that VIIa was originally written to
                    replace an earlier VIIb, an idea which no substantive comparison of the two
                    Nights will support. But this is far from being the end of the story, for Blake
                    made major changes in both Nights as <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> turned into <hi rend="i">The
Four Zoas.</hi> To VIIa he added a few small passages and then
                    the long section of pp. 85-90, one of the crucial episodes of the present poem.
                    He appears to have made few major additions to VIIb, but he left three notes
                    directing that the first 153 lines be moved to the end, thus reversing the order
                    of the two main episodes of the Night (Erdman, 762). These revisions so
                    thoroughly undermine the original narrative continuity of VIIa-VIIb, and raise
                    such doubts concerning Blake’s ultimate intentions, that the editor of
                        <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> finds his basic problem still unsolved
                    despite the discovery of the <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> sequence. If the order of
                    the original Nights was clear enough, the order of the present Nights is not; it
                    is, in effect, a separate question.</p>
        <p>There is no real possibility of reading VIIb first and then VIIa; but once the
                    added passages of VIIa are taken into account, the opposite sequence becomes
                    equally unsatisfactory. It is clear enough why such critics as J. Middleton
                    Murry, Northrop Frye, and Harold Bloom, once persuaded that it was necessary to
                    choose between the two Nights, should be eager to believe that VIIa was the
                    later and authoritative version. For in the present VIIa we have not only the
                    great dramatic confrontation of Orc and Urizen, but the climactic 
<hi rend="i">rapprochement</hi> between Los, his Spectre, and Enitharmon. The latter
                    event in particular, which takes place entirely in the added passages, provides
                    a crucial link in Blake’s myth. Prior to VIIa, Los is a merely natural
                    imagination, a formidable but basically inhuman demiurge. He is often called a
                    “demon” and a “terror,” and he has helped Urizen to enslave
                    Luvah and later Orc. Up to this point all his creations have been
                    semi-instinctive, <hi rend="i">ad hoc</hi> responses to the fallen state, and
                    the remainder of his energy has been spent in lovers’ quarrels with
                    Enitharmon. But the sequence of events which begins with the Spectre of
                    Urthona’s seduction of Enitharmon (84-86) works a profound change in Los.
                    By embracing Enitharmon, the Spectre gains the power to “enter Los’s
                    bosom,” and then is embraced in his turn by Los, “first as a brother /
                    Then as another Self.” Under the force of the Spectre’s
                    “inspired” persuasion, Los suddenly feels “A World within /
                    Opening its gates” and vows to “teach / Peace to the Soul of dark
                    revenge &amp; repentance to Cruelty.” It is at this point that we hear,
                    for the very first time in all Blake’s works, of the necessity of
                    “Self-Annihilation”—henceforth one of Blake’s two or
                    three most important themes.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51"
type="note">9</ref> The new
                    alliance and new vision lead directly to the discovery of Los’s true
                    mission: he will progressively reconstruct the fallen Albion, first by weaving
                    “bodies” for the “Spectres of the Dead,” then by creating
                    “forms sublime” which the spectres can assimilate into (87:36-39
                    &amp; 90:15-25). The Spectre of Urthona changes at this point from a
                    “ravning” Selfhood to a helpful “medium,” and Enitharmon,
                    still more dramatically, from an aberrant Female Will into a loving source of
                    creative inspiration. Finally, in a fitting climax to these climaxes, the
                    three-way alliance manages to regenerate and redeem the fallen Urizen. 
<note id="n51"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Concordance, p. 1654.</note></p>
        <p>Thus the extraordinary added passages on pp. 85-90 point the way, not only to the
                    apocalypse of Night IX, but to the central myths and themes of Blake’s
                    two subsequent epics. Given the importance of the Los-Spectre relationship in
                        <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, and of the weaving of bodies in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>,
one gets the impression that in these pages of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> Blake achieved an imaginative
breakthrough which
                    profoundly affected his conception of the later poems—unless, indeed, it
                    was his work on the later poems which showed him how to solve his problems with
                        <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> It is understandable, then, that critics
                    should find VIIa more faithful to the spirit of Blake’s mature vision
                    than VIIb, and should therefore be reluctant to surrender the traditional view
                    of the problem. The tendency can be observed in Harold Bloom’s discussion
                    of the Nights seven in the Erdman edition of Blake: 
					<q> The two sections of
                        Night VII are alternate ways of preparing for the blackness of Night VIII
                        and the liberation of Night IX. I find it difficult to believe that VIIa is
                        not the later in composition, but in this belief I am guided only by what I
                        take to be internal evidence. Whichever was later, our understanding of the
                        poem’s total design can only benefit by a study of both versions. I
                        do not think it accurate (or fair to the poem) to read Nights VIIa and VIIb
                        as being an intentional sequence, in that order. VIIa in at least some
                        respects is an imaginative advance on VIIb.<lb/>
<lb/>
 (Erdman, 876) </q>
One
                    cannot fault Bloom’s sense that VIIb makes an 
<pb id="p12-110" n="110"/>
                    unsatisfactory sequel to the present VIIa; for in VIIb we confront the old Los
                    again, a warrior Los with “his knees / Bathed in bloody clouds. his loins
                    in fires of war where spears / And swords rage . . . ” (96:21).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">10</ref> Similarly, Tharmas, Orc, and Urizen, all
                    of whom have been partially rehabilitated in the triumphant reconciliations of
                    VIIa, reappear in VIIb, without explanation, in more primitive stages of fall.
                    As a sequel to the present VIIa, then, VIIb would give us at best a very sour
                    irony, sufficient to undercut the new ending of VIIa, and with it the
                    justification for the poem’s apocalyptic conclusion.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53" type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Similarly, Stevenson notes that in VIIb,
                        “The regeneration of Los and Enitharmon is ignored,” p. 389. Cf.
                        Margoliouth, p. 144, and Paley, p. 161.</note>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Of course Night VIII is a war Night too; but
                        here the battle scenes are matched in stirring counterpoint to scenes which
                        depict Los’s mighty efforts to resist the forces of fall, so that the
                        outlook is not nearly so bleak as in VIIb. On the whole, the tone of VIII
                        seems to me one of breathtaking suspense tending strongly toward
                        optimism.</note></p>
        <p>Moreover, the present VIIa tallies fairly well with Night VIII, while VIIb does
                    not. At the beginning of VIII we have a “Council of God”
                    passage—one of Blake’s favorite setpieces—and then Los and
                    Enitharmon in effect resume the conversation they have been having near the end
                    of VIIa: 
					<q> Then Los said I behold the Divine Vision thro the broken Gates<lb/>
                        Of thy poor broken heart astonishd melted into Compassion &amp; Love<lb/>
                        And Enitharmon said I see the Lamb of God upon Mount Zion<lb/>
 Wondring with
                        love &amp; Awe they felt the divine hand upon them<lb/>
<lb/>
 (VIII, 99:15;
                        cf. VIIa, 86:44-60) </q>
References to the apocalyptic mission quickly
                    follow, with Enitharmon once again “sighing forth” the spectres and
                    Los “recieving them into his hands” (99:23-100:2; cf. VIIa, 90:35-67).
                    Late additions throughout Night VIII continue to develop the same theme (cf. p.
                    113), supporting the conclusion that Blake was assuming the final version of
                    VIIa as the immediately preceding Night. One could, conceivably, make a similar
                    argument for the continuity of VIIb (in the revised sequence) and Night VIII, on
                    the basis that the spectres of the dead descend from Beulah at both 95:11 and
                    99:19. But the spectres also descend late in VIIa (85:18), and on the whole a
                    VIIb-VIII sequence would present an inexplicable shift from sardonic gloom to
                    prophetic hope. The Los and Enitharmon of VIII are unmistakably the prophetic
                    figures who emerge at the end of the revised VIIa; they have little in common
                    with the savage Los and hysterical Enitharmon of VIIb.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n54"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Erdman, p. 758, offers a rather curious
                        argument to show that the two Nights were closely joined at a 
<hi rend="i">previous</hi> stage of composition. He theorizes that the marginal note
                        Blake left on page 100, calling for the insertion of a passage beginning
                        “Los stood” between 100:1 and 100:2, refers to most of page
                        90—i.e., basically to the present ending of VIIa—but that
                        Blake later changed his mind and left the passage on 90 in its present
                        position. His conclusion is that “this bit of masonry” (the
                        provisional insertion of 90 into 100) “which cements VIIa closely to
                        VIII, seems to indicate a time when Blake considered VIIb as abandoned (or
                        moved).” Wagenknecht reviews the argument on pp. 298-300; I agree with
                        his conclusion that Erdman’s theory about pages 90 and 100 is
                        “extremely suppositious . . . on the basis of physical evidence
                        alone,” and also improbable for stylistic and thematic reasons. But
                        unless I misread, Erdman’s conclusion still stands, for the different
                        and much more obvious reason that VIIa in its present state is <hi rend="i">still</hi>
“cemented closely” to VIII. Cf. Paley, p.
                        161.</note></p>
        <p>It seems, then, that at a late stage of revision Blake decided to route the poem
                    around VIIb. This means that the traditional account of the two Nights may not
                    be so far mistaken after all. Nothing says that Blake had to write VIIb first in
                    order to be dissatisfied with it, or VIIa second in order to prefer it if a
                    choice had to be made. It is quite possible that he first wrote both Nights (as
                    consecutive rather than alternate episodes), next started feeling that his
                    approach to apocalypse was unsatisfactory, and then saw that his best opening
                    for a more suitable approach could be found in the earlier VIIa. Once he had
                    made his changes in VIIa, he would have found that VIIb no longer fit as a
                    sequel; since at this point he had ten Nights anyway, he might then have decided
                    to keep VIIa as Night VII (reversing his earlier decision to squeeze it back
                    into I-VI), revising Night VIII accordingly. Thus VIIa, though not originally a
                    replacement for VIIb, would have become one by the time Blake finished his
                    revisions.</p>
        <p>This theory would seemingly allow us to go on reading VIIb in the way it has
                    usually been read—as an alternate but rejected approach to Night
                    VIII—if we stipulated that VIIb’s previous niche is presently
                    filled by the added section of VIIa alone, rather than by the Night as a whole.
                    Once again, however, matters cannot be so simple. Blake was not a poet to delete
                    material he liked if he thought he could possibly find a place for it, and the
                    very fact that he kept VIIb together with the rest of his manuscript testifies
                    to his hope that it could somehow be reintegrated into the poem. Moreover,
                    though VIIb seems to be excluded by the VI-VIIa-VIII sequence upon which Blake
                    finally settled, its disentanglement from the other Nights is incomplete. For
                    instance, the references to war in the added passages of VIIa come quite
                    abruptly; when Los draws Urizen “from out the ranks of war,” it is
                    very difficult to tell just what war Blake is talking about.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">13</ref> Then on reflection one has to conclude that it is the
                    war described in VIIb. Of course the poem’s tendency to subvert linear
                    chronology should never be underestimated, and it is just possible that we are
                    dealing with a proleptic reference to the wars of Night VIII. Still, on the
                    whole the climactic turn toward peace, mercy, and art at the end of VIIa seems
                    more comprehensible if played against the backdrop of Orc’s violent
                    rising in VIIb. It is as if Blake, once having written VIIb, could not wholly
                    refrain from assuming it as a basis for his revisions to VIIa, or as if he
                    worked with the intention of later transplanting parts of VIIb into VIIa. 
<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">13</hi> There are four previous references to war in
                        VIIa, but these are brief and casual. Concordance, p. 2069.</note></p>
        <p>Wagenknecht offers a substantial demonstration of VIIb’s importance to
                    Blake’s overall argument (225ff.), and shows that Night VIII contains
                    back-references to VIIb as well as VIIa; his conclusion is that Blake left
                    “two integral, not alternative, Nights VII.” If Blake had suppressed
                    VIIb, perhaps no one would ever have noticed that it was missing; with the Night
                    before us, however, we see many things that the poem as a whole seems to need.
                    The very dramatic meeting between Tharmas and Vala brings Tharmas up to
                    date—he has been rather scarce since Night IV—and prepares for his
                    next appearance, in VIII. The emergence of Vala herself as a fully distinct
                    character obviously provides a crucial continuation to the story of her birth in
                    VIIa, and a prelude to her appearance as Rahab in the apocalypse. In some ways
                    her epiphany is redone in Night VIII, yet the later treatment is less full, and
                    can be better understood by the light of the earlier one.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">14</ref> For instance, the descent of the spectres,
                    “tempted by the Shadowy females sweet / Delusive cruelty” (VIII,
                    99:20), makes more sense if one has first read the exquisite description of
                    Vala’s beauty which Blake provides in VIIb. <note id="n56"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Cf.
especially 101:20ff: 
<q> . . . While the dark
                                shadowy female brooding over<lb/>
 Measurd his [Orc’s] food
                                morning &amp; evening in cups &amp; baskets of iron<lb/>
 With
                                tears of sorrow incessant she labourd the food of Orc<lb/>
 Compelld
                                by the iron hearted sisters Daughters of Urizen </q>
Here we have in
                            little the <hi rend="i">Preludium</hi> of America—and the
                            original beginning of VIIb—yet again. This could mean that Blake
                            was thinking of VIIb as abandoned, and was trying to sketch in one
                            portion of its contents which he considered vital. On the other hand,
                            the passage is brief enough to have been intended as a refrain or echo,
                            so it is equally possible that Balke was still committed to including
                            VIIb.
                    </note></p>
        <p>In sum, we have to regard VIIb as part of the poem, but there is no really
                    satisfactory way to fit it in. Blake left the Night as a unit, but as a unit it
                    resists placement anywhere in the present 
<pb id="p12-111" n="111"/>
text. It
                    seems that VIIb was originally designed to carry the poem all the way from the
                    birth of Vala to the brink of apocalypse—albeit a simpler apocalypse than
                    the one Blake finally imagined—and it has a cataclysmic finality which
                    makes it seem to belong—somewhere—late in the present Night
                        VIII.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">15</ref> Yet
its general pessimism and
                    the unregenerate state of its protagonists make VIIb seem to fit best into the
                    juncture between the old and new portions of VIIa, where it originally began. No
                    doubt this is the least unsatisfactory niche; still, VIIb rises to a climax of
                    its own which would throw the alternate climax of the revised VIIa off center.
                    In VIIb the apocalypse seems imminent; in VIIa it is not to come for another six
                    thousand years (87:26). In VIIb Tharmas and Vala seem destined to be key figures
                    in bringing about the final consummation; in VIIa they are supernumeraries.
                    Moreover, if restored to its original position, VIIb would interrupt the story
                    of Los’s reconciliation with his Spectre and Emanation, spoiling the
                    narrative rhythm of VIIa. It is certain that Blake himself, once he had
                    conceived of the regeneration of Los, preferred to avoid such interruption and
                    to pursue the narrative of VIIa directly to its present climax. 
<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">15</hi> In Margoliouth’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>,
                        the ending of VIIb in its original order is joined directly to the original
                        beginning of IX—so that VIIb is in effect the Night VIII of <hi rend="i">Vala.</hi>
I do not find this arrangement of the text quite
                        persuasive, even as representing an earlier state of the manuscript, but I
                        do agree with Margoliouth’s general sense (and with Bentley’s)
                        that the material of VIIb was originally conceived as part of the last Night
                        before the apocalypse. It is mainly the emphasis on climactic war (a
                        “signal of the dawn” for which Blake had the authority of 
<hi rend="i">Revelation</hi>) which persuades me of this. But by the time
                        Blake made the present transcript of VIIb, with the heading “Night the
                        Seventh,” another Night VIII must have existed.</note></p>
        <p>The puzzle grows still more perplexing when one tries to grasp Blake’s
                    reasons for changing the order of VIIb. It seems logical to suppose that the
                    change would have come after Blake had written the new ending of VIIa, since the
                    original continuity of VIIa-VIIb would already have been lost. If at this point
                    Blake was toying with the idea of a VIIa-VIIb-VIII sequence, the switch would
                    have the advantage of moving the descent of the spectres to the end, creating a
                    bridge between VIIb and VIII. Yet the corresponding transition from the new
                    ending of VIIa to the new beginning of VIIb seems quite wayward. At the end of
                    VIIa Urizen is an infant in Los’s arms; the reordered VIIb begins,
                    “But in the deeps beneath the Roots of Mystery in darkest night / Where
                    Urizen sat on his rock the Shadow brooded / Urizen saw &amp; triumphd &amp; he
                    cried to his warriors.” Of course, this is just enough of a non sequitur to
                    be possibly intentional—especially since Blake has noted at the end of
                    VIIa that Los was able to redeem all of Urizen <hi rend="i">except</hi>
                    “his Spectrous form which could not be drawn away” (90:60). The lines
                    take us back to that troublesome crossroads in the narrative, Vala’s
                    birth from the Shadow of Enitharmon, and it is this event rather than
                    Los’s regeneration—or this event together with a misconception of
                    what has happened to Los—which causes Urizen to triumph.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">16</ref> It seems just conceivable that Blake was trying to
                    rearrange VIIb in such a way that, having traced the consequences of the
                    Enitharmon-Spectre union in the upper world of Los, the narrative now backtracks
                    and begins to trace the consequences of the union in the lower world of the
                    spectrous Urizen. Yet such a change, supposing that Blake once intended it,
                    would do nothing to solve the weightier problems involved in a VIIa-VIIb
                    sequence, leaving us with an inexplicable contrast between prophetic hope and
                    ironic despair. <note id="n58"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Vala was originally
                        mentioned in the third as well as the first line of the passage, which read
                        “Urizen cried to the Shadowy Female” rather than “Urizen
                        cried to his warriors.” The change, however, does not affect the fact
                        that Urizen is gloating over the birth of Vala: it merely means that his
                        speech is now directed to his warriors rather than her. An additional,
                        deleted line on the same page reads, “The shadowy voice answerd O
                        Urizen Prince of Light,” showing that Blake at one time conceived of
                        Urizen’s speech as part of a conversation between Urizen and Vala.
                        Since no other trace of Vala’s half of the conversation remains here
                        (it has conceivably been moved to VIII, 102:28 ff.), it seems probable that
                        the change in the third line came quite early, before the reordering of the
                        Night.</note></p>
        <p>The other possible explanation, to which I tentatively incline, is that Blake
                    changed the order of VIIb before writing the new ending to VIIa. On this
                    hypothesis, the change would be the first expression of Blake’s
                    dissatisfaction with the <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> sequence, and the first sign of
                    his search for a more humanistic approach to apocalypse. The advantage of the
                    new order is in moving the confrontation of Tharmas and Vala—which,
                    though gloomy enough, is at least more hopeful than the frantic violence which
                    dominates the other portion of the Night—to the end.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">17</ref> The idea is supported by Blake’s late addition,
                    at 94:12, of a lament for Luvah which makes the portrait of Vala considerably
                    more sympathetic. Moreover, the reversed VIIb would still be fairly continuous
                    with the original VIIa (though less so than formerly), since the revised
                    beginning returns to the moment of Vala’s birth. But if the reordering of
                    VIIb did in fact occur at a fairly early stage, it probably corresponded to a
                    plan of revision which Blake abandoned when he decided to merge Los and the
                    Spectre. At whatever point it was executed, the flip-flopping of the Night was a
                    mechanical tactic, incapable by itself of solving any of the serious problems
                    confronting Blake. His failure to change the numbering of the Nights seven is,
                    by itself, sufficient evidence that he was never finally satisfied to place VIIb
                    between VIIa and VIII. <note id="n59"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Stevenson, p. 390,
                        gives the opposite opinion: “In the second half (as it now is) Orc
                        appears. In transferring this passage to the end, Blake has delayed till
                        last the revelation of the worst evil.”</note></p>
        <p>Still, it is not difficult to arrive at a general sense of Night VIIb’s
                    place in Blake’s vision, even though it is impossible to find a physical
                    place for it in the text of his poem. In effect, Blake’s narrative
                    separates into parallel strands when Vala is born from the Shadow of Enitharmon,
                    at the point of the original ending of VIIa. Frye’s account of this
                    doubling refers only to the present VIIa, but seems valid even if applied to
                    both Nights seven: “In Night VII [i.e., VIIa] . . . a double crisis takes
                    place, one an imaginative advance, symbolized by the mingling of Los and the
                    Spectre of Urthona, the other a consolidation of error symbolized by the birth
                    of Rahab [i.e., Vala] from the Spectre of Urthona and . . . the Shadow of
                    Enitharmon” (Frye, 278). Roughly speaking, the path of “consolidation
                    of error” leads through VIIb, with its emphasis on climactic war, the
                    catastrophic rising of Orc, the triumph of Urizen, the epiphany of Vala, and the
                    inconsolable rage of Tharmas; the path of “imaginative advance” leads
                    through the added passages of VIIa, where for the first time we find a fully
                    prophetic Los, aided by his Spectre and Emanation, struggling to save mankind
                    through creative action. The two strands come back together again in VIII
                    (though with some fairly messy duplication of VIIb), where a sense of breakneck
                    progress toward apocalypse is brilliantly captured in the counterpointing of
                    Los’s furious acts of creation and Urizen-Satan-Rahab’s equally
                    furious acts of subversion and destruction.</p>
        <p>Likewise, though no exact chronology of the composition of these Nights can be
                    given, it is possible to speak with reasonable assurance about the process of
                    imaginative growth which must have been involved. At an early stage, it would
                    seem, Blake conceived of an apocalypse motivated almost exclusively by the
                    “consolidation of error,” a mechanical apocalypse entailing an almost
                    instantaneous leap from nadir to zenith. What this vision lacked was 
<pb id="p12-112" n="112"/>
the myth of the fully human and self-conscious Los,
                    and thus any sense of the possibility for positive human action in the fallen
                    world. Possibly Blake was astonished at the oversight once he recognized it;
                    possibly he came to regard <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as
categorically superior to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
                    because in those poems the mature Los, the self-conscious visionary confronting
                    human problems on the stage of human history, is dominant throughout, whereas
                    the far-ranging fantasy of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> deals largely with a
                    sort of cosmic pre-history.</p>
        <p>In any case, the new ending to VIIa marks a decisive change in Blake’s
                    concepts of apocalypse and prophecy. By mingling Los and the Spectre Blake
                    creates a human agency capable of turning fallen history in the direction of a
                    Last Judgement, thus transforming the apocalypse into a quest story with the
                    poet-prophet as its unequivocal hero. It was a change which strained the
                    narrative structure of the epic to the breaking point, squeezing VIIb halfway
                    out of the poem and causing major revisions in Night VIII. Yet the new vision
                    does not really invalidate the old; rather, as a later stage in a dialectic, it
                    necessarily implies and incorporates the earlier stages. The essential coherence
                    of the structure which Blake finally left—VIIa, VIII, and IX, with VIIb
                    lounging somewhere in the shadows—is not diminished by the fact that it
                    presumably grew out of a poetic process whose beginning did not know its
                    end.</p>
        <p>Why, then, did Blake lack the stamina to make a final disposition of VIIb, if
                    indeed that was all he had to do in order to finish his poem? The question is
                    especially troubling in that Blake apparently had a logical moment at which to
                    attempt the reintegration of the displaced Night when he revised Night VIII to
                    bring it into line with the new VIIa. It would seem more natural to bring in
                    passages from VIIb at this point than to plan on yet another revision of VIII
                    later on. On the other hand, one can imagine that Blake would find the problem
                    of VIIb an unwelcome distraction from the new vision which absorbed him as he
                    reworked Night VIII. Moreover, he might have been rather slow to part with the
                    idea that VIIb could be retained as a unit. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is,
                    finally, a story, yet its narrative structure is formed by the spatial accretion
                    of alternate myths and symbols around a central core of events (Fall,
                    Incarnation, Redemption, Apocalypse) which they interpret and exemplify, as well
                    as by the linear unfolding of the plot. It may have taken Blake some time to
                    decide that the clash of the old VIIb with the new VIIa and VIII was a greater
                    incongruity than even this structure could tolerate.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the recognition of VIIb’s incompatibility eventually came,
                    and one still must wonder why Blake never solved the problem. The speculation
                    which suggests itself, supposing that we have guessed right up till now, is that
                    the new inspiration proved all too potent. It drew Blake’s energies away
                    from <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> toward <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, but persuaded him more and more that further
                    revisions of the earlier poem were necessary, or at least desirable. Night VIII
                    in particular makes extensive use of the symbolic “Machinery” of the
                    later epics, in a way that sometimes justifies Margoliouth’s remark that
                    “Blake abandoned the poem because the new wine was bursting the old
                        bottles.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">18</ref> It
is as if Blake could
                    not content himself with completing <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> as such, but
                    had to go on to attempt a wholesale demonstration of the poem’s
                    consistency with its offspring; as if, after a certain point, everything had to
                    be said over again from the stand-point of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Nights I
                    and II contain certain late additions which suggest that Blake may have decided
                    to work through his first six Nights yet again, installing passages which would
                    anticipate the new vision, before tackling the problem of VIIb. Yet at the same
                    time, judging by the virtually atemporal structures of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
                    and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Blake was undergoing a crisis of disenchantment
                    with narrative itself. In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> he seems completely
                    unwilling to impose anything resembling a narrative chronology on the actions
                    and events of his myth. As he grew more and more accustomed to letting spatial
                    principles of symbolic association prevail over “clock-time,” Blake no
                    doubt found himself less and less inspired to resolve the narrative tangles of
                    the Nights seven. <note id="n60"><hi rend="s">18</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake</hi>
(London: Oxford Univ. Press, 1951), p.
                        115.</note></p>
        <p>How, then, should the two Nights be presented to the reader? My not very
                    earthshaking conclusion is that K in this particular is superior to E. VIIb
                    should come after VIIa, but is too important to the poem to be treated as an
                    appendix. Both editions are undoubtedly correct in presenting each Night as a
                    unit, rather than attempting to reintegrate VIIb into VIIa or VIII or both, for
                    such an attempt would be highly presumptuous, and would obscure a problem it
                    could not solve. Likewise, it seems best to print VIIb in the revised order, a
                    step which is dictated by the general policy of following the latest intentions
                    for which there is direct evidence in the manuscript.</p>
        <p>Whether the critic should be bound by this arrangement of the Nights is another
                    question, or perhaps no question at all, since the critic is always at liberty
                    to choose the order of the passages which he wishes to discuss. But for the
                    purpose of a linear commentary, or of having a theoretical model of the
                    poem’s narrative sequence, I would recommend a critical order much like
                    the one Wagenknecht uses in his reading of the poem.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">19</ref> Having read VIIa up to the point of Vala’s birth
                    from the Shadow of Enitharmon, I would then take up VIIb, considering it in its
                    original position in order to get a coherent view of Blake’s first
                    attempt to depict approaching apocalypse. I would choose the original rather
                    than the revised version of VIIb (though with some hesitation), for the sake of
                    preserving the original continuity of VIIa-VIIb, and because I suspect that the
                    reordering of the Night corresponded to a plan of revision which Blake never
                    carried out. Having read VIIb straight through in this order, I would return to
                    the added passages of VIIa; then on to VIII and IX. I do not, of course, claim
                    that this ordering of the text would have any authority; it is merely a sequence
                    for which there is some scholarly justification, and one which would be useful
                    for some critical purposes. <note id="n61"><hi rend="s">19</hi> See <hi rend="i">Blake’s
Night</hi>, pp. 224-25.</note></p>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p12-113" n="113" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
