<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>12.2.mla</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">MLA Blake Seminar 1978</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">12.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Special Design and Pasteup for this issue</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Everett Frost</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Terrence Hoagwood</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John Kilgore</name>
              <name>Mark Lefebvre</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Cettina Magno</name>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <name>Jeffry Spencer</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_12">
    <body>
      <pb id="p12-159" n="159"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-12-2-0017">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">NEWSLETTER</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">MLA BLAKE SEMINAR 1978</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>The Special Session on “Blake’s Concept of Self” is
                        scheduled for the annual meeting of the Modern Language Association in New
                        York this December. Prof. Anne Mellor of Stanford University will be heading
                        the session. An abstract of each paper to be presented follows:</p>
          <p>Robert N. Essick, “William Blake: The Printmaker as Poet”</p>
          <p>The paper will consider some of the ways in which Blake’s profession
                        influences his poetry. Eighteenth-century etching and engraving involved
                        procedures, both mental and physical, that shaped the imagery of the
                        Illuminated Books. In <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,
Blake’s struggles as a printmaker became part of
                        the biographical material he transformed into universal myth. A study of
                        these influences and references offers insights into Blake’s habits
                        of mind as a poet and into his conception of himself as an artist.</p>
          <p>Christine Gallant, “Blake’s Presence as First-Person Voice in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>”</p>
          <p>Blake is concerned with the unification of the Self—a Self that
                        includes the unconscious, or Chaos—and he explores the unconscious
                        throughout his poetry. He strongly desires his reader to understand this
                        hidden part of the Self as well, as he leads the reader of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
through day-by-day experiences of “the Chaos of
                        Satan.” We can see this in Blake’s use of the first-person
                        voice, an unusual tense for him (save in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>). Jung
                        helps to understand the use of this tense as he analyzes the authoritative
                        voice appearing in dreams, a voice seeming to come from outside the
                        dream’s context. He says that such a voice may be either a spokesman
                        of the unconscious for the dreamer or (very rarely) a messenger from
                        “the supraordinate Self.” The first-person voice functions in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as does this dream-voice. Blake’s use of
                        this tense reveals that in these passages he saw himself as such a
                        spokesman, both for the unconscious and for the unified center of the total
                        personality which is the Self.</p>
          <p>John H. Sutherland, “Some Blake Self-Images in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
                        and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>”</p>
          <p>The term “self-images” is used to refer to pictures in which Blake
                        reveals fairly directly something of his own inward state. Five plates from
                            <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (<hi rend="i">M</hi> 10, 32, 37, 40, 47) and
                        three plates from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 1, 6,
                        100) are discussed (plates numbered here as in <hi rend="i">The Illuminated
                            Blake</hi>). It is argued that some of these are pictures connected with
                        peak experiences in Blake’s life. A pattern of spiritual
                        auto-biography is suggested, and the question is raised as to whether this
                        pattern directly reflects Blake’s perception of his own life, or
                        whether the pattern is a partial fiction designed to enhance the structures
                        of his two works. Particular attention is given to <hi rend="i">J</hi> 100,
                        which is taken as an interesting vision, by Blake, of his own spiritual
                        state late in life.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
