<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>12.2.hoagwood</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The Four Zoas and “The Philosophick Cabbala”</title>
        <author n="Hoagwood">Terence Allan Hoagwood</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">12.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Special Design and Pasteup for this issue</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Everett Frost</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Terrence Hoagwood</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John Kilgore</name>
              <name>Mark Lefebvre</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Cettina Magno</name>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <name>Jeffry Spencer</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_12">
    <body>
      <pb id="p12-87" n="87"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-12-2-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">THE FOUR ZOAS</hi> AND “THE PHILOSOPHICK
                            CABBALA”</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">TERENCE ALLAN</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">HOAGWOOD</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>The relation of Blake’s poetry to Platonic and Neoplatonic thought has
                    attracted discussion for many years.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21"
type="note">1</ref> Blake
                    apparently read works by Thomas Taylor, the Platonist,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">2</ref> and by Henry More, the Cambridge Platonist.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">3</ref> James King has shown that Blake personally
                    knew Thomas Taylor,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24"
type="note">4</ref> who read and wrote
                    about Henry More.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">5</ref>
In the course of their
                    documentation of some analogues to Blake, S. Foster Damon, Desirée Hirst,
                    and Morton D. Paley briefly indicate some resemblances between Henry More and
                        Blake;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">6</ref> and
“The Philosophick
                    Cabbala,” from <hi rend="i">Conjectura Cabbalistica</hi> by More,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">7</ref> in fact furnishes several specific
                    parallels to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> which these scholars have not
                    discussed. “The Philosophick Cabbala,” part of More’s retelling
                    of the fall of man as narrated in the Book of Genesis, bears close resemblance
                    in many points to Blake’s retelling of the fall of man in <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas.</hi> The fact that <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is a long
                    poem and “The Philosophick Cabbala” is a shorter work in prose
                    entails, of course, some distinctions in style and formal intention; but some
                    philosophic assumptions and even specific thoughts and specific passages
                    correspond so closely as to suggest comparison: these works have similar casts
                    of symbolic characters, similar accounts of the cause of the fall, and similar
                    accounts of certain consequences of the fall, and some of these similarities are
                    sufficiently close and sufficiently unusual to suggest indirect if not direct
                    relation of the two books. <note id="n21"><hi rend="s">1</hi> For book-length
                        studies of this relation, see especially George Mills Harper, <hi rend="i">The
Neoplatonism of William Blake</hi> (Chapel Hill: Univ. of North
                        Carolina Press, 1961), and Kathleen Raine, <hi rend="i">Blake and
                            Tradition</hi> (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1968).</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Mona Wilson, <hi rend="i">The Life of William
                            Blake</hi> (London: Nonesuch Press, 1927). My citation is from the
                        reprint of the revised edition (New York: Cooper Square Publishers, 1969),
                        p. 52; Harper, pp. 43-44; and Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Energy and the
                            Imagination, A Study of the Development of Blake’s Thought</hi>
                        (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1970), p. 206.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">3</hi> S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">William Blake:
                            His Philosophy and Symbols</hi> (Boston and New York: Houghton Mifflin
                        Co., 1924), p. 167, and Wilson, p. 52.</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">4</hi> James King, “The Meredith Family, Thomas
                        Taylor, and William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 2
                        (1972), pp. 153-57.</note>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Harper, p. 11.</note>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">6</hi> e.g., Damon, pp. 167, 328, 341, 367, 384,
                        467; Desirée Hirst, <hi rend="i">Hidden Riches: Traditional Symbolism
                            from the Renaissance to Blake</hi> (London: Eyre and Spottiswoode,
                        1964), pp. 158-59; and Paley, pp. 216-17.</note>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Henry More, <hi rend="i">Conjectura
                            Cabbalistica. or, A Conjectural Essay of Interpreting the Minde of
                            Moses, according to a Threefold Cabbala: viz., Literal, Philosophical,
                            Mystical, or, Divinely Moral</hi> (London: J. Flesher, 1653); also
                        printed in <hi rend="i">A Collection of Several Philosophical Writings of
                            Dr. Henry More</hi> . . . 4th ed. (London: J. Downing, 1/12), from which
                        I quote.</note></p>
        <p>Specifically, More’s concept of the “Soul’s <hi rend="i">Vehicle</hi>” (II, 20) resembles
Blake’s concept of emanation.
                    Each is a feminine portion of an original, masculine character; each is the
                    faculty of joy; and each is the faculty of connecting man with the material
                    world. More describes the creation of this “<hi rend="i">Feminine</hi>
                    part” (III, 1) or “Soul’s <hi rend="i">Vehicle</hi>”:
                    after the creation of the original man, Adam, “God indued the Soul of Man
                    with a Faculty of being united with vital joy and complacency to the
                    Matter” of the universe (II, 20). Blake similarly describes the creation of
                    the feminine portion of an original man: 
					<q> The manhood was divided for the
                        gentle passions making way<lb/>
 Thro the infinite labyrinths of the heart .
                        . .<lb/>
 . . . stood before the Eyes of Man<lb/>
 A female bright.<lb/>
<lb/>
                            (84:13-16<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28"
type="note">8</ref>) <note id="n28"><hi rend="s">8</hi> I use the text of <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose
                                of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman (Garden City, N.Y.:
                            Doubleday &amp; Co., 1965), pp. 296-392. Citations include
                            Blake’s manuscript page number and line number as indicated by
                            Erdman.</note></q>
More defines this feminine portion as the source of “vital joy”
                    and writes that she represents “joyous and chearful <hi rend="i">life</hi>” (II, 24);
similarly, Blake’s representation of the
                    feminine portion, in the person of Enitharmon, says: “I wake sweet
                    joy” and “wake the bubbling springs of life” (34:85,87). Both
                    writers also clearly characterize the feminine portion of the original man as
                    the faculty of connecting him with the material world. More writes that the
                    original “<hi rend="i">masculine Adam</hi> . . . consists in pure subtile
                    Intellectual Knowledge” (II, 18), whereas the “<hi rend="i">Feminine</hi> part” (III, 1)
with which he is subsequently indued
                    “is that Vital principle that joins the Soul to the Matter of the
                    Universe” (II, 20). The feminine portion of the man is the faculty of
                    sensation of matter in Blake’s description, too, and he thus catalogues
                    the bodily senses as attributes of the union of masculine character with his new
                    feminine portion: 
					<q> They eat the fleshly bread, they drank the nervous
                        wine<lb/>
 They listend to the Elemental Harps &amp; Sphery Song<lb/>
 They
                        view’d the dancing Hours, quick sporting thro’ the sky<lb/>
                        With winged radiance scattering joys thro the ever changing light<lb/>
<lb/>
                        (12:44-13:3) </q>
	<pb id="p12-88" n="88"/>
Again,
<q> . . . Los &amp; Enitharmon walkd forth on
                        the dewy Earth<lb/>
 Contracting or expanding their all flexible senses<lb/>
                        At will to murmur in the flowers small as the honey bee<lb/>
 At will to
                        stretch across the heavens &amp; step from star to star<lb/>
 Or standing on
                        the Earth erect, or on the stormy waves<lb/>
 Driving the storms before them
                        or delighting in sunny beams<lb/>
 While round their heads the Elemental Gods
                        kept harmony<lb/>
<lb/>
 (34:9-15) </q></p>
        <p>In both More’s account and Blake’s, the activation of this feminine
                    portion, with her functions of joy and connection with matter, is explicitly
                    described as a profound sleep of the man. This profound sleep has, of course,
                    its original in Genesis 2:21-22, where God is said to have caused a deep sleep
                    to fall on Adam, during which God creates Eve from Adam’s rib. Both More
                    and Blake retell the events of Genesis; but both More and Blake also interpret
                    those events and attach special significance to such symbols as the sleep. The
                    significance of the sleep, in which More and Blake largely agree, does not
                    derive directly from the narrative of Genesis, but seems to be peculiar to the
                    interpreters, and consequently to constitute a parallel that cannot be accounted
                    for by reference to their common source in Genesis. In both writers, the
                    feminine portion of the man is characterized as a state of intellectual sleep
                    and material excitement. 
					<q> . . . God, to gratify <hi rend="i">Adam</hi>, made
                        him not indefatigable in his aspirings towards Intellectual things;
                        Lassitude of Contemplation, and of Affectation of Immateriality . . .
                        brought upon him remisness and drowsiness to such like exercises, till, by
                        degrees, he fell into a more profound sleep. At what time . . . that lower
                        Vivificative principle of his Soul did grow so strong, and did so
                        vigorously, and with such exultant sympathy and joy, actuate his 
<hi rend="i">Vehicle</hi>, that, in virtue of his Integrity, which he yet
                        retain’d, this became more dear to him, and of greater contentment
                        than any thing he yet had experience of.<lb/>
<lb/>
 (II, 21) </q>
In
                    Blake’s account, too, the feminine portion of the man is characterized as
                    a gratifying sleep and a repose from the tiring intellectual activities of the
                    man. The emanation of Los is characterized thus: “Lovely delight of Men
                    Enitharmon shady refuge from furious war / Thy bosom translucent is a soft
                    repose” (90:5-6). Just as in More’s account the “<hi rend="i">Feminine</hi> part” was
“highly invigorated in <hi rend="i">Adam</hi>, by the remission of exercise in his more subtile and immaterial
                    Faculties” (III, 1), so too in Blake’s account the feminine
                    emanation represents a drowsy slackening of exercise. Enitharmon, for example,
                    was “Once born for the sport &amp; amusement of Man” (10:25), just as
                    the “<hi rend="i">Feminine</hi> part” in More was born “to
                    gratify <hi rend="i">Adam</hi>” (II, 21); then Enitharmon is said to
                    “drink up all his Powers” (10:25), just as in More the “<hi rend="i">Feminine</hi> part”
is associated with a remission of
                    Adam’s powers. Ahania, another emanation in <hi rend="i">The Four
                        Zoas</hi>, is said by her masculine portion to reflect “all my
                    indolence my weakness” (43:18), just as in “The Philosophick
                    Cabbala” the “<hi rend="i">Feminine</hi> part” is said to result
                    from a “not indefatigable” male and is associated with his
                    “drowsiness” (II, 21). This explicit and repeated characterization of
                    the feminine portion as a “Vivificative” state of material
                    consciousness and a “profound sleep” of intellectual consciousness
                    (II, 21) is another instance in which More and Blake are parallel.</p>
        <p>Blake writes that in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> he will sing of a “fall
                    into Division” (4:4), and in this very long and very complex poem, he
                    divides his symbolic characters in more ways than one. Like More, he divides
                    masculine from feminine, as described above; but he also divides an original
                    man—Albion—into “Four Mighty Ones” (3:4), the four zoas
                    themselves. These zoas are said to live “in the Brain of Man,” and
                    their “bright world . . . is in the Human Brain” (11:15-16). In <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>, the division of these mental faculties and a
                    contention that arises between two of them are specifically said to precipitate
                    the fall from grace; in “The Philosophick Cabbala” also, two very
                    similar mental faculties are considered separately and a similar contention
                    between them is said, equally specifically, to precipitate the fall from
                    grace.</p>
        <p>In “The philosophick Cabbala,” a faculty of strong feeling, which More
                    calls “the <hi rend="i">Concupiscible</hi>,” usurps the function of
                    “Reason” (III, 6), and this usurpation is given as the cause of the
                    fall from grace. Similarly, in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Luvah, the zoa
                    of passion and lust, usurps the function of Urizen, the zoa of reason, and this
                    usurpation is given as the cause of the fall. The faculty symbolized by Luvah
                    corresponds closely to “the <hi rend="i">Concupiscible</hi>” faculty:
                    Luvah is called “Love” and his “place the place of seed”
                    (126:7-8). Urizen closely corresponds to the faculty of Reason, as his place is
                    the brain (23:12), and he receives the command from the “holy voice”
                    (64:21) to “Go forth &amp; guide my Son” (64:24), which is symbolized
                    by his command of the “horses of Light” (119:27). The contention
                    between them causes the fall in both writers’ explanations. More explains
                    the cause: “the <hi rend="i">Concupiscible</hi> . . . snatch’d away
                    with it <hi rend="i">Adam</hi>’s Will and Reason” (III, 6). Blake
                    explains with equal concision: “Urizen gave the horses of Light into the
                    hands of Luvah” (119:27), and, again, “Luvah siez’d the Horses
                    of Light” (10:13). This is the repeated description of the cause of the
                    fall in both writers. More writes that while Adam’s Reason was asleep,
                        “<hi rend="i">Adam</hi> was wholly set upon doing things . . . as the
                    various toyings and titillations of the lascivient <hi rend="i">Life of the
                        Vehicle</hi> [that is, the Concupiscible faculty] suggested to him”
                    (III, 6), and “<hi rend="i">Adam</hi> again excused himself within himself,
                    that it was the vigour and impetuosity of that <hi rend="i">Life of the
                        Vehicle</hi> . . . whereby he miscarried” (III, 12). In Blake’s
                    words, while “Urizen sleeps in the porch / Luvah and Vala woke &amp; flew
                    up from the Human Heart / <pb id="p12-89" n="89"/>
Into the Brain”
                    (10:10-12). Vala is the emanation of Luvah, and is consequently a function of
                    passion, which is here again said to usurp the place of the sleeping reason.</p>
        <p>I do not argue that “The Philosophick Cabbala” is the only source in
                    which Blake could have found such a model: in <hi rend="i">Energy and the
                        Imagination</hi> Morton D. Paley, who does not mention “The
                    Philosophick Cabbala” in this connection, cites several other writers who
                    explain that “Passion subverts the place of Reason.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">9</ref> Nevertheless, the parallel of Urizen’s
                    [reason’s] displacement by Luvah [passion] with the Intellectual
                    faculty’s displacement by “the <hi rend="i">Concupiscible</hi>”
                    furnishes another in a series of parallels between More’s account of the
                    fall and Blake’s. <note id="n29"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Paley, 91 ff. Paley
                        cites Plato’s <hi rend="i">Phaedrus</hi>, Ovid’s story of
                        Phaeton, Prudentius’ <hi rend="i">Psychomachia</hi>, 11. 740-42, and
                        Milton’s <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, IX:1125-31.</note></p>
        <p>The foregoing passages illustrate the parallels of the Urizen/Luvah pair with the
                    Concupiscible/Reason pair; but “the <hi rend="i">Concupiscible</hi>”
                    or “the Soul’s <hi rend="i">Vehicle</hi>” also corresponds to
                    the concept of emanation in Blake. Clearly, however, we can expect
                    Blake’s long and complex poem to contain a more complicated system of
                    symbols than More’s short prose chapters. The fact that the Vehicle seems
                    to be like the emanation in many ways and also to be like Luvah in many ways
                    need not suggest a failure of correspondence between Blake and More;
                    Blake’s longer and more complicated work contains a longer and more
                    complicated system of concepts. The sleep of Urizen and uprising of Luvah
                    parallels the sleep of Reason and uprising of the “lascivient <hi rend="i">Life of the
Vehicle</hi>” in More; but, at the same time, the
                    “drowsiness” of Adam and “vital joy” of his Vehicle also
                    parallels the “indolence” and “weakness” and “soft
                    repose” of Blake’s males and the concomitant vitality of their
                    feminine portions. Thus, the dichotomy of masculine zoa and feminine emanation
                    seems to correspond closely; but when describing the usurpation of
                    Reason’s function by a “lascivient” faculty, Blake uses the
                    symbols of Urizen and Luvah. The Vehicle in More therefore parallels the
                    emanation in Blake, and it also parallels Luvah; whereas More’s shorter
                    and simpler account uses one dichotomy only, Blake’s longer and more
                    complicated account of the same story uses more than one. Both pairs in Blake
                    behave very much like More’s pair: a similar opposition of similar mental
                    faculties causes the fall from grace in both accounts.</p>
        <p>After interpreting its cause, both Blake and More describe a consequence of the
                    fall from grace which constitutes a particularly striking parallel, because it
                    has no apparent source or suggestion in their common source, the Book of
                    Genesis: both writers treat the incarnation of humans in the material world as a
                    result rather than an antecedent of the fall, and they similarly describe the
                    process by which this occurs. More writes that “the Eternal Lord God
                    decreed, that he [Adam] should descend down to be an Inhabitant of the
                    Earth” (III, 16), and Adam does so: “At last the <hi rend="i">Plastick
                        power</hi> being fully awakened, <hi rend="i">Adam’s</hi> Soul
                    descended into the prepared Matter of the Earth, and, in due process of time,
                        <hi rend="i">Adam</hi> appeared cloth’d in the skins of beasts; that
                    is, he became a down-right <hi rend="i">Terrestrial Animal</hi>, and a mortal
                    creature upon Earth” (III, 21). According to More, this is the process by
                    which all creatures are incarnated in mortal forms: “ . . . God, by his 
<hi rend="i">Inward Word</hi> and <hi rend="i">Power</hi>, prepared the Matter
                    in the waters, and near the waters, with several <hi rend="i">Vital
                        congruities</hi>, so that it drew in sundry Souls from <hi rend="i">the
                        World of Life</hi>” (I, 20). According to More, this does not occur to
                    humanity until after the eating of the forbidden fuit; it occurs as a
                    consequence of the fall from grace. In Blake’s account, after the eating
                    of the forbidden fruit, Los exercises a “<hi rend="i">Plastick
                    power</hi>,” saying: “Stern desire / I feel to fabricate embodied
                    semblances” (90:8-9). Enitharmon, his emanation, responds, urging him to
                    “fabricate forms” (90:22), which the two of them proceed to do. In
                    Blake’s account, as in More’s, a “spectrous” multitude
                    begins “Assimilating to those forms” (90:41-42): “Enitharmon
                    erected Looms” and “in these Looms She wove the Spectres / Bodies of
                    Vegetation” (100:2-4). Again, 
					<q> Enitharmon wove in tears Singing Songs of
                        Lamentations<lb/>
 And pitying comfort as she sighd forth on the wind the
                        spectres<lb/>
 And wove them bodies . . .<lb/>
<lb/>
 (103:32-34) </q>
while
						<q> . . . Los employed the Sons<lb/>
 In Golgonoozas Furnaces among the
                        Anvils of time &amp; space<lb/>
 Thus forming a Vast family . . .<lb/>
<lb/>
                        (103:35-37) </q>
Although in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> it is Los and
                    his emanation, and not God himself, who form the bodies into which souls
                    descend, Los is enabled to do this because “the Divine hand was upon
                    him” (100:6). Blake’s version, then, of mortal incarnation follows
                    “The Philosophick Cabbala” rather than Genesis by making human
                    incarnation in bodily form a result of the fall rather than a development that
                    occurred before it. Furthermore, both Blake and More depict the process of
                    bodily incarnation with a vision of divinely prepared matter into which
                    previously bodiless spirits descend.</p>
        <p>Although the focus of this study is on the relation of <hi rend="i">The Four
                        Zoas</hi> to “The Philosophick Cabbala,” I would by no means
                    suggest that <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> alone among Blake’s poems
                    bears comparison with More’s work; Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, for example,
repeats echoes from “The Philosophick
                    Cabbala.” Morton D. Paley has pointed out to me that the speech of Leutha,
                    from 11:35 through 13:6 in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, which is generally
                    recognized to recall <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, II:747-814, also clearly
                    recalls More’s <hi rend="i">Conjectura Cabbalistica.</hi> Leutha says
                    that 
					<q> . . . entering the doors of Satans brain night after night<lb/>
 Like
                        sweet perfumes I stupified the masculine perceptions<lb/>
 And kept only the
                        feminine awake.<lb/>
<lb/>
 (12:4-6) </q>
This passage has obvious affinities
                    with More’s passage in which the “<hi rend="i">masculine
                    Adam</hi>” suffers 
<pb id="p12-90" n="90"/> “remisness and
                    drowsiness” as the feminine portion or “Vivificative principle of his
                    Soul did grow so strong” (II, 18,21). Further, just as More writes 
					<q> . .
                        . Adam again excused himself within himself, that it was the vigour and
                        impetuosity of that <hi rend="i">Life in the Vehicle</hi>, which God himself
                        implanted in it, whereby he miscarried: the woman that God had given
                        him,<lb/>
<lb/>
 (III, 12) </q>
Leutha, the counterpart of this feminine
                    Vehicle in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, says: “I am the Author of this
                    Sin!” (11:35) and 
					<q> . . . my fault, when at noon of day<lb/>
 The Horses
                        of Palamabron call’d for rest and pleasant death:<lb/>
 I sprang out
                        of the breast of Satan, over the Harrow beaming<lb/>
 In all my beauty! that
                        I might unloose the flaming steeds<lb/>
<lb/>
 (12:8-11) </q>
Here, as in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Blake repeats the emergence of a feminine
                    portion from a masculine character, recalling the pattern in More’s work;
                    and here, too, he repeats yet another pattern found in “The Philosophick
                    Cabbala”: a crisis following an intrapsychic division and a usurpation by
                    one mental faculty of another. Just as in “The Philosophick Cabbala”
                    “the <hi rend="i">Concupiscible</hi> . . . snatch’d away with it 
<hi rend="i">Adam’s</hi> Will and Reason” (III, 6), and in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, “Luvah siez’d the
Horses of
                    Light” (10:13), in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> the pattern is repeated:
                    Leutha’s attempt to “unloose the flaming steeds / As Elynittria
                    use’d to do” (12:11-12) precipitates a crisis; “they brake the
                    traces” (12:13) and thereby bring about “A Hell of our own making.
                    see, its flames still gird me round” (12:23). In the pattern of the
                    feminine portion’s emergence, then, and in the pattern of <corr type="emend">intrapsychic</corr>
                    usurpation precipitating a crisis, <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, like <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>, bears comparison with “The Philosophick
                    Cabbala.” Thus, neither Blake’s tendency to recall More’s
                    work no the specific ideas and configurations that he adopts are strictly
                    limited to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></p>
        <p>Clearly, at any rate, “The Philosophick Cabbala” furnishes a long
                    series of parallels to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: there are similarities
                    between More’s “<hi rend="i">Feminine</hi> part” and
                    Blake’s emanation; between the two writers’ explanations that
                    conflicts among mental faculties caused the fall from grace; and between their
                    descriptions of the descent of spirits into bodily form as a consequence of the
                    fall. So many parallels may suggest a relation between Blake’s work and
                    More’s. The probable availability of More’s work to Blake may even
                    suggest a possible direct relation; but the internal evidence alone of so many
                    similarities constitutes at least, I believe, some indirect relation that
                    may—or may not—be coincidental.</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
