<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>12.2.wilton</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Raymond Lister, The Letters of Samuel Palmer and Samuel Palmer A Biography</title>
        <author n="Wilton">Andrew Wilton</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">12.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Special Design and Pasteup for this issue</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Everett Frost</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Terrence Hoagwood</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John Kilgore</name>
              <name>Mark Lefebvre</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Cettina Magno</name>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <name>Jeffry Spencer</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_12">
    <body>
      <pb id="p12-150" n="150"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-12-2-0016">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Raymond Lister, ed. <hi rend="b">The Letters of Samuel Palmer.</hi>
                            Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1974. 2 vols., 1123 pp., $80.00.; Raymond
                            Lister. <hi rend="b">Samuel Palmer A Biography.</hi> London: Faber
                            &amp; Faber, 1975. 299 pp., $12.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Andrew</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Wilton</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>It is now over fifty years since Samuel Palmer’s son organized the
                        exhibition at the Victoria and Albert Museum from which the general interest
                        in Palmer dates. The artist was presented then as a “Disciple of
                        William Blake,” and that loose description has stuck. Geoffrey
                        Grigson’s important account, <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer the Visionary
                            Years</hi> of 1947, was constructed on the foundation of that
                        description, and even David Cecil’s brief but comprehensive
                        biographical sketch in <hi rend="i">Visionary and Dreamer</hi> of 1969 lays
                        the same firm emphasis. There has been much praise of Palmer—or at
                        least of certain aspects of his work—but no great willingness to
                        accord him any role other than that of “disciple.”</p>
          <p>Palmer himself unintentionally encouraged this approach. The very word
                        “disciple” with its New Testament overtones perfectly evokes the
                        passionate religious wellspring of his art. He spoke of Blake with fervor as
                        one of the great spirits of history, morally as well as artistically
                        excellent, in a class apart. The intensity of response that Blake
                        characteristically showed is apparent also in Palmer’s best work, and
                        Palmer indicated that he felt such a response to be in some way
                        “Blakean.” Yet his art is in almost every way of a different kind
                        from that of Blake, and, in sum, is by no means the work of a
                        “follower,” either in its content or in its technique. We have
                        long been in possession of the circumstantial evidence necessary to form a
                        judgment of its real character, for not only have we had access to much of
                        his output, but A. H. Palmer’s illuminating <hi rend="i">Life and
                            Letters</hi> has been in print since 1892. Now that Raymond Lister has
                        edited the complete correspondence, still more of the essential material is
                        easily available.</p>
          <p>For Palmer wrote a great deal about both the theory and technique of his art.
                        He was a remarkably gifted prose writer, with a natural sense of rhythm, of
                        rhetoric, of imagery, and a voluminous store of quotations. There were
                        moments in his life when he contemplated turning to literature for his
                        livelihood, and he would have been well fitted for such work. “It is
                        very much easier to give vent to the romantic by speech than by
                        [painting],” he said. Accordingly, we have a vivid picture of those
                        aspects of the world and those ideas that moved him, or repelled him, and
                        can trace accurately in his letters the genesis of particular images in his
                        pictures from particular experiences in his travels. There is also a great
                        deal of information about his methods of working, especially after he became
                        associated with Philip Gilbert Hamerton, editor of the art magazine 
                        <hi rend="i">Portfolio</hi>, who got Palmer to write for him on the use of
                        watercolor and on etching. There are letters to pupils that give detailed
                        directions as to how to create special effects in watercolors, and long
                        letters to his patron Leonard Rowe Valpy expounding his personal
                        interpretation of natural phenomena as the substance of art.</p>
          <p>The mass of correspondence from Italy during his honeymoon, which Mr. Lister
                        prints with all Hannah Palmer’s contributions, charts not only
                        personal matters like the gradually opening rift between Palmer and his
                        interfering father-in-law, John Linnell, but the whole slow, marvellous
                        dawning of the Italian experience on Palmer’s sensibility—the
                        realization of “certain types of landscape only found in perfection in
                        Italy,” as he said. It was for him “a course of
                        purgation—getting a quantity of rubbish and confusion out of my
                        mind.” These reactions seem odd in the hermit of Shoreham, the
                        quintessentially English rural visionary. What need had Palmer of Italy, any
                        more than Blake? Yet Blake esteemed Michelangelo above all artists, and even
                        at the very beginning of the Shoreham period, Palmer was dreaming of Italy
                        and the great works of the Italian 
                        <pb id="p12-151" n="151"/>
                        <figure n="PalmerHoneymoon.12.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="511">
                        	<head>A rare record of the Palmers’ honeymoon in Italy has
                                recently come to light, and as it is, as far as I know, the only
                                representation of Samuel and Hannah together at that time, it seems
                                worth publishing here.</head>
                            <figDesc>It is a drawing in pen and brown ink, on a cut fragment of
                                envelope, 4 by 7 ½ inches, and was acquired by the British
                                Museum in 1975 among a group of pencil drawings which, though
                                unattributed, are identifiable as the work of the Welsh artist Penry
                                Williams (1800-85) who lived in Italy for much of his life and
                                became acquainted with most English artists visiting Rome. The back
                                of the sheet seems once to have been inscribed with Williams’
                                name and address—in the Piazza Mignanelli, off the Piazza di
                                Spagna; only the final letters of the two lines are visible at the
                                edge of the sheet. A further inscription reads: “ . . . of
                                Civitella has been made (for the poor,) amongst residents at Don O.
                                Mss a considerable sum has been realized, / July 1839”. On the
                                recto, the drawing is bordered by a line, above which is written
                                “Civitella Gazette.” Below, “price 2 Biagi. View of
                                the Serpentara .. July. 1. 1839. presented gratis.” The drawing
                                itself is annotated with names of the various figures who are
                                depicted sitting and sketching on the rocks in an expansive
                                landscape: within the border, a “Boy” in a tree is
                                apparently the object of several of the sketchers’ attention;
                                and “M. Ainslie”, “Mrs P.” and “M.
                                Lear” are all easily identifiable. Samuel James Ainslie
                                (1806-74) is seated under an umbrella held by a manservant; he spent
                                much time in Italy, and travelled with George Dennis, author of 
                                <hi rend="i">The Cities and Cemetries of Etruria</hi>, published in
                                1848. “Mrs P” is evidently Hannah Palmer; she is shown as
                                a tiny figure, in a large bonnet, perched on the edge of a rock near
                                the ungainly form of her husband. ‘M. Lear’ is Edward
                                Lear (1812-88), whose lithographed <hi rend="i">Views in Rome and
                                its Environs</hi> was to appear in 1841. Outside the border the
                                other members of the party are indicated; most of these are
                                unidentified, some of the names even illegible. They seem to be
                                “M. Schitter. M.Martin. M.Palmer Mr McNiven (?) Herr Fritz. Fr.
                                Frankson (?).M Duvivier (?)”. “M.Martin” is Albin
                                Martin, a pupil and protégé of Linnell’s, who
                                had joined the Palmers in Rome in the Summer of 1838.<lb/>
                                <lb/>
                                Shortly after this expedition, Hannah wrote home from Civitella:
                                “Our life now is so thoroughly that of working people that not
                                knowing the days of the week we rose last Sunday morning in haste at
                                4 oclock in the morning, got all our sketching apparatus packed up
                                for going down into the valley to our daily work thinking it was
                                Saturday; not [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>; nor?] should we have been the
                                wiser had not Mr Lear, an artist here who keeps a journal, told us.
                                Mr Martin works as hard as anybody.” Palmer, under the same
                                date, wrote: “Yesterday and today—for the first time in
                                our travels I have been wholly unable to work which is very
                                miserable as Civitella abounds so with beautiful foreground studies
                                that our time being short not a moment should be lost. Of Mr. Martin
                                I am sorry to be obliged to give a much worse account. In spite of
                                every precaution against sun etc. he has suffered every fortnight
                                since coming to Rome—with sickness at the stomach—so
                                as to be for several days unable to eat— . . . at Subiaco we
                                attributed it to the intense heat—but the air is much cooler
                                here and Mr. M. never sits late in the sun—nor without an
                                umbrella at any time.” This may explain the large, wide-brimmed
                                hat that Martin wears in the drawing.<lb/>
                                <lb/>
                                The sketch is a
                                delightful insight into the lives of Palmer and Hannah and their
                                friends during the Italian tour, and is strikingly similar not only
                                in its humor but in technique to the pen drawings of Lear himself.
                                It includes almost certainly the least sympathetic portrait of
                                Palmer to have come down to us; but a portrait at which, no doubt,
                                Palmer would have laughed heartily. (A.W.)</figDesc>
						</figure>
						<pb id="p12-152" n="152"/>
						masters. To George Richmond, about to tour the
                        continent, he wrote, “I should like to know how the Giants of the
                        Sistine Vault strike first upon your soul, in words as near as possible like
                        those you would break forth into on entering the chapel . . . I suppose,
                        with most young men that go to Rome, you will disagree with me when I
                        suggest that it is not most useful to spend time in copying one or two
                        pictures elaborately in colours: in a shorter stay how well might you serve
                        the arts in your country by making small drawings for engravings, of a few
                        of the very finest sculptures . . . I fancy myself working intensely hard
                        for a week on grey paper; the quickest way of copying statues; to give my
                        country a true version of the divine St. George of Donatello . . . .”
                        In imagination, Palmer was already (and he at Shoreham!) deep in the wonders
                        of the Italian Renaissance, planning not only what he would look at, but how
                        he would draw it. The progression from Shoreham to Rome was inevitable, and
                        in this at least Palmer is at one with his contemporaries, and very far from
                        Blake, who was self-sufficient in his opinions and responses, content with
                        prints and “dealers’ Titians” to use the barest clues in
                        constructing his own vast world-picture.</p>
          <p>And so Palmer moved on, impelled by a spirit of his age that exercised
                        remarkably tight control over him, considering that he was in almost every
                        respect a reactionary, one who cringed away from the present, who sought to
                        hide from the evils of “progress,” who mistrusted science and was
                        terrified of the increase of agnosticism, tight lacing, urban sprawl,
                        pollution and public schools—a pattern of the conservative mentality
                        past and present. As he grew older, indeed, his very religion, the motive
                        force behind his greatest art, became prosy and prudish, the agent of
                        repression to his children and the subject of endless discourses that we
                        should now label typically “Victorian.” Mr. Lister betrays an odd
                        lack of understanding of the educational methods of the period when he
                        castigates Palmer for feeding his three-year-old son on the Bible, Bunyan,
                        and <hi rend="i">Sandford and Merton.</hi> Palmer’s advocacy of a
                        bowdlerized Shakespeare is disconcerting, however, given his strong feeling
                        for literature, and his acquaintance with Blake’s own unselfconscious
                        modes of expression. Like many other talented artists of his time, he
                        succumbed to the stifling climate of general opinion (one almost senses that
                        he knew it, in his constant complaints about the unhealthy atmosphere of
                        London), and his art suffered like everything else. When in 1859 he wrote
                        “I seem doomed never to see again that first flush of summer splendour
                        which entranced me at Shoreham,” he expressed the same nostalgia for
                        his own creative youth that Millais was to feel when, standing in front of
                        one of his early canvases during a retrospective show in 1886, he was moved
                        to tears by the contrast between that and his current work.</p>
          <p>The comparison with Millais, however, points up Palmer’s real
                        distinction from the successful Millais’ world of fashionable and
                        glib virtuosity. He never had any success as a “society” painter,
                        and although in a sense he never wished it, we catch an unmistakable note of
                        frustration and puzzlement when, in Rome, he watches his friend Richmond
                        moving in fashionable circles while he and Hannah are left out of the social
                        life of the city, and are given no commissions. When he returned to England,
                        fully equipped with the right subjects, he waited many years to be admitted
                        to the Society of Painters in Water-Colour, and there is no doubt that he
                        very much wanted to belong to that body of artists. It is in the context of
                        the Society, and of another, more informal institution, the “Etching
                        Club,” that his later work can best be assessed.</p>
          <p>It was an avowed object of the instituted watercolor artists that they should
                        create works of high seriousness in their chosen medium, and indeed it was
                        to facilitate the exhibition of such works, without the unfair competition
                        of oil-paintings, that they had founded their society in 1804. They treated
                        subjects that ranged from the kind of picturesque landscape that is most
                        associated with watercolor to the grandest figure pieces, historical or
                        mythological, and elaborately detailed scenes in exotic countries,
                        especially Italy and Spain. Palmer worked in oil for much of his life, but
                        in practice showed a decided preference for watercolor, especially in the
                        second half of his career. He employed the methods of enriching and
                        strengthening watercolor used by many of his colleagues: bodycolor made its
                        appearance early on at Shoreham, and much of his later work was “a kind
                        of Tempera” as he said in a letter of 1873—which recalls,
                        perhaps, Blake’s use of that vehicle. Whatever the details of his
                        method, he strove to load his watercolors with a density of feeling and a
                        richness of detail that was precisely analogous to the intentions of the
                        Society. What we recognise as distinctive is the continuing strain of the
                        visionary insight into rural life that was so active in the 1820s; if
                        feebler and more rarefied, that fervid instinct for the inwardness of the
                        countryside and the religious force of its beauty informs much of his late
                        work, and makes him, in fact, one of the finest of the Society’s
                        artists.</p>
          <p>The technical range and power of watercolor at this period undoubtedly owed
                        much to the example of Turner, who was an inspiration to the founders of the
                        Society, even though by virtue of his membership of the Royal Academy he
                        could not belong to it. What emerges very clearly from the letters of Palmer
                        is that, while Blake was never superseded as his spiritual guide, Turner
                        became a technical and practical inspiration of the greatest importance. The
                        effect on him of Turner’s <hi rend="i">Orange Merchant</hi> of 1819
                        is often noted; but that large marine painting can hardly have had much
                        practical bearing on Palmer’s work. Even the atmospheric little
                        watercolor studies that date from about that time are hardly
                        “Turnerian” in any serious sense. But the meticulous precision
                        with which he constructed his later watercolors can have been based on no
                        other master. References to Turner’s watercolors are frequent in
                        Palmer’s writings; it is true that he asserts that Claude is the
                        greatest of all landscape painters—but then Turner would himself have
                        sympathized with that view; and Turner, he observed, “had the faculty
                        to which Claude never appeals in vain.” While he was in Italy, he often
                        saw landscape through Turner’s eyes, and he indicates that Turner
                        conveyed the poetry of the scenery, just as he wished to do himself: 
                        “ . . . what beautiful country must 
                        <pb id="p12-153" n="153"/> 
                        be here in
                        summer it is difficult to conceive—the lights of Canaletti are like
                        the literal versions, and Turners more like the poetical . . . .” He
                        notes that Turner was very fond of the Val d’Aosta, and that he did
                        not like Subiaco; he inquires eagerly after “the fine collection of
                        Turner’s drawing at <corr type="emend">Mr. Windus’s”;</corr> he often asks about the
                        pictures Turner was showing at the Academy, and once comments on the
                        “corruscation of tints and blooms in the middle distance of his Apollo
                        and Daphne”—which “is nearly, tho’ not quite so much
                        a mystery as ever,” and adds “I am inclined to think that it is
                        like what Paganini’s violin playing is said to have been; something
                        to which no one ever did or will do the like.” In the same place he
                        says “I would give anything to see some of Turner’s best
                        water-colour drawings now; and if I am preserved to come home, shall beg the
                        favour of Mr Daniel to get me a sight of a most splendid collection . . .
                        .” He observed that “the plenitude of light [in Italy] gives a
                        coolness of shadow and a glow of reflection of which we have no notion in
                        England. No one has done it but Turner and he makes the shadows and
                        reflected lights much lighter than in nature.” He carried this
                        enthusiasm home with him, and waited many years in anticipation before he
                        had access to the artist’s bequest, which was at first exhibited in
                        the South Kensington Museum at Brompton: “As soon as the Turners
                        come,” he wrote in 1859, “I shall be out enough you may be sure,
                        in the direction of Brompton.” Turner crops up in Palmer’s
                        letters as a figure whose every action and thought he has studied with love:
                        he adjures his correspondents to look at Turner’s prints for
                        particular subjects; to visit the Fawkes collection of Turner’s
                        drawings at Farnley Hall; he notes that Turner knew Margate well, and that a
                        house near Turner’s was haunted. In short, there are ubiquitous
                        indications that Palmer knew much about the life and work of Turner and had
                        “adopted” him as a touchstone of excellence in the field of
                        contemporary landscape.</p>
          <p>This may seem self-evident, given Turner’s preeminence. But the
                        significance of such a respectful regard in Palmer is far greater than that
                        of the mere professional esteem of the mediocrities in the Water-Colour
                        Society. In Palmer’s later work, we sense the striving to achieve
                        what Turner achieved of enhanced and rapturous union with nature; Turner was
                        not at all like Blake, but in his way he was a visionary artist, and as a
                        practical example for Palmer was far more immediately relevant. Mrs.
                        Hamerton recalled Palmer’s conversation as being spiced with
                        “anecdotes of Turner and Blake,” and this coupling has never, I
                        think, been given its proper weight. Of all the ambitious watercolorists who
                        were influenced by Turner, Palmer was perhaps the only one with the
                        intensity and honesty of vision to benefit from more than his technical
                        lessons. Hence, he is a landscape artist of real distinction in a generation
                        of somewhat shallow virtuosos. Judged by the standards of his youthful
                        achievement—his own standards—he did not maintain his early
                        quality; but judged by <hi rend="i">theirs</hi>, he was a conspicuously fine
                        exponent of the grand watercolor style of the period.</p>
          <p>In his biography, Mr. Lister does not explore Palmer’s achievement in
                        any depth, contenting himself with a reiteration of the conventional summary
                        of his art, and reaffirming what he himself made clear in his book on the
                        etchings (1969), that it was as a printmaker that Palmer, late in life,
                        found himself once more. He concentrates on the personal aspects of
                        Palmer’s life, giving a full account of the long-drawn-out quarrel
                        with Linnell, though he follows A. H. Palmer’s conclusions in
                        apportioning the blame pretty evenly on both sides, while the letters
                        strongly suggest that Palmer was consistently well-intentioned and gentle in
                        his responses to a very difficult man (and the tone of Albin Martin’s
                        correspondence with Linnell—printed here when subjoined to
                        Palmer’s own—is quite as obsequious; which suggests that
                        Palmer was not unusual in being somewhat cowed by his father-in-law). He
                        recounts the appalling tragedy of the deaths of Palmer’s two eldest
                        children; but it is not difficult to present them in their full horror,
                        since Palmer himself put his anguish only too painfully into words. Oddly
                        enough, Mr. Lister offers no explanation for the death of Mary,
                        Palmer’s daughter, in 1847, although in the <hi rend="i">Letters</hi>
                        he quotes a statement by Hannah Palmer that the little girl had been
                        poisoned by a weed she had picked and eaten. All in all, considering the
                        range of documentary material to which he has access, he does not present a
                        picture that differs essentially from the existing one; and he fails to
                        narrate the story in a coherent or interesting way, flinging scraps together
                        as best he can, without giving them an overall and purposeful form. The main
                        facts are, for the most part, there; but Grigson and Cecil make better
                        reading.</p>
          <p>The editing of the letters is handled with much greater success. Mr. Lister
                        has assiduously transcribed, ordered and annotated a mass of confused
                        material, and makes very good sense of it. He has identified a large
                        proportion of the people mentioned, and pinpointed most of the multitudinous
                        quotations. His footnotes are helpful and plentiful. I would suggest that he
                        has erred in identifying the “West” to whose “recollections
                        from the old Masters” Hannah Palmer refers on 8 April 1839, and who
                        also appears in a note of 17 February 1829 as Benjamin West, P. R. A: this
                        is surely Joseph West, the watercolor copyist who made transcriptions of
                        pictures in the Louvre and other collections in a style influenced by
                        Bonington. I think, too, that it is mistaken to identify the phrase
                        “The thing that is not” as a quotation from <hi rend="i">Julius
                            Caesar</hi>, Act v, scene iii: it is surely the Houynhmhm paraphrase for
                        a lie, in the fourth book of <hi rend="i">Gulliver’s Travels</hi>,
                        which we know Palmer had read. The letters are very agreeably presented by
                        the Clarendon Press, and Mr. Lister’s system of transcription is on
                        the whole lucid. He eschews the editorial <hi rend="i">sic</hi>, but the
                        printers have not befriended him here, for there are many misprints which
                        can only mislead users of the volumes, who will have no guide as to which
                        are Palmer’s oddities and which the printers’ errors. The
                        editor himself seems guilty of a number of puzzling lapses, as when he
                        transcribes a phrase in a letter of 1839: “inveighed Hannah into the
                        conspiracy” is nonsense as read—the word must be
                        “inveigled”; the misreading is repeated several times. Again, Mr.
                        Lister occasionally interprets lacunae rather oddly: once Palmer ends a
                        letter, after a reference to Heaven, <corr type="emend">“which</corr> 
                        that we may ( ) day see together in good earnest is the hearty prayer of 
                        . . . Yours affectionately,
                        <pb id="p12-154" n="154"/> 
                        S. Palmer”: Mr. Lister inserts (to) in
                        the gap; clearly (one) is the correct reading. I am not sure that I concur
                        with his expansion of ampersand and contractions such as “affy”
                        for “affectionately,” since he does not always expand
                        “ye” for “the” or “wd” for “would.”
                        How very different Blake texts would look if “&amp;” were
                        invariably treated to editorial expansion! But these are minor
                        inconsistencies in a remarkable feat of careful research and consistent
                        editing which, whatever the merits of the biography, itself makes a book
                        extraordinarily well worth reading for its account of the mind of a
                        pathetic, lonely and pessimistic, yet distinguished man. It is a fit summary
                        of Palmer’s naivety and self-denigration, and of his lifelong
                        earnestness in pursuit of an art which was, as Blake had taught him, at
                        least half divine, that he should sign himself, at the conclusion of one of
                        his last letters, “A blind baby feeling for the bosom of
                        truth.”</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
