<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>12.2.frost</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">A New Television Production of the Job Ballet</title>
        <author n="Frost">Everett C. Frost</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">12.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Special Design and Pasteup for this issue</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Everett Frost</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Terrence Hoagwood</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John Kilgore</name>
              <name>Mark Lefebvre</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Cettina Magno</name>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <name>Jeffry Spencer</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_12">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-12-2-0016">
        <pb id="p12-155" n="155"/>
        <div2>
          <figure n="God.12.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="527">
            <head>1 GOD (Robert North).</head>
          </figure>
          <head>
            <title type="main"><hi rend="b">The Story of Job:</hi> An original treatment by Lester
                            Clarke and David Wickes for a television ballet of <hi rend="i">Job: A
                                Masque for Dancing</hi> by Ralph Vaughan Williams (from a treatment
                            by Sir Geoffrey Keynes). Choreography by Robert Cohan. Produced for
                            Thames Television (London) by Lester Clark and Anton Bowler. Directed by
                            Anton Bowler. Performed by members of the London Philharmonic Orchestra
                            (conducted by Vernon Handley) and by members of the London Contemporary
                            Dance Theatre.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Everett C.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Frost</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">I</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Story of Job</hi> is a visual marvel, and creates some
                            interesting puzzles for a reviewer with loyalties both to broadcast
                            media and to Blake which I shall discuss in turn. Perhaps the most
                            impressive aspect of the production is the full and imaginative use it
                            makes of television as a medium for the creation as well as the
                            transmission of art. This is a virtue worth emphasizing (in particular
                            since the production was invested in by a <hi rend="i">commercial</hi>
                            television house rather than one—hypothetically at any
                            rate—freed to invent by public subsidy) for it represents a
                            standard of invention against which television production can be
                            measured.</p>
            <p>The television screen allows for the presentation of two, not three,
                            dimensions. A third dimension can only be suggested by proportion,
                            scale, camera angle, and spatial relationships: long landscape shots,
                            for example, “flatten out.” Further, on television, colors are
                            themselves and do not blend easily, but transmit gravitating in the
                            direction of primaries and secondaries; though television can manage
                            luminescent pastels. This makes the medium ideally suited for
                            two-dimensional visual works such as the water colors of Blake.</p>
            <p>The ballet’s exploitation of these inherent characteristics of the
                            medium is brilliant and operates at all levels of the
                            production—in the treatment, choreography, performance, and
                            post-production mixing of the final videotape. Thus, for example, using
                            overlays of one video image upon another, coupled with effective
                            lighting and the use of lasers, the television ballet creates a visually
                            enriched heaven that is plausibly Blakean. At one moment a circle of
                            angels choreographed for Blakean motion revolves around the throne of
                            God transcending what a stage could allow and creating an environment
                            that is fully mental and unrestricted by the bounds of space and time.
                            At another moment, Satan is represented in fall or flight (the
                            simultaneity of these two points of view being enhanced by the medium)
                            against a backdrop of moving stars, so that he—as in Blakean
                            representation—is simultaneously static and moving, undoubtedly
                            in transition from one place to another, and yet between two places that
                            are wholly out of nature. Unhappily none of the photographic stills of
                            the performance provided by Thames Television to accompany this review
                            exemplifies this, most crucial and most effective, aspect of the
                            production. The intricate collaboration among the people responsible for
                            the initial treatment, the choreography, the performance, and its
                            realization on videotape is masterful.</p>
            <p>Similarly, the collaborators have achieved success with the use of color.
                            For technical reasons having to do with greater success in coping with
                            blue as a backdrop, primary use is made of the Butts set of water colors
                            (as reproduced in the 1935 Morgan facsimile).</p>
            <pb id="p12-156" n="156"/>
            <p>Coloration, costume, backdrop, choreography, and Blake design have been
                            carefully integrated to heighten the visual impact of the ballet, and
                            the luminosity of the television screen assists a striking transference
                            of Blake’s water colors into another medium. The angels and the
                            sons and daughters of Job, for example, wear filmy Blakean gowns of
                            yellow, green, blue, or red. Blake’s water colors are often
                            quoted by the gestures of the dancers and, by crossfading, the water
                            colors and the dancers sometimes coincide, the Blake water color fading
                            into the screen to conclude a scene of danced action.</p>
            <p>For budgetary reasons the scenes in heaven are visually enriched more
                            than the scenes on earth; and the production is thrown off balance by
                            relying more heavily on Blake’s water colors to move the action
                            on earth along than that in heaven.</p>
            <p>The ballet as a television production leaves only two things to complain
                            of:</p>
            <p>If one sees, as I do, Blake’s <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the
                                Book of Job</hi> capturing a mental scene in motion at key moments
                            in the action (as if caught by a candid photographer of the mental drama
                            rather than postures arrived at as poses for the recording angel), then
                            there are moments in the ballet which betray an annoying instinct for
                            reverencing rather than incorporating the key moments Blake hath left
                            us. Thus, for example, Satan and Job dance postures which tantalizingly
                            and dramatically suggest Blake’s well known “Satan Smiting
                            Job with Sore Boils” (and a Blakean thrills at the effectively
                            executed <figure n="ThreeComforters.12.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="750" height="456">
	<head>2 JOB (Robert North), JOB’S WIFE (Siobahn Davies, and
                                    the three COMFORTERS.</head>
</figure> counterpoint between the painting and the ballet) only to
                            conclude with the dancers freezing into a tableau and holding it for the
                            predictable fade to the water color itself. What Blake made
                            dynamic—a moment to be quoted by the dancers in
                            passing—has become self-consciously posed. There are other
                            moments in which the pictures are used more fluidly and effectively (Job
                            and his Accusers, for example); and the illustrations themselves do not
                            always appear when the ballet quotes them, but the overall effect is as
                            I have described it in this instance. There are, I think, reasons for
                            this rigidity which I shall suggest below.</p>
            <p>The second complaint about the production has to do with the generally
                            conservative and conventional nature of television production. In
                            television land, highly imaginative heavens inevitably suggest that
                            conflation of romance and technology known as science fiction. Thus
                            Blake’s enigmatic stony furniture in heaven, as designed for the
                            sets in this ballet, is made to resemble a generalized futuristic design
                            suggested, say, by the smooth slab that serves as a metaphoric motif in
                            Kubrick’s <hi rend="i">2001.</hi> Similarly, Satan’s
                            descent through the heavens, striking as it is in simultaneously
                            conveying stasis, motion, and transition, additionally carries the
                            unfortunate trappings of the movement of a spaceship through
                            intergalactic space as in conventional science fiction programming like
                                <hi rend="i">Star Trek.</hi></p>
            <p>The music for the production is the Vaughan Williams <hi rend="i">Job: A
                                Masque for Dancing.</hi> It is not, however, the fully orchestrated
                            version available 
<pb id="p12-157" n="157"/>
              <figure n="Job.12.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="798">
	<head>3 JOB (Robert North) with his WIFE (Siobahn Davies).</head>
</figure> commercially on the recording made by Sir Adrian Boult, but
                            the version rescored (by Vaughan Williams) for the touring ballet
                            company in the 1930’s and not given public performance since.
                            This is, of course, a reason in itself for experiencing the production,
                            for this previously unrecorded chamber orchestra version of the work is
                            sensitively done (conducted by Vernon Handley with members of the London
                            Philharmonic Orchestra). Unfortunately one hears it through the tinny
                            speakers reserved for television broadcast and so loses richness.
                            —When, Oh When will television broadcasters and manufacturers
                            conspire to learn that they operate in the same FM band that allows for
                            such magnificent recreation of sound on radio?—</p>
            <p>The dancing is entirely effective and captivating. This is a highly
                            skilled ensemble, fully capable of performing this difficult piece. Of
                            particular note is Namron, who performs the role of Satan—a
                            demanding role, done with flawless articulation and skill. There has
                            been some irritated response for having cast the only black dancer in
                            the production as Satan. The reply has to be, of course, that he
                            interprets the role magnificently and that no racial slur is implied.
                            Still, the production might easily have clarified the racial ambiguities
                            simply by integrating the casting of the sons and daughters and/or the
                            comforters of Job.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">II</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The second portion of the review is more problematic than the first; and
                            its problematic nature is suggested by the lineage that results in this
                            production.</p>
            <p>In the beginning there was Job. Then there were Blake’s
                            illustrations of it, and then the scenario by Sir Geoffrey Keynes from
                            which Ralph Vaughan Williams composed a score, out of which Dame Ninette
                            de Valois created a ballet. The music is now used for a new treatment
                            and a new choreography. To whom should a reviewer owe his allegiance if
                            he does not want simply to bloom in a demonstration of the anxieties of
                            influence? For purposes of the second portion of this review, I will
                            place mine squarely with Blake on the grounds that no one involved in
                            the conception of <hi rend="i">The Story of Job</hi> thought they were
                            doing it without him. I do so with the insistence that it is possible to
                            make a satisfying artistic experience unintentionally abusing or even
                            deliberately misreading Blake.</p>
            <p>On its merits, this is a wonderful production. It is not Blake, though
                            its producers would like it to be so. The ballet contains a narration
                            (competently managed by Andrew Cruickshank) from the Authorized Version
                            of the Bible, amounting to a plot synopsis, and implying that Blake is
                            merely illustrating the well-known text. This ignores Blake’s own
                            inscriptions on the engraved designs which quote the Bible from Genesis
                            to Revelation and additionally provide invented “captions” of
                            his own. Nor is this complaint easily dismissed as one made on behalf of
                            Blake specialists petulant for being dispensible; for it is the main
                            thrust of the designs that is bypassed in ways that some basic awareness
                            of Blake’s work might well have precluded. Blake’s
                            relationship to any text he illuminates is enigmatic and elliptical;
                            seldom does he simply illustrate; and nowhere is this more true than in
                            his intricate visual <hi rend="i">interpretation</hi> of The Book of
                            Job—as the commentary by Keynes and Binyon in the Morgan
                            facsimile might have indicated.</p>
            <p>The designs are variously mimed, quoted, and shown without much attention
                            to what they mean because they are taken as illustrations rather than
                            illuminations of Job; and this, I think, accounts for some of the
                            woodenness mentioned earlier in the review.</p>
            <pb id="p12-158" n="158"/>
            <p>The ballet dutifully (and promisingly) begins and ends with the first and
                            last of Blake’s illustrations—with the musical instruments
                            hanging up in the tree in the first illustration and being played in the
                            last. But the ballet has the performers dancing about with queer Blakean
                            instruments in the concluding scene without knowing what to do with them
                            other than to freeze in place for the final quotation, cross-mix, and
                            fade. For the point has been missed—that Job has undergone a last
                            judgment from a pious and dutiful reverence for his gifts to an
                            energetic and creative use of them. The end of the ballet seems piously
                            grateful for the hard time just got over; and we are <hi rend="i">still</hi> in
need of the Blakean vision we ought just to have had
                            to correct it. This is an error of interpretation that interferes with
                            the entire ballet. The initial relationship between Job and his wife and
                            between Job and his children is danced as far too affectionate and
                            caring for the story Blake is telling. This provides an opportunity for
                            some beautifully rendered ensemble and duet dancing, particularly by Job
                            (Robert North) and his wife (Siobahn Davies), but it is not Blake.</p>
            <p>In Blake’s designs, Job and his God are reflections of each other,
                            and this feature is somewhat enhanced by having both characters
                            interpreted by the same dancer, Robert North. North sustains both roles
                            with eloquence and skill; but the roles, makeup, hair style, and manner
                            have been made different and so the point is lost. As Job, he is fluid,
                            emotionally vigorous and appealing, and too young; while as God he is
                            staccato, deliberate, and a bit harried, but not convincingly
                            authoritative.</p>
            <p>But perhaps most annoying, and attributable to the same failure of
              interpretation outlined above: <figure n="JobDaughters.12.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="578">
	<head>4 JOB (Robert North) rejoicing with his daughters after his
                                    new understanding of GOD.</head>
</figure> the sequence of the designs is altered. It is out of the
                            fourteenth illustration (When the Morning Stars Sang Together)
                            beautifully rendered that Satan’s descent emerges, thus losing
                            the point of struggling to arrive at that epiphany. Further,
                            Job’s Evil Dream (illustration 11) is moved considerably forward
                            such that the sequence of Job’s torments emerge out of his dream,
                            rather than Blake’s way, that among Job’s
                            torments—and perhaps the most decisive of them—is his
                            apocalyptic dream. Thus the ballet conveys the uneasy implication that
                            all that occurs to Job is “only” a dream, albeit a moving and
                            prophetic one. It must be added, however, that within the context of the
                            dream, the sequence of devastations is eloquently rendered, as is the
                            interaction between Job and his Comforters, including Elihu (Ross
                            McKim)—these last being rendered in a Blakean way.</p>
            <p>There is no reason why the production of a ballet cannot rework
                            Blake’s visual materials to its own ends. But for what purpose?
                            to what end? In this instance I infer that the producers had not
                            intended to do so; and that a production which moved me and which I
                            liked might have been more moving yet had it adhered to what it tried to
                            convey in a centrifugal rather than centripetal manner. In the form we
                            have it, the production loses an imaginative center and focus.</p>
            <p>I close with a lament that while an English audience has had an
                            opportunity to view the production, no such prospect seems imminent for
                            American television audiences. The approximate cost for securing rights
                            to American broadcast is estimated at $16,000—not much as these
                            things go—but initial reactions from American public television
                            are discouraging.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
