<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>12.2.spencer</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">The Book of Job Illustrated by William Blake (Paddington Masterpiece
series)</title>
        <author n="Spencer">Jeffry Spencer</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">12.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Special Design and Pasteup for this issue</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Everett Frost</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Terrence Hoagwood</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John Kilgore</name>
              <name>Mark Lefebvre</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Cettina Magno</name>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <name>Jeffry Spencer</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_12">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-12-2-0016">
		<pb id="p12-154" n="154"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main"><hi rend="b">The Book of Job Illustrated by William Blake.</hi>
                            Introduction by Michael Marqusee. Paddington Masterpieces of the
                            Illustrated Book. London and New York: Paddington Press Ltd., Two
                            Continents Publishing Group, 1976. 52 pp., illus. $4.95, paper.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Jeffry</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Spencer</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>This paperback volume represents more of a tribute to Blake’s
                        marketability than to his artistry. Its modest price will ensure its
                        popularity in museum shops from Los Angeles to London, where, regrettably,
                        it will attract buyers who are interested in Blake but relatively uninformed
                        about him. For their five-dollar investment they will receive a fairly
                        competent eleven-page introduction to the poet-artist and to the Job
                        illustrations, a thirty-five page reprint of the Book of Job in the
                        Authorized Version, and twenty-two plates of decidedly inferior quality.</p>
          <p>The title page of this book suggests that it has been designed as one of a
                        series of “Masterpieces of the Illustrated Book,” and Michael
                        Marqusee’s introductory essay is directed at the appreciative
                        amateur. Its three-part division discusses “Blake and the Bible,”
                        “Blake as a Visual Artist,” and “Blake’s Illustrations
                        of the Book of Job” in, respectively, three, two-and-a-half, and six
                        double-columned pages. The brevity of these sections prevents any
                        exploration of those complexities and contradictions that make the
                        interpretation of Blake’s works so difficult and yet so rewarding;
                        what remains is an over-generalized, simplified rehash of prior scholarship
                        (although no debts are acknowledged in this undocumented introduction),
                        studded with illustrative quotations from the poetry and prose. Although
                        there is nothing here that one can condemn as blatantly wrong-headed, there
                        is equally little that is fresh or exciting to praise. The best that can be
                        said is that no one coming to Blake through this introduction will be
                        seriously misinformed. Had the publishers of this volume chosen to trim that
                        half of its length that is given over to needlessly reprinting the entire
                        Book of Job, replacing those pages with a more substantial introduction to
                        the plates, the prospective purchaser would have been better served. Space
                        might then have been found for a section listing Blake’s textual
                        variations from the King James Job, similar to the ones that appear in
                        Foster Damon’s <hi rend="i">Blake’s Job</hi> (Brown, 1966) and
                        in Appendix I of Andrew Wright’s <hi rend="i">Blake’s Job</hi>
                        (Oxford, 1972). Additionally, the reader would profit from the sort of
                        sensible analysis of the marginal texts provided by Jenijoy LaBelle in 
<hi rend="i">The Visionary Hand</hi> (ed. Robert N. Essick, Los Angeles,
                        1973).</p>
          <p>Passing from text to picture provides further grounds for even deeper
                        dissatisfaction. Reproductions are slightly larger (about five-eighths of an
                        inch) than the originals, though this discrepancy is not noted. Such
                        enlargement may have been deemed necessary to show detail: the printing is
                        very dark, and highly shadowed sections of many plates are muddy and
                        indistinct, despite the dead white paper that provides a brighter background
                        than the grayish or creamy tones of papers used at the time of the
                        publication of the originals. Night scenes like Plate XII (“I am Young
                        &amp; ye are very Old . . . ”) are especially poor; in this plate the
                        outline of Elihu’s figure is indistinct at the left, and the
                        configuration of the mountain behind Job is not wholly visible. Comparing
                        these plates, page by page, with those in the clothbound edition of 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Job</hi> published by Brown University, one
                        cannot fail to be dismayed at the very much poorer quality of the newer set.
                        Indeed, even the Dutton paperback version of Damon (with illustrations in
                        reduced size) provides clearer reproduction—and at half the cost of
                        the Paddington Press volume.</p>
          <p>Wearied as perhaps we are by the crescendo of lamentations that bewail the
                        encroachment of pop culture into the Temple of Art, we must regard this
                        volume as another bit of evidence that an increasing interest in
                        museum-going and concomitant rise in museum shop sales are combining to make
                        ventures like this one more and more commercially rewarding. We who love
                        Blake ordinarily rejoice when reproductions of his work are made more
                        available and inexpensive. If, however, as here, greater accessibility is
                        offset by a significant decrease in quality, what appears gain may well be
                        loss.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
