<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>12.2.lincoln</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The Four Zoas: The Text of Pages 5, 6, &amp; 7, Night the First</title>
        <author n="Lincoln">Andrew Lincoln</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">12.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Special Design and Pasteup for this issue</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Everett Frost</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Terrence Hoagwood</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John Kilgore</name>
              <name>Mark Lefebvre</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Cettina Magno</name>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <name>Jeffry Spencer</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_12">
    <body>
      <pb id="p12-91" n="91"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-12-2-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">THE FOUR ZOAS:</hi> THE TEXT OF PAGES 5, 6, &amp;
                            7, NIGHT THE FIRST</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">ANDREW</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">LINCOLN</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>The first Night of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is one of the most heavily
                    revised parts of the poem, and the physical evidence in the manuscript is
                    sometimes highly confusing, especially where Blake changed his mind more than
                    once about a particular revision. Blake’s editors have the daunting task
                    of trying to establish the latest revision of the text when the process of
                    revision was probably never finally completed. The conflicting evidence about
                    the ending of Night the First has been interpreted convincingly,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">1</ref> but there are some areas of the text which
                    require further consideration. <note id="n30"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See W. H.
                        Stevenson, “Two problems in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter</hi> 3 (Dec. 1967), pp. 14-17.</note></p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">THE UNION OF THARMAS AND ENION</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Erdman says that the fragment page 143 represents Blake’s revision of
                        the text of page 7 of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">2</ref> and in his text (pages 299-300) its readings are
                        given priority over the readings of page 7. The relationship between the two
                        manuscript pages is complicated, and requires consideration in some detail.
                            <note id="n31"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i"> The Poetry and Prose of William
Blake</hi>, ed. David V.
                            Erdman, commentary by Harold Bloom, rev. ed. (New York, 1968), p.
                            742.</note></p>
          <p>The modified copperplate text on pages 5-7<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">3</ref> describes how Tharmas sinks into the sea and his Spectre
                        emerges to woo Enion. A dialogue between Enion and the Spectre leads into
                        the description of their mating in the surviving copperplate lines on the
                        lower half of page 7. Hardly and of the original copperplate text that was
                        erased on pages 3-6 can be deciphered, but Erdman has reconstructed the
                        first six copperplate lines at the top of page 7 thus: 
						<q> ? “Weeping,
                            then bending from his Clouds he stoopd his innocent head”<lb/>
 ?
                            “And stretching out his holy hand in the vast Deep
                            sublime”<lb/>
 ? “Turnd round the circle of Destiny with tears
                            &amp; bitter sighs”<lb/>
 And said Return O Wanderer when the day
                            of clouds is o’er;<lb/>
 So saying he . . . ? fell . . . into the
                            restless sea<lb/>
 Round rolld ?the . . . globe self balanc’d.
						</q>
						It appears from these lines that in the original copperplate text the
                        union between Tharmas and Enion occurred when the “innocent”
                        Tharmas fell into the sea, and that he, rather than the Spectre, was
                        Enion’s partner. It is possible that there was no mention of the
                        Spectre in the copperplate text. Centainly, the term only appears in
                        additions in the copperplate lines surviving on page 7 (in lines 23 and 27).
                        Erdman (p. 743) observes that the first six lines at the top of page 7
                        “were apparently moved to p 5 for the modified copperplate addition
                        there of lines 9-14 and 25,” and they may well have been moved towards
                        the beginning of the Night to make room for the account of the emergence of
                        the Spectre introduced on pages 5-7. It is very strange that Enion’s
                        partner in the union, in the copperplate text, should have been the
                        “innocent” Tharmas, as the description of the union on page 7
                        refers to his “horrible brightness” and his “poisons,”
                        which seem to be qualities characteristic of the Spectre. This anomaly
                        suggests that when he transcribed the copperplate text, Blake had already
                        developed a myth involving the union of Enion with a spectre-like Tharmas,
                        but that for some reason he decided to omit the description of this
                        character. Perhaps he had found no way of relating the spectre-like figure
                        to the innocent Tharmas: these conflicting aspects of Tharmas’
                        divided character are related in the modified copperplate revisions by the
                        device of the Spectre. Blake’s difficulties in the copperplate text
                        may have arisen from the fact that he had not yet invented this device, and
                        that the spectre-like character was called simply Tharmas—as in the
                        fragment page 141. <note id="n32"><hi rend="s">3</hi> In all quotations line
                            numbering follows that in <hi rend="i">Vala, or The Four Zoas</hi>, ed.
                            G. E. Bentley, Jr. (Oxford, 1963), hereafter referred to as
                            Bentley.</note></p>
          <p>Bearing this possibility in mind, I want to turn to the text of the fragment
                        pages 143-44, <pb id="p12-92" n="92"/>
which is transcribed below.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">4</ref> Additions are enclosed in angle
                        brackets &lt;&gt;; pencil additions are preceded by <hi rend="s">0</hi>; deletions and
erasures are in italics within square brackets,
                            [<hi rend="i">thus</hi>].
<q> &lt;<hi rend="s">0</hi>Opening his
                            rifted rocks&gt; mingling [<hi rend="i">their bodies</hi>]
                                &lt;<hi rend="s">0</hi>together they&gt; join in burning
                            anguish<lb/>
 Mingling his horrible [<hi rend="i">brightness</hi>]
                                &lt;<hi rend="s">0</hi>darkness&gt; with her tender limbs
                            then high she soard &lt;<hi rend="s">0</hi>72&gt;<lb/>
 Shrieking
                            above the ocean: a bright wonder that nature shudderd at<lb/>
 Half Woman
                            &amp; half [<hi rend="i">Serpent</hi>] &lt;<hi rend="s">0</hi>beast&gt; all his
[<hi rend="i">lovely changing</hi>]
                                &lt;<hi rend="s">0</hi>darkly waving&gt; colours mix<lb/>
                            With her fair crystal clearness in her lips &amp; cheeks his 
[<hi rend="i">poisons</hi>] &lt;metals&gt; rose<lb/>
 In blushes
                            like the morning &amp; his [<hi rend="i">scaly armour</hi>] &lt;<hi
rend="s">0</hi>rocky features&gt; softning<lb/>
 A [<hi rend="i">monster</hi>] &lt;<hi rend="s">0</hi>wonder&gt; lovely in
                            the heavens or wandring on the earth 140<lb/>
 With [<hi rend="i">Serpent</hi>] &lt;female&gt; voice &lt;warbling upon
                            the [<hi rend="i">hills</hi>] &amp; hollow vales&gt;<lb/>
 Beauty
                            all blushing with desire &lt;a Self enjoying wonder&gt;<lb/>
                            &lt;For Enion brooded groaning loud the rough seas vegetate. Golden
                            rocks rise from the [<hi rend="i">vorte</hi>]
                            &lt;vast&gt;&gt;<lb/>
 And thus her voice; &lt;Glory,
                            delight, &amp; sweet enjoyment born&gt;<lb/>
 &lt;To mild
                            Eternity shut in a threefold shape delightful&gt;<lb/>
 To wander in
                            &lt;sweet&gt; solitude &lt;enrapturd&gt; at every
                            wind<lb/>
 &lt;[<hi rend="i">Shining across the ocean/ Enion brooded
                                groaning the golden rocks vegetate The</hi> ?<hi rend="i">b</hi>]&gt; &lt;[<hi
rend="i">to</hi>] Infolding the bright
                            woman [<hi rend="i">from the desolating winds / &amp; thus her voice
                                &amp;</hi>]&gt; </q>
On the verso of this leaf (page 144) are
                        two lines, one cut short where the page is torn: 
						<q> That I should hide thee
                            with my power &amp;<lb/>
 And now thou darknest in my presence, never
                            from my sight </q>
Beneath these lines is a drawing of a nude figure
                        entwined by a serpent. <note id="n33"><hi rend="s">4</hi> This transcript
                            differs in some readings (and in the marking of passages as insertions)
                            from the 1968 text, since it incorporates corrections made by Erdman
                            after reading this essay in draft and consulting the manuscript
                            again.</note></p>
          <figure n="BB209.1.144.MS" rend="file" width="958" height="674">
            <head><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 144 (fragment).</head>
          </figure>
          <p>Bentley, commenting on this fragment, argues that “Blake was copying
                        from the copperplate draft (probably already bound at this point) into his
                        notebook.” His argument rests chiefly on the fact that the lines on
                        page 144 appear as an addition on page 7, and on the observation that
                        “the first draft of the notebook clearly reproduces corrections in
                        Night I, while none of the changes introduced into the notebook are repeated
                        in Night I.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">5</ref>
The two lines on page
                        144 reappear on page 7 as part of a modified copperplate revision describing
                        the Spectre’s relationship with Enion. If, as I suggest, the
                        description of the spectre-like Tharmas existed before the copperplate text
                        of Night I was transcribed, it follows that the lines on page 144 may have
                        existed long before they appeared as additions on page 7. Parts of the basic
                        text of both pages 7 and 143 have been obscured by subsequent revisions, but
                        there are two examples of additions on page 7 which appear in the basic text
                        of page 143. Unfortunately, both of these are problematic. On page 7
                        “Shrieking” was added in the margin before “Above the
                        ocean” in line 22; it was subsequently deleted, which suggests that
                        Blake changed his mind more than once about including it. In the same line
                        “Nature” is clearly an addition replacing “Beulah”;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">6</ref> but “Beulah” was an addition
                        over an erased word, which introduces the possibility that when Blake
                        deleted Beulah he was restoring the original term.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">7</ref> In other words it is not really clear whether page
                        143 does incorporate corrections made on page 7, or whether Blake derived
                        the account on page 7 from the fragment, making changes which were
                        subsequently revoked; and the fact that none of the changes made in the
                        fragment were repeated in Night I gives no indication of relative date.
                            <note id="n34"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Bentley, p. 160.</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">6</hi> When he composed the description of
                                the union, Blake may have been thinking of Milton’s
                                description of the original sin: 
<q> Earth felt the wound, and
                                    Nature from her seat<lb/>
 Sighing through all her works gave
                                    signs of woe.<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, IX, 781-82 </q></note>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">7</hi> I now make out the erased word to be
                            “Nature”—D.V.E.</note></p>
          <p>The text of page 143 has been subject to three distinct sets of revisions.
                        The earliest are probably the additions made over erasures. That Blake
                        should have bothered to make erasures here casts some doubt on the idea that
                        the fragment comes from a notebook, as it indicates that he had some concern
                        for the appearance of the page—that it was regarded in the first
                        place as a fair copy, and that the revisions were not intended to be
                        retranscribed in a subsequent fair copy. The additions made over erasures
                        were probably appropriate to the original context of the fragment, but they
                        seem inappropriate for the context of Night I. They consistently emphasize
                        that the product of the union is an epitome of the female will: the words
                        “female,” “warbling,” “sweet,”
                        “enrapturd” all contribute to the feeling of sexual bliss. Bentley
                        suggests that the words “Glory delight &amp; sweet enjoyment
                        born” are the beginning of “Enion’s song about the beauties
                        of the natural world.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37"
type="note">8</ref> However,
                        the song seems singularly inappropriate to Enion, who in <hi rend="i">The
                            Four Zoas</hi> consistently complains about the conditions of experience
                        (in the first two Nights she sings two great laments about the horrors of
                        the natural world). This anomaly is emphasized by a separate 
<pb id="p12-93" n="93"/>
set of revisions in the fragment which introduce a
                        “groaning” Enion to sing the song (lines 10, 14, 15). 
<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Bentley, p. 160. Bentley apparently thinks
                            that the descriptive passage 8:14-17 was to become part of
                            Enitharmon’s song.</note></p>
          <p>In the basic text of the fragment the song is sung by the product of the
                        union of the male and female partners. Raine suggests that the description
                        of the union is derived from Ovid’s story of Hermaphroditus,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">9</ref> the youth who is ensnared in a river by
                        the water nymph Salmacis, until both are fused into a single, hermaphroditic
                        body. Thus, the union in the fragment appears to be a union in the literal
                        sense, a “mingling” of two bodies to form a new creature which has
                        a dual nature. Ovid’s tale is a story of female triumph, and the tone
                        of ironic rapture in the song on page 143 seems appropriate to the beginning
                        of a song celebrating the triumph of the female will. It is a song which
                        would be more appropriate to Enitharmon than to Enion (see for example
                        Enitharmon’s songs in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> and <hi rend="i">The
                            Four Zoas</hi> 34:56-90); and Enitharmon would seem to be the likely
                        product of the union of two characters called Tharmas and Enion who are
                        fused into a single, fallen being. <note id="n38"><hi rend="s">9</hi>
                            Kathleen Raine, <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi> (Princeton, 1968),
                            I, 282-85.</note></p>
          <p>So far, then, I have made two suggestions: (a) that in the copperplate text
                        of pages 3-7 Blake was adapting an earlier myth with only partial success,
                        omitting the description of the spectre-like Tharmas; and (b) that the basic
                        text of page 143 may have been part of a myth describing the creation of
                        Enitharmon. These are both conjectures drawn from meager evidence, but I
                        believe they are supported by other available evidence, and that they help
                        to illuminate the problem of the relative dates of pages 7 and 143.</p>
          <p>One set of revisions on page 143 is in pencil. These revisions consistently
                        modify the “bright” or spectre-like qualities of Tharmas in the
                        union. For example, “horrible brightness” becomes “horrible
                        darkness,” “lovely changing colours” become “darkly
                        waving colours,” and “scaly armour” becomes “rocky
                        features.” All of these changes seem designed to suggest that Tharmas
                        degenerates into a desolate marine god as he mates with Enion. If Blake did
                        omit the Spectre from the copperplate text of pages 3 to 7, he may well have
                        considered making changes like these to eradicate the spectral qualities
                        which remained in the description of the union. However, being in pencil
                        they may have been tentative suggestions which Blake decided not to adopt
                        when he transcribed page 7.</p>
          <p>The remaining revisions on page 143 were in ink. Blake began these revisions
                        by inserting two lines (written as one) between lines 9 and 11: “For
                        Enion brooded groaning loud the rough seas vegetate. Golden rocks rise from
                        the vorte . . . ” (part of the second line was lost when the page was
                        torn). He made a second attempt at this revision at the foot of the page,
                        lines 14 and 15. The initial half-line “Shining across the ocean”
                        would replace the end of line 9. Blake conflated the two lines of his
                        previous insertion into a single line by substituting “golden
                        rocks” in the second line for “rough seas” in the first. The
                        conflated line is followed by “The V . . . ,” or “The b . . .
                        ,” the remains of words which were lost when the page was torn. The
                        next line reads “[<hi rend="i">to</hi>] Infolding the bright woman [<hi rend="i">from
the desolating winds</hi>],” the initial
                        “to” being part of an instruction: in other words, Blake was
                        probably indicating that another passage, from “The ?b . . . ” to
                        “Infolding the bright woman . . . ” should be introduced here. The
                        conflated line appears in the copperplate text of page 8 as “Enion
                        brooded, oer the rocks, the rough rocks &lt;groaning
                        vegetate&gt;,” and this line introduces a description of the
                        awakening natural world which begins “The barked oak . . . ” and
                        ends with the line “Infolding the bright children from the desolating
                        winds.” This may have been the passage cited for inclusion in the text
                        of page 143.</p>
          <p>If the basic text of page 143 originally described how Tharmas and Enion lose
                        their individual identities to become Enitharmon, Blake would have made
                        revisions like these when he adapted the text for use in <hi rend="i">The
                            Four Zoas.</hi> Tharmas and Enion were to remain separate, and he had to
                        account for the creation of Enitharmon’s consort, Los. The added
                        reference to Enion brooding identifies the woman-serpent with Enion herself,
                        suggesting that Enion temporarily assumes this form while mating with
                        Tharmas. The additions still end with “&amp; thus her voice,” so
                        at this stage Blake still intended to introduce the lyric song which would
                        be inappropriate to Enion; but the additions introduce “rough
                        seas,” a “groaning” Enion and “desolating winds,”
                        all in stark contrast to the blissful tone of the rest of the passage. In
                        the copperplate text the revisions begun in the fragment are apparently
                        taken one stage further: the song is omitted; “golden rocks”
                        become “rough rocks,” “golden” probably being eliminated
                        because it seemed out of keeping with Enion’s desolate condition; and
                        the “bright woman” of 143:15, a phrase inappropriate to the
                        degenerate Enion, becomes “bright children,” enabling Blake to
                        suggest that both Los and Enitharmon were created by the union. It seems,
                        then, that in the fragment Blake was beginning to make necessary adjustments
                        to the tone of the passage, and that this process is more complete in the
                        copperplate text. Page 143 may represent an intermediate stage in the
                        composition of the copperplate text, and all of the revisions on the page
                        may have been made before the copperplate text was transcribed. The
                        substitution of page 143 for page 7 in the text of <hi rend="i">The Four
                            Zoas</hi> therefore seems unjustified. We must turn to the copperplate
                        text itself to establish a final text.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">THE INK CIRCLES ON PAGES 5, 6, &amp; 7</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>In three places near the beginning of the poem, deleted passages were circled
                        in ink. These are: 5:46-55, Enion’s horrified reaction to the
                        Spectre; 6:26, 28-38 (a single block), the Spectre’s accusation of
                        Enion and her reply; 7:1-11, the rest of Enion’s reply to the
                        Spectre. Blake did not normally draw an ink circle around a passage he
                        wanted to delete, which suggests that these circles have a special
                        significance.</p>
          <p>The circled passage at the foot of page 5 was deleted by three slanting ink
            strokes. However, part of the circle was erased when lines 29 and 30 
<pb id="p12-94" n="94"/>
<figure n="BB209.1.5.MS" rend="file" width="747" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>In Eden, Females sleep the winter in soft silken veils<lb/>
					Woven by their own hands to hide them in the darksom grave<lb/>
					But Males immortal live renewd by female deaths. in soft<lb/>
					Delight they die &amp; they revive in spring with music &amp; songs<lb/>
					Enion said Farewell I die I hide. from thy searching eyes<lb/>
					<lb/>
					So saying—From her bosom weaving soft in Sinewy threads<lb/>
					A tabernacle for Jerusalem she sat among the Rocks<lb/>
					Singing her lamentation. Tharmas groand among his Clouds<lb/>
					Weeping, then bending from his Clouds he stoopd his innocent head<lb/>
					And stretching out his holy hand in the vast Deep sublime<lb/>
					Turnd round the circle of Destiny with tears &amp; bitter sighs<lb/>
					And said. Return O Wanderer when the Day of Clouds is oer<lb/>
					<lb/>
					So saying he sunk down into the sea a pale white corse<lb/>
					In torment he sunk down &amp; flowd among her filmy Woof<lb/>
					His Spectre issuing from his feet in flames of fire<lb/>
					In gnawing pain drawn out by her lovd fingers every nerve<lb/>
					She counted. every vein &amp; lacteal threading them among<lb/>
					Her woof of terror. Terrified &amp; drinking tears of woe<lb/>
					Shuddring she wove—nine days &amp; nights Sleepless her food was tears<lb/>
					Wondring she saw her woof begin to animate. &amp; not<lb/>
					<lb/>
					As Garments woven subservient to her hands but having a will	<lb/>
					Of its own perverse &amp; wayward Enion lovd &amp; wept<lb/>
					<lb/>
					Nine days she labourd at her work. &amp; nine dark sleepless nights<lb/>
					But on the tenth trembling morn the Circle of Destiny Complete<lb/>
					Round rolld the Sea Englobing in a watry Globe self balancd<lb/>
					A Frowning Continent appeard Where Enion in the Desart<lb/>
					Terrified in her own Creation viewing her woven shadow<lb/>
					Sat in a dread intoxication of Repentance &amp; Contrition<lb/>
					<lb/>
					{He spurnd Enion with his foot he sprang aloft in Clouds<lb/>
					Alighting in his drunken joy in a far distant Grove}<lb/>
					<lb/>
					There is from Great Eternity a mild &amp; pleasant rest<lb/>
					Namd Beulah a Soft Moony Universe feminine lovely<lb/>
					Pure mild &amp; Gentle given in Mercy to those who sleep<lb/>
					Eternally. Created by the Lamb of God around<lb/>
					On all sides within &amp; without the Universal Man<lb/>
					The Daughters of Beulah follow sleepers in all their Dreams<lb/>
					Creating Spaces lest they fall into Eternal Death<lb/>
					The Circle of Destiny complete they gave to it a Space<lb/>
					And namd the Space Ulro &amp; brooded over it in care &amp; love<lb/>
	<lb/>
					<lb/>
					They said The Spectre is in every man insane &amp; most<lb/>
					Deformd Thro the three heavens descending in fury &amp; fire<lb/>
					We meet it with our Songs &amp; loving blandishments &amp; give<lb/>
					To it a form of vegetation But this Spectre of Tharmas<lb/>
	<lb/>
					Is Eternal Death What shall we do O God pity &amp; help<lb/>
					So spoke they &amp; closd the Gate of the Tongue in trembling fear<lb/>
					<lb/>
					What have I done! said Enion accursed wretch! What deed.<lb/>
					Is this a deed of Love I know what I have done. I know<lb/>
					Too late now to repent. Love is changd to deadly Hate<lb/>
					A[ll] life is blotted out &amp; I alone remain possessd with Fears<lb/>
					I see the Shadow of the dead within my Soul wandering<lb/>
					In darkness &amp; solitude forming Seas of Doubt &amp; rocks of Repentance<lb/>
					Already are my Eyes reverted. all that I behold<lb/>
					Within my Soul has lost its splendor &amp; a brooding Fear<lb/>
					Shadows me oer &amp; drives me outward to a world of woe<lb/>
					So waild she trembling before her own Created Phantasm<lb/>
					<lb/>
					{Who animating times on times by the Force of her sweet song}<lb/>
					{But standing on the Rocks her woven shadow glowing bright}<lb/>
					<lb/>
					Reard</figTranscr>
	<head><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 5.</head>
</figure> were added, and part of a deleting line was erased when Blake
                        revised the end of line 48 (Bentley does not record this revision, but
                        Erdman shows that “Love is changed to . . . hate” is a subsequent
                        addition). The passage was revised after it had been deleted, and after it
                        had been circled. The circled passage at the foot of page 6 was deleted by
                        two slanting ink strokes, but these strokes were partly erased when Blake
                        made additions in lines 29-31, and part of the circle was erased when Blake
                        added line 38 at the bottom of the passage. Again, this means that the
                        passage was revised after both the ink circle and the deleting lines had
                        been added. On the same page lines 9-25 were deleted by ink strokes and also
                        by a grey wash. The grey wash, however, does not cover the circled passage.
                        At the top of page 7 two long slanting ink strokes deleted the text down to
                        line 18, extending down below the ink circle (which surrounds lines 1 to
                        11). Within the circle the deleting lines were partly erased when lines 1 to
                        8 were added. Here, as in the other circled passages, the text was revised
                        after it had been deleted. Revisions to the deleted text only occur within
                        the ink circles, which suggests that the passages were first deleted, and
                        subsequently circled in ink because Blake changed his mind and decided to
                        retain them. The fact that the gray wash on page 6 avoids the circled
                        passage but covers the other deleted lines on the page seems to confirm
                        this.</p>
          <figure n="BB209.1.6.MS" rend="file" width="781" height="1000">
            <head><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 6.</head>
          </figure>
          <p>It seems possible, then, that the final text on pages 5, 6, and 7 should
                        include some lines which were once deleted, and which are not included in
                        the text edited by Erdman and Stevenson:</p>
          <p>PAGE 5. All the lines within the circle (46-55) should probably be retained
                        as none were individually deleted; but not two lines (29 and 30) added above
                        the circle, which were individually deleted by ink strokes; nor the two
                        lines below the circle—the pencilled insert line 56 (which seems to
                        have been partly erased), and line 57 (which was deleted individually by a
                        pencil stroke).</p>
          <p>PAGE 6. Line 1 follows on from 5:55. Lines 9-25 were deleted by ink strokes
                        and gray wash, and none of the deletion was superseded by subsequent
                        revisions, so these lines are definitely excluded. The circled passage
                        (lines 26-38) was revised after deletion, but some lines within the passage
                        were deleted individually in pencil. The end of the first line and all of
                        the second line (“Art thou not my slave &amp; shalt thou dare / To
                        smite me with thy tongue beware lest I sting thee also”) were deleted
                        and replaced by an addition of one-and-a-half lines (the full line
                        subsequently deleted): 
						<q> Who art thou Diminutive husk &amp; shell 
[<hi rend="i">Broke from my bonds I scorn my prison I scorn &amp; yet I
                          love.</hi>] </q>
	<pb id="p12-95" n="95"/>
<figure n="BB209.1.7.MS" rend="file" width="783" height="1000">
	<head><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 7.</head>
</figure> Lines 29-36 follow on from these. Part of the circle was erased
                        when line 38 was added, effectively replacing line 37 which was deleted in
                        pencil. The circled passage, thus revised, should probably be retained in
                        the text.</p>
          <p>PAGE 7. An ink circle surrounds lines 1-11, and deleting strokes within the
                        circle were superseded when lines 1-8 were added. Lines 1 and 2 were
                        subsequently deleted individually. Line 8 was revised as follows: “[<hi rend="i">Among
wild beasts to roam</hi>] And thou the delusive tempter
                        &lt;to these deeds&gt; sittest before me.” (The first part of
                        the line was deleted in pencil, and the words “to these deeds”
                        were written above a gap between “tempter” and
                        “sittest”). Lines 9, 10, and 11 were deleted individually in
                        pencil, but a pencilled note in the margin by line 11 reads “this line
                        to come in,” indicating that the deletion of this line has been
                        revoked. The final text at the top of page 7, therefore, should probably
                        include lines 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, &amp; 11. The text continues from line 11
                        with the undeleted lines 21-26, which describe the union of the Spectre of
                        Tharmas and Enion. The transition from line 11 to line 21 is unsatisfactory,
                        and Blake made no other addition on the page to ease this transition.
                        However, as this seems to be the latest, if incomplete, revision of the text
                        of page 7, this may be the textual arrangement we should adopt.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
