<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>12.2.derdman</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Night the Seventh: The Editorial Problem</title>
        <author n="Erdman">David V. Erdman</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">12.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Special Design and Pasteup for this issue</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Everett Frost</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Terrence Hoagwood</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John Kilgore</name>
              <name>Mark Lefebvre</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Cettina Magno</name>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <name>Jeffry Spencer</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_12">
    <body>
      <pb id="p12-135" n="135"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-12-2-0013">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">NIGHT THE SEVENTH: THE EDITORIAL PROBLEM</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">DAVID V.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">ERDMAN</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>Henry James managed to overlook typographical errors in his text while
                    concentrating on the serious business of removing commas which the printers had
                    inserted (and some of his own).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86"
type="note">1</ref> William
                    Blake while revising and reorganizing his text managed to overlook cumbrous
                    redundancies—two “Chap: IV” headings in <hi rend="i">The Book
                        of Urizen</hi>, two of “Night the Seventh” in <hi rend="i">The
                        Four Zoas.</hi> Neither writer should be thought to have
                    “abandoned” his works. Perhaps Blake as his own printer (or scribe)
                    might have settled the fate of all those dangling insertions and the two chapter
                    headings if he had lived to inscribe one more fair copy. We shall never know.
                    And we tend to forget that we cannot know how many drafts and revisions and fair
                    copies were made and discarded before the assembling and inscription of the
                    surviving manuscript of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, although it is built on
                    the remains of several fair copies beginning with the one dated “1797”
                    and patched even after the etching of his other epics. When we come upon the
                    insertion of a reference to annihilation of the Selfhood, we may think we are
                    witnessing the dawn of that concept in Blake’s mind: we should allow for
                    the possibility that he had already written his <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> When
                    we debate whether to move the parts or the wholes of the two Nights the Seventh
                    from their positions “in the manuscript,” we forget that Blake did not
                    number his pages (beyond “14” in the first Night) and that the
                    manuscript was a heap of unbound and unsorted sheets when the Linnell brothers
                    lent it to the first editors, Ellis and Yeats. “An attempt had been made to
                    put it in order, but without success,” records Ellis. “The arrangement
                    of the loose sheets occupied us during several long days” (<hi rend="i">The
                        Works of William Blake</hi>, ed. E. J. Ellis and W. B. Yeats, 1893, II,
                    300). <note id="n86"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See H. K. Girling, “A Toot of a
                        Trumpet against the Regiment of Editors,” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of
                            Research in the Humanities</hi>, 81, iii (1978): 297-323.</note></p>
        <p>It has been traditional to scoff at the editorial casualness of Ellis and Yeats,
                    whose transcription of Blake’s words is full of howlers. It has not been
                    recognized that the sequence of pages we accept today is pretty much that
                    established by Ellis’s arrangement, not over those several days but over
                    several years. Many of the sequences were fairly easy to discover, with the help
                    of Blake’s occasional catchwords, his handwriting sizes, his counting of
                    lines by tens and fifties and by Nights, as well as the frequently incontestable
                    narrative flow. But most of these aids are lacking for the area of the present
                    investigation. Here editors are often entirely on their own, attempting by
                    conjectural leaps and plodding deductions to trace the intentions of the
                    apocalyptic imagination. Bentley’s conclusion (p. 197) that each editor
                    is “at liberty to rearrange the leaves as seems best” cannot be taken
                    as a serious generalization, but is practically operative for Night VII. How did
                    the two Nights the Seventh survive? Were they together when Blake turned over
                    the heap of unbound separate leaves (half-sheets) to John Linnell? Had he placed
                    some leaves at the bottom of the pile?</p>
        <p>Let us consider what Ellis found for evidence of order in the manuscript pages of
                    what we are calling VIIa2. The three leaves bearing the pages now numbered
                    85-86, 87, 90 (in our editions, not in the manuscript) were not found where we
                    think they belong. Ellis at one stage considered pages 87 and 90 as part of
                    “5th N[ight]” and tried p. 87 as “p 3” and p. 90 as “p
                    4” of that Night. Later, assembling the leaves bearing pages 90, 87, and
                    86, facing versos up and in that order, Ellis numbered them 1, 2, 3 and queried
                    the first (p. 90) “?fragment 7th (1).” Before press time Ellis and
                    Yeats had assembled and paginated the first ten pages of VIIa and had discovered
                    that the text on 86 (their page 10) follows from the text on the other side,
                    i.e. 85 (their page 
                    9).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n87" type="note">2</ref> 
                    Subsequent editors
                    (perhaps Ellis in the first place) confirmed the sequence of pages 77 through 85
                    by Blake’s own line-counting—but not quite. Margoliouth and
                    Bentley noticed evidence of a potential gap between 84 and 85, but quickly
                    dismissed it. Blake’s pencilled line-count at the bottom of p. 84
                    (“292 or 297”: the poet hesitating whether to keep or cancel five
                    lines of his marginal insertion preceding the last two lines of the page) must
                    signify, judging from his other totals at 
                    <pb id="p12-136" n="136"/> 
                    ends of
                    Nights, that he considered 84:42 as the end of a Night; there is certainly
                    sufficient cadence. Much later (according to Margoliouth and Bentley)
                    Blake’s numbering in ink by fifties produced a line-count of
                    “350” (mended, however, from “370”) alongside line 12 of p.
                    85 (line 8 before insertion of lines 1-4). When Blake made that count he had
                    extended the Night beyond the 292 or 297 lines of pages 77-84, presumably on an
                    intervening leaf containing from 46 to 71 lines (depending on how many of the
                    inserted lines on 84 and 85 he included in his count). The insertion of 85:1-4
                    could have been made to bridge the gap made by removal of the leaf. Margoliouth
                    simply notes that “no lacuna is indicated by the sense” (but of
                    course) and rules that “Blake’s ‘350’ must be meant
                    for ‘300’.” His confidence derives from the consideration
                    that “a lacuna would mean a whole leaf missing with 50 lines (far too few
                    for two pages)”—and from neglect of the fact that some pages have
                    pictures (76, for instance) that take up space. Bentley (pp. 199, 204) repeats
                    the argument: “a missing leaf would probably have about seventy lines on
                    it.” Neither Bentley nor Margoliouth was influenced by the mending of the
                    numeral from 370 to 350, which they did not 
                    observe.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n88" type="note">3</ref> 
                    Confident that there can’t be 50 lines missing
                    because there would have to be 70, Bentley fails to consider that Blake could
                    have written 70 lines and cancelled 20. Blake’s way of working must often
                    have resulted in leaves removed or moved to other positions. I have no
                    hypothesis about the missing leaf, but perhaps Andrew Lincoln can evolve one
                    that suits his hypothetical reconstruction of the movements of parts of Night
                    the Seventh. 
                    <note id="n87"><hi rend="s">2</hi> The Ellis and Yeats edition,
                            1893, numbers lines Night by Night and does not indicate manuscript
                            pages, but the textual sequence is that of the first pencilled series of
                            folio numbers in the manuscript, running from 1 to 68. The texts of pp.
                            15-16 and 111 are given in an Appendix of “fragments.” Some
                            indication of the ordering problems faced by Ellis and Yeats is given by
                            the queries on the leaves of VIIa2 trying them for Night V, then as a
                            misplaced “fragment” of VII, and by the numbering of some
                            Nights by leaves (“sheets”) and by pages. Night V apparently
                            gave difficulty, with some sheets facing wrong side up; the only number
                            on the proper 4th page is “6” (p. 60) and p. 62 was once
                            numbered “5” then “6”—possibly when pp. 87
                            and 90 were queried “5th N p. 3” and “5th N p. 4.”
                            The 9th page has “8” changed to “9.” Finally the
                            proper sequence of leaves 2-5 was marked as “sh2,” “Sht
                            3,” “sht 4,” and “5th sheet,” in pencil notes
                            (partly erased) that seem to cite “cat. Ellis”: perhaps Ellis
                            had made some sort of catalogue of sheets which could be consulted when
                            reshuffling had caused disarray. (It must have been later that these
                            five leaves were <hi rend="i">heavily</hi> designated “Book 5 Page
                            1” etc., with “Book” only twice corrected to
                            “Night”—or can these heavy markings have been
                            Blake’s own, whose heading for this Night first read
                            “Book”? The g’s are more like Ellis’s, but I am
                            uncertain.)
                        <p>Night VI was also marked by sheets, 2d, 3d, 4th, and 5th, correctly, but
                            only the first three pages were given numbers: did doubts remain, or had
                            the problem vanished? Night VIIa was paginated up through “11”
                            (p. 87) and “VII” was written beside Ellis’s “?7th
                            (3)” query. Ellis queried “?what night?” at the top of p.
                            97, but by press-time had taken the plunge of including the sequence we
                            think of as VIIa and VIIb as a single Night. We do not know where the
                            parts had been found—except that they had not been found together
                            and that VIIa1 and a2 had not been together.</p>
						<p>It was not hard to see “what night<corr type="emend">”</corr> p. 97 belonged to, since
                            its verso bears the unerased legend “End of The Seventh
                            Night,” and we find a revealing outcry in Ellis &amp; Yeats (III,
                            173): “Line 786 [95:14] is the only possible end of Night VII”
                            (accepting the transposition of the halves of VIIb). This declaration
                            solved the editorial problem, and pp. 78-98 were printed as a continuous
                            Night. But the failure to paginate VIIb may indicate lingering
                            reservations.</p>
						<p>Night VIII presented no difficulty, except that leaves 56 and 57 were not
                            included in the text until after page numbering—and that the
                            concluding page was not numbered. Night IX has page numbers that only
                            begin with “5” but run correctly to “20” but then
                            jump to “27” followed by “27,” again, with no number
                            on the final page.</p>
						<p>How can we be sure that Edwin J. Ellis wrote these queries? For one
                            thing, they clearly precede the ordering decisions reflected in the 1893
                            edition. For another, Ellis identifies the handwriting by initialing and
                            dating a longish note on page 15: “(a separate sheet. It cannot be
                            placed as its sequel is missing.)—E J E—1891.” The
                            letters, especially the g and t, are distinctive and are identical to
                            those in the word “fragment” on p. 90. Thirteen years later
                            Ellis adds a further note below it: “Perhaps it is all an insertion
                            designed to preceed ‘Enion blind &amp; age bent wept upon the
                            desolate wind, [line] 373,—in the 1st printed numbering [i.e. the
                            1893 text]—Suggestion of Mr. F G Fleay 1904” (i.e. Frederick
                            Gerard Fleay, 1831-1909, editor and poet). These notes tell us why pp.
                            15-16 were kept at the end of the Ellis-Yeats text as
                            “fragments” (along with p. 111, also unplaced). And apparently
                            Fleay’s suggestion was too late for the Ellis 1906 edition, in
                            the press by 1904. Actually both pp. 15-16 and p. 111 remain in the
                            Keynes <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi> (1921) as “additional leaves
                            and fragments” foliated “69” and “70.” Sloss
                            and Wallis finally put both these stray leaves into proper places though
                            they continued some of the confusion of sequences in Nights I and II.
                            For example, the order now accepted, of pp. 18, 21-22, 19-20, was
                            arrived at by much editorial agony. If Ellis had managed, accidentally
                            or with care, to put the leaves in that order, subsequent editors
                            instead of weighing and reasoning might have felt they were merely
                            “retaining the manuscript order.”</p>
						<p>Perhaps it should be noted that the pencil foliation that runs from 1 to
                            68 corresponds to the Ellis-Yeats sequences, while the revision that
                            runs to 70 is made after insertion of pp. 15-16 as folio 8 and of pp.
                            111-12 as folio 56, with the numbers moved forward one after
                            “8” and two after “56.”</p></note>
	<note id="n88"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Margoliouth (p. 133) does note the mending
                        but takes it as 350 “perhaps imperfectly corrected to
                        ‘300’.” I need another look at the manuscript.</note></p>
        <p>Until getting involved in the present discussion, which has been going on for a
                    couple of years, I tended to assume that leaving the manuscript “as it
                    was” meant accepting the order VIIa, VIIb. I have come to realize that
                    there is even less evidence for doing that than for relegating one Night the
                    Seventh to the bottom of the pile. There is evidence, we see, for concluding
                    that Blake, with at least temporary intent, sidetracked VIIb when he inserted
                    VIIa2 as a firm piece of masonry fitting VIIa directly to VIII.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n89" type="note">4</ref> There is also evidence, in the fact that Ellis found
                    pages 85-90 not obviously “in” Night the Seventh at all, that Blake
                    may have removed the masonry unit of pp. 85-90 (all of 7a2 and its bridge from
                    7a1) to leave open a sequence from 84 to 91—or to 99. Ellis does not give
                    page numbers to the pages of 7b and clearly did not find it “in place”
                    either. What finally decided Ellis and Yeats was there being only one terminal
                    rubric “End of The Seventh Night,” the one on p. 98. We all seem to
                    agree that no part of VIIb nor VIIa should be discarded. Blake left no
                    instructions—to himself or posterity—for their arrangement, and
                    those of us who have become familiar enough with the text to face the problem of
                    its arrangement already “have” both Nights, whatever order we read
                    them in. The editorial problem remains: to choose a sequence which will work
                    best, in the context of the whole poem, for the new or the occasional
                        reader.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n90" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n89"><hi rend="s">4</hi> A misreading by Wagenknecht, followed by
                        Kilgore, of my textual note (<hi rend="i">Poetry &amp; Prose</hi>, p. 758)
                        referring to additions on pp. 87 and 90 that tighten the sequence to VIII as
                        a bit of masonry makes for some mirth at that lunatic Erdman who sees
                        masonry in a misfitting conjecture (they take me to refer to possible use of
                        87-90 as an insert on p. 100). I didn’t, of course. But I do write
                        difficult sentences. Recently Robert Essick (in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 43,
                        p. 181) joined Gerald Bentley in misreading my shorthand attempt to define
                        the gesture of the angel embracing “All Religions” as “with
                        arms around stone tablets . . . and a bearded priest . . . ”; I seemed
                        to be saying that the arms were around the tablets only! (<hi rend="i">The
                            Illuminated Blake</hi>, p. 24)</note>
	<note id="n90"><hi rend="s">5</hi> The ideal edition for scholars will be a
                        photographic and typographic facsimile, with better photographs, and
                        transcripts freed of the misleading features of the Margoliouth and Bentley
                        editions. New photographic techniques may one day restore the erasures and
                        palimpsest to legibility. The transcripts should not confuse fair copy and
                        palimpsest, as Bentley’s do.</note></p>
        <p>My editorial self has been moved by the present discussion, further homework, and
                    discussions with John Grant and Harold Bloom, to abandon those non-solutions,
                    the relegating of VIIb to a postscript or the printing of VIIa and VIIb in
                    tandem. Neither arrangement responds adequately to the manuscript or to the
                    reader’s appreciation of an inclusive yet coherent narrative or thematic
                    sequence or structure. As the search for Blake’s “final
                    intentions” disappoints us, we arrive at the idea that the best editorial
                    service will be to place VIIb in the most effective location within the flow of
                    the text. Even the graphic evidence contradicts itself: Blake left two
                    ornamentally lettered headings, “Vala / Night the Seventh”—but
                    he left, as Ellis noted, only one “End of the Seventh Night,” at the
                    conclusion not of VIIa but of VIIb! Perhaps the greatest liberty to be taken in
                    accepting the textual masonry cementing VIIa to VIII will be our snatching the
                    finis line from page 98.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n91"
type="note">6</ref> Ellis’s
                    point was in justification, not of printing two Nights Seventh but of conflating
                    them as one. <note id="n91"><hi rend="s">6</hi> No editor, so far as I know, has
                        felt guilty about ignoring Blake’s own page numbering in copies of
                            <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> that put Plate 8 after Plate 10, and we all
                        restore the rejected Plate 4. Incidentally, my note on p. 727 contains a
                        howling non sequitur. In support of the hypothesis that Plate 8 was designed
                        to replace Plate 10, I argue that in two copies the lines on Plate 10 that
                        contain the refrain words “first Age” are marked for erasure. The
                        evidence rather supports the contrary view, as I ought to have seen, that
                        Plate 10 was meant to be <hi rend="i">kept.</hi> I report this somewhat in
                        the spirit of Charles Lamb hissing his own farce.</note></p>
        <p>To return to the specific analyses and hypotheses about the two Nights, I should
                    like to sum up my understanding of the arguments by using a compact symbolism
                    without further verbalizing—with Arabic numerals (6, 7, 8 instead of VI,
                    VII, VIII) and the following sigla: 
					<q><hi rend="s">°</hi> = original fitting in
fair-copy, or a linkage
                        directed by Blake<lb/>
 + = a more or less good fit<lb/>
 ! = an abrupt jump
                        (such as Blake created when he transposed 7b1 <hi rend="s">°</hi> 2
                        to 7b2 ! 1)<lb/>
 ? = a bad fitting, what Kilgore calls “a bewildering
                        non sequitur” </q></p>
        <p>As I understand Lincoln’s reconstruction, there was once this sequence,
                    before revisions: 6 <hi rend="s">°</hi> 7a1 <hi rend="s">°</hi>
                    7b1 <hi rend="s">°</hi> 7b2 <hi rend="s">°</hi> (+) 8. There was
                    never the bewildering non sequitur either of 6 ?! 7b1 or of 7b2 ? 7a1. Then,
                    when Blake transposed the halves of 7b, by his inked instructions, a fairly
                    abrupt but obviously tolerated linkage resulted: 7b2 <hi rend="s">°</hi>!
                    7b1, the aim perhaps being to link 6 + 7b2 ! 7b1 + 8 and to eliminate 7a, which
                    consisted entirely of 7a1. The reversal made a poor linkage of 7b1 ? 7a1, if he
                    meant to retain 7a between 7b and 8; on the other hand 6 <hi rend="s">°</hi> 7a1 + 7b2
was not impossible. But then Blake added 7a2,
                    confirming the retention of 7a but making a place for it problematic What were
                    the possibilities? To retain 7b with either part of 7a would be difficult.</p>
        <p>6 + 7b2 ! 7b1 ? 7a1 <hi rend="s">°</hi> 8 would produce a bad
                    sequitur.</p>
        <p>More successful would have been the sequence 6 + 7b2 ! 7b1 + 7a2 + 8, although
                    the tidiest set of transitions (disregarding structural omissions) would have
                    been: 6 <hi rend="s">°</hi> 7a1 <hi rend="s">°</hi> 7a2 + 8,
                    dropping 7b altogether.</p>
        <p>Blake shows no signs of having considered the proposals that are now being made
                    in the interest of incorporating, somehow, the indispensable 7b: 
					<q>
                        Lincoln’s suggestion: 6 + 7b2 ? 7a1 <hi rend="s">°</hi> 7a2 ?
                        7b1 + 8.<lb/>
 Kilgore’s main suggestion: 6 <hi rend="s">°</hi>
                        7a1 <hi rend="s">°</hi> 7b1 <hi rend="s">°</hi> 7b2 ! 7a2 +
                        8.<lb/>
 Lefebvre’s suggestion: 6 <hi rend="s">°</hi> 7a1 + 7b2
                            <hi rend="s">°</hi>! 7b1 + 7a2 + 8. </q>
	<pb id="p12-137" n="137"/>
Lincoln would revise the ? between 7a2 and 7b1 to !
                    by restoring the word “Now” to 91:1 (which Blake may have misquoted as
                    “Thus”). The sequence he proposes makes good sense as a conclusion
                    from his analysis of the probable evolution of the extant texts. And it
                    preserves the linkage made by Blake when he added 7a2 to 7a1, while it only
                    moves further apart the halves of 7b which Blake had already rearranged. But the
                    proposal to fit VIIb between the two parts of VIIa seems to make the better
                    reading sequence. Between the Kilgore alternative, to restore b1 and b2 to their
                    earlier order, and the Lefebvre alternative, to retain the reversed order called
                    for in the manuscript, I incline to prefer the latter as doing the least
                    injustice to the claims of narrative and the manuscript evidence. And on that
                    point Kilgore agrees, if we are talking about a published edition.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n92" type="note">7</ref> Harold Bloom, whose Commentary (as he
                    points out) will work quite well when rearranged, agrees with me that most
                    people reading the poem will find it more available in this form—and that
                    no editorial handling, in any case, can possibly acquaint the reader with the
                    full nature of the editorial problem, let alone the “manuscript
                    evidence.” Perhaps it tells us something about the sequences of the text,
                    as well as about Bloom’s Commentary, that we can easily see that
                    rearranging will cause no difficulty and, indeed, will give the reader a
                    stronger epic sequence. “You must state, though,” says he, “that
                    we really do not know how Blake perceived narrative continuity, how much
                    departure from the Homeric norm he felt comfortable with.” Ault’s
                    theory, that Blake as it were got a twentieth-century charge out of narrative
                    discontinuities, is of course somewhat anachronistic.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n93" type="note">8</ref> Mitchell is perhaps closer to Blakean thinking when he
                    argues that “Blake intentionally designed <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> to
                    allow only an approximate sense of structural orientation” as, in part, a
                    rhetorical strategy.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n94"
type="note">9</ref> Not that <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> have the same
shape;
                    nine Nights are round and they revolve, while four Chapters reverberate. 
<note id="n92"><hi rend="s">7</hi> What I have called Kilgore’s main
                        suggestion is what he recommends as “a critical order” to be
                        followed in reading, the order used by Wagenknecht. Kilgore would, however,
                        “print VIIb in the reversed order.” When he is considering a
                        printed text he is guided by the policy of “following the latest
                        intentions for which there is direct evidence in the manuscript”; when
                        recommending the original order, for reading, he is guided by a suspicion
                        “that the reordering of the Night corresponded to a plan of revision
                        which Blake never carried out.” These are proper distinctions. I find
                        myself concurring (for a printed text) with the “direct evidence”
                        rather than the suspicion; what I am less certain is that presenting 
<hi rend="i">each</hi> Night Seventh as a unit must be “undoubtedly
                        correct.” The discussion, the evidence and the considerations brought
                        forward, have inclined me to doubt that Blake’s manuscript, not known
                        to have been in its present bound order, makes it feasible to present each
                        of the two Nights Seventh “as a unit” while attempting to preserve
                        the unity of the entire poem as comprised of nine Nights.</note>
	<note id="n93"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Donald Ault, “Incommensurability and
                        Interconnection in Blake’s Anti-Newtonian Text,” <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi>, 16 (1977): 277-303. Yet there is much
                        wisdom in Ault’s analysis of what is happening in <hi rend="i">The
                            Four Zoas.</hi> “The basic formula . . . is: incommensurability
                        does not entail disconnection; and interconnection does not entail
                        unity” (298). “From the opening of the poem Blake has been
                        striving to dissolve a solid framework right before our eyes. . . . The
                        final version [of Night the First] frustrates all attempts at causal
                        connection by deleting the predicate forms which allow the language to be
                        divided into causally related phrases” (299). Even so, Night I, heavily
                        and rather carelessly patched (to judge by Blake’s general practive
                        elsewhere in the poem), is a special case, not altogether relevant here; and
                        Ault at times misreads to find his “inversion or reversal of narrative
                        ‘facts’”—as in the evidence he produces on p. 282
                        from pages 4 and 22. Tharmas’ saying that he bears pity to
                        Enitharmon, who “hath taken refuge in my bosom” (p. 4) will appear
                        to be reversed on p. 22, “And Tharmas took her in pitying,” only
                        if the reader chooses to misconstrue by attaching the “pitying” to
                        Enitharmon and not Tharmas. A witty fellow can do this with many a text but
                        cannot convince us that the author or his contemporary reader would have
                        faltered into such misprision.</note>
	<note id="n94"><hi rend="s">9</hi> W. J. T. Mitchell, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art</hi> (Princeton
University Press, 1978),
                        p. 215. I have talked too much about “narrative sequence” perhaps;
                        the linkages I have diagrammed as ! and + and ! do not threaten to order
                        Blake’s text into anything tidier than what Mitchell calls
                        “approximate structure and centripetal focus.”</note></p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">CENTRIFUGAL ANIMADVERSIONS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>The question of the earliness or lateness of VIIa “taken as a
                        whole” has been quite sufficiently flogged, but I feel some
                        responsibility for the confusion. My note at the head of VIIa should not
                        have read “Written later than and presumably to replace Night Seven
                        b” but something like this: “Nights VIIa and VIIb were at one
                        stage a continuous pair of chapters with identical titles. Additions were
                        made to VIIa (on pp 85-90) which linked it directly with VIII. Blake left no
                        instructions for relocating VIIb; it is here given following IX.” But
                        once the discussion gets down to the lateness of VIIa1 <hi rend="s">°</hi> 2, most of
the disagreement vanishes. As Kilgore says,
                        ceasing his heavy fire, “the traditional account . . . may not be so
                        far mistaken after all. . . . Thus VIIa [he means 7a1] though not originally
                        a replacement for VIIb, would have become one by the time Blake finished his
                        revisions [i.e. added a2].” Q.E.D. He even comes round
                        “tentatively” to the thought that “Blake changed the order of
                        VIIb before writing [VIIa2].” So we can “break through” to
                        where the discussion should have begun. I cannot believe that
                        Margoliouth’s observation of the narrative continuity of a1 <hi rend="s">°</hi> b1
was news to anyone working on the text; I find
                        no excitement about it in his correspondence with me when he was preparing
                        his edition. The textual question was whether Blake’s revisions
                        culminated in a “structure which Blake finally left . . . with VIIb
                        lounging somewhere in the shadows” (Kilgore’s language as he
                        puts up his sword).</p>
          <p>The stitch-mark argument is threadbare now; as Kilgore says, one hypothesis
                        “is not more convincing” than the other; neither accounts for the
                        narrative continuity, which in either case can be accounted for by several
                        hypotheses. That was my point in my “Binding” review of
                        Bentley’s <hi rend="i">Vala.</hi> You test a theory by seeing if it
                        withstands assault; since Bentley hadn’t tried, I did. But the
                        reactions of Kilgore (and Wagenknecht, whom he quotes) tell me that I
                        overdramatized the criticism. Bentley had enlivened his bibliographical
                        prose by declaring that Erdman had “gambled heavily . . . and lost a
                        sizeable proportion of his shirt” (p. 168). Bentley was right, except
                        perhaps in his proportions, but some of his dating evidence was left without
                        a stitch. His theory of “anomalous” leaves, rather arbitrarily
                        defined, put seven late pages into VIIa and only six early ones; it seemed a
                        hypothesis that just got in the way. I was testing the structure of his
                        argument, not building one of my own. Lincoln, now, makes a carefully
                        elaborated extension of Bentley’s valuable suggestion that VIIb was
                        matter displaced from VIII.</p>
          <p>Lincoln’s tracing out the probabilities of a coherent evolution which
                        involves VII in relation to the whole, especially the additions and changes
                        in IV, VIII, and IX, I find generally plausible, often convincing, and
                        elegantly handled. His sigla (VIIa, *IX, etc.) are clear and keep us aware
                        of moving in a world of hypotheses. But I am uneasy about some of his
                        arguments that appear to assume the possibility, where it seems slight, of
                        distinguishing plot requirements from changing intentions. We are all guilty
                        at times of confusing time of conception or composition with time of
                        inscription; he appears to be doing so when he finds a “reassessment of
                        the role of Los” in “late” passages (or takes it as evidence
                        of lateness: just which, is not always clear). The “tension rather than
                        cooperation between Los and Enitharmon” which Lincoln sees as
                        characteristic of Los before a reassessment interpreted as a product of
                        Blake’s changes of thought in 1803-04 is not unlike the tension
                        between Los and Enitharmon that occurs in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as the
                        poet’s song “draws to its period” (see <hi rend="i">J</hi>
                        83-88). No one has suggested—but perhaps someone should—that
                        Blake underwent a reassessment of Los while composing the final plates of
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></p>
          <p>Lincoln replies that he is concerned strictly with changing plot requirements
                        and that his argument is that the text of 7b2 was excluded from the poem
                        until Blake had made a number of other important revisions—a matter
                        which requires trying to draw a distinction between time of composition and
                        time of inscription. “I don’t argue,” he writes, “that
                        7a2 must be an addition because it describes the conversion of Los, but that
                        as this 
<pb id="p12-138" n="138"/>
material appears to be an addition it
                        seems likely that Blake’s plot requirements changed; and that as the
                        Los passages in 8 seem to be a sequel to 7a2, they may be part of the
                        change.”</p>
          <p>This is not a proper occasion to argue about the conversions of William
                        Blake, nor about the roles of Los or Orc or the shadowy Female who has found
                        him and will not let him go, in the <hi rend="i">America</hi> Preludium. The
                        revolutionary embrace (of 1776/1793) is surely not presented as an act of
                        jealous possession; yet possibly Andrew Lincoln is right to read the
                        Preludium as equivocal.</p>
          <pb id="p12-139" n="139"/>
          <figure n="BB209.1.98.MS.detail3" rend="file" width="958" height="993">
            <head><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 98 (detail).</head>
          </figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
