<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>12.2.minnick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="checklist">A Checklist of Recent Blake Scholarship</title>
        <author n="Minnick">Thomas L. Minnick</author>
        <author n="Dörrbecker">Detlef W. Dörrbecker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">12.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Special Design and Pasteup for this issue</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Everett Frost</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Terrence Hoagwood</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John Kilgore</name>
              <name>Mark Lefebvre</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Cettina Magno</name>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <name>Jeffry Spencer</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_12">
    <body>
      <pb id="p12-142" n="142"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-12-2-0015">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">A CHECKLIST OF RECENT BLAKE SCHOLARSHIP</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline><docAuthor><hi rend="b">THOMAS L. </hi><name><hi rend="b">MINNICK</hi></name></docAuthor> WITH
THE ASSISTANCE OF
                            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">DETLEF W. </hi><name><hi
rend="b">DÖRRBECKER</hi></name></docAuthor></byline>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">I. BIBLIOGRAPHIES, BIBLIOGRAPHICAL ESSAYS, EXHIBITION
                                CATALOGUES</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>[Auld, Alasdair A.]. William Blake 1757-1827: Six Paintings in the Stirling
                        Maxwell Collection, Pollok House. Glasgow: Corporation of Glasgow (Museums
                        and Art Galleries Department), n.d. [c. 1973?].</p>
          <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr. “Blake Among the Slavs: A Checklist.”
                        Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 50-54.</p>
          <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr. “<hi rend="i">Cumberland Bibliography</hi>
                        Addenda.” Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 128.</p>
          <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr. “A Supplement to <hi rend="i">Blake
                        Books.</hi>” Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 136-177.
                        [“The present supplement . . . is intended to bring <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Books</hi> up to date . . . [to] 31 March 1977.”]</p>
          <p>[Bindman, David, and Christopher Powney]. John Flaxman, Spring exhb. London:
                        Heim Gallery, 1976 (Heim exhibition catalogue, no. 24).</p>
          <p>Butlin, Martin. William Blake. London: The Tate Gallery Publications
                        Department, 1978. £4.75. [Catalogue of the exhibition held at the Tate
                        Gallery, 9 March to 21 May 1978, and at the Whitworth Art Gallery,
                        Manchester, 10 June to 15 July 1978; 339 illus., 17 in color.]</p>
          <p>Dargan, Tom. See Wolf, Donald A.</p>
          <p>Dixon, Yvonne Romney. “The Drawings of George Romney in the Folger
                        Shakespeare Library.” Diss. University of Maryland, 1977. Dissertation
                        Abstracts International, 38 (1978), 5099-A. [Catalogues and analyzes the 489
                        Romney drawings in the Folger Shakespeare Library.]</p>
          <p>Doctorow, Erica. See Wolf, Donald A.</p>
          <p>Dörrbecker, Detlef W. “Blake Goes German: A Critical Review of
                        Exhibitions in Hamburg and Frankfurt 1975.” Blake/An Illustrated
                        Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 44-49. [Includes a checklist of “Articles
                        Published in Newspapers, Weekly and Monthly Magazines” and “Blake
                        Scholarship (Books and journal articles)” in Germany, pp. 48-49.]</p>
          <p>Dörrbecker, Detlef W. See also Minnick, Thomas L.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V., ed., with the assistance of Robert R. Mollenauer and James
                        S. Patty. “The Romantic Movement: A Selective and Critical Bibliography
                        for 1976.” English Language Notes, 15 (1977), supplement to number
                        1.</p>
          <p>Goodison, J. W. Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge: Catalogue of Paintings. vol. 3:
                        British School. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1977. [See pp. 16-19
                        for Blake; pp. 155-158 for John Linnell; pp. 207-208 for George Richmond;
                        and passim.]</p>
          <p>Gross, Rochelle C., and C. M. Henning. “Dissertations on Blake:
                        1963-1975.” Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 54-59.</p>
          <p>Henning, C. M. See Gross, Rochelle C.</p>
          <p>Hofmann, Werner, ed. Runge in seiner Zeit, exhb. cat. Hamburger Kunsthalle.
                        Munich: Prestel, 1977 [“Kunst um 1800”]. [Includes several items
                        by Blake, Flaxman, and Fuseli.]</p>
          <p>Minnick, Thomas L., with the assistance of Detlef W. Dörrbecker.
                        “A Checklist of Recent Blake Scholarship 1976-1977.” Blake/An
                        Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 104-109.</p>
          <p>Powney, Christopher. See Bindman, David.</p>
          <p>Robinson, K. E. “The Eighteenth Century,” pp. 242-276 in James
                        Redmond, ed., The Year’s Work in English Studies. Vol. 56 (1975).
                        London: for The English Association by John Murray, 1977. [For reviews of
                        recent books and articles about Blake, see pp. 256-258.]</p>
          <p>Wolf, Donald A., Tom Dargan, and Erica Doctorow. William Blake: The Poet as
                        Painter. Garden City: Swirbul Library Gallery, Adelphi University, 1977.
                        $1.50. [Exhibition catalogue.]</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="p12-143" n="143"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">II. EDITIONS, TRANSLATIONS, FACSIMILES, REPRODUCTIONS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>*Bernus, Alexander von, ed. and trans. “[Gedichte von] William
                        Blake” in Das Irdische Paradies: Englische Lyrik des XIX. Jahrhunderts
                        in Umdichtung. 2 vols. Nürnberg: Hans Carl, 1947. I, 7-34. [A copy of
                        this edition is in the Frankfurt University Library. The first printing was
                        published in Weimar: Lichtenstein, n.d. (c. 1930). The translations were
                        reprinted in the edition of Blake’s poems by Bernus and Schmiele,
                        1958.]</p>
          <p>*Beutler, Ernst, ed. John Flaxman’s Zeichnungen [sic] zu Sagen des
                        klassischen Altertums. Leipzig: Insel, 1910. [A much reduced reproduction of
                        143 of Flaxman’s outline engravings—not “drawings,”
                        of course—including the complete Hesiod series.]</p>
          <p>Bindman, David. Assisted by Deirdre Toomey. The Complete Graphic Works of
                        William Blake. London: Thames and Hudson, 1978.</p>
          <p>The Book of Job. Illustrated by William Blake; with a new introduction by
                        Michael Marqusee. New York: Paddington, 1976. [In the series <hi rend="i">Masterpieces
of the Illustrated Book.</hi>]</p>
          <p>Darwin, Erasmus. The Botanic Garden [facsimile of the first combined edition
                        of parts one and two (1791)], ed. Desmond King-Hele. London and Menston,
                        Yorkshire: Scolar, 1973. [Edition limited to 500 numbered copies; includes
                        reproductions of Blake’s engravings after Fuseli and the Portland
                        Vase.]</p>
          <p>Darwin, Erasmus. The Temple of Nature [facsimile of the first edition
                        (1803)], ed. Desmond King-Hele. London and Menston, Yorkshire: Scolar, 1973.
                        [Includes reproductions from Moses Haughton’s engravings after Henry
                        Fuseli.]</p>
          <p>Elliott, Patricia Dell. “A Critical Variorum Edition of William
                        Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.</hi>” Diss. University
                        of Arkansas, 1977. Dissertation Abstracts International, 38 (1977),
                        2804-A.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V., ed., with the assistance of Donald K. Moore. The Notebook
                        of William Blake: A Photographic and Typographic Facsimile. Revised edition.
                        New York: Readex Books, 1977.</p>
          <p>Fuseli, Henry. “The Fall of the Titans.” Reproduced in Milton
                        Quarterly, 12 (1978), 14.</p>
          <p>Johnson, E. D. H. “Romantic, Victorian, and Edwardian.” The
                        Princeton University Library Chronicle, 38 (1977), 198-224. [Notes the
                        presence of two Blake watercolors and two Blake pencil drawings in
                        Princeton’s Robert H. Taylor Collection (p. 222), and reproduces one
                        of the pencil drawings (following p. 224).]</p>
          <p>Latona, Joseph J. “Thomas Holcroft’s <hi rend="i">Seduction:</hi>
                        A Critical Edition with Annotations.” Diss. New York University, 1976.
                        Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1977), 5853-A.</p>
          <p>Leyris, Pierre, ed. and trans. Œuvres de William Blake, vol. II.
                        Paris: Aubier-Flammarion, 1977. [Contents: Poèmes tirés de
                        divers manuscrits; L’évangile Etérnel; Les Portes du
                        Paradis; Annotations aux Lavater; with introduction and notes by
                        Leyris.]</p>
          <p>Moore, Donald K. See Erdman, David V.</p>
          <p>*Praz, Mario, ed. Poeti Inglesi dell’ Ottocento. Florence: Bemporad,
                        1925. [Includes translations of some of Blake’s poems and several
                        references to Blake in the introductory essay.]</p>
          <p>Reynolds, Joshua. Discourses on Art, ed. Robert R. Wark. New Haven, Ct., and
                        London: Yale University Press for the Paul Mellon Centre for British
                        Studies, 1975. [Rpt. of the 1959-San Marino edition, with added appendices,
                        including Blake’s annotations in full.]</p>
          <p>Toomey, Deirdre. See Bindman, David.</p>
          <p>Urnov, D., and V. Vitkovskij, eds. Poèzija anglijskogo romantizma [The
                        Poetry of English Romanticism]: William Blake, Walter Scott, Samuel Taylor
                        Coleridge, William Wordsworth, Robert Southey, Thomas Moore, George Gordon
                        Byron, Percy Bysshe Shelley, John Keats. Moscow: Xudoz. lit., 1975.</p>
          <p>*Worbs, Erich, ed. In die Ewigkeit gesprochen: Letzte Gedanken, eine
                        tröstliche Anthologie. Munich: Südwest Verlag, 1970. [About
                        Blake’s death, with translations of fragments of his last letters,
                        plus the 3rd and 4th stanzas of the poem known as “Jerusalem” from
                            <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 1; see pp. 176 f.]</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">III. CRITICAL STUDIES</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Adlard, John. “Blake Enters Beulah.” Neuphilologische Mitteilungen,
                        78 (1977), 62-64.</p>
          <p>Aers, D. “William Blake and the Dialectics of Sex.” ELH, 44 (1977),
                        500-514.</p>
          <p>Allentuck, Marcia R. “Henry Fuseli’s ‘Queen
                        Katherine’s Vision’ and Macklin’s Poets’
                        Gallery: A New Critique.” Journal of the Warburg and Courtauld
                        Institutes, 39 (1976), 266-268.</p>
          <p>Anon. “William Blake.” Süddeutsche Zeitung [Munich], 12
                        August 1977. [A short commemorative note only, including a paragraph quoted
                        from Blake’s <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> in the German translation of
                        1975.]</p>
          <p>*Ansaldi, Giulio R. “Pittura neoclassica inglese: Nota su George
                        Romney” in Vittorio Gabrieli, ed., Friendship’s Garland, Essays
                        presented to Mario Praz on his seventieth birthday. 2 vols. Rome: Edizioni
                        di Storia e Letteratura, 1966. II, 43-50.</p>
          <p>Ault, Donald D. “Incommensurability and Interconnection in
                        Blake’s Anti-Newtonian Text.” Studies in Romanticism, 16 (1977),
                        277-303.</p>
          <p>*Barfield, Owen. “William Blake zum 200. Geburtstag.” Die Drei;
                        Anthroposophische Zeitung, 27 (1957), 305-312. [Includes four poems from the
                        Bernus translation.]</p>
          <p>Behrendt, Stephen C. “Blake’s Illustrations to Milton’s
                            <hi rend="i">Nativity Ode.</hi>” Philological Quarterly, 55 (1976),
                        65-95.</p>
          <p>Behrendt, Stephen C. “Bright Pilgrimage: William Blake’s Designs
                        for ‘L’Allegro’ and ‘Il Penseroso’,”
                        Milton Studies, 8 (1975), 123-147.</p>
          <p>Bennett, Shelley Margaret. “Thomas Stothard, R. A.” Diss.
                        University of California, Los Angeles, 1977. Dissertation Abstracts
                        International, 38 (1977), 2380-A.</p>
          <p>Benzel, Michael Arnold. “Vision and Revision in <hi rend="i">The Four
                            Zoas</hi>: The Evidence of the Manuscript,” Diss. University of
                        Toledo, 1976. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1977), 6492-A.</p>
          <p>Bindman, David. Blake as an Artist. Oxford: Phaidon Press, and New York: E.
                        P. Dutton, 1977. $18.95.</p>
          <p>Bindman, David. “John Flaxman’s Funerary Monuments,” pp.
                        9-13 in Neoclassicismo: Atti del convegno internazionale dal Comité
                        International d’Histoire 
<pb id="p12-144" n="144"/>
de l’Art.
                        Genoa: Istituto di Storia dell’arte della Universita degli Studi di
                        Genova, 1973.</p>
          <p>Boddon, Horst, and Herbert Kaussen. “William Blake,
                        ‘London’,” in Modellanalysen Englischer Lyrik:
                        Shakespeare, Marvell, Milton, Blake, Keats, Shelley, Hopkins, Yeats, Hughes.
                        Stuttgart: Ernest Klett, 1974, pp. 66-79.</p>
          <p>Brown, Norman O. Love’s Body: Wider die Trennung von Geist un
                        Körper, Wort und Tat, Rede und Schweigen, trans. Anna and Dietrich
                        Leube. Munich: Carl Hanser, 1977 [“Hanser Anthropologie,” ed. Wolf
                        Lepenies and Henning Ritter.]</p>
          <p>Carey, Frances. “Blake’s ‘Warring Angels’.”
                        Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 120-123. [Announces,
                        reproduces a hitherto unknown drawing.]</p>
          <p>Carner, Frank Kenneth. “Four Contexts for the Study of the Relationship
                        of Text and Design in the Illuminated Books of William Blake.” Diss.
                        University of Toronto, 1976. Dissertation Abstracts International, 38
                        (1978), 6138-A.</p>
          <p>Carothers, Yvonne Marie. “Romantic Enthusiasm: Blake, Coleridge and
                        Shelley.” Diss. University of California, Irvine, 1977. Dissertation
                        Abstracts International, 38 (1978), 5492-A.</p>
          <p>Cohen, Paul Nathan. “‘Words Alone are Certain Good’: Yeats
                        and the Unity of the Arts.” Diss. The State University of Rutgers,
                        1977. Dissertation Abstracts International, 38 (1977), 2801-A. [Blake is
                        treated as one of Yeats’s earliest literary models.]</p>
          <p>Cooke, Michael G. The Romantic Will. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1976.
                        $15.00 [<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is discussed on pp. 118-144,
                        187-201.]</p>
          <p>Coomar, Devinder Mohan. “Silence, Language and the Poetry of Criticism
                        in Romantic Expression: Blake, Keats, Foscolo, and Tagore.” Diss.
                        University of California, Riverside, 1976. Dissertation Abstracts
                        International, 37 (1976), 3601-A.</p>
          <p>Coon, Stephen William. “Roads of Excess: Towards a Poetics of Visionary
                        Writing: Blake, Burroughs, <corr type="emend">Lautréamont,</corr> Michaux.” Diss. Brown
                        University, 1976. Dissertation Abstracts International, 38 (1977),
                        242-A.</p>
          <p>Corti, Claudia. “Acque natali e acque lustrali nei ‘Songs of
                        Innocence’ di Blake.” Rivista di letterature moderne e
                        comparate, 30 (1977), 5-19.</p>
          <p>Crown, Patricia Dahlman. “Edward F. Burney: An Historical Study in
                        English Romantic Art.” Diss. University of California, Los Angeles,
                        1977. Dissertation Abstracts International, 38 (1977), 4414-A.</p>
          <p>Deck, Raymond H., Jr. “An American Original: Mrs. Colman’s
                        Illustrated Printings of Blake’s Poems, 1843-44.” Blake/An
                        Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 4-18. [20 illus.]</p>
          <p>Deck, Raymond H., Jr. “Mr. Rudall, The Flautist: An Authentic Blake
                        Anecdote.” Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 123.</p>
          <p>Deck, Raymond H., Jr. “New Light on C. A. Tulk, Blake’s
                        Nineteenth-Century Patron.” Studies in Romanticism, 16 (1977),
                        217-236.</p>
          <p>Dillon, Ralph G. “Source for Blake’s ‘The Sick
                        Rose’.” American Notes and Queries, 12 (1974), 157-158.</p>
          <p>Dilworth, Thomas R. “Blake’s Babe in the Woods.” Blake/An
                        Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 35-37.</p>
          <p>Disalvo, Jacqueline Anne. “War of Titans: Blake’s Confrontation
                        with Milton. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> as Political Critique of 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and the Genesis Tradition.” Diss.
                        University of Wisconsin, Madison, 1977. Dissertation Abstracts
                        International, 38 (1977), 3456-A.</p>
          <p>Dörrbecker, Detlef W. “Jean Paul Friedrich Richter and
                        Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi>” Blake/An Illustrated
                        Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 124-125.</p>
          <p>Dörrbecker, Detlef W. “‘That Man be separate from
                        Man’: überlegungen zu einer Zeichnung William Blakes.”
                        Jahrbuch der Hamburger Kunstsammlungen, 22 (1977), 101-126. [8 illus.]</p>
          <p>Duerksen, Roland A. “The Life of Love: Blake’s Oothoon.”
                        Colby Library Quarterly, 13 (1977), 186-194.</p>
          <p>Eaves, Morris. “Blake and the Artistic Machine: An Essay in Decorum and
                        Technology.” PMLA, 92 (1977), 903-927. [9 illus.]</p>
          <p>Eaves, Morris. “What Is the ‘History of Publishing’?”
                        Publishing History, 2 (1977), 57-77.</p>
          <p>*Eliot, Thomas Stearns. “William Blake” in Hans Hennecke, ed. and
                        trans. T. S. Eliot: Ausgewählte Essays 1917-1947. Berlin and
                        Frankfurt am Main: Suhrkamp, 1950, pp. 335-344. [Obviously the first
                        printing of this 1920 essay in a German translation, reprinted in the next
                        entry; cf. Bentley, Blake Books, item 1544.]</p>
          <p>*Eliot, Thomas Stearns. “William Blake” in Helmut Viebrock, ed. T.
                        S. Eliot Werke, vol. III: Essays 2: Literaturkritik, trans. Hans Hennecke.
                        Frankfurt am Main: Suhrkamp, 1969, pp. 201-207.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V. “Errors in the Signet Classic Edition of The Selected
                        Poetry of Blake.” Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 37.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V. “Preface to the Revised Edition of Blake’s
                        Notebook.” Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 21-23.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V. “The Symmetries of <hi rend="i">The Song of
                        Los.</hi>” Studies in Romanticism, 16 (1977), 179-188.</p>
          <p>Farmer, John David. “Henry Fuseli, Milton and English Romanticism.”
                        Bulletin of the Art Institute of Chicago, 68 (1974), 14-19.</p>
          <p>Farwell, Brice. “More than Music Composed after Blake by Arthur
                        Farwell.” Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 86-103.</p>
          <p>Fawcett, Trevor. Art in the English Provinces: Artists, Patrons, and
                        Institutions outside London 1800-1830. Oxford University Press, 1974.
                        $24.00.</p>
          <p>Ferber, Michael. “Blake’s Idea of Brotherhood.” PMLA, 93
                        (1978), 438-447.</p>
          <p>Finke, Ulrich. “Dürers ‘Melancholie’ in der
                        französischen und englischen Literatur und Kunst des 19.
                        Jahrhunderts.” Zeitschrift des deutschen Vereins für
                        Kunstwissenschaft, 30 (1976), 67-85. [On Blake, see p. 81.]</p>
          <p>Foley, Matthew Joseph. “English Printing &amp; Book Illustration
                        1780-1820.” Diss. University of California, Santa Cruz, 1977.
                        Dissertation Abstracts International, 38 (1978), 6368-A.</p>
          <p>Folkenflik, Robert. “Macpherson, Chatterton, Blake and the Great Age of
                        Literary Forgery.” The Centennial Review, 18 (1974), 378-391.</p>
          <p>Gallagher, Philip J. “The Word Made Flesh: Blake’s ‘A
                        Poison Tree’ and the Book of Genesis.” Studies in Romanticism,
                        16 (1977), 237-249.</p>
          <p>Gallant, Christine Condit. “Regeneration through Archetype: William
                        Blake’s Changing Myth in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Diss.
                        University of Minnesota, 1976. Dissertation Abstracts International, 38
                        (1977), 3480-A.</p>
          <p>Gandolfo, Anita Marie. “Every Man’s Wisdom: Literary Affiliation
                        Among Blake, Yeats, and Joyce.” <pb id="p12-145" n="145"/>
Diss. City
                        University of New York, 1977. Dissertation Abstracts International, 38
                        (1977), 1408-A.</p>
          <p>Gear, Josephine M. “Masters or Servants? A Study of Selected English
                        Painters and Their Patrons of the Late Eighteenth and Early Nineteenth
                        Centuries.” Diss. New York University, 1976. Dissertation Abstracts
                        International, 37 (1977), 5410-A. [Treats Gainsborough, Morland, Ibbetson,
                        Wheatley, Stubbs, Collins, Westall, Northcote, Wilkie, and Haydon.]</p>
          <p>Gillham, David G. “Ideas of Human Perfection.” Theoria, 45 (1975),
                        13-27. [Discusses ideas of human perfection in Milton, Blake, and
                        Wordsworth.]</p>
          <p>Gleckner, Robert F. “Blake, Gray, and the Illustrations.”
                        Criticism, 19 (1977), 118-140.</p>
          <p>Gleckner, Robert F. “Blake’s Illustration of the Third Temptation
                        in <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained.</hi>” Blake/An Illustrated
                        Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 126-127.</p>
          <p>Gleckner, Robert F. “Blake’s Miltonizing of Chatterton.”
                        Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 27-29.</p>
          <p>Grant, John E. “The Female Awakening at the End of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>,” pp.
78-102 in John Karl Franson, ed., Milton
                        Reconsidered: Essays in Honour of Arthur E. Barker. Salzburg, Austria, 1976.
                        $12.12.</p>
          <p>* Hartlaub, Gustav Friedrich. “William Blake, der Mystiker des
                        Klassizismus” in Die grossen englischen Maler der Blütezeit
                        1730-1840. Munich: Münchner Verlag (bisher F. Bruckmann), 1948, pp.
                        151-162.</p>
          <p>Harvey, A. D. “The English Epic in the Romantic Period.”
                        Philological Quarterly, 55 (1976), 241-259. [“Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,
despite the consensus of critical opinion, is
                        surely in the apocalyptic rather than the epic tradition . . . ”;
                        treats Ogden, Cottle, Thelwall, Ogilvie, Northmore, Cumberland, and
                        company.]</p>
          <p>Heinzelman, Kurt. “Blake’s Golden Word.” English Language
                        Notes, 15 (1977), 33-38.</p>
          <p>Henning, C. M. “Blake’s Baptismal Font.” Blake/An
                        Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 38.</p>
          <p>Heppner, Christopher. “‘A Desire of Being’: Identity and
                            <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel.</hi>” Colby Library Quarterly, 13
                        (1977), 79-98.</p>
          <p>Hoeveler, Diane Long. “The Erotic Apocalypse: The Androgynous Ideal in
                        Blake and Shelley.” Diss. University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign,
                        1976. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1977), 6498-A.</p>
          <p>* Hönnighausen, Lothar. Präraphaeliten und Fin de Siecle:
                        Symbolistische Tendenzen in der englischen Spätromantik. Munich:
                        Wilhelm Fink, 1971. [Includes numerous references to Blake and the
                        Preraphaelites.]</p>
          <p>* Izzo, Carlo. “Responsibilita del traduttore.” in Gabrieli,
                        Vittore, ed. Friendship’s Garland, Essays presented to Mario Praz on
                        his seventieth birthday. 2 vols. Rome: Edizioni di Storia e Letteratura,
                        1966; II, 361-380. [On translating Blake’s ‘Tyger’, see
                        pp. 368 f., 373.]</p>
          <p>Jackson, Mary. “Blake and Zoroastrianism.” Blake/An Illustrated
                        Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 72-85.</p>
          <p>Jaffé, Patricia. Drawings by George Romney. Cambridge, England: for
                        the Fitzwilliam Museum by Cambridge University Press, 1977. £6.00 cloth;
                        £2.00 paperbound.</p>
          <p>James, G. Ingli. “Blake’s Mixed Media: A Mixed Blessing,”
                        ch. 6, pp. 61-69, in W. Moelwyn Merchant, ed., Essays and Studies. Vol. 30
                        (1977). London: for The English Association by John Murray, 1977.</p>
          <p>James, William Lloyd. “The Black Man in English Romantic Literature,
                        1772-1833.” Diss. University of California, Los Angeles, 1977.
                        Dissertation Abstracts International, 38 (1977), 2808-A. [Blake and slavery
                        is the subject of the final chapter.]</p>
          <p>Janson, Horst Woldemar. “Fuseli’s
                        ‘Nightmare’,” rpt. in Sixteen Studies. New York, N.Y.:
                        Abrams, 1974.</p>
          <p>John, Brian. “Yeats’s Butterflies.” Canadian Journal of
                        Irish Studies, 2 (1976), 51-53. [Mentions Blake as a source of Yeats.]</p>
          <p>* Kassner, Rudolf. Die Mystik, die Künstler und das Leben: über
                        englische Dichter und Maler im 19. Jahrhundert; Accorde [1900]. Reprinted in
                            <hi rend="i">Sämtliche Werke</hi> [Collected Works], vol. I, ed.
                        Ernst Zinn. Pfullingen: Neske, 1969 [The chapter on “William
                        Blake” now appears on pp. 23-68; cf. Keynes, 1921, item 328; Bentley
                        &amp; Nurmi, 1964, item 1446; Bentley, Blake Books, item 1988.]</p>
          <p>Kaussen, Herbert. See Boddon, Horst.</p>
          <p>* Kayser, Eugénie de. Das Abendland der Romantik. Geneva: Skira, 1965.
                        [Blake is discussed on pp. 100 f. and passim.]</p>
          <p>Keene, Michael Lawrence. “The Expansive Vision: Visual Perception and
                        Romantic Poetry.” Diss. University of Texas at Austin, 1976.
                        Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1977), 5143-A. [Theories of visual
                        perception common in eighteenth-century England are related to the poetry of
                        Blake, Wordsworth, Coleridge, Byron, Shelley, and Keats.]</p>
          <p>Kent, Donald L. See Roti, Grant C.</p>
          <p>Klonsky, Milton. William Blake: The Seer and His Visions. New York, N. Y.:
                        Harmony Books, and London: Orbis, 1977.</p>
          <p>Ko, So Woong. “A Study of Japanese Criticism of William Blake’s
                        Poetry.” Diss. University of Nebraska, Lincoln, 1976. Dissertation
                        Abstracts International, 38 (1977), 2141-A.</p>
          <p>Lenorski, Daniel S. “The Descent from the Mountain.” Canadian
                        Journal of Irish Studies, 2 (1976), 21-31. [Comments on Blake’s
                        influence on Yeats.]</p>
          <p>Leonard, Harris Kieth. “William Blake and ‘The Mental
                        Traveller’.” Diss. Howard University, 1976. Dissertation
                        Abstracts International 38 (1978), 6743-A.</p>
          <p>Lindop, Grevel. “Blake: ‘The Little Girl Lost’ and
                        ‘The Little Girl Found’.” The Critical Survey, 6 (1973),
                        36-40.</p>
          <p>Lindsay, David W. “‘The Song of Los’: An Interpretation of
                        the Text.” Forum for Modern Language Studies, 13 (1977), 1-5.</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond. “Samuel Palmer’s Milton Watercolours.”
                        Connoisseur, 194 (1977), 16-19.</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond. “‘The Ancients’ and the Classics.”
                        Studies in Romanticism, 15 (1976), 395-404.</p>
          <p>Livingston, Judith Hochstein. “The Impact of Africa Upon Major British
                        Literary Figures, 1787-1902.” Diss. University of Wisconsin, Madison,
                        1977. Dissertation Abstracts International, 38 (1977), 4847-A.</p>
          <p>Ludman, Joan. See Mason, Lauris.</p>
          <p>M. “Holy Thursday.” Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78),
                        38-40. [Reprints a letter to the Editor of the Monthly Magazine, 23 (1 July
                        1807), 554-556.]</p>
          <p>Manlove, C. N. “Engineered Innocence: Blake’s ‘The Little
                        Black Boy’ and ‘The Fly’.” Essays in Criticism, 27
                        (1977), 112-121.</p>
          <p>Mason, Lauris, and Joan Ludman, eds. Print Collector’s 
<pb id="p12-146" n="146"/>
Quarterly: An
Anthology of Essays on Eminent
                        Printmakers of the World, vol. I: Abbé to Blake. Millwood, N. Y.: kto
                        press [Kraus-Thomson Organization], 1977, 512-621. [Reprints of
                        contributions by E. L. Cary, L. Binyon, R. McDonald, J. S. Newberry, G. S.
                        Hellman, and R. Todd.]</p>
          <p>Mathews, Lawrence McKay. “Stems of Generation: The Figure of the Victim
                        in the Poetry of William Blake.” Diss. University of British Columbia,
                        1976. Dissertation Abstracts International, 38 (1977), 285-A.</p>
          <p>McClellan, Jane. “Dramatic Movement as a Structuring Device in
                        Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” Colby Library Quarterly,
                        13 (1977), 195-208.</p>
          <p>McCord, James David. “William Blake’s Experiments in Illuminated
                        Printing: 1793-1795.” Diss. University of California, Santa Barbara,
                        1977. Dissertation Abstracts International, 38 (1977), 4142-A.</p>
          <p>McGinnis, W. D. “Lawrence’s ‘Odour of
                        Chrysanthemums’ and Blake.” Research Studies, 44 (1976),
                        251-252.</p>
          <p>Meltzer, Helen Lora. “The Ancients: Samuel Palmer, Edward Calvert,
                        George Richmond and Francis Oliver Finch.” Diss. Columbia University,
                        1975. Dissertation Abstracts International, 38 (1977), 3776-A.</p>
          <p>Mercier, Vivian. “Blake Echoes in Victorian Dublin.” Blake/An
                        Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 32-34.</p>
          <p>Meyer, Jerry D. “Benjamin West’s Chapel of Revealed Religion: A
                        Study in Eighteenth-Century Protestant Religious Art.” Art Bulletin, 57
                        (1975), 247-265. [Includes a brief discussion of Blake’s
                        ‘Death on a Pale Horse’ which is compared with other
                        contemporary artist’s treatments of the same subject.]</p>
          <p>Mitchell, <corr type="emend">W. J. T. Blake’s Composite Art: A Study of the Illuminated
                        Poetry.</corr> Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1978. [112 illus.]</p>
          <p>Mitchell, W. J. T. “Style as Epistemology: Blake and the Movement toward
                        Abstraction in Romantic Art.” Studies in Romanticism, 16 (1977),
                        145-164.</p>
          <p>Moss, John G. “William Blake and Wilson Harris: The Objective
                        Vision.” Journal of Commonwealth Literature, 9, no. 3 (1975),
                        29-40.</p>
          <p>Mulhallen, Karen G. “‘For Friendship’s Sake’: Some
                        Additions to Blake’s Sheet for ‘Designs to a Series of
                        Ballads’ (1802).” Studies in Bibliography, 29 (1976),
                        331-341.</p>
          <p>Newsome, David. Two Classes of Men: Platonism and English Romantic Thought.
                        New York: St. Martin’s Press, 1975. $12.95. [Chapters 1-3 include
                        treatment of Blake as a Platonist.]</p>
          <p>Noll, Jacqueline Ann. “Old Testament Prophecy in Blake’s Lambeth
                        Poems.” Diss. University of Maryland, 1977. Dissertation Abstracts
                        International, 38 (1978), 5500-A.</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D. “The Truchsessian Gallery Revisited.” Studies in
                        Romanticism, 16 (1977), 165-177.</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D. William Blake. Oxford: Phaidon, and New York: E. P. Dutton,
                        1978. $19.95. [116 illus.]</p>
          <p>Pananides, Dean Nicholas. “Vision and Form in William Blake’s
                        Illuminated Poetry.” Diss. University of California, Santa Barbara,
                        1976. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1977), 7765-A.</p>
          <p>Perry, Donna Marie. “From Innocence through Experience: A Study of the
                        Romantic Child in Five Nineteenth Century Novels.” Diss. Marquette
                        University, 1976. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1976), 3599-A.
                        [Grounding her study in a consideration of Blake and Wordsworth, Ms. Perry
                        traces the figure of the Romantic child in <hi rend="i">Jane Eyre, David
                            Copperfield, The Mill on the Floss, Great Expectations</hi>, and <hi rend="i">What
Maisie Knew.</hi>]</p>
          <p>Peterfreund, Stuart S. “Blake’s Attack on Johnson.”
                        Transactions of the Samuel Johnson Society of the Northwest, 7 (1974),
                        44-57.</p>
          <p>Phillips, Michael. “William Blake and the ‘Unincreasable
                        Club’: The Printing of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches.</hi>”
                        Bulletin of the New York Public Library, 80 (1976), 6-18.</p>
          <p>Piper, David, ed. The Genius of English Painting. New York: William Morrow
                        &amp; Company, 1975. $27.50. [Includes Mary Webster, “The Eighteenth
                        Century,” pp. 145-197; Alan Bird, “The Romantics,” pp.
                        198-248. Many illustrations in color and black and white.]</p>
          <p>* Praz, Mario. “I libri profetici di W. Blake.” La Fiera
                        Letteraria, 14 (1926).</p>
          <p>* Praz, Mario. “Blake occultista.” La Stampa, 13 December 1930.
                        [This seems to be the first printing of Bentley and Nurmi, 1964, item 1780;
                        Bentley, Blake Books, item 2450.]</p>
          <p>* Praz, Mario. “Poeti maghi.” Il Tempo, 16 April 1965; rpt. in
                        Praz, Mario. Letture di pensiero e d’arte. vol. 3: Cronache
                        letterarie anglosassoni. Rome: Edizioni di Storia e Letteratura, 1966, pp.
                        328-333. [In the same volume, and vol. 4 of the series the reader will find
                        numerous other references to Blake.]</p>
          <p>Pressly, William L., Jr. “James Barry’s <hi rend="i">The Baptism
                            of the King of Cashul by St. Patrick.</hi>” The Burlington
                        Magazine, 118 (1976), 643-648. [5 illustrations.]</p>
          <p>Prickett, Stephen. Romanticism and Religion: The Tradition of Coleridge and
                        Wordsworth in the Victorian Church. Cambridge University Press, 1976.
                        $21.95. [Pp. 72-89 discuss Blake’s reaction to Wordsworth’s
                        pantheism.]</p>
          <p>Radner, John B. “The Youthful Harlot’s Curse: The Prostitute as
                        Symbol of the City in 18th-Century English Literature.”
                        Eighteenth-Century Life, 2 (March, 1976), 59-64.</p>
          <p>Raine, Kathleen. “Blake’s Christ-Consciousness.” Studies in
                        Comparative Religion, 10 (1976), 213-218.</p>
          <p>Ray, Gordon N. The Illustrator and the Book in England from 1790 to 1914.
                        Oxford, London, and New York: Oxford University Press for the Pierpont
                        Morgan Library, 1976. $59.95.</p>
          <p>Read, Dennis M. “George Frederick Cooke: Another Grave Subscriber Heard
                        From.” Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 37-38.</p>
          <p>Read, Dennis M. “William Blake and <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi>”
                        Diss. University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee, 1976. Dissertation Abstracts
                        International, 37 (1977), 6478-A.</p>
          <p>* Robinson, Henry Crabb. “William Blake, Künstler, Dichter und
                        religiöser Schwärmer.” Vaterländisches Museum, 2
                        (1811): facsimile reprint, Nendeln, Liechtenstein: Kraus Reprint, 1971, pp.
                        107-131. [See Bentley, Blake Books, item 2538.]</p>
          <p>Roche, Denis, ed. and trans. Pour les Sexes: Les Grilles de Paradise par
                        William Blake. Paris: L’Energumène, 1976.</p>
          <p>Rose, Edward J. “Blake and the Double: The Spectre as <hi rend="i">Doppelgänger.</hi>” Colby
Library Quarterly, 13 (1977),
                        127-139.</p>
          <p>Rose, Edward J. “The Gate of Los: Vision and Symbol in Blake.”
                        Texas Studies in Literature and Language, 20 (1978), 1-14.</p>
          <p>Rosenberg, Pierre. “Un dessin de Füssli à Narbonne.”
                            <pb id="p12-147" n="147"/>
La Revue du Louvre et des Musées de France,
                        27 (1977), 17-18.</p>
          <p>* Roszak, Theodore. “Blake . . . or Bacon,” and “Blake: The
                        Fourfold Vision” in Where the Wasteland Ends: Politics and
                        Transcendence in Post Industrial Society. Garden City, N. Y.: Doubleday,
                        1972, and London: Faber and Faber, 1973, pp. 144-148, and pp. 296-314. [The
                        Faber edition was reprinted in 1974.]</p>
          <p>Roti, Grant C., and Donald L. Kent. “The Last Stanza of Blake’s
                        London.” Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 19-21.</p>
          <p>Rump, Gerhard Charles. George Romney (1734-1802): Zur Bildform der
                        Bürgerlichen Mitte in der Englischen Neoklassik. 2 vols. Hildesheim
                        and New York, N. Y.: Georg Olms Verlag, 1974. [The first full-length study
                        of Romney’s art for at least half a century, including several
                        references to Blake.]</p>
          <p>Rump, Gerhard Charles. “Heroismus contra <corr type="emend">Natürlichkeit</corr>: Vom
                        aristokratischen zum burgerlichen ästhetischen Ideal in der
                        englischen Kunst des Neoklassizismus.” Kunstchronik, 30 (1977),
                        113-114.</p>
          <p>Scheffler, Karl. “England: John Flaxman—William
                        Blake—Johann C. [sic] Füssli” in Geschichte der
                        europäischen Malerei: Vom Klassizismus zum Impressionismus. Berlin:
                        Bruno Cassirer, n.d. [c. 1927], pp. 95 ff. [Vol. I of Die europäische
                        Kunst im neunzehnten Jahrhundert.]</p>
          <p>Schiff, Gert, and Paola Viotto. L’opera completa di Füssli.
                        Milan: Rizzoli Editore, 1977 [“Classici dell’ Arte,” vol.
                        91/n.s. vol. 6.]</p>
          <p>Schlumberger, Eveline. “Füssli ou la fureur
                        d’être.” Connaissance des arts, 279 (1975), 66-75.</p>
          <p>Schmied, Wieland. “Füssli oder die Maske der Literatur,” and
                        “William Blake oder die Maske der Mystik.” in Zweihundert Jahre
                        phantastische Malerei. Berlin: Rembrandt Verlag, 1973, pp. 107-117.</p>
          <p>Schmutzler, Robert. “Die Wirkung William Blakes” in Art
                        Nouveau—Jugendstil, [2nd] rev. ed. Stuttgart: Gerd Hatje, 1977, pp.
                        44-53. [Blake is mentioned throughout as an important influence on art
                        nouveau.]</p>
          <p>Scholz, Joachim Josef. “Blake and Novalis: A Comparison of
                        Romanticism’s High Arguments.” Diss. University of Chicago,
                        1977. Dissertation Abstracts International, 38 (1977), 4808-A.</p>
          <p>Shrimpton, Nick. “Hell’s Hymnbook: Blake’s ‘Songs
                        of Innocence and of Experience’ and Their Models” in Literature
                        of the Romantic Period 1750-1850. Liverpool: Liverpool University Press,
                        1976, pp. 19-35.</p>
          <p>Shroyer, Richard J. “The 1788 Publication Date of Lavater’s
                        Aphorisms on Man.” Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78),
                        23-26.</p>
          <p>Shroyer, Richard James. “Studies in the Chronology and Contexts of
                        William Blake’s Early Poems: The First Decade, 1783-1793.” Diss.
                        University of Toronto (Canada), 1975. Dissertation Abstracts International,
                        37 (1977), 6513-A.</p>
          <p>Smith, S. “Some Responses to Heather Glen’s ‘The Poet in
                        Society’: Blake and Wordsworth on London.” Literature &amp;
                        History, no. 4 (1976), 94-98.</p>
          <p>Stanculescu, Liana P. “William Blake and the English Renaissance.”
                        Diss. University of Miami, 1976. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37
                        (1976), 2902-A.</p>
          <p>Steinberg, Leo. “Remarks on Certain Prints Relative to a Leningrad
                        Rubens on the Occasion of the First Visit of the Original to the United
                        States.” Print Collector’s Newsletter, 6 (1975), 97-102.
                        [Includes remarks on Blake’s burin style in his early
                        engravings.]</p>
          <p>Stempel, Daniel. “Angels of Reason: Science and Myth in the
                        Enlightenment.” Journal of the History of Ideas, 36 (1975), 63-78.
                        [Discusses Voltaire, Blake (see pp. 72-74), and others.]</p>
          <p>Stevenson, Warren. “Interpreting Blake’s <hi rend="i">Canterbury
                            Pilgrims.</hi>” Colby Library Quarterly, 13 (1977), 115-126.</p>
          <p>Stewart, Clark, illustrator. The Marriage of Heaven and Hell. Knoxville,
                        Tenn.: Darkpool Press, 1972. $55.00. [Stewart’s 13 plates were issued
                        in a limited edition of 100 numbered copies.]</p>
          <p>Sutherland, John H. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: The
                        Bard’s Song.” Colby Library Quarterly, 13 (1977), 142-157.</p>
          <p>Syamken, Georg. “Die ‘Tageszeiten’ von Philipp Otto Runge
                        und ‘The Book of Job’ von William Blake.” Jahrbuch der
                        Hamburger Kunstsammlungen, 20 (1975), 61-70.</p>
          <p>Tannenbaum, Leslie. “Lord Byron in the Wilderness: Biblical Tradition in
                        Byron’s ‘Cain’ and Blake’s ‘The Ghost of
                        Abel’.” Modern Philology, 72 (1974-75), 350-364.</p>
          <p>Taylor, Anya. “Blake’s Moving Words and the Dread of
                        Embodiment.” Cithara, 15 (1976), 75-85.</p>
          <p>Taylor, Ronald Clayton. “The Semantics of Time in the Later Poetry of
                        William Blake: A Stylistic Study.” Diss. University of California,
                        Berkeley, 1976. Dissertation Abstracts International, 37 (1977), 5857-A.</p>
          <p>Tebbetts, Terrell L. “Harmonious Spheres: The Relation of Preludium and
                        Prophecy in Blake’s ‘America’.” Publications of
                        the Arkansas Philological Association, 1 (1975), 49-55.</p>
          <p>* Tietze, Hans. “Blake und Runge.” Der Kreis, Zeitschrift
                        für künstlerische Kultur, 4 (1927), 449-455.</p>
          <p>Todd, Ruthven. “A Tentative Note on the Economics of The Canterbury
                        Pilgrims.” Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 30-31.</p>
          <p>Tomory, Peter A. “Opie’s Portrait of Mrs. Fuseli?” Pantheon,
                        32 (1974), 379-381.</p>
          <p>* Torbruegge, Marilyn K. “Johann Heinrich Füssli und
                        ‘Bodmer-Longinus’: Das Wunderbare und das Erhabene.”
                        Deutsche Vierteljahrsschrift für Literaturwissenschaft und
                        Geistesgeschichte, 46 (1972), 161-185.</p>
          <p>Traeger, Jörg. Philipp Otto Runge: Monographie und kritischer Katalog
                        [Catalogue raissoné]. Munich: Prestel, 1975 [“Studien zur Kunst
                        des 19. Jahrhunderts,” Sonderband. On Blake and Runge see pp. 26, 153,
                        159, 190-193, 279.]</p>
          <p>Trawick, Leonard M. “William Blake’s German Connection.”
                        Colby Library Quarterly, 13 (1977), 229-245.</p>
          <p>Valiukénaité, Delija J. “Jurgis Baltrušaitis ir
                        William Blake: Tarp mistikos ir humanizmo” in Rimvydas Silbajoris, ed.
                        Lituanistikos Instituto 1973 metu suvažianmo darbai: Proceedings of
                        the Institute of Lithuanian Studies 1973. Chicago, Ill.: Lithuanian
                        Institute, 1975.</p>
          <p>Warner, Janet. “Blake and the Language of Art: From Copy to
                        Vision.” Colby Library Quarterly, 13 (1977), 99-114.</p>
          <p>Weaver, Jack Wayne. “AE’s [i.e., George William Russell’s]
                        Use of Blake in ‘The Irish Homestead’.” Journal of Irish
                        Literature, 5 (1976), 144-147.</p>
          <p>Wills, James Thomas. “William Blake’s Designs for Bunyan’s
                            <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress.</hi>” Diss. University of
                        Toronto, 1975. Dissertation Abstracts International, 38 (1977), 3525-A.</p>
          <p>Wilner, Eleanor. Gathering the Winds: Visionary Transformations of Self and
                        Society. Baltimore: <pb id="p12-148" n="148"/>
The Johns Hopkins University
                        Press, 1975.</p>
          <p>Wilson, William Lewis, Jr. “Process and Imagination: The Romantic
                        Absolute in Blake and D. H. Lawrence.” Diss. Emory University, 1977.
                        Dissertation Abstracts International, 38 (1977), 1421-A.</p>
          <p>Wilton, Andrew. “Blake and the antique.” The British Museum
                        Yearbook, 1 (1976 [“The Classical Tradition”]), 187-218.</p>
          <p>Wilton, Andrew. “William Blake” in British Watercolours 1750 to
                        1850. Oxford: Phaidon, 1977, pp. 21-26.</p>
          <p>Winter, David. “George Morland (1763-1804).” Diss. Stanford
                        University, 1977. Dissertation Abstracts International, 38 (1978),
                        5103-A.</p>
          <p>Wolff-Windegg, Philipp. “Fesselung und Freiheit als Grundthemen: Zum
                        150. Todestag des Dichters und Künstlers William Blake.”
                        Tages-Anzeiger [Zurich], 12 August 1977.</p>
          <p>Worrall, David. “Blake’s Derbyshire: A Visionary Locale in
                        Jerusalem.” Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 34-35.</p>
          <p>Worrall, David. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and the
                        Visionary History of Britain.” Studies in Romanticism, 16 (1977),
                        189-216.</p>
          <p>* Yeats, William Butler. “William Blake und die Phantasie (1897)”
                        and “William Blake und seine Illustrationen zur
                        ‘Göttlichen Komödie’ (1897) [sic, for
                        1896]” in Friedrich Eckstein, ed. and trans. William Butler Yeats:
                        Erzählungen und Essays. Leipzig: Insel, 1916, pp. 108-150. [Probably
                        the first German translation of Bentley, Blake Books, items 3047 and
                        3051.]</p>
          <p>* Yeats, William Butler. “William Blake und die Imagination” in
                        Ausgewählte Werke: Nobelpreis 1923. Zurich: Coron, n.d. (1971), pp.
                        319-323. [Reihe des literarischen Nobelpreises, vol. 23.]</p>
          <p>* Yeats, William Butler. “William Blake und die Einbildungskraft”
                        and “William Blake und seine Illustrationen zur
                        ‘Göttlichen Komödie’” in Werner Vordtriede,
                        ed. William Butler Yeats: Werke, vol. 5: Essays und Einführungen,
                        trans. Elizabeth Gilbert. Neuwied and Berlin: Hermann Luchterhand, 1972, pp.
                        104-139.</p>
          <p>Yura, Kimiyoshi. “[Johann Heinrich Füssli—Epiphany of
                        Nightmare and Terror].” Mizue, 2 (1974), 29-49. [More than half of the
                        entire issue of this Japanese journal is devoted to an article on Fuseli,
                        including numerous illustrations.]</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">IV. REVIEWS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Ault, Donald D. Visionary Physics. Reviewed by David Wagenknecht, Modern
                        Philology, 74 (1976-77), 429-431.</p>
          <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr. Blake Books. Reviewed by Adrian Eeles, The [London]
                        Times Literary Supplement, 27 January 1978, p. 100; and by Robert N. Essick,
                        Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 178-199.</p>
          <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr. William Blake: The Critical Heritage. Reviewed by
                        Penelope B. Wilson, Modern Language Review, 72 (1977), 913-916.</p>
          <p>Bindman, David. Blake as an Artist. Reviewed by Bevis Hillier, The [London]
                        Times Literary Supplement, 17 February 1978, p. 212.</p>
          <p>Bindman, David, et al. William Blake 1757-1827. Reviewed by Detlef W.
                        Dörrbecker, Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 44-49.</p>
          <p>Bloom, Harold. The Anxiety of Influence. Reviewed by J. Blondel,
                        études Anglaises, 30 (1977), 76.</p>
          <p>Bloom, Harold. A Map of Misreading. Reviewed by J. Blondel, études
                        Anglaises, 30 (1977), 77.</p>
          <p>Bloom, Harold. Poetry and Repression. Reviewed by Morton D. Paley, Studia
                        Neophilologica, 49 (1977), 159-161; by Alan Rodway, Notes and Queries, n.s.,
                        24 (1977), 180-181; by J. Blondel, études Anglaises, 30 (1977),
                        77-78; by Frank Lentricchia, Modern Language Quarterly, 38 (1977), 110-112;
                        by Paul D. Sheats, Keats-Shelly Journal, 37 (1978), 138-144.</p>
          <p>Buchkunst von William Blake, an exhibition of the Blake Trust Facsimiles at
                        the österreichisches Museum für angewandte Kunst, Vienna,
                        May-June 1976. Reviewed by Buchsbaum, Wiener Zeitung, 9 May 1976; by Walter
                        Zeleny, Salzburger Volksblatt, 11 May 1976; in Die Presse [Vienna], 8 [?14]
                        May 1976; and in Wochenpresse [Vienna], 12 May 1976.</p>
          <p>Burke, Joseph. English Art 1714-1800. Reviewed by Hugh Honour, The [London]
                        Times Literary Supplement, 21 January 1978, p. 63.</p>
          <p>Colby Library Quarterly. Blake Issue. Spring, 1977 [Vol. 13, no. 2; see
                        Heppner, Christopher; Warner, Janet; Stevenson, Warren; Rose, Edward J.; and
                        Sutherland, John H., under “Critical Studies”]. Reviewed by Bevis
                        Hillier, The [London] Times Literary Supplement, 17 February 1978, p.
                        212.</p>
          <p>Cooke, Michael G. The Romantic Will. Reviewed by Karl Kroeber, Keats-Shelley
                        Journal, 37 (1978), 135-138.</p>
          <p>Curran, Stuart, and Joseph A. Wittreich, Jr., eds. Blake’s Sublime
                        Allegory. Reviewed by P. Malekin, Review of English Studies, n.s., 26
                        (1975), 339-343.</p>
          <p>Dargan, Tom. See Wolf, Donald A.</p>
          <p>Darwin, Erasmus. The Botanic Garden 1791, ed. Desmond King-Hele. Reviewed by
                        Donald M. Hassler, Studies in Burke and His Time, 16 (1975), 291-293.</p>
          <p>Davis, Michael. William Blake: A New Kind of Man. Reviewed by Morchard
                        Bishop, The [London] Times Literary Supplement, 20 May 1978, p. 622.</p>
          <p>Doctorow, Erica. See Wolf, Donald A.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V. The Illuminated Blake. Reviewed by David Bindman, Burlington
                        Magazine, 119 (1977), 451-452.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V. The Notebook of William Blake, 1st ed. Reviewed by Leonard
                        M. Trawick, Studies in Burke and His Time, 17 (1976), 71-74; by John E.
                        Grant, Modern Philology, 75 (1977), 196-201; revised edition, by Thomas L.
                        Minnick, Studies in Romanticism, 16 (1977), 267-268.</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert, and Jenijoy La Belle, eds. Night Thoughts. Reviewed by Karen
                        Mulhallen, Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 41-42.</p>
          <p>John Flaxman, exhibition at the Heim Gallery, London. Reviewed by David
                        Irwin, Burlington Magazine, 118 (1976), 335-336.</p>
          <p>Fox, Susan. Poetic Form in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> Reviewed
                        by Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr., Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11
                        (1977-78), 114-117; by P. Malekin, The Review of English Studies, n.s. 29
                        (1978), 101-103; by Leslie Brisman, Studies in Romanticism, 16 (1977),
                        260-267.</p>
          <p>Frosch, Thomas R. The Awakening of Albion: The Renovation of the Body in the
                        Poetry of William Blake. Reviewed by James C. Evans, Queen’s
                        Quarterly: A Canadian Review, 81 (1974), 635-636.</p>
          <p>Henry Fuseli, exhibition at the Tate Gallery, London. Reviewed by Robert
                        Melville, Architectural Review, 157 (1975), 305-307; by Christopher Neve,
                        Country Life, no. 4052, 27 February 1975, 492-493.</p>
          <pb id="p12-149" n="149"/>
          <p>Johann Heinrich Füssli, exhibition at the Petit Palais, Paris.
                        Reviewed by Juliette de Butler, L’Information d’histoire de
                        l’art, 20 (1975), 230-234.</p>
          <p>Hofmann, Werner, ed. William Blake: Lieder der Unschuld und Erfahrung.
                        Reviewed by Detlef W. Dörrbecker, Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11
                        (1977-78), 44-49; in Tagesspiegel [Berlin], 13 April 1975; in Frankfurter
                        Abendpost Nachtausgabe, 15 May 1975; in Oberösterreichische
                        Nachrichten [Linz, Austria], 24 July 1975; in Elseviers Magazine
                        [Netherlands], 26 July 1975; in Berliner Morgenpost, 26 August 1975; by
                        Helmuth A. Niederle, österreichischer Rundfunk [radio broadcast], 19
                        June 1976; by Konrad Holzer, österreichischer Rundfunk [radio
                        broadcast], 20 December 1976.</p>
          <p>Howard, John. Blake’s “Milton”: A Study in the Selfhood.
                        Reviewed by Morris Eaves, Studies in Romanticism, 16 (1977), 251-260.</p>
          <p>John, Brian. Supreme Fictions; Studies in the Work of William Blake, Thomas
                        Carlyle, W. B. Yeats, and D. H. Lawrence. Reviewed by Denis Donoghue, Modern
                        Language Review, 72 (1977), 155-156; by M. P. Scofield, The Review of
                        English Studies, 28 (1977), 102-110.</p>
          <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. William Blake: Die Vermählung von Himmel und
                        Hölle. Reviewed by Detlef W. Dörrbecker, Blake/An Illustrated
                        Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 44-49; and in National-Zeitung [Basel], 27 March
                        1975.</p>
          <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. William Blake: The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.
                        Reviewed by John Beer, Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78),
                        42-44.</p>
          <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. William Blake’s <corr type="emend">Laocoön.</corr> Reviewed by
                        Charles Ryskamp, The [London] Times Literary Supplement, 1 April 1977, p.
                        413.</p>
          <p>Klonsky, Milton. William Blake: The Seer and His Visions. Reviewed by Anatole
                        Broyard, New York Times, 9 November 1977, section C, p. 22.</p>
          <p>La Belle, Jenijoy. See Essick, Robert.</p>
          <p>Lindberg, Bo. William Blake’s ‘Illustrations to the Book of
                        Job’. Reviewed by David Bindman, Burlington Magazine, 119 (1977),
                        451-452; by Martin Butlin, Art Bulletin, 57 (1975), 295-296.</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond. Infernal Methods: A Study of William Blake’s Art
                        Techniques. Reviewed by Corlette Walker, Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11
                        (1977-78), 203-204; by Morris Eaves, Publishing History, 2 (1978),
                        57-77.</p>
          <p>Mellor, Anne K. Blake’s Human Form Divine. Reviewed by David Bindman,
                        Burlington Magazine, 119 (1977), 451-452.</p>
          <p>Nathan, Norman. Prince William B.: The Philosophical Conceptions of William
                        Blake. Reviewed by Penelope B. Wilson, Modern Language Review, 72 (1977),
                        913-916.</p>
          <p>Newsome, David. Two Classes of Men. Reviewed by Melvin Rader, English
                        Language Notes, 14 (1977), 303-305.</p>
          <p>Paananen, Victor N. William Blake. Reviewed by Edward J. Rose, Blake/An
                        Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 205-206.</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D., and Michael Phillips, eds. William Blake: Essays in honour
                        of Sir Geoffrey Keynes. Reviewed by P. Malekin, Review of English Studies,
                        n.s., 26 (1975), 339-343; by Leonard M. Trawick, Studies in Burke and His
                        Time, 17 (1976), 156-159.</p>
          <p>Rosenblum, Robert. Modern Painting and the Northern Tradition: Friedrich to
                        Rothko. Reviewed by W. J. T. Mitchell, Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11
                        (1977-78), 200-202.</p>
          <p>Rump, Gerhard Charles. Romney (1974). Reviewed by Johannes Dobai,
                        Kunstchronik, 29 (1976), 351-355.</p>
          <p>Stewart, Clark, illustrator. The Marriage of Heaven and Hell. Reviewed by
                        Judith Ott, Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 117-119.</p>
          <p>Tomory, Peter. The Life and Art of Henry Fuseli. Reviewed by Peter Alan
                        Taylor, Studies in Burke and His Time, 17 (1976), 141-145.</p>
          <p>Viebrock, Helmut. [A lecture on Blake delivered at the Städel museum,
                        Frankfurt, in connection with the 1975-Blake exhibition]. Reviewed in
                        Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung, 24 June 1975.</p>
          <p>Wagenknecht, David. Blake’s Night: William Blake and the Idea of the
                        Pastoral. Reviewed by P. Malekin, Review of English Studies, n.s., 26
                        (1975), 339-343.</p>
          <p>Wilkinson, A. M. William Blake and the Great Sin: An Inaugural Lecture.
                        Reviewed by Penelope B. Wilson, Modern Language Review, 72 (1977),
                        913-916.</p>
          <p>Wittreich, Joseph A., Jr. Angel of Apocalypse. Reviewed by P. Malekin, The
                        Review of English Studies, 28 (1977), 350-353.</p>
          <p>Wolf, Donald A., Tom Dargan, and Erica Doctorow. William Blake: The Poet as
                        Painter. [Catalogue of the Adelphi University exhibition.] Reviewed by Ruth
                        Fine, Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 11 (1977-78), 110-114.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
