<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>12.2.erdman</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The Four Zoas: New Text for Pages 5, 6, &amp; 7, Night the First</title>
        <author n="Erdman">David V. Erdman</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">12.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Special Design and Pasteup for this issue</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Everett Frost</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Terrence Hoagwood</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John Kilgore</name>
              <name>Mark Lefebvre</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Cettina Magno</name>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <name>Jeffry Spencer</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_12">
    <body>
      <pb id="p12-96" n="96"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-12-2-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">THE FOUR ZOAS:</hi> NEW TEXT FOR PAGES 5, 6,
                            &amp; 7, NIGHT THE FIRST</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">DAVID V.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">ERDMAN</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>Andrew Lincoln’s demonstration that <hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 143 is not
                    necessarily later than <hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 7 is fully persuasive. I have now
                    looked once more at the manuscript and can see that my previous misconstruction
                    of the sequence of revisions had prevented me from recognizing what constituted
                    the proper final text. It had also given me misleading clues that distracted me
                    from deciphering two of the heavily erased words. I can now see that
                    “Serpent” is the original reading in 7:10 as well as in 143:4 and
                    143:8—and that the second reading in 143:8 is “female”. The
                    evidence is hence clear that the final variants in page 143 constitute a layer
                    of revision intermediate between the first readings of that page and the final
                    readings of page 7. And it is impressively evident that the second
                    “half” of the creature that is half woman and half something else, in
                    7:23 and 143:4, begins as a serpent and ends as a spectre, with this sequence of
                    metamorphoses: 
					<q> Half Woman &amp; half Serpent<hi rend="s">7,143</hi> /
                            beast<hi rend="s">143</hi> / Spectre<hi rend="s">7</hi></q>
But what does this
sequence establish in the other variants on these
                    pages?</p>
        <p>HYPOTHESIS 1: That the movement from serpent to beast to spectre is a spiral, the
                    spectre evolving as a higher kind of serpent.</p>
        <p>If this is true, then unchanged terms in page 7 should apply first to serpent and
                    finally to spectre. The “scaly armour” of 7:25 and 143:6 (1st rdg)
                    belongs to serpent and finally to spectre; the “rocky features” of
                    143:6 2nd rdg belong only to the beast. The “brightness” of 7:21
                    remains unchanged but shifts in 143:2 to “darkness” for the beast. The
                    combination of woman and serpent or spectre is a “monster”; the
                    combination of woman and beast is a “wonder”; it has “rocky
                    features” and “darkly waving colours” rather than the
                    “lovely changing colours” of the “monster”. The somewhat
                    anomalous shift from “Serpent voice” to “female voice” in
                    143:8 seems to make both halves female: that voice is given to
                    “warbling”; but in page 7 the voice, whether of Serpent or of Spectre
                    (first and final readings), keeps to “incessant wailing”.</p>
        <p>HYPOTHESIS 2: That the movement is from “Serpent” and/or
                    “Spectre” to “beast”.</p>
        <p>In that case (assumed to be true by Bentley and Erdman) the changes introduced by
                    the second readings of page 143, when treated as revisions to page 7 (as in the
                    Doubleday text), produce final readings that are inconsistent with the context
                    established in pages 5 and 6, where “Spectre” is the latest reading.
                    (Keynes avoided such confusion by keeping page 143 separate as an
                    “additional fragment”; but then neither Keynes nor Bentley unearthed
                    the “beast,” being lost in a misreading of that word as
                    “desart”.) (For a demonstration deducing hypothesis 2 from the fact
                    that “brightness” and “scaly armour” et cetera are unchanged
                    in page 7, see Bentley, “The Composition and Growth of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>,” in his
1963 facsimile edition, p. 160, fn. 4.)</p>
        <p>The changes required in the Doubleday text and textual notes (pp. 299-300 and
                    740-42) and also in the Longmans text (pp. 298-99) can be spelled out in the
                    Doubleday format as follows:</p>
        <p>Doubleday page 299. PAGE 5. After line 43 add ten lines as follows: 
        <table rows="10" cols="3">
        	<row>
	<cell>What have I done! said Enion accursed wretch! What deed.</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
        	<row>
	<cell>Is this a deed of Love I know what I have done. I know</cell>
	<cell/>
	<cell>45</cell>
</row>
        </table>
        <pb id="p12-97" n="97"/>
        <table>
        	<row>
	<cell>Too late now to repent. Love is changd to deadly Hate</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
        	<row>
	<cell>A[<hi rend="i">ll</hi>] life is blotted out &amp; I alone remain
                                possessd with Fears</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
            <row>
	<cell>I see the Shadow of the dead within my Soul wandering</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
            <row>
	<cell>In darkness &amp; solitude forming Seas of Doubt &amp; rocks of
                                Repentance</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
            <row>
	<cell>Already are my Eyes reverted. all that I behold</cell>
	<cell/>
	<cell>50</cell>
</row>
            <row>
	<cell>Within my Soul has lost its splendor &amp; a brooding Fear</cell>
	<cell/><cell/>
</row>
            <row>
	<cell>Shadows me oer &amp; drives me outward to a world of woe</cell>
	<cell/><cell/>
</row>
            <row>
	<cell>So waild she trembling before her own Created Phantasm<lb/>
                                [space]</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
        </table>
        </p>
        <p>PAGE 6. After line 8 add ten lines as follows: (no extra space): <table rows="10" cols="3"><row>
	<cell>The Spectre thus spoke. Who art thou Diminutive husk &amp;
                                shell</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>If thou hast sinnd &amp; art polluted know that I am pure</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell>10</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>And unpolluted &amp; will bring to rigid strict account</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>All thy past deeds [So] hear what I tell thee! mark it well!
                                remember!</cell>
	<cell/><cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>This world is Thine in which thou dwellest that within thy
                                soul</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>That dark &amp; dismal infinite where Thought roams up &amp;
                                down</cell>
	<cell/><cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>Is Mine &amp; there thou goest when with one Sting of my
                                tongue</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell>15</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>Envenomd thou rollst inwards to the place whence I emergd<lb/>
                                [space]</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>She trembling answerd Wherefore was I born &amp; what am I</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>I thought to weave a Covering for my Sins from wrath of
                                Tharmas</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row></table></p>
        <p>PAGE 7. Without a space, insert the following seven lines at the beginning:
                        <table rows="7" cols="3"><row>
	<cell>I thought Tharmas a Sinner &amp; I murderd his Emanations</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>His secret loves &amp; Graces Ah me wretched What have I
                                done</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>For now I find that all those Emanations were my Childrens
                                Souls</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>And I have murderd them with Cruelty above atonement</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>Those that remain have fled from my cruelty into the
                                desarts</cell>
	<cell/>
	<cell>5</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>And thou the delusive tempter to these deeds sittest before
                                me</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>In this thy world not mine tho dark I feel my world within</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row></table></p>
        <p>After a space, replace the 14 lines of text with the following six: <table rows="6" cols="3"><row>
	<cell>Mingling his horrible brightness with her tender limbs; then high
                                she soar’d</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>Above the ocean; a bright wonder [<hi rend="i">that</hi>] Nature
                                    [<hi rend="i">shudder’d at</hi>]</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>Half Woman &amp; half Spectre, all his lovely changing colours
                                mix</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell>10</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>With her fair crystal clearness; in her lips &amp; cheeks his
                                poisons rose</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>In blushes like the morning, and his scaly armour softening</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>A monster lovely in the heavens or wandering on the earth,</cell>
	<cell>t</cell>
	<cell/>
</row></table></p>
        <p>PAGE 8 follows, with no extra space.</p>
        <p>These changes in the text necessitate the following changes in the Textual Notes,
                    pages 740-43:</p>
        <p>740-41: delete everything from “Ten deleted lines follow” through
                    “line it would replace”; insert the following:</p>
        <p>Lines 44-53 were cancelled by three diagonal strokes but then circled in ink for
                    restoration to the text. (For a convincing demonstration that such circling, on
                    pages 5-7 and not found elsewhere, was <corr type="emend">intended</corr> to bring the circled lines back
                    “in,” see Andrew Lincoln in (this issue of) <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi></p>
        <p>46 Love is changed to . . . Hate] ?Alone ?possessed by . . . Fears <hi rend="i">1st rdg
del</hi></p>
        <p>47 All life] [<hi rend="i">All</hi>] &lt;A&gt; life <hi rend="i">ms
                        rdg</hi>; the erasure of “All” was evidently a slip; Blake never
                    used the phrase “a life” in the meaning it would have here.</p>
        <p>48 Shadow . . . Soul] remembrance . . . eyes <hi rend="i">1st rdg del</hi></p>
        <p>49 Doubt . . . Repentance] Trouble . . . sorrow <hi rend="i">1st rdg del</hi></p>
        <p>53] There follow a penciled insert and a deleted line it would replace:</p>
        <p>Revise the central line on p. 741 to read: “After line 8 follow 17 lines
                    deleted by diagonal strokes and a grey wash:” and then delete everything
                    after the 17th line, ending “manifest,” to the end of the note (i. e.
                    from “The Spectre thus spoke” through “wrath of Tharmas”).
                    Insert the following page 6 notes:</p>
        <p>Lines 9-19 were deleted by diagonal strokes but then restored by a circling ink
                    line.</p>
        <p>9-10 Who art thou . . . shell] An insertion, with this continuation (later
                    deleted) up the right margin:</p>
		<q> Broke from thy bonds I scorn my prison I scorn &amp; yet I love </q>
        <p>The insertion before deletion was to replace this 1st rdg:</p>
		<q> Art thou not my slave &amp; shalt thou dare<lb/>
 To smite me with thy tongue
                    beware lest I sting also thee </q>
        <p>10-12 If thou . . . past deeds] inserted over erasure.</p>
        <p>12 So] conjectural reading of strokes imperfectly inked.</p>
        <p>13 Thine] Mine <hi rend="i">1st rdg del</hi></p>
        <p>15 Mine] <hi rend="i">mended from</hi> thine The Spectre is crowding Enion into
                    the outer world while he invades the infinite within.</p>
        <p>16 whence I emergd] of death &amp; hell <hi rend="i">1st rdg del</hi>; where <hi rend="i">2nd rdg
del</hi></p>
        <p>17] A deleted line follows: A sorrow &amp; a fear a living torment &amp; naked
                    Victim</p>
        <p>18 for my] for his <hi rend="i">1st rdg del</hi></p>
        <pb id="p12-98" n="98"/>
        <p>Replace all of the “PAGE 7 (&amp; 143)” note, up through the fifth
                    printed line at the top of p. 743, with the following:</p>
        <p>PAGE 7</p>
        <p>Page 7 is a thicket of erased and deleted original and additional lines. The top
                    block of 9 added lines has been deleted, then restored by an ink circle, then
                    heavily revised; the last of these (line 7 in the present text) is so crossed
                    out and mended that to restore it Blake has written “This line to come
                    in” alongside it. The lower half of the page consists of original
                    copperplate writing, with some mending and some deletion of lines. The undeleted
                    original lines appear also on p 143 (a <figure n="BB209.1.7.MS.detail" rend="file" width="958" height="413">
	<head><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 7 (detail).</head>
</figure> smaller leaf but neatly written as if begun as fair copy, perhaps of a
                    draft preceding the large copperplate pages) and are there revised. Until
                    recently it has been assumed that the revisions of p 143 were later than the
                    final text of p 7, but Andrew Lincoln argues convincingly that the final
                    revisions on p 7 are later than those on p 143.</p>
        <p>1] Preceded by two lines, mended and then heavily cancelled after Blake’s
                    encircling: 
					<q> Examining the sins of Tharmas I 
                    [<hi rend="i">have</hi>]<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied>&lt;soon&gt; found my own<lb/>
 O slay me not thou art his Wrath
                        embodied in Deceit </q></p>
        <p>2] An inserted line.</p>
        <p>3 For] But <hi rend="i">1st rdg del</hi></p>
        <p>Under lines 1-3 and the preceding cancelled lines are three erased lines in
                    Blake’s usual hand, the last</p>
        <p>[Here retain the Doubleday textual note, from “word of the 1st line”
                    through “globe self balanc’d”; replace the remainder of the
                    note with the following:]</p>
        <p>4] An inserted line.</p>
        <p>6] Among wild beasts to roam And thou the delusive tempter <hi rend="i">1st rdg
                        del</hi>, followed by two cancelled lines:</p>
        <p>[<hi rend="i">But where is</hi>]&lt;[<hi rend="i">Thou art
                    not</hi>]&gt;&lt;And art thou&gt;Tharmas all thy Soft delusive
                    beauty cannot Tempt me to murder 
                    [<hi rend="i">honest love</hi>]<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied>&lt;my own
                    soul&gt;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied>&amp; wipe my tears &amp; smile</p>
        <p>7 not mine tho] for ah! how <hi rend="i">1st rdg del</hi> Six cancelled lines
                    follow, after a stanza break: 
					<q> The Spectre said Thou sinful Woman. was it thy
                        Desire<lb/>
 That I should hide thee with my power &amp; delight thee with
                        my beauty<lb/>
 And now thou darknest in my presence. never from my
                        sight<lb/>
 Shalt thou depart to weep in secret. In my jealous wings<lb/>
 I
                        evermore will hold thee when thou goest out or comest in 5<lb/>
<pb id="p12-99" n="99"/>
Tis thou hast darkend all My World O Woman lovely
                        bane </q></p>
        <p>After another stanza break, we return to the original copperplate text, beginning
                    with three deleted lines: 
					<q> Thus they contended all the day among the Caves of
                        Tharmas<lb/>
 Twisting in fearful forms &amp; howling &lt;howling harsh
                        shrieking&gt;<lb/>
 &lt;Howling&gt;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied>harsh shrieking, mingling
                        their bodies join in burning anguish </q>
Page 143 begins with a variant of
                    the last line: 
					<q> &lt;Opening his rifted rocks&gt; mingling [<hi rend="i">their
bodies</hi>]<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied>&lt;together they&gt; join in burning
                        anguish </q></p>
        <p>(The rocks accord with the “rocky features” of the “beast” of
                    the middle version; see below.)</p>
        <p>8 horrible] <hi rend="i">1st and 3rd rdg, del but not erased p 7, only rdg p
                        143;</hi> terrible <hi rend="i">2nd rdg erased p 7</hi> brightness] <hi rend="i">p 7,
1st rdg del p 143;</hi> darkness <hi rend="i">2nd rdg p
                        143</hi></p>
        <p>9 Above the ocean;] <hi rend="i">p 7</hi>; Shrieking above the ocean: <hi rend="i">p 143;</hi> on p
7 “Shrieking” is inserted before the
                    line but then deleted. Nature] <hi rend="i">1st rdg del and 3rd rdg, p 7;</hi>
                    Beulah <hi rend="i">2nd rdg del p 7;</hi> “that” and
                    “shudder’d at” are cancelled but not replaced on p 7; p 143
                    reads “that nature shudderd at”.</p>
        <p>10 Spectre] <hi rend="i">2nd rdg p 7;</hi> Serpent <hi rend="i">1st rdg del p 7,
                        1st rdg p 143;</hi> beast <hi rend="i">2nd rdg p 143</hi> lovely changing]
                        <hi rend="i">p 7 and 1st rdg del p 143;</hi> darkly waving <hi rend="i">2nd
                        rdg p 143</hi></p>
        <p>11 poisons] <hi rend="i">p 7 and 1st rdg del p 143;</hi> metals <hi rend="i">2nd
                        rdg p 143</hi></p>
        <p>12 scaly armour] <hi rend="i">p 7 and 1st rdg del p 143;</hi> rocky features <hi rend="i">2nd rdg p
143</hi> softening] softning <hi rend="i">p 143</hi></p>
        <p>13 monster] <hi rend="i">p 7 and 1st rdg del p 143;</hi> wonder <hi rend="i">2nd
                        rdg p 143</hi> wandering] wandring <hi rend="i">p 143</hi></p>
        <p>Page 143 continues: 
		<q> With [<hi rend="i">Serpent</hi>]<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied>&lt;female&gt;
                        voice &lt;warbling upon the [<hi rend="i">hills</hi>] &amp; hollow
                        vales&gt;<lb/>
 Beauty all blushing with desire a Self enjoying wonder
					</q>
					(The insertions are written on top of almost illegible erasures, but the
                        <hi rend="i">p</hi> and <hi rend="i">t</hi> of “Serpent” have left
                    traces in precisely the right places.)</p>
        <p>Page 7 continues with three deleted lines: 
		<q> With [<hi rend="i">Serpent</hi>]<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied>&lt;Spectre&gt; voice incessant wailing; in incessant
                        thirst<lb/>
 Beauty all blushing with desire mocking her fell
                        despair<lb/>
<lb/>
 [space]<lb/>
 Wandering desolate, a wonder abhorr’d
                        by Gods &amp; Men </q>
The revision to “Spectre” suggests that p
                    143 was put aside before these line on p 7 were deleted. Page 143 originally
                    continued, after a stanza break: 
					<q> And thus her voice; &lt;Glory, delight,
                        &amp; sweet enjoyment born&gt;<lb/>
 &lt;To mild Eternity shut in a
                        threefold shape delightful&gt;<lb/>
 To wander in
                        &lt;sweet&gt;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied>solitude<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied>&lt;enrapturd&gt;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied>at every wind </q>
                    (The second line and the two words bracketed in the third were written over
                    erasures.) In the break before these three lines and in the bottom margin below
                    them are two versions of a passage to be adapted from the deleted copperplate
                    text of p 8 and to be followed by line 11 (“And thus her voice”) et
                    cetera. In the deleted text (lines 5-13 following 8:7) Enion broods, after
                    bearing two infants, and vegetation grows up from the rough rocks to shelter
                    them. The revision may be intended to have the vegetation grow up to shelter
                    Enion <hi rend="i">before</hi> she gives birth to the children.</p>
        <p>The version at the bottom of p 143 (possibly written first) is crowded in like
                    prose but may be lined out, with the help of Blake’s slashes and
                    capitals. It begins with a half line that could be meant to replace “a Self
                    enjoying wonder” at the end of 143:9: 
					<q> Shining across the ocean /<lb/>
                        Enion brooded groaning the golden rocks vegetate<lb/>
 The b . . . [paper
                        torn away]<lb/>
 to<lb/>
 Infolding the bright woman from the desolating winds
                        /<lb/>
 &amp; thus her voice &amp;[c] [paper torn away] </q>
The suggestion
                    is to follow the “Enion brooded” line with its successor (before
                    insertions) in p 8 which reads: 
					<q> The barked Oak, the long limbd Beech; the
                        Ches’nut tree; the Pine. </q>
and to continue the passage, which
                    fills five more lines with vegetation and animation, to conclude with Infolding
                    the bright Infants from the desolating winds</p>
        <p>—with the woman replacing the Infants. Blake subsequently deleted all
                    these instructions except the phrase “Infolding the bright woman”.</p>
        <p>The alternative version, undeleted, consists of a double line crowded into the
                    stanza break between “a Self enjoying wonder” (presumably to be left
                    intact) and “And thus her voice”. Here the vegetating process is more
                    complex, involving seas, rocks, and vortex: 
					<q> For Enion brooded groaning loud
                        the rough seas <corr type="emend">vegetate.</corr><lb/>
 Golden rocks rise from the [<hi rend="i">vorte</hi> . . . ]&lt;vast&gt; [paper torn] </q>
Possibly the
                    plan was to have this triple vegetating proceed at once to “Infolding the
                    bright woman” (undeleted portion of the first version): it would make up a
                    full line (if there weren’t too many words on the torn paper): and
                    perhaps to conclude as before with “Thus her voice” et cetera.</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
