<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>12.2.tate</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">Tate Blake Gallery</title>
        <author n="Butlin">Martin Butlin</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">12.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Special Design and Pasteup for this issue</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Everett Frost</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Terrence Hoagwood</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John Kilgore</name>
              <name>Mark Lefebvre</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Cettina Magno</name>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <name>Jeffry Spencer</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_12">
    <body>
      <pb id="p12-159" n="159"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-12-2-0017">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">NEWSLETTER</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">TATE BLAKE GALLERY</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>A new gallery specially designed for the Tate Gallery’s Blake
                        collection is scheduled to open in Autumn 1978. As well as the majority of
                        the Tate’s own Blake collection and a section devoted to such artists
                        as Samuel Palmer and George Richmond, the display will include the two
                        panels “Winter” and “Evening” lent by the Vaughan
                        Johnson Trust, the watercolor sketch “Job and His Daughters” lent
                        by Dr. R. E. Hemphill and a group of works from the Bateson Collection. The
                        Bateson Collection, which was previously on long loan to the Honolulu
                        Academy of Arts, includes the four works shown in the large Tate Gallery
                        exhibition earlier in the year, “Pestilence,” the color print
                        “Satan exulting over Eve,” the sketch for the alternative design
                        for the title page to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, and the late book
                        illustration discussed elsewhere in this issue of <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi>
                        In addition the collection contains three other works which have also been
                        placed on long loan at the Tate Gallery, a tracing possibly by Blake himself
                        from the drawing of “The Last Judgment” in the Rosenwald
                        Collection, the drawing of “Adam and Eve sleeping” included by
                        Geoffrey Keynes in his first book of <hi rend="i">Pencil Drawings by William
                            Blake</hi>, 1927, as no. 35 but later recognized by him as a drawing by
                        Edward Francis Burney, and a pen and wash drawing of “The Expulsion of
                        Adam and Eve” which bears a false signature of Blake and the date
                        “1803” but is certainly not by him. Not all of these works will be
                        on view but those in store can be seen by appointment.
                        <byline><docAuthor>MARTIN <name>BUTLIN</name>,</docAuthor> 
                        KEEPER OF THE BRITISH COLLECTION, TATE GALLERY, LONDON.</byline></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
