<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>12.2.hilton</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The Sweet Science of Atmospheres in The Four Zoas</title>
        <author n="Hilton">Nelson Hilton</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">12.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Special Design and Pasteup for this issue</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Everett Frost</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Terrence Hoagwood</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John Kilgore</name>
              <name>Mark Lefebvre</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Cettina Magno</name>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <name>Jeffry Spencer</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_12">
    <body>
      <pb id="p12-80" n="80"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-12-2-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">THE SWEET SCIENCE OF ATMOSPHERES IN <hi rend="i">THE FOUR
                                ZOAS</hi></hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">NELSON</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">HILTON</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
		<q> And all the time in Caverns shut, the golden Looms erected<lb/>
 First spun, then
                    wove the Atmospheres, there the Spider &amp; Worm<lb/>
 Plied the wingd shuttle
                    piping shrill thro’ all the list’ning threads<lb/>
 Beneath the
                    Caverns roll the weights of lead &amp; spindles of iron<lb/>
 The enormous warp
                    &amp; woof rage direful in the affrighted deep<lb/>
<lb/>
 While far into the
                    vast unknown, the strong wing’d Eagles bend<lb/>
 Their venturous flight,
                    in Human forms distinct; thro darkness deep<lb/>
 They bear the woven draperies;
                    on golden hooks they hang abroad<lb/>
 The universal curtains &amp; spread out
                    from Sun to Sun<lb/>
 The vehicles of light, they separate the furious
                    particles<lb/>
 Into mild currents as the water mingles with the wine.<lb/>
<lb/>
                    While thus the Spirits of strongest wing enlighten the dark deep<lb/>
 The
                    threads are spun &amp; the cords twisted &amp; drawn out; then the weak<lb/>
                    Begin their work; &amp; many a net is netted; many a net<lb/>
 Spread &amp;
                    many a Spirit caught, innumerable the nets<lb/>
 Innumerable the gins &amp;
                    traps; &amp; many a soothing flute<lb/>
 Is form’d &amp; many a corded
                    lyre, outspread over the immense<lb/>
 In cruel delight they trap the listeners,
                    &amp; in cruel delight<lb/>
 Bind them, condensing the strong energies into
                    little compass<lb/>
 Some became seed of every plant that shall be planted;
                    some<lb/>
 The bulbous roots, thrown up together into barns &amp;
                    garners<lb/>
<lb/>
 (29.2-30.7)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Blake references are to David V. Erdman, ed.,
                            <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, 3rd printing
                        rev. (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1968); here pp. 312-13.</note></q>
        <p>This passage, a type of the cosmogonic moment variously presented by Blake, has
                    largely been passed over in the silence accorded self-evident meaning, or when
                    discussed, glided through with such selective paraphrase and assured comment as
                    to belie any but an undemanding significance.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n2" type="note">2</ref> The three sections present a nearly simultaneous temporal unity
                    (“And all the time. . . . While. . . . While”) strongly grounded in a
                    sequence of interrelated images, already suggesting to the painstaking reader
                    that the passage is structured around a coherent underlying meaning. 
<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> D. J. Sloss and J. P. R. Wallis remarked in
                        their edition (speaking specifically of the second verse grouping) that,
                        “This passage presents some difficulty, if, as elsewhere . . . a
                        definitely mental significance is to be read into this myth. For it is
                        impossible to reconcile the intellectual light with the obscurantism denoted
                        by Urizen himself, and manifested in the creation of his new world. It may
                        be therefore that the reference is to the light of the sun, not to mental
                        light”; <hi rend="i">The Prophetic Writings of William Blake</hi>
                        (Oxford: Clarendon, 1926), I, 180 n. Milton O. Percival states simply that
                        “The looms weave the spiritual clothing”; while, on the other
                        hand, “The net of the moral law is beginning to take shape”; <hi rend="i">William
Blake’s Circle of Destiny</hi> (1938; rpt. New
                        York: Octagon Books, 1970), p. 63. Erdman sees “the caverns of
                        manufactory” where children are represented by “silkworms”
                        and spiders, and notes the appearance of Blake’s “favorite
                        theme, the spinning and twisting by the weak of the ‘gins &amp;
                        traps’ of Church and State propaganda”; <hi rend="i">Blake:
                            Prophet Against Empire</hi>, rev. ed. (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday,
                        1969), pp. 335-36.</note></p>
        <p>A first reading reveals that the Atmospheres are woven, spread through space and
                    then reintroduced as a spirit-catching and spirit-condensing net. In the first
                    of two brief notes on the passage (E 871), Bloom answers the strangeness of the
                    “first spun, then wove” Atmospheres with a reference to <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>
7.241, where God “spun out the Air.” Milton
                    was only one of the first to use what became a standard and sometimes very
                    involved eighteenth-century image of the woven “fabric” or
                    “texture” of air. Blackmore’s popular <hi rend="i">The
                        Creation</hi> (1712) set the tone: <pb id="p12-81" n="81"/>
<figure n="BB209.1.29.MS" rend="file" width="783" height="1000">
	<head><hi rend="i">Vala or The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 29.</head>
	<figDesc>London, British Museum.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p12-82" n="82"/>
	<q> Remark the air’s transparent element,<lb/>
 Its curious structures,
                        and its vast extent:<lb/>
 Its wondrous web proclaims the loom divine;<lb/>
                        Its threads, the hand that drew them out so fine.<lb/>
 This thin contexture
                        makes its bosom fit,<lb/>
 Celestial heat and lustre to transmit;<lb/>
<lb/>
                            (2.618-23)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Richard Blackmore, <hi rend="i">The
                                Creation: A Philosophical Poem in Seven Books</hi>, in <hi rend="i">The Works
of the English Poets. with Prefaces, Biographical and
                                Critical by Samuel Johnson</hi>, vol. 24 (London: J. Nichols et al.,
                            1779).</note></q></p>
        <p>The scientific exactitude of “Atmospheres” calls attention to the
                    figurative loom in which they were woven. The formula “Looms erected”
                    recalls an image fifteen lines earlier where the Children of Man, “schools
                    Erected forming Instruments / To measure out the course of heaven”
                        (28.20-21).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref>
The looms are the schools of
                    warped thought, an image presented more explicitly in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, where
<q> I turn my eyes to the Schools &amp; Universities
                        of Europe<lb/>
 And there behold the Loom of Locke whose Woof rages
                        dire<lb/>
<lb/>
 (15.14-15). </q>
The Caverns then, as the site of this mental
                    manufacture, contain the mind-loom in its perceptual and physical shell.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> “Beneath” the caverns is without,
                    the vast unknown of the unconscious. <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
                        Hell</hi> presents a similar transition: “an Eagle with wings and
                    feathers of air, he caused the inside of the cave to be infinite” (pl. 15).
                    This mental space was entered by Er at the end of the <hi rend="i">Republic</hi>
                    in one of the earliest journeys through the unknown. There he saw “the
                    light which binds heaven” and, hanging from its extremities, “the
                    spindle [atraktos] of Necessity” and its “weight” [sphondulos]
                    (616c ff., cf. <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 35. 14-15). The “Atmospheres”
                    offer a later instance of that myth. Ostensibly as natural as the air we
                    breathe, the “Atmospheres” are in fact woven by “the
                    Spider,” known for his entrapping web of thought, and the “Worm,”
                    who otherwise spins the veiling cocoon of “silken thought” (cf. <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi>, 1.157-58). <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi>
                        Night the Second, with half of Blake’s ten uses, is the center for
                        things “erected”; four pages earlier the Bands of Heaven “the
                        loom erected” (24.10) next to “golden compasses, the
                        quadrant” and other technical instruments, and “They erected the
                        furnaces” (24.13). Shortly after the passage under discussion, the qoal
                        of all the preceding, “the Altar . . . was Erected”
                        (30.38-42).</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> “Caverns,” moreover, glance at the
                        received idea that the atmospheres were made underground: “ . . . by
                        the continual fermentations made in the bowels of the earth there are aerial
                        substances raised out of all kinds of bodies, all which together make the
                        atmosphere,” wrote Newton; I. Bernard Cohen, ed., <hi rend="i">Isaac
                            Newton’s Papers and Letters On Natural Philosophy and related
                            documents</hi>, assisted by Robert E. Schofield, with explanatory
                        prefaces by Marie Boas, Charles Coulston Gillispie, Thomas S. Kuhn, and
                        Perry Miller (Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard Univ. Press, 1958), p. 253.
                        Chamber’s <hi rend="i">Cyclopedia</hi> defined “atmosphere”
                        as that part of air “which receives vapours and exhalations”
                        (1751, OED). In Night the Ninth, Urizen and family “pourd their light /
                        To exhale the spirits of Luvah &amp; Vala thro the atmosphere”
                        (131.33-34).</note></p>
        <p>The close proximity of the formulaic “wingd shuttle” to the
                    “wing’d Eagles” intimates that those “Human forms”
                    are being manipulated by the “Spider” and “Worm,” an
                    impression strengthened by the fact that the Eagles “bend,” where
                    those weavers “plied”—a very rare verb for Blake, a significant
                    meaning of which was “to bend.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref>
                    Both shuttle and Eagles are moving back and forth filling up space. These eagles
                    suggest the great scientists of the century, like Halley and Newton, who, even
                    in life, were very commonly presented as pursuing extramundane, cosmic voyages
                    of intellect.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> Here
Blake sees them drawing
                    their threads or theories of aethereal atmosphere behind them—bringing
                    not light, but darkness visible. This point is confirmed by the application of
                    the remaining three instances of “venturous” to the spider-scientist
                    Urizen, whose “dire Web / Followed behind him” (73.31-32)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> in his exploration of the Abyss at the end
                    of Night the Sixth (also the only Night where “the vast unknown”
                    reappears): 
					<q> Creating many a vortex fixing many a Science in the deep<lb/>
                        And thence throwing his venturous limbs into the vast unknown<lb/>
<lb/>
                            (72.13-14)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">9</ref></q>
The “woven draperies” they bear must be the woven Atmospheres of
                    the previous section, now expanded to “The universal curtains” and
                    “the vehicles of light.” These curtains cannot fail to bring to mind
                    Urizen’s “woven darkness” in <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>
                    (7.25) or those created by the Eternals in <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>
                    in order to “bind in the Void” and close the fallen worlds from their
                    sight: 
					<q> 12. They began to weave curtains of darkness<lb/>
 They erected large
                        pillars round the Void<lb/>
 With golden hooks fastend in the pillars<lb/>
                        With infinite labour the Eternals<lb/>
 A woof wove, and called it
                        Science<lb/>
<lb/>
 (19.5-9) </q>
This work parallels the Lord’s
                    instructions to Moses that His temple is to be furnished with pillars and hooks
                    of gold from which to hang “the vail that shall divide unto you between the
                    holy place and the most holy” (Ex. 26:32, 33, et al.). In Night the Second
                    the golden hooks are suns. The woven Atmospheres/curtains which serve also as
                    “the vehicles of light” suggest Newton’s formulation of
                    “an ethereal medium, much of the same constitution with air, but far rarer,
                    subtler, and more strongly elastic” (Cohen, p. 179). <hi rend="i">The Book
                        of Los</hi> speaks of “Light. . . . conducted by fluid so pure”
                    (5.10-11). <note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Ply, “bend,” and ply,
                        “employ,” are distinct verbs; the former, although now rare, rates
                        an entry half the length of the latter in the OED.</note>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> William Powell Jones quotes a number of
                        examples in his <hi rend="i">The Rhetoric of Science: A Study of Scientific
                            Ideas and Imagery in Eighteenth-Century English Poetry</hi> (Berkeley
                        &amp; Los Angeles: Univ. of California Press, 1966), pp. 99-103; see also
                        Marjorie Hope Nicolson, <hi rend="i">Newton Demands the Muse:
                            Newton’s “Opticks” and the Eighteenth Century
                            Poets</hi>, Princeton Paperback (1946; rpt. Princeton: Princeton Univ.
                        Press, 1966), p. 68. One high point of the tradition is Wordsworth’s
                        image of Newton as “a mind for ever / Voyaging through strange seas of
                        Thought, alone” (<hi rend="i">Prelude</hi> 3.62-63).</note>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> This web can represent a different aspect of
                        perceptual entrapment, based on schematic diagrams of the solar
                        system.</note>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> The variant form describing “the
                        ventrous feet / Of Urizen” (FZ 125.12-13) associates venturing with
                        “giving birth” via “venter,” the womb, and the
                        spectre’s podalic birth (FZ 5.15). “Venturous” also
                        represents one of Urizen’s many associations with Milton’s
                        Satan (cf. PL 5.64, 9.690) and his flight through the Abyss.</note></p>
        <p>Atmosphere is both woven and fluid at the same time. Its aethereal nature blends
                    into “particles” and “currents,” the proper combination of
                    corpuscular and wave theory: “A ray of light is a continued stream of these
                        particles.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref>
Water mingling with
                    wine offers a theoretical illustration similar to that of Grimaldi in his 
<hi rend="i">Physico-Mathesis de Lumine</hi>, where “He was led to conclude
                    that light did not go through diaphanous material by direct penetration but
                    rather in an indirect manner . . . . like wine in water.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> Note the direction of dilution: the wine of light is
                    being watered, but water requires spiritual transformation to turn to wine. On
                    the other hand, this same aethereal atmosphere was seen as being composed of
                    invisible threads by which light was transmitted. Blackmore explained: 
					<q> The
                        ever-rolling Orb’s impulsive Ray<lb/>
 On the next Threads and
                        Filaments does bear,<lb/>
 Which form the springy Texture of the Air,<lb/>
 .
                        . . these still strike the next, till to the Sight<lb/>
 The quick Vibration
                        propagates the Light;<lb/>
<lb/>
 (2.401-05) </q>
Henry Brooke’s <hi rend="i">Universal Beauty</hi> described the air, “Its mantle wove of
                    elemental threads,” which, invisible, “enfolds the sphere.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> “The various 
<pb id="p12-83" n="83"/>
                    twine of light” was untwisted by Newton in Thomson’s famous image
                    (“Spring,” 211), and Erasmus Darwin speaks simply of “the
                    sevenfold threads of light.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13"
type="note">13</ref> The
                    curtains woven from these imagined threads appear to be diaphanous—just
                    so the Inhabitants in <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi><q> Discernd not the woven
hipocrisy<lb/>
 But the streaky slime in their
                        heavens<lb/>
 Brought together by narrowing perceptions<lb/>
 Appeard
                        transparent air<lb/>
<lb/>
 (25.32-35) </q>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> “Optics,” <hi rend="i">Encyclopedia Britannica</hi>, vol. III (Edinburgh:
A Bell,
                        1771).</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Vasco Ronchi, <hi rend="i">The Nature of
                            Light, An Historical Survey</hi>, trans. V. Barocas (London: Heinemann,
                        1970), p. 135.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Cited in Nicolson, p. 68.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi><hi rend="i"> The Botanic Garden; A Poem, in Two Parts. Part I containing
                                The Economy of Vegetation. Part II, The Loves of the Plants. with
                                Philosophical Notes</hi> [10 plates engraved by Blake] (1791; rpt.
                            Menston, Eng.: Scholar Press, 1973); <hi rend="i">The Loves of the
                                Plants</hi>, I. 118, p. 10. In <hi rend="i">The Temple of
                                Nature</hi> (London: J. Johnson, 1803) Darwin was to see in
                            “threads” an even more basic unit of life: 
<q> Last, as fine
                                goads the glutton-threads excite<lb/>
 Cords grapple cords, and webs
                                with webs unite;<lb/>
 And quick CONTRACTION with ethereal flame<lb/>
                                Lights into life the fibre-woven frame,—<lb/>
 Hence without
                                parent by spontaneous birth<lb/>
 Rise the first spects of animated
                                earth;<lb/>
 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
                                Life’s subtle woof in Nature’s loom is wove;<lb/>
<lb/>
                                (I.243-48, 252) </q>
This was published, presumably, after Night the
                            Second was written. Darwin used analogous imagery of the origin of life
                            from “a simple living filament” in his prose study, <hi rend="i">Zoonomia; or The
Laws of Organic Life</hi> (London: J.
                            Johnson, 1794), I, 489-98.
                    </note></p>
        <p>The third section returns to the initial spinning as “The threads are spun
                    &amp; the cords twisted &amp; drawn out” which the weak, having
                    “power to resist energy” (MHH 16), make into “many a net.”
                    The twisted cords offer another evocation of <hi rend="i">The Book of
                        Urizen</hi>, pl. 25, which describes Urizen’s spider-web (25.10 ff.),
                    concluding 
					<q> 8. So twisted the cords, &amp; so knotted The meshes: twisted
                        like to the human brain<lb/>
<lb/>
 9. And all calld it, The Net of
                        Religion.<lb/>
<lb/>
 (25.20-22) </q>
The nets are identified with the
                    curtains and Atmospheres, not only being made from the same material (in turn,
                    “like to the human brain”), but, like the draperies they are
                    “Spread . . . outspread over the immense.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n14" type="note">14</ref> Blake draws attention to the luminescent component of
                    the image by twice repeating in a single line the “cruel de<hi rend="i">light</hi>” of
these activities. The nets of the weak “trap the
                    listeners” and catch “many a Spirit,” condensing their
                    “strong energies.” The Spirits caught are evidently those same
                    “strong wing’d Eagles. . . . spirits of strongest wing” that
                    originally spread the curtains (now nets), while the trapped listeners are those
                    “list’ning threads” through which the wingd shuttle plied. So
                    the spirits are bound in the web they thought to spread and the listeners are
                    woven into what they heard. <note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi><q> Donne saw a different
kind of mental net:<lb/>
 for of Meridians, and
                                Parallels,<lb/>
 Man hath weav’d out a net, and this net
                                throwne<lb/>
 Upon the Heavens, and now they are his own.<lb/>
<lb/>
                                (“The first Anniversary,” 278-80) </q></note></p>
        <p>The listeners hear the “chords” of “nature’s harmony,”
                    like the entrancing unheard musical air of the spheres. At the Wedding Feast of
                    Nature, Los and Enitharmon “listend to the Elemental Harps &amp; Sphery
                    Song” (13.1) presented by the “Bright Souls of vegetative life”
                    (13.24). But in Night the Second the flute and mendacious lyre are instruments
                    (“schools Erected forming instruments”) playing a seductive,
                    fallacious harmony. In Night the Fourth Tharmas compells Los to “choose
                    life”: 
					<q> And all the Elements shall serve thee to their soothing
                        flutes<lb/>
 Their sweet inspiriting lyres thy labours shall
                        administer<lb/>
<lb/>
 (52.3-4) </q>
This single instance of
                    “inspiriting” indicates that the lyres are to do more than
                    “uplift moods.” Los must play the lyre to draw spirits into the
                    furnaces of Urizen he is rebuilding; their bound energy is necessary to fuel his
                    work of constructing the fallen world.</p>
        <p>The passage from Night the Second concludes with the unexpected information that
                    the spirits are condensed “into little compass / Some became seed of every
                    plant . . . some / The bulbous roots . . . ” It is a striking conclusion to
                    the sequence of events that began with the weaving of the Atmospheres. One such
                    process of condensation was evident in <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>, where
                    the prophet caught the spiritual light to make the “glowing illusion”
                    of the mundane sun: 
					<q> 4: And first from those infinite fires<lb/>
 The light
                        that flow’d down on the winds<lb/>
 He siez’d; beating
                        incessant, condensing<lb/>
 The subtil particles in an Orb.<lb/>
<lb/>
                        (5.27-30) </q>
The illustration shows that sun to be “black but
                    shining” (SL 8, MHH 18). Urizen reveals in Night the Sixth that when
                    “death” shuts up his powers, he is “then a seed in the vast womb
                    of darkness” (73.8-9)—misremembering his ruined furnaces and
                    “stoned stupor” of Night the Fourth.</p>
        <p>It was probably in 1789, at the height of his involvement with The New Jerusalem
                    Church, that Blake read and extensively annotated Swedenborg’s <hi rend="i">The Wisdom
of Angels concerning Divine Love and Divine Wisdom</hi>
                    (London: W. Chalklen, 1788). One of the principal motifs of the book is the
                    descending correspondence running from “the Lord” to the
                    “spiritual sun” to the “natural sun.” Divine Love and Divine
                    Wisdom “appear in the spiritual world as a Sun” (no. 83, p. 69) and
                    from that sun proceed a corresponding “spiritual Heat and spiritual
                    Light” (no. 290, p. 264).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15"
type="note">15</ref> The
                    “assertion that the spiritual Sun is not Life” (e.g., according to
                    Swedenborg it is from the Lord but not the Lord, so “not life in
                    itself”) annotated Blake, “explains how the natural Sun is dead”
                    (p. 268). In addition to the Lord’s presenting himself “as to Love
                    by Heat, as to Wisdom by Light,” Swedenborg adds another correspondence,
                    that of “use,” presented “by the Atmosphere” (no. 299, p.
                    271). Atmosphere is invoked because it is “the Continent of Heat and
                    Light” as Use is “Of Love and Wisdom” (ibid.). Thus the
                    Atmosphere is the necessary element “by means of” which the Spiritual
                    Sun “produces the varieties of all Things in the created Universe”
                    (no. 300, p. 273). There are three Atmospheres in both the Spiritual and Natural
                    Worlds, which “in descending decrease,” that is, “become
                    continually more compressed and more inert” until “they are no longer
                    Atmospheres but Substances” (no. 302, p. 274). Swedenborg reiterates that
                    “the Substances and Matter, of which Earths consist . . . are, as it were,
                    the Ends and Terminations of the Atmospheres” (no. 305, p. 277). These
                    substances, however, still “have brought with them by Continuation from the
                    Substance of the spiritual Sun that which was there from the Divine” and as
                    a result continue to manifest “a perpetual Endeavour to produce Forms of
                    Uses” (no. 310, p. 280). “The 
<pb id="p12-84" n="84"/>
first
                    Production of those Earths, when they were still recent, and in their
                    Simplicity, was the Production of Seeds” (no. 312, p. 283). The Seeds, in
                    turn, become an “image of creation” moving from their “first
                    Principles to their Ultimates,” a movement characterized in Blake’s
                    annotation as “A Going forth &amp; returning” (p. 285), a perception
                    which underlies his whole work. “This World is too poor to produce one
                    Seed,” Blake wrote in the margins of Reynold’s <hi rend="i">Discourses on Art</hi> (E
646), and returning to the image in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, we see that the effect of the Atmosphere
is to catch
                    the Spirits of the Spiritual Sun and condense them into seeds. 
<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi><q> Cf. “The Little Black Boy”:<lb/>
 Look on the rising sun:
                                there God does live<lb/>
 And gives his light, and gives his heat
                                away.<lb/>
<lb/>
 (11. 9-10) </q>
Blake told Crabb Robinson that he
                            had seen “the Spiritual Sun” on Primrose Hill (G. E. Bentley,
                            Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> [Oxford: Clarendon, 1969], p.
                            541).
                    </note></p>
        <p>Having worked through this involved spiritualist account some may be surprised to
                    discover that Newton was of the same mind. Indeed it is evident that Swedenborg
                    adapts material he would surely have come across in his wide scientific reading.
                    In the “Second Paper on Light and Colours,” not fully printed until
                    1757 but known since its presentation in 1675,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n16" type="note">16</ref> Newton begins by supposing that the “aethereal medium”
                    is “compounded, partly of the main phlegmatic body of aether, partly of
                    other various aethereal spirits, much after the manner, that air is compounded
                    of the phlegmatic body of air intermixed with various vapours and exhalations:
                    for the electric and magnetic effluvia, and gravitating principle, seem to argue
                    such variety” (Cohen, p. 180). Blake knew these “spirits” as
                    “Devils. . . . Powers of the Air” and remarked, “the air was full
                    of them, &amp; seemd composed of them” (MHH 18). Newton continues: 
					<q>
                        Perhaps the whole frame of nature may be nothing but various contextures of
                        some certain aethereal spirits, or vapours, condensed as it were by
                        precipitation, much after the manner, that vapours are condensed into water,
                        or exhalations into grosser substances, though not so easily condensible;
                        and after condensation wrought into various forms; at first by the immediate
                        hand of the Creator; and ever since by the power of nature; which, by virtue
                        of the command, increase and multiply, became a complete imitator of the
                        copies set her by the protoplast. Thus perhaps may all things be originated
                        from aether.<lb/>
<lb/>
 (Cohen, p. 180) </q>
In one of the last
                    “Queries” added to the <hi rend="i">Opticks</hi> Newton limited
                    himself to suggesting that “The changing of Bodies into Light, and Light
                    into Bodies, is very conformable to the Course of Nature, which seems delighted
                    with Transmutations.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">17</ref>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> The relevant material is collected in
                            Cohen, <hi rend="i">Newton’s Papers and Letters</hi>, etc. The
                            letter to Oldenburg which emends the paper, and in so doing
                            recapitulates the idea of condensation, first appeared in Thomas
                            Birch’s <hi rend="i">The Works of Robert Boyle</hi> in 1744 (I,
                            74; Cohen, p. 254) and was quickly reprinted in other sources. The
                            complete paper was first published in Birch’s <hi rend="i">The
                                History of the Royal Society of London</hi> in 1757 (III, 247-305;
                            Cohen, pp. 177-235). But the image was well known before; at the
                            “Academy of Lagado” in <hi rend="i">Gulliver’s
                                Travels</hi> (1726), “some were condensing Air into a dry
                            tangible Substance, by extracting the Nitre, and letting the aqueous or
                            fluid Particles percolate” (Pt. III, ch. 5). Swedenborg’s
                                <hi rend="i">Divine Love and Divine Wisdom</hi> was first published
                            in 1763.
                        <p>Donald Ault seems to have been the first to mention the “Second
                            Paper” in connection with Blake (<hi rend="i">Visionary Physics:
                                Blake’s Response to Newton</hi> [Chicago &amp; London: Univ.
                            of Chicago Press, 1974], pp. 11, 85) though he does not realize its
                            connection to Swedenborg or to Night the Second. He focuses on the
                            negative “condensations” of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,
                            suggesting that the void which “shrinks and condenses”
                            entering objects is directed, “very possibly, against
                            Newton’s doctrine of solid bodies deriving from condensation of
                            ‘aether’” (p. 85).</p></note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Isaac Newton, <hi rend="i">Opticks: or A
                            Treatise of the Reflections, Refractions, Inflections and Colours of
                            Light</hi>; fore. Albert Einstein; intro. Edmund Whittaker; pref. I.
                        Bernard Cohen; table of contents, Duane H. D. Roller; based on the 4th ed.,
                        London, 1730 (New York: Dover, 1952), p. 374. Cf. Ault’s peculiar
                        remark: “Blake, by taking things spiritual and mental and causing the
                        Newtonian figures in his myth to condense and contract them into solids, is
                        in this way criticizing Newton’s doctrine that there could be no such
                        transformation” (p. 88).</note></p>
        <p>These two accounts may mark the distinction between “Science” and
                    “Sweet Science” which operates in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>
                    Newton withheld his idea from publication; “The fact is,” observes E.
                    A. Burtt, “Newton’s positivism was powerful enough to prevent his
                    carrying his speculations very far in this direction.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref> This for Blake is “Science,” the suspension
                    of belief and emphasis on doubt in the interests of the profitability and
                    utility of experimental results. Swedenborg, on the other hand, though he
                    “has not written one new truth” (MHH 22) is a practitioner of the
                    “Sweet Science” of belief and imaginative relation to the world. The
                    distinction, ultimately, has to do with the place of man in the scientific
                    endeavor; for Newton, “Man exists to know and applaud” (Burtt, p. 297)
                    the order of the God of Nature in His unchanging laws, whereas for Blake the
                    Imagination is to realize itself as the Being that instituted Nature and
                    continually bodies forth new creations. The use of the term “Science”
                    for both endeavors shows that the two will eventually be one. 
                    <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Edwin <corr type="emend">Arthur</corr> Burtt, 
<hi rend="i">The Metaphysical
                            Foundations of Modern Physical Science</hi>, 2nd ed. rev., Anchor Books
                        (1932; rpt. Garden City, N. Y.: Doubleday, 1954), p. 282.</note></p>
        <p>Both Newton and Swedenborg say that the aethereal condenses in the atmosphere, so
                    that the physical world is, literally, <hi rend="i">spiritual.</hi> But while
                    Newton imagines no purpose for the “transmutations,” Blake sees in
                    Swedenborg a vision of “a going forth &amp; returning,” the
                    circulating, spiraling, expanding movement of the imagination. At the close of
                    the atmospheric moment in Night the Second some of the Spirits are shown
                    condensed into seed to be sown, others condensed into roots, already harvested
                    and stored in “barns &amp; garners,” the “store house” of
                    thought (cf. 110[1st]. 12-13). The seeds may be new thoughts—spiritual
                    energy and enlightenment caught up in an image that will grow and bear—as
                    the roots may be accomplished thought, the organic base for further visions
                    which, Blake says, are always of “somewhat on earth.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref> “The Imaginative Image,” writes Blake,
                    “returns by the seed of contemplative Thought” (VLJ, E 545; cf. J
                    85.27-29). In <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> it is the passage through
                    atmosphere that materializes the image. <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Ann.
                        Lavater, E 590; the single instance of “bulbous” eliminates any
                        possibility for the frequently negative associations involved with
                        “roots.”</note></p>
        <p>Blake reintroduces Swedenborg’s three atmospheres in Night the Seventh
                    (a). Los builds Golgonooza in “the nether heavens” where “new
                    heavens &amp; a new Earth” have opened. They are “Threefold within
                    the brain within the heart within the loins” (87.10) and so represent,
                    “A Threefold Atmosphere Sublime continuous from Urthonas world”
                    (87.11) or the second of the threefold atmospheres of Swedenborg’s
                    Spiritual and Natural Worlds, arranged in the traditional hierarchy of elemental
                    (loins), celestial (heart), and intellectual (head).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> This second, natural Atmosphere has a “Limit
                    Twofold named Satan &amp; Adam” (87.12), or Opacity (cf. 56.19) and
                    “Translucence” (87.13, sometimes called “Contraction”).
                    These two limits were in a sense present in the two aspects of the Atmospheres:
                    vehicles of light and condensing net. The medium of these two limits is itself
                    the limit to perception through it. But this atmosphere also provides a
                    necessary secure space in which to sleep and grow: 
					<q> And we are put on earth a
                        little space,<lb/>
 That we may learn to bear the beams of love,<lb/>
<lb/>
                        “The Little Black Boy,” 13-14 </q>
“The Natural Earth &amp;
                    Atmosphere,” Blake wrote in his annotations to <hi rend="i">Divine Love and
                        Divine Wisdom</hi>, “is a Phantasy” (p. 285). The real atmosphere,
                    to use the metaphor the OED first dates at 1797-1803, is the mental one (s.v.
                    “atmosphere,” 4). Young agreed: <pb id="p12-85" n="85"/>
	<q> . . . fine spun Air?<lb/>
 Fine spun to sense; but gross and feculent<lb/>
 To
                        Souls celestial. . . .<lb/>
<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>,
                        6.140-42) </q>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> See for example the illustration to
                        Fludd’s <hi rend="i">Utriusque cosmi . . . historia</hi> reproduced
                        in S. K. Heninger, Jr., <hi rend="i">The Cosmographical Glass: Renaissance
                            Diagrams of the Universe</hi> (San Marino, Ca.: Huntington Library,
                        1977), p. 145.</note></p>
        <p>One of the Eternals at their Feast in Night the Ninth describes the netting of
                    Spirits from the Eternal point of view. When man is wearied, “Folding the
                    pure wings of his mind . . . Abstracted from the roots of Science 
[<hi rend="i">Nature</hi> del.]” (133.14-15), then the Eternals “cast him like
                    a Seed into the Earth” (133.16). According to <hi rend="i">The Book of
                        Ahania</hi>, the Spirit is cast “On the Human soul” as “The
                    Seed of eternal Science” (5.33-34). Toward the end of the Night the golden
                    looms and wingd shuttle appear for the second time in the poem: 
					<q> Then Enion
                        &amp; Ahania &amp; Vala &amp; the wife of Dark Urthona<lb/>
 Rose from the
                        feast in joy ascending to their Golden Looms<lb/>
 Where the wingd shuttle
                        Sang the spindle &amp; the distaff &amp; the Reel<lb/>
 Rang sweet the
                        praise of industry.<lb/>
<lb/>
 (137.11-14) </q>
There they fabricate bodies
                    for the spectres, the spirits that the Eternal Man casts into “the world of
                    shadows thro the air” (137.31; cf. 100[1st].2 ff.). The woven atmosphere is
                    one medium of materialization, one instance of the “wide woof” which
                    flows from the looms down into the Chasms “where the Nations are gatherd
                    together” (137.17). These references converge at the end of the poem where
                    “The Sun has left his blackness” (138.20) and 
					<q> The sun arises from
                        his dewy bed &amp; the fresh airs<lb/>
 Play in his smiling beams giving the
                        seeds of life to grow<lb/>
 And the fresh Earth beams forth ten thousand
                        thousand springs of life<lb/>
<lb/>
 (139.1-3) </q>
The sun perceptible is now
                    the spiritual sun, and the earth itself is luminous with the fresh airs of
                    “sweet Science” sweeping away the stale atmosphere of binding
                    “dark Religions” (139.10).</p>
        <pb id="p12-86" n="86"/>
        <figure n="FourZoas27Detail.12.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="458">
          <head><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 27 (detail).</head>
          <figDesc>London, British Museum.</figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
