<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>12.2.johnson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The Spectrous Embrace in The Four Zoas, VIIa</title>
        <author n="Johnson">Mary Lynn Johnson</author>
        <author n="Wilkie">Brian Wilkie</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1978</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1978</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">12.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
              <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Special Design and Pasteup for this issue</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Everett Frost</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Terrence Hoagwood</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John Kilgore</name>
              <name>Mark Lefebvre</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Cettina Magno</name>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <name>Jeffry Spencer</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1978"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_12">
    <body>
      <pb id="p12-100" n="100"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-12-2-0009">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">THE SPECTROUS EMBRACE IN <hi rend="i">THE FOUR ZOAS</hi>,
                            VIIa</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">MARY LYNN</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">JOHNSON</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
          <hi rend="b">AND</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">BRIAN</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">WILKIE</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>Of all the abrupt shifts in the plot of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, perhaps
                    the most startling is the sudden embrace of Los and the Spectre of Urthona in
                    Night VIIA, the climactic reversal of the pattern of further and further
                    fragmentation in the poem, the first unequivocal gesture toward reconciliation
                    that results finally in the reunification of Albion in Night IX. Nothing in the
                    immediate situation leads up to this right-angled turn in the action.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">1</ref> On the contrary, Blake erased “End of
                    the Seventh Night” in order to write in the account of this embrace, thus
                    changing the natural stopping point for the Night into a surprising turning
                    point for the entire poem. The reconciliation scene follows immediately upon the
                    Spectre’s re-enactment with Enitharmon of the fall of Adam and Eve,
                    during which they copulate and engender the Shadowy Female, whose appearance
                    releases “male forms without female counterparts or Emanations / Cruel and
                    ravening with Enmity &amp; Hatred &amp; War / In dreams of Ulro dark delusive
                    drawn by the lovely shadow” (VIIA.329-31; 85:19-21, E353).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">2</ref> The only grammatical, temporal, and logical transition
                    between the moment of the Shadowy Female’s birth and the moment of
                    Los’s embrace of his Spectre is “But then” (VIIA.336; 85:26,
                    E353). This juxtaposition of scenes of fall and redemption, spectrous enmity and
                    genuine fraternal love, is related to the Blakean paradox that revelation is
                    concurrent with—and contingent upon—the consolidation of error. It
                    is not difficult to grasp the thematic purpose of the juxtaposition, then, but
                    as a quasi-realistic dramatic scene among members of a love-triangle who
                    symbolize aspects of the imaginative faculty, it raises numerous problems of
                    interpretation. Should this apparently arbitrary gesture of loving forgiveness
                    be considered a structural weakness of the poem? Does it indicate a lapse in the
                    profoundly accurate insight into human psychology that Blake’s work
                    usually exhibits? Does the suddenness of reversal reflect a religious or
                    psychological conversion of the man Blake, as John Middleton Murry surmised?<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">3</ref> Or, perhaps, may Blake be saying that he
                    does not know how such apparently unconditioned recoveries happen but that they
                    do and must happen, through the agency of imagination, a going out of ourselves
                    into others? <note id="n39"><hi rend="s">1</hi> M. H. Abrams, <hi rend="i">Natural
Supernaturalism: Tradition and Revolution in Romantic
                            Literature</hi> (New York: Norton, 1971), pp. 36, 300, discusses this
                        sort of reversal as one of the features of biblical design adopted by the
                        Romantics.</note>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">2</hi> All quotations from Blake are based on David
                        V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>
                        (1965; Garden City, N. Y.: Doubleday, 4th printing, rev., 1970), abbreviated
                        as E, with parallel references to <hi rend="i">The Complete Writings of
                            William Blake</hi> (1966; London &amp; New York: Oxford University
                        Press, rpt. with corr., 1974), abbreviated as K. To simplify references to
                            <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, we give citations in the following
                        order: the Night number in roman numerals, followed by the line number in
                        Keynes, followed by the MS. page number as cited in Erdman, followed by the
                        line numbers of the MS. page and finally the page number of the Erdman
                        edition. Thus the present citation refers to the passage from Night VIIA
                        running in Keynes from line 329 to 331, running in Erdman from line 19 to 21
                        on MS. page 85, and printed on page 353 of Erdman’s edition.
                        Citations from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, abbreviated <hi rend="i">J</hi>,
                        provide plate and line numbers, followed by page references to Erdman and
                        Keynes.</note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Murry’s essay, “Los and the
                            Spectre,” chapter XI of <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (1933; rpt.
                            New York: McGraw-Hill, 1964), pp. 153-71, is one of the few extended
                            discussions of the spectrous embrace, which Murry sees as a pivotal
                            moment both in the poem and in the development of Blake’s thought
                            and work; it expresses Blake’s own discovery that the final
                            resistance to vision lies within the artist himself, “a necessary
                            element of [his] being,” and by recognizing and receiving his
                            spectrous personality, “Los-Blake attains a new understanding, a
                            new synthesis” (pp. 164-65). In <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi>
                            (1947; rpt. Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1969), Northrop Frye cites
                            Murry’s chapter as the basis for his own observation that the
                            “conception of the Spectre of Urthona seems to have broken on Blake
                            quite suddenly when he was proceeding to a simpler climax, and
                            occasioned the rewriting of Night VII, if not of the next two Nights as
                            well” (p. 298). As for the significance of the Spectre himself, S.
                            Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Philosophy and
                                Symbols</hi> (1924; rpt. Gloucester, Mass.: Peter Smith, 1958),
                            identifies Urthona as Spirit, Los as Poet, Enitharmon as Inspiration,
                            the Spectre of Urthona as Spiritual Logic, the Spectre of Los as Poetic
                            Logic, and the Shadow of Enitharmon as Suppressed Imagination (p. 379).
                            Frye has identified the Spectre with “clock time,” “the
                            will,” and—in a poet—“what is usually called the
                            ‘man’ in him” (p. 292); he is “the inventive
                            faculty,” a sorcerer’s apprentice as capable of inventing
                            instruments of destruction as works of art, and is expressed in society
                            as the “sheer automatic compulsion to produce” (pp.
                            294-95).
                        <p>The significance of the Spectre is illuminated by Bloom’s use of
                            apt analogies from Shelley: the Spectre is “the ruin or desolation
                            that shadows love” near the end of the first act of <hi rend="i">Prometheus
Unbound</hi> and the doubting, negating First Spirit in
                            “The Two Spirits: An Allegory” (<hi rend="i">Blake’s
                                Apocalypse</hi>, Ithaca: Cornell Univ. Press, rev. ed., 1970, p.
                            253). In a lecture on the Spectre as Doppelgänger at an MLA
                            seminar in 1975, E. J. Rose was primarily concerned with the
                            Spectre’s role in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> C. William Spinks
                            has briefly noted that the Spectre embodies a sense of absurdity that
                            must be incorporated into the artist’s work if it is to be
                            redemptive (“Blake’s Spectre,” in <hi rend="i">Studies
                                in Relevance: Romantic and Victorian Writers in 1972</hi>, ed.
                            Thomas Meade Harwell, Salzburg: Institüt für Englische
                            Sprache und Literatur, 1973, pp. 30-34).</p></note></p>
        <p>The dramatic reversal takes place on two planes of action, signifying the
                    importance of imagination both in artistic creation and in intimate personal
                    relationships. Insofar as Los, the Spectre, and Enitharmon are fragmented
                    aspects of the imaginative faculty, representing the artist, his self-doubt, and
                    his inspiration, the sudden shift from hostility to cooperation means that the
                    mature artistic imagination becomes capable of acknowledging inner doubt and
                    sublimating it in art. Insofar as Los and Enitharmon are a husband and wife
                    whose deteriorating relationship has been further strained by the competition
                    for Enitharmon between Los and his false personality, the Spectre, the sudden
                    shift from sexual rivalry to fraternal cooperation and marital concord must mean
                    that imaginative love is capable of overcoming jealousy and self-division. On
                    both these planes of action the contact of Los and Enitharmon with the Spectre
                    is all-important.</p>
        <p>Until the moment of the fraternal embrace, the primary bond among the three
                    estranged fragments of the primal Urthona is a sexual attraction, rivalry, and
                    jealousy so intense that Enitharmon is very nearly split into two characters.
                    The problematical new figure called the Shadow of Enitharmon is not a separate
                    person but rather a manifestation of that element in the female personality
                    which is attracted to selfishness and deadness in the male and repelled by vital
                    desire. The Shadow corresponds to one side of the Spectre’s character,
                    but she is not a complete counterpart to him. During her entire relationship
                    with the Spectre, at the roots of the Tree of Mystery, Enitharmon remains
                    physically present to 
<pb id="p12-101" n="101"/>
Los, outstretched upon his
                    knees, in his upper region above the branches of the Tree. While she is
                    indulging her shadowy moods or fantasies, she appears to Los as “the image
                    of death upon his witherd valleys” (VIIA.172; 81:13, E349). He complains
                    that she is cold and wintry when he approaches her but summery and delectable
                    when he is absent. Whenever Enitharmon is dead to Los, her Shadow is alive to
                    the Spectre. In her relationship with Los, she has given birth to Orc, a fully
                    defined character, the personification of energy. In her relationship with the
                    Spectre “in sweet delusion” (VIIA.229; 82:35, E351) she becomes the
                    mother of the Shadowy Female, a vague manifestation of Vala who exists briefly
                    during one stage of the consolidation of error, before reappearing in definite
                    form in Night VIII as the new characters Rahab and Tirzah. The specific,
                    localized affinity between the Shadow and the Spectre is seen in their parallel
                    accounts of humanity’s fall from Eternity, in which both reveal an acute
                    sense of sexual jealousy and possessiveness. In short, the Shadow represents the
                    fickle, self-deluded side of Enitharmon; by the device of separating Enitharmon
                    from her Shadow Blake is able to dramatize a stage in her education without
                    making it necessary for Enitharmon, in her primary personality, to renounce the
                    wisdom she has gained through her suffering in Night V. Traces of the old
                    Enitharmon, power-mad and sadistic, appear only in deleted lines: “She
                    Secret joyd to see She fed herself on his Despair She said I am avengd for all
                    my sufferings of old” (VIIA.177-78; E755). Since she has still not learned
                    to love her husband either as creative artist or as craftsman, she is brought
                    down through her Shadow to mate with the “lower” side of Los in
                    preparation for accepting him at his best.</p>
        <p>Enitharmon’s scorn of Los and her pleasureless coupling with the Spectre
                    are not especially remarkable among the numerous experiences of fallen sexuality
                    in the poem. The turning point for Enitharmon comes as she gives birth to the
                    Shadowy Female. In the “Worlds above” Los weeps in anguish because he
                    cannot perceive the cause of her travail (VIIA.318-20; 85:8-10, E353), but in
                    the “deeps beneath” her “shadow pregnant” brings forth the
                    Shadowy Female, whereupon the gates of Enitharmon’s heart burst from
                    their hinges (VIIA.316-24; 85:6-14, E353). It seems that imaginative
                    productivity is now possible only at this debased level, but that as a result of
                    this act of procreation, in which the Shadow and Spectre externalize their worst
                    selves in the form of the Shadowy Female, both are purified. Blake’s
                    language here is effectively ambiguous: Enitharmon writhes “till her shadow
                    was deliverd then she ran / Raving about the upper Elements in maddning
                    fury” (VIIA.321-22; 85:11-12, E353). This means both that the true
                    Enitharmon writhes until the shadowy Enitharmon gives birth and that in giving
                    birth Enitharmon is delivered of her shadowy personality. The Shadow of
                    Enitharmon is heard of no more, and the true Enitharmon, now permanently
                    heart-broken (but also made open-hearted and tender-hearted), becomes the
                    vehicle for the Spectre’s passage back to Los: “Every sigh &amp;
                    groan / Of Enitharmon bore Urthonas Spectre on its wings” (VIIA.336-37;
                    85:26-27, E353). This statement appears immediately after “But then the
                    Spectre entered Los’s bosom” and, while taking away none of the
                    element of surprise, partly explains how the miraculous embrace was made
                    possible.</p>
        <p>Drawing on the accounts of the fall which she and the Spectre had exchanged after
                    partaking of the fruit of the Tree, “Enitharmon told the tale / Of
                    Urthona” to Los, whereupon Los embraces the Spectre and gives up “his
                    Domineering lust” (VIIA.338-41; 85:28-31, E353). Los, the creator of the
                    Chain of Jealousy in Night V, is impelled to accept his rival for the sake of
                    reunifying the divided fragments of Urthona: “Come then into my Bosom
                    &amp; in thy shadowy arms bring with thee / My lovely Enitharmon. I will quell
                    my fury &amp; teach / Peace to the Soul of dark revenge &amp; repentance to
                    Cruelty” (VIIA.367-69; 86:10-12, E354). Correspondingly, “Urthonas
                    spectre in part mingling with him comforted him / Being a medium between him
                    &amp; Enitharmon” (VIIA.397-98; 87:26-27, E355). The fact that the
                    reconciliation of Los and his Spectre takes place against a background of sexual
                    rivalry emphasizes the importance of the imagination in human relationships as
                    well as the arts. The overcoming of jealousy is an act of imagination as surely
                    as the writing of a poem. Enitharmon’s withdrawal from this scene of
                    “Extacy &amp; Love” to hide “beneath Urizens tree”
                    indicates, however, that the importance of imagination in overcoming guilt and
                    shame has not yet been fully realized. Full union of Los and Enitharmon does not
                    occur within fallen history; it is “not to be Effected without Cares &amp;
                    Sorrows &amp; Troubles / Of six thousand Years of self denial and of bitter
                    Contrition” (VIIA.399-400; 87:28-29, E355). Though Los is now able to see
                    the Lamb of God within Enitharmon’s broken heart, Enitharmon herself
                    shrinks before the punishment she is sure the Lamb will inflict.</p>
        <p>In releasing the imagination to function in life as well as art, the Spectre, who
                    among other things personifies the artist’s self-censorship, plays a
                    crucial role, and Blake’s characterization of this figure is extremely
                    subtle. His prominence in Night VIIA seems to indicate that the selfish
                    impediment to creativity has come to realize that it cannot be overcome by mere
                    repression, enslavement to Los, but must be acknowledged and dealt with
                    honestly, as the Spectre insists to Los in the very act of embracing him
                    (VIIA.336-51; 85:26-39, E353). Despite his repellent attributes, he reveals even
                    as he seduces Enitharmon a spiritual and psychological perceptiveness not yet
                    possible for her. Although his boast to her that he is the creator and superior
                    of Los is unfounded, his nostalgia for the unity and happiness of Eternity is
                    genuine, and he can see the possibility and necessity for reunion with their
                    Emanations of Tharmas, Luvah, and himself as Urthona. He also deplores his own
                    spectrous condition, knowing that spectres as such are insane, brutish, and
                    deformed; and he interprets his longing for Enitharmon as evidence that he is a
                    spectre of the living rather than of the dead (VIIA.269-310; 84:3-40, E352). As
                    a spectre himself, he perceives the threat to productive activity presented by
                    imageless, disembodied thoughts of futility and negativity, the “spectres
                    of the dead.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">4</ref> The
spectrous insight
                    which finally wins Enitharmon over is that “till these terrors [the
                    spectres of the dead] planted round the Gates of 
<pb id="p12-102" n="102"/>
                    Eternal life / Are driven away &amp; annihilated we never can repass the
                    Gates” (VIIA.302-03; 84:41-42, E353). It takes the spectrous side of the
                    imaginative mind to understand that the true Covering Cherub is made up of
                    one’s own shapeless, negative fears and fantasies. Regeneration, the
                    Spectre understands, is possible for him because in Los he has a living
                    counterpart which the spectres of the dead lack altogether, ravening after
                    emptiness and nothingness. After the Spectre is accepted by Los, his sense of
                    responsibility for the creation of the spectres of the dead, who were released
                    by his begetting of the Shadowy Female, is the basis of his urging Los to give
                    form and beauty to these shapeless abstractions (VIIA.401-10; 87:30-39, E355).
                    The suggestion inaugurates a great cultural renaissance, a new kind of
                    redemptive artistic activity. Even his terror at Vala’s new appearance
                    (VIIA.332; 85:22, E353) is evidence of his special insight, an insight which can
                    deepen art rather than block it, a recognition of evil and deadness that need
                    not break an artist’s spirit but can drive him to develop a more complex
                    form of art.</p>
        <p>One of the most suggestive of the Spectre’s ideas is his view of the Tree
                    of Mystery as something “given us for a Shelter from the tempests of Void
                    &amp; Solid / Till once again the morn of ages shall renew upon us”
                    (VIIA.268-69; 84:2-3, E352). This statement seems a radical distortion of the
                    truth, but it also comes very close to the Christian interpretation of the
                    “Law,” the old dispensation, as a divinely-appointed stopgap, and
                    indeed in Night VIII the Lamb of God, assuming Luvah’s robes of blood,
                    will transfigure the image of the crucifixion on the Tree. Here in Night VIIA
                    the very ascendancy of the Tree of Mystery over both passion and imagination,
                    the very urgency and clarity of the sense of sin, however falsely defined,
                    builds up a pressure for imminent liberation. Despair over evil and guilt can be
                    psychologically beneficial if it awakens an acute and agonizing need for an
                    utterly new state of existence. The fact that, after the Spectre puts the
                    Shadowy Female in charge of Orc in the lower world, the topmost branch of the
                    Tree sprouts to form roots of the same Tree in the upper, conscious, world of
                    Los (VIIA.332-35; 85:22-25, E353) makes the influence of evil and Mystery
                    recognizable now on all levels of the human imagination. When the serpent-wound
                    Tree, with its outrageously false Urizenic identification of energy and evil,
                    overshadows Los, and he joins Enitharmon in eating its fruit and falls also into
                    the moral system (VIIA.395; 87:24, E355), he experiences a psychic suffocation
                    and a wasteful sense of guilt so terrible that they can only be remedied by a
                    clean break, a free existential act like that of Shelley’s Prometheus. On
                    the dramatic level this new direction is possible because Los and Enitharmon
                    have lived and suffered enough to have become different persons; in grief and
                    sorrow they have found a depth of humanity capable of reconciliation and
                    forgiveness. From no other fallen faculty can this act arise; it is truly an
                    imaginative leap. Yet this act is precipitated by the eating of the fruit,
                    through “self accusation” and “Self conviction”
                    (VIIA.385-93; 87:14-22, E354), through the assumption of an unbearable burden of
                    guilt and the definitive imposition of a clearly defined but grossly
                    misunderstood “morality,” through a despair which would lead to
                    “death Eternal” but for the Spectre’s role as comforter and
                    mediator between Los and Enitharmon (VIIA.396-98; 87:25-27, E355).</p>
        <p>In retrospect, one can see that events and characterizations introduced earlier
                    in the poem, especially in Nights IV and V and earlier in Night VIIA, without
                    clear significance for human recovery when they first appeared, have contributed
                    to the moment of reconciliation. In forming a body for Urizen, for example, Los
                    had begun to feel sympathetic pains for his enemy (IV.284-95; 55:20-31, E331), a
                    sympathy that has extended even to his silent sharing of Urizen’s envy
                    (VIIA.19,27; 77:19, 27, E346). Los and Enitharmon, repenting the binding of Orc
                    in Night V, had drawn closer in their grief and become more aware of their
                    responsibilities, less selfish. The Spectre, though reluctant to cooperate in
                    Los’s labors, had shown concern for the parental distress of the couple:
                    after Los and Enitharmon fainted over Orc, the Spectre “found herbs of the
                    pit / Rubbing their temples he reviv’d them” (V.173-74; 63: 7-8,
                    E336).</p>
        <p>Undeniably, though, Blake leaves an area of disjunction between despair and
                    recovery, something not spelled out for us. But far from being a flaw in <hi rend="i">The
Four Zoas</hi>, this gap reflects Blake’s honesty and
                    acumen. If the conversion were totally explainable, the training of
                    psychiatrists could be much abbreviated and all mental illness, perhaps also all
                    social problems related to it, could be cured in one and the same way.
                    Blake’s wisdom in leaving this hiatus of explanation is confirmed in
                    other great works which explore the spiritual dark night and recovery from it.
                    The reversal in <hi rend="i">Prometheus Unbound</hi> arises from the
                    hero’s free, imaginative act of loving forgiveness, but the <hi rend="i">agency</hi> of
regeneration is embodied in Demogorgon, a personified
                    question mark, the “somehow” in statements like “Somehow we
                    survived.” The same arbitrariness of recovery occurs with Wordsworth in <hi rend="i">The
Prelude</hi> and with the Red Cross Knight in Book I of <hi rend="i">The Faerie Queene</hi>, where the
protagonists are reduced to
                    something near despair and then rescued through a form of grace, something they
                    cannot fully understand or explain. Blake takes us further than either
                    Wordsworth or Spenser into the psychology of recovery, regeneration, renewal,
                    but like them he presents the <hi rend="i">experience</hi> of grace, not a
                    formula for obtaining it. If a formula were possible, the concept of grace would
                    not be necessary in theology nor the metaphor of the breakthrough in psychology
                    (or in the physical sciences, for that matter). It happens or it does not
                    happen; if it happens at all, it happens in the midst of despair, both because
                    of and in spite of an intolerable sense of sin and need. Even in such a
                    realistic work as “The Death of Ivan Ilyich,” the conversion, when it
                    finally comes, is not explained with the fullness that is offered in the
                    presentation of the other incidents in the story. In <hi rend="i">The Four
                        Zoas</hi> Blake does not anatomize the moment of relief and reconciliation
                    itself, as he does through the splintered personalities and actions of 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>; instead, he concentrates on the renewal of life as it
                    flows out from that moment.</p>
        <p>The surge of new life takes the form of creative activity. The benefits to both
                    human nature and art are reciprocal. Man’s spiritual sickness is treated
                        <pb id="p12-103" n="103"/>
by therapeutic art. At the same time this
                    sickness provides new subjects for a deeper, more troubled and more complex
                    artistic vision; the pressure of these new and disturbing
                    subjects—shadows from the inner life rather than reflections of the outer
                    world—bring new art forms into being. All this is presented in the new
                    relationship among Los, the Spectre, and Enitharmon. In the unwilling drudgery
                    of their collaboration in Night IV, they had rebuilt the fallen mental and
                    physical world; art in Night IV is the mirror held up to nature—nature as
                    seen by the fallen imagination and organized according to human conceptions of
                    time and space. But in Night VII the collaboration of the Spectre and Los is
                    willing and mutual, and Enitharmon—though fearful—is cooperative.
                    Instead of working as artisan and apprentice to build a body for Urizen as in
                    Night IV, Los and his Spectre join to build in the “nether heavens” a
                    new and separate world for art, the city of Golgonooza, placed within the
                    merciful limits of Satan and Adam, opacity and contraction, discovered in Night
                    IV (VIIA. 379-83; 87:8-12, E354). <note id="n42"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Both Bloom
                        and Damon seem to think of the spectres of the dead as human beings without
                        art, or human souls without bodies (see Bloom, <hi rend="i">Blake’s
                            Apocalypse</hi>, p. 255, and Damon, <hi rend="i">A Blake
                        Dictionary</hi>, Providence: Brown Univ. Press, 1965, pp. 382-83), but the
                        context suggests that they are formless, destructive ideas and fantasies
                        which Los, with the help of the Spectre and Enitharmon, redeems by embodying
                        them in art.</note></p>
        <p>In the blended consciousness of Los and his Spectre is “a World within /
                    Opening its gates &amp; in it all the real substances / Of which these in the
                    outward World are shadows which pass away” (VIIA. 364-66; 86:7-9, E354).
                    Although the Spectre’s claim on Los, “I am thy real Self,” is
                    untrue as a bald, isolated statement, it is effective as a means of forcing Los
                    to act on his moment of self-recognition. After his impulsive embrace of the
                    Spectre “first as a brother / Then as another Self; astonishd humanizing
                    &amp; in tears,” Los is forced to listen to the insistent voice of his
                    repressed negative and sinister personality: 
					<q> I am thy real Self<lb/>
 Tho
                        thus divided from thee &amp; the Slave of Every passion<lb/>
 Of thy fierce
                        Soul Unbar the Gates of Memory look upon me<lb/>
 Not as another but as thy
                        real Self I am thy Spectre<lb/>
 Tho horrible &amp; Ghastly to thine Eyes
                        tho buried beneath<lb/>
 The ruins of the Universe.<lb/>
<lb/>
 (VIIA. 339-52;
                        85:29-40, E353) </q>
When a new world opens within and Los again embraces
                    the Spectre as well as Enitharmon, the Spectre also “Wondering beheld the
                    Center opend by Divine Mercy inspired / He in his turn Gave Tasks to Los”
                    (VIIA. 374-75; 87:3-4, E354); his destructive impulses are, however, rendered
                    harmless by Los’s concentration on the work at hand. The Spectre’s
                    claim that he is Los’s self is a demand that Los acknowledge his errors;
                    this claim on Los is entirely different from Urizen’s reductive blasphemy
                    in Night I, the insistence that there is nothing <hi rend="i">else</hi> in man:
                    “The Spectre is the Man the rest is only delusion &amp; fancy” (I.
                    341; 12:29, E303). Los directs the continued building of Golgonooza, where
                    “beneath / Was opend new heavens &amp; a new Earth beneath &amp;
                    within” (VIIA. 379-80; 87:8-9, E354), but it is the Spectre who proposes
                    the new direction for art, the creation of forms for man’s shadowy hopes,
                    fears, negative thoughts, desires, failures of nerve, frustrations: “Let us
                    Create them Counterparts / For without a Created body the Spectre is Eternal
                    Death” (VIIA. 409-10; 87:38-39, E355).</p>
        <p>The Spectre has found his place within the mature artistic consciousness as a
                    dark vision of emptiness and longing, an intimate knowledge of passion, guilt,
                    and sin, the negative and doubting shadow of idealism which annihilates the
                    ideal if it is disowned and denied but strengthens it if honestly admitted. From
                    Los’s acceptance of his Spectre comes the power of Romantic and modern
                    art which admits its own vulnerability and thus speaks to man’s doubts as
                    well as his faith. Acceptance of what the Spectre represents allows Wordsworth
                    apparently to undercut his most affirmative statements with such formulations as
                    “If this be but a vain belief.” From the same source flows the power
                    of Byron’s self-deflations in <hi rend="i">Don Juan</hi>, along with his
                    self-assured mockery both of his own creation and of his reader’s
                    illusions. This is also the principle of Friederich Schlegel’s
                    “divine buffoonery” or Romantic Irony: acceptance in art of that which
                    destroys art, acceptance by the self of that which destroys the self. Just as
                    the artist’s admission of his difficulties and his incorporation of
                    negative possibilities into his work may actually serve to enrich and enliven
                    his efforts, so an acceptance of doubt can strengthen any act of imaginative
                    faith. Thus in the last two stanzas of the Intimations Ode, Wordsworth can
                    affirm the thoughts too deep for tears because he no longer shuts out the dark
                    truths avoided in strophes iii and iv.</p>
        <p>Since the Spectre’s vision is blended with Los’s own and the
                    Spectre no longer serves merely as an apprentice-slave, Los is now free to share
                    his creative work with his spouse and to turn to her for inspiration. Their
                    complementary activity in art gives rise to a new intimacy in their male-female
                    relationship. The Enitharmon who calls Los “wonder of Eternity,” her
                    “defence &amp; guide,” and says, “Thy works are all my joy.
                    &amp; in thy fires my soul delights” (VIIA. 447-48; 90:16-17, E356), has
                    become a different person from the tease who evaded her husband’s sexual
                    advances or even the sullen adulteress who tearfully and bitterly accepted the
                    shadowy embrace of the Spectre. In their new partnership they work like Blake
                    and his wife as draughtsman and colorist to create celestial murals (VIIA.
                    467-71; 90:35-39, E356). Enitharmon sighs forth vanishing forms from her bosom,
                    from which Los fabricates sublime and permanent forms “Such as the piteous
                    spectres may assimilate themselves into.” In response to her plea for
                    “sweet moderated fury,” Los, “his hands divine inspired began /
                    To modulate his fires.” No longer the dogged blacksmith imposing his will
                    on his spectre, his emanation, his material, his technique, and his form, he
                    becomes the genius whom the very elements gladly obey. His flames are
                    “delighted” and the weeping spectres willingly “Assimilating to
                    those forms” become young and lovely (VIIA. 439-74; 90:8-42, E356).</p>
        <p>Troubled by the sense of sin, Los, the Spectre, and Enitharmon have felt the need
                    for redemption and have planned to use their artistic creations as sacrificial
                    offerings, ransoms for their sins. But the translucent center opened in
                    Enitharmon’s broken heart affords Los a brief glimpse of the possibility
                    of mental sacrifice, self-annihilation, mutual 
<pb id="p12-104" n="104"/>
                    forgiveness of each vice, the spirit of Jesus: 
					<q> Turn inwardly thine Eyes
                        &amp; there behold the Lamb of God<lb/>
 Clothed in Luvahs robes of blood
                        descending to redeem<lb/>
 O Spectre of Urthona take comfort O Enitharmon
                        Couldst thou but cease from terror &amp; trembling &amp; affright<lb/>
                        When I appear before thee in forgiveness of ancient injuries<lb/>
 Why
                        shouldst thou remember &amp; be afraid. I surely have died in pain<lb/>
                        Often enough to convince thy jealousy &amp; fear &amp; terror<lb/>
 Come
                        hither be patient let us converse together because<lb/>
 I also tremble at
                        myself &amp; at all my former life.<lb/>
<lb/>
 (VIIA. 415-23; 87:44-52,
                        E355) </q>
Although Enitharmon resists this vision and persists in seeing
                    Jesus as punisher, Los has discovered the spirit of self-sacrifice and mutual
                    forgiveness that opens the Gates of Paradise. In his appearance before
                    Enitharmon “in forgiveness of ancient injuries” he is an embodiment of
                    Jesus, and in having “died in pain / Often enough to convince thy jealousy
                    &amp; fear &amp; terror” he has enacted what is meaningful in
                    Jesus’ death, the loving gesture of self-annihilation. If this husband
                    and wife could forgive each other, they wouldn’t need a Redeemer, nor
                    would they need to sacrifice their “children,” their mutual creations,
                    to an imagined Accuser. No more is said in Night VIIA about Los’s vision
                    of Jesus, but when the moment for sacrifice comes 
					<q> Los loved them &amp;
                        refusd to Sacrifice their infant limbs<lb/>
 And Enitharmons smiles &amp;
                        tears prevaild over self protection<lb/>
 They rather chose to meet Eternal
                        death than to destroy<lb/>
 The offspring of their Care &amp; Pity Urthonas
                        spectre was comforted<lb/>
<lb/>
 (VIIA. 482-85; 90:50-53, E357) </q>
The
                    imaginative act of creating form, of embodying these ghostly negative ideas, has
                    taught Los and Enitharmon how to sacrifice themselves, not their
                    “offspring.” No longer are they the selfish parents who sacrificed Orc
                    to their own jealousies in Night V. Through their artistic endeavors they have
                    given living form to the deadly aggressions that fuel the Urizenic wars; they
                    are now able to see their enemies, Urizen and his eldest son Thiriel, as their
                    own children, Rintrah and Palamabron (VIIA. 476-94; 90:44-62, E356-57). The
                    possibility of a reconciliation with Orc is also suggested: “Orc was
                    comforted in the deeps his soul revivd in them / As the Eldest brother is the
                    fathers image So Orc became / As Los a father to his brethren.” Tharmas,
                    organizing instinct now fallen into shapelessness, is heartened by the new forms
                    being created, for he hopes to find among them his lost Enion (VIIA. 478-87;
                    90:46-55, E356-57), the hope that had proved vain in the earlier craftsmanlike
                    work of Los in Night IV (IV. 32-33; 48:9-10, E325). Even Urizen finds
                    himself—or a portion of himself—in the loving and shaping hands of
                    a Los who now loves him, and who is surprised at his own ability to love (VIIA.
                    496-99; 90:64-67, E357).</p>
        <p>Although Los’s conflict with his Spectre is a major theme of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, the
spectrous embrace is not a part of its resolution.
                    Perhaps Blake thought tightness of plot and clarity of motivation were more
                    important than the theme of Los’s acknowledgement and acceptance of his
                    negative double. In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> there is no disjunction between
                    juxtaposed scenes of error and illumination, no sudden reversal. Instead, Los
                    first attempts in vain to resist the forces that separate him from his Spectre
                    and Emanation: 
					<q> Los rag’d and stamp’d the earth in his might
                        &amp; terrible wrath!<lb/>
 He stood and stampd the earth! then he threw
                        down his hammer in rage &amp;<lb/>
 In fury: then he sat down and wept,
                        terrified! Then arose<lb/>
 And chaunted his song, labouring with the tongs
                        and hammer:<lb/>
 But still the Spectre divided, and still his pain
                        increas’d!<lb/>
<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">J</hi>6:8-12, E147, K625) </q>
                    When the separated Spectre attempts to block Los’s work, the artist
                    combats his influence first by kindness and then by self-assertion. In his first
                    speech to the Spectre, he sounds as though he has already learned the lesson of
                        <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night VIIA:
<q> I know that Albion hath
                        divided me, and that thou O my Spectre,<lb/>
 Hast just cause to be
                        irritated: but look stedfastly upon me:<lb/>
 Comfort thyself in my strength
                        the time will arrive,<lb/>
 When all Albions injuries shall cease, and when
                        we shall<lb/>
 Embrace him tenfold bright, rising from his tomb in
                        immortality.<lb/>
<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">J</hi>7:52-56, E149, K626) </q>
It is
                    Los’s resolution, self-confidence, and unselfish concern with
                    Albion’s regeneration that give him power over his Spectre in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, a point just touched upon in Night VIIA, when the
                    Spectre’s desire to destroy Los’s body is defeated by Los’s
                    concentration on the building of Golgonooza. Los’s stern words to his
                    Spectre, out of context, might even be mistaken for one of Urizen’s
                    threatening speeches against Albion: 
					<q> unless<lb/>
 Thou abstain ravening I
                        will create an eternal Hell for thee.<lb/>
 Take thou this Hammer &amp; in
                        patience heave the thundering Bellows<lb/>
 Take thou these Tongs: strike
                        thou alternate with me: labour obedient[.]<lb/>
<pb id="p12-105" n="105"/> . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
                        .<lb/>
<lb/>
 Obey my voice &amp; never deviate from my will And I will be
                        merciful to thee:<lb/>
<lb/>
 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
                        .<lb/>
<lb/>
 If thou refuse, thy present torments will seem southern
                        breezes<lb/>
 To what thou shalt endure if thou obey not my great
                        will.<lb/>
<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">J</hi>8:37-40, E150, K627; <hi rend="i">J</hi>10:29-30, 35-36, E152, K629) </q></p>
        <p>This change in Los’s tone toward his Spectre in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> may indicate,
however, not that Blake had changed his mind
                    about the importance of the embrace in Night VIIA but that in the illuminated
                    book he was concerned primarily with the establishment of Los’s authority
                    and control, the attitude toward one’s Spectre that one must assume as a
                    day-to-day working artist. Los’s gesture of wiping the dark tears of his
                    Spectre in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 10:60-61 suggests that Los is still aware
                    of the Spectre as a brother, if not as another self. The final resolution of the
                    conflict occurs in Chapter IV, when Los, after allowing his Spectre freedom to
                    produce his anticreation, smites the Spectre upon his anvil “&amp; every
                    Ratio of his Reason / He alterd time after time, with dire pain &amp; many
                    tears / Till he had completely divided him into a separate space” 
(<hi rend="i">J</hi>91:50-52, E249, K739). Yet in the final plate of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> the Spectre is
shown to be present as in his best moments in
                        <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, cooperating with Los and Enitharmon,
                    carrying out his proper duties as Los’s assistant, working with the
                    material of the fallen universe. Though the text of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                    never presents a reconciliation scene, this concluding design suggests that
                    Blake continued to accord the Spectre his subordinate but significant function
                    in shaping the products of imaginative activity.</p>
        <pb id="p12-106" n="106"/>
        <figure n="BB209.1.91.MS" rend="file" width="796" height="1000">
          <head><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 91<gap type="emend" rend="plain"/>.</head>
        </figure>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
