<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.3.heppner</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="article">Another “New” Blake Engraving: More About Blake &amp; William
Nicholson</title>
                <author n="Heppner">Christopher Heppner</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1978-79</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978-79</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Production Office</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>E. B. Bentley</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>David Bindman</name>
                            <name>Izak Bouwer</name>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>Arnold Cheskin</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>Martha Winburn England</name>
                            <name>J. Karl Franson</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>David Irwin</name>
                            <name>Paul McNally</name>
                            <name>Marta Slowikova</name>
                            <name>Robert R. Wark</name>
                            <name>Kazumitsu Watarai</name>
                            <name>Dwight Weber</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1979"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
            <pb id="p12-193" n="193"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-3-0008">
                <head>
                    <title type="main">
                        <hi rend="b">ANOTHER “NEW” BLAKE ENGRAVING: MORE ABOUT
                            BLAKE &amp; WILLIAM NICHOLSON</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="b">CHRISTOPHER</hi>
                        <name>
                            <hi rend="b">HEPPNER</hi>
                        </name>
                    </docAuthor>
                </byline>
                <p>In an interesting recent essay, Rodney M. and Mary R. Baine offer good evidence
                    for proposing William Nicholson as the original model for Inflammable Gass the
                    Wind finder in Blake’s <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon.</hi>
                    <ref target="n75" type="note">1</ref> The weakest link in their argument is
                    perhaps the merely circumstantial nature of the connections between Blake and
                    Nicholson before the 1800s: “Blake is almost certain to have known
                    Nicholson in the 1800’s; but he could have met him in the late
                    1770’s or early ’80’s.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76"
type="note">2</ref>
                    <note id="n75">
                        <hi rend="s">1</hi> Rodney M. and Mary R. Baine,
                        “Blake’s Inflammable Gass,” <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Newsletter 38</hi> (Fall 1976), pp. 51-52. It was this essay which drew
                        my attention to Nicholson’s book.</note>
                    <note id="n76">
                        <hi rend="s">2</hi> Baine, p. 51.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In the same paragraph, however, lies a clue that, when followed up, provides the
                    definite evidence missing in the argument. The Baines, in suggesting that Blake
                    may have met Nicholson through the publisher Joseph Johnson, comment that Blake
                    in 1782 may have “engraved some of the twenty-five unsigned plates for
                    Nicholson’s <hi rend="i">An Introduction to Natural Philosophy</hi>,
                    published . . . by Johnson.” Blake did in fact sign one of the plates
                    in this book, for the vignette used on the title-page of both volumes of the
                    first, 1782, edition (see illus. 1 for title-page) is unmistakably signed
                    “Blake sc,” and there seems no doubt<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77"
type="note">3</ref> that it was indeed William Blake the poet who engraved
                    this admittedly not very exciting temple of science in the clouds (illus. 2).
                    The same plate has been used for both volumes; it is small (the plate-mark
                    measures 81 × 44 mm.), and the signature (illus. 3) very small indeed
                    (approximately 3.5 mm.), and quite faint. The signature is in fact at least as
                    difficult to see as that on the small engraving by Blake on p. 127 of Vol. I of
                    Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi>, which managed to
                    escape detection for so many years.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78"
type="note">4</ref> This
                    does raise the possibility that Blake has placed other micro-signatures on
                    plates which have been seen often without recognition. Obviously engravers made
                    much use of magnifying lenses for their work, though Blake’s modest
                        myopia<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79" type="note">5</ref> may
have helped a little. It is
                    not surprising that Blake adapted with great skill, if little enthusiasm, to the
                    craft of miniature painting. <note id="n77">
                        <hi rend="s">3</hi> The combination
                        of date, publisher, and style of signature make this virtually certain. I do
                        not know who designed the plate; it may have been Stothard, who designed
                        many of Blake’s early plates for Johnson, but a search through
                        the Stothard material in the British Museum Print Room failed to turn up any
                        evidence.</note>
                    <note id="n78">
                        <hi rend="s">4</hi> See G. E. Bentley, Jr., “A
                        ‘New’ Blake Engraving in Lavater’s
                        Physiognomy,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter 22</hi> (Fall 1972),
                        pp. 48-49.</note>
                    <note id="n79">
                        <hi rend="s">5</hi> See David Bindman, ed., <hi rend="i">William
                            Blake: Catalogue of the Collection in the Fitzwilliam Museum
                            Cambridge</hi> (Cambridge: Heffer and Sons, 1970), p. 60.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Baines’ essay suggests that Blake may have engraved some or all of
                    the other plates in these volumes. That is certainly possible, but in largely
                    technical engravings such as these are for the most part, it is impossible to
                    draw definite conclusions in the absence of clearly defined stylistic features.
                    The clumsy handling of the small temple on Plate XV of Vol. I, p. 281 (illus.
                    4), however, contrasts badly with the fineness of the basically similar temple
                    in Blake’s vignette. Blake is known to have done the technical
                    engravings for James Earle’s <hi rend="i">Practical Observations on
                        the Operation for the Stone</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80"
type="note">6</ref> but
                    they are again considerably finer than the work in the plates in the Nicholson
                    volumes. In fact, Blake’s commercial work in this early period was
                    usually small in scale and quite fine-toned, as demonstrated by such plates as
                    those for <hi rend="i">The Poetical Works of John Scott</hi> (1782), <hi rend="i">The
Novelist’s Magazine</hi> (1782-83), and
                    Ritson’s <hi rend="i">Select Collection of English Songs</hi> (1783).
                    Blake himself later took some pride in this early work, much of it after
                    Stothard’s designs, and refers in the “Public
                    Address” to “those little prints which I engraved after him
                    five &amp; twenty years ago &amp; by which he got his reputation as a
                        draughtsman.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81" type="note">7</ref>
My own view
                    therefore is that it is relatively unlikely, though just possible, that Blake
                    engraved more than the title-page vignette for <hi rend="i">An Introduction to
                        Natural Philosophy.</hi>
                    <note id="n80">
                        <hi rend="s">6</hi> See Leslie F. Chard II, “Two
                        ‘New’ Blake Engravings: Blake, James Earle, and the
                        Surgeon’s Art,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 6:2
                        (1975), 153-65.</note>
                    <note id="n81">
                        <hi rend="s">7</hi> David V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Poetry
                            and Prose of William Blake</hi> (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1970), p.
                        561. Further references to this edition will take the form E 561.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The work was popular, and went through five English editions. “The
                    Second Edition, with Improvements,” is dated 1787,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n82" type="note">8</ref> and keeps Blake’s vignette, though in the
                    British Library’s copy the signature is almost invisible. It would
                    appear that the fine lines of Blake’s plate did not stand 
<pb id="p12-194" n="194"/>
up
to the heavy wear of substantial editions, for the
                    third, fourth, and fifth London editions, dated 1790, 1796, and 1805, substitute
                    a new and unsigned vignette (illus. 5) for the title-page, similar to
                    Blake’s in general outline but considerably coarser. I do not know
                    who made this later plate, but its style seems much too crude to be attributable
                    to Blake. <note id="n82">
                        <hi rend="s">8</hi> An
                        “Advertisement” in this edition states that “Many
                        additional figures have been inserted in the plates”; proof that
                        the same plates were used can be found on pl. 22 of Vol. II, where the
                        original title of one figure, “Refractive power of the Air Fig.
                        III, p. 57” has been altered to read “Fig. 130,”
                        though the original “57” is still barely
                    visible.</note>
                </p>
                <p>There were also several American editions of Nicholson’s work, the
                    National Union Catalogue listing editions published in Philadelphia in 1787,
                    1788, and 1795-93 [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>]. Of these I have seen only the edition
                    published in 1788 by Thomas Dobson; it is in one volume and is called
                    “The Third Edition.” There is no engraving on the title-page;
                    most of the other plates in the book are extremely close but reversed copies of
                    the plates in the first London edition, suggesting that some process of tracing
                    was used to make the plates for the American editions.</p>
                <p>The uncovering of this overlooked Blake engraving is a useful reminder that Blake
                    seems very often to have made intellectual and poetic use of the books he
                    illustrated. I do not know if it was the custom of 
<figure n="NicholsonTitlePage.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="552" height="1000">
                        <head>1 Titlepage of first edition of William Nicholson, <hi rend="i">Introduction to
Natural Philosophy</hi>, London, 1782.</head>
                    </figure>
                    <figure n="NicholsonVignette.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="573">
                        <figTranscr>QUIS : BASIN : DEMONSTRET :</figTranscr>
                        <head>2 Blake’s vignette for titlepage of Nicholson’s
                                <hi rend="i">Introduction to Natural Philosophy</hi>, 1782; plate
                            size 81 × 44 mm.</head>
                    </figure>
                    <pb id="p12-195" n="195"/>
                    <figure n="VignetteSignature.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="421">
                        <figTranscr>[DEM]ONSTRET<lb/>
                        Blake sc</figTranscr>
                        <head>3 Enlargement of Blake’s signature (3.5 mm.) from titlepage
                            vignette.</head>
                    </figure>
                    <figure n="TheoryoftheRainbow.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="774">
                        <head>4 Figure illustrating “Theory of the Rainbow” from
                            Nicholson, 1782; Vol. I, p. 281.</head>
                        <figDesc>The plate is 173 × 166 mm.; this figure is 109
                            × 72 mm.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <pb id="p12-196" n="196"/>
                    publishers to present courtesy copies of books to
                    their illustrators, but the evidence already offered by the Baines in their
                    article suggests strongly that Nicholson’s <hi rend="i">An
                        Introduction to Natural Philosophy</hi> joins such books as
                    Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man</hi> and Stedman’s
                        <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi>
                    <ref target="n83" type="note">9</ref> in the
                    group of works that Blake both illustrated and used. With the confidence born of
                    knowing for certain that Blake did illustrate Nicholson’s work, I
                    would like to make a few further suggestions about the possible intellectual
                    relations between the two men. <note id="n83">
                        <hi rend="s">9</hi> See David V.
                        Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire</hi>, revised ed. (Garden
                        City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1969), pp. 230-42. See also G. E. Bentley, Jr., 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1977), pp. 685-88 for
                        books illustrated by Blake for Cumberland and Hayley that the writers
                        presented to him.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The Baines state that Nicholson shared Blake’s “political and
                    religious views.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84"
type="note">10</ref> This may well
                    be true in general terms, but it would seem that the two were far apart on
                    fundamental questions of method in the arts and sciences. Nicholson begins with
                    an “Introduction” that defines
                    “Demonstration” and gives three “Rules of
                    Philosophizing,” in the following schematization: 
					<q> I<lb/>
                        <lb/>
 No
                        more causes of natural things ought to be admitted than are true, and
                        sufficient to explain the phenomena.<lb/>
                        <lb/>
 II<lb/>
                        <lb/>
 And therefore
                        effects of the same kind are produced by the same causes.<lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        III<lb/>
                        <lb/>
 Those qualities which do not vary, and are found in all bodies
                        with which experiments can be made, ought to be admitted as qualities of all
                        bodies in general.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n85"
type="note">11</ref>
					</q>
                    <figure n="NicholsonTitleVignette.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="502">
                        <figTranscr>QUIS BASIN DEMONSTRET</figTranscr>
                        <head>5 Titlepage vignette for Nicholson, <hi rend="i">Introduction to
                                Natural Philosophy</hi>, 5th ed., London, 1805; plate size 78
                            × 43 mm.</head>
                    </figure> The mode of argument here is reminiscent of that found in <hi rend="i">There is
                    No Natural Religion</hi>, and this added to the evidence that the
                    Baines present for Blake’s mockery of Nicholson as Inflammable Gass
                    suggests that Blake may have thought of Nicholson as a type of the rationalizing
                    enlightenment mind intent upon narrowing philosophy to natural philosophy. <note id="n84">
                        <hi rend="s">10</hi> Baine, p. 51.</note>
                    <note id="n85">
                        <hi rend="s">11</hi> William Nicholson, <hi rend="i">An
                            Introduction to Natural Philosophy</hi> (London: J. Johnson, 1782),
                        I, 6.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In the world of the arts, it is worth noting that the first version of
                    “Holy Thursday” cuts across and silences (for “a
                    quarter of an hour”) the games that Inflammable Gass has been playing
                    with his dangerous toys and “magic pictures” of fleas and lice
                        (<hi rend="i">Island in the Moon</hi>, E 452-53). The Baines mention
                    Nicholson’s camera obscura in reference to Inflammable
                    Gass’s claim to own such a device (E 443). There is an illustration
                    of one in Nicholson’s book (my illus. 6), and a description:
                    “This is one of the most pleasing and delightful experiments in optics,
                    and never fails to strike the beholder with surprise and admiration. Which
                    indeed is not to be wondered at, for if there be any pleasure in contemplating a
                    well executed painting, how much more 
<pb id="p12-197" n="197"/>
forcibly must
                    the attention be fixed when the painting is drawn by the unerring hand of
                        nature?”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86" type="note">12</ref> In
<hi rend="i">The
                        Ghost of Abel</hi>, many years later, Blake stated that “Nature has
                    no Outline: but Imagination has” (E 268); I suspect that even in the
                    1780’s Blake would have found Nicholson’s natural
                    aesthetics as unsatisfying as his natural philosophy. <note id="n86">
                        <hi rend="s">12</hi> Nicholson, I, 368.</note>
                </p>
                <figure n="CameraObscura.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="672">
                    <head>6 Figure of a “Camera Obscura” from Nicholson, 1782,
                        Vol. I, p. 368.</head>
                    <figDesc>The plate is 170 × 161 mm., and this figure approximately 70
                        × 38 mm.</figDesc>
                </figure>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
