<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.3.irwin</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Joseph Burke, English Art 1714-1800</title>
                <author n="Irwin">David Irwin</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1978-79</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978-79</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Production Office</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>E. B. Bentley</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>David Bindman</name>
                            <name>Izak Bouwer</name>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>Arnold Cheskin</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>Martha Winburn England</name>
                            <name>J. Karl Franson</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>David Irwin</name>
                            <name>Paul McNally</name>
                            <name>Marta Slowikova</name>
                            <name>Robert R. Wark</name>
                            <name>Kazumitsu Watarai</name>
                            <name>Dwight Weber</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1979"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
	<pb id="p12-212" n="212"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-3-0011">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <figure n="BurkeEnglishArt.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="447"/>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Joseph Burke. <hi rend="b">English Art 1714-1800.</hi> Oxford
History
                            of English Art, vol. IX. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977. xxxii + 425 pp.,
                            120 plates. £ 12.50.</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="b">David</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">Irwin</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>The eighteenth century in artistic terms did not stop in 1800. Crucial ideas
                        were still developing and flourishing well into the nineteenth century. The
                        period about 1800 was one of artistic excitement, as well as a time of
                        literary and political upheavals. Neoclassicism, the main movement or style,
                        was only in the middle of its second phase about 1800; the final, third
                        stage had yet to emerge. This fact was recognized by the organizers of the
                        “Age of Neoclassicism” exhibition held in London in 1972;
                        they gave themselves a brief covering the period up to 1840. The other main
                        umbrella often used to cover the late eighteenth and the early nineteenth
                        centuries is obviously that of Romanticism. That interesting show in Detroit
                        and Philadelphia in 1968, “Romantic Art in Britain,” was
                        devoted to the century between 1760 and 1860. Although these dates were
                        arguably a bit too far apart, especially at the latter end, it was a fault
                        in the right direction.</p>
                    <p>Yet for chronological convenience the editors of the Oxford History of
                        English Art and the Pelican History of Art have chosen either 1800 or 1790
                        as terminal dates when commissioning eighteenth-century studies. At least in
                        the Pelican series the British sculpture and architecture volumes by
                        Margaret Whinney and John Summerson go as far as 1830, but the painting
                        survey by Ellis Waterhouse stops in 
<pb id="p12-213" n="213"/>
1790. For a
                        continuation into the nineteenth century in the Pelican series we await
                        Michael Kitson’s volume. In the Oxford series we have T. S. R.
                        Boase’s volume, which covers the first seventy years after 1800.
                        In this instance a terminal date of 1870 makes sense, but that is another
                        story not for discussion here.</p>
                    <p>Burke seems to hint at the difficulty of his concluding date in the final
                        paragraph of his book. Discussing Wordsworth, in a chapter entitled
                        “The Transition to Romanticism,” Burke writes that the
                        poet, “who disliked the picturesque and described it in <hi rend="i">The Prelude</hi>
as ‘ . . . a strong infection of
                        the age. . . . / Bent overmuch on superficial things’, has in
                        these two passages identified the dividing line between the Rule of Taste
                        and the liberty of nature, crossed by artists as well as poets <hi rend="i">well
before</hi> the close of the century in which he spent the first
                        thirty years of his life” (my italics).</p>
                    <p>Not only do the dates of 1790 or 1800 distort what was actually happening in
                        the art world, it also cuts through the careers of major artists whose lives
                        happen to span the end and the beginning of the centuries. This is of course
                        inevitable with any date that is selected at any period. But in the case of
                        these standard histories there are some unfortunately truncated artists
                        whose two halves never seem to meet each other, apparently leading separate
                        lives, and reminding one of the two halves of the <hi rend="i">Visconte
                            dimezzato</hi> in Italo Calvino’s fairy tale.</p>
                    <p>In the context of this periodical, it will be appropriate to start by looking
                        at the results of editorial policy in the Oxford series on the career of
                        William Blake. In Burke’s volume he is mentioned on four
                        occasions. In an excellent chapter devoted to “The Royal Academy
                        and the Great Style” Blake appears, along with Turner, as one of
                        the painters whose imaginations were “haunted all their lives by
                        themes of <hi rend="i">istoria.</hi>” Later in the same chapter,
                        whilst discussing James Barry’s paintings at the Society of Arts,
                        Burke says that the Irishman lacked the “mystic fervour”
                        of Blake, a fair comparison since Barry could on occasions be singularly
                        earthbound. Still in the same chapter, whilst mentioning single-handed
                        undertakings to illustrate the works of famous authors, Burke mentions
                        Fuseli’s Milton Gallery and Blake’s Dante project. The
                        only other citation of Blake is in a chapter on “The Expansion of
                        Neo-Classicism,” where Burke quotes from the 1809 <hi rend="i">Descriptive
Catalogue.</hi> Each of the references is apposite, but the
                        main discussion of Blake does not occur until Boase’s volume.</p>
                    <p>Some of the other artists who have suffered similarly by being torn between
                        two volumes include John Flaxman. His early period, embracing commissions
                        for Wedgwood and major works in the 1790’s, features in Burke,
                        but later works have had to be omitted and appear in Boase. As a result, in
                        neither volume is Flaxman’s overall development discussed
                        properly. Fuseli hardly comes into Burke at all. Sir Thomas Lawrence and
                        Thomas Rowlandson are omitted. Sir Henry Raeburn, a fine portraitist who is
                        much underrated in the general literature, appears on only one page in
                        Burke, and is also scantily treated by Boase, and is therefore virtually
                        omitted by both authors. Of the principal artists at the turn of the century
                        one of the few to receive anything like adequate coverage is Benjamin West.
                        But like Flaxman his oeuvre as a whole is unsatisfactorily treated.</p>
                    <p>Editorial decisions over dates are one matter, the actual content of Joseph
                        Burke’s volume is quite another. It is a brilliantly skillful
                        compression within four hundred pages of a great deal of material and
                        especially valuable since it discusses all the arts, including gardening and
                        the decorative arts, within the covers of one book—a virtue of
                        editorial policy, since this is a characteristic of all the Oxford History
                        of English Art series. Too often in art historical literature, painting,
                        sculpture and architecture are discussed in isolation from each other, and
                        the decorative arts are usually squeezed out or given a mere nod. Art
                        historians, with a few exceptions, have been such snobs over the decorative
                        arts in the post-medieval period, relegating research on
                        them—quite wrongly—to a lower order of intellectual
                        activity. The barrier between the so-called “fine” arts
                        and the rest is only a recent invention, for which Michelangelo is partially
                        to blame. It is a barrier which did not exist in the eighteenth century,
                        since artists like Robert Adam and Flaxman were not alone in designing in
                        several fields. Across the Channel, the decorative arts were of crucial
                        importance in contemporary France, and an integral part of the artistic
                        creativity of the time, yet they are omitted from the Pelican History of Art
                        volume by Wend Graf Kalnein and Michael Levy, thus diminishing its
                        usefulness.</p>
                    <p>It was particularly encouraging therefore to open Burke’s volume
                        and find amongst the plates a double-page spread showing a Rococo staircase
                        in a country-house in Devon opposite a Rococo design for a table and a
                        silver wine cooler. The plates in general are in fact refreshingly
                        unhackneyed. Other plates include a Roubiliac monument opposite a Paul de
                        Lamerie ewer; and a Robert Adam staircase opposite a sideboard and other
                        furnishings designed by him. Such juxtapositions make a fuller and deeper
                        understanding of the whole period possible, in a way that cannot be achieved
                        in volumes devoted to the arts separately. Some styles cannot be discussed
                        adequately without taking all the arts into account; this is especially the
                        case with the Rococo and with Neoclassicism.</p>
                    <p>Burke has some particularly good passages on the decorative arts. His
                        discussion of the “Impact of the Rococo” in his fifth
                        <corr type="emend">chapter</corr> is a model of its kind, in which the essential
interweaving of all
                        the arts in the eighteenth century is very apparent, embracing also
                        literature and music. The author had given a foretaste of his ideas in an
                        interesting article published in <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century
                            Studies</hi> in 1969, entitled “Hogarth, Handel and Roubiliac:
                        a note on the interrelationship of the arts in England 1730-1760.”
                        In the same spirit Jean Hagstrum had written his important <hi rend="i">Sister
Arts</hi> (Chicago Univ. Press, 1958) and more recently Morris
                        Brownell has 
<pb id="p12-214" n="214"/>
published his <hi rend="i">Alexander
                            Pope and the Arts of Georgian England</hi> (Oxford Univ. Press, 1978).
                        Ronald Paulson has produced some particularly stimulating articles on art
                        written from the vantage point of an historian of English literature, often
                        giving a refreshing new look at eighteenth-century Britain. Some of his
                        articles on art have been usefully gathered together under the title of 
<hi rend="i">Emblem and Expression</hi> (Harvard Univ. Press, 1975). Within
                        this growing awareness of interrelationships, Burke firmly places the
                        silver, ceramics and furnishings of the period. The more boundaries that are
                        broken down between the arts, and in many instances between disciplines
                        themselves, the better. For a masterly new look at all the arts in
                        eighteenth-century Britain, Burke’s book is to be greatly
                        welcomed and much valued.</p>
                    <p>As Britain has so often since the medieval period been a follower rather than
                        a leader in the arts within a European context, the eighteenth century is an
                        especially creative period. British contributions were of major importance
                        in the areas of landscape-gardening and of Neoclassicism. Although one
                        recent scholar would like to take Britain’s lead away from her by
                        saying that the “picturesque” garden was invented in
                        France (heretical and unconvincing view!), any study of British art in the
                        eighteenth century must have a great deal to say on the subject of both
                        landscape gardening as well as landscape painting. Such a discussion must be
                        interdisciplinary, and Paulson in his collected essays almost inevitably has
                        a piece on “The Poetic Garden,” starting with a walk at
                        Castle Howard. Burke, on the other hand, starts his discussion with theory,
                        with Shaftesbury and Pliny. Within less than thirty pages, Burke manages to
                        squeeze in all the essentials, in an area of research that is now at last
                        being developed, having lain largely dormant since Christopher
                        Hussey’s <hi rend="i">magnum opus.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>As one would expect in a history of this kind, Burke discusses all the main
                        artists and a surprisingly large number of minor ones as well. He is able,
                        because he is looking at all the arts, to discuss Hogarth and Roubiliac in
                        the same chapter; he naturally gives prominence to Reynolds; and he has much
                        to say of interest about the development of architecture from the Palladians
                        onwards. The only shift in the balance of priorities that I would like to
                        have seen was more space devoted to Allan Ramsay, whose portaits are just as
                        fine as—and occasionally finer than—those of either
                        Reynolds or Gainsborough. Indeed in eighteenth-century studies in general,
                        Gainsborough is in danger of being overrated. It is unfortunate that Ramsay
                        is only allocated one plate, and that of the unusually dull portrait of the
                        third Duke of Argyll.</p>
                    <p>Other reviewers have already pointed out that the long delay in the
                        publication of the manuscript, finished in 1973, with parts completed even
                        earlier, has meant that recent books and articles—although in
                        some instances mentioned by the author—were not available for the
                        main writing. The delay has also meant that minor details have not been
                        updated, of which only two instances will be cited. We now know more about
                        the mysterious Mr. Lightfoot responsible for the delightful Chinoiserie
                        decorations in Claydon House, including even his Christian name. Amongst the
                        plates, it would have been better to have included a more recent photograph
                        of the Library at Kenwood. The later bookcases on either side of the
                        fireplace have now been removed, and replaced by a very successful
                        reconstruction of Adam’s original mirrors, which has given the
                        room an additional vitality in their reflecting light. But all such outdated
                        information can easily be remedied in a second edition.</p>
                    <p>Overall, the author has written an immensely useful and indispensible working
                        tool for anyone studying the eighteenth century. As Burke’s
                        volume is conceived quite differently from the rival Pelican series, he has
                        provided the kind of book for which there has long been a need.</p>
                    <figure n="GoliathDetail.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="393"/>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
