<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.3.mla</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">MLA Blake 1979</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1978-79</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978-79</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Production Office</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>E. B. Bentley</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>David Bindman</name>
                            <name>Izak Bouwer</name>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>Arnold Cheskin</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>Martha Winburn England</name>
                            <name>J. Karl Franson</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>David Irwin</name>
                            <name>Paul McNally</name>
                            <name>Marta Slowikova</name>
                            <name>Robert R. Wark</name>
                            <name>Kazumitsu Watarai</name>
                            <name>Dwight Weber</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1979"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
            <pb id="p12-218" n="218"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-3-0012">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">NEWSLETTER</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">MLA BLAKE 1979</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <figure n="MLA.11.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="150" height="67">
                    	<figTranscr>MLA</figTranscr>
                    </figure>
                    <p>W. J. T. Mitchell of the University of Chicago will be discussion leader for
                        the 1979 Special Session on Blake at the MLA Annual Meeting. The topic will
                        be “Blake on Language and Writing.” Those interested in
                        being on a panel should send Mitchell a paper of not more than fifteen pages
                        by 30 March 1979 at the latest, sooner if possible.</p>
                    <p>The topic for the 1979 meeting of the English Romantics Group of the MLA will
                        be “Death &amp; Dying in the Romantics.” Papers
                        should have a reading time of 20 minutes, and they should be submitted
                        before 15 April to David V. Erdman, Crane Neck Point, Setauket, New York
                        11733.</p>
                    <p>At the next meeting of the Modern Language association of America (San
                        Francisco, 27-30 December 1979), the Division of Literature and the Other
                        Arts will sponsor a meeting on the subject of literary illustration. If you
                        or any of your colleagues would like to submit a paper to be considered for
                        inclusion on the program for this meeting, I would be very grateful for your
                        interest and participation.</p>
                    <p>By literary illustration, the Executive Committee means visual art designed
                        to be viewed and interpreted in conjunction with literary texts. The texts
                        may be written in any of the languages normally represented at the MLA, and
                        may date from any period. Medieval manuscript illuminations are no less
                        eligible than, say, the Boydell Shakespeare Gallery or the works of Phiz.
                        The Executive Committee does <hi rend="i">not</hi> encourage the submission
                        of papers on pictorialist texts which are not actually illustrated.</p>
                    <p>Three or four papers will be selected for oral presentation by the authors in
                        San Francisco. Papers should be 15-20 minutes in length, and should be
                        submitted in full rather than in abstract. If slides are included in the
                        presentation, please send them with the manuscript or describe them on an
                        accompanying list. (Projection facilities will be provided at the meeting.)
                        Papers should be sent to me at the Department of English, University of New
                        Mexico, Albuquerque, New Mexico 87131, by April 20 (March 20 for non-members
                        of the MLA which has some travel funds for distinguished speakers in fields
                        other than those directly represented by the MLA (such as art history), and
                        for speakers who reside outside the United States and Canada. The Division
                        must request such funds no later than April 15, and is not certain to
                        receive them). Results will be announced by May 20. HUGH WITEMEYER,
                        UNIVERSITY OF NEW MEXICO, CHAIRMAN, EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE, DIVISION OF
                        LITERATURE AND THE OTHER ARTS, MLA.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
