<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.3.butlin</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="minute">An Illustration to Robert Bage</title>
                <author n="Butlin">Martin Butlin</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1978-79</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978-79</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Production Office</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>E. B. Bentley</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>David Bindman</name>
                            <name>Izak Bouwer</name>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>Arnold Cheskin</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>Martha Winburn England</name>
                            <name>J. Karl Franson</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>David Irwin</name>
                            <name>Paul McNally</name>
                            <name>Marta Slowikova</name>
                            <name>Robert R. Wark</name>
                            <name>Kazumitsu Watarai</name>
                            <name>Dwight Weber</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1979"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
            <pb id="p12-202" n="202"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-3-0010">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">AN ILLUSTRATION TO ROBERT BAGE</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="b">Martin</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">Butlin</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>The Blake exhibition at the Tate, and the happy coincidence of a BBC Radio 4
                        serial, produced one discovery of interest, the subject of the hitherto
                        unidentified book illustration in the Bateson Collection.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n88" type="note">1</ref> In the “Times Diary” in <hi rend="i">The Times</hi> for 25
May 1978 it was reported that Professor
                        Noel McLachlan of Melbourne University had recognized the drawing as being
                        an illustration to Robert Bage’s <hi rend="i">Hermsprong, or Man
                            as He is Not</hi>, first published in 1796 and again in 1799, 1809, 1810
                        and 1828. The novel, subtitled to contrast it to Bage’s previous
                        novel <hi rend="i">Man as He is</hi> of 1792, deals with the opposition
                        between Lord Grondale and the radical Mr. Hermsprong, brought up in savage
                        America and a reader of Thomas Paine’s <hi rend="i">Rights of
                            Man</hi>; he is only revealed at the close to be Charles Campinet, the
                        wrongfully disinherited heir of Lord Grondale’s elder brother.
                            <note id="n88">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi> Exh. Tate Gallery 1978 (255, repr.);
                            also repr. Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">A Bibliography of William
                                Blake</hi>, 1921, pl. 25. It is No. 682 in my detailed catalogue of
                            Blake’s works, now in the press.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The drawing shows the encounter in chapter 5 between Lord Grondale and
                        Hermsprong following the latter’s rescue of Lord
                        Grondale’s daughter Caroline Campinet and her aunt Mrs. Merrick
                        from being nearly “smashed to pieces down Lippen Crag”
                        after the horse pulling their “chair,” a form of light
                        chaise, had bolted. Lord Grondale, who has not yet learned of the near
                        accident, is highly angry to find his niece “leaning on the bosom
                        of a young man. . . . Yet he did not knock the stranger down—he
                        did not. He only said, with the air of a great and angry man,
                        ‘Who are you, Sir?’” To this Hermsprong, a
                        “well dressed young man,” replies at first with silence,
                        then with “I am a man, sir.” When asked his rank and
                        fortune he replies, “ . . . As to rank,—I have been
                        taught only to distinguish men by virtue,” a sentiment that would
                        have appealed to Blake. Behind, Mrs. Merrick sits in the chair, still dazed
                        “with open eyes, which seemed not to see,” while the
                        servant Philip holds the horse’s head. Blake has shown the
                        setting, “a steep declivity” running down to the river
                        Gron by which stands the village of Grondale; it is “a 
<figure n="BageHermsprong.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="739" height="1000">
                            <head>William Blake, Illustration to Robert Bage’s <hi rend="i">Hermsprong</hi>,
c. 1820.</head>
                            <figDesc>Pen and wash. Bateson Collection, on loan to the Tate Gallery,
                                London.</figDesc>
                        </figure> fine autumnal evening.” The drawing, which is in
                        monochrome pen and sepia and measures 6 ⅜ × 4 9/16
                        ins. (16.3 × 11.6 cm.), is close in style to Blake’s
                        illustrations to Milton’s <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi>
                        and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi> which are on paper watermarked 1816 and
                        may indeed date from even later, say <hi rend="i">c.</hi> 1820. It is just
                        possible, allowing for the fact that the book illustration is even more
                        accomplished in Blake’s late, sensuous manner than the Milton
                        illustrations, that it may have been done in connection with the 1828
                        edition of <hi rend="i">Hermsprong</hi>, which has a vignette frontispiece
                        by T. Williams showing the same episode. Blake’s more ambitious
                        design could have been abandoned as unsuitable or as the result of his death
                        in 1827. However, there is no documentary evidence for Blake’s
                        connection with this edition. (I am indebted to Professor McLachlan and Judy
                        Egerton for this identification and much of its elaboration
                        respectively.)</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
