<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.3.franson</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="article">The Serpent-Driving Females in Blake’s Comus 4</title>
                <author n="Franson">J. Karl Franson</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1978-79</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978-79</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Production Office</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>E. B. Bentley</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>David Bindman</name>
                            <name>Izak Bouwer</name>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>Arnold Cheskin</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>Martha Winburn England</name>
                            <name>J. Karl Franson</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>David Irwin</name>
                            <name>Paul McNally</name>
                            <name>Marta Slowikova</name>
                            <name>Robert R. Wark</name>
                            <name>Kazumitsu Watarai</name>
                            <name>Dwight Weber</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1979"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
        <pb id="p12-164" n="164"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-3-0005">
                <head>
                    <title type="main">
                        <hi rend="b">THE SERPENT-DRIVING FEMALES IN BLAKE’S <hi rend="i">COMUS</hi> 4</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="b">J. KARL</hi>
                        <name>
                            <hi rend="b">FRANSON</hi>
                        </name>
                    </docAuthor>
                </byline>
                <p>A female figure driving a serpent-team through the treetops appears in both
                    versions of Blake’s watercolor designs for Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, Scene
                    4—the earlier series now in the
                    Huntington Library (cited below as H) and the later series in the Museum of Fine
                    Arts, Boston (B).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref>
                    Despite striking differences between the two 
                    sets,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> 
                    and specifically between the two female figures in this scene, between their
                    serpent-teams, and the darkness of the night, commentators almost never consider
                    both versions when discussing Blake’s visual interpretations of the
                    masque. As a consequence, they generally regard the two females as the same
                    character. Irene Tayler, taking into account only the H series in her pioneering
                    essay on the designs, refers to the “draped female overhead”
                    as “the strange dragon or snake-lady,” “that veiled
                    tyrant of women” whom Blake might intend to suggest “the
                    moon-goddess Cynthia” or maybe 
                    Medea.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> 
                    Commenting on the B series only, Marcia R. Pointon calls the woman
                    above the trees “Diana, goddess of the moon” (p. 139). More
                    recently, Joseph A. Wittreich, Jr. labels the females Blake’s
                    personification of 
                    Jealousy,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> 
                    and Stephen C. Behrendt follows Pointon in calling the figures 
                    Cynthia-Diana.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref>
                    <note id="n1">
                        <hi rend="s">1</hi> The two series, although of the same scenes or
                        combination of scenes in <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, are considerably different
                        (see n. 2 below). The date of the Huntington set of eight is probably about
                        1801-1802, as Blake refers to the unfinished designs in a letter to John
                        Flaxman dated 19 October 1801 (Blake, <hi rend="i">Complete Writings</hi>,
                        ed. Geoffrey Keynes [London: Oxford Univ. Press, 1966], p. 810). The date of
                        the Boston series of eight is less certain. Marcia R. Pointon suggests that
                        they were done “probably a little later” than the first
                        set (<hi rend="i">Milton &amp; English Art</hi> [Toronto: Univ. of
                        Toronto Press, 1970], p. 139); Angus Fletcher dates them between 1805 and
                        1810 (<hi rend="i">The Transcendental Masque: An Essay on
                            Milton’s “Comus”</hi> [Ithaca, N.Y.:
                        Cornell Univ. Press, 1971], p. 253); Joseph A. Wittreich, Jr. proposes 1809
                            (<hi rend="i">Angel of Apocalypse: Blake’s Idea of
                            Milton</hi> [Madison: Univ. of Wisconsin Press, 1975], p. 80); and more
                        recently David Bindman asserts that they were done “probably about
                        1815,” although he offers no evidence for so late a date (<hi rend="i">Blake As an
                        Artist</hi> [Oxford: Phaidon, 1977], p. 186). The
                        important question of whether the B series was completed before or after
                        Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, the date of which is also open
                        to question, thus remains unresolved. Both sets are reproduced in color by
                        A. Fletcher, but the H series in the copies of Fletcher I have seen is badly
                        printed and potentially misleading. Having examined the originals of both
                        sets, I am impressed that a quality reproduction of them in color is sorely
                        needed. For kind permission to reproduce these two sets of designs, I wish
                        to thank the Huntington Library and Art Gallery, San Marino, Calif., and the
                        Museum of Fine Arts, Boston.</note>
                    <note id="n2">
                        <hi rend="s">2</hi> A few of the differences are discussed by A.
                        Fletcher, who credits Diane Christian for much of the analysis (pp. 253-56);
                        by Wittreich, <hi rend="i">Angel of Apocalypse</hi> (pp. 81-86); and by
                        Bindman (p. 186).</note>
                    <note id="n3">
                        <hi rend="s">3</hi> Irene Tayler, “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> Designs,” 
                        <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>,
                        4 (Spring 1972), 45-80; citations above come from pp. 48, 51, 76, 48 (to
                        which cf. p. 75n). The reference to Medea is on p. 237 in her expanded
                        version, “Say First! What Mov’d Blake?
                        Blake’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> Designs and <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>,” in 
                        <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory: Essays on “The Four Zoas,”
                        “Milton,” and “Jerusalem,”</hi> ed.
                        Stuart Curran and Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr. (Madison: Univ. of Wisconsin
                        Press, 1973), pp. 233-58.</note>
                    <note id="n4">
                        <hi rend="s">4</hi>
                        <hi rend="i"> Angel of Apocalypse</hi>, p. 83.</note>
                    <note id="n5">
                        <hi rend="s">5</hi> “The Mental Contest:
                        Blake’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> Designs,” forthcoming in
                            <hi rend="i">Blake Studies.</hi> I am much obliged to Professor Behrendt
                        for allowing me to read those portions of his manuscript that relate to this
                        study, and for offering perceptive suggestions regarding my
                    analysis.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Compounding this confusion concerning the figures is the repeated assertion that
                    they cannot be found in the standard versions of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> at all,
                    but are Blake’s invention.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref>
                    Wittreich cites as Blake’s source for these figures several lines
                    about a dragon that were cancelled in the Trinity (College) Manuscript of the
                    masque, but first published in 1798 and thus available to Blake. Certain details
                    of Wittreich’s argument are persuasive, but his fundamental assertion
                    that the cancelled lines constitute Blake’s primary source for the
                    serpent-teams and the female figures is essentially 
                    unconvincing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> 
                    These figures, to the contrary, are identified in the
                    standard published texts of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> in circulation during
                    Blake’s day.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> 
                    In addition, a matching of text and design reveals that Blake’s females in this
                    scene, one in each version, are not variations of the same person, but are two
                    different persons.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref>
                    <note id="n6">
                        <hi rend="s">6</hi> Tayler, “This strange figure is not
                        in Milton’s masque” (“Blake’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> Designs,” p. 48; see also,
                        “Say First!” p. 237); Pointon, “Above the trees rides the
                        moon-goddess . . . a figure which does not feature in Milton’s
                        poem” (p. 139), even though Blake is “precise in following
                        details of the text” (p. 138); Behrendt, “The figure in
                        the dragon-car above the trees is unmentioned in Milton’s
                        [standard] text.”</note>
                    <note id="n7">
                        <hi rend="s">7</hi> The heart of Wittreich’s argument
                        is as follows: “Charles Lamb reminds us that the following lines,
                        ‘not printed in the common editions of Milton’ and not
                        ‘generally known to belong to that divine
                        “Masque”,’ were printed in both the 1801 and
                        1809 editions by Henry John Todd, having first been published in
                        Todd’s 1798 edition of <hi rend="i">Comus.</hi> The Attendant
                        Spirit, descending and entering, explains that his mansion is 
                        <hi rend="i">‘Amidst th’ Hesperian gardens . . . / . . . on
                        whose faire tree / The scalie-harnest dragon ever keeps / His
                        uninchanted eye.’</hi> A few lines later we read of the
                        ‘jealous ocean’ winding his ‘farre extended
                        armes, till with steepe fall / Halfe his wast flood the wild Atlantique
                        fills.’ The scaly dragon derives from these lines, and so does
                        the figure of jealousy, which is transformed by Blake into the
                        ‘female’ riding the dragon. The arching trees,
                        creating a den-like place, may also be explained by turning to the cancelled
                        lines that speak of ‘this <hi rend="i">arched</hi>
                        wood’ and its ‘<hi rend="i">yawning
                        dens</hi>’” (<hi rend="i">Angel of Apocalypse</hi>, pp.
                        82-83). That the single dragon in the cancelled lines is
                        “scalie,” “harnest,” and that the trees
                        of the forest are “arched” and form “yawning
                        dens” coincide with elements in Blake’s
                        illustrations—the H serpents (but not the B) are scaled, in both
                        series they are harnessed, and the trees are noticeably arched, particularly
                        in H. But Blake’s dragons are a team, they are not keeping watch
                        over precious fruit, and they are driven by female figures (not male, like
                        Milton’s Jealous Ocean) who ostensibly have no direct connection
                        with the Attendant Spirit or with the Hesperian Gardens from whence he
                        comes. The cancelled lines are discussed by John. S. Diekhoff, who points
                        out that the central images in this cancelled passage (the Hesperian tree,
                        the dragon guarding the fruit with “uninchanted eye”) are
                        inserted by Milton further on in the masque and thus appear in all standard
                        versions, including those Blake most likely used (“The Text of 
                        <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, 1634 to 1645” [1937; rpt. as an appendix
                        to <hi rend="i">A Maske at Ludlow: Essays on Milton’s
                        “Comus,”</hi> ed. Diekhoff, Cleveland: The Press of
                        Case Western Reserve Univ., 1968, pp. 251-75; the discussion of these
                        cancelled lines appears on pp. 265-66]). For a discussion of the versions of
                        <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, see n. 8 below.</note>
                    <note id="n8">
                        <hi rend="s">8</hi> Of the five important versions of the
                            masque, Blake probably was familiar with a reproduction of the 1645 or
                            the 1673 version. Thomas Warton’s ed., which is a mixture of
                            both these versions, appeared in 1785 and 1791 (“A Maske
                            Presented at Ludlow Castle, 1634” in <hi rend="i">Poems upon
                            Several Occasions</hi> [London: J. Dodsley]). Henry John
                            Todd’s ed. of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> in 1798 follows the
                            1645 version, although like Warton’s it updates the spelling,
                            punctuation, and capitalization (<hi rend="i">A Mask . . . With Notes
                            Critical and Explanatory . . .</hi> [Canterbury: W. Bristow, <hi rend="i">et
                            al.</hi>]; rpt. as part of Todd’s edn. of
                            Milton’s <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi> in 1801, 1809,
                            1826, etc. The passages I cite, which do not vary significantly from
                            version to version, come from Todd’s 1798 ed. Because Todd
                            reproduces the 1645 version, his line numbers are the same as those in
                            the more accessible modern ed. by Merritt Y. Hughes, who also reprints
                            the 1645 edn. (<hi rend="i">Complete Poems and Major Prose</hi>
                            [Indianapolis, Ind.: Odyssey, 1957]).
                        <p>The five versions of the masque are: (1) the Trinity Manuscript, a
                            transcript in Milton’s hand made sometime after the original
                            and reproduced in part in 1861, in full in 1899; (2) the
                            “expurgated” and shortened Bridgewater Manuscript,
                            apparently a stage copy, transcribed and printed by Todd in 1798; (3)
                            the first published version (anonymous), 1637, based on the Trinity
                            Manuscript early in its correction stage; (4) the 1645 ed., authorized
                            by Milton; and (5) the 1673 ed., set from the 1645 ed. Facsimiles and
                            discussions of all five versions appear in Harris F.
                            Fletcher’s ed., <hi rend="i">John Milton’s
                            Complete Poetical Works, Reproduced in Photographic Facsimile</hi>
                            (Urbana: Univ. of Illinois Press, 1943), vol. I.</p>
                        <p>Corrupted stage adaptations of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> were performed
                            frequently during 1738-1850, but Blake’s designs show no
                            evidence that he followed an adaptation over the standard texts. The
                            first major adaptation, that of John Dalton in 1738, adds scenes,
                            shortens speeches, and inserts additional characters: a second attendant
                            spirit, Philidel, is to watch over the Lady in the forest; Euphrosyne
                            adds to Comus’s argument at the castle; and a spirit assists
                            Sabrina late in the masque (<hi rend="i">Comus, a Mask . . . As
                            Alter’d from Milton’s Mask . . .</hi> [London:
                            R. Dodsley, 1738]. Blake does not include these figures: H 2 portrays
                            Milton’s Attendant Spirit (so identified because he holds the
                            magic herb, as he later tells the brothers, 638-47). H 5 and B 5 do not
                            include a female persuader. Dalton’s adaptation,
                            incidentally, does include the Cotytto-Hecate passage cited previously;
                            but its successor, that by George Colman in 1772, shortens the passage
                            and omits all reference to Cotytto, rendering the lines nonsensical 
                            (<hi rend="i">Comus: A Masque, Altered from Milton . . .</hi> [London: T.
                            Lowndes, <hi rend="i">et al.</hi>]). For further analysis of the stage
                            adaptations, see Alwin Thaler, “Milton in the
                            Theatre,” <hi rend="i">SP</hi>, 18 (July 1920), 269-308.</p>
                    </note>
                    <note id="n9">
                        <hi rend="s">9</hi> After completing this study, I came upon an
                        apparent but very brief corroboration of the identifications I present below
                        in John E. Grant and Robert E. Brown’s
                        “Blake’s Vision of Spenser’s <hi rend="i">Faerie Queene</hi>: A Report and an
                        Anatomy,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter 31</hi>, 8 (Winter 1974-75), 64, n. 5, wherein the
                        authors refer to the dragons “that pull the cars of Cotytto-Hecate
                        in <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 4.” This identification, so far as I
                        have been able to determine, is not expanded elsewhere.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Blake’s fourth scenes, in which the Attendant Spirit dressed as the
                    shepherd Thyrsis shows the brothers the magic herb <hi rend="i">haemony</hi>,
                    illustrate lines 617-58 in the Todd and the Hughes editions. However, Milton
                    describes much earlier in the masque the serpent-ladies that Blake places in the
                    treetops. During Comus’s initial appearance as the forest
                    enchanter-seducer, he calls upon his retinue, partially transformed into beasts,
                    to join him in a libidinous ceremony: 
					<q>
						Come, let us our rights begin,<lb/>
                        ’Tis only day-light that makes sin,<lb/>
                        Which these dun shades will ne’er report.<lb/>
                        Hail, Goddess of nocturnal sport,<lb/>
                        Dark-veil’d Cotytto! t’whom the secret flame<lb/>
                        Of midnight torches burns; mysterious dame,<lb/>
                        That ne’er art call’d, but when the dragon woom<lb/>
                        Of Stygian darkness spetts her thickest gloom,<lb/>
                        And makes one blot of all the air;<lb/>
					<pb id="p12-165" n="165"/>
					<figure n="HuntingtonComus4Detail.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="282"/>
					<figure n="BostonComus4Detail.12.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="284">
						<head>Detail, Scene 4: “The Brothers Meet the Attendant Spirit
							in the Wood.”</head>
						<figDesc>Huntington at top; Boston, below.<lb/>
							<lb/>
							In the following
							pages, the Huntington set of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> designs is
							reproduced courtesy of the Henry E. Huntington Library &amp;
							Art Gallery, San Marino, California. The Boston set (gift of Mrs.
							John L. Gardner &amp; George N. Black) is reproduced courtesy
							of the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston.</figDesc>
					</figure>
                        Stay thy cloudy ebon chair,<lb/>
                        Wherein thou rid’st with Hecat’, and befriend<lb/>
                        Us thy vow’d priests, till utmost end<lb/>
                        Of all thy dues be done, and none left out.<lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        (125-37)
                    </q>
                    Certainly this invocation to “Dark-veil’d
                    Cotytto” is Blake’s primary source for the darkly draped
                    female in H 4. This Thracian goddess of licentiousness, worshipped only on the
                    darkest (or Stygian) nights, appears in Blake’s dark scene riding
                    through a treetop gloom that obscures sky, stars, and 
                    moon.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> 
                    Since Comus and his monsters begin their rites to the
                    goddess five hundred lines before Scene 4, we might be surprised by her
                    appearance here instead of in Blake’s first scene, that of Comus and
                    his revelers. But the text does not specify that she actually appears in
                    response to the invocation, probably because the chaste Lady’s
                    approach interrupts the rites at their beginning. Comus directs his rabble to
                    hide (147-48), enchants the spot (150 ff.), and entices the Lady who enters to
                    proceed with him to his cottage (244 ff.), where unknown to her he obviously
                    plans to reinitiate the rites to Cotytto. Thus Blake’s choice to
                    portray Cotytto in H 4, riding through the same forest in which she was earlier
                    invoked, is logical even though the text does not specify her presence here.
                    Seemingly she is enroute to the castle for the rites, which Blake suggests by
                    her direction toward the right margin, forward to the next scene inside the
                    castle. 
                    <note id="n10">
                        <hi rend="s">10</hi> The sky is not visible partly
                        because the woman rides through rather than above the foliage. In the B
                        series, the female rides atop the trees, the night is clear, and the sky and
                        moon are plainly visible. The gloom Blake portrays in H is consistent with
                        numerous allusions by the masque characters to the absolute darkness of the
                        night, caused by heavy clouds (e.g., 193-96; 203; 330-38; and so forth). The
                        only light to appear during these early forest scenes, according to the
                        text, is a momentary glimmer in the clouds detected by the Lady
                        (220-24).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Milton alludes metaphorically to a dragon in this Cotytto-Hecate passage (131)
                    and later to a dragon guarding the Hesperian Tree in the regions whence the
                    Attendant Spirit has come (395); but Blake’s primary source for the
                    serpent-team is probably the dragon-team traditionally associated with
                    Hecate’s car (in Ovid, for instance, and mentioned elsewhere by
                    Milton<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref>).
                    Blake’s red and
                    blue scaled beasts in H 4 might most accurately be labeled crested snakes or
                    serpents rather than dragons, as they have no legs or 
                    wings.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref>
                    <note id="n11">
                        <hi rend="s">11</hi> In Ovid’s <hi rend="i">Metamorphoses</hi>, a dragon-drawn
                        chariot descends in answer to
                        Medea’s prayer to Hecate (VII. 218-19). Milton alludes to the
                        dragon-team in his Latin elegy “<hi rend="i">In Obitum Praesulis
                        Eliensis</hi>” (“On the Death of the Bishop of
                        Ely”), 11. 56-58, which antedates <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> by six
                        years.</note>
                    <note id="n12">
                        <hi rend="s">12</hi> David V. Erdman, for instance, maintains the
                        distinction in <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> (Garden City, N. Y.:
                        Anchor / Doubleday, 1974). “Serpents” or
                        “snakes” elsewhere in Blake that bear close resemblance to
                        these harnessed creatures are the similarly harnessed serpents in 
                        <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 6<hi rend="s">I</hi> (Erdman, p. 40) and 
                        <hi rend="i">America</hi> 11<hi rend="s">N</hi> (Erdman, p. 149). 
                        In contrast, a Blake “dragon” (to use his own term) with forelegs and
                        wings is pictured in <hi rend="i">America</hi> 4<hi rend="s">N</hi> (Erdman,
                        p. 142) and a variation in <hi rend="i">America</hi> b (Erdman, p.
                        393).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Hecate, however, with whom Milton’s Cotytto rides, does not appear in
                    H 4, nor in H 1. Because Milton aligns Cotytto so closely with her, because the
                    Attendant Spirit claims that Comus frequently performs rites to her (535), and
                    because she does appear in Blake’s B series, consideration should be
                    given to Hecate’s role in Blake’s H interpretation. 
                    <pb id="p12-166" n="166"/>
                    <figure n="but527.1.1.wc" id="but527.1.wc.01" work-copy="but527.1" rend="db" width="838" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
</figure>
                    <figure n="but528.1.1.wc" id="but528.1.wc.01" work-copy="but528.1" rend="db" width="795" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>WBlake</figTranscr>
                        <head>Scene 1: “Comus with his Revellers.”</head>
                        <figDesc>Huntington at top; Boston, lower.</figDesc>
                    </figure> 
                    Surely Blake does not intend her to be hidden in the gloom beside
                    Cotytto in H 4. Does he interpret Milton’s line (“Wherein
                    thou rid’st with Hecat’”) to mean that Cotytto
                    sometimes rides with Hecate, but not always? Or has he in mind the Attendant
                    Spirit’s claim to the brothers during this scene that as their
                    father’s shepherd he has often heard Comus and his revelers
                    performing rites to Hecate and hence is drawing attention to the duality of
                    nocturnal rites performed by Comus—some to Hecate as goddess of
                    witchcraft, and on the darkest nights, other rites (or additional rites) to
                    Cotytto as a goddess of lechery? If this is Blake’s intent, H 1 would
                    not represent rites to Hecate only, as a reader might presume from the Attendant
                    Spirit’s assertion, but rites either to Hecate (but preliminary to
                    Cotytto rites on this Stygian night) or rites to Cotytto, the noise of which the
                    Spirit has interpreted as Hecate rites, and over which Hecate ultimately
                    presides. But if H 1 and H 4 involve Hecate, where is she?</p>
                <p>I believe her absence from the scene can be explained satisfactorily in terms of
                    a logical presence elsewhere in the forest. Is it not reasonable to conceive of
                    Hecate being involved, not directly in H 1, but in H 2? Although she is not
                    invoked this particular night, she is Comus’s reigning deity and
                    ostensibly his ultimate source of enchanting power. So when he enchants the spot
                    that Blake depicts in H 2, as well as himself, with “dazling
                    spells” (154) and “magic dust” (165), then leads the
                    beguiled Lady from the place through the forest to his castle, might not Blake
                    have intended Hecate to preside over this spell that continues through the
                    forest trek, according to the text, until the Lady is seated inside the castle
                    in Scene 5? Though Blake does not depict Hecate visually in H 2, and though the
                    text does not specify her appearance or direct involvement, her presence in the
                    scene is logical. If H 2 is viewed in this manner, and if we consider carefully
                    the chronology of the masque, Hecate would be journeying to the castle (and the
                    rites) with Comus and the Lady at the same time Cotytto rides there in H 4.</p>
                <p>If we consider the details of Cotytto worship, we will quickly comprehend the
                    aptness of Milton’s allusion to her in <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and
                    the aptness of Blake’s inclusion of her in H 4. A Greek goddess of
                    wantonness, Cotytto was not well known in Milton’s day or in
                    Blake’s. Milton does not mention her elsewhere, and Blake never
                    refers to her by name. Milton associates her with the better-known Hecate,
                    goddess of the underworld and witchcraft, presumably because both were said to
                    originate in Thrace. There is historical evidence of Cotytto worship in Corinth,
                    perhaps in Athens, and with great license in 
                    Rome.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref>
                    <pb id="p12-167" n="167"/> 
                    The longest account of Cotytto worship appears in
                    Juvenal’s Second Satire, “Moralists without
                    Morals,” with which Milton was familiar (Osgood, pp. 24-25). Juvenal
                    associates the goddess with orgiastic rites conducted by priests that were
                    secret, nocturnal, torchlit, gluttonous, accompanied by dancing, and chiefly
                    sodomistic. The orgiastic elements in <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> approximate these
                    closely, with the possible exception of sodomy: Comus calls together his
                    followers in secret, at night; they carry torches; they later feast at a
                    banquet; and they “knit hands, and beat the ground / In a light
                    fantastic round” (143-44). Also similar to elements in <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> are
                    Juvenal’s references in Cotytto worship to
                    metamorphoses (in <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, the monsters); Stygian blackness (in
                    <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, 132); a cup or glass used in the rites (in 
                    <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, the crystal goblet with enchanting liquid); and the
                    initiation rite (in <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, the drink). In view of Barbara
                    Breasted’s recent discovery that Milton wrote <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>
                    in the wake of a notorious sex scandal that included rape, incest, and sodomy
                    among relatives of the <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> Bridgewater family—and
                    the masque thus being an attempt to help re-establish the family’s
                    integrity—Cotytto’s presence in the masque is doubly
                    appropriate.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref>
                    Blake probably did not
                    know of the Castlehaven Scandal, and he may not have been familiar with all the
                    details of Juvenal’s account of her, but he surely was familiar with
                    her role as a goddess of lechery, an identification provided in Thomas
                    Newton’s and Todd’s annotations to <hi rend="i">Comus.</hi>
                    <ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> And he obviously detected
                    in the masque a central theme of the conflict between chastity and perversity.
                    <note id="n13">
                        <hi rend="s">13</hi> Charles Grosvenor Osgood, <hi rend="i">The Classical Mythology of
                        Milton’s English Poems</hi>
                        (1900; rpt. New York: Gordian, 1964), pp. 24-25.</note>
                    <note id="n14">
                        <hi rend="s">14</hi> Barbara Breasted, “<hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and the Castlehaven
                        Scandal,” <hi rend="i">Milton Studies</hi>, 3 (1971), 201-24.</note>
                    <note id="n15">
                        <hi rend="s">15</hi> Todd’s annotation to
                        “Dark-veil’d Cotytto” (129) includes material
                        from Newton’s earlier note: 
                        “<hi rend="i">The Goddess of wantonness. . . .</hi> 
                        Dr. Newton observes, that ‘she was originally a 
                        <corr type="emend">strumpet,</corr> and had midnight sacrifices at Athens, and is 
                        <corr type="emend">therefore</corr> very properly said to be <hi rend="i">dark-veiled.</hi>’ 
                        Her orgies were celebrated also by the
                        Thracians, Chians, Corinthians, and others. Her rites were termed 
                        <hi rend="i">Cotyttia</hi>, and her priests <hi rend="i">Baptae.</hi> See
                        Juvenal Sat. ii. v. 91. Milton makes her the companion of Hecate, the
                        patroness of enchantments, to whom Comus and his crew v. 535 ‘do
                        abhorred <corr type="emend">rites:’ her</corr> mysteries requiring <hi rend="i">the veil of
                        that darkness</hi>, over which Hecate presided” (p. 23n).
                        Thomas Newton, ed., <hi rend="i">Paradise Regain’d . . . To Which
                        Is Added . . . Poems upon Several Occasions . . .</hi> (London: J.
                        &amp; R. Tonson, &amp; S. Draper, 1752).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Cotytto’s serpents in H 4, or more precisely Hecate’s
                    serpents, which Cotytto is driving, are typical Blake serpents: crested, mouths
                    open, tongues out, and thus active. For Blake, serpents represent (among other
                    things) hypocrisy, corrupt priesthood, and 
                    sexuality.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> 
                    Indeed, one can conceive a close similarity between the
                    attempt by Comus to force the Lady into sexual experience (particularly if one
                    remembers the serpent above Comus’s wand in B 5) and the theme of
                    Blake’s “I saw a chapel all of gold”: that forced
                    and undesired acts of sex are perversions of real 
                    love.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> 
                    In addition, the serpent-team represents the
                    spiritual-moral warfare that constitutes the foundation of the 
                    masque:<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref> 
                    the struggle of the brothers with each
                    other, the Lady with Comus and with herself, Comus with himself, and the
                    brothers with Comus and his monsters. We should note that these conflicts are
                    essentially dissolved, rather than overcome, by the magic herb <hi rend="i">haemony</hi>
                    that Blake portrays in this 
                    scene.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref>
                    Also worth noting is Blake’s placing of the
                    herb, held by the Spirit, almost directly below Cotytto’s triangular, scale-shaped 
                    skirt.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> 
                    Possibly this juxtaposition of herb beneath the scale is Blake’s way of drawing
                    attention to the importance of the herb’s function in eliminating the
                    stalemates in the 
                    masque.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref>
                    <note id="n16">
                        <hi rend="s">16</hi> See S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">A Blake
                            Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols of William Blake</hi> (Providence, R.
                        I.: Brown Univ. Press, 1965), pp. 365-66.</note>
                    <note id="n17">
                        <hi rend="s">17</hi> Blake’s “I saw a
                            chapel” comes from his Note-Book and was written about 1793.
                            Below are the first two stanzas: 
                            <q>
                            	I saw a chapel all of gold<lb/>
                                That none did dare to enter in,<lb/>
                                And many weeping stood without,<lb/>
                                Weeping, mourning, worshipping.<lb/>
                                <lb/>
                                I saw a serpent rise between<lb/>
                                The white pillars of the door,<lb/>
                                And he forc’d &amp; forc’d &amp; forc’d,<lb/>
                                [Till he broke the pearly door <hi rend="i">del.</hi>]<lb/>
                                Down the golden hinges tore. (<hi rend="i">Complete Writings</hi>, p.163)
                            </q>
                    </note>
                    <note id="n18">
                        <hi rend="s">18</hi> See Damon under “Dragon,”
                        p. 107.</note>
                    <note id="n19">
                        <hi rend="s">19</hi> Milton’s <hi rend="i">haemony</hi> as an emblem representing
                        legitimate vs. illegitimate
                        sexual experience is a thesis I present in “An Anglo-Saxon
                        Etymology for Milton’s <hi rend="i">Haemony</hi>,” <hi rend="i">American Notes &amp;
                        Queries</hi>, 14 (October 1975),
                        18-19.</note>
                    <note id="n20">
                        <hi rend="s">20</hi> In the original one can plainly see that the
                        triangular design is created by folds in Cotytto’s dress. But in
                        reproductions, especially A. Fletcher’s, the configuration might
                        be taken as a car or chariot. Vertical lines directly beneath the triangular
                        skirt, however, do imply a platform on which Cotytto is riding.</note>
                    <note id="n21">
                        <hi rend="s">21</hi> In <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> the scale
                        constitutes a key symbol, where Libra’s position in the Zodiac
                        between Virgo (Eve) and Scorpio (Satan) is a striking and profound image
                        (III. 558; cf. IV. 997). Blake may also be including the scale image in his
                        fifth <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> scenes, the Banquet: in both versions, he
                        includes hanging lamps triangular and scale-shaped, one almost directly over
                        the seated Lady. And in H 6, a lamp is visible below the second
                        brother’s sword, where it looks more like a hanging scale (in
                        connection with the sword) than a lamp. It seems significant that the
                        notorious cup, wrenched from the  <corr type="emend">sorcerer’s</corr> hand by the nearest
                        brother, is directly below the lamp-scale.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In the second <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> series, Blake makes significant changes in
                    Scene 4. The figure driving the serpent-team in B 4 is also female, as denoted
                    by her flowing hair, but she wears a light-colored garment, has no hood or veil,
                    and rides under a crescent 
                    moon.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref> 
                    Clearly this female cannot be “Dark-veil’d Cotytto,” who
                    appears only on the darkest nights. Because of her light-colored clothing 
                    <figure n="but527.1.2.wc" id="but527.1.wc.02" work-copy="but527.1" rend="db" width="845" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
</figure>
                    <figure n="but528.1.2.wc" id="but528.1.wc.02" work-copy="but528.1" rend="db" width="796" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>WBlake</figTranscr>
                        <head>Scene 2: “Comus, Disguised as a Rustic, Addresses the Lady in
                            the Wood.”</head>
                        <figDesc>Huntington, top; Boston, lower.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <pb id="p12-168" n="168"/>
                    <figure n="but527.1.3.wc" id="but527.1.wc.03" work-copy="but527.1" rend="db" width="839" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
</figure>
                    <figure n="but528.1.3.wc" id="but528.1.wc.03" work-copy="but528.1" rend="db" width="786" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>WBlake</figTranscr>
                        <head>Scene 3: “The Brothers Observed by Comus Plucking
                            Grapes.”</head>
                        <figDesc>Huntington, left; Boston, right.</figDesc>
                    </figure> 
                    and the general brightness of the scene, she cannot be Night, who is
                    personified in the masque (195-200). The most convincing identification of this
                    figure is Hecate, Cotytto’s companion in the masque. Evidence
                    supporting this is that Blake has portrayed Hecate’s companion with
                    Hecate’s serpent-team in H 4; and thus, when serpents (albeit not the
                    same serpents) reappear with a new driver, the sensible identification would be
                    their mistress Hecate. More evidence of the figure’s identity is the
                    Spirit’s reference (cited above) to having heard Comus and his rabble
                    performing rites to Hecate earlier in the night; consequently, her appearance in
                    B 4 is as logical as Cotytto’s presence in H 4. Third, in classical
                    authors Hecate (but not Cotytto) is frequently associated with the moon, as she
                    is here with the moon above her head. Originally she was a moon goddess (Osgood,
                    p. 29); Plutarch, for example, labels the moon Hecate’s province (<hi rend="i">Cess. of
                    Oracles</hi>, 13). Blake refers to Hecate by name a number
                    of times, and he did several versions of a color-printed drawing of Hecate as
                    the triform goddess.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref>
                    <note id="n22">
                        <hi rend="s">22</hi> A similarity worth observing exists between
                        this female figure and one in the watercolor version (done for Thomas Butts)
                        of Plate 14, “The Morning Stars Sang Together,” of
                        Blake’s <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>; the
                        similarity is pointed out by Pointon, who claims erroneously that the
                        figures are the same person (p. 171, n. 102). The female in <hi rend="i">Job</hi> also
                        leads a red, blue, and scaled serpent-team much like
                        Blake’s H serpent-team, and also rides under a crescent moon.
                        However, the female figure has wings. For a color reproduction, see Kathleen
                        Raine, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (New York: Praeger, 1971), p.
                        165.</note>
                    <note id="n23">
                        <hi rend="s">23</hi> Blake’s references to Hecate are
                        on the following pages in the <hi rend="i">Complete Writings</hi>: 41, 840,
                        849, 855 (three references). Versions of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> are in the
                        Huntington Art Gallery, the Tate Gallery, and
                        the National Gallery of Scotland. Raine provides a black and white
                        reproduction of the Tate version (p. 86); the Huntington version is
                        reproduced in black and white as “The Triple Hecate” in
                        the Library’s <hi rend="i">Catalogue of William
                        Blake’s Drawings and Paintings in the Huntington
                        Library</hi>, C. H. Collins Baker, enl. and rev. R. R. Wark (San Marino,
                        Calif.: The Huntington Library, 1969), pl. XXXV; it is also reproduced in
                        <hi rend="i">The Huntington Library Quarterly</hi>, 18 (May 1955). Blake
                        refers to a Hecate “drawing” or
                        “cartoon” (<hi rend="i">Complete Writings</hi>, p. 855) by
                        George Romney in his possession in 1804 (p. 849) and which he claims was
                        both well executed and well known (p. 855). This Romney <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> may
                        have influenced his own portrayals of the goddess;
                        certainly it must bear a relationship to the <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> Hecate,
                        for Blake describes it as “the figure with the torch and
                        snake” (p. 840). I have been unable to locate Romney’s
                        drawing, despite the able assistance of Shirley Martin of the Univ. of Maine
                        library at Farmington, who has made inquiries for me at Yale and Princeton,
                        which hold major Romney collections, and at Huntington, Frick, Courtland,
                        and Tate. Jean H. Hagstrum kindly referred my inquiry to his former student
                        Warren Jones, who is currently working on the Blake color-printed drawings
                        of 1795; Jones made inquiries of Martin Butlin and of Ann Crookshank, a
                        leading Romney authority. Jones thinks Blake may have owned it, Butlin
                        believes that it probably belonged to Hayley, and Miss Crookshank surmises
                        that it is probably lost among the numerous Romney drawings scattered
                        throughout the world.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Hecate’s identity proliferates in the later Classical poets, whose
                    view Milton follows (Osgood, p. 29). She is identified as Artemis,
                    Apollo’s twin sister and daughter of Zeus and Leto, and is said to
                    possess three identities: Selene (or Luna or Cynthia) in the sky, Artemis (or
                    Diana) on earth, and Proserpina (or Hecate) in hell and on the earth at
                    night.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref> 
                    She later becomes identified with malignant divinity, witchcraft (Osgood, p. 29), and 
                    terror.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref> 
                    Moreover, she represents choice and
                    uncertainty: “She was associated with deeds of darkness, the Goddess of
                    the Crossways, which were held to be ghostly places of evil magic. . . . In her
                    is shown most vividly the uncertainty between good and evil which is apparent in
                    every one of the divinities” (Hamilton, p. 32). <note id="n24">
                        <hi rend="s">24</hi> Edith Hamilton, <hi rend="i">Mythology</hi> (1940; rpt.
                        New York: New American Library, 1969), p. 31; see also Alastair
                        Fowler’s note, <hi rend="i">The Poems of Milton</hi>, ed. John
                        Carey and Fowler (London: Longman, 1968), p. 26.</note>
                    <note id="n25">
                        <hi rend="s">25</hi> Charles M. Gayley, <hi rend="i">The
                            Classical Myths in English Literature</hi>, 3rd ed. (Boston: Ginn,
                        1894), p. 84.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Blake’s decision to switch Cotytto for Hecate in B must be regarded as
                    a significantly different view of the masque—a second interpretation
                    that does not necessarily supersede the first. If Hecate now rides to attend the
                    Banquet of B 5, she would appear to supersede Cotytto as the reigning evil deity
                    over this and other B scenes, leaving Cotytto’s whereabouts a puzzle.
                    If we consider the masque again chronologically, she cannot be attending Comus
                    in B 1 during the events of B 4 because both B 1 and B 2 are past when B 4
                    occurs. Perhaps Blake thought of her as switching roles with Hecate and present
                    but not visible in B 2. The text, as discussed above, emphasizes the sorcery
                    (and by extension, Hecate) in the second scenes; yet in B 2 Blake does not
                    include (as he does in H) the visual emblem of 
<pb id="p12-169" n="169"/>
                    <figure n="but527.1.4.wc" id="but527.1.wc.04" work-copy="but527.1" rend="db" width="813" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
                        <head>Scene 4: “The Brothers Meet the Attendant Spirit in the
                            Wood.”</head>
                        <figDesc>Huntington.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <pb id="p12-170" n="170"/>
                    <figure n="but528.1.4.wc" id="but528.1.wc.04" work-copy="but528.1" rend="db" width="781" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>WBlake</figTranscr>
                        <head>Scene 4: “The Brothers Meet the Attendant Spirit in the
                            Wood.”</head>
                        <figDesc>Boston.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <pb id="p12-171" n="171"/>
magic, the <hi rend="i">haemony</hi>, and thus
                    appears to de-emphasize the elements of enchantment.</p>
                <p>Hecate’s visual presence in the B designs draws attention away from
                    the themes Cotytto represents as it emphasizes the importance of sorcery and the
                    supernatural: the Attendant Spirit, Comus’s wand, the cup with
                    transmogrifying liquor, the monsters, the spells on the travelers and later on
                    the Lady, the enchanted herb, and Sabrina’s counter-spell releasing
                    the Lady. As Goddess of the Crossroads, Hecate also reinforces the theme of
                    choice, of the difficulty of making decisions in a deceptive world. A
                    cross-examination of all sixteen designs in terms of these motifs reveals a
                    general consistency: the H series usually emphasizes sensuality and the threat
                    of sexual force, as well as a strict virginity opposing that threat, rather than
                    the elements of witchcraft, deception, and choice. In the B series, the emphasis
                    is generally the reverse.</p>
                <figure n="but527.1.5.wc" id="but527.1.wc.05" work-copy="but527.1" rend="db" width="821" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
</figure>
                <figure n="but528.1.5.wc" id="but528.1.wc.05" work-copy="but528.1" rend="db" width="788" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>WBlake</figTranscr>
                    <head>Scene 5: “The Magic Banquet with the Lady
                        Spell-Bound.”</head>
                    <figDesc>Huntington, left; Boston, right.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p>In H 1 a stress on sexuality is apparent in the nudity of Comus and the
                    wolf-headed monster; in B all the figures are clad. Comus’s body is
                    more muscular than in B, and therefore more sexual and more <corr type="emend">threatening</corr>. The Lady
                    clasps her hands between her breasts (even more pronounced in H 5 where she
                    folds her hands protectively over her breasts), highlighting the theme of
                    defensive virginity; in B 1 her hands are unclasped and held away from her body.
                    Elements of sorcery in B are suggested by the attention Blake affords to the cup
                    with the magic potion: Comus holds it high and appears to be casting a spell
                    over it with his powerful wand; in H, however, the cup is not nearly so
                    conspicuous in the hand of the hog-monster. Also, the right foot of this female
                    monster is cloven, suggesting the demonic; but in H it is 
                    not.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref>
                    <note id="n26">
                        <hi rend="s">26</hi> This detail, apparent in the original, is
                        not so visible in reproductions: my copy of A. Fletcher’s color
                        reprints fails to show the clearly differentiated toes of the H
                        female’s left foot, making <hi rend="i">it</hi> appear cloven,
                        and his reprint of B is not sufficiently clear to show the
                        figure’s seemingly cloven left foot. The reproduction of H in the
                        Huntington catalog cited above is much clearer.</note>
                </p>
                <p>In H 2 the sexuality-virginity emphasis continues with an aged but still muscular
                    Comus in disguise: his neck and right arm are bullish, his frame solid; in B
                    Comus is noticeably younger and his build slighter. The Lady in H appears
                    distressed, fearful, anxious, and holds her upraised hands close to her body; in
                    B she displays no such worried expression, and her upraised hands are away from
                    her body in a less-threatened, more relaxed pose. Seemingly inconsistent with
                    Blake’s emphasis in H, as noted previously, is the appearance of 
                    <hi rend="i">haemony</hi> in the Spirit’s hand, an emblem of the
                    supernatural.</p>
                <p>Neither version of Scene 3 stresses sexuality over sorcery. The H Comus now
                    appears younger, the 
                    <pb id="p12-172" n="172"/>
                    <figure n="but527.1.6.wc" id="but527.1.wc.06" work-copy="but527.1" rend="db" width="798" height="1000">
						<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
						WB</figTranscr>
					</figure>
                    <figure n="but528.1.6.wc" id="but528.1.wc.06" work-copy="but528.1" rend="db" width="800" height="1000">
						<figTranscr>WBlake</figTranscr>
                        <head>Scene 6: “The Brothers Driving out Comus.”</head>
                        <figDesc><corr type="emend">Huntington, upper<gap type="emend" rend="plain"/>; Boston, lower<gap type="emend" rend="plain"/>.</corr></figDesc>
                    </figure> 
                    B Comus older (as shown by the lines in his face and neck).</p>
                <p>H 5 continues the muscular Comus; the B Comus is delicate, effeminate. However,
                    both are clothed, although thinly. Yet Comus in H is barefooted, with his right
                    foot close to the Lady’s and the big toe oddly short and raised
                    toward her. The H Lady covers her breasts in defense of her virginity, and she
                    sits in a chair with carvings of three bare-breasted female figures entwined
                    apparently with serpents; the carvings plainly embody the sensual temptation
                    that Comus is offering the Lady, and they contrast well with the
                    Lady’s defensive posture. The carved figures are absent in the B
                    chair, and the Lady’s hands are relaxed on her thighs. An emphasis in
                    B on sorcery can be seen in Blake’s positioning of the magic cup.
                    Just as in B 1, Blake in B 5 draws attention to it: Comus holds it high enough
                    to outline it clearly against the plain column behind; in H, Comus holds it so
                    low that its lines blend with those of Comus’s arm, hand, cape, the
                    bird-monster behind, and the covered dish below, which repeats the triangular
                    shape of the cup’s pedestal, reverses the shape of the cup itself,
                    and therewith obscures it. Also highlighting the sorcery in B is the visionary
                    and amazing serpent above Comus’s wand; clearly designed to represent
                    the spell Comus is casting over the Lady, the snake has no body apart from that
                    suggested by the lines of a nearly invisible two-layered cloud over the Lady.
                    Finally, the oddly shaped carafe held on a platter by the strange dwarf, to
                    which Comus points his wand, seems to reinforce the element of magic. The
                    cat-monster to the Lady’s left also holds an unusual container
                    apparently containing transforming liquid. Perhaps with the cup and these two
                    containers Blake is amplifying the text in providing Comus with several choices
                    for the Lady.</p>
                <p>In H 6 Comus is again more muscular than in B, and naked (as in H 1); the B Comus
                    is still clothed. Again the Lady in H tightly covers her breasts as she sits in
                    the carved chair; in B her hands still rest on her thighs. Suggestions of
                    sorcery are present in both versions: in B the four vanishing faces below
                    Comus’s wand are evil and demonic, especially the lowest one; in H
                    the faces, from bottom up, are a point-eared human face that seems to be
                    breathing red flames toward the brothers (Milton’s stage directions
                    after line 813 specify that the monsters give a show of resistance); a
                    bird-monster like that in B 5 (nearest the Lady); another human face, this one
                    with stubby horns; and above the wand, a long-eared horse head (from lines
                    553-54?).</p>
                <pb id="p12-173" n="173"/>
                <p>Neither seventh scene emphasizes sensuality. B suggests Sabrina’s
                    magic power more than H: she is covered by a bright rainbow at the end of which
                    sits the Lady; and Sabrina’s magic drops to purify the Lady are
                    emphasized visually by the shell in which she carries the 
                    liquid.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref> 
                    In H she merely holds her hand over the Lady’s head. 
                    <note id="n27">
                        <hi rend="s">27</hi>
                            Sabrina’s purification rite (910-21) does not mention a
                            shell, but much earlier the Lady alludes to one in her lovely song,
                            song, “Sweet Echo”: 
                            <q> “<hi rend="i">Sweet
                                    Echo, sweetest Nymph that liv’st unseen / Within thy
                                    airy shell / By slow Meander’s margent green</hi> 
                                . . . ” (230-32). </q>
                            Blake’s shell in B 7 thus
                            stresses visually Sabrina’s identity as a water nymph; but
                            more important, it ties Sabrina to the Lady’s early plea to
                            the Nymph Echo for assistance in finding her brothers, consequently
                            involving Sabrina from the very beginning of the Lady’s
                            confrontation with evil.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Neither eighth scene emphasizes sensuality. But the magical is clearly the
                    highlight of B, wherein the departing Attendant Spirit is executed with a
                    delicacy and a translucence complementing the brightness of the scene and giving
                    the sensation that one can almost see through him, that he is dissolving into
                    the air.</p>
                <p>Blake’s two series for <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, then, are
                    considerations of the masque from different viewpoints. The masque itself is
                    particularly rich in connotations of both the sexuality-virginity theme and the
                    theme of witchcraft, magic, and the supernatural. The visual representatives of
                    these themes—the reigning powers of this particular night during
                    which the chaste Lady is in serious danger of seduction—are Cotytto
                    in H and Hecate in B. Blake’s use of these two pagan goddesses to
                    represent themes he accentuates fairly consistently throughout the two series
                    not only illuminates the masque by focusing attention on Milton’s
                    themes, but also highlights Blake’s own perception that Cotytto and
                    Hecate as powers of evil are at the very center of Milton’s drama in
                    which good and evil clash openly and forcibly, and in which both Milton and
                    Blake ultimately assert the necessity of making a proper choice between the
                    two.</p>
				<figure n="but527.1.7.wc" id="but527.1.wc.07" work-copy="but527.1" rend="db" width="837" height="1000">
					<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
					WB</figTranscr>
				</figure>
				<figure n="but528.1.7.wc" id="but528.1.wc.07" work-copy="but528.1" rend="db" width="787" height="1000">
					<figTranscr>WBlake</figTranscr>
					<head>Scene 7: “Sabrina Disenchanting the Lady.”</head>
					<figDesc><corr type="emend">Huntington, upper; Boston, lower.</corr></figDesc>
				</figure>
				<pb id="p12-174" n="174" rend="hidden"/>
				<pb id="p12-175" n="175"/>
				<figure n="but527.1.8.wc" id="but527.1.wc.08" work-copy="but527.1" rend="db" width="819" height="1000">
					<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
					WB</figTranscr>
				</figure>
				<pb id="p12-176" n="176"/>
				<figure n="but528.1.8.wc" id="but528.1.wc.08" work-copy="but528.1" rend="db" width="778" height="1000">
					<figTranscr>WBlake</figTranscr>
				</figure>
				<pb id="p12-177" n="177" rend="hidden"/>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
