<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.3.bindman</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="minute">A New Blake Drawing in the Boston Museum of Fine Art</title>
                <author n="Bindman">David Bindman</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1978-79</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978-79</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Production Office</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>E. B. Bentley</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>David Bindman</name>
                            <name>Izak Bouwer</name>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>Arnold Cheskin</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>Martha Winburn England</name>
                            <name>J. Karl Franson</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>David Irwin</name>
                            <name>Paul McNally</name>
                            <name>Marta Slowikova</name>
                            <name>Robert R. Wark</name>
                            <name>Kazumitsu Watarai</name>
                            <name>Dwight Weber</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1979"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-3-0010">
                <pb id="p12-205" n="205"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">A NEW BLAKE DRAWING IN THE BOSTON MUSEUM OF FINE ART</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="b">David</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">Bindman</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>The pages of this journal have frequently recorded the reappearance of early
                        Blake drawings and I am happy to add another one, this time in the Boston
                        Museum of Fine Art.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n96"
type="note">1</ref> It is a large
                        double-sided sheet measuring 30.2 × 48.2 cm and the recto (illus.
                        1) contains a fine study of <hi rend="i">Goliath cursing David</hi> in pen
                        over a pencil underdrawing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n97"
type="note">2</ref> There can
                        be no doubt that it is an early drawing, dating from the early 1780s, but it
                        contains in all essentials the composition of the Butts watercolor of the
                        same subject, dated by Butlin c. 1803-05 (illus. 3). Other early drawings
                        are often crude foreshadowings of later motifs, and we begin to see from
                        them why Blake could claim in the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>
                        that “the productions of our youth and of our maturer age are equal
                        in all essential points.” <note id="n96">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi> I
                            would like to thank the staff of the Print Room at the Boston Museum who
                            so kindly showed me the drawing and Martin Butlin who confirmed the
                            attribution and provided the information on the provenance. The drawing
                            will appear in his forthcoming catalogue raisonné as no.
                            119A.</note>
                        <note id="n97">
                            <hi rend="s">2</hi> Museum no. 14. 955.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The verso (illus. 2) is much less finished but contains a motif, otherwise
                        unknown in Blake’s 
                        <figure n="but119a.1.1r.pid" id="but119Ar.1.penink.01" work-copy="pid" rend="db" width="958" height="611">
							<figTranscr/>
                            <head>1 W. Blake, <hi rend="i">Goliath cursing David</hi> (I Samuel, 17:
                                41-43).</head>
                            <figDesc>Courtesy Museum of Fine Art, Boston, Gift of David Keppel,
                                1914.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        oeuvre, of a Pulchinello-like figure with a long nose fighting a
                        child which appears to cling to its mother. The form on the left seems to be
                        a kind of boat reflected in water, but the connection with the rest of the
                        design is unclear. Again the style suggests an early date.</p>
                    <p>An inscription on the verso tells us that the drawing belonged to the
                        well-known Blake collection of Henry Cunliffe from whose sale it was bought
                        by Keppel and subsequently given to the Museum by David Keppel in 1914.
                        According to Martin Butlin the drawing passed with others from Mrs. Blake to
                        Frederick Tatham, and it was in lot 170 at his sale on 29 April 1862, where
                        it was bought with five others for 14/-by Toovey for Henry Cunliffe.</p>
                    <p>One might ask why Blake’s early drawings have so often gone
                        unrecognized even in major collections. We can now appreciate their seminal
                        qualities and 
<pb id="p12-206" n="206"/>
                        <figure n="BUT119A.1.1v.PD" rend="file" width="958" height="610">
                            <head>2 Verso of illus. 1</head>
                        </figure>
                        <figure n="but457.1.1.wc" id="but457.1.wc.01" work-copy="biblicalwc" rend="db" width="958" height="911">
							<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
							WB</figTranscr>
                            <head>3 W. Blake, <hi rend="i">Goliath cursing David</hi>,
                                watercolor.</head>
                            <figDesc>Courtesy Museum of Fine Art, Boston.</figDesc>
                        </figure> 
                        enjoy their individuality of handling, but it must be admitted
                        that they are rather crude if compared to those of his contemporaries like
                        Stothard and Flaxman. Although Blake was not an autodidact, the originality
                        of the motifs tends to outstrip his mechanical abilities, which were
                        evidently not finely honed by constant drawing from the model. As a result
                        there are often embarrassing defects in Blake’s early drawings
                        which have led connoisseurs to dismiss them as inferior examples by one of
                        the many unidentified English Neoclassical artists of the late eighteenth
                        century. No doubt they will continue to turn up in odd places, and we might
                        well find among them more early prototypes for mature compositions.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
