<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.3.wark</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Morton D. Paley, William Blake</title>
                <author n="Wark">Robert R. Wark</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1978-79</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978-79</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Production Office</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>E. B. Bentley</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>David Bindman</name>
                            <name>Izak Bouwer</name>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>Arnold Cheskin</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>Martha Winburn England</name>
                            <name>J. Karl Franson</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>David Irwin</name>
                            <name>Paul McNally</name>
                            <name>Marta Slowikova</name>
                            <name>Robert R. Wark</name>
                            <name>Kazumitsu Watarai</name>
                            <name>Dwight Weber</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1979"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
            <pb id="p12-211" n="211"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-3-0011">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <figure n="PaleyWilliamBlake.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="371"/>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Morton D. Paley. <hi rend="b">William Blake.</hi> Oxford: Phaidon
                            Press. New York: E. P. Dutton, 1978. 192 pp. + 148 black-and-white
                            illustrations, 15 in color. $19.95.</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="b">Robert R.</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">Wark</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>Readers of this journal are well aware of the quantity and complexity of
                        studies related to Blake. They are probably also aware that the rapid
                        proliferation of these often recondite monographs tends to build a wall
                        around Blake, cutting him off from the general public and even from the
                        interested but non-specialist student. It is necessary that this wall be
                        breached periodically if Blake is not to become a remote cult image,
                        familiar only to a coterie of initiates. Morton Paley’s Phaidon
                            <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> is a praiseworthy attempt to provide
                        this access for people who are not inside the camp of regular Blakeans.</p>
                    <p>The book is physically well-designed for its purpose. Produced in the normal
                        Phaidon monograph format, it consists of sixty-four pages of text with
                        forty-seven text illustrations; a section of one hundred and sixteen plates
                        with fifteen in color; a convenient chronology; a glossary; and a separate
                        section of notes on the plates. The plates are of fine quality; the text is
                        spaciously printed; the book is a pleasure to handle.</p>
                    <p>To provide a brief, general introduction to Blake that is also valid is a
                        formidable task. Ideally the person undertaking it should be a Blake
                        specialist, familiar with the enormous literature on the man, but at the
                        same time able to extricate himself sufficiently from this terrain to map
                        its general contours clearly for the non-specialist. He should be equally at
                        home with the visual and verbal components of Blake’s art, and
                        familiar with the currents of late eighteenth century thought, history, and
                        culture with which Blake came in contact. Paley comes close to being such a
                        paragon, although he is perhaps too much the specialist to be sensitive to
                        every point at which the layman and non-specialist need guidance.</p>
                    <p>Paley chooses a biographical framework for his text, but allows himself
                        sufficient flexibility to discuss coherent topics within that framework.
                        It’s a sensible solution to the problem of organization that
                        works well for the task at hand. There are ten sections: (1)
                        Blake’s early life, training, and work down to 1790. (2) The
                        Lambeth books, to the mid-1790s (this is the longest section). (3) The
                        color-printed monotypes, and illustrations to <hi rend="i">Night
                            Thoughts</hi> and Gray. (4) The Felpham episode. (5) Return to London,
                            <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, Canterbury Pilgrims. (6) Blake’s
                        thoughts on art. (7) Bible illustrations. (8) <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and
                        the illustrations to Milton’s poems. (9) <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> (10) Job and
Dante. A large amount of information is
                        packed into the text; there is no significant aspect of Blake’s
                        work of potential interest to the non-specialist that is not touched on.</p>
                    <p>Ideally the person to measure the success of the book should be a member of
                        the audience to whom it is presumably directed, the interested layman with
                        no special knowledge of Blake or his art. The present reviewer is an art
                        historian, concerned with Blake in the general context of Georgian art, but
                        not a Blake specialist. I find it interesting that Paley, who is an
                        historian of literature, gives more of his text to an explication of the
                        visual than the verbal side of Blake. He provides what I find a clear,
                        consistently well-informed account of Blake’s artistic training,
                        of his affiliations with older artists (such as Barry, Fuseli, and Mortimer)
                            <pb id="p12-212" n="212"/>
and with those of his own generation (such as
                        Flaxman and Stothard). His remarks on Blake’s frequently complex
                        technical procedures are brief but lucid. The section on Blake’s
                        theory of art is unusually well-balanced and perceptive, especially in
                        assessing Blake’s thought relative to Reynolds’s.
                        Furthermore, I find it reasurring to read a Blake specialist who is aware of
                        his hero’s limitations as an artist and does not feel obliged to
                        justify or explain away these weaknesses. There should be more on the
                        general stylistic and formal affiliations of Blake’s art, how
                        Blake relates to the general currents of late eighteenth century British and
                        European art. But this aside, Paley seems to me to do an admirable job of
                        telling the interested layman what he will want to know about the visual
                        side of Blake. The bulk of the text is devoted to explanations of individual
                        plates and designs. Paley also demonstrates the various ways in which the
                        visual and verbal interrelate in the illuminated books, choosing a series of
                        plates from <hi rend="i">America</hi> as the primary vehicle for this
                        purpose.</p>
                    <p>I did not find a comparable overview of the verbal component of Blake. Paley
                        seems to assume a much broader knowledge of late eighteenth century British
                        poetry in general and of Blake’s poetry in particular than he
                        does for the visual side. Nor did I find any general assessment of
                        Blake’s intellectual position relative to his contemporaries. The
                        text is richly sprinkled with penetrating remarks on both these matters. But
                        they nearly all deal with particulars—the interpretation of an
                        individual page or verse. There are illuminating paragraphs on
                        Blake’s relations with the Swedenborgians. There is nearly always
                        a helpful sentence or two about the theme of a particular poem. But the
                        interested layman looking for guidelines in approaching the verbal component
                        of Blake’s art will find less than for the visual. Obviously
                        Paley is well qualified to supply this information. That it is not there may
                        be the result of unconscious assumptions concerning the audience for the
                        book. Or perhaps the expected audience is students of literature already
                        familiar with the verbal side of Blake, seeking a guide to the visual. I
                        think the book meets admirably the needs of this last group, but is not yet
                        the ideal answer for those unfortunates totally beyond the pale.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
