<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.3.bouwer</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="article">“The Mental Traveller”: Man’s Eternal Journey</title>
                <author n="Bouwer">Izak Bouwer</author>
                <author n="McNally">Paul McNally</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1978-79</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978-79</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Production Office</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>E. B. Bentley</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>David Bindman</name>
                            <name>Izak Bouwer</name>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>Arnold Cheskin</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>Martha Winburn England</name>
                            <name>J. Karl Franson</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>David Irwin</name>
                            <name>Paul McNally</name>
                            <name>Marta Slowikova</name>
                            <name>Robert R. Wark</name>
                            <name>Kazumitsu Watarai</name>
                            <name>Dwight Weber</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1979"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
            <pb id="p12-184" n="184"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-3-0007">
                <head>
                    <title type="main">
                        <hi rend="b">“THE MENTAL TRAVELLER”: MAN’S
                            ETERNAL JOURNEY</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="b">IZAK</hi>
                        <name>
                            <hi rend="b">BOUWER</hi>
                        </name>
                    </docAuthor>
                    <hi rend="b">&amp;</hi>
                    <docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="b">PAUL</hi>
                        <name>
                            <hi rend="b">McNALLY</hi>
                        </name>
                    </docAuthor>
                </byline>
				<q>
                    <hi rend="b">The spiritual States of the Soul are all Eternal Distinguish
                        between the man, &amp; his present State</hi> (Jerusalem <hi rend="b">52, E198,
K681</hi>)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">1</ref>
				</q>
				<note id="n48">
					<hi rend="s">1</hi> Our main reference for Blake’s
					work is D. V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William
					Blake</hi> (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1965), hereafter referred to
					parenthetically in the text as “E” followed by a page
					number. “K” followed by a page number indicates the
					location of a passage in G. Keynes, ed., <hi rend="i">Blake: Complete
					Writings</hi> (London: Oxford University Press, 1969).</note>
                <p><corr type="emend">“The</corr> Mental Traveller” describes a cycle in which two figures, one male
                    and one female, grow from infancy to old age and back to infancy again. Each
                    grows younger as the other grows older, so that each is oldest when the other is
                    at the point of birth. This curious round of change becomes understandable when
                    we realize that the figures personify two complementary principles. However, the
                    interpretation of these principles and of their cycle of change has proved to be
                    puzzling and controversial. Of two main critical traditions, the earlier
                    represents the cycle as essentially prototypical of cyclic process, and in
                    particular of historical 
                    cycles.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">2</ref> 
                    Such a generalizing approach is out of character for Blake, and the cyclic 
                    processes of history are certainly within the grasp of “cold Earth
                    wanderers,” while this cycle is explicitly said to go beyond their
                    knowledge. However, this tradition incorporates, in a simple and natural way,
                    the fact that each principle develops to its fullest manifestation and then
                    diminishes in the face of the growing opposing principle. The later tradition
                    involves interpretations in terms of the so-called “Orc
                    cycle”: the Male Babe personifies revolt (Orc) and ages into a
                    personification of oppression 
                    (Urizen).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">3</ref>
                    Such a cycle is complete half way through the poem, and in spite of various
                    attempts to interpret the Female Babe, the second half of Blake’s
                    cycle remains logically 
                    impertinent.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">4</ref> 
                    In both traditions, the cycle is seen as repeating. 
                    <note id="n49">
                        <hi rend="s">2</hi> This tradition had its starting point with W. M. Rossetti in
                        Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (1880: rpt. New
                        York: Phaeton Press, 1969), II, 112-13, and with E. J. Ellis and W. B.
                        Yeats, <hi rend="i">The Works of William Blake</hi> (1893; rpt. New York:
                        AMS Press, 1973), II, 34-36. It was further developed, indirectly, by W. B.
                        Yeats, <hi rend="i">A Vision</hi> (London: Macmillan, 1937), and, directly,
                        by Kathleen Raine, <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi>, I, 302-25.</note>
                    <note id="n50">
                        <hi rend="s">3</hi> The “Orc cycle” tradition
                        was initiated by Northrop Frye in <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi>
                        (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1947), p. 229, and has been taken up
                        by a number of scholars, including John H. Sutherland,
                        “Blake’s ‘Mental Traveller’,” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi>, 22 (1955), 136-47, 
                        reprinted in Judith O’Neill, ed., <hi rend="i">Critics on Blake</hi> 
                        (London: Allen &amp; Unwin, 1970), pp. 69-78; Morton D. Paley, “The Female
                        Babe and ‘The Mental Traveller’,” <hi rend="i">SiR</hi>, 1 (1962), 97-104,
                        incorporated, in somewhat altered
                        form, in Chapter 5 of Paley’s <hi rend="i">Energy and the
                        Imagination</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1970), pp. 122-41; and Hazard
                        Adams, <hi rend="i">William Blake: A Reading of the Shorter Poems</hi>
                        (Seattle: University of Washington Press, 1963), pp. 77-100. In 
                        <hi rend="i">Anatomy of Criticism</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press,
                        1957), pp. 322-23, Frye expresses a view more akin to the earlier
                        tradition.</note>
                    <note id="n51">
                        <hi rend="s">4</hi> Frye (<hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi>, p.
                        444, n. 7) expressed dissatisfaction with his own reading of the Female Babe
                        as “imaginative achievements,” a reading followed by
                        Sutherland and Adams, and later (<hi rend="i">Anatomy of Criticism</hi>, p.
                        322) he identifies the female figure with “the natural
                        environment.” Paley (“Blake’s ‘The
                        Mental Traveller’,” pp. 100-01), who points out the
                        significance of the concept of the Female Babe, finds Frye’s
                        later reading also unsatisfactory, and sees her instead as a united form of
                        the “numerous evil females of Blake’s
                        pantheon.”</note>
                </p>
                <p>The reading we give in this paper follows the earlier tradition to the extent
                    that each principle is seen as aging into a mature form of itself. However, our
                    reading differs from that of the earlier tradition in that the cycle is
                    specifically seen as the theological cycle of Man’s fall from and
                    return to Eden. It is our aim to show that “The Mental
                    Traveller” portrays the successive states through which Man passes on
                    his eternal journey, as determined by the complementary interplay of two
                    principles in him: the Spiritual, expressed through his imaginative faculty, and
                    the Natural, expressed through his earthly 
                    nature.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">5</ref> 
                    This theme of Man’s eternal journey was of profound
                    importance to Blake, and inspires his entire mythology, so that the poem emerges
                    as a compact counterpart to his major work, and a summary of his spiritual
                    vision. 
                    <note id="n52">
                        <hi rend="s">5</hi> We thus agree with John Sampson, 
                        <hi rend="i">The Poetical Works of William Blake</hi> (1905; rpt. Boston:
                        Milford House, 1973), p. 273: “The poem . . . must be understood as
                        a picture of man’s spirit, passing through successive mental
                        states, and at last returning, ‘in endless circle,’ to
                        the point from which he started. In other words it is a restatement of
                        Blake’s favourite doctrine of constant generation and
                        regeneration.” However, Sampson does not elaborate his
                    view.</note>
                </p>
                <p>It was Blake’s conviction that “Mental Things are alone
                    Real” (<hi rend="i">VLJ</hi>, E555, K617), and he considered it his
                    great task to “open the Eternal Worlds, to open the immortal Eyes / Of
                    Man inwards into the Worlds of Thought: into Eternity . . . ” 
                    (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 5:18-19, E146, K623). Whether we see the traveler as
                    the poet in his exploration of eternal reality, or as Man on his eternal
                    journey, the title of the poem indicates that the business of the poem is with
                    eternal things: “What are the Treasures of Heaven which we are to lay
                    up for ourselves, are they any other than Mental Studies &amp;
                    Performances? What are all the Gifts of the Gospel, are they not all Mental
                    Gifts?” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 77, E229, K717). It was also
                    Blake’s conviction that Man’s eternal states are
                    determined by a simple two-fold process in which truth is discovered as error is
                    destroyed: “All Life consists of these Two Throwing off Error
                    &lt;&amp;Knaves from our company&gt; continually &amp;
                    recieving Truth &lt;or Wise Men into our Company&gt;
                    Continually” (<hi rend="i">VLJ</hi>, E551, 
                    K612-13).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53" type="note">6</ref> 
                    This two-fold process extends logically to encompass the
                    entire myth of Man’s fall and redemption: in the period when error,
                    or the Natural principle, is dominant, the states of Man are those associated
                    with the fall and Man’s subsequent history in the dimensions of time
                    and space; in the period when truth, or the Spiritual principle, 
<pb id="p12-185" n="185"/>
                    <figure n="JourneyDiagram.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="513">
                    	<figTranscr>EDEN<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Man<lb/>
                    	awakening<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	APOCALYPSE<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	FALL<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Man<lb/>
                    	falling<lb/>
                    	asleep<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	INCARNATION<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	Figure 1</figTranscr>
                    </figure> 
                    is dominant, the states of Man are those associated with the
                    apocalypse and Man’s sojourn in 
                    paradise.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">7</ref> 
                    There is one state where there is no error, and in this
                    state Man is wholly divine and coincident with 
                    God.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">8</ref> 
                    This state, the state of Eden, closes the biblical narrative into a
                    circle.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">9</ref>
                    <note id="n53">
                        <hi rend="s">6</hi> “The Mental Traveller” and
                            <hi rend="i">A Vision of the Last Judgment</hi> are of about the same
                        period. Blake’s letter to Ozias Humphrey, explaining his design
                        of the Last Judgment, is dated 1808 (E544, K442), and the Notebook
                        descriptions are “For the Year 1810” (E544, K604). G. E.
                        Bentley, Jr., (cited in Paley, <hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination</hi>,
                        p. 122, n. 1) dates the entire Pickering manuscript, in which “The
                        Mental Traveller” appears, as no earlier than 1805.</note>
                    <note id="n54">
                        <hi rend="s">7</hi> In identifying the two components of Man as
                        “Spiritual” and “Natural,” we follow
                        Blake’s occasional usage. For instance: “The Natural
                        Body is an Obstruction to the Soul or Spiritual Body” (<hi rend="i">Anno.
                        Berkeley</hi>, E653, K775). Error is identified with Nature:
                        “Error or Creation will be Burned Up . . . ” (<hi rend="i">VLJ</hi>, E555,
                        K617).</note>
                    <note id="n55">
                        <hi rend="s">8</hi> Cf. “God is Man &amp; exists in
                        us &amp; we in him” (<hi rend="i">Anno. Berkeley</hi>, E654,
                        K775). For Blake’s theology, we refer the reader to Frye, 
                        <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi>, especially Chapter 2, “The
                        Rising God,” pp. 30-54. Another useful account is contained in
                        Albert S. Roe, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations to the Divine
                        Comedy</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1953), pp.
                        8-29.</note>
                    <note id="n56">
                        <hi rend="s">9</hi> We differ here from Frye 
                        (<hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi>, p. 386). He rejects the idea of
                        “pulling the Bible around in a circle” on the grounds that
                        that would imply unending time, which would pervert the biblical meaning of
                        the word “eternity.” However, the gap between the two ends
                        of the biblical narrative is included in Blake’s cycle and
                        transcends time.</note>
                </p>
                <p>We contend that “The Mental Traveller” describes this same
                    circle. Because Blake shows the continuity of states, the circle appears to be a
                    repetitive cycle, but is in fact merely complete. The poem is anti-Aristotelian
                    and, like eternity, has no beginning, middle, or end. In Blake’s
                    vision in the poem, Man, composed of contrary but complementary principles, is
                    seen as a continuous progression of states which in themselves form a unity, the
                    perfect form of the circle. The two principles in Man, the Spiritual and the
                    Natural, are personified, respectively, by the principal male and female figures
                    of the poem, the age of each representing the extent to which the corresponding
                    principle manifests in the being of Man. The cycle of the poem may be
                    graphically represented as in Figure 1.</p>
                <p>The poem begins at the point, shown at the bottom of the circle in Figure 1,
                    where the Natural principle is in its fullest manifestation, and the incarnation
                    of the Divine into the world of the Natural takes place. This incarnation is
                    represented by the birth of the Male Babe, who is most naturally associated with
                    Jesus. As the Spiritual gains in strength, the Natural principle becomes
                    correspondingly less dominant until, at the left-most point of the circle, it is
                    overpowered by the Spiritual principle. In the life-cycle of Man, this
                    overpowering of the Natural by the Divine corresponds to the spiritual awakening
                    of Man at the apocalypse. In the continuing process of the Last Judgment, the
                    errors of the natural world are progressively destroyed as eternal truths are
                    recognized. This process reaches its completion only when the natural delusion
                    has decreased to vanishing point and all creation is consumed. Here, at the
                    topmost point of the circle, Man finds himself in the state of Eden, where he is
                    coincident with God, the “Heavenly Father.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n57" type="note">10</ref> When the Natural principle reappears as the Female
                    Babe, it is in a growing phase, and increases in strength until, at the
                    right-most point of the circle, the Spiritual is drawn into its power. This
                    overpowering of the Divine by the Natural corresponds to the fall, where Man
                    sinks into a spiritual sleep.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58"
type="note">11</ref> The Natural
                    principle continues to gain in strength, while the Spiritual principle grows
                    correspondingly weaker, until Humanity identifies itself with purely natural
                    Man, who lives in the state of the earthly paradise, or lower garden. Thus we
                    arrive again at the point where the incarnation of the Spiritual principle is to
                    take place. <note id="n57">
                        <hi rend="s">10</hi> “ . . . the Spiritual
                        Body or Angel . . . always behold the Face of the Heavenly Father”
                            (<hi rend="i">Anno. Berkeley</hi>, E653, K774).</note>
                    <note id="n58">
                        <hi rend="s">11</hi> Just as the Last Judgment is seen as a
                        process lasting a full half-cycle (from the incarnation to the state of
                        Eden), so the fall is seen as a process lasting the remaining half-cycle
                        (from the state of Eden to the state where the incarnation takes place).
                        However, we use the word “fall” to denote the specific
                        stage of the process where the Natural principle attains dominance over the
                        Spiritual.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The images that Blake uses in the poem to express the varying relationships of
                    the two principles, especially at the cardinal points of the cycle, have their
                    parallels in the biblical narrative and are used in similar contexts elsewhere
                    in Blake’s work.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59"
type="note">12</ref> The torture of
                    the Male Babe is fairly closely paralleled in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (66:
                    17-33, E216, K702; 68:57-58, E220, K706-07). The sexual act as metaphoric
                    portrayal of the apocalypse (implicit in the biblical image of the Bride and
                    Bridegroom) is found as part of a prophetic vision in the
                    “Preludium” to <hi rend="i">America</hi> (2:3-4, E50-51,
                    K196). The banquet encountered towards the end of the quarter cycle leading to
                    the state of Eden (corresponding to the “supper of the great
                    God” at the Last Harvest and Vintage, in Rev. 19:17) is the golden
                    feast of the Eternals described in Night 9 of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
                    <pb id="p12-186" n="186"/> (E385-90, K372-78). The representation of the fall in
                    terms of a man drawn into the power of a woman (which is symbolically related to
                    the biblical theme of the Sons of God descending to the daughters of men, prior
                    to the Flood), is encountered in Night 1 of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
                    (5:13-14, E298, K266: 76-77) in the image of Tharmas sinking into the sea into
                    Enion’s woof. <note id="n59">
                        <hi rend="s">12</hi> The parallels for
                        imagery at the points of the fall, incarnation, and apocalypse have been
                        pointed out by various writers. Of these writers, Raine (<hi rend="i">Blake
                            and Tradition</hi>, I, 306-25) offers the most comprehensive
                        identifications. Raine has also been most successful in tracing
                        Blake’s imagery for the fall. In his earlier work, Blake,
                        possibly inspired by Thomas Taylor’s account of the Persephone
                        myth (see Raine, I, 67, 133), concentrates on the theme of the descent of
                        the soul, personified by a female figure (Lyca, Thel, Oothoon, the early
                        Vala).</note>
                </p>
                <p>Before we come to a more detailed discussion of the poem, we would like to refer
                    to passages from Henry Crabb Robinson’s record of conversations with
                    Blake<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n104" type="note">13</ref> which
help to clarify certain of Blake’s theological ideas
                    relevant to our reading of the poem.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60"
type="note">14</ref>
                    Robinson writes:“ . . . his philosophy he repeated—Denying
                    Causation asserting everything to be the work of God or the Devil, That there is
                    a constant falling off from God— Angels becoming Devils . . . Every
                    man has a Devil in him and the conflict is eternal between a man’s
                    Self and God . . . ” (BBR 318). The “constant” fall
                    is redeemed by Imagination, which Blake identifies with Jesus and God, as he
                    asserts in the <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> inscription: “The
                    Eternal Body of Man is the IMAGINATION. that is God himself The Divine Body
                    Jesus” (E271, K776). It is important to our reading of the poem to
                    realize that although Jesus, the Imagination, is one with God, they are
                    distinguished in the sense that Jesus <hi rend="i">becomes</hi> the Father. This
                    is explained by Blake in the following conversation delightfully recorded by
                    Robinson: 
					<q> . . . I had suggested . . . the <hi rend="i">impossibility</hi> of
                        supposing an immortal being created—An eternity a parte
                        post—without an eternity a parte ante . . . His eye brightened on
                        my saying this And he eagerly concurred—’To be sure it
                        is impossible—We are all coexistent with God—Members
                        of the Divine body—We are all partakers of the divine
                        nature’ . . . on my asking in what light he viewed the great
                        question concerning the Divinity of Jesus Christ He
                            said—‘<hi rend="i">He is the only
                        God.</hi>’—But then he
                        added—’And so am I and so are
                        you’—Now he had just before . . . been speaking of the
                        errors of Jesus Christ: ‘he was wrong in suffering himself to be
                        crucified. He should not have attacked the government; he had no business
                        with such matters.’ On my enquiring how he reconciled this with
                        the Sanctity &amp; divine qualities of Jesus—he said
                        ‘He was not then become the father.’ (BBR 310-11) </q>
                    Jesus, therefore, personifies to Blake the Spiritual principle in its early
                    stages, when it is still weak and at the mercy of the Natural. The Father is the
                    Spiritual principle when it is dominant and nature is subjugated. 
                    <note id="n104">
                        <hi rend="s">13</hi> Our quotations from
                        Crabb Robinson’s records are taken from G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969), hereafter
                        referred to as “BBR.” We silently incorporate
                        Bentley’s emendations of the punctuation, and write abbreviations
                        out in full.</note>
                    <note id="n60">
                        <hi rend="s">14</hi> While these two principles function as
                        though autonomous, the Spiritual is superior. In <hi rend="i">The Marriage
                            of Heaven and Hell</hi>, in the “Devil’s”
                        voice, Blake states as an error the notion “That Man has two real
                        existing principles Viz: a Body &amp; a Soul,” and that, on
                        the contrary, “that calld Body is a portion of Soul discernd by the
                        five Senses” (<hi rend="i">MHH</hi> 4, E34, K149). The Devil only
                        exists “by God’s permission” (BBR 318).
                        Kathleen Raine therefore rightly states that “There is only one
                        agent” (<hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi>, I, 313). It follows
                        that an apt visual image for representing the two components in Man is
                        provided by the complementary bright and dark parts of the moon’s
                        disk in its cycle of phases. The lunar symbolism has been elaborated upon by
                        Yeats in the construction of his theory of the double gyres in <hi rend="i">A
Vision</hi>, and Raine applies this theory in her reading of the
                        poem.</note>
                </p>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="b">II</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>No short reading of “The Mental Traveller” (E475-77,
                        K424-27) can do justice to its rich and varied allusions. We wish primarily
                        to associate the narrative in the poem with the biblical narrative,
                        indicating parallels in Blake’s other works where these appear
                        helpful, in order to show that the cycle of the poem is that of
                        Man’s eternal journey. Where we pass over details, we may be
                        understood to accept the excellent and generally thorough exegeses of the
                        poem by Raine, Paley, and Adams.</p>
                    <p>In the first stanza, Blake alludes to the visionary perspective adopted in
                        the poem: 
						<q> I traveld thro’ a Land of Men<lb/>
 A Land of Men
                            &amp; Women too<lb/>
 And heard &amp; saw such dreadful
                            things<lb/>
 As cold Earth wanderers never knew. </q>
“Men
                        &amp; Women,” as Sutherland points out
                        (“Blake’s ‘Mental
                        Traveller’,” p. 140), refers to eternal archetypes, and
                        it follows that the poet visited the regions of Man’s eternal
                        reality. In Blake, the eternal energies, such as the Zoas, have emanations,
                        to which they stand in a primary relationship, so that the eternal world is
                        a land of Men “&amp; Women too.” The
                        “dreadful” things recounted by the traveler are the events
                        of this land of eternal reality, which are awe-ful, or sublime. Earth
                        wanderers are “cold” because they are antipodally removed
                        from the fire in the spiritual hearth, which we meet in stanza 11.</p>
                    <p>The second stanza explains the events at the four cardinal points of the
                        cycle in terms of conception and birth. The lines “For there the
                        Babe is born in joy / That was begotten in dire woe” refer to both
                        of the births in the poem, that of the Boy, and that of the Female Babe. The
                        “joy” is experienced by the principle that is born anew,
                        for it is in a growing and assertive phase, and will triumph over the
                        opposing principle a quarter-cycle later. At the sexual encounter a
                        quarter-cycle earlier, the diminishing principle entered the
                        “womb” of the other, which to it is a “dire
                        woe.” The Boy is conceived at the fall, and the implication is
                        simply that Jesus is born of the flesh. Hence, in “To
                        Tirzah” Blake’s narrator can ask, “Thou Mother
                        of my Mortal part / . . . what have I to do with thee?” (E30,
                        K220), and in <hi rend="i">The Everlasting Gospel</hi> Blake writes of the
                        “Serpent Bulk of Natures dross” (E515, K749) which is to
                        be nailed to the cross. In the case of the Female Babe, the sexual encounter
                        is the “dire woe” of the apocalypse, when nature is
                        subjugated to the Eternal Imagination.</p>
                    <p>The first line of the third stanza, “And if the Babe is born a
                        Boy,” identifies the point at which Blake chooses to begin his
                        description of the traversal of the cycle, that of the incarnation of the
                        spirit into the natural world. Evidently, Blake is interested in charting
                        the “dreadful” events of the spirit, following it in its
                        cycle of evolution, from its birth, through subsequent growth, to its
                        decline. The diverse images of torture that follow evoke associations with
                        Prometheus, Orc, and as Raine suggests, with Dionysus (who was lacerated,
                        and who like Christ had a heavenly father and an earthly mother). However,
                        the most sustained reference is to the suffering of Christ (as is the case
                        in the parallel description in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 66). Incarnated
                        in the natural world, the spirit has to undergo the excruciating tensions of
                        the contraries operating in this world: The Old Woman cuts the
                        Boy’s heart out “To make it feel both cold &amp;
                        heat.” As the Boy grows older, thus stronger, his sufferings become
                        less intense. Since she lives “upon his 
<pb id="p12-187" n="187"/>
                        shrieks &amp; cries,” she is increasingly deprived of
                        sustenance, and in the process grows weaker and, paradoxically, younger and
                        more becoming, until, in the sixth stanza, she is a “Virgin
                        bright.” Thus nature, as she becomes suffused with the imaginative,
                        loses her threatening aspect and actually becomes the delight of the
                        Spiritual. The dialectic of nature and spirit thus moves towards
                        apocalypse.</p>
                    <p>The apocalypse is described, in the sixth stanza, in terms of the male
                        sexually overpowering the female. In this state, Man (or Albion) awakes and
                        begins to live imaginatively, aware of his divinity. The Spiritual
                        principle, now dominant, is able to control the natural world with
                        increasing ease and joy, where before the apocalypse it could express itself
                        in nature only through suffering. Before, the Old Woman’s fingers
                        numbered his every nerve (stanza five); now, he plants himself in all her
                        nerves, and she becomes his dwelling place (stanza seven). This natural
                        world, however, is shrinking, and as it shrinks, it yields up a harvest in
                        ever more concentrated form. Thus, in stanza 7 nature is reduced, through
                        spiritual husbandry, to a garden which bears its fruit abundantly, and in
                        stanza 8 to an earthly cottage, filled with treasure. Thus, as the treasure
                        is gathered in, it becomes purer, for its spiritual density increases, and
                        of smaller dimension, as error is removed. The nature of this treasure is
                        explained in stanza 9. It is the “gems of the Human Soul,”
                        described in images of suffering, drawn from courtly-love poetry:
                        “a lovesick eye,” “the lovers sigh,”
                        “the akeing heart” and “The martyrs
                        groan.” The treasure which nature delivers up is therefore that of
                        the spiritual loves and sufferings of Man on this earth. These have been
                        preserved, and are now brought forth, in ever purer form, to serve as food
                        for the Spiritual: “ . . . the gems of the Human Soul / . . . / . .
                        . are his meat . . . are his drink” (ninth and tenth stanzas).</p>
                    <p>The meaning of the first two lines of stanza eight is crucial, for divergent
                        interpretations of the poem hinge on it: “An aged Shadow soon he
                        fades / Wandring round an Earthly Cot.” In the tradition of
                        Rossetti—Ellis &amp; Yeats—Raine, the
                        “aged Shadow,” fading, is seen as effete, and in the Orc
                        cycle tradition, as restrictive. We suggest that “aged”
                        merely indicates that the Spiritual principle is nearing full manifestation
                        and greatest potency, just as the Female was most powerful when most old. To
                        the natural eye, however, the Spiritual when most manifest is paradoxically
                        least visible, thus becoming a “Shadow” that fades, as it
                        wanders around the last vestiges of the natural in a world that has become
                        nearly completely spiritual. Although eternal substance appears shadowy to
                        mortal man, the poet, the visionary traveler, knows that the world of the
                        Father is the “Imagination the real &amp; eternal World . . .
                        in which we shall live in our Eternal or Imaginative Bodies, when these
                        Vegetable Mortal Bodies are no more” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                        77, E229, K717). In this world, the “Land of Men,” the
                        “ . . . Inhabitants [are] walking up &amp; down in
                        Conversations concerning Mental Delights . . . Here they are . . .
                        Conversing with Eternal Realities as they Exist in the Human Imagination 
                        . . . ” (<hi rend="i">VLJ</hi>, E552, K613). Paradise is therefore
                        populated with eternal forms.</p>
                    <p>Like the Good Samaritan, the Spiritual nourishes the developing eternal forms
                        as well as the visiting poet: “He feeds the Beggar &amp; the
                        Poor / And the wayfaring Traveller / For ever open is his door”
                        (stanza 10). As Jesus becomes the beneficent Father, his hospitality is
                        reminiscent of the parable of the marriage feast, and of the miracle of the
                        feeding of the multitude. The grief that the Father experienced in nature
                        while he was the Son is transformed and experienced as joy by the guests:
                        “His grief is their eternal joy” (stanza 11). The joy of
                        the guests (whom we shall meet again “scatterd thro’ the
                        land” in stanza 16) is in antipodal contrast to the agony of the
                        Boy, whose sufferings fed the Old Woman.</p>
                    <p>As the last vestiges of nature, or error, disappear, the atmosphere at the
                        feast becomes that of an ale-house: “They make the roofs &amp;
                        walls to ring.” We are reminded of “The Little
                        Vagabond” in <hi rend="i">The Songs of Experience</hi>:
<q> But if
                            at the Church they would give us some Ale.<lb/>
 And a pleasant fire, our
                            souls to regale;<lb/>
 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
                            .<lb/>
 Then the Parson might preach &amp; drink &amp;
                            sing.<lb/>
 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
 And God
                            like a father rejoicing to see,<lb/>
 His children as pleasant and happy
                            as he:<lb/>
 Would have no more quarrel with the Devil . . .<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            (E26, K216) </q>
In the description of the golden feast, in <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>, Night 9, we find a similar allusion to
                        intoxication: 
						<q> Attempting to be more than Man We become less said
                            Luvah<lb/>
 As he arose from the bright feast drunk with the wine of
                            ages<lb/>
 His crown of thorns fell from his head . . .<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            (135:21-23, E388, K376:709-11) </q>
This recurring emphasis on drunken
                        revels in sacred context is explained by Blake’s remark to Henry
                        Crabb Robinson that “What are called the vices in the natural
                        world, are the highest sublimities in the spiritual world” (BBR
                        316).</p>
                    <p>Stanzas 10 and 11, then, describe the state of Eden. Here, there are no more
                        traces of the natural (thus, “no more quarrel with the
                        Devil”). The treasure has shrunk to its vanishing point, and the
                        eternal forms appear fully assembled as the “Family
                        Divine.” This family is the “Council of God”
                        which, omnipresent, watches over the “Body / Of Man” (<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>,
Night 4, 55:10-11, E330, K304: 247-48). The
                        divine family is not visible to mortal eyes. Here, in the state of Eden, the
                        dominant Zoa in Man is Urthona. S. Foster Damon (<hi rend="i">A Blake
                            Dictionary</hi>, 1965; rpt. New York: Dutton, 1971, p. 426) mentions
                        that Urthona never manifests in his own person, and is frequently called
                        “dark.”</p>
                    <p>In the process of the Last Judgment, “Error or Creation” is
                        “Burned Up” (<hi rend="i">VLJ</hi>, E555, K617). In stanza
                        11 we find fire in the hearth, the center of the divine dwelling.
                        Nature’s last vestiges have 
<pb id="p12-188" n="188"/>
                        disappeared into this fire, from which nature is reborn, phoenix-like, as
                        “A little Female Babe.” In stanza 12, she is said to be
                        “all of solid fire/And gems &amp; gold.” Solidity,
                        alien to fire, and characteristic of the natural, already indicates the
                        beginning of the fall. The “gems &amp; gold” which
                        filled the cottage in stanza 8 were associated there with the last
                        transfigured residue of the Natural. Now we encounter the same image once
                        again. It is one that Blake uses elsewhere in his work to describe the
                        adornment of the serpent form (for instance, <hi rend="i">VDA</hi> 8:7, E49,
                        K195), and here it gives a fleeting glimpse of the serpent’s
                        presence in Eden.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61"
type="note">15</ref>
                        <note id="n61">
                            <hi rend="s">15</hi> Viewing the infant Natural principle as
                            a serpent coiled around the “tree” of the fully
                            manifested spirit, we would, antipodally, view the infant Spiritual
                            principle as a serpent coiled around the “tree” of
                            fully manifested nature. This is supported in <hi rend="i">The Four
                                Zoas</hi>, Night 7 (a), where Orc is described as organizing a
                            serpent body and stretching up Urizen’s tree of mystery (80:
                            44, 81: 3-5, E349, K324: 152, 162-64). The first tree is the tree of
                            life, and the second tree is the tree of the knowledge of good and
                            evil.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The Natural principle, in its growing phase, is not susceptible to control:
                        “ . . . none his hand / Dares stretch to touch her Baby form / Or
                        wrap her in his swaddling-band” (stanza 12). By contrast, Jesus
                        submitted to swaddling clothes. In the previous quarter-cycle, approaching
                        Eden, nature was pleased to serve the Divine, as in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>:
<q>
The Female searches sea &amp; land for
                            gratifications to the<lb/>
 Male Genius: who in return clothes her in
                            gems &amp; gold<lb/>
 And feeds her with the food of Eden . .
                            .<lb/>
                            <lb/>
 (69:16-18, E221, K707) </q>
But now the situation
                        corresponds to that described in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night 9:
						<q> And Many Eternal Men sat at the golden feast to see<lb/>
 The female
                            form now separate They shudderd at the horrible thing<lb/>
 Not born for
                            the sport and amusement of Man but born to drink up all his powers<lb/>
                            They wept to see their shadows they said to one another this is Sin<lb/>
                            This is the Generative world they rememberd the Days of old.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            (133:5-9, E386, K373:621-25) </q>
In Robinson’s diary we
                        read: “On my inquiring whether the Devil would not be destroyed by
                        God as being of less power—he denied that God has any
                        power—Asserted that the Devil is eternally created not by
                        God—but by God’s permission” (BBR 318). In
                        view of this lack of power on the part of the Divine principle, the birth of
                        the Female Babe is thematically associated with the creation of Adam and
                        Eve, who will disobey the Father. Adam and Eve are to be seen as united in
                        forming the natural component. This tallies with Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi>
inscription: “Adam is only The
                        Natural Man &amp; not the Soul or Imagination” (E271, K776),
                        and with the Chapter titles of his Genesis manuscript: “Chapter 1
                        The Creation of the Natural Man / Chapter 11 The Natural Man divided into
                        Male &amp; Female . . . ” (E667, K933).</p>
                    <p>The growing Natural principle organizes whatever mental forms prove
                        susceptible to her influence: “But She comes to the Man she loves /
                        If young or old or rich or poor” (stanza 13). In this process the
                        “aged Host” is driven out, and he is now a beggar
                        “at another’s door,” rather than the earlier
                        benevolent host. He develops a need for companionship and turns to the
                        maiden. Coming at the stage just before the fall, this action is reminiscent
                        of the Genesis account of the Lord walking in the Garden in the cool of the
                        evening and calling out to Adam and Eve. The
                        Divine—“freezing,” since it has wandered far
                        from the spiritual hearth—now succumbs to the attraction of the
                        Natural, and the fall takes place: “The Cottage fades before his
                        sight / The Garden &amp; its lovely Charms” (stanza 15). With
                        the fall, Man’s perceptions undergo a radical change. His senses
                        conglobe and perceive everything in distorted fashion, round and bounded:
                        “For the Eye altering alters all / The Senses roll themselves in
                        fear / And the flat Earth becomes a Ball” (stanza 16). Blake states
                        elsewhere that “Reality was Forgot &amp; the Vanities of Time
                        &amp; Space only Rememberd &amp; calld Reality” (<hi rend="i">VLJ</hi>, E545, K605).
Thus it is that Man begins to live in
                        the fallen world of time and space: Albion has fallen asleep.</p>
                    <p>The living forms of the “Stars Sun Moon” now shrink away
                        (stanza 17), leaving an imaginative desert in which the heavenly bodies are
                        experienced only through Man’s fallen senses. There is no more
                        sustenance for the former guests (eternal forms), and they are
                        “scatterd thro’ the land” (stanza 16). There
                        is, however, mention of another banquet in stanza 18: 
						<q> The honey of her
                            Infant lips<lb/>
 The bread &amp; wine of her sweet smile<lb/>
 The
                            wild game of her roving Eye<lb/>
 Does him to Infancy beguile. </q>
This
                        banquet is the antipodal counterpart to the divine banquet and corresponds
                        to the feast of Los and Enitharmon, described in <hi rend="i">The Four
                            Zoas</hi>, Night 1: 
<q> The Earth spread forth her table wide. the Night
                            a silver cup<lb/>
 Fill’d with the wine of anguish . . .<lb/>
                            They eat the fleshly bread, they drank the nervous wine.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            (12:36-37, 44, E303, K273:347-48, 274:355) </q>
In stanzas 20-22 the
                        word “Love,” or a derivative, occurs four times: the food
                        of the banquet is that of natural love.</p>
                    <p>Nature continues to be alluring and is pursued by the spirit: 
					<q> Like the
                            wild Stag she flees away<lb/>
 Her fear plants many a thicket wild<lb/>
                            While he pursues her night &amp; day<lb/>
 By various arts of Love
                            beguild. (stanza 20) </q>
Both principles are in a state of dislocation:
                        they wander “in terror &amp; dismay” (stanza 19). Her
                        flight from him is not to entice; she actually fears him. Her resistance
                        causes thickets to grow in the desert. The thickets and
                        “Labyrinths” (stanza 21) describe the state that is
                        created when the Spiritual principle is led into the pursuit of the riddle
                        of matter. We thus arrive at the stage where, of his four faces, Man
                        presents that of reason, the Zoa 
<pb id="p12-189" n="189"/>
Urizen.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62" type="note">16</ref> In this labyrinthine state roam the
                        enemies of the spirit: the “Lion Wolf &amp; Boar”
                        (stanza 21), those animals that will flee howling at the incarnation, in
                        stanza 25. In the Book of Enoch, in a dream-vision of Enoch, in which the
                        history of the world is related with animal characters, these animals, among
                        others, appear in the role of enemies of Israel: the boars are the Edomites,
                        the lions the Babylonians, and the wolves the Egyptians.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63" type="note">17</ref>
                        <note id="n62">
                            <hi rend="s">16</hi> S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">William
                                Blake: His Philosophy and Symbols</hi> (1924; rpt. London: Dawsons,
                            1969), p. 297, and Raine, <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi>, I,
                            319-20. Also, Raine (I, 320) calls the activity of stanza 23 the
                            building of “rational Rome,” an identification which
                            we adopt.</note>
                        <note id="n63">
                            <hi rend="s">17</hi> R. H. Charles, <hi rend="i">The Book of
                                Enoch</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1912), p. 191: footnote to
                            verse 9, p. 195: footnote to verse 42, and p. 199: footnote to verse 55.
                            Blake made drawings for the Book of Enoch, first translated into English
                            in 1821.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>As the Natural principle increases to full maturity, we move towards the
                        construction of the earthly paradise (stanzas 22,23): 
						<q> Then many a Lover
                            wanders here<lb/>
 The Sun &amp; Stars are nearer rolld<lb/>
 The
                            trees bring forth sweet Extacy. </q>
This state is called, in 
<hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, “the vales of Har” (4:10, E5,
                        K129), and, in <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>, “the pleasant gardens of
                        Har” (2:10, E274, K100) and “the lower garden”
                        (8:1, E281, K109). In this state, Man is infatuated with physical forms,
                        well expressed in the senile preoccupations of Har and Heva in 
<hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> (2, E274-75, K100-02).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64"
type="note">18</ref> Like the Romans at the time of the birth of Christ, Man wants
                        to create “the good life,” independent of his eternal
                        destiny. Thus, in the desert “many a City . . . is Built / And many
                        a pleasant Shepherds home” (stanza 23). Man tries to establish
                        “a joy without pain, / . . . a solid without fluctuation”
                            (<hi rend="i">BU</hi> 4:10-11, E70, K224). <note id="n64">
                            <hi rend="s">18</hi> One sees in Har and Heva an aged form of Adam and Eve,
                            watched over by the “now aged” Mnetha (<hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> 2: 6, E274, K100),
their nurse, or Mother Nature. All
                            three of these figures are of course associated with the Natural
                            principle: we recall that Adam (with Eve) is natural Man, while
                            “Goddess Nature” is “Satan’s
                            Wife” (<hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi>, E270, K777). In
                            the second illustration to <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>, reproduced in G. E.
                            Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">William Blake: Tiriel</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon
                            Press, 1967), plate II, Mnetha is drawn in an elongated form,
                            inexplicably so unless we take her to suggest the serpent. This
                            illustration shows the advanced state, deep in the fall, of the 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> illustration, <hi rend="i">Satan
                                Watching Adam and Eve</hi> (reproduced in <hi rend="i">William
                                Blake: water-color drawings</hi>, Boston: Museum of Fine Arts,
                            1957), where Satan is shown with the serpent, his wife, coiled about
                            him.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The references to “Stars . . . nearer rolld” and
                        “Shepherds” serve to remind us of the circumstances
                        preceding Christ’s birth. When the birth of the Babe is
                        discovered, it strikes terror “thro the region wide”
                        (stanza 25). The Spiritual principle is now emerging from its
                        sojourn in the “womb” of nature, where an integument has
                        been woven for it, enabling it to exist in this world and declare its own
                        nature. The spirit is no longer available to serve in the pursuit of earthly
                        love and happiness. It will of course be tortured in this world. Thel,
                        brooding over the self-contained processes of the womb of nature, innocently
                        anticipates that she will once again “gentle hear the voice / Of
                        him that walketh in the garden in the evening time” (<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 1:13-14,
E3, K127), the state of the spirit before the fall.
                        However, allowed to view the incarnated state, she witnesses instead the
                        suffering of the Boy, and flees back in horror to the safety of the vales of
                        Har.</p>
                    <p>With the birth and torture of the Male Babe, we arrive at the same event
                        described at the start of the ballad. The last two lines, “She
                        nails him down upon the Rock / And all is done as I have told”
                        (stanza 26), suggest that the process continues in the way described in the
                        poem. However, as we argued above, the cycle is merely a representation of
                        the various states in which Man may find himself, and the apparent
                        sequentiality is part of the metaphor used to represent contiguous
                        states.</p>
                    <p>The history of Man as a cycle from eternity to eternity is also recounted in
                        Blake’s epic, <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>
                        <ref target="n65" type="note">19</ref> We conjecture that there is a basic
correspondence
                        between “The Mental Traveller” narrative and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
narrative. A sketch of the alternation of the Zoas,
                        as we understand them to reach prominence as we traverse the Mental
                        Traveller’s cycle, might serve to suggest an alignment between
                        the two narratives, as indicated in Figure 2. 
<figure n="FourZoasDiagram.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="518">
	<figTranscr>URTHONA<lb/>
	<lb/>
	LUVAH<lb/>
	<lb/>
	THARMAS<lb/>
	<lb/>
	URIZEN<lb/>
	<lb/>
	Figure 2</figTranscr>
</figure>
<pb id="p12-190" n="190"/>
It
                        seems natural to assume, with Roe, that all four Zoas, together with their
                        Emanations, are present at every stage of Blake’s cycle, and that
                        the predominance of any one depends upon the state of the cycle in which the
                        Divine Humanity finds itself.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66"
type="note">20</ref> In
                        eternity, the Emanations are absorbed in their respective Zoas, but at the
                        fall they separate and progressively reject eternity until the limit of
                        opacity is reached and the incarnation takes place. <note id="n65">
                            <hi rend="s">19</hi> See, for instance, James Evans,
                            “Epistemology, Aesthetics, and ‘Divine
                            Analogy’: A Study of the Poetics of William Blake,”
                            Diss. Queen’s University at Kingston 1974, p. 147.</note>
                        <note id="n66">
                            <hi rend="s">20</hi> For interpretations of the Zoas and
                            their Emanations, see, for instance, Roe, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations to
the Divine Comedy</hi>, pp.
                            23-29, 165-71, and Milton O. Percival, <hi rend="i">William
                                Blake’s Circle of Destiny</hi> (1938; rpt. New York:
                            Octagon Press, 1964), pp. 18-46. In <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>,
                            Night 9, seven Zoas and Emanations are named as they arise from the
                            feast, while Urizen is in the vicinity (E385, 388, 390; K372, 376,
                            377).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>It will be useful to visualize the Zoas, the “Four Faces”
                        of Man (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 98:26, E255, K745), round the four sides
                        of a head, as in Blake’s drawing <hi rend="i">Ezekiel’s Vision</hi> 
(<hi rend="i">William Blake:
                            water-color drawings</hi>, Boston: Museum of Fine Arts, 1957, n. pag.).
                        When one face is fronting us, the two faces on either side are seen in
                        profile, and the one at the back is not visible. Luvah is the Zoa who
                        presides over the apocalypse. However, his face already begins to show (as
                        Orc) with the birth of the Spiritual at the incarnation. Similarly, the face
                        of Urthona starts to take shape at the apocalypse, but will only be fully
                        exposed as the heavenly Father when the eternal company is gathered for the
                        divine feast in Eden. In Eden, the face of Tharmas, the Zoa in terms of whom
                        the fall is described, is already appearing. And at the fall, the face of
                        Urizen comes into view, but will only manifest frontally when reason is
                        dominant and trying to establish the earthly paradise.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">21</ref>
                        <note id="n67">
                            <hi rend="s">21</hi> Blake’s diagram,
                            “Miltons Track” (E132, K523) in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 36, depicts the Zoas in a
cyclic order which is the
                            mirror image of that shown in Figure 2. His fourteenth Job illustration,
                                <hi rend="i">When the morning Stars</hi>, shows the regions of the
                            Zoas arranged around the central figure in accordance with the order
                            shown in Figure 2.</note>
                    </p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="b">III</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>We turn now to possible equivalents of the cycle of “The Mental
                        Traveller” in Blake’s pictorial art. Like many of
                        Blake’s works, the designs discussed below demonstrate
                        Blake’s belief in the co-presence of the Natural and Spiritual
                        principles in Man. Also, like “The Mental Traveller,”
                        these designs are apocalyptic visions which not only describe
                        Man’s destiny in and through the Natural, but also complete his
                        destiny by imaginative inference of the Spiritual or Divine.</p>
                    <p>In the title-page to his Job illustrations, Blake chose to arrange the seven
                        angels in a semi-circular form. If we superimpose this half-circle onto the
                        bottom half of the circle in Figure 1, it covers that part of the cycle that
                        stretches from the fall to the apocalypse. We agree with Damon that the
                        seven angels are the seven Eyes of God, and that they are seven states which
                        “were divinely instituted so that man should mechanically be
                        brought back to communion with God.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n68" type="note">22</ref> The first Eye, Lucifer, is the angel associated with the fall.
                        He looks out of the page, a glance followed by most of the angels coming
                        after and indicating the error of turning outward towards the natural. The
                        bottom angel, Shaddai, is given a prominent position and provides the pivot
                        for the upward movement which is to follow. The seventh Eye, Jesus, looks
                        inward toward the recognition of the eternal forms. The top half of the
                        circle is present by implication, for it is not visible to our vegetative
                        eye. The eighth Eye is, however, not invisible to the poet who has
                        experienced the apocalypse in imagination: appropriately, it is discovered
                        in <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> There it is the “Eighth / Image Divine
                        tho’ darken’d” (15:5-6, E108, K496) that
                        accompanies the “Spirits of the Seven Angels of the
                        Presence,” and the “Shadowy Eighth” (20:47, E114,
                        K502). It is called “Shadowy” and
                        “darken’d” since it is entering the region
                        wrapped in darkness from the understanding of natural Man. <note id="n68">
                            <hi rend="s">22</hi> Damon, <hi rend="i">William Blake: His
                                Philosophy and Symbols</hi>, p. 224.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Plate 15, <hi rend="i">Behold now Behemoth</hi>, of the Job series may be an
                        attempt to depict the same cycle as “The Mental
                        Traveller.” Behemoth (“the chief of the ways of
                        God”) is positioned where the Spiritual principle is dominant, its
                        head at the point of the apocalypse, its tail at the fall. Leviathan
                        (“King over all the Children of Pride”) rears its head at
                        the fall and tails off towards the apocalypse. Significantly, water fills
                        the lower half of the disk. Both in this design and in the frontispiece to
                            <hi rend="i">Europe, The Ancient of Days</hi>, an apparently divine
                        figure is situated above and extends his arm towards the actual or implied
                        circle. In the frontispiece to <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, this figure, shown
                        with compasses, is frequently identified with Urizen, in the act of
                        creation. It may, however, also be seen as the figure of Tharmas, at the
                        moment prior to his fall: 
						<q> Tharmas groand among his Clouds<lb/>
 Weeping,
                            then bending from his Clouds he stoopd his innocent head<lb/>
 And
                            stretching out his holy hand in the vast Deep sublime<lb/>
 Turnd round
                            the circle of Destiny . . .<lb/>
                            <lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>,
                            Night 1, 5:8-11, E298, K266: 71-74) </q>
Some critics incline to view
                        the circle of destiny as a purely natural cycle, one which Man can traverse
                        repeatedly until escape is possible through a process of rebirth.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69" type="note">23</ref> The implication is that the circle of
                        destiny is attached to a separate supernal cycle. It is our contention that
                        the supernal cycle is not separate from the circle of destiny, but
                        intertwined with it. That is, there is but a single cycle, and the circle of
                        destiny, which Tharmas turns round, is but the natural component of the
                        cycle, in complementary relationship with the supernal component.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70" type="note">24</ref> In the frontispiece to 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, then, the divine figure depicts the face of Man at the
                        stage when we enter the fall and meet our earthly destiny. At this stage
                        Tharmas is dominant, and it is he who can say: “Return O Wanderer
                        when the Day of Clouds is oer” (<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>,
                        Night 1, 5:12, E298, K266: 75). <note id="n69">
                            <hi rend="s">23</hi> For
                            instance, Percival, p. 12, and Roe, p. 21. Paley (<hi rend="i">Energy
                                and the Imagination</hi>, pp. 122-23) similarly indicates that Man,
                            to be regenerated, must break “a bound circle.”</note>
                        <note id="n70">
                            <hi rend="s">24</hi> Blake talks of “the vast form
                            of Nature like a serpent . . . ” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                            43: 76, E190, K655). The natural component of the cycle is thus aptly
                            represented in versions of the Uroboros in which the
                            serpent’s body is thick in its middle and thins out towards
                            its ends (see, for instance, Carl Jung, <hi rend="i">Psychology and
                                Alchemy, Collected Works</hi>, 2nd ed., Princeton: Princeton
                            University Press, 1970, XII, p. 103). The implied complementary serpent,
                            thickest where the serpent of nature is thinnest, and vice versa,
                            represents the spirit.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The cogency and centrality of the theme of Man’s fall from and
                        return to Eden in other work of Blake may be pointed out briefly, if
                        superficially. The title-page for the combined <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Innocence and of Experience</hi> depicts Adam and Eve being turned out
                        of paradise: the first series consists of songs in which the joy of paradise
                        is remembered and expressed through correspondent symbols in this world; the
                        second series consists of songs in which eternity is forgotten, and Man
                        makes his bitter progress towards the point where hope of regeneration has
                        to be introduced. The 16 plates of <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi>
                        emblematically tell the tale of travel through the fallen world, from the
                        exit gate of paradise round to the entrance gate. The early prophetic books
                        describe various portions of the journey. The myth of <hi rend="i">The Four
                            Zoas</hi> spans the entire 
<pb id="p12-191" n="191"/>
cycle; this myth
                        is condensed and re-worked in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem. Milton</hi> focuses on
                        the apocalyptic event within the poet. Even in his incidental illustrations,
                        Blake frequently chose material related to the cycle, for instance, <hi rend="i">The
Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained.</hi> Judith
                        Rhodes has shown that the 12 illustrations to <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi> may be
                        arranged in a circular form with striking correspondences to the cycle we
                        argue for “The Mental Traveller.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71"
type="note">25</ref>
                        <note id="n71">
                            <hi rend="s">25</hi> Judith Rhodes,
                            “Blake’s Designs for <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il
Penseroso:</hi>
                            Thematic Relationships in Diagram”, <hi rend="i">Blake
                                Newsletter</hi>, 4 (1971), 135-36, reprinted in Robert N. Essick,
                            ed., <hi rend="i">The Visionary Hand</hi> (Los Angeles: Hennessey
                            &amp; Ingalls, 1973), pp. 449-51.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Blake’s various versions of his picture <hi rend="i">A Vision of
                            the Last Judgment</hi> make a radical connection between the eternal
                        journey as a cycle of fall and return, and the eternal journey as the form
                        of Divine Humanity.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72"
type="note">26</ref> At the top of the
                        picture Jesus is shown seated on his throne in paradise. The fall takes
                        place on the right, in the form of figures falling downward. At the bottom,
                        beneath the “dragon’s cavern,” lies Albion, who
                        is awakened by his wife. The resurrection into paradise is shown on the
                        left, in the form of figures moving upwards towards the throne of Jesus. We
                        are fortunate to have Blake’s description of a version of the
                        picture (E542-55, K442-44, 604-17), in which he emphasizes the mental nature
                        of his vision. For instance, the falling and rising figures, with biblical
                        names, are meant to represent “the States Signified by those Names
                        the Individuals being representatives or Visions of those States as they
                        were reveald to Mortal Man in the Series of Divine Revelations. as they are
                        written in the Bible these various States I have seen in my Imagination when
                        distant they appear as One Man but as you approach they appear Multitudes of
                        Nations” (<hi rend="i">VLJ</hi>, E546, K607). In the version of the
                        picture which is in the Rosenwald collection, the details of the picture do
                        dissolve into the outline of this “One Man.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n73" type="note">27</ref> Blake writes: “All Things are
                        comprehended in their Eternal Forms in the Divine body of the Saviour . . .
                        The Human Imagination who appeard to Me as Coming to Judgment . . . throwing
                        off the Temporal that the Eternal might be Established” (<hi rend="i">VLJ</hi>, E545,
K605-06). The Last Judgment is thus viewed as a
                        process in which the divine spirit in Man leads him to discard the states of
                        error and to reach his eternal state, which forms his true home, the place
                        “Where the travellers journey is done.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n74" type="note">28</ref>
                        <note id="n72">
                            <hi rend="s">26</hi> See “Blake’s Visions
                            of the Last Judgment,” a pamphlet issued by <hi rend="i">Blake
                                Newsletter, An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> for the MLA Blake Seminar,
                            1975.</note>
                        <note id="n73">
                            <hi rend="s">27</hi>
                            <hi rend="i"> Ibid.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <note id="n74">
                            <hi rend="s">28</hi> “Ah! Sun-flower” (E25,
                            K215), another poem with a “curious circular movement”
                            (Rosemary Freeman, <hi rend="i">English Emblem Books</hi>, London:
                            Chatto &amp; Windus, 1948, p. 28).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>A final design may be mentioned: the watercolor picture, <hi rend="i">Ezekiel’s
Vision.</hi> Here, as in the title-page to <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, Blake configures the Eyes of God in the
lower part of
                        a circle. As in <hi rend="i">A Vision of the Last Judgment</hi>, the eternal
                        cycle is equally the human form. These motifs, along with that of the four
                        faces of Man, combine to make the Ezekiel design a comprehensive vision of
                        Man’s eternal form.</p>
                    <p>It is a symbolical reading of the Bible, as Blake’s own commentary
                        on <hi rend="i">A Vision of the Last Judgment</hi> suggests, that makes it
                        possible to interpret cohesively his most challenging works. Robinson
                        reports that Blake “warmly declared that all he knew was in the
                        Bible; but then he understands by the Bible the Spiritual Sense”
                        (BBR 322). Blake held that “The Old &amp; New Testaments are
                        the Great Code of Art” (<hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi>, E271,
                        K777). The biblical narrative, seized as a whole and transfigured into a
                        ballad, is complete and cohesive in “The Mental
                        Traveller.” Any more restricted reading entails internal
                        contradictions or indicates interpretations contrary to Blake’s
                        distinct theological ideas. Because “The Mental Traveller”
                        is a radically compressed version of Blake’s most important
                        theme, that of Man’s fall from and return to Eden, and an
                        audacious announcement of reality’s mental nature, a mastery of
                        its form and its visionary conceit is, in microcosm, a mastery of Blake.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
	<pb id="p12-192" n="192" rend="hidden"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
