<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.3.england</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Donald Davie, A Gathered Church: The Literature of the English
Dissenting Interest, 1700-1930</title>
                <author n="England">Martha W. England</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1978-79</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978-79</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Production Office</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>E. B. Bentley</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>David Bindman</name>
                            <name>Izak Bouwer</name>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>Arnold Cheskin</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>Martha Winburn England</name>
                            <name>J. Karl Franson</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>David Irwin</name>
                            <name>Paul McNally</name>
                            <name>Marta Slowikova</name>
                            <name>Robert R. Wark</name>
                            <name>Kazumitsu Watarai</name>
                            <name>Dwight Weber</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1979"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-3-0011">
                <pb id="p12-215" n="215"/>
                <div2>
                    <figure n="DavieGatheredChurch.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="320"/>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Donald Davie. <hi rend="b">A Gathered Church: The Literature of the
                                English Dissenting Interest, 1700-1930.</hi> New York: Oxford
                            University Press. $19.95.</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="b">Martha W.</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">England</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>This book contains the six Clark Lectures delivered at Cambridge University
                        in 1976, with thirty-five pages of notes and eleven photographs of
                        architecture and memorials illuminating the points at issue. The first
                        lecture charts the field. From Milton to the present, the writer searches
                        for evidences of culture as these have changed. Primary consideration is
                        given to esthetic patterns, proclivities and values. Two other questions are
                        never far from the mind: political groupings and patterns of behavior; and
                        religious groupings, beliefs and patterns of worship. At the close of the
                        last lecture Mr. Davie remarks: “Some day I may stray from my
                        proper field so far as to challenge certain received notions about the
                        social and political history of the English Dissent over the past three
                        centuries.” These fields also are at least foreshadowed in the
                        present publication.</p>
                    <p>Isaac Watts is the central figure of the second lecture, “Old
                        Dissent, 1700-1740.” Two lines of relationship are traced, between
                        the work of Watts and Calvinist ideals of art on the Continent, those
                        artistic ideals of simplicity, sobriety, and measure, manifested in
                        Watts’s ability to subordinate parts to the whole conception in a
                        form of classicism so different from that of Pope that the speaker calls it
                        “non-English.” The other relation is to Hebrew poetry.
                        Because the Old Dissent thought of itself as a chosen people living in
                        tension with neighbors, Watts was “a poet of the tribal lay, a true
                        analogue in Augustan England of David.”</p>
                    <p>“Dissent and the Wesleyans, 1740-1800” first considers the
                        lapsed Quaker, Matthew Green, whose poem <hi rend="i">The Spleen</hi>
                        comments with rueful wit upon the changes from the time of George Fox to the
                        day when the Quakers entered into the Industrial Revolution. <hi rend="i">The
Spleen</hi> was admired by Pope and Walpole and Gray; admired also
                        by Johnson as wit, but not as poetry, and he did not include Green in the
                            <hi rend="i">Lives of the Poets.</hi> But Johnson would not omit Isaac
                        Watts; he said nothing about the hymns (Johnson did not approve of hymns),
                        and little about Watts as a poet, but praised him as man, as prose writer
                        and especially as teacher. Watts and the Wesleys are the central figures,
                        not that the Wesleys dissented from the Church, but because their followers
                        did. The questions of “offensive” sexuality and masochism
                        are raised here, and one is reminded that the dignified and decorous Dr.
                        Watts was accused of such faults, as well as the extravagant Moravians.</p>
                    <p>The “Old Dissent” is represented by Robert Hall, Baptist
                        minister, in the fourth lecture, “Dissent and the Evangelicals,
                        1800-1850.” Hall, because dissenters could not be members of the
                        University, was not quite “every inch a Cambridge man,”
                        but his love of Cambridge, and of scholarship, and of his friend Samuel Parr
                        almost qualify him for that description. The New Dissent, Unitarians and
                        Sandemanians, has Mrs. Elizabeth Gaskell for the Unitarian representative.
                        The Unitarians, the intellectual <hi rend="i">élite</hi> of the
                        Dissent, contributed to culture ideas, argument, speculative thought rather
                        than works of art, and Mrs. Gaskell with her novels “is probably
                        the nearest we can come to an exception to this rule.” The
                        Sandemanians are represented by the great scientist Michael Faraday. His
                        popular lectures on science were a major source of income for the Royal
                        Institute, and his love of the theater and novels and poetry enlivened these
                        lectures, eloquent and energetic in style. The style of his sermons (he was
                        an elected Elder) contrasts with the lectures, being “patient and
                        formal exposition.” He had been too poor to have any academic
                        training. He had educated himself from <hi rend="i">The Improvement of the
                            Mind</hi> by Watts and his first publication was on that book. Faraday
                        alone would go far to justify Johnson’s praise of
                        Watts’s book; and as for Watts, it should 
<pb id="p12-216" n="216"/>
be glory enough
for any teacher to have educated
                        Faraday—even, or perhaps especially—posthumously.</p>
                    <p>Lecture V, “Dissent and the Agnostics, 1850-1900,” tells of
                        the “loss of faith,” in particular, George Eliot and
                        Leslie Stephen. Many arguments with the two Arnolds, father and son, are
                        brought into the discussion. Chiefly considered is their allegation that the
                        Dissent had abandoned all cultural responsibilities. “Mark
                        Rutherford” is compared with André Gide in a very
                        illuminating discussion. The villain of this lecture is the evangelist
                        Charles Spurgeon, whose effect upon the Dissent was
                        “disastrous.”</p>
                    <p>The sixth lecture, “Dissent in the Present Century,” takes
                        D. H. Lawrence as its battleground, the opponents being T. S. Eliot against
                        F. R. Leavis. Eliot held in contempt Lawrence’s Chapel
                        background; Leavis defended it on the grounds that it was “the
                        center of a strong social life.” It seems to Mr. Davie, for all
                        that, that this background failed Lawrence, just as the background of
                        Dissent failed to sustain W. H. White. But the tradition did not wholly fail
                        Edmund Gosse. <hi rend="i">Father and Son</hi> demonstrates this fact, and
                        “one of the great and unexpected virtues of Gosse’s
                        beautifully tender book is the proof it gives of how a culture and a
                        tradition were transmitted even within a sect so late-come and so rigid as
                        that of the Plymouth Brethren.”</p>
                    <p>If I were competent to do so, I should set this book beside the work of
                        another poet and critic, Matthew Arnold. I am not. I have given a rather
                        drab summary, which stands in relation to the book itself as a 
<hi rend="i">précis</hi> of a libretto stands in relation to its musical
                        drama. Only major characters and plot line. But I can at least mention the
                        music.</p>
                    <p>From the printed page there comes the sound of a voice, luminous and just.
                        The thematic construction takes its ground bass from the heroic age of
                        Milton and Bunyan. The action begins when the Hanoverians made the Dissent a
                        part of the bourgeois culture. One major theme is stated in “O God,
                        our help in ages past,” the need of Establishment and Dissent for
                        one another; the song is used in Establishment ceremonies in England, Canada
                        and America. Another song by Watts introduces a major theme, “We
                        are a garden.” It is part of Watts’s only song cycle,
                        made from The Song of Solomon, and as that book has virtually been removed
                        from the canon, so are Watts’s songs almost unknown. The charge
                        of “offensive sexuality” is part of the theme, and another
                        part is the celebration of the Lord’s Supper. This particular
                        song describes the careful and loving preparation for the sacrament and the
                        invitation to the Spirit to come, now that all has been made ready. With the
                        song come thoughts of a real garden where Watts was a guest for more than
                        thirty years, a decorous eighteenth-century garden. Here he walked and sang
                        with the Wesleys, and said that one song by Charles Wesley was worth more
                        than all of his own. And so this song is next quoted, “Wrestling
                        Jacob,” on the great paradoxes involved in the wounding of God and
                        Man, of victory in defeat.</p>
                    <p>Thus the eloquent tongue of Mr. Davie evokes the very times as they pass in
                        historical succession. Sometimes that tongue is in his cheek. The lecture on
                        the late nineteenth century opens (appropriately) with something like a
                        Gilbert and Sullivan patter song on the divisions among the Baptists. A
                        Gathered Church, indeed! Sectarianism with a vengeance! And, appropriate to
                        that era, <hi rend="i">The Importance of Being Earnest</hi> comes to mind;
                        Froude and Stephen sound rather like Lady Bracknell. Sacred poetry and
                        religious fictions have no place in literature at all. Ah, so? Well, that
                        disposes of Milton and Bunyan. Bunyan, in fact, is “the
                        Poet-apostle of the English Middle-Class imperfectly educated like
                        himself.” How delightful to contemplate the perfection of
                        one’s own education, and, of course, one’s two good
                        addresses.</p>
                    <p>In the lecture, a poem by Tyutchev sounds with grief for loss, the loss of
                        faith, the loss of belief in the efficacy of prayer. The lecture closes in
                        contrasting tone, Samuel Butler’s satiric celebration of Charles
                        Spurgeon in his flamboyant vulgarity; and in the satire there is still the
                        sound of grief for something lost.</p>
                    <p>I take issue with two statements about Blake. I am reluctant to do so for
                        readers who may not have Mr. Davie’s book at hand, for his tone
                        is quite as important as I represent it to be, and in both cases, it is the
                        tone I dispute, not the facts stated. My ears are notoriously better than
                        the brain between them; but they may not be infallible. Of
                        Blake’s <hi rend="i">Mystery</hi>, he says: “this term
                        that the prayer book gives to the sacrament is consistently a term of
                        abuse” (p. 98). So far as I recall, that is true. But Blake was not
                        working from the prayer book. His most celebrated Mystery is from
                        Revelation, used at the close of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as St. John
                        used it, an evil female. The Tree of Mystery is associated with the
                        sacrament in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> (Night VII, p. 80). Urizen
                        compels his exhausted daughters to knead the fruit of the Tree into bread
                        for a parody of a communion service and preaches a “communion
                        sermon” that should have brought down upon him the
                        “Woes” of Matthew 23 and the special
                        “Woes” in 1 Corinthians 11:27 &amp; 29. Blake, for
                        about ten years, from 1795 was bitter in his comments on an Establishment
                        that used its authority to support wars. And, in another context, Mr. Davie
                        himself gives proof that the “daughters” were reluctant to
                        take part in the sacrament: in St. Paul’s Cathedral, Easter 1800,
                        there were six communicants (p. 64).</p>
                    <p>It is true (p. 52) that Blake found no sustenance in any organized religion.
                        His Mr. Huffcap could stand in for Spurgeon with his vulgar ranting. But
                        Blake saw no good in any other sort of organization, school, art academy,
                        nothing suited him. During a time when London’s organized
                        charities drew praise from the Continent, Blake had no part in them, and
                        even “Holy Thursday” has been interpreted as an expression
                        of his contempt for such works. Hogarth, quite a different sort of man,
                        opened London’s first art gallery in support of that charity and
                        served with Handel on the board. Yet Blake apparently was not uncharitable
                        by nature, nor does all of this add up to Blake’s holding in
                        contempt the true Bread and Wine that images the broken body and spilt
                        blood. Lord David Cecil’s life of Samuel Palmer describes that
                        group of young men who made Blake’s last years 
<pb id="p12-217" n="217"/>
happy.
They were devout, intellectually sophisticated to
                        various degrees, able to construe Blake’s poems and his pictures,
                        two of them artists, one of the two a great artist. They accepted
                        Blake’s special relation with Milton, and they established his
                        special relation with Bunyan. They met at The House of the Interpreter. I am
                        content to rest on their opinion.</p>
                    <p>I am not in agreement with another of Mr. Davie’s opinions. The
                        whole long passage (p. 53 f.) is relevant. The gist is that one may admire
                        Blake “and still regard with alarm, as a very ominous symptom, the
                        veneration which is now so freely accorded him.” Mr. Davie spoke in
                        1976. For some years prior to that date, I had cause to think quite the
                        contrary. I was living in a chancy and fascinating era in the history of
                        education, every newspaper announcing some lower level of literacy and some
                        higher estimate of the number of hours out of twentyfour that my students
                        spent watching television commercials. The spontaneous interest of students
                        in Blake was like money in the bank. Blake is, as Mr. Davie says, an
                        “engaging” creature. <hi rend="i">Engaging</hi> is
                        precisely the word. Think of how many things Blake was interested in! Think
                        of the avenues he can open! Art, and his pictures of Chaucer and Spenser.
                        Milton. Blake can lead students happily to concordances, analytical grammar,
                        scholarly opinions. If Blake were nothing more than a means to an end, I
                        should owe him much. But to me Blake is more, and perhaps I am <hi rend="i">particeps
criminis.</hi>
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
