<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.3.ebbentley</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="minute">Vision in Fiction: Two Novels About William Blake</title>
                <author n="Bentley">Elizabeth B. Bentley</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1978-79</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978-79</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Production Office</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>E. B. Bentley</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>David Bindman</name>
                            <name>Izak Bouwer</name>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>Arnold Cheskin</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>Martha Winburn England</name>
                            <name>J. Karl Franson</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>David Irwin</name>
                            <name>Paul McNally</name>
                            <name>Marta Slowikova</name>
                            <name>Robert R. Wark</name>
                            <name>Kazumitsu Watarai</name>
                            <name>Dwight Weber</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1979"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-3-0010">
                <pb id="p12-209" n="209"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">VISION IN FICTION: TWO NOVELS ABOUT WILLIAM BLAKE</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="b">E. B.</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">Bentley</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>William Blake has rarely been the subject of fiction, if we bar the accounts
                        of his Irish grandparentage, his sojourn in a madhouse, and the more
                        decorative flights of his 
                        critics.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n100" type="note">1</ref>
                        <figure n="HeygateTitlePage.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="685">
                            <head>1 Titlepage to Heygate, <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi>
                            </head>
                        </figure> 
                        Only two novels seem to have been written explicitly about William
                        Blake, both listed in the <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> of 1975: The
                        Rev. W. E. Heygate, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (London: John Masters,
                        1848) and Peter Carter, <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi> (London:
                        Oxford University Press, 1974). The former is an
                        “improving” book (p. viii) about a feckless young yeoman
                        named William Blake who is turned to God, or at least to conforming
                        Christianity, with the help of a quietly sententious village rector, and it
                        concludes with all well in the Moat House: 
						<q>
							It was the reign of rest and
                            peace; that time to which many hearts are looking, a time when the work
                            of life is over, and there is a tarrying and reposing before the break
                            of endless day.<lb/>
                            (p. 204)
                        </q>
                        <figure n="HeygateFrontispiece.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="334">
                            <head>2 Frontispiece by N. D. Sears to W. E. Heygate, <hi rend="i">William
                            Blake</hi> (1848) showing Moat House (reproduced from
                            the copy in Bodley).</head>
                        </figure>
                        <figure n="RockerDesign.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="319">
                            <head>3 Fermin Rocker’s design (one of fourteen in <hi rend="i">The Gates of
                            	Paradise</hi>) showing Blake and Ben
                                studying the text of “London” which they have just
                                made on the rolling press in Blake’s work-room in
                                Hercules Buildings, Lambeth.</head>
                            <figDesc>In the dust jacket illustration, Blake’s hair is
                                shown as fiery red.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                        <pb id="p12-210" n="210"/> 
                        The subtitle of the novel, “The English
                        Farmer” (omitted in the <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>
                        listing), indicates its subject and its irrelevance to the 
                        poet-painter.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n101" type="note">2</ref>
                        <note id="n100">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi> E. J. Ellis &amp; W. B. Yeats, <hi rend="i">The Works of
                            William Blake</hi> (1893) and E. J. Ellis, <hi rend="i">The Real Blake</hi> 
                            (1907); Elizabeth O’Higgins,
                            “Blake’s Joy of the Yew”, <hi rend="i">Dublin Magazine</hi>, XXX, i (1956),
                            21-29; S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary</hi> (1965); Anon.,
                            “Hôpital des fous á Londres”,
                            <hi rend="i">Revue Britanique</hi>, 3 S, 4 (1833), 179-87).</note>
                        <note id="n101">
                            <hi rend="s">2</hi> The Rev. W. E. Heygate, <hi rend="i">William Blake:</hi> or,
                            The English Farmer (London: John Masters,
                            1848).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="i">The Gates of 
                        Paradise</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n102" type="note">3</ref> 
                        on the other hand, does deal with the author of <hi rend="i">Songs of
                        Innocence and of Experience</hi>, and in the Preface Peter
                        Carter notes that “The details concerning Blake, his wife, and his
                        friends are factual. The rest is fiction . . . .” 
                        <note id="n102">
                            <hi rend="s">3</hi> Peter Carter, <hi rend="i">The Gates of
                            Paradise</hi>, Illustrated by Fermin Rocker (London: Oxford
                            University Press, 1974).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>It’s a good tale, set in 1796 and woven around William and
                        Catherine Blake, a runaway apprentice named Ben Pendrill who needs
                        befriending, and a grubby old man named Grale who spies for a living.</p>
                    <p>The year 1796 is right for the politics although wrong for <hi rend="i">Songs
                        of Experience</hi>, since Mr. Carter has Blake write 
                        “The Tyger<supplied type="emend">”</supplied>
                        (p. 38) and “The Sick Rose” (p. 106) during the course of
                        the story.</p>
                    <p>The Blakes actually did assist a young artist, though in different
                        circumstances,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n103" type="note">4</ref> 
                        and in Carter’s story the Blakes take in runaway Ben and teach him to
                        read from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (p. 8), to print (p. 11), to
                        engrave (p. 17 etc.), and Ben helps with <hi rend="i">Songs of
                        Experience.</hi> Some details of the eighteenth-century apprenticeship
                        system are neatly worked in with Ben, who becomes an apprentice engraver.
                    <note id="n103"><hi rend="s">4</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., 
                        <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (1969), 524-25.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>We meet members of the real world of William Blake, including Mr. Godwin,
                        Miss Wollstonecraft, Mr. Parker, Mr. Stothard, Mr. Moser (d. 1783), and
                        especially Mr. Flaxman and Mr. Butts. With the assistance of John Flaxman,
                        “Muster-Master General” Thomas Butts takes Blake
                        “under [<hi rend="i">his</hi>] protection” (pp. 103, 105)
                        and thus deflects the thought-police from him.</p>
                    <p>Often the dialogue is plausibly Blakean: 
						<q>
							‘Do you still attend
                            that church, the one with the strange beliefs?’ Godwin
                            asked.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            ‘The Church of Swedenborg? Occasionally.
                            Their beliefs are not strange enough for us these days.’
                            William’s face was expressionless but his voice was light,
                            almost mocking. (p. 13) </q>
                            Later Blake says to Stothard: 
                            <q>
                            ‘ . . . you speak of the new age; I tell you this, Sir, these
                            changes, and any others in the world, are without meaning unless men are
                            changed in their hearts and learn to live in
                            eternity.’<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            Parker was indignant. ‘Live
                            in eternity? Come, Mr. Blake. This is close to
                            priest-craft.’<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            ‘Those words do not
                            frighten me,’ William said. ‘We hear too much of
                            priest-craft in these days. Let us hear a little more of soldier-craft,
                            or business-craft, or politician-craft. I tell you that all ages are the
                            same, but that genius is above the age.’ (p. 47)
                        </q>
                    </p>
                    <p>The story is, of course, about a boy, and Carter often sketches the
                        relationship of Blake and Ben deftly. When Ben first arrives, Blake shows
                        him a woodcut: 
						<q>
							He took an inked roller and ran it over the wood. Then he
                            placed a strip of paper over the wood and pressed it down. When he took
                            the paper away there was an animal on it.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            Ben whistled in
                            surprise. ‘It’s a dog,’ he
                            said.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            William was slightly offended.
                            ‘It’s a lamb,’ he said. ‘Do
                            you know what a lamb is?’<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            ‘No.’ Ben didn’t.<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            ‘Well, that is one,’ William said firmly, but he
                            stole another glance at the sketch as he put it down. (pp. 17-18)
                        </q>
                    </p>
                    <p>At the end, Mr. Grale the spy, abandoned by his secret police paymaster and
                        left to his rather horrible self, is taken in by the Blakes, to
                        Ben’s astonishment, and Ben himself is apprenticed to Mr. Fox the
                        engraver, his sixty-guinea fee being paid by Thomas Butts.</p>
                    <p>The story presents a loving and sensitive relationship amongst the Blakes and
                        their young friend Ben. Blake’s poems, visions, and ideas are
                        seen through Ben and his reactions in a believable way. The unfolding of
                        William’s generosity of spirit and deed with Mr. Grale is
                        especially satisfying to the sentimental reader. Peter Carter’s
                        <hi rend="i">Gates of Paradise</hi> is interesting reading for the way
                        it presents and interprets William Blake and is rewarding for more than the
                        story to young readers.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
