<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.3.weber</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="minute">William Blake’s Visions of the Daughters of Albion: A Poem Based on
Doubt</title>
                <author n="Weber">Dwight E. Weber</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1978-79</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978-79</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Production Office</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>E. B. Bentley</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>David Bindman</name>
                            <name>Izak Bouwer</name>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>Arnold Cheskin</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>Martha Winburn England</name>
                            <name>J. Karl Franson</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>David Irwin</name>
                            <name>Paul McNally</name>
                            <name>Marta Slowikova</name>
                            <name>Robert R. Wark</name>
                            <name>Kazumitsu Watarai</name>
                            <name>Dwight Weber</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1979"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
	<pb id="p12-203" n="203"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-3-0010">
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">WILLIAM BLAKE’S</hi> VISIONS OF THE DAUGHTERS
                            OF ALBION: <hi rend="b">A POEM BASED ON DOUBT</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>
                            <hi rend="b">Dwight E.</hi>
                            <name>
                                <hi rend="b">Weber</hi>
                            </name>
                        </docAuthor>
                    </byline>
                    <p>Among the unique features of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Visions
                            of the Daughters of Albion</hi> are the names. The names of all five
                        major “characters” appear for the first time in this poem.
                        Harold Bloom has stated that the “Father of Jealousy . . . whom we
                        have met before in Blake as Winter, Tiriel, Restraint, the Devourer, and the
                        Nobodaddy who successfully masquerades as God the Father in <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence</hi>” is “first introduced in this
                        poem under his Blakean name of Urizen.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n89" type="note">1</ref> Moreover, while Oothoon and Theotormon, the doubtful
                        lovers, reappear in <hi rend="i">Europe a Prophecy</hi> and <hi rend="i">The
                            Song of Los</hi> and, along with the Daughters of Albion and Bromion, in
                            <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, they all
originate in the 1793 printing of <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi>
                        <ref target="n90" type="note">2</ref> Blake may have selected the names for their
derivative
                        significance. For instance, Theotormon is nominally “the man
                        tormented by his own idea of God.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n91" type="note">3</ref> The name of Urizen, likewise, may suggest “the <hi rend="i">horizon</hi> of
thought,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n92" type="note">4</ref> as he and his agent try to
restrain Oothoon’s
                        imagination, or, quite possibly, it may play upon the words “your
                        reason.” However, another, more covert method of naming exists,
                        antecedent to this search for derivatives. <note id="n89">
                            <hi rend="s">1</hi> Harold Bloom, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse: A
                                Study in Poetic Argument</hi> (Ithaca, New York: Cornell University
                            Press, 1970), p. 106.</note>
                        <note id="n90">
                            <hi rend="s">2</hi> “Bromion,”
                            “Daughters of Albion,” “Oothoon,”
                            “Theotormon,” in Samuel Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">A
                                Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols of William Blake</hi>
                            (Providence: Brown University Press, 1965).</note>
                        <note id="n91">
                            <hi rend="s">3</hi> Bloom, p. 102.</note>
                        <note id="n92">
                            <hi rend="s">4</hi> Bloom, p. 17.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Blake’s names, all original with this poem, are functions of their
                        first letters. That is, the poet started with the initial letters and then
                        found apt names to complete each letter, or character. These characters form
                        an anagram for “doubt” (<hi rend="u">D</hi>aughters, <hi rend="u">O</hi>othoon, 
<hi rend="u">U</hi>rizen, <hi rend="u">B</hi>romion, <hi rend="u">T</hi>heotormon). Indeed, the poem begins and
                        ends with doubt. The Daughters of Albion watch Oothoon’s progress
                        and doubt their ability to seize a similar freedom from Leutha’s
                        vale. Bromion assaults the exultant Oothoon and casts doubt upon the
                        validity of her so-called independence. Finally, Theotormon’s
                        conscience keeps him dubious of the love and sexual freedom to which Oothoon
                        wishes him to awake. Blake, then, reveals his poetic theme anagrammatically
                        through his names.</p>
                    <p>Certainly, doubt is a major theme in the poetry of William Blake. Plate 4,
                        “Air,” of <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of
                            Paradise</hi> shows a miserable character “On Cloudy Doubts and
                        Reasoning Cares”;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n93"
type="note">5</ref> moreover, in
                        the accompanying poem, Blake attacks “Doubt which is Self
                        contradiction” (E265). His “Auguries of
                        Innocence” warns: “He who shall teach the Child to Doubt /
                        The rotting Grave shall neer get out” (E483). One may think of the
                        Daughters, the children, of Albion in this connection. Urizen, the source of
                        all this doubt, may come to mind as well in Blake’s satiric
                        verse, “You dont believe I wont attempt to make ye”
                        (E492). Here the word “Doubt” is placed in the mouth of
                        Sir Isaac Newton, the scientist parodied by Blake in “The Ancient
                        of Days,” who, in the frontispiece to <hi rend="i">Europe a
                            Prophecy</hi>, defines the “horizons of thought” with
                        his compass.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n94" type="note">6</ref>
Doubt limits a person,
                        hinders him from becoming all he can be, and prevents him from drawing the
                        “distinct, sharp, . . . and wirey . . . bounding line”
                        (E540) by which he will live his own life. In <hi rend="i">Visions of the
                            Daughters of Albion</hi>, Blake places Urizen at the center of doubt,
                        both in a thematic and anagrammatical way. In fact, <hi rend="u">U</hi>rizen
                        and <hi rend="u">B</hi>romion act in the poem and in the anagram to separate
                        the <hi rend="u">D</hi>aughters and <hi rend="u">O</hi>othoon, the females,
                        from any consummation with <hi rend="u">T</hi>heotormon, the male. <note id="n93">
                            <hi rend="s">5</hi> William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Poetry and
                                Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman (Garden City, New
                            York: Doubleday, 1965), p. 259. Hereafter E.</note>
                        <note id="n94">
                            <hi rend="s">6</hi> Bloom, p. 157.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>This approach to the poem through anagram does not refute any of the previous
                        speculations about the derivations of the characters’ names. The
                        names of Theotormon, Bromion, and Oothoon, as Northrop Frye claims, may well
                        be Ossianic, in so oceanic a poem.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n95" type="note">7</ref> Yet
                        the focus on the anagram places the horse back before the cart. Blake
                        appears to have predetermined 
<pb id="p12-204" n="204"/>
his thematic
                        anagram prior to his selection of suitable, properly lettered names from
                        Ossian or elsewhere. Furthermore, the word play seems to indicate the
                        presence of an eighteenth-century wit in Blake, even as he dealt with the
                        most Romantic of themes. <note id="n95">
                            <hi rend="s">7</hi> Northrop Frye,
                                <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry: A Study of William Blake</hi>
                            (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1974), p. 238.</note>
                    </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
