<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.3.blake</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">MLA Blake 1978</title>
                <author n="Mellor">Anne K. Mellor</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1978-79</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978-79</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Production Office</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>E. B. Bentley</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>David Bindman</name>
                            <name>Izak Bouwer</name>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>Arnold Cheskin</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>Martha Winburn England</name>
                            <name>J. Karl Franson</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>David Irwin</name>
                            <name>Paul McNally</name>
                            <name>Marta Slowikova</name>
                            <name>Robert R. Wark</name>
                            <name>Kazumitsu Watarai</name>
                            <name>Dwight Weber</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1979"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
            <pb id="p12-218" n="218"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-3-0012">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">NEWSLETTER</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="b">MLA BLAKE 1978</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>Each year the MLA awards the William Riley Parker prize to the author of an
                        outstanding article published in <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi> during the year.
                        This year the Prize went to Morris Eaves, University of New Mexico, for
                        “Blake &amp; the Artistic Machine: An Essay in Decorum
                        &amp; Technology,” which appeared in the October 1977 issue.
                        At the general meeting Eaves accepted the cash prize of $500 and a citation
                        which reads as follows: “This essay not only illuminates William
                        Blake’s esthetic and his stance as an artist and a critic of
                        society but also casts new light on the relationship between art and
                        technology. Morris E. Eaves sets his lucid exposition of Blake’s
                        attitudes toward technological change within the broad contexts of
                        conceptual analysis, cultural history from the Renaissance to the present,
                        and the influence of the machine on the human condition.”</p>
                    <p>At the Special Session on “Editing the Romantics”
                        (discussion leader E. B. Murray, University of Missouri, St. Louis), G. E.
                        Bentley, Jr., presented an illustrated lecture on the special editorial
                        problems faced by an editor of Blake.</p>
                    <p>An overflow audience of more than 100 attended the 1978 MLA Special Session
                        on Blake’s Concept of Self. Since abstracts of the first three
                        papers read by John H. Sutherland, Christine Gallant, and Robert N. Essick
                        appeared in the fall 1978 issue of <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, I shall
                        summarize them only briefly here. The discussion focused primarily upon
                        points raised in the last paper on Blake’s Spectre by Morton
                        Paley, which I shall therefore report in more detail.</p>
                    <p>In “Some Blake Self-Images in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>:
The Blake-Los Relationship,” John
                        Sutherland traced Blake’s move from self-division to
                        self-integration (defined as a union with Los) in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
                        10 and <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 47. In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Los and
                        Blake seem “close to full identification” with each other:
                        both are engaged in the same “great task” and both are
                        visually fused in the frontispiece. In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 6,
                        Los/Blake has gained control over his Spectre, his own self-defeating
                        “pride and self-righteousness” which had appeared as
                        separate entities in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 10. And on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
100, Los/Blake compels his Spectre (his rational powers)
                        and his Emanation (his now acknowledged “unconsious realms of
                        imagination”) to work “harmoniously for the integrated
                        individual” and at the same time to create the world of space and
                        time in which that individual can exist. Here, Sutherland concluded, Los
                        “represents Blake’s integrated self” and this
                        plate therefore is “Blake’s most convincing
                        demonstration of his own hard-won inner harmony.”</p>
                    <p>Christine Gallant then argued, in “Blake’s Presence as
                        First-Person Voice in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,” that the
                        first-person voice operates much as does the authoritative dream-voice that
                        Jung said emerged from the center of the total personality or what he called
                        “the supraordinate Self.” The message of this dream-voice
                        “is a final summing-up of a long process of unconscious
                        deliberation and weighing of arguments.” In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Blake acts
“as spokesman 
<pb id="p12-219" n="219"/>
for the unconscious as he encouragingly speaks to the reader
                        who has not yet dared to descend into it.” Blake also claims to
                        speak the “Testimony of Jesus” and
                        “God’s words,” thus utilizing the archetypes of
                        Christ and God to preserve his conscious ego in the face of an overwhelming
                        unconsciousness. Blake thereby identifies his first-person voice with that
                        Self that includes both the conscious and the unconscious. Gallant then
                        discussed the nine first-person passages in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> The
                        first six (1:1-5, 5:16-26, 15:4-35, 36:58-9, 34:27-48, 74:14-75:27) tell of
                        Blake’s life in an Ulro that grows closer and closer and in which
                        he is increasingly separated from Jesus; the last three (97:5, 98:40-41,
                        99:5) define Blake’s hardwon conviction that he has guided us
                        through Ulro to the divine vision. By using the first-person voice in the
                        last line of the poem, Gallant concluded, Blake emphasizes that this is a
                        journey that we must <hi rend="i">each</hi> undergo, again and again.</p>
                    <p>Robert N. Essick’s “William Blake: The Printmaker as
                        Poet” traced Blake’s use of imagery drawn from his
                        etching and engraving techniques. The minute particulars of his discussion
                        are too rich to be crudely summarized; readers should go to his forthcoming
                        book on Blake as a printmaker (Princeton University Press, 1979) for a full
                        exposition of this imagery. But his concluding argument can be described.
                        Blake had a love-hate relationship with his commercial profession. He
                        deliberately identified many of his printmaking activities with Urizen, thus
                        suggesting that “commercial copy engraving could become a trap, a
                        degradation of the artist’s vision, and an aesthetic-economic
                        system antithetical to Blake’s highest aspirations.” On
                        the other hand, print-making can be “a medium for the expression of
                        imagination and the transcendence of this world”; hence Blake 
<hi rend="i">reverses</hi> Urizen’s unintelligible forms in the
                        process of printing. As Essick emphasizes, “Urizen does not print
                        his books. The <hi rend="i">reversal</hi> inherent in the printing process
                        makes all the difference, just as it does in various
                        forms—turning around, converting a state into its contrary,
                        transforming finite into infinite—at key points in the journey
                        towards apocalypse in Blake’s poetry.” Through <hi rend="i">Milton, The Four
Zoas</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,
                        Blake struggled to define the proper relationship of craft to art, of his
                        potentially destructive Spectre to the imagination of Los. As Essick
                        concluded, “the drama of Los and his Spectre in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is in part
a mythic portrayal of the subordination of
                        copy work to original composition presented in the <hi rend="i">Public
                            Address</hi> and a vast metaphor for the redemption of traditional
                        techniques underlying the maturation of Blake’s graphic style
                        from 1804 to the end of his life.” Finally, Essick suggested that
                        the physical labor and disciplined energy required of the engraver acted as
                        a necessary counter-balance to Blake’s “speculative and
                        digressive mind,” enabling him to combine in his best poems
                        “his mental adventures and his keen sense of physical
                        reality.”</p>
                    <p>Morton Paley’s essay on “Blake’s
                        Spectre” emphasized the <hi rend="i">personal</hi> aspect of the
                        Spectre, i.e., Blake’s Spectre as the embodiment of what Blake
                        didn’t like about <hi rend="i">himself</hi>, namely his fearful
                        anxiety, his hostility (both passive and active), his envy, pride, and black
                        melancholy, and his extreme sexual jealousy. Paley stressed
                        Blake’s use of the Spectre to reveal his “deep
                        ambivalence about sexual feeling” in “My Spectre around
                        me”; Blake characteristically separated sexual desire (which he
                        associated with the Spectre) from a healthy love, and thus, Paley concluded,
                        Blake is far from being “the exemplum of sexual harmony that some
                        readers may wish to make him.”</p>
                    <p>Paley then analyzed the strategies that Blake used to dominate and control
                        his own evil “spectrous” feelings. He first had to
                        recognize them, as Los does when he divides the Spectre from his Emanation
                            (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 86:54); he then attempted to dominate and control
                        them. But rather than merely casting them out, which Blake knew well could
                        not be easily or permanently done, Blake offered an alternative solution. In
                        Night VIIa of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and on plate 100 of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Blake envisioned a triumphant resolution in
                        which his healthy imagination embraced the Spectre, acknowledging that the
                        Spectre too has his place in the story. Only by coming to terms with his own
                        jealousies, pride and vindictiveness could Blake attain his ultimate vision
                        of imaginative unity: “Therefore the Sons of Eden praise Urthonas
                        Spectre in songs / Because he kept the Divine Vision in time of
                        trouble.”</p>
                    <p>The questioning centered on the degree of success Blake achieved in his
                        acceptance of and control over his Spectre, and especially on whether he
                        liberated himself from a possessive, sexist attitude toward women (let me
                        say, parenthetically, that I happen to think he did not). Even if
                        Blake’s self is imaged in his poetry as finally integrated, does
                        that integration lead to productive relationships with other people, and
                        especially with women? It was suggested that these questions could be
                        fruitfully explored in another MLA Special Session on Blake and sexuality.
                        ANNE K. MELLOR, STANFORD UNIVERSITY.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
