<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>12.3.cheskin</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="article">The Echoing Greenhorn: Blake as Hebraist</title>
                <author n="Cheskin">Arnold Cheskin</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1978-79</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1978-79</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">12.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Production Office</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Cynthia Lewiecki</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>David Anderson</name>
                            <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
                            <name>Lynn Goldstein</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>E. B. Bentley</name>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>David Bindman</name>
                            <name>Izak Bouwer</name>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>Arnold Cheskin</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>Martha Winburn England</name>
                            <name>J. Karl Franson</name>
                            <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>David Irwin</name>
                            <name>Paul McNally</name>
                            <name>Marta Slowikova</name>
                            <name>Robert R. Wark</name>
                            <name>Kazumitsu Watarai</name>
                            <name>Dwight Weber</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1979"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_12">
        <body>
            <pb id="p12-178" n="178"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-12-3-0006">
                <head>
                    <title type="main">
                        <hi rend="b">THE ECHOING GREENHORN: BLAKE AS HEBRAIST</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="b">ARNOLD</hi>
                        <name>
                            <hi rend="b">CHESKIN</hi>
                        </name>
                    </docAuthor>
                </byline>
                <p>As students of Blake know, “the most formative literary and spiritual
                    influence” on him was the Bible.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28"
type="note">1</ref>
                    There is considerable uncertainty, however, about the extent of
                    Blake’s familiarity with the original language of the Old Testament,
                    Hebrew. Although at least eight of his illuminations contain Hebrew
                    inscriptions, “we do not know how much Hebrew Blake had . . .
                        .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">2</ref> In the
thirteen years since
                    Harold Bloom’s acknowledgment, that small island in the sea of Blake
                    scholarship has not, apparently, been covered. I will attempt, then, on the
                    basis of the inscriptions to assess Blake’s knowledge of and facility
                    with Hebrew. Because the irregularities in the inscriptions are so telling, we
                    can focus our attention exclusively on them. If they had been accurate and in a
                    good hand, their evidence would be equivocal. We could not know, in that case,
                    if Blake merely possessed a good eye for copying. <note id="n28">
                        <hi rend="s">1</hi> Jean Hagstrum, <hi rend="i">William Blake: Poet and Painter</hi>
                        (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1964), p. 48.</note>
                    <note id="n29">
                        <hi rend="s">2</hi> Harold Bloom, “Commentary,”
                        in <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David Erdman
                        (New York: Doubleday, 1965), p. 838.</note>
                </p>
                <p>An obvious reason for the uncertainty about Blake’s grasp is that most
                    critics themselves have no Hebrew. One such figure, Mr. A. G. B. Russell,
                    concluded that the subject of Blake’s only lithograph, a bearded
                    “ancient” holding a book inscribed with his name, was
                    “Job in Prosperity.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30"
type="note">3</ref>
                    <note id="n30">
                        <hi rend="s">3</hi> Geoffrey Keynes, introductory monograph to
                            <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes
                        (New York: Pierpont Morgan Library, 1935), p. 8.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Only after the ascription had gained general acceptance did someone notice that
                    the name in Hebrew characters identifies the subject of the lithograph not as
                    Job, but as Enoch. “And he was no more because God took him”
                    (Genesis 5:24), the Biblical description of Enoch’s signal death, is
                    being scrutinized by two naked figures on the right side of the composition. A
                    further irony lies in the very name that was missed—for
                    “Enoch” (“Hanokh” in Hebrew) can mean
                    “education.”</p>
                <p>Unable to assess Blake’s grasp of Hebrew from internal evidence,
                    Frederick Tatham, an early biographer, relied on circumstantial evidence from
                    Blake’s book collection. Finding Hebrew books “well thumbed
                    and dirtied by his graving hands,” Tatham concluded that Blake had
                    “a most consummate knowledge” of the great Hebrew writers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">4</ref> This highly questionable deduction can be
                    put in its proper perspective with the help of G. E. Bentley, Jr.: “As
                    a source of biographical facts [Tatham’s] <hi rend="i">Life</hi> is
                    of dubious value.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">5</ref>
                    <note id="n31">
                        <hi rend="s">4</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Records</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1969), p. 41.</note>
                    <note id="n32">
                        <hi rend="s">5</hi> Bentley, p. 507.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Unfamiliarity with the language seems to be responsible for another disturbing
                    problem in Hebrew-related Blake scholarship. Blake’s lone reference
                    to his Hebrew studies, found in an 1803 letter to his brother James, contains
                    Hebrew characters. They have, however, been printed at least six different ways.
                    In 1921, Geoffrey Keynes printed the series as <rtl>אבכ</rtl> (ABK—’<hi
rend="i">alef, bēth</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">6</ref>
                    <hi rend="i">kaf</hi>) i.e., “am now learning my Hebrew
                        ABK.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">7</ref> (Hebrew
is written from
                    right to left. For ease of comprehension, however, I have written the English
                    equivalents which follow directly, and then the names of the Hebrew letters,
                    from left to right. An alphabet table is printed with my essay for the
                    reader’s reference.) This meaningless series was replaced by an
                    equally meaningless one in 1927: <rtl>אידב</rtl> (AYDB—’<hi rend="i">alef, yōd,
daleth, bēth</hi>), four characters
                    instead of three.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">8</ref>
Finally, in 1968 Keynes
                    proposed <rtl>אבג</rtl> (ABC—<hi rend="i">’alef, bēth,
                        gīmel</hi>)—a rendering which would put Blake at the
                    beginning of his Hebrew language studies.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n36" type="note">9</ref>
                    <note id="n33">
                        <hi rend="s">6</hi> This character would technically require a
                        dot (<hi rend="i">dagesh</hi>) within it in order to be considered a 
<hi rend="i">beth.</hi> But in unvocalized Hebrew the dot is not used. I
                        have read other such letters in the same fashion when clearly
                        appropriate.</note>
                    <note id="n34">
                        <hi rend="s">7</hi> Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">A Bibliography
                            of William Blake</hi> (New York: Grollier Club of New York, 1921), p.
                        451.</note>
                    <note id="n35">
                        <hi rend="s">8</hi> William Blake, <hi rend="i">Pencil
                            Drawings</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes (Great Britain: Nonesuch Press,
                        1927), sketch 27.</note>
                    <note id="n36">
                        <hi rend="s">9</hi> William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Letters of
                            William Blake</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes, (London: Rupert Hart-Davis,
                        1968 [revised edition]), p. 65.</note>
                </p>
                <pb id="p12-179" n="179"/>
                <figure n="EnochDetail.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="678">
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi> (detail).</head>
                    <figDesc>Private collection.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <figure n="lt30jan1803.1.4.lt" id="lt30jan1803.1.ltr.04" work-copy="letters" rend="db" width="611" height="1000">
					<figTranscr>for we have Sold all that we have had time to print. Evans<lb/>
					the Bookseller in Pallmall says they go off very well &amp; why<lb/>
					should we repent of having done them it is doing Nothing<lb/>
					that is to be repented of &amp; not doing such things as these<lb/>
					Pray remember us both to Mr Hall when you see him<lb/>
					I write in great haste &amp; with a head full of botheration<lb/>
					about various projected works &amp; particularly. a work now<lb/>
					Proposed to the Public at the End of Cowpers Life. which<lb/>
					will very likely be of great consequence it is Cowpers<lb/>
					Milton the same that Fuselis Milton Gallery was<lb/>
					painted for, &amp; if we succeed in our intentions the<lb/>
					prints to this work will be very profitable to me &amp;<lb/>
					not only profitable but honourable at any rate The<lb/>
					Project pleases Lord Cowpers family. &amp; I am now<lb/>
					labouring in my thoughts Designs for this &amp; other<lb/>
					works equally creditable These are works to be boasted<lb/>
					of &amp; therefore I cannot feel depressd tho I know that<lb/>
					as far as Designing &amp; Poetry are concernd I am Envied<lb/>
					in many Quarters. but I will cram the dogs for I<lb/>
					know that the Public are my friends &amp; love my works &amp;<lb/>
					will embrace them whenever they see them My only Difficulty<lb/>
					is to produce fast enough.<lb/>
					I go on Merrily with my Greek &amp; Latin. am very<lb/>
					sorry that I did not begin to learn languages early in life<lb/>
					as I find it very Easy. am now learning my Hebrew. א ב ג<lb/>
					I read Greek as fluently as an Oxford scholar &amp; the Testament<lb/>
					is my chief master astonishing indeed is the English Translation<lb/>
					it is almost word for word &amp; if the Hebrew Bible is as well<lb/>
					translated which I do not doubt it is we need not doubt of<lb/>
					its having been translated as well as written by the Holy Ghost<lb/>
					my wife joins me in Love to you both I am Sincerely yours<lb/>
					W Blake</figTranscr>
                    <head>Blake’s letter to his brother James, 30 January, 1803.</head>
                    <figDesc>Library of Congress, Rosenwald Collection.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <pb id="p12-180" n="180"/>
                <figure n="milton.d.p18-15" id="milton.d.illbk.18" work-copy="milton.d" rend="db" width="655" height="1000">
					<figTranscr>18<lb/>
					 תחו<lb/>
					 יומ ו׃סה<lb/>
					 שסע ה וא סש<lb/>
					To Annihilate the Selfhood of Deceit &amp;<lb/>
					False Forgiveness</figTranscr>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, pl. 15 (detail).</head>
                    <figDesc>Library of Congress, Rosenwald collection.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p>Mona Wilson, generally regarded as the best twentieth-century biographer of
                    Blake, remains consistent in printing the series as a four-letter group.
                    However, her 1949 rendering, <rtl>איונ</rtl> (AYON—<hi rend="i">‘alef, yōd, wāw,
nūn</hi>),
                    becomes <rtl>איוב</rtl> (IYOV—<hi rend="i">‘alef, yōd,
                        wāw, vēth</hi>) in the 1969 revision.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n37" type="note">10</ref> This latter version, in striking contrast to
                    Keynes’s latest version (ABC), makes Blake a good Hebraist since <hi rend="i">IYOV</hi>,
the original name for Job, is one of the most difficult
                    books in the Bible. Who, then, is correct? <note id="n37">
                        <hi rend="s">10</hi>
                        Wilson actually seems to be returning here to a second reading offered by
                        Keynes in 1927—and abandoned as early as 1956.</note>
                </p>
                <p>By examining a photographic reproduction of the relevant portion of the letter
                    containing Blake’s lone reference to his Hebrew studies, I have found
                    that Keynes’s last variation, <rtl>אבג</rtl> (ABC), is accurate. No
                    explanation for Keynes’s forty-seven year delay or for other
                    divergent readings is provided by the difficulty “of mak[ing] out what
                    Blake [actually] wrote before he deleted the manuscript or erased the engraving
                    . . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">11</ref> It is
unmistakably
                    legible, as the reproduction below shows. Elsewhere in Blake’s Hebrew
                    inscriptions, however, there are relatively many obscurities and irregularities.
                    Their special character, in contrast to that of the English ones, suggests that
                    Blake never did master all of the Hebrew ABC’s. <note id="n38">
                        <hi rend="s">11</hi> F. W. Bateson, review of <hi rend="i">The Poetry and
                            Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David Erdman, <hi rend="i">New York
                            Review of Books</hi>, 28 October 1965, p. 24.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Plate 18A of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, which contains “letters so
                    erroneous that it seems impossible to identify or 
                    <figure n="TablesoftheLaw.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="761" height="1000">
                        <figTranscr>לא יהי<lb/>
                        לא תש<lb/>
                        זכור<lb/>
                        כבד<lb/>
                        <lb/>
                        לא ת<lb/>
                        לא ת<lb/>
                        לא ת<lb/>
                        לא ת<lb/>
                        לא ת</figTranscr>
                        <head>Tables of the Law.</head>
                        <figDesc>From the Collection of the Jewish Museum, New York.</figDesc>
                    </figure> 
                    translate them,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">12</ref> 
                    serves as a good starting point. This evaluation by S. Foster Damon was actually make
                    of a 1797 inscription in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi> That it applies
                    equally well to this one of 1804 throws into question Damon’s own
                    implication that Blake improved significantly in the years after <hi rend="i">Night
                    Thoughts.</hi> To facilitate an evaluation here, I have included
                    alongside it a typical pair of tablets (a familiar motif in Jewish ceremonial
                    art).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">13</ref>
                    Although several letters
                    scrawled on the tablets in Urizen’s hands are identifiable, they do
                    not form, without interpolation, Commandments or abbreviations for Commandments
                    that sometimes run to several sentences. If this plate existed in isolation, one
                    could argue for the appropriateness of the illegibility in that Urizen and the
                    tablets he holds are, to borrow a word from Blake’s caption, in the
                    process of annihilation. 
                    <note id="n39">
                        <hi rend="s">12</hi> S. Foster Damon,
                            <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols of William
                            Blake</hi> (Providence, R. I.: Brown University Press, 1965), p.
                        215.</note>
                    <note id="n40">
                        <hi rend="s">13</hi> Tablets of unknown origin and date from the
                        collection of The Jewish Museum, New York.</note>
                </p>
                <p>Another set of stone tablets of the Law, in “Job’s Evil
                    Dream” from the Butts watercolors of Blake’s 
                    <hi rend="i">Job</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">14</ref> 
                    begins to make such a
                    sympathetic view untenable. The last three letters from right to left in the
                    line indicated by Job’s persecutor compose “gave,”
                    incorrectly spelled as <rtl>נתנ</rtl> (NTN—<hi rend="i">nūn,
                        tāw, nūn</hi>). The <hi rend="i">nūn</hi>
                    (circled in reproduction), like several other Hebrew letters, requires a
                    different form at the end of a word. It is easily seen that Blake merely repeats
                    the regular <hi rend="i">nūn</hi> (<rtl>נ</rtl>). This loose parallel in
                    English may clarify 
<pb id="p12-181" n="181"/>
                    the fundamental nature of the
                    error: spelling “jeopardy” with an
                    “i”—“jeopardi”—instead
                    of a “y” because the verb form uses the
                    “ize” suffix (“jeopardize”). Just as the
                    “i” cannot end “jeopardy,” so a regular <hi rend="i">nūn</hi> cannot end
                    <rtl>נתן</rtl>. This is not, apparently, the
                    only such error. <note id="n41">
                        <hi rend="s">14</hi>
                        <hi rend="i"> Job</hi>, pl. 11.</note>
                </p>
                <p>One way of explaining this inscription is by positing Blake’s use of a
                    transliteration. Since both regular letters and their final counterparts sound
                    identical, the English (Roman) character would not distinguish them. I have not
                    found evidence of printed transliterations of the Hebrew Bible extant in
                    Blake’s time, but it is possible that his instructor transliterated
                    the Ten Commandments for Blake.</p>
                <p>This hypothesis might also explain another “letter interchange”
                    committed in the Milton tablets. On the one in Urizen’s right hand,
                    Blake substitutes a ס (S—<hi rend="i">samkh</hi>) for what should
                    be a ת (S [according to the Ashkenazic pronunciation]—<hi rend="i">taw</hi>). These
Commandments, however, are listed out of order
                    (10, 
                    <figure n="but550.1.11.wc" id="but550.1.wc.11" work-copy="but550.1" rend="db" width="958" height="787">
						<figTranscr>אלהיך נתנ<lb/>
						<lb/>
						שםיה        לא תרצח<lb/>
						<lb/>
						לא תנאף<lb/>
						<lb/>
						תגנב<lb/>
						<lb/>
						inv<lb/>
						WB</figTranscr>
                        <head>
                            <hi rend="i">Job’s Evil Dreams</hi> (detail).</head>
                        <figDesc>Pierpont Morgan Library.</figDesc>
                    </figure> 
                    probably 9, 3), forcing us to posit more specifically a faulty
                    transliteration or a faulty reading of a correct transliteration.</p>
                <p>Another way of explaining some of Blake’s irregularities arises from
                    the tablets in “Job’s Evil Dream.” There the sixth,
                    seventh, and eighth Commandments, according to the Hebrew reckoning, are listed
                    in correct sequence, although they appear in the seventh, eighth, and ninth
                    positions. In the sixth position is the phrase <rtl>א-להך נתנ</rtl> (“Your God
                    has given”); (the dash is to be disregarded. Jewish law prohibits
                    writing God’s name in this kind of context.) which we have discussed
                    earlier from a formal standpoint. Although neither a Commandment nor an
                    abbreviation for one, the phrase actually does originate in the sections of the
                    Bible containing the Ten Commandments (Exodus, ch. 20 and Deuteronomy, ch. 5).
                    In fact, these words are among the last in the fifth Commandment:
                    “Honor your father and mother so that your days may be many upon the
                    land which the Lord <hi rend="i">your God has given</hi> you.” One may
                    be inclined to posit that Blake mistook the end of the fifth Commandment for the
                    beginning of the sixth. This would not explain, though, how Blake managed to
                    miscopy the final <hi rend="i">nūn</hi> (correctly written as ן,
                    not נ), if he had a text in front of him.</p>
                <pb id="p12-182" n="182"/>
                <figure n="laocoon.b.p1" id="laocoon.b.illbk.01" work-copy="laocoon.b" rend="db" width="822" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>If Morality was Christianity Socrates was the Saviour<lb/>
 יה &amp; his two Sons Satan &amp; Adam as they were copied from the Cherubim<lb/>
		of Solomons Temple by three Rhodians &amp; applied to Natural Fact. or History of Ilium<lb/>
		              Art Degraded Imagination Denied War Governed the Nations<lb/>
		Evil<lb/>
		                  Good &amp; Evil are<lb/>
		Riches &amp; Poverty a Tree of<lb/>
		                                        Misery<lb/>
		                  propagating<lb/>
		                  Generation &amp; Death<lb/>
		The Gods of Priam are the Cherubim of Moses &amp; Solomon: The Hosts<lb/>
		                                                                                             of Heaven<lb/>
		    Without Unceasing Practise nothing can be done Practise is Art<lb/>
		     If you leave off you are Lost<lb/>
		The Angel of the Divine Presence<lb/>
		                                             מלאך       יהוה<lb/>
		ΟΦΙουΧος<lb/>
		                                              Hebrew Art is<lb/>
		                                       called Sin by the Deist Science<lb/>
		                            All that we See is Vision<lb/>
		from Generated Organs gone as soon as come<lb/>
		                     Permanent in The Imagination; Considerd<lb/>
		                                 as Nothing by the<lb/>
		                                       Natural Man<lb/>
		What can be Created<lb/>
		Can be Destroyed<lb/>
		    Adam is only<lb/>
		The Natural Man<lb/>
		&amp; not the Soul<lb/>
		or Imagination<lb/>
		Good<lb/>
		                                       לילית<lb/>
		Satans Wife The Goddess Nature is War &amp; Misery &amp; Heroism a Miser<lb/>
		    Spiritual War<lb/>
		Israel deliverd from Egypt<lb/>
		    is Art deliverd from<lb/>
		       Nature &amp; Imitation<lb/>
		         A Poet a Painter a Musician an Architect : the Man<lb/>
		         Or Woman who is not one of these is not a Christian<lb/>
		You must leave Fathers &amp; Mothers &amp; Houses &amp; Lands if they stand in the way of Art<lb/>
		The Eternal Body of Man is The Imagination, that is God himself<lb/>
		                                   The Divine Body }    ישע     Jesus   we are his<lb/>
		                                                                                             Members<lb/>
		                     It manifests itself in his Works of Art (In Eternity All is Vision)<lb/>
		The True Christian Charity not dependent on Money (the lifes blood of Poor Families)<lb/>
		         that is on Caesar or Empire or Natural Religion<lb/>
		Money, which is The Great Satan or Reason<lb/>
		              the Root of Good &amp; Evil<lb/>
		                  In The Accusation of Sin<lb/>
		Prayer is the Study of Art                            <lb/>
		Praise is the Practise of Art                            <lb/>
		Fasting &amp;c. all relate to Art<lb/>
		The outward Ceremony is Antichrist<lb/>
		       Where any view of Money exists Art cannot be carried on, but War only Read Matthew C X. 9 &amp; 10v<lb/>
		by pretences to the Two Impossibilities Chastity &amp; Abstinence Gods of the Heathen<lb/>
		He repented that he had made Adam<lb/>
		            (of the Female, the Adamah)<lb/>
		                                       &amp; it grieved him at his heart<lb/>
		Art can never exist without<lb/>
		         Naked Beauty displayed<lb/>
		The Gods of Greece &amp; Egypt were Mathematical<lb/>
		                                                        Diagrams<lb/>
		                                                            See Plato’s<lb/>
		                                                                   Works<lb/>
		       Divine Union<lb/>
		    Deriding<lb/>
		And Denying Immediate<lb/>
		Communion with God<lb/>
		The Spoilers say<lb/>
		Where are his Works<lb/>
		That he did in the Wilderness<lb/>
		           Lo what are these<lb/>
		Whence came they<lb/>
		These are not the Works<lb/>
		Of Egypt nor Babylon<lb/>
		Whose Gods are the Powers<lb/>
		Of this World. Goddess, Nature.<lb/>
		Who first spoil &amp; then destroy<lb/>
		Imaginative Art<lb/>
		For their Glory is<lb/>
		War and Dominion<lb/>
		Empire against Art          See Virgils Eneid.<lb/>
		                                               Lib. VI.v 848<lb/>
		For every<lb/>
		Pleasure<lb/>
		Money<lb/>
		Is Useless<lb/>
		     There are States<lb/>
		         in which. all<lb/>
		     Visionary Men<lb/>
		     are accounted<lb/>
		           Mad Men<lb/>
		         such are<lb/>
		     Greece &amp; Rome<lb/>
		     Such is<lb/>
		     Empire<lb/>
		     or Tax<lb/>
		See Luke Ch 2 v 1<lb/>
		Jesus &amp; his Apostles &amp; Disciples were all Artists Their Works were destroyd by the Seven Angels of the Seven Churches in Asia    Antichrist      Science<lb/>
		                            The unproductive Man is not a Christian much less the Destroyer<lb/>
		The Old &amp; New Testaments are<lb/>
		    the Great Code of Art       Art is the<lb/>
		                                                   Tree<lb/>
		                                               of Life<lb/>
		                                                   GOD<lb/>
		                                               is Jesus<lb/>
		                                               Science is the<lb/>
		                                               Tree of Death<lb/>
		The Whole Business of Man Is<lb/>
		The Arts &amp; All Things     Common<lb/>
		                         No Secresy in Art<lb/>
		What we call Antique Gems                 <lb/>
		                are the Gems of Aarons Breast Plate<lb/>
		                Christianity is Art<lb/>
		                &amp; not Money<lb/>
		                Money is its Curse<lb/>
		       Is not every Vice possible to Man<lb/>
		                described in the Bible openly<lb/>
		       All is not Sin that Satan calls so<lb/>
		                  all the Loves &amp; Graces of Eternity.<lb/>
		Drawn &amp; Engraved by William Blake.</figTranscr>
                    <head>
                        <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> (detail).</head>
                    <figDesc>Collection of Mrs. Charles T. Rosenbloom.</figDesc>
                </figure>
                <p>However well they explain individual phenomena, neither of the hypotheses
                    suggested so far—nor others like faulty memory, which give Blake the
                    benefit of the doubt—explains everything. The unmethodical character
                    of the irregularities leaves us with two possible explanations: willful
                    subversion or ignorance. But the case for willful subversion—that
                    Blake knew better but deliberately made errors to disparage the tradition he saw
                    as “One [tyrannical] Law for the Lion and the Ox”; or that he
                    chose to keep himself a greenhorn to Hebrew on principle—is
                    simultaneously unsupportable and irrefutable. We do not know his mind.
                    Nevertheless, we seem justified in one conclusion. Given their elementary
                    nature, it makes most sense to see the 
<pb id="p12-183" n="183"/>
                    irregularities
                    as arising from ignorance. To see intention here is to argue that
                    “jeopardi” spelled by an immigrant or elementary-school
                    student is deliberate.</p>
                <p>That mere carelessness is not Blake’s bane in the inscriptions can
                    best be seen through his rendering of the first letter of the Hebrew alphabet,
                    <rtl>א</rtl> (<hi rend="i">‘alef</hi>). The letter requires a diagonal bar
                    slanting up from right to left. In “The Laocoön” he
                    slants the bar in the opposite direction, down from right to left. In the
                    frontispiece to <hi rend="i">Job</hi> (1825), he slants it correctly. And in
                    “Job’s Evil Dream” (also 1825), he does both. Since
                    only an inch separates letters in the latter illumination, it is practically
                    impossible to believe that he did not notice the discrepancy. In all
                    probability, he thought that either form was acceptable—as in the
                    Arabic numeral “four,” written “4” and
                    “4.”</p>
                <p>We can, at this point, formulate a judgment more specific than Harold
                    Fisch’s when he says: Blake “knew little or no
                    Hebrew.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">15</ref> We
                    have seen that he
                    was not entirely without Hebrew. Even a brief note like the following found
                    among the many proverb-like sayings in “The
                    Laocoön” suggests some familiarity: “He repented
                    that he had made Adam (of the Female, the Adamah).” A complete
                    foreigner to Hebrew would not know that the “ah” (<rtl> ָה</rtl>)
                    ending is feminine. We have seen, nonetheless, that the first of
                    Fisch’s possibilities—that Blake knew little
                    Hebrew—best fits the 
                    evidence.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">16</ref>
                    <note id="n42">
                        <hi rend="s">15</hi> Harold Fisch, “William
                        Blake,” <hi rend="i">The Encyclopedia Judaica</hi> (Jerusalem:
                        Keter Publishing House, 1971), IV, 1071-72.</note>
                    <note id="n43">
                        <hi rend="s">16</hi> An assessment of Blake’s Hebrew
                        does not require treatment of his every use of Hebrew. When taken as a
                        whole, the instances not discussed in this paper (listed below) corroborate
                        my findings. See “Figure Studies” in <hi rend="i">The
                        Paintings of William Blake</hi>, ed. Darrell Figgis (New York: Charles
                        Scribner’s Sons, 1925), p. 82; the title page and pl. 2 of <hi rend="i">Job</hi>,
                        the last page of the third of the <hi rend="i">Night
                        Thoughts</hi>, and pl. 35 of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, copy
                        D.</note>
                </p>
                <p>One of the interesting unsolved problems connected with Blake’s Hebrew
                    is his means of acquiring it. Unfortunately, even in an area like this, where no
                    Hebrew writing is involved, the scholarship is problematic. Damon indicates the
                    problem of Blake’s acquisition this way: “We do not know who
                    Blake’s teachers were . . . [In] London . . . he continued his
                    [Hebrew] studies, probably with some local rabbi . . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">17</ref> G. E. Bentley, Jr. seems to have found the
                    solution. Basing his claim on the January 1803 letter to James, Bentley
                    identifies William Hayley as Blake’s 
                    tutor.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">18</ref> 
                    The letter, however, contains no reference to Hayley in
                    this capacity. And a perusal of the <hi rend="i">Dictionary of National
                    Biography</hi> and Hayley’s own <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi> reveals
                    no evidence that Hayley knew enough Hebrew to serve as 
                    tutor.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">19</ref> 
                    Even with some energetic digging and good fortune, it
                    is possible, to use Blake’s words, that “this mystery never
                    shall cease.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">20</ref>
                    <note id="n44">
                        <hi rend="s">17</hi> Damon, p. 215.</note>
                    <note id="n45">
                        <hi rend="s">18</hi> Bentley, p. 526, n. 3.</note>
                    <note id="n46">
                        <hi rend="s">19</hi> William Hayley, <hi rend="i">Memoirs of the
                            Life and Writings of William Hayley, Esq.</hi>, ed. John Johnson
                        (London: Henry Colburn &amp; Co., 1823).</note>
                    <note id="n47">
                        <hi rend="s">20</hi> William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Poetry and
                            Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes (London: Nonesuch
                        Press, 1927), p. 94.</note>
                </p>
                <figure n="HebrewKey.12.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="705" height="1000"/>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
