<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>12.4.mellor</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Karl Kroeber and William Walling, eds., Images of Romanticism: 
Verbal and Visual Affinities</title>
        <author n="Mellor">Anne K. Mellor</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1979</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1979</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">12.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Cindy Lewiecki</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Marietta Barnes</name>
              <name>Lynn Goldtein</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Katharyn R. Gabriella</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>G. Ingli James</name>
              <name>John Kilgore</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>Anne Mellor</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>R.J. Shroyer</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1979"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_12">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-12-4-0009">
        <pb id="p12-267" n="267"/>
        <div2>
          <figure n="ImagesofRomanticism.12.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="353"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Karl Kroeber and William Walling, eds. <hi rend="b">Images of Romanticism:
Verbal and Visual Affinities.</hi> New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press, 1978. 232 pp., 63 pls.
$18.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Anne K.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Mellor</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The twelve original essays in this exciting collection approach the interdisciplinary study of
literature and the visual arts in nineteenth century England from a broadly humanistic perspective. Wisely
avoiding the obsessively verbal and overly abstract methodology of the structuralists, these essays see both
literary and artistic works as “complexly engaged in a cultural density of particular time, place and
circumstance.” They range from Rudolph Arnheim’s speculations on the translatability of temporal experiences
into spatial form to detailed analyses of Turner’s imagery. En route, they establish the breadth of concerns
and vitality of such an interdisciplinary approach to romanticism.</p>
          <p>Of most immediate interest to Blakists will be Jean H. Hagstrum’s “Blake and British Art: The
Gifts of Grace and Terror.” Defining two distinct traditions in Blake’s art, the sublime or 
<hi rend="i">terribilità</hi> of Michelangelo and the beautiful or delicate, Hagstrum identifies several possible
and hitherto overlooked influences on Blake’s art. Most convincing is his analysis of the affinities of
George Romney’s black chalk drawings in the classically sublime style (now in the Walker Gallery, Liverpool)
to Blake’s depictions of Urizen and of Romney’s images of threatened innocence (in the same collection) to
Blake’s depictions of Thel. Hagstrum quite rightly emphasizes Blake’s conscious emulation of the style of
delicate beauty also found in works by Stothard, Flaxman, Banks and Romney, which is a useful corrective to
the tendency to focus primarily upon Blake’s monumental or horrific images in the sublime style of
Fuseli.</p>
          <p>All of these essays will reward the reader interested in the relations of literary to visual
texts, and I have space here only to point to a few of the highlights. Lorenz Eitner provides an extensive
survey of the imagery of cages and prisons in nineteenth century literature and art, developing the historical
interpretation that one might expect, namely, that the eighteenth century cages of security and protected
innocence gave way, after the French Revolution, to a negative view of the cage as a repressive prison.
William Walling’s superb study of Sir David Wilkie and the Scottish literary tradition suggests that an
overriding concern with the energy and diversity of social life led both Wilkie and his literary
contemporaries, Robert Fergusson, John Galt, Robert Burns and Sir Walter Scott, to eschew abstract formal
designs. When, in response to Enlightenment aesthetic demands, they attempted to give a clear structure to
their works, these structures seem forced, insincere and theatrical. Walling’s concluding “regret” that a
critical, academic concern with abstract structures has led us to ignore or undervalue the richness of human
diversity and hence of such “episodic” artworks, should give us all pause.</p>
          <p>Several essays concern themselves wholly or in part with Turner’s art. James A. W. Heffernan,
in “The English Romantic Perception of Color,” argues that Turner’s use of color parallels Wordsworth’s
conception of the “moulding” eye of the imagination which sees every object in nature as distinct and yet part
of a single harmonious whole. Karl Kroeber’s fine essay on “Romantic Historicism: The Temporal Sublime”
rightly emphasizes the insistence in the works of Turner, Carlyle and Tolstoy upon the ways in which the past
is dynamically recreated in the present. Ronald Paulson’s searching essay on the meaning of Turner’s
images, “Turner’s Graffiti: The Sun and Its Glosses,” brilliantly analyzes the range of
associations—religious, political,
<pb id="p12-268" n="268"/>
psychological—carried by Turner’s sublimely overwhelming sun/god/king/father. And Paulson argues that the
vortex structure within which this sun characteristically appears grows as much out of verbal signs and ideas
(“turner”’s name, his barber-father’s whorled pole) as out of Turner’s early sketches of vortically
copulating bodies. Paulson’s psychoanalytical speculations are carried to an extreme by R. F. Storch who
argues, somewhat simplistically, that Shelley’s and Turner’s tendencies to abstraction can be equated with
an alternation between aggression toward women and a dream-fantasy of total love. Storch then applauds
Constable’s and Wordsworth’s “sobriety” at the expense of Shelley’s and Turner’s overly dissociated
object-relations, a position that many will find controversial. Martin Meisel, in his concluding study of the
use of John Martin’s and Turner’s designs as theatrical scenery, speculates that Martin’s designs were
preferred for infernal and apocalyptic scenes and Turner’s for paradisiacal scenes because Martin’s clear
outlines emphasize the separation and insignificance of man while Turner’s visual blurring of all
distinctions between the human form and its environment creates an impression of heavenly reconciliation.</p>
          <p>I have saved the first essay, Rudolph Arnheim’s “Space as an Image of Time,” for final
discussion because I find myself in partial disagreement with Arnheim’s contention “that any organized
entity, in order to be grasped as a whole by the mind, must be translated into the synoptic condition of
space.” Arnheim seems to believe, not only that all memory images of temporal experiences are spatial, but
that they are also synoptic, i.e. instantaneously perceptible as a comprehensive whole. I would like to
suggest instead that all spatial images, however static and complete as objects, are experienced temporally by
the human mind. In other works, we “read” a painting or piece of sculpture or building in much the same way as
we read a page. After isolating the object to be read, we begin at the upper left, move our eyes across and
down the object; when this scanning process is complete, we return to the images of greatest density and
complexity, or to those which the formal design emphasizes, for closer study. However quickly this process of
framing, scanning and focusing occurs, it is a process with a definite temporal dimension. In this sense,
spatial and temporal artistic works have even more in common than Arnheim acknowledges; temporal works are
recalled as spatial structures, but those spatial structures must in turn be “read” or dynamically apprehended
through a temporal process.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
