<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>13.1.malmqvist</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake in China</title>
        <author n="Malmqvist">N. G. D. Malmqvist</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1979</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1979</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">13.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Cindy Lewiecki</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Susan Fox</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>N.G.D. Malmqvist</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Warren H. Stevenson</name>
              <name>Robert H. Tener</name>
              <name>Raymond E. Thompson</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1979"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_13">
    <body>
      <pb id="p13-24" n="24"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-13-1-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">BLAKE IN CHINA</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <figure n="KejiaSelectedPoems.13.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="694" height="1000">
          <figTranscr>布萊克詩选</figTranscr>
          <head>1 <hi rend="i">Selected Poems of Blake</hi>, trans. and ed. by Yuan Kejia et al.</head>
          <figDesc>Contents include: “Songs of Innocence,” “Songs of Experience,” “Poetical Sketches,”
“Miscellaneous Poems,” and “Fragments of Letters and Other Sayings.”</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor><hi rend="b">N. G. D.</hi> <name><hi rend="b">MALMQVIST</hi></name></docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>“Some twenty years ago the Chinese poet Hsü Chih-mo took down a book from my shelves, and after
reading a few lines he exclaimed: ‘This man is a Taoist!’” These words served as introduction to a BBC
lecture by Arthur Waley which was broadcast in January 1948. (The lecture, “Blake the Taoist,” was later
published in Waley’s <hi rend="i">The Secret History of the Mongols</hi>, London 1963.) The lines which the
young poet Hsü Chih-mo (1895-1931) had read introduce Book the Second of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>:
<q>
There is a place where Contrarities are equally True:<lb/>
This place is called Beulah. It is a pleasant lovely Shadow<lb/>
Where no dispute can come, Because of those who Sleep.
</q>
It is easy enough to substantiate the claim that Blake and the Taoist thinker Chuang-tzu were brethren in
spirit. The first stanza of <hi rend="i">Auguries of Innocence</hi> contains a lyrical summary of the
teachings of the early Taoist thinkers.</p>
        <p>Waley speculates over the possibility that Blake may have been influenced by the work 
<hi rend="i">Tao Te Ching</hi> (The Book on Tao and its Power), the classic of Chinese Taoism. He points out that
a translation of that work into Latin had been acquired by the Royal Society in 1788 and noted in 
<hi rend="i">Philosophical Transactions.</hi> Blake may well have seen the work and gained some knowledge of its
content. Whether he did so or not, we do know that he shared the Taoist thinkers’ distrust of rational
intellect as a means for true understanding. Chance may have guided Hsü Chih-mo to Blake in the late 1920s.
He is known to have translated at least one of Blake’s poems—his best known, “The Tyger.” Unfortunately I
have not succeeded in tracing his translation.</p>
        <p>A search through the various indices and bibliographies which register translations of foreign
literature into Chinese yields very meagre results as far as Blake is concerned. Prior to 1957 only a handful
of Blake’s poems had made their way into Chinese anthologies of English poetry in translation.</p>
        <p>In 1957 interest in Blake flared up in China. This was not due to mere chance: the World Peace
Congress had elected William Blake the poet of that year. A great many translations and analyses of Blake’s
writings were published in 1957. In the late summer of 1957 the Chinese Writers’ Union organized a Blake
evening in Peking, to which I was invited. Old Bob Winter, an American scholar who during several decades has
lectured on English and American literature at Peking University, gave an introductory lecture on Blake and
his work, and Guo
<pb id="p13-25" n="25"/>
Moruo, President of the Academia Sinica and nestor among Chinese poets, extemporized poetry, hailing the
memory of the English poet.</p>
        <p>The poet Feng Zhi, formerly Chairman of the Department of Foreign Literature at Peking University
and presently Director of the Institute of Foreign Literature at the newly established Academy of Social
Sciences, has provided me with the following list of translations of and studies on Blake’s writings.</p>
        <p>Yuan Kejia, “Bulaike ersan shi” (Random notes on a few poems by Blake), <hi rend="i">Renmin
Ribao</hi> (People’s Daily), 22/5/57</p>
        <p>Yuan Kejia, “Bulaike de shi” (The poetry of Blake), <hi rend="i">Wenxue yanjiu</hi> (Literary
Studies), 4/57</p>
        <p>Yuan Kejia, and others, <hi rend="i">Bulaike shixuan</hi> (Blake Anthology), <hi rend="i">Renmin
wenxue chubanshe</hi>, 9/57</p>
        <p>Dai Liuling, “Lun Bulaike de ‘Lundun’” (On Blake’s “London”), <hi rend="i">Zhongshan daxue
xuebao</hi>, 3/57</p>
        <p>Song Xueting, “Bulaike de shixuan” (Selections of Blake’s poetry), <hi rend="i">Yiwen</hi>
(Literature in translation), 9/57</p>
        <p>Zhao Luorui, “Neng shen ai yi neng shen hen de Weilian Bulaike,” (William Blake who was capable of
great love and of great hatred), <hi rend="i">Wenhuibao</hi>, 25/6/57</p>
        <p>Bian Zhilin, “Tantan Bulaike de jishou shi” (Random notes on a few poems by Blake), 
<hi rend="i">Shikan</hi> (Poetry), 7/57</p>
        <p><corr type="emend">Yuan Kejia’s</corr> <hi rend="i">Blake Anthology</hi>, which comprises 176 pages, contains a large
selection from Blake’s lyrical poetry. The work is divided into the following five parts: (1) 
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (<hi rend="i">Shide sumiao</hi>), which contains all the poems of that
collection, with the exception of “Fair Elenor,” “Gwin, King of Norway,” “An Imitation of Spenser,” “King
Edward the Third,” “Prologue to King John,” “A War Song to Englishmen,” and the prose-poems. The translations
have been done by Cha Liangzheng, who has published poetry under the pseudonym <corr type="emend">Mu Dan.</corr> (2) <hi rend="i">Songs
of Innocence</hi> (<hi rend="i">Tianzhen zhi ge</hi>). translated in entirety by Yuan Kejia. (3) 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> (<hi rend="i">Jingyan zhi ge</hi>), containing all the poems of that
collection with the exception of “The Human Abstract,” translated by Song Xueting. (4) Poems from the 
<hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> 1800-1803, and poems from the Pickering manuscript, translated by Huang Yushi, Song
Xueting, and Cha Liangzheng. (5) Fragments, epigrams and parts of <hi rend="i">Proverbs of Hell</hi>,
translated by Huang Yushi.</p>
        <figure n="TitlePagePekingBlake.13.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="639" height="1000">
          <figTranscr>布萊克詩选<lb/>
          <lb/>
          人民文学出版社<lb/>
          一九五七年 · 北京</figTranscr>
          <head>2 Title page.</head>
          <figDesc>Pu lai k’e shih hsüan (Selected Poems of Blake), Renmin wenxue chubanshe (People’s
Literature Publishing House), 1957, Peking.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <figure n="FrontispiecePekingBlake.13.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="910" height="1000">
          <figTranscr>作者像</figTranscr>
          <head>3 Frontispiece, <hi rend="i">Selected Poems of Blake.</hi></head>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p13-26" n="26"/>
        <p>In his book <hi rend="i">The Chinese Literary Scene</hi> (Penguin 1977, pp. 222-32) Professor Hsu
Kai-yu gives a biographical sketch of Yuan Kejia, who was born in 1921. As a young student Yuan Kejia took a
great interest in modernistic poetry and was particularly infatuated with the works of T. S. Eliot. At the end
of the 1940s he lectured in English Literature at Peking University, while at the same time editing the
literary pages of the celebrated Tientsin paper <hi rend="i">Da Gong Bao</hi>, which earlier had been edited
by the author Shen Congwen, and, after him, by the poet Feng Zhi. After the Liberation Yuan Kejia left his
teaching post at Peking University and was enrolled in the team which had been given the task of translating
<hi rend="i">Mao Zedong xuanji</hi> (Selected Works of Mao Zedong) into English. His talents as a translator
secured him a post on the editorial board of <hi rend="i">Chinese Literature.</hi> In 1957 Yuan Kejia was
offered a post in Academia Sinica, where he was charged with editing the <hi rend="i">Blake
Anthology.</hi></p>
        <p>In his preface to the <hi rend="i">Blake Anthology</hi> Yuan Kejia suggests that 
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> may be considered a turning-point in the development of English literature.
The false classicism which hails reason and is content with society as it is
<figure n="ThePiperTranslation.13.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="652" height="1000">
	<head>4 “The Piper.”</head>
	<figDesc>Literal translation, lines 1-3: “ I come down from a deserted valley, blowing my flute,/ I play
joyful songs,/ I see a child in the cloud.”</figDesc>
</figure>
yields to a revolutionary romanticism which places enthusiasm and fantasy in the seats of honour and demands
political and social change. According to Yuan Kejia <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> expresses a
revolutionary humanism which—coupled with Blake’s Christian idealism—embodies both the positive
(progressive) and negative (reactionary) aspects of Blake’s writings. Blake’s fundamentally humanitarian
views make it possible for him to attack the inhuman conditions in society. But as a result of the failure of
the French Revolution, Blake’s humanism loses its revolutionary characteristics. The truce between England
and France in 1802 inspired Blake with the mistaken notions that violence cannot lead to peace and that a
tyrannical authority is capable of bettering itself on its own initiative. Thereafter, says Yuan Kejia, Blake
preached a message of conciliation which makes him appear a defeatist. Finally Yuan Kejia suggests that
Blake’s enthusiastic support for the bourgeois revolution, his social criticism, and his demands for the
emancipation of the individual make him a pioneer among the English revolutionary-romantic writers.</p>
        <p>A few months after the publication of the <hi rend="i">Blake Anthology</hi>, Yuan Kejia followed
the stream of
<figure n="ToSpringTranslation.13.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="820" height="1000">
	<head>5 “To Spring.”</head>
</figure>
<pb id="p13-27" n="27"/>
intellectuals down to the countryside, in order to be cleansed through participation in physical labour. In
1959 he returned to his post at the Academy, where he was charged with the compilation of a volume of
translations of the poetry of Robert Burns, whom the World Peace Congress had chosen as the year’s writer
for 1959. In his preface to that volume Yuan Kejia hands out both praise and blame: Burns’ sympathy with the
poor and his hatred against landowners and aristocrats cannot altogether compensate for his lack of class
spirit and his reactionary view that man should be content with his lot in life and grab what little is
offered while life lasts. Apart from Yuan Kejia’s short preface, the <hi rend="i">Blake Anthology</hi>
contains no critique of Blake’s writings. Yuan Kejia does not seem to have pruned the selection in order to
accommodate the Chinese readers.</p>
        <p>Using Blake’s “London” as point of departure Dai Liuling discusses the evil social conditions in
London of the late eighteenth century. The author suggests that the deep significance of Blake’s “London”
“only recently” has been noticed by certain progressive critics. (Reading Dai Liuling’s paper I was reminded
of the film version of Dickens’s <hi rend="i">Great Expectations</hi> which was shown in Peking in 1957 and
which many Chinese no doubt believed to be an authentic description of England in the 1950s.) Discussing the
widespread prostitution in eighteenth century England, Dai Liuling states that poverty and hunger—these evil
products of the capitalist society—were not solely responsible for the spread of prostitution. The brunt of
the blame must be borne by the hypocritical sexual morality of the Establishment and the intolerant
Church.</p>
        <p>Discussing Blake’s poem “A Little Girl Lost” (<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>) Dai Liuling
decries the fate of “a fallen women” in bourgeois society: “Her parents refused to regard her as a human
being, since she had disgraced the family. She could find neither work nor a roof over her head, since the
factories refused to employ her and even the gates of the poor-house were closed to her. Her one and only way
out was therefore to earn her living as a prostitute.” With an indignation which appears as genuine as
Blake’s own, Dai Liuling concludes her essay by quoting the first stanza of “A Little Girl Lost”:
<q>
Children of the future Age<lb/>
Reading this indignant page<lb/>
know that in a former time<lb/>
love! Sweet love! was thought a Crime.
</q>
It is not altogether inconceivable that Dai Liuling’s indignation was directed at closer quarters than the
worldly authorities and the Church in eighteenth century England.</p>
        <p>Song Xueting’s “Bulaike de shixuan” (Selections of Blake’s poetry), which appeared in the
journal <hi rend="i">Yiwen</hi> (Literature in translation), 9/57, contains a few poems from 
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (“To Spring,” “To the Evening Star,” “How sweet I roam’d,” and “Mad Song”);
three poems from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (“Introduction,” “Spring,” “Night”); a few poems from
<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> (“Introduction,” “The Tyger,” “Holy Thursday,” “London,” and “The
Chimney Sweeper”), together with some poems from the <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> and short excerpts from 
<hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> (Plate 6: Asia) and <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> Song Xueting divides Blake’s
writings into two main categories. To the first category belong <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches, Songs of
Innocence</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, which are said to contain “glittering jewels and
sharp dagger edges.” In the second category Song Xueting groups <hi rend="i">The French Revolution,
America</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Vision of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, which sing of the Revolution and the
emancipation of women; <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Jerusalem</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, which are
said to contain Blake’s own mythological system which is difficult to fathom. Song Xueting finally mentions
<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, which he considers the best prose writing of Blake.</p>
        <p>Song Xueting states that Blake was well ahead of his time and that he therefore failed to gain the
appreciation of his contemporaries. After his death bourgeois critics rendered the understanding of his works
difficult, by obscuring the significance of the symbolism in his social criticism. “When we now celebrate the
200th anniversary of Blake’s birth,” says Song Xueting, “our main duty is to weed out all these misleading
notions and restore the fundamental significance of Blake’s writings.” Zhao Lourui’s essay “Neng shen ai
yi neng shen hen de Weilian Bulaike” (William Blake who was capable of great love and of great hatred) was
published in the <hi rend="i">Wenhuibao</hi> 6/57, which appeared on 12 May 1957, a few weeks before the
Anti-rightist Campaign was initiated. The author characterizes Blake as “the most kind-hearted, the purest and
the most sincere humanitarian,” a man who refused to compromise and who never hesitated to follow the road
which he himself considered the right one. Zhao Luorui presents a very fine translation of “The Sick Rose,”
fair renderings of “London,” together with passages translated from <hi rend="i">Auguries of
Innocence.</hi></p>
        <p>Bian Zhilin’s essay “Tantan Bulaike de jishou shi” (Random notes on a few poems by Blake)
appeared in the journal <hi rend="i">Shikan</hi> (Poetry) 7/57, an issue dedicated to the Anti-rightist
Campaign. The essay is accompanied by translations of five of Blake’s poems, namely “Laughing Song” and “The
Chimney Sweeper” from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, and “The Chimney Sweeper,” “The Tyger,” and “A
Poison tree” from <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi> As may be expected from a translator who must be
considered as one of China’s major poets, Bian Zhilin’s rendering of “Tyger” is technically superb. The
analysis which accompanies the translation I personally find too concretized and politicized:
<q>
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Tyger</hi> has altogether sprung from his own imagination. Blake wrote his 
<hi rend="i">Tyger</hi> in the same way as our traditional painters depicted dragons and tigers. But the main
theme in Blake’s poem is the fearful act of creation which gave the tiger its form. The traditional view
that God created the world has here given way to the new conception that physical labour created the world.
Throughout his poem Blake uses the image of the smith and his work, an image which often recurs in Blake’s
writings. The second stanza (“In
<pb id="p13-28" n="28"/>
what distant deeps or skies / burnt the fire of thine eyes?”) makes us today think of the prospecting teams
which, struggling to build up a socialist China, search out the natural resources that lie hidden under
thousand mountains and ten thousand rivers. The final verses of the fourth stanza (“What the anvil? What dread
grasp / dare its deadly terror clasp?”) remind us of the taming of nuclear power which will bestow great
blessings on mankind. The poem teaches us that creation is struggle, in which contrarieties are finally
united. In the penultimate stanza of the poem (“When the stars threw down their spears / and water’d Heaven
with their tears”) the poet creates another synthesis of oppositions, and the martial song changes into a mild
melody. The struggle is over and the worker, who has laboured with his task, sees the result and smiles
contentedly. The mild lamb and the ferocious tiger, innocence and experience, have been united and that
synthesis harbours a new innocence.
</q>
Bian Zhilin’s interpretation of the lines “When the stars threw down their spears / and water’d Heaven
with their tears” is interesting, as it shows that the poet here pushes the ideologist to the side.</p>
        <p>Bian Zhilin suggests that many people may have been surprised at the decision of the World Peace
Congress to elect Blake the writer for the year 1957, as he is generally regarded as a mystic. No, says Bian
Zhilin, Blake was no mystic: the verses that may suggest that he was a mystic have been deliberately tampered
with. Throughout his life Blake sided with the common people; he supported endeavors to realize national
democracy, national independence, and the emancipation of women. He sympathized with the downtrodden masses in
England and abroad, with the French Revolution and the American War of Independence; he supported the struggle
for the abolition of slavery, openly opposed war, advocated peace, and stood in firm opposition to the
Establishment and the Church. Even though he was unable entirely to emancipate himself from the traditions of
the Christian faith, he was foremost a humanitarian. Fundamentally an idealist, with a tendency towards
utopian ideas, he clearly comprehended the dialectic principles: “Without contrarieties there can be no
progression.”</p>
        <p>Bian Zhilin has a ready answer to the question why Blake, in spite of his progressive views, failed
to influence the masses of his time. It is commonly known, says Bian Zhilin, that the reactionary English
Establishment with all means suppressed opinions which were inimical to its own interests. As a result
thinkers and writers had to express themselves in allegorical terms, which in turn led to misinterpretations
of their works. We must also remember, says Bian Zhilin, that Blake lacked experience of political struggle
and that he therefore sometimes tended to empty speculation. Blake was ahead of his time and was therefore not
appreciated by his contemporaries. . Posterity lacks knowledge of the concrete historical background of his
writings. This is another reason why Blake has been misinterpreted as a mystic.</p>
        <p>Bian Zhilin’s close friend Hsü Chih-mo (Xu Zhimo) needed only to read a few lines of Blake’s
writings to comprehend that Blake was a Taoist. Bian Zhilin, who apparently had devoted a close study to Blake
and his English and American interpreters, found it necessary, in 1957, to explain away the mystic elements in
Blake’s writings, with reference to misinterpretations which were occasioned by the reactionary English
Establishment’s suppression of dissidents. Obviously there was no room for Taoist ideas in the political and
literary climate of China in 1957.</p>
        <figure n="KaiSongsofInnocence.13.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="633" height="1000">
          <figTranscr>3<lb/>
          <lb/>
          SONGS<lb/>
          of<lb/>
          Innocence<lb/>
          <lb/>
          1789<lb/>
          <lb/>
          The Author &amp; Printer W Blake<lb/>
          <lb/>
          “天真之歌” 初版封面</figTranscr>
          <head>6 From <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi></head>
          <figDesc>Illustrations and captions were kindly provided by Professor Kai yu hsu, Dept. of World and
Comparative Literature, San Francisco State Univ. and author of <hi rend="i">Literary Scene</hi>
(Vintage).</figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
