<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>13.1.welch</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake’s Response to Wollstonecraft’s Original Stories</title>
        <author n="Welch">Dennis M. Welch</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1979</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1979</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">13.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Cindy Lewiecki</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Susan Fox</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>N.G.D. Malmqvist</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Warren H. Stevenson</name>
              <name>Robert H. Tener</name>
              <name>Raymond E. Thompson</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1979"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_13">
    <body>
    <pb id="p13-4" n="4"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-13-1-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">BLAKE’S RESPONSE TO WOLLSTONECRAFT’S <hi rend="i">ORIGINAL
              STORIES</hi></hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <figure n="songsie.z.p48" id="songsie.z.illbk.48" work-copy="songsie.z" rend="db" width="650" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>48<lb/>
	INFANT SORROW<lb/>
	My mother groand! my father wept.<lb/>
	Into the dangerous world I leapt:<lb/>
	Helpless, naked, piping loud:<lb/>
	Like a fiend hid in a cloud.<lb/>
	Struggling in my fathers hands:<lb/>
	Striving against my swadling bands:<lb/>
	Bound and weary I thought best<lb/>
	To sulk upon my mothers breast.</figTranscr>
          <head>1 “Infant Sorrow,” pl. 48, Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
              Experience</hi>, Library of Congress, Rosenwald Collection.</head>
        </figure>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">DENNIS M.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">WELCH</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>It appears certain that William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
            Albion</hi> (1793) was partly inspired by Mary Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Vindication
            of the Rights of Woman</hi> 
            (1792).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> 
            It likewise
          appears true that two of his songs of Innocence, “The Little Boy Lost” and “Found,” had
          their source in C. G. Salzmann’s <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality</hi>, which
          Wollstonecraft was translating in 1789 and which Blake did several engravings 
          for.<ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> That he met Wollstonecraft through his acquaintance with
          her novel, <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi>, also seems 
          likely.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> 
          For the second edition of the novel, published in 1791, he designed <hi rend="i">and</hi> engraved 
          six plates.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> 
          But whether his poetry and art were influenced by <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi> has never
          been clarified. The purpose of this essay is to reveal a number of relationships between
          Wollstonecraft’s novel and Blake’s writing, art, and ideas. 
	<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against
            Empire</hi>, 2nd ed.
            (Princeton Univ. Press, 1969), p. 243; and Mark Schorer, <hi rend="i">William Blake: The
              Politics of Vision</hi> (New York: Henry Holt, 1946), p. 290. In “Notes on 
              <hi rend="i">The Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>,” <hi rend="i">MLQ</hi>, 9
            (1948), 292-97, Henry H. Wasser argues that <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> is about
            Wollstonecraft and Fuseli, Blake’s friend.</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi>
            Joseph Wicksteed, “Blake’s Songs of Innocence,” <hi rend="i">TLS</hi>, 18 February 1932,
            p. 112. In “The Figure in the Carpet,” <hi rend="i">Blake: An Illustrated
            Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 10-14, Robert N. Essick notes stylistic similarities between
            two engravings in <hi rend="i">Elements</hi> (pls. 28 and 47) and two of Balke’s
            illustrations for <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi> (the frontispiece and pl.
            6).</note>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, p.
            156.</note>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi><hi rend="i"> Original Stories from Real
              Life</hi>; with Conversations, Calculated to Regulate the Affections, and Form the
            Mind to Truth and Goodness (London: Printed for J. Johnson, 1791). See Geoffrey Keynes,
              <hi rend="i">A Bibliography of William Blake</hi> (New York: The Grolier Club, 1921),
            p. 199; and Roger R. Easson and Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake: Book
              Illustrator</hi> (Normal, Ill.: American Blake Foundation, 1972), I, 9-12. All
            subsequent quotations from <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi> are from the 1791 edition,
            indicated with page numbers in parentheses.</note></p>
        <p>As the book’s illustrator and as the author of the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>
          (1789), Blake was likely to have read this short novel on the moral education of children.
          D. G. Gillham says that the poet “alludes to” or “uses” it in the <hi rend="i">Songs of
            Experience</hi> (1793). Referring apparently to the novel and Wollstonecraft’s other
          works on “education,” Stanley Gardner says that Blake knew her views “well” and that he
          turned them “into poetry in which we recognize our own adult anticipation, which caresses
          the infant inevitably toward 
          Experience.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> Gillham and
          Gardner to not add anything further to these comments, but they are well taken, especially
          Gardner’s. Although he understates the force of “adult anticipation” (in both
          Wollstonecraft and Blake), his assertion is particularly important to our understanding of
          Blake’s response to <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi>, a novel that 
          <pb id="p13-5" n="5"/>
          seems to compare with Rousseau’s <hi rend="i">Ëmile.</hi> In <hi rend="i">Original
          Stories</hi> the main character, Mrs. Mason, acts as a governess for two young girls,
          Mary and Caroline. Like Ëmile the girls need a tutor since they are for all practical
          purposes orphans. Their mother has died and they have been left to the care of servants
          (p. vii). To teach these girls to be good, Mrs. Mason continually exposes them to their
          faults and to the need to behave morally in the “real world.” The thesis of this article
          is that, while Blake recognized the necessity of living in experience, he responded
          unfavorably to the novel’s emphasis on experienced vision, which divides life into false
          categories like good and evil and is negative, oppressive, and dehumanizing. Such vision
          had already been of some concern to him in a few poems in the <hi rend="i">Songs of
          Innocence.</hi> I suggest that his reaction to it was intensified by his familiarity
          with Wollstonecraft’s novel and its main character, Mrs. Mason, who, unlike Ëmile’s tutor,
          neither regards children as independent nor educates them to be 
          so.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> 
          In the following paragraphs I discuss the character of the
          governess, showing how Blake reacted to her kinds of attitudes and concerns in (1) his own
          writing, (2) some of the designs for his illuminated works, and (3) the illustrations for
          the novel itself. <note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Gillham, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Contrary
              States: The “Songs of Innocence and of Experience” as Dramatic Poems</hi> (Cambridge
            Univ. Press, 1966), p. 97; Gardner, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (New York: Arco Publishing,
            1969), p. 124.</note>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> According to Rousseau, female
            independence is subservient to man’s, however. See the section entitled “Sophie ou la
            femme” in <hi rend="i">Ëmile</hi> (Paris: Garnier Frères, 1964), pp. 445-574.</note></p>
        <p>Wollstonecraft’s aim in writing <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi> was to make up for
          some of the parental neglect in her society (p. v). To accomplish her aim she used her
          novel to impart “premature knowledge” about good and evil to the young (p. v), who,
          according to her personal views and those of other educators (including Rousseau), ought
          to receive such knowledge only gradually (p. iv). At the center of her effort is the
          character of Mrs. Mason, whose attitudes toward life and children and whose approach and
          emphasis in teaching were no doubt offensive to Blake. For Mrs. Mason life has been “very
          unfortunate,” as she says (p. 122). Having suffered the loss of loved ones, she cannot
          dispel her sense of “gloom” (p. 123). Preoccupied with her bleak view of existence (see p.
          148), the governess imposes it on her charges just as the speaker in Blake’s “Infant
          Sorrow” imposes her dark vision on the child in her 
          care.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> 
          According to this speaker, whom I take to be the maternal figure in the
          illustration of the poem (illus. 1), her birth was a tragedy and so she tells her child:
          “My mother groand! my father wept. / Into the dangerous world I 
          leapt. . . .”<ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> 
          With this attitude it is no wonder that the mother in
          the illumination of “Infant Sorrow” appears so solicitous, wishing like Mrs. Mason to give
          all the adult knowledge and help she can to the youth for whom she is responsible. 
            <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> I agree essentially with Gillham’s and Brian Wilkie’s views
            that the speaker in “Infant Sorrow” is an embittered adult who dwells on the sorrows of
            birth and life (<hi rend="i">Blake’s Contrary States</hi>, pp. 180-81; “Blake’s 
              <hi rend="i">Innocence and Experience:</hi> An Approach,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>,
            6 [1975], 127).</note>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi><hi rend="i"> The Poetry and
              Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman, commentary by Harold Bloom (Garden
            City, N. Y.: Doubleday, 1970), p. 28, 11. 1-2. The subsequent quotations from Blake’s
            writings are from this edition (E), indicated with page or plate and, where appropriate,
            line numbers in parentheses.</note></p>
        <p>Like the governess she means well. But her view of youth (her own and presumably her
          child’s) is mostly negative (11. 3-4). It is a view that resembles Mrs. Mason’s. Children
          are ignorant, helpless, and potentially wayward—in need of guidance and control (11. 5-8,
          “Infant Sorrow”; pp. 103-06, <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi>). Because Mary and
          Caroline are so undiscerning, the governess seldom allows them to read the Bible (p. 13)!
          Instead, like the gloomy instructress on plate 14 of <hi rend="i">America</hi> (illus. 2),
          she keeps them steadily occupied with her teaching; without her direction they will not be
          able to get along in society. Blake may be satirizing her excessive sort of care in
          another of his guardian figures—the nurse in his design for “The Fly” (illus. 3). This
          nurse hovers over a child “in a solicitous manner which seems stifling,” as John Grant
          says.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> 
          Like the nurse, Mrs. Mason tries not to let
          her wards “out of her sight” (p. viii). She fosters their dependence on her, for despite
          her efforts to teach them goodness and virtue she does not trust them to remain steadfast.
          Thus, at the end of the novel when the girls are about to return to their father, the
          governess says that she fears for them (p. 175). <note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> John E.
            Grant, “Interpreting ‘The Fly,’” in <hi rend="i">Blake: A Collection of Critical
              Essays</hi>, ed. Northrop Frye (Englewood Cliffs, N. J.: Prentice-Hall, 1966), p. 49.
            See also Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> (Garden City, N. Y.: Anchor
            Books, 1974), p. 82.</note></p>
        <p>Children, alas, are weak, all too prone to forming “illusions” (p. 122) and being
          deceitful. For Blake such an opinion is an adult imposition on the young, an imposition
          that begins with the earliest stages of child rearing and invariably affects many a
          child’s view of himself. The poet 
          <figure n="america.e.p16" id="america.e.illbk.16" work-copy="america.e" rend="db" width="746" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>In the flames stood &amp; view’d the armies drawn out in the sky<lb/>
	Washington Franklin Paine &amp; Warren Allen Gates &amp; Lee:<lb/>
	And heard the voice of Albions Angel give the thunderous command<lb/>
	His plagues obedient to his voice flew forth out of their clouds<lb/>
	Falling upon America, as a storm to cut them off<lb/>
	As a blight cuts the tender corn when it begins to appear.<lb/>
	Dark is the heaven above, &amp; cold &amp; hard the earth beneath;<lb/>
	And as a plague wind fill’d with insects cuts off man &amp; beast;<lb/>
	And as a sea o’erwhelms a land in the day of an earthquake;<lb/>
	Fury! rage! madness! in a wind swept through America<lb/>
	And the red flames of Orc that folded roaring fierce around<lb/>
	The angry shores, and the fierce rushing of th’ inhabitants together;<lb/>
	The citizens of New-York close their books &amp; lock their chests;<lb/>
	The mariners of Boston drop their anchors and unlade;<lb/>
	The scribe of Pensylvania casts his pen upon the earth;<lb/>
	The builder of Virginia throws his hammer down in fear.<lb/>
	Then had America been lost, o’erwhelm’d by the Atlantic,<lb/>
	And Earth had lost another portion of the infinite,<lb/>
	But all rush together in the night in wrath and raging fire<lb/>
	The red fires rag’d! the plagues recoil’d! then rolld they back<lb/>
	with fury</figTranscr>
            <head>2 Pl. 14, Blake’s <hi rend="i">America.</hi></head>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p13-6" n="6"/>
          <figure n="songsie.z.p40" id="songsie.z.illbk.40" work-copy="songsie.z" rend="db" width="635" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>40<lb/>
	THE FLY.<lb/>
	Little Fly<lb/>
	Thy summers play.<lb/>
	My thoughtless hand<lb/>
	Has brush’d away.<lb/>
	Am not I<lb/>
	A fly like thee?<lb/>
	Or art not thou<lb/>
	A man like me?<lb/>
	For I dance<lb/>
	And drink &amp; sing:<lb/>
	Till some blind hand<lb/>
	Shall brush my wing.<lb/>
	If thought is life<lb/>
	And strength &amp; breath;<lb/>
	And the want<lb/>
	Of thought is death;<lb/>
	Then am I<lb/>
	A happy fly,<lb/>
	If I live,<lb/>
	Or if I die.</figTranscr>
            <head>3 “The Fly,” pl. 40, Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                Experience</hi>, Library of Congress, Rosenwald Collection.</head>
          </figure>
          <figure n="bb514.3.1.com" id="bb514.3.comb.01" work-copy="bb514.3" rend="db" width="520" height="1000">
          	<figTranscr>Frontispiece.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Blake. d. &amp; sc:<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Look what a fine morning it is. __ Insects,<lb/>
          	Birds, &amp; Animals, are all enjoying existence.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Published by J. Johnson. Septr. 1st. 1791.</figTranscr>
            <head>4 Blake’s frontispiece to Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Original Stories from Real
                Life</hi>, The Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.</head>
          </figure> 
          reacted to this kind of imposition in his notebook lyric, “A Cradle Song” (c.
          1793), wherein the speaker assumes that smiles “steal” furtively from her child in order
          to elicit continued personal comfort (i.e., fondling and caressing). According to this
          speaker, her child’s grins are expressions of “cunning wiles that creep” in the “heart” (E
          459, 11. 10, 13-14). The speaker’s assumptions, like Mrs. Mason’s, suggest ironically that
          guile is inherent in youth—instead of 
          adulthood.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref>
          <note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> My understanding of this lyric is largely
            indebted to D. G. Gillham, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (Cambridge Univ. Press,
            1973), p. 66.</note></p>
        <p>The governess’s lack of trust in young people is revealed also by her disapproving
          eye—the kind of eye that Blake was to describe with bitter irony in “A Little Girl Lost.”
          Just as Mary and Caroline move toward experience and feelings of guilt under Mrs. Mason’s
          suspicious eye, so does Ona under her father’s “loving [actually condemning] look” (E 29,
          1. 27). The governess’s “quiet steady displeasure” makes her charges feel “so little in
          their own eyes” that they appear visibly ashamed (p. 52). Ona appears likewise; with her
          father’s disfavor she looks “pale and weak” (1. 30). Mary and Caroline are also frightened
          by Mason’s disapproving eye (p. 53); similarly, Ona shakes “with terror” at her father’s
          look (1. 29).</p>
        <pb id="p13-7" n="7"/>
        <figure n="songsie.z.p38" id="songsie.z.illbk.38" work-copy="songsie.z" rend="db" width="647" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>38<lb/>
	NURSES Song<lb/>
	When the voices of children. are heard on the green<lb/>
	And whisprings are in the dale:<lb/>
	The days of my youth rise fresh in my mind,<lb/>
	My face turns green and pale.<lb/>
	Then come home my children. the sun is gone down<lb/>
	And the dews of night arise<lb/>
	Your spring &amp; your day. are wasted in play<lb/>
	And your winter and night in disguise.</figTranscr>
          <head>5 “Nurse’s Song,” pl. 38, Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
              Experience</hi>, Library of Congress, Rosenwald Collection.</head>
        </figure>
        <p>The real significance of attitudes like those of the governess and Ona’s father did not
          elude Blake. As guardians committed to moral virtue these characters are, in fact,
          accusers of sin—the likes of which angered the poet throughout his entire career.
          According to his annotations to Berkeley’s <hi rend="i">Siris</hi> (c. 1820), “The Moral
          Virtues [and their advocates] are continual Accusers of Sin &amp; [they] promote . . .
          Dominency over others” (E 653). Although Mrs. Mason uses the word “sin” only once (p.
          108), she domineers over her charges, continually correcting them for offenses against
          mildness, obedience, industry, and temperance. To some extent, the “admonishers” whom
          Blake was to satirize in <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> (1795) resemble her, especially
          those admonishers who “restrain the child . . . That the remnant may learn to obey, [and]
          / That the pride of the heart may fail . . . ” (6:19-7:3). Closer in time to the
          publication of the second edition of <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi>, Blake’s “Nurses
          Song” (in <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>) presents another accuser of sin like Mrs. Mason.
          The nurse’s language implies that the children for whom she is responsible are either
          wasting their youth at play or up to something, whispering “in the dale” (E 23, 11. 2, 7).
          Because of her suspicions she believes, as D. G. Gillham says, that the children “must be 
          <figure n="but244.1.4.wd" id="but244.1.wd.04" work-copy="but244.1" rend="db" width="530" height="1000">
	<figTranscr/>
            <head>6 Blake’s preliminary drawing for frontispiece of <hi rend="i">Original
                Stories</hi>, Library of Congress, Rosenwald Collection.</head>
          </figure> 
          . . . constantly watched” (<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, p. 38); and so she
          calls them home (1. 5), limiting their enjoyment as Mrs. Mason does Mary’s and Caroline’s
          (pp. 42, 128, 154, 177).</p>
        <p>Mrs. Mason strives to teach Mary and Caroline moral virtue by focusing their attention
          not only on their shortcomings but also on the “real” world. Unlike the tutor in 
            <hi rend="i">Ëmile</hi> she is mirthless, heaping excessive care on her charges. For
          example, she tries to inculcate patience and long-suffering by introducing the girls to
          Mrs. Trueman, who has retained her moral values despite having been grossly cheated by
          Lady Sly (p. 49). Mrs. Mason attempts to teach her charges kindness by telling them about
          one man who drowned his dog’s litter (p. 18) and about another who “let two guinea-pigs
          roll down sloping tiles, to see if the fall would kill them” (p. 18). As the last two
          examples indicate, some of the experiences to which the governess introduces her charges
          are scarcely appropriate or edifying. Although they make mistakes, Mary and Caroline are
          neither heartless nor cruel. They would hardly learn mildness and self-control by hearing
          about Jane Fretful, who threw a stool and unintentionally killed her pregnant dog because
          it had taken a piece of her 
          <pb id="p13-8" n="8"/>
          food (pp. 33-34), or about Mr. Lofty, who killed himself after duelling with a man he 
          thought had insulted him (pp. 134-135).</p>
        <p>As most of the experiences that Mrs. Mason deals with are in some way negative or
          unhappy, Blake devoted three of his five rejected designs and five of his six engravings
          for <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi> to 
          them.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> All
          of his engravings for the novel reveal together his strongest response to the governess’s
          dour perspective. For the most part, however, the illustrations have been disregarded by
          Blakeans as either “native and rude” or “competent” but “conventional and 
          uninspired.”<ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> 
          Differing with such views, Roger Easson and Robert Essick suggest that the engravings 
          ought to be studied 
          closely.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> 
          I agree. The illustrations were among Blake’s early 
            <hi rend="i">original</hi> copper-plate engravings. It is likely that he would have done them well
          to secure further work for himself, but more importantly to complete his original designs.
          He despised the separation of design work from engraving and believed, as Morris Eaves
          says, that “the artistic process is a perfect combination . . . of conception and
          execution. . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> 
          The engravings, then, are not hack
          work. On the contrary, they are subtle, ironic, and revealing. Except for the
          frontispiece, which is introductory in nature, they depict stories and situations whereby
          Mrs. Mason pushes Mary and Caroline more and more directly into experience. 
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> W. Clark Durant’s edition of William Godwin’s 
              <hi rend="i">Memoirs of Mary Wollstonecraft</hi> (1927; rpt. New York: Haskell House Publishers,
            1969) includes copies of the rejected and used designs for <hi rend="i">Original
              Stories.</hi></note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Alexander Gilchrist, 
              <hi rend="i">The Life of William Blake</hi>, 2nd ed. (London: John Lane the Bodley Head,
            n.d.), p. 92; Jean Hagstrum, <hi rend="i">William Blake: Poet and Painter</hi> (Univ. of
            Chicago Press, 1964), p. 119.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Easson and
            Essick, p. vii. The engravings studies here are from the 1791 edition of 
              <hi rend="i">Original Stories.</hi></note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Morris Eaves, “Blake
            and the Artistic Machine: An essay in Decorum and Technology,” <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi>,
            92 (1977), 909.</note></p>
        <p>According to David Erdman, Blake parodied the frontispiece (illus. 4) in his illumination
          for the “Nurses Song” of <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> (illus. 5), which depicts a
          governess assisting one of her charges just outside a doorway (<hi rend="i">The
            Illuminated Blake</hi>, p. 80). Indeed, there are images in the frontispiece that are
          parodied. Furthermore, there are details in it that are ironic. The plate shows Mrs. Mason
          with her charges in front of a doorway. They are beginning to take a walk. And the
          governess’s influence is beginning to reveal itself as the nurse’s does in the
          illumination of Blake’s lyric. Mary and Caroline appear uniform and neatly groomed (like
          the boy in the design for “Nurses Song”). The girls’ hats, which look a little like halos,
          imply the virtue and probity that they are supposed to learn under their teacher’s
          direction. But the girl on the right is out of step with her sister and the governess. And
          the children’s hands are in different positions, indicating perhaps different degrees of
          repressed vitality (like the boy’s in Blake’s poem). Despite the engraving’s subscription
          (words that Mrs. Mason speaks in Chapter I), there is little spontaneity or joy here. The
          children and their guardian are not smiling although they appear to be doing so a little
          in the preliminary drawing for the frontispiece (illus. 6). The governess is not even
          looking upward or outward at the “fine morning” but instead downward watchfully at her
          charges. She holds her arms outstretched not in joy but as if to present Mary and Caroline
          to the world. Having turned the girls’ eyes and heads slightly toward her, however, Blake
          foreshadowed their inevitable dependence on her. He implied similar dependence in a
          rejected drawing entitled “Every prospect smiled” (illus. 7), which involves the same 
          <figure n="but244.1.1.wd" id="but244.1.wd.01" work-copy="but244.1" rend="db" width="546" height="1000">
          	<figTranscr>Every prospect smiled</figTranscr>
            <head>7 Blake’s preliminary drawing for <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi>’ “Every
              prospect smiled,” Library of Congress, Rosenwald Collection.</head>
          </figure>
          <figure n="bb514.3.2.com" id="bb514.3.comb.02" work-copy="bb514.3" rend="db" width="521" height="1000">
          	<figTranscr>P. 24<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	The Dog strove to attract his attention. __<lb/>
          	He said, Thou wilt not leave me!<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Published by J. Johnson, Septr. 1, 1791.</figTranscr>
            <head>8 Pl. 2, from Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi>, The Beinecke
              Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.</head>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p13-9" n="9"/>
          <figure n="but244.1.6.wd" id="but244.1.wd.06" work-copy="but244.1" rend="db" width="601" height="1000">
	<figTranscr/>
            <head>9 Blake’s preliminary drawing for pl. 2, <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi>,
              Library of Congress, Rosenwald Collection.</head>
          </figure>
          <figure n="bb514.3.3.com" id="bb514.3.comb.03" work-copy="bb514.3" rend="db" width="540" height="1000">
          	<figTranscr>P. 74.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Indeed we are very happy! ________<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Published by J. Johnson, Septr. 1, 1791.</figTranscr>
            <head>10 Pl. 3, from Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi>, The Beinecke
              Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.</head>
          </figure> subject matter as that of the frontispiece (but without its subtlety), and in
          the relationship between the governess and her charges in “Nurses Song.”</p>
        <p>The second plate in the novel (illus. 8) depicts part of a tragic story that Mrs. Mason
          tells Mary and Caroline. The story concerns a man named Robin, who fell into debt, went to
          jail, and lost his wife and two of his four children to poverty and disease. His remaining
          children and the family dog joined him in jail, but soon afterwards the children died of a
          fever. They lie on a bed in his cell. To present the woeful image that Mrs. Mason tries to
          create in Mary’s and Caroline’s minds, Blake stayed fairly close to the verbal
          description: “The poor father . . . hung over their bed in a speechless anguish; not a . .
          . tear escaped from him, whilst he stood, two or three hours, in the same attitude,
          looking at the dead bodies of his little darlings. The dog licked his hands, and strove to
          attract his attention . . . ” (p. 23). Blake’s engraving illustrates this man’s grief
          perfectly. Robin stands rigidly with his shoulders drawn up, his arms held straight down
          in front of him, and his hands closed in fists. His gaze, while more poignant and less
          horrified than in the preliminary drawing (illus. 9), is fixed on his children. All of
          these details suggest a prolonged contraction of grief. Few signs of hope appear in his
          cell—only the prayerful position of one of his children and the consoling lick of Robin’s
          hand by his dog. One wonders why the governess tells Mary and Caroline about this man and
          his family, except to make her charges conscious of life’s cruelty and misfortune. She
          draws no specific moral, except the implicit one of being charitable to debtors; but her
          example is much too extreme for her audience. Despite the grief and hopelessness in this
          story, Blake captured something in Robin’s stance and gaze that Mrs. Mason finds
          pathetic—namely, his determination or will to believe in life regardless of the evidence
          before him. At the end of his contraction of grief, he says to his dog, which he later
          calls by his children’s names: “thou wilt not leave me . . . ” (p. 23).</p>
        <pb id="p13-10" n="10"/>
        <p>The third engraving in <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi> (illus. 10) shows the governess
          and her charges in “honest” Jack’s cottage, listening to tales about his life as a
          sailor—tales of imprisonment, shipwreck, and personal injury. Mrs. Mason wanted the
          children to hear about his experiences, for she had heard about them before and
          undoubtedly considered them edifying in light of his assertion that he and his family are
          now “very happy” (p. 74). Blake, however, did not emphasize this moral so much as 
            <hi rend="i">his</hi> interpretation of the children’s reaction to it and of the adults’
          reaction to them. Satirizing the theme of misery leading to happiness, the illustration
          shows Mary, Caroline, and Jack’s family grieving about his stories. (The novel says
          nothing of this.) The plate is critical of Mrs. Mason and especially Jack; they sit back
          unresponsive to the children’s distress. The governess watches her charges calmly, her
          hands not even turned up in support of them as they cry in her lap. Jack is even less
          supportive as he sits stiffly with his hands in his lap, looking at Mrs. Mason, ignoring
          Mary’s, Caroline’s, and his family’s sorrow. As if retelling his experiences were not
          enough (we get the impression that he cannot forget them), on the wall to the left of his
          fireplace is a picture of a sinking vessel—a constant reminder to his family and visitors
          that the world is a dangerous place.</p>
        <figure n="bb514.3.4.com" id="bb514.3.comb.04" work-copy="bb514.3" rend="db" width="500" height="1000">
          <figTranscr>P.94.<lb/>
          <lb/>
          Be calm, my child, remember that you<lb/>
          must do all the good you can the present day.<lb/>
          <lb/>
          Published by J. Johnson, Septr. 1. 1791.</figTranscr>
          <head>11 Pl. 4, from Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi>, The Beinecke
            Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.</head>
        </figure>
        <p>In the fourth plate (illus. 11), Blake illustrated the governess trying to make her
          charges confront a scene in experience directly. The scene is a ruined estate once owned
          by Charles Townley, a young man who continually procrastinated and as a result lost a
          fortune and the chance to help a friend in dire need. Blake’s illustration is gloomy and
          ominous with trees that overhang and twine serpent-like in the setting—trees that contrast
          with the opening plate’s foliage which dances innocently upward (illus. 4) and which Mary
          and Caroline enjoy very little of. Less detailed than the description in the text, the
          fourth plate emphasizes not so much Townley’s estate as the girls’ reaction to mutability
          and Mrs. Mason’s response to them. Faced with this setting and the story behind it, the
          girl on the right leans against the governess for comfort. Mrs. Mason holds her
          reassuringly but mostly (I think) in attention to the 
          scene.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> 
          The governess’s right foot suggests that she may be about to step back as if
          to anticipate this girl’s retreat (her right heel is also visible) and her increased
          distress like that of the other girl, whose hand Mrs. Mason holds. This situation is
          similar to an earlier one in the novel, wherein both “children turned away” from another
          view of experience—the sight of a bird shot down by a young boy (p. 7). In spite of the
          girls’ distress, the governess insisted that they “look at” the bird and learn how much
          suffering there is in life. <note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> In <hi rend="i">The
              Engravings of William Blake</hi> (1912; rpt. New York: Benjamin Blom, 1968), p. 58,
            Archibald G. B. Russell says that the girl “trembles . . . and is gently reproved by
            Mrs. Mason, who . . . clasps her to herself.”</note></p>
        <p>The fifth engraving in <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi> (illus. 12) deals with one of
          Mrs. Mason’s own experiences, which she tells Mary and Caroline. Like the previous
          illustration this one emphasizes the governess’s concern about mutability (p. 119). During
          a trip through Wales she was detained “near the ruins of an old castle” (pp. 113-14).
          While pondering the castle, she heard the sound of a harp, and tracing that sound she came
          upon “a little hut, rudely built” (p. 114). Like the “desolate” castle (and the estate
          depicted in the previous plate), the harper’s abode was dilapidated (pp. 114-15). Blake’s
          engraving suggests hesitancy in Mrs. Mason’s approach to that abode—hesitancy born out of
          her apprehensions about the 
          scene.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> Her hands,
          positioned anxiously at her sides, resemble those of the woman at the top of “Holy
          Thursday” (in <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>), which also presents a desolate landscape
          (illus. 13). The position of the governess’s hands contrasts sharply with that in the
          frontispiece (illus. 4), where her hands imply receptiveness and acceptance, and in plates
          3 and 4 (illus. 10 and 11), where her hands encourage these traits in her charges. This
          contrast suggests her fears and perhaps some hypocrisy. In spite of the decrepit condition
          of the harper’s abode, the difficulties in his life (p. 117-118), 
          <pb id="p13-11" n="11"/>
          and his “old” age (p. 115), Blake portrayed him as an inspired young man sitting in a
          shaft of light, his hair ablaze while he plays his 
          instrument.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> 
          The engraver’s perception indeed contrasted with Mrs. Mason’s.
          According to her story, the meeting with the harper was “providential” (p. 119), but that
          was only because she was able to extend to him her charity—not because she perceived (as
          Blake did) his imaginative power which enabled him to play both the melancholy strains of
          experience (p. 118) and the delightful melodies of innocence (p. 119). 
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> In the fifth plate of the 1796 edition of 
          <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi>, Mrs. Mason’s “eyes have been partly closed” (Easson 
          and Essick, p. 12).</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Erdman (<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, p. 181)
            and Laurence Binyon (<hi rend="i">The Engraved Designs of William Blake</hi> [1926; rpt.
            New York: Da Capo Press, 1967], p. 40) note the difference in age between the harper in
            the text and the harper in the engraving. Binyon feels that Blake “put more of his own
            spirit [into the plate] than into the rest of the set” (p. 40).</note></p>
        <p>The sixth and last plate (illus. 14) depicts appropriately the culmination of Mrs.
          Mason’s effort to expose Mary and Caroline to experience, for here they face directly a
          poor family in despair. Like several “edifying” situations in the novel, this one is
          arranged by the governess. Caroline has just spent the last of her money during a visit to
          London. To show the child that “prodigality and generosity are incompatible” (p. 173),
          Mrs. Mason asks a poor woman to take them to her family, which lives in a filthy garret.
          The focus of Blake’s plate is on the family’s suffering and Mary’s and Caroline’s
          recognition of it. According to the narrator of the novel, the father in this family is
          ill and out of work (p. 170). The illustration shows him sitting despondently in a chair.
          His muscular body suggests that he has done a great deal of work and could do more—if he
          were well and there were any work available. In front of him two of his children sit on
          the floor, one of them huddled in misery on one side of a grate while the other on the
          opposite side of the grate stares blankly into his lap. For these children this is no
          world of innocence: “The gaiety natural to their age, did not animate their eyes. . . .
          Life was nipped in the bud; shut up just as it began to unfold itself” (p. 172). These
          children look as unhappy as “honest” Jack’s family in plate 3 (illus. 10). In plates 3 and
          6 Blake portrayed similar and contrasting details such as the unhappiness in each, Jack
          sitting upright in a chair while the poor man sits slumped over in his, and the ample
          furnishings and fire in Jack’s living room versus the starkness of the poor man’s. Blake’s
          aim in depicting these comparisons and contrasts was probably to help us see that the
          preoccupations of a parent like Jack and the situation of one like the poor man can
          consign their families to the same condition—unhappiness.</p>
        <p>Standing with an infant in her arms, the mother in plate 6 presents the most disturbing
          image in her family. The floppy brim of her hat indicates its age and her poverty. With
          her mouth open and the look of fear in her face, she stares at Mrs. Mason as if to ask
          what is going to happen. The situation is truly grim. As the governess looks on somberly,
          she holds one hand of each of her charges. The girl on the left appears uneasy, her mouth
          contracted in a frown and her head tilted to the side and slightly back. The girl on the
          right appears dismayed, her eyes wide open and staring at the misery in front of her. The
          gesture of this girl’s left hand may hint at a desire to offer some comfort; but the
          gesture is too constrained and therefore ineffective.</p>
        <p>Blake may have also produced an unnamed and unused drawing concerning the visit to London
          by Mrs. Mason and her charges (illus. 15). It appears to deal with an elderly woman,
          possibly the “distressed stationer” whom the governess and Mary and Caroline visit. The
          stationer is distraught with the burden of her grandchildren and a declining family
          business, her son having been jailed for debt and her daughter-in-law having died (pp.
          165-68). The drawing seems to picture the stationer with her grandchildren at her side and
          a cloth clutched in her hands, her face turned upward in 
          misery.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref> 
          A faint outline of Mrs. Mason’s profile appears to be on the
          right-hand side of the drawing where she observes another example of human suffering.
            <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> A copy of a wood-cut of this drawing appears in
            Gilchrist, p. 91.</note></p>
        <p>As a result of Mrs. Mason’s influence these girls learn about the “real” world. By the 
          <figure n="bb514.3.5.com" id="bb514.3.comb.05" work-copy="bb514.3" rend="db" width="498" height="1000">
          	<figTranscr>P.114.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Trying to trace the sound, I discovered<lb/>
          	a little hut, rudely built.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Published by J. Johnson, Septr. 1, 1791.</figTranscr>
            <head>12 Pl. 5, from Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi>, The Beinecke
              Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.</head>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p13-12" n="12"/>
          concluding pages of the novel Mary “has acquired
          experience” and Caroline “an air of intelligence” (p. 161). The governess’s purpose in
          getting them to focus on their shortcomings and on experience has been to convince them
          that in a world of cruelty and misfortune they should live rationally, for it is reason
          that “exalts a man” (p. 105). In her rational concern, however, she threatens to stifle
          Mary’s and Caroline’s vigor, imagination, and individuality. For example, she reasons that
          duty should always come before pleasure (pp. 42, 177). Hence, we see her charges playing
          only occasionally. And when they do enjoy themselves, she imposes limitations on them (pp.
          128, 154). Quite unlike Blake, who claimed that “The road of excess leads to the palace of
          wisdom” (<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, 1790-93), Mrs. Mason believes
          that “Wisdom consists in avoiding extremes . . . ” (p. 97). She advises that “the
          ripenings of reason [should] regulate the imagination” (p. 108), and she warns against
          “wild pursuits of fancy” (p. 176). The governess also condemns the girls’ “folly” as
          “inexcusable” (p. 30; see also pp. 50, 66-67, 76). They, in turn, strive “to gain Mrs.
          Mason’s good opinions” (p. 37; see p. 52). It is almost as if Mary and Caroline had been
          on Blake’s mind when he wrote the first four lines of his “Motto to the Songs of Innocence
          &amp; of Experience”: 
		<q>
		The Good are attracted by Mens perceptions<lb/>
		And Think not for themselves<lb/>
		Till Experience teaches them to catch<lb/>
		And to cage the Fairies &amp; Elves. . . .<lb/>
		(E 490, 11. 1-4)
		</q></p>
        <p>Mrs. Mason inculcates in her charges what the psychologist Jean Piaget would call “moral
          realism”—a kind of literalism that tends “to regard duty . . . as self-subsistent . . . as
          imposing itself regardless of the circumstances in which the individual may find himself.”
          According to Piaget, moral realism involves obedience to authority and the judgment of
          others according to their conformity with established rules and not according to their
          intentions. For Blake such realism is repressive: “One Law for the Lion &amp; Ox is
          Oppression.” As the author of “The Little Black Boy,” “The Chimney Sweeper” (in 
            <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>), “Infant Sorrow,” and “A Little Girl Lost,” the poet recognized
          some of the consequences of this kind of realism: prejudice, child labor, and
          suffering.</p>
        <p>In discussing moral realism Piaget says that when children have moral “stories” told to
          them (as Mary and Caroline often do), they “will . . . make judgments devoid of pity and
          lacking in psychological [Blake would use the term ‘imaginative’] insight. . . .” Thus, in
          accordance with Mrs. Mason’s stories and example, her charges begin to judge wrongdoing
          strictly and inflexibly. In moral realism, in moralism, there is a certain arbitrariness,
          an egocentrism (Piaget’s 
          term).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref> 
          Hence, even in her
          almsgiving the governess is egocentric—unable to get beyond her narrow perspective: 
          “ . . . we exercise every benevolent affection to enjoy comfort here, and to fit ourselves to be
          angels hereafter . . . ” (p. 13). By the end of <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi>,
          Caroline and Mary reflect their guardian’s self-concern and self-righteousness. Caroline
          is embarrassed because she has only her scarf to give the family depicted in plate 6
          (illus. 14), whereas Mary has the rest of her spending money to give them and is “proud”
          of her “privilege” (p. 172). The significance of such self-righteousness, which adults
          often exemplify to children, did not elude Blake, who eventually called it “Satanic.”
            <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi><hi rend="i"> The Moral Judgment of the Child</hi>,
            trans. Marjorie Gabain (New York: Free Press, 1965), pp. 111-112, 185, 33-34.</note></p>
        <p>In contrast to Mrs. Mason’s oppressive and self-righteous attitudes toward others,
          particularly children, Blake’s were much more positive. As S. Foster Damon says, for Blake
          “Children symbolize the fecundity of the imagination, the ‘Eternal Creation flowing from
          The Divine Humanity in 
          Jesus.’”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> 
          In a letter to Dr.
          Trusler (23 August 1799), Blake declared that “a vast Majority” of children possess
          “Imagination or Spiritual Sensation” (E 677). And in a poem describing one of his visions
          to Thomas Butts (2 October 1800), he suggested that to see as a child while an adult
          enhances the visionary experience: “I remaind as a Child / All I ever had known / Before
          me bright Shone” (E 684, 11. 72-74). <note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi><hi rend="i"> A
              Blake Dictionary</hi> (Providence, R. I.: Brown Univ. Press, 1965), pp.
          81-82.</note></p>
        <p>Even though most of Mrs. Mason’s views are negative (especially those concerning youth),
          not all are so from a Blakean perspective. For example, she urges Mary and Caroline to be
          considerate of all creatures and to base every friendship on truth. Blake certainly would
          have agreed with these ideals, for he was soon to complete poems like “The Fly” and “A
          Poison Tree” (both of <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>). As the author of “On Anothers Sorrow”
            (<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>), he would have agreed also with the governess’s charity to
          the poor, though it sometimes appears to be self-serving (“While we impart pleasure we
          receive it”).</p>
        <p>One of Mary Wollstonecraft’s biographers has suggested that the novelist and Mrs. Mason
          are similar, but the two are actually 
          different.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref> I
          think that Blake as a creator of various characters and personae would have recognized the
          differences between Mary and the governess. According to Edna Nixon, several of the ideas
          and attitudes expressed in <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi> were not “mature”
          Wollstonecraft.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref> 
          Indeed, her goal and strategy in
          writing the novel troubled her. On the one hand, she favored conveying knowledge gradually
          to children (p. iv). On the other, she wished to impart “premature knowledge” to them and
          thereby compensate for some of the parental neglect in her society (p. v). Her attempt to
          recommend the novel to adults as well as children did not resolve, however, the
          “objection” which she expected against it, namely, that its “sentiments are not quite on a
          level with the capacity of a child” (p. v). <note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Emily W.
            Sunstein, <hi rend="i">A Different Face: The Life of Mary Wollstonecraft</hi> (New York:
            Harper &amp; Row, 1975), p. 161. For the principal differences between the novelist and
            Mrs. Mason, see Ralph M. Wardle, <hi rend="i">Mary Wollstonecraft: A Critical
              Biography</hi> (Lawrence: Univ. of Kansas Press, 1951), p. 89.</note>	
              <note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi><hi rend="i"> Mary Wollstonecraft: Her Life and Times</hi>
            (London: J. M. Dent, 1971), p. 56. See E. V. Lucas’s Introduction to <hi rend="i">Mary
              Wollstonecraft</hi>’s Original Stories (1906; rpt. Folcroft, Pa.: Folcroft Library
            Editions, 1972), pp. iv, x.</note></p>
        <p>Like Wollstonecraft, Blake understood the importance of living in experience. Thel’s
          failure to do so is tragic. Such failure risks prolonging innocence to the point of
          narcissism, whose dangers are as great as those of experience. But to try continually to
          confront experience creates risks, too, especially the risk of becoming what one beholds.
          This could stifle whatever energy and 
          <pb id="p13-13" n="13"/>
          <figure n="songsie.z.p33" id="songsie.z.illbk.33" work-copy="songsie.z" rend="db" width="681" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>33<lb/>
	HOLY THURSDAY<lb/>
	Is this a holy thing to see,<lb/>
	In a rich and fruitful land,<lb/>
	Babes reducd to misery<lb/>
	Fed with cold and usurous hand?<lb/>
	Is that trembling cry a song?<lb/>
	Can it be a song of joy?<lb/>
	And so many children poor?<lb/>
	It is a land of poverty!<lb/>
	And their sun does never shine.<lb/>
	And their fields are bleak &amp; bare.<lb/>
	And their ways are fill’d with thorns<lb/>
	It is eternal winter there.<lb/>
	For where-e’er the sun does shine.<lb/>
	And where-e’er the rain does fall:<lb/>
	Babe can never hunger there,<lb/>
	Nor poverty the mind appall.</figTranscr>
            <head>13 “Holy Thursday,” pl. 33, from Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                Experience</hi>, Library of Congress, Rosenwald Collection.</head>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p13-14" n="14"/>
          <figure n="bb514.3.6.com" id="bb514.3.comb.06" work-copy="bb514.3" rend="db" width="502" height="1000">
          	<figTranscr>P. 173.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Œconomy &amp; Self-denial are necessary, in<lb/>
          	every station, to enable us to be generous.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Published by J. Johnson, Septr. 1, 1791.</figTranscr>
            <head>14 Pl. 6, from Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Original Stories</hi>, The Beinecke
              Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.</head>
          </figure> 
          imagination a person has. Thus, Mrs. Mason admits being “melancholy” in her
          recollection of sad stories (p. 149) and being disturbed at the sight of “misery” (p.
          174). Effects like these, though the novel mentions only a few of them, are bound to occur
          throughout the lives of her charges, too. As Blake’s “School Boy” (in 
            <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> and later in <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>) says, “How can a child when
          fears annoy, / But droop his tender wing, / And forget his youthful spring” (E 31, 11.
          18-20). For Blake a person’s involvement in experience must be relieved periodically with
          exuberance and delight. As Lavater’s thirteenth aphorism—to which Blake annotated “All
          Gold”—says, “Joy and grief decide character” (E 573). Neither joy nor grief can by itself
          create character, but together they can. The poet’s joint publication of 
            <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> in 1794 implies that innocence is as
          important to human existence as experience. Without joy as well as grief, Mary, Caroline,
          and 
          <figure n="but244.1.10.wd" id="but244.1.wd.10" work-copy="but244.1" rend="db" width="577" height="1000">
	<figTranscr/>
            <head>15 A drawing by Blake, probably related to the series for <hi rend="i">Original
                Stories</hi>, Library of Congress, Rosenwald Collection.</head>
          </figure> 
          all of us risk surrendering to experience and its ways as the speaker of the
          notebook version of “Infant Sorrow” has: 
          <q> 
          Struggling in my fathers hands:<lb/>
          Striving against my swadling bands:<lb/>
          Bound and weary I thought best<lb/>
          To sulk upon my mothers breast.<lb/>
          <lb/>
          When I saw that rage was vain<lb/>
          And to sulk would nothing gain<lb/>
          Turning many a trick &amp; wile<lb/>
          I began to soothe &amp; smile. . . .<lb/>
          (E 28, 11. 5-8; E 720, 11. 9-12)
          </q>
          Like these words, Enitharmon’s in 
          <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> consist of a warning, though she probably does not intend them as such,
          that concerns both the sexual and the psychological education of not only young 
          <pb id="p13-15" n="15"/>
          girls but everyone:
          <q>
          Forbid all Joy, &amp; from her childhood shall the little female<lb/>
          Spread nets in every secret path.<lb/>
          (6:8-9)
          </q></p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
