<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>13.1.gleckner</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Priestley and Chameleon Angel in The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</title>
        <author n="Gleckner">Robert F. Gleckner</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1979</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1979</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">13.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Cindy Lewiecki</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Susan Fox</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>N.G.D. Malmqvist</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Warren H. Stevenson</name>
              <name>Robert H. Tener</name>
              <name>Raymond E. Thompson</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1979"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_13">
    <body>
	<pb id="p13-37" n="37"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-13-1-0010">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main"><hi rend="b">PRIESTLEY AND THE CHAMELEON ANGEL IN</hi> THE MARRIAGE OF HEAVEN
AND HELL</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Robert F.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Gleckner</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>In the final “Memorable Fancy” of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> Blake created
a mini-seriocomic dramatic scene between an Angel and a Devil, in which he himself acts as both narrator and
participant. The essentials of the scene are well known and offer little difficulty of interpretation. The
Devil begins, without apparent provocation or occasion, by identifying man and God—“for there is no other
God” (Plate 23). The Angel, apoplectically changing color, responds that God is “One,” unique and separate
from men who are “fools, sinners &amp; nothings.” Then follows the oft-quoted Devil’s diatribe on how Jesus
Christ, who is the “greatest man,” systematically broke the ten commandments rather than, as the Angel
insisted, giving “his sanction” to them: “I tell you, no virtue can exist without breaking these ten
commandments.<hi rend="s">.</hi>. Jesus was all virtue, and acted from impulse, not from rules,” he concludes
(Plates 23-24). The Angel, evidently convinced, embraces the flame of fire in which the Devil stands and is
“consumed” to arise “as Elijah”—that is, like Elijah in the fiery chariot. The “Memorable Fancy” concludes
with the transfigured Angel (“now become a Devil”) reading “the Bible . . . in its infernal or diabolical
sense” along with the speaker (presumably Blake) whose “particular friend” the Angel has now become. This
“sense” of the Bible the speaker will deliver to the world, “if they behave well” and, whether the world “will
or no,” “The Bible of Hell” itself, which the speaker says he has ready (Plate 24).</p>
          <p>The Angel’s embracing the flame of fire, of course, is his embrace of the Devil “in” the flame
of fire with which the Memorable Fancy begins—and hence the corrosive melting away of apparent surface
(Angel) to display the infinite (imaginative man-prophet Elijah) “which was hid.” The embrace may be seen,
then, as paradigmatically or symbolically a marriage of heaven and hell as well,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">1</ref> though such an interpretation of the entire Memorable Fancy
ignores the fact that Blake does not conclude the passage with this metamorphosis: the Angel-become-Elijah
becomes in turn a Devil and the speaker’s “Particular friend.” Some sense, I think, may be made out of this
apparent confusion—or even self-contradiction—by turning our attention to the extraordinary, and to my
knowledge as yet unexplained, chameleon-like mutations of the Angel in response to the Devil’s opening
words: “The Angel hearing this became almost blue but mastering himself he grew yellow, &amp; at last white
pink &amp; smiling . . . .” The standard readings of this passage are notably unhelpful. Nurmi supposes, not
without justification, that the Angel “almost allows himself to indulge in infernal wrath” but masters himself
to regain “the vapid sweetness of his piety.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42"
type="note">2</ref> Erdman sees the Angel as “frightened” and “violently upset”;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">3</ref> and others merely describe the change as chameleon-like. In a
passing reference Hazard Adams, to some extent echoing Bloom’s essay on <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>,
comes closest to the essence of the passage, attributing to Blake’s “comic disdain” the Angel’s “turning
the colors of the spectrum.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">4</ref> While
this is spectroscopically incorrect (and there is little doubt that Blake knew the spectrum), it is the right
idea here. <note id="n41"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Frye calls the episode “orthodox theology” (<hi rend="i">Fearful
Symmetry</hi> [Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1947], p. 196), and Bloom extrapolates on this: “The Angel
teaches light without heat [i.e. without energy]; the vitalist—or Devil—heat without light; Blake wants
both, hence the marriage of contraries” (“Dialectic in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>,” in
<hi rend="i">English Romantic Poets: Modern Essays in Criticism</hi>, ed. M. H. Abrams [New York: Oxford Univ.
Press, 1960], p. 80). Erdman, however, cautions against too readily identifying the embracing figures on the
title page of <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> as male or female, heaven or hell, angel or devil 
(<hi rend="i">The Illustrated Blake</hi> [Garden City: Doubleday, 1974], p. 98).</note>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake’s “Marriage of Heaven and Hell”</hi> (Kent: Kent
State Univ. Press, 1957), p. 58.</note>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake: Prophet Against Empire</hi>, rev. ed. (Garden City:
Doubleday, 1969), p. 177.</note>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">4</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake: A Reading of the Shorter Poems</hi> (Seattle:
Univ. of Washington Press, 1963), p. 293.</note></p>
          <p>A passage in Joseph Priestley’s <hi rend="i">The History and Present State of Discoveries
Relating to Vision, Light, and Colours</hi>, published in two volumes by Joseph Johnson in 1772 and very
possibly known to Blake, seems curiously apropos.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45"
type="note">5</ref> Boyle, Priestley writes, noted that change of color “is the chief, and sometimes the only
thing by which the artist regulates his process” in the preparation of
<pb id="p13-38" n="38"/>
“tinctures.” One major instance of this sort of change is
<q>
the method of tempering steel for gravers, drills, springs, &amp;c. . . . First the steel to be tempered is
hardened, by heating it in glowing coals, and not quenched as soon as taken from the fire, but held over a
bason of water, till it pass from a white heat to a red one, when it is immediately quenched in cold water.
The steel thus hardened will, if it be good, look whitish, and being brightened at the end, and held in the
flame of a candle, that the bright end may be about half an inch distant from the flame, it will swiftly pass
from one colour to another; as from a bright yellow to a deeper and reddish yellow, from that first to a
fainter, and then to a deeper blue; each of which succeeding colours argues such a change made in the texture
of the steel, that, if it be taken from the flame, and immediately quenched in tallow, whilst it is yellow, it
will be of such hardness as fits it for drills; but if kept for a few minutes longer in the flame, till it
burns blue, it becomes much softer, and proper to make springs for watches; which are, therefore, commonly of
that colour. Lastly, if the steel be kept in the flame after the deep blue has appeared, it will grow too soft
even for penknives. (I, 141-142)
</q>
Had Blake indeed seen the passage he certainly would have been interested in Priestley’s references to
tempering steel for gravers and penknives, and to the artist’s preparation of his colors. But the idea of
the relative hardness of steel when exposed to “a flame of fire” may well be at the base of the Angel’s
color transformation in <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>, since the sequence of color changes Blake invents for
him is precisely the opposite of that produced by the tempering process Boyle and Priestley speak of. Thus the
Angel’s first reaction is submissive, so powerful is the Devil’s flame: that is, he turns 
“<hi rend="i">almost</hi> blue” (my emphasis), the degree of softness fit for watch springs and perhaps even that
deeper blue which indicates Priestley’s ultimate malleability (“too soft even for penknives”). But
“mastering himself” the Angel recovers his imperviousness, changing from blue to yellow to “white pink &amp;
smiling.” The effect is precisely that of the quenching action in Priestley’s passage and, accordingly, with
hardened, steely self-righteousness the Angel delivers his attack on the Devil’s “idolatry”—thus
reassuming “the vanity to speak of [himself] as the only wise” (Plate 21). <note id="n45"><hi rend="s">5</hi>
The evidence that Blake had actually met Priestley is shaky. We know from letters and diaries that “more or
less frequent guests” of Joseph Johnson included Priestley (from the 1770’s to 1793), and we can “assume
that Blake sometimes attended Johnson’s conversational Tuesday dinners in the early ’90s” (Erdman, 
<hi rend="i">Prophet Against Empire</hi>, p. 156). The two may have met there. If only because of Priestley’s
connection with Johnson—and given Blake’s intense interest, even early, in matters of
vision—Priestley’s book almost surely would have attracted the poet’s especial attention. Erdman also
notes that the will-o’-the-wisp-like light in “The Little Boy Lost” and “The Little Boy Found” was a
“phenomenon in which Priestley was greatly interested” (<hi rend="i">Prophet</hi>, p. 126n). As a matter of
fact there is a long section on the ignis fatuus (which, Priestley notes, Newton in his 
<hi rend="i">Opticks</hi> called “a vapour shining without heat”) in <hi rend="i">The History and Present State of
Discoveries Relative to Vision, Light, and Colours</hi> (I, 579-84). Donald D. Ault, in his 
<hi rend="i">Visionary Physics</hi> (Chicago: Univ. of Chicago Press, 1974), cites Priestley’s two-volume work
several times, though without indicating whether he believes that Blake had seen it. Morton D. Paley has
argued that Blake knew Priestley’s <hi rend="i">Matter and Spirit</hi> (<hi rend="i">Energy and the
Imagination</hi> [Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1970], pp.8-10, 66-67). And, finally, it is still possible, though
less acceptable these days, to see Priestley behind the character of Inflammable Gass in <hi rend="i">An
Island in the Moon.</hi></note></p>
          <p>The Devil’s exasperated response to all this Blake interestingly couches in the metaphor of
wheat and chaff, with the clear implication that chaff will remain chaff whatever one does to it: 
<hi rend="i">this</hi> fool, even if he “persists in his folly,” will not become “wise” as the Proverb of Hell
promises. Yet this Angel is no mere chaff. His doors of perception cleansed by the Devil’s corrosively
prophetic utterance, he “stretched out his arms embracing the flame of fire &amp; he was consumed and arose as
Elijah.” Like Christ he acts from impulse, not from rules. In Priestley’s terms he has not only reached the
malleability of blueness but has become molten—in precisely the same sense that in the fourth chamber of the
“Printing house in Hell” the “Lions of flaming fire [were] raging around &amp; melting the metals into living
fluids” (Plate 15). The mere change of color, Priestley reminds us, does
<q>
not always denote any great difference in the internal structure of bodies; yet he [i.e. Boyle] was induced to
think that it was often an indication of considerable alterations in the disposition of their parts, as
appears, he says, from the extraction of tinctures, wherein the change of colour is the chief, and sometimes
the only thing by which the artist regulates his process in their preparation. (I, 141)
</q>
Tempering, then, is an insufficient apocalypse: no amount of alteration in the disposition of parts transforms
error into truth, finiteness into the infinite, the fool into the prophet.</p>
          <p>That brings us to the conclusion of the Memorable Fancy: “This Angel,” the speaker tells us, “is
now become a Devil” and moreover his “particular friend.” So anticlimactic does this “resolution” seem that it
has been adduced as evidence of what Nurmi calls the “tentative apocalypse” of <hi rend="i">The
Marriage.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">6</ref> In the total context
of the work, however, it may be argued, more persuasively I think, that the Elijahs of <hi rend="i">this</hi>
world, like the “I” of the entire Memorable Fancy, appear <hi rend="i">to</hi> this world as Devils.
Imaginatively they are, I suggest, those “living fluids” which melt apparent surfaces away, or which
analogically dis-cover the “infernal or diabolical sense” of the Bible which is to be prophetically revealed
to “the world . . . if they behave well”—i.e. if they continue in their angelic ways (the
tongue-in-cheekness of the phrase adapting this world’s language in the same manner as the new Devil assumes
conventional shape and the Bible of Hell parodically worldly status). In <hi rend="i">A Vision of the Last
Judgment</hi> Blake wrote: “whenever any Individual Rejects Error &amp; Embraces Truth a Last Judgment passes
upon that Individual.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">7</ref> The embrace
here and the Angel’s embrace of the fire are the same; and if he arises as Elijah rose, he also arises 
<hi rend="i">as</hi> Elijah—as, that is, Blake’s symbolic figure of Elijah in <hi rend="i">A Vision of the
Last Judgment</hi> who “comprehends all the Prophetic Characters.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n48" type="note">8</ref> The Memorable Fancy as a whole, then, concluding <hi rend="i">The
Marriage</hi> proper, enacts an individual last judgment which preludically leads to, while appropriately
symbolizing, the totality of last judgments that is the apocalypse of “A Song of Liberty.” 
<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake’s “Marriage of Heaven and Hell,”</hi> p. 61.</note>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">7</hi> D. V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>
(Garden City: Doubleday, 1965), p. 551.</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">8</hi><hi rend="i"> Poetry and Prose</hi>, p. 550.</note></p>
          <p>In her recent essay, “Blake and the Symbolism of the New Iron Age,” Eileen Sanzo calls our
attention to Blake’s mythologizing of his own age as the archetypal iron age: “Urizen writes with ‘his
iron pen’ in ‘books of iron and brass,’ the Bible and all law rigidly interpreted.” Apocalypse thus
comes about, fittingly, by a “marriage” of Urizenic iron and the fire of Los’s furnaces, the
<pb id="p13-39" n="39"/>
iron age “alchemized into the new golden age” in Blake’s imaginative version of the industrial blast
furnace.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">9</ref> The last Memorable Fancy of
<hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>, then, may be seen profitably as one of Blake’s earliest efforts (if not the
earliest) to incorporate “the symbolism of the new iron age,” of which Priestley had to be considered one of
the high priests, into his art. <note id="n49"><hi rend="s">9</hi><hi rend="i"> The Evidence of the
Imagination</hi>, ed. D. H. Reiman, M. C. Jaye, B. T. Bennett (New York Univ. Press, 1978), pp. 1-11. The
quotations are from pp. 8-9.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
