<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>13.1.thompson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The “Double” of the Double Portrait of Blake: A Description of Tatham’s
Replica Portrait</title>
        <author n="Thompson">Raymond E. Thompson</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1979</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1979</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">13.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Cindy Lewiecki</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Susan Fox</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>N.G.D. Malmqvist</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Warren H. Stevenson</name>
              <name>Robert H. Tener</name>
              <name>Raymond E. Thompson</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1979"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_13">
    <body>
      <pb id="p13-29" n="29"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-13-1-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">THE “DOUBLE” OF THE DOUBLE PORTRAIT OF BLAKE: A DESCRIPTION OF TATHAM’S REPLICA
PORTRAIT</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">RAYMOND E.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">THOMPSON</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>The double portrait of Blake, “William Blake in Youth and Age,” by Frederick Tatham, in the
Collection of Mr. and Mrs. Paul Mellon since 1964, is surely one of the better known representations of the
poet. It has been reproduced in Blake—related publications on several occasions and recently in the William
Blake Trust volume devoted to Blake portraiture.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23"
type="note">1</ref> There, Keynes discusses this drawing in some detail and then reminds the reader that
Tatham also made an enlarged replica of it for the Butts family. Having done so, he at once passes on to his
next topic leaving those desiring further information on the replica portrait to seek it elsewhere. But
where?—a question which prompted me to look into this matter, and which resulted in this account of my
findings. <note id="n23"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">The Complete Portraiture of William
and Catherine Blake</hi> (London: Trianon Press for Blake Trust, 1977). The double portrait is reproduced as
Plate 41 and is discussed on p. 144. This is a reproduction of the entire sheet, whereas most, if not all,
prior reproductions omitted the inscription portion of the sheet.</note></p>
        <p>In contrast with the original portrait, it appears that detailed information about the replica is
not widely known. I found no account specific to this work. And while it has been exhibited on several
occasions, with one important exception, these exhibitions were otherwise unrelated to Blake. Further, I found
but two reproductions, both of them illustrations in catalogues for exhibitions which probably had limited
exposure. The replica’s existence has been largely forgotten; at the very least, it has been neglected.
However, for most of the past decade it has been on public display in The Denver [Colorado] Art Museum. Quite
by chance I came upon it there some five years ago—a bit of good fortune which gave me a head start in my
investigation. In addition, I received a most helpful tip from Sir Geoffrey Keynes early on.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">2</hi> It should not be thought that the brevity of Keynes’ remarks about the
replica in <hi rend="i">Portraiture</hi> resulted from a lack of information on his part. He not only informed
me as to which Butts sale it was consigned, but indicated that he had some personal contact with this work
about the time of the sale.</note></p>
        <p>As in the case of the original portrait, the year in which the replica was executed is not
precisely known. However, Keynes now ascribes “circa 1830” to the former and it seems likely the replica was
done soon after.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">3</ref> The replica portrait
remained in the Butts family and in 1905, upon the death of Captain Butts (the grandson of Blake’s great
patron, Thomas Butts), passed into the hands of his son, Anthony Bacon Drury Butts. It was later included in
the Sotheby &amp; Co. auction of 19 December 1932. The portrait (Lot 117 in the sale catalogue)<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">4</ref> was the first of twelve lots consigned by Mr.
Butts, collectively designated “Relics of and Miniatures Painted by William Blake.” The Sotheby catalogue file
in The British Library indicates that it was purchased by “Ulysses” for five pounds. The purchaser was, in
fact, Jacob Schwartz the expatriate American who operated The Ulysses Bookshop in London and New York. The
portrait was then listed in the shop’s catalogue issued in early 1933, and the American collector T. Edward
Hanley obtained it from Dr. Schwartz in that year.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27"
type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Keynes’ <hi rend="i">Portraiture</hi> contains revised dates for some of
the Blake portraits previously listed in his <hi rend="i">A Bibliography of William Blake</hi>, (1921). There,
Tatham’s original portrait is dated “1827”; the replica is not cited. Catherine Blake’s sketch (“William
Blake as a Young Man”), long considered to be a source for Tatham, is there dated “1785”; Keynes now favors
“circa 1828.” The drawing “William Blake” by Thomas Stothard, which Keynes now considers to be another
possible source for Tatham’s youthful image of Blake, was not cited in the 1921 publication, but carries a
date of “circa 1780” in <hi rend="i">Portraiture.</hi> Catalogue citations for the replica portrait have
usually carried the date “circa 1826” which placed it earlier than the previously accepted date for the
original.</note>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">4</hi><hi rend="i"> Catalogue of Valuable Printed Books, Illuminated &amp; Other
Manuscripts, Autograph Letters and Historical Documents, Relics of William Blake, &amp;c.</hi> . . . Messrs.
Sotheby &amp; Co. . . . Monday, the 19th of December, 1932, [London]. This sale is sometimes referred to as
the “final” Butts sale.</note>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">5</hi><hi rend="i"> A Catalogue of Rare Books, Pictures, Manuscripts &amp;
Letters</hi>, (The Ulysses Bookshop, New York, [1933]). The replica is Item 3. The citation discusses both the
original and replica portraits, and clearly indicates that it is the larger copy being offered. However, the
reader is instructed to “see front cover” which, curiously, features a reproduction of the portrait area only
of the original rather than the replica.</note></p>
        <p>The Hanley art collection, which was both extensive and diverse and eventually included at least
three works by Blake, was kept at the Hanley home in Bradford, Pennsylvania. Selections from the collection,
which often included the replica portrait, were loaned for public exhibitions on numerous occasions. Mrs.
Tullah Hanley informed
<pb id="p13-30" n="30"/>
<figure n="BlakeinYouthandAge.13.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="683" height="1000">
	<head>1 “William Blake in Youth and Age” by Frederick Tatham.</head>
	<figDesc>From the Collection of Mr. And Mrs. Paul Mellon.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p13-31" n="31"/>
<figure n="ReplicaBlakePortrait.13.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="852" height="1000">
	<head>2 Replica “Portrait of William Blake” by Frederick Tatham.</head>
	<figDesc>The Denver Art Museum.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p13-32" n="32"/>
me that the replica was a favorite of Dr. Hanley who, when given the opportunity, included it in these
exhibitions along with their Blake works. The earliest and most notable such instance I uncovered was the
great Blake exhibition held at the Philadelphia Museum of Art in 1939. The replica is Number 216 in the
exhibition catalogue.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">6</ref> All later
showings of the replica were in “Hanley exhibitions” held during the next thirty years. Two of the earliest,
1946 and 1960, were at the Albright (now Albright-Knox) Art Gallery. The catalogue for the 1946 showing
includes a small reproduction. In 1957 the replica was exhibited at the Philadelphia Museum of Art. During the
period 1967-70, foremost among a number of exhibitions of selections from the Hanley Collection that included
the replica portrait was a series of four showings of an exhibition initiated jointly in 1967 by the Gallery
of Modern Art—including the Huntington Hartford Collection—and the Philadelphia Museum of Art. The
exhibition later traveled to the de Young Memorial Museum, San Francisco (1967-68) and finally, to the Denver
Art Museum (1968). Another exhibition, this one in 1969 at Canisius College in Buffalo, N.Y., included the
replica, which was reproduced at a very small size in the exhibition 
catalogue.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">7</ref> 
In 1969 the portrait, with numerous other works, was given in
trust to the Denver Art Museum, and in 1974 the trust was converted to a gift—the T. Edward and Tullah
Hanley Memorial Gift to the People of Denver and the Area.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n30" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake 1757-1827: A Descriptive Catalogue of an
Exhibition of the Works of William Blake Selected from Collections in the United States</hi> (Philadelphia:
Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1939).</note>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">7</hi> The two Albright exhibitions were “The T. Edward Hanley Collection:
Drawings,” <corr type="emend">4 October–3 November 1946</corr> (cat. no. 18, illustrated), and “The T. Edward 
Hanley Collection: Drawings, Watercolors, Pastels,” <corr type="emend">6 January–14 February 1960</corr> 
(cat. no. 50). The Philadelphia exhibition was “The T. Edward Hanley Collection,” 
<corr type="emend">8 February–28 April 1957</corr> (p. 3 of unnumbered checklist). The four
identical exhibitions were all entitled “Selections from the Collection of Dr. and Mrs. T. Edward Hanley,
Bradford, Pennsylvania” and shown as follows: New York, <corr type="emend">3 January–12 March 1967;</corr> 
Philadelphia, <corr type="emend">6 April–28 May 1967;</corr> San Francisco, 
<corr type="emend">[?] December 1967–11 February 1968;</corr> and Denver, 
<corr type="emend">22 February–30 April 1968.</corr> The first two shared a common catalogue (unnumbered, p. 67). 
The same catalogue, with a new title page, was used at Denver; it appears that the San Francisco catalogue 
was similarly produced. The Buffalo exhibition was “Works from the Hanley Collection at Canisius College,” 
<corr type="emend">23 November–23 December 1969</corr> (cat. no. 233, illustrated).</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">8</hi> The present acquisition number of the replica is 1974, 398.</note></p>
        <p>Both Tatham’s original and replica portraits are presented here as illus. 1 and illus. 2,
respectively. The titles listed are those presently used, though in some exhibitions the replica was titled
“Double Portrait of William Blake.” The original is in sepia wash and pencil; the head of Blake in age is a
finished wash drawing, the head in youth a pencil sketch. The sheet measures 343 × 264 mm, a considerable
portion of which is taken up by the inscription. The replica is on brown paper and drawn in black and brown
chalk with white highlights. The sheet measures 645 × 525 mm and is “glued” to a wood panel, and the whole is
mounted in an “ebonised frame”—presumably the same frame mentioned in the Sotheby sale catalogue. There is
no signature or other notation visible on the sheet.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Details concerning the physical characteristics of the replica portrait
and its relationship to the Denver Art Museum were provided through the kindness of Ms. Cameron Wolfe,
Associate Curator of European Art for the Museum.</note></p>
        <p>Apart from the obvious difference in size, the replica is a reasonably good double for the
original. However, it appears to be a somewhat less finished work. And, while the replica rather carefully
duplicates the image of Blake in age, the youthful image is less faithful. This is most apparent in the
rendering of the nose, if not the entire profile. In this respect, the original is more akin to the Blake
portraits by Thomas Stothard and Catherine Blake which Keynes considers as probable sources of Tatham’s
youthful Blake. Since it is a direct copy of the original, the replica cannot be considered an independent
portrait of Blake, and so cannot provide additional insight into his appearance. However, its association with
the Butts family gives it a considerable measure of importance. Indeed, it is yet another Blakean legacy that
has come down to us from Thomas Butts; one which, due to the generosity of the Hanleys, is in the public
domain. And, I hope, by virtue of this account, now better known to those interested in Blake portraiture.</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
