<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>13.2.erdman</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">South Bounding!</title>
        <author n="Erdman">David V. Erdman</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1979</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1979</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">13.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>F.R. Duplantier</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>James King</name>
              <name>N.G.D. Malmqvist</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>R.J. Shroyer</name>
              <name>Shawn Thompson</name>
              <name>Kazumitsu Watarai</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1979"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_13">
    <body>
      <pb id="p13-106" n="106"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-13-2-0009">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">SOUTH BOUNDING!</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">David V.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Erdman</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
		<q>
“Here is signed . . . Names which are too Holy to be Written”<lb/>
Blake’s Thornton Marginalia
</q>
          <p>The double meaning in Blake’s wirey bounding line is perhaps present in all of his uses of the
word “bounding”—or at least of the terms “bounding line” and “outline.” Blake’s line of beauty/energy,
“the bounding line and its infinite inflexions and movements” (<hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> 15), is
conceived of as doing two things: (1) delineating—“the falling Mind labour’d / Organizing itself” 
(<hi rend="i">B Los</hi> 4:49-50), “And Orc began to Organize a Serpent body” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 7:80:44),
“embodied and organized in solid marble” (<hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> 4), “Branchy forms:
organizing the Human” (<hi rend="i">B Los</hi> 4:44)—(2) leaping—as when Tharmas, boundary god, travels by
“high bounding over hills &amp; desarts floods &amp; horrible chasms” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 6:69:24). In
short, delineating through movement.</p>
          <p>Less noticed, or noticed but seldom recalled, is Blake’s expression of the delight he and
Catherine felt in their Felpham cottage as the first winter set in:
<q>
Our cottage is surrounded by the same guardians you left with us; they keep off every wind. We hear the west
howl at a distance, the south bounds on high over our thatch, and smiling on our cottage says: “You lay too
low for my anger to injure.” As to the east and north, I believe they cannot get past the Turret. (To Hayley
26 November 1800)
</q>
<figure n="JerusalemD.13.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="750" height="225">
	<head><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 32(36).</head>
	<figDesc>Copy D, Harvard College Library.</figDesc>
</figure>
Is it only the south <hi rend="i">wind</hi> that bounds (a sufficient meaning for Hayley) or is it not the
South itself? Los’s furnaces are in the south now and cathedron’s looms (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
59:23); in the south remains a burning fire (18), a furnace of dire flames from Orc’s cave 
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 6:74:14). The south is where the golden bow lies, to be seized (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
97); it is where the golden fire burns when the day begins, the revolution; unfallen, Urizen prince of light
dwelt in the south, the “bright South.” When Luvah took charge it became the “fiery south.” Orc the first born
coiled in the South—for the serpent can coil to bind . . . or to bound up in Human form.</p>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 32(36) when the poet describes the Four Zoas raging in East &amp;
West &amp; North &amp; South and changing their situations, he watches Albion seeing the Elements divide. “And
Urizen assumes the East, Luvah assumes the South.” Blake then begins to announce the names of the Zoas “in the
Vegetative Generation” (line 33)—only to scour from the copper plate and keep secret the list of their names
that was to be line 34. Fifteen years ago in “The Suppressed and Altered Passages in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>” (<hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi> 17 [1964]:21) I managed to decipher the
four compass-point names, with their actions—all but the “action” of South that must be a transforming match
for the weighing and dividing of the three others:
<q>
[<hi rend="i">West Weighing East &amp; North dividing Generation South</hi> [ ]<hi rend="i">ing</hi>]
</q></p>
          <p>Yesterday the mail brought a thesis chapter from Nelson Hilton on Blake’s polysemous language,
and when I returned to the task of one more try at the unsolved riddles of text the question that hung over
this line was What polysemous word can fit here for South? I brought out my enlarged photographs of that part
of the <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> page in all copies, and a piece of workable acetate, and the
Concordance—where Blake’s winter letter to Hayley offered the perfect fit: South bounding! The bounce in
“bounding” sets the South in motion, to leap over the Blakes’ thatch. A fine hypothesis: would Blake’s
inscribed “bounding” fit the remnant edges of letters in the photographs? I am bound to confess that it
delights me to say that it did; it does!</p>
          <pb id="p13-107" n="107"/>
          <p>Here is a full restoration—with semicolons added for the phrasing Blake seems to have wanted
(though no punctuation can be recovered from this gouged abyss; see how he uses semicolons in line 42 of this
page): [<hi rend="i">West Weighing; East &amp; North dividing Generation; South bounding</hi>]</p>
          <figure n="JerusalemF.13.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="750" height="267">
            <head>Copy F, Pierpont Morgan Library.</head>
          </figure>
          <figure n="JerusalemH.13.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="750" height="267">
            <head>Copy H (posthumously printed), Fitzwilliam Museum.</head>
            <figDesc>For the techniques employed in verification, see “The Suppressed and Altered Passages,”
pages 3-6 and plate IIa.</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
