<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>13.2.king</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Charlotte Smith, William Cowper, and William Blake: Some New Documents</title>
        <author n="King">James King</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1979</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1979</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">13.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>F.R. Duplantier</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>James King</name>
              <name>N.G.D. Malmqvist</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>R.J. Shroyer</name>
              <name>Shawn Thompson</name>
              <name>Kazumitsu Watarai</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1979"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_13">
    <body>
      <pb id="p13-100" n="100"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-13-2-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">CHARLOTTE SMITH, WILLIAM COWPER, AND WILLIAM BLAKE: SOME NEW DOCUMENTS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">JAMES</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">KING</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>Although her reputation is somewhat diminished now, Charlotte Smith was the most celebrated
novelist in England in the early 1790s. Like George Romney, John Flaxman, William Cowper, and William Blake,
Mrs. Smith was one of a number of writers and painters assisted by William Hayley in various ways. Mrs. Smith
met Cowper at Eartham in 1792, and the events of that friendship have been chronicled.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n116" type="note">1</ref> Mrs. Smith never met William Blake, and only one excerpt
from a letter linking them has previously been published. In this note, I should like to provide some
additional information on Mrs. Smith and Cowper, but I shall as well cite three unpublished excerpts from her
correspondence in which she comments on Blake. <note id="n116"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See Morchard Bishop, 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Hayley</hi> (London, 1951), pp. 161-66.</note></p>
        <p>In an article of 1952, Alan Dugald McKillop provided an excellent account of Charlotte Smith’s
letters.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n117" type="note">2</ref> In the course of that
essay, McKillop notes a facetious and denigrating remark of 20 March 1806 (Huntington) about Hayley’s 
<hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads</hi> (1802) and <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805) which includes a
comment on William Blake: “ . . . &amp; at his [Hayley’s] strange tho benevolent fancy of writing such very
sad doggrell, for the purpose of serving a Man, who might be any thing than an 
engraver . . . ”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n118" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n117"><hi rend="s">2</hi> “Charlotte Smith’s Letters,” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library
Quarterly</hi>, 45 (1952), 237-55. McKillop confines himself to a description of the forty-five letters in the
Huntington collection. The letters contain details on Mrs. Smith’s harrowing domestic conflicts, the arduous
life of a professional writer in the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries, and details of her
quarrels with Lord Egremont and William Hayley. Neither Bishop nor Florence Hilbish, <hi rend="i">Charlotte
Smith</hi> (Philadelphia, 1941), still the standard work on its subject, provides any evidence of the
hostility Charlotte Smith felt towards Hayley from c. 1800 until her death in 1806.</note>
	<note id="n118"><hi rend="s">3</hi> HM 10843.</note></p>
        <p>There is a more substantial reference to Blake in a letter to the same correspondent, Sarah Farr
Rose, of 25 April 1806 (Huntington).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n119" type="note">4</ref>
As before, Mrs. Smith is complaining about Hayley’s neglect of her.
<q>
I lose a great part of the regret I might otherwise feel in recollecting, that a mind so indiscriminating, who
is now seized with a rage for a crooked figure=maker &amp; now for an engraver of Ballad pictures (the young
Mans tragedy; &amp; the jolly Sailers Farewell to his true love Sally)—I dont mean the Hayleyan collection
of pretty ballads)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n120" type="note">5</ref>—Such a mind,
can never be really attached; or is the attachment it can feel worth having— 
					</q>
The “crooked figure=maker” is probably a reference to Flaxman and his hunch-back; despite the disclaimer, the
engraver is more than likely to be Blake. 
                    <note id="n119"><hi rend="s">4</hi> HM 10844. I am grateful to Professor G. E. Bentley,
Jr. for his kindness in providing me with this citation.</note>
	<note id="n120"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Mrs. Smith is again referring to <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of
Ballads</hi> and <hi rend="i">Ballads.</hi> See G. E. Bentley, Jr., “William Blake as a Private Publisher,”
<hi rend="i">Bulletin of the New York Public Library</hi>, 61 (1957), 539-60.</note></p>
        <p>Recently, three previously <corr type="emend">unknown</corr> Charlotte Smith letters were discovered in Brantford, Ontario,
and these letters, acquired by the Research Collections division of Mills Memorial Library, McMaster
University, supplement the references to Blake in the Huntington collection and contain as well a significant
reference to Cowper.</p>
        <pb id="p13-101" n="101"/>
        <p>The McMaster letters are of 9 September 1802, 9 February 1803, and 19 February 1803; all three
signed autograph letters are addressed to Samuel Rose (1767-1804), Cowper’s friend and correspondent, and
the lawyer who defended Blake against the charge of sedition at Chichester in 1804. Rose apparently acted as
Lord Egremont’s London agent in handling Mrs. Smith’s affairs. Although the Huntington owns a dozen
letters to his wife, Sarah, from Mrs. Smith,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n121"
type="note">6</ref> they have only a single letter to Rose himself of 11 September 1803, and there do not seem
to be letters to Rose in any other collection. <note id="n121"><hi rend="s">6</hi> There are Charlotte Smith
letters to Mrs. Rose in the Berg Collection, New York Public Library (2), the Houghton Library, Harvard
University (2), and the Charles Roberts Autograph Collection, Haverford College (1). In her letter to Mrs.
Rose of 10 September 1804 (Harvard), she makes her only comment on Blake by name; she is deliberating whether
to send Hayley a copy of <hi rend="i">Conversations Introducing Poetry.</hi> “Before I venture to send him my
little book, I [want] to know if it would be acceptable for notwithstanding he has begun a Poetical Buffon
[<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] himself, to assist his worldly friend Mr Blake, I was afraid mine, would be deem’d
too juvenile.”</note></p>
        <p>Despite what might be termed worldly success, Mrs. Smith’s financial and family difficulties made
her of a melancholy cast, and she and Cowper recognized in each other in 1792 a shared response to the vanity
of human wishes. Mrs. Smith’s dedication of her poem, <hi rend="i">The Emigrants</hi> (1793), to Cowper is
beautifully expressed and touching, and she notes the “force, clearness, and sublimity” which allows Cowper to
give “dignity and effect” to “the most familiar objects.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n122" type="note">7</ref> in her letter of 9 September 1802, she refers to the “two Letters of Mr
Cowpers which he honord me with some years since —”.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n123"
type="note">8</ref> It is her letter of 9 February 1803, in which she movingly reflects on Cowper’s death,
which has the most significant material; she has just received the first two volumes of Hayley’s 
<hi rend="i">Life of Cowper</hi> (1803). <note id="n122"><hi rend="s">7</hi> P. v.</note>
	<note id="n123"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Cowper’s letter to Mrs. Smith of 25 July 1793 is known only from its
printing in Havley’s <hi rend="i">Life of Cowper</hi> (Chichester and London, 1803), II, 234; the holograph
of his letter of 26 October 1793 is at Princeton.</note></p>
		<q>
Allow me also to beg (for the same reason) that you will make known to Mr Hayley my gratitude for the Work I
so earnestly wish’d to see, and which arrived here on Tuesday—I have only had time to read the dedication
&amp; some pages of the first volume—My spirits I hope will serve me to go thro it in the course of the next
three or four days—Yet it is not a book (relating as it does to such a person)—which can be read, at least
I cannot read it, without a variety of sensations that, no other book in the World can excite—<lb/>
Alas! for the friends I have lost—for the days that are gone!
</q>
        <p>Earlier, in the same letter, Mrs. Smith refers to a possible commission for Flaxman and goes on to
make inquiries for an engraver for the plates she intended for <hi rend="i">Conversations Introducing
Poetry</hi> (1804).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n124" type="note">9</ref><q>
I am afraid of addressing myself to Mr Hayley now on any subject whatever—I have not been favord with any
answer to the Letters I took the liberty to address to him under cover to you—which related to information
my daughter<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n125" type="note">10</ref> desird me to obtain of
Mr Flaxman, relative to the means of sending over a small Marble tablet or urn to Barbados inscribed to the
Memory of my unfortunate Charles<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n126" type="note">11</ref>
— Perhaps however he has been so good as to send an answer to Miss Smith—My present purpose, is, to
enquire, whether there is not an ingenious Engraver who executed certain plates for a small work of Mr
Hayley’s relating to Animals.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n127" type="note">12</ref> I
know not what it is as I have never seen it. 
                        <note id="n124"><hi rend="s">9</hi> There is no evidence that Flaxman ever became
involved in such a project, and <hi rend="i">Conversations</hi> does not contain any plates.</note>
	<note id="n125"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Probably Charlotte Mary (<hi rend="i">pre</hi> 1774-<hi
rend="i">post</hi> 1807).</note>
	<note id="n126"><hi rend="s">11</hi> In 1800 Charles Dyer Smith (1773-1801) had been appointed paymaster of
the 47th Regiment at Bermuda. He contracted yellow fever in Barbados en route to his new post and died
there.</note>
	<note id="n127"><hi rend="s">12</hi><hi rend="i"> Designs to a Series of Ballads.</hi></note></q>
In the McMaster letter of 1803, Mrs. Smith simply inquires about an “ingenious Engraver” whereas in the later
Harvard and Huntington letters of 1804 and 1806, the references to Blake are clearly hostile. This change is
probably due in large part to the fact that by 1804 Mrs. Smith was fully aware of the extent of Hayley’s
patronage of Blake at Felpham from 1800-1803, and she had obviously heard of Blake’s trial at Chichester. 
                </p>
        <p>The McMaster letters demonstrate further the omnipresent patronage and involvement of William
Hayley in the careers of some of the most gifted writers and artists of his age. They help reveal as well
Charlotte Smith’s dissatisfaction with Hayley. Finally, although the letters at McMaster contain only
passing references by Mrs. Smith on William Cowper and William Blake, they are of interest in showing how one
of the most widely-known and published authors of the time reacted to the celebrated recluse at Weston
Underwood and to the relatively obscure “ingenious” engraver-poet.</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
