<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>13.2.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Almost Blake</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1979</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1979</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">13.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>F.R. Duplantier</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>James King</name>
              <name>N.G.D. Malmqvist</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>R.J. Shroyer</name>
              <name>Shawn Thompson</name>
              <name>Kazumitsu Watarai</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1979"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_13">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-13-2-0009">
        <pb id="p13-109" n="109"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">ALMOST BLAKE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">G. E. </hi><name><hi rend="b">Bentley</hi></name>, 
<hi rend="b">Jr.</hi></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Occasionally works not by William Blake seem momentarily as intriguing and alluring as those
genuinely by him. I offer three examples:</p>
          <p>(1) A letter said to be by our William Blake was listed in the American Art Association Catalogue
of First Editions and Autographs of 13-14 March 1928, lot 37, with the explanation that it is “to his old
friend John Thomas Smith.” It reads:
<q>
Wed<hi rend="s">n</hi><lb/>
morn.<lb/>
24<hi rend="s">th</hi> Ap[<hi rend="i">ril 1811</hi>].<lb/>
My dear Sir,<lb/>
<lb/>
I am just returned from taking another look at the little picture of the Pope—<hi rend="i">it wont do
for</hi> me upon <hi rend="i">any terms cheap or dear</hi>—<lb/>
<lb/>
Have the goodness therefore to inform M<hi rend="s">r</hi>. Christie that I have no wish to possess it—<lb/>
<lb/>
—I long for the Grimthorpe display—when we may hope to see a few genuine pictures in good condition—
Ever yrs, my d<hi rend="s">r</hi> Sir,<lb/>
most cordially W B—
</q>
The picture in question seems to be (as the catalogue says) the one of Pope Leo X sold at Christies on 25 May
1811—and 24 April, when the letter was written, <hi rend="i">was</hi> a Wednesday in 1811. William Blake 
<hi rend="i">was</hi> a friend of J. T. Smith, who wrote a brief anecdotal life of him some years later (1828),
and he was of course interested in pictures. But he certainly was not a buyer of such expensive pictures,
especially in 1811 when his fortunes were at a particularly low ebb, and the handwriting of the letter
(reproduced in the catalogue) is not his. Smith was doubtless being consulted in his capacity as Keeper of
Prints and Drawings in the British Museum. I suggest that this W. B. the buyer may have been the opulent
collector William Beckford.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n148" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n148"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Another work signed “W B” attributed to our William Blake is an undated
manuscript headed “Directions for ‘Landscape Painting’” (8 pp.), on preparing a palette, reproducing the
effect of shadows, bark, etc. (Anderson Galleries, 3 April 1928, lot *13). The hand and contents are quite
unlike Blake’s.</note></p>
          <p>(2) The letter of 15 June 1806 from Blake’s friend Ozias Humphry to “D<hi rend="s"><hi
rend="u">r</hi></hi> William” quoted in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (1969), 178, is not to our William.
The suggestion there that it is concerned with “applying for permission to dedicate his 
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> designs to the Queen” (and this is the letter’s only clear connection with William
Blake) is irrelevant, for this application to the Queen was not made until April 1807 (see “Blake and Cromek:
The Wheat and the Tares,” <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi>, 71 [1974], 566-79).</p>
          <p>(3) In <hi rend="i">The New Yorker</hi> for 26 February 1979, p. 3, and doubtless elsewhere,
appeared an advertisement for Florence Eiseman, evidently a designer of children’s clothing, with the
following inspirational motto:
<q>
To be a child is to live in a world where everything is new and exciting and beckoning us toward delight—<hi
rend="i">William Blake</hi></q>
This somewhat flabby statement does not sound like Blake to me, and certainly Blake did not use either
“exciting” or “beckoning” at all in his writings, according to the <hi rend="i">Concordance.</hi> Perhaps some
hardpressed copy-writer thought Blake <hi rend="i">ought</hi> to have written it—or was companioned by Blake
and was told it by him.</p>
          <p>Clearly the name of William Blake is an almost irresistible lure to authors of some auction
catalogues, <hi rend="i">New Yorker</hi> advertisements, and <hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
