<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>13.2.rome</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">The English in Rome</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1979</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1979</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">13.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>F.R. Duplantier</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>James King</name>
              <name>N.G.D. Malmqvist</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>R.J. Shroyer</name>
              <name>Shawn Thompson</name>
              <name>Kazumitsu Watarai</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1979"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_13">
    <body>
      <pb id="p13-110" n="110"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-13-2-0010">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">NEWSLETTER</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">THE ENGLISH IN ROME</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>On 29 September a public symposium entitled <hi rend="i">The English in Rome</hi> was held at the
Yale Center for British Art. The program was designed to examine the cultural milieu of Rome at the end of the
eighteenth century from the perspectives of various disciplines. The papers read focused not only on the
artistic and physical environment encountered by the expatriates of this period but also on the environment of
ideas. Concurrent with the symposium was an exhibit at the British Art Center, <hi rend="i">The Fuseli Circle
in Rome.</hi> The exhibit was designed to assess and define the stylistic and thematic innovations of an
international group of artists associated with Fuseli in Rome in the 1770s.</p>
          <p>A theoretical introduction to the subject of the symposium was presented by Frederick J.
Cummings, Director, The Detroit Institute of Arts, who spoke on <hi rend="i">The Beginnings of
Romanticism.</hi> Presented to enlarge the disciplinary scope of the program were <hi rend="i">Gibbon, Burke
and the Sublime</hi> by Martin Price, Thomas E. Donnelly Professor of English, Yale University, and 
<hi rend="i">Roman Impressions: Some Personal Views</hi> by Patricia Meyer Spacks, Professor of English, Yale
University. Following these papers was a public tour conducted by Nancy Pressly, Guest Curator for the
exhibition.</p>
          <p>In the afternoon Jules David Prown, Professor of Art History, Yale University, discussed the
ramifications of Rome and the antique in <hi rend="i">Benjamin West, Antiquity, and the American Indian.
Fuseli’s Use of the Antique</hi> was presented by Gert Schiff, Professor of Fine Arts, Institute of Fine
Arts, New York University. The Center’s Curator of Prints and Drawings, Andrew Wilton, ended the papers with
<hi rend="i">William Pars in Rome.</hi></p>
          <figure n="HenryFuseli.13.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="710"/>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
