<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>13.2.shroyer</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake’s Copy of Lavater’s Aphorisms on Man: A Correction of G. E Bentley,
Jr., Blake Books</title>
        <author n="Shroyer">R. J. Shroyer</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1979</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1979</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">13.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>F.R. Duplantier</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>James King</name>
              <name>N.G.D. Malmqvist</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>R.J. Shroyer</name>
              <name>Shawn Thompson</name>
              <name>Kazumitsu Watarai</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1979"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_13">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-13-2-0009">
        <pb id="p13-108" n="108"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main"><hi rend="b">BLAKE’S COPY OF LAVATER’S</hi> <hi rend="i">APHORISMS ON
MAN: </hi><hi rend="b">A CORRECTION OF G. E. BENTLEY, JR.</hi>, <hi rend="i">BLAKE BOOKS</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">R. J.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Shroyer</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The history of Blake’s annotated copy of J. C. Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man</hi>
(1788) provided by G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1977), invites
correction of some minute particulars. Bentley describes three stages in the history of the book:
<q>
(1) Blake made his notes when the sheets were not bound and showed them “to Fuseli; who said one could
assuredly read their writer’s character in <hi rend="i">them</hi>”;* (2) Acquired by Robert Hoe, who added
his bookplate, and wrote a note now pasted in: “This copy which was Blake’s, had to be rebound; it was in
broken sheepskin, and more than dirty. All the writing by Blake on the [<hi rend="i">back</hi>] fly leaves is
carefully preserved. R. H.”; sold posthumously with Hoe’s Library at Anderson Galleries, 25 April 1911, lot
396, for $1,525 to (3) The HUNTINGTON LIBRARY.<lb/>
<lb/>
*Gilchrist <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (1863), i. 62. He also showed them to John Linnell, who
transcribed them into a copy of the 1794 edition now in Yale.<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 691; bracketed word and footnote in original
</q></p>
          <p>First of all, it was John Linnell <hi rend="i">Junior</hi> (seven years of age when Blake died in
1827) rather than his more famous father who transcribed with great care Blake’s underlinings and notes into
a secondhand copy of the third edition of <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> (1794) now in the Beinecke Rare Book and
Manuscript Library at Yale.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n142" type="note">1</ref> In
addition to the transcription John Linnell Junior wrote notes on the first and last endpapers of the book in
which he identifies himself as the transcriber, dates the transcription 1874, and—most importantly—claims
that Blake’s copy of <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> belonged to Samuel Palmer. The first endpaper reads: “John
Linnell Jun<hi rend="s">r</hi>. . . . <hi rend="i">Blake’s notes</hi> in the orig[inal]. edit[ion].
belonging to S. Palmer Esq[uire] I have transcribed correctly in this edit[ion]. differences between this
edit[ion]. &amp; the orig[inal]. I mark in <hi rend="i">red ink—W. Blake’s writing &amp; marks are in
black ink</hi>[.]” The note on the last endpaper contains substantially the same information, with the
addition of “J L. jun<hi rend="s">r</hi>. (1874).” <note id="n142"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Shelfmark
Im/B581/Zz794. A previous owner, Eckermann, signed the book on endpaper 7<hi rend="s">r</hi>, wrote the date
17 Feb. 1829, and copied out two of Goethe’s comments on Lavater. Beneath these quotations, John Linnell
Junior scrupulously noted: “The above writing was here when I bought this copy—(not in Blake’s
edit[ion]).” References to J. Knowles’s <hi rend="i">Life of Fuseli</hi> (1831) in the younger Linnell’s
hand are on pp. vii and viii. According to an unattached acquisitions slip in the book, Yale purchased it from
W. H. Robinson [the Dealer] on 20 Nov. 1942 for $15. I had hoped to find that an early transcription of
Blake’s annotations preserved some of Blake’s notes not now legible in the original (Huntington 57431),
but this proved not to be the case.</note></p>
          <p>Samuel Palmer’s ownership of Blake’s copy of <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> prior to Robert Hoe
is supported by A. H. Palmer’s recollection of his father’s library, written in Blake’s copy of Boyd’s
Dante:
<q>
This volume as far back as I can remember, stood upon one of my father’s [<hi rend="i">i.e., Samuel
Palmer’s</hi>] book-shelves by the side of books annotated or illustrated by Blake. Among them was the now
well-known copy of Lavater’s “Aphorisms” . . . <ref target="n143" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n143"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Books</hi>, p. 686. A. H. Palmer’s undated note
presumably dates from after his father’s death in 1881. The book is “now well-known” probably because of
Gilchrist’s extensive quotation of Blake’s notes (I, 62-67), or perhaps because of the full but inaccurate
transcription of Blake’s notes in E. J. Ellis, <hi rend="i">The Real Blake</hi> (1907), pp.
122-51.</note></q>
Samuel Palmer’s own testimony in a letter to Frederick G. Stephens would seem to settle the question of
ownership:
<q>
See Lavater’s “Aphorisms”, translated by Fuseli, I think. I cannot find my copy, which was doubly valuable
as having belonged to the illustrious William Blake. That great man had written his own name close to
Lavater’s on the title-page, and had enclosed both in one <hi rend="i">heart</hi> drawn in pencil . . . 
<ref target="n144" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n144"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Frederick G. Stephens, <hi rend="i">Memorials of William Mulready, R.
A.</hi> (London, 1890); quoted and conjecturally dated ?Jan. 1872 by Raymond Lister in his <hi rend="i">The
Letters of Samuel Palmer</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1974), II, 837.</note></q></p>
          <p>In sum, there is no evidence that Blake showed his copy of Lavater’s 
<hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> to John Linnell, but there is good evidence that the book belonged to Samuel Palmer,
as Geoffrey Keynes asserted in 1921.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n145" type="note">4</ref>
One final point: G. E. Bentley, Jr., and David V. Erdman<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n146"
type="note">5</ref> once claimed that Samuel Palmer’s signature is visible in Blake’s copy of 
<hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi>, but neither I nor Carey S. Bliss of the Huntington Library can find this
signature.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n147" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n145"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">A Bibliography of William Blake</hi> (New
York: Grolier Club, 1921), p. 49. I know of no evidence that would confirm Keynes’s further assertion that
Blake’s copy of <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> remained for some time in the possession of Samuel Palmer’s
descendants before its acquisition by Robert Hoe.</note>
	<note id="n146"><hi rend="s">5</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., and Martin K. Nurmi, <hi rend="i">A Blake
Bibliography</hi> (Minneapolis: Univ. of Minnesota Press, 1964), p. 207; <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of
William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman (Garden City, N. Y.: Doubleday, 1965), p. 799.</note>
	<note id="n147"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Another ghost is the half-title described by Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake
Books</hi>, p. 593. I have found no half-title in four copies of the first edition (including Blake’s copy)
and six copies of the second edition. The third edition of 1794, however, in some copies has a half-title that
reads “APHORISMS. / VOL. I.” It is a bit surprising to find this half-title so long after Fuseli is supposed
to have abandoned his intention to add a second volume of his own aphorisms on art.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
