<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>13.2.minnick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="checklist">Blake &amp; His Circle: A Checklist of Recent Scholarship</title>
        <author n="Minnick">Thomas L. Minnick</author>
        <author n="Dörrbecker">Detlef W. Dörrbecker</author>
        <author n="Watarai">Kazumitsu Watarai</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1979</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1979</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">13.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>David Anderson</name>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>F.R. Duplantier</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>James King</name>
              <name>N.G.D. Malmqvist</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>R.J. Shroyer</name>
              <name>Shawn Thompson</name>
              <name>Kazumitsu Watarai</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1979"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_13">
    <body>
      <pb id="p13-91" n="91"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-13-2-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">BLAKE &amp; HIS CIRCLE: A CHECKLIST OF RECENT SCHOLARSHIP</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline><docAuthor><hi rend="b">THOMAS L. </hi><name><hi rend="b">MINNICK</hi></name></docAuthor> WITH
THE ASSISTANCE OF <docAuthor><hi rend="b">DETLEF W. </hi><name><hi
rend="b">DÖRRBECKER</hi></name></docAuthor> AND <docAuthor><hi rend="b">KAZUMITSU </hi><name><hi
rend="b">WATARAI</hi></name></docAuthor></byline>
        <p>Readers may notice several changes in this year’s checklist, beginning with the title. “A
Checklist of Recent Blake Scholarship,” our title for the last several years, has been enlarged to include
Blake’s “circle,” a term we interpret very broadly. In fact, this has been, in intention and in practice,
the range of the checklist since its beginning, and our change merely acknowledges a continuing policy. Thus,
items on Fuseli, Flaxman, Runge, the Pre-Raphaelites, and Maurice Sendak in his Blakean moments (as one critic
judges them) are included—even a biography of John Middleton Murry and <hi rend="i">his</hi> circle, because
of Murry’s early work on Blake. Casting so wide a net we cannot hope to be exhaustive; but we try.</p>
        <p>In a second major change, we welcome Kazumitsu Watarai, Head Librarian of Japan’s Reitaku
University Library, to our annual hunt. Mr. Watarai’s bibliography of Blake scholarship in Japan from 1969
to 1977 was published too late for inclusion in this year’s checklist (wait till next year, or see the
Winter 1978-79 issue of <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>). He will be helping us keep up to
date on Japanese writing on Blake—a long neglected group of works.</p>
        <p>Finally, we have made several changes in the format of the checklist, including somewhat greater
annotation. Readers may expect to see additional changes (and are encouraged to send suggestions) as we work
toward the most usable organization and format. As has become our common practice, an asterisk designates
items published more than five years ago that have not been noted in other standard sources.</p>
        <p>As always, we thank contributors for sending along notice of their own publications. My personal
thanks to Professor G. E. Bentley, Jr., for his helpful correspondence concerning previous checklists.</p>
        <p>T. L. M.</p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">I. BIBLIOGRAPHIES, BIBLIOGRAPHICAL ESSAYS, EXHIBITION CATALOGUES</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Bindman, David, <hi rend="i">et al. John Flaxman 1755-1826: Mythologie und Industrie</hi>, ed.
Werner Hofmann. Hamburg: Kunsthalle, and Munich: Prestel, 1979. (Kunst um 1800, vol. 8) [Catalogue of an
exhibition which included, besides the most representative selection from Flaxman’s oeuvre ever to be shown
to the present day, works by many of his contemporaries and followers.]</p>
          <p>Boerlin-Brodbeck, Yvonne. <hi rend="i">Zeichnungen des 18. Jahrhunderts aus dem Basler
Kupferstichkabinett.</hi> Basle: Kunstmuseum, 1978. [Exhibition catalogue, including an important collection
of Fuseli drawings under cat. nos. 72-103, pp. 44-53.]</p>
          <p>Curtis, Melinda, and George Levitine. <hi rend="i">Search for Innocence: Primitive and
Primitivistic Art of the 19th Century</hi>, exhb. cat. College Park, Md.: University of Maryland Art Gallery,
1975. [Includes material by Flaxman and Blake.]</p>
          <p>Dörrbecker, Detlef W. <hi rend="i">See</hi> Minnick, Thomas L.</p>
          <p>Easson, Roger R., and Robert N. Essick. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Book Illustrator.</hi> Vol.
II: “Plates Designed
<pb id="p13-92" n="92"/>
or Engraved Between the Years 1774-1796.” Memphis: American Blake Foundation, Inc., 1979. [Ltd. ed., 100
copies, $125.00; trade ed., 200 copies, $45.00. 205 illus.]</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N. “Handlist of the Huntington Blake Collection.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 11 (1978), 236-259. [26 illus.]</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">See also</hi> Easson, Roger R.</p>
          <p>Farr, Dennis, and Brian Sewell. <hi rend="i">Pittura Inglese 1660/1840: due secoli di cultura,
storia e costume in Inghilterra</hi>, exhb. cat. Palazzo Reale. Milan: Electa, 1975. [A background survey;
works by Gavin Hamilton, Angelica Kauffmann, Reynolds, Romney, Fuseli, Haydon, Martin, etc., were included in
the exhibition.]</p>
          <p>Hall, Spencer. “Some Recent Directions in Blake Studies—a Review Essay.” <hi rend="i">Southern
Humanities Review</hi>, 10 (1976), 172-177.</p>
          <p>Hofmann, Werner. <hi rend="i">See</hi> Bindman, David, <hi rend="i">et al.</hi></p>
          <p>Krueger, Ingeborg. <hi rend="i">Illustrierte Ausgaben von Homers Ilias und Odyssee vom 16. bis
ins 20. Jahrhundert.</hi> Ulm: [printed for the author], 1971. [Pp. 47-60 of this Tübingen Ph.D. thesis
contain a bibliographical checklist of Homer editions which employ Flaxman’s outlines as book
illustrations.]</p>
          <p>Levitine, George. <hi rend="i">See</hi> Curtis, Melinda.</p>
          <p>Lyle, Janice S. “Handlist of the Essick Blake Collection.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 11 (1978), 216-235. [17 illus.]</p>
          <p>Minnick, Thomas L., with the assistance of Detlef W. Dörrbecker. “A Checklist of Recent Blake
Scholarship.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 142-149.</p>
          <p>Modern Language Association of America. <hi rend="i">1977 MLA International Bibliography of Books
and Articles on the Modern Languages and Literatures.</hi> Vol. I, 79-81.</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D., assisted by Michael Davies. “Handlists of Four Blake Collections.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 11 (1978), 260-275. [Lists materials on Blake and his circle
held by the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Boston Museum of Fine Arts, the Fogg Art Museum of Harvard
University, and the Victoria and Albert Museum. 9 illus.]</p>
          <p>*Ragghianti Collobi, Licia. <hi rend="i">Disegni della Fondazione Horne in Firenze</hi>, exhb.
cat. La Strozzina—Palazzo Strozzi. Florence: Fondazione Horne, 1963. [See nos. 194-197, 220, and 230 for
drawings by Fuseli, Flaxman, Blake, and Varley.]</p>
          <p>Sewell, Brian. <hi rend="i">See</hi> Farr, Dennis.</p>
          <p>*Waterhouse, Ellis K., <hi rend="i">et al. Die grossen Maler Englands von Hogarth bis
Turner</hi>, exhb. cat. Hamburg: Kunsthalle, 1949. [On show were six Blakes, two Palmer watercolors, etc.]</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">II. EDITIONS, TRANSLATIONS, FACSIMILES, REPRODUCTIONS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr., ed. <hi rend="i">Materials for the Study of William Blake’s Europe: A
Prophecy.</hi> Memphis: American Blake Foundation, Inc., 1979. [Ltd. ed., 100 copies, $60.00. Reproduces copy
H, with 20 additional plates.]</p>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings.</hi> Vol. I: Engraved and Etched
Writings. Vol. II: Writings in Conventional Typography and in Manuscript. Oxford: The Clarendon Press, 1978.
$125.00 the set.</p>
          <p>Bindman, David, ed., assisted by Deirdre Toomey. <hi rend="i">The Complete Graphic Works of
William Blake.</hi> New York: Putnam, 1978.</p>
          <p>Easson, Kay Parkhurst, and Roger R. Easson, eds. <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen by William
Blake.</hi> New York: Shambhala Publications in association with Random House, Inc., 1978. Cloth $15.00;
paperback $6.95. [Reproduces copy G.]</p>
          <p>Easson, Kay Parkhurst, and Roger R. Easson, eds. <hi rend="i">Milton: A Poem by William
Blake.</hi> New York: Shambhala Publications in association with Random House, Inc., 1978. Cloth, $17.95;
paperback, $9.95. [Reproduces in color copy B, with 6 monochrome plates from copies C and D.]</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N., and Jenijoy La Belle, eds. <hi rend="i">Flaxman’s Illustrations to
Homer.</hi> New York: Dover, and London: Constable, 1977. £3.20.</p>
          <p>Farington, Joseph. <hi rend="i">The Diary of Joseph Farington</hi>, ed. Kenneth Garlick and Angus
Macintyre. 2 vols. (July 1793 to August 1796). New Haven, Conn. and London: Yale University Press, published
for the Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art, 1978 [“Studies in British Art”]. [These are the first
two volumes of the first complete edition of the Farington Diary; the text volumes will be followed by a full
index and a commentary.]</p>
          <p>Lavater, Johann Caspar. <hi rend="i">Physiognomische Fragmente zur Beförderung der
Menschenkenntnis und Menschenliebe.</hi> 4 vols. Zurich: Orell Füssli, 1969. [A facsimile reprint of the
Winterthur 1775-78 edition.]</p>
          <p>Rousselot, Jean, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, trans. Jean Rousselot, with the assistance
of Anne-Marie Rousselot. 2nd edition. Paris: Seghers, 1975. [Poètes d’aujourd’hui, vol. 118]. [Cf.
Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, item 352.]</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">III. CRITICAL STUDIES</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Abrahams, Cecil Anthony. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Fourfold Man.</hi> Bonn: Bouvier Verlag
Herbert Grundmann, 1978 [Studien zur Germanistik, Anglistik und Komparatistik, ed. Armin Arnold and Alois M.
Haas, vol. 72].</p>
          <p>Adams, Hazard. “Revisiting Reynold’s [sic] <hi rend="i">Discourses</hi> and Blake’s
Annotations.” Pp. 128-144 in Essick and Pearce, <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, q. v.</p>
          <p>*Adrian, [?Johann Valentin]. “John Flaxman.” <hi rend="i">Morgenblatt für gebildete Stände:
Kunst-Blatt</hi>, 25 (1831), 261-264 [i.e. Morgenblatt, no. 197 (Kunst-Blatt, no. 66), 18 August 1831]. [This
short biography of the sculptor, based on the report in vol. XII of the Annual Biography and Obituary, also
mentions Blake as an early acquaintance of Flaxman and as the engraver of his Hesiod designs.]</p>
          <p>Allen, Orphia Jane. “Blake’s Archetypal Criticism: <hi rend="i">The Canterbury Pilgrims.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">Genre</hi>, 11 (1978), 173-189.</p>
          <p>Ando, Eiko. “W. Blake no kami ni tsuite no ichikosatsu—Blake no tsumi no ishiki o chushin ni”
[A Study of William Blake’s God—On the Consciousness of Blake’s Sin]. <hi rend="i">Hokkaido
Eigoeibungaku</hi> [<hi rend="i">English Literature in Hokkaido</hi>], 23 (1978), 1-14.</p>
          <pb id="p13-93" n="93"/>
          <p>*Antal, Frederick. <hi rend="i">Studi su Fuseli</hi>, trans. Luciano Capra, ed. Evelyn Antal.
Turin: Einaudi, 1971. [The Italian edition of Antal’s <hi rend="i">Fuseli Studies</hi> of 1956.]</p>
          <p>Antal, Frederick. <hi rend="i">Zwischen Renaissance und Romantik: Studien zur
Kunstgeschichte</hi>, trans. Inge Frommhold. Dresden: VEB Verlag der Kunst, 1975 [Fundus-Bücher, vol. 38/39].
[The German edition of <hi rend="i">Classicism and Romanticism</hi> (1966).]</p>
          <p>Banta, Martha. “Adonais and the Angel: Light, Color, and the Occult Sublime.” 
<hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 8 (1977), 113-120.</p>
          <p>Behrendt, Stephen C. “The Mental Contest: Blake’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> Designs.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 8 (1978), 65-88.</p>
          <p>Behrendt, Stephen C. “The Polished Artifact: Some Observations on Imitative Criticism.” 
<hi rend="i">Genre</hi>, 10 (1977), 47-62. [Includes examples from Blake on <hi rend="i">Comus.</hi>]</p>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Blake’s Shadow.” <hi rend="i">The</hi> [<hi rend="i">London</hi>] 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 17 March 1978, p. 320. [Publishes and discusses two recently
discovered letters from Catherine Blake. This article has been translated into Japanese by Akiko Iwahara and
published in <hi rend="i">Mizue (Water-Color Paintings: A Monthly Review of the Fine Arts)</hi> no. 882
(1978), 74-77, under the title “Blake no kage.”]</p>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “The First Printed Reference to the Publication of <hi rend="i">Job</hi>:
Disraeli (?) in <hi rend="i">The Star Chamber</hi> (1826).” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>,
12 (1978), 69-70.</p>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “A Jewel in an Ethiop’s Ear.” Pp. 213-240 in Essick and Pearce, 
<hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, q. v. [On Blake and the apocryphal Book of Enoch.]</p>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “The Selling of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> Designs in the
1870s.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 70-71.</p>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “The Vicissitudes of Vision: The First Account of William Blake in Russian
(1834).” <hi rend="i">J. Univ. Poona, Humanities</hi>, 43 (1978), 43-64. [Includes the full text of a
translation, by Christine Moisan, “into English (1975) of a translation into Russian (1834) of a rough
adaptation into French (1833) of Cunningham’s biography in English (1830) which was in turn largely derived
from J. T. Smith’s biography of Blake (1828) . . . .” Bentley’s preface to the translation was printed in
<hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 10 (1977), 112-114.]</p>
          <p>Berwick, J. F. “‘The Sick Rose’: A Second Opinion.” <hi rend="i">Theoria</hi>, 47 (1976),
77-81.</p>
          <p>Bindman, David. “Blake’s Theory and Practice of Imitation.” Pp. 91-98 in Essick and Pearce, 
<hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, q. v.</p>
          <p>Bindman, David. “Blake’s Visions of Eternity.” <hi rend="i">The Sunday Times Magazine</hi>, 5
March 1978, pp. 40-49.</p>
          <p>Blondel, Jacques. <hi rend="i">Imaginaire et croyance.</hi> Grenoble: Presses Universitaires de
Grenoble, 1976. [Includes a chapter devoted to Blake.]</p>
          <p>Blunt, Anthony F. “Keynes on Blake.” <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 120 (1978), 675-676.
[A rebuke to Sir Geoffrey’s critique of Blunt’s <hi rend="i">The Art of William Blake</hi> in his review
of Bindman’s <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist.</hi>]</p>
          <p>Briganti, Giuliano. <hi rend="i">I pittori dell’immaginario: arte e rivulizione
psicologica.</hi> Milan: Electa, 1977.</p>
          <p>Brodersen, Waltraud, et al. “‘In der Zeit liegt wohl eine grosse Geburt.’ Philipp Otto Runges
Kunst als Reflexion und Aneignung gesellschaftlicher Totalität.” <hi rend="i">Kritische Berichte</hi>, 6
(1978), 5-77. [This special issue of <hi rend="i">Kritische Berichte</hi> has also been published in book
format in Giessen: Anabas, 1978.]</p>
          <p>Brogan, Howard O. “Blake and the Occult: ‘The Real Man the Imagination which Liveth for
Ever’.” <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 8 (1977), 147-160.</p>
          <p>Brown, David. “Fuseli’s Drawings for Ben Johnson’s [sic] ‘Masque of Queenes’, and a
Figure Study, Rediscovered in the Ashmolean Museum.” <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 121 (1979),
111-113.</p>
          <p>Butlin, Martin. “Cataloguing William Blake.” Pp. 77-90 in Essick and Pearce, <hi rend="i">Blake
in His Time</hi>, q. v.</p>
          <p>Butlin, Martin. “James Jefferys Update.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 11
(1978), 298-299. [Notes two recent articles on James Jefferys by John Sunderland and Nancy L. Pressly, q.
v.]</p>
          <p>Carothers, Yvonne M. “Space and Time in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: The ‘Bard’s Song’.” Pp.
116-127 in Essick and Pearce, <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, q. v.</p>
          <p>Carswell, John. <hi rend="i">Lives and Letters: A. R. Orage, Katherine Mansfield, Beatrice
Hastings, John Middleton Murry, S. S. Koteliansky 1906-1957.</hi> London &amp; Boston, Mass.: Faber &amp;
Faber, 1978. [The biography of Murry, a well known interpreter of Blake, as well as the members of his
“circle.”]</p>
          <p>Chayes, Irene H. “Blake and Tibaldi.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi>,
81 (1978), 113-125.</p>
          <p>Christensen, Bodil Krongaard. <hi rend="i">Dialektik og bevidsthedsudvikling: En studie i William
Blakes tilvaerelsesforstaelse.</hi> Odense: Udgivelsesudvalget ved Odense, 1977. [Udgivelsesudvalgets samling
af studenter-afhandlinger, 9.]</p>
          <p>*Clark, Kenneth McKenzie. <hi rend="i">Glorie des Abendlandes</hi>, trans. Thomas Monrad. Reinbek
bei Hamburg: Rowohlt, 1970, rpt. 1977. [The German edition of Lord Clark’s 
<hi rend="i">Civilization.</hi>]</p>
          <p>Clark, Kenneth McKenzie. “Samuel Palmer et la peinture visionnaire—Samuel Palmer and Visionary
Painting.” <hi rend="i">Revue de l’art</hi>, 30 (1975), 55-60 and 102-104.</p>
          <p>Clarke, Mary. “The Job Ballet.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978),
18-25. [Reprinted from Ms. Clarke’s 1955 study, <hi rend="i">The Sadler’s Wells Ballet/A History and
Appreciation</hi>, this excerpt describes the 1931 production of “Job: A Masque for Dancing” at the Old Vic.
10 illus.]</p>
          <p>Dargan, Thomas Raymond. “Blake, Stonehenge, and the New Jerusalem.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation
Abstracts International</hi>, 39 (1978), 893-A. Diss., State University of New York at Stony Brook, 1978.</p>
          <p>Dargan, Tom. Response to Michael Ferber, “Blake’s Idea of Brotherhood,” <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi>,
94 (1979), 146-147. [Ferber’s article, noted in last year’s checklist, was published in 
<hi rend="i">PMLA</hi>, 93 (1978), 438-447.]</p>
          <p>*Day, Martin S. “The Poetry of Blake,” in <hi rend="i">History of English Literature
1660-1837.</hi> Garden City, N. Y.: Doubleday, 1963 [“Doubleday College Course Guides”], pp. 284-308.</p>
          <p>Deck, Raymond H., Jr. “Another Early Printing of Blake’s ‘Night’.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12(1978), 69.</p>
          <p>Deck, Raymond H., Jr. “Blake and Swedenborg.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
International</hi>, 39 (1978), 3594-A-3595-A. Diss., Brandeis University, 1978.</p>
          <p>Deck, Raymond H., Jr. “‘Blake, William’ in the <hi rend="i">New American Cyclopedia</hi>
(1861).” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 68-69.</p>
          <p>De Luca, V. A. “Proper Names in the Structural Design of Blake’s Myth-Making.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 8(1978), 5-22.</p>
          <p>Dobai, Johannes. <hi rend="i">Die Kunstliteratur des Klassizismus</hi>
	<pb id="p13-94" n="94"/>
	<hi rend="i">und der Romantik in England.</hi> vol. 3: 1790-1840. Bern: Benteli, 1977.</p>
          <p>Dörrbecker, Detlef W. “<hi rend="i">Job</hi> in Frankfurt Schauspielhaus.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 11 (1978), 298. [Notes the use of a Blake design in the scenery for a play at the
Frankfurt Schauspielhaus.]</p>
          <p>Easson, Kay Parkhurst. “Blake and the Art of the Book.” Pp. 35-52 in Essick and Pearce, 
<hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, q. v.</p>
          <p>Easson, Roger R. “Blake and the Gothic.” Pp. 145-154 in Essick and Pearce, <hi rend="i">Blake in
His Time</hi>, q. v.</p>
          <p>Einem, Herbert von. <hi rend="i">Deutsche Malerei des Klassizismus und der Romantik 1760 bis
1840.</hi> Munich: C. H. Beck, 1978. [Contains discussions of Fuseli, Carstens, and Runge.]</p>
          <p>Ellis, Helen B., and Warren U. Ober. “<hi rend="i">Grendel</hi> and Blake: The Contraries of
Existence.” <hi rend="i">English Studies in Canada</hi> (Toronto), 3(1977), 87-102. [That is, Blake and John
Gardner’s <hi rend="i">Grendel.</hi>]</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V. “<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: New Text for Pages 5, 6, &amp; 7, Night the
First.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 96-99.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V. “Night the Seventh: The Editorial Problem.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 135-139.</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N. “Blake in the Marketplace, 1976-77.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 26-38.</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N. “The Figure in the Carpet: Blake’s Engravings in Salzmann’s 
<hi rend="i">Elements of Morality.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 10-14. [6
illus.]</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N. “William Blake and Sir Thomas Lawrence.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>,
n. s., 25 (1978), 211-213. [An addendum to <hi rend="i">Blake Records.</hi>]</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Relief Inventions.</hi> Los Angeles: William
&amp; Victoria Dailey, 1978. [Ltd. ed.: 365 copies at $75.00; copies 1-15 with an extra suite of plates at
$150.00; a few copies available in sheets at $65.00 for hand binding.]</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N., and Donald Pearce, eds. <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, Bloomington &amp;
London: Indiana University Press, 1978. [Publishes 14 essays, all but one (by Morton D. Paley) from the 1976
University of California at Santa Barbara conference “Blake in the Art of His Time”; preface, “ . . . &amp;
his Resurrection to Unity” by Donald Pearce, and preludium, “Meditations on a Fiery Pegasus,” by Robert N.
Essick. 144 illus.]</p>
          <p>Ferber, Michael. “Coleridge’s ‘Anacalyptic’ Blake: An Exegesis.” <hi rend="i">Modern
Philology</hi>, 76 (1978), 189-193. [A reading of the famous letter about Blake by Coleridge.]</p>
          <p>Fernow, Carl L. <hi rend="i">Carstens: Leben und Werke</hi>, ed. Hermann Riegel. Hildesheim and
New York, N. Y.: Olms, 1978. [A reprint of the Hannover 1867 edition, with catalogue raisonné.]</p>
          <p>Finke, Ulrich. <hi rend="i">Französische und englische Dürer-Rezeption im 19. Jahrhundert.</hi>
Nuremberg: Stadtgeschichtliche Museen, 1976 [“Renaissance Vorträge,” 4-5], pp. 19ff.</p>
          <p>Fitch, Donald. “Blake as Book Illustrator.” <hi rend="i">Soundings: Collections of the University
Library</hi>, University of California, Santa Barbara, 8 (1976), 37-41.</p>
          <p>Flory, Wendy Stallard. “Pound’s Blake and Blake’s Dante: ‘The Circle of the Lustful’ and
Canto 20.” <hi rend="i">Paideuma</hi>, 6 (1977), 155-165.</p>
          <p>Fox, Susan. “The Female as Metaphor in William Blake’s Poetry.” <hi rend="i">Critical
Inquiry</hi>, 3 (1977), 507-519.</p>
          <p>Gabbett-Mulhallen, Karen Ann. “William Blake’s Illustrations to Edward Young’s 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>: Context, Christology and Composite Worlds.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
International</hi>, 39 (1979), 4269-A. Diss., University of Toronto (Canada), 1976.</p>
          <p>Gallant, Christine. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Assimilation of Chaos.</hi> Princeton, N. J.:
Princeton University Press, 1978.</p>
          <p>Gandolfo, Anita. “‘This is Doubbllinnbbayyates’: A Further Blake-Joyce Note.” <hi rend="i">A
Wake Newsletter: Studies in James Joyce’s Finnegan’s Wake</hi>, 14 (1977), 77-79.</p>
          <p>Gilpin, George H. “Blake, Hogarth, and the Engraver’s Art of Line.” <hi rend="i">The Carrell:
Journal of the Friends of the University of Miami</hi> [<hi rend="i">Florida</hi>] <hi rend="i">Library</hi>,
17 (1976), 1-7.</p>
          <p>Givone, Sergio. “Blake e la tradizione neoplatonica.” <hi rend="i">Rivista de Storia e
Letteratura Religiosa</hi>, 13 (1977), 167-178.</p>
          <p>Gleckner, Robert F. “Blake and the Four Daughters of God.” <hi rend="i">English Language
Notes</hi>, 15 (1977), 110-115.</p>
          <p>Gleckner, Robert F. “Blake and Satire.” <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 8 (1977),
311-326.</p>
          <p>Gleckner, Robert F. “Skelton, Blake, and Diodorus Siculus.” <hi rend="i">The USF Language
Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1978), 25, 56.</p>
          <p>Godfrey, Richard T. <hi rend="i">Printmaking in Britain.</hi> Oxford: Phaidon, 1978. £9.95. [168
illus.]</p>
          <p>Goldberg, Jerome Edmund. “William Blake: A Study in the Human Sciences.” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 39 (1979), 4271-A-4272-A. Diss., University of Toronto
(Canada), 1978. [“Blake’s poetry is a revolt against traditional ontology of objects and absolutes and an
effort to develop an ontology in psychological terms—a ‘human science’ of ‘Mental forms Creating’
that will possess the world of nature.”]</p>
          <p>Haas, Rudolph. “Sozialgeschichte und Soziologie: Zugänge zur Literatur?” Pp. 145-189 in Rudolph
Haas, <hi rend="i">Theorie und Praxis der Interpretation: Modellanalysen englischer und amerikanischer
Texte.</hi> Berlin: Schmidt, 1977 [Grundlagen der Anglistik &amp; Amerikanistik, 5].</p>
          <p>*Haenlein, Charlotte. “Wiederentdeckung. Johann Heinrich Füssli: Ödipus verflucht seinen Sohn
Polyneikes.” du: <hi rend="i">Atlantis</hi>, 34 (1974), no. 403, 3.</p>
          <p>Hagstrum, Jean H. “Romney and Blake: Gifts of Grace and Terror.” Pp. 201-212 in Essick and
Pearce, <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, q. v.</p>
          <p>Hamlyn, Robin. “An Irish Shakespeare Gallery.” <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 120 (1978),
515-529. [Woodmason’s Shakespeare Gallery, the contributors to which included Fuseli, Northcote, and
Opie.]</p>
          <p>Hanke, Amala Maria. “Spatiotemporal Consciousness in English and German Romanticism: A
Comparative Study of Blake, Novalis, Wordsworth, and Eichendorff.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
International</hi>, 39 (1979), 4226-A-4227-A. Diss., University of California, Los Angeles, 1978.</p>
          <p>Harper, George Mills. <hi rend="i">See</hi> McClellan, Jane.</p>
          <p>Harvey, J. R. “Blake’s Art.” <hi rend="i">The Cambridge Quarterly</hi>, 7 (1977), 129-150.</p>
          <p>Hay, Eloise. “Songs of William Blake and Music of Blake’s Time.” <hi rend="i">Soundings:
Collections of the University Library</hi>, University of California, Santa
<pb id="p13-95" n="95"/>
Barbara, 8 (1976), 31-36.</p>
          <p>Heffernan, James A. W. “Politics and Freedom: Refractions of Blake in Joyce Cary and Allen
Ginsberg.” Pp. 177-195 in George Bornstein, ed., <hi rend="i">Romantic and Modern: Revaluations of Literary
Tradition.</hi> Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1977.</p>
          <p>Helmstadter, Thomas H. “‘Bright Visions of Eternity’: Blake’s Designs for Blair’s 
<hi rend="i">Grave.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 8 (1978), 37-64.</p>
          <p>Heppner, Christopher. “Blake and <hi rend="i">The Seaman’s Recorder</hi>: The Letter and the
Spirit in a Problem of Attribution.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 15-17.</p>
          <p>Hilton, Nelson. “The Sweet Science of Atmosphere in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 80-86.</p>
          <p>Hoagwood, Terence Allan. “<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and ‘The Philosophick Cabala’.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 87-90.</p>
          <p>Hoagwood, Terence Allan. “Holbach and Blake’s Philosophical Statement in ‘The Voice of the
Devil’.” <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi>, 15 (1978), 181-186.</p>
          <p>Hofmann, Werner. <hi rend="i">Bruchlinien: Aufsätze zur Kunst des 19. Jahrhunderts.</hi> Munich:
Prestel, 1979. [Hofmann’s Collected Essays on 19th-century art.]</p>
          <p>Jackson, Wallace. <hi rend="i">The Probable and the Marvelous: Blake, Wordsworth, and the
Eighteenth-Century Critical Tradition.</hi> Athens: University of Georgia Press, 1979. $14.00</p>
          <p>Johnson, Mary Lynn. <hi rend="i">See</hi> Wilkie, Brian.</p>
          <p>James, David E. <hi rend="i">Written Within and Without. A Study of Blake’s Milton.</hi>
Frankfurt am Main, Bern, Las Vegas: Peter Lang, 1978. [“European University Papers,” Series XIV: Anglo-Saxon
Language and Literature, vol. 54].</p>
          <p>Johnson, Mary Lynn, and Brian Wilkie. “The Spectrous Embrace in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>,
VIIa.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 100-105.</p>
          <p>Keynes, Sir Geoffrey, ed. <hi rend="i">Complete Portraiture of William and Catherine Blake.</hi>
Oxford: Oxford University Press, for the William Blake Trust, 1978. $129.00.</p>
          <p>Kilgore, John. “The Order of Nights VIIa and VIIb in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 107-113.</p>
          <p>*Kleinstück, Johannes Walter. <hi rend="i">Mythos und Symbol in Englischer Dichtung.</hi>
Stuttgart: W. Kohlhammer, 1964 [“Sprache und Literatur,” vol. 18].</p>
          <p>Kowle, Carol P. “Plate III and the Meaning of <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake
Studies</hi>, 8 (1978), 89-99.</p>
          <p>Kumashiro, Soho. <hi rend="i">William Blake—sono shogai to sakuhin no subete</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">William Blake—On His Life and the Works</hi>]. Tokyo: Kodansha, 1979. ¥3,000.</p>
          <p>Kumbier, William. “Blake’s Epic Meter.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 17 (1978),
163-192.</p>
          <p>La Belle, Jenijoy. “Blake’s Visions and Re-visions of Michelangelo.” Pp. 13-22 in Essick and
Pearce, <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, q. v.</p>
          <p>Lawson, Mildred. “Creative and Sexual Energy in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">American Notes &amp; Queries</hi>, 15 (1977), 68-70.</p>
          <p><corr type="emend">Lefebvre, Mark S.</corr> “A Note on the Structural Necessity of Night VIIb.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 134.</p>
          <p>Lincoln, A. W. J. “Blake’s ‘Europe’: An Early Version?” <hi rend="i">Notes and
Queries</hi>, n. s. 25 (1978), 213. [Copy a (the monochrome BM copy) as “an early draft of 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, printed before Blake had decided to introduce Enitharmon’s dream.”]</p>
          <p>Lincoln, Andrew. “<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: The Text of Pages 5, 6, &amp; 7, Night the
First.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 91-95.</p>
          <p>Lincoln, Andrew. “The Revision of the Seventh and Eighth Nights of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 115-133.</p>
          <p>Lindsay, David. “The Resurrection of Man: A Short Commentary on Night Nine of Blake’s ‘Vala
or The Four Zoas’.” <hi rend="i">University of Cape Town Studies in English</hi>, 6 (1976), 14-23.</p>
          <p>Lindsay, David W. “‘The Book of Ahania’: An Interpretation of the Text.” <hi rend="i">Durham
University Journal</hi>, 68, n. s. 37 (1976), 144-147.</p>
          <p>Lindsay, David W. “Prelude to Apocalypse: A Short Commentary on Night VIII of Blake’s ‘Vala
or The Four Zoas’.” <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi>, 70, n. s. 39 (1977-1978), 179-185.</p>
          <p>Lindsay, Jack. <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Life and Work.</hi> London: Constable, 1978.</p>
          <p>Maeda, Masahiko. “E. Young ‘Yaso’ eno Blake no sashie—hyoshaku no kokoromi sono 1”
[Illustrations to E. Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> by William Blake—An Attempt of the
Annotation No. 1]. <hi rend="i">Eibeibungaku, Rikkyo Daigaku Bungakubu Eibeibungaku Kenkyushitsu</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">English and American Literature, The Rikkyo Review, Arts &amp; Letters</hi> (The Department of
Literature of Rikkyo University)], 38 (1978), 1-113.</p>
          <p>Maeda, Yoshihiko. “William Blake’s Metamorphosis and His Composite Art.” <hi rend="i">The
Rikkyo Review</hi> (Japan), 37 (1977), 1-42. [In Japanese.]</p>
          <p>Magno, Cettina. “<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> in Italy.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 140-141.</p>
          <p>Marks, Mollyanne. “Renovation of Form: Time as Hero in Blake’s Major Prophecies.” Pp. 55-66 in
Ronald C. Rosbottom, ed., <hi rend="i">Studies in Eighteenth-Century Culture</hi>, vol. 5. Madison, Wisc.:
University of Wisconsin Press, for the American Society of Eighteenth-Century Studies, 1976.</p>
          <p>Masini, Lara-Vinca. <hi rend="i">Art Nouveau: un’ avventura artistica internazionale tra
rivoluzione e reazione, tra cosmopolitismo e provincia, tra costante ed effimero, tra ‘sublime’ e
stravagante.</hi> Florence: Giunti, 1976. [Blake discussed among the “Precedenti dell’ art nouveau.”]</p>
          <p>Matsuo, Rikio. “A Study on William Blake—The Essence of Mental Traveller.” <hi rend="i">Hannan
Ronshu: Journal of Hannan University</hi>, 12-6 (1977), 1-20.</p>
          <p>Maxwell-Mahon, W. D. “William Blake: A Man without a Mask.” <hi rend="i">Lantern</hi> (Pretoria),
27 (1977), 12-17.</p>
          <p>McClellan, Jane, and George Mills Harper. “Blake’s Demonic Triad.” <hi rend="i">Wordsworth
Circle</hi>, 8 (1977), 172-182.</p>
          <p>Meller, Horst. “Die Absetzung des Vaters: Blake, Shelley und der Traditionshintergrund
romantischer Revolte,” in <hi rend="i">Das Vaterbild im Abendland II: Literatur und Dichtung Europas</hi>, ed.
Hubertus Tellenbach. Stuttgart: W. Kohlhammer, 1978, pp. 62-77.</p>
          <p>Mellor, Anne K. “Physiognomy, Phrenology, and Blake’s Visionary Heads.” Pp. 53-74 in Essick and
Pearce, <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, q. v.</p>
          <p>*Meynell, Alice. “Blake,” in <hi rend="i">The Wares of Autolycus</hi>, London, Oxford and New
York, N. Y.: Oxford University Press, 1965, pp. 145-150.</p>
          <p>Milosz, Czeslaw. <hi rend="i">The Land of Ulro.</hi> [In Polish.] Paris: Kultura, 1977.</p>
          <p>Morgan, Norman Louis. <hi rend="i">See</hi> Tidwell, Paul.</p>
          <pb id="p13-96" n="96"/>
          <p>*Mourey, Gabriel. “Les Peintres d’histoire et de genre,” in <hi rend="i">La Peinture Anglaises
du XVIIIe siècle.</hi> Paris and Brussels: G. van Oest, 1928 [“Bibliotheque de l’Art du XVIIIe siècle,” n.
s.], pp. 125-136. [For a glimpse at Blake, “que je me sens incapable de comprendre,” see pp. 130ff.]</p>
          <p>Mulhallen, Karen Ann. <hi rend="i">See also</hi> Gabbett-Mulhallen, Karen Ann.</p>
          <p>Mullins, Edwin. “The Visions of William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Telegraph Sunday Magazine</hi>, no.
75, 26 February 1978, 36-42.</p>
          <p>Murray, Roger. “Working Sir Joshua: Blake’s Marginalia in Reynolds.” <hi rend="i">British
Journal of Aesthetics</hi>, 17 (1977), 82-91.</p>
          <p>Namikawa, Ryo. <hi rend="i">William Blake—Geijutsu to shiso.</hi> [<hi rend="i">William
Blake—On His Art and Thought</hi>]. Tokyo: Harashobo, 1978. ¥3,600.</p>
          <p>Nanavutty, Piloo. “Blake and Gnostic Legends.” <hi rend="i">The Aligarh Journal of English
Studies</hi>, 1 (1976), 168-190.</p>
          <p>Nørlyng, Ole. “Den patetiske og politiske Ugolino.” <hi rend="i">Meddelelser fra ny Carlsberg
Glyptotek</hi>, 33 (1976), 53-77. [Aiming at an interpretation of J. B. Carpeaux’s “Ugolino,” the author
discusses the iconographical tradition from Reynolds, Fuseli, and Flaxman to Delacroix.]</p>
          <p>Ober, Warren U. <hi rend="i">See</hi> Ellis, Helen B.</p>
          <p><corr type="emend">Oliver, W. H. <hi rend="i">Prophets and Millennialists: The Uses of Biblical Prophecy in England
from the 1790s to the 1840s.</hi> Auckland, N. Z.: Auckland University Press and Oxford University Press New
Zealand, 1978.</corr></p>
          <p>*Oppel, Horst. <hi rend="i">Die Shakespeare-Illustration als Interpretation der Dichtung.</hi>
Mainz: Verlag der Akademie der Wissenschaften und der Literatur, and Wiesbaden: in Kommission bei Franz
Steiner, 1965 [“Akademie der Wissenschaften und der Literatur: Abhandlungen der Geistes und
Sozialwissenschaftlichen Klasse,” Jg. 1965, no. 2].</p>
          <p>Osterkamp, Ernst. <hi rend="i">Lucifer: Stationen eines Motivs.</hi> Berlin and New York, N. Y.:
Walter de Gruyter, 1979 [“Komparistische Studien,” Beihefte zu Arcadia, vol. 9]. [There are short discussions
of Blake and Fuseli on pp. 179-181 and passim; the book and its subject, however, should be of general
interest.]</p>
          <p>Paananen, Victor N. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> [Twayne English Authors Series.] Boston:
Twayne, 1977.</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, trans. Priska-Monika Hottenroth. Stuttgart: W.
Kohlhammer, 1978. [The German edition of the 1978 Phaidon Press edition.]</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D. “‘Wonderful Originals’—Blake and Ancient Sculpture.” Pp. 170-197 in Essick
and Pearce, <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, q. v.</p>
          <p>Payne, Michael D. “Blake and the Politics of Poetry.” <hi rend="i">Style</hi>, 10 (1976),
467-480.</p>
          <p>Pearce, Donald R. “Blake in the Art of His Time: The Santa Barbara Blake Conference.” 
<hi rend="i">Soundings: Collections of the University L<hi rend="u">i</hi>brary</hi>, University of California,
Santa Barbara, 8 (1976), 25-27.</p>
          <p>Pearce, Donald R. “Natural Religion and the Plight of Thel.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 8
(1978), 23-35.</p>
          <p>Pearce, Donald. <hi rend="i">See also</hi> Essick, Robert N.</p>
          <p>Peattie, R. W. “William Michael Rossetti’s Aldine Edition of Blake.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 4-9.</p>
          <p>*Pevsner, Nikolaus. “Blake und die flammende Linie,” in <hi rend="i">Das Englische in der
englischen Kunst</hi>, trans. Heidi Canrad. Munich: Prestel, 1974, pp. 145-178. [The German edition of 
<hi rend="i">The Englishness of English Art.</hi>]</p>
          <p>Phillips, Michael C. <hi rend="i">Interpreting Blake: A Volume of Studies.</hi> Cambridge:
Cambridge University Press 1979. £14.50.</p>
          <p>Pittman, Philip McM. “Blake, Rossetti, and the Genesis of the Pre-Raphaelite Idea.” 
<hi rend="i">The Bulletin of the West Virginia Association of College English Teachers</hi>, 2 (1975), 1-17.</p>
          <p>Punter, David. “Blake: Creative and Uncreative Labor.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>,
16 (1977), 535-561.</p>
          <p>Reinhart, Charles William. “The Universal Brotherhood: Blake, Milton, and the Reader in Blake’s
<hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 39 (1979), 4283-A. Diss.,
Indiana University, 1978.</p>
          <p>Reisner, Thomas A., and Mary Ellen Reisner. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Auguries of Innocence.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">Explicator</hi>, 35 (1977), 32-33.</p>
          <p>*Richter, Helene. “William Blake,” in <hi rend="i">Geschichte der englishchen Romantik</hi>, vol.
½: Die Anfänge der Romantik. Halle a. d. Saale: Max Niemeyer, 1911, pp. 483-520.</p>
          <p>Rix, Donna Standifer. “The Function of Biblical Sources in the Structure and Meaning of Blake’s
<hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 38 (1978), 7349-A. Diss.,
University of New Mexico, 1978.</p>
          <p>Roberts-Jones, Philippe. <hi rend="i">Beyond Time and Place: Non-Realist Painting in the
Nineteenth Century.</hi> Oxford, London and New York, N. Y.: Oxford University Press, 1978. [Includes
discussions of Blake and Fuseli in the company of Goya, Whistler, Munch, Klimt, and others.]</p>
          <p>Roberts-Jones, Philippe. <hi rend="i">Irrealismus: Das Visionäre in der Malerei des 19.
Jahrhunderts.</hi> Munich: Hirmer, 1978. [The German edition of the preceding entry.]</p>
          <p>Rose, Edward J. “The ‘Gothicized Imagination’ of ‘Michelangelo Blake’.” Pp. 155-169 in
Essick and Pearce, <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, q. v.</p>
          <p>Ross, Donald, Jr. “The Use of Word-Class Distribution Data for Stylistics: Keats’ Sonnets and
Chicken Soup.” <hi rend="i">Poetics</hi>, 6 (1977), 169-195. [Linguistic analysis of Keats and Blake.]</p>
          <p>Roth, Herbert John. “A Literary Study of the Calvinistic and Deistic Implications in the Hymns of
Isaac Watts, Charles Wesley, and William Cowper.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 39
(1978), 3604-A-3605-A. Diss., Texas Christian University, 1978.</p>
          <p>Rump, Gerhard Charles. “Naturalistische und realistische Tendenzen im englischen
neoklassizistischen Portrait.” <hi rend="i">Kunstchronik</hi>, 28 (1975), 100-101. [On Romney’s “proto
realism.”]</p>
          <p>Sakai, Tadayasu. “Muku to Keiken no aida de—Blake, sono idainaru konton” [“Between Innocence
and Experience—Blake, his Great Confusion”]. <hi rend="i">Mizue</hi> [<hi rend="i">Water-Color Paintings: A
Monthly Review of the Fine Arts</hi>], no. 882 (1978), 61-67.</p>
          <p>Sanzo, Eileen. “Blake and the Great Mother Archetype.” <hi rend="i">the nassau review 1978</hi>,
3 (1978), 105-116.</p>
          <p>Sanzo, Eileen. “Blake and the Symbolism of the New Iron Age.” Pp. 1-12 in Donald H. Rieman,
Michael C. Jaye, and Betty T. Bennett, eds., <hi rend="i">The Evidence of the Imagination: Studies of
Interactions between Life and Art in English Romantic Poetry.</hi> New York: New York University Press,
1978.</p>
          <p>Sanzo, Eileen. “The Convergence of Blake and Teilhard.” <hi rend="i">The Teilhard Review</hi>, 12
(1977), 73-78.</p>
          <pb id="p13-97" n="97"/>
          <p>*Sauerlandt, Max. “John Flaxman.” <hi rend="i">Zeitschrift fürbildende Kunst</hi>, n. s., 19
(1908), 189-197.</p>
          <p>Scholz, Joachim J. <hi rend="i">Blake and Novalis: A Comparison of Romanticism’s High
Arguments.</hi> Bern, Frankfurt am Main, and Las Vegas: Peter Lang, 1978 [“European University Papers,” Series
XVIII: Comparative Literature, vol. 19].</p>
          <p>Sherry, Peggy Meyer. “The ‘Predicament’ of the Autograph: ‘William Blake’.” 
<hi rend="i">Glyph</hi> (Johns Hopkins Textual Studies), 4 (1978), 131-155.</p>
          <p>Shioe, Kozo. “Blake no geijutsu shiko—dento to kindai no hazama de” [“Blake’s Thinking on
Art—At the Interstice of Tradition and Modern”]. <hi rend="i">Mizue</hi> [<hi rend="i">Water-Color
Paintings: A Monthly Review of the Fine Arts</hi>], no. 882 (1978), 68-73.</p>
          <p>Shioe, Kozo. <hi rend="i">Bureiku</hi> [<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>]. Tokyo: Kodansha, 1978. ¥880.
Sekai no sobyo, 14 (The Drawing of the World, no. 14).</p>
          <p>Simon, Howard. <hi rend="i">500 Years of Art in Illustration.</hi> Hacker Art Books, £30.00
[Includes discussions of Holbein, Blake, Bewick, Goya, Rowlandson, Cruikshank, and Beardsley.]</p>
          <p>Skovgaard, Bente. “Abildgaard eller Füssli: en tegning i Kobberstiksamling.” 
<hi rend="i">Kunstmuseets Årsskrift</hi>, 62 (1975), 57-76.</p>
          <p>Starobinski, Jean. “Die Vision der Schläferin,” in <hi rend="i">Besessenheit und Exorzismus:
Drei Figuren der Umnachtung</hi>, trans. Helmut Kossodo. Percha and Kempfenhausen am Starnberger See: R. S.
Schulz, 1976, pp. 141-183; reprinted [2nd edition] Berlin, Vienna and Frankfurt am Main: Ullstein, 1978, pp.#
141-183. [The German edition of <hi rend="i">Trois fureurs.</hi>]</p>
          <p>Stepto, Michele Leiss. “Blake, Urizen, and the Feminine: The Development of a Poetic Logic.” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 39 (1978), 2960-A. Diss., University of Massachusetts,
1978.</p>
          <p>Sutherland, James, ed. “William Blake,” in <hi rend="i">The Oxford Book of Literary
Anecdotes.</hi> Oxford, London, and New York, N. Y.: Oxford University Press, 1975, pp. 126-129.</p>
          <p>*Swinburne, Algernon Charles. “William Blake,” in <hi rend="i">Swinburne as Critic</hi>, ed.
Clyde K. Hyder. London and Boston, Mass.: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1972 [The Routledge Critical Series], pp.
101-124. [Excerpts from Swinburne’s Critical Essay of 1868.]</p>
          <p>Taniguchi, Shigeru. “The Four Zoas, Night the Fifth no bunseki—saikuru no aratana kaiten” [“An
Analysis of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night the Fifth—A New Revolution of Cycle”]. 
<hi rend="i">Reitaku Daigaku Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Reitaku University</hi>], 25 (1978), 131-137.</p>
          <p>Tannenbaum, Leslie. “Blake and the Iconography of Cain.” Pp. 23-34 in Essick and Pearce, 
<hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, q. v.</p>
          <p>Taylor, Anya. <hi rend="i">Magic and English Romanticism.</hi> Athens: University of Georgia
Press, 1979. $16.00.</p>
          <p>Taylor, Irene. “Blake Meets Byron on April Fool’s.” <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi>,
16 (1978), 85-93. [Laughter, playful and serious, in William Blake’s writings.]</p>
          <p>Tidwell, Paul, and Norman Louis Morgan. “A Blake-Joyce Note.” <hi rend="i">A Wake Newsletter:
Studies in James Joyce’s Finnegan’s Wake</hi>, 13 (1976), 112-114.</p>
          <p>Traeger, Jörg. <hi rend="i">Philipp Otto Runge oder Die Geburt einer neuen Kunst.</hi> Munich:
Prestel, 1977. [The abridged version of the same author’s catalogue raisonné.]</p>
          <p>Trawick, Leonard M. “Blake’s Empirical Occult.” <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 8 (1977),
161-171.</p>
          <p>Trout, Henry R. “A Reading of Blake’s The Little Girl Lost and The Little Girl Found.” 
<hi rend="i">West Virginia University Bulletin: Philological Papers</hi>, 23 (1977), 37-46.</p>
          <p>Tsuchiya, Shigeko. <hi rend="i">Blake no sekai—genshika no yogensho</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">Blake’s World—On His Prophetic Books</hi>]. Tokyo: Kenkyusha, 1978. ¥980.</p>
          <p>Tsuchiya, Shigeko. “Blake no ‘chichi’ to ‘kami’” [“Blake’s ‘Father’ and
‘God’”]. <hi rend="i">Igirisu Romanha no Kenkyu</hi> [<hi rend="i">A Study of English Romanticism</hi>], 1
(1977).</p>
          <p>Tzougros, Penelope Stephanie. “Hopkins and Blake: A New Heaven and a New Earth.” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 39 (1979), 4290-A. Diss., University of Toronto (Canada),
1977.</p>
          <p>Umetsu, Narumi. <hi rend="i">Blake kenkyu</hi> [<hi rend="i">A Study of William Blake</hi>]<hi
rend="i">: Songs of Innocence and of Experience.</hi> Tokyo: Yashio-shuppansha, 1977. ¥3,500.</p>
          <p>Valdes, Mario J. “The Aesthetic Relationship of William Blake and Miguel de Unamuno.” Pp. 809-811
in Michel Cadot, Milan V. Dimic, David Malone, and <corr type="emend">Mikos Szabolcsi,</corr> eds., <hi rend="i">Actes de VIe Congrès
de l’Association Internationale de Littérature Comparée/Proceedings of the 6th Congress of the
International Comparative Literature Association.</hi> Stuttgart: Bieber, 1975.</p>
          <p>Vasil’eva, T. N. “Blejk i Šekspir” [Blake and Shakespeare]. Pp. 403-408 in E. A. Smirnova,
ed., <hi rend="i">Sravnitel’nce izučenie literatur: Sbornik statej k 80-letiju akademika M. P.
Alekseeva.</hi> Leningrad: Nanka, 1976.</p>
          <p>Vaughan, William. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> London: Thames and Hudson, and New York: St.
Martin’s Press, 1977. $5.95.</p>
          <p>Vaughan, William. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Paris: Chêne, 1978. [The French edition of
the preceding entry.]</p>
          <p>*Volkmann, Ludwig. <hi rend="i">Iconografia Dantesca: Die bildlichen Darstellungen zur
göttlichen Komödie.</hi> Leipzig: Breitkopf &amp; Härtel, 1897, pp. 95-99 and passim. [Probably the first
German reference to Blake’s Dante illustrations (pl. 13), written under the influence of Yeats’ essay of
1896; the discussion of Flaxman’s series, however, is more extensive and also contains a valuable
chalcographical checklist.]</p>
          <p>Walker, Corlette R. “Blake in the Galleries.” <hi rend="i">Soundings: Collections of the
University Library</hi>, University of California, Santa Barbara, 8 (1976), 28-30.</p>
          <p>Waller, Jennifer R. “Maurice Sendak and the Blakean Vision of Childhood.” 
<hi rend="i">Children’s Literature: Annual of the Modern Language Association Seminar on Children’s Literature
and the Children’s Literature Association</hi>, 6 (1977), 130-140.</p>
          <p>Wardle, Judith. “‘For Hatching ripe’: Blake and the Educational Uses of Emblem and
Illustrated Literature.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi>, 81 (1978), 324-348.</p>
          <p>Warner, Nicholas Oliver. “Blake’s Iconic Mode: Tradition and Transformation in the Works of
William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 39 (1978), 877-A. Diss., University of
California, Berkeley, 1977.</p>
          <p>Warren, Leland E. “Poetic Vision and the Natural World: The Spider and His Web in the Poetry of
William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Enlightenment Essays</hi>, 6 (1975), 50-62.</p>
          <p>Weinglass, D. H. “The Painter’s Muse: Henry Fuseli and Maria Riddell.” <hi rend="i">Gazette des
Beaux-Arts</hi>, 6th ser., 92 (1978), 75-83. [In this volume, the pagination of the <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi>
starts anew in the July issue; this article is to be found in the issue for
<pb id="p13-98" n="98"/>
September 1978.]</p>
          <p>Weinsheimer, Joel. “[Reynolds’] Mrs. Siddons, The Tragic Muse, and the Problem of ‘As’.”
<hi rend="i">Journal of Aesthetics and Art Criticism</hi>, 36 (1978), 317-328.</p>
          <p>Weissman, Judith. “A Note on the Pleasant Bank by Moonlight in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
Heaven and Hell.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>, n. s. 24 (1977), 321-322.</p>
          <p>Welch, Dennis M. “Center, Circumference, and Vegetation Symbolism in the Writings of William
Blake.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Philology</hi>, 75 (1978), 223-242.</p>
          <p>Welch, Dennis M. “In the Throes of Eros: Blake’s Early Career.” <hi rend="i">Mosaic</hi>, 11
(1978), 101-113.</p>
          <p>Whitehead, Fred. “William Blake and Radical Tradition.” Pp. 191-214 in Norman Rudich, ed., 
<hi rend="i">Weapons of Criticism: Marxism in America and the Literary Tradition.</hi> Palo Alto: Ramparts Press,
1976.</p>
          <p>Wieland-Burston, Joanne Barbara. “Blake in France: The Poet and the Painter as Seen by French
Critics in the Nineteenth and Twentieth Centuries.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 39
(1978), 914-A. Diss., Vanderbilt University, 1977.</p>
          <p>Wilkie, Brian, and Mary Lynn Johnson. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Four Zoas: The Design of a
Dream.</hi> Cambridge, Mass. and London: Harvard University Press, 1978. $15.00.</p>
          <p>Wilkie, Brian. <hi rend="i">See also</hi> Johnson, Mary Lynn.</p>
          <p>*Wimsatt, W. K. “Imitation as Freedom—1717-1798.” <hi rend="i">New Literary History</hi>, 1
(1970), 215-236.</p>
          <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr. “Painted Prophecies: The Tradition of Blake’s Illuminated
Books.” Pp. 101-115 in Essick and Pearce, <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, q. v.</p>
          <p>Woodman, Ross. “The Death and Resurrection of Milton According to the Gospel of Blake.” 
<hi rend="i">English Studies in Canada</hi> (Toronto), 3 (1977), 416-432.</p>
          <p>Yamamoto, Toshiki. “Bunyan to Blake” [“Bunyan and Blake”]. <hi rend="i">Seikei Daigaku Ippan
Kenkyu Hokoku</hi> [<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Seikei University</hi>], 13 (1977), 67-84.</p>
          <p>Yasuda, Masayoshi. “Blake to Johnson shiron” [“Some Comparative Notes on Blake and Johnson”]. 
<hi rend="i">Bungaku gogaku ronshu, Ueki Ren nosuke kyoju taishoku kinen, Kwansai gakuin daigaku keizai
gakubu</hi> [<hi rend="i">Essays in Language and Literatures, In Commemoration of Prof. Rennosuke Ueki, The
Faculty of Economics of Kwansai Gakuin University</hi>], April, 1977, pp. 21-36.</p>
          <p>Yura, Kimiyoshi. “Blake—totaru na kagekisei” [“Blake—A Total Extremeness”]. 
<hi rend="i">Bungaku</hi> [<hi rend="i">Literature</hi>], 45, 10 (1977), 114-120. <hi rend="i">Romanshugi: On
Romanticism.</hi></p>
          <p>Yura, Kimiyoshi. “Blake to warabeuta” [“Blake and A Children’s Song”]. <hi rend="i">Gakuto</hi>
[<hi rend="i">Lamplight of Learning</hi>], 11 (1976), 18-21.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">IV. REVIEWS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi> Reviewed by Ronald Paulson, <hi rend="i">The
Georgia Review</hi>, 32 (1978), 435-443; by Andrew Lincoln, <hi rend="i">The Review of English Studies</hi>,
29 (1978), 347-349; by Joseph A. Wittreich, Jr., <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 9 (1978), 290-292; and
by Adrian Eeles, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [<hi rend="i">London</hi>] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>,
27 January 1978, p. 100.</p>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Critical Heritage.</hi> Reviewed by Graham
Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 105 (1977), 147.</p>
          <p>Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist.</hi> Reviewed by Geoffrey L. Keynes, 
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 120 (1978), 544-547; by Ronald Paulson, <hi rend="i">The Georgia
Review</hi>, 32 (1978), 435-443; by Jean H. Hagstrum, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12
(1978), 64-67; by Zachary Leader, <hi rend="i">Essays in Criticism</hi>, 29 (1979), 81-88; by S. Hoyal, 
<hi rend="i">Connoisseur</hi>, 198 (1978), 174; by K. Garlick, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, n. s. 107 (1978),
439-440; by Edward Larrissy, <hi rend="i">English</hi>, 27 (1978), 196-200; and by Tom Phillips, 
<hi rend="i">The</hi> [<hi rend="i">London</hi>] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 24 March 1978, pp.
349-350.</p>
          <p>Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">The Complete Graphic Works of William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by P.
Southcott, <hi rend="i">Art &amp; Artists</hi>, 13 (1978), 48; by Ronald Paulson, <hi rend="i">The Georgia
Review</hi>, 32 (1978), 435-443; and by Tom Phillips, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [<hi rend="i">London</hi>] 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 24 March 1978, pp. 349-350.</p>
          <p>Blake exhibition, Tate Gallery. Reviewed by Gwen Stone, <hi rend="i">Visual Dialog</hi>, 4
(1978), 16-17; by David Bindman, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 120 (1978), 418-419; and by Tom
Phillips, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [<hi rend="i">London</hi>] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 24
March 1978, pp. 349-350. See also reviews of the exhibition catalogue by Martin Butlin.</p>
          <p>Blondel, Jacques. <hi rend="i">Imaginaire et croyance.</hi> Reviewed by Heather Dubrow, 
<hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi>, 71, n. s. 40 (1978-1979), 133-134.</p>
          <p>Bloom, Harold. <hi rend="i">Poetry and Repression.</hi> Reviewed by Sharon Bassett, 
<hi rend="i">Literature and Psychology</hi>, 27 (1977), 106-112; by Khachig Tololyan, <hi rend="i">English
Language Notes</hi>, 15 (1978), 229-237; and by Robert Pinsky, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi>, 76 (1979),
300-303.</p>
          <p>Burke, Joseph. <hi rend="i">English Art 1717-1800.</hi> Reviewed by Edward J. Nygren, 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Burke and His Time</hi>, 19 (1978), 161-162.</p>
          <p>Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (exhib. cat.). Reviewed by David Bindman, 
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 120 (1978), 418-421; by Ronald Paulson, <hi rend="i">The Georgia
Review</hi>, 32 (1978), 435-443; by Ruth E. Fine, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12
(1978-1979), 42-55; by Karl-Heinz Bohrer, <hi rend="i">Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung</hi>, 16 May 1978; in
<hi rend="i">The Book Collector</hi>, 27 (1978), 159-168; by Edda Schmitt, <hi rend="i">Frankfurter Neue
Presse</hi>, 6 May 1978; by Gertrud Mander, <hi rend="i">Stuttgarter Zeitung</hi>, 4 April 1978; and by Tom
Phillips, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [<hi rend="i">London</hi>] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 24
March 1978, pp. 349-350.</p>
          <p>Clarke, Lester, and David Wickes. “The Story of Job” (television ballet of <hi rend="i">Job: A
Masque for Dancing</hi>). Reviewed by Everett C. Frost, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12
(1978), 155-158.</p>
          <p>Cooke, Michael G. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Will.</hi> Reviewed by Stuart Curran, 
<hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi>, 77 (1978), 287-289; and by Laurence Goldstein, 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 11 (1978), 284-287.</p>
          <p>Davis, Michael. <hi rend="i">William Blake: A New Kind of Man.</hi> Reviewed by Susan C. Fox, 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 11 (1978), 289-290; by Ronald Paulson, <hi rend="i">The Georgia
Review</hi>, 32 (1978), 435-443; and by Brian Wilkie, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic
Philology</hi>, 77 (1978), 144-146.</p>
          <p>Dolmetsch, Joan D. <hi rend="i">Rebellion and Reconciliation: Satirical Prints on the Revolution
at Williamsburg.</hi> Reviewed by Ronald Paulson, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 11 (1978),
291-297.</p>
          <p>Downey, James, and Ben Jones, eds. <hi rend="i">Fearful Joy: Papers from the Thomas Gray
Bicentenary Conference.</hi> Reviewed by C. J. Rawson, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi>, 76 (1978),
202-206.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David. V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake.</hi>
	<pb id="p13-99" n="99"/>
Reviewed by J. Duncan Macmillan, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 104 (1976), 142-143.</p>
          <p>Evans, Joan. <hi rend="i">A History of The Society of Antiquaries.</hi> Reviewed by David Worral,
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 11 (1978), 287-288.</p>
          <p>Fox, Susan. <hi rend="i">Poetic Form in Blake’s Milton.</hi> Reviewed by Stuart Curran, 
<hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi>, 16 (1978), 55-58.</p>
          <p>Franson, John Karl, ed. <hi rend="i">Milton Reconsidered: Essays in Honor of Arthur E.
Barker.</hi> Reviewed by Martin K. Nurmi, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978),
56-57.</p>
          <p>Frye, Northrop. <hi rend="i">The Secular Scripture</hi> [and] <hi rend="i">Spiritus Mundi.</hi>
Reviewed by Michael Fischer, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 11 (1978), 276-283.</p>
          <p>Howard, John. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Milton.</hi> Reviewed by Susan Fox, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth
Circle</hi>, 9 (1978), 293-296; and by Martin K. Nurmi, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12
(1978), 56-57.</p>
          <p>Irwin, David, and Francina Irwin. <hi rend="i">Scottish Painters at Home and Abroad
1700-1900.</hi> Reviewed by Lindsay Errington, <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi>, 59 (1977), 443-444.</p>
          <p>Kelly, Gary. <hi rend="i">The English Jacobin Novel 1780-1805.</hi> Reviewed by Ronald Paulson,
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 11 (1978), 291-297.</p>
          <p>Keynes, Sir Geoffrey L. <hi rend="i">Complete Portraiture of William and Catherine Blake.</hi>
Reviewed by Nicholas Barker, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [<hi rend="i">London</hi>] <hi rend="i">Times Literary
Supplement</hi>, 17 March 1978, p. 320; and by David Bindman, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 120
(1978), 418-421.</p>
          <p>Keynes, <hi rend="i">Sir</hi> Geoffrey L., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Marriage of Heaven
and Hell.</hi> Reviewed by Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 105 (1977), 147.</p>
          <p>Klonsky, Milton. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Seer and His Visions.</hi> Reviewed by K.
Garlick, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, n. s. 107 (1978), 439-440; and by Ronald Paulson, <hi rend="i">The Georgia
Review</hi>, 32 (1978), 435-443.</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">Infernal Methods.</hi> Reviewed by J. Duncan Macmillan, 
<hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 104 (1976), 143.</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond, ed. <hi rend="i">The Letters of Samuel Palmer.</hi> Reviewed by William L.
Pressly, Jr., <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi>, 58 (1976), 462-464; and by Andrew Wilton, <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978-1979), 150-154.</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer A Biography.</hi> Reviewed by Andrew Wilton, 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 150-154.</p>
          <p>Marqusee, Michael, introd. <hi rend="i">The Book of Job Illustrated by William Blake.</hi>
Reviewed by Jeffry Spencer, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 154.</p>
          <p>Mitchell, W. J. T. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art.</hi> Reviewed by Ronald Paulson, 
<hi rend="i">The Georgia Review</hi>, 32 (1978), 435-443.</p>
          <p>Namikawa, Ryo. <hi rend="i">William Blake—geijutsu to shiso</hi> [<hi rend="i">William
Blake—On His Art and Thought</hi>]. Reviewed by Narumi Umetsu, <hi rend="i">Shinkan shoka</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">The Review of New Books</hi>] <hi rend="i">Eigo Seinen</hi> [<hi rend="i">The Rising
Generation</hi>], 124, 6 (1978), 39.</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by Zachary Leader, <hi rend="i">Essays
in Criticism</hi>, 29 (1979), 81-88; by Ronald Paulson, <hi rend="i">The Georgia Review</hi>, 32 (1978),
435-443; in <hi rend="i">Neue Zürcher Zeitung</hi>, 30 August 1978, p. 33; in <hi rend="i">Neue Osnabrücker
Zeitung</hi>, 28 November 1978; in <hi rend="i">Fuldaer Zeitung</hi>, 4 December 1978; in <hi rend="i">Der
Bund</hi> (Switzerland), 23 December 1978; in <hi rend="i">Cuxhavener Nachrichten</hi>, 9 February 1979.
[Leader and Paulson Review the English edition; the short newspaper articles all deal with the German
edition.]</p>
          <p>Palmer exhibition, Victoria and Albert Museum. Reviewed by Christopher Neve, <hi rend="i">Country
Life</hi>, 25 January 1979, pp. 200-201.</p>
          <p>Paulson, Ronald. <hi rend="i">Emblem and Expression.</hi> Reviewed by Ruth Emery, 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Burke and His Time</hi>, 19 (1978), 84-88.</p>
          <p>Powell, Nicolas. <hi rend="i">Fuseli: The Nightmare.</hi> Reviewed by John F. Moffitt, 
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 118 (1976), 526-527.</p>
          <p>Sellars, James. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer.</hi> Reviewed by William L. Pressly, Jr., 
<hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi>, 58 (1976), 462-464.</p>
          <p>Tomalin, Claire. <hi rend="i">The Life and Death of Mary Wollstonecraft.</hi> Reviewed by Marcia
Tillotson, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 58-64.</p>
          <p>Traeger, Jörg. <hi rend="i">Philipp Otto Runge und sein Werk.</hi> Reviewed by Rudolf M. Bisanz,
<hi rend="i">Art Journal</hi>, 37 (1977-1978), 190-192.</p>
          <p>Wardel, Ralph M., ed. <hi rend="i">Godwin &amp; Mary: Letters of William Godwin and Mary
Wollstonecraft.</hi> Reviewed by Marcia Tillotson, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12
(1978), 58-64.</p>
          <p>Weiskel, Thomas. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Sublime.</hi> Reviewed by J. Robert Barth, 
<hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi>, 15 (1978), 219-222; and by E. D. Mackerness, <hi rend="i">Notes and
Queries</hi>, n. s., 25 (1978), 251-253.</p>
          <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr. <hi rend="i">Angel of Apocalypse.</hi> Reviewed by William F.
Halloran, <hi rend="i">SCN</hi>, Winter 1977, pp. 101-104.</p>
          <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr., ed. <hi rend="i">Milton and the Line of Vision.</hi> Reviewed by
Mary Ann Radzinowicz, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi>, 73 (1978), 404-405.</p>
          <p>Wollstonecraft, Mary. <hi rend="i">Mary, A Fiction, and The Wrongs of Woman</hi>, ed. Gary Kelly;
<hi rend="i">Letters Written during a Short Residence in Sweden, Norway, and Denmark</hi>, ed. Carol H.
Poston; <hi rend="i">A Vindication of the Rights of Woman</hi>, ed. Miriam Brody Kramnick. Reviewed by Marcia
Tillotson, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 58-64.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
