<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>13.4.sternbach</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Donald H. Reiman, Michael C. Jaye, and Betty T. Bennett, eds., 
The Evidence of the Imagination: Studies of Interactions between Life and Art in English Romantic Literature</title>
        <author n="Sternbach">Robert Sternbach</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1980</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">13.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Joe Zimmerman</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Betsy Bowden</name>
              <name>Wayne Glausser</name>
              <name>Robert Sternbach</name>
              <name>Leslie Tannenbaum</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_13">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-13-4-0007">
        <pb id="p13-203" n="203"/>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Donald H. Reiman, <corr type="emend">Michael C. Jaye, and Betty T. Bennett, eds.</corr> 
<hi rend="b">The Evidence of the Imagination: Studies of Interactions between Life and Art in English Romantic Literature.</hi> 
New York: New York University Press, 1978.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">Robert</hi> <name><hi rend="b">Sternbach</hi></name></docAuthor>.
          </byline>
          <p>The book’s title provides, properly, an avenue toward its contents. The “evidence” of the
imagination, of course, is the finished work of art, or, alternatively, a specific attitude toward experience
on the part of the writer that is expressed and given shape in his letters, notebooks, or diaries. “Evidence”
signifies the interaction between art and life, certifying that an imagination has existed and that it has
interacted with life.</p>
          <p>These sixteen various essays on Romantic writers, collected by Donald H. Reiman <hi rend="i">et
al.</hi>, fall roughly into two groups: those that draw extensively on biographical materials, such as
letters, literary anecdotes, or journals, to illustrate the transforming force of imagination on the raw
events of an author’s life, and those that use mainly that author’s published texts to establish a
specific theme or line of argument in his works. In both cases, as Donald Reiman makes clear in his
introduction, the objective has been primarily a scholarly one: the studies seek to clarify particular themes
and attitudes developed by the authors with which they are concerned, and to derive these themes and attitudes
from the context of the authors’ lives and times. But the studies do not seek primarily to evaluate or
comment on these themes or attitudes; this, as Professor Reiman says, would be a task for the general
critic.</p>
          <p>Notwithstanding this delimitation, I find that many of the essays, including some of my favorites
in the collection, have been written “from within the bosom of Romanticism.” I list some phrases that
illustrate the prevailing sympathy of the scholars with the subjects of their study: Eileen Sanzo’s
“stretched across the city’s own iron darkness”; Michael Jaye’s “the empathic bond between men under the
kindly auspices of nature”; and Carl Woodring’s “Richard Payne Knight . . . went <hi rend="i">far
beyond</hi> John Baillie’s point . . . that an encounter with the sublime expands the mind.” It should
probably be said that not all the Romantic attitudes discovered in the volume would win immediate assent from
all unindoctrinated readers, and I would have opted for a greater overall effort to maintain the distinction
between the specialist scholar and the general critic.</p>
          <p>The grouping takes in an extremely wide range of Romantic figures, from William Blake to Thomas
Love Peacock, including three studies of female writers—one on “Plin” Clairmont as revealed in her journals,
one on Mary Shelley, and one on Mary Wollstonecraft. This is a generous and helpful selection—and yet I must
complain that with six essays devoted to Wordsworth there are none on Coleridge!</p>
          <p>Five outstanding essays in the volume are those by Michael C. Jaye (“William Wordsworth’s
Alfoxden Notebook: 1798”), Irene Tayler (“By Peculiar Grace: Wordsworth in 1802”), Donald H. Reiman (“Poetry
of Familiarity: Wordsworth, Dorothy, and Mary Hutchinson”), Aileen Ward (“That Last Infirmity of Noble Mind:
Keats and the Idea of Fame”), and William Walling (“‘On Fishing Up the Moon’: In
<pb id="p13-204" n="204"/>
Search of Thomas Love Peacock”). Jaye’s essay discusses Wordsworth’s Alfoxden Notebook as evidence of a
fundamental advance in his poetic practice in 1798 in several areas. Especially useful and suggestive are his
remarks on Wordsworth’s establishment of a linguistic usage capable of conveying the distinct mode of
self-apprehension which is Wordsworth’s subject in <hi rend="i">The Prelude.</hi> Also subtle and
intelligent are his analyses of passages in the Notebook which reveal Wordsworth’s initial explorations of
transcendental experience in his poetry, and various modes of interaction between the self and nature. At
times, however, his language becomes a bit too abstract and ambiguous, such as in the sentence: “Experiential
clarity depends on prolonging the temporal experience, perceiving its inclusivity through diffusion and
radiating pervasiveness.”</p>
          <p>Irene Tayler finely recreates Wordsworth’s circumstances in 1802 in order to show how he
produced several monitory figures in his poetry to guide and sustain him during that year of stress. The
conjunction of the Leechgatherer, the Pedlar, and Wordsworth’s brother John as “silent poets” is very good,
especially since it is often overlooked that these figures are all idealized versions of the poet, and not
really Wordsworth as he was in himself.</p>
          <p>Donald Reiman’s thesis in “Poetry of Familiarity” is a bold one. He asserts not only that
Wordsworth’s art was made out of his psycho-sexual conflicts, but that Wordsworth’s poetic decline was the
direct result of the resolution of those conflicts. The interaction between Wordsworth’s personal life and
the specific quality of his art is very complex, however, perhaps more complex than will ever be sorted out
entirely satisfactorily; so that while on the one hand Reiman is surely right in proclaiming a connection
between Wordsworth’s relationships and his art, on the other hand he runs the risk of being reductive in
this essay. Nevertheless, he identifies a fascinating sequence in discussing the different nature of
Wordsworth’s feelings for Dorothy and then Mary, and finally in turning to the effect on Wordsworth’s
marriage of the deaths of his young son and daughter.</p>
          <p>In Aileen Ward’s lucid essay, the “evidence of the imagination” resides not so much in works of
art as in the transformations which Keats’s attitude underwent toward art and his own role as an artist.
Interesting for a theory of Romanticism is the final transformation which Miss Ward suggests, occurring toward
the end of Keats’s life: Keats’s “Public” became in his mind an idealized notion of the “People” who would
be influenced by his works in future generations.</p>
          <p>William Walling’s interesting and stimulating discussion of Peacock is a departure for this
group of essays in that it attempts a more general assessment of its subject, perhaps because Peacock has been
less extensively interpreted elsewhere. Walling defines the comic element in Peacock as a paradoxical
harmoniousness achieved by the fragmented, jarring subjectivities which are 
<corr type="emend">displayed</corr> in his novels. Peacock’s work, according to Walling, can be seen as a
criticism both of the excesses of Romantic subjectivity and of the idea that moral progress was embodied in
the laissez-faire economic system of the nineteenth century.</p>
          <p>Among the other essays in the volume, David Erdman’s interesting study raises large questions
about Wordsworth’s practical response to the French Revolution, ultimately about the extent to which he
would have been willing to use force to achieve any revolutionary purpose. Carl Woodring points out that the
Romantic emphasis on the mind’s role in perceiving the sublime underlies Wordsworth’s description of the
phenomenon in “Tintern Abbey.” Interestingly, Woodring suggests that the Romantic sublime has something to do
with the “terror of the divided self,” but doesn’t expand on the phrase in his study. Paul Magnuson valuably
clarifies the term “spontaneity” in Wordsworth’s poetic theory, linking it through the idea of voluntary
excitement to the self-sufficiency or self-generating quality of the imagination. Joyce Hemlow demonstrates
the modification of fact in Lamb’s attempt to create a unity of feeling in his essay “The Wedding.” Marcelle
Thiebaux’s compendium of citations enables us to gauge the response to Mary Wollstonecraft’s writings in
America, though most of the cited criticisms of Wollstonecraft’s work are tangential or superficial. G. M.
Matthews’ essay on Shelley is filled with rich biographical detail which makes his interpretations of three
fragments entertaining as well as persuasive. John J. Lavelle demonstrates Shelley’s admiration for
Pythagorean teachings which proclaimed the semi-divinity of a certain order of men who sought to embody their
superior knowledge of virtue and truth in “lasting Monuments.” Leslie Marchand documents the relation between
Byron and Francis Hodgson. Betty Bennett shows the consistency of Mary Shelley’s novels with the beliefs of
P. B. Shelley, William Godwin, and Mary Wollstonecraft. Margaret Kingston Stocking provides interesting
information about an unconventional lady, Pauline (“Plin”) Clairmont, niece of Claire.</p>
          <p>The only essay in the volume devoted to Blake, by Eileen Sanzo, explores the alchemical metaphor
in Blake’s belief that the imagination must turn the iron (industrial) age to one of gold, though I miss the
specifics of Blake’s vision in the essay—how is the Golden Age to come about? Nevertheless, though Miss
Sanzo—or Blake—fails to name the alchemical formula by which the iron age of oppression may lead towards
social justice and the millenium, her essay—like the others in this volume—testifies to the power of the
imagination to encounter reality, and to give evidence of its encounters in fructifying, seminal works of
art.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
