<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>13.4.bowden</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The Artistic and Interpretive Context of Blake’s “Canterbury
          Pilgrims”</title>
        <author n="Bowden">Betsy Bowden</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1980</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">13.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Joe Zimmerman</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Betsy Bowden</name>
              <name>Wayne Glausser</name>
              <name>Robert Sternbach</name>
              <name>Leslie Tannenbaum</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_13">
    <body>
      <pb id="p13-164" n="164"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-13-4-0005">
        <figure n="ChaucerRiding.13.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="549"></figure>
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">THE ARTISTIC AND INTERPRETIVE CONTEXT OF BLAKE’S “CANTERBURY PILGRIMS”</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">BETSY</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">BOWDEN</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>In the past decade, three critics have discussed the painting itself of “Chaucers
          Canterbury Pilgrims,” along with Blake’s commentary on it in the <hi rend="i">Descriptive
            Catalogue</hi> to his 1809 Exhibition.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1"
type="note">1</ref> But Blake,
          though timeless as ever, was working not in a vacuum but in a historical context of
          commentary on and illustrations to Chaucer’s <hi rend="i">Canterbury Tales.</hi><note
            id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> The critics, cited hereafter by authors’ names, are Karl
            Kiralis, “William Blake as an Intellectual and Spiritual Guide to Chaucer’s 
              <hi rend="i">Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 1 (Spring 1969),
139-90;
            Warren Stevenson, “Interpreting Blake’s <hi rend="i">Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>,” 
              <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi>, 13 (June 1977), 115-26; and Orphia Jane Allen,
            “Blake’s Archetypal Criticism: <hi rend="i">The Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>,” 
              <hi rend="i">Genre</hi>, 2 (Summer 1978), 173-89.</note></p>
        <p>A look at the artistic tradition Blake could have known will show that he fit the
          Canterbury pilgrims into his own cosmology with only slight changes from earlier artists’
          representations. Although he tells in words the Blakean meanings of many of the pilgrims,
          he portrays only two of them as unmistakable symbols or types: he renders the Wife of Bath
          as Whore of Babylon; and he shows the Parson as the Good Old Man, like the one dying in
          his illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi> Otherwise, to picture the
          pilgrims as “physiognomies or lineaments of universal human life,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
            type="note">2</ref> Blake principally does what artists before him had done: he goes
          straight to Chaucer’s poem. <note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i"> The Poetry and
              Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman (Garden City: Doubleday, 1965), pp.
            523-24. Page references for Blake quotations are to this edition, abbreviated
            “E.”</note></p>
        <p>Because Chaucer’s General Prologue pictures the pilgrims so minutely, artist-to-artist
          influences are hard to pin down. The Merchant sports a tall hat and forked beard in the
          fifteenth-century Ellesmere manuscript, in the woodcut of Thynne’s 1532 edition, in the
          engraving of Urry’s 1721 edition, in Blake’s painting. Blake must have seen one of these
          prototypes? No—“A Marchant was ther with a forked berd / . . . And on his hed a Flaundrish
          bever hat.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> And neither can
Blake’s portrait of
          Chaucer indicate a source, despite its similarity to earlier portraits. Chaucer’s image
          had been passed on as if through a four-century Xerox machine, thanks mostly to a life
          portrait in the margin of his pupil Thomas Hoccleve’s <hi rend="i">De Regimine
            Principum</hi>, now Harl. MS 4866. Blake could have examined this manuscript itself in
          the British Museum at Montagu House, or worked from one of the scores of paintings and
          engravings that evolved from it. <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Geoffrey Chaucer, 
              <hi rend="i">Canterbury Tales</hi>, ed. Thomas Tyrwhitt, 2nd ed. (Oxford: Clarendon Press,
            1798), vv. 272, 274. References for Chaucer quotations are to this, the most accurate
            edition of Blake’s time. Poetry references are line numbers, continuous through the two
            volumes; prose references include volume and page.</note></p>
        <p>Clearly, however, Blake goes beyond any of his sources. He portrays the pilgrims all
          together on horseback, as no one before him had; and he positions them to show particular
          relationships in his own Blakean cosmos. Even a glance at his picture (illus. 1) suggests
          Blake’s interest in binary symmetry and the pairing of characters.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
            type="note">4</ref> For example, the Parson and Pardoner stand in defiant contrast, face
          to face, like Good and Evil, with the cruciform Host midway between. The Wife of Bath and
          Prioress also form a symmetrical pair, though not such a direct contrast, as they ride
          midway in back and front halves of the procession. Blake also pairs the Knight and Squire
          who head the procession and the Poet and Philosopher who end it. The picture is balanced
          artistically, both in structure and in details. And the <hi rend="i">Descriptive
            Catalogue</hi> suggests how such visual symmetry often indicates Blake’s spiritual
          interpretation of each pilgrim. But, how often? Can a boundary be drawn between Blake’s
          visual unity as an artist and his symbolic unity as a poet-philosopher? 
              <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> I am discussing not the painting itself, but the engraving
Blake made
            from it in 1810—precisely, the fourth state of that engraving, as displayed in and
            reproduced by the Huntington Library. The painting itself hangs in Pollock House,
            Glasgow, and differs in details—facial expressions, most noticeably—from the later
            engraving. Reproductions of this painting should not be trusted indiscriminately,
            especially as to color. For some account of the states of the engraving, see Kiralis’
            Appendix B, pp. 174-77.</note></p>
        <pb id="p13-165" n="165"/>
        <p>To interpret Blake’s interpretation, I will look at precisely how he has changed each
          pilgrim away from artistic tradition and, in several cases, away from the details of
          Chaucer’s poem. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> commentary, too, differs
          in small but significant ways from previous Chaucer criticism. His does seem to share one
          problem with the other, though: a continual use of vague, abstract terms like “grand” and
          “first rate” and “powerful,” non-descriptive non-individualized words applied to general
          classes of mankind by the man who said, “To Generalize is to be an Idiot.” Blake, I will
          suggest, is purposely teasing the reader with the inaccuracy and ambiguity inherent in
          such abstract language, and thus forcing his audience to look instead at the picture.</p>
        <p>To analyze the picture, to generalize will sometimes be necessary. I will discuss in
          general earlier literary interpretations of <hi rend="i">Canterbury Tales</hi>, and in
          general the group portraits of Canterbury pilgrims which Blake could have seen in London
          or Felpham before 1809. Then I will discuss in particular each figure in Blake’s
          procession and its relationship to Blake’s text, to Chaucer’s poem, to earlier artists’
          portrayals of that character, and to other figures in the procession. (I will mention only
          in passing the picture’s background—the rising sun, Gothic arches, and so on—so as to keep
          bounds on this article.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> And
I will suggest, also, how
          Blake uses the binary symmetry of the picture to convey a spiritual meaning like that he
          illuminates elsewhere. In “Canterbury Pilgrims,” the types of mankind do not stand in
          static one-to-one binary relationships. Within the frozen time and space of this picture,
          a constant cell-like bisection and re-bisection of types goes on, such that a given figure
          may be the spectre of one character, the complementary completing half of another, and the
          contrary of a third. <note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Kiralis, throughout his cited
            article, discusses fairly thoroughly the background of the picture.</note></p>
        <p>No literary critic before Blake had seen the pilgrims in complicated binary
          relationships. But what at first seems very Blakean about his <hi rend="i">Descriptive
            Catalogue</hi> commentary—that the pilgrims represent eternal types that exist in all
          ages—was a standard interpretation in the eighteenth century. The earliest and most
          eloquent expression came from John Dryden. Blake says: 
		<q> Of Chaucer’s characters, as
            described in his Canterbury Tales, some of the names or titles are altered by time, but
            the characters themselves for ever remain unaltered, and consequently they are the
            physiognomies or lineaments of universal human life, beyond which Nature never steps.
            Names alter, things never alter. I have known multitudes of those who would have been
            monks in the age of monkery, who in this deistical age are deists. As Newton numbered
            the stars, and as Linneus numbered the plants, so Chaucer numbered the classes of men.
            (E 523-24) </q>
A century earlier, in the preface to his <hi rend="i">Fable Ancient and
            Modern</hi> (London: J. Tonson, 1700), Dryden says, 
			<q><hi rend="i">Chaucer</hi>
            follow’d Nature every where; but was never so bold to go beyond her. . . . he has taken
            into the Compass of his <hi rend="i">Canterbury Tales</hi> the various Manners and
            Humours (as we now call them) of the whole <hi rend="i">English</hi> Nation, in his Age.
            Not a single Character has escap’d him. All his Pilgrims are severally distinguish’d
            from each other; and not only in their Inclinations, but in their very Phisiognomies and
            Persons. . . . Some of his Persons are Vicious, and some Vertuous; some are unlearn’d,
            or (as <hi rend="i">Chaucer</hi> calls them) Lewd, and some are Learn’d. Even the
            Ribaldry of the Low Characters is different: The <hi rend="i">Reeve</hi>, the 
              <hi rend="i">Miller</hi>, and the <hi rend="i">Cook</hi>, are several Men, and
            distinguish’d from each other, as much as the mincing Lady Prioress, and the
            broad-speaking gap-tooth’d Wife of <hi rend="i">Bathe.</hi> . . . We have our
            Fore-fathers and Great Grand-dames all before us, as they were in 
              <hi rend="i">Chaucer</hi>’s Days; their general Characters are still remaining in Mankind, and
            even in <hi rend="i">England</hi>, though they are call’d by other Names than those of
              <hi rend="i">Moncks</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Fryars</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Chanons</hi>,
            and <hi rend="i">Lady Abbesses</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Nuns</hi>: For Mankind is ever the
            same, and nothing lost out of Nature, though every thing is alter’d. </q>
Dryden’s essay
          would have suggested to Blake not only the constancy of the types of mankind but also
          several binary contrasts among Chaucer’s pilgrims: vice and virtue, lewd and learned, Wife
          of Bath and Prioress.</p>
        <p>Other eighteenth-century commentators also saw the Canterbury pilgrims as enduring types
          of mankind. As a sampling, George Ogle in 1739 paraphrases Dryden at great length,
          suggesting 
		<q> an Examination of the various Tempers and Manners of Mankind, as We find
            them more expressly delineated in the ampler Designs of the Tales these Persons are made
            to relate. . . . I shall venture . . . to rank our <hi rend="i">Chaucer</hi> with . . .
            the best Drawers of Characters.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n6"><hi
                rend="s">6</hi> “A Letter to a Friend,” <hi rend="i">Gualtherus and Griselda</hi>
              (London: R. Dodsley, 1739), pp. viii-ix. This letter as reprinted two years later was
              definitely available to Blake, as described in n. 29.</note></q>
Sir John Hawkins in
          1776 says that Chaucer 
<pb id="p13-166-167" n="166-167"/>
<figure n="ESXVI.1.4BB.SP" rend="file" width="958" height="349">
            <head>“Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims,” engraved by William Blake in 1810.</head>
            <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the Huntington Library, San Marino, Ca. Actual
              size, 37-1/2″ × 12″.</figDesc>
          </figure>
<pb id="p13-168" n="168"/>
<figure n="pilgrimagefrontispiece.13.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="659">
            <head>“Pilgrimage to Canterbury,” drawn by Thomas Stothard and engraved by Delattre,
              frontispiece to vol. 14 of John Bell’s edition of <hi rend="i">British Poets</hi>
              (Edinburgh, 1782-83).</head>
            <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of Robert N. Essick. Actual size, 2-5/8″ ×
              4-1/4″.</figDesc>
          </figure>
<pb id="p13-169" n="169"/>
<figure n="poetsofgbritainfrontispiece.13.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="660">
            <head>“Sampson yhad experience,” drawn by Thomas Stothard and engraved by William Blake,
              frontispiece to vol. 13 of John Bell’s edition of <hi rend="i">British Poets</hi>
              (Edinburgh, 1782-83).</head>
            <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of Robert N. Essick. Actual size, 2-1/2″ ×
              4″.</figDesc>
          </figure>
<pb id="p13-170" n="170"/>
	<q> has feigned an assemblage of persons of different
            ranks, the most various and artful that can be imagined, and with an amazing propriety
            has made each of them the type of a peculiar 
            character.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi><hi rend="i"> A General History of the
                science and practice of Music</hi> (London, 1776), II, 101. Quoted by Caroline F. E.
              Spurgeon in her <hi rend="i">Five Hundred Years of Chaucer Criticism and Allusion,
                1357-1900</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge U. Press, 1925), I, 446-47; cited hereafter by
              author’s name.</note></q>
            In 1789, Philip Neve says of the General Prologue, 
        	<q> Nor
            is it wonderful that a mind, possessing much native humour, and enriched by long
            experience and extensive information, should exhibit characters such as are there to be
            found, with striking resemblance to nature and living manners.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
              type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi><hi rend="i"> Cursory Remarks on
                some of the Ancient English Poets</hi> (London, 1789), pp. 2-3; quoted by Spurgeon,
              I, 488.</note></q></p>
        <p>Blake further declares that “Visions of these eternal principles or characters of human
          life appear to poets, in all ages” (E 527). Neither Dryden nor these minor writers
          specifically suggests, as does Blake, that “nature and living manners” extend backward as
          well as forward in time. In the eighteenth century, only Blake compares Chaucer’s
          characters to Antique Statues and Grecian gods and the Cherubim of Phoenicia (E 527). But
          Blake’s twist is not dramatically original. Chaucer himself, like many medieval writers,
          thought in terms of typology—of classical parallels to Christian ideas, of Old Testament
          parallels to New Testament scenes, of symbolic similarities that transcend historical
          rationality. For instance, Chaucer calls the Franklin “Epicures owen sone” (v. 338), and
          adds “Seint Julian he was in his contree” (v. 342). To associations generated by mention
          of the supposedly luxury-loving pagan philosopher and of the patron saint of hospitality.
          Blake adds that the Franklin is “the genius of eating and drinking, the Bacchus” (E
          527).</p>
        <p>In his <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> pages, then, Blake combines Dryden’s
          precedent with the common medieval literary technique of regarding one character or
          incident as the type of another. To these ideas Blake adds his own style of moralizing,
          particularly familiar from <hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi> and from plate 11 of
            <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>: “Thus men forgot that All deities
          reside in the human breast” (E 37). Blake vehemently believes that the pilgrims represent
          “eternal attributes, or divine names, which . . . ought to be the servants, and not the
          masters of man, or of society” (E 527). These moralizing passages tell what Blake and
          Chaucer did not do. Another negative tangent takes up the last third of the commentary (E
          529-31), as Blake venomously sets out to “shew the stupidity of this class of men” (E
          529)—of Cromek and Stothard, mostly, who stole his idea for the painting. Blake attacks
          them to again exclaim what he and Chaucer did not do.</p>
        <p>Blake’s anger at Robert Cromek and Thomas Stothard seems justified, historically. Blake
          was the first artist to conceive of painting the pilgrims all together on horseback, and
          Blake showed Cromek the sketch of his idea, and Stothard’s painting of the pilgrimage was
          first to be finished.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> That
painting cannot be
          considered a prototype for Blake’s, either chronologically or emotionally. But an earlier
          picture of Stothard’s, from the days of the two men’s friendship, does have its place in
          the tradition of Chaucerian illustration that Blake could have known. 
              <note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> For accounts of the incident, see Mona Wilson, 
<hi rend="i">The Life
              of William Blake</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes, 3rd ed. (Oxford: Oxford U. Press, 1971),
            pp. 232-41; and Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, 2nd ed.
            (London: Macmillan, 1880), I, 250-55.</note></p>
        <p>In 1782-83, Edinburgh printer John Bell put out 109 pocket-sized volumes of 
            <hi rend="i">British Poets</hi>, including fourteen volumes of Chaucer. An engraved portrait of
          Chaucer prefaces the first volume; each of the first thirteen volumes features as
          frontispiece a scene from a Tale or a poem; the fourteenth frontispiece shows the
          “Pilgrimage to Canterbury,” in which the Wife of Bath, Monk, Friar, and Squire ride
          straight toward the observer (illus. 2). Thomas Stothard designed all these frontispieces,
          and the young Blake engraved the thirteenth one, “Sampson yhad experience” (illus. 3).<ref
            target="n10" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> See G. E. Bentley,
            Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Oxford U. Press, 1977), p. 539, cited
            hereafter by author’s name. “Sampson had experience” was re-engraved by Cooke in 1787;
            in later editions of Bell, Blake’s plate was replaced by Cooke’s.</note></p>
        <p>In Stothard’s “Pilgrimage to Canterbury” (illus. 2), which Blake must have seen, the Wife
          flirts blatantly with all three men. Stothard toned down his conception of the Wife during
          the next quarter century, for in his painting she flirts only with the two clergymen, and
          keeps her hands to herself. Blake, in contrast, ignores Chaucer’s hints at such a
            grouping.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> His Wife/Whore
of Bath/Babylon lifts her
          chalice, laughs, and spreads her legs toward the observer of the picture, with a sideways
          glance toward the back of the Parson, the one man she cannot seduce. 
              <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> For example, the Wife’s dialogue with the Friar, vv.
          6411-38.</note></p>
        <p>Stothard’s conceptions of these four characters—a particular detail being the Wife’s
          pointed hat—seem derived from the engravings in Urry’s 1721 edition of Chaucer. Before
          discussing that key edition in the artistic tradition, let me describe the other instances
          of group pictures of Canterbury pilgrims: in Royal MS 18 D 2, in Caxton’s
          fifteenth-century Chaucer edition, and in a drawing by J. H. Mortimer. There is no
          certainty, as there is for Bell’s and Urry’s editions, that Blake saw these three works.
          The first two are not important because the pilgrims in them are not individualized; but
          the Mortimer drawing, if Blake saw it, might well have influenced his conception.</p>
        <p>In a fifteenth-century manuscript of John Lydgate’s <hi rend="i">Siege of Thebes</hi>, a
          sequel to his master Chaucer’s work wherein Lydgate tells a tale on the return trip from
          Canterbury, a half-page illustration shows Lydgate and five other pilgrims.<ref
            target="n12" type="note">12</ref> The riders talk and gesture; one smacks his horse as
          it reaches for a mouthful of grass. The walls, cathedral, and hills of Canterbury fill the
          background. <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Reproduced in Richard Garnett and Edmund
            Gosse, <hi rend="i">English Literature: An Illustrated Record</hi> (New York: Macmillan,
            1923). This useful book reproduces several other pictures I will refer to, such as the
            manuscript portraits of Chaucer.</note></p>
        <p>Could Blake have examined this Lydgate manuscript, had he wished to do research outside
          his imagination before painting the pilgrimage? Yes. As Royal MS 18 D 2, it came to the
          British Museum 
<pb id="p13-171" n="171"/>
<figure n="departureofpilgrimes.13.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="546">
            <head>“Departure of the Canterbury Pilgrimes,” drawn by J. H. Mortimer and engraved by
              J. Hogg, on p. 22 of <hi rend="i">Mortimer’s Works</hi>, by Thomas Palser (London,
              1816).</head>
            <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the Victoria and Albert Museum, London. Actual
              size, 7-¾″ × 10-¼″.</figDesc>
          </figure>
<pb id="p13-172" n="172"/>
in 1757, when George II handed over to the new
          institution the entire royal library. Stothard and Blake could have examined this and
          other manuscripts —including Harl. MS 4866, with Chaucer’s oft-copied life portrait, which
          had come as part of the original bequests by which the British Museum was founded.
          Authorized by Act of Parliament in 1753, the British Museum opened to the public on 15
          January 1759, at Montagu House, Bloomsbury. Until 1808, for most people, visiting the
          Museum meant applying several weeks in advance, returning to pick up a ticket for a
          certain time, and again returning to be ushered through in a group. Then the policy was
          changed to allow immediate admission to “any person of decent appearance.” But all along,
          artists had preferential treatment. In 1808, for example, the general public could tour
          the collections only four days a week; Fridays were reserved for artists.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13"
            type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> History from J. Mordaunt Crook,
              <hi rend="i">The British Museum</hi> (New York: Praeger, 1972), pp. 39-71; and from
            Henry C. Shelley, <hi rend="i">The British Museum: Its History and Treasures</hi>
            (Boston: L. C. Page, 1911), pp. 48-70.</note></p>
        <p>A later picture of the pilgrims shows them around a table, not on horseback. William
          Caxton produced the first printed edition of <hi rend="i">Canterbury Tales.</hi> His
          second edition, in 1483(?), includes twenty-four illustrations: twenty-three pilgrims,
          each beside his Tale, plus a group portrayal as frontispiece. “Several [woodcuts] are made
          to do duty twice over, a common custom with early printers. Thus the ‘poor parson’ and the
          ‘doctor of physick,’ the ‘sumnour’ and the ‘Franklin,’ are represented by the same cuts;
          while the large illustration depicting the pilgrims sitting at supper at a round table
          does duty in some later publications for the Assembly of the Gods.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
            type="note">14</ref> Caxton’s edition, never numerous, was rare by Blake’s time. Only
          one full copy survives today, at St. John’s College, Oxford.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> E. Gordon Duff, <hi rend="i">William
              Caxton</hi> (Chicago: The Caxton Club, 1905), p. 58.</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi><hi rend="i"> Ibid.</hi> The edition is available on film.</note></p>
        <p>Another group picture is Mortimer’s. Some time before his death in 1779, for a projected
          edition of the <hi rend="i">Tales</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16"
type="note">16</ref> J. H.
          Mortimer made eight drawings not of the pilgrims but of characters in the tales—January
          and May, the Three Gamblers and Time, and so on. The ninth in the series might well have
          inspired Blake, for its subject is “Departure of the Canterbury Pilgrimes” (illus. 4). On
          12 February 1787, J. R. Smith published the drawings, engraved by J. K. Sherwin, E.
          Williams, William Sharp, and Jacob Hogg.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">17</ref> They were
          reproduced in some but not all copies of Tyrwhitt’s 1798 edition of Chaucer, and then in
            <hi rend="i">Mortimer’s Works: A Collection of Fifty Historical Designs</hi> (London:
          Thos. Palser, 1816).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> F. J. Furnivall comments on this unknown edition in <hi rend="i">Notes
and
              Queries</hi>, 6th ser., 2 (1880), 325-26.</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi>
            Eleanor P. Hammond, <hi rend="i">Chaucer: A Bibliographical Manual</hi> (1908; rpt. New
            York: Peter Smith, 1933), p. 324, cited hereafter by author’s name. Hogg engraved the
            Departure scene. See also Spurgeon, I, 447.</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi>
            Plates from both these books are at the Victoria and Albert, along with the original
            drawings of four of the nine scenes, excluding the Departure. I have located neither
            book in the U. S.; Tyrwhitt’s 1798 edition is common here, but each library I have
            contacted owns a copy illustrated only by a frontispiece portrait of the editor.
            According to Henry G. Bohn, ed., <hi rend="i">The Bibliographer’s Manual</hi>, by
            William Lowndes (London: George Bell and Sons, 1890), I, 427, the Mortimer plates were
            in copies sold at Roxburghe auction (catalogue no. 3253), at White Knight’s (no. 954),
            and at Edward’s (no. 125).</note></p>
        <p>Although Mortimer’s “Departure” portrays only seven pilgrims in the courtyard of the inn,
          rather than all of them on the road, his conception shares several attributes with
          Blake’s. Mortimer’s Prioress and Wife of Bath are focal points in the picture: at the
          left, the Prioress has just been helped to mount by a fat Squire; toward the right, the
          Wife has just mounted with the aid of the Friar or Monk. This Wife resembles a witch, an
          old hag, like the one in the Tale she tells—her nose and chin are pointed like her hat, as
          she smiles into sunken cheeks. Between the two women, also, are two mounted pilgrims—the
          full-bearded Miller, smiling and fingering his bagpipe, and the Merchant with forked
          beard. To the right of the Wife rides the Knight, dressed with an Elizabethan
          elaborateness that belies Chaucer’s description of him, in a wide-brimmed plumed hat,
          ruff, cape, medallion, puffed sleeves, codpiece, rosette at his knee, gloves, boots,
          spurs.</p>
        <p>Blake perhaps saw Mortimer’s overdressed Knight, his pairing of the two principal women,
          his grouping of Wife with Miller and Merchant—perhaps, but not certainly. Only one group
          picture preceding Blake’s was definitely available to him, that in Urry’s 1721 edition of
          Chaucer. To portray Chaucer among the “Heads of the Poets” for Hayley’s library at
          Felpham, Blake “could have used the plate Vertue engraved for Urry’s edition of Chaucer’s
          works (1721) which appears in the sale catalogue of Hayley’s library. . . . Blake must
          have consulted Urry’s edition of Chaucer, for the two subsidiary figures of the Merchant
          and Wife of Bath are faithful copies of the engraved headpieces on pages 66 and 76.”<ref
            target="n19" type="note">19</ref>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> [William Wells,]
              <hi rend="i">William Blake’s “Heads of the Poets”</hi> (Manchester: City of Manchester
            Art Gallery, 1969), pp. 18-19. An exhibition pamphlet.</note></p>
        <p>In this folio edition of Urry’s, a half-page engraving (illus. 5) before the General
          Prologue shows some of the pilgrims setting out from the Tabard Inn while others mount up
          in the courtyard. The houses of Southwark dominate the picture, each pilgrim standing
          perhaps half an inch high. But because a half-page medallion of each pilgrim precedes his
          Tale, most figures in the departure scene can be identified as exact miniatures. The
          Miller leads the procession, as in Stothard’s later painting—“A baggepipe wel coude he
          blowe and soune, / And therwithall he brought us out of toune” (vv. 567-68). Then follow
          the Squire, the robed Knight, the Squire’s Yeoman, the Parson, the Monk, the rail-thin
          Clerk, and probably the Nun’s Priest. Side by side then, set apart from the others, ride
          the Prioress and the Wife of Bath. Behind them, inexplicably but unmistakably, gallops Sir
          Thopas, his lance half-lowered to charge. The rest of the figures are too small to
          identify, even compared with the medallions.</p>
        <p>That charmingly absurd insertion of Sir Thopas among the pilgrims can symbolize the total
          <corr type="emend">irresponsibility</corr> with which John Urry put together this 1721 edition. He includes all
          spurious works ever attributed to Chaucer, and alters for the worse all real ones. Urry
          apparently had the editing task thrust upon him and went at it without enthusiasm, for he
          himself apologizes for the badness of the text: “Thou wilt, may be, not thank me for what
          I have done, and complain of me for having left so much undone. . . . if thou art not yet
          an Editor, I beg truce of thee till thou art one, before thou censurest my Endeavours.”
          This apology is quoted by Timothy Thomas, who helped finish the edition after Urry’s
          sudden death in 1714/15. Thomas specifies one major task left undone: Urry had set out to
          regularize Chaucer’s grammar and meter after an idiosyncratic scheme of his own, and had
          intended to bracket his frequent interpolations, but never did. Thomas says in this same
          Preface that Urry was “perswaded that <hi rend="i">Chaucer</hi> made [his verses] exact
          Metre, and therefore he proposed in this Edition to restore him (to use his own
          Expression) <hi rend="i">to his feet again.</hi>”</p>
        <p>“The strange licence, in which Mr. Urry appears to have indulged himself . . . has made
          the text of Chaucer in his Edition by far the worst that was 
<pb id="p13-173" n="173"/>
          ever published,” says Thomas Tyrwhitt, Chaucer’s next editor (I, xiii). Modern scholars
          agree that Urry’s text is “quite the worst ever issued” (Spurgeon, I, cxx). But at least
          three threads tie it to Blake: he certainly used the book, at least in Hayley’s library;
          Blake the artist might have appreciated the illustrator’s exact delineation and
          character-by-character discrimination, though not his romanticized drawing style; and
          Blake [the, as it were, starving artist] might have appreciated this edition’s easy
          availability and low price in second-hand bookstalls, especially after Tyrwhitt’s 1775
          edition superseded its text.</p>
        <p>We have no records from second-hand bookstalls, of course. But Urry’s edition is still
          plentiful today, even in American libraries. Back in 1721, the publishers issued such a
          numerous first edition that twelve years later Urry’s executor was complaining that he
          still had copies “upon hand.” Urry’s estate, and therefore the proceeds of the edition,
          had been divided three ways, among that executor, and a bookseller, and the college of
          Christ Church, Oxford. “The College authorities had adopted a simple and effective method
          of disposing of theirs, which was to oblige all scholars upon entrance to buy a copy. The
          picture of the young fox-hunting squires of Christ Church being forced willy-nilly to
          carry off their Chaucer folios is a delightful one; and it may perhaps account for the
          number of copies of Urry’s Chaucer to be found in the old country houses of England”
          (Spurgeon, I, cxx-cxxi).</p>
        <p>Did Blake own or use a copy of Urry’s elaborately illustrated edition, while he painted
          the “Canterbury Pilgrims”? Kiralis rejects the possibility, largely on the grounds that
          Blake would not have owned a corrupt text (p. 169). But Blake was not a well-to-do,
          modern, conscientious literary scholar. And Blake’s use of Urry’s text would help explain
          one of the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>’s minor mysteries: where does Blake
          find his Chaucer quotations? They match up with no known edition of Chaucer. Blake
          mentions “Thynne in his Glossary” (E 523), but Thynne’s 1532 edition has no glossary. A
          later editor, Speght, in his preface credits Thynne’s son Francis with proposing that this
          1602 edition include a glossary, and for helping prepare it. The information about the
          Tabard, which Blake credits to Thynne, is printed in Speght’s glossary with no mention of
          father or son Thynne. The same information is quoted and credited to Speght by both Urry’s
          glossary and by Tyrwhitt, the responsible editor of 1775 (I, 76, n. 6). Bell’s edition
          reprints Tyrwhitt’s.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> In a letter to <hi rend="i">Gentlemen’s Magazine</hi>, 53 (1783), 461,
            Tyrwhitt rather good-naturedly reports that Bell had lifted his name, text, and entire
            scholarly apparatus without even consulting him. See Spurgeon, I, 474.</note></p>
        <p>Kiralis shows in detail (pp. 169-74) that Blake’s quotations in the 
            <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> come from no known edition of Chaucer. As a sampling,
          compare a few phrases from the Squire’s description: 
		<q> Thynne, 1532: syt on an horse . .
            . portray . . . lowly and servysable<lb/>
 Stowe, 1561: sit on an horse . . . portraie .
            . . lowlie and servisable<lb/>
 Speght, 1602: sitte on a horse . . . portray . lowly, and
            servisable<lb/>
 Urry, 1721: sit an hors . . . portraie . . . . . lowly, and
            servisable<lb/>
 Tyrwhitt, 1775: sitte on hors . . . pourtraie . . . lowly, and
            servisable<lb/>
 Blake, 1809: sit a horse . . . pourtray . . . and meek, and serviceable
		</q>
		Meek?? Clearly Blake feels no responsibility to reproduce exactly whichever text of
          Chaucer he is quoting from (as, in his Job illustrations, he quotes from no known edition
          of the Bible). Kiralis settles on Tyrwhitt’s as Blake’s most likely text. He disagrees
          with Nurmi and Bentley that Blake probably owned Speght.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n21" type="note">21</ref> I would propose in turn that Urry’s corrupt but illustrated and presumably
          inexpensive text is just as likely. Blake then even has a motive for reworking the text:
          knowing he has before him the sense but not the exact words of Chaucer, he feels free to
          delineate that sense more clearly. <note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> In <hi rend="i">A
              Blake Bibliography</hi> (Minneapolis: U. of Minnesota Press, 1964), pp. 201-02, G. E.
            Bentley, Jr. and Martin K. Nurmi include Speght’s edition of Chaucer among “Books Owned
            by Blake.” In the 1977 <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, however, Bentley has eliminated
            any suggestion for a Chaucer edition owned by Blake.</note></p>
        <p>Judging from these phrases about the Squire chosen at random, though, Blake seems not to
          care about Chaucer’s exact sense so much as about making the words tell his own Blakean
          meaning. Why substitute “and meek” for “lowly”? So the reader will not confuse social rank
          with personality, presumably. But why “meek”? Why not “humble” or another term that fits
          the meter? “Meek” suggests a lamb. A lamb suggests the Christ of Revelation. The Squire is
          the son of the Knight. So . . . meek as a lamb, Lamb of God. Father, Son, and Holy
          Ghost—the first three characters in Blake’s procession. The Knight’s sullen black dog,
          present neither in poem nor tradition, as the repressive Holy Spirit of institutionalized
          Christianity. The front half of the procession as repressed Heaven; the back half as the
          Hell of energy, both creative and destructive. Thus the last three characters must be the
          Unholy Trinity of unrepressed energy—Chaucer as Poet, Clerk as Philosopher . . . and that
          shifty-eyed Reeve? Rich, by mismanaging the estate of his adolescent lord? A Haldeman,
          rather than a Hitler, of destructive energy? How can <hi rend="i">he</hi> fit into the
          symbolism? Intuitive leaps to interpretation have their limits, unfortunately. Despite
          what Blake would have preferred, let me amass some cold hard facts as ballast, before
          jumping to conclusions.</p>
        <pb id="p13-174-175" n="174-175"/>
        <figure n="UrryDepartureChaucer.13.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="850" height="410">
          <head>Departure scene, from p. 1 of John Urry’s edition of the <hi rend="i">Works</hi> of
            G. Chaucer (London, 1721).</head>
          <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the Bancroft Library, University of California at
            Berkeley. Actual size, 6-1/4″ × 3″.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p13-176" n="176"/>
        <figure n="equestrianchaucer.13.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="539">
          <head>Equestrian portrait of Chaucer, from p. 147 of John Urry’s edition of the 
              <hi rend="i">Works</hi> of G. Chaucer (London, 1721).</head>
          <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the Bancroft Library, University of California at
            Berkeley. Actual size, 4″ × 5-1/2″.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p13-177" n="177"/>
        <figure n="ellesmeremanuscript.13.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="750" height="924">
          <figTranscr>[w]as a compaignye<lb/>
			[hau]nteden folye,<lb/>
			[stywe]s, and tavernes,<lb/>
			lutes, and gyt[er]nes<lb/>
			bothe day and nyght,<lb/>
			myght,<lb/>
			sacrifise<lb/>
			[cu]rsed wise,<lb/>
			<lb/>
			[dam]pnable<lb/>
			swere<lb/>
			[toter]e<lb/>
			noght ynough<lb/>
			[l]ough<lb/>
			[to]mbesteres<lb/>
			[fru]testeres<lb/>
			[wa]fereres<lb/>
			officeres<lb/>
			[l]echerye</figTranscr>
          <head>The Pardoner, from the Ellesmere manuscript (late fifteenth century).</head>
          <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the Huntington Library, San Marino, Ca. Actual size,
            52mm × 65mm.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p13-178" n="178"/>
        <p>The bulk of the artistic tradition that Blake could have known can be traced within the
          textual history of Chaucer’s works. In all but one instance, each artist who undertook
          individual portraits of the pilgrims had illustrated the <hi rend="i">Canterbury
            Tales</hi> by picturing each pilgrim next to either his verses in the General Prologue
          or his Tale. That one exception is a series of pilgrim portraits by James Jefferys, who
          was born in 1751, at age 23 won a Royal Academy gold medal for one of his drawings styled
          after Mortimer and Barry, and died of a cold at age 33. He executed “A series of 24 sepia
          and wash drawings [ea. 14-1/2″ × 11″] illustrating Chaucer’s Pilgrims” (Spurgeon, I,
          458-59). Since Jefferys did eleven public exhibitions in London, 1773-83, Blake might
          perhaps have examined these portraits a quarter century before he began his own.<ref
            target="n22" type="note">22</ref>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> According to the
              <hi rend="i">Dictionary of Artists who have Exhibited Works in the Principal London
              Exhibitions from 1760 to 1893</hi>, comp. Algernon Graves, 3rd ed. (1901; rpt. New
            York: B. Franklin, 1970), Jefferys exhibited eight times with the Society of Artists (a
            London group which lasted 1760-91, not to be confused with the Free Society of Artists,
            1761-83), and three times with the Royal Academy. The Canterbury pilgrims were not in
            the two of those three exhibits accounted for in <hi rend="i">The Royal Academy of
              Arts</hi> [<hi rend="i">Exhibitors 1769-1904</hi>,] comp. Algernon Graves (1905-06;
            rpt. New York: B. Franklin, 1972). Neither were they included in the recent Victoria and
            Albert exhibition of <corr type="emend">Jefferys’</corr> works, described by Martin Butlin in
“The Rediscovery of
            an Artist: James Jefferys 1751-84,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 10 (1977),
            123-24. In “James Jefferys, Historical Draughtsman (1751-84),” <hi rend="i">Burlington
              Magazine</hi>, 118 (March 1976), 148-57, Timothy Clifford and Susan Legouix include
            among “Lost Works by James Jefferys” two items that apparently align with Spurgeon’s
            description of the 24 Chaucer drawings: “Designs from Chaucer’s Pilgrimage to
            Canterbury, made during his stay with Mr Davy of One House, Suffolk, later in collection
            of Sir George Beaumont” (ref. Clement Taylor Smythe coll., Maidstone Museum, IV, f.
            318); and “‘JAMES JEFFREYS / Lot 72, THE PARDONNIER; HARRY BAILLEY and FRIAR—from
            Chaucer—three pictures,’ in sale of late John Newington Hughes, Esq., of Winchester,
            Christie and Manson, 14th-15th April 1848. According to annotated catalogue at Maidstone
            Museum bought ‘?Manger’.” Apparently the set of drawings was broken up for
          sale.</note></p>
        <p>Besides these unpublished and now-lost drawings, and besides Caxton’s edition whose
          woodcuts were re-used to illustrate Thynne’s edition, three printed editions and the
          Ellesmere manuscript make up the whole rest of the artistic tradition that Blake might
          have known as he painted “Canterbury Pilgrims.” Thus, a brief orientation in
          “Chauceriana.”</p>
        <p>Of the sixty-six manuscripts of <hi rend="i">Canterbury Tales</hi> now extant, only two
          picture the pilgrims: Cambridge MS Gg 4 27,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23"
type="note">23</ref> and the
          Ellesmere. Then, William Caxton in about 1477 first put Chaucer into print. His second
          edition (1483?) adds works other than the <hi rend="i">Tales</hi>, and the first set of
          woodblock prints. His same woodblocks, noticeably worn, are re-used for the next major
          edition of Chaucer, William Thynne’s in 1532. In 1561, John Stowe’s new edition is
          illustrated with a different set of woodblocks. Thomas Speght in 1598 produced the last
          edition of Chaucer to be set in black-letter type, its only illustrations a half-page
          engraving of a knight and a full-page frontispiece, the “first engraved portrait of
            Chaucer,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref> framed by his
arms and “Progenie.” Over
          a century passed; the next edition was Urry’s in 1721, and finally Tyrwhitt’s in 1775,
          without illustrations except in those fancy few that included plates by Mortimer. 
            <note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> This manuscript was in the Cambridge library at Blake’s
            time, according to John M. Manly and Edith Rickert, <hi rend="i">The Text of the
              Canterbury Tales</hi> (Chicago: U. of Chicago Press, 1940), I, 182. It shows “Drawings
            of 6 Tellers of 6 Canterbury Tales and 6 Allegorical Figures for the 
              <hi rend="i">Parson’s Tale</hi> (being all that were not cut out of the ms. by some
scoundrel)”—as
            reproduced in <hi rend="i">Cambridge MS Appendix</hi>, ed. F. J. Furnivall, Chaucer Soc.
            Pubs., Ser. 1, No. 66, part 8 (London: N. Trübner, 1884). These long-bodied turbaned
            pilgrims are considered the work of a Dutch or Flemish artist employed by some English
            lord; the manuscript is “entirely outside the main stream of development in 15 C English
            illumination” (Manly and Rickert, I, 564).</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi>
            According to the Grolier Club, <hi rend="i">An Exhibition of Original and Other
              Editions, Portraits and Prints, Commemorative of the Five Hundredth Anniversary of the
              Death of Geoffrey Chaucer, the Father of English Poetry</hi> (New York: DeVinne Press,
            1900), p. 19. Speght’s frontispiece is reproduced in Spurgeon’s work cited.</note></p>
        <p>Spurgeon gives a brief chatty account (I, cxv-cxxiii) and Hammond a factual survey (pp.
          114-30 and 202-11) of these pre-Victorian editions. Each major editor’s work was
          rearranged, re-edited, reprinted, plagarized—but such details are not vital to the history
          of illustration. The following four items, all but the last now available in facsimile,
          constitute nearly the whole artistic tradition of Canterbury pilgrims before Blake:
          Ellesmere manuscript (late fifteenth century), Thynne’s edition (1532), Stowe’s edition
          (1561), and Urry’s edition (1721).</p>
        <p>In London, the two sixteenth-century editions were presumably obtainable, had Blake
          wished to examine their illustrations. He certainly examined Urry’s. And, only a few years
          before Blake began his painting, the Ellesmere itself had arrived in London. The Duke of
          Bridgewater owned the manuscript then. In 1802, supervised by Rev. Henry John Todd, the
          work traveled from Ashridge House to Bridgewater House, London, for rebinding. It stayed
          in London with the Duke and his heirs until the Huntington Library bought it in 1917.<ref
            target="n25" type="note">25</ref> The equestrian portrait of Chaucer was first
          reproduced in 1809,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref> the
pilgrims years later. But it
          seems safe to assume that the Duke would permit artists, besides the one in 1809, to
          examine his famous manuscript, and that Blake might have done so. 
              <note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi> History from Manly and Rickert, cited in n. 23, I, 149; and
from Alix
            Egerton, preface to <hi rend="i">The Ellesmere Manuscript, Reproduced in Facsimile</hi>
            (Manchester: University Press, 1911), I, 7.</note>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> By
            F. C. and J. Rivington, St. Paul’s, 1 Aug. 1809; then as frontispiece to Henry J. Todd,
              <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Lives and Writings of Gower and Chaucer</hi>
            (London: Rivingtons et al., 1810).</note></p>
        <p>The Ellesmere positions each pilgrim next to his Tale—all twenty-three tale-telling
          pilgrims, including Chaucer. Thynne’s 1532 edition uses fifteen woodcuts to portray twenty
          of those pilgrims, excluding Chaucer. Stowe in 1561 follows a different plan, placing each
          pilgrim beside his description in the General Prologue. Thus he eliminates Chaucer and the
          Canon’s Yeoman (who tell tales but do not appear in the General Prologue) and adds
          Squire’s Yeoman, Haberdasher, and Plowman (who tell no tales) for a total of twenty-two
          pilgrims from nineteen woodblocks.</p>
        <p>The artist for Urry’s edition—perhaps George Vertue, whose name is on Chaucer’s
          portrait—has engraved twenty-six half-page medallions of the pilgrims, including Chaucer
          (illus. 6). Urry prints all twenty-three Tales, plus the spurious Plowman’s Tale; and he
          assigns the spurious “Coke’s Tale of Gamelyn” to the Squire’s Yeoman.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27"
            type="note">27</ref> The twenty-sixth medallion shows a knight in armor,<gap
            type="emend"/> jousting, somewhat resembling the one engraved illustration to Speght’s
          1598 edition. “N.B. The following [sic] Cut should have been placed before the Rhime of
          Sir <hi rend="i">Thopaz</hi>,” explains its caption, from its final resting-place on the
          Contents page. <note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> For airy reasons typical of Urry:
            “because I think there is not any one [tale] that would fit him so well as this, I have
            ventur’d to place his Picture before this Tale, tho’ I leave the Cook in Possession of
            the Title” (p. 36).</note></p>
        <p>Urry’s artist tends to portray each pilgrim in realistic detail, usually in accord with
          Chaucer’s text. But all, even the slovenly Cook, are consistently pleasant-faced,
          prettified, inoffensive. The two sixteenth-century editions, using more awkward
          woodblocks, discriminate less among characters. For instance, Stowe makes a woodcut do
          double duty as Doctor of Physick and Parson. Such haphazard indistinguishability would
          presumably have displeased Blake, who in picture and commentary and cosmology makes the
          two types quite different.</p>
        <p>Blake, however, would probably have appreciated all but a few of the Ellesmere portraits,
          which were executed by three or four different artists. Each of the more spirited
          Ellesmere pilgrims exactly illustrates the vivid details in Chaucer’s description of him,
          and thereby conveys the character traits Chaucer saw. For instance, all five portrayed
          Pardoners do have long, stringy, blond hair, as Chaucer describes. But only the Ellesmere
          Pardoner (illus. 7) wears also a “vernicle . . . sewed upon his cappe” (v. 686), so that
          its face eerily echoes 
<pb id="p13-179" n="179"/>
<figure n="chaucersquire.13.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="645">
            <head>The Squire, from fo. 29 of William Thynne’s edition of the <hi rend="i">Works</hi>
              of G. Chaucer (London, 1532).</head>
            <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of Pattee Library, Pennsylvania State University.
              Actual Size, 2-3/4″ × 3-3/4″.</figDesc>
          </figure>
<pb id="p13-180" n="180"/>
his. And only the Ellesmere Pardoner and Blake’s carry
          the “crois of laton ful of stones” (v. 701), which Blake uses as artistic focal point and
          symbol of religious repression, poised over the horse’s arched straining neck in the
          center of the front-rank cluster of clergy. But, there is no proof that Blake ever
          examined the Ellesmere. And I see no details in the “Canterbury Pilgrims” that must have
          come from the Ellesmere or from anyplace else but the combination of Chaucer’s poem and
          Urry’s illustrations and Blake’s imagination.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, a comparison of each of Blake’s pilgrims with all four prototypes will help
          define what of each characterization is idiosyncratic to Blake and what of it has occurred
          to other artists interpreting the same Chaucerian passage. To start, the Squire leads the
          procession on the rearing steed with which Blake and the Urry and Ellesmere artists all
          interpret “Wel coude he sitte on hors” (v. 94). All three artists also reproduce the curly
          locks and wide-sleeved flowered tunic that Chaucer describes. Blake adds the round baby
          face, the fuzz of a mustache, and the plumed hat.</p>
        <p>The two woodcut Squires wear plumes also, however, and wear plenty of gewgaws besides.
          They are, in a word, fops. Thynne’s Squire particularly seems a caricature, resembling
          perhaps Tweedledum, or the Duchess in drag (illus. 8). Thus, when Blake in the 
            <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> snaps, “Was this a fop?” (E 529), he is attacking
          not only Cromek’s prospectus to Stothard’s rival painting,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">28</ref> but also an interpretation long established in picture and
in word.<ref
            target="n29" type="note">29</ref> To deny the Squire’s foppishness, Blake quotes the
          same lines that could just as validly have proven that the Squire is a mindless,
          subservient clotheshorse (he can sing, dance, joust, and he “carf before his fader at the
          table,” v. 100). And Blake conveniently ignores other lines, such as Chaucer’s satiric
          jabs at the Squire as a “hoote” lover. He replaces Chaucer’s picturable details with
          verbal abstractions: “greater perfection,” “first rate,” “true grandeur,” “unaffected
          simplicity” (E 524). A reader familiar with Chaucerian interpretation of the time would
          wonder at Blake’s abstracted one-sided praise for Chaucer’s ironically portrayed complex
          character, and would thereby look to the picture to see what Blake means. 
              <note id="n28"><hi rend="s">28</hi> The prospectus and advertisement for Stothard’s
“Canterbury
            Pilgrims” were first published in the 1808 edition of Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The
              Grave</hi>, which features the very plates that Cromek had commissioned Blake to both
            design and engrave, but then—treacherously, as Blake believed—handed over to
            Schiavonetti to engrave.</note>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">29</hi> As an example, George
            Ogle in “Letter to a Friend,” <hi rend="i">The Canterbury Tales of Chaucer, Modernis’d
              by several Hands</hi>, by John Dryden and others (London: J. &amp; R. Tonson, 1741),
            III, xvi-xvii, lists some of Chaucer’s “most singularly happy. . . . Touches taken from
            his Descriptions of the Pilgrims,” among them, “The <hi rend="i">Squire</hi>; with Locks
            curl’d, just <hi rend="i">fresh</hi> from the <hi rend="i">Press</hi>!” Blake certainly
            had access to Ogle, for in the later pamphlet that publicizes his engraving, 
              <hi rend="i">The Prologue and Characters of Chaucer’s Pilgrims</hi>, “The original reading
            is copied from the edition of Thomas Speight, printed Anno. 1687; and the Translation
            from Mr. Ogle’s edition, 1741,” as quoted by Bentley, p. 540.</note></p>
        <p>There, he would notice symmetrical pairs—Knight and Squire at the front of the
          procession, Chaucer and Clerk at the rear—and the facial similarity of Squire and Clerk.
          But the Clerk’s inappropriately chubby face is framed in long straight hair and square
          hat, while the Squire’s curly locks are topped by awkwardly perched plumes that echo the
          shapes of birds, particularly of those two nuzzling beak-to-beak on the Tabard archway.
          And just above them, above the Gothic spires and the Wife’s elaborate headpiece, swoops a
          bird that Erdman would see as “an ironic negation of its own hopeful potential, not simply
          an evil force”—<hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake</hi> (Anchor Doubleday, 1974), pp. 19-20.
          This bird also visually evokes the dove of the Holy Spirit in the standard medieval
          representation of Christ’s baptism, as in Blake’s rendering of that scene in his later 
            <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> series: down through opening clouds plunges just such a
          bird, along with rays of light (like those above the Squire’s head here) and God’s booming
          voice of approval. God is pleased with his beloved son, who has now ceased to follow his
          own inspiration and has submitted to his father’s authority. I would suggest that the
          Biblical scene evoked by Blake’s Squire, as visually linked to background details, would
          be a spiritually ambivalent one for Blake: a moment of second-hand enlightenment. And
          Blake offers the reader no easy resolution to this visual ambivalence: in the 
            <hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi> he describes the Squire only with abstractions and then with the term
          “Apollo” (E. 527), the beautiful unconquerable sun-god who is shown being overthrown in
          Blake’s fourth illustration to Milton’s “On the Morning of Christ’s Nativity” (ca. 1808).
          Modern mythologists regard Apollo and Christ as two variants of the dying-and-resurrected
          fertility deity; Blake here interprets Chaucer to suggest a similar connection.<ref
            target="n30" type="note">30</ref>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">30</hi> For more on Blake’s
            place in the development of ideas about mythology, see Burton Feldman and Robert D.
            Richardson, <hi rend="i">The Rise of Modern Mythology 1680-1860</hi> (Bloomington:
            Indiana U. Press, 1972).</note></p>
        <p>Neither the appearance nor the description of the Squire makes him a negative force, nor
          a purely positive one. His role as obedient son in a repressive Trinity becomes clearer in
          comparison to the other figures in the procession—though never so clear as to lack the
          ambiguity inherent in all but a few of these “eternal principles or characters of human
          life” (E 527). The discrepancy between visually suggested spiritual ambivalence and
          abstract verbal praise becomes greater in regard to the Squire’s father, the Knight.</p>
        <p>Chaucer carefully describes the Knight’s appearance and “arraie”: 
		<q> His hors was good,
            but he ne was nat gaie.<lb/>
 Of fustian he wered a gipon,<lb/>
 Alle besmotred with his
            habergeon<lb/>
<lb/>
 (vv. 74-76) </q>
From the glossary in any edition available to him,
          Blake could have learned that Chaucer’s Knight wore a short doublet of cotton cloth, and a
          partial coat of mail.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">31</ref> No
previous illustrator had
          exactly followed Chaucer either, though. Mortimer’s elegantly attired Knight wears no
          chain mail (illus. 4). The Ellesmere Knight’s robe, long droopy shoes, high-piled turban,
          and rich but practical tack are so similar to those on Urry’s Knight that it seems
          possible that Urry’s artist in 1721 worked from the Ellesmere. If either robed Knight
          wears chain mail, it remains hidden under his gipon. But Blake was not the first to give
          the Knight armor plating. The two woodcut Knights, as well as the only illustration to
          Speght’s 1598 edition, all go contrary to Chaucer’s insistence that “he ne was nat gaie.”
          All three sixteenth-century Knights and their horses wear full armor plating and helmets
          with flamboyant plumage, as does the unprecedented Sir Thopas in Urry’s edition. Rather
          than Chaucer’s Knight in particular, these artists rendered the popular notion of a
          knight. But compared to Blake’s armored figures elsewhere—the Ghost of a Flea, the
          soldiers around the Whore of Babylon in the Bible series, the Satanic “Fire” in 
            <hi rend="i">Gates of Paradise</hi>, the Warrior in <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, and so
          on—Blake’s Knight with his segmented armor plating seems not merely unparticularized, but
          also sinister. <note id="n31"><hi rend="s">31</hi> For example, from Urry’s Glossary:
            “Gipon, Gippon: A short doublet, or light coat” (p. 32) and “Habergeon . . . A little
            Coat of Mail, or only Sleeves and Gorget of Mail” (p. 34).</note></p>
        <pb id="p13-181" n="181"/>
        <p>Also, like Mortimer’s Knight, he wears many layers of clothing: a chain-mail headpiece
          (which resembles, for instance, the scaley Rintrah of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, pl. 5), a
          neckpiece and medallion (with cross and equestrian figure), a uselessly swishing cape, a
          sash with another medallion, a chain-mail jacket, a gathered shirt, and plate-armor
          trousers. By outfitting his Knight so elaborately, Blake goes contrary to Chaucer’s
          description, to the one proto-type he saw for sure (Urry’s), and to his own
          commentary—“without ostentation,” “unaffected simplicity” (E 524). And if Blake is so
          tricky about clothing, is he straight forward when he praises the Knight as a “true Hero,
          a good, great, and wise man . . . that species of character which in every age stands as
          the guardian of man against the oppressor” (E 524)? I would suggest that the Knight, as an
          eternal type, takes it upon himself to define man’s oppressor. And with the rules and
          trappings of chivalry, he guards against forces that man—if left to his own
          inspiration—might embrace rather than fear. Like his son, then, the Knight in the picture
          is spiritually ambivalent, neither clearly good nor clearly evil.</p>
        <p>The Host “directs them to the Knight as the person who would be likely to commence their
          task of each telling a tale” (E 523). He gestures toward the Knight, whose
          backward-gesturing hand mirrors the Host’s—their fingertips at a level, as if strung
          together. The procession, in fact, features a series of prominent hands. The Knight and
          Chaucer, at beginning and end, clutch reins to breasts with left hands. But the Poet holds
          in his right hand a rosary, as tradition dictates for Chaucer portraits, whereas the
          Knight makes the open-palmed gesture that seems to pull the Host toward him. Next in line,
          the Prioress’ tiny and spidery right hand is writ large as the Pardoner’s huge,
          bejewelled, writhing, clutching hand. The Host’s armspread bisects the picture. His left
          hand presents the Knight; his right hand presents the Parson, who will be the last pilgrim
          to tell a tale. The Parson’s hand rests placidly on his knee. The Wife of Bath, with two
          fingers extended, delicately clutches her chalice of evil. The Cook’s rubbery right hand
          steadies his mug. And the positioning of Chaucer’s hands, as I will show, are an
          iconographic attribute of the poet in a long artistic tradition.</p>
        <p>The third pilgrim in line is the Squire’s Yeoman. Chaucer lists the implements he
          carries: a “mighty bowe,” sheaf of arrows, arm-guard, sword and buckler, dagger, St.
          Christopher medal, horn, and green belt to match his coat and hood (vv. 103-16). He tells
          no tale, so is not pictured in the Ellesmere nor in Thynne’s edition. In Urry’s edition,
          the tight-lipped Yeoman carries every weapon specified. In Stowe’s 1561 edition he carries
          only bow and arrows, and wears a strapped cap. Both prototypes are beardless. Blake has
          added the whiskers, the huge soft hypnotic eyes (he is the only pilgrim who looks directly
          out of the picture at the observer), and the dark “broune visage” (v. 109). The Squire’s
          Yeoman in Blake’s conception seems seductively Satanic. But the face in the procession
          very similar to his is Chaucer’s, the Poet’s; again, spiritual ambivalence remains
          unresolved.</p>
        <p>Next in line come the three priests. Only the one Nun’s Priest had been portrayed before,
          in the Ellesmere and in Urry. Both those are young and beardless; whereas Blake portrays a
          middle-aged, fat, smug priest, a glaring dark-bearded one, and an old tired hooknose with
          white beard. They appear as three variations on a theme, perhaps hypocrisy.</p>
        <p>The Second Nun tells a tale but is not described in the General Prologue, which says only
          that she is chaplain to the Prioress. One might assume, then, that their habits would be
          of the same order of nuns. In the Ellesmere, both wear plain black robes and veils, and
          close-fitting white covers over forehead and neck. Thynne uses the same woodcut for both;
          Stowe omits the Second Nun. Urry’s artist reproduces the Ellesmere habit for both,
          altering the high collar into a ruff.</p>
        <p>But it seems that Blake’s two clergywomen would not be caught dead wearing identical
          outfits on a pilgrimage. Compared to the Prioress, Blake’s Second Nun wears white rather
          than dark sleeves, a clasped rather than a thrown-back veil, a high neckline, no tiara,
          and dark curls rather than long straight blond hair—whereas nuns did not show their hair
          at all.</p>
        <p>The Second Nun’s round face, angle of profile, and wreathlike curls pair her off visually
          with that “Devil of the first magnitude” (E 526), the Summoner, And the Prioress resembles
          the Summoner’s cohort, the Pardoner. Each wears pointed headgear and long blond hair, and
          each holds a cross by a writhing spidery right hand. (Notice too the other crosses in the
          procession: between the breasts of the Wife of Bath, among the Knight’s decorations, atop
          the Prioress’ head, on the forehead of the Pardoner’s horse, and on his own back and
          satchel. Chaucer’s rosary consists of beads, without the usual cross. And the Host’s body
          forms a cross that bisects the group, for better or for worse.)</p>
        <p>Besides visual details, Blake uses similar words in the <hi rend="i">Descriptive
            Catalogue</hi> to link Prioress and Pardoner. The Pardoner is a scourge and a blight (E
          526), and also “grand, terrific, rich and honoured in the rank of which he holds the
          destiny” (E 526). The Prioress is “of the first rank; rich and honoured . . . truly grand
          and really polite” (E 524), and is equated with the Wife of Bath as “also a scourge and a
          blight” (E 528). Kiralis explains why the “also” in this sentence must mean “likewise”
          rather than “in addition,” syntactically (pp. 160-61). But I believe that Blake here
          intended an unresolved syntactic <corr type="emend">ambivalence,</corr> intended that the Urizenic
mind reading the
          passage dichotomize, and try to choose logically, and fail, and thereby look at the
          picture to find out whether or not the Prioress is visually paired with the Wife as being
          also, likewise, a scourge and a blight. And indeed, she is.</p>
        <p>Kiralis brings outside evidence to bear on his extensive analysis of the Wife and
          Prioress as Rahab and Tirzah, as grasping and repressed female sexuality.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
            type="note">32</ref> He documents descriptions of female beauty from medieval sources
          (none certainly available to Blake), Blake’s use of nets as symbols of repression
          elsewhere, and opinions of modern Chaucerians on the 
<pb id="p13-182" n="182"/>
Prioress’
          behavior. Interpreters of <hi rend="i">Canterbury Tales</hi> before Blake had also paired
          the two women described therein. In the passage quoted above, for example, Dryden speaks
          of the “mincing Prioress and the broad-speaking gap-tooth’d Wife of 
            <hi rend="i">Bathe</hi>”—thus suggesting the contrast between repressed propriety and outgoing
          promiscuity that <hi rend="i">Canterbury Tales</hi> might easily convey to anybody except
          to the Victorian scholars who were trying to interpret Chaucer without mentioning sex. The
          visual and verbal details shared by Blake’s Prioress and Pardoner further clarify her
          Tirzah nature. Thus, one should question the moral nature not only of the Prioress but
          also of other characters who are termed grand, rich, honored, first-rank,
          polite—characters like the Knight, at whom the Prioress gazes seductively. 
              <note id="n32"><hi rend="s">32</hi> Kiralis, pp. 148 and 151-59. He thereby supports S. Foster
            Damon’s suggestions in <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary</hi> (1965; rpt. New York:
            Dutton, 1971), p. 79.</note></p>
        <p>The Prioress is paired in one way with the Second Nun, in another way with the Pardoner,
          and in yet another with the Wife of Bath. The two vain nuns, out of pictorial context,
          would display rather innocent female folly. But as an observer simultaneously sees what
          the pair of nuns shares with the Pardoner/Summoner pair, who in Chaucer’s poem and Blake’s
          painting represent the corrupted and clearly evil elements of organized religion, the
          innocence of vanity is called into question. Furthermore, the flirtatious Prioress seeks
          to pull the Knight into her corrupted society. As Kiralis points out (pp. 158-59), the
          Knight discreetly returns her gaze. In this he differs from the incorruptible Parson,
          whose back is solidly turned from the Wife of Bath.</p>
        <p>The pairing of Wife and Prioress also occurs in other artists’ interpretations. Stowe’s
          1561 edition simply uses the same nunlike woodcut for both. But Thynne’s artist carefully
          distinguishes the Wife from the Prioress, and they particularly seem two variants on one
          theme because of their identical spraddle-legged nags. Each sits toward the off (i. e.,
          improper, right-hand) side of her horse. The Prioress faces three-quarters sideways; the
          Wife turns full face toward the observer. Thynne’s Prioress, high-collared and properly
          veiled, peers toward her horse’s front hooves with an expression of severity or nausea.
          The Wife wears a scarved sunhat “as brode as is a bokeler, or a targe” (v. 473). Her eyes
          are blurred in the woodcut, but certainly her mouth smiles directly at the observer. Each
          woman reins with her left hand. The Prioress’ right hand points forward, and over her
          right elbow she loops her heavy-looking “pair of bedes [and] broche of gold” (vv. 159-60).
          The Wife carries a rosary, and places her right hand somewhat suggestively in her lap. Her
          pointed shoe peeks from beneath the skirt of her tight-bodiced gown. Thus, Thynne’s artist
          does seem to intend a contrast between smiling outgoing sexuality and stern repressed
          propriety, in these two different women on identical horses.</p>
        <p>The horses of the Ellesmere Wife (illus. 9) and Prioress likewise resemble one another in
          head and feet positions, color, and tack. The women ride in opposite directions, such that
          the Prioress faces toward the off (improper) and the Wife toward the near (proper) side of
          her horse.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">33</ref> Each woman, in
three-quarter profile,
          reins with her left hand and raises her right—the Prioress apparently in blessing, the
          Wife apparently ready to strike with a stiff quirt her horse’s tender neck. But,
          especially because the two portrayals may be by different artists, I would not emphasize
          an intentional artistic contrast. More importantly, each Ellesmere portrait exactly
          depicts details in Chaucer’s text. The matronly Wife’s costume is precise to the last
          wimple and coverchief—to the details that Blake manipulates to make the Wife into a
          bejewelled Whore of Babylon figure. The Ellesmere Prioress has the “fayre forehed . . . a
          spanne brode” (vv. 154-55) with which Chaucer suggests her vanity; and unlike Blake’s
          Prioress, she keeps her forehead, hair, and bodice properly covered. 
              <note id="n33"><hi rend="s">33</hi> Actually, the Ellesmere Wife’s seating is obscured by the
sacklike
            “fote-mantel about hire hippes large” (v. 474)—this drawing being “the only known
            authority for what a foot-mantle was,” according to John Saunders, ed., 
              <hi rend="i">Chaucer’s Canterbury Tales</hi>, rev. ed. (London: J. M. Dent, 1889), p. 168, n.
3.
            Kiralis (p. 148) uses the Wife’s improperly-directed seating as a point of contrast
            between her and the Prioress. Particularly because these supposed proprieties are
            reversed in the Ellesmere, however, I would state the contrast not in terms of the
            direction of the seating, but in terms of the Prioress’ hidden legs vs. the Wife’s
            spread legs.</note></p>
        <p>The artist of Urry’s edition pairs the two women, especially by placing them side by
          side, set apart, in his engraving of the departure scene (illus. 5). His <corr type="emend">miniatures</corr> are so
          exact that one can be sure it is the Prioress’ back, not the Second Nun’s, because their
          horses and riding styles differ.</p>
        <p>In her medallion portrait, with a stern, purse-lipped gaze directly at the observer,
          Urry’s Prioress seems neither flirtatious nor particularly pious, but mainly disapproving.
          Neither does the unsmiling Wife, also gazing directly outward, seem harmlessly
          flirtatious. She instead seems an embodiment of evil, with her high-peaked witches’ hat
          and her stiff quirt. She ignores her double stirrup to spread her legs and display her
          ankles. Blake transfers this last detail to his “Canterbury Pilgrims,” along with her
          overall witchlike aura as a symbol of openly dangerous female evil. And in the picture’s
          composition, as Kiralis shows extensively, Blake balances the Wife with the less obvious
          and thereby possibly more dangerous evil of the Prioress’ repressed sexuality.</p>
        <p>Behind the Prioress rides the Tapiser, or Tapestry Weaver (E 523 and 528). His particular
          skill accentuates the link between the two women, for Blake’s Rahab and Tirzah are
          elsewhere forever weaving falsehoods, nets, veils, the Natural Body, the web of Religion,
          and other unpleasantness. The net over the Prioress’ horse also suggests weaving; and of
          course Chaucer’s Wife of Bath earns her living by “cloth making” (v. 449) as well as by
          outliving rich husbands.</p>
        <p>Next follow the Monk and Friar. The two female clergy, from the same order of nuns, wore
          different clothing; these two principal male clergy, of altogether different
          organizations, wear identical clothing. Every previous illustrator had discriminated, had
          given each man the proper robes of his order. Chaucer likewise discriminates. Chaucer’s
          Monk trims his robe with expensive fur, and fastens his hood with an elaborate gold pin
          (vv. 193-97). The Friar wears a short flared cape of double worsted 
            <pb id="p13-183" n="183"/>
          <figure n="ellesmerewifeofbath.13.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="750" height="927">
            <figTranscr>[K]yng Arthour<lb/>
			[Briton]s speken greet honour<lb/>
			[fu]lfild of fairye<lb/>
			hir joly compaignye<lb/>
			mede<lb/>
			[red]e<lb/>
			[ag]o<lb/>
			[elv]es mo<lb/>
			[pra]yeres<lb/>
			[fr]eres<lb/>
			streem<lb/>
			beem<lb/>
			[kichen]es boures<lb/>
			[tour]es<lb/>
			[dayerye]s<lb/>
			[fair]yes</figTranscr>
            <head>The Wife of Bath, from the Ellesmere manuscript (late fifteenth century).</head>
            <figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the Huntington Library, San Marino, Ca. Actual
              size, 52mm × 72mm.</figDesc>
          </figure>
<pb id="p13-184" n="184"/>
          (vv. 264-65) in which he carries “knives / And pinnes,
          for to given fayre wives” (vv. 233-34). Blake ignores Chaucer’s rich details, to show the
          two clutching at identical thrown-back hoods. In earnest argument or conversation, the
          Monk looks stern; the Friar points, apparently asking advice or admonishing him.</p>
        <p>In his text, Blake attacks those who consider the Monk and Friar to be burlesque
          characters (E 525). Presumably he attacks Cromek’s prospectus for Stothard’s painting. But
          the prospectus included in the 1808 edition of Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, the
          prospectus Blake likeliest saw, does not use the term “burlesque” or “buffoon.” Blake may
          be interpolating from Cromek’s overall understanding of <hi rend="i">Canterbury Tales</hi>
          as “<hi rend="i">a pleasurable Tour, sanctified by the name of Pilgrimage.</hi> The covert
          ridicule on these eccentric excursions, which Chaucer intended, is very happily preserved
          in his Face.” Further, Cromek was not alone in his interpretation. Spurgeon notes that
          during the eighteenth century, the quality most frequently attributed to Chaucer was
          jocosity: “‘Joking,’ ‘jocound,’ ‘sprightly,’ ‘gleeful,’ ‘blithe,’ ‘merry,’ ‘gay,’
          ‘frolic,’ ‘facetious,’ are among the adjectives used quite constantly in speaking of
          Chaucer or his work at this time” (I, xcix). When Blake declares that he must “set certain
          mistaken critics right in their conception of the humour and fun that occurs on the
          journey” (E 525), then, the plural “critics” is probably literal, not sarcastic, for he
          attacks others along with Cromek.</p>
        <p>The Monk and Friar, Blake insists, are characters of “a mixed kind” (E 525), not wholly
          comic. He points out the Monk’s knowledge of the tragic, as an example of how Chaucer
          complicates a reader’s interpretive response to the cleric. Blake, while seeming to praise
          the Monk, also warns not to trust surface appearances: “Though a man of luxury, pride and
          pleasure, he is a master of art and learning, though affecting to despise it” (E525). This
          doubly-masked Monk pretends education matters and further pretends he doesn’t care. From
          Chaucer’s description, Blake points out details that specify the Monk’s ambiguity—that
          show him neither good nor evil, neither comic nor tragic, neither lewd nor learned. Again,
          one must must look at the picture to interpret the character, and there see him as the
          twin of the Friar.</p>
        <p>Of the Friar, Blake points out, Chaucer likewise uses two apparently contradictory
          concepts to complicate a reader’s response to the character—he is “a wanton and a merry,”
          but also “full solemn” in his office. Blake describes the Monk and Friar with many of the
          same adjectives of apparent praise that he uses for others in the front half of the
          procession: “of the first rank in society, noble, rich . . . a leader of the age . . .
          young, handsome, and rich . . . a master of art and learning” (E 524-25). But further on,
          Blake condemns the Friar outright. In praise of the Good Parson, he says, “Search O ye
          rich and powerful, for these men and obey their <corr type="emend">counsel</corr> . . . 
          But alas! you will not easily
          distinguish him from the Friar or the Pardoner, they also are ‘full solemn men,’ and their
          counsel, you will continue to follow” (E 526).</p>
        <p>Whenever Blake seems to be using wealth or social power as positive attributes of a
          character, certainly, he intends some degree of irony. The “rich and powerful,” addressed
          here, clearly rank far below the Parson on Blake’s scale of values. The overtly evil
          Summoner is “rich and honoured” (E 526); the brutal Miller “exists . . . to get rich and
          powerful to curb the pride of Man” (E 527).</p>
        <p>Previous artists’ conceptions of the Monk and Friar do little to either support or deny
          the moral ambivalence that Chaucer’s poem and Blake’s picture and commentary suggest. Most
          earlier portrayals lack energy and appropriateness—one exception being, surprisingly,
          Stowe’s woodcut Friar.</p>
        <p>Even Urry’s usually accurate artist fails to follow Chaucer’s details for the Monk and
          Friar, who simply wear proper robes of their brotherhoods. An Ellesmere artist who painted
          small and unspirited pilgrims did the Friar and also the Parson. They merely display their
          identities—the Friar by his tonsure, the Parson by folding his arms in blessing. A more
          inspired Ellesmere artist portrayed the Monk, however. With his hood thrown over a
          wide-brimmed hat, he rides accompanied by his greyhounds (eliminated by Blake) and his
          bells “gingeling . . . as loude, as doth the chapell belle” (vv. 170-71). Stowe’s Monk is
          a hooded robed figure; Thynne’s edition includes no Monk. But a reader with some
          imagination could see a self-satisfied inertia in the heavy-lidded eyes of Thynne’s Friar,
          and see also what might be a bottle in his hand. And the woodcut in Stowe’s edition picks
          up on that hint. His wanton and merry Friar does carry a bottle, and in addition he smiles
          a small smile and closes one eye in an unmistakable wink.</p>
        <p>What is the significance, in Blake’s symbolism, of the identical robes and serious
          tête-à-tête conversation of Monk and Friar? Their pose is mirrored by the next pair, the
          Summoner and Pardoner. But we know well why these two gaze lovingly at one another: they
          indulge in “that abhominable sinne, of which abhominable sinne no man unneth ought to
          speke ne write” (says the Parson, II, 369). The Pardoner and Summoner, also, gleefully
          cheat the poor and helpless. They are evil in anyone’s judgment in any age; but still the
          Christian church provides their livelihoods. Blake’s description of them is full: “the
          Pardoner . . . commands and domineers over the high and low vulgar. This man is sent in
          every age for a rod and scourge, and for a blight . . . and he is suffered by Providence
          for wise ends, and has also his great use, and his grand leading destiny. His companion
          the Sompnour, is also a Devil of the first magnitude, grand, terrific, rich and honoured”
          (E 526). The same as the Monk and Friar and Prioress and Knight and Squire, then, the
          satanic Pardoner and Summoner are grand, rich, and honored leaders of the first rank.</p>
        <p>Earlier portrayals of the Pardoner and Summoner show effectively that an artist who
          reproduces the details of Chaucer’s text can thereby create a character who suggests the
          spiritual nature that is elaborated by Blake. The two woodcut editions tend to ignore
          potentially picturable details; Urry’s engraver, likewise, gives the Pardoner long blond
            <pb id="p13-185" n="185"/>
hair but little else from Chaucer’s account, so that this
          prettified Pardoner seems not very sinister. In contrast, the Ellesmere Pardoner’s flowing
          yellow hair combines with his scarlet robe, his vernicle, and his huge bejewelled cross,
          to portray a character not to be trusted (illus. 7). Two-faced, as it were. The Summoner’s
          acne and “gerlond . . . upon his hede” (v. 668) appear only in the Ellesmere, Urry, and
          Blake. His pitted face and headwreath do, in all three, create the supernatural aura that
          Blake would expect of a Devil. In Thynne’s edition, the same woodcut portrays
          indiscriminately Summoner, Merchant, Franklin, and Manciple; in Stowe, the Summoner
          arbitrarily carries a spear and rides a rearing horse.</p>
        <p>The sixteenth-century editions’ use of the same woodcut to portray several pilgrims
          highlights an artistic problem. Neither Urry’s careful engraver nor Blake follows the
          Ellesmere’s example of carefully distinguishing each business and professional man by
          costume and other attributes. Urry’s artist does show each bourgeois pilgrim differently.
          But if you shuffled his engravings like a pack of cards, you would have a lot of trouble
          sorting out which was the Reeve, which the Man of Law, and so on. Blake tucks the
          bourgeois pilgrims into the background and, I think, is less interested in an artistic
          balance of their spiritual attributes.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, Blake’s Manciple—looking as if he wishes he had been tucked anywhere but in
          between these two loathly lovers—does form a pair with the Reeve. Blake places the
          Manciple at the end of the first half, and emphatically places the Reeve “hinderest of the
          rout” (E 523). Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, like Chaucer’s General
          Prologue, pairs the Manciple and Reeve. The “worldly wisdom” Blake attributes to them both
          (E 527) is a term from morality plays and John Bunyan’s <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s
            Progress</hi> (“Mr. Worldly Wiseman”), suggesting the delusive nature of such wisdom.
          Chaucer makes it clear that Manciple and Reeve both get rich by cheating in business—to
          either Blake or Chaucer, presumably, less severe an evil than using religion to cheat the
          helpless poor, but nevertheless a distinctly negative moral trait.</p>
        <p>The genial Host, his face not so jolly as Chaucer’s poem might suggest,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34"
            type="note">34</ref> divides both the picture space and the cavalcade itself in half:
          fifteen pilgrims follow him, fourteen people and three dogs come before. Many details of
          the Host’s appearance echo visual details of other pilgrims. For instance, the two spiky
          feathers in his cap link him to the Franklin—and both men are variants on the Bacchus
          type, the genius of hospitality. But spiky upward protrusions, like the feathers, also
          appear as the Yeoman’s bow, the Prioress’ tiara, the Pardoner’s cap, the Parson’s cap that
          slants exactly opposite the Pardoner’s, the Wife’s peak, the Miller’s pipe, the Gothic
          spires of Southwark, and most of the horses’ ears except for the flaccid ones on the
          Parson’s nag. Or again, the Host’s low-cut ruff is echoed in the Knight’s sashes and the
          Wife’s bodice. His horse’s front legs are placed as awkwardly as those of the Pardoner’s
          horse. Without counting and assigning each visual detail to the company fore and aft, one
          can see that the Host both bisects and unifies the procession, artistically. He likewise
          serves a centering role in Blake’s moral schema: he is a sort of presiding spirit over
          this pilgrimage through life, representing neither good nor evil, neither expression nor
          repression, neither heaven nor hell but both together, in the unresolvable world of
          Experience. No earlier artist had portrayed the Host. <note id="n34"><hi rend="s">34</hi>
            In the second prospectus (composite draft) to the engraving of the painting, Blake
            deleted “(the Fun afterwards exhibited on the road may be seen depicted in his [the
            Host’s] jolly face”—E 557..</note></p>
        <p>Of the earlier portrayals of the Shipman, only the Ellesmere artist uses his “hewe al
          broun” (v. 396) to give him a sinister appearance, as does Blake. “The Shipman, or Sailor,
          is a similar genius of Ulyssean art”—similar to Reeve and Manciple—“but with the highest
          courage superadded” (E 527). Ulysses sailed, of course, but he is also a type of the
          trickster. Thus the Shipman fits with the two shady money-managers, as variants on one
          type of “consummate worldly wisdom.”</p>
        <p>He is placed just behind the Host, paired with the gruesome Summoner just before. The
          Shipman’s furry cap echoes the Summoner’s headwreath, and the dark faces of the two are
          intensified by thick eyebrows and by the Shipman’s beard, the Summoner’s acne. The Shipman
          does not look longingly at a lover, though; instead he faces directly backward, to glare
          at the Plowman. The slanted caps of Parson and Pardoner frame the less prominent angles of
          Plowman and Shipman, their profiles in direct confrontation. Chaucer’s poem offers no hint
          of hostility between Plowman and Shipman, of earth and sea. Blake, I would suggest,
          intends a confrontation—framed by the purely good Parson and the evil Pardoner—of two
          types of courage: the Plowman’s simple selfless courage, as opposed to the Shipman’s
          tricky self-serving courage.</p>
        <p>All four bourgeoisie who ride behind the Shipman watch him anxiously. The Franklin seems
          particularly worried that a fight is about to flare. Among these man, Blake terms the
          Franklin the Bacchus of the company, and the Physician the Esculapius (E 527). Such
          references to classical tradition clarify Blake’s interpretation of Chaucer. Blake has
          elsewhere invented his own names but he describes the same characters, the same eternal
          Principles, as does classical or Norse or Christian or any other mythology. Any true poet
          does the same, says Blake; any poet creates his own imaginative mythology. “Canterbury
          Pilgrims” shows in artistic detail how Chaucer’s mythology parallels Blake’s and
          others’.</p>
        <p>To skip the Plowman for a moment, the Physician and Man of Law form a professional pair,
          one that balances the Monk and Friar. Blake uses the term “master” only to describe these
          four: the Monk is “master of art and learning” (E 525); the Friar, “master of all the
          pleasures of the world” (E 525); the Lawyer, “master of the jurisprudence of his age” (E
          526); the Physician, “Master and Doctor in his art” (E 527). Chaucer does not directly
          link the two professionals, but he does use a distinctive technique in their General
          Prologue descriptions. Chaucer appears to praise each man unreservedly, until a final,
          neat, balloon-pricking couplet. The Lawyer: “Nowher so besy a man as he ther n’as, / And
          yet he semed besier than he was” (vv. 323-24). The Doctor: “For gold in phisike is a
          cordial; / Therfore he loved gold in special” (vv. 445-46). I have suggested that Blake’s
          pairings of bourgeois pilgrims are less striking, visually, than are those 
            <pb id="p13-186" n="186"/>
of the characters he portrays full-length. But a Doctor/Lawyer
          pairing does contribute to the picture’s visual and symbolic symmetry. In front of the
          Host’s left hand ride two purely evil clergy and two smooth-surfaced, hypocritical,
          educated clergy—each pair introverted, Monk and Friar linking eye contact as do Pardoner
          and Summoner. Behind the Host’s right hand ride two purely good pilgrims, eyes straight
          ahead, and two educated and mildly hypocritical professional men, their faces at
          three-quarter profile. Blake hopes that they will continue to ride and keep counsel with
          the Parson and Plowman (E 526).</p>
        <p>Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> becomes less misleading concerning the
          characters in the second half of the procession. He usually says in words what he means in
          the picture; and he explains precisely what he is doing with binary symmetry. He describes
          the Plowman as “Hercules in his supreme eternal state, divested of his spectrous shadow;
          which is the Miller . . . . Chaucer has divided the ancient character of Hercules between
          his Miller and his Plowman” (E 527). Here is perhaps Blake’s clearest statement of just
          how he sees different mythologies interrelate: not as one-to-one relabelings of one
          another’s deities, but as once-inspired attempts to divide the continuous spectrum of the
          human psyche into discrete but interacting bundles of characteristics.</p>
        <p>The Plowman and Miller both display physical strength and stamina. But the Miller uses
          his strength to terrify people, whereas the Plowman uses his to help. He is “simplicity
          itself, with wisdom and strength for its stamina” (E 527). Kiralis suggests that Blake
          intends his portrait of the Plowman to be his own idealized self-image (p. 147). The
          Plowman also evokes the apocalyptic imagery in Revelation, the most poetically inspired
          book of the Bible, and in Langland’s <hi rend="i">Piers Plowman</hi> as well. Further,
          Blake emphatically portrays the Plowman as young, and his brother the Parson as very old.
          The physical wisdom and strength of the good young man must complement the spiritual
          wisdom and strength of the good old man, even if such symbolism makes them look more like
          father and son than brothers.</p>
        <p>For these two, Blake creates no conflict between text and picture. For the Parson, he
          resurrects from his <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> illustrations the Counsellor and the Good Old
          Man. He ignores artistic tradition to do so: in the Ellesmere, Thynne, and particularly
          Urry, the Parson is young and beardless. Chaucer gives no hint of the Parson’s age. In the
          book of <hi rend="i">Fables Ancient and Modern</hi> that I have suggested Blake knew,
          however, Dryden expands Chaucer’s General Prologue paragraph into a seven-page “Character
          of A Good Parson,” in couplets, and there describes the Parson as a “good old Man” (p.
          534).</p>
        <p>Because the Plowman tells no tale, only Stowe and Urry had portrayed him earlier. The
          nobility of Blake’s rendering suggests that he would be displeased at Stowe’s Plowman, a
          nondescript fellow who seems a misplaced cleric. Urry’s Plowman at least looks proud,
          reining his draft horse with a thick rope.</p>
        <p>Urry’s Wife of Bath, similarly, is characterized with a hint of the symbolism that Blake
          renders full-blown. Blake copied Urry’s Wife exactly, for Hayley’s library at Felpham. He
          certainly also saw the openly flirtatious Wife in Bell’s 1782-83 edition of 
            <hi rend="i">British Poets</hi> (illus. 2). And whether Blake saw them or not, Mortimer’s Wife
is a
          sinister witchlike hag (illus. 4), and the Ellesmere Wife (illus. 9) shows how she looks
          when an artist exactly follows the details of Chaucer’s text. Kiralis (pp. 148-53)
          summarizes the visual details that support an intuitive response to Blake’s Wife of Bath
          as Rahab, the Whore of Babylon.</p>
        <p>The Wife’s thronelike headpiece is framed by Miller and Merchant. Blake in his text
          barely mentions the Merchant, who wears a forked beard and tall hat, as specified by
          Chaucer and shown by earlier artists. He looks somewhat sinister, especially in comparison
          to the kindlier-looking Physician (who also wears forked beard and tall hat), and to his
          prototypes, including the one that Blake copied from Urry’s edition to accompany the “Head
          of Chaucer” in Hayley’s library. Why does Blake pick the Merchant to escort the Wife, both
          for the library and here? From Chaucer’s poem come tenuous connections: the Merchant is
          newly wed to a shrewish wife (vv. 9089-9115); he perhaps cheats at business (vv. 276-84);
          his Tale of <hi rend="i">senex amans</hi> and young lust makes sexuality disgusting and,
          like the Wife’s Tale, it suggests female dominance; a character within the Merchant’s Tale
          mentions the Wife of Bath, in one of those fine Chaucerian inconsistencies that keep 
            <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> chugging along for decades. But none of these threads
          seems quite substantial enough to pair him spiritually with the Whore of Babylon and with
          Hercules’ discarded spectrous shadow, the Miller, as his position in Blake’s composition
          (and in Mortimer’s, illus. 4) would suggest.</p>
        <p>Concerning the Plowman’s spectrous counterpart, Blake’s text is again a straightforward
          explication of his painting, with the negative connotations of abstract words made
          explicit: “the Miller, a terrible fellow, such as exists in all times and places, for the
          trial of men, to astonish every neighbourhood with brutal strength and courage, to get
          rich and powerful to curb the pride of Man” (E 527). Like the Pardoner, he exists “for a
          trial of men” (E 526); like many of the front-rank pilgrims, and unlike millers in the
          real world, he is “rich and powerful.”</p>
        <p>The Ellesmere artist, following Chaucer’s details except for the red beard, has painted a
          hunched, loutish, very sinister-looking Miller. Each of the woodcut Millers rides a mule,
          plays a clarinet-like pipe, lacks the beard that Chaucer specifies, and looks rather frail
          to break a door “at a renning with his hede” (v. 553). But at least they are unmistakably
          millers; a windmill in the background assures the identity, in Stowe. Urry’s
          bagpipe-bearing Miller seems too genteel for the part, as the artist follows his tendency
          to soften into detailed realism rather than harden into characterization. And Blake’s
          seems not particularly sinister, either, although Blake incorporates the same details as
          does the Ellesmere—big bones and brawn, thick neck, bagpipe. Brutal strength and courage
          pose a “trial of men” that terrifies them openly, in contrast to the insidious moral
          terror, of hellfire and summonses, with which systematized religion scourges and divides
          the classes of men.</p>
        <pb id="p13-187" n="187"/>
        <p>Behind the Miller, and oblivious even to the Wife’s charms, rides the most vulgar
          pilgrim. The Cook falls lolling drunk off his horse, in the prologue to the Manciple’s
          Tale. And Chaucer gives him no professional ethics whatsoever. He serves stale pastry
          disguised as fresh, and old tough goose disguised in sauces; his customers fall ill
          because “in thy shop goth many a flie loos” (v. 4350). Blake says only that the Cook is
          the leader of a class of men (E 527). He mentions leadership also as an attribute of the
          Knight, Monk, Host, Three Citizens, Prioress, and Wife of Bath. Thus Blake uses
          leadership, like wealth and power, as an intentionally ambiguous abstract term. Like
          perfection as an attribute, leadership describes without necessarily praising: “every one
          of his characters [is] perfect in his kind, every one is an Antique Statue; the image of a
          class, and not of an imperfect individual” (E 527). (Analogously, Chaucer’s narrator
          describes, for example, the gold-loving Physician as “a veray parfite practisour”—v.
          424.)</p>
        <p>Blake’s Cook looks more animal-like than do any of his prototypes—in particular more than
          Urry’s Cook, who resembles Urry’s Knight. The Ellesmere Cook looks slovenly and mean; he
          incorporates all the details of Chaucer’s text, even to the bandage over his running sore.
          But the Cook’s ape-like forehead, pig-like nose and lips, and spidery right hand are all
          original to Blake’s conception. The Cook represents brutality divested even of strength
          and courage—the spectrous shadow in his turn of the already spectrous Miller.</p>
        <p>Blake’s intention to pair off eternal Principles is again shown in his description of
          “two classes of learned sages, the poetical and the philosophical . . . side by side, as
          if the youthful clerk had put himself under the tuition of the mature poet” (E 528).
          Visually, then, the two might have presented a third age/youth pair, with Knight/Squire
          and Parson/Plowman. But, I will suggest that Chaucer here is a noticeably younger man than
          he is in any prototype available to Blake. Thus Blake sacrifices to his spiritual
          symbolism the visual impact that a third clearly-defined age/youth pair would produce. And
          he sacrifices to his binary symmetry the Clerk’s carefully-described preference for books
          over food.</p>
        <p>The Clerk’s round face and tiny mustache are original to Blake. Chaucer specifies that he
          was “not right fat . . . But loked holwe” (vv. 290-91). The Ellesmere and Urry Clerks have
          thin faces; and none of the previous four Clerks wore whiskers. The adolescent visage of
          Blake’s Clerk mirrors the face of the Squire. The two youths, balanced in the picture’s
          composition, also share spiritual attributes, for each student learns from a mature
          teacher. The Clerk is “servant and scholar of inspiration” (E 528). The Squire is servant
          and scholar instead of an armored, overdressed Knight who teaches the involuted rules and
          strictures of the chivalric code.</p>
        <p>The Clerk’s teacher, Blake’s Poet, is only the third equestrian Chaucer portrayed,
          perhaps excluding those lost drawings by James Jefferys. Blake could have examined the
          Ellesmere equestrian Chaucer, at Bridgewater House, and he certainly examined the portrait
          in Urry’s edition. Urry’s book includes three engraved portraits of Chaucer: miniature
          full-length on a small picture of his monument, full-page half-length as frontispiece, and
          a half-page equestrian medallion before the Tale of Melibeus, which reproduces the pose
          and facial features of the frontispiece (illus. 6). The edition includes also a typical
          description of the poet, pieced together from tradition, hints in Chaucer’s poetry,
          remarks by his contemporaries, portraits genuine and not, and much interpolation: “He was
          . . . of a middle stature, the latter part of his Life inclinable to be fat and corpulent.
          . . . His face was fleshy, his features just and regular, his complexion fair, and
          somewhat pale, his hair of a dusky yellow, short and thin; the hair of his beard in two
          forked tufts, of a wheat colour; his forehead broad and smooth; his eyes inclining usually
          to the ground, which is intimated by the Host’s words [vv. 13626-27]; his whole face full
          of liveliness, a calm easy sweetness, and a studious venerable aspect.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35"
            type="note">35</ref>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">35</hi> John Dart, “Life of Chaucer,” in
            Urry’s edition, no p.</note></p>
        <p>Lively, sweet, and venerable certainly describe Vertue’s portrait of Chaucer, which Blake
          probably copied for Hayley’s library. The caption to this frontispiece attributes the
          drawing to Thomas Hoccleve, whose fifteenth-century <hi rend="i">De Regimine
            Principum</hi> has a verse beside which an artist can insert Chaucer’s “lyknesse.” But
          Vertue’s engraving little resembles the marginal Chaucer in what was by Blake’s time
          Harleian MS 4866 in the British Museum.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36"
type="note">36</ref> Without
          intending deception, Vertue had engraved not a copy from the Hoccleve manuscript but
          instead one in a long line of pleasant-faced and firm-fleshed Chaucers, all facing
          three-quarter profile, smiling wisely, and fingering dangling pencases with their right
          hands and rosaries with their left. Most were sixteenth- or seventeenth-century paintings
          on panel, owned by various lords or the two universities.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n37" type="note">37</ref> Blake’s portrait for Hayley’s library is one more in the line. But his
          equestrian Chaucer in “Canterbury Pilgrims” shows significant alterations. 
              <note id="n36"><hi rend="s">36</hi> Text available in <hi rend="i">The Regement of Princes and
14
              Minor Poems</hi>, Vol. 3 of <hi rend="i">Hoccleve’s Works</hi>, ed. F. J. Furnivall,
            E. E. T. S., Ser. 2, No. 72 (London: K. Paul, Trench, Trübner, &amp; Co., 1897), p. 180,
            11. 4992-98. One might expect to find Chaucer’s portrait also beside the appropriate
            verse in every manuscript of Hoccleve’s <hi rend="i">De Regimine Principum</hi>; but
            only Harl. MS 4866, Royal MS 17 D 6, and Phillipps MS 1099 do preserve such a picture,
            and the latter seem copies of the former by less skillful artists. See Spurgeon, I,
            21-23 and 82-83; Reginald Call, “The Plimpton Chaucer and Other Problems of Chaucerian
            Portraiture,” <hi rend="i">Speculum</hi>, 22 (1947), 135-44; George L. Lam and Warren H.
            Smith, “George Vertue’s Contributions to Chaucerian Iconography,” <hi rend="i">MLQ</hi>,
            5 (1944), 303-22; Donald R. Howard, <hi rend="i">The Idea of the Canterbury Tales</hi>
            (Berkeley: U. of Calif. Press, 1976), pp. 7-13; and James H. McGregor, “The Iconography
            of Chaucer in Hoccleve’s <hi rend="i">De Regimine Principum</hi> and in the 
              <hi rend="i">Troilus</hi> Frontispiece,” <hi rend="i">Chaucer Review</hi>, 11 (1977),
            338-50.</note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">37</hi> Five of these portraits, all eerily
            resembling Vertue’s in expression and position, are reproduced in Marian Harry
            Spielmann’s <hi rend="i">Portraits of Geoffrey Chaucer</hi> (London: K. Paul, Trench,
            Trübner, &amp; Co., 1900), pp. 12-14 and 18-19. Vertue himself engraved at least three
            other portraits of Chaucer, including one first published in his own Heads of the Poets
            series in 1730. Wells, as cited in n. 19, says that Blake more probably worked from this
            latter engraving than from the frontispiece in Urry’s edition, for Hayley’s library,
            because Vertue’s 1730 Chaucer shows three buttons (not two) as does Blake’s (pp.
            18-19).</note></p>
        <p>And neither does Blake’s Poet-pilgrim much resemble the earliest manuscript Chaucers, in
          the Ellesmere and in Harl. MS 4866. Both fifteenth-century portraits show Chaucer as a
          noticeably old man, with white hair and sharp facial lines and contours. Both have
          downturned mouths and stern, almost suspicious gazes. From each one’s neck button dangles
          a pencase; each points to the text with one hand and holds a rosary in the other.</p>
        <p>The Ellesmere equestrian Chaucer holds reins and rosary in the same hand; Blake’s
          Poet-pilgrim holds them separately. Other nearly obligatory, iconographic details—the
          forked beard, downcast eyes, and positioning of hands—remain constant with the tradition.
          But, Blake’s Poet wears a white robe; the others, to a man, wear dark. His headcovering
          somewhat resembles earlier versions; but the cut of his gown differs from all, with its
          low-cut neckline, embroidery, and billowing folds. His heretofore ubiquitous pencase is
          gone, or hidden (perhaps signifying that poetic inspiration need not be in writing). His
          is a pensive expression, not one of wisdom like the tradition nor of severity like the
          earliest manuscripts. He is thinner and younger than any previous Chaucer. His mouth and
          goatee are 
<pb id="p13-188" n="188"/>
smaller than tradition suggests, and his eyes and
          forehead larger.</p>
        <p>Here Blake is continuing the tradition represented by Vertue’s portrait, but with
          variations that make Chaucer look younger and saintlier than ever before. To some degree
          his youthful appearance suggests the poetic genius of Los; he also appears Christlike,
          with eyes and whiskers that particularly resemble those of the Christ in Blake’s 
            <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> series (ca. 1816-18). Chaucer’s awkward riding posture
          also draws attention to itself: the Host forms a living cross, and the Pardoner a
          contorted swastika, while the Poet’s body forms a hunched, soon-to-be-saddle-sore
          counterpoint to the Knight’s professionally balanced seat.</p>
        <p>Blake pairs the Poet with the Knight because each of these two types teaches a different,
          contrasting, way of life to his young follower. Also, Chaucer and the Clerk form a
          complementary pair, a yin/yang pair, encompassing the dual aspects of the eternal Sage,
          “the poetical and the philosophical” (E 528). Chaucer forms a visual pair with the
          Pardoner, as well. Each has a similar style of head-piece, a clinging and flowing
          light-colored robe, a dark horse, and awkward anatomy. The Parson and Knight form a
          similarly balanced pair of dark-clothed figures on light-colored horses. The Pardoner and
          Parson confront in direct profile; the Poet faces three-quarters forward and the Knight
          three-quarters backward.</p>
        <p>The symmetry of these major figures in the fore-ground shows varying degrees of spiritual
          opposition. The Knight, unlike the Pardoner, can avoid a direct confrontation with the
          Parson—perhaps because the moral code of chivalry has some eternal validity. And the Poet,
          to the same degree, can avoid a direct confrontation with the Pardoner’s corrupt and
          worldly evil—perhaps because eternal poetic inspiration can make a heaven of hell and a
          hell of heaven. The Poet and the Knight, who frame the procession, confront even less
          directly. Their lines of sight would intersect even with the Host, midway, at 45° outward.
          Outward, toward the observer of the picture. The observer must make up his own mind which
          way to go. For the dichotomy of poetic inspiration vs. chivalric structure, there is no
          such simple choice as between Parson and Pardoner.</p>
        <p>The spiritual dichotomy represented by the Knight and the Poet extends to the front and
          rear halves of the procession. With the two female figures as keystones, many of the
          figures in the front half—those “above the common rank in life or attendants on those who
          were so” (E 524)—repress their energies into static systems, into set structures. Visual
          details suggest introversion and repression: the net over the Prioress’ horse, the
          Knight’s multilayered clothing, the eye contact within each pair of principal clergy.
          Blake’s text likewise suggests the static nature of language. Most of his tricky wording,
          his seeming praise in abstractions called into question by visual portraits, refers to
          these front-rank characters. When he refers to figures in the rear half of the procession,
          Blake usually makes words and picture agree. And these lower-rank characters include more
          whose energies are extroverted—whether they turn those energies toward constructive ends,
          like the Poet, or destructive ends, like the spraddle-legged Wife of Bath.</p>
        <p>The procession is a universe made up of active and passive halves, of characters who
          express or who repress energies. Blake does not pass moral judgment on either half.
          Although his Poet and Parson are outer-directed forces for “good,” they share their
          expressive half of the universe with the most dangerously seductive force for “evil,” the
          Wife of Bath. The repressive half of the procession does not include such extremities of
          moral blacks and whites. Except for Pardoner/Summoner, the pilgrims who follow set
          structures appear ambivalent, as moral shades of grey. But as if a newsprint photograph,
          the picture from a distance shows black-and-white as also grey. Even the sheer moral
          blackness of Pardoner/Summoner is balanced at a far enough distance by the bright white
          light of Parson/Plowman. Blake preaches the value of the expressive half. But both halves
          are always there, in every person’s mind, even Blake’s. “Man or humanity” 
            <hi rend="i">is</hi> the characters, all together.</p>
        <p>And no individual ought to pattern himself after any one ideal, after Plowman or Parson
          or Poet, or Jerusalem or Jesus Christ, without realizing that they are all manifestations
          of “man or humanity” (E 527). Blake says that all these pilgrims, both good and evil, both
          expressive and repressive, that all these “visions of the eternal attributes” (E 527) are
          happening simultaneously inside each man’s head. And if a person follows his poetic
          inspiration, he will be able to recognize and separate out bundles of characteristics from
          the forces writhing inside his psyche. He can separate and shape them into symbols, into
          characters, into dieties. These symbols must keep on interacting, then, because the human
          mind never stops moving, never accepts a static relationship among forces. Systems and
          religions, Blake would say, do try to pin down psychological forces into set patterns. But
          a dynamic bundle of characteristics, say a creation like Hamlet, will never offer final
          answers—just more and more questions as the play goes on.</p>
        <p>It is beyond my scope in this paper to try to label the dynamic binary relationship of
          every figure to every other one in “Canterbury Pilgrims.” For an example, though, let me
          begin with the Plowman, define his binary relationships to other figures, and show how in
          this particular picture Blake overcomes the limitations of time and space by means of a
          cell-like growth involving bisection and re-bisection of his symbols, his types.</p>
        <p>Blake states clearly that “the Plowman of Chaucer is Hercules in his supreme eternal
          state, divested of his spectrous shadow; which is the Miller” (E 527). Thus no single
          pilgrim is Hercules, the type of physical strength and courage; the Plowman and Miller
          together make up Hercules’ eternal type. The Plowman aspect of this pair can simply
          discard and ignore his spectre of brute strength and animal courage, the Miller—which
          spectre in turn, but simultaneously within this picture, sloughs off his own animal
          spectre, the Cook. But the Plowman must confront and keep at bay, ready to 
            <pb id="p13-189" n="189"/>
fight, another spectre: the type of sly self-serving courage
          rather than selfless benevolent courage, the Shipman. To call the Miller the spectre of
          “bad” strength and the Shipman the spectre of “bad” courage, and to say that the
          strong-and-courageous-and-good man must rid himself of both spectres, misleadingly sounds
          like a moral plan that an individual human being might follow, in linear time, whereas the
          types are eternal. But “the strong-and-courageous-and-good man” is perhaps as close as one
          can come, in words, to saying what Blake’s portrait of the Plowman shows to the eye.</p>
        <p>The Plowman also forms half of the complementary pair, Parson and Plowman. Like yin and
          yang, they together make up a larger whole, which could be termed benevolence (E 527). To
          emphasize this unification of dualities—dualities that might be labelled spiritual and
          physical benevolence—Blake portrays the brothers as old and young, encompassing in one
          pair two terms that in a logical system would be <corr type="emend">mutually</corr> exclusive (A and not-A, old and
          young). The Plowman and Parson together make up a symbol that keeps the mind in motion as
          does, say, the symbol Virgin Mother, likewise A and not-A. One’s knowledge of pregnancy
          makes the two halves mutually contradictory, like old and young in Blake’s picture. By
          poetic faith, however, one can understand such a symbol as one <hi rend="i">and</hi> as
          two, at the same time.</p>
        <p>This dual symbol of benevolence, Parson and Plowman, cannot remain static either. It
          balances visually with the Pardoner/Summoner pair, whose evil appearance makes them
          symbolize some quality that is mutually exclusive of benevolence, and whose
          position—especially the opposition between Pardoner and Parson—indicates a direct conflict
          between binary oppositions. What do they represent, as the opposite of benevolence?
          Perhaps avarice, the topic of the Pardoner’s Tale? It is with good reason that Blake turns
          away from the limitations of verbal abstraction, to communicate visually. His portrayals
          of Pardoner and Summoner call up a richer and exacter reproduction of Blake’s intentions
          than such words as “avarice” or “absence of benevolence” or “pure evil” ever could.</p>
        <p>The cell bisects and doubles itself once again, but all within the same space and time of
          this picture. The Pardoner/Summoner combines with Monk/Friar, such that Pardoner/Summoner
          seems the discarded spectrous shadow of the whole bundle Pardoner/Summoner/Monk/Friar.
          What verbal label could cover the visual group of avaricious clergymen, two of them
          hypocritical and two overt? Simultaneously, in the rear half of the procession, the
          Parson/Plowman joins forces with Doctor/Lawyer, to balance with the four churchmen ahead.
          The Doctor and Lawyer are somewhat benevolent in that their professions are
          outward-directed, but unlike Parson and Plowman they do not help people for selfless
          reasons.</p>
        <p>The symbolism cannot keep bisecting neatly. That last eightsome was already getting
          blurry—getting out of microscope range, so to speak. I started with the Plowman and
          bisected his symbolism both inward (to the Hercules he “was” before he eliminated his
          spectre) and outward (to what he “becomes” in the procession). Could one do the same,
          starting with any pilgrim chosen at random? No, because the pilgrimage would then
          represent a universe without chaos. The mind of “man or humanity” pairs many, but not all,
          sets of stimuli in order to understand them. Sometimes, misled, the mind believes it must
          choose logically between the opposite poles it perceives, and eliminate Urizenically one
          or the other. “Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims” shows that even though some pairs may
          temporarily appear to cancel out each other, that still all the oppositions and all the
          other binary relationships and even all the odds and ends of perception keep on happening.
          All possibilities remain. All possibilities remain in motion. Nothing was delivered. And
          the Reeve and the bristling black dog go their snarling ways.</p>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p13-190" n="190" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
