<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>13.4.mla</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">MLA Seminar</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1980</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">13.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Joe Zimmerman</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Betsy Bowden</name>
              <name>Wayne Glausser</name>
              <name>Robert Sternbach</name>
              <name>Leslie Tannenbaum</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_13">
    <body>
      <pb id="p13-205" n="205"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-13-4-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">NEWSLETTER</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">MLA SEMINAR</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>W. J. T. Mitchell was discussion leader of the special session on Blake at the annual MLA meeting
in San Francisco this past December. He reports:</p>
          <p>The basic idea of this year’s seminar was to explore Blake’s ideas about language, with
particular emphasis on his notions of writing, both as a material craft and as a symbolic activity. A
secondary purpose was to bring Blake’s thought into contact with post-structuralist theories of language,
particularly Jacques Derrida’s concept of “writing” in the extended sense (mental writing, pictograms,
ideograms, imprints, tracks, traces, and “marks”). Peggy Meyer Sherry of the German Department at Princeton
seemed most explicitly indebted to the Derridean vocabulary, discussing the metaphors of the human body as
writing surface and as alphabetic form in <hi rend="i">The Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, and
showing by references to Blake’s Notebook, how and why the pictorial figures in <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>
embody calligraphic forms. Stephen Behrendt of the English Department at Elizabethtown College, Elizabethtown,
Pennsylvania, discussed Blake’s notion of a language of art (primarily pictorial) in terms of the
problematic notions of original and copy, and in relations to the revisions in Blake’s series of pictures on
the theme of the “Plague.” Nelson Hilton of the English Department at the University of Georgia enriched our
sense of “Blake’s Polysemous Words” with a series of meditations on key word clusters (e.g. vale, veil,
vile, evil) that are the focus of Blake’s phonetic and typographic playfulness. Hilton’s presentation
included a textual emendation to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (worship/warship) that David Erdman promises to
include in the new revised edition. David Herrstrom of Roosevelt, New Jersey, presented what he called a
“literal” account of Blake’s ideas on writing, stressing Blake’s concern with the material signifier
(calligraphic or pictorial) in the context of his understanding of the incarnation. Herrstrom illustrated his
presentation with a close analysis of verbal and pictorial symbolism in the Laocoön engraving. Finally,
Ronald Paulson of the Yale English Department stepped outside the circle of Blake studies to bring us news of
other Romantic poet-painters who were concerned with problems in language and writing. Paulson’s
presentation focused on the way emblems, marks, “graffitti,” and other verbal elaborations (titles,
accompanying poems) tend to <hi rend="i">suppress</hi> meaning in the work of landscape artists like Turner
and Constable, in contrast to the augmenting and disseminating power of verbal-pictorial interactions in
Blake.</p>
          <p>It will come as no surprise to anyone familiar with the genre of reportage on MLA Seminars that
the session this year was a stunning success. All questions were discussed fully, and with the most rigorous
respect for logic and rules of evidence, all the basic problems were solved, and all had a chance to speak
their minds. The only sour note occurred when the participants rejected the Discussion Leader’s proposal to
conclude with a rousing chorus of “And did those feet. . . . ” W. J. T. MITCHELL, DEPARTMENT OF ENGLISH,
UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
