<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.1.dilworth</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake’s Argument with Newberry in “Laughing Song”</title>
        <author n="Dilworth">Thomas Dilworth</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1980</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <name>Joe Zimmerman</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Thomas Dilworth</name>
              <name>Judy Egerton</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Edward Strickland</name>
              <name>Ruthven Todd</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1980"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
	<pb id="p14-36" n="36"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-1-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">BLAKE’S ARGUMENT WITH NEWBERRY IN “LAUGHING SONG”</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">By</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Thomas</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Dilworth</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Although David Erdman claims that “Laughing Song” in <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> owes
much to Anna Barbauld’s <hi rend="i">Hymns in Prose for Children</hi> (1781), and David Bindman has
discovered a visual influence on Blake’s illumination for “Laughing Song,” no specific literary source or
influence has been proposed for Blake’s lyric.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">1</ref> Certain affinities in form and content suggest, however, that in literature for children
Blake’s song does have a prototype—a short lyric entitled “How to Laugh,” which appears in Newbery’s 
<hi rend="i">A Pretty Book for Children</hi> (1761) and <hi rend="i">A Collection of Pretty Poems</hi> (1770).
<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet against Empire</hi> (Princeton, 1969), p.
124. In <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist</hi> (Oxford, 1977), pp. 59-60, Bindman discusses the probable
influence on Blake of Stothard’s illustration for “Drinking Song” in Joseph Ritson’s <hi rend="i">English
Songs</hi> (1783). Blake executed engravings after Stothard for this book.</note></p>
          <p>John Newbery (1713-1767) wrote, printed, and published some of the best and most beautifully
bound books produced for children during the eighteenth century. His collections of rhymes are relatively free
of the repressive moral and religious indoctrination characteristic of the vast majority of books for children
then in print. For this reason, he has been seen as a possible influence on Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">2</ref> At the very least, Newbery’s work can be said to stand
largely outside the implied criticism, in <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, of traditional and
contemporary literature for children. His rhyme “How to Laugh” seems a special case, however, in that it is
Newbery’s only lyric to which Blake specifically alludes, and with which he apparently takes issue. 
<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">William Blake, his Philosophy and Symbols</hi> (New
York, 1924), p. 42.</note></p>
          <p>The verbal and conceptual similarities between Blake’s “Laughing Song” and Newbery’s “How to
Laugh” are striking. Newbery’s four-line rhyme concerns human laughter as an expression of Nature in
relation to other of Nature’s modes of expression:
<q>
Nature a thousand Ways complains,<lb/>
A thousand Words express her Pains:<lb/>
But for her Laughter has but three.<lb/>
And very small ones, Ha, Ha, He.
</q>
Blake’s subject is the same, and he uses the same laughing sounds to conclude the last two of his three
            <corr type="emend">stanzas.</corr></p>
          <p>But Blake contradicts the assertion in Newbery’s rhyme that Nature has only “three
words”—“and very small ones”—to express happiness, whereas her numerous other sounds complain and express
pain. In Blake’s lyric, expressions of pain are altogether absent. And instead of personifying nature as a
whole, Blake humanizes her various aspects. Parts of the landscape, together with birds, grasshoppers, and
even the air, laugh independently though in harmony with man’s own preverbal “Ha, Ha, He”:
<q>
When the green woods laugh, with the voice of joy<lb/>
And the dimpling stream runs laughing by,<lb/>
When the air does laugh with our merry wit,<lb/>
And the green hill laughs with the noise of it.<lb/>
<lb/>
When the meadows laugh with lively green<lb/>
And the grasshopper laughs in the merry scene,<lb/>
When Mary and Susan and Emily,<lb/>
With their sweet round mouths sing Ha, Ha, He.<lb/>
<lb/>
When the painted birds laugh in the shade<lb/>
Where our table with cherries and nuts is spread<lb/>
Come live &amp; be merry and join with me,<lb/>
To sing the sweet chorus of Ha, Ha, He.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David Erdman
(New York, 1970), p. 11. The subsequent quotation from Blake is also from this edition.</note></q>
Joyful innocence is here shared equally by man and by nature in its broad diversity and particularity. This is
not mere personification or pathetic fallacy, but a clarity of vision in which, as Blake later put it, “All
Human Forms” are “identified even Tree. Metal Earth &amp; Stone” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> Ch. 4, pl.
99:57).</p>
          <p>The whole of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> implies the metaphysical equality and communion
of man, nature, and the divine. But there is more human expression on the part of nature in “Laughing Song”
than in all the rest of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n9" type="note">4</ref> That makes “Laughing Song” a focal point in the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> for
the
<pb id="p14-37" n="37"/>
visionary identification of “Human Forms” in nature. The poem is exceptional in this regard probably because
it was conceived and written as an antithesis or corrective to Newbery’s “How to Laugh,” which excludes
nature from full and equal participation in human life. <note id="n9"><hi rend="s">4</hi> In “Night,” the moon
smiles, and a lion speaks. In “A Dream,” an emmet and glow worm speak. In “Spring,” birds delight—which may
or may not be a humanization.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
