<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.1.todd</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">“Poisonous Blues” and Other Pigments</title>
        <author n="Todd">Ruthven Todd</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1980</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <name>Joe Zimmerman</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Thomas Dilworth</name>
              <name>Judy Egerton</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Edward Strickland</name>
              <name>Ruthven Todd</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1980"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <pb id="p14-31" n="31"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-1-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">“POISONOUS BLUES,” AND OTHER PIGMENTS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">By</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Ruthven</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Todd</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>NOTE: Several years ago, in <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 28, we published a short piece by
Robert M. Ryan on Blake’s phrase “poisonous blue,” concerning some of the chemical properties of the
painter’s pigment “prussian blue.” Soon we received a letter from Ruthven Todd giving us his preliminary
thoughts on the matter and promising, as Ruthven’s letters always did, further thoughts in publishable form.
After his death in 1979, the following unfinished draft was found among his papers. THE EDITORS.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">DRAFT 28 DE NOVIEMBRE DE 1974</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>As a consistent contributor to “Minute Particulars” I feel somewhat abashed in querying or even
contradicting any other contributor, so I hope that Robert M. Ryan will accept my apologies in advance.</p>
          <p>For a man whose principal occupation has been that of a writer, I have spent a possibly
unreasonable amount of my life experimenting with and using the tools and materials of the graphic artist.
Abetted by my friends, particularly S. W. Hayter, Joan Miró, Fred Becker and the late Harry Hoehn, I have
engraved and etched, learning how to handle a burin and how to behave with acids, for more years than I like
to recall. Most of my interest in the techniques having been historical, I had never, until the spring of 1974
(when I made some experiments with Harvey Breverman and his associates at Buffalo) tried zinc or any other
etchable material, such as magnesium or iron. So my experience practically, and visually, can be said to be
that of a worker in copper.</p>
          <p>The basic mordant used in the biting of copper is Nitric acid (HNO<hi rend="s">3</hi>), prepared
as follows, according to that standard work, S. W. Hayter, <hi rend="i">New Ways of Gravure</hi>, Oxford
University Press, London, New York, Toronto, 1966, p. 57: “1 part nitric acid to 2 parts water. There should
be some copper in the solution or the acid will not bite regularly. Some old acid may be added; or a copper
penny dropped in for a few minutes until the acid is coloured blue. Nitric acid reacts with copper to produce
bubbles of nitric oxide gas.”</p>
          <p>The virulence of this brilliant blue liquid, from which the fumes curl off, as the copper is
bitten, in yellowish-brown purlings, has always suggested to me that this was the “poisonous blue” with which
“They stain’d him” on Plate 65 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> I knew that the acid destroyed clothing
easily and that my skin, over-dipped in the stuff, and inadequately washed, peeled off in vegetative or
seaweed-like strips of autumnal coloring. I also knew that the fumes hurt my breathing during the long bitings
which I used when experimenting with Joan Miró.</p>
          <p>Now it seems to me that, firstly, since I will not live forever, and, secondly, the information
should be immediately available, I should go beyond the assumption which I had, and give away whatever
information I have at hand or can remember.</p>
          <p>For a start, and in support of my belief that nitric acid was, indeed, the “poisonous blue,” I
have looked up and quote from W. F. von Oettingen, M. D., Ph. D., <hi rend="i">Poisoning A Guide to Clinical
Diagnosis and Treatment</hi>, Second Edition, W. B. Saunders Co., Philadelphia, London, 1963, p. 454: “Nitric
acid is a clear colorless, fuming, corrosive liquid, which upon contact with air and exposure to light turns
yellow to brown-red because of formation of nitrogen oxide. [This, of course, makes no allowance for the
bluing action of copper]. The reagent grade nitric acid [used by etchers] contains 68 to 70 per cent and the
‘diluted’ nitric acid, 10 per cent of nitric acid. Nitric acid is used in many industries and trades and
in medicine as a caustic agent. Its contact with the skin causes yellow discoloration (xanthoprotein
reaction), very painful inflammation, blisters, necroses, and gangrene. Prolonged exposure to the fumes of
nitric acid causes discoloration and corrosion of the teeth. Splashes in the eye cause severe conjunctivitis,
palpebral edema, ulceration of the conjunctiva and cornea, and subsequently turbidity of the latter. The
inhalation of the fumes causes more or less severe irritation of the upper respiratory tract.”</p>
          <p>While “There is no chronic copper poisoning analogous to that of lead,” it should be remembered
that copper, particularly in its various combinations with other substances, is also a poison. When I was
young and the modern pesticides or parasiticides had not yet appeared, those who were unlucky enough to be
attacked by the crab louse, <hi rend="i">Phthirus pubis</hi> (which, according to <hi rend="i">The Merck
Manual</hi>, Twelfth Edition, Rahway, N. J., 1972, p. 1457, <hi rend="i">is</hi> acquirable “from such objects
as toilet seats, clothing, and bedclothes”) used to go to a chemist’s and buy, for a few pence, a jar of
“blue ointment” with which to rout the invaders. This was Cupric Sulfate, also known as copper sulfate, blue
vitriol and blue stone, and commonly understood to be a solution of copper in dilute sulfuric acid. While it
is no longer listed as a cure for crabs, it still retains its place in <hi rend="i">United States Dispensatory
and Physicians’ Pharmacology</hi>, 26th Edition, J. B. Lippincott Co., Philadelphia &amp; Toronto, 1967, p.
343, for, among other uses, its value in abolishing algae from swimming pools.</p>
          <p>I think I have shown that copper, in combination with acids, is not only blue but also poisonous.
I could, with access to a larger library than I have here in Spain, probably extend the matter, with gruesome
details, but feel that to do so would be to attempt to blue the Mediterranean. Further, I cannot think of any
liquid blue capable of staining
<pb id="p14-32" n="32"/>
and also leaving the impression of vegetation, in the peeling strands of yellow-grown skin, which Blake could
have meant except the nitric acid, colored with copper, which he used all his working life.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>II</title>
            </head>
            <p>By chance it happens that the other blues, with two exceptions, which could have been known to
Blake are reasonably innocuous. In this part, I am going to have to rely very largely upon that most important
book, Rosamond D. Harley, <hi rend="i">Artists’ Pigments c. 1600-1835 A Study in English Documentary
Sources</hi>, London, Butterworths, 1970, and I am going to steal from it in the most unashamed way since it
seems that my effort to say how important it is, in <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 4 (August 1970), has
passed unnoticed. All references to Harley are, unless specified as coming from personal correspondence, to
this book.</p>
            <p>To dispose, first of all, of the matter of Prussian Blue, I am going to give Dr. Harley’s
entry on this from her book, pp. 65-68. [In all my quotations from Rosamond Harley and, later, Geoffrey
Grigson, I have omitted their references to their sources, not only because such an action saves space, but
also because I think that students should also investigate them, as nobody knows what peripheral material may
prove to be pertinent.]</p>
			<q>
Prussian blue, potassium ferric ferrocyanide, has been described as ‘the first of the artificial pigments
with a known history and an established date of preparation’.<hi rend="s">97</hi> However, the idea that a
definite date may be associated with it may be a modern misconception. It is true that the circumstances of
its accidental discovery were reported by Stahl some years after the event and that his account has been
referred to many times since, but it is noticeable that throughout the period up to 1835 every writer who
mentions any date in connection with the pigment states that it was discovered <hi rend="i">circa</hi> 1710,
whereas the date, 1704, given by so many later writers was not mentioned until the late nineteenth century.
Earlier writers based the date on the knowledge that the pigment had been advertised for sale in Berlin in
1710 and on the words of the German chemist, Stahl, whose account of the discovery was printed in 1731. He
wrote of it as occurring by chance twenty years previously ‘<hi rend="i">ante quatuor forte lustra</hi>’
(one <hi rend="i">lustrum</hi> being a period of five years). Unfortunately, nineteenth-century and
twentieth-century writers who quote the date 1704 fail to state the source on which their information is
based, and, in the absence of new evidence, any enquiry into the date of the discovery must begin with an
examination of the remainder of Stahl’s account: he mentions two people, Diesbach the colour-maker who made
the discovery and Dippel the alchemist who supplied some of the raw materials, and he states that both were
resident in Berlin. Dippel did not live there permanently, however; an eighteenth-century biography contains
the information that just before 1704 he was in Giessen and Darmstadt, and, after some time, he went to
Berlin. From there he went to Frankfurt-am-Main and then moved on to Holland at the end of 1707.<hi
rend="s">98</hi> This evidence suggests that the discovery of Prussian blue could have been made at any time
between 1704 and 1707. A modern authority states that Dippel is known to have been practising chemistry in
Berlin in 1705.<hi rend="s">39</hi><lb/>
<lb/>
Stahl’s account of Prussian blue was written because the fortuitous nature of its discovery appealed to him.
The chance manufacture of the pigment resulted indirectly from Dippel’s production of an animal oil which
was used medicinally; in the purification process the oil was distilled over some potash which was then
treated as waste. Diesbach, who used to make Florence lake from cochineal, alum, English vitriol (ferrous
sulphate) and a fixed alkali, ran short of alkali and asked Dippel for some of the potash which he saw had
been thrown away. He was allowed to use it, and, after he had proceeded by his usual method, the lake appeared
to be very pale. When he attempted to concentrate it, it turned purple and then deep blue. Diesbach returned
to Dippel for an explanation and was told that the potash was tainted with animal matter. Stahl’s account
concludes with the comment that for some considerable time the pigment was made only in Berlin.<hi
rend="s">100</hi><lb/>
<lb/>
Details of the manufacturing process were kept secret until 1724, when an account was sent from Germany to
Woodward in England who allowed it to be published in <hi rend="i">Philosophical Transactions.</hi> The
instructions were lengthy, but the method can be summarised as follows. To an alkali calcined with bullock’s
blood, dissolved and brought to boiling point, a solution of alum and ferrous sulphate was added while also
boiling. During the effervescence which followed the mixture turned green, and, after it had been allowed to
stand, it was strained. The residual greenish precipitate turned blue as soon as spirit of salt (hydrochloric
acid) was poured on it. The pigment was then left to stand and was washed several times with pure water the
next day, after which it was filtered and dried under gentle heat.<hi rend="s">101</hi> Woodward’s
communication was written in Latin and it doubtless became common knowledge quite quickly. By the 1730s
manufacture of Prussian blue was widespread, as Shaw states in his <hi rend="i">Chemical Lectures</hi>, which
contain manufacturing instructions in English: ‘The Method of making this Prussian Blue in perfection, has
been held and purchased as a very valuable Secret, both in England, Germany and elsewhere; but it is now got
into several hands.’<hi rend="s">102</hi> No evidence has been found concerning the early manufacture of the
pigment in England, nor has it been possible to verify statements concerning early manufacture which appear in
nineteenth-century and twentieth-century works. For example, a number of modern writers give the impression
that a colour-maker named Wilkinson was the first English manufacturer and that Wilkinson’s
<pb id="p14-33" n="33"/>
blue became a synonym for Prussian blue. The information can be traced back to Hurst writing in the late
nineteenth century, but he merely states that Wilkinson developed the pigment.<hi rend="s">103</hi> Literary
sources of the eighteenth century contain no evidence that the name Wilkinson’s blue was ever used by
artists. Colour names listed by Field in the nineteenth century are Berlin blue, Parisian blue and cyanide of
iron. The origin of the first and last is obvious, and the second can be explained by the fact that a good
quality blue was made in Paris. During the second half of the eighteenth century, considerable research was
undertaken by French chemists in order to analyse the pigment and extend its use to the dyeing industry.<hi
rend="s">104</hi><lb/>
<lb/>
Although Prussian blue was at one time used as a dye, it must be emphasised that it was originally advertised
in 1710 as a pigment for artists’ use. Following a summary of the limitations of other available blues, the
notice in <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">Miscellanea Berolinensia</hi></corr> contained the announcement that the new blue which had
been discovered a few years previously had been subjected to accurate tests. It was said to be absolutely
durable in either oil or water colour and totally unaffected by nitric acid, fire or exposure to air. It could
be ground to an impalpable powder and easily tempered with a knife, so it was suitable for miniature painters
and oil painters alike; in addition, its softness meant that it would brush out well and mix easily with any
other colour. Its versatility was such that, at full saturation, it was useful in painting shadows and, when
thinned, it could be used as a lighter and brighter colour without any need for tinting with white. A great
recommendation was its non-poisonous quality; it was said to be made from a kind of sugar so that it was
edible, which meant that beginners could safely lick their brushes as they were liable to do. Finally, its
price was attractive, being scarcely one-tenth that of ultramarine.<hi rend="s">105</hi><lb/>
<lb/>
Following the extravagant claims of the original manufacturer, one might expect the pigment to have been
acclaimed immediately by artists, but such was not the case. Dossie states that anyone desiring permanent
Prussian blue should prepare it himself instead of buying the pigment from a shop, because the commercial sort
varied in strength and was unreliable. He further states that it can be used in all techniques except enamel,
apparently overlooking fresco, a technique for which it is unsuitable. Quite possibly English painters were
not particularly concerned with fresco, but Dayes mentions that Prussian blue is liable to be destroyed by
alkali and that its colour is extracted by lime. Although no very early references to the uses of the oil
colour in England have been found, it appears to have been well established by the middle of the eighteenth
century, and painters in oils were well satisfied with the colour. Bardwell states that it ‘is a very fine
Blue and a kind working Colour’, adding only the reservation that it should not be used alone in painting
flesh. Nevertheless, he does not give <corr type="emend">it</corr> such high praise as ultramarine, 
and it was not until the second half
of the eighteenth century that Prussian blue came to be the most important oil colour blue, as in Williams’
<hi rend="i">Mechanic of Oil Colours</hi> where it is the only blue mentioned. The colour was reasonably
priced, so amateurs used it as well as professionals, although not always without difficulty. It was probably
no coincidence that a writer chose Prussian blue, a strongly staining colour, as an example in describing the
difficulties to which self-taught amateurs were prone: ‘ . . . a bladder of Prussian blue bursts over
one’s arm, and paints one’s fingers and clothes.’<hi rend="s">106</hi><lb/>
<lb/>
In water-colour painting Prussian blue was held in distrust for a considerable time. It appears somewhat as an
afterthought in Smith’s <hi rend="i">Method of Painting in Water Colours</hi>, where ultramarine is
recommended for the best painting, otherwise smalt ‘or Prussian-Blue will do as well’. In <hi rend="i">The
Art of Drawing</hi>, 1731, the colour is said to be difficult to use because of its oily quality. Water
colours were kept in shells ready for use, and it appears that whenever a wet pencil was applied to Prussian
blue in the shell the colour went yellow where the water ran round the edge, suggesting therefore that the
pigment was poorly manufactured at that time. Naturally, the presence of yellow was unwelcome because it
accentuated the tendency towards green which is a natural characteristic of Prussian blue. By the end of the
eighteenth century its manufacture must have improved, because Payne states that it is a good colour for
miniature painting and that no other blue can equal its strength and transparency. Even so, there were many
complaints that it did not flow freely and some writers, including Field, cast doubts on its permanence.
</q>
            <p>I hope that this, rather lengthy, quotation will clear things up a bit. [Over the years, I,
myself an amateur given to pointing my brush (or <hi rend="i">pencil</hi> as it would have been called in the
18th Century), with my tongue and lips, must have ingested a monstrous amount of Prussian Blue without real
hurt.]</p>
            <p>My immediate feeling, not having access to the translation of Scheele’s 
<hi rend="i">Essays</hi> by Thomas Beddoes (father of the author of <hi rend="i">Death’s Jest Book</hi>, is that
there is a general chemical mix-up which has led Robert M. Ryan astray, and that the sorting of matters
requires further reference to Scheele’s essays in German and in the modern translation by L. Dobbin, London,
1931, as well as the <hi rend="i">Encyclopédie</hi>, in French. It should be mentioned that the Swedish
Scheele, investigating the properties of arsenic, did discover a green, later to be refined as Emerald Green,
of copper arsenite. This discovery was made in 1775, but its composition is “made known because, as Scheele
explained in 1777 in a letter to another scientist, he felt that potential users should be
<pb id="p14-34" n="34"/>
warned of its highly poisonous nature, and, in addition, he wished to prevent anyone else claiming credit for
the discovery,” Harley, pp. 75-76. Ralph Mayer, whose <hi rend="i">The Artist’s Handbook</hi>, Third
Edition, The Viking Press, New York, 1970, is invaluable in many ways, is slightly untrustworthy on the
history of pigments, during the period with which we are concerned, as are the authors of another necessary
book, Rutherford J. Gettens &amp; George L. Stout, <hi rend="i">Painting Materials A Short Encyclopaedia</hi>,
Dover, New York, 1966, but both mention the more widespread use of copper acetoarsenite, Emerald Green,
probably first produced commercially in Schweinfurt in 1914, as a popular insecticide, Paris Green, which was
in use, to my personal knowledge, into the 1940s, and it still retains an important place in von Oettingen,
<hi rend="i">op. cit.</hi>, p. 242, as well as, still a pigment, in the newspapers recording the misfortunes
of children eating the flaking paint in old houses.</p>
            <p>One thing that is certain is that Prussian Blue has nothing whatever to do with the Zyklon-B
used at Auschwitz or the cyanide-tablets formerly employed in certain American states. There is no possible
excuse for giving a good color a bad name, Junkers, Berlin, Prussian, and condemning it with no trial or
reason, as Robert M. Ryan has done in <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 7 (Spring 1974), 87-89. [If I can
digress for a moment, I would like to say that whenever I have a brilliant idea, I note it down and then spend
a week or two in playing the Devil’s Advocate and trying to tear it to pieces. If it stands up to my vicious
attacks, I assume that, even if I am wrong, it is worth exposing to the blasts of my peers. A plenitude of
references <hi rend="i">is</hi> too persuasive, and, even though the theory is false, can lead others
astray.]</p>
            <p>Now, having stated my tentative idea that the “poisonous blue” was merely the nitric acid with
which Blake bit his copperplates, and having done my best, thanks to Dr. Harley, to show the innocence of
Prussian Blue, I feel that I should list the various blues, with some note of their toxicity, which were
available to William Blake. In doing this I draw not only upon Dr. Harley’s book but also upon personal
correspondence with her. I should remark here that Woad is kept for a third section of these notes. It had a
more symbolical than actual pigmentary meaning by the end of the 18th Century.</p>
            <p>[Todd’s typescript leaves off here.]</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
