<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.1.minnick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="index">Index to Volume 12</title>
		<author n="Minnick">Thomas L. Minnick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1980</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <name>Joe Zimmerman</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Thomas Dilworth</name>
              <name>Judy Egerton</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Edward Strickland</name>
              <name>Ruthven Todd</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1980"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <pb id="p14-i" n="i"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-1-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="main">BLAKE/AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY INDEX TO VOLUME XII</title>
        </head>
        <byline>Compiled by <docAuthor>Thomas L. <name>Minnick</name>,</docAuthor> The Ohio State
University</byline>
		<q>
The first number in the reference is the whole number of the issue (#45-48); the second is the page within the
issue. Thus 47: 193 signifies whole number 47, page 193.
</q>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>AUTHORS</title>
          </head>
          <p>Bentley, E. B., Vision in Fiction: Two Novels About William Blake, 47:209-210.</p>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr., Echoes of Blake’s Grave Designs in 1838, 47:207-209.</p>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr., “The Eternal Wheels of Intellect”: Dissertations on William Blake,
48:224-243.</p>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr., The First Printed Reference to the Publication of <hi rend="i">Job</hi>:
Disraeli (?) in <hi rend="i">The Star Chamber</hi> (1826), 45:69-70.</p>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr., “New” Blake Engravings after Blake’s Designs, 1837, 1859, 1861,
47:204.</p>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr., The Selling of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> Designs in the
1870s, 45:70-71.</p>
          <p>Bindman, David, A New Blake Drawing in the Boston Museum of Fine Art, 47:205-206.</p>
          <p>Bouwer, Izak, and Paul McNally, “The Mental Traveller”: Man’s Eternal Journey, 47:184-192.</p>
          <p>Butlin, Martin, An Illustration to Robert Bage, 47:202.</p>
          <p>Cheskin, Arnold, The Echoing Greenhorn: Blake as Hebraist, 47:178-183.</p>
          <p>Clarke, Mary, The Job Ballet, 45:18-25.</p>
          <p>Deck, Raymond H., Jr., Another Early Printing of Blake’s “Night,” 45:69.</p>
          <p>Deck, Raymond H., Jr., “Blake, William” in the <hi rend="i">New American Cyclopedia</hi> (1861),
45:68-69.</p>
          <p>Dörrbecker, Detlef W., and Marta Slowiková, Some Minor Additions to Bentley’s “Blake Among
the Slavs,” 47:198.</p>
          <p>Dörrbecker, Detlef W., see also Minnick, Thomas L.</p>
          <p>England, Martha W., rev. of Davie, 47:215-217.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V., <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: New Text for Pages 5, 6, &amp; 7, Night the
First, 46:96-99.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V., Night the Seventh: The Editorial Problem, 46:135-139.</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N., Blake in the Marketplace, 1976-77, 45:26-38.</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N., The Figure in the Carpet: Blake’s Engravings in Salzmann’s 
<hi rend="i">Elements of Morality</hi>, 45:10-14.</p>
          <p>Fine, Ruth E., rev. of Butlin and Tate Gallery Exhibition, 45:42-55.</p>
          <p>Franson, J. Karl, The Serpent-Driving Female’s in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 4,
47:164-177.</p>
          <p>Frost, Everett C., rev. of <hi rend="i">The Story of Job</hi> (ballet), 46:155-158.</p>
          <p>Gabriella, Katharyn R., Los’s Visit [poem], 48:266.</p>
          <p>Graziano, Frank, The Last Judgement [poem], 45:40-41.</p>
          <p>Hagstrum, Jean H., rev. of Bindman, 45:64-67.</p>
          <p>Harding, Gunnar, trans. from the Swedish by Gunnel Tottie, Two Poems, 45:39-40.</p>
          <p>Heppner, Christopher, Another <hi rend="i">Cumberland Bibliography Addendum</hi>, 48:261-262.</p>
          <p>Heppner, Christopher, Another “New” Blake Engraving: More About Blake &amp; William Nicholson,
47:193-197.</p>
          <p>Heppner, Christopher, Blake and <hi rend="i">The Seaman’s Recorder</hi>: The Letter and the
Spirit in a Problem of Attribution, 45:15-17.</p>
          <p>Hilton, Nelson, A Note on Cowper and A Poison Tree, 47:203.</p>
          <p>Hilton, Nelson, The Sweet Science of Atmospheres in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>,
46:80-86.</p>
          <p>Hoagwood, Terence Allan, <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and “The Philosophick Cabbala,”
46:87-90.</p>
          <p>Irwin, David, rev. of Burke, 47:212-214.</p>
          <p>James, G. Ingli, Some Not-So-Familiar Visionary Heads, 48:244-249.</p>
          <p>Johnson, Mary Lynn, and Brian Wilkie, The Spectrous Embrace in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>,
VIIa, 46:100-105.</p>
          <p>Kilgore, John, The Order of Nights VIIa and VIIb in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>,
46:107-113.</p>
          <p>Kilgore, John, rev. of Ostriker, 48:268-270.</p>
          <p>La Belle, Jenijoy, Blake and Morland: The First State of “The Industrious Cottager,”
48:258-261.</p>
          <p>Lefebvre, Mark S., A Note on the Structural Necessity of Night VIIb, 46:134.</p>
          <p>Lincoln, Andrew, <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: The Text of Pages 5, 6, &amp; 7, Night the
First, 46:91-95.</p>
          <p>Lincoln, Andrew, rev. of Wilkie and Johnson, 48:264-266.</p>
          <p>Lincoln, Andrew, The Revision of the Seventh and Eighth Nights of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>, 46:115-133.</p>
          <p>Magno, Cettina, <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> for Italy, 46:140-141.</p>
          <p>McNally, Paul, see Bouwer, Izak.</p>
          <p>Mellor, Anne K., rev. of Kroeber and Walling, 48:267-268.</p>
          <p>Minnick, Thomas L., with the assistance of Detlef W. Dörrbecker, A Checklist of Recent Blake
Scholarship, 46:142-149.</p>
          <p>Napora, Joe, Trickster’s Song [poem], 45:39.</p>
          <p>Nurmi, Martin K., rev. of Howard and Franson, 45:56-57.</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D., Mr. Blake’s Spectacles, at the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge [poem],
45:39.</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D., rev. of Altick, 48:271-273.</p>
          <p>Peattie, R. W., William Michael Rossetti’s Aldine Edition of Blake, 45:4-9.</p>
          <p>Shroyer, R. J., Mr. Jacko “Knows What Riding Is” in 1785: Dating Blake’s <hi rend="i">Island in
the Moon</hi>, 48:250-256.</p>
          <p>Slowiková, Marta, see Dörrbecker, Detlef W.</p>
          <p>Spencer, Jeffry, rev. of Marqusee, 46:154.</p>
          <p>Tillotson, Marcia, rev. of Wollstonecraft, Wardle, and Tomalin [rev. art.], 45:58-64.</p>
          <p>Wark, Robert R., rev. of Paley, 47:211-212.</p>
          <p>Watarai, Kazumitsu, A Bibliography of William Blake in Japan, 1969-1977, 47:198-201.</p>
          <p>Weber, Dwight E., William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>: A Poem
Based on Doubt, 47:203-204.</p>
          <p>Wilkie, Brian, see Johnson, Mary Lynn.</p>
          <p>Wilton, Andrew, rev. of Lister, 46:150-154.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>TITLES</title>
          </head>
          <p>Another <hi rend="i">Cumberland Bibliography</hi> Addendum, 48:261-252.</p>
          <p>Another Early Printing of Blake’s “Night,” 45:69.</p>
          <p>Another “New” Blake Engraving: More About Blake &amp; William Nicholson, 47:193-197.</p>
          <p>A Bibliography of William Blake in Japan, 1969-1977, 47:198-201.</p>
          <p>Blake and Morland: The First State of “The Industrious Cottager,” 48:258-261.</p>
          <p>Blake and <hi rend="i">The Seaman’s Recorder</hi>: The Letter and the Spirit in a Problem of
Attribution, 45:15-17.</p>
          <p>Blake in the Marketplace, 1976-77, 45:26-38.</p>
          <p>“Blake, William” in the <hi rend="i">New American Cyclopedia</hi> (1861), 45:68-69.</p>
          <p>A Checklist of Recent Blake Scholarship, 46:142-149.</p>
          <p>Echoes of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> Designs in 1838, 47:207-209.</p>
          <p>The Echoing Greenhorn: Blake as Hebraist, 47:178-183.</p>
          <p>“The Eternal Wheels of Intellect”: Dissertations on William Blake, 48:224-243.</p>
          <p>The Figure in the Carpet: Blake’s Engravings in Salzmann’s <hi rend="i">Elements of
Morality</hi>, 45:10-14.</p>
          <p>The First Printed Reference to the Publication of <hi rend="i">Job</hi>: Disraeli (?) in 
<hi rend="i">The Star Chamber</hi> (1826), 45:69-70.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and “The Philosophick Cabbala,” 46:87-90.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> for Italy, 46:140-141.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: New Text for Pages 5, 6, &amp; 7, Night the First, 46:96-99.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: The Text of Pages 5, 6, &amp; 7, Night the First, 46:91-95.</p>
          <p>An Illustration to Robert Bage, 47:202.</p>
          <p>The Job Ballet, 45:18-25.</p>
          <p>The Last Judgement [poem], 45:40-41.</p>
          <p>Los’s Visit [poem], 48:266.</p>
          <p>“The Mental Traveller”: Man’s Eternal Journey, 47:184-192.</p>
          <p>Mr. Blake’s Spectacles, at the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge [poem], 45:39.</p>
          <p>Mr. Jacko “Knows What Riding Is” in 1785: Dating Blake’s <hi rend="i">Island in the Moon</hi>,
48:250-256.</p>
          <p>A New Blake Drawing in the Boston Museum of Fine Art, 47:205-206.</p>
          <p>“New” Blake Engravings after Blake’s Designs, 1837, 1859, 1861, 47:204.</p>
          <p>Night the Seventh: The Editorial Problem, 46:135-139.</p>
          <p>A Note on Cowper and A Poison Tree, 47:203.</p>
          <p>A Note on the Structural Necessity of Night VIIb, 46:134.</p>
          <p>The Order of Nights VIIa and VIIb in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, 46:107-113.</p>
          <p>The Revision of the Seventh and Eighth Nights of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, 46:115-133.</p>
          <p>The Selling of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> Designs in the 1870s, 45:70-71.</p>
          <p>The Serpent-Driving Females in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 4, 47:164-177.</p>
          <p>Some Minor Additions to Bentley’s “Blake Among the Slavs,” 47:198.</p>
          <p>Some Not-So-Familiar Visionary Heads, 48:244-249.</p>
          <p>The Spectrous Embrace in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, VIIa, 46:100-105.</p>
          <p>The Sweet Science of Atmospheres in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, 46:80-86.</p>
          <p>Trickster’s Song [poem], 45:39.</p>
          <p>Two Poems [Song of Innocence, An Evening at Home with William Blake], 45:39-40.</p>
          <p>Vision in Fiction: Two Novels about William Blake, 47:209-210.</p>
          <p>William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>: A Poem Based on Doubt,
47:203-204.</p>
          <p>William Michael Rossetti’s Aldine Edition of Blake, 45:4-9.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>WORKS REVIEWED</title>
          </head>
          <p>Altick, Richard D., The Shows of London, 48:271-273.</p>
          <p>Bindman, David, Blake as an Artist, 45:64-67.</p>
          <p>Burke, Joseph, English Art 1714-1800, 47:212-214.</p>
          <p>Butlin, Martin, William Blake, 45:42-55.</p>
          <p>Davie, Donald, A Gathered Church: The Literature of the English Dissenting Interest,
47:215-217.</p>
          <p>Franson, John Karl, ed., Milton Reconsidered: Essays in Honor of Arthur E. Barker, 45:56-57.</p>
          <p>Howard, John, Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: A Study in Selfhood, 45:56-57.</p>
          <pb id="p14-ii" n="ii"/>
          <p>Johnson, Mary Lynn, see Wilkie, Brian.</p>
          <p>Kroeber, Karl, and William Walling, eds., Images of Romanticism: Verbal and Visual Affinities,
48:267-268.</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond, ed., The Letters of Samuel Palmer, 46:150-154.</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond, Samuel Palmer, A Biography, 46:150-154.</p>
          <p>Marqusee, Michael, introd., The Book of Job Illustrated by William Blake, 46:154.</p>
          <p>Ostriker, Alicia, ed., William Blake: The Complete Poems, 48:268-270.</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D., William Blake, 47:211-212.</p>
          <p>Tomalin, Claire, The Life and Death of Mary Wollstonecraft, 45:58-64.</p>
          <p>Walling, William, see Kroeber, Karl.</p>
          <p>Wardle, Ralph M., ed., Godwin &amp; Mary: Letters of William Godwin and Mary Wollstonecraft,
45:58-64.</p>
          <p>Wilkie, Brian, and Mary Lynn Johnson, Blake’s <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi>: The Design of a
Dream, 48:264-266.</p>
          <p>Wollstonecraft, Mary, Letters Written during a Short Residence in Sweden, Norway, and Denmark,
ed. Carol Poston, 45:58-64.</p>
          <p>Wollstonecraft, Mary, Mary, A Fiction, ed. Gary Kelly, 45:58-64.</p>
          <p>Wollstonecraft, Mary, A Vindication of the Rights of Woman, ed. Miriam Brody Kramnick,
45:58-64.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>ILLUSTRATIONS</title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>45</title>
            </head>
            <p>Plate 34 in C. G. Salzmann, <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality</hi> (1791), III, facing p. 23.
First state, Blake after Chodowiecki, 11.</p>
            <p>Plate 38 in Salzmann, <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality</hi> (1791), III, facing p. 68. First
state, Blake after Chodowiecki, 12.</p>
            <p>“Beggar’s Opera, Act III,” Blake after Hogarth, 1788. Detail, fourth state (1790), 12.</p>
            <p>“Moore and Co’s Advertisement,” designed and engraved by Blake, c. 1797. Detail, 12.</p>
            <p>Plate 28 in Salzmann, <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality</hi> (1791), facing p. 104. First
state, tentatively attributed to Blake as designer and engraver, 13.</p>
            <p>Frontispiece in Mary Wollstonecraft, <hi rend="i">Original Stories from Real Life</hi>, 1791.
Second state, designed and engraved by Blake, 14.</p>
            <p>[E. Blake’s] Signature on plate of “Lord Byron in a Storm,” <hi rend="i">The Seaman’s
Recorder</hi>, II, 1, 16.</p>
            <p>[E. Blake’s] Signature on plate of “M<hi rend="s">r</hi>. H. Kemble, as Massaniello,” 
<hi rend="i">West’s Theatrical Characters</hi>, 16.</p>
            <p>[E. Blake’s] Signature on plate of “M<hi rend="s">r</hi>. Huntley, as Bagzed,” 
<hi rend="i">West’s Theatrical Characters</hi>, 16.</p>
            <p>[E. Blake’s] Signature on plate of Nelson’s monument, frontispiece to <hi rend="i">The
Seaman’s Recorder</hi>, Vol. II, 17.</p>
            <p>[W. Blake’s] Signature on plate 21 of Vol. III of <hi rend="i">The Antiquities of
Athens</hi>, 1791, 17.</p>
            <p>Backdrop design for <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, Gwen Raverat, 18.</p>
            <p>Toy theater model for <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, Gwen Raverat design, 19.</p>
            <p>Notebook sketches, Ninette de Valois, 19.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Job</hi> television production, Harold Turner as Satan, 19.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Job</hi> original production programme, 5 July 1931, 20-21.</p>
            <p>Michael <corr type="emend">Somes</corr> as Job, later production, 22.</p>
            <p>Studio picture of Anton Dolin for a later Raverat production, 22.</p>
            <p>Joy Newton, original production, 23.</p>
            <p>Original production of <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, 24.</p>
            <p>Robert Helpmann as Satan, 25.</p>
            <p>Blake, “The Virgin Hushing the Young Baptist as He Approaches Jesus,” tempera, 27.</p>
            <p>Blake, “The Good Farmer,” recto, pencil, black ink, and grey wash, 28.</p>
            <p>Blake, “The Good Farmer,” verso, pencil, black ink, and grey wash, 29.</p>
            <p>Blake, “Saint Augustine Converting King Ethelbert of Kent,” watercolor, 33.</p>
            <p>Blake, “The Gambols of the Ghosts,” pencil, 34.</p>
            <p>Louis Schiavonetti after Blake, “The Descent of Man into the Vale of Death,” 35.</p>
            <p>Blake, <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi>, series a, copy G<hi rend="s">1</hi>, p1,
3, 37.</p>
            <p>Blake, <hi rend="i">Satan Calling Up His Legions</hi>, c. 1805, 46.</p>
            <p>Blake, <hi rend="i">Satan Calling Up His Legions</hi>, c. 1800-1809, 47.</p>
            <p>Blake, <hi rend="i">Moses Indignant at the Golden Calf</hi>, 48.</p>
            <p>Blake, <hi rend="i">The Christ Child Asleep on the Cross</hi>, 49.</p>
            <p>Blake, <hi rend="i">The Flight into Egypt</hi>, 49.</p>
            <p>Title page of Godwin’s <hi rend="i">Memoirs of the Author of a Vindication of the Rights of
Woman</hi>, 1798, 61.</p>
            <p>John Opie, <hi rend="i">Mary Wollstonecraft</hi>, 62.</p>
            <p>Etching, after Opie, <hi rend="i">Mary Wollstonecraft</hi>, 62.</p>
            <p>Portrait of Mary Wollstonecraft, 63.</p>
            <p>Portrait of Joseph Johnson the printer, 63.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>46</title>
            </head>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 27, detail, 86.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Vala or The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 29, 81.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, fragment, p. 144, 92.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 5, 94.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 6, 94.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 7, 95.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 7, detail, 98.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 91, 106.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 86, 117.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 112, 114.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 55, 124.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 98, detail, 128.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 116, 131.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 115, 132.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 82, detail, 133.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 98, detail, 139.</p>
            <p>Samuel Palmer, “View of the Serpentara,” drawing, 151.</p>
            <p>Photographs of the Clark and Bowler Thames Television production of <hi rend="i">The Story of
Job</hi> [ballet], 155, 156, 157, 158.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>47</title>
            </head>
            <p>Blake, “The Brothers Meet the Attendant Spirit in the Wood,” <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 4,
Huntington series, 165.</p>
            <p>Blake, “Comus with his Revellers,” <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 1, Huntington, 166; also Boston, 1,
166.</p>
            <p>Blake, “Comus, Disguised as a Rustic,” <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 2, Huntington, 167; Boston,
167.</p>
            <p>Blake, “The Brothers Observed by Comus Plucking Grapes,” <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 3, Huntington,
168; Boston, 168.</p>
            <p>Blake, “The Brothers Meet the Attendant Spirit in the Wood,” <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 4,
Huntington, 169; Boston, 170.</p>
            <p>Blake, “The Magic Banquet with the Lady Spellbound,” <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 5, Huntington,
171; Boston, 171.</p>
            <p>Blake, “The Brothers Driving Out Comus,” <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 6, Huntington, 172; Boston,
172.</p>
            <p>Blake, “Sabrina Disenchanting the Lady,” <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 7, Huntington, 173; Boston,
173.</p>
            <p>Blake, <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 8, Huntington, 175; Boston, 176.</p>
            <p>Blake, <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi>, detail, 179.</p>
            <p>Blake’s letter to his brother James, 30 January 1803, detail, 179.</p>
            <p>Blake, <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, p1. 15, detail, 180.</p>
            <p>Tables of the Law, from the Collection of the Jewish Museum, New York, 180.</p>
            <p>Blake, <hi rend="i">Job’s Evil Dreams</hi>, detail, 181.</p>
            <p>Blake, <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi>, detail, 182.</p>
            <p>Titlepage, William Nicholson, <hi rend="i">Introduction to Natural Philosophy</hi> (1782), 194.
With enlargement (detail) of Blake’s vignette, 194.</p>
            <p>Enlargement of Blake’s signature from Nicholson titlepage, 195.</p>
            <p>Figure illustrating “Theory of the Rainbow” from Nicholson, 1782, I, 281, 195.</p>
            <p>Titlepage vignette for Nicholson, <hi rend="i">Introduction to Natural Philosophy</hi>, 5th ed,
1805, 196.</p>
            <p>Figure of a Camera Obscura from Nicholson, 1782, I, 368, 197.</p>
            <p>Blake, Illustration to Robert Bage’s <hi rend="i">Hermsprong</hi>, c. 1820, 202.</p>
            <p>After Blake, “Death’s Door,” 204.</p>
            <p>Blake, <hi rend="i">Goliath cursing David</hi>, drawing, 205.</p>
            <p>Blake, <hi rend="i">Goliath cursing David</hi>, verso, 206.</p>
            <p>Blake, <hi rend="i">Goliath cursing David</hi>, watercolor, 206.</p>
            <p>Initial letter, “Christ with the keys of Hell and Death” from <hi rend="i">Pictorial Edition of
the Book of Common Prayer</hi>, p. 192, 207.</p>
            <p>Louis Schiavonetti after Blake, “Christ Descending into the Grave,” 207.</p>
            <p>Chapter Heading from Rubens’ “Resurrection” from <hi rend="i">Pictorial Edition of the Book
of Common Prayer</hi>, p. 199, 208.</p>
            <p>Blake, titlepage design for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> engraved by Schiavonetti,
208.</p>
            <p>Blake, design fro “The Death of the Good Old Man,” Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> (1808),
208.</p>
            <p>Titlepage to Heygate, <hi rend="i">William Blake: or, The English Farmer</hi>, 1848, 209.</p>
            <p>Frontispiece by N. D. Sears to Heygate, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (1848), 209.</p>
            <p>Fermin Rocker, design for <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi>, 209.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>48</title>
            </head>
            <p>Blake, “Nebuchadnezar/Coin as seen in a Vision,” 245.</p>
            <p>Blake, “Socrates,” 210.</p>
            <p>Blake, “Rd. Coeur de LION,” 211.</p>
            <p>Blake, “Caractacus,” 212.</p>
            <p>Blake, “King Edward the first as he now exists,” 249.</p>
            <p>“The Downfall of Taste &amp; Genius or The World as it goes,” 252-253.</p>
            <p>Blake after George Morland, “The Industrious Cottager,” first state, 258.</p>
            <p>Blake after George Morland, “The Industrious Cottager,” second state, 259.</p>
            <p>Blake, “The Little Girl Lost,” <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, copy N,
detail, 260.</p>
            <p>Blake, <hi rend="i">Illustrations of The Book of Job</hi>, pl. 6, detail, 260.</p>
            <p>Datura Arobria, 262.</p>
            <p>Diagram of a Mexican sun altar, 262.</p>
            <p>Thomas Rowlandson, <hi rend="i">The Wonderful Pig</hi>, 1785, 273.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
