<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.1.gebentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake’s Trial Documents</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1980</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas Minnick</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <name>Joe Zimmerman</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Thomas Dilworth</name>
              <name>Judy Egerton</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Edward Strickland</name>
              <name>Ruthven Todd</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1980"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
	<pb id="p14-37" n="37"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-1-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">BLAKE’S TRIAL DOCUMENTS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">By</hi>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">G. E. </hi><name><hi rend="b">Bentley</hi></name>, 
<hi rend="b">Jr.</hi></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The court documents concerning William Blake’s trials for sedition and assault at Petworth in
October 1803 and at Chichester in January 1804 are set out in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (1969), pp.
127-40. Recently I asked my colleague John Beattie, whose office is next to mine and whose field is the
administration of justice in England in the eighteenth century, whether the court documents reported in 
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> were likely to be all that survived and whether they were there interpreted
plausibly. After reflecting for an embarrassingly brief time, he replied in as friendly and helpful a way as
possible, No, and No. More important, he explained the way trials of the time were recorded and preserved and
lent me his copy of a directory of the Sussex Record offices. The most obvious point he made is that the court
documents quoted in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> are in the West Sussex Record Office in Chichester, while
no reference is made to the East Sussex Record Office in Lewes, which preserves materials relating not only to
East Sussex but to the County as a whole. I am sorry to say that it had never occurred to me that there might
be <hi rend="i">another</hi> relevant Sussex Record Office. The tardiness of this note I can only attribute to
John Beattie’s not telling me so earlier.</p>
          <p>I therefore wrote to Lewes and was sent very promptly by A. A. Dibben, County Records Officer of
the East Sussex County Council, reproductions of four documents relating to Blake’s trial. Two of these are
minor; the third and fourth are of major importance but are already quoted in their entirety in 
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> from the transcripts of Herbert Jenkins, who had not indicated the locations of
the originals. Using the information so generously provided by John Beattie and A. A. Dibben, the alterations
to <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> should be as follows:
<q>
PAGE 127, for the last paragraph read:<lb/>
<lb/>
On the morning of Tuesday the 16th, Blake, the soldier named Scolfield, his accomplice John Cock, and their
lieutenant, who was responsible for preferring the charge, entered into recognizances for their appearance at
the Quarter Sessions: . . .<lb/>
<lb/>
PAGE 128, for the end of the top paragraph and the beginning of the next read:<lb/>
<lb/>
Blake misremembered Hayley’s recognizance as £100 rather than £50. <hi rend="i">N.B.</hi> No money changed
hands.<lb/>
<lb/>
Scholfield and Cock had to enter recognizances for £50 each:<lb/>
<lb/>
No “bonds were taken” from them; they merely acknowledged that, if they didn’t appear at the Quarter
Sessions, they <hi rend="i">would</hi> “be indebted to our Sovereign Lord the King” in the sums specified. No
borrowing was necessary, no cash was needed.<lb/>
<lb/>
PAGE 131, fn 2: Omit<lb/>
<lb/>
The primary source is in the Sussex County Record Office . . . . The secondary document, which amplifies the
primary one and which may be the transcript Blake’s lawyer applied for on December 25th 1803 (q.v.), was
transcribed, from an original I have not traced, by Herbert Jenkins in a typescript (now in my possession) and
printed in his ‘The Trial of William Blake for High Treason [<hi rend="i">i.e., Sedition and
Assault</hi>],’ <hi rend="i">Nineteenth Century</hi>, 1xvii (1910), 853-5, and <hi rend="i">William
Blake</hi>, London, 1925. The Jenkins transcript has a few words . . . Sussex County Record Office . . .
Sussex County Record Office . . .
<pb id="p14-38" n="38"/>
Jenkins typescript . . . Record Office . . . Record Office . . . Jenkins transcript . . . Record Office . . .
Jenkins typescript<lb/>
<lb/>
In their place read:<lb/>
<lb/>
The primary source is in the West Sussex Record Office . . . . The secondary document, transcribed from a
reproduction of Q0 / EW35 (Order Book) in the East Sussex Record Office, has a few words . . . West Sussex
Record Office . . . West Sussex County Record Office . . . East Sussex Record Office . . . West Sussex Record
Office . . . West Sussex Record Office . . . East Sussex Record Office. . . . West Sussex Record Office . . .
East Sussex Record Office.<lb/>
<lb/>
As I understand, the main document, the Indenture &amp;c., was inscribed on a parchment roll and annotated as
the trial proceeds, e.g., “Trav<hi rend="s">d</hi>”. The lesser documents such as recognizances were inscribed
on paper and often wrapped in the parchment roll to preserve them. Sometimes the paper documents were
separated from the parchment roll and even destroyed, but the main parchment document was normally preserved
if anything was. However, in this case there seems to be no surviving roll, and the paper documents are widely
dispersed.<lb/>
<lb/>
I ignore most differences in capitalization (the East Sussex document gives “ff” for “F”), punctuation, and
size of writing. The substantive differences in the East Sussex document are as follows: PAGE 131, 1. 5 of the
document adds after “(that is to say)”: “SUSSEX, to wit”; PAGE 132, 1. 3 omits “said”; 1. 7 reads “said said”;
1. 13 reads “incite”; 1. 16 omits the dash; PAGE 133, 1. 17 “(to wit)” is within parentheses; PAGE 134, 11.
3-5 are omitted.
</q></p>
          <p>The Jenkins transcript was wrong in giving “would” for “could” on p. 132, 1. 30.
<q>
PAGE 134, 1. 11, for “<hi rend="i">raise</hi>” read “<hi rend="i">cause</hi>”; 1. 13, for 
    “<hi rend="i">Ackw. 100£</hi>” read “<hi rend="i">Acknd 100<hi rend="s">1</hi></hi>.”; 
    1. 14, “<hi rend="i">William Hayley</hi>” should not be in capitals; 1. 15, for 
    “<hi rend="i">50£</hi>.” read “<hi rend="i">50<hi rend="s">1</hi></hi>.”; 1. 17, for 
    “<hi rend="i">Ackwd</hi>” read “<hi rend="i">Ackwd</hi>”.
</q></p>
          <p>The East Sussex document continues:
<table rows="3" cols="3"><row>
	<cell><hi rend="i">Plea not Guilty</hi></cell>
	<cell><hi rend="i">THE SAID WILLIAM BLAKE late of the Parish of ffelpham in the County of Sussex Designer and
Engraver came here in Court in his own proper person and desired to hear the Indictment of Record against him
Read why he on the twelfth Day of August in the fforty third year of the Reign of our Sovereign Lord George
the Third of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland now King with fforce and Arms at the Parish of
ffelpham aforesaid in the County aforesaid in and upon one John Scholfield in the Peace of God and of our said
Lord the King then and there being Did make an Assault and him the said John Scholfield then and there Did
beat wound and ill treat, so that his life was greatly despaired of and other wrongs to the said John
Scholfield then and there did, to the great Damage of the said John Scholfield and against the Peace of our
said Lord the King his Crown and Dignity, And having heard the same Read says and pleads that he is thereof
not Guilty and for his Trial puts himself upon the County and William Ellis Gentleman Clerk of the Peace for
the said County who for our Sovereign Lord the King in this behalf prosecute &amp;<hi rend="s">c</hi> doth so
likewise therefore the Sheriff of the said County is Commanded &amp;<hi rend="s">c</hi> to cause to Come a
Jury &amp;<hi rend="s">c</hi> To try &amp;<hi rend="s">c</hi></hi></cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell><hi rend="i">Recogn<hi rend="s">s</hi>. to prosecute</hi></cell>
	<cell><hi rend="i">AND the William Blake Acknd.<lb/>
AND William Hayley of ffelpham aforesaid Esquire and Joseph Seagrave of Chichester in the said County Printer
........ Ackn<hi rend="s">d</hi>.</hi></cell>
	<cell>100<hi rend="s">1</hi>.<lb/>
<hi rend="i">50<hi rend="s">1</hi>. each</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell/>
	<cell><hi rend="i">UPON CONDITION for the said William Blake to appear at the next Sessions and try his
Traverse with Effect &amp;<hi rend="s">c</hi> Then &amp;<hi rend="s">c</hi> Otherwise &amp;<hi
rend="s">c</hi></hi> // . —</cell>
	<cell/>
</row></table></p>
          <p>This True Bill was also reported upon a printed form:</p>
          <p>Add at the bottom of the page:</p>
          <p>It should be noticed that the violence of these statements concerning Assault (“his Life was
greatly despaired of”) is in the printed part of the document and is merely a matter of form.</p>
          <pb id="p14-39" n="39"/>
          <p>If Blake had pleaded Guilty to the Indictment (a rare occurrence in 18th Century rural courts),
the case would have been tried immediately. When the accused pleads Not Guilty, however, ‘the officer of the
court asks the party whether he be ready to try then, or will traverse [put off the trial] to the next
sessions’, as was normal. Blake clearly denied his guilt and chose to be tried for sedition and assault at
the next Quarter Sessions in January 1804, so the Bill was marked ‘Trav<hi rend="s">d</hi>.’</p>
          <p>And in the summary of the proceedings in the Minute Book was recorded:
<table rows="2" cols="2"><row>
	<cell>W<hi rend="s">m</hi>. Blakes Ind<hi rend="s">t</hi>. for Sedit<hi rend="s">n</hi>.<lb/>
D<hi rend="s">o</hi>. for an assault</cell>
	<cell>Ind<hi rend="s">ts</hi>. trav<hi rend="s">d</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>. . .<lb/>
W<hi rend="s">m</hi>. Blake’s 2 Trav<hi rend="s">s</hi> tried—</cell>
	<cell/>
</row></table></p>
          <p>Purged of redundancies, ‘said’ and ‘to wit’, what Blake was alleged to have said was:
<q>
The English know within themselves that Buonaparte could take possession of England in an hour’s time, and
then it would be put to every Englishman’s choice for to either fight for the French or to have his throat
cut. I think that I am as strong a man as most, and it shall be throat cut for throat cut, and the strongest
man will be the conqueror. You will not fight against the French. Damn the King and Country and all his
subjects. I have told this before to greater people than you. Damn the King and his Country; his subjects and
all you soldiers are sold for slaves.<lb/>
<lb/>
PAGE 134, fn. 1: Omit paragraph 2 and all but the first sentence in paragraph 1 as being no longer
necessary.<lb/>
<lb/>
PAGE 134, fn. 2: Richard Burn, <hi rend="i">The Justice of the Peace, and Parish Officer</hi>, rev. George
Chetwynd (1825), V, 541.<lb/>
<lb/>
PAGE 134, fn. 3: East Sussex Record Office QM / EW 16 (Minute Book).<lb/>
<lb/>
PAGE 135, fn. 1 should read:<lb/>
<lb/>
These sums [<hi rend="i">£1,000</hi>] are absurdly exaggerated, for in Jan 1803 and Oct 1804 Blake’s
recognizance was for £100, and those for Hayley and Seagrave, his two sureties, were for only £50.<lb/>
<lb/>
PAGE 140, 1. 7: for “registered the indictment” read “taken the evidence.”<lb/>
<lb/>
PAGE 140, in the indented quotation read:<lb/>
<lb/>
ffogden . . . premised [<hi rend="i">for</hi> premises] . . . Assault [<hi rend="i">not</hi> Assualt] . . .
alledged [<hi rend="i">not</hi> alleged]<lb/>
<lb/>
PAGE 145, at the end of the first paragraph add:<lb/>
<lb/>
As a last formality, Hayley, Seagrave, and Blake were discharged from their recognizances, since they had
appeared at the trials:<lb/>
<lb/>
Sussex / s[<hi rend="i">ession</hi>]s / Epiphany Sessions at Chichester on Tuesday the 10<hi rend="s">th</hi>:
Day of Janry 1804—<lb/>
. . .
    <table rows="3" cols="2"><row>
	<cell>In Co<hi rend="s">t</hi>. last Sess W<hi rend="s">m</hi>. Blake of Felpham C<hi rend="overline">om</hi>
Sussack<hi rend="overline">u</hi> 100<hi rend="s">1</hi>. W<hi rend="s">m</hi>. Hayley of the same place Esq
&amp; Joseph Seagrave of Chichester C<hi rend="overline">om</hi> p<hi rend="overline">roed</hi> printeruc<hi
rend="overline">ku</hi> 50<hi rend="s">1</hi>. ea. Cond[<hi rend="i">iti</hi>]<hi rend="overline">on</hi> for
s<hi rend="s">d</hi>. W<hi rend="s">m</hi>. Blake to app<hi rend="s">r</hi>. at the next Sess &amp; try his
traverse with effect for Sedition</cell>
	<cell>Disch<hi rend="s">d</hi></cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>D<hi rend="s">o</hi> The s<hi rend="s">d</hi>. W<hi rend="s">m</hi>. Blake ackn 100<hi rend="s">1</hi>.
&amp; the s<hi rend="s">d</hi>. W<hi rend="s">m</hi>: Hayl[<hi rend="i">e</hi>]y &amp; Joseph Seagrave ack<hi
rend="overline">n</hi> 50<hi rend="s">1</hi>. Cond<hi rend="s">n</hi>. for s<hi rend="s">d</hi>. W<hi
rend="s">m</hi>. Blake to app<hi rend="s">r</hi>. at the next Sess &amp; try his traverse with effect for an
Assault on John Scholfield—</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>WILLIAM BLAKE of Felpham C<hi rend="overline">om</hi> S<hi rend="overline">uss</hi> [<hi rend="i">in
the County of Sussex</hi>] Designer &amp; Engraver ac<hi rend="overline">kn</hi> 100<hi rend="s">1</hi>.
William Hayl[<hi rend="i">e</hi>]y of the same place Esq<hi rend="s">re</hi> Joseph Seagrave of the City of
Chichester Printer ac<hi rend="overline">kn</hi> 50<hi rend="s">1</hi> ea. Condn for s<hi rend="s">d</hi>.
W<hi rend="s">m</hi>. Blake to app<hi rend="s">r</hi> &amp; answer to the above—<hi rend="s">1</hi></cell>
	<cell>Disch<hi rend="s">d</hi></cell>
</row></table>
PAGE 145, fn. 1: Quoted from a reproduction of QZ / EW 9 (Recognizance Book) in the East Sussex Record Office.
</q></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
