<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.2.read</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">A New Blake Engraving: Gilchrist and the Cromek Connection</title>
        <author n="Read">Dennis M. Read</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1980</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Detlef Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Leonard M. Trawick</name>
              <name>Nicholas O. Warner</name>
              <name>Kasumitsu Watarai</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-2-0006">
        <pb id="p14-60" n="60"/>
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">A NEW BLAKE ENGRAVING: GILCHRIST AND THE CROMEK CONNECTION</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">DENNIS M.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">READ</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>In his letter to Thomas Johnes dated 4 January 1806 and published as an introduction to
            <hi rend="i">A Father’s Memoirs of His Child</hi> (1806), Benjamin Heath Malkin provides
          much information about and kind words for William Blake, the designer of “the ornamental
          device, round the portrait in this book.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35"
type="note">1</ref> Malkin,
          however, neglects to mention the engraver of this device, Robert Hartley Cromek, who had
          much to do with Blake and his vicissitudes between 1805 and 1808. Fifty-seven years later,
          in Alexander Gilchrist’s biography of Blake, there appears the additional information that
          “Blake designed, and originally engraved, the ‘ornamental device’ to the frontispiece for
          Malkin’s <hi rend="i">A Father’s Memoirs of His Child</hi>, but it was erased before the
          appearance of the work, and the same design reengraved by Cromek.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36"
            type="note">2</ref> It is a curious assertion and, without corroboration, lonely as a
          cloud. <note id="n35"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Malkin’s discussion of Blake is reprinted in G.
            E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1969), pp.
            421-431.</note>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life
              of William Blake, “Pictor Ignotus”</hi> (London and Cambridge: Macmillan, 1863), I, p.
            210.</note></p>
        <p>Recently, however, I have found information which has led me to the print Gilchrist
          contends Blake made. It comes from R. H. Cromek’s son, Thomas Hartley Cromek (1809-1873),
          who in 1864 wrote a MS memoir of his father. In it he discloses that he possesses a proof
          print of the original engraving Gilchrist describes: 
		<q> I have an impression of this
            plate [which belonged to my father <hi rend="i">del.</hi>], with the figures round the
            Portrait, engraved by <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> These were erased, and re-engraved by
            Cromek, in 1806. . . . From the fragments of lettering at the edges of Blake’s print, it
            seems clear that he not only designed and engraved the figures, but even printed it,
            himself, on some peice [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] of waste paper that came to his hand. It
            is not in the British Museum, and my impression is probably 
              <hi rend="i">unique.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37"
type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">3</hi>
              “Memorials of the Life of R. H. Cromek. Engraver. F[ellow] A[ntiquaries] S[ociety]
                Edinb<hi rend="s">r</hi>. Editor of the ‘Reliques of Burns’; ‘Remains of Nithsdale
              and Galloway Song’ &amp;c with the unpublished correspondence on those works; and
              other papers relative to his professional and literary career. Collected and Edited by
              his son.” Thomas H. Cromek’s “Memorials” was never published, and two MS versions of
              it, one dated 23 December 1864 and the other dated 27 July 1865, survive in the
              collections of Cromek’s present-day heirs, Mr. Paul Warrington and Mr. Wilfred
              Warrington, whose permission to publish parts of these and other materials in their
              possession I gratefully acknowledge. The working of the two “Memorials” MSS is nearly
              identical; quotations, however, have been taken from the “Memorials” bearing the later
              date.</note></q></p>
        <p>The print is now in the British Museum, for in 1867 Thomas Cromek included it in a group
          of 119 engravings and drawings by R. H. Cromek which he presented to the Print Room (now
          the Department of Prints and Drawings). Thomas Cromek’s daughter, Mary Cromek, makes
          specific reference to the print in her letter of 9 April 1867 to Mr. W. Reid of the
          British Museum: “Together with that of young Malkin there is also Blake’s engraving,
          probably a unique impression.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38"
type="note">4</ref> In the volume of
          Cromek’s works, the alleged Blake engraving is mounted on page 42 and numbered 91 (Plate
          1). Cromek’s own proof engraving, numbered 92, is mounted below it on the same page (Plate
          2). <note id="n38"><hi rend="s">4</hi> The letter is pasted on a page at the beginning of
            the volume. Thomas Cromek suffered paralysis in his last years, rendering him unable to
            write, and his daughter, Mary Cromek, therefore attended to his
          correspondence.</note></p>
        <p>The “unique impression,” which has the same dimensions (7 3/4 × 5 3/16 in.) as the
          published print, clearly differs from the published print in several ways. First, the rays
          of sunlight are presented as long, slender shafts, rather like those in Blake’s own
          engraving of “Death’s Door,” instead of the stylized, regular rays in the published
          version which resemble so many spotlight beams. Second, the clouds are shaped and arranged
          differently. Third, there are many small differences between the two versions in the hair,
          drapery, hands, and feet of the figures in the ornamental device, as well as in the
          positions of the figures. Particularly noteworthy is the refined curve of the 
            <pb id="p14-61" n="61"/>
teacher’s neck and shoulder, rather than the inelegant and strained
          angle of her head, neck, and shoulder in the published version. The published version
          indeed seems inferior in both design and execution to this presumably earlier print.</p>
        <p>The “fragments of lettering” Thomas Cromek refers to confirm Blake’s association with the
          print. Along the left-hand border are printed in letter-press “reast,” and “ss,” and along
          the right-hand border “BA,” “The,” “Sec;” “So,” “But,” “Th,” and “Ra.” These words and
          word fragments match exactly those along the right-hand border of page 26 and the
          left-hand border of page 19 of William Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Designs to A Series of
            Ballads</hi> (Chichester: J. Seagrave, 1802). On the verso of the sheet along the
          left-hand border are printed “nt” and the catchword “With” and along the right-hand border
          “R,” “S,” “L,” “O,” and “Sh.” These words and fragments correspond exactly with those
          along the right-hand border of page 20 and left-hand border of page 25 of Hayley’s 
            <hi rend="i">Ballads.</hi> Blake had a generous supply of quarto sheets of Hayley’s 
            <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> because the first four numbers of the projected series of fifteen
          had sold so poorly, in spite of Hayley’s professed intention of publishing and selling the
            <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> “for the sake of serving” Blake, whose engraved designs
          accompanied the ballads.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">5</ref>
The 
            <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> instead served Blake chiefly as scrap paper. He drew various sketches in
          the ample spaces between the printed pages of the sheets or otherwise used the sheets. To
          date, twenty-one specific instances of his doing so have been noted.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
            type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Letter to Lady Hesketh, 24 May
            1802; transcribed in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 96.</note>
	<note id="n40"><hi
              rend="s">6</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., “The Date of Blake’s Pickering Manuscript or The
            Way of a Poet with Paper,” <hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi>, 19 (1955), 232-43
            and Karen G. Mulhallen, “‘For Friendship’s Sake’: Some Additions to Blake’s Sheets for
              <hi rend="i">Designs To A Series of Ballads</hi> (1802),” <hi rend="i">Studies in
              Bibliography</hi>, 29 (1976), 331-41. For bibliographic information about Hayley’s 
              <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>, see G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford:
            Clarendon, 1977), pp. 572-75 and Roger R. Easson and Robert N. Essick, 
              <hi rend="i">William Blake: Book Illustrator</hi> (Normal, Illinois: American Blake Foundation,
            1972), pp. 31-33. I wish to thank Prof. Bentley for his help and encouragement in
            preparing this article.</note></p>
        <p>The many letter-press letters on the sheet used for the Malkin print identify beyond any
          doubt the pages in Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> where they appear. Page 19, for
          instance, yields the following configuration: 
		<q> BA[LLAD THE THIRD]<lb/>
<lb/>
 The[ir
            shouts united, and each arm<lb/>
 In bold protection spread]<lb/>
 Sec[ur’d the kid from
            real harm<lb/>
 Tho’ now with fear half dead,]<lb/>
<lb/>
 So[me furlongs from their
            cottage still,<lb/>
 Now pass’d this anxious scene;]<lb/>
 But [they had left, as safe
            from ill,<lb/>
 The sleeping babe serene.]<lb/>
<lb/>
 Th[e savage bird the kid
            renounc’d,<lb/>
 But round the cottage oft]<lb/>
 Ra[pid he wheel’d, and there he
            pounc’d<lb/>
 And bore the babe aloft.] </q>
Pages 20, 25, and 26 produce the same exact
          fit with the words and letters that show on the sheet.</p>
        <p>Blake used copies of this sheet to draw four of the sketches noted by Bentley and
          Mulhallen, one between pages 26 and 19 (no. 3 in Mulhallen) and three between pages 20 and
          25 (nos. 5 and 11 in Bentley and no. 6 in Mulhallen). The Malkin print, however, marks the
          only known instance of Blake’s printing an engraving impression on a sheet from Hayley’s
            <hi rend="i">Ballads.</hi> The Malkin print also appears to be the earliest known
          instance of Blake’s using a sheet of the <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> as scrap paper, the
          next earliest being his letter to Richard Phillips dated 14 October 1807 (no. 9 in
          Bentley).</p>
        <p>The published version of the Malkin print, however, was re-engraved by Cromek—or at least
          the “ornamental device” originally engraved by Blake. According to his son in the
          “Memorials,” Cromek had nothing to do with the stipple portrait of young Malkin, which
          actually was completed by another engraver: “The medallion Portrait is in the same
          unfinished state in Blake’s print, and in my father’s proof: it was, no doubt, engraved by
          Robt Cooper.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">7</ref> Thomas Cromek
arrives at this
          conclusion by pointing out first that his father seems never to have executed a stipple
          engraving, except for a medallion portrait of Dante dated 1802 and a portrait of Romney
          Robinson for William Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Life of Romney</hi> (1809), and second that the
          signature on the engraved portrait of Robinson seems to have been altered: 
		<q> I have
            three impressions of the plate;—one has the name of <hi rend="i">Robert Cooper</hi>; the
            other two—<hi rend="i">Robert Cromac.</hi> For some time I was much puzzled with these
            facts: at last, I was glad to receive a satisfactory explanation from my highly-gifted
            friend, [Miss <hi rend="i">del.</hi>] Harriet Kearsley,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n42" type="note">8</ref> who wrote to me as follows—“If you examine it carefully, you will see by
the
            crowding of the three last letters, the inequality of the strokes of the 
              <hi rend="i">m</hi>, the first of which is longer than the other two; the <hi rend="i">r</hi>
            which looks as if made out of an <hi rend="i">o</hi>; and the <hi rend="i">c</hi>, which
            is not a good one,—but is top-heavy, like an <hi rend="i">r</hi>, that Cooper was the
            original name, and that the error was afterwards corrected.” Now, as this plate, and
            those of Dante and of young Malkin are the only specimens of <hi rend="i">dotted</hi>
            engraving bearing my father’s name; to which may be added the evidence of Hayley’s
            letter to my father;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">9</ref> I
feel quite sure that none of
            these <hi rend="i">portraits</hi> were [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] engraved by him, but that
            they were all the work of <hi rend="i">Robert Cooper</hi>, whom my father seems to have
            employed occasionally. <note id="n41"><hi rend="s">7</hi> “Memorials.”</note>	
              <note id="n42"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Cromek elsewhere gives Miss Kearsley’s address as 25,
              Alfred Place, Bedford Square, London (as of 1862). I have not been able to learn any
              other details about her.</note>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">9</hi> In a letter of 15
              July 1805 which Thomas Cromek transcribes in his “Memorials,” Hayley thanks Cromek for
              the engraving of Romney Robinson and praises “the fidelity, tenderness, and spirit,
              with which your friend has executed his very interesting portrait.” The statement
              suggests to Thomas Cromek that Hayley knew Cooper had engraved the portrait—or at
              least that Cromek had not.</note></q></p>
        <p>The information about Blake’s Malkin engraving reached Gilchrist’s widow in 1862, and she
          incorporated it in her husband’s biography in a way not satisfactory to Thomas Cromek:
			<q> My friend M<hi rend="s">r</hi>. Frost A.R.A.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n44" type="note">10</ref>
            after he had seen my probably <hi rend="i">unique</hi> impression of it, communicated to
              M<hi rend="s">rs</hi>. Gilchrist the particulars relating to it, and thought that
            being perhaps a “unique print,” it would be interesting to 
              <pb id="p14-62" n="62"/>
<figure n="MalkinFathersMemoirFrontispiece.14.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="691" height="1000">
              <head>1 Proof of frontispiece to Malkin’s <hi rend="i">A Father’s Memoirs of His
                  Child</hi> (1806), designed by Blake and engraved by R. H. Cromek, British Museum
                Department of Prints and Drawings.</head>
              </figure>
<pb id="p14-63" n="63"/>
<figure n="BlakeEngravingBallads.14.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="684" height="1000">
              <head>2 Blake’s own engraving of his design, printed on a quarto sheet of Hayley’s 
                  <hi rend="i">Ballads.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>British Museum Department of Prints and Drawings.</figDesc>
            </figure>
<pb id="p14-64" n="64"/>
Blake’s admirers to know in whose possession it was.
            Now it seems evident, that it had been predetermined that my existence should be
            ignored: else why is M<hi rend="s">r</hi>. Frost’s interesting communication, reduced to
            the mere statement, that “the design was re-engraved by Cromek”?<ref target="n45"
              type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">10</hi> William Edward Frost
              (1810-1877) was a painter chiefly of scenes derived from literary works, especially
              those of Spenser, Milton, and Shakespeare. He was elected an associate of the Royal
              Academy in 1846 and a member in 1870. In <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, II, 263,
              Gilchrist transcribes the contents of a previously unknown Prospectus by Blake dated
              10 October, 1793, made available to him “through perseveringly kind efforts on the
              part of Mr. Frost.” See also Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p.
              450.</note>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">11</hi> The statement appears in a MS volume by
              Thomas Cromek containing extracts from Gilchrist’s biography of Blake and other works
              which discuss R. H. Cromek, with Thomas Cromek’s responses to these extracts written
              on the facing page. The volume is in the possession of Mr. Paul Warrington.</note></q>
          Thomas Cromek’s complaint has grounds, for the wording Mrs. Gilchrist chooses implies that
          no impression of Blake’s Malkin engraving survives. His interpreting the oversight as a
          personal affront, however, seems to be stretching a point.</p>
        <p>Other information incorporated in Gilchrist’s biography of Blake from items in the
          possession of Thomas Cromek has to do with the engraving Cromek had made from Stothard’s
            <hi rend="i">Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> painting. This information was evidently obtained
          not from Thomas Cromek, but from Anne Eliza Bray, the author of <hi rend="i">The Life of
            Thomas Stothard, R.A.</hi> More than two years after its publication in 1852, Thomas
          Cromek wrote a letter to her dated 8 October 1854 in which he attempted to correct
          misinformation in her biography by quoting documents relating to the 
            <hi rend="i">Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> engraving that were in his possession. For instance, in
order
          to dispute the figure of 330 guineas Mrs. Bray states Cromek was to pay Schiavonetti for
          the <hi rend="i">Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> engraving, he refers to a bill for £75 to R. H.
          Cromek from Schiavonetti dated 23 November 1809, to a receipt from Schiavonetti dated 12
          December 1809 and worded “Received of R. H. Cromek, the sum of two Hundred Pounds, in part
          of 840£ for Engraving Stothard’s Picture of the Canterbury Pilgrims,” and to a memorandum
          of Cromek’s delineating the “Expenses attending the completion of the Pilgrims, from the
          Etching, as left by M<hi rend="s">r</hi>. Schiavonetti. The Plate was begun in the 20th
            Sep<hi rend="s">r</hi> 1810.” Immediately below are the subsequent dates and amounts
          “Paid [to] M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Engleheart,” totalling forty-four pounds and one shilling,
          with the last entry dated December 31.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46"
type="note">12</ref>	
              <note id="n46"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Thomas Cromek transcribes his letter to Mrs. Bray in his
            “Memorials”; the documents are in the collection of Mr. Paul Warrington.</note></p>
        <p>These documents clearly are the basis for Gilchrist’s reporting that “Schiavonetti was to
          have had £840 for his engraving, but only lived to receive or entitle himself to £275. In
          the following autumn . . . the plate was confided to George Engleheart, who worked on it
          from 20th September to the end of December, receiving some £44.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47"
            type="note">13</ref> Gilchrist learned as well from Thomas Cromek’s letter to Mrs. Bray
          that Cromek’s widow was forced to borrow money from her father in order to have the
          engraving completed, although he perhaps mercifully neglects to mention that her father
          required her to repay not only the loan but also interest upon it. 
              <note id="n47"><hi rend="s">13</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake</hi>, I, pp. 239-40.</note></p>
        <p>Gilchrist’s biography therefore benefitted from various documents of R. H. Cromek
          preserved and transmitted by his son. In addition, these documents, as well as Thomas
          Cromek’s “Memorials” and other writings about his father, enable us to locate the Malkin
          engraving the biography mentions and to identify it with confidence as Blake’s own work.
          Blake’s engraving the design and Cromek’s erasing it to re-engrave the design himself
          suggests that the two men had differences and misunderstandings even in their first
          collaboration. Perhaps the Malkin print can be regarded as an indication of the
          difficulties to come in the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> and <hi rend="i">Canterbury
            Pilgrims</hi> projects, in which both Blake and Cromek had much more at stake. Whatever
          the reasons were for Cromek’s destroying Blake’s engraving, he thought enough of Blake’s
          proof to keep it, and his son thought enough of it to present it to the British Museum.
          Now it finally can be added to the catalog of Blake’s works.</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
