<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.2.warner</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake’s Moon-Ark Symbolism</title>
        <author n="Warner">Nicholas O. Warner</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1980</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Detlef Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Leonard M. Trawick</name>
              <name>Nicholas O. Warner</name>
              <name>Kasumitsu Watarai</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
    <pb id="p14-44" n="44"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-2-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">BLAKE’S MOON-ARK SYMBOLISM</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">NICHOLAS O.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">WARNER</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>To a reader-viewer going through Blake’s work chronologically, the moon-ark or moon-boat
          probably seems a minor, perhaps even merely decorative motif. The image does not enter the
          Blakean canon until fairly late, 1804 and after, and then appears but sparsely—one line in
            <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, four pictures in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, a design from
          the Dante illustrations. Yet an examination of the moon-boat image will reveal its close
          connections to the basic Blakean themes of spiritual degeneration and ultimate redemption
          through the saving power of the imagination and of Christ’s mercy. Furthermore, Blake’s
          yoking of moon and boat results in an image of both spiritual illumination and spiritual
          transportation from one state of moral consciousness to another. Thus, if we study the
          moon-boat in relation to its sources in art and myth, modified by Blake into a motif
          compatible with his own iconography, we will discern its value as a vehicle of transition
          from a lower to a higher state of spiritual perception, and as a symbol of redemptive
          power.</p>
        <p>So far, the only critic to discuss the subject in detail has been Albert S. Roe, who
          concentrates on a moon-boat from one of Blake’s designs for Dante’s <hi rend="i">Divine
            Comedy.</hi> I would like to begin by examining this illustration, and then go on to a
          more thorough analysis of the whole phenomenon of the moon-ark in Blake’s work. My
          procedure will be to demonstrate the symbolic values of the moon-boat as they arise from
          Blake’s assimilation and transformation of traditional motifs.</p>
        <p>The moon-boat described by Roe appears in the drawing entitled “The Angelic Boat Wafting
          Over the Souls for Purgation,” in which an angel standing in a crescent-shaped boat bears
          souls away to Purgatory (illus. 1). Roe convincingly argues that this crescent boat
          indicates Blake’s association of this “scene with Beulah, for Beulah too is a place where
          spirits come and go. . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref>
Implicit in Roe’s analysis
          is the view of the moon-boat as a symbol of spiritual transit, and of Beulah as a
          transitional state: “Man is thus shown in this design in the in-between realm of Beulah.
          As the spirits embrace on the shore, the angelic boat guided by the Divine Imagination
          waits to take them back to the eternal joy of Eden.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n2" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Albert S. Roe, <hi rend="i">Blake’s
              Illustrations to the “Divine Comedy”</hi> (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1953), p.
            140.</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Roe, p. 141.</note></p>
        <p>I believe that Roe’s interpretation can be elaborated and extended to the moon-ark images
          of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> The sole moon-ark image in
            <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> occurs verbally, in Blake’s reference to Ololon, the emanation
          of Milton, who descends into “Felphams Vale” and the “Fires of Intellect” in the form of a
          “Moony Ark” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 42:7-9). Ololon’s descent marks the poem’s
          triumphant conclusion, in which God and man, as well as Milton and his emanation, are
          united. But why does Blake describe Ololon as an ark, and why is the ark “Moony”? To
          answer this question we must first turn to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> After examining
          the moon-boat illustrations from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, we can return to the figure
          of Ololon with a fuller, more lucid sense of her symbolic value. However, in order to
          understand how Blake uses the moon-arks of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as symbols of 
            <pb id="p14-45" n="45"/>
          <figure n="BlakeAngelicBoat.14.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="709">
            <head>1 Blake: “The Angelic Boat Wafting Over the Souls for Purgation.”</head>
            <figDesc>Courtesy of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
          </figure>
<pb id="p14-46" n="46"/>
redemption, spiritual transition and refuge, we must
          also see how Blake re-casts a number of traditional images to form his own moon-ark
          iconography.</p>
        <p>Blake was rather miscellaneous in adapting general and specific sources for his union of
          boat and moon into a single image. The positive symbolism of the boat in Blake is not
          surprising, as the image of the ship or boat is nearly always benign both in Western and
          Eastern symbolism. The moon, on the other hand, often functions as a baleful symbol, a
          source of lunacy, an emblem of mutability and inconstancy. Yet there exist positive
          alternative instances of lunar symbolism, and it is on these that Blake seems to have
          drawn for the purposes of his own image of the moon-ark. I would like to focus briefly on
          three such areas of positive lunar associations—first, some general, scattered images of
          the moon as positive; second, a moon-boat motif possibly familiar to Blake from medieval
          and Renaissance Christian art; third, the moon-boat symbolism set forth by the English
          antiquarian, Jacob Bryant.</p>
        <p>As an object of light, the moon often functions as a symbolic promise of the return of
          the sun, as in Isaiah 30:26 (“Moreover the light of the moon shall be as the light of the
          sun”) and Jeremiah 31:35 (“Thus saith the Lord, which giveth the sun for a light by day,
          and the ordinances of the moon and of the stars for a light by night”). A sign of
          something hopeful, bright, and definite in an amorphous sea of darkness (broken only by
          stars), the moon goes through its cycle of phases with reassuring regularity<ref
            target="n3" type="note">3</ref> (hence its many cross-cultural associations with
            rebirth.)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> As for the ship
or boat, its positive
          meanings, as I mentioned earlier, are numerous and wide-ranging. The ship is often
          depicted as an image of sanctuary, as well as of rebirth and immortality.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5"
            type="note">5</ref> A frequent symbol of refuge from a hostile sea, the ship also
          appears as a means of transcending mundane existence by transporting the soul to other
            worlds.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Juan
            Cirlot, <hi rend="i">A Dictionary of Symbols</hi>, trans. Jack Sage (N. Y.:
            Philosophical Library, 1962), p. 206.</note>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> M. Esther
            Harding, <hi rend="i">Woman’s Mysteries Ancient and Modern</hi> (N. Y.: Colophon Books,
            1971), p. 109.</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Cirlot, p. 281.</note>	
            <note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Cirlot, pp. 281-82.</note></p>
        <p>Perhaps some of these associations lie behind a motif in Christian art that strikingly
          anticipates <figure n="jerusalem.A.P18.detail" rend="file" width="958" height="333">
            <head>2 Blake: detail, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 18, 8 ¾ × 6 ¼ in.</head>
            <figDesc>Courtesy of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
          </figure> Blake’s own use of the moon-boat, namely the appearance in medieval and early
          Renaissance art of distinctly crescent-shaped ships and boats. Now, whether there is any
          intended significance underlying the resemblance of boat to moon in certain works of art
          has not, as far as I know, received any scholarly attention. However, it is likely that an
          active imagination like Blake’s, prone to complex symbolic associations, might very well
          have made something significant of such a resemblance. Both the moon and the boat were
          accepted emblems of the Church in Christian iconography,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n7" type="note">7</ref> and perhaps it is this link that such works express, or that itself appealed
to
          Blake. One frequent symbol of the Church, Noah’s Ark, was occasionally portrayed in
          crescent-like form, as in a medieval manuscript of uncertain date in which the ark
          consists of a house set in an exaggerated crescent-shaped boat (illus. 7). This picture
          even brings to mind some lines about Los who, practical visionary that he is, provides
          Ulro with a moon to replace the lost moon of Beulah: “And Sixty Winters Los raged in the
          Divisions of Reuben: / Building the Moon of Ulro, plank by plank, &amp; rib by rib” 
            (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 32:3-4). <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> George Ferguson, 
              <hi rend="i">Signs and Symbols in Christian Art</hi> (N. Y.: Oxford Univ. Press, 1973), pp.
            180-81.</note></p>
        <p>Similarly shaped boats abound in the well-known Stuttgart Psalter, though it is doubtful
          that Blake would have seen it. One motif from the Psalter, however, a crescent-shaped boat
          in a monster-infested sea (illus. 8) is particularly interesting. The same motif occurs
          several times in illustrations to the Geneva, or so-called “Breeches” or Queen Elizabeth
          Bible, an English Bible of which there were numerous editions and copies that Blake may
          well have seen.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> The
significance, for Blake, of a 
            <pb id="p14-47" n="47"/>
<figure n="jerusalem.A.P20" rend="file" width="724" height="1000">
            <head>3 Blake: <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 20, 8 ¾ × 6 ¼ in.</head>
            <figDesc>Courtesy of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
          </figure>
<pb id="p14-48" n="48"/>
crescent boat as a refuge from monstrous creatures will
          become obvious when we realize how his own moon-arks, especially those of plates 24 and 39
          of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, symbolize refuge from the spiritual monstrosity
          surrounding Albion. <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Between its first edition in 1560
            and its last in 1616, the Geneva Bible was the most popular Bible in English, especially
            among the kinds of Protestant sects with which Blake felt sympathy. Even after 1616,
            many illustrated Geneva Bibles were available in England, and this version continued
            into the eighteenth century to be more widely circulated among many Protestants than the
            official King James Version. For useful information on the Geneva Bible, see Hugh Pope,
            O. P., <hi rend="i">English Versions of the Bible</hi> (Birghamton and N. Y.:
            Vail-Ballou Press, Inc., 1952) and T. H. Darlow and H. F. Moule, <hi rend="i">Historical
              Catalogue of the Printed Editions of Holy Scripture</hi>, Vol. I (London: Bible House,
            1903).</note></p>
        <p>The presence of a moon-boat in Blake’s Dante drawings leads one to suspect the possible
          influence of Dante’s earlier illustrators on Blake. (We should remember, however, that in
          Dante there is no mention of actual moon-boats.) Flaxman immediately comes to mind, but
          his Dante illustrations reveal no moons at all, let alone moon-boats. In one French
          version of Dante, however, the Bergaigne translation of 1517-25, Dante is shown riding in
          a small crescent-like rowboat. And in a fourteenth-century Italian manuscript, a
          distinctly crescent-shaped boat appears in an illustration of the City of Dis (illus.
          9).</p>
        <p>The similarity of such illustrations as those found in the Bergaigne translation, the
          Stuttgart Psalter, and the Queen Elizabeth Bible to Blake’s moon-arks suggests that Blake
          may have been familiar with these or similar sources. Although there does not seem to be
          any evidence for a deliberate association of moons and boats in Western art, it seems
          clear that Blake probably encountered some Eastern designs in which he might have noticed
          a similarity between boats and the crescent moon, for Egyptian art and Sumerian hymns and
          pictures abound in moon-boat images.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">9</ref> Even so, we can
          only speculate on Blake’s possible interpretation and transformation of the crescent boat
          motif into a symbol suitable for his own work. Whether or not earlier artists consciously
          imitated the lunar crescent in their moon-like boats, Blake’s creatively assimilative mind
          could easily have drawn such a correlation from their work. 
              <note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Maurice Farbridge, <hi rend="i">Studies in Biblical and
Semitic Symbolism</hi>
            (N. Y.: KTAV Publishing House, Inc., 1970), p. 92.</note></p>
        <p>On a less esoteric level, we might note that the young Blake would probably have known
          the bit of British folklore that interprets a crescent moon on its side, thus resembling a
          boat, as a good omen, a sign of favorable weather.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n10" type="note">10</ref>
          But it is even more certain that Blake’s moon-ark imagery derives in part from Bryant’s
            <hi rend="i">Analysis of Antient Mythology</hi>, for which Blake is said to have
          engraved a tailpiece depicting Noah’s ark as a crescent moon (illus. 6).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
            type="note">11</ref> From Bryant Blake would have learned of the ark’s association with
          the moon, as well as of many <corr type="emend">intriguing</corr>, if often far-fetched interpretations of Noah’s
          ark and its connections to mythical figures such as Osiris and Dionysus. According to
          Bryant, the ark “was a kind of crescent, such as is exhibited by the new moon; which in
          consequence of it was made a type of the Ark. Hence, in the mythology of the Ark . . .
          there is continually some reference to the moon . . . the Moon and the Ark were synonymous
            terms.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> Bryant goes on
to link Noah’s ark to the
          festival of Osiris, when the Egyptians “constructed by way of memorial a remarkable
          machine . . . an Ark in the shape of a crescent or new moon. In this the image of Osiris
          was for a time concealed.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref>
One of the illustrations
          in Bryant’s book (again, possibly designed by Blake himself)<ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref>
depicts Osiris in such a boat, a crescent-shaped canoe. As the ark of Noah and
          of Osiris the moon was, says Bryant, symbolic of renewal and birth: “The Ark was certainly
          looked upon as the womb of nature; and the descent from it as the birth of the world.”<ref
            target="n15" type="note">15</ref> Both this positive value of the Ark, and the general
          association of the ark with the crescent moon discussed above, were accepted and
          elaborated by Blake in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> John Adlard, <hi rend="i">The Sports of
              Cruelty</hi> (London: Cecil &amp; Amelia Woolf, 1972), p. 66.</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi
              rend="s">11</hi> Ruthven Todd, <hi rend="i">Tracks in the Snow</hi> (N. Y.: Charles
            Scribner’s &amp; Sons, 1947), pp. 47-50.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Jacob
            Bryant, <hi rend="i">Analysis of Antient Mythology</hi> (London: J. Walker, 1807), Vol.
            III, p. 178.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Bryant, pp. 181-83.</note>	
            <note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Roger R. Easson, Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William
              Blake: Book Illustrator</hi> (Memphis: American Blake Foundation, 1979), Vol. II, p.
            2.</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Bryant, p. 218.</note>
	<note id="n16"><hi
              rend="s">16</hi> It would seem that Bryant’s association of the Ark of Osiris with
            resurrection received a curiously negative adaptation in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 21,
            where Blake says of the Daughters of Albion: 
			<q> I see them die beneath the whips of the
              Captains! they are taken<lb/>
 In solemn pomp into Chaldea across the bredths of
              Europe<lb/>
 Six months they lie embalmed in silent death: worshipped<lb/>
 Carried in
              Arks of Oak before the armies in the spring<lb/>
 Bursting their Arks they rise again
              to life: they play before<lb/>
 The Armies: I hear their loud cymbals &amp; their
              deadly cries<lb/>
<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 21:42-47) </q>
In this perversion of
            resurrection and of the Israelites’ practice of carrying the Ark of the Covenant before
            them, we may find a Blakean version of victim-oppressor identification that recalls the
            vicious cycles of “The Mental Traveller.” In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 21, the
            Daughters of Albion emerge from their arks only to incite their former
            oppressor-worshippers to further evil. The relationship between the Daughters and the
            armies receives detailed exposition in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 68. </note></p>
        <p>The first instance of moon-ark symbolism in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> occurs at plate
          18, where Blake depicts two small crescent sailboats apparently gliding toward one another
          as parallels to the two figures flying into an embrace on this plate (illus. 2). It is
          difficult to assign a specific valence to these moon-boats, but we can interpret them
          positively if, as seems reasonable, we see them as accompanying and/or paralleling the two
          embracing figures, and if in turn we identify these figures as the necessary,
          complementary fruits of Vala’s and Jerusalem’s labors, as described in the text: “For Vala
          produc’d the Bodies. Jerusalem gave the Souls” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 18:7). At the same
          time, these moon-boats could be images of hope, offering us light or escape from the
          disasters of this plate—the rejection of the innocent Jerusalem by the warlike “Sons of
          Albion, join’d in dark Assembly” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 18:5), who set up the all too
          obliging Vala as their queen, the “Goddess Virgin-Mother” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 18:29). The
          usurpation of Jerusalem’s rightful place and the disruption of cosmic harmony that begin
          on plate 18 continue through plate 19, where Albion fails to stagger out of his spiritual
          stupor, and extend into plate 20, where some miniscule moon-boats reappear as tokens of
          hope (illus. 3). In a plate thick with despair in both the text and scattered designs,
          these three crescents (one with a sail, thus recalling the boats of plate 18) are the only
          signs of refuge or hope. Such an interpretation of these moon-boats will be more strongly
          confirmed if we now examine the moon-boats they seem to prefigure—the larger, more
          impressive arks of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 24 and 39. The moon-arks of these later
          plates embrace the meanings of those on plates 18 and 20, while also seeming to offer
          Albion an alternative from the Ulroic state he approaches in those plates, a refuge from
          the temporal-spatial sea that threatens to engulf him.</p>
        <p>On plate 24 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Blake presents a crescent moon in water as a
          kind of Noah’s ark, much like the one he supposedly engraved for Bryant’s 
            <hi rend="i">Mythology.</hi> The suggestion of Noah’s ark is intensified by the presence of a
small,
          winged, dovelike figure in the boat.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">17</ref> (One thinks
          here not only of the dove in the Biblical account of the deluge, but of the moon-ark
          tailpiece in Bryant, with a dove hovering over it.) <note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi>
            Copies BE of this plate depict a dove with human face, a <hi rend="i">humanized</hi>
            form divine that perhaps underscores the supernatural, redemptive qualities of the
            image.</note></p>
        <p>In keeping with iconographic tradition, Blake depicts the ark during a rainstorm and on a
          turbulent sea.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref> This
moon-ark, with even its
          partially submerged hull shining luminously through the water, clearly functions as a
          Noah’s-ark symbol, traditionally suggestive of hope,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n19" type="note">19</ref>
          and as a symbol of the security and love of moon-ruled Beulah (illus. 4). 
              <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Louis Réau, <hi rend="i">Iconographie de l’art
chretien</hi>
            (Paris: Presses Universitaires de France, 1956), Vol. II, no. 1, p. 109.</note>	
            <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Réau, p. 109.</note></p>
        <p>In addition to these positive associations, Blake’s moon-ark very possibly serves as an
          image of rebirth. Such a connection is certainly implicit in Bryant, in the same volume
          where he links the ark with the moon: “Osiris . . . having been confined in an ark, or
          coffin, and in a state of 
<pb id="p14-49" n="49"/>
<figure n="jerusalem.A.P24.detail" rend="file" width="958" height="357">
            <head>4 Blake: detail, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 24, 8 ¾ × 6 ¼ in.</head>
            <figDesc>Courtesy of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
          </figure>
<figure n="jerusalem.A.P39-44.detail" rend="file" width="958" height="359">
            <head>5 Blake: detail, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 39, 8 ¾ × 6 ¼ in.</head>
            <figDesc>Courtesy of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
          </figure> death, at last quitted his prison and enjoyed a renewal of life . . . the
          renewal of mankind commenced from their issuing to light from the Ark.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20"
            type="note">20</ref> M. Esther Harding, who has made a study of moon myths, points out a
          number of other sources in which the moon symbolizes the renewal of life. Considering his
          interest in Eastern myths, perhaps Blake knew that “the Hindus . . . speak of the moon as
          carrying the souls of the dead over the waters to the sun where they live a redeemed
          life,” or that “the Chinese moon goddess after the flood gives birth to all living
            things.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref> These myths,
like Blake’s designs,
          present the moon-boat as a vehicle of spiritual transition. Whatever Blake’s specific
          sources (apart from Bryant) may have been, it is clear that previous appearances of the
          moon-boat in both Western and Eastern traditions would appeal to Blake in their richness
          of symbolic reference and association. <note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Bryant, p.
            248.</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Harding, p. 109.</note></p>
        <p>But what is the significance of all this symbolic richness for reader-viewers of 
            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>? What is the moon-ark’s relation to the text of plate 24, which
          itself depicts the weakness, delusion and despair afflicting Albion? For one thing, the
          visual image of the moon-boat counters and corrects Albion’s assertions of hopelessness.
          The text of plate 24 concludes with one of Albion’s numerous failures at 
            <pb id="p14-50" n="50"/>
rejuvenation, and despite the appearance of Christ, Albion sinks back to
          deathly sleep: “I die! I die in thy arms tho Hope is banished from me” 
            (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 24:60). Yet the moon-ark dominating the plate, with its suggestions of
Noah’s
          ark, of life and hope, shows that hope is not actually banished at all, as Albion
          erroneously thinks. The moon-ark stands as a reminder of the very life that Albion is in
          danger of losing, for it can bear him away from Ulro toward Beulah and Eden itself, which
          Blake elsewhere calls “the land of life” (<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, I, 21:6). As
          Albion himself indicates, spiritual death and annihilation are not identical—if he fails
          to escape from his lethargy, he will “live” an eternal death of the spirit 
            (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 23:40). This moon-ship of Beulah, though tempest-tossed, offers Albion a
shelter
          of love and hope that can still bear him away from the torments of Ulroic death, if only
          he can muster the courage to board it.</p>
        <p>A symbol of Beulah, of its love and hope, the moon-ark also suggests itself as a
          boundary, for Beulah serves as a boundary between Eden and Ulro, Blake’s Heaven and Hell.
          (Perhaps the aspect of the moon-ark that signifies a boundary even implies some sense of a
          tension or balance between the positive associations of the moon-ark and the moon’s
          frequent negative associations with mutability. While a refuge, the state of Beulah that
          the moon-ark symbolizes is also characterized by a “perilous 
          <figure n="BlakeNoahsArk.14.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="363">
            <head>6 Blake: “Noah’s Ark,” in Jacob Bryant’s <hi rend="i">Analysis of Antient
                Mythology</hi>, 1807, Vol. III.</head>
          </figure> 
          equipoise”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref>
          between the ascent to Eden and
          the fall into Ulro.) As the text of plate 24 shows, Beulah is a boundary that Ulro-bound
          Albion is quickly slipping past. The moon-ark reminds us that Beulah, limited as it is, is
          a step to Eden, a step that can lead to Albion’s redemption if he will only attempt to
          regain Beulah and then move on to Eden. As the moon itself has served as a token of the
          warming light of the sun in numerous cultures, so here the moon-boat is a reminder to
          Albion of Eden, the fiery, sun-ruled world of the imagination. But instead of regaining
          Beulah at this point, Albion continues to degenerate, as evidenced by the cosmic
          disruption within his own system: “The Sun fled from the Britons forehead: the Moon from
          his mighty loins” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 24:10). This line constitutes a verbal prophecy of
          what we will see graphically presented on the following plate, 25—Albion in utter 
            <pb id="p14-51" n="51"/>
          <figure n="AnonLeRetour.14.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="676">
            <figTranscr>Ici est [com]me noe est en larche o universete de totes<lb/>
            bestes par le [com]mandement n[ost]re seignor.</figTranscr>
            <head>7 Anonymous: “Le retour de la coulombe a l’àrche,” plate xxv of <hi rend="i">La
                Bible toute historiee et figurée de la John Rylands Library.</hi></head>
            <figDesc>Courtesy of the John Rylands Library.</figDesc>
          </figure>
<pb id="p14-52" n="52"/>
          <figure n="ChristCalmingSea.14.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="271">
            <figTranscr>[&amp; laetati sunt] quia [siluerunt]<lb/>
            &amp; deduxit eos in portum voluntatis eorum</figTranscr>
            <head>8 Anonymous: “Christ Calming the Sea,” from <hi rend="i">The Stuttgart
                Psalter.</hi></head>
            <figDesc>Courtesy of Princeton Univ. Press and the Department of Art and Archaeology of
              Princeton University with the cooperation of the University of Utrecht.</figDesc>
            </figure>
          <figure n="CityOfDis.14.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="336">
            <figTranscr>[impor]tar chiesa sacrata. Seguita nel testo.</figTranscr>
            <head>9 Anonymous: “The City of Dis,” from the 14th century illustrated manuscript of
              Dante’s <hi rend="i">Divine Comedy.</hi></head>
          </figure>
<pb id="p14-53" n="53"/>
degradation as he is tortured by the Female Will (illus.
          10). The shift of the moon image of plate 24 to that of plate 25 strikingly parallels
          Albion’s own degeneration. Both the moon (Albion’s emotional center) and the sun (his
          spiritual center) are displaced from their positions of loins and forehead (the sources of
          passion and thought?) and end up on Albion’s legs in a kind of symmetry that is fearful
          for all the wrong reasons. Blake, of course, frequently links sun and moon; yet here, in
          the context of both the design and text of this plate, their pairing possesses negative
          connotations as it underscores their displacement from the original positions of forehead
          and loins. <note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Northrop Frye, <hi rend="i">Fearful
              Symmetry</hi> (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1947), p. 233.</note></p>
        <p>Blake’s repetition of the moon image of plate 24 on the plate following it serves as a
          bitter reminder of Albion’s unfallen state, as well as of the rich promises the moon-ark
          of plate 24 still held. The hopes symbolized by the moon-boat seem far away indeed when
          their emblem, like the sun, has metamorphosed into a mere tattoo on Albion’s leg.</p>
        <p>Besides incorporating the positive symbolic associations of plate 24, the moon-ark of
          plate 39 illustrates, if somewhat obliquely, the text which accompanies it. The struggle
          for Albion’s spiritual awakening has been dragging on throughout the poem, and finally,
          “furious raging” Los exhorts Albion’s friends and brothers to stretch a “hand to save the
          falling Man” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 38: 12-14). Responding to Los’s urging,
<q> With one
            accord in love sublime, &amp; as on Cherubs wings<lb/>
 They Albion surround with kindest
            violence to bear him back<lb/>
 Against his will thro Los’s Gate to Eden: Fourfold;
            loud!<lb/>
 Their Wings waving over the bottomless Immense: to bear<lb/>
 Their awful
            charge back to his native home: but Albion dark,<lb/>
 Repugnant; rolls his Wheels
            backward into Non-Entity<lb/>
<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 39:1-6) </q></p>
        <p>We can easily see the extension of the symbolism of plate 24 into plate 39, where a
          related yet different sort of moon-boat sails over the water. The simple crescent of plate
          24 has grown into a house set in a moon-like boat, and the dove of the earlier plate has
          been replaced by two great wings flanking the house (illus. 5). In addition to offering a
          vision of hope and rebirth, the design on the upper part of plate 39 supplies a visual
          complement to the text. This winged moon-boat, followed and perhaps impelled by the two
          angelic spirits behind it (two of the friends and brothers mentioned in the text),
          symbolically parallels the text’s account of the attempt to bear the fallen Albion back
          through Los’s gate to Eden. As a refuge from the non-entity threatening Albion, this
          moon-boat seems to symbolize those qualities, already suggested on plate 24, that can
          serve as a kind of spiritual barque bearing Albion back to spiritual health.</p>
        <p>In its very function as a conveyance between two states, the moon-ark of plate 39 can
          also be seen as the kind of boundary between Eden and Ulro that we recognized in the ark
          of plate 24. Indeed, the winged moon-boat of plate 39 seems a variant of the winged
          disk-boundary appearing on plate 33 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> The design on plate 33
          reveals Albion fainting back in Christ’s arms, a scene verbally described on plates 23 and
          24, when Albion declares all hope to be banished from him (illus. 11). Now, just what the
          winged globe of plate 33 represents is unclear. In discussing this image, W. J. T.
          Mitchell notes that in William Stukeley’s <hi rend="i">Abury</hi>, winged orbs are
          interpreted as symbols of divinity, while Mitchell himself, without specifically
          <corr type="emend">identifying</corr> the globe in Blake, argues that it is an emblem of the “eternal support of
            Pity.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref> Such an
interpretation of the winged orb of
          plate 33 would be consistent with Blake’s parallel depiction of both Christ and the disk
          as supporting Albion—the winged disk supports Albion’s foot, just as Christ supports him
          in his arms. However, it is also possible that the orb actually does represent the moon.
          David Erdman identifies the orb as such, maintaining that its “continents are those of the
          moon, not earth.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref>
Furthermore, winged moons are not
          unknown in mythology. An ancient Assyrian motif represents the moon as winged<ref
            target="n25" type="note">25</ref> (illus. 12); Jacob Bryant, in a section of his 
            <hi rend="i">Mythology</hi> on the symbolic links between moon and bull, presents an
          illustration of a winged full moon among other lunar emblems (illus. 13). Should we
          interpret this winged orb as a moon, we can go on to see it as an emblem of Beulah,
          serving as a kind of border between Albion and the Ulroic scene at the bottom of the
          plate, presided over by a bat-winged creature (illus. 11).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n26" type="note">26</ref> (In Blake’s textual counterpart to this design, 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
          23:24-25, Albion is described as being upon the “edge of Beulah.”) The similarity between
          the winged moon images of plates 33 and 39 (if indeed the disk of 33 is the moon)
          emphasizes the similarity of their symbolic functions. In any event, the disk of plate 33,
          be it moon, sun, earth, or some other orb, is equipped with wings, and hence is ready to
          move, if necessary. The vehicular, winged moon-boat of plate 39, like its motionless
          counterpart in the earlier plate, represents a boundary between Eden and Ulro at the same
          time that it is already moving, under the guidance of the two spirits, to convey Albion
          back to Eden. 
          <note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> W. J. T. Mitchell, <hi rend="i">Blake’s
              Composite Art</hi> (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1978), pp. 181-82.</note>
          <note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi>
            (Garden City, N. Y.: Anchor Press/Doubleday, 1974), p. 312.</note>
          <note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi> Harding, p. 47.</note>
          <note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> The fallen
            world of the bottom portion of plate 33 shows the moon dominated by the bat-like
            creature, and demonstrates the inversion of order that typifies Ulro, as the moon has
            its bright side turned <hi rend="i">away</hi> from the sun. The moon in this lower
            section quite possibly represents a corrupted moon, the emblem of Beulah transformed,
            like the sun of this design, into part of a fallen, evil universe. Or perhaps we are
            looking at Los’s moon of Ulro, which he builds “plank by plank” to replace the moon of
            Beulah in the fallen world, as described on the plate preceding this illustration 
              (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 32:4).</note></p>
        <p>It is in connection with the idea of the moon-boat as both conveyance and boundary that a
          suggestion in Bryant’s <hi rend="i">Mythology</hi> becomes useful. Throughout his
          discussion of the ark’s ancient 
        <pb id="p14-54" n="54"/> 
          symbolism, Bryant implies that
          the moon-ark, in addition to its other symbolic values, represents “an intermediate state
          between a lost world, and a world 
          renewed.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref> In terms
          of Blake’s own symbolism, Beulah (of which the moon is chief emblem) could be viewed as
          such an intermediate state, between the lost death-world of Ulro and the renewed and
          renewing world of Eden. Albion himself needs to be redeemed from the lost world of Ulro,
          of non-entity, through the intermediate stage of Beulah, before going on into Eden; and
          what more appropriate image for his spiritual conveyance than a moon-ark, at once a boat,
          source of light, emblem of Beulah, and symbol of the redemption that Albion so desperately
          needs. <note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> Bryant, p. 81.</note></p>
        <p>In addition to the moon-boats we have been discussing, there is a verbal instance of what
          might be called a moon-boat in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> when, in a pair of obscure
          verses, Los announces that “The Sun shall be a scythed chariot of Britain: the Moon, a
          Ship / In the British Ocean” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 56: 18-19). These lines appear in a
          passage marked by images of holocaust, and are difficult to interpret, for the
          relationship of sun and moon to the surrounding imagery is not clear. S. Foster Damon sees
          the moon here as a symbol of love and Beulah, representing a barque of refuge from the Sea
          of Time and Space.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">28</ref> Yet the
imagery of sun and moon
          in these lines disturbs, rather than calms. What we have here, after all, is imagery of
          great cosmic disorder, 
          <figure n="jerusalem.A.P25" rend="file" width="742" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>And there was heard a great lamenting in Beulah: all the Regions<lb/>
					Of Beulah were moved as the tender bowels are moved: &amp; they said:<lb/>
					Why did you take Vengeance O ye Sons of the mighty Albion?<lb/>
					Planting these Oaken Groves: Erecting these Dragon Temples<lb/>
					Injury the Lord heals but Vengeance cannot be healed:<lb/>
					As the Sons of Albion have done to Luvah: so they have in him<lb/>
					Done to the Divine Lord &amp; Saviour. who suffers with those that suffer;<lb/>
					For not one sparrow can suffer. &amp; the whole Universe not suffer also,<lb/>
					In all its Regions, &amp; its Father &amp; Saviour not pity and weep.<lb/>
					But Vengeance is the destroyer of Grace &amp; Repentance in the bosom<lb/>
					Of the Injurer; in which the Divine Lamb is cruelly slain;<lb/>
					Descend O Lamb of God &amp; take away the imputation of Sin<lb/>
					By the Creation of States &amp; the deliverance of Individuals Evermore Amen<lb/>
					Thus wept they in Beulah over the Four Regions of Albion<lb/>
					But many doubted &amp; despaird &amp; imputed Sin &amp; Righteousness<lb/>
					To Individuals &amp; not to States, and these Slept in Ulro.</figTranscr>
            <head>10 Blake: <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 25, 8 ¾ × 6 ¼ in.</head>
            <figDesc>Courtesy of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
          </figure> 
          with sun and moon fallen to earth. The sun as a “scythed chariot” suggests
          destruction, and the real moon, if one may be permitted so fatuous a statement, simply
          does not belong in the British ocean. There is nothing in the context of these two lines
          to indicate a positive reading of these displaced celestial objects, and the only way to
          make sense of them is to fit them in with the entire litany of evils of which they are a
          part. In this moon image we have not a redemptive moon-ark, but a symbol of disruption
          similar to that of plate 25, where the sun flees from Albion’s forehead, and the moon from
          his “mighty loins.” <note id="n28"><hi rend="s">28</hi> S. Foster Damon, 
              <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Philosophy and Symbols</hi>, 2nd ed. (1924; rpt. Gloucester,
            Mass.: Peter Smith, 1958), p. 471.</note></p>
        <p>Thus far we have considered Blake’s ark as the union of moon and boat. Yet there is
          another <figure n="jerusalem.A.P33-37" rend="file" width="724" height="1000">
            <head>11 Blake: <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 33, 83/4 × 6 ¼ in.</head>
            <figDesc>Courtesy of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
          </figure>
<pb id="p14-55" n="55"/>
dimension to Blake’s moon-ark symbolism that depends on
          an apparent link, in Blake’s mind, between the Ark of Noah and the Ark of the Covenant.
          The connection between the two arks will provide us with a transition from the symbolism
          of the moon-boats to that of Ololon, the “Moony Ark” of <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi></p>
        <p>In his commentary on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Joseph Wicksteed finds several
          connections between Noah’s Ark and the Ark of the Covenant, suggested by one of the
          designs we have been discussing, plate 39 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Wicksteed notes
          that the ark of this plate must have been “associated by Blake with the Ark of the
          Covenant as described in Bacon’s <hi rend="i">New Atlantis</hi>, with its attendant angels
          guiding it from heaven.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">29</ref>
Wicksteed goes on to note
          the close association between the two arks as the result of the Vulgate’s use of the word
            <hi rend="i">arca</hi> for both, although the Hebrew words for the two arks are quite
          different. A similar association is found in Bryant, who discusses the merging of the
          symbolism of Noah’s ark, the rainbow (God’s first covenant with man), and the Ark of the
          Covenant: “Upon the resting of the ark upon Mount Baris, and the appearance of the Bow in
          the clouds, it pleased God to make a covenant with man . . . A memorial of this was
          preserved in the Gentile worlds. They represented the great event under the type of an Ark
          . . . which they styled Barith, in allusion to the covenant. Some ages after . . . another
          Ark by divine appointment was framed . . . and this too was called the Ark of the
            Covenant.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">30</ref> It is worth
noting, in light of
          Bryant’s comments, that there seems to be a similar linking of Noah’s ark, the rainbow,
          and the Ark of the Covenant in Blake. Blake’s depiction of Noah’s ark in his illustration,
          “Epitome of Hervey’s Meditations Among the Tombs,<supplied type="emend">”</supplied> 
          shows the rainbow above the ark
          illustrated in Bryant, in that both vessels seem to be mirrored or paralleled by the
          rainbow arc in the sky (illus. 6 and 14). In both “Hervey’s Meditations” and the design
          from Bryant, it is almost as if the rainbow covenant and Noah’s ark become analogous
          images, both figures of God’s mercy, a significance that, as I have shown, is appropriate
          for the moon-arks of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as well. 
              <note id="n29"><hi rend="s">29</hi> Joseph Hartley Wicksteed, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Jerusalem: A
              Commentary</hi> (London: Trianon Press, 1954), p. 178.</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi
              rend="s">30</hi> Bryant, p. 429.</note></p>
        <p>Blake himself gave us a visual rendition of the Ark of the Covenant that resembles the
          house-like structure of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 39 (illus. 15). Here, in this
          engraving for the <hi rend="i">Protestant’s Family Bible</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
            type="note">31</ref> Blake has shown Joshua safely crossing <hi rend="i">Jordan</hi>
          through the miraculous powers of the Ark. Blake would not fail to note that both Biblical
          arks had provided salvation from water, both were signs of God’s mercy, both were places
          of refuge (in Noah’s case, for living beings, in the case of the Ark of the Covenant, for
          sacred objects). Moreover, the winged house-boat of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 39 can
          reasonably be said to recall the Biblical description of the Ark of the Covenant found in
          Exodus 37 and 38, for, as Blake himself noted, that Ark was attended by winged cherubim:
          “The holy spirit like a Dove is surrounded by a blue Heaven in which are the two cherubim
          that bowd over the Ark for here the temple is opened in Heaven.” The very next line that
          Blake writes links the Ark of the Covenant with that of Noah, through the image of the
          Dove—“the Ark of the Covenant is as a Dove of Peace.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n32" type="note">32</ref>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">31</hi> Easson and Essick, p. 28.</note>	
            <note id="n32"><hi rend="s">32</hi> William Blake, “A Vision of the Last Judgment,” 
              <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman (Garden City,
            N. Y.: Doubleday &amp; Co., 1965), p. 552.</note></p>
        <figure n="AssyrianWingedMoon.14.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="558">
          <head>12 Assyrian Winged Moon on Assyrian cylinder, from <hi rend="i">Symbolism of Greek
              Coins</hi>, by Agnes Baldwin Brett, 1916.</head>
          <figDesc>Courtesy of the American Numismatic Society.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <p>These subtle yet deep links between the two arks in Blake multiply the iconic force of
          the moon-ark, and extend not only its own range of symbolic reference, but that of Ololon
          as well. Having examined Blake’s transformative vision of traditional iconography, we can
          return to the image of Ololon with a fuller understanding of her identity as a “Moony
          Ark”—as a figure that incorporates many of the symbolic aspects of the arks we have been
          studying.</p>
        <p>Both “Dove upon a stormy sea” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 42:6) (we should remember here
          Blake’s association of the Dove of Noah with the Ark of the Covenant) and “Moony Ark,”
          Ololon descends to Felpham’s Vale. In so doing, she, like the moon-arks of 
            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, transcends the barriers between various states of consciousness and
          being. She contains within herself Beulah’s love, as well as the redemptive, merciful
          qualities that characterize Blake’s moon-ark symbols. Hence, Ololon too is a “Moony Ark,”
          a metaphor that becomes even more suitable because she is female, and thus, in accordance
          with much traditional feminine symbolism, has a mysterious link to the moon and is also a
          type of protective vessel. Even Christ is wrapped in a kind of sheltering mantle by
          Ololon—“wonderful! round his limbs / The Clouds of Ololon folded as a Garment dipped in
          Blood” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 42:11-12). This protective, enclosing aspect of Ololon
          connects her to the Ark of the Covenant, which, in Catholic tradition, was interpreted as
          a type of the protective Virgin.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33"
type="note">33</ref> If, moreover, as
          Roe points out, Beulah is equivalent to Blake’s Purgatory, then Ololon may be his
          “Foederis Arca,” the Church’s traditional symbol of woman as sheltering Ark of the
          Covenant which enshrines the Son of God, as Ololon enwraps Christ. 
              <note id="n33"><hi rend="s">33</hi> Charles L. Souvay, “Ark,” <hi rend="i">The Catholic
            Encyclopedia</hi>, ed. Charles G. Herbermann et al., Vol. I (N. Y.: Robert Appleton Co.,
            1907), p. 724.</note></p>
        <pb id="p14-56" n="56"/>
        <figure n="BlakeTauriLunati.14.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="645">
          <head>13 Blake: “Tauri Lunati,” in Jacob Bryant’s <hi rend="i">Analysis of Antient
              Mythology</hi>, 1807, Vol. III.</head>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p14-57" n="57"/>
        <figure n="BUT770.1.1.WC" rend="file" width="686" height="1000">
          <head>14 Blake: “Epitome of James Hervey’s ‘Meditations Among the Tombs,’” 16 ⅞ × 11 ½
            in.</head>
          <figDesc>Courtesy of the Trustees of the Tate Gallery.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p14-58" n="58"/>
        <figure n="BB419.1.5.COM" rend="file" width="764" height="1000">
          <head>15 Blake: “Joshua Crossing Jordan,” in the <hi rend="i">Protestant’s Family
              Bible.</hi></head>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p14-59" n="59"/>
        <p>In connection with this dimension of Ololon’s symbolism, we might observe that Erich
          Neumann defines images of the ship, and Noah’s ark in particular, as components of the
          “vessel symbolism of the feminine,” and describes the many myths in which the moon
          functions as “the great lamp, the vessel of light of the female godhead.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34"
            type="note">34</ref> Ololon, as both ark and moon, clearly incorporates the powerful
          symbolism Neumann describes. Only when we recognize Ololon’s relation to the moon-ark and
          Ark of the Covenant do these added layers of her meaning become apparent. 
              <note id="n34"><hi rend="s">34</hi> Erich Neumann, <hi rend="i">The Great Mother</hi>, trans.
Ralph
            Manheim (N. Y.: Princeton Univ. Press, 1955), pp. 256-57.</note></p>
        <p>As I indicated earlier, the reference to Ololon as a “Moony Ark” is not clear within the
          context of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> alone. It would seem that Blake had already conceived
          of Ololon’s significance in the terms I have used, yet he did not develop the moon-ark
          image fully and coherently enough for his reader-viewers until he produced the series of
          moon-arks in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Looking back, then, from 
            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, we can perceive how abundant the phrase “Moony Ark” actually is.
          Furthermore, the moon-boat’s relation to the text in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, however
          oblique, is nonetheless definite. A careful attention to the rapport between text and
          design from plate 18 through 39 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> can expand our perception
          of that poem while also shedding light on the figure of Ololon. The similar rapport
          between Blake’s symbolism and earlier motifs can help us more fully understand his
          moon-ark iconography, as well as his creative assimilation of tradition.</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
