<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.2.paley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">J. C. F. Harrison, The Second Coming: Popular Millenarianism 1780-1850</title>
        <author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1980</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Detlef Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Leonard M. Trawick</name>
              <name>Nicholas O. Warner</name>
              <name>Kasumitsu Watarai</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
	<pb id="p14-104" n="104"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-2-0010">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">J. C. F. Harrison. <hi rend="b">The Second Coming, Popular Millenarianism
1780-1850.</hi> New Brunswick, N.J.: Rutgers University Press, 1979. xvii + 230 pp. (with 8 pp. of illus.).
$19.50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Morton D.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Paley</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>As Professor Harrison points out in his “Bibliographical Note,” the subject of popular
millenarianism has not been given serious attention by scholars until comparatively recent times. This is to
distinguish <hi rend="i">popular</hi> millenarianism as a field of study from millenarianism in the Old and
New Testaments and in the early Christian church. The latter has always been a respectable subject for
research, but the former has all too often been relegated to what Harrison calls “the semi-popular synopsis
which provides a rag-bag of freaks, curiosities, imposters and ‘unbelievable’ characters” (p. 264). Norman
Cohn’s <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">The Pursuit of the Millennium</hi>,</corr> first published in 1957, was perhaps the first book
to study popular millenarianism with the seriousness that had previously been given to theological
millenarianism. Cohn’s work, however, is mainly devoted to the medieval period; and its argument that the
movements it studies were precursors of modern totalitarianism may be more pertinent to the Middle Ages than
to the seventeenth century and after. Christopher Hill’s work on seventeenth-century radicalism includes
much of the greatest interest on millenarianism during the Puritan revolution.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n88" type="note">1</ref> For the period in which Blake lived, the indispensable book
on this as well as other aspects of social history is of course <hi rend="i">The Making of the English Working
Class</hi> by E. P. Thompson, first published in 1963. More
<pb id="p14-105" n="105"/>
<figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
recently, Clarke Garrett has surveyed millenarianism during the period of the French Revolution.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n89" type="note">2</ref> To these important books we can now add 
<hi rend="i">The Second Coming</hi>, which studies the millenarianism of a century with considerable erudition,
sympathy and insight. <note id="n88"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See <hi rend="i">Antichrist in Seventeenth-Century
England</hi> (Oxford University Press, 1971) and <hi rend="i">The World Turned Upside Down</hi> (1972; Penguin
ed., 1975).</note>
	<note id="n89"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i"> Respectable Folly: Millenarianism and the French Revolution
in France and England</hi> (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins, 1975).</note></p>
          <p>The first of the three main divisions of <hi rend="i">The Second Coming</hi> provides a useful
overview of the millennial tradition. It does suffer from a problem which besets any overview: there is simply
not enough space to treat important subjects as they deserve. To John Pordage and Jane Lead, for example,
Harrison can devote only a single paragraph, with a second on their follower Richard Roach; yet this circle
has been the subject of an entire book.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n90"
type="note">3</ref> Likewise Swedenborgianism—or rather the millenarian element of
Swedenborgianism—demands far more than the three pages it is given in the second part of <hi rend="i">The
Second Coming.</hi> Nevertheless, the author is right to concentrate on certain aspects of his subject at the
expense of others, for this is not a history of the expectation of the millennium from 1750 to 1850 so much as
a study in depth of two millenarian movements set in a wider perspective. The movements are those of Richard
Brothers and Joanna Southcott. <hi rend="i">The Second Coming</hi> probably gives more details about the
career and adherents of the Prince of the Hebrews than have been presented before, but it is in his study of
Southcott, her followers, and her would-be heirs that Harrison breaks new ground, giving us the beginnings of
a social history of the subject. For example the breakdown of Southcottonians by occupation, while necessarily
incomplete, is fascinating, leading to the conclusion that “With a following made up of artisans, small
tradesman and servants, and a top leadership drawn from the more educated and affluent classes, the believers
were socially parallel to the radical reformers or the Methodists” (pp. 110-11). This type of information,
along with a sense of the historical importance of what people believed to be true (as, for example, in the
case of almanacs), makes <hi rend="i">The Second Coming</hi> an important contribution to our knowledge of the
period in which Blake lived. The third part of the book, devoted mostly to Shakers, Mormons, and Millerites,
is useful chiefly in making comparisons with the subject matter of the second in order to determine what
elements were common to millenarian sects. <note id="n90"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Nils Thune: <hi rend="i">The
Behmenists and the Philadelphians, a Contribution to the Study of English Mysticism in the Seventeenth and
Eighteenth Centuries</hi> (Uppsala: Almquist and Wiksell, 1948).</note></p>
          <p>What of the relation of millenarian movements to Blake himself? A case has been made for
connecting Blake, on the basis of similarities of ideas expressed in printed texts, with the antinomians of
the seventeenth century<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n91" type="note">4</ref>; but Blake
needs to be “placed” in relation to the millenarianism of his own time as well. I think it fair to say that in
this respect <hi rend="i">The Second Coming</hi> does not go beyond my own article of 1973,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n92" type="note">5</ref> although it does make mention of Blake a
number of times and reproduces two pictures it attributes to him. Furthermore, two errors should be corrected.
A quotation from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 27 has been garbled so as to read “ . . . Jerusalem was and is
the Emanation of the Giant Shore” and then continue “Your ancestors derived . . . ” (pp. 80-81). More than
four lines of Blake’s original text have been dropped by the printer here. Also, one picture reproduced as
Blake’s is actually a copy after Blake of <hi rend="i">The Wise and Foolish Virgins</hi>, possibly by John
Linnell<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n93" type="note">6</ref>; and the bracketed title in
the caption for this reproduction, “The Midnight Cry” (alluding to Matt. 25.6) has no authority. In general,
however, the suggestions about Blake and millenarianism in <hi rend="i">The Second Coming</hi> are well taken.
A much more extensive treatment of this subject is now in order, but whoever undertakes it will necessarily
make use of J. C. F. Harrison’s thoughtful and informative book. <note id="n91"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See A.
L. Morton, <hi rend="i">The Everlasting Gospel</hi> (London: Lawrence and Wishart, 1957).</note>
	<note id="n92"><hi rend="s">5</hi> “William Blake, the Prince of the Hebrews, and the Woman Clothed with the
Sun,” <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays in Honour of Sir Geoffrey Keynes</hi>, ed. Morton D. Paley and
Michael Phillips (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1973), pp. 260-93.</note>
	<note id="n93"><hi rend="s">6</hi> See Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">William Blake: a Complete Catalogue of the
Works in the Tate Gallery</hi>, rev. ed. (London: Tate Gallery, 1971), p. 54, no. 44.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
