<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.2.minnick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="checklist">Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Recent Scholarship</title>
        <author n="Minnick">Thomas L. Minnick</author>
        <author n="Dörrbecker">Detlef W. Dörrbecker</author>
        <author n="Watarai">Kasumitsu Watarai</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1980</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Detlef Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Leonard M. Trawick</name>
              <name>Nicholas O. Warner</name>
              <name>Kasumitsu Watarai</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <pb id="p14-85" n="85"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-2-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">BLAKE AND HIS CIRCLE: A CHECKLIST OF RECENT SCHOLARSHIP</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">THOMAS L.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">MINNICK</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
          <hi rend="b">WITH THE ASSISTANCE OF</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">DETLEF W.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">DÖRRBECKER</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
          <hi rend="b">AND</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">KASUMITSU</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">WATARAI</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>As we promised last year, this edition of the checklist of recent scholarship on Blake and his
circle incorporates several modifications that will, we hope, help to make it more useful. We have increased
the amount of annotation and have set items on Blake’s circle into a separate section. Works that treat
Blake and one or more of his circle are listed in Part I, “William Blake,” and cross-referenced in Part II,
“Blake’s Circle.”</p>
        <p>By the time this year’s checklist is published, several important (but at this writing still
imminent) works may be available to Blake’s public. However near to publication they may be, we do not
include them here, though we look forward eagerly to Butlin’s catalogue and the <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> of Erdman, Grant, and Tolley, among other major forthcoming works.</p>
        <p>Authors whom we have overlooked are encouraged to bring unnoted items to our attention. I’d like
to extend a special word of thanks to Ray Thompson (of Columbus, Ohio) for passing on several important items,
and to G. E. Bentley, Jr., for continuing helpful correspondence.</p>
        <p>T. L. M.</p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">PART I</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">WILLIAM BLAKE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">EDITIONS, TRANSLATIONS, FACSIMILES, REPRODUCTIONS</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Bindman, David, ed., assisted by Deirdre Toomey. <hi rend="i">Het complete grafische werk van
William Blake.</hi> Amsterdam: Meulenhoff, 1978. [The Dutch edition of this important compilation which was
first published in London and New York.]</p>
            <p>Blake, William. <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">Bodas del cielo y del infierno y las Puertas del Paraíso</hi>,</corr>
trsl. Carlo Liberio del Zotti. Zaragoza: Litho Arte, 1976 [“Biblioteca esencial”].</p>
            <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">Cancons d’Innocencia i d’Experiencia</hi>, trsl. Antoni
Turull. Barcelona: Curial Edicions Catalanes, 1975 [“Llibres del Mall”].</p>
            <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">Canti dell’ innocenza e dell’ esperienza</hi>, trsl. and ed.
G. Gallizzi. Milan: MIRCU, n.d.</p>
            <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">Cantos de Inocencia: Cantos de Experienca</hi>, trsl. Elena
Valenti. Barcelona: Bosch, 1977 [“Erasmo,” textos bilingues].</p>
            <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">Llibres profétics de William Blake</hi>, trsl. María Manent.
Barcelona: Edicions 62, 1976 [“Escorpi-Poesia”].</p>
            <pb id="p14-86" n="86"/>
            <p>Grant, John. <hi rend="i">See</hi> Johnson, Mary Lynn.</p>
            <p>Johnson, Mary Lynn, and John Grant, eds. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Poetry and Designs.</hi> [A
Norton Critical Edition.] New York and London: W. W. Norton &amp; Co., 1979.</p>
            <p>Keynes, <hi rend="i">Sir</hi> Geoffrey, ed. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations of Dante.</hi>
London: for The William Blake Trust, 1978. [A Trianon Press edition, limited to 440 copies priced from
£360.]</p>
            <p>Schmitz, Siegfried, ed. “William Blake,” in <hi rend="i">Lyrik der englischen Romantik.</hi>
Munich: Winkler, 1967 [“Die Fundgrube,” vol. 31], pp. 7-20.</p>
            <p>Toomey, Deirdre. <hi rend="i">See</hi> Bindman, David.</p>
            <p>Yeats, William Butler, ed. <hi rend="i">The Poems of William Blake.</hi> London, 1905;
reprinted London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1979. Paper, £2.50.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">BIBLIOGRAPHIES, BIBLIOGRAPHICAL ESSAYS, EXHIBITION CATALOGUES</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Allen, Robert R., ed. “William Blake (1757-1827).” Pp. 250-257 in <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth
Century: A Current Bibliography, n.s.—for 1975.</hi> Philadelphia and Los Angeles: The American Society for
Eighteenth-Century Studies, 1978.</p>
            <p>Bentley, G.E., Jr. “‘The Eternal Wheels of Intellect’: Dissertations on William Blake.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 224-243.</p>
            <p>Carey, Frances A. “Angleterre: ‘Gothic Revival’,” in Louis Grodecki et al., <hi rend="i">Le
‘Gothique’ retrouvé avant Viollet-le-Duc.</hi> [Exhibition catalogue.] Paris: Caisse National des
Monuments Historiques et des Sites, 1979. [Three of the drawings for Gough’s <hi rend="i">Sepulchral
Monuments</hi> which are attributed to Blake were shown as nos. 15-17 in this exhibition at the Hotel de
Sully.]</p>
            <p>Dörrbecker, Detlef W., and Marta Slowikovà. “Some Minor Additions to Bentley’s ‘Blake
Among the Slavs’.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 198.</p>
            <p>Dörrbecker, Detlef W. <hi rend="i">See also</hi> Minnick, Thomas L. Erdman, David V., ed.
“Blake” in <hi rend="i">The Romantic Movement: A Selective and Critical Bibliography for 1978. English
Language Notes</hi>, 17, supp. to no. 1 (1979), 60-72.</p>
            <p>Gage, John, ed. <hi rend="i">SWEI Jahrhunderte Englische Malerei: Britische Kunst und Europa
1680 bis 1880.</hi> [Exhibition catalogue.] Munich: Haus der Kunst, 1979. [Barry, Blake, Calvert, Flaxman,
Fuseli, Linnell, Palmer etc. were represented in this exhibition; the catalogue—some six hundred pages—was
written by John Gage, Michael Kitson, William Vaughan, and Christopher White.]</p>
            <p>Keitel, Bruce, comp. <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter and Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly: A
Cumulative Index 1967-1978 Vols. 1-11.</hi> Albuquerque, New Mexico: for <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 1980.</p>
            <p>Minnick, Thomas L., with the assistance of Detlef W. Dörrbecker and Kazumitsu Watarai. “Blake
&amp; His Circle: A Checklist of Recent Scholarship.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 13
(1979), 91-99.</p>
            <p>Modern Language Association of America. “Blake, William” in <hi rend="i">1978 MLA International
Bibliography on the Modern Languages and Literatures.</hi> Vol. I, 101-103.</p>
            <p>Slowikovà, Marta. <hi rend="i">See</hi> Dörrbecker, Detlef W. Tomory, Peter A. 
<hi rend="i">The Poetical Circle: Fuseli and the British.</hi> [Exhibition catalogue.] Florence: Centro Di, for
the Australian Gallery Directors’ Council, 1979 [Centro Di cat. 108]. [The exhibition included, besides the
Auckland Fuselis, works by James Barry, William Blake, John Brown, John Flaxman, James Jefferys, John Hamilton
Mortimer, Goerge Romney, and Alexander Runciman.] Watarai, Kazumitsu. “A Bibliography of William Blake in
Japan, 1969-1977.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 198-201.</p>
            <p>Watarai, Kazumitsu. <hi rend="i">See also</hi> Minnick, Thomas L.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">CRITICAL STUDIES</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Aers, David R. “William Blake and the Dialectics of Sex.” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi>, 44 (1977),
500-514.</p>
            <p>Alkjaer, Niels. “William Blake: Köpist, hanvaerker, kunster.” Pp. 94-128 in Nynne Koch, Povl
Meisner, and Frede Møller-Kristensen, eds., <hi rend="i">Det indre invers.</hi> Copenhagen: Rhodos/Det
kongelige Bibliothek, 1972.</p>
            <p>Allen, Orphia Jane. “William Blake’s Criticism of the English Poets.” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 40 (1979), 2068-A. Diss., University of Oklahoma, 1979.
[Discusses Blake on Chaucer, Shakespeare, Spenser, Milton, Young, Gray, Blair, Wordsworth, and Byron as a
“significant body of archetypal literary criticism.”]</p>
            <p>Anonymous. “William Blake and Samuel Palmer: The Vision and the Vision Recaptured.” 
<hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi>, 28 (1979), 7 ff.</p>
            <p>Baine, Rodney M., and Mary R. Baine. “Blake’s ‘Blossom’.” <hi rend="i">Colby Library
Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1978), 22-27.</p>
            <p>Behrendt, Stephen C. “<hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained:</hi>
Blake’s View of Trial in the Wilderness.” <hi rend="i">Milton and the Romantics</hi>, 3 (1977), 8-13.</p>
            <p>Behrendt, Stephen C. “‘The Worst Disease’: Blake’s <hi rend="i">Tiriel.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1979), 175-187.</p>
            <p>Bentley, E. B. “Vision in Fiction: Two Novels About William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 209-210.</p>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Almost Blake.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 13
(1979), 109.</p>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “‘A Different Face’: William Blake and Mary Wollstonecraft.” 
<hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 10 (1979), 349-350.</p>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “The Disconcerting Riches of <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 10 (1979), 126-128.</p>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Echoes of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> Designs in 1838.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 207-209.</p>
            <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. “‘New’ Blake Engravings after Blake’s Designs, 1837, 1859, 
            <corr type="emend">1861.”</corr> <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 204.</p>
            <p>Bidney, Martin. “<hi rend="i">Cain</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi>: Contexts for
Understanding Blake’s Response to Byron.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 8 (1979), 145-165.</p>
            <p>Bidney, Martin. “Urizen and the Comedy of Automatism in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi>, 56 (1977), 204-220.</p>
            <p>Bindman, David. “Blake and Runge,” pp. 86-95 in <hi rend="i">Runge: Fragen und Antworten.</hi>
Munich: Prestel, 1979. [One of the papers read on occasion of the symposion organized by the Hamburg
Kunsthalle in connection with their Runge exhibition in 1978.]</p>
            <p>Bindman, David. “A New Blake Drawing in the
<pb id="p14-87" n="87"/>
Boston Museum of Fine Art.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 205-206.</p>
            <p>Bogan, James Joseph, Jr. “A Guidebook to William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 40 (1980), 4603-A. Diss., University of Kansas, 1979.
[Includes discussion of the critical reception of the poem, its autobiographical elements, the psychology of
Albion, the geography of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, the “rhythms and plot” of the poem, and a reading of the
pictures.]</p>
            <p>Borné, Gerhard F. <hi rend="i">Christlicher Atheismus und radikales Christentum: Studien zur
Theologie von Thomas Altizer im Zusammenhang mit Ketzereien der Kirchengeschichte, der Dichtung von William
Blake und der Philosophie von Georg Friedrich Wilhelm Hegel.</hi> Munich: Chr. Kaiser, 1979. [For a discussion
of Altizer’s interpretation of Blake see pp. 95-165.]</p>
            <p>Bottrall, Margaret. “Blake’s Songs of Innocence and Experience.” Battle, East Sussex. 1979.
[This item is a cassette tape, number 11 in the series “The Critical Forum,” available from Norwich Tapes
Ltd., Markfield House, Caldbec Hill, BATTLE, East Sussex TN 33 OJS.]</p>
            <p>Bouwer, Izak and Paul McNally, “‘The Mental Traveller’: Man’s Eternal Journey.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 184-192.</p>
            <p>Brinkley, Robert A. “Romanticism and the Desire Called Milton.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation
Abstracts International</hi>, 40 (1980), 4603-A. Diss., University of Massachusetts, 1979. [Discusses Romantic
views—Blake’s, Wordsworth’s, Keats’s—of Miltonic vision, using Harold Bloom’s criticism as a
foil.]</p>
            <p>Butlin, Martin. “An Illustration to Robert Bage.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 202.</p>
            <p>Butlin, Martin. “Thoughts on the 1978 Tate Gallery Exhibition.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 13 (1979), 16-23.</p>
            <p>Carr, Stephen Leo. “‘Striving with Systems’: William Blake’s Print-making Process and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 40 (1979), 867-A. Diss.,
University of Michigan, 1979. [“Blake’s process of producing his illuminated books is the antithesis or
‘contrary’ of contemporary systems of engraving.”]</p>
            <p>Cheskin, Arnold. “The Echoing Greenhorn: Blake as Hebraist.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 178-183.</p>
            <p>Christian, Diane. “Inversion and the Erotic: The Case of William Blake.” Pp. 91-98 in Barbara
A. Babcock, ed., <hi rend="i">The Reversible World: Symbolic Inversion in Art and Society.</hi> Ithaca, New
York: Cornell University Press, 1978.</p>
            <p>Clifford, Mallory Young. “The Storyteller’s Apology: A Study of Truth and Storytelling in the
<hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi>, Genesis, Spenser, Milton, and Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
International</hi>, 40 (1980), 5041-A. Diss., State University of New York at Buffalo, 1979. [“In the Blakean
conception . . . truth resides in art itself. But experience is not thereby reduced to the ‘aesthetic’.”
Discusses storytelling in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>]</p>
            <p>Conner, William Fox. “Satan as Negative Consciousness in Milton, Blake, and Shelley.” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 40 (1980), 4604-A-4605-A. Diss., University of Missouri,
Columbia, 1979. [Investigates “the unique role of Satan in the evolution of consciousness that has taken place
from the time of Milton through the romantic period,” focusing on Blake’s <hi rend="i">Book of Urizen,
Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in chapter 3.]</p>
            <p>Curtis, F. B. “William Blake and Eighteenth-Century Medicine.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>,
8 (1979), 187-199.</p>
            <p>DeLuca, V. A. “The Lost Traveller’s Dream: Blake and the Seductions of Continuity.” 
<hi rend="i">Ariel</hi>, 11 (1980), 49-69. [Focuses on Urizen, journeying in Night VI of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>, as a lost traveller.]</p>
            <p>Dorfman, Deborah. “‘King of Beauty’ and ‘Golden World’ in Blake’s ‘America’: The
Reader and the Archetype.” <hi rend="i">ELH: Journal of English Literary History</hi>, 46 (1979), 122-135.</p>
            <p>Doskow, Minna. “William Blake’s <hi rend="i">America</hi>: The Story of a Revolution
Betrayed.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 8 (1979), 167-186.</p>
            <p>Duplantier, F. R. “Method in Blake’s ‘Mad Song’.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 13 (1979), 102-104.</p>
            <p>Erdman, David V. “South Bounding.’” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 13
(1979), 106-107.</p>
            <p>Franson, J. Karl. “The Serpent-Driving Females in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 4.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 164-177.</p>
            <p>Franz, Rolaine Marie. “All the Ship’s Company: A Wesleyan Paradigm for the Poetry of
Christopher Smart, William Cowper, and William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>,
39 (1979), 5523-A. Diss., Brown University, 1978. [Not a study of sources, this dissertation “explores the
Wesleyan theology as a mode for reading” Blake and Cowper: “Blake used the hymn tradition—it becomes more
than analogue in his writing—most obviously as he composed <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience.</hi>”]</p>
            <p>Frost, Everett C. “William Blake’s John Taylor.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>, n.s.
26, no. 1 (February 1979), 48-49.</p>
            <p>Gandolfo, Anita. “Whose Blake Did Joyce Know and What Difference Does It Make?” 
<hi rend="i">James Joyce Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1978), 215-221.</p>
            <p>George, Diana Hume. “Is She Also the Divine Image? Feminine Form in the Art of William Blake.”
<hi rend="i">The Centennial Review</hi>, 23 (1979), 129-140.</p>
            <p>George, Diana Hume. “Is She Also the Divine Image? Values for the Feminine in Blake, Milton,
and Freud.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 37 (1979), 7356-A. Diss., SUNY, Buffalo,
1979. [Argues first that “Milton was of the woman’s party without knowing it.” Then argues that “in her most
expansive, creative, and most fully human form, woman is indeed the divine image for Blake. But in the fallen
world, Blake sees her as the servant of materialism and the victim of repression.”]</p>
            <p>Gittings, Fred. <hi rend="i">The Hidden Art. A Study of Occult Symbolism in Art.</hi> London:
Studio Vista, 1978. [Pages 109-160 form a chapter entitled “The Divine Principle: Blake, Varley, and the
Spirits of the Past.”]</p>
            <p>Glausser, Wayne Edward. “Blake and the Daughters of Memory.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation
Abstracts International</hi>, 40 (1979), 267-A. Diss., Yale University, 1978. [Glausser “attempts to penetrate
beneath Blake’s explicit rejection of memory as a visionary resource, and finds in his epic poetry a more
difficult struggle with the powers and dangers
<pb id="p14-88" n="88"/>
of retrospection.”]</p>
            <p>Gleckner, Robert F. “Blake’s ‘I Saw a Chapel All of Gold’.” <hi rend="i">Colby Library
Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1979), 37-47.</p>
            <p>Gleckner, Robert F. “Priestly and the Chameleon Angel in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven
and Hell.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 13 (1979), 37-39.</p>
            <p>Goslee, Nancy M. “From Marble to Living Form: Sculpture as Art and Analogue from the
Renaissance to Blake.” <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi>, 77 (1978), 188-211.</p>
            <p>Greenberg, Mark. “Blake’s Vortex.” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1978),
198-212.</p>
            <p>Greenberg, Mark Lawrence. “Dante Gabriel Rossetti and William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation
Abstracts International</hi>, 37 (1979), 6141-A-6142-A. Diss., University of Michigan, 1978. [Argues that
“Blake shapes Rossetti’s concept of art and, concomitantly, provides a remarkable range of images, ideas,
and techniques which Rossetti incorporates in his compositions . . . . A proto-Pre-Raphaelite, Rossetti’s
Blake becomes the forerunner of a new school of painting and writing which Rossetti perceives himself
culminate.”]</p>
            <p>Grove, Robin. “Blake: The Note of Innocence.” <hi rend="i">Melbourne Critical Review</hi>, no.
21 (1979), 45-56.</p>
            <p>Hall, Carol Louise. “Henry Fuseli and the Aesthetics of William Blake: Fuseli as Transmitter of
J. J. Winckelmann, J. J. Rousseau, and J. C. Lavater.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>,
40 (1979), 2651-A-2652-A. Diss., University of Maryland, 1979. [“ . . . examines the role of Henry Fuseli . .
. as a transmitter of German and Swiss preromantic ideas to the English poet William Blake. . . .” Part II is
“Fuseli and Blake: Documentary Evidence of Their Friendship”; part III is “Blake and Fuseli’s Winckelmann”;
part IV is “Blake and Fuseli’s Rousseau”; part V is “Blake and Fuseli’s Lavater.”]</p>
            <p>Haraguchi, Masao. “W. Blake saku ‘Albion no musume tachi no genso’ ni tsuite no ichikosatsu
[An Approach to William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Kyushu
Sangyo Kaigaku Kyoyobu Kiyo</hi> [<hi rend="i">Bulletin of The College of Liberal Arts, Kyushu Sangyo
University</hi>], 15, 2 (1979), 53-71.</p>
            <p>Heinzelman, Kurt. “William Blake and the Economics of the Imagination.” <hi rend="i">Modern
Language Quarterly</hi>, 39 (1978), 99-120.</p>
            <p>Helms, Randel. “Blake’s Use of the Bible in ‘A Song of Liberty’.” <hi rend="i">English
Language Notes</hi>, 16 (1979), 287-291.</p>
            <p>Helms, Randel. “Why Ezekiel Ate Dung.” <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi>, 15 (1978),
279-281.</p>
            <p>Heppner, Christopher. “Another ‘New’ Blake Engraving: More About Blake &amp; William
Nicholson.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 193-197.</p>
            <p>Hilton, Nelson. “A Note on Cowper and ‘A Poison Tree’.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 203.</p>
            <p>Hilton, Howard Nelson. “Revelation in the Litteral Expression: Blake’s Polysemous Words.” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 40 (1979), 2073-A-2074-A. Diss., University of California,
Santa Cruz, 1979. [Discusses Blake’s uses of polysemy and treats his word play with “chains,”
“grave/engrave,” “morning/mourning,” “lamentation,” “fibres, nerves, and the polypus,” “weaving,” “veil, vale,
and Vala,” “stars,” “vortex and wheel,” “mountains,” and “spectre.”]</p>
            <p>Hinkel, Howard H. “From Energy and Desire to Eternity: Blake’s <hi rend="i">Visions of the
Daughters of Albion.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Papers on Language &amp; Literature</hi>, 15 (1979), 278-289.</p>
            <p>Hoagwood, Terence Allan. “Prophecy and the Philosophy of Mind in the Poetry of Blake and
Shelley.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 40 (1979), 2696-A. Diss., University of
Maryland, 1979. [“Romantic Symbolism is the result of Romantic idealism which is in turn the point of contact
between empirical philosophy and prophecy. These contrary traditions, sacred and profane, unite in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and <hi rend="i">Prometheus Unbound</hi>, which are two examples of a new literary
form—Romantic prophecy.”]</p>
            <p>Hori, Keiko. “William Blake: sono dokusôteki geijutsu no sekai -<hi rend="i">The Marriage of
Heaven and Hell</hi> ni tsuite no ichikosatsu [William Blake: On His Creative Art—A Study of 
<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Kobe Kaisei Jogakuin Daigaku Kenkyu Kiyo</hi>
[<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Kobe Kaisei Women’s University</hi>], 17 (1978), 79-99.</p>
            <p>Horn, William Dennis. “Blake’s Gnosticism: The Material World as Allegory.” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 39 (1979), 5527-A. Diss., University of California, Los
Angeles, 1978. [“This study examines Blake’s Gnosticism in terms of his use of traditional forms of
allegorical representation, the Gnostic practice of parodying the biblical Genesis, the deprecation of the
physical world which Blake voiced with true Gnostic fervor, and the continuation into modern critical theory
of certain Romantic attitudes which have their ultimate basis in Gnostic thought.”]</p>
            <p>Jackson, John R. de. <hi rend="i">Poetry of the Romantic Period.</hi> London: Routledge and
Kegan Paul, 1979 [“Routledge History of English Poetry,” vol. 4].</p>
            <p>Jacobson, Sibyl C. “The Creation and Fall in the ‘Book of Urizen’ and the ‘Book of
Los’—A Study of Corresponding Images.” <hi rend="i">Concerning Poetry</hi>, 12 (1979), 61-74.</p>
            <p>James, David E. “Angels out of the Sun: Art, Religion and Politics in Blake’s ‘America’.”
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 18 (1979), 235-252.</p>
            <p>James, G. Ingli. “Some Not-So-Familiar Visionary Heads.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 244-249.</p>
            <p>Keynes, <hi rend="i">Sir</hi> Geoffrey. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Spectre.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi>, 28 (1979), 60-66.</p>
            <p>Kilgore, John Dodge. “The Human Universal: Studies in the Structure of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 39 (1979), 6144-A. Diss., University of
California, Irvine, 1979. [Argues that “ . . . the ‘human forms’ of which Blake’s zoas are the supreme
exemplars must replace or absorb both the abstract universals of reflective thought and the sensuous objects
of fallen experience, so that the world appears in the image of the human faculties, fully identified with the
mind. A consistent application of these principles to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> clarifies both the form
and language of the epic.”]</p>
            <p>King, James. “Charlotte Smith, William Cowper, and William Blake: Some New Documents.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 13 (1979), 100-101.</p>
            <p>Koyabashi, Keiko. “Blake no inritsu -shoki shihen o chushin ni shite [Blake’s Prosody in His
Early
<pb id="p14-89" n="89"/>
Poetical Works].” <hi rend="i">Gaikokubungaku kenkyu, Ritsumeikan Daigaku Jinbunkagaku Kenkyusho</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">Studies in Foreign Literatures, The Research Institute of the Cultural Sciences, Ritsumeikan
University</hi>], 47 (1980), 25-44.</p>
            <p>LaBelle, Jenijoy. “Blake and Morland: The First State of ‘The Industrious Cottager’.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 258-261.</p>
            <p>Lange, Thomas V. “Blake’s Engraving of Wollstonecraft After Opie.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 13 (1979), 36-37. [A later issue of this journal corrects the title of Lange’s
article to “An Engraving of Wollstonecraft After Opie.”]</p>
            <p>Leader, Zachary. “Blake’s Symbols.” <hi rend="i">Essays in Criticism</hi>, 29 (1979),
81-88.</p>
            <p>Leonard, David Charles. “Erasmus Darwin and William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century
Life</hi>, 4 (1978), 79-81.</p>
            <p>Levitt, Annette S. “Comus, Cloud, and Thel’s ‘Unacted Desires’.” <hi rend="i">Colby
Library Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1978), 72-83.</p>
            <p>Lindsay, David W. “Blake’s Imitation of Sterne: The Unity of ‘An Island in the Moon’.”
<hi rend="i">Archiv für das Studium der neueren Sprachen und Literaturen</hi>, 215 (1978), 102-103.</p>
            <p>Maeda, Masahiko. “E. Young ‘Yaso’ eno Blake no sashie -hyoshaku no kokoromi sono 2-
[Illustrations to E. Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> by William Blake—An Attempt of the
Annotation No. 2-].” <hi rend="i">Eibeibungaku, Rikkyo Daigaku Bungakubu Eibeibungaku Kenkyushitsu</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">English and American Literature, The Rikkyo Review, Arts and Letters, The Department of Literature of
Rikkyo University</hi>], 39 (1979), 177-267.</p>
            <p>Malmqvist, Göran. “The Dean of Morocco = George Cumberland?” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 13 (1979), 109.</p>
            <p>Malmqvist, N. G. D. “Blake in China.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 13
(1979), 24-28.</p>
            <p>McGowan, James. “The Integrity of the <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>: A New Approach to
Blake’s Earliest Poems.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 8 (1979), 121-144.</p>
            <p>McNally, Paul. <hi rend="i">See</hi> Bouwer, Izak.</p>
            <p>Mulhallen, Karen. “William Blake’s Milton Portraiture and Eighteenth Century Milton
Iconography.” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1978), 7-21.</p>
            <p>Murphy, Karen Middleton. “The Emanations of the Four Zoas: Ahania, Enion, Vala, Enitharmon.”
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 40 (1979), 2077-A. Diss., University of Toledo, 1979.
[Discusses the relationship of each Emanation to her Zoa and to the Fall, the Emanation as a dramatic
character, the eternal function of the Emanation, and the Emanation as “the artistic product or poetic text,
and some theorizing as to what each Emanation, as a feminine counterpart of a psychological aspect of Albion,
contributes as a component to creativity.”]</p>
            <p>Myers, Victoria. “The Dialogue as Interpretive Focus in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi>, 56 (1977), 221-239.</p>
            <p><corr type="emend">Nanavutty, Piloo.</corr> “Blake’s Satan.” <hi rend="i">The Aligarh Journal of English Studies</hi>,
3 (1978), 166-198.</p>
            <p>Norvig, Gerda S. “Images of Wonder, Images of Truth: Blake’s Illustrations to 
<hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 37 (1979),
7360-A-7361-A. Diss., Brande is University, 1979. [Treats Blake’s “engagement with the myth, the method and
the meaning of John Bunyan’s <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>—a life-long preoccupation culminating,
in 1824, in the set of 28 watercolor drawings” examined in chapter 3 of this study.]</p>
            <p>Ogude, S. E. “Swedenborg and Blake’s ‘Little Black Boy’.” <hi rend="i">Asemka: A Literary
Journal of the University of Cape Coast</hi>, 4 (1976), 85-96.</p>
            <p>Paley, Morton D. “‘A New Heaven is Begun’: William Blake and Swedenborgianism.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 13 (1979), 64-90.</p>
            <p>Phillips, Michael. “William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> from Manuscript Draft to Illuminated Plate.” <hi rend="i">Book
Collector</hi>, 28 (1979), 17-59.</p>
            <p>Privateer, Paul Charles. “The Romantic <hi rend="i">Cogito</hi>: Poetic Identity in Blake and
Wordsworth.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 39 (1979), 7361-A. Diss., University of
California, Davis, 1978. [A phenomenological approach to “the ‘transubjective’ aspect of English
romanticism,” showing that Blake’s and Wordsworth’s evolving <hi rend="i">cogitos</hi> “can be understood
as a conscious effort to communicate . . . the reality of what it means to struggle with the ambitious terror
and freedom of subjectivity” and that romantic literature attempts to “unify experience and consciousness in a
universal vision of human reality.”]</p>
            <p>Raine, Kathleen J. <hi rend="i">Blake and the New Age.</hi> London: Allen and Unwin, 1979.
Reviewed by Peter Redgrove, <hi rend="i">The Guardian</hi> [London], 29 November 1979, p. 14.</p>
            <p>Raine, Kathleen J. <hi rend="i">From Blake to ‘A Vision’.</hi> London: Dolmen Press, 1979
[“New Yeats Papers”]. Reviewed by Peter Redgrove, <hi rend="i">The Guardian</hi> [London], 29 November 1979,
p. 14.</p>
            <p>Rao, Valli. “Vivie Warren in the Blakean World of Experience.” <hi rend="i">The Shaw
Review</hi>, 22 (1979), 123-134. [After reviewing evidence of G. B. Shaw’s continued interest in Blake, Rao
studies <hi rend="i">Mrs. Warren’s Profession</hi> “in terms of Blake’s early ideas of innocence and
experience, but with no concern for any direct indebtedness on Shaw’s part to Blake.”]</p>
            <p>Reeves, William J. “Blake and Dickens: The Similar Vision.” <hi rend="i">American Notes and
Queries</hi>, 17, no. 3 (November, 1978), 37-40. [Focuses on “London,” “Holy Thursday,” and 
<hi rend="i">Oliver Twist.</hi>]</p>
            <p>Rose, Edward J. “The Shape of Blake’s Vision.” <hi rend="i">Bucknell Review</hi>, 23 (1977),
57-77.</p>
            <p>Roth, James Peter. “The Bible of Hell: William Blake’s Lambeth Books.” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 40 (1980), 5454-A-5455-A. Diss., University of Wisconsin,
Milwaukee, 1979. [Includes close readings of the Lambeth books, “focusing on the interaction of poetry and
visual art within them.”]</p>
            <p>Schwinning, Heiner. <hi rend="i">Dichtung und Radikalismus in der Epoche 1780-1806: Studien zu
Blake, Wordsworth und Burns.</hi> Frankfurt am Main, Bern and Las Vegas: Peter Lang, 1979 [“European
University Papers,” Series XIV: Anglo-Saxon Language and Literature, vol. 67]. [Part II:A, pp. 53-134 of this
Ph.D. thesis are devoted to a discussion of Blake’s radical inclinations.]</p>
            <p>Shain, Ronald. “A Sociological Study of the Romantic Imagination: Blake’s Mythic Conception
of Man’s Fall Into Outer Selfhood.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 39 (1979),
6783-A. Diss.,
<pb id="p14-90" n="90"/>
University of California, Santa Barbara, 1976. [Examines “Blake’s conception of metaphysical
self-estrangement,” concentrating on the fall of the self, first into Eden, then into materialism.] Sherry,
Margaret Meyer. “The Human Form Divine, the Marionette and the Actor: Articulation of the Subject in William
Blake, Heinrich von Kleist, and Bertolt Brecht.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 39
(1979), 5494-A-5495-A. Diss., The Johns Hopkins University, 1978. [Includes discussion of Blake’s autograph
in the album of William Upcott, <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, and the Notebook.]</p>
            <p>Shroyer, R. J. “Blake’s Copy of Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man</hi>: A Correction
of G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 13
(1979), 108.</p>
            <p>Shroyer, R. J. “Mr. Jacko ‘Knows What Riding Is’ in 1785: Dating Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Island in the Moon.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 250-256.</p>
            <p>Smailes, T. A. “William Blake: Two Notes.” <hi rend="i">Unisa English Studies: Journal of the
Department of English, University of South Africa</hi>, 15 (1977), 21-23.</p>
            <p>Stepto, Michael Leiss. “Mothers and Fathers in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">The Yale Review</hi>, 67 (1978), 357-370.</p>
            <p>Stuart Simon. <hi rend="i">New Phoenix Wings: Literature and Reparation.</hi> London: Routledge
and Kegan Paul, 1979. [Deals prominently with Blake and Wordsworth.]</p>
            <p>Suzuki, Hiroshi. “Yeat no ‘Vision’ to Blake [Blake and Yeats’s ‘A Vision’].” 
<hi rend="i">Kyoyo Shogaku Kenkyu</hi> [<hi rend="i">Journal of Liberal Arts, The Liberal Arts Research Center,
The School of Political Science and Economics, Waseda University</hi>], 58-60 (1979), 119-139.</p>
            <p>Suzuki, Masashi. “Blake to Collins no setten - gijinho to kekken no onyu [What Connects Blake
with Collins—Personification and the Metaphor of Marriage].” <hi rend="i">Eigo to Eibeibungaku, Yamaguchi
Daigaku Bunrigakubu Eibeibungaku Kenkyushitsu</hi> [<hi rend="i">English and Anglo-American Literature, The
Departments of English and American Literature of Yamaguchi University</hi>], 13 (1978), 45-62.</p>
            <p>Suzuki, Masashi. “Kodomo no ‘Image’ no henbo-<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and
Experience</hi> no ichikosatsu [Transformations of the Image of Child—An Essay on <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence and Experience</hi>].” <hi rend="i">Eigo to Eibeibungaku, Yamaguchi Daigaku Bunrigakubu Eibeibungaku
Kenkyushitsu</hi> [<hi rend="i">English and Anglo-American Literature, The Departments of English and American
Literature of Yamaguchi University</hi>], 12 (1977), 33-59.</p>
            <p>Thompson, Raymond E. “The ‘Double’ of the Double Portrait of Blake: A Description of
Tatham’s Replica Portrait.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 13 (1979), 29-32.</p>
            <p>Thorpe, James. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Power of the Imagination.</hi> San Marino, Cal.:
The Huntington Library, 1979.</p>
            <p>Utsunomiya, Tariho. “Blake no shikai -inochi no eizo to jitsuzon eno michi [Blake’s
Imaginative World—The Soul and its Path of Eternal Life].” <hi rend="i">Sonoda Gakuen Joshi Daigaku
Ronbunshu</hi> [<hi rend="i">Sonoda Women’s College Studies</hi>], 13 (1978), 117-130.</p>
            <p>Wagner, Brian John. “Affinities of Imaginative Conception and Expressive Form between Primitive
Initiation Rituals and Major Works of William Blake and D. H. Lawrence.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
International</hi>, 40 (1979), 3326-A. Diss., Kansas State University, 1979. [The “desire to produce an
existential change in the reader by altering his perception relates the works of Blake and Lawrence to many
puberty initiation rituals . . . .”]</p>
            <p>Wardle, Judith. “Blake and Iconography: Analogues of Urizen and Vala.” <hi rend="i">Colby
Library Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1978), 125-165.</p>
            <p>Warnke, Martin. “Inszenierte Widersprüche: William Blake,” in <hi rend="i">Künstler,
Kunsthistoriker, Museen: Beiträge zu einer kritischen Kunstgeschichte</hi>, ed. Heinrich Klotz. Luzern and
Frankfurt am Main: C. J. Bucher, 1979 [“Bucher Report,” vol. 6], pp. 45-51.</p>
            <p>Water, Gregory. “Blake and Rossetti.” <hi rend="i">English Record</hi>, 29 (1978), 23-27.</p>
            <p>Watson, J. R. “The Romantics.” <hi rend="i">Critical Quarterly</hi>, 21 (1979), 3-15. [Pp. 6-8
discuss Blake’s concept of the prophet.]</p>
            <p>Weber, Dwight E. “William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>: A
Poem Based on Doubt.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 203-204.</p>
            <p>Welch, Dennis M. “Blake’s Response to Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Original Stories.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 13 (1979), 4-15.</p>
            <p>Wills, James T. “‘For I Discern Thee Other Then thou Seem’st’: An Extra Illustration for
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> Series.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 8 (1979), 109-119.</p>
            <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr. “Blake’s Milton: ‘To Immortals, . . . a Mighty Angel’.”
<hi rend="i">Milton Studies</hi>, 11 (1978), 51-82.</p>
            <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr. <hi rend="i">Visionary Poetics: Milton’s Tradition and His
Legacy.</hi> San Marino, CA: The Huntington Library, 1979. $18.50. Reviewed by Roy Flanagan, 
<hi rend="i">Milton Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 23.</p>
            <p>Wurtenberger, Franzsepp. “Musik im Sturm und Drang: W. Blake—Der musikbegeisterte Literat W.
Heinse und der Typus des musikalischen Malers in der Dichtung,” in <hi rend="i">Malerei und Musik: Die
Geschichte des Verhaltens zweier Künste zueinander—dargestellt nach den Quellen im Zeitraum von Leonardo da
Vinci bis John Cage.</hi> Frankfurt am Main, Bern and Las Vegas: Peter Lang, 1979 [“Galerie: Beiträge zur
Kunstgeschichte,” vol. 1], pp. 46-50.</p>
            <p>Yasuda, Masayoshi. “Blake ni okeru ‘Muse’ [Muse in W. Blake’s Poems].” 
<hi rend="i">Kansei Gakuin Dagaku Ronko</hi> [<hi rend="i">Kansei Gakuin Studies in English</hi>], 32 (1976),
13-30.</p>
            <p>Yasuda, Masayoshi. “J. Dennis to Blake [Blake and Dennis—A Note].” <hi rend="i">Kansei Gakuin
Daigaku Ronko</hi> [<hi rend="i">Kansei Gakuin Studies in English</hi>], 35 (1977), 1-17.</p>
            <p>Yasuda, Masayoshi. “W. Blake ni okeru ‘hae’ no shudai [On the Problems of Blake’s ‘The
Fly’].” <hi rend="i">Kansei Gakuin Daigaku Ronko</hi> [<hi rend="i">Kansei Gakuin Studies in English</hi>],
38 (1978), 1-17.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">PART II</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">BLAKE’S CIRCLE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>James Barry.</title>
            </head>
            <p>See Part I: Blake: Bibliographies. Gage, John; and Tomory, Peter A.</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p14-91" n="91"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Robert Blair.</title>
            </head>
            <p>See Part I: Blake: Critical Studies, Allen, Orphia Jane; and Bentley, G. E. Jr., “Echoes . 
. . . ”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Edward Calvert.</title>
            </head>
            <p>See Part I: Blake: Bibliographies, Gage, John.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>William Cowper.</title>
            </head>
            <p>See Part I: Blake: Critical Studies, Franson, J. Karl; Hilton, Nelson, “A Note . . . . ”; King,
James; and Part II, William Hayley.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>George Cumberland</title>
            </head>
            <p>Heppner, Christopher. “Another <hi rend="i">Cumberland Bibliography</hi> Addendum.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 261-261.</p>
            <p>See also Part I, Blake: Critical Studies, <corr type="emend">Malmqvist, Göran,</corr> “The Dean . . . .”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Erasmus Darwin</title>
            </head>
            <p>King-Hele, Desmond. <hi rend="i">Doctor of Revolution: The Life and Genius of Erasmus
Darwin.</hi> London: Faber and Faber, 1977. £12.50. Reviewed by G. L’E. Turner, <hi rend="i">Notes and
Queries</hi>, n.s. 26, no. 1 (February 1979), 76-68.</p>
            <p>See also Part I, Blake: Critical Studies, Leonard, David Charles.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>John Flaxman</title>
            </head>
            <p>Banks, Ada Shadmi. “Two Letters from Girodet to Flaxman.” <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi>, 61
(1979), 100-101. [Some documentary evidence of the influence of Flaxman on Girodet.]</p>
            <p>Bindman, David, ed. <hi rend="i">John Flaxman, R.A.</hi> London: Thames and Hudson, for the
Royal Academy of Arts, 1979. [The English-language edition, slightly revised, of the Hamburg catalogue
published earlier in 1979.]</p>
            <p>Wolsdorff, Christian. “John Flaxmann—Mythologie und Industrie: Anmerkungen zur Ausstellung
der Hamburger Kunsthalle.” <hi rend="i">Kunstchronik</hi>, 33 (1980), 14-37.</p>
            <p>See also Part I, Blake: Bibliographies, Gage, John; and Tomory, Peter A.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Henry Fuseli</title>
            </head>
            <p>[Fuseli, Henry]. <hi rend="i">Shakespeares Dramatische Werke</hi>, 10 vols., trsl. A. W.
Schlegel and L. Tieck, ed. and rev. Hans Matter, illustrated by Johann Heinrich Füssli. Zurich: Diogenes,
1979 [“detebe,” vols. 201/1-10]. [Reproduced are Fuseli’s designs for the London 1805 edition of 
<hi rend="i">The Plays of William Shakespeare.</hi>]</p>
            <p>Hnikova, Dagmar. <hi rend="i">Johann Heinrich Füssli.</hi> Genève: Musée Rath, 1978.</p>
            <p>Mosele, Franz. “Johann Heinrich Füssli,” in <hi rend="i">Sammlungskatalog Aargauer
Kunsthaus</hi>, vol. 1: “Gemälde und Skulpturen vom 18. Jahrhundert bis zum Ersten Weltkrieg.” Aarau:
              Aargauer Kunsthaus, 1979 [<corr type="emend">Schweizerisches</corr> Institut für Kunstwissenschaft, “Kataloge Schweizer Museen und
Sammlungen,” vol. 5/1], pp. 64-67.</p>
            <p>Vitali, Lamberto, ed. <hi rend="i">Johann Heinrich Füssli: Disegni e dipinti.</hi> Milan:
Electa, 1977. [Catalogue of an exhibition held at the Museo Pezzoli.]</p>
            <p>Weinglass, D. H. “The Painter’s Muse: Henry Fuseli and Maria Riddell.” <hi rend="i">Gazette
des Beaux-Arts</hi>, September 1978, pp. 75-83.</p>
            <p>See also Part I, Blake: Bibliographies, Gage, John; and Tomory, Peter A.; and Critical Studies,
Hall, Carol Louise.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>William Hayley</title>
            </head>
            <p>[Hayley, William]. <hi rend="i">Memoirs of the Life and Writings of William Hayley Esq., The
Friend and Biographer of Cowper, Written by Himself</hi>, 2 vols., ed. John Johnson [1823]. Westmead,
Farnborough, Hants.: Gregg International, 1971.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Joseph Johnson</title>
            </head>
            <p>Tyson, Gerald F. <hi rend="i">Joseph Johnson, A Liberal Publisher.</hi> Iowa City, Iowa:
University of Iowa Press, 1979. $14.95. [Includes a bibliography of more than 1300 items published by
Johnson.]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>John Linnell.</title>
            </head>
            <p>See Part I, Blake: Bibliographies, Gage, John.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>George Morland.</title>
            </head>
            <p>See Part I, Blake: Critical Studies, LaBelle, Jenijoy.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>John Hamilton Mortimer.</title>
            </head>
            <p>See Part I, Blake: Bibliographies, Tomory, Peter A.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Samuel Palmer</title>
            </head>
            <p>Lister, Raymond, et al. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer, A Vision Recaptured: The complete Etchings
and the Paintings for Milton and for Virgil.</hi> London: for The William Blake Trust, 1978. [Includes a
Foreword by <corr type="emend">Ronald Lightbown,</corr> an Introduction by Sir Geoffrey Keynes and Arnold Fawcus, “A Vision Recaptured:
the Etchings and the Designs for Milton and Virgil” by Raymond Lister, “Samuel Palmer, Milton and Virgil” by
Graham Reynolds, and catalogues of Palmer’s etchings and his designs for Virgil and Milton by Raymond
Lister, reproductions of related paintings and of portraits of Palmer, a chronology, and a bibliography.
Edition limited to 3826 copies. A commemorative handbook published on the occasion of the Victoria and Albert
Palmer exhibition.] Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi>, 28 (1979), 104-108.</p>
            <p>See also Part I, Blake: Bibliographies, Gage, John; and Part I, Blake: Critical Studies,
Anonymous.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Joseph Priestley.</title>
            </head>
            <p>See Part I, Blake: Critical Studies, Gleckner, Robert F., “Priestley . . . .”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>George Romney.</title>
            </head>
            <p>See Part I, Blake: Bibliographies, Tomory, Peter A.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Emanuel Swedenborg.</title>
            </head>
            <p>See Part I, Blake: Critical Studies, Ogude, S. E.; and Paley, Morton D.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>John Varley.</title>
            </head>
            <p>See Part I, Blake: Critical Studies, Gittings, Fred.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>James Ward</title>
            </head>
            <p>Nygren, Edward John. “The Art of James Ward, R.A. (1769-1859). (Volumes I and II).” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 40 (1980), 4283-A. Diss., Yale University, 1976.
[“Previous studies of James Ward have dealt almost entirely with the facts of his life. The present study,
while using his biography as a framework, focuses on his artistic development and sources and offers an
iconographic analysis of some of his major
<pb id="p14-92" n="92"/>
works.”]</p>
            <p>Nygren, Edward J. “James Ward’s Exhibition Pictures of 1838: Controversy in Paint.” 
<hi rend="i">The Art Bulletin</hi>, 61 (1979), 448-459.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Mary Wollstonecraft.</title>
            </head>
            <p>See Part I, Blake: Critical Studies, Bentley, G. E., Jr., “A Different Face . . . . ”; Lange,
Thomas V.; and Welch, Dennis M.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Edward Young</title>
            </head>
            <p>Brodine, Dorothy Jane. “Love of Fame, the Universal Passion: Edward Young’s Personal Response
to the Enlightenment.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 40 (1979), 2642-A-2643-A.
Diss., St. John’s University, 1979. [After detailing classical influences on Young, this study examines each
of the seven satires that make up Young’s series, <hi rend="i">Love of Fame.</hi>]</p>
            <p>Peplow, Michael Webster. “Orthodoxy and Neoclassicism in Edward Young: Studies in His Sermons
and Satires.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 39 (1979), 6108-A-6109-A. Diss., Texas
Christian University, 1966.</p>
            <p>Watkins, Charlotte Crawford. “The Satires of Edward Young.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
International</hi>, 40 (1980), 5458-A. Diss., Yale University, 1937 [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>].</p>
            <p>See also Part I, Blake: Critical Studies, Allen, Orphia Jane; and Maeda, Masahiko.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">PART III</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">WORKS OF RELATED INTEREST</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Allen Memorial Art Museum. “Acquisitions: 1976-78.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of the Allen Memorial
Art Museum</hi>, 36 (1979), 119-128. [Pp. 121-123 describe and illustrate John Martin’s painting, 
<hi rend="i">Cadmus and the Dragon</hi> (1813), now in the collection of the Allen Memorial Art Museum of Oberlin
College.]</p>
          <p>Barrett, Jeannine Allison. “Frye and Jung: Mirrored Harmonies. A Jungian Explication of Northrop
Frye’s <hi rend="i">Anatomy of Criticism.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 37
(1979), 7331-A. Diss., New York University, 1978.</p>
          <p>Cassavant, Sharron Greer. “John Middleton Murry: The Critic as Moralist.” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 40 (1980), 5062-A. Diss., Tufts University, 1979. [“ . . .
Murry’s humanistic perspective offered a valuable corrective to narrow technical analysis” of works by Blake
and others.]</p>
          <p>Garlick, Kenneth, and Angus D. Macintyre, eds. <hi rend="i">The Diary of Joseph Farington</hi>,
vols. 3 and 4 (September 1796 to July 1801). New Haven, Conn. and London: Yale University Press, for the Paul
Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art, 1979 [“Studies in British Art”]. £30.00 the set.</p>
          <p>Hartmann, Jørgen Birkedahl. <hi rend="i">Antike Motive bei Thorvaldsen: Studien zur
Antikenrezeption des Klassizismus</hi>, ed. Klaus Parlasca. Tübingen: Ernst Wasmuth, for the Deutsches
Archäologisches Institut, 1979. DM 110.—</p>
          <p>Hofmann, Werner, and P[ierre] G[eorgel]. “Les écrivains-dessinateurs [introduction et
Dictionnaire].” <hi rend="i">Revue de l’Art</hi>, no. 44 (1979), 7-18, 23.</p>
          <p>Klingender, Francis D. <hi rend="i">Kunst und industrielle Revolution</hi>, trsl. Eva Schumann.
Frankfurt am Main: Syndikat, 1977. [The German-language version of the revised edition of <hi rend="i">Art and
the Industrial Revolution</hi>, ed. Arthur Elton, 1968.]</p>
          <p>Mason, Lauris, and Joan Ludman. <hi rend="i">Print Reference Sources: A Selected Bibliography,
18th-20th Centuries.</hi> 2nd ed. Millwood, N.J.: KTO Press, 1979. $36.00.<lb/>
Reviewed by Melvin Huan, <hi rend="i">American Notes and Queries</hi>,, 17, no. 9 (May 1979), 150.</p>
          <p>Mellor, Anne K. “On Romantic Irony, Symbolism and Allegory.” <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi>, 21
(1979), 217-229. [Concerned primarily with the theories of Friedrich Schlegel, this article may still be of
interest for the study of Blake’s theory of poetry as well.]</p>
          <p>Mugerauer, Robert. “The Form of Northrop Frye’s Literary Universe: An Expanding Circle.” 
<hi rend="i">Mosaic</hi>, 12 (1979), 135-147.</p>
          <p>Muthmann, Ruth-Maria, ed. <hi rend="i">Angelika Kauffmann und Ihre Zeit: Graphik und Zeichnungen
1760-1810.</hi> Düsseldorf: C. G. Boerner, 1979 [“Neue Lagerliste,” 70].</p>
          <p>U. S. Library of Congress. <hi rend="i">The Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection: A Catalog of the
Gifts of Lessing J. Rosenwald to the Library of Congress, 1943 to 1975.</hi> Washington: Library of Congress,
1977. Reviewed by Murray W. Zachary, <hi rend="i">American Notes and Queries</hi>, 17, no. 3 (1978),
50-51.</p>
          <p>Storey, Mark. “Why Stevie Smith Matters.” <hi rend="i">Critical Quarterly</hi>, 21 (1979), 41-55.
[Includes extended comparisons between Ms. Smith’s poems and Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi> Ms. Smith
won the Queen’s Medal for Poetry in 1969, and her collected poems were published by Allen Lane in 1975.]</p>
          <p>Symons, Julian. “Ruthven Todd 1914-1978: Some Details for a Portrait.” <hi rend="i">London
Magazine</hi>, n.s., 19 (1979), 62-80. [Todd’s work on Blake is mentioned on pp. 69, 77, 79.]</p>
          <p>Taylor, Donald S. <hi rend="i">Thomas Chatterton’s Art: Experiments in Imagined History.</hi>
Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1978. £11.00. Reviewed by Pat Rogers, <hi rend="i">The</hi>
[London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 7 December 1979, p. 105.</p>
          <p>Tener, Robert E. “The Authorship of the <hi rend="i">Spectator</hi> Reviews of Gilchrist.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 13 (1979), 33-35.</p>
          <p>Thorpe, Peter. “Harold Bloom’s Revisionary Ratios and the Augustan Satirists.” 
<hi rend="i">Southern Humanities Review</hi>, 13 (1979), 181-196.</p>
          <p>Vaughan, William. <hi rend="i">German Romanticism and English Art.</hi> New Haven, Conn. and
London: Yale University Press, for the Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art, 1979 [“Studies in
British Art”].</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">PART IV</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">REVIEWS OF WORKS CITED IN PREVIOUS CHECKLISTS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Altick, Richard D. <hi rend="i">The Shows of London.</hi> Reviewed by Morton D. Paley, 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 271-273; and by Jane W. Stedman, 
<hi rend="i">Victorian Studies</hi>, 22 (1979), 470-472.</p>
          <p>Bentley, Gerald E., Jr., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings.</hi> Reviewed by Grevel
Lindop, <hi rend="i">Critical Quarterly</hi>, 21 (1979), 86.</p>
          <pb id="p14-93" n="93"/>
          <p>Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist.</hi> Reviewed by Barbara M. Stafford, 
<hi rend="i">The Art Quarterly</hi>, n.s. 2 (1979), 118-122; by Jerrold Ziff, <hi rend="i">The Art Bulletin</hi>,
61 (1979), 326-328; by Anne K. Mellor, <hi rend="i">Art Journal</hi>, 39 (1979), 76-78.</p>
          <p>Bindman, David, <hi rend="i">et al. John Flaxman 1755-1826: Mythologie und Industrie.</hi>
Reviewed by Petra Kipphoff, <hi rend="i">Die Zeit</hi>, 27 April 1979. [It is hoped that through access to the
Hamburg Kunsthalle’s file material we will be able to include a comprehensive list of reviews of this
important exhibition and catalogue in next year’s checklist.]</p>
          <p>Burke, Joseph. <hi rend="i">English Art 1714-1800.</hi> Reviewed by David Irwin, 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 212-214.</p>
          <p>Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by Anne K. Mellor, <hi rend="i">Art
Journal</hi>, 39 (1979), 76-78.</p>
          <p>Davie, Donald. <hi rend="i">A Gathered Church: The Literature of the English Dissenting Interest,
1700-1930.</hi> Reviewed by Martha W. England, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979),
215-217.</p>
          <p>Davis, Michael. <hi rend="i">William Blake: A New Kind of Man.</hi> Reviewed by Barbara M.
Stafford, <hi rend="i">The Art Quarterly</hi>, n.s. 2 (1979), 118-122.</p>
          <p>Easson, Kay Parkhurst, and Roger R. Easson, eds. <hi rend="i">Milton: A Poem by William
Blake.</hi> Reviewed by Joseph A. Wittreich, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 13 (1979),
49-51. [With a note on the illustrations by Morton D. Paley, p. 51.]</p>
          <p>Fox, Susan. <hi rend="i">Poetic Form in Blake’s Milton.</hi> Reviewed by W. J. T. Mitchell, 
<hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi>, 77 (1979), 234-238.</p>
          <p>Frosch, Thomas R. <hi rend="i">The Awakening of Albion.</hi> Reviewed by Cornelia Nixon, 
<hi rend="i">University Publishing</hi>, 3 (1978), 3.</p>
          <p>Jackson, Wallace. <hi rend="i">The Probable and the Marvelous: Blake, Wordsworth, and the
Eighteenth-Century Critical Tradition.</hi> Reviewed by Laurence Goldstein, <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth
Circle</hi>, 10 (1979), 256-258; and in <hi rend="i">Johnsonian News Letter</hi>, 39 (1979), 22-23.</p>
          <p>James, David E. <hi rend="i">Written Within and Without: A Study of Blake’s Milton.</hi>
Reviewed by Susan Fox, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 13 (1979), 52-54.</p>
          <p>Keynes, <hi rend="i">Sir</hi> Geoffrey. <hi rend="i">The Complete Portraiture of William and
Catherine Blake.</hi> Reviewed by Jerrold Ziff, <hi rend="i">The Art Bulletin</hi>, 61 (1979), 326-328.</p>
          <p>Kroeber, Karl, and William Walling, eds. <hi rend="i">Images of Romanticism: Verbal and Visual
Affinities.</hi> Reviewed by Anne K. Mellor, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979),
267-268; by W. J. B. Owen, <hi rend="i">The Review of English Studies</hi>, 30 (1979), 362-364; and by David
G. Williams, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi>, 77 (1979), 99-102.</p>
          <p>Kumashiro, Soho. <hi rend="i">William Blake (-sono shogai to sakuhin no subete)</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">William Blake: On His Life and Works</hi>]. Reviewed by Hisayoshi Toriumi, <hi rend="i">Shinkan
Shoka</hi> [<hi rend="i">The Review of New Books</hi>], <hi rend="i">Eigo Seinen</hi> [<hi rend="i">The Rising
Generation</hi>], 125, 5 (1979), 225.</p>
          <p>Lindsay, Jack. <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Life and Work.</hi> Reviewed by David Bromwich,
<hi rend="i">The New York Times Book Review</hi>, 24 June 1979, pp. 7, 32.</p>
          <p>Mitchell, W. J. T. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art.</hi> Reviewed by Barbara M. Stafford,
<hi rend="i">The Art Quarterly</hi>, n.s. 2 (1979), 118-122; by Anne K. Mellor, <hi rend="i">Art Journal</hi>,
39 (1979), 76-78; by Brian Wilkie, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi>, 78 (1979),
137-139; by Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr., in <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 13 (1980),
348-352; by Thomas Frosch, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 13 (1979), 40-48; by P. Malekin,
<hi rend="i">The Review of English Studies</hi>, 30 (1979), 358-360; by Hazard Adams, <hi rend="i">Modern
Language Quarterly</hi>, 40 (1979), 204-207; and by Morris Eaves, <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 10
(1979), 275-278.</p>
          <p>Ostriker, Alicia, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Complete Poems.</hi> Reviewed by John
Kilgore, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 268-270.</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by Barbara M. Stafford, 
<hi rend="i">The Art Quarterly</hi>, n.s. 2 (1979), 118-122; by Jerrold Ziff, <hi rend="i">The Art Bulletin</hi>,
61 (1979), 326-328; by Anne K. Mellor, <hi rend="i">Art Journal</hi>, 39 (1979), 76-78; and by Robert R. Wark,
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 211-212.</p>
          <p>Raine, Kathleen J. <hi rend="i">Blake and Antiquity.</hi> Reviewed by Peter Redgrove, 
<hi rend="i">The Guardian</hi> [London], 29 November 1979, p. 14.</p>
          <p>Tsuchiya, Shigeko. <hi rend="i">Blake no sekai (-genshika no yogensho</hi> 
[<hi rend="i">Blake’s World: On His Prophetic Books</hi>]. Reviewed by Hisayoshi Toriumi, <hi rend="i">Shinkan
Shoka</hi> [<hi rend="i">The Review of New Books</hi>], <hi rend="i">Eigo Seinen</hi> [<hi rend="i">The Rising
Generation</hi>], 125, 5 (1979), 225.</p>
          <p>Walker, Corlette P. <hi rend="i">William Blake in the Art of His Time.</hi> Reviewed by Barbara
M. Stafford, <hi rend="i">The Art Quarterly</hi>, n.s. 2 (1979), 118-122.</p>
          <p>Wilkie, Brian, and Mary Lynn Johnson, <hi rend="i">Blake’s “Four Zoas”: The Design of a
Dream.</hi> Reviewed by Robert F. Gleckner, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi>, 78
(1979), 133-137; by Donald D. Ault, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 13 (1980), 352-56; by Andrew
Lincoln, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1979), 264-66; and by Martin K. Nurmi, 
<hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 10 (1979), 279-80.</p>
          <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr. <hi rend="i">Angel of Apocalypse: Blake’s Idea of Milton.</hi>
Reviewed by Florence Sandler, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi>, 77 (1979), 228-234.</p>
          <p>Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr., ed. <hi rend="i">Milton and the Line of Vision.</hi> Reviewed by
A. H. Elliott in <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>, n.s. 25, no. 1 (February 1978), 77-79.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
