<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.2.labelle</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Michelangelo’s Sistine Frescoes and Blake’s 1795 Color-printed
          Drawings: A Study in Structural Relationships</title>
        <author n="La Belle">Jenijoy La Belle</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1980</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Detlef Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Leonard M. Trawick</name>
              <name>Nicholas O. Warner</name>
              <name>Kasumitsu Watarai</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <pb id="p14-66" n="66"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-2-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">MICHELANGELO’S SISTINE FRESCOES AND BLAKE’S 1795 COLOR-PRINTED DRAWINGS: A
              STUDY IN STRUCTURAL RELATIONSHIPS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">JENIJOY</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">LA BELLE</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>William Blake’s large color-printed drawings of 1795 have often been recognized as among
          his greatest achievements in the visual arts. While some of the individual prints have
          received detailed attention, the interrelationships among all twelve designs have never
          been satisfactorily explained. The subjects of the prints range through both Biblical and
          secular literature: the Old and New Testaments, Shakespeare, Milton, and, perhaps, Blake’s
          own writings. The fact that the designs were all executed in the same technique in the
          same year, are of about the same size (approximately 45 by 58 cm.), and would seem to
          express similar emotions and basic concepts suggests that the prints may form a series.
          Yet the range of subject matter makes it extremely difficult to describe the format of
          such a group. A comparison, however, between the color-prints and Michelangelo’s frescoes
          on the Sistine Ceiling offers new insights into Blake’s work. As I will attempt to
          demonstrate here, Blake not only borrowed motifs and styles from Michelangelo for the
          creation of his great color-printed drawings, but also based their organization on the
          pictorial program of the Sistine Ceiling.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48"
type="note">1</ref>	
            <note id="n48"><hi rend="s">1</hi> The most important published studies of the color-printed
            drawings are Martin Butlin, “The Evolution of Blake’s Large Color Prints of 1795” and
            Anne T. Kostelanetz, “Blake’s 1795 Color Prints: An Interpretation,” both in 
              <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays for S. Foster Damon</hi>, ed. Alvin H. Rosenfeld
            (Providence: Brown Univ. Press, 1969), pp. 109-16, 117-30; and Butlin, 
              <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, catalogue of an exhibition at the Tate Gallery (London: Tate
            Gallery, 1978), pp. 59-65. See also Warren Jones’ unpublished doctoral dissertation 
              <hi rend="i">Blake’s Large Color-printed Drawings of 1795</hi> (Northwestern Univ., 1972).
            Briefer discussions may be found in David Bindman, <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist</hi>
            (Oxford: Phaidon, 1977), pp. 98-100; Anthony Blunt, <hi rend="i">The Art of William
              Blake</hi> (N. Y.: Columbia Univ. Press, 1959), pp. 57-62; Butlin, 
              <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (London: Tate Gallery, 1966), pp. [3-6]; and Morton D. Paley, 
              <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (Oxford: Phaidon, 1978), pp. 37-8. None of these studies
            has considered the thesis I will present here.</note></p>
        <p>Blake’s debt to Michelangelo is apparent throughout a great deal of his best work and has
          been mentioned by many Blake scholars.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49"
type="note">2</ref> The
          color-printed drawings are no exception. The heroic musculature of the figures, the
          brooding or terrified visages, the dramatic postures, and even the schematic simplicity of
          the backgrounds all bespeak Blake’s unbounded admiration for and borrowings from
          Michelangelo. Blake, of course, knew Michelangelo only through engraved reproductions,
          many of which were probably known to him from his earliest years. Blake’s very first
          signed engraving, <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion</hi>, is
          based on a figure from Michelangelo’s fresco of the <hi rend="i">Crucifixion of St.
            Peter</hi> in the Cappella Paolina at the Vatican, and in the 1780s Blake meticulously
          copied seven of Michelangelo’s figures from the Sistine Chapel—following the engravings in
          a small book by Adam Ghisi.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">3</ref>
These careful studies
          from Michelangelo, as well as many other borrowings from his work, indicate that Blake
          knew the Sistine frescoes intimately. There were a number of engravings of the Ceiling
          available in Blake’s day, including Domenico Cunego’s outline print (105 by 48.3 cm.) of
          the ceiling, vaults, and lunettes, published in 1780 (illus. 1). The schematic linearity
          of this engraving places particular emphasis on the structure of Michelangelo’s designs,
          rather than on details of motif, expression, or color. Blake could have learned more about
          the Sistine Chapel from friends such as Flaxman, who returned from Rome in 1794, and
          Fuseli. <note id="n49"><hi rend="s">2</hi> See, for example, Blunt, <hi rend="i">The Art
              of William Blake</hi>, p. 35; Jean Hagstrum, <hi rend="i">William Blake Poet and
              Painter</hi> (Chicago: Univ. of Chicago Press, 1964), p. 40; and Anne Kostelanetz
            Mellor, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Human Form Divine</hi> (Berkeley: Univ. of
            California Press, 1974), pp. 126-31.</note>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">3</hi> I discuss
            the influence of these designs on Blake’s later works in “Blake’s Visions and Re-visions
            of Michelangelo,” <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, ed. Robert N. Essick and Donald
            Pearce (Bloomington: Indiana Univ. Press, 1978), pp. 13-22.</note></p>
        <p>Blake wrote the word “Fresco” on five of the color prints,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n51" type="note">4</ref> a word he also used to describe his so-called tempera paintings of a later
          date. He apparently believed that his own opaque glue or gum-based pigments and perhaps
          even his methods of preparing paper or canvas were the same as the fresco technique of
          painting on damp plaster used by the great Renaissance masters.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52"
            type="note">5</ref> Blake hoped that his work in this medium would achieve the same
          greatness for his country and age that the works of 
<pb id="p14-67" n="67"/>
Michelangelo
          and Rafael had achieved for the Italian Renaissance. In his <hi rend="i">Descriptive
            Catalogue</hi> of 1809, Blake wrote that he wished four of his drawings were “in Fresco,
          on an enlarged scale to ornament the altars of churches, and to make England like Italy,
          respected by respectable men of other countries on account of Art.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53"
            type="note">6</ref> That Blake believed, however wrongly, that his color-printed
          drawings were in the same medium as the Sistine Chapel frescoes forms a small but
          significant technical connection between Blake’s works and Michelangelo’s. 
              <note id="n51"><hi rend="s">4</hi> These are <hi rend="i">Naomi entreating Ruth</hi> (Victoria
and
            Albert Museum copy), <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> (Lutheran Church in America), 
              <hi rend="i">God judging Adam</hi> (Metropolitan Museum, N. Y.), <hi rend="i">Christ Appearing
to
              the Apostles</hi> (Rosenwald Collection, National Gallery of Art), and 
              <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> (National Gallery of Scotland).</note>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">5</hi>
            For descriptions of Blake’s color-printing technique, see Ruthven Todd, “The Techniques
            of William Blake’s Illuminated Printing,” <hi rend="i">The Visionary Hand: Essays for
              the Study of William Blake’s Art and Aesthetics</hi>, ed. Robert N. Essick, (Los
            Angeles: Hennessey &amp; Ingalls, 1973), pp. 19-44; and Robert N. Essick, 
              <hi rend="i">William Blake Printmaker</hi> (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1980), pp.
            121-35.</note>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> The Poetry and Prose of
              William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman (Garden City, N. Y.: Doubleday, 4th printing,
            1970), p. 539. All further quotations from Blake’s writing are from this edition,
            referred to hereafter as E followed by page number.</note></p>
        <p>Before turning to specific comparisons between the color-prints and Michelangelo’s
          paintings, we must consider for a moment the relationships among the various sections of
          the Sistine frescoes themselves. The central span of the ceiling is dominated by nine
          panels recording the Biblical history of the world from the <hi rend="i">Separation of
            Light and Darkness</hi> to the <hi rend="i">Drunkenness of Noah.</hi> We enter the
          Chapel at the end of the story, under the <hi rend="i">Drunkenness of Noah</hi>, and
          proceed backward in time through the <hi rend="i">Deluge</hi>, the <hi rend="i">Sacrifice
            of Noah, The Fall and the Expulsion</hi>, the <hi rend="i">Creation of Eve</hi>, the 
            <hi rend="i">Creation of Adam</hi>, the <hi rend="i">Separation of Heaven from the
            Water</hi>, the <hi rend="i">Creation of the Sun and Moon</hi>, and finally the 
            <hi rend="i">Separation of Light and Darkness.</hi> If one conceives of the series as
          running in the other direction, from altar to entrance, then the central panels proceed in
          chronological sequence—yet with one exception. Noah’s sacrifice happened after the flood
          and therefore we should, when entering the room, come upon it as the second panel, not the
          third. Some modern scholars believe that Michelangelo desired the viewer to follow the
          reverse chronology and that he transposed the second and third panels because he wished
          not just to tell a Bible story, but to indicate a symbolic progression of human
          consciousness as it ascends from a beastly level to an awareness of God’s primal
            being.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">7</ref> Michelangelo was
conversant with the
          Christian Neo-Platonism of the Italian Renaissance,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n55" type="note">8</ref>
          and his organization of the ceiling was very likely influenced by a Neo-Platonic concern
          for the stages of spiritual enlightenment. We come upon the <hi rend="i">Deluge</hi>
          before the <hi rend="i">Sacrifice of Noah</hi> since the latter event indicates a turning
          to God and a growth of spiritual awareness. The parallels between Blake’s group of
          color-prints and the sequence of Michelangelo’s central panels hold true whether one reads
          the panels from entrance to altar (as I do here, following De Tolnay) or from altar to
          entrance (thus emphasizing a fall into sensual degradation rather than a progression
          toward enlightenment). <note id="n54"><hi rend="s">7</hi> The major discussion of this
            point of view can be found in Charles De Tolnay, <hi rend="i">The Sistine Ceiling</hi>
            (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1945), pp. 24-43. De Tolnay is generally considered
            to be one of the standard modern authorities on the Sistine paintings. Unfortunately,
            none of the discussions of the Sistine frescoes that Blake would have been familiar with
            goes beyond the barest description of the program of the ceiling. In this discussion I
            refer to several modern commentators, although of course Blake’s own interpretations
            would not have corresponded exactly to theirs. The parallels between modern
            interpretations of Michelangelo and the themes in Blake’s color-prints may be the result
            of a common source in the Sistine frescoes themselves.</note>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">8</hi> See Erwin Panofsky, “The Neoplatonic Movement and Michelangelo,” 
              <hi rend="i">Studies in Iconology: Humanistic Themes in the Art of the Renaissance</hi> (1939;
N.
            Y.: Harper &amp; Row, 1962), pp. 171-230; and Johannes Wilde, <hi rend="i">Michelangelo:
              Six Lectures</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1978), pp. 58-63.</note></p>
        <p>About the central sequence Michelangelo arranged several types of figures, related
          thematically but not sequentially to other parts of the entire composition. Again the
          concept of levels of spiritual awareness would seem to provide the organizational key. In
          the four corner spandrels are the deeds of Old Testament heroes which aided the earthly
          well-being of the Israelites. In the eight side spandrels are portraits of unredeemed
          humanity who, as St. Luke writes, “sit in darkness and in the shadow of death” (Luke
          1:79). Between the spandrels are the largest figures on the ceiling—all of whom
          experienced a level of spiritual enlightenment that raised them above the earthly
          limitations of the spandrel figures. These majestic characters are of two types—Old
          Testament Prophets who foretold the destiny of their people and the coming of Christ, and
          the Sibyls, those female soothsayers of classical history whose words were seen as
          harbingers of the Christian era by Renaissance theologians. The spiritual struggles of
          these contemplative figures are given dramatic physical embodiment in the 
            <hi rend="i">ignudi</hi>, youthful male nudes who serve as intermediaries between the seers and
the
          central panels. Thus, Michelangelo has combined sequential narrative and a more open
          organization based upon levels of human consciousness—with the conceptual arrangement
          dominant over temporal order. By this flexible principle, Michelangelo has been able to
          bring together a vast array of events from both Biblical and non-Biblical history and to
          offer the viewer the opportunity to recapitulate on the psychological level man’s fall and
          progress toward redemption. We find a similar architectonic program in Blake’s
          color-prints of 1795.</p>
        <p>The most famous and in many respects most important panel in Michelangelo’s central
          sequence is the <hi rend="i">Creation of Adam</hi> (illus. 2). We are not given the
          creation of Adam’s physical form, but rather the moment when God brings to man the divine
          spark of intellect. Adam seems to be rising physically from the primordial earth as an
          indication of incipient spiritual awareness. God’s heroic form framed by attendant spirits
          and a swirling cloak is an epitome of the eighteenth century’s sense of the pictorial
          sublime—a mixture of beauty and power that cannot fail to touch the viewer with awe. Yet
          God’s face expresses tenderness as well as majesty.</p>
        <p>David Bindman has suggested that <hi rend="i">Elohim creating Adam</hi> (illus. 3) is
          “the most probable starting design” for Blake’s color-printed drawings and that its
          “ultimate prototype” is Michelangelo’s <hi rend="i">Creation of Adam.</hi><ref
            target="n56" type="note">9</ref> In this investigation of the conceptual ties between
          Michelangelo’s entire series and Blake’s, the general similarities in subject and style
          are perhaps less significant than the contrasts that link these two designs. In Blake’s
          creation of Adam, we see not spiritual enlightenment, but the physical creation of Adam’s
          body—a body not rising from the earth but crucified upon it. God’s face mixes melancholy
          with terror and while this God may, like Michelangelo’s, touch us with awe, He gives us no
          hope. Rather than enlightening Adam, with His right hand He seems to be forcing Adam’s
          head closer to the earth. Like “the father [who] ready stands to form / The infant head”
          (E 281) in <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>, Blake’s Elohim is restricting, not expanding, human
          consciousness. With His left hand God reaches for more clay to add to Adam’s partially
          fleshed body. Adam’s lower limbs are bound by a worm, often associated with the merely
          physical in Blake’s writings<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57"
type="note">10</ref> and, in this context,
          suggestive of the serpent who leads to man’s fall into mortality. In contrast to God’s
          attendants and cloak in Michelangelo’s creation of Adam, Blake gives his Creator gigantic
          wings, copied from a Greek portrayal of the Pagan god Skiron,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">11</ref> and, in the background, the mottled disc of the sun. Blake
inscribed 
            <hi rend="i">Elohim creating Adam</hi> on the only known impression of this design,<ref
            target="n59" type="note">12</ref> thereby indicating that God is here the 
            <pb id="p14-68-69" n="68-69"/>
          <figure n="MichelangeloSistineOutline.14.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="750" height="336">
            <head>1 Michelangelo, frescoes on the Sistine Ceiling, engraved in outline by Domenico
              Cunego, 1780, 103.4 × 45.5 cm.</head>
            <figDesc>Author’s collection.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p14-70" n="70"/>
          <figure n="MichelangeloSistineAdam.14.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="742" height="388">
            <head>2 Michelangelo, <hi rend="i">Creation of Adam.</hi></head>
          </figure>
          <figure n="but289.1.1.cpd" id="but289.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="765">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	1795 WB</figTranscr>
            <head>3 Blake, <hi rend="i">Elohim creating Adam</hi>, 43.1 × 53.6 cm.</head>
            <figDesc>Tate Gallery.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p14-71" n="71"/>
          <figure n="MichelangeloSistineEve.14.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="361">
            <head>4 Michelangelo, <hi rend="i">Creation of Eve.</hi></head>
          </figure>
          <figure n="but292.1.1.cpd" id="but292.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="765">
            <figTranscr>WBlake 1795</figTranscr>
            <head>5 Blake, <hi rend="i">Satan exulting over Eve</hi>, 42.5 × 53.2 cm.</head>
            <figDesc>Gregory Bateson Collection.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p14-72" n="72"/>
          <figure n="MichelangeloSistineFall.14.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="709" height="358">
            <head>6 Michelangelo, <hi rend="i">The Fall and the Expulsion.</hi></head>
          </figure> creator in Genesis and a God of justice and vengeance—not of pity.
          Michelangelo’s design is both prototype and antitype, both model and contrary, for
          Blake’s. With terrible energy, Blake has transformed Michelangelo’s conception from the
          spiritual to the physical, from creation to bondage, from hope to despair. 
            <hi rend="i">Elohim creating Adam</hi>, particularly when viewed in its relationship to
          Michelangelo, makes it clear why Blake referred to this period in his career as among his
          “dark, but very profitable years.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60"
type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n56"><hi
              rend="s">9</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake as an Artist</hi>, pp. 98-99. By “starting design,”
            I (and I suspect Bindman as well) do not mean that this was the first composition in the
            group that Blake began to work on. That distinction may belong to 
              <hi rend="i">Pity.</hi> Besides the three full scale color-printed drawings of this design, it
            exists in two drawings, the earlier of which has a vertical major axis, and an
            incomplete color-printed drawing (British Museum) considerably smaller than all the
            other color-prints.</note>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">10</hi> See, for example, Blake’s
            references to man as a “worm of sixty winters” in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (pl. 6, 1.
            6), E 61; <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> (p. 8, 1. 11), E 281; <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
            (pl. 30, 1. 57), E 175; and “the Winding Worm” in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (pl. 85,
            1. 1), E 241. The worm in the color-print may have been suggested by Bildad’s statement
            in Job 25:6 that man “is a worm.”</note>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">11</hi> See C. H.
            Collins Baker, “The Sources of Blake’s Pictorial Expression” in <hi rend="i">The
              Visionary Hand</hi>, pp. 124-25 and n. 5 on p. 126.</note>
	<note id="n59"><hi rend="s">12</hi> For basic information on inscriptions, sizes, and locations of copies
of the
            color-printed drawings, see Butlin, <hi rend="i">William Blake: A Complete Catalogue of
              the Works in the Tate Gallery</hi> (London: Tate Gallery, 1971), pp. 34-41, and 
              <hi rend="i">The Visionary Hand</hi>, pp. 37-38.</note>
	<note id="n60"><hi rend="s">13</hi>
            From a letter to William Hayley, 23 October 1804, E 703.</note></p>
        <p>Michelangelo’s <hi rend="i">Creation of Eve</hi> (illus. 4) embodies a lower level of
          intellectual consciousness than his creation of Adam. On the left is the inert form of
          Adam, clearly at this point a physical, not spiritual, being. Eve rises heavily from his
          side as if she were being levitated by God’s commanding right hand. And God, now enclosed
          by his mantle rather than soaring energetically before it, seems wrapped in solemn
          contemplation. Blake’s equivalent (illus. 5) shifts the scene to a later event—the
          exultation of Satan over the fallen Eve, the fatal apple under her right hand. Yet the
          close parallel in the arrangement of the figures between this scene and Blake’s creation
          of Adam suggests that Satan may also be the creator of Eve.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n61" type="note">14</ref> In both color-prints we have scenes of simultaneous creation and fall, much
as
          we do in the creation myth of <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.</hi> The worm wound about
          Adam is compositionally replaced in <hi rend="i">Satan exulting over Eve</hi> by a giant
          serpent, his head resting victoriously on Eve’s breast. A youthful and heroic, yet
          saddened, figure of Satan hovers like a triumphant warrior, spear and shield in hand,
          above his earth-bound victim and in front of hellish flames. Here again Blake has shifted
          Michelangelo’s prototype to an even darker view of human nature and Biblical history; yet
          he remains within the general compass of Michelangelo’s subject matter and organizational
          strategy. <note id="n61"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Similarly, Michelangelo suggests a parallel
            between his portrayal of the <hi rend="i">Creation of Adam</hi> (illus. 2) and the 
              <hi rend="i">Fall and the Expulsion</hi> (illus. 6). In the latter design, the serpent’s
            gesture as she hands the apple of corruption to Eve mimics God’s gesture (in illus. 2)
            as He brings intelligence to Adam.</note></p>
        <p>Progressing backwards in states of consciousness but forward in the chronological
          narrative, we come to Michelangelo’s panel showing both the fall and the expulsion from
          the Garden of Eden (illus. 6). As we have seen, Blake’s first two color-prints embody
          images of the fall, and both contain a worm or serpent wrapped about the human form much
          as Michelangelo’s serpent wraps herself around the tree of the knowledge of Good and Evil.
          As far as we know, Blake never made a color-print of the expulsion; rather he shows us the
          central event which must necessarily come between the fall and the punishment—<hi rend="i">God
judging Adam</hi> (illus. 7). A stern Elohim with his left hand on the tablet of
          the law comes to man in a blazing sun-chariot. His steeds with fiery manes would seem to
          be combinations of those two beasts Blake contrasts in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven
            and Hell</hi>—“the horses of instruction” and “the tygers of wrath” (E 36). Adam,
          bearing the burden of mortality, has grown as aged as his God. The gesture of God’s right
          arm and hand and the suggestion of a sword or shaft extending from his hand to Adam’s head
          recall the gesture and sword of the angel expelling Adam and Eve from Paradise in
          Michelangelo’s design.</p>
        <p>Michelangelo’s three panels on the creation and fall are matched thematically and in
          their narrative relationships by three of Blake’s color-printed drawings. Given these
          significant parallels, reinforced in some cases by stylistic similarities and perhaps even
          a few borrowings of specific motifs, <pb id="p14-73" n="73"/>
          <figure n="but294.1.1.cpd" id="but294.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="796">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB 1795</figTranscr>
            <head>7 Blake, <hi rend="i">God judging Adam</hi>, 43.2 × 53.5 cm.</head>
            <figDesc>Tate Gallery.</figDesc>
          </figure> it would seem reasonable to relate the other color-prints to Michelangelo’s
          program in order to test the basic hypothesis of this essay. What one immediately finds is
          that Blake responded in a different and much freer way to the panels depicting the story
          of Noah. None of the extant color-printed designs relate directly to the sacrifice of
          Noah, but through a curious transformation, Blake seems to have fulfilled the programmatic
          functions of Michelangelo’s <hi rend="i">Deluge</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Drunkenness of
            Noah</hi> through two of his most powerful and horrific color-prints. 
            <hi rend="i">Deluge</hi> shows not the total inundation of the earth, but rather an early point in
          that catastrophe where men and women struggle among themselves for the remaining patches
          of dry ground and for the last places in small boats or on the gunwales of the Ark. The
          less active groups of characters in this composition are not overcome by sudden terror,
          but stand as mute embodiments of suffering and despair—the dominant mental states pictured
          in Blake’s <hi rend="i">House of Death</hi> (illus. 8). On the version in the Tate Gallery
          Blake inscribed the title and the word “Milton,” thereby referring us to the description
          of the Lazar House in <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi> We would seem to have here an
          illustration to Milton and not a Blakean re-casting of the Sistine Chapel; the
          relationship to Michelangelo, however, becomes clear when we consult the context of
          Milton’s description of the Lazar House. It is part of the Pisgah sight, a vision of the
          future, given by the Angel Michael to Adam. By this means, Adam (with the reader of 
            <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>) experiences the history of the world from the creation to
          the flood—the same history envisioned for us in the Sistine panels. Milton presents three
          central incidents which show the consequence of Adam’s fall: Cain’s murder of Abel, the
          Lazar House, and the Deluge. This Miltonic association between the last two events, both
          embodiments of death and despair, gave Blake ample precedent for using the 
            <hi rend="i">House of Death</hi> to fulfill the same thematic function as Michelangelo’s flood
in
          Blake’s group of color-prints. Blake’s design would seem to be a synthesis of influences:
          the most important poet in his literary heritage and the greatest artist in his pictorial
            heritage.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62" type="note">15</ref> Blake has
taken his subject from Milton,
          but that subject remains within the conceptual framework presented by the Sistine
          frescoes. <note id="n62"><hi rend="s">15</hi> E. J. Rose points out that Blake perceived a
            correspondence between Milton and Michelangelo, “The ‘Gothicized Imagination’ of
            ‘Michelangelo Blake,’” <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi> p. 161, 168 n. 15.</note></p>
        <pb id="p14-74" n="74"/>
        <figure n="but320.1.1.cpd" id="but320.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="767">
          <figTranscr>WB 1795</figTranscr>
          <head>8 Blake, <hi rend="i">House of Death</hi>, 48.5 × 61 cm.</head>
          <figDesc>Tate Gallery.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <figure n="but301.1.1.cpd" id="but301.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="690">
          <figTranscr>inv<lb/>
          1795 WB</figTranscr>
          <head>9 Blake, <hi rend="i">Nebuchadnezzar</hi>, 44.6 × 62 cm.</head>
          <figDesc>Tate Gallery.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p14-75" n="75"/>
        <figure n="but323.1.1.cpd" id="but323.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="727">
          <figTranscr>inv<lb/>
          WB 1795</figTranscr>
          <head>10 Blake, <hi rend="i">The Good and Evil Angels</hi>, 44.5 × 59.4 cm.</head>
          <figDesc>Tate Gallery.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <figure n="MichelangeloSistineSun.14.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="650" height="296">
          <head>11 Michelangelo, <hi rend="i">Creation of the Sun and Moon.</hi></head>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p14-76" n="76"/>
        <p>Milton describes “a Lazar-house” 
		<q> wherein were laid<lb/>
 Numbers of all diseas’d, all
            maladies<lb/>
 Of ghastly Spasm, or racking torture. . . .<lb/>
 Dire was the tossing,
            deep the groans, despair<lb/>
 Tended the sick busiest from Couch to Couch;<lb/>
 And over
            them triumphant Death his Dart<lb/>
 Shook, but delay’d to strike, though oft
            invok’t<lb/>
 With vows, as thir chief good, and final hope.<lb/>
<lb/> 
              (<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, XI, 479-81, 489-93)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n63" type="note">16</ref>	
              <note id="n63"><hi rend="s">16</hi><hi rend="i"> John Milton: Complete Poems and Major
                Prose</hi>, ed. Merritt Y. Hughes (N. Y.: Odyssey Press, 1957), p. 444.</note></q>
          Blake has personified these states of pain and despair in the six victims below the figure
          of Death, his features generally reminiscent of the Elohim we have seen earlier. His eyes
          closed, Death holds between his outstretched hands an object suggesting both a bow (from
          which his darts are about to be shot) and a scroll, a list of victims who will suffer the
          penalty of mortality announced in <hi rend="i">God judging Adam.</hi> Despair, standing on
          the right, does not so much tend to the sick as sink into thoughts of murder or suicide,
          emblemized by the dagger in his left hand.</p>
        <p>The lowest state of consciousness symbolized in the central Sistine panels is presented
          by the <hi rend="i">Drunkenness of Noah.</hi> Noah has sunk into a drunken stupor, into
          unconsciousness, and his nakedness is not an image of the human form divine but of the
          imprisonment of the soul in gross physicality. Blake’s <hi rend="i">Nebuchadnezzar</hi>
          (illus. 9) gives us a more horrific portrayal of an equally low, or even lower, state of
          bondage. The color-print illustrates a passage from the Book of Daniel: 
		<q> The same hour
            was the thing fulfilled upon Nebuchadnezzar: and he was driven from men, and did eat
            grass as oxen, and his body was wet with the dew of heaven, till his hairs were grown
            like eagles’ feathers, and his nails like birds’ claws (4:33.) </q>
The Babylonian
          monarch has been reduced to a subhuman, animalistic condition—much as Michelangelo showed
          a hero at the moment of his greatest shame.</p>
        <p>While following the conceptual scheme of the Sistine Ceiling, Blake has given us a darker
          vision of Biblical history and human consciousness than Michelangelo. The Sistine Adam
          receives divine intellect; Blake’s the imprisoning body. Michelangelo’s Eve rises into
          being; Blake’s sinks under Satan’s dominion. Michelangelo shows us the fall and expulsion;
          Blake gives us the direct act of judgement and the penalty of mortality brought to the
          aged Adam. The deluge kills but it also cleanses; the House of Death offers no
          amelioration of its punishment. Finally, Noah is still clearly a human form;
          Nebuchadnezzar has become half-beast. The two series of “frescoes” correspond to each
          other through contrariety, that structural relationship we so frequently find in Blake’s
          own works from the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> to 
            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></p>
        <p>The three Sistine panels at the end of the room over the altar all portray God the
          creator. There has been some disagreement over exactly what is represented in each panel,
          but they would seem to be the following: the <hi rend="i">Separation of Heaven from the
          Water</hi>; next, the <hi rend="i">Creation of the Sun and Moon</hi>; and last, the 
          <hi rend="i">Separation of Light and 
          Darkness.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64" type="note">17</ref> In
          each case, Michelangelo presents primal acts of binary differentiation as the essential
          feature of divine creativity. Blake has embodied with equal mystery and force this basic
          process in <hi rend="i">The Good and Evil Angels</hi> (illus. 10). Blake first used a much
          smaller, cruder form of this design on plate 4 of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
            Hell</hi> (c. 1790) which has as one of its central themes the idea of contraries as the
          underlying structure for the moral distinction between good and evil. Blake writes that
          “Without Contraries is no progression. Attraction and Repulsion, Reason and Energy, Love
          and Hate, are necessary to Human existence. From these contraries spring what the
          religious call Good &amp; Evil” (E 34). Thus Blake sees a causal connection between those
          creative acts which necessarily entail division and the contraries of good and evil
          personified in the color-print. Blake could have used this same line of reasoning to
          generate his design in response to the three panels where Michelangelo shows the creation
          of contrary states: heaven and earth, land and water, sun and moon, darkness and light.
          Rather than showing the creator, Blake pictures the created, with man as a child
          struggling between opposing forces, much as Michelangelo’s <hi rend="i">ignudi</hi> are
          caught between base materiality and a higher state of 
          consciousness.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65" type="note">18</ref> 
          The design includes the four classical elements—fire on the left
          with what may be its personified form shackled by the left ankle to the earth below, and,
          on the right, water with the air above. Both Blake and Michelangelo are embodying in their
          designs the same elemental process, and both are more concerned with the dramatic
          presentation of energy than with straightforward narrative. The visual parallels between
          the chained figure in the color-print and the portrayal of God on the right in
          Michelangelo’s <hi rend="i">Creation of the Sun and Moon</hi> (illus. 11) hint at the more
          important conceptual similarities. De Tolnay’s description of the Sistine figure can be
          applied with equal validity to Blake’s chained angel: 
		<q> His being is of a fiery nature:
            His face is illuminated by a red glow. . . . His hair floats like fiery tongues blazing
            from His strongly built forehead. In the downward curve of His mouth and the wrinkles of
            His forehead is marked His superhuman will. . . . His body describes a curve which
            swings upward to terminate in the extended arms which burst forth diagonally from His
            body. (p. 38) </q>
          The figure on the left in Michelangelo’s panel is another view of the
          same creator. Similarly, Blake’s two angels may be the two halves or contrary states of
          the same principle. Although the drama in Blake’s color-print is presented through very
          specific motifs, the theme is as universal as the acts of creation represented by
          Michelangelo: Blake is calling us to a perception not of any specific binary opposition,
          but of the nature of binary opposition as a psychological and philosophical category.
            <note id="n64"><hi rend="s">17</hi> These titles are all from <hi rend="i">The Sistine
              Ceiling</hi>, pp. 37-40. Anthony Bertram calls the first panel in this group 
              <hi rend="i">God Separating the Waters from the Earth</hi> in 
              <hi rend="i">Michelangelo</hi> (London: Studio Vista, 1964), p. 41; Enzo Carli titles this same
            panel <hi rend="i">God Creates the Animals</hi> in <hi rend="i">All the Paintings of
              Michelangelo</hi> (N. Y.: Hawthorn Books, 1963), p. 28; and Herbert Von Einem calls
            the panel <hi rend="i">The Creation of the Creatures of the Sea</hi> in 
              <hi rend="i">Michelangelo</hi> (London: Methuen &amp; Co., 1973), p. 70. Von Einem points out
that
            this scene “raised difficulties” even for Renaissance interpreters of the Sistine
            frescoes.</note>
	<note id="n65"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Bertram describes the 
              <hi rend="i">ignudi</hi> as “thrusting against their imprisonment,” trying “to break out of the
            bondage of the world” (<hi rend="i">Michelangelo</hi>, p. 70). Compare, particularly,
            the face of the child in <hi rend="i">The Good and Evil Angels</hi> with the head of the
            nude youth above and to the right of the Persian Sibyl. The leftward turn of the head,
            open mouth, bridge of the nose (distinctly different from Blake’s usual classically
            straight nose), flashing eye, and general expression of terror are almost identical (see
            illus. 19). Compare also the face of the angel on the right in Blake’s color print with
            the nude youth above and to the left of the Prophet Daniel. Both of these 
              <hi rend="i">ignudi</hi> frame the <hi rend="i">Separation of Heaven from the Water</hi>, one of
            the three panels to which <hi rend="i">The Good and Evil Angels</hi> is conceptually
            related.</note></p>
        <pb id="p14-77" n="77"/>
        <p>Blake’s six color-printed drawings I have considered so far correspond in a variety of
          important ways to Michelangelo’s central panels. Three of the remaining prints follow
          conceptually Michelangelo’s corner spandrels. The iconographic significance of the corner
          compartments and their relationship to the entire composition are complex. One can
          emphasize the heroic context of these scenes and the way in which the events portrayed
          contributed to the triumph of the Israelites. Typologically, these scenes may even refer
          to Christ. On the other hand, these incidents may be seen as tragic. For example, one
          design has been alternately titled <hi rend="i">The Triumph of Esther</hi> and 
            <hi rend="i">The Punishment of Haman.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66"
type="note">19</ref> The three
          other scenes, <hi rend="i">David and Goliath, Judith and Holophernes</hi>, and 
            <hi rend="i">The Brazen Serpent</hi>, also emphasize violent deaths rather than the
          salvation they foretell. Three of Blake’s color-prints are similarly poised between
          tragedy and divine comedy, with the visual emphasis on the former. <hi rend="i">Lamech and
            His Two Wives</hi> (illus. 12) returns us to a story in Genesis (4:23-24)—the murder of
          a young man<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">20</ref> by Cain’s
great-great-great grandson.
          Lamech pulls at his hair in despair over the penalty which will fall on him seventy and
          sevenfold while his wives cling to each other for comfort. The Biblical story offers no
          hope, but by suggesting a cruciform posture in the fallen youth, Blake may be hinting at
          typological possibilities much as Michelangelo does in his proto-crucifixion scenes, 
            <hi rend="i">The Punishment of Haman</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Brazen Serpent.</hi> The bold
          and oddly abstract corner of a tent trusting into the design at the left margin may have
          been suggested to Blake by the similarly schematic background tent in Michelangelo’s 
            <hi rend="i">David and Goliath.</hi> A further parallel comes to us by way of contrast: in
            <hi rend="i">David and Goliath</hi>, youth heroically slays age; in 
            <hi rend="i">Lamech</hi>, age tragically murders youth. <note id="n66"><hi rend="s">19</hi> For
the
            first title see Carli, <hi rend="i">All the Paintings of Michelangelo</hi>, p. 31; for
            the second, De Tolnay, <hi rend="i">The Sistine Ceiling</hi>, p. 96.</note>	
            <note id="n67"><hi rend="s">20</hi> The Hyacinthine curls of the fallen figure are
            characteristic of Blake’s youthful males. See, for example, Orc in <hi rend="i">America,
              Albion rose</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> (illus. 17). The youth may be
            Tubalcain—see <hi rend="i">William Blake in the Art of His Time</hi>, exhibition
            catalogue, Univ. of California, Santa Barbara, 1976, p. 84.</note></p>
        <p>The finest copy of <hi rend="i">Naomi entreating Ruth and Orpah to return to the Land of
            Moab</hi> (illus. 13), like the best impression of <hi rend="i">Lamech and His Two
            Wives</hi>, has its corners cut off on a diagonal. This fact, as well as compositional
          similarities, links the two designs.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68"
type="note">21</ref> Further, both
          deal with family turmoil, division, anguish, and pity. <hi rend="i">Naomi entreating
            Ruth</hi>, much more than <hi rend="i">Lamech</hi>, is ambiguously poised between
          tragedy and restoration. Naomi, on the left, is pictured as an old woman with a somewhat
          sinister visage and a veil draped over her head, linking her to figures in the 
            <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs who may be prototypes for Vala.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69"
            type="note">22</ref> Yet she is given a halo in the Victoria and Albert Museum copy and
          assumes a Christlike posture (cf. illus. 18) with the palms of her hands turned outward.
          Ruth cleaves to her even though this will carry her away from family and homeland (Ruth
          1:11-17), much as the apostles sacrificed their familial bonds to follow Christ. And the
          two women will travel to Bethlehem in typological anticipation of the journey of Joseph
          and Mary. <note id="n68"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Suggested in Butlin, <hi rend="i">William
              Blake</hi>, exhibition catalogue (1978), p. 62.</note>
	<note id="n69"><hi rend="s">22</hi> See <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> watercolors (Night VII, p. 22), 
              <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> engravings (Night II, p. 35), and my discussion of these
            figures and their basis in Blake’s drawing of Michelangelo’s Solomon lunette in 
              <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, pp. 17-18.</note></p>
        <p>The pathetic qualities latent in <hi rend="i">Naomi entreating Ruth</hi> and 
            <hi rend="i">Lamech</hi> are directly personified in <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> (illus. 14). Blake
never
          inscribed a title on the known copies of this color-print, but Frederick Tatham indicated
          what is very likely the subject and source for the design: the images of “pity, like a
          naked new-born babe, / Striding the blast” and of “Heaven’s cherubin horsed / Upon the
          sightless couriers of the air” are from Shakespeare’s <hi rend="i">Macbeth.</hi><ref
            target="n70" type="note">23</ref> Like the last two color-prints considered here and
          like Michelangelo’s corner spandrels, the iconography of the design is complex and
          somewhat ambiguous—as demonstrated by the differences in the interpretive comments 
            <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> has elicited.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71"
type="note">24</ref> In the 
            <hi rend="i">Book of Urizen</hi> of 1794, pity is associated with the fallen world and the
          divisive creation of the first female. The prone figure in the design also recalls Eve in
            <hi rend="i">Satan exulting over Eve.</hi> On the other hand, pity is not always a
          negative emotion in Blake’s writings, and, as personified as a child in the color-print,
          would seem to represent life, energy, and freedom within an otherwise dead or darkened
          world. The ambiguities of this design are similar to those in Blake’s aphorism in “The
          Human Abstract” (<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, 1794) that “Pity would be no more
          / If we did not make somebody poor.” However valuable pity is in a fallen world, it is
          still the product of an evil deed. In <hi rend="i">Macbeth</hi>, the pity will result from
          a murder, and perhaps Blake seized upon this passage because it presents the paradoxical
          birth of a virtue out of a vice. Similarly, the Sistine corner spandrels prophesy
          political and even spiritual liberation resulting from bloody and terrible events. 
            <note id="n70"><hi rend="s">23</hi> Tatham’s title inscription appears on one of the two
            preliminary pencil drawings of the design in the British Museum. It is interesting to
            note that in the late 1770s Henry Fuseli did a series of sketches (now in the British
            Museum) illustrating Shakespeare in a format based loosely on the Sistine Ceiling. These
            drawings, perhaps only imaginative experiments rather than preliminaries for actual
            frescoes, include a group of lunette and spandrel designs for <hi rend="i">Macbeth.</hi>
            See Gert Schiff, <hi rend="i">Johann Heinrich Füssli</hi> (Zurich: Verlag Berichthaus,
            1973), I, 108-09, II, 113; <hi rend="i">Henry Fuseli</hi>, exhibition catalogue (London:
            Tate Gallery, 1975), pp. 72-73.</note>
	<note id="n71"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Butlin
            associates this design with pity “as a negative force” in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> in
              <hi rend="i">William Blake: a Complete Catalogue of the Works in the Tate
            Gallery</hi>, p. 38; Paley points out that “<hi rend="i">Pity</hi> introduces another
            gleam of grace into the nightmare world of the colour prints” in <hi rend="i">William
              Blake</hi>, p. 38. The latter view would seem to gain support from the similarity
            between the child in <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> and the infant Jesus, soaring between the
            swooning Mary and Saint Elizabeth’s outstretched arms, in both Blake’s tempera 
              <hi rend="i">The Nativity</hi> (c. 1799) and <hi rend="i">The Descent of Peace</hi> in the
            Huntington Library set of watercolor illustrations (c. 1808) to Milton’s “On the Morning
            of Christ’s Nativity.”</note></p>
        <p>Some of the most illuminating parallels between the organization of the Sistine frescoes
          and Blake’s color-prints are between Michelangelo’s Sibyls and Prophets and Blake’s two
          designs, <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> and <hi rend="i">Newton</hi>, designs which would seem
          to present the most difficulties in any attempt at fitting them into a structured group
          with the other color-printed drawings. Around his central sequence of nine panels
          Michelangelo arranged gigantic figures of five Sibyls <corr type="emend">alternating</corr> with
seven Prophets. The
          female soothsayers have their dark parallel in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> (illus.
          15), a figure traditionally associated with necromancy and prophecy. Although the Sibyls
          did not, of course, know the Christian possibilities in their predictions, their sayings
          were transformed by Christian commentators into prophecies of Christ’s coming. Hecate is
          their contrastive analogue, much as black magic relates to white; she foretells not
          enlightenment, but mystery and the same sort of imprisonment of the human spirit we have
          seen in <hi rend="i">Elohim creating Adam</hi> and <hi rend="i">Nebuchadnezzar.</hi> Ever
          since Rossetti’s catalogue of Blake’s art appeared in 1863,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72" type="note">25</ref> this design has usually been associated with Shakespeare’s
references to
          Hecate in <hi rend="i">Macbeth</hi> and <hi rend="i">A Midsummer Night’s Dream</hi>,
          although Paley has pointed to Virgil’s <hi rend="i">Aeneid</hi>, translated by Dryden, as
          a possible source.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73" type="note">26</ref>
          <pb id="p14-78" n="78"/>
          <figure n="but297.1.1.cpd" id="but297.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="684">
            <figTranscr>inv<lb/>
            WB 1795</figTranscr>
            <head>12 Blake, <hi rend="i">Lamech and His Two Wives</hi>, 43.1 × 60.8 cm.</head>
            <figDesc>Tate Gallery.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <figure n="but299.1.1.cpd" id="but299.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="716">
            <figTranscr>Fresco WBlake inv</figTranscr>
            <head>13 Blake, <hi rend="i">Naomi entreating Ruth and Orpah</hi>, 42.8 × 58 cm.</head>
            <figDesc>Victoria and Albert Museum.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p14-79" n="79"/>
          <figure n="but310.1.1.cpd" id="but310.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="759">
          	<figTranscr>Blake</figTranscr>
            <head>14 Blake, <hi rend="i">Pity</hi>, 42.5 × 53.9 cm.</head>
            <figDesc>Tate Gallery.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <figure n="but316.1.1.cpd" id="but316.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="725">
          	<figTranscr>Blake</figTranscr>
            <head>15 Blake, <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi>, 43.9 × 58.1 cm.</head>
            <figDesc>Tate Gallery.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p14-80" n="80"/>
          <figure n="MichelangeloSibyl.14.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="410">
            <head>16 Michelangelo, <hi rend="i">Erythraean Sibyl.</hi></head>
          </figure> Several motifs in the design—the book, the dark and bat-filled environment, and
          the background rock—may have been stimulated by Blake’s own reference to Hecate in his
          fragment “then She bore Pale desire,” written before 1777: 
		<q> The Gods all Serve her
            [Envy] at her will so great her Power is [.] like. fabled hecate She doth bind them to
            her law. Far in a Direful Cave She lives unseen Closd from the Eye of Day. to the hard
            Rock transfixt by fate and here She works her witcheries. (E 438) </q>
These possible
          literary sources fit within the compass of Michelangelo’s pictorial presentation of the
          Sibyls. Four of the Sibyls have large open books and one holds a scroll (but has a book
          behind her). The prophetic character of these writings finds its antithesis in Hecate’s
          book of mystery or law, similar to Urizen’s book (<hi rend="i">Book of Urizen</hi>, plates
          1 and 5) in the illegible swirls of color-printing on its leaves. Behind each of
          Michelangelo’s Sibyls are two Genii, personifications of their inspired imaginations. And
          in Blake’s color-print we have two strange figures which are so intimately associated with
          the main human form in the composition that they would seem to be, like the Genii,
          projections of the internal nature of the Triple Hecate. The kneeling figure on the left
          appears to be female, and that on the right, male—the two universal principles of human
          character whose relationships play such a major role in Blake’s writing. The animals
          further associate the main figure with the divisive, fallen world, for they are creatures
          of darkness (owl, lizard, monstrous bat) or, like the donkey, are bound by necessity to
          the vegetative world. In her crossed-leg posture, with a mantle over her knees but the
          upper part of her body and her feet exposed, Hecate’s presentation corresponds visually to
          the twisted postures of the Sibyls, their uncovered feet, and the bare upper torso and
          arms of the Libyan Sibyl. Further, the Erythraean Sibyl’s right hand (illus. 16), like
          Hecate’s, falls within a fold of her garment, and her left hand touches the pages of an
          open book. Yet these admittedly minor visual similarities are less significant than the
          conceptual ones. The Sibyls prophesy liberation from bondage to the material world and
          point toward that higher vision the viewer must entertain to experience the expansion of
          consciousness presented by Michelangelo’s central panels. In antithetical parallel, Hecate
          is the female embodiment and interpreter of the fallen state of consciousness and of
          bondage to the material world dominating Blake’s color-prints, as well as his writings, of
          the mid 1790s. <note id="n72"><hi rend="s">25</hi> W. M. Rossetti’s “Annotated List of
            Blake’s Paintings, Drawings, and Engravings” in Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life
              of William Blake</hi> (London and Cambridge: Macmillan, 1863), II, 238, no.
            228.</note>
	<note id="n73"><hi rend="s">26</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake</hi>, p. 38.
            The most significant references to Hecate in Dryden’s translation of the 
              <hi rend="i">Aeneid</hi> are in the Sixth Book in conjunction with the activities of the Cumaean
            Sibyl, one of the five portrayed by Michelangelo. There are also several references to
            Triple Hecate in the Seventh Book of Ovid’s <hi rend="i">Metamorphoses.</hi></note></p>
        <p>The role played by the Prophets in the Sistine frescoes is fulfilled in Blake’s series by
            <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> (illus. 17). As De Tolnay points out, Michelangelo accentuated
          the “indecision, passivity, and ambiguity” of the Sibyls and placed them “nearer to nature
          and to the earth” than the Prophets, who exemplify “intellectual concentration” (p. 57).
            <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> and <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> have a similar relationship: 
            <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> presents the dark mysteries of the fallen world; 
            <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> the attempt by fallen reason to understand that world through
mathematical
          and geometric abstraction. The great British scientist of the seventeenth century was for
          Blake the prophet of the rational philosophies and natural religions ruling the
          intellectual life of the eighteenth century. Newton’s prophetical character is
          demonstrated by the role he plays in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (1794):
<q> The red limb’d
            Angel siez’d, in horror and torment;<lb/>
 The Trump of the last doom; but he could not
            blow the iron tube!<lb/>
 A mighty Spirit leap’d from the land of Albion,<lb/>
 Nam’d
            Newton; he siez’d the Trump, &amp; blow’d the enormous blast!<lb/>
<lb/>
 (E 63) </q>
          Newtonian philosophy—not so much Newton’s scientific discoveries as the application of his
          theories to moral and religious thought—is the herald of the French Revolution, itself a
          harbinger of “the last doom.” Michelangelo’s Prophets, with their books and scrolls,
          foretell release from mortality through the coming of Christ. Blake’s Newton, working with
          rapt attention on his scroll, embodies the rationalist and abstract thought which will
          lead to an inevitable revolt against such thought and the material world to which it is
          bound.</p>
        <p>This color-print is in many ways the most remarkable in the series because of both its
          unusual 
<pb id="p14-81" n="81"/>
subject and its great beauty. It is very likely an
          underwater scene with Newton immersed in the waters of materialism, “the sea of Time &amp;
            Space.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">27</ref> The rock on
which he sits is covered with
          what may be lichenous growths and just beneath him are two polyps that look like sea
          anemones. Newton’s rock assumes the same pictorial function in this color-print as the
          rock jutting in from the left in <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi>, a compositional similarity
          which further links these two designs much as Michelangelo’s Prophets and Sibyls are
          associated through visual parallels. This rock may be based on the similar motif in
          Michelangelo’s <hi rend="i">Creation of Adam</hi> and <hi rend="i">Creation of Eve.</hi>
          Newton attempts to understand his world through the simple geometric diagram he is
          measuring with compasses. What he fails to perceive is his own magnificent “human form
          divine” (“The Divine Image,” E 12), a form which links man to God, not to the world of
          undersea vegetation. Newton’s failure of perception may be the reason that Blake bases his
          visual portrayal of the scientist (as distinct from the figure’s programmatic role) not on
          one of Michelangelo’s Prophets, but on the Abia lunette (also part of the Sistine ceiling
          frescoes), for Abia is a representative of fallen and unenlightened humanity.<ref
            target="n75" type="note">28</ref> Much as Hecate is the Blakean antitype to
          Michelangelo’s Sibyls, Newton is the fallen form of Michelangelo’s Prophets.<ref
            target="n76" type="note">29</ref>
	<note id="n74"><hi rend="s">27</hi> This image is first
            used in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night the Fourth, p. 56, line 13 (E 331). See
            Essick, “Blake’s Newton,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 3 (1971), 149-62.</note>	
            <note id="n75"><hi rend="s">28</hi> See Blake’s wash drawing of the Abia lunette (British
            Museum), reproduced in <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, pl. 13. Daniel, one of the
            Prophets, is also included in this group of drawings (<hi rend="i">Blake in His
              Time</hi>, pl. 25).</note>
	<note id="n76"><hi rend="s">29</hi> Butlin 
              (<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, 1978, p. 64) associates <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> with 
              <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> because they may both have sources in Shakespeare and they emphasize
            vegetative nature. Clearly, however, the visual character of <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi>
            links it to <hi rend="i">Newton</hi>: the landscape in both designs is divided by a
            diagonal, running from upper left to lower right, created by the edge of a rocky ledge.
            Both rocks are inhabited by unusual creatures, and Newton’s scroll is paralleled by
            Hecate’s book. There are, of course, many thematic and visual interconnections among all
            the color-printed drawings, just as there are among Michelangelo’s frescoes.</note></p>
        <p>Blake’s idealized portrayal of Newton’s body contains a potential for salvation through
          the realization of man’s divinity. The central realization of the human form divine in
          Blake’s later works is Christ, who is both man and God. He is not represented in the
          Sistine Ceiling, but many of the 
          <figure n="but306.1.1.cpd" id="but306.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="737">
            <figTranscr>inv<lb/>
            1795 WB</figTranscr>
            <head>17 Blake, <hi rend="i">Newton</hi>, 46 × 60 cm.</head>
            <figDesc>Tate Gallery.</figDesc>
          </figure> 
          individual motifs and the conception of the whole point toward His coming. As
          Bertram writes, “Everything in the ceiling . . . leads up to Christ, but He appears
          nowhere. The most satisfactory explanation of this astonishing omission is that
          Michelangelo did not consider that Christ’s real presence in the Sacrament on the altar
          needed any painted substitute.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77"
type="note">30</ref> Blake, having no
          chapel and no altar with its sacraments, does give us a vision of Christ (illus. 18). It
          is the culmination of this linear group and an answer to the problems of material and
          spiritual bondage presented in the other eleven color-prints. <hi rend="i">Christ
            Appearing to the Apostles after the Resurrection</hi> is consistent with the dark vision
          of the other designs in that Christ is not shown in glory, but rather at the moment when
          He reveals to His followers His stigmata, those emblems of His own mortal sufferings and
          His own crucifixion in the fallen world of man. He is indeed the new Adam, but for Blake
          one who has undergone the same cruciform bondage to the world and the flesh shown in the
          first color-print considered here. Again, salvation is not presented in its full glory but
          as a potential within the darkness of this world. Blake hovers between hope and despair,
          between divine comedy and earthly tragedy. It is only in his later poetry and paintings
          that he transforms this image of suffering into the triumphant ideal. 
              <note id="n77"><hi rend="s">30</hi><hi rend="i"> Michelangelo</hi>, p. 37. <hi rend="i">The Last
              Judgement</hi> on the west wall behind the altar was a later addition to the chapel
            and not part of Michelangelo’s original format for the ceiling frescoes.</note></p>
        <p>In the illuminated books and his intaglio print series <hi rend="i">The Gates of
            Paradise</hi>, we can see Blake absorbing and then transforming the conventional
          eighteenth century formats of illustrated books and of numbered sequences of emblematic
          pictures. He needed the traditional systems, but often assumed an adversary relationship
          with them, struggling with the old forms in order to open them to new possibilities. The
          standard eighteenth century format for a series of narrative prints was the Hogarthian
          Progress. A less adventuresome artist than Blake would have arranged a series of prints in
          general accordance with Hogarth’s schema. Blake required a more flexible model which could
          encompass more than direct causal and temporal relationships, just as in his poetic
          narratives he had, by 1794, developed the polysemous vision and non-linear narrative of
            <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.</hi> Michelangelo’s frescoes, linking Biblical and
          non-Biblical subjects, provided just such an expansive and comprehensive form for Blake’s
          own group of “frescoes.”</p>
        <p>If we treat Blake’s color-printed drawings as a collection to be experienced in sequence
          and as though they were true frescoes on the walls of a room, like the Sistine Chapel or
          Job’s chamber in Blake’s Plate 20 of his engraved illustrations, then the color-prints can
          unfold before us like Michelangelo’s paintings. Blake’s group begins with three designs
            (<hi rend="i">Elohim creating Adam, Satan exulting over Eve, God judging Adam</hi>) that
          parallel in subject three of Michelangelo’s central panels (<hi rend="i">Creation of Adam,
            Creation of Eve, The Fall and the Expulsion</hi>). Next we come upon two designs 
            (<hi rend="i">House of Death</hi> and <hi rend="i">Nebuchadnezzar</hi>) showing the despair
          and degradation of man also portrayed in Michelangelo’s <hi rend="i">Deluge</hi> and 
            <hi rend="i">Noah.</hi> The elemental acts of creation and division in Michelangelo’s three
          panels nearest the altar are summarized in <hi rend="i">The Good</hi>
          <pb id="p14-82" n="82"/>
          <figure n="but326.1.1.cpd" id="but326.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="729">
            <figTranscr>Fresco WBlake inv.</figTranscr>
            <head>18 Blake, <hi rend="i">Christ Appearing to the Apostles</hi>, 45.7 × 59.7
              cm.</head>
            <figDesc>National Gallery of Art, Rosenwald Collection.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <hi rend="i">and Evil Angels.</hi> Like the Sistine corner spandrels, Blake’s next group
          of three (<hi rend="i">Lamech, Naomi entreating Ruth, Pity</hi>) presents us with scenes
          poised between destruction and the promise of salvation. Blake’s antithetical Prophet 
            (<hi rend="i">Newton</hi>) and Sibyl (<hi rend="i">Hecate</hi>) lead us finally to 
            <hi rend="i">Christ Appearing to the Apostles</hi>, the Savior whose coming is necessitated
          by all we see in the Sistine Chapel.</p>
        <p>It is difficult to prove, given the information we have, that Blake consciously modeled
          his color-prints on the Sistine Ceiling, but the organizational parallels between these
          two groups are strong enough to indicate, at the very least, an indirect influence. It is
          certainly safe to assume that Blake knew the Sistine designs so well that their structure
          had become part of his own artistic habits of mind, and that when he came in 1795 to
          execute his own group of frescoes, Michelangelo’s influence would inevitably make itself
          felt. The essential ingredient was a core linear narrative, not of consecutive but of
          selected scenes, surrounded by actions and characters related thematically to the core.
          The complexities of spatial, temporal, and causal relationships suggested by such a format
          are part of those complexities Blake was beginning to investigate in his writings of the
          mid 1790s. Just as Blake modified for his own purposes the great texts in his literary
          tradition—preeminently the Bible and Milton—so too he did not simply reproduce the vault
          of the Sistine Chapel, but used its plan as the beginning of his own dark vision of
          creation, fall, death, and the promise of redemption.</p>
      </div1>
      <pb id="p14-83" n="83"/>
      <figure n="MichelangeloIgnudi.14.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="351">
        <head>19 Michelangelo, head of one of the <hi rend="i">ignudi.</hi></head>
      </figure>
	<pb id="p14-84" n="84" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
