<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.2.special</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">IO Special Issue</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1980</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Detlef Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Leonard M. Trawick</name>
              <name>Nicholas O. Warner</name>
              <name>Kasumitsu Watarai</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <pb id="p14-108" n="108"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-2-0011">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">NEWSLETTER</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">IO</hi> SPECIAL ISSUE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Jim Bogan and Fred Goss are editing a special Blake issue of <hi rend="i">IO</hi> which they have
announced as follows.</p>
          <p>Greetings: Almost 200 years ago William Blake engraved these prophetic words: “Rouze up, O Young
Men of the New Age! set your foreheads against the ignorant Hirelings; For we have Hirelings in the Camp, the
Court, and the University, who would, if they could, for ever depress Mental and prolong Corporeal War.” In
response to Blake’s summons, number 29 of the <hi rend="i">IO</hi> series will be a Blake issue which will
gather some of the sparks of inspiration that are flying from Los’ hammer in this new age. We are interested
in any work that makes use of energies sympathetically awakened by contact with Blake’s works/spirit. The
meeting might be as direct as Ginsberg’s visitation by Blake in Harlem or as indirect, say, as Snyder’s
“It” arising from the reading of a Blake poem during a storm.</p>
          <p>The traditional concerns of <hi rend="i">IO</hi> may certainly be focused on Blake: cabala,
alchemy, astrology, anthropology, psychology, shamanism, intuitive scholarship. We are looking for prose,
verse, and black/white graphics. Forms may include: poems, creative essays, aphorisms, meditations, inspired
scholarship beyond the MLA mold, speculations, jokes, maps, charts, dreams, visions, experiences when reading
Blake aloud—PRIMARY RESPONSES. A second emphasis of the issue will be works that provide ways into Blake for
those who would like guides high in clarity and low in jive. Subjects of interest here are Blake’s prosody,
myth-structures, the sexes, the evolution of his understandings, etc.</p>
          <p>Send submissions at your earliest convenience or whenever they blossom. Deadline: 15 February
<corr type="emend">1981.</corr> Please include stamped, self-addressed envelope. Kindly pass the word along to
anyone you know who might be interested in contributing to this project. SWEET JOYS BEFALL THEE, JIM
BOGAN/FRED GOSS, ART DEPARTMENT, UNIVERSITY OF MISSOURI-ROLLA, ROLLA, MO. 65401.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
