<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.2.yale</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">Yale/Toronto Exhibition</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1980</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Detlef Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Leonard M. Trawick</name>
              <name>Nicholas O. Warner</name>
              <name>Kasumitsu Watarai</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <pb id="p14-108" n="108"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-2-0011">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">NEWSLETTER</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">YALE/TORONTO EXHIBITION</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>David Bindman is organizing an exhibition of Blake’s work that will open at Yale in September
1982 and move to Toronto in January 1983. The exhibition prospectus reads as follows:</p>
          <p>The last full-scale Blake exhibition to be held in North America was in 1939 at Philadelphia, and
the most recent in Great Britain was the highly successful one at the Tate Gallery in 1978. The Tate
exhibition had an unequivocal purpose, which was to establish Blake as one of the greatest of British artists
in the same rank as his great contemporaries Constable and Turner. In my view and that of many people who saw
the exhibition, it proved the point beyond reasonable doubt. For this reason, I think that an exhibition in
which attention is focused exclusively upon Blake’s qualities as a visual artist does not need doing again
in the same way. We need now to take a wider and more exploratory view of Blake, and try to answer the kind of
questions which must arise once Blake’s stature as an artist has been accepted. While I think it is vital to
show Blake at his very best, I feel we must go further in setting the intellectual and artistic context of his
work and revealing his mind. There is a danger of being too didactic and I propose that this be avoided by
separating visually the main display of Blake’s art from the comparative material, which will run parallel
to it. To give an example of how this might work: the earliest illuminated books my be shown according to
their chronological development within Blake’s work, but nearby, perhaps on an adjacent wall, there might be
a small display explaining Blake’s new printing techniques with samples of other eighteenth-century
experiments. While there will be, wherever appropriate, works by Blake’s friends and contemporaries, efforts
will be made to define their relationship to Blake in intellectual terms rather than just through visual
parallels.</p>
          <p>It will be necessary to make a considerable representation of the great watercolor series such as
the illustrations to the Bible, Milton and Dante, but I also want to try to bring the illuminated books into
the foreground and take advantage of the great strides that have been made in recent years in their
elucidation. American libraries are astonishingly rich in fine hand-colored copies, and an important place
would be given to Blake’s masterpiece, Mr. Mellon’s unique colored copy of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>
There are difficulties in “explaining” these works in visual form, but I think it can be done by drawing
attention to the historical and religious themes in the books. For example, a small number of images can be
brought in to illustrate Blake’s idea of Jerusalem, e.g., Richard Brothers’ designs for the rebuilding of
the Holy City; and antiquarian treatises can be used to show the importance of Stonehenge in Blake’s
conception of ancient British history.</p>
          <p>The result should be an exhibition which will reveal the breadth and quality of Blake’s art,
but will also open up vistas to the serious inquirer by making connections between his art and wider currents
of thought in his time. DAVID BINDMAN, WESTFIELD COLLEGE, UNIVERSITY OF LONDON.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
