<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.2.lange</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake in American Almanacs</title>
        <author n="Lange">Thomas V. Lange</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1980</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Detlef Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Leonard M. Trawick</name>
              <name>Nicholas O. Warner</name>
              <name>Kasumitsu Watarai</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <pb id="p14-94" n="94"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-2-0009">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">BLAKE IN AMERICAN ALMANACS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Thomas V.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Lange</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Few of William Blake’s engraved designs were reprinted between his death in 1827 and the
publication of Gilchrist’s biography of 1863 (as G. E. Bentley, Jr. has 
noted<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78" type="note">1</ref>), 
and it seems worth continuing to record those that have
escaped the notice of Blake bibliographers. 
<note id="n78"><hi rend="s">1</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr. 
<hi rend="i"><corr type="emend">“‘New’</corr> Blake engravings . . . ,” Blake</hi> 47, p. 204.</note></p>
          <p>Two early American piratings of Blake plates appear in issues of <hi rend="i">The People’s
Almanac</hi> for 1834 and 1836. An article on page 29 of the 1834 issue (Boston, Willard Felt and Co., and
Charles Ellms)—vol. I, no. I—is entitled, “Account of a monstrous snake, Captured by Captain Stedman, in
the Wilds of Surrinam [sic] and Skinned Alive by a daring Negro.” The full-page wood-engraved illustration
accompanying this article generally copies a well-known and often-reproduced<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79" type="note">2</ref> Blake design for J. G. Stedman’s <hi rend="i">Narrative of
a five years’ expedition against the revolted negroes of Surinam</hi>, London, 1796 (there found in vol. I,
p. 182). In the reduced American version, prepared by a talented but anonymous wood-engraver, many details are
significantly altered. In the original engraved illustration entitled “The skinning of the Aboma snake, shot
by Capt. Stedman,” two natives are laboriously hoisting a limp snake aloft by a rope, while in the background
can be seen the lake and boat in which the enormous serpent was captured. The American copy omits the entire
back-ground and the two natives, showing instead the supporting rope tied firmly around the trunk of a tree.
In the copy, Captain Stedman has donned a pair of sandals, and the snake is writhing in a most animated
fashion while being skinned alive. The text of the episode is considerably edited and abridged in 
<hi rend="i">The People’s Almanac</hi> version, most probably to compress it into one page of unleaded text.
There are no embellishments of either style or content. <note id="n79"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Reproduced, for
instance, by Keynes, <hi rend="i">Bibliography of William Blake</hi> (New York, 1921), at p. 241.</note></p>
          <figure n="PeoplesAlmanac1834.14.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="710">
            <head>1 Wood-engraved illustration from <hi rend="i">The People’s Almanac</hi>, 1834.</head>
          </figure>
          <figure n="PeoplesAlmanac1836.14.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="746">
            <head>2 Wood-engraved illustration from <hi rend="i">The People’s Almanac</hi>, 1836.</head>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p14-95" n="95"/>
          <figure n="bb499.1.5.com" id="bb499.1.comeng.05" work-copy="bb499.1" rend="db" width="608" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>Blake Sculpt.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              The skinning of the Aboma Snake, shot by Cap. Stedman.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              London, Published Decr. 2d. 1793, by J. Johnson, St. Paul’s Church Yard.<lb/>
              19</figTranscr>
            <head>3 Blake’s design for J. G. Stedman’s <hi rend="i">Narrative of a five years’
expedition against the revolted negroes of Surinam</hi>, London, 1796, vol. I, p. 182.</head>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p14-96" n="96"/>
          <p>Another illustration from the Stedman work appears on p. 37 of the 1836 issue of the 
<hi rend="i">Almanac</hi> (vol. I, no. 3). The imprint—as with so many short-lived periodicals of the time—has
changed, and now reads: Boston, sold by Lemuel Gulliver,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80"
type="note">3</ref> published by Charles Ellms.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81"
type="note">4</ref> The original illustration (unsigned in the Stedman volume but given to Blake by both
Keynes and Bentley) entitled “The Sculls of Lieu<hi rend="s">t</hi>. Lepper, and Six of his Men,” appears in
vol. I, p. 237, where two soldiers are seen lamenting and gesticulating over the skull of the unfortunate
Lieutenant Lepper. A third soldier leans contemplatively on his flintlock, surveying the skulls of the six men
who “ . . . had one by one been stripped naked by the rebel negroes at their arrival at their village, and
(for the <hi rend="i">recreation</hi> of their wives and children) . . . flogged to death.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82" type="note">5</ref> The modified American version shows only a
single soldier reflecting on the skulls on poles, surrounded by scattered bones—this last detail added by
the American woodcutter. The text beneath, only nine lines long, very briefly summarizes the scene. The 
<hi rend="i">People’s Almanac</hi> cut is signed at the lower right, “Downes,” most surely J. Downes of
Worcester, Mass., working c. 1834-1850.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83"
type="note">6</ref> He is recorded as illustrating other almanacs for Charles Ellms: <hi rend="i">The American
Comic Almanac, The Comic Token.</hi> He was also responsible for numerous book illustrations.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n80"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Despite his remarkable name, this Gulliver was indeed a bookseller in
Boston, and is listed in the Boston city directory for 1836.</note>
	<note id="n81"><hi rend="s">4</hi><hi rend="i"> The People’s Almanac</hi> was published between 1834 and
1841; various issues are found at the New York Public Library, the American Antiquarian Society, and other
institutions. Copies are found with varying imprints—some have Boston addresses, some Philadelphia
addresses, and some are entirely without imprints. The contents of these various copies are identical. See
Drake, <hi rend="i">Early American Almanacs</hi> (New York, 1962).</note>
	<note id="n82"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Stedman, vol. I, p. 237.</note>
	<note id="n83"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Groce and Wallace, <hi rend="i">The New-York Historical Society’s
Dictionary of Artists in America, 1564-1860</hi> (New Haven, 1957), p. 186.</note>
	<note id="n84"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Hamilton, <hi rend="i">Early American Book Illustrators and Wood
Engravers, 1670-1840</hi> [including supplements] (Princeton, 1958-1968).</note></p>
          <p>It seems reasonable to assume that the publisher or editor of <hi rend="i">The People’s
Almanac</hi> had access to or himself owned a copy of the Stedman work, which formed but one source for the
illustrations of the many sensational articles commonly found in such publications. Other articles in 
<hi rend="i">The People’s Almanac</hi>, for instance, include pieces on the island of Tristan D’Achuna [sic],
the shipwreck of the <hi rend="i">Blendenhall</hi>, “Terrific contest with a lion,” “The affecting narrative
of [Elizabeth Woodcock’s] sufferings in a snow bank,” and the more predictable ephemeral information of
tides, lunar charts, and astronomical tables. It was common to include sensational articles with these
necessary charts to make almanacs more salable and attractive, and Ellms boasted in print that future issues
of <hi rend="i">The People’s Almanac</hi> would appear “containing numerous large Engravings, and
astonishing but true accounts of Adventures, Exploits and Escapes. Also fights between wild beasts,
Alligators, Snakes, Men, and Eagles.” The high quality of the wood-engraving is noteworthy, as is the wide
range of pictorial sources from which illustrations were taken. One article in the 1834 issue on Napoleon
crossing the Alps, for instance, copies the famous painting of Napoleon by David.</p>
          <p>It may well be that a systematic examination of the large numbers of American almanacs issued in
the mid-nineteenth century will reveal other such copies after Blake.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
