<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.3.grant</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">S. Foster Damon, A Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols of William Blake, with
a new index by Morris Eaves</title>
        <author n="Grant">John E. Grant</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1980/1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980-81</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Stuart Curran</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Bo Lindberg</name>
              <name>Ann Bermingham Miller</name>
              <name>W.J.T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>E.B. Murray</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Hoyt Trowbridge</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980/1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
	<pb id="p14-131" n="131"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">S. Foster Damon. <hi rend="b">A Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and
                                Symbols of William Blake</hi>, with a new index by Morris Eaves.
                            Boulder: Shambhala, 1979. xii + 532 pp. $9.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">John E.</hi> <name><hi rend="b">Grant</hi></name></docAuthor>.
          </byline>
          <p>When Damon’s <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> was published in 1965 almost
                        all scholars recognized it as an indispensable companion to Blake studies.
                        It was handsomely printed in large clear type and thus quite expensive. Not
                        many who acquired the first printing also got the slightly revised and
                        amplified second printing in 1967, which Brown University Press has
                        commendably kept in print. In 1971 Dutton brought out a small paperback
                        edition of the 1965 printing with severely reduced print and narrowed
                        margins—presumably because Brown University Press wished to reserve
                        the small improvements of the 1967 printing (chiefly articles on EVERLASTING
                        GOSPEL, INNOCENCE AND EXPERIENCE, and LAVATER). The Dutton edition went out
                        of print some years ago. Now Shambhala has reissued the 1965 version in the
                        same small print as the Dutton reprint but with more generous margins and
                        also an excellent index (pp. 463-532) by Morris Eaves. May Damon’s
                        great work of scholarship, thus helpfully embellished, long remain available
                        at a moderate price.</p>
          <p>It may not be obvious why a “dictionary” should need an index,
                        especially since the interconnected entries are usually cross-referenced.
                        But Damon’s <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> is practically an
                        encyclopedia of the subjects indicated in the subtitle, and anyone who
                        consults the <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> needs to be able to skim over its
                        entries without turning every page, for one symbol leads into another beyond
                        the cross-references given under any one entry. Only after running through
                        Eaves’s index can one answer the elementary pre-publication question:
                        “Have you checked Damon’s <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi>?” (I
                        did notice an important unindexed mention of Joseph of Arimathea on p. 136;
                        this is fair warning that one must also consult Erdman’s 
<hi rend="i">Concordance.</hi>)</p>
          <p>Damon was a great scholar because he had read deeply in all the authors Blake
                        himself read and also in more recent authors like Melville and Joyce that
                        Blake would have cared for had he lived long enough. Gossip used to
                        represent Damon as a mystagoge, but nobody who conversed with him thought of
                        him as a crank, even though some of his students admitted they
                        couldn’t work up an interest in subjects he knew deeply. During the
                        meetings I had with him late in his life, Damon was a wonderful 
<pb id="p14-132" n="132"/>
guide and companion, speaking clearly on abstruse
                        subjects and exhibiting a love of life such as many are not capable of, at
                        least in this culture. To be sure, it was not easy to argue a point with
                        him, but this was evidently due to his having become hard of hearing, rather
                        than to a dogmatic or authoritative cast of mind. It must be admitted that
                        nobody could persuade Damon that the evidence for Shelley’s being THE
                        BARD OF OXFORD (<hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi>, pp. 314-15; also eight other
                        references in the index) is weak, but he was also able to recognize the
                        complicating evidence of a letter to Hayley in which Blake had referred to
                        the insignificant Edward Marsh as “the Bard of Oxford.” Damon
                        correctly felt that Marsh lacked the stature for the poetic role in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> But in order for Blake to have had any chance
                        of being aware of Shelley, Damon had to imagine <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                        45 [40]: 30 being first issued as late as 1822. Meanwhile early copies of
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> required a Bard of Oxford fit to be
                        entrusted with the leaves of the Tree of Life. What cannot be denied by any
                        lover of Blake is that, if the Bard of Oxford must be imagined as some
                        actual person known to history, Shelley would have fitted the bill and Marsh
                        would not. This is Damon’s essential point and as such the proposed
                        identification fosters rather than contradicts true scholarship.</p>
          <p>The hostile reviewer in <hi rend="i">TLS</hi> 2 September 1965, p. 756,
                        complained that Damon’s Freudian views “seem
                        old-fashioned.” Considering the current flood tide of books, articles,
                        and remarks concerning Blake and Freud, Damon’s outlook, has, on the
                        contrary, proven to be prophetic. Neither Blake, Freud, nor Damon can, of
                        course, be held responsible for the sexual politics causing this
                        overproduction. A more specific challenge by the <hi rend="i">TLS</hi>
                        reviewer better identifies a weakness in Damon’s method. Noting that
                        Damon’s expository manner is simply affirmative rather than
                        suggestive, she pointed out that in the awesome picture on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
41 [46] the formidable flaming chariot—composed
                        of coiled serpents in which are seated an aged couple drawn by humanized
                        leonine bulls against a background of flames—is too flatly identified
                        as a version of Elijah’s fiery chariot (art. ELIJAH, p.
                        118—thanks to Eaves’s index). Indeed, she declared, without
                        counter-evidence, that there is no connection whatever with Elijah’s
                        chariot. She must have persuaded Erdman, who does not mention
                        Elijah’s chariot in <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi>, pp.
                        320-21. In this case the redesignation of the color print now called <hi rend="i">God
Judging Adam</hi> (formerly <hi rend="i">Elijah in the
                            Fiery Chariot</hi>) has complicated the problem of identifying all the
                        meaningful elements in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 41 [46]. Briefly, the
                        chariot remains either that of Elijah or of “God” even when its
                        vehicular power is supplied by Assyrian-descended bulls and great serpents
                        related to the ones ridden by children in <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 6 and 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> 11. But in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 41 [46] the
                        context has become pessimistic and parodistic so that the aged couple are
                        carried along whither the supervising eagle-spirits (related to Los) would
                        have them go. Though Blake’s images change somewhat in the last
                        chapter of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, the reader approaching them on the
                        Fiery Chariot of his Contemplative Thought will recognize that the aged
                        couple must take control again to be transported and transfigured.</p>
          <p>What Damon actually tells us leaves out too many of the refinements and
                        conditionals in this picture. But it is surprising how often he was able to
                        justify the concision of his confident expository manner. Because Blake is
                        normally not mystifying and only complicated according to principles mostly
                        made clear in Damon’s first book, Blake’s ideas and symbols
                        can usually be coherently explained. Damon did not pretend to say the last
                        word about any subject, and few readers will have the impression that he was
                        condescending to them or attempting to lead them around by the nose.</p>
          <p>The best way to assess the continued usefulness of Damon’s <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> is to
follow it in action. As a research tool,
                        it seems never to lose its freshness. Recently I noticed that Bentley, 
<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi> I, 14, glossed the
                        concluding aphorism of <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi>,
                        “God becomes as we are that we may be as he is,” with a remarkably
                        apposite quotation from Irenaeus’s <hi rend="i">Five Books Against
                            Heresies</hi>, which Bo Lindberg, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
                            Illustrations to the Book of Job</hi> (1973), p. 38, also cited in Latin
                        only. In checking the <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> (p. 402), I found that
                        Damon had chosen to quote Athanasius: “He indeed assumed humanity that
                        we might become God,” though he also gives references to Irenaeus (Book
                        III, not Book V, which was preferred by Lindberg and Bentley) and Calvin.
                        Damon’s conclusion, however, concentrates on the difference that
                        keeps Blake’s use of traditional ideas from ever seeming commonplace:
                        “Whereas the theologians all use the past tense, as of an historical
                        event, Blake uses the present tense, for the act is eternal and is always
                        going on.” Often the real force of Blake’s ideas can be
                        recognized neither by those of Eliot’s persuasion who suppose that
                        Blake had no tradition nor by those of Raine’s persuasion who suppose
                        that all Blake’s ideas were already in the Perennial Philosophy.
                        Damon is usually right in spirit because he could see the element of truth
                        in both these schools.</p>
          <p>Damon used to insist on the spelling “Tyger” whenever one referred
                        to Blake’s creation: I remember his checking my convictions about
                        this matter before he could relax and speak joyfully about Blake and the
                        other visionaries such as Dante and Dostoevsky (cf. p. 410 re. THE TREE).
                        Curiously, Damon was less scrupulous in referring to design 10 for
                        Dante’s <hi rend="i">Comedy</hi> by the Victorian title, “The
                        Circle of the Lustful” (p. 97)—a traditional solecism that
                        negates Blake’s own (reversed) inscription. The only appropriate
                        title for the greatest of pictorial ideas ever related to this wonderful
                        episode is “The Whirlwind of Lovers.” One can be confident that
                        Damon would have immediately corrected this anti-Blakean error if it had
                        been called to his attention, perhaps even troubling to explain why it is
                        misleading, as he did in the case of “Glad Day” (p. 14). Since the
                        old customarily wrong title falsifies Blake’s vision it is an error
                        in the usages of Blake scholarship that must forthwith be corrected.</p>
          <p>Let us suppose that we wanted to look up Blake’s idea of The Covering
                        Cherub. The long way would be to start with Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Concordance</hi>,
but Damon’s <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi>, pp.
                        93-94, COVERING CHERUB, gives a good 
<pb id="p14-133" n="133"/>
account of
                        the essence of this basic symbol, which has also been well discussed by
                        Frye, but few others. Unfortunately Damon neglected to cross-reference
                        CHERUBIM (p. 80) where the crucial early reference in <hi rend="i">The
                            Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> 14 is correctly identified so that one
                        can understand that this Cherub has a key place in all Blake’s
                        subsequent symbolism. If one had started at CHERUBIM Damon’s own
                        cross-reference to COVERING CHERUB would have sufficed, but no student would
                        ever hunt to find the fourteen other references given in the Eaves index.
                        (One of these, a reference to IEREUS (p. 194—i.e. <hi rend="i">priest</hi>—is
incorrectly spelled “lereus” in the
                        index, p. 478). The Covering Cherub is two-faced and many-faceted. Naturally
                        the Covering Cherub flourishes in an age obsessed with problematics,
                        ambiguities, and anxieties. The most learned of Blake scholars, Sir Geoffrey
                        Keynes, to whom the <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> was dedicated, even
                        professed to see the Covering Cherub where he is not, on the frontispiece of
                            <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi> Damon was a great critic because
                        he recognized the face of error and could uncover the difference between
                        what Blake was driving at and much else that can be thought and said about
                        the same thing.</p>
          <p>Damon’s method with pictures is simple and productive: his
                        thoroughness in matching the figures with words had rarely been equaled
                        except by Wicksteed and Roe. As a rule Damon refrained from translating
                        Blake’s pictorial symbolism into terms of Blake’s
                        “system”—the finding of Zoas and Emanations wherever men
                        and women were gathered together—at least when there is no call to do
                        so. For this reason, one can readily sort out truth from error in
                        Damon’s interpretations, whereas the cloudy equivocations of another
                        sort of critic are built on presumed ambiguities and thus are neither hot
                        nor cold.</p>
          <p>In my earlier review in <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi>, XLV(1966),
                        533-35 I praised Damon’s precision and also called attention to some
                        errors in the exegesis of major pictures, which are an important part of the
                            <hi rend="i">Dictionary.</hi> Damon reproduces and discusses ten major
                        pictures, starting with the greatest, as represented by the Rosenwald
                        drawing of the <hi rend="i">Last Judgment.</hi> For this picture he also
                        provides a shadow picture in which most of the fugures are numbered and
                        keyed, usually with appropriate passages from “A Vision of the Last
                        Judgment” as given in the Keynes text. Among the errors to be noted are
                        that Damon called group 71 Hagar and Ishmael, but they are certainly Sarah
                        and Isaac; the other pair are an unnumbered group between 64, The Church
                        Universal, and 70, Abraham. This error and part of Blake’s
                        description of the lost tempera, which must have differed from the drawing,
                        led Damon to identify the winged and bearded record keeper below them as
                        Mohammed. This is a major error, for the figure accords clearly with
                        Blake’s own description (which follows directly after that for 64,
                        the Church Universal): “The Aged Figure with Wings, having a writing
                        tablet and taking account of the numbers who arise, is That Angel of the
                        Divine Presence mentioned in Exodus XIVC., 19 v. and in other Places; this
                        Angel is frequently called by the Name of Jehovah Elohim, The ‘I
                        am’ of the Oaks of Albion” (<hi rend="i">N</hi> pp. 80-81, K
                        610). Damon must have realized that the Angel of the Divine Presence had to
                        be somewhere so he put him in at the upper right as number 12; unfortunately
                        this is a <hi rend="i">pair</hi> of kneeling figures associated with the
                        Communion above the clouds where damnation begins to operate. I am sorry to
                        say that this severe dislocation of Blake’s master design went
                        unremarked at the MLA meeting devoted to the <hi rend="i">Last Judgment</hi>
                        some years ago. All of us who were there seem to have had our minds on other
                        matters that Damon had handled with ease. I must add, however, that
                        Damon’s article on THE ANGEL OF DIVINE PRESENCE, p. 23, is concise
                        and suggestive.</p>
          <p>A word of caution for anyone who sets out to correct Damon’s <hi rend="i">Last Judgment</hi>:
the picture in the <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> is fairly clear but in the Shambhala format it is so
                        much reduced that one must use a magnifying glass. Even in the more elegant
                        treatment of the Brown University Press edition where the shadow picture and
                        key fold out and face the reproduction, not enough is visible for certainty.
                        Much preferable is the reproduction in Keynes’ <hi rend="i">Pencil
                            Drawings</hi>: Second Series (1956), pl. 27, or Keynes’s 1970
                        Dover edition of the <hi rend="i">Drawings</hi>, illus. 51; both, though
                        considerably reduced, are a good deal clearer. Though we must lament the
                        loss of the great tempera of the Last Judgment, we ought to realize just how
                        good the Rosenwald drawing is in its own right, not just as an indication of
                        what is lost. Roe’s description is entirely justified: “A great
                        masterpiece of design and linear draftsmanship, with an amazing feeling for
                        delicate and swift movement which weaves through the wonderfully organized
                        multitude of figures, preserving complete clarity amidst complexity, this
                        drawing ranks as one of the outstanding achievements of Blake’s
                        life” (A. S. Roe, “A Drawing of the Last Judgment,” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library
Quarterly</hi>, 21 [1957], 40; reprinted in
                        R. N. Essick, ed., <hi rend="i">The Visionary Hand</hi>, 1973, p. 205).</p>
          <p>Elsewhere, often in this journal, I have written at some length on five other
                        pictures reproduced in the <hi rend="i">Dictionary.</hi> In every case I
                        have profited from Damon’s observations, yet I have usually had to
                        disagree with or refine some aspect of his basic interpretations. As regards
                        the central figure in the Spenser cavalcade, for example, I show that she is
                        undoubtedly Britomart, not Amoret, as Damon had proposed (see 
<hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi>, illus. VIII and p. 384, vs. Grant-Brown in <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 31, 8
[Winter 1974-75], 66-67). And in
                        the Arlington Court Picture, referred to by Damon as “The Circle of
                        Life,” I have argued that the figures at the center must be Los and
                        Jerusalem, not Luvah and Vala (see <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi>, illus. IV
                        and p. 87, vs. Grant in <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 11, 3 [May 1970],
                        98 and 13, 4 [August 1970], 17-18; also <hi rend="i">Studies in
                            Romanticism</hi> 10 [1971], 21-26—repr. <hi rend="i">The
                            Visionary Hand</hi>, pp. 483-91). As for my discussions of the designs
                        for <hi rend="i">L’ Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi>,
                        two of which Damon reproduces, which appeared in <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Newsletter</hi> 16, 4[1971], 117-34, repr. <hi rend="i">The Visionary
                            Hand</hi>, pp. 418-48, and <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 19, 5
                        [1971-72], 190-202—Eaves’s index shows me that my note
                        references to passages in the <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> were incomplete,
                        but that luckily what I had over-looked does not affect my understanding of
                        Damon’s position. In his article on PLATO Damon saw well enough that
                        in <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi> 9, “Milton and the Spirit 
<pb id="p14-134" n="134"/>
of Plato” (illus. IX and pp. 327-28), Blake
                        was attacking Plato, not defending him, as Raine had wished to suppose. Yet
                        Damon remained enough affected by the Platonizers to declare that Plato was
                        Blake’s “former idol,” whereas he should have said Blake
                        had never been a Platonist.</p>
          <p>In my <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> review of the <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> I
complained of Damon’s identification of the
                        male figure who stands on the curve of the earth and receives a scroll from
                        Jesus in the <hi rend="i">second</hi> version of the Genesis title page as
                        the Holy Ghost. As a caption for the picture, illustration II, Damon refers
                        to the article ZOA, p. 459, but the discussion in the article GENESIS, p.
                        151, is more informative, indicating also that Damon had confused the first
                        and second versions of the title page. The additional five references
                        identified in Eaves’s index do not make the theory more persuasive
                        that the receiver of the scroll should be identified as the Holy Spirit.</p>
          <p>Curiously, Damon neglected to mention the third divine figure in the heavenly
                        regions who is represented as rushing with outspread wings above the top of
                        the picture, thus appearing in a position of superiority both to the Son on
                        the left and the Father on the right. While the body of this superior figure
                        is quite distinct, his actions and circumstances are only sketchily
                        indicated. First we must recognize that the Father (with his
                        compasses—not a bow, as I had asserted—held at his side) who
                        stands in a mandorla above the Tree of Life, is dividing the waters above
                        the firmament from those below. It is an extension of the supernal waters
                        that the superior spirit is rushing across as, with outstretched arms, he
                        wields a gigantic bow-shaped object that arcs around him and even over the
                        horizontal line sketched across the top to indicate the planned limit of the
                        picture.</p>
          <p>The figure himself is a direct quotation (reversed) from <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> 3 and 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> 3—as noted in
                        Erdman’s <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi>—but in the
                        final context he is freed from the flames that variously crippled the
                        attempts of both Orc and Los to resist the devastating hegemony of Urizen.
                        The sketched bow-shaped object he deploys is perhaps best understood as a
                        more regular version of the involved scroll that curves around the genial
                        self-image Blake drew in the Upcott autograph book on 26 January 1826. From
                        the directing right wing of the Holy Spirit descend two continuations of
                        this scroll: they blend into the second letter of the “Genesis”
                        title and thence pervade the whole word, being also passed on below in the
                        smaller scroll from Jesus to regenerate man who has arisen above the curve
                        of the Earth and even the sphere of air to receive it. The wings and
                        position of the originating figure alone show that in the end (on paper
                        watermarked 1826) Blake wanted to depict the Holy Spirit not as a bird (as
                        he had done as recently as the <hi rend="i">Last Judgment</hi>, and
                        elsewhere)—and certainly not as a vacuum—but as a virile man
                        with the power to disseminate the spirit of prophecy.</p>
          <p>Damon tried to draw some of these implications out of the fourth figure who
                        stands on the curve of the earth wearing as a loincloth the phallic letter
                        “I” of the title, but his position as the receptor of a scroll
                        from Jesus shows that he is human, not a Spirit. He is, to be sure, a
                        glorified human who wears a large plate halo, which is perhaps the Sun
                        itself, as he reaches up to receive the scroll from the Son while drawing
                        sustenance with his outspread left hand from the mandorla of the Father. I
                        am convinced, though I cannot prove it, that the scroll must contain the
                        Everlasting Gospel, which was promised to regenerate man in the Book of
                        Revelation and partly written out in Blake’s own Notebook. The new
                        Adam who receives it is the energetic embodiment of Albion who has arisen
                        and, after his dance, is fit to return to paradise, to make a human fourth
                        with the three persons of the Trinity. His posture is nearly identical with
                        that of the giant man who reaches up in <hi rend="i">The Angel of
                            Revelation</hi> and declares “that there should be time no
                        longer.”</p>
          <p>In the first version of the Genesis title page (watermarked 1821) there are
                        many different ideas and symbols which Blake refined and also altered in the
                        second version. Here three of the Four Zoas at the bottom also raise their
                        arms, thus echoing the gesture of the central man, while the fourth, though
                        bound, looks inward to witness the transfer of wisdom. But in the final
                        version the Four Zoas appear in animal forms and only one, a dishumanized
                        serpentine man, raises his (left) arm toward the Tree of Death, which is
                        added in this later version. Here it appears that even Los as the Eagle can
                        sight with only one eye the redemptive transmission of the Everlasting
                        Gospel, which in the last day can tell unobfuscated truth. These bestial
                        Four Zoas appear still bathing their feet in the waters outside of Eden, but
                        the flames that play over their figures in the earlier version of the title
                        page are no longer shown. The spectator is to infer that until after all the
                        Zoas have bathed in the other waters, the waters of life evident above the
                        firmament, the Zoas constitute bestial impersonations of the Covering
                        Cherub, as yet unable to find their places within the bosom of Albion.</p>
          <p>Still, the story of “Genesis” that Blake wished at last to show
                        correctly must have been that of paradise regained rather than of paradise
                        still lost. It will be interesting to see whether the edition of the Genesis
                        manuscript that has been promised for some time by the American Blake
                        Foundation has been conceived so as to reveal the extent of Blake’s
                        purposes in this project of the wonderful last year of his life. If so,
                        correct understanding will have grown out of the leads Damon left us by
                        calling attention to what is important and, what is even rarer, in
                        communicating the right spirit of interpretation even when details, even
                        major details, of the interpretation offered were inaccurate. Because
                        Damon’s imagination was always in the right place, the need for his
                            <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> will continue to be felt by every Blake
                        scholar. With Eaves’s assistance in locating all Damon had to say, we
                        cannot envision a time when it will be possible to get along without the 
<hi rend="i">Dictionary.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="p134u1" type="note">*</ref>
	<note id="p134u1">* Evidently my concluding and opening exhortations do not
                            quite express a consensus. Michael J. Tolley, for one, does not agree.
                            He calls my attention to his review of Damon’s <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> in
<hi rend="i">Southern Review</hi> (Australia) 2
                            (1967), esp. 271-74, which showed in detail that Damon was often wrong
                            about Blake’s understanding of the Bible. Perhaps the number of
                            scholars who, like Tolley, can forego use of the <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> is
larger than I have supposed. Still, I can think
                            of few books or articles published during the last fifteen years that
                            would not have been better if the elementary pre-publication question I
                            ask in my second paragraph could really <corr type="emend">be</corr> answered
                            “yes.”</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p14-135" n="135" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
