<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.3.trowbridge</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Wallace Jackson, The Probable and the Marvelous: Blake, Wordsworth, and the
Eighteenth-Century Critical Tradition</title>
        <author n="Trowbridge">Hoyt Trowbridge</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1980/1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980-81</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Stuart Curran</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Bo Lindberg</name>
              <name>Ann Bermingham Miller</name>
              <name>W.J.T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>E.B. Murray</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Hoyt Trowbridge</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980/1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
	<pb id="p14-143" n="143"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Wallace Jackson. <hi rend="b">The Probable and the Marvelous: Blake,
                                Wordsworth, and the Eighteenth-Century Critical Tradition.</hi>
                            Athens: University of Georgia Press, 1978. vi + 218 pp. $14.00</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">Hoyt</hi> <name><hi rend="b">Trowbridge</hi></name>.</docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The purpose of this study, Jackson says in his introductory chapter, is
                        “to propose yet another approach to the complicated subject of English
                        poetry and criticism in the later years of the eighteenth century, my
                        inquiry guided by sustained reference to the informing theme of the probable
                        and the marvelous” (p. 3). At the beginning of his concluding chapter,
                        he suggests that the usefulness of the work lies not “in the way of
                        discrete analysis,” of which there is a considerable amount but for the
                        most part not unfamiliar to students of the period, but rather “within
                        the area of general interpretation” (p. 169). The interpretation he
                        offers is historical, laying out a kind of map of the changes occurring not
                        only in the ways in which poems were made and responded to but in
                        assumptions about the arts, human nature, and the relation between the ideal
                        and the real. The changes are focused in two revolutions, the first in the
                        middle and the second at the end of the eighteenth century.</p>
          <p>The contours of Jackson’s map can be clarified by comparing it with
                        that presented by the students of “pre-romanticism” seventy or
                        eighty years ago, who covered the same time-span and the same critics and
                        poets. Beers, Phelps, Gosse, Saintsbury, and others of that school were like
                        Jackson in seeing the mid-century writers as “intentionally and
                        radically disruptive of the complex equilibrium maintained by the major late
                        seventeenth-and early eighteenth-century writers” (p. 15)—as in
                        revolt against what Saintsbury called the “neo-classic creed” and
                        Jackson “neoclassical restraint” (p. 30) or “Augustan
                        humanism” (p. 62). They differ from him in their
                        late-nineteenth-century assumption, tacit but unshakable, that the Romantics
                        had discovered the true nature of poetry and in their contention that
                        Collins, Gray, the Wartons, Hurd, and other contemporaries had at least
                        partially glimpsed the same truth and striven to follow it; as Gosse
                        quaintly remarked, they were “bicyclist scouts who prophesied of an
                        advance that was nearly fifty years delayed.” Jackson is much too
                        sophisticated to make the first assumption, and he finds much more
                        difference than resemblance between the mid-century poets and the Romantics.
                        In his view, the revolution of Blake and Wordsworth was made necessary by
                        “a mid-century poetic of such drastic limitations that it offered the
                        poet no specifically contemporary act of mind and no imitative models other
                        than the extrapolated sublimities of past poets” (p. 80; cf. 87, 144,
                        180-81, etc.), and the reform was directed at least as 
<pb id="p14-144" n="144"/>
much
against that poetic and the art it produced as it was
                        against Dryden, Pope, and Swift. If anything important was shared by the two
                        revolutions, it was a desire to restore passion to poetry, but they differed
                        radically on the nature of passion and the means by which it could be
                        realized poetically.</p>
          <p>Jackson argues for a historical continuity from Shakespeare, Spenser, and
                        Milton through the eighteenth century to Blake and Wordsworth, but in a
                        curious way most of the causal connections seem to lie in the kind of
                        influence that Harold Bloom has called “creative misprision.” Each
                        generation made its own selection from and interpretation of its
                        predecessors. Collins and Gray found inspiration and a model in
                        Milton’s minor works, especially <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi>
                        and <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi>,</corr> but were blind to the Christian and
                        Platonic elements that were essential to Miltonic sublimity. As Irene
                        Tayler, John Grant, and Kathleen Raine have previously observed,
                        Blake’s illustrations of Milton, Gray, Young, and Blair reveal the
                        terms in which he preferred to read their poems, often contrary to their
                        authors’ intentions, reinterpreting and reorganizing “the latent
                        potentialities of vision which Blake discerned within them” (p. 90; cf.
                        88, 89, 91). In his own poems he returned to the subject of <hi rend="i">Paradise
Lost</hi> and <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>, but he
                        rewrote the Miltonic theme of innocence and experience, correcting what
                        seemed to him the limitations and misconceptions of his great predecessor
                        (pp. 112-14). Jackson does not make this kind of point about Wordsworth,
                        however.</p>
          <p>Since his interest is in historical continuity, it is understandable that
                        Jackson should concentrate on the early works of the two Romantic poets whom
                        he discusses, without attempting any comprehensive treatment of their total
                            <hi rend="i">oeuvres.</hi> In the chapter on Blake (ch. 4) his main
                        concern is with the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, with some supporting evidence from the early, shorter
                        prophetic works and a few references to the still earlier <hi rend="i">Poetical
Sketches.</hi> On the side of general interpretation,
                        Jackson’s main contentions are that Blake built his revolution on
                        that of the mid-century poets, inheriting the passions from them but
                        mythologizing the gift and transforming it into the terms of his own vision;
                        that the emergence of Romanticism is best accounted for by the confluence of
                        mid-century passion with the dissenting religious tradition, heterodox
                        Christianity; and that Blake’s lifetime task was to reimagine
                        Milton’s myth of innocence and experience (pp. 108-14). On the side
                        of discrete analysis, as Jackson calls it, his readings are interesting but
                        somewhat unorthodox. He thinks that E. D. Hirsch is misleading in
                        recommending that the poems of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> should be read
                        seriatim and as an autonomous whole, and Robert Gleckner mistaken in
                        claiming that the meaning of Blake’s symbols is accretively
                        established from occurrence to occurrence. In Jackson’s less unitary
                        view, the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> are not exclusively about
                        innocence, although they unmethodically explore that state, and the various
                        speakers see it in different perspectives. In “The Chimney
                        Sweeper,” for example, the speaker is a corrupt, rationalizing voice of
                        experience which offers a hypocritical moral about “duty” at the
                        end of the poem. The morality of “pity” in “Holy
                        Thursday” is similarly corrupt, “the rigorous and stony-eyed truth
                        of an abstract morality” (pp. 97-99). It would be interesting to see
                        some responses to these readings.</p>
          <p>In the chapter on Wordsworth (ch. 5) Jackson’s evidence is primarily
                        drawn from the <hi rend="i">Lyrical Ballads</hi> and <hi rend="i">Poems in
                            Two Volumes</hi>, 1798-1807, though with full awareness of the 
<hi rend="i">Prelude</hi> and <hi rend="i">Excursion.</hi> The argument is
                        more diffuse than that of the Blake chapter, almost half of it being a
                        prolegomenon (pp. 123-44) on the mid-century poets, with a few pages on
                        Coleridge; much of this background material repeats points already made in
                        chapters 2 and 3, and its pertinence to Wordsworth is not always clear.
                        Although Wordsworth had apparently not read Blake until 1807, after the
                        publication of <hi rend="i">Poems in Two Volumes</hi>, Jackson finds the
                        poems in that work to be commonly concerned with innocence and experience as
                        states of the soul. “To a Butterfly,” “The Green
                        Linnet,” “To a Young Lady,” “The Sparrow’s
                        Nest,” <corr type="emend">“Written</corr> in March,” and “To the Cuckoo” are all
                        songs of innocence, while “The Small Celandine” and “A
                        Complaint” describe the contrary state. Wordsworth’s conception
                        of the fall from innocence to experience is different from Blake’s,
                        according to Jackson, since the latter recognizes it as not only inevitable
                        but productive of good through the prophetic imagination and the mental
                        warfare it generates, while Wordsworth “seeks ways to minimize its
                        reality, to limit and curtail its effects by strategies that begin with
                        recovery and lead to transcendence” (p. 156). Jackson supports this
                        interpretation by extended exegeses of the Lucy poems, “Resolution and
                        Independence,” and the “Immortality” ode. In this major phase
                        of his career, Jackson concludes, Wordsworth “has recreated an image of
                        human nature both probable and marvelous, the fusion of the ordinary and the
                        sublime within the permanent image of man” (p. 168).</p>
          <p>If I have any serious reservations about this well-written and challenging
                        study, they arise from two distortions, as they seem to me, which he shares
                        with the old-fashioned students of pre-romanticism. The first is to
                        exaggerate greatly the revolutionary thrust of mid-century critics, as when
                        he asserts that their position on the relation between the probable and the
                        marvelous was “hardly tempered at all by moderate neoclassic
                        principles” (p. 26). Hurd sounded radical to Beers and Phelps when he
                        defended Gothic elements in Renaissance epic poems, but he did so in terms
                        of imitation, nature, the rules, and poetic effects proportioned to the
                        kinds. In spite of his belief that the chief nerves of genuine poetry are
                        the sublime and the pathetic, so that <hi rend="i">Eloisa to Abelard</hi>
                        and the <hi rend="i">Elegy to an Unfortunate Lady</hi> are superior to
                        Pope’s satires and moral epistles, Joseph Warton still operates
                        within the traditional framework summed up in Dryden’s definition,
                        “just and lively images of human nature” and Johnson’s
                        “just representations of general nature.” The Time-Spirit may have
                        been carrying Warton along, as Saintsbury said, but it did not sweep him far
                        out to sea.</p>
          <p>The fundamental error of the Beers-Phelps school was to apply
                        nineteenth-century categories and criteria in interpreting the thought and
                        art of the mid-eighteenth century. In my opinion, Jackson 
<pb id="p14-145" n="145"/>
distorts Blake and Wordsworth by a similar but converse
                        anachronism, interpreting them through the theme of the probable and the
                        marvelous, an issue and a terminology that belong to a different, earlier
                        realm of thought and discourse. The resulting account, which he describes as
                        “no distortion of literary history”—“not a
                        historian’s invention but a discovery”—has some prima
                        facie descriptive plausibility as applied to Wordsworth, since he avowedly
                        attempted in the <hi rend="i">Lyrical Ballads</hi> to present ordinary
                        things to the mind in an unusual aspect, throwing a certain coloring of
                        imagination over incidents and situations from common life (Preface of
                        1800). He can even say, in a letter defending <hi rend="i">Peter Bell</hi>,
                        that the action of the imagination does not require supernatural agency but
                        may be called forth “by incidents within the compass of poetic
                        probability” (quoted by Jackson, p. 146). But neither he nor Blake
                        thought habitually or systematically in terms of such an opposition; it is
                        drawn from a radically different intellectual context and is alien to their
                        new ways of conceiving man, God, nature, and art. If we may adopt M. H.
                        Abram’s fruitful contrast, the notion of a mean or balance between
                        the probable and the marvelous belongs to the aesthetics of the mirror, not
                        to the Romantic poetic of the lamp.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
