<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.3.mitchell</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Robert N. Essick and Donald Pearce, eds., Blake in His Time</title>
        <author n="Mitchell">W. J. T. Mitchell</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1980/1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980-81</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Stuart Curran</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Bo Lindberg</name>
              <name>Ann Bermingham Miller</name>
              <name>W.J.T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>E.B. Murray</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Hoyt Trowbridge</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980/1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <pb id="p14-116" n="116"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">HOW ORIGINAL WAS BLAKE?</title>
            <title type="main">Robert N. Essick and Donald Pearce, eds. <hi rend="b">Blake in His Time.</hi>
Bloomington: Indiana University
                            Press, 1978. xx + 253 pp., 144 illus.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">W. J. T.</hi> <name><hi rend="b">Mitchell</hi></name>.</docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Blake has, on the whole, been well-served by scholarly anthologies. <hi rend="i">Visionary Forms
Dramatic</hi> (ed. David Erdman and John Grant)
                        showed us how to read his pictorial language in harness with his visionary
                        poetry; <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory</hi> (ed. Stuart Curran
                        and Joseph Wittreich) taught us that his major prophecies have a formal and
                        rhetorical integrity to match their intellectual brilliance. Now Donald
                        Pearce and Robert Essick give us <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi> to make
                        clear what should have been obvious all along, that Blake’s work did
                        not spring from nothing, but emerged out of a deeply learned and thoughtful
                        examination of his cultural milieu. In some ways this message does nothing
                        to redeem Blake from his splendid isolation: seeing him in his own time does
                        not necessarily make him more accessible to ours, and nothing will ever
                        remedy the combination of bad luck, intransigence, and indifference which
                        led to Blake’s neglect by all but a handful of his contemporaries.
                        But the other kind of isolation, the kind that T. S. Eliot referred to when
                        he complained of Blake’s “meanness of culture”—this
                        misconception has been decisively eliminated. Most major artists encounter
                        precisely the opposite sort of fortunes in cultural history. Criticism of
                        them begins with the study of influences, and attempts to place them in a
                        network of historical relationships. With Blake this sort of thing has come
                        very late, having to wait, it seems, for the formation of a modern community
                        of scholars and general readers, the fit audience that Blake so fervently
                        desired.</p>
          <p>To judge by this collection of essays the scholarly audience is very fit and
                        in no danger of being few. Some of the essays manage that most difficult of
                        balancing acts, reconstructing the historical context of a work of art while
                        suggesting its renewed importance for our own time. Gerald Bentley’s
                        meticulous reconstruction of the artistic response to <hi rend="i">The Book
                            of Enoch</hi> when it appeared in England in 1821 recovers a tiny but
                        fascinating moment in cultural history (five major artists and poets
                        illustrated or wrote about this apocryphal book when it appeared) at the
                        same time that it makes visible the remarkable inventiveness of
                        Blake’s designs for <hi rend="i">Enoch.</hi> Where Flaxman had
                        translated the Angels who couple with the daughters of men into his
                        predictable classical warriors, and Westall made them winged shepherds in a
                        sentimental pastoral, Blake <corr type="emend">seized</corr> upon a passage much later
in <hi rend="i">The Book of Enoch</hi> (message for illustrators: read the whole book)
                        in which the fallen angels are seen in the shape of “great stars, whose
                        parts of shame resembled those of horses.” Blake, as Bentley shows,
                        presents this image pictorially as a pair of Apollonian nudes with starry
                        rays and giant phalluses emanating from their loins. This grotesquely 
<pb id="p14-117" n="117"/>
effective invention (which sounds a bit
                        ridiculous, but is quite powerful in visual form) exemplifies Blake’s
                        rare gift as an illustrator, his ability to express something independent
                        of, almost in spite of his text (in this case, an affirmation of the
                        eroticism which is condemned by Enoch), and to do so not by violating the
                        text, but by imitating some carefully selected particular image in a
                        surprisingly literal way. Bentley’s account of this invention
                        highlights the central problem that unites the essays in this collection,
                        the question of Blake’s originality, uniqueness, and novelty; or, to
                        put the matter in its more vexed form, the question of Blake as a copyist,
                        imitator, and borrower—a parasite on the art of his precursors and
                        contemporaries.</p>
          <p>A practical and sensible way out of this dilemma is the formula enunciated by
                        Morton Paley, who speaks for most of the other contributors on this issue:
						<q> In discussing Blake’s theory and practice in the light of
                            traditions about ancient sculpture, we do not at all detract from his
                            uniqueness as an artist; nor do we violate Blake’s own view of
                            art. “The difference between a bad Artist &amp; a Good One,”
                            Blake wrote in his Annotations to Reynolds, “Is the Bad Artist
                            Seems to Copy a Great Deal: The Good One Really does Copy a Great
                            Deal” (E 634). Blake really did copy a great deal. The material he
                            copies often originated in other works of art but was assimilated by his
                            own mind and thoroughly recast, so that Blake could truly say, no matter
                            how important or how numerous his “sources,” that he copied
                            Imagination. (193) </q>
Paley’s formula raises, of course, as
                        many questions as it answers: What <hi rend="i">is</hi> the difference
                        between “seeming” to copy, and “really” copying? What
                        exactly is the “material” that is copied (motifs? style or
                        technique? inventions and compositional arrangements of figures?)? What does
                        “recasting” this material imply? Melting it down into a shapeless
                        mass to be molded into Blake’s own “new” forms? Or taking
                        the old forms and casting the raw material of new circumstances, ideas, and
                        meanings in those forms? What, finally, does it mean to “copy
                        Imagination”? Paley’s excellent essay on “Blake and Ancient
                        Sculpture” does not answer these questions, but it provides the
                        materials that might help us answer them, and his formula for reconciling
                        Blake’s tradition with his individual talent allows us to have our
                        cake, eat it too, and get on with the practical work of interpreting Blake:
                        Blake is an original copyist, an imaginative <corr type="emend">imitator</corr>.</p>
          <p>But other voices are not able to utter this paradox with the same sort of
                        equanimity. David Bindman traces Blake’s theory and practice of
                        imitation to neoclassic traditions expressed by, among others,
                        Blake’s arch-foe, Joshua Reynolds, who claimed that “Invention,
                        strictly speaking, is little more than a new combination of those images
                        which have been previously gathered and deposited in the memory: <corr type="emend">nothing</corr> can
                        come of nothing: he who has laid up no materials can produce no
                        combinations” (quoted in Bindman, 93). But Bindman notes that
                        “there are potential problems in such imitation” for an artist who
                        has Blake’s sort of ambivalence about tradition: “So long as
                        Blake accepted the widespread eighteenth century assumption of the supremacy
                        of Greek art—and there is every evidence that he did so in the
                        1790s—then Blake’s practice of imitation did not present a
                        dilemma . . . . But after 1800 or so he began to turn against ‘the
                        silly Greek &amp; Latin slaves of the Sword’ (E 94) and to regard
                        Greek art and literature as Allegory rather than Inspiration; i.e., the
                        product of Memory rather than Imagination” (95). This turnabout was
                        not, however, accompanied by a straightforward repudiation of classical art
                        or art theory. “Unable to relinquish his profound feelings for Greek
                        art,” Bindman argues, Blake devises from his “conflicting impulses
                        . . . one of the more bizarre artistic theories in the history of art, in
                        which all contradictions are reconciled and only historical probability is
                        sacrificed” (96). This is, of course, the notorious idea that classical
                        art is all derived from lost Hebrew prototypes, and is a weak (but the only
                        available) imitation of the divinely inspired originals. Blake’s
                        theory thus frees him to vilify classical art while borrowing from it, to
                        profess a Romantic theory of imagination and original inspiration while
                        practicing the classical method of imitation and invention. Bindman’s
                        theory psychologizes Paley’s paradox of the “original
                        copyist,” making it the irrational solution to an insoluble conflict,
                        and historicizes it at the same time, presenting us with a classical Blake
                        to 1800, and an apparently anti-classical Blake after 1800. The really
                        fundamental Blake, however, remains for Bindman “eighteenth century in
                        spirit . . . determined even to the end of his career by classical
                        idealism” (98).</p>
          <p>One could wish for a strong counter-statement to Bindman’s
                        neoclassical Blake from the spokesmen for the Gothic tradition in this
                        volume. After all, one of the unmistakable “materials” of
                        Blake’s imitation is the illuminated manuscript, a form which
                        presupposes a rather different sense of artistic imitation based in the
                        roles of the scribe, grammarian, translator, and illustrator, and a
                        different sense of the text (radically unlike that of print culture) as open
                        to indefinite embellishment, correction, and imitative
                        “improvement” (this attitude persists in England at least up until
                        Dryden’s “creative” translations of Chaucer). The words
                        “imitation,” “copy,” and “invention,” are not
                        exhaustively defined by eighteenth-century neoclassicism with its
                        Greco-Roman pantheon, its library of printed (and thus, in an important
                        sense, closed) classical texts, and its empirical, associationist psychology
                        of the creative process.</p>
          <p>The essays on Blake’s relation to Gothicism in this volume tend,
                        however, to treat this influence in a rather generalized way. Roger
                        Easson’s essay on “Blake and the Gothic” consists mainly of
                        pronouncements about “the Gothic reality” and “the Western
                        view of the world.” When Easson descends to particulars his comments
                        often seem odd or unconvincing. “The decisive factor” in
                        neoclassical art is proclaimed to be “verisimilitude” defined as
                        representation of the “material world” (147; a cursory look at
                        Reynolds’ <hi rend="i">Discourses</hi> or at Bindman’s 
<pb id="p14-118" n="118"/>
essay would correct this impression). We are told
                        that, for Blake, “the fall always has to do with the act of drawing
                        fine distinctions, differentiating between the Good and the Evil, between
                        heavy and light, between strong and weak, between right and wrong”
                        (152). Easson has here mixed a half-truth with a host of patent falsehoods.
                        It is true that Blake criticizes the construction of abstract
                        “Negations,” particularly the reduction of existence to abstract
                        categories of good and evil. But no one has ever been more insistent than
                        Blake on the importance of “fine distinctions” and “minute
                        discriminations” as an intellectual and artistic duty, and this
                        includes the distinctions between right and wrong, honesty and dishonesty,
                        knaves and fools. This sort of obfuscation is not surprising, however, in an
                        essay which concludes by defining Blake’s Gothic as “the spirit
                        of vision that embraces mystery rather than allegory” (153), at one
                        fell swoop identifying Blake with a phenomenon (mystery) that he
                        consistently despised, and opposing him to a literary form which, with
                        qualifications, he practiced throughout his career.</p>
          <p>Edward J. Rose’s essay, “The Gothicized Imagination of
                        Michelangelo Blake,” is considerably more substantial and reliable than
                        Easson’s, suggesting in its linkage of Michelangelo with the Gothic
                        tradition one way of mediating the conflict between the neoclassic and
                        Romantic versions of Blake, and pointing us toward an exemplary predecessor
                        who was himself a genius at “imitating” the antique, but in a
                        spirit rather unlike that of eighteenth-century neoclassicism. Yet
                        Rose’s essay leads to a conclusion which seems, curiously enough, to
                        leave Blake not “in his time” but more isolated than ever:
                        “Blake was not really committed to the direction of the art of the next
                        hundred years any more than he was at peace with the art of the hundred
                        years that preceded his time” (166).</p>
          <p>The best theoretical account of Blake’s struggle with the classical
                        tradition comes in Hazard Adams’ analysis of the annotations to
                        Reynolds’ <hi rend="i">Discourses.</hi> Adams shows, in the same
                        spirit as Bindman, that there are many issues on which there is “really
                        no contradiction” between Reynolds and Blake, “but Blake wants
                        there to be one,” partly because of Blake’s resentment of
                        Reynolds’ status in the art world in contrast to his own neglect,
                        partly because of Blake’s fundamentally different understanding of
                        the psychology and epistemology of art. Adams is strongest in showing why
                        Blake attacks Reynolds’ disparagement of “minute neatness”
                        in imitation: “On the matter of this kind of deception [illusionistic
                        verisimilitude] Blake must have been in agreement with Reynolds” (134),
                        yet it is more important for Blake to defend “Minute Neatness of
                        Execution” than to concur with Reynolds’ attack on 
<corr type="emend">illusionism,</corr>
                        because Blake wants to insist on a concrete, particular, and individualized
                        sense of the universal, as against Reynolds’ “general
                        form,” an incoherent hybrid of Platonic and empirical psychology. On
                        “the whole matter of copying and drawing from models,” Adams notes
                        that Blake “sometimes agrees and sometimes disagrees with
                        Reynolds” (138). Blake agrees with Reynolds’ idea that copying
                        is an essential part of artistic apprenticeship, the way to learn the
                        “language of art,” but he takes issue with Reynolds’
                        relegation of copying to a <hi rend="i">merely</hi> preparatory function;
                        like “mechanical excellence” and “facility in composing”
                        (which Reynolds also disparages), copying is for Blake the activity of the
                        mature artist who “copies Imagination,” and not a merely
                        subordinate or preliminary function. That is why Blake can sound even more
                        conservative and “classical” on the issue of copying than
                        Reynolds, calling “Servile Copying . . . the Great Merit of
                        Copying” (E 634): for Blake, ends and means, invention and execution,
                        realization and conception are not, as they are for Reynolds, separable
                        aspects of the creative act.</p>
          <p>The essays in <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi> that deal with his
                        imitation of particular motifs or techniques of predecessors and
                        contemporaries tend to rely upon the formula of imitative transformation or
                        criticism without reflecting upon it, generally with useful results. Leslie
                        Tannenbaum’s “Blake and the Iconography of Cain” presents
                        the most deeply developed critical argument in this group, showing how
                        Blake’s pictorial treatments of the Cain and Abel story criticize the
                        sentimental and moralistic treatments that Blake could have known, and
                        transform the story into a “sublime” confrontation with the nature
                        of divine justice. The other essays on pictorial motifs are more in the line
                        of preliminary efforts, mapping out areas for future research. Jenijoy La
                        Belle’s discussion of “Blake’s Visions and Re-visions of
                        Michelangelo” traces one route of Michelangelo’s influence from
                        the Sistine frescoes through the sixteenth-century engravings of Adam Ghisi,
                        to the drawings which Blake made after these engravings when he was a
                        student. La Belle’s attempts to show significant “alterations in
                        emphasis” between original and copy are hampered, however, by the lack
                        of reproductions of many of the Ghisi engravings and Michelangelo originals.
                        One wishes also that La Belle had been more persistent in raising the
                        question of how much allusiveness to the original figure is operative in
                        Blake’s echoes of these motifs in later work: she seems content to
                        generalize Michelangelo’s figures into familiar <hi rend="i">pathos
                            formulae</hi> (thus “Blake learned from the Manasses lunette how to
                        show devitalized humanity,” but is evidently unconcerned about who
                        Manasses is). The only figure from Michelangelo that La Belle credits with
                        “a pre-existing conceptual context” that Blake might have employed
                        allusively is that of the Prophet Daniel. Her conclusion, that Blake
                        “approached Michelangelo’s art in much the same way” that
                        he approached his own visions, “and that the usual distinction between
                        copying another artist and envisioning one’s own designs does not
                        pertain” (22), seems exactly right, and an important contribution to
                        the discussion of Blake’s concepts of imitation and invention. But if
                        it leads to an emptying out or generalizing of the “original”
                        which is being copied then it is hard to see how the imitation can have much
                        critical, transformative, or inventive content.</p>
          <p>The other two essays which deal with “regions” of Blake’s
                        imitation are solid, reliable efforts. Kay Easson’s discussion of
                        “Blake and the Art of the Book” is a good introduction to
                        Blake’s use of and departures from traditional patterns in the layout
                        of illustrated books. The most important departure 
<pb id="p14-119" n="119"/>
is, of
course, the Blakean invention of relief printing, a technological
                        “advance” which is employed, paradoxically, to “regress”
                        to the integrated form of the illuminated manuscript, and to eliminate the
                        division of labor and form (while employing the mechanical means) of the
                        modern illustrated book. Easson is very good on the ways in which Blake
                        imitates and parodies conventional features like tail-pieces, borders,
                        frames, column pictures, marginal designs, frontispieces, and title-pages,
                        but too often she is content merely to suggest that illustrative features
                        have significance without going on to say what that significance is.
                        Finally, Anne Mellor’s account of “Physiognomy, Phrenology, and
                        Blake’s Visionary Heads” is a judicious and workmanlike effort,
                        full of curious learning which (thank heavens!) is not taken too seriously,
                        as it certainly was not by Blake.</p>
          <p>One thing that must strike a reader of <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi> is
                        the relative scarcity of professional art historians among its contributors.
                        It is one of the great misfortunes of Blake scholarship that he continues to
                        be neglected by all but a few art historians, and his pictures thus have to
                        be explained by moonlighting literary scholars. Aside from David Bindman,
                        whose training in traditional art history partly accounts for his
                        neoclassical version of Blake, the only certified art historian in this
                        volume is Martin Butlin, who finds himself explaining to the Blakeans what
                        would be perfectly obvious and trivial to an audience of art historians, the
                        mysteries of “Cataloguing William Blake.” Butlin’s essay is
                        a treasure trove of information in problems of dating, authenticity, and the
                        nuances of “evidence of the eye,” and should be studied
                        attentively by any Blake scholar concerned with the historical context of
                        Blake’s pictorial art.</p>
          <p>The other essays which focus on Blake’s pictorial achievement are the
                        work of literary critics who have been doing their homework in art history
                        for so long they should have honorary degrees. Jean Hagstrum contributes a
                        richly suggestive exploration of the possible influence of Romney’s
                        drawings on Blake’s early work, and Robert Essick discusses the
                        subject he probably understands better than any other scholar in the world,
                        Blake’s “iconography of techniques.” Essick shows how
                        “controlled accidents” in Blake’s printing procedures can
                        take on significance—a significance that, one suspects, is sometimes
                        more attributable to the beholder than the creator. Essick seems on solid
                        ground when he discusses the multi-representational effect of patterns of
                        color printing which “refer simultaneously to geological, biological,
                        and psychological forms.” But when we are told that Blake’s
                        “foul inking” on plate 47 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> copy C
                        “is part of his revolt against empire, against the hegemony of machine
                        over man” (6), we feel that the boundaries of probability are being
                        breached. Either that or Blake was expressing in an ineffective and
                        self-defeating way what he was capable of saying much better in other
                        ways.</p>
          <p>I save for the last the two essays which deal with subjects closest to my own
                        interest in Blake, his work in composite art forms which unite poetry and
                        painting, and, by implication, time and space. Yvonne Carothers’
                        essay on “Space and Time in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>” is a worthy,
                        but seriously flawed attempt to relate Kant’s understanding of time
                        and space to Blake’s art (the flaws are: an understanding of Kant
                        which seems to come mainly through secondary sources; a failure to make an
                        argument as to why Blake should be connected with Kant; and some uncertainty
                        about exactly what the subject of the essay is). Joseph Wittreich’s
                        “Painted Prophecies,” on the other hand, is one of the most
                        important essays on the nature of Blake’s composite art in recent
                        years. Wittreich takes up that side of the <hi rend="i">ut pictura
                            poesis</hi> tradition too often ignored by scholars steeped in the
                        classical tradition, the model of “sacramental” and Biblical
                        pictorialism embodied in the text and interpretive traditions of the Book of
                        Revelation. Wittreich surveys the complex variety of verbal/visual and
                        textual/pictorial relationships that inform the peculiar discourse of
                        prophecy: the prophetic experience as a psychological drama that combines
                        visual and verbal material; the rhetorical concept of visionary prophecy as
                        a “universal language of visual icons”; and descriptions of the
                        book which is given to John on Patmos as a scroll adorned with pictures and
                        hieroglyphs.</p>
          <p>There is an unacknowledged tension in Wittreich’s presentation,
                        however, that bears on the problem of original and copy that we have been
                        tracing throughout this volume. In one sense, of course, there is for the
                        prophetic artist no such thing as “imitation” in the classical
                        sense because the prophet is always at the origin, in direct, unmediated
                        contact with divine inspiration, and thus freed from the historical chain of
                        influence and imitation. The visual, visionary, and pictorial
                        characterizations of prophecy are, in fact, a way of stressing this
                        unmediated, intuitive access to the divine message. The verbal element of
                        prophecy is, for the commentators on Revelation, a kind of supplement to the
                        original message: “the assumption of all these commentators is that
                        Christ’s vision is presented initially as a picture; for
                        John’s (and our) sakes, that vision is preserved in a book, this time
                        with words accompanying the pictures; and this book, in turn, is translated
                        by John into the Apocalypse, into its verbal icons” (104). The text is
                        added as an accommodation “for our sakes”.: it mediates,
                        preserves, and interprets the original vision for those of us who do not
                        have access to prophetic insight, or to the original illustrated scroll
                        given by Christ to St. John. But we need to ask at this point why these
                        secondary, supplemental steps are necessary if the original vision is
                        inscribed in the universal language of pictorial representation, the medium
                        which needs no learned reading or interpretation, but needs only be beheld
                        to be understood? Isn’t this universalizing and democratizing of the
                        divine message precisely the point of illustrating or illuminating the
                        sacred text? What else but this is the logic of producing an illustrated 
<hi rend="i">biblia pauperum</hi> that can be read by the illiterate laity?
                        Why doesn’t the prophet simply paint what he sees, or copy the
                        pictures from Christ’s scroll, thus eliminating the priestly, scribal
                        middleman who will become custodian of the prophet’s verbal
                        translation of the divine vision? The answer can only be that those pictures
                        are <hi rend="i">not</hi> transparent, unmediated, universally readable 
<pb id="p14-120" n="120"/>
revelations of divine messages, but are
                        “concealed and dumb prophecies,” hieroglyphs which require
                        interpretation, a verbal supplement to unveil their hidden meaning. The
                        pictorial expression no longer reveals the original inspiration but conceals
                        it, is no longer eloquent but dumb; the verbal translation no longer appears
                        as a superfluous covering or husk to the original prophetic picture, but
                        becomes “revelation in the litteral expression,” a textual
                        expression of the original meaning intended by and concealed in the picture.
                        This new genealogy of prophetic expression reverses the priority of visual
                        to verbal expression insisted on by the commentators on Revelation, and
                        restores the priorities of Old Testament and English Protestant prophecy:
                        “There are three kinds of prophecy, says Luther in his 1545 Preface to
                        the Apocalypse: Moses’ kind which consists only of words,
                        Daniel’s which combines words with symbols, and John’s which
                        is purely visionary and consists only of ‘Pictures’”
                        (103). As Wittreich notes, “Hebrew law, in fact, forbade the kind of
                        pictorial adornment that Christianity encouraged” (104). The picture is
                        not simply supplemental and secondary, a necessary evil, but now becomes an
                        unnecessary evil, a vain idol to be smashed by the iconoclast.</p>
          <p>These reversals in the verbal/visual dialectic of prophetic poetics provide
                        new perspective on the exact character of Blake’s illuminated books.
                        Blake’s refusal to grant privilege or priority to text or design, his
                        construction of his illuminated books as a kind of icono-logo-machia, the
                        text a battleground of verbal and pictorial modes, is a strategy for
                        dramatizing a fundamental conflict in the network of religious signs upon
                        which he draws. The ambivalence about the icon or image in Protestant
                        culture, its double life as a transparent window on the divine message, or
                        an obscure hieroglyph which conceals that message and threatens to become an
                        object of idolatry—this ambivalence is converted by Blake into a
                        source of energy for the poetic and pictorial circuits of his illuminated
                        texts.</p>
          <p>The tension between verbal and visual expression which is revealed in
                        Wittreich’s account of “painted prophecies” also clarifies,
                        I would suggest, Blake’s complex attitude toward the problems of
                        origin and copy, invention and imitation. Verbal and pictorial modes are
                        continually discussed in prophetic poetics in terms of priority and
                        supplementation, “original” vision (or verbal message) and a
                        secondary translation, interpretation, or illumination which replaces,
                        transforms, or unveils the “original meaning” concealed in the
                        “original work.” The relation of text and design shares in the
                        same dialectic that informs Blake’s understanding of copy and
                        original. The important distinction for Blake is not between copy and
                        original, but between a weak (or tame or “seeming”) copy and a
                        strong, “real” copy. Blake could, like Bindman’s good
                        classicist, speak of imitation and invention, but without meaning quite the
                        same thing as Fuseli, whom Bindman quotes: 
						<q> 
                        	The term invention never
                            ought to be so far misconstrued as to be confounded with that of
                            creation, incompatible with our notions of limited being, an idea of
                            pure <corr type="emend">astonishment,</corr> and admissable only 
                            when we mention Omnipotence; to
                            invent is to find: to find something, presupposes its existence
                            somewhere, implicitly or explicitly, scattered or in a mass. (93) 
						</q>
                        What if one is a classicist who believes that the only omnipotent deity
                        worth mentioning is the one that “resides in the human breast,”
                        the Poetic Genius or human imagination? The notion of imitating a previous
                        work of art cannot be seen from this point of view as supplemental,
                        secondary, or parasitical, cannot be incompatible with creation. In fact,
                        “Imitation is Criticism,” not a slavish copying of the external
                        form of a prior work, but an interpretation which reveals what the text has
                        previously hidden, an illumination or explanation. The “original
                        meaning” of a text is not lost, or locked forever in the receding
                        moment of its historical creation, but unfolds in the history of its
                        imitative interpretations. That is why Blake can seem to have both an
                        ahistorical view of art as unprogressive revelations of the imagination, and
                        yet see himself as building his own art progressively out of Milton and the
                        Bible (both read in the “infernal sense”), and out of a classical
                        tradition which has fallen prey to “tame imitation” by treating
                        its sacred texts as closed books, traces of an unrecoverable origin. When
                        Blake imitates a work of art (which will itself, he knows, be an
                        imitation—an engraving of a Renaissance master, a text which
                        supplements or interprets a vision, a picture which illustrates a text) he
                        imitates the original authority that enables human beings to construct for
                        themselves a world of signs, and thus “copies Imagination.” There
                        is thus no distinction for Blake, as there is for Reynolds, between the
                        phase in the life of an artist, or the history of art, when we must copy and
                        invent: we learn the language of art by copying other works of art; we
                        execute original works of art by copying forever.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
