<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.3.simpson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Michael Phillips, ed., Interpreting Blake</title>
        <author n="Simpson">David Simpson</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1980/1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980-81</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Stuart Curran</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Bo Lindberg</name>
              <name>Ann Bermingham Miller</name>
              <name>W.J.T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>E.B. Murray</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Hoyt Trowbridge</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980/1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-3-0006">
        <pb id="p14-121" n="121"/>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Michael Phillips, ed. <hi rend="i">Interpreting Blake.</hi>
                            Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1979. x + 269 pp., 20 illus.
                            $34.50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">David</hi> <name><hi rend="b">Simpson</hi></name>.</docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>With Blake of all writers most aware of the positives and negatives of
                        imposition in all its forms, does it help, I wonder, to distinguish the poet
                        read in Britain from the poet read in North America? If so, then British
                        Blake is the function of an audience not entirely sure that their poet
                        “makes sense,” and one which tends to insist that where he does
                        make sense then it is in terms of a directly embodied concrete image,
                        historical pressure, or social outrage. Conversely, American Blake might be
                        cast as the apostle of visionary novelty and eternal history, a poet
                        therefore infinitely generative of further critical riches, neither wanting
                        nor daring to stop (for there lies standing water), and conformable thereby
                        to a logic of the imaginative body and bodily discovery, one suggesting the
                        secondary determinability of culture and history by the devolutions of the
                        individual mind which is divine. Blockages may appear, and repetition invade
                        creation, but the blockages are never quite the same twice running.</p>
          <p>Complications of course arise. The best book on British Blake has been
                        written in America, by David Erdman, and it may be that the above version of
                        American Blake is to be related to the generations of the late 1960s. But I
                        find the distinction useful if only as a way to say that there is very
                        little of that American Blake in this British book. Two versions of Blake,
                        in the form of two questions addressed to him, may be specified in it.
                        First, does he make sense? As usual, this question tends not to question
                        itself, never recognizing “sense” as ideological rather than
                        universal. Fortunately, there is not too much of this. Second, where does
                        Blake stand in history, and can we establish a history which entitles us to
                        dismiss certain kinds of ambiguity or puzzlement as beside the point, while
                        establishing others as central to “meaning”? This second question
                        is more firmly and usefully addressed, if not always with the
                        self-consciousness one might hope for in the presentation of its
                        implications. But then self-consciousness and dialectical agility tend not
                        to belong to British Blake, being matters ordered in France.</p>
          <p>Michael Phillips’ brief introduction indeed tries to set the tone of
                        what is to follow. He promises a series of “close analyses”
                        helping us to “read and objectively explain” Blake’s
                        meanings. Indeterminacy is insinuated, but only under constraint:
                        “Where interpretation is concerned, an essential principle has been
                        observed that it should not be imposed” (p. 1). No patience here, it
                        seems, with those who see only imposition; or those who find, as I myself
                        do, a more troublesome and dialectical obligation in the concept of
                        “interpretation,” one which questions or at least demands closer
                            <pb id="p14-122" n="122"/>
definition of the aspiration to
                        “articulate objectively.” The best essays in this book do address
                        themselves to that aspiration.</p>
          <p>The anthology opens with E. P. Thompson’s “London,” a poem
                        which is notoriously central to the debate between history, vision, and
                        visionary history. In its length and closeness of focus, Thompson’s
                        reading must be admitted to the canon of “necessary reading” for
                        this poem. The thesis is that “London” is a “unitary
                        analysis” (p. 20) of a historical condition, a poem whose
                        “symbolic organization is within the clearly conceived and developing
                        logic of market relations” (p. 22). The strongest part of this case is
                        the context provided for Blake’s use of the word
                        “charter’d,” which is I think of undeniable importance. The
                        other word on which Thompson spends a good deal of time is, predictably,
                        “mark.” Though he generally claims to accept “seventeen types
                        of ambiguity in Blake” (p. 15), Thompson strongly objects to any
                        “gesture towards an ulterior ‘ambivalence’ in which Blake
                        has assimilated the damned to the elect.” Such a reading would
                        “destroy the poem” and introduce “into its heart a direct
                        contradiction of intention and of feeling.” A possible reference to 
<hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi> is dismissed as that to <hi rend="i">Revelation</hi> is asserted. Blake is “not setting
marks on
                        foreheads, he is observing them” (p. 12).</p>
          <p>I find this case interestingly tendentious. Perhaps the word
                        “heart” tells all. Do poems have hearts? No, the people who write
                        them do. But could not that heart be divided between intention and feeling,
                        and could not that division itself be an important part of social history?
                        For Thompson, it seems that the heart is what gives authority to unambiguous
                        perception, and to a social outrage uncontaminated by self-implication. The
                        logic of the heart is an important theme in nineteenth-century literature,
                        and I hope my point does not seem trite. What is the credibility, for
                        example, of the unitary heart with which Dickens endows Esther Summerson in
                            <hi rend="i">Bleak House</hi>? Can we not ask questions about its
                        sufficiency? Are we not meant to? In making Blake an angry outsider,
                        commenting on a situation with which he has nothing to do, and which he
                        objectively transcribes, Thompson removes him from membership of that class
                        of dialectically constructed Romantic subjectivities who experienced
                        alienation not as something going on <hi rend="i">around</hi> them but also
                        as something reduplicated or created <hi rend="i">within</hi> them. Thus
                        Wordsworth is able to chronicle, with an honesty which at times almost
                        creates incoherence, the problems of power and exchange which occur in the
                        most solitary encounters and the most spontaneous perceptions. The mind is
                        inescapably social even in its assertions of separateness, and a wider
                        reading of Blake might at least suggest a poet very well aware of the
                        intersubjective determinants and consequences of outrage. I cannot quite 
<hi rend="i">complain</hi> that Thompson wants a Blake who is pure of heart
                        and eye (an unregenerated Milton?), devoted to one law and one polemic,
                        without being uncomfortably aware of the literary critic’s besetting
                        interest in ambiguity. But I can wish him to be more aware of the
                        alternative <hi rend="i">history</hi> of consciousness which I think he is
                        ignoring.</p>
          <p>Thompson’s reading of the last two stanzas is, to my mind, less
                        convincingly maintained. The idea that there is a reference to “the
                        smoke of expanding commerce” (p. 16) in the word “blackning”
                        needs refining. Commerce itself does not produce smoke. Industry does, and
                        it is industry which helps to make commerce possible. This may seem a
                        pernickety objection, but to ask what kind of <hi rend="i">industry</hi>
                        Blake might have had in mind seems to me rather important for the poem.
                        Erdman notes that London in 1803 was not so much a standard factory town as
                        “a war arsenal and the hub of the machinery of war.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> Could it have been so earlier, at the
                        time “London” was being meditated? If so, then this would specify
                        Blake’s positioning of commerce as hand-in-hand with empire and war.
                        Taken together with Erdman’s reading of this poem, which suggests
                        that the “hapless soldier” could be either the foreign mercenary
                        or indeed the now superfluous English yeoman made redundant by him (pp.
                        277-78), we can see an important issue here. The wealth which enabled the
                        king to afford mercenaries would have been related to commerce, and J. G. A.
                        Pocock’s work has shown us the importance of this debate in the
                        eighteenth century.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref> Commerce erodes the
                        rights of freeborn Englishmen by replacing militias with standing armies in
                        the pay of the king, as it also erodes their capacity for civic virtue.
                        Instead of being self-sufficient and self-determining, they now indirectly
                        pay other people to fight their wars. They therefore have no control over
                        war, which can happen without their wanting it, and in addition a force has
                        been created which can be turned against the people itself. If this
                        situation is indeed behind Blake’s poem, then it importantly
                        differentiates him from an economist like Adam Smith, who had seen in
                        commerce and free trade a civilizing and peacemaking function. Soldiers too
                        may be chartered, and hapless in their expression of the alienation imposed
                        upon them by the division of labor; haplessness affects both those employed
                        and those displaced and affronted. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> David
                            V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire</hi>, 3rd ed.
                            (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1977), p. 396. See also p. 60. Where
                            I refer to Erdman, it is to this book.</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> I am thinking particularly of <hi rend="i">The Machiavellian Moment:
Florentine Political Thought and the
                                Atlantic Republican Tradition</hi> (Princeton: Princeton Univ.
                            Press, 1975), chs. 13 &amp; 14.</note></p>
          <p>Thompson’s essay concludes with an account and eventual dismissal of a
                        Swedenborgian context for the poem. Finding Swedenborg’s writing
                        “remote from experiential controls and affective references” (p.
                        26), he concludes that it has little to do with “London.” What he
                        says of Swedenborg is, however, a useful preliminary to Morton
                        Paley’s more extended account of the relation between Swedenborg and
                        Blake’s writing (<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 50).</p>
          <p>Focus is widened somewhat in Heather Glen’s essay,
                        “Blake’s Criticism of Moral Thinking in <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Innocence and of Experience.</hi>” The argument is that the 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> both express and subvert the terms and assumptions
                        of “contemporary ethical discussion” (p. 32), showing forth a
                        “distrust of moral thinking itself” (p. 33). By “moral
                        thinking” Glen means not only the assertive imposition or deduction of
                        values, but also the more elusive logic of the feelings—charity,
                        pity, and so forth. The case is carried on in a close reading of several
                        among the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, paying particular attention to the status
                        of the speaking voice, and to the metrical patterns and local ambiguities
                        that enforce it. Impressively, this traditionally “literary” way
                        of reading is incorporated with a historical specification of the allusions
                        these poems demand or invite. Readings 
<pb id="p14-123" n="123"/>
of
                        “The Chimney Sweeper” of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, of the two
                        “Holy Thursday” poems, of “London,” and of “The
                        Human Abstract” are offered. In general they contrast usefully and
                        provocatively with Thompson’s account of “London,” in their
                        argument for inclusive rather than exclusive reference (see, for example,
                        Glen’s comments on “mark”). Thus the figure of the sweep is
                        described as a “potent image of subversive passion” (p. 42) in
                        ways which are at once sexual, social, and political. Not that Glen presents
                        ambivalence as itself a virtue; on the contrary, she composes it into a more
                        sophisticated concept of the “unitary” than the one Thompson
                        offers. In so doing, she leads us closer to the point where social and
                        individual determination coincide in the construction of Blake’s
                        speakers.</p>
          <p>In this achievement, it might in fact be said that Glen goes almost too far.
                        The speaker of “London” is thus presented as “imaginatively
                        bankrupt” (p. 57), one who is “more deeply and consciously
                        implicated in the abstracting modes of his society than anyone else”
                        (p. 60). Glen’s general contention about the speakers of 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi> is that they reveal “the same abstracting,
                        distancing strategies which have produced the social consequences that they
                        seek to condemn” (p. 66). Why, then, should the speaker of
                        “London” be <hi rend="i">more</hi> deeply contaminated by this
                        habit of mind than others in his society? This seems to me to go too far in
                        locating essential responsibility with the speaker; it fails to stress
                        (though it implies) the degree to which his options about what to 
<hi rend="i">see</hi> are themselves foreclosed and pressured by what is
                        around him, the real historical situation whose terms we can adduce from
                        Thompson and Erdman. (It depends, too, on an implicit antithesis between the
                        innocent and experienced speakers which we need not, I think, follow.) The
                        point may be tested against Glen’s reading of the second of the
                        “Holy Thursday” poems. She admits that this is a difficult case,
                        and one is grateful for an account of this often ignored poem. It becomes
                        wholly a poem about the speaker, who is presented as totally cut off from
                        what is <hi rend="i">really</hi> around him in a gesture of hysterical moral
                        inscription. He “reduces things to their moral qualities, and robs them
                        of their rich reality”; he is responsible for a linguistic vapidity
                        which gives no sense of “a rendition of a real scene, the expression of
                        a moment when the speaker saw what was before him with more than usual
                        vividness and clarity” (p. 54). Glen’s reading is more
                        sophisticated than I suggest here, and is to be taken seriously, but I want
                        to pick out this contention to highlight a question: is there really a
                        “rich reality” which the speaker simply cannot see because of
                        strictly subjective limitations? This suggests that the speaker’s
                        view is in fact <hi rend="i">not</hi> socially determined, and does not at
                        all represent what is <hi rend="i">there.</hi> Thompson might well complain,
                        and I would complain with him, that this view does not allow for any
                        credibility or conviction at all in the voice of outrage. Surely the details
                        of the world of <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> are not just “a series of
                        self-produced abstractions” (p. 56)? It is in the nature of social
                        institutions that they are already there when a new generation opens its
                        eyes, and it is a fact of particular societies that they produce particular
                        forms of defining the human condition, differently indeed for different
                        people. Chapels, palaces, and arsenals were and are built, and constitute
                        what it would not be ambitious to call a <hi rend="i">reality</hi>. I think
                        this is a point at which Glen could afford to make the assumptions implicit
                        in her thesis more clear, and indeed more historical. Is Blake a Godwinian
                        idealist who believes that revolutions of the mind precede and determine
                        social structures, and does he then rely on the same prospectus for
                        “truth” as Godwin does, that once put abroad it will spread and
                        conquer by its own energies, without revolutionary effort? Or is he a more
                        devious and deflected spirit, conscious, like Wordsworth, of all that
                        interferes with the development of the mind (perhaps initially innocent,
                        perhaps not)? My own sense is that Blake partakes of both these figures; he
                        often implies that the subjective imagination is a way beyond the
                        constraints of imposed ways of seeing, but those constraints are there to be
                        reexperienced again in the periods when the claims of habitual perception
                        accrue. This mediated view of Blake becomes itself “historical”
                        when we recognize all that came in the way, in the 1790s, of openly
                        expressed revolutionary fervor, and understand the pressures toward the
                        advocacy of private experiences as redemptive. (No one has done more than
                        Thompson, in <hi rend="i">The Making of the English Working Class</hi>, to
                        make this information available.) In the <hi rend="i">communication</hi> of
                        that privacy, I think that Blake made a place for all the versions of
                        pathological and social opposition which occur when interests clash in the
                        forum of “meaning” and authority. Glen’s is a fine essay,
                        but it would be the poorer if it were not set against what is of worth in
                        Thompson’s more trenchant pronouncements. Taken together, they
                        present a useful tension to help us decide between authoritatively
                        single-hearted and hysterically alienated speakers in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Songs.</hi></p>
          <p>Frank M. Parisi’s “Emblems of Melancholy: <hi rend="i">For
                            Children: The Gates of Paradise</hi>,” shifts the focus wholly from
                        the verbal to the visual aspect of Blake’s work. Concentrating on the
                        first issue of these designs, Parisi seeks to recover what Blake
                        “originally intended” (p. 71) by them, which he argues to be an
                        embodying of and response to eighteenth century conventions of melancholy:
						<q> My conclusion is that the <hi rend="i">Gates</hi> presents the life
                            of fallen man as a melancholy cycle turning on frustration, defeat and
                            despair, the more insidious for being self-renewing. At the same time
                            the <hi rend="i">Gates</hi> goes far beyond contemporary analogues, for
                            it points unequivocally to a way one may break out of the cycle into a
                            visionary and creative state. (p. 74) </q>
Let me say at once that I am
                        in no sense qualified to offer a proper assessment of the success or failure
                        of this argument. But I will say that I am not given much information on
                        which to base a judgment. For an essay which discusses entirely visual
                        contexts, it is perversely under-illustrated. One might perhaps pass over
                        the absence of Blake’s own designs, which have often been reproduced
                        elsewhere, though this is at the least an inconvenience. But I frequently
                        find that reference is made to, and arguments built on, pictures or
                        engravings which are not reproduced. For example, <pb id="p14-124" n="124"/>
                        Dürer’s <hi rend="i">Melencolia I</hi> is often cited as of
                        great importance: but we have to head for a library to confirm that
                        importance. Exhaustive descriptions of things which depend for conviction on
                        being <hi rend="i">seen</hi> make this essay very hard to follow. Other
                        frustrations appear in an occasional lack of evidence, or lack of
                        consideration of alternatives. What is the force of seeing the
                        “butterflies” of plate 7 as “the female aspect of
                        nature” (p. 73), and of Blake’s conversion of a traditional
                        motif into anthropomorphic images? Why is the insect of the frontispiece a
                        “worm” rather than a caterpillar (p. 76)? It is about as obvious a
                        caterpillar as one could hope for, and clearly differentiated from the worm
                        of plate 16. Points like this matter because they threaten to qualify the
                        whole drift of Parisi’s argument, making the designs look more like
                        what Erdman saw as a “series illustrating the progression of
                        contraries” (p. 204). Against this, Parisi wants to argue that plate 13
                        is the only one which offers a pointer beyond the constraints of earthly
                        melancholy. The rest belong to a “closed cycle” and present a
                        “problematic view of life” (p. 108). See the worm as a
                        caterpillar, however, and it is hard not to think also of the butterfly, and
                        of its immanence as an emblem of the soul. Moreover, if plate 13 really is
                        authoritative in the way Parisi suggests, “the most articulate event in
                        the series” (p. 110), why does it not come at the end? At least, one
                        might ask for some discussion of the point of its <hi rend="i">not</hi>
                        being final.</p>
          <p>There are good things in this essay. The context provided for resolving (or
                        beginning to resolve) the nature of Blake’s response to Gillray
                        (noted by Erdman, pp. 202-04) in plate 9 is well-constructed, taking us
                        through Ariosto, Milton and Burton. Indeed, on every design Parisi has
                        something new and insightful to say. There seems to be no doubt that Blake
                        invokes reference to desire and melancholy at key points in the series.
                        However, I remain unconvinced that the invocation of melancholy constitutes
                        the unitary message of these designs. There is an obvious problem with
                        visual images in that their significations are naturally less determinate
                        than verbal ones often are; I am left wanting a stronger case, with more
                        evidence illustrated, to convince me that the essay does all that it says it
                        does. But, with this essay more than the others, I must plead a measure of
                        incompetence.</p>
          <p>Harald A. Kittel’s “<hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> and <hi rend="i">An Essay Concerning
Human Understanding</hi>” poses a
                        different kind of difficulty. There is much here of real value and interest,
                        but its leading ideas are not emphasized with sufficient force. This
                        produces an argument of considerable density, likely to inform at first only
                        those already very familiar with the special vocabularies Locke uses. It
                        lacks the declaration of priorities which makes the first chapter of
                        Frye’s <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi> so memorable. There is also
                        some confusion about what <hi rend="i">kind</hi> of relation is being argued
                        for between the two texts; this becomes problematic because of the closeness
                        of the correspondences apparently being adduced. Is Blake really reading
                        Locke closely, and incorporating point-by-point responses to his arguments,
                        or is there in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> a general satire on the rational
                        tradition which Locke’s <hi rend="i">Essay</hi> happens, in exemplary
                        ways, to embody? Kittel reads <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> as “satire
                        directed against John Locke’s theory of knowledge” (p.
                        111)—in other words, principally against the second book of the 
<hi rend="i">Essay</hi>—but it is only at the end of his account that
                        he admits that “<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> is neither a systematic nor an
                        explicit critique of Locke’s <hi rend="i">Essay.</hi> Nevertheless,
                        elements of Locke’s theory of knowledge affect theme, symbolism and
                        structure of the poem” (p. 143). Had this declaration come earlier, it
                        might have suggested to the author that he look elsewhere in the rationalist
                        tradition for suggestions informing the argument and imagery of the poem.
                        Newton, for example, is not mentioned, and yet Donald Ault has published a
                        very important book on the Blake-Newton relation, with significant reference
                        to <hi rend="i">Urizen.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3"
type="note">3</ref> For
                        example, Kittel glosses the “globes of attraction” (<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> 3:36) as
specifying reference to Locke’s primary
                        qualities—bulk, figure, texture, and motion of parts—whereas a
                        much more obvious allusion, to my mind, is to atomism (planets as atoms
                        involves the familiar Blakean conjunction of microcosm and macrocosm) and to
                        its exponents in scientific method, Newton and perhaps Boyle, whose account
                        of forms and qualities itself informed Locke’s argument but was
                        stressed by Locke in a different way. Globes of attraction are the primary
                        particles of matter or body which are variously composed into form, whether
                        through names alone (as suggested by Boyle) or through some form of
                        figurative perception. As such, they do indeed lie behind Locke’s
                        account of qualities, but in a way which brings out the <hi rend="i">mental</hi>
element in the apprehension of “things” (an
                        element stressed also by Hobbes). Locke is here much more sophisticated than
                        he was often seen to be by later readers who saw in him merely the apologist
                        of materialism, and Kittel’s over-brief statement of the connection
                        misses the complexity of Locke’s account, as it deals with the way in
                        which qualities are assembled into “things” (which things Hobbes
                        had actually called “phantasms”). He thus does not stress the
                        radically <hi rend="i">unstable</hi> element in Locke’s epistemology,
                        which in fact could be taken to inform a much more thoroughly
                        “Romantic” notion of how we perceive. Ault (p. 59) argues in this
                        context for a discontinuity between Newton and Locke over how
                        “reality” is knowable, and over what it is that is called
                        “real.” What matters most for Locke is how we <hi rend="i">share</hi> perceptions.
Although information comes to us through the
                        senses, it takes mental processes to convert it into <hi rend="i">ideas</hi>, and it
is the nature of that conversion which was so widely
                        argued. If it is done through <hi rend="i">names</hi>, which impose unitary
                        identity on assemblies of ideas, and thus insinuate the idea of substance,
                        then Kittel passes over a useful angle on his own case for Urizen as imaging
                        Locke’s complex idea of substance (p. 128). For the name
                        “Urizen” is itself infinitely decomposable (you reason, your
                        reason, horizon, etc.), just as the identities of Los and Urizen
                        consistently merge and overlap throughout the book. Locke argues for
                        personal identity in consciousness, not in substance (<hi rend="i">Essay</hi>, II, ch.
27, 19); Urizen finds that both body and
                        consciousness shift and divide, or impose impossible pressures on themselves
                        in trying not to. Urizen’s faith in one law, and one name, then
                        becomes a satire on something Locke’s theory might itself satirize; a
                        belief in the substantial identity of something which has a name. 
<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Donald D. Ault, <hi rend="i">Visionary
                                Physics: Blake’s Response to Newton</hi> (Chicago &amp;
                            London: Univ. of Chicago Press, 1974). I am also surprised to see no
                            reference to Ernest Lee Tuveson’s <hi rend="i">The Imagination as
                                a Means of Grace: John Locke and the Aesthetics of Romanticism</hi>
                            (Berkeley &amp; Los Angeles: Univ. of California Press,
                        1960).</note></p>
          <pb id="p14-125" n="125"/>
          <p>I think that the reader who does not already know Locke will find this essay
                        very hard to follow; and the reader who does might wish for fuller
                        explanations of some of the subtleties of Locke’s positions. His
                        rather evasive use of arguments from divine sanction (“our Maker”)
                        and its relation to the coherence of the social contract might be seen to
                        inform Urizen’s parodic construction of a community, one which
                        attempts to be a series of self-images. Does Blake mean to imply the inner
                        identity of consent and authoritarian mandate? “I am your reason”?
                        Kittel’s account of the Urizenic versions of space and time also
                        needs, to my mind, stronger emphasis. They are clearly very important to the
                        poem, and Ault has much to say of them. They have a suggestive relation,
                        moreover, to the questions of narration (text/time) and perspective
                        (design/space) which are deliberately put into crisis in this poem. Perhaps
                        different readers will find this essay helpful in different ways, and impose
                        emphases for themselves. I think the notion of Urizen’s world being
                        composed of primary qualities (pp. 127, 136) is an interesting one (though I
                        would then want some analysis of his relation to the Eternals, which need
                        not be read as straightforwardly negative), and I am fascinated by the
                        suggestion that the basis of the Urizenic mode in deferral by rational
                        decision (pp. 118, 140) might come from Locke. This suggests nothing less
                        than a taxonomy of desire, which was of great importance to the eighteenth
                        century: witness, for example, its place in Adam Smith’s <hi rend="i">The Theory of
Moral Sentiments.</hi> Locke’s delineation of
                        rational doubt, whereby “we are able to suspend the present
                        satisfaction of any desire” (II, ch. 21, 52), is full of prophetic
                        futurity in this respect. Thus do sun and moon go out.</p>
          <p>Peter Butter’s contribution, “<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: The Final
                        Plates,” is of a kind which makes me wonder whether opposition can
                        really be true friendship, and leaves me affirming a case for refusing to
                        meet halfway. It belongs to the “Does it make sense?” aspect of
                        British Blake, but unfortunately sense itself is not questioned or
                        reconstituted. Butter’s curiosity emanates from a genre of literary
                        criticism which nowadays tends not to read Blake at all. Thus his comments
                        will strike readers variously as refreshing bursts of common sense or as
                        grotesquely out of place appeals to an inhibitive consensus. Of course, one
                        must beware of demanding that every reader of Blake should approach with
                        reverence and take off his shoes before walking on the purples. And, in one
                        way, this essay partakes of some of the negative virtues of Leavis’
                        classic misreading of Shelley,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
type="note">4</ref> which by
                        the very precision of its dismissals alerts us to an ulterior motive in
                        Shelley, and an alternative way of reading. Thus Butter looks for “an
                        immediate appeal to the senses” (p. 147), for something “touching
                        and effective” (p. 148), and for what helps us to “visualize . . .
                        clearly” (p. 149). His war-cry is indeed the classic one of “fully
                        realized presence” (p. 157), and needless to say it does not come up
                        with much to admire in this poem. When Butter says that Blake too often
                        “leaves the reader without firm ground under his feet” (p. 157), I
                        am reminded of a whole tradition of firmness, concretion, grasping and
                        embodying (different from Thompson, who at least provides the heart). It
                        belongs to the browbeating school of criticism which asserts that
                        “poetic quality” (p. 145) is an entity mysteriously removed from
                        ideas, and to be elucidated from the loaded comparison of good poets and bad
                        poets. <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> F. R. Leavis, <hi rend="i">Revaluation:
Tradition and Development in English Poetry</hi>
                            (London: Chatto &amp; Windus, 1936), ch. 6.</note></p>
          <p>Substantially, the centerpiece of Butter’s account is the argument
                        that Satan is presented incoherently, and that is perhaps the issue on which
                        readers might most profit from his essay. However, I hope it would not be
                        adjudicated with exclusive reference to the end of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>,
                        which even the most diligent readers are unlikely to resort to with
                        expectations of immediate transparency. Blake might have expected a reader
                        who had seen the rest of the poem, and perhaps knew something of John
                        Milton; he undeniably would have expected a reader who saw before him a
                        composite art, and not just a text on a page. Remarkably, Butter manages to
                        discuss the end of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> without any reference to the
                        designs (which by now should hardly surprise us in this anthology), and
                        without any mention of sexuality. Who are the naked figures on the rock in
                        the famous full-page plate, reengraved for copy D? Albion and
                        Jerusalem/Babylon? Milton and Ololon? Blake and Catherine, waking from a
                        dream? Prometheus, now joined by a female, and with the eagle of Zeus now
                        also bespeaking prophecy in dismemberment? Had he at least <hi rend="i">looked</hi> at
the plates, in some modest acknowledgment of what Blake
                        actually “wrote,” Butter might have found some clues to the
                        problem of identity which bothers him when he finds (e.g., p. 152) more than
                        one persona offering itself for the ownership of a pronoun.</p>
          <p>The test of this kind of essay must be, I think, whether the impositions are
                        generous or not. Ultimately, it is not the things of which I have written
                        above which I find myself resenting most strongly; it is the tactic of false
                        modesty. In the same paragraph we find the conventional critical
                        humility—“With more understanding I shall probably withdraw some
                        of the criticisms in this essay”—and the firm dismissal which it
                        is used to insinuate: Blake becomes one “whose command of language is
                        not equal to the reach of his imagination” (p. 163). As proof of this,
                        we have a gallery of the dirty tricks which are the embarrassment of the
                        trade. A comparison is introduced—“These lines remind one of
                        Hopkins”—only to be turned immediately into a
                        judgment—“Hopkins’ lines convey greater intensity than
                        Blake’s longer and slacker ones”—without the relevance of
                        Hopkins (or anybody else) ever being established. Literary history exists
                        here as an unanalyzed spectrum of the effective and the less effective, the
                        one functioning as a stick with which to beat the other. Butter centers
                        himself as the arbiter of taste, the “literary critic” who is
                        “entitled to ask the questions” (p. 161), having dismissed (as it
                        happens) Harold Bloom as a critic “telling his own story”;
                        something which, we are told with coy humor, is “quite common in Blake
                        studies” (p. 155).</p>
          <p>If opposition is to be friendship, then there is no place in it for the
                        smiler with the knife under the cloak. This is British Blake at its worst, a
                        product of difficulty and embarrassment which has gone hard, so that it is
                        no longer felt 
<pb id="p14-126" n="126"/>
or thought out. Like those who
                        complain of the limited number of orifices in the human body, Butter finds
                        in the prophetic books an “obsessive return to a rather small number of
                        ideas, repeated sometimes without enough variation or addition to make the
                        repetition acceptable” (p. 157). This essay, to my mind (and I am a
                        partial reader), has no ideas at all.</p>
          <p>James Ferguson’s “Prefaces to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>”
                        sets out to show that the four prefaces to the four chapters of the poem
                        provide structural guidelines for reading it. The themes he selects for
                        emphasis are interesting in themselves, but they do not provide what we seem
                        to be promised, which is a firm anticipation in the prefaces of the most
                        important ideas in the poem. Moreover, themes are selected from each of the
                        prefaces, which are thus in no sense completely expounded or interpreted.
                        From the first, Ferguson takes up the issue of style (mildness and
                        ruggedness), but explores it in a way which is neither historical (as an
                        analysis of the conventions Blake reacts to might be) or intrinsic in any
                        fully sustained way. Stylistic plurality and many-voicedness are undoubtedly
                        very important in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, but in much deeper ways than
                        Ferguson seems to specify. Ruggedness, for example, is explained almost by
                        apology, as “by no means the most important of the diverse poetic
                        styles to which Blake refers in his defence” (p. 169), instead of being
                        recognized as an integral part of meaning and idea, which is how Blake might
                        well have meant it to be seen. The accounts of Reuben, Rehab and Ezekiel
                        (very useful in themselves) which form the substance of the rest of the
                        essay seem to be very loosely connected to the prefaces to chapters 2, 3,
                        and 4, so that I begin to wonder if Ferguson has forgotten his own thesis.
                        Scholars concerned with the interpretation of those figures should certainly
                        not miss this essay, but Ferguson’s claim to set forth a new
                        structural patterning does not convince me. The essay is thus not quite an
                        authoritative introduction for people coming to the poem for the first time,
                        but it does illuminate certain special items in it.</p>
          <p>The book concludes with John Beer’s “Influence and Independence
                        in Blake,” which not only summarizes and (very modestly) answers many
                        of the positions taken up by other authors in the volume, but does so
                        without distracting attention from its own subject matter. The essay
                        presents a synopsis of problems encountered and methods adopted in reading
                        Blake for influences, and proceeds under the control of a most admirable
                        self-consciousness. Beer states his positions and declares his assumptions.
                        The tact is genuine, informing the arguments themselves rather than
                        remaining a preliminary ploy. Seeing Blake as an artist whose response to
                        influence was “dominated above all by his own obsessive concerns”
                        (p. 202), Beer examines a series of ways in which we might find Blake to
                        have been influenced.</p>
          <p>Dealing first with visual sources, he produces one of the few arguments in
                        this book which is adequately illustrated. Two kinds of influence are
                        examined. First, that of a general context, in this case the iconographic
                        conventions surrounding the “Ugolino” scene in late eighteenth
                        century art. A very convincing case is made for Blake being aware of a
                        reading of the incident as depicting “the tyranny of the
                        priesthood” (p. 207). Second, the possible bearing of the engraving of
                        Cipriani’s “Perseus and Andromeda” on the frontispiece to
                        ‘Visions of the Daughters of Albion’ is rehearsed. Here, the
                        influence (if it is there) is more specific and direct.</p>
          <p>In the account of possible modes of verbal influence, Beer’s comments
                        on the word “mark” in “London” (pp. 218-21) offer a
                        response to Thompson and Glen, and also add something else, a possible
                        Shakespearean echo. He sees the range of choices open to the reader of the
                        poem as rather wider than the other two authors do, but at the same time he
                        communicates a sense of the urgency of choosing. Ambivalence is not
                        avoidance, but a form of crisis. In general, the remarks on verbal influence
                        open up an area of possible influence on Blake which is comparatively new
                        (at least to me); that composed by seventeenth century literature. Allusions
                        he finds to Donne and Herbert are especially interesting, and there is a
                        convincing account of the neoplatonic background to Blake’s use of
                        the word “intellectual” (pp. 221-23), and of the philosophical
                        contexts for the word “inlet” (pp. 223-27). Of particular
                        relevance to Kittel’s case is Beer’s reading of Blake’s
                        “minute particulars” (pp. 227-29) in the context of specific
                        passages in Locke’s <hi rend="i">Essay.</hi> He sees a positive
                        implication (for Blake) in Locke’s description of “minute
                        particles, which open out a source of light that would otherwise be
                        invisible to the eye . . . bringing out the visionary nature of every detail
                        while remaining faithful to their own nature” (p. 229). Locke becomes,
                        in this way, a precursor of imaginative vision.</p>
          <p>Having described and embodied ways of plotting specific influences in both
                        visual and verbal contexts. Beer passes on (p. 237f.) to an assessment of
                        “extensive influences,” those which may be thought to have been
                        behind Blake’s work over an extended period of time. Three successive
                        pages of Whichcote’s <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> are seen to appear
                        in various forms and at various points in Blake’s writings, and a
                        similar “cluster of words and expressions” (p. 241) is discovered
                        in Pope’s “Eloisa to Abelard.”</p>
          <p>The final section of the essay makes a case for the importance of alchemical
                        imagery and reference in <hi rend="i">Tiriel.</hi> The result of the whole
                        is to suggest the highly eclectic and specifically motivated nature of
                        Blake’s philosophical, literary, and artistic borrowings or stimuli.
                        The coherence which ensues then <corr type="emend">becomes</corr> a function of
“Blake’s
                        originating artistic identity” (p. 261), which is able to react to a
                        wide range of influence without ever merely repeating a preestablished
                        doctrine. Influence is neither anxious nor burdensome; it provides a field
                        of intellectual and imaginative experience for redisposition and
                        interpretation. It is imagination, not guilt or shame, which determines
                        Blake’s reconstruction of the past. Implicitly, Beer frees Blake from
                        some of the limits imposed upon him by other authors in the book who have
                        more monothematic priorities.</p>
          <p>If one were to ask “What is the audience for 
<pb id="p14-127" n="127"/>
                        these essays?” then Beer’s essay comes through with the clearest
                        answer. In its wealth of local observation and specific attentions (which I
                        have not done justice to), it will be of use to any specialist. At the same
                        time, because of the clarity and self-consciousness of its format and
                        taxonomy, it comes over as a very recommendable starting point for, say, a
                        graduate student reading Blake for the first time, and wanting to know what
                        methods and approaches are possible. It has both scholarly and pedagogical
                        virtues, and as such it sets a standard which few of the other essays
                        attain. Glen and Thompson, to my mind, come closest to it, but they are best
                        taken as a pair, with interesting questions arising from the interaction of
                        the two accounts. The teacher who wishes to suggest to students a mode of
                        close reading which is both literary and historical could confidently
                        recommend Glen’s essay, in particular.</p>
          <p>For essays which took so long in coming into print—five years between
                        the Edinburgh conference and the appearance of the book—many parts of
                        the other essays have an unfinished quality, as if the passage from first
                        draft to reworked statement has not been made. This may appear as an
                        omission of the emphasis helpful to a reader in following an argument, or as
                        the ignoring of alternative possibilities supplied by the work of other
                        critics. More seriously, the book as a whole is lamentably
                        under-illustrated. This applies to Parisi’s essay, which depends upon
                        illustration, but it also reflects the lack of attention paid to composite
                        art by most of the other authors, John Beer aside. Thompson, Glen, and
                        Butter do not discuss it at all; nor do Kittel and Ferguson, though their
                        arguments do not as obviously suggest that they ought to do so. I do not
                        mean to assert that this emphasis away from design is any kind of fault, for
                        it will always be appropriate for some essays to concentrate on 
<hi rend="i">aspects</hi> of Blake’s work. But it may be significant in view
                        of the declared ambitions of the anthology (objective articulation without
                        imposition) that the visual side of the composite design is so often elided.
                        Conviction is often easier to come by when one considers the text alone; the
                            <hi rend="i">relation</hi> of text to design often sets up reflections
                        which are less stable, and not verifiable in the conventional ways. In many
                        cases, in this act of relation, there seem to be no obvious
                        “influences.” It thus becomes hard to “read” it without
                        confronting the more indeterminate aspects of Blake’s aesthetic.</p>
          <p>Even in the realm of the verbal, intrinsically considered, it may be a
                        peculiar justice that “mark” emerges as in many ways the fugal
                        word of the book. The variant readings offered by Thompson, Glen, and Beer
                        would serve as a means of articulating some of the questions generated by
                        the chosen title word, “Interpreting.” I have found that
                        interpreting Blake is an activity calling for thought <hi rend="i">about</hi>
interpretation. That element is built into Glen’s
                        essay, and into Beer’s. But I have the sense, perhaps unjustly, that
                        such a concern would be dismissed by some of the other authors as a piece of
                        fashionable nonsense. If so, then I am left wishing that British Blake might
                        set out to be a little less authoritarian, and perhaps thereby start to
                        explore the evidence for the <hi rend="i">historicality</hi> of the various
                        aesthetic indeterminacies in Blake’s work. Meanwhile, some mark with
                        the eye, some through it, and some with red pens.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
