<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.3.ostriker</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Janet M. Todd, ed., A Wollstonecraft Anthology</title>
        <author n="Ostriker">Alicia Ostriker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1980/1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980-81</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Stuart Curran</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Bo Lindberg</name>
              <name>Ann Bermingham Miller</name>
              <name>W.J.T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>E.B. Murray</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Hoyt Trowbridge</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980/1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
	<pb id="p14-129" n="129"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Janet M. Todd, ed. <hi rend="b">A Wollstonecraft Anthology.</hi>
                            Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1977. $16.50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">Alicia</hi> <name><hi rend="b">Ostriker</hi></name>.</docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Two years Blake’s junior, an ambitious Mary Wollstonecraft arrived in
                        London in 1787 at the age of twenty-eight, seeking a living by her pen and
                        declaring in a letter to her sister, “I am going to be the first of a
                        new genus.” Like Blake, Wollstonecraft was essentially self-educated.
                        She had survived a penurious childhood and the conventional and humiliating
                        employments of widow’s companion and governess. She had abducted a
                        sister from a bad marriage, organized a school for girls, participated in
                        Newington Green’s community of intellectual Dissenters which included
                        Richard Price, and attended the deathbeds of her mother and of a best friend
                        in Portugal. Having written <hi rend="i">Thoughts on the Education of
                            Daughters</hi> and <hi rend="i">Mary, a Fiction</hi>, both published by
                        Joseph Johnson, she meant to support herself—and a number of kin. She
                        was, she told Johnson, “not fond of grovelling.”</p>
          <p>Working for Johnson first as translator and reader, later as reviewer and
                        editorial assistant for <hi rend="i">The Analytical Review</hi>,
                        Wollstonecraft continued 
<pb id="p14-130" n="130"/>
to produce tracts: at
                        first moral, then—under the influence of the Johnson
                        circle—profoundly political. Her <hi rend="i">Original Stories from
                            Real Life</hi>, in which two girls are taught virtue and benevolence by
                        a stern but compassionate mother-figure, was illustrated by Blake in 1788,
                        and contained no revolutionary notions. In 1789 the Bastille fell, and all
                        was changed utterly. Price preached his sermon welcoming the revolution and
                        urging reform in England. Edmund Burke replied with the eloquently
                        conservative <hi rend="i">Reflections on the Revolution in France.</hi> And
                        Wollstonecraft excitedly wrote <hi rend="i">Vindication of the Rights of
                            Men</hi>, defending reason and liberty, attacking “the demon of
                        property,” inherited privilege, and the hypocrisy of Burkean
                        sentiment—which could pity queens but not the hungry poor. In one
                        important digression, Wollstonecraft assails Burke’s opinion of
                        women. Another passage criticizes the “narrow circle” of the
                        wealthy family which loves only itself instead of all mankind (cf. Blake on
                        “soft family love” and “storgous appetite”) and sells
                        its children into “legal prostitution.” Johnson published the book
                        immediately in 1790, and it was widely reviewed. The argument extended in
                        1792 to the <hi rend="i">Vindication of the Rights of Woman</hi> brought
                        fame and notoriety; for Horace Walpole the author was “a hyena in
                        petticoats.”</p>
          <p>Though ardent, impulsive, and thirsty for love, Wollstonecraft seems to have
                        had no affairs of the heart before 1791. In this year she became infatuated
                        with Fuseli, pursued him desperately in person and by letter, and proposed
                        to live with him and his wife. Rejected, she sailed for France. There ensued
                        the self-deluding, initially ecstatic and finally <corr type="emend">disastrous</corr>
affair with
                        Gilbert Imlay, which resulted in a daughter, two suicide attempts, and an
                        offer—again rejected—to live with Imlay and his new mistress.
                        A tract on the French Revolution, and a book of travel letters, come from
                        this period. Wolstonecraft’s ultimate liaison and secret marriage
                        with Godwin ended in her death in 1797 after the birth of Mary Godwin, and
                        the shattering of her reputation when her widower fondly published her 
<hi rend="i">Posthumous Works</hi> including her love-letters to Imlay,
                        which he praised for their “sentiment and passion,” and his <hi rend="i">Memoir</hi>,
which told the tale of Fuseli as well as Imlay. A
                        torrent of abuse hailed down. A 1798 poem entitled <hi rend="i">The
                            Unsex’d Females</hi> depicts a licentious and voluptuous
                        Wollstonecraft. The <hi rend="i">Anti-Jacobin Review</hi> ridicules both
                        Godwins and calls <hi rend="i">The Rights of Woman</hi> “a scripture,
                        archly fram’d, for propagating whores.” Its author had met, by
                        common consent, the death she deserved. If the Pickering “Mary” is
                        a tribute to Mary Wollstonecraft, born like Blake with “a different
                        face,” it may owe as much to Blake’s horror at her critics as to
                        her actual character.</p>
          <p>The largest debt, if debt there be, of Blake to Wollstonecraft, is in <hi rend="i">Visions of the
Daughters of Albion</hi>, whose heroine is
                        unique in romantic literature—and unique for Blake, since his later
                        heroines do not feel and think at the same time. Like Wollstonecraft,
                        Oothoon is heart <hi rend="i">and</hi> head. She is both assertively erotic
                        and brilliantly intellectual, generous of spirit yet smart enough to attack
                        patriarchy root and branch. Though the “story” of <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> is not
Wollstonecraft’s, her proposition to the
                        Fuselis (assuming these matters were gossipped about) might have made
                        Oothoon’s offer to fetch silver and gold girls for Theotormon seem
                        plausible. Moreover, the <hi rend="i">Vindication of the Rights of Man</hi>
                        may be linked to <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> by imagery and rhetoric as well
                        as ideology and the fact that we have a distinctly unladylike female
                        addressing a man who loves chivalry. “Why cannot estates be divided
                        into small farms?” Wollstonecraft asks Burke: 
						<q> Why does the brown
                            waste meet the traveller’s view, when men want to work? . . . .
                            Why might not the industrious peasant be allowed to steal a farm from
                            the heath? . . . . how much misery lurks in pestilential corners . . .
                            how many mechanics, by a flux of trade or fashion, lose their employment
                            . . . . Where is the eye that marks these evils, more gigantic than any
                            of the infringements of property, which you piously deprecate? Let these
                            sorrows hide their diminished head before the tremendous mountain of woe
                            that thus defaces our globe! Man preys on man, and you mourn for the
                            idle tapestry that decorated a gothic pile, and the dronish bell that
                            summoned the fat priest to prayer. </q>
From <hi rend="i">Vindication of
                            the Rights of Woman</hi>, Blake might, while ignoring its central
                        argument in favor of female independence, have been impressed by a woman who
                        could declare, “I . . . deny the existence of sexual virtues, not
                        excepting modesty” and “the modesty of women . . . will often be
                        only the artful veil of wantonness.” The Blake of “London,”
                        “To the Accuser who is the God of This World” and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> would
have approved Wollstonecraft’s sympathetic
                        treatment of prostitutes, and the fact that one of the two heroines in her
                        second novel, <hi rend="i">The Wrongs of Woman</hi>, is an ex-thief and
                        prostitute, while the other lives with the man she loves though married to a
                        brute, and assails the marriage laws in court. Blake would, I think (this is
                        my understanding of the major prophecies) have agreed with Wollstonecraft
                        that “from the tyranny of men . . . the greater number of female
                        follies proceed; and the cunning, which I allow makes at present a part of
                        their character . . . is produced by oppression.” And if he read
                        Wollstonecraft on the French Revolution, he would surely have been
                        struck—as Janet Todd points out that John Adams and Percy Bysshe
                        Shelley were—by its idea of mental evolution (“the image of God
                        implanted in our nature is now more rapidly expanding”), her
                        dialectical view of history and politics, and her ability both to deplore
                        and to analyze the causes of revolutionary violence.</p>
          <p>Todd’s <hi rend="i">Wollstonecraft Anthology</hi> performs the
                        valuable service of making selections available from all the author’s
                        works, some of which exist in print only in expensive facsimile editions.
                        The general introduction gives a good synopsis of Wollstonecraft’s
                        life, writing, and reputation, stressing the development of her thought from
                        rationalism to radicalism, and seeing her life essentially as a
                        “struggle” against her own social conditioning. Blakeans may be
                        interested in this point, though Blake’s personal struggle with
                        Reason is archetypically male, while Wollstonecraft’s with Passion is
                        archetypically female.</p>
          <pb id="p14-131" n="131"/>
          <p>The headnotes to individual selections in this volume place them in the
                        context of their genres, and the selections themselves are ample,
                        illustrating the variety of the writer’s styles and concerns. I
                        personally would have enjoyed seeing fewer of the not-immensely-original
                        “Thoughts on the Education of Daughters” and the uniformly
                        disdainful reviews of novels by women Wollstonecraft thought were idiots. I
                        would have liked more of <hi rend="i">The Wrongs of Woman</hi> and some of
                        the early letters to friends and family as well as the letters to Imlay and
                        Godwin, and perhaps one of the <hi rend="i">Vindications</hi> in full. On
                        the other hand, the decision to give a large sampling of hard-to-find
                        material makes sense. All in all, this will be a highly useful book.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
