<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.3.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Gerald P. Tyson, Joseph Johnson: A Liberal Publisher</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1980/1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980-81</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Stuart Curran</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Bo Lindberg</name>
              <name>Ann Bermingham Miller</name>
              <name>W.J.T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>E.B. Murray</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Hoyt Trowbridge</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980/1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
	<pb id="p14-145" n="145"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">THE CIRCLE WITHOUT A CENTER; Gerald P. Tyson. <hi rend="b">Joseph
                                Johnson: A Liberal Publisher.</hi> Iowa City: University of Iowa
                            Press, 1979. xix + 276 pp., 8 plates, endpapers from Horwood’s
                            map of London (1799). $14.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">G. E. </hi><name><hi rend="b">Bentley</hi></name>, 
<hi rend="b">Jr.</hi></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <figure n="HaughtonPortrait.14.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="552">
            <head>Engraving of Moses Haughton’s portrait of Joseph</head>
            <figDesc>Johnson (ca. 1800), when the bookseller was about sixty-five.
                            Reproduced by permission of The Huntington Library, San Marino,
                            California.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>Joseph Johnson was a major publisher, a friend of Henry Fuseli and William
                        Godwin, patron of William Cowper and Mary Wollstonecraft and William Blake,
                        publisher of Erasmus Darwin and William Wordsworth, of S. T. Coleridge and
                        Joseph Priestley, of Tom Paine and Horne Tooke, of Humphrey Davy and T. R.
                        Malthus, of Maria Edgworth and William Beckford. The most advanced poets,
                        political, medical, and religious writers, and scientists of the last
                        quarter of the eighteenth century in London were his authors, his customers,
                        and his friends. Any work seriously concerned with such authors or such
                        books must deal with Joseph Johnson and his publishing house. And until Dr.
                        Gerald Tyson published <hi rend="i">Joseph Johnson</hi>: A Liberal Publisher
                        in May 1979, very little was known of either.</p>
          <p>A symptom of the neglect of Johnson is the fact that Joseph Aikin’s
                        obituary of him in <hi rend="i">The Gentleman’s Magazine</hi> in 1809
                        “found its way unchanged into the <hi rend="i">Dictionary of National
                            Biography</hi>” ninety years later (pp. 215, 217). There have been
                        a few articles about him in the last decade and a half, by Tyson, Phyllis
                        Mann, Jane Smyser, Paul Zall, and especially Leslie Chard, but previous to
                        this there 
<pb id="p14-146" n="146"/>
was little in print about Johnson
                        beyond what Gilchrist published in his biography of Blake in 1863.</p>
          <p>To tell the truth, there is <hi rend="i">still</hi> not much known about
                        Joseph Johnson as an individual, for clearly he was a genial but
                        self-effacing man. He did not write books himself, very little of his
                        correspondence has been traced, and his contemporaries did not write much
                        about him. This book is not so much about Joseph Johnson as it is about his
                        publishing house, or rather about the books he published and his
                        relationships with their authors. It is a topological paradox, a circle
                        without a center. Of the books Johnson published, what contemporaries
                        thought of them, Johnson’s generosity to their authors, we learn a
                        good deal. But of the man who focused and fostered so much of this activity,
                        we still know surprisingly little.</p>
          <p>This is not for lack of energy or thoroughness on Dr. Tyson’s part. He
                        has used an impressive range of original sources, from reviews of the most
                        important books Johnson published to manuscript diaries of their authors,
                        and he has consulted manuscripts in Guildhall Library, Stationers’
                        Hall, the Public Record Office, Houghton Library, Bodley, Dr.
                        Williams’ Library, Manchester Public Library, and the Library of
                        Congress, as well, of course, as the most important books Johnson
                            published.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">1</ref>
We must reconcile
                        ourselves to knowing little of Joseph Johnson the man, for if Dr. Tyson has
                        not found such information it is not likely to survive. And in any case,
                        even though Fuseli lived with Johnson for eight years and Mary
                        Wollstonecraft treated him as father, brother, and priest, his chief
                        importance is as a publisher and a patron of authors. In these roles we see
                        him in considerable detail. <note id="n6"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Despite this
                            admirable research, a good deal of the information in the book,
                            particularly about Johnson’s authors, still derives from <hi rend="i">The
Dictionary of National Biography.</hi> It might
                            profitably have been extended by refernece to London directories, to Ian
                            Maxted’s <hi rend="i">The London Book Trades 1775-1800</hi>
                            (1977), and to voting records of the time.</note></p>
          <p>Of his life outside publishing, there are comparatively few facts. Among the
                        more intriguing are that he was apprenticed in 1754 for a fee of £63 to
                        the Musicians’ Guild (p. 6), not to the Stationers’ Company,
                        that he was a stout Unitarian and numbered many Unitarians among his
                        authors, and that the epitaph on his tombstone was composed by Fuseli (p.
                        215).</p>
          <p>His generosity and hospitality were instinctive to the man and were
                        enormously important in attracting and securing authors to him. In 1839
                        William West wrote: 
						<q> Under his roof were, perhaps, as much genius, taste,
                            and talent combined among the distinguished writers who assembled at his
                            weekly literary parties, as at any house in the kingdom. . . . I believe
                            the only picture that ornamented his plain old dining room was
                            Fuseli’s original painting of the Nightmare. . . . Mr.
                            Johnson’s business was for some time conducted by a person of the
                            name of Redman, who had, I believe, originally followed the Profession
                            of a schoolmaster, and retained the cross habits and manners of the
                            pedagogue. . . . [<hi rend="i">Once when I owed Johnson money</hi> which
                            I could not immediately <hi rend="i">pay</hi>] He handed me a check on
                            Coutts for upwards of 300 <hi rend="i">l.</hi>; told me to take what I
                            required, bring him the difference, and pay the remainder as soon as I
                            conveniently could.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
type="note">2</ref></q>
Cowper wrote that “his behavior to me has been so liberal, that I
                        can refuse him nothing,” and when Johnson corrected the poetry of <hi rend="i">The
Task</hi> Cowper was profoundly grateful: 
<q> as often as I
                            could, I paid all possible respect to his animadversions. . . . I do not
                            know where I could have found a bookseller who could have pointed out to
                            me my defects with more discernment. . . .<lb/>
<lb/>
 (William Hayley,
                                <hi rend="i">Life of . . . William Cowper</hi>, 1804, III, 134) </q>
                        Coleridge wrote that “purely out of affection conceived for me, &amp;
                        as part of anything I <hi rend="i">might</hi> do for him, [<hi rend="i">Johnson</hi>]
gave me an order . . . for 30 pound” (p. 173). And
                        James Hurdis complained ruefully: 
						<q> I have sometimes gone to town with the
                            determination of playing the tyrant [<hi rend="i">with my
                                bookseller</hi>], but that good-humoured face of Johnson’s,
                            with a candid shake of the hand, &amp; <hi rend="i">how d’ye do
                                Sir, I dine at three</hi>, always disarms me of my resolution,
                            &amp; I leave his house without speaking a single dagger.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">3</ref></q>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">2</hi> William West, “Annals of Authors,
                            Artists, Books, and Booksellers, Letter XI: Mr. Johnson, of St.
                            Paul’s Church-Yard, and his Literary Connexions,” <hi rend="i">Aldine
Magazine</hi> (1839), p. 205. Neither West nor
                            Redman appears in the quite inadequate index, and West is not mentioned
                            in the “Note on Writings about Johnson” (pp.
                            217-18).</note>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">3</hi> “Letters of James Hurdis to
                            William Cowper,” ed. W. F. Tattersall, <hi rend="i">Sussex
                                County Magazine</hi>, 1 (1926-27), 75, quoted in L. F. Chard,
                            “Joseph Johnson: Father of the Book Trade,” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of the New York
Public Library</hi>, 79, (1975),
                            52.</note></p>
          <p>The facts about Johnson as a radical are particularly well handled. Johnson
                        was not only a publisher of radicals such as Tom Paine and Horne Tooke, but
                        he was active privately in radical causes as well. For instance, he
                        contributed £2. 11.0 for boots for the French Army in 1792 (p. 155), at
                        a time when official England was mobilizing its resources for war with
                        France. Dr. Tyson has found the documents in the Public Record Office
                        concerning Johnson’s trial for sedition under the gag laws, and he
                        quotes Johnson’s modest description of himself there: 
						<q> this
                            Deponent further saith that his connections have been with respectable
                            and scientific Writers and his publications generally of a Moral,
                            Philosophical, and Medical Nature, many of which as this Deponent is
                            informed are an honour to his Country.<lb/>
 (p. 160) </q>
Such has been
                        the verdict of history, but a packed jury found him guilty of selling a
                        radical book, and he was sentenced to six months in prison. During his
                        incarceration, his business was carried on, doubtless to the
                        Government’s chagrin, but, as William Gifford exulted in <hi rend="i">The
Anti-Jacobin Review</hi>, the 
<q> objects of our immediate attacks,
                            the <hi rend="i">Analytical Review</hi> [published by Joseph Johnson],
                            has received its death-blow, and we have more reason to congratulate
                            ourselves upon the share which we have had in producing its dissolution,
                            than it would be expedient here to unfold.<lb/>
<lb/>
 (p. 167) </q>
	<pb id="p14-147" n="147"/>
As Dr. Tyson remarks, <hi rend="i">The
                            Anti-Jacobin Review</hi> was a treasury journal (p. 166).</p>
          <p>Joseph Johnson’s name appears on several thousand imprints. About half
                        of these were pamphlets, and more than half of the total were reprints.
                        About a quarter of the titles were anonymous, mostly religious and political
                        works, and the largest single category was religion. Johnson published
                        comparatively little fiction, and most of the fiction he did produce was
                        propagandistic. (Dr. Tyson does not mention Johnson’s important
                        relationship with Charlotte Smith as publisher of her novels.) The most
                        important lack in the book is a bibliography, or even a list, of
                        Johnson’s publications. Clearly such a list would have been enormous
                        and would have quite altered the character of the book, but without details
                        of either publisher or publications the reader often feels himself to be in
                        a twilight land, seeing uncertainly in the half-light and unable to
                        distinguish for himself the woods from the trees. We may hope that Dr. Tyson
                        will publish the list of Johnson’s publications which, according to
                            <hi rend="i">his</hi> publisher’s blurb, he has already
                        collected. Only then will we be able to place this book in a proper
                        context.</p>
          <p>It should also be recognized that there are few technical details here about
                        Johnson’s publishing house. There is no list of the printers he used,
                        cost analyses, description of his house style, account of the paper in the
                        books, the mode of issue (stitched, in parts, by subscription, etc.), or the
                        publishers with whom he joined in partnership or in congeries. This is a
                        publishing history in the perfectly legitimate old-fashioned sense of an
                        account of patronage and friendship and how they affected literary
                        substance. <hi rend="i">Joseph Johnson</hi>: <hi rend="i">A Liberal
                            Publisher</hi> is a worthy publication of modest pretensions and
                        dimensions, and careful scholars concerned with the last quarter of the
                        eighteenth century will long be indebted to Dr. Tyson’s devoted
                        labors. We are unlikely to have a more comprehensive account of
                        Johnson’s circle, and that circle was of major importance in the
                        political, religious, medical, intellectual, and poetic life of his time.
                        But a circle without a center is a ring, and in this book it is the ring
                        which is important. And doubtless this is as Joseph Johnson would have
                        wished. A publisher lives through his publications and his authors, and it
                        is astonishing how many of Johnson’s authors are considered, in 1800
                        and in 1980, to be of major importance. It is through this ring of bright
                        authors that Johnson lives today.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
