<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.3.lindberg</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Jack Lindsay, William Blake: His Life and Work</title>
        <author n="Lindberg">Bo Ossian Lindberg</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1980/1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980-81</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Stuart Curran</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Bo Lindberg</name>
              <name>Ann Bermingham Miller</name>
              <name>W.J.T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>E.B. Murray</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Hoyt Trowbridge</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980/1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-3-0006">
        <pb id="p14-164" n="164"/>
        <div2>
            <figure n="BlakePortrait.14.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="513"></figure>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Jack Lindsay. <hi rend="b">William Blake: His Life and Work.</hi> New
                            York: George Braziller, Inc., 1979. (originally published in London:
                            Constable and Company Ltd.) 334 pp., 21 illus. $15.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">Bo Ossian</hi> <name><hi rend="b">Lindberg</hi></name></docAuthor>.
          </byline>
          <p>Jack Lindsay first read Blake in 1917-18 when he was in his teens. His
                        world-view was provided by Blake and by Dostoevsky and Shakespeare. In 1927
                        he published a small but surprisingly informative booklet, <hi rend="i">William
Blake</hi>, which saw a second edition in 1929.
                        Lindsay’s essay on Blake’s meter in the Scholaris Press
                        edition of the <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> appeared in the same
                        year. Then, for about forty years, Lindsay published little on Blake (a few
                        reviews and essays), but, as he writes in the foreword to the full-scale
                        biography on Blake which he published in 1978, “through the years I
                        have kept returning to him and seeking to revalue him in terms of the
                        problems thrown up by my own development.” And he adds: “I do not
                        write as someone interested in Blake from the outside, but as someone for
                        whom he has been a vitally formative influence throughout life.”</p>
          <p>Every reader of Lindsay’s book should have these words in mind. They
                        explain the author’s personal approach to Blake. This emphasis on the
                        applicability of Blake’s ideas to the social, political and
                        economical thinking of a man living in the twentieth century is the most
                        attractive feature of Lindsay’s book. At the same time it makes the
                        book misleading to any reader not already familiar with Blake. Lindsay
                        stresses what is of interest to him: Blake’s political radicalism,
                        his heretical antinomianism, his prophetical revolutionarism, his
                        imaginative humanism, his pre-<corr type="emend">Marxian</corr> dialectics and the strong—and
                        by other commentators frequently undervalued—materialistic element in
                        his thought. But Lindsay never takes seriously Blake’s definition of
                        himself as a Christian visionary, and he is out of sympathy with
                        Blake’s gradual development from political radical to spiritualist
                        mystic. Lindsay’s Blake never grows older than forty. Blake’s
                        comments on the spiritual world to Crabb Robinson make “painful
                        reading” to him.</p>
          <p>Lindsay tolerates religious ideas only so far as they can be used as
                        stand-ins for lampoons against the established econo-political system. As a
                        consequence, he gives us a denaturalized Blake. For this reason
                        Lindsay’s book is not a biography in the sense that
                        Gilchrist’s and Mona Wilson’s books are biographies. It is a
                        specialized investigation of one single question: why read Blake today?</p>
          <p>Oddly enough, although Jack Lindsay is son and pupil of the artist Norman
                        Lindsay, he does not seem to be particularly interested in Blake as a
                        pictorial artist. The most notable defects, also, are found in the sections
                        on Blake’s pictorial works. In a way this is understandable. In
                        Blake, Lindsay seeks help to clarify his own view of man as he appears
                        today, formed by history and living under an industrialized capitalist
                        economic system. From this point of view Blake the writer seems more
                        rewarding than Blake the artist. In spite of this I feel that
                        Lindsay’s treatment of Blake’s artistic achievements is more
                        cavalier than it should be. To substantiate this criticism, I shall give
                        examples of dubious or incomplete statements in Lindsay’s book.</p>
          <pb id="p14-165" n="165"/>
          <p>The section on the anonymous drawings made at the opening of the coffin of
                        Edward I in 1774 (p. 2) is incorrect. There are two drawings, and King
                        Edward appears twice in each of them.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n10" type="note">1</ref>
                        According to Lindsay both drawings are inscribed in a hand resembling that
                        of young Blake, but this is true only of one of them, namely the one showing
                        coffin and corpse strictly from above. The other drawing, made in isometric
                        perspective, differs in style and bears inscriptions in a different
                        hand—I doubt its general inclusion in the oeuvre of Blake. 
<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">William
                                Blake</hi>, exhibition catalogue (Tate Gallery, 1978), nos. 6-7;
                            Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> (Oxford, 1971), pp. 17
                            ff., repr. pls. 9, 10.</note></p>
          <p>However that may be, Blake certainly did not get his idea of figures clad in
                        tight-fitting garments from this source, as Lindsay maintains. Such a
                        supposition seems likely only if we confine ourselves to Ayloffe’s
                        account of the opening, but is rendered impossible by the drawings
                        themselves, none of which reveals the form of the limbs or the body under
                        the garment. In three of the sketches even the face is only dimly seen
                        through the veil covering it, or not seen at all; only one of the isometric
                        sketches shows the uncovered face.</p>
          <p>Much has been written about the tight fitting dresses in Blake’s
                        figures. Strictly speaking there are two different kinds of such dresses:
                        body-tights made from fabric, resembling those used by modern dancers, and
                        made visible on the naked body only by their color, a few folds, and by
                        rings around wrists and ankles; and tight-fitting scaly armour. A likely
                        source for the latter has been found by Morton Paley in the English edition
                        of Montfaucon: 
						<q> The military habit of the <hi rend="i">Sarmatians</hi> is
                            the most extraordinary one we have yet seen. For it’s so closely
                            adjusted to their Body from the Neck to the very Sole of the Foot, that
                            all the Motions of the Members and Muscles appear as plainly through it,
                            as if the Body was naked. ‘Tis also covered with Scales without
                            the least Interval, even as low as the Hand, and down to the Sole of the
                                Foot.<gap type="emend"/> <ref target="n11" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Morton D. Paley,
                                “‘Wonderful Originals’—Blake and Antique
                                Sculpture,” <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, ed. Robert N.
                                Essick and Donald Pearce (Bloomington and London, 1978), p.
                                176.</note></q></p>
          <p>According to Tacitus the Sarmatian armor was made from leather, with metal
                        scales attached to it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12"
type="note">3</ref> He adds that it
                        was very resistant to blows, but it was also very stiff, restricted the
                        movements of the Sarmatian soldiers, and made it difficult for them to mount
                        their horses. <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> Tac. Hist.</hi> I:79.
Cf. <hi rend="i">Tac. Germ.</hi>
                            46.</note></p>
          <p>Several of the Roman Emperors bore the name of honor Sarmaticus, because they
                        had defeated Sarmatians, notably Trajanus, on whose column at Rome
                        Sarmatians are shown, all clad in tight-fitting scaly armour, covering even
                        the hands but not the feet.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13"
type="note">4</ref> A rider of
                        this type is shown in Raphael’s fresco of <hi rend="i">Leo the Great
                            and Attila</hi> in the Vatican <hi rend="i">Stanza di Eliodoro</hi>
                        (foreground, extreme right), which Blake certainly knew from engravings.
                        Raphael had a good reason for including a Sarmatian soldier among the Huns.
                        According to Kretschmer early copies of Ptolemaios’ cartographic work
                        identify the Sarmatians with the <hi rend="i">Chunoi</hi>, that is, the
                            Huns.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">5</ref> In
medieval and renaissance
                        times the Sarmatians were commonly thought to be a branch of the Huns. 
<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">4</hi> K. Kretschmer, “Sarmatae,” <hi rend="i">Paulys Real-Encyclopädie der Klassischen
                                Altertumswissenschaft</hi>, neue Bearb. beg. von Georg Wissowa,
                            zweite Reihe Bd. 1 (Stuttgart, 1920), pp. 2542 ff.</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Above, n. 4.</note></p>
          <p>The textile body-tights have a similar source. Tight-fitting trousers of
                        linen were used by several barbarian tribes in classical times. Blouses of a
                        similar kind were also common. By the time of Trajan they had spread into
                        the Roman army, and Roman <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">auxiliaria</hi></corr> and
legionaries are
                        shown wearing them on the column of Trajanus, and also on the column of
                        Marcus Aurelius. Such dresses are frequent in Raphael’s works in the
                        Vatican <hi rend="i">stanze</hi> and a few examples are found in the
                        cartoons for the Sistina tapestries.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n15" type="note">6</ref>
                        They were a favorite formula with Giulio Romano and several other
                        mannerists, and they are common in the works of some of Blake’s
                        contemporaries, especially Fuseli. In view of Raphael’s practice of
                        making sketches of the nude bodies for figures who were to appear draped in
                        the finished pictures, the use of tight-fitting clothes was logical: it
                        saved the maximum amount of work in drawing the nudes. 
<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">6</hi> See the figure of Heliodorus in <hi rend="i">The
                                Expulsion of Heliodorus</hi>, the rider in the middle foreground of
                                <hi rend="i">Leo the Great and Attila</hi>, and the soldier in the
                            middle foreground of <hi rend="i">The Battle of Ostia.</hi> For the
                            cartoons, see the figure in foreground left of <hi rend="i">The Death of
                                Ananias</hi>, repr. John White, <hi rend="i">The Raphael
                                Cartoons</hi> (Victoria and Albert Museum, 1972), pl. 4; see also
                            pl. 13.</note></p>
          <p>On p. 8, writing about the early engraving of <hi rend="i">Joseph of
                            Arimathea</hi>, Lindsay identifies the direct source (the ultimate
                        source being Michelangelo’s “Joseph of Arimathea” in <hi rend="i">The Crucifixion of
Peter</hi>) as an engraving by
                        “Béatrizat” (misprint for Nicolas Beatrizet) although Blake
                        himself stated that he had copied “a drawing by Salviati after Michael
                            Angelo.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">7</ref>
Blake the engraver
                        was likely to know the difference between a drawing and an engraving. If
                        Blake was right in attributing the former to Salviati we cannot know, since
                        it has not been traced. He seems to have had some doubts about the
                        attribution; in another annotation he calls the work merely “an old
                        Italian Drawing.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>,
                            p. 28, pl. 14.</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">8</hi> G. Keynes, <hi rend="i">The Complete
                                Writings of William Blake</hi>, (London 1966), p. 604; hereafter
                            abbreviated K.</note></p>
          <p>On p. 12 Lindsay calls into doubt the story about Blake and Moser. But he
                        misses the fact that the issue at stake was not Florentine versus Venetian
                        and Flemish painting, but sixteenth-century Italian engraving versus
                        engravings of the Rubens and Le Brun workshops. Moser evidently disliked the
                        “hard and dry” engravings after Raphael and Michelangelo by
                        Marcantonio Raimondi, Agostino Veneziano, Giorgio Ghisi, etc., not Raphael
                        and Michelangelo themselves, which Moser and Reynolds, of course, valued
                        highly.</p>
          <p>The date 1780 on the engraving <hi rend="i">Albion Rose</hi> should be
                        treated with more caution than Lindsay allows. The only known state is
                        signed and dated “WB inv 1780.” Most commentators, including
                        Lindsay, find this date difficult to reconcile with the mature style of
                        engraving and with the lettering and symbolism of the caption in the lower
                        margin. I agree that the state must be dated after 1800, probably 1804. But
                        unlike Lindsay I believe that an earlier state has existed, the date 1780
                        being the almost only survivor from the lost first state. The existence of
                        an earlier state is supported by the color-printed versions. All
                        color-prints by Blake which can be dated were done in or about 1795; the
                        Huntington Library copy of <hi rend="i">Albion Rose</hi> is printed on paper
                        watermarked 1794, which indicates a date for the print about
                        1795—Blake seldom kept large stores of paper, and was in a habit of
                        using paper fresh.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">9</ref> Several of the
                        color-prints were printed from the same plates as the engravings. It is
                        therefore possible that the color-printed versions of <hi rend="i">Albion
                            Rose</hi> conceal an earlier state of the engraving. A description of
                        the state was published by Essick in 1980, after the appearance of
                        Lindsay’s book. <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">9</hi> As far as I am
                            aware no one has yet made a systematic investigation of watermarks on
                            paper used by Blake, or systematically compared dated watermarks with
                            the accepted dates of Blake’s works on paper. The rule seems to
                            be that whenever Blake needed a considerable amount of paper, he bought
                            it fresh. His 537 watercolors for Young were begun in 1795, and the
                            engravings from them were executed in 1796 and 1797; the only dated
                            watermarks are 1794. The color-prints dated 1795 also have watermarks
                            1794. The first copies of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, completed in
                            1819, have watermarks 1818 and 1819. But notice that many of the Dante
                            watercolors of 1824-27 were done on paper watermarked “WELGAR
                            1796.”</note></p>
          <p>I also think that the signature on the known 
<pb id="p14-166" n="166"/>
                        state, “WB inv”, is a later addition. It is engraved in a
                        different way from the date, is not quite on a line with it, and shows no
                        signs of polishing or erasure, while marks of scraping are obvious on the
                        date.</p>
          <p>Then comes the question of Blake’s technique. Lindsay uncritically
                        reproduces several mistakes by other writers, and is not quite up to date
                        with recent research. This question will have to be dealt with more fully in
                        a separate article, to be published later. The following remarks are only
                        meant as a short abstract.</p>
          <p>Lindsay is in error in thinking that Cumberland’s method of printing
                        text from etched plates was a stereotype process (p. 31).
                        Cumberland’s recipe for it in <hi rend="i">A New Review with Literary
                            Curiosities and Literary Intelligence</hi>, 1784, and his letters
                        describing the process to his brother about the same time, make it clear
                        that Cumberland’s plates were done in ordinary etching on a
                        wax-asphaltum-rosin ground, and printed in intaglio.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">10</ref> Blake’s reference to a method for
                        illuminated printing in <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi> was almost
                        certainly to Cumberland’s method, not to Blake’s own, contrary
                        to what Lindsay thinks.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20"
type="note">11</ref> 
                        <hi rend="i">An Island</hi> was almost certainly written in the winter of
                        1784-85, and Blake himself wrote that he invented the stereotype process in
                            1788.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">12</ref>
Lindsay also neglects
                        Blake’s only surviving stereotype plate, a fragment of a cancelled
                        plate for <hi rend="i">America.</hi> As Robert Essick has shown, this plate
                        was step-etched in order to hinder underbiting of the raised lines.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">13</ref> Since stereotype etching was known
                        before Blake’s time,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23"
type="note">14</ref> his
                        invention was likely to have been of a method for step-etching the plates,
                        and not of “an ink impervious to acid,” as Lindsay thinks.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">15</ref>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Article printed by Mona Wilson, <hi rend="i">The Life of William
Blake</hi> (New York, 1969), p. 318.
                            For the letters, see Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, pp. 230
                            ff.</note>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Lindsay, p. 31. Cf. K 62. The ms. is in
                            the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge. For a facsimile, see Göran
                            Malmqvist, <hi rend="i">William Blake En ö på
                                månen</hi> (Stockholm, 1979); text, Swedish translation and
                            facsimile of the ms.</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">12</hi> For dating of <hi rend="i">An
                                Island</hi>, see G. E. Bentley Jr., <hi rend="i">William
                                Blake’s Writings</hi> (Oxford, 1978), II, 1697-99, and David
                            V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake Prophet Against Empire</hi> (New York,
                            1969), pp. 90-92. Blake’s colophon to <hi rend="i">The Ghost of
                                Abel</hi> (1822) reads: “W Blakes Original Stereotype was
                            1788” (K 781).</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Robert N. Essick, “William Blake as
                            an Engraver and Etcher,” <hi rend="i">William Blake in the Art of
                                His Time</hi>, exhib. cat. (University of California: Santa Barbara
                            Art Galleries, 1976), pp. 16 ff. Repr. also by Bentley, <hi rend="i">William
Blake’s Writings</hi> (Oxford, 1978), p. 154. For
                            Blake’s pull of the cancelled plate before cutting it up, 
<hi rend="i">ibid.</hi>, p. 152.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">14</hi> A stereotype process is described in
                            anon., <hi rend="i">Valuable Secrets Concerning Arts and Trades</hi>,
                            London 1758, ch. 1. This work, translated from the French, had seen
                            seven English editions by 1810.</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Lindsay, p. 32. This supposition is an
                            unacknowledged quotation from Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>
                            (Oxford, 1969), p. 32 n. 1. It is wrong. Stoppers have been known as
                            long as etching has been practiced. Their composition differs and I
                            cannot here attempt and hypothetical reconstruction of the composition
                            of Blake’s stopper. See also <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p.
                            460 n. 1.</note></p>
          <p>Lindsay also writes that the reason for Blake’s rejection of oil
                        painting was his inability to handle oil paint, an inability which he
                        rationalized by condemning oil as an inferior medium.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">16</ref> He also says that Blake’s alternative to oil
                        painting was the color-printing process.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n26" type="note">17</ref> In my opinion both statements are incorrect. 
<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Lindsay, p. 38.</note>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Lindsay, p. 38.</note></p>
          <p>In the eighteenth century most artists found oils difficult to handle. For
                        this reason Reynolds, for instance, introduced a variety of binders into his
                        paintings: egg white, gum, wax, mastic dissolved in spirits of turpentine,
                        copaiba balsam, and meguilp (a mixture of mastic dissolved in boiling oil
                        with lead siccative), often with disastrous results.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">18</ref> It is common knowledge that paintings of the
                        eighteenth and nineteenth centuries are often in a worse state of
                        preservation than earlier works, due to the heterogenous mixtures used in
                        their composition. For the same reason they are often difficult or
                        impossible to clean and restore.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28"
type="note">19</ref>
                        Examples abound among the works of even the greatest painters: Chardin,
                        Pilo, Reynolds, Ingres, Delacroix, Corot, Daumier. <note id="n27"><hi rend="s">18</hi>
A Collection of memoranda by Reynolds, listing the
                            different binders, pigments and protective varnishes used for many of
                            his works, is printed by Charles Lock Eastlake, <hi rend="i">Materials
                                for a History of Oil Painting</hi>, I (London, 1847); Dover reprint
                            under the title <hi rend="i">Methods &amp; Materials of Painting</hi>
                            (New York, 1960), pp. 539-44.</note>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">19</hi> See Helmut Ruhemann, <hi rend="i">The
                                Cleaning of Paintings</hi> (London, 1968), pp. 202-03, 205, 231, and
                            Ralph Mayer, <hi rend="i">The Artist’s Handbook</hi> (New York,
                            1945), pp. 18-23.</note></p>
          <p>The main difficulty in handling oils and achieving a reasonbly permanent
                        result is incurred by the drying of the vegetable oils. This process is slow
                        compared with that of aqueous paint. All the oils used in painting dry
                        because of a chemical reaction with atmospheric oxygen; they
                        “burn” dry, and at the same time they increase in weight up to
                        26%, and also in volume.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29"
type="note">20</ref> This process
                        is complicated by the metal salts used as pigments. Some of them, containing
                        lead, copper, mangan or cobalt, make the drying faster; others, containing
                        zinc, aluminum, quicksilver or cadmium, slow it down.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">21</ref> Some combine—to varying degrees—with
                        the fatty acids in the oils, forming soaps, which make the layers
                        increasingly transparent, and cause underlayers to show through.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">22</ref> Paints containing such pigments must
                        be applied thicker than at first seems necessary. <note id="n29"><hi rend="s">20</hi>
The great pioneer works on the drying of oils are
                            by Alexander Eibner, <hi rend="i">Sorung und Rissbildung an trocknenden
                                Ölfarbenaufstrichen und auf Ölbildern</hi> (Munich,
                            1920); <hi rend="i">Über fette Öle</hi> (Munich, 1922);
                                <hi rend="i">Entwicklung und Werkstoffe der Tafelmilerei</hi>
                            (Munich, 1928), esp. ch. 1; “The Yellowing of Oil Films and Its
                            Prevention,” <hi rend="i">Paint and Varnish Production
                            Manager</hi>, 13 (1935), 7-11. See also Rutherford J. Gettens and George
                            L. Stout, <hi rend="i">Painting Materials A Short Encyclopedia</hi> (New
                            York, 1942); Dover reprint (New York, 1966), pp. 36-46; George L. Stout,
                                <hi rend="i">The Care of Pictures</hi> (New York, 1948); Dover
                            reprint (New York, 1975), pp. 11-12; and Ruhemann, <hi rend="i">The
                                Cleaning of Paintings</hi>, pp. 101, 114, 243-44, 388-89.</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Stout, <hi rend="i">The Care of
                                Pictures.</hi> p. 40.</note>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Saponification changes the refractive
                            index of the film.</note></p>
          <p>It therefore becomes very difficult for the artist to calculate the variety
                        of chemical reactions going on in a drying oil painting. Yet, if he intends
                        to achieve any perfection of detail in a work too large to be completed in a
                        single sitting, then he will have to apply several coats of paint, one on
                        top of the other, over a long period of time. It will then be necessary for
                        him to use only rapidly drying pigments in the undercoats (white lead,
                        verdigris, umber, cobalt blue), and reserve the slowly drying pigments for
                        the top layers (zinc white, organic dyes precipitated on alum, vermilion,
                        cadmium yellow). He will also have to calculate the drying times of mixtures
                        of rapid and slow driers, such as white lead and vermilion, or cobalt blue
                        and cadmium yellow. Any neglect of the different drying times of different
                        paints will result in over-long waiting for underlayers to dry, will cause
                        solvent action on insufficiently dried layers, sinking in, soiling,
                        discoloration, and erratic changes of chroma and light values. It will also,
                        for obvious reasons, produce cracking. A coat rapid in drying applied on top
                        of a coat slow in drying will crack, because the latter will go on combining
                        with oxygen long after the former has ceased to do so; it will swell
                        underneath the already hard layer, and crack and dislocate it. The addition
                        of substances meant to equalize drying  <corr type="emend">speed</corr> (driers to slow-drying pigments,
                        retarders to fast-drying pigments) is likely to complicate the processes
                        beyond calculation, and cause more problems than it was meant to solve.</p>
          <p>In the middle ages oil painting was known at least from the eleventh century,
                        but for works of high quality aqueous binders were preferred. This was made
                        clear by R. E. Raspe in his <hi rend="i">A Critical Essay on Oil Painting;
                            proving that the Art of Painting in Oil was known before the pretended
                            discovery of John and Hubert van Eyck; to which are added
                            Theophilus</hi> De Arte Pingendi, <hi rend="i">Eraclius</hi> De Artibus
                        Romanorum. <hi rend="i">And a review of Farinator’s</hi> Lumen
                        Animae, London, 1781. Theophilos’s work, now known by its authentic
                        title <hi rend="i">De diversis artibus</hi>, is generally dated to the early
                        twelfth century, though Raspe dated it earlier, and it contains an account
                        of how to make linseed oil and how to use it for painting.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">23</ref> Heraclius (early eleventh century) also mentions
                        oil painting in his third book. Farinator’s <hi rend="i">Lumen
                            animae</hi> was written in Vienna in the early fourteenth century, and
                        printed in Augsburg, 1477; it contains several quotations from Theophilus,
                        though nothing on oil painting. <note id="n32"><hi rend="s">23</hi>
                            Theophilos Presbyter, <hi rend="i">De diversis artibus</hi>, ch. 20 (The
                            making of linseed oil), ch. 21 (The making of a varnish by boiling
                            sandarac in linseed oil), ch. 25-26 (How to grind colors in oil or gum,
                            and how to apply them), ch. 24, 27 (How to paint in oils on metal foil).
                            For a modern edition, see C. R. Dodwell, Theophilos <hi rend="i">De
                                Diversis artibus</hi> (London, 1961). An error in Dodwell’s
                            translation of chapter 25, headed “De coloribus oleo et gvmmi
                            terendis” (p. 24), should be pointed out. Theophilos refers to
                            pigments which can be ground either with linseed oil or gum, not with an
                            emulsion of oil in a solution of gum in water, as Dodwell mistakenly
                            believes, since he translates “gummi” as “this [drying]
                            medium” (the brackets are Dodwell’s) or “medium.”
                            It should be “gum.” For a discussion of mss. and former
                            editions, see Dodwell, pp. liv-lxix.</note></p>
          <p>Blake is likely to have known this book. When he wrote, in his <hi rend="i">Descriptive
Catalogue</hi>, that he will inquire “in another work
                        on Painting . . . who first 
<pb id="p14-167" n="167"/>
forged the silly
                        story and known falsehood, about John of Bruges [Jan van Eyck] inventing oil
                        colours,” he was probably referring to Raspe’s work.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">24</ref> Blake’s own treatise on
                        painting having disappeared,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34"
type="note">25</ref> we can
                        only guess about its contents; but if he had read Raspe he must have known
                        that Theophilos did not recommend oils for works of high quality, and
                        complained of the tedious waiting for undercoats to dry.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">26</ref> The “forger” alluded to by Blake must
                        have been Giorgio Vasari, who was the first writer to ascribe the invention
                        of oil colors to Jan van Eyck.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36"
type="note">27</ref> Since
                        Blake wrote that “Oil was not used, except by blundering ignorance,
                        till after Vandyke’s time,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37"
type="note">28</ref> he must have thought that the binding medium employed by the
                        van Eycks was aqueous. He believed that all the old easel paintings were in
                        “fresco,” by which term he meant “Water Colours,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">29</ref> that is, painting with any aqueous
                        binder. This view was by no means stupid, and was later shared by many
                        scholars, notably by Doerner, who thought that the invention of the van
                        Eycks was an emulsion of oil and resin in egg, which binder could be thinned
                        with water.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">30</ref>
Not until 1950, when Paul
                        Coremans restored <hi rend="i">The Adoration of the Lamb</hi> at Ghent, was
                        it finally proved that the van Eycks painted in oils.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">31</ref>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">24</hi><hi rend="i"> Descr. Cat.</hi> 2, K 565.</note>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">25</hi> A work by Blake describing his technical
                            inventions in art certainly existed, and was close to publication in
                            1809, though it disappeared later. It is mentioned for the first time in
                            Blake’s letter to Butts 10 Jan. 1802 (K 812), and again in his
                            letter to Cumberland 19 Dec. 1808 (K 865), where he says that he has
                            begun to print it, and has a publisher for it. It is referred to again
                            in his advertisement for the 1809 exhibition (K 561). It cannot be
                            identical with the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, for it is
                            mentioned in it (K 565). Cumberland refers to it in two notes 1807, and
                            in a letter to Blake 18 Dec. 1808 he volunteers to “prepare it for
                            the Press” (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, pp. 187, 188, 211 f.;
                            see also p. 211 n. 1).</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Theophilos, <hi rend="i">De diversis
                                artibus</hi>, ch. 25: “because each time that you apply a
                            colour, you cannot apply another over it until the first has dried. On
                            figures this is a particularly long and tedious process.”
                            (Dodwell’s translation in his ed. of Theophilos, p. 24). I agree
                            with Dodwell’s translation of “imagines” as
                            “figures,” not “pictures.” Notice also that Raspe,
                                <hi rend="i">A Critical Essay on Oil Painting</hi> (1781) describes
                            a ground of glue and chalk similar to that used by Blake, and says that
                            it is found underlying the colors on Egyptian mummy-cases, and is common
                            in medieval painting (pp. 22, 25). The making of a hide glue identical
                            with the carpenter’s glue of more recent times is described by
                            Theophilos in ch. 18, and the laying of a ground of glue and chalk (or,
                            alternatively, of burnt gypsum) in ch. 19. Blake could have got his
                            recipe for the chalk ground from this source. Cf. also my n. 23.</note>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">27</hi> Giorgio Vasari, <hi rend="i">Le vite
                                de’ più eccellenti pittori, scultori ed
                                architetori</hi>, ed. Milanesi (Florence, 1878-1885), II, 564, ff.
                            (Life of Antonello da Messina).</note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">28</hi><hi rend="i"> Descr. Cat.</hi> 2, K 566.</note>
	<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">29</hi> For Blake’s definition of <hi rend="i">fresco</hi> as watercolors, see
K 561, 563, 577. For this
                            reason Blake wrote that there was “no difference between
                            Rafael’s Cartoons and his frescos” (K 584). It is hardly
                            necessary to point out that Blake’s use of the term
                            “fresco” is idiosyncratic.</note>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">30</hi> Max Doerner, <hi rend="i">The Materials
                                of the Artist</hi> (London, 1976), pp. 329-36, with a summary on pp.
                            335-36. The first English edition (translation by Eugen Neuhaus) was
                            1934, the first German edition 1921. The passage on van Eyck is similar
                            in all editions I have seen.</note>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">31</hi> See Paul Coreman, “L’ Agneau
                            Mystique au laboratoire,” <hi rend="i">Les primitifs Flamands</hi>,
                            II (Antwerp, 1953), pub. in shortened form in <hi rend="i">Studies in
                                Conservation</hi> (Oct. 1954), pp. 145 ff., and in <hi rend="i">Museum</hi> IV
(1951).</note></p>
          <p>Oil is also known to yellow in drying. A paint rich in oil will yellow more
                        than a lean one. But a lean paint will be too thick to handle. The addition
                        of a thinner such as spirits of turpentine would be expedient, but this, if
                        added to top layers, would greatly increase the dangers of solvent action on
                        newly dried coats, and also of sinking in and darkening. The use of resinous
                        solutions, either as intermediary varnishes between coats, or as additions
                        to the paints used for top layers, would increase viscosity and thus hinder
                        the undercoats from absorbing the medium from the top coat—and this
                        absorption is the cause of most of the troubles mentioned above. However,
                        even if resins are slower in yellowing than the oils, they in the end yellow
                        more, and they also make the film brittle and thus increase the risk of
                        cracking, as well as of yellowing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n41" type="note">32</ref>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">32</hi> Alexander Eibner, <hi rend="i">Entwicklung und Werkstoffe der
Malerei</hi>, p. 175 and Appendix E.
                            This was known already to Leonardo, who wrote that resin varnishes
                            “col lungo tenpo pigliano vn cierto giallo che pende in nero”
                            (“with time acquire a certain yellow [hue] which tends to
                            brown”), J. P. Richter, ed., <hi rend="i">The Literary Works of
                                Leonardo da Vinci</hi> (1883; New York, 1970), I,
                            §634.</note></p>
          <p>For this reason the old masters often chose an aqueous binder for pigments
                        especially likely to be altered by the yellowing of the oil, such as the
                        blues. In the Ghent altarpiece by van Eyck, otherwise painted in oil, the
                        ultramarine mantle of the Virgin was found to have been painted in gum;<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">33</ref> van Dyck told Theodore de Mayerne that
                        he often painted his blues with an aqueous binder, and he also knew how to
                        make gum adhere to an oily surface by means of juice of garlic, and how to
                        make such a paint waterproof by passing a varnish over it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">34</ref>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">33</hi> Above, n. 31.</note>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">34</hi> Theodore Turquet de Mayerne, <hi rend="i">Pictorja Sculptorja &amp; quae
subalternarum artium</hi>,
                            1620 (the ms. was begun at that date), p. 153, BM Sloane MS 2052; ed.
                            Ernst Berger in <hi rend="i">Beiträge zur Entwickelungsgeschichte
                                der Malerei</hi>, IV (Munich, 1901), pp. 336-38.</note></p>
          <p>The old masters understood the problems created by oily vehicles and knew how
                        to solve them, but with the rise of Academies, which taught no mean
                        handicrafts, and the simultaneous decline of workshop education for artists,
                        the old rules were soon forgotten, and the oil painters found themselves
                        entangled in difficulties.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44"
type="note">35</ref> Oil had
                        become a hindrance to free and easy execution and a danger to the
                        preservation of pictures, or, as Blake wrote, “a fetter to genius and a
                        dungeon to art.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45"
type="note">36</ref>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">35</hi> The rules could be summarized thus: make
                            undercoats strong in binding, rapid in drying, hard and lean. Make top
                            coats weak in binding, slow in drying, soft, fat. The old masters knew
                            which binders and which pigments were suitable for undercoats, which for
                            top coats; which pigments were compatible with which binders, and which
                            pigments could not be mixed with each other. The “secret” of
                            their success was not something that could be kept in a bottle; it was
                            the result of knowledge, training and skill. See Cennini’s
                            introduction to his list of pigments (ch. 35, Milanesi ed., p. 49):
                            “let us come to the grinding of colours, showing you which colours
                            are the finest, and the coarsest, and the worst; which one wants to be
                            ground or worked up little, which one much; which one wants one binder,
                            which one wants another; and just as they differ in their colours, so
                            they do in the natures of their binders, and in grinding.” In ch.
                            56 (p. 60) he warns against the mixture of verdigris and white lead, and
                            in ch. 117 (p. 97) he says that the lower layers in gessoing ought to be
                            stronger in binding, “because the gesso grosso [undercoat] is your
                            foundation for everything.”</note>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">36</hi> K 566.</note></p>
          <p>The easiest way out of these difficulties would be to paint <hi rend="i">alla
                            prima</hi>, never or seldom having to add any paint on top of a layer
                        already completed. Not surprisingly, this method became more and more
                        dominant during the nineteenth century. In the hands of the impressionists
                        it led to a sketchy manner, but it is possible to paint a large, detailed
                        painting <hi rend="i">alla prima</hi>, completing it piece by piece, as in
                            <hi rend="i">fresco.</hi> This method was used by Caspar David
                        Friedrich, Adolf von Menzel, Wilhelm Leibl, William Holman Hunt and, in his
                        early works, by J. E. Millais.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46"
type="note">37</ref> Such a
                        mode of painting, of course, makes the calculation of the effect of the
                        whole difficult. Extensive retouching afterwards is often found necessary,
                        and thus the advantages of the method are lost. <note id="n46"><hi rend="s">37</hi>
The <hi rend="i">alla prima</hi> technique of the
                            pre-raphaelites is described by William Holman Hunt, <hi rend="i">Pre-Raphaelitism
and the Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood</hi> (1905-06),
                            I, 276. For the technique of the Germans, see Kurt Wehlte, <hi rend="i">Werkstoffe
und Techniken der Malerei</hi>, (Ravensburg, 1967), pp.
                            662-66, repr. of an unfinished <hi rend="i">alla prima</hi> painting by
                            Adolph von Menzel, B58.56.03.1 (original destroyed in World War
                            II).</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s easy way out was to discard oil altogether, and to use an
                        aqueous paint instead. He seems to have had a good reason to do so. Such
                        paints dry uniformly with the evaporation of water, and the painter may
                        disregard the differences in drying times which cause such problems in oil
                        painting. Aqueous paints do not yellow either.</p>
          <p>To this purpose Blake adopted carpenter’s glue, dissolved in warm
                        water. Admittedly he used the same binder for his color-prints, some of
                        which he marked “fresco.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47"
type="note">38</ref>
                        But since he seems to have experimented with color-printing only for a short
                        time about 1795,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48"
type="note">39</ref> it can hardly be
                        described as Blake’s “alternative” to oil painting, as
                        Lindsay calls it. Glue as a painting medium was recommended by
                            Vitruvius,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49"
type="note">40</ref> and also by Cennino
                            Cennini.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">41</ref>
It was used by Raphael
                        for his cartoons, now at the Victoria and Albert Museum.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">42</ref> It is a sound technique, but one has to remember
                        that a painting in glue should never be varnished with the varnishes
                        commonly employed for giving a protective top coat to oil paintings.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">43</ref> Oil or any thin varnish will turn such
                        a picture yellow, as Catherine Blake told Lord Egremont in a letter recently
                        published by Bentley.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53"
type="note">44</ref> The composition
                        of Blake’s own varnish is not known, but Catherine and Tatham
                        described it as “white” (i.e. colorless), hard and of
                        Blake’s own making.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54"
type="note">45</ref> Blake could
                        have used either egg white or bee’s wax, though the latter could not
                        properly be called “hard,” or a composition of resin and wax
                        viscous enough not to penetrate into the paint. <note id="n47"><hi rend="s">38</hi>
The Metropolitan Museum (New York) copy of <hi rend="i">God
                                Judging Adam</hi> is signed “Fresco. WBlake inv.,” and the
                            Victoria and Albert Museum copy of <hi rend="i">Naomi</hi> “Fresco
                            WBlake.” This shows that Tatham was wrong when he supposed the
                            color-prints were printed in oil (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, pp.
                            33 f.; Gilchrist, 1942, p. 366). Note that, according to John Linnell,
                            the account of the oil printing process was inaccurate (<hi rend="i">Blake
Records</hi>, p. 34 n. 1).</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">39</hi> None of the large color-prints bears any
                            date other than 1795; some are printed on paper watermarked 1794; but
                            many are undated. In one copy of the color-printed <hi rend="i">Small
                                Book of Designs</hi> the date of the title of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, 1794,
has been changed to 1796. See Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford, 1977), the sections on the
                            illuminated works, which show that color-printed copies, whenever they
                            can be dated with any certainty, were printed 1794-96.</note>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">40</hi> Vitruvius, VII.X.2. Morris Hicky Morgan
                            (trans.), <hi rend="i">Vitruvius The Ten Books on Architecture</hi>
                            (Harvard Univ. Press, 1914), Dover reprint (New York, 1960), p.
                            218.</note>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">41</hi> Cennino Cennini, <hi rend="i">Il libro
                                dell’ arte o Trattato della pittura</hi>, ch. 109, recommends
                            “colla di caravella,” made from goat’s muzzles, hoofs
                            and clippings of skin, as a binder for pigments, “in temperar
                            colori,” and also for carpenter’s work “attacar legni,
                            far liuti,” and as a binder for grounds “temperar
                            gessi”—see Tambroni ed. (1821), pp. 94-95; Milanesi ed.
                            (1859; 1975), p. 92. Blake is known to have read Linnell’s copy
                            of the Tambroni ed.; see <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 33 n. 3,
                            where Cennini’s name is misspelled “Ceninni.”</note>
	<note id="n51"><hi rend="s">42</hi> John White, <hi rend="i">The Raphael
                                Cartoons</hi> (Victoria and Albert Museum, 1972), p. 5.</note>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">43</hi> Ruhemann, <hi rend="i">The Cleaning of
                                Paintings</hi>, pp. 269-70.</note>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">44</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., “Blake’s
                            Shadow,” <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 17 March
                            1978, p. 320.</note>
	<note id="n54"><hi rend="s">45</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi>, p. 517, and above, n. 44.</note></p>
          <p>Caution in varnishing is especially important if the distemper or glue
                        painting contains white pigments consisting of whiting, i.e., chalk. Oily or
                        resinous varnishes will be absorbed by the chalk, which makes it transparent
                        and brown, like putty (Blake used that word<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n55" type="note">46</ref>)—and the putty commonly used for fastening window glass
                        is nothing but linseed oil and chalk. Blake knew this; he adopted whiting or
                        chalk, and wrote that oil painting “has compelled the use of that
                        destroyer of color, white lead.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56"
type="note">47</ref>
                        He was right. White lead was the only white pigment in general use in his
                        day that would not absorb oil, and thus remain white and opaque when mixed
                        with an oily vehicle. <note id="n55"><hi rend="s">46</hi> “It [oil]
                            turns every permanent white to a yellow and brown putty,” 566. Note
                            the force of the word “permanent.” Blake did not consider
                            white lead a permanent white because, unprotected by an oily vehicle, it
                            is known to blacken.</note>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">47</hi> K 566. Further proof that Blake did not
                            use white lead is given by Tatham: “he has touched the lights with
                            white compound of whiting &amp; glue, of which material he laid the
                            ground of his panel” (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 515).
                            Whiting (chalk) is, of course, much more permanent than white lead, if
                            an oil-free and resin-free vehicle is used; but if such a painting is
                            varnished, the whites are instantly killed.</note></p>
          <p>I am sure that the chief cause of the darkening of many of Blake’s
                        paintings in glue is inexpert varnishing after Blake’s time.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">48</ref> For this reason I do not believe, as
                        Lindsay does (p. 129), that Blake 
<pb id="p14-168" n="168"/>
was influenced
                        by Rembrandt; the Rembrandtesque brown chiaroscuro in some of Blake’s
                        “temperas” was produced, not by Blake himself, but by unskilled
                        varnishers of the mid nineteenth century. <note id="n57"><hi rend="s">48</hi> Consider
the large color-prints: those that have been
                            varnished (for instance <hi rend="i">Christ Appearing</hi>, in the Tate)
                            are as brown as the “frescos” of <hi rend="i">Nelson</hi> and
                                <hi rend="i">Pitt</hi>, while the unvarnished ones are in a perfect
                            condition.</note></p>
          <p>Since Blake knew that “the nature of gum was to crack” if applied
                        in thick, opaque layers,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58"
type="note">49</ref> it is obvious
                        that he used the glue precisely in order to be able to paint thick, and to
                        cover underlayers with more or less opaque top coats. Glue would have given
                        him no advantages in painting traditional, transparent watercolors on paper.
                        For this reason I think that he employed the ordinary gum (either gum arabic
                        or gum tragacanth) for normal watercolor drawings. Gum can be applied cold,
                        which is a great advantage, while the glue-water has to be used warm;
                        otherwise it would gelatinize to an unmanageable jelly. 
<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">49</hi> According to Tatham, confirmed by J. T. Smith, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, pp. 517,
472.</note></p>
          <p>According to J. T. Smith Blake knew that top layers in glue painting should
                        be “more dilute” than the ground layers,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n59" type="note">50</ref> which is true—the reverse would produce
                        cracking and flaking. Blake also said that glue was less sensitive to
                        changes in atmospheric moisture than gum.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n60" type="note">51</ref> This means that he must have added a hardener to the glue. The
                        addition of alum to glue in order to make it more water-resistant and less
                        hygroscopic was ordinary workshop practice in Blake’s day.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">52</ref>
	<note id="n59"><hi rend="s">50</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi>, p. 472.</note>
	<note id="n60"><hi rend="s">51</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi>, p. 472.</note>
	<note id="n61"><hi rend="s">52</hi> See Ralph Mayer, <hi rend="i">The
                                Artist’s Handbook</hi> (1945), pp. 370-71.</note></p>
          <p>All this shows that Blake’s technique was rational and sound. I only
                        have doubts about his invention of the “Portable Fresco,” which he
                        described as “a Wall on Canvas or Wood.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n62" type="note">53</ref> A thick ground of whiting and glue on canvas is
                        extremely apt to crack, as Linnell remarked.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n63" type="note">54</ref> Blake himself seems to have noticed this, for in the 1820s he
                        began to use very thin grounds.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64"
type="note">55</ref>
	<note id="n62"><hi rend="s">53</hi><hi rend="i"> Advertisement of Exhibition</hi> 1809, K 560.</note>
	<note id="n63"><hi rend="s">54</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi>, p. 33 n. 3.</note>
	<note id="n64"><hi rend="s">55</hi> See <hi rend="i">Count Ugolino</hi> (c.
                            1826, Keynes Coll.), <hi rend="i">The Body of Abel Found by Adam and
                                Eve</hi> (c. 1826, Tate), <hi rend="i">Satan Smiting Job</hi> (c.
                            1826, Tate), <hi rend="i">The Arlington Court Picture</hi> (signed and
                            dated 1821, on thin chalk ground on paper), <hi rend="i">The Faerie
                                Queene</hi> (c. 1825, National Trust, Petworth House). Cf. Martin
                            Butlin, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, Tate Gallery exhib. cat.
                            (1978), nos. 311, 312, 313, 307, 310.</note></p>
          <p>Minor suggestions and corrections.</p>
          <p>Lindsay’s book is, on the whole, carefully proof-read. It is odd,
                        however, that personal names are often found in an incorrect form: Scamuzzi
                        for Scamozzi (p. 16), Behman for Behmen (p. 40), Schöngauer for
                        Schongauer (p. 171), Béatrizat for Beatrizet (p. 8), Woolett for
                        Woollett (p. 213, fn.; Lindsay has silently reproduced Blake’s
                        misspelling of the name in the <hi rend="i">Public Address</hi>). Once even
                        the sex of an unfortunate artist is changed, as in Antonina de Messina for
                        Antonello da Messina (p. 171).</p>
          <p>Sometimes Lindsay’s handling of source material is careless. The story
                        of William’s and Catherine’s courtship (p. 481) is quoted from
                        Tatham and Lindsay adds that he must have based his account on what
                        Catherine herself told him. But Tatham’s biographical sketch is
                        written on paper watermarked 183(2?), and the same story appears, partly
                        verbatim, in J. T. Smith, 1828 (Smith quotes “a friend”), and in
                        Cunningham, 1830. There is, of course, a possibility that the friend Smith
                        quoted was indeed Tatham, but this should not be taken for granted.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65" type="note">56</ref>
	<note id="n65"><hi rend="s">56</hi> See <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, pp.
                            517, 459, 481.</note></p>
          <p>Lindsay seems to believe (p. 33) that the two states of the engraving <hi rend="i">Job</hi> are
two separate platès.</p>
          <p>The reference on p. 34 f. to W. Meredith’s <hi rend="i">Commonplace
                            Book</hi> is unsatisfactory, and the book is not in the bibliography. In
                        general, Lindsay’s notes and bibliography seem to have been written
                        more for the convenience of the author than for that of the reader. The
                        foreshortenings are cumbersome, and misspellings occur, such as N. D. Paley
                        for Morton D. Paley, and Acta Academiae Absensis (lovely!) for Acta
                        Academiae Aboensis.</p>
          <p>Misprints in references to and quotations from Blake’s writings may
                        occasionally cause confusion. On p. 212 Lindsay makes Blake say that his art
                        was that of “Dürer and the engravers.” This is rather
                        pointless. What Blake wrote in his <hi rend="i">Public Address</hi> was that
                        his technique of engraving was that of “Alb Durers Histories &amp; the
                        old Engravers,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66"
type="note">57</ref> meaning, as the
                        context shows, sixteenth century engraving as opposed to that of the
                        eighteenth century print industry. <note id="n66"><hi rend="s">57</hi><hi rend="i">
Notebook</hi>, p. 51 (K 592).</note></p>
          <p>It is not clear why Lindsay, on p. 225, calls <hi rend="i">The Everlasting
                            Gospel</hi> “The Everlasting Mercy,” but many of his remarks
                        earlier on the contents of the poem are just and sound. Yet he goes too far
                        when he says that the poem “shows no concern for the texts of the New
                        Testament.” Actually it consists mainly of allusions to it and
                        quotations from it. Admittedly Blake’s interpretation of
                        Christ’s teaching differs from that of most Christian congregations,
                        but that does not necessarily mean that they are without foundation in the
                        Bible. It should be observed, also, that the most outrageous interpretation
                        of Christ’s teaching and character is put into the mouth of
                        Caiphas.</p>
          <p>The quotation on p. 49 f., “Each man . . . ,” is given in an
                        incorrect form, and on p. 194 “then” is substituted for
                        “thus” in a quote from the <hi rend="i">Notebook.</hi> And why,
                        indeed, does Lindsay identify Blake’s Jesus in the 1790s with
                        Theotormon? In the <hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi> Blake wrote: “And
                        Jesus . . . recievd A Gospel from wretched Theotormon.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">58</ref> The two characters are clearly
                        separate here. <note id="n67"><hi rend="s">58</hi> K 246.</note></p>
          <p>On p. 131 Lindsay quotes the annotation “Blake Dim’d with
                        Superstition” on Blake’s letter to Trusler of 23 August 1799 as
                        if it were by Trusler, although it is, according to Keynes, in George
                        Cumberland’s hand.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68"
type="note">59</ref>
	<note id="n68"><hi rend="s">59</hi> Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>,
                            p. 252.</note></p>
          <p>On p. 213 Lindsay quotes Blake’s remark “Models are difficult -
                        enslave one.” He misunderstands imaginative art when he criticizes
                        Blake for never asking “if the conception should not be strong enough
                        to stand up against nature.” This is exactly what Blake demanded of
                        art, and the reason why he rejected working from models. If a work of art is
                        copied from nature, and thus is dependent on it, how can it stand up against
                        it? If someone really wants to be imaginative, he certainly has to sacrifice
                        some of the charms of nature.</p>
          <p>On p. 141 Lindsay uncritically reproduces an error of editing on the part of
                        Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 83, when he quotes the
                        quatrains by Hayley, in which the author invokes his dead son to inspirit
                        Blake and steady “a Failing Brother’s Hand &amp; Eyes or temper
                        his eccentric Soul.” As Bentley carefully points out, the manuscript
                        clearly has “Foiling.” According to the OED this word means 
<pb id="p14-169" n="169"/>
“Baffling, disappointing.” In my view
                        “foiling” makes excellent sense in this context, and I can see no
                        need for the substitution “failing.”</p>
          <p>Is Blake’s accusation that Hayley despised his designs
                        “completely untrue” as Lindsay writes on p. 156? Already the
                        quatrains quoted above show that Hayley did not find Blake’s hand and
                        eye quite to his taste, or his eccentricity tempered enough. It is quite
                        clear that he tried to instruct Blake and correct his engraving, and he
                        asked him to alter the expression of the mouth in the engraving after
                        Flaxman’s medallion of Thomas Hayley, to give the impression of
                        “gay juvenility.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69"
type="note">60</ref> Blake
                        obeyed, and produced an awkward dawb at the corner of the mouth. Hayley did
                        not defend Blake against those who criticized him; instead he tried to
                        excuse him, as his letters to Lady Hesketh show.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70" type="note">61</ref> The main cause of tension between Blake and many of
                        his friends, including Hayley, was that they tried to curb his imagination,
                        for which they had no use, and make him a portrait painter, a reproductive
                        engraver, and an illustrator of literary works (such as Hayley’s),
                        which Blake knew were inferior to his own poems. No wonder that Blake got
                        annoyed, and could not be as grateful as he tried to be, or as his friends
                        thought he ought to be. <note id="n69"><hi rend="s">60</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake
Records</hi>, pp. 65 f., 69-71, repr. pl. 11.</note>
	<note id="n70"><hi rend="s">61</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi>, pp. 105 f., 162, 163 f.</note></p>
          <p>I do not believe, either, that Scolfield’s accusation against Blake
                        “bears every mark of truth” (p. 160). Indeed Blake would have been
                        likely to damn the king and call his soldiers slaves but in this case there
                        were too many witnesses who, despite threats by Scolfield and his companion,
                        testified that they had heard no seditious words spoken—and
                        Scolfield’s only witness was proved not to have been present at all,
                        but asleep in a stable, and only to have come out after the witnesses had
                        gathered at the stable door.</p>
          <p>Blake’s later accusation against Hayley for having “hired”
                        Scolfield to “bereave” Blake’s life,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n71" type="note">62</ref> was, of course, groundless and inexcusable, as
                        shown by Hayley’s exemplary conduct at the time of trial. 
<note id="n71"><hi rend="s">62</hi> K 544.</note></p>
          <p>Such suspicions can be explained only by the paranoid sense of persecution
                        which Blake developed around 1806-1809; I agree with Lindsay so far that I
                        believe Blake was not in his right mind from about 1806 to about 1818,
                        during which time he quarrelled with most of his friends and lived in
                        isolation for long periods of time.</p>
          <p>Moreover, the “Long Poem” describing Blake’s “Spiritual
                        Acts of [his] three Years’ Slumber on the banks of the Ocean”
                        comprising “an immense number of Verses on One Grand Theme” and
                        written “from immediate Dictation” (letter to Butts 25 April 1803)
                        is certainly the lost manuscript of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> It
                        consisted of twenty-four books, but one cannot be sure if these books were
                        as long as the four eventually printed. Note that chapter 1 originally ended
                        at pl. 14. <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, as we know it today, could well be a
                        compact version, edited on the basis of the entire manuscript, which must
                        have been completed at Felpham, since the engraving of it was begun at South
                        Molton Street in 1804. In the preface to the printed version Blake refers to
                        his “three years slumber on the banks of the Ocean,” and says that
                        “this Verse” was “dictated” to him. And the poem begins:
                        “Of the Sleep of Ulro! and of the passage through / Eternal Death! and
                        of the waking to Eternal Life. / This theme calls me in sleep night after
                        night, &amp; evry morn / Awakes me at sun-rise.” All this is in
                        agreement with what Blake told Butts in his letter; therefore the two works
                        are the same. The letter cannot refer to the <hi rend="i">The Four
                        Zoas</hi>, dated on the title-page 1797, although this manuscript was
                        revised and added to later, probably at Felpham.</p>
          <p>However, <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> should not be excluded from consideration
                        on account of its shortness. The printed two books, comprising about 1600
                        lines, are only a fragment of the twelve books planned, as shown by the
                        title, where “12” has been changed to “2.” The
                        manuscript could have had as many as 9600 lines. It is indeed possible that
                            <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> are editions of
                        portions of one single manuscript, as long as the <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> or
                        the <hi rend="i">Odyssey.</hi> According to Henry Crabb Robinson, Blake had
                        “six or seven mss. as long as Homer” and “20 tragedies as
                        long as Macbeth.” Here the problem is in distinguishing existing
                        manuscripts at least one of which was seen by Crabb Robinson, from other
                        works only produced in the spiritual world.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n72" type="note">63</ref> Merely because Blake sometimes composed verses which he did
                        not bother to write down, one should not suppose—as Lindsay
                        does—that none of Blake’s lost works were ever written down on
                        paper. There must at least have been manuscripts for the printed works, but
                        not one of them has survived. <note id="n72"><hi rend="s">63</hi> Robinson
                            wrote to Dorothy Wordsworth 16 Feb. 1826 that Blake’s “MSS.
                            are immense in quantity” (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 324).
                            He must have seen at least one of them 18 Feb. 1826 when he wrote in his
                            diary: “I inquired abot. his writings—[‘]I have
                            written more than Voltaire or Rousseau—Six or Seven Epic poems as
                            long as Homer and 20 Tragedies as long as Macbeth[.’] He shewed
                            me his Version (for so it may be called) of Genesis—‘as
                            understood by a Christian Visionary’ in which in [the <hi rend="i">del.</hi>] a
style resemblg the Bible—The spirit is
                            given[;] he read a passage at random[.] It was striking” (<hi rend="i">Blake
Records</hi>, p. 322). Cunningham, also, wrote that
                            Blake “has left volumes of verse, amounting, it is said, to nearly
                            an hundred, prepared for the press” (<hi rend="i">Blake
                                Records</hi>, p. 506).</note></p>
          <p>Since we know that Tatham burned several of Blake’s manuscripts, it is
                        reasonable to suppose that he was responsible for the destruction of most,
                        if not all, of the lost works.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73"
type="note">64</ref> We also
                        have every reason to believe that the lost six books of <hi rend="i">The
                            French Revolution</hi> were actually written by 1791, as Blake himself
                        explicitly stated.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74"
type="note">65</ref> When Lindsay thinks
                        that Blake’s lost works never existed in writing, he seems to have
                        been misled by his own thesis that Blake “published” his works
                        mainly for the spirits. On p. 235 he adds that Blake needed to believe in
                        angels and devils “as a projection of the missing audience which he
                        feels to be potentially present.” This is a possible explanation,
                        especially in view of some of Blake’s remarks to Crabb Robinson, but
                        I wonder if an entirely different explanation is not even more probable:
                        because Blake believed in angels and devils, his lack of a fit audience was
                        less severely felt. Thus, what Lindsay thinks is the cause, in my opinion is
                        the effect. <note id="n73"><hi rend="s">64</hi> See Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake
Books</hi>, pp. 479-84, and <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>,
                            p. 414 n. 3.</note>
	<note id="n74"><hi rend="s">65</hi> “The remaining Books of this Poem
                            are finished, and will be published in their Order,” says the
                            advertisement of <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi>, and Blake and
                            Johnson had no reason to lie (K 134).</note></p>
          <p>On the whole, Lindsay is not in sympathy with the “spiritual” side
                        of Blake. It is true that most educated people today do not believe in
                        spirits, and consequently Blake’s belief in spirits means little to
                        us. If we otherwise sympathize with Blake, as Lindsay does, we are inclined
                        to hope that the spirits did not mean very much to Blake either. But I am
                        quite sure that they did. Blake believed in the existence of angels and
                        devils; they were as real to him as Leonid Bresnev or Jane Fonda are real to
                        us. I do not think it is possible to understand Blake unless this fact is
                        recognized.</p>
          <p>Notwithstanding Lindsay’s lack of interest in the spirits, his section
                        on Blake’s visions is sound 
<pb id="p14-170" n="170"/> (pp. 228 ff.).
                        He also describes a personal experience from 1931, when he, after a
                        fortnight of fasting, “saw the Egyptian goddess Sekhmet,” and he
                        quotes Jaensch’s definition of eidetic phenomena from Morton D.
                        Paley’s <hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination.</hi></p>
          <p>Lindsay quotes Keynes’ suggestion that the vision of <hi rend="i">The
                            Ghost of the Flea</hi> (1819) was based on an engraving of a flea in
                        Hooke’s <hi rend="i">Micrographia.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n75" type="note">66</ref> I cannot see much resemblance. However, if one examines the
                        background monsters in Blake’s illustrations of 1797-98 of
                        Gray’s <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, no. 18 for the <hi rend="i">Ode on a
                            Distant Prospect of Eton College</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n76" type="note">67</ref> one is immediately struck by the resemblance of one of them to
                        the <hi rend="i">Ghost of a Flea.</hi> Thus, in 1819, Blake saw a vision of
                        his own illustration of one of the “murderous band” that stand in
                        ambush around the playing children “to seize their prey”; one of
                        the “monsters of human fate / And black Misfortune’s baleful
                        train.” This agrees very well with Jaensch’s definition of one
                        of the main types of eidetic vision, namely that which consists of
                        “modified after-images.” <note id="n75"><hi rend="s">66</hi> Repr.
                            Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, pl. 33.</note>
	<note id="n76"><hi rend="s">67</hi> See Irene Tayler, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations to the Poems of
Gray</hi>
                            (1971).</note></p>
          <p>Titles, dates and descriptions of Blake’s pictorial works are
                        sometimes wrong. The date of the color-print <hi rend="i">Elohim Creating
                            Adam</hi> should be 1795 (p. 80). Lindsay is wrong when he says (p. 100)
                        that the color-print <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi> is lost; there are
                        copies at the Tate, at the Metropolitan Museum in New York and at the
                        Philadelphia Museum of Art.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77"
type="note">68</ref> As Butlin
                        has shown, the Tate Gallery copy bears the inscription “God Judging
                        Adam” (under the mount).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78"
type="note">69</ref> This
                        work was mistakenly given the title “Elijah in the Fiery Chariot”
                        by W. M. Rossetti in 1863, yet Lindsay still thinks that a work with that
                        title exists. To add to the confusion Lindsay has invented one more subject
                        which never existed, called by him “Adam Cast Out by God.” These
                        two ghosts should be immediately cast out of Blake’s oeuvre. 
<note id="n77"><hi rend="s">68</hi> Butlin, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>,
                            exhib. cat. 1978, nos. 87-89.</note>
	<note id="n78"><hi rend="s">69</hi> Martin Butlin, “Blake’s
                            ‘God Judging Adam’ Rediscovered,” <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 107
(1965), 86-89; and Butlin, <hi rend="i">William Blake A Complete Catalogue of the Works in the Tate
                                Gallery</hi>, (1971), no. 15.</note></p>
          <p>On p. 54, n., <hi rend="i">The Book of Enoch</hi> is listed among the sources
                        for <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, but it is unlikely that Blake knew anything
                        about the book before 1789, although he illustrated the first English
                        translation of it, which appeared in 1821.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n79" type="note">70</ref> The lithograph <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi>, 1807, was based on the
                        short text on Enoch in Genesis 5:24. <note id="n79"><hi rend="s">70</hi>
                            Allan R. Brown, “Blake’s Drawings for the Book of
                            Enoch,” <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 77 (Sept. 1940),
                            80-85.</note></p>
          <p>Why does Lindsay say (p. 68) that the old blind and lame man in Jerusalem pl.
                        84 is led to an open door? He is led into a square with two churches in the
                        background, one resembling Westminster Abbey, the doors of which are shut,
                        the other resembling St. Paul’s, the doors of which are not shown.
                        Moreover, I cannot see any “inkhorn at his side.”</p>
          <p>Dates and imprints on engravings should be treated with caution. Especially
                        in commercial engraving it was often found convenient to use a date
                        different from that of actual publication, if, for instance, publication was
                        delayed beyond the date planned when the engravings were executed. Thus they
                        cannot be used to estimate how fast an engraver was in completing his
                        plates, especially since engravers were in the habit of putting the same
                        date on different engravings meant for the same publication, even if the
                        engravings were finished at different times. Yet Lindsay does this on p.
                        227.</p>
          <p>Incidentally, the same caution applies to dates in watermarks. The dates on
                        Whatman papers generally agree with the date when the sheets were formed on
                        the molds, but other papermakers sometimes used old molds with watermark
                        dates, without bothering to change the date.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n80" type="note">71</ref>
	<note id="n80"><hi rend="s">71</hi> Dard Hunter, <hi rend="i">Papermaking
                                The History and Technique of an Ancient Craft</hi> (New York, 1943,
                            1947, 1974), pp. 264-65.</note></p>
          <p>Erdman’s opinion about the “irony” in <hi rend="i">Nelson</hi> and <hi rend="i">Pitt</hi> is
quoted on p. 204, the
                        argument being that these paintings, far from being apotheoses of Pitt and
                        Nelson, are really concealed lampoons against them. Lindsay says that Blake,
                        if Erdman is right, managed to conceal his real feelings completely, and
                        suspects that Blake, anxious for state support, deliberately posed as a
                        patriotic propagandist for the war against France. If he is right in
                        this—and I agree that Lindsay’s view is more reasonable than
                        Erdman’s—then these paintings were meant to be what Blake
                        himself called them, grand apotheoses of the real heroes of the nation. It
                        is clear from the vehement attack in <hi rend="i">The Examiner</hi> that
                        <corr type="emend">contemporaries</corr> thought that Blake supported 
                        the war policy. If this is so,
                        Erdman’s interpretation is wrong. In these works Blake meant to
                        celebrate the heroes of the British nation. The only relevant question that
                        remains is whether Blake was honest or not in painting these apotheoses. Had
                        his opinions about France changed, or was he merely trying to make himself
                        acceptable to those in power? I am glad to see that Lindsay asks this
                        straightforward question, but I am not sure that I agree with his answer
                        that Blake deliberately lied in the hope of getting a government
                        commission.</p>
          <p>It has to be observed that England, which in the 1790s had been an accomplice
                        in the crusade against the French republic, now waged a war on the
                        Napoleonic empire. After 1804 Napoleon fitted Blake’s description of
                        “a Tyrant crownd,” and at least after that date—or perhaps
                        already from 1799 when Napoleon abolished the democratic institutions in
                        France and declared himself First Consul—Pitt and Nelson could be
                        seen in a new light, as angels pleased to perform the divine command to
                        crush that tyrant. Blake’s exalted hopes in the peace negotiations of
                            1801-1802<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81"
type="note">72</ref> had already come to
                        nought in 1803, when the French conquered the formerly British Hannover. In
                        1804 Napoleon caused the Spanish declaration of war on Britain. The war of
                        1805 was clearly provoked by the French, who in 1803 had already planned an
                        invasion of England. The only witness who, in 1803, had heard William and
                        Catherine Blake volunteer to cut throats with Napoleon, was the proven liar
                        John Scolfield. <note id="n81"><hi rend="s">72</hi> Letter to Flaxman, 19
                            Oct. 1801 (K 810).</note></p>
          <p>In a letter to Hayley 28 May 1804 Blake criticized the French for idolizing
                        Bonaparte, and in 1815 Cumberland wrote that “Blake says he is fearful
                        they will make too great a Man of Napoleon and enable him to come to this
                            country.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82"
type="note">73</ref> That Blake
                        condemned the British attack on Copenhagen in 1807<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83" type="note">74</ref> does not mean that he thought the war against
                        Napoleon unjustified. He could well have disliked the government’s
                        organized graft in selling army commissions, and yet deemed resistance to
                        the French imperialism necessary. If we today condemn the British
                        colonization of India, or the allied bombardment of Dresden in the second
                        world war, it does not mean that we think that Britain and France should
                        never have resisted Hitler. <note id="n82"><hi rend="s">73</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake
Records</hi>, p. 236.</note>
	<note id="n83"><hi rend="s">74</hi> See David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake
                                Prophet Against Empire</hi>, pp. 452 f., and n. 52.</note></p>
          <pb id="p14-171" n="171"/>
          <p>I can understand that many commentators find it hard to agree that the author
                        of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> could ever have found the British war against
                        Napoleon justified. Notice the song of the Spectre Sons of Albion in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> pl. 65: “We were carried away in thousands
                        from London . . . compell’d to fight under the iron whips / Of our
                        captains, fearing our officers more than the enemy” (K 700). But is not
                        the point here that war is the natural result of industrialization and the
                        alienation and oppression of the workers, “that they may grind / And
                        polish brass &amp; iron hour after hour, laborious task, / Kept ignorant of
                        its use: that they may spend the days of wisdom / In sorrowful drudgery to
                        obtain a scanty pittance of bread, / In ignorance to view a small portion
                        and think that All”? And is not all this the result of natural
                        philosophy advocated by Bacon, Newton and Locke, and also by Voltaire and
                        Rousseau, the inspirers of British capitalism and of the bourgeois
                        revolution in France and its child Napoleon? Certainly capitalism is a
                        universal state, in the world and in the soul.</p>
          <p>Perhaps even Erdman would agree with me so far, that the war is the evil
                        means to overthrow war, and that Nelson and Pitt in this apocalyptic sense
                        perform the divine command. Yet I feel there is more to it; Pitt and Nelson
                        are not the senseless tools of a superior will; they are, as Blake says,
                            “<hi rend="i">pleased</hi> to perform the Almighty’s
                        orders” (italics mine). They seem to know exactly what they are
                        doing.</p>
          <p>On p. 246 Jack Lindsay uncritically reproduces H. H. Gilchrist’s
                        technically improbable account (pub. 1887, based on a recent interview with
                        George Richmond), of how James Deville took a plaster cast of Blake’s
                            head.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84" type="note">75</ref>
According to Richmond, this
                        was the first cast Deville made, and Blake’s mouth is said to have
                        been given an uncharacteristic look of severity because he suffered much
                        pain through the plaster pulling out a quantity of his hair. This pulling
                        out, however, could only have occurred when the mold was being removed from
                        Blake’s face, after the plaster had hardened. No expression of pain
                        at that stage could have left any impression on the plaster. The making of
                        the mold was described somewhat differently by Herbert P. Horne, also in
                        1887 and also after a conversation with Richmond: “Much of the forced
                        expression of the nostrils and more particularly of the mouth is due to the
                        discomforture which the taking of the cast involved, many of Blake’s
                        hairs adhering to the plaster until quite recently.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n85" type="note">76</ref> There is a hint here that Richmond made two
                        separate statements which were innocently joined together by the
                        interviewers, and particularly by H. H. Gilchrist. Richmond, being a
                        painter, was certainly familiar with the technique of making casts from
                        nature, so I think that he must have told his interviewers something like
                        the following: that Blake’s mouth was distorted, because he found it
                        unpleasant to have his face covered with wet plaster, which, when it begins
                        to harden, gets very warm; that his nostrils were abnormally dilated,
                        because he had to breathe through tubes inserted into them, otherwise he
                        would have died from suffocation under the wet plaster; that these two
                        circumstances accounted for the look of severity; that a number of
                        Blake’s hairs stuck to the mold when it was removed from his face,
                        after having hardened; and that some of the hairs which had stuck to the
                        mold afterwards became attached to the cast, when the cast was made from the
                        mold. <note id="n84"><hi rend="s">75</hi> H. H. Gilchrist, ed., <hi rend="i">Anne
Gilchrist</hi> (London, 1887), pp. 258-60; <hi rend="i">Blake
                                Records</hi>, pp. 278 f. and n. 3. Cennino Cennini gives an account
                            of how to take a cast of the face of a living person (Tambroni ed. 1821,
                            chs. 164-66; Milanesi ed. 1859, chs. 182-84). This is for taking the
                            face only, not the whole head, but in the following two chapters a
                            method is described for taking a cast of the whole body, or any part of
                            it, using a divided mold. It is tempting to believe that Deville used
                            this text as a reference in 1823.</note>
	<note id="n85"><hi rend="s">76</hi> Herbert P. Horne, <hi rend="i">Century
                                Guild Hobby Horse</hi> (1887), p. 27, quoted from David Bindman, 
<hi rend="i">William Blake An Illustrated Catalogue of Works in the
                                Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge</hi> (1970), no. 55.</note></p>
          <p>When Richmond said that this was the first cast Deville took he was almost
                        certainly mistaken. The National Portrait Gallery cast is inscribed:
                        “A. 66 / PUBd AUG. 1, 1823. I DEVILL [sic!] / 17 Strand, London.”
                        If the mold was also made about this date, it could hardly have been
                        Deville’s first work, since he, according to J. T. Smith, “when
                        a young man was employed by Mr Nollekens to make casts from
                            moulds.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86" type="note">77</ref>
Deville was born in
                        1776; would the devoted phrenologist really have delayed the making of his
                        first mold until he was about 47, although he was familiar with the taking
                        of casts from molds since his youth? It is indeed possible that the mold was
                        made much earlier than the National Portrait Gallery cast; Richmond, who
                        owned the undated cast now at the Fitzwilliam, said that Blake was about 50
                        when the mold was made. That would suggest a date around 1807, when Deville
                        was 31. <note id="n86"><hi rend="s">77</hi> John Thomas Smith, <hi rend="i">Nollekens
and His Times</hi> (1828), p. 371.</note></p>
          <p>Unfortunately, the “A. 66” on the National Portrait Gallery cast
                        must reasonably refer to Blake’s age when the mold was made. It is
                        true that he was 65, not 66, in August 1823, but the error could be
                        explained by assuming that Deville knew the year but not the day of his
                        birth.</p>
          <p>At present the evidence is hopelessly contradictory. Personally, I would
                        rather trust Deville’s inscription than the Richmond interviews.
                        Richmond met Blake in the spring of 1825, when he was 16; in 1807 he was not
                        born, and in 1823 he did not yet know Blake.</p>
          <p>On p. 268 Lindsay throws doubt on Richmond’s “edifying tale”
                        of Blake’s death because he “in a letter three days later says
                        nothing of having been in at the death.” In his letter 15 August 1827
                        to Samuel Palmer, Richmond wrote: “Just before he died His Countenance
                        became fair—His eyes brighten’d and He burst out in Singing of
                        the things he Saw in Heaven[.] In truth He Died like a Saint as a person who
                        was standing by Him Observed.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n87"
type="note">78</ref>
                        This is an eyewitness account. That Richmond did not expressly say “I
                        was there at the death” is only natural, because at that time no one
                        suspected that he was not. Later H. H. Gilchrist, quoting Richmond himself,
                        wrote that “George Richmond . . . closed the poet’s eyes and
                        kissed William Blake in death.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n88"
type="note">79</ref>
	<note id="n87"><hi rend="s">78</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi>, pp. 346-47.</note>
	<note id="n88"><hi rend="s">79</hi> H. H. Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Anne
                                Gilchrist</hi>, p. 258. The interview must have been after 1882 when
                            Linnell died, Samuel Palmer having died in 1881, since Gilchrist says
                            that Richmond at that time was the only living man who had seen William
                            Blake.</note></p>
          <p>Jack Lindsay is often careless in the handling of sources, and sometimes
                        seems to twist the evidence deliberately in order to discredit
                        “edifying tales spread about by the Ancients,” and make Blake less
                        offensively “Christian.” I think it is because Lindsay is
                        basically in sympathy with Blake that he tries to play down his
                        “spiritual side”—would he not have been an even grander
                        fellow, had he been an atheist? There is still every reason for Blake to
                        implore God to protect him from his friends.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p14-172-174" n="172-174" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
