<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.3.murray</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">G. E. Bentley, Jr., ed., William Blake’s Writings</title>
        <author n="Murray">E. B. Murray</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1980/1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980-81</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Stuart Curran</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Bo Lindberg</name>
              <name>Ann Bermingham Miller</name>
              <name>W.J.T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>E.B. Murray</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Hoyt Trowbridge</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980/1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-3-0006">
        <pb id="p14-148" n="148"/>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">G. E. Bentley, Jr., ed. <hi rend="b">William Blake’s
                                Writings.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1978. Vol. I, lvi + 745 pp.;
                            Vol. II, ix + 1080 pp. £ 65.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">E. B.</hi> <name><hi rend="b">Murray</hi></name>.</docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p><hi rend="i">Blake’s Writings</hi> is the natural yet transcendent
                        culmination of the monumental trilogy which Professor Bentley has been
                        constructing for us since he began his work on Blake some twenty-five years
                        ago. As the capstone to a library cromlech otherwise comprised of <hi rend="i">Blake
                        Records</hi> (1969) and <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>
                        (1977), it inevitably participates a good deal in the essential matter of
                        the double pillars which support it, and, as Bentley suggests, is meant to
                        be supplemented by them when economies of time, space, and editorial policy
                        curtail bibliographical description and certain annotative and referential
                        materials. The editor’s primary purpose here has been to
                        “present Blake’s writings in a form as close to his originals as
                        type will permit.” Volume I contains the engraved and etched writings,
                        with all (or nearly all) significant illuminations reproduced in black and
                        white. Volume II contains all writings in conventional typography and in
                        manuscript, including the letters and marginalia. The Introduction includes
                        a brief account of previous important editions, statements of purpose and
                        editorial methods, and is followed by comparably brief accounts of the
                        printing and coloring of the illuminated works. Typically, the
                        Bibliographical Notes for each illuminated work provide information about
                        date, publication, coloring, catchwords, order, significant variants,
                        errata, and copytext, with <hi rend="i">ad hoc</hi> notices of running
                        heads, designs, and plate sizes, as they seem necessary or helpful. The
                        Notes for the writings in conventional typography and in manuscript vary
                        considerably according to the demands of the text described, but generally
                        include location, watermark, leafsize, date, and description, with specific
                        notice as needed of copytext, page and line numbering, design, running
                        heads, full title page, collation, press figures, catchwords, corrections,
                        ornaments, stab-holes, and order, while certain works are provided with
                        selectively expansive commentary: <hi rend="i">Vala’</hi>s dating,
                        description, and variant handwriting; the <hi rend="i">Notebook’</hi>s designs,
                        description, and location. Supplementary
                        materials include a chronologically arranged table of contents which locates
                        both texts and corresponding bibliographical notes, a list and description
                        of lost works, a list of the source and location of each plate reproduced,
                        an alphabetized list of present-day locations of contemporary copies of
                        Blake’s writings, tables of ambiguously broken words, of repeated
                        lines and designs, along with keys (maps) to Blake’s London, Britain,
                        and Holy Land, and a preface containing about sixty addenda and corrigenda,
                        which selectively update through 1967 a text that went to press in 1971 and
                        achieved its galley-proof definition in 1974.</p>
          <p>In the body of the text each illuminated work is provided with brief
                        footnotes describing the design, variants in different copies (repeated in
                        the Notes), as well as cross references, verbal changes, and identifications
                        of people and places (usually historical or biblical). As a rule, the design
                        descriptions are physically representative and conservative rather than
                        symbolic and expansive, while the informational notes are relatively lean
                        when compared with, say, those in the Longman <hi rend="i">Complete
                        Poems.</hi> Volume II does not categorize its notes in the same way, but
                        it provides, when apt, essentially the same kind of information. With a few
                        exceptions, the design reproductions compare favorably with those in <hi rend="i">The
                        Illuminated Blake</hi>, though one may feel Bentley has
                        omitted some plates significant enough for reproduction, and one may lament
                        the fact that it was apparently necessary on 
<pb id="p14-149" n="149"/>
                        occasion to divide the top and bottom designs on a given plate by placing
                        them on successive pages. While the notes make no attempt at variorum
                        inclusiveness by providing a history of editorial readings and misreadings,
                        they do often (though perhaps not often enough) retail the textual
                        recoveries and alternative readings of David Erdman, at times with a hint or
                        statement that the Erdman eye has seen what Bentley does not believe is
                        strictly there to be seen.</p>
          <p>While there is still some disagreement about a very small number of
                        substantive readings in Blake’s illuminated works, the fact that for
                        virtually all their extant impressions there was in the beginning only one
                        (lost) archetypal source—the original copperplates—means that,
                        except for a few notorious scratchings out and maskings over and even fewer
                        verbal alterations, there is little question about the words of
                        Blake’s text from copy to copy, nor is there likely to be, even when
                        a substantive (e.g., <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>’s “Mne” and
                        “o’erfired”) balks all effort at extracting any definitive
                        sense from it. Perhaps Bentley or Erdman or another keen-sighted adept in
                        Blake and in mechanical aids to perception will recover an erasure here and
                        a blot-out there—or perhaps rectify a word or two on the basis of
                        relevant collations—but diminishing returns from this much-gleaned
                        field may hardly seem to repay the scholarly effort at work in it.</p>
          <p>The continuing uneasiness which must afflict the conscientious editor as he
                        moves from impression to impression of a given copperplate will most likely
                        be inspired by the punctuation. At first glance, several reproductions from
                        a single archetype may seem to provide an editor with the maximum
                        opportunity for a punctilious fidelity to an author’s text but, in
                        this instance, wind up providing him with a minimum temptation to take
                        advantage of it. What abstractly considered seems to represent an ideal
                        combination of author, illustrator, printer, and publisher—a
                        veritable fourfold vision of a canon from its conceptual origin in Eden to
                        its empirical dissemination in Ulro—disorganizes into a mere chaos of
                        variable signs and inferences, chance associations, and contextual guesswork
                        which not only makes a given editor (and his readers) the victim of the
                        impression he chooses to rely on but threatens besides to invite the spectre
                        of deconstructionism into the very sanctum of bibliographical objectivity by
                        making every editor his own copytext, at least insofar as it matters what
                        impression he decides to call his copytext. While times and expectations
                        have changed since Geoffrey Keynes could tell us that he was redeeming
                        Blake’s text from the multitudinous accretions of error piled on it
                        by previous editors in providing a thoroughly accurate text which, in
                        effect, ignores Blake’s pointing, it is not yet certain that times
                        and expectations have therefore changed for the discernible better. How far
                        beyond varying kinds and degrees of editorial ignorance have we moved, and
                        can we move, when we find both Erdman and Bentley in fundamental agreement
                        about one major premise at least—that there is no telling from copy
                        to copy whether a given point at a given place in a given work by Blake is a
                        comma or period, or, by logical extension, a semicolon or a colon?</p>
          <p>The fact that the problem is compounded beyond a given editor’s choice
                        of copytext may be briefly highlighted by noting the different pointing
                        inferred from the unique copy of <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> by Erdman
                        (E) in his “diplomatic” text (1965) and by Bentley (B) in this
                        present “reconstructable” one. That is, E reproduces the pointing
                        (or lack of it) as he reads it from the impression(s) he uses; B provides
                        italics and half-brackets to indicate where he departs from the pointing in
                        his copytext. (I assume throughout that B relies on his copytext even in
                        accidentals unless he tells us otherwise.) Ideally—or perhaps as a
                        matter of course—we would expect that two such editors exercising
                        their eye-sight on a single mirror image of the archetypal copper would
                        evidence a fairly high degree of correlation when their points were
                        juxtaposed and added up. In fact, the editors disagree about nearly one
                        third of the pointings possible in the three relevant plates. What may we
                        infer? First of all, that Blake’s pointing is often so ambiguous in
                        its appearance that there is no defining it except arbitrarily.
                        Consequently, we may suppose that the editors tend to read these ambiguous
                        points differently, for whatever subjective, objective, or contextual
                        reasons. There is of course the possibility that one editor sees more keenly
                        than another, but insofar as that may be an applicable criterion, it
                        probably does not generally enter into differing inferences about
                        punctuation marks. The relative daring which E displays elsewhere in some of
                        his suggested recoveries and the conservatism evident in B’s sometime
                        dismay at what E has so recovered may be ascribed to other causes than
                        eyesight, not all of which are bibliographically relevant. What may be
                        bibliographically relevant is the fact that E, in reproducing his diplomatic
                        text, confesses to “wobbling” perhaps more than he should have in
                        the direction of “usual expectation” when grooming Blake’s
                        dots and digs to the periods and commas of a letterpress edition. B, on the
                        other hand, may save himself and his readers) from a temptation to so wobble
                        by his use of italics and semi-brackets, which allow him to print a
                        functional reading text for a modern audience while still preserving for the
                        scholar the underlying text as B thinks Blake etched it and which the
                        scholar can then reconstruct at his need and leisure. The happy result may
                        then be that B here provides a more accessible diplomatic text because he is
                        not beguiled by his concern for modern expectations into departing from a
                        computer-eyed rigor exercised on behalf of a consistent determination of a
                        given appearance of a Blakean point, at least within the confines of a given
                        context. That is the way it might have been. It does not really work out
                        that neatly in practice, nor is there any unassailable argument in favor of
                        its doing so.</p>
          <p>To return to <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>, we may first note in passing
                        that here (as often elsewhere) substantive disagreements between B and E can
                        be definitively arbitrated in E’s favor: E’s “Not”
                        (10), “organs” (113), “the floods” (122),
                        “those” (146) are right, B’s readings wrong. Because the
                        copy rates in the upper percentiles among Blake impressions for its finely
                        etched clarity, a reviewer may take advantage of the invitation or challenge
                        provided by the numerous pointing disagreements between B and E by further,
                        if not definitive, arbitration, as a way 
<pb id="p14-150" n="150"/>
                        into more circumstantially focusing on one or more of the sources of those
                        disagreements. As I see them, E’s points are preferable in 11. 9, 40,
                        50 (after “not”), 62 (after “durance”), 83
                        (“tho’”), 105, 109, 125, 151, but in another twenty-odd
                        instances of disagreement B seems to me to have read the points as Blake
                        made them—e.g., 11. 18, 20, 58, 65, 69, 73, 112, 132, 175. At times,
                        even in this relatively clear impression, the pointing may be seen as either
                        B or E sees it (e.g., 80, 164, 171); at times they may both seem wrong
                        (e.g., 117 a semicolon or colon, 123 a period). On balance, B’s
                        punctuation looks most like what appears in the unique copy more often than
                        E’s does, partly because B more often allows us to have or
                        reconstruct the dot Blake seems to have made whereas E tends to opt for the
                        commas he and his anticipated readers may feel more comfortable with, though
                        this tendency is not so marked here as it is elsewhere. To what extent this
                        evaluation applies to other works will be partly indicated by what I say
                        later, but it should be noted at once that as the potential
                        “copy-texts” multiply, so do the variant apparitions of commas and
                        dots that dance before one’s eyes in the same place in different
                        copies. Given the high incidence of discrepant appearances of a given point
                        in different impressions from the same copperplate, it may well be that a
                        second copy of <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> could have sanctioned more
                        of E’s commas and fewer of B’s dots than the unique copy
                        warrants. Lo, what should an editor do? The answer may seem to
                        be—whatever he wants.</p>
          <p>Both B and E remind us, in their degree, that to supply punctuation is to
                        change it—and of course to change it is to change it. But if
                        it’s not a clear or consensus case that the mark Blake etched is a
                        comma or a period (as we may finally be obliged to call the indubitable dot,
                        even where it is fairly clear that Blake did not use it that way), how can
                        we be at all sure we are not changing his punctuation with every decision we
                        make? Even in supplying bracketed pointings an editor is often on the brink
                        of a misleading assumption simply because he is trying, however tentatively,
                        to suggest a needed relationship (according to modern needs, that is) which
                        may well have nothing at all to do with Blake’s asyntactical flow (or
                        blockage), and, who knows, may actually interfere with a submerged
                        rhetorical significance which a given reader might, if unaided,
                        apprehend.</p>
          <p>A related problem which may at first worry the editor and later occur to the
                        reader is that it is not at all clear that Blake was himself typically
                        concerned whether his etching tool discriminated a given point as a comma or
                        a period—whether in fact he distinguished between them either by
                        themselves or as bases for a semicolon or colon (or exclamation). What does
                        one finally make of those series and catalogs of epithets and names wherein
                        half the marks are well-rounded dots and half are stabbed out in the general
                        direction of a comma tail? Or how does one respond to a comparable series of
                        parallel phrases or clauses which initially separate their components with a
                        neat colon that evolves from point to point into a full-fledged exclamation
                        mark at series end? It may be that we are being so presented with a
                        progressive revelation of Blake’s growing emotional involvement with
                        his text and tool—something in the manner of Henry Moore’s
                        sculpting into his stone until the sky broke through—so that we might
                        engage all the more vitally in the immediacy of the poet’s creative
                        act. Perhaps. On the merely mechanical side, one may conjecture that not
                        only does a clearly imprinted comma in a given “best” or consensus
                        copytext look like a period in a few seemingly less preferable impressions
                        but also that it might have been made in the shape of a period in the
                        original copper. Peripheral hindrances to an accurate sighting on
                        Blake’s points appear in some impressions as stray splatter, wash
                        smudges, designing bits of vine, chaff, or pestilential blight, which,
                        depending on where they occur, could as well be dots and commas.</p>
          <p>As noted, B’s principles allow him to supply suggested punctuation as
                        he feels it desirable. More specifically, he supplies points where Blake had
                        none at all or he supplies alternatives to Blake’s ubiquitous dot as
                        he deems necessary. Besides the comparative virtues of this method as
                        already noted, another blessing is that intrusive signs of editorial
                        emendation are relatively minimal. But there are two main problems with the
                        method. The first, a side effect of the virtue just noted, is that stops
                        other than dots (or periods) will at times cry out with equal claim for 
                        <hi rend="i">ad hoc</hi> editorial attention. E.g., the interruptive
                        semicolon which Blake will occasionally plant between a subject and verb or
                        between a verb and its object. The second and more fundamental problem
                        deserves iteration: if one does not know whether a given point is a comma or
                        a period, how can he arbitrate his italics and semi-brackets into place with
                        any comfortable degree of assurance that he is living up either to
                        Blake’s syntactical guidelines, such as they may be, or to
                        one’s own editorial principles? If a comma in one impression appears
                        as a period in another (or even a dozen others), the reader may feel that he
                        is very nearly as much “at the mercy of the editor’s
                        judgment” in B’s text as he is in Keynes’. To some extent
                        these problems may seem to be resolved by the choice of copytext. But other
                        subliminal problems then begin to surface. Assuming that accidentals in
                        Blake might indeed have some authorial significance and therefore must be
                        presumed to have editorial significance, we may want a more exacting
                        justification of the choice of copytext than B (or E or anyone) provides
                        before we agree, plate by plate and line by line, that an editor has
                        exercised his judgment in such matters to, and perhaps beyond the limit of
                        the possible when he prefers copy O’s exclamation mark to copy
                        P’s colon. How does one decide whether the best text, as he sees it,
                        or the consensus text, as he arrives at it, provides him with the period he
                        may change to a comma or with the comma he cannot change to a period? Or can
                        one definitively wobble in such cases? And even if we agree that, roughly
                        speaking, the latest and least colored of many impressions (assuming that
                        <hi rend="i">that</hi> is an ascertainable choice) provides the best
                        overall guide to accident as well as to substance, may we be sure that
                        adherence to it in a given instance is not more the result of inertia than
                        of requisite collation? Or, what may be worse, a perfunctory adherence to a
                        principle of copytext selection which cannot really apply to Blake’s
                        methods of production 
<pb id="p14-151" n="151"/>
                        and dissemination? Given
                        the conditions of publication, couldn’t it be that an assumed best
                        text may in a number of clear instances be much less than best? When several
                        impressions may have equal authority, it may well seem that a species of
                        eclectic edition is the only way to go, however arduous a task in collation
                        it may be for the editor and however suspect the result may seem to the
                        bibliographical fundamentalist. B has had the unique opportunity, as he
                        tells us, of inspecting all of the extant copies of the illuminated works.
                        It is not so clear as it might be that he has made the best use of that
                        opportunity from plate to plate and from line to line.</p>
          <p>In order for me to make the best use of the space available, I’d like
                        to pin-point specific problems about pointing, as perceived and supplied by
                        B, which will as well suggest more comprehensive problems of editorial
                        principles and copytext. As a general rule, these specifics are
                        representative of a host of others I’ve accumulated, but I should
                        note that I am mainly concerned with pointing out grounds for further
                        editorial surmise rather than with pointing an invidious finger at the bulk
                        of B’s volumes. Lest my overall appreciation of this quite handsome
                        and painstakingly compiled edition be lost in the shuffle of my sometimes
                        captious highlights and comments, I should note at the outset my comparative
                        estimate of its worth: it is on balance the best complete edition of
                        Blake’s works currently available for both the scholar and the
                        serious reader. Following B, I make frequent use of E for comparative
                        purposes where his editions are specifically relevant. I also use customary
                        or easily interpreted abbreviations for Blake’s works.</p>
          <p>MHH 8: 34 “The rat, the mouse, the fox, the rabbet; watch the roots, /
                        The lion, the tyger, the horse, the elephant, watch the fruits.”
                        B’s principles allow him to do nothing with the interruptive
                        semicolon in 1. 1 but in 1. 2 allow him to remove the dot he sees before
                        each subject, including the one separating the parallel “watch”
                        predicate from its most immediate subject, “elephant.” The comma
                        he supplies could have been eliminated altogether according to his
                        principles and modern practice, though in so mediating extremes as he does
                        he perhaps comes closer to what may be an implicit Blakean and/or rhetorical
                        norm at this point. Of course “normative” punctuation, when
                        aligned with one of B’s principles, could also have prescribed here
                        the semicolon before “watches” retained above as having more
                        contextual authority, but it would have been as bothersome to the modern
                        reader to so supply it as is the preceding semicolon which is allowed to
                        stand. E maintains his diplomatic credentials here (and keeps his readers
                        comfortable) by seeing B’s dots as commas. Without moving farther
                        afield, one may note comparable interruptive semicolons which must be
                        retained in 6:par. 24, “When I came home; on the abyss of the five
                        senses,” and after “confirm’d” 12:par. 32, where
                        commas would probably have been provided if Blake had used dots instead of
                        semicolons. The apparent assumption behind such a distinction in editorial
                        practice is that Blake himself distinguished between semicolons and periods
                        in parallel constructions.</p>
          <p>MHH 7:par. 24 “with corroding fires [;] he wrote . . . ” The
                        semicolon seems arbitrarily supplied to break up a relation that 
                        <hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi> pointing suggests he meant: “corroding
                        fires” describes the process by which the writing was done. Admittedly
                        these are judgment calls which the brackets make rebukeable. Nonetheless, if
                        left unquestioned they may work their way into the reader’s (or into
                        another editor’s) mind to define a possible ambiguity that should be
                        kept intact. Again, both E and B supply a semicolon after
                        “shining,” 18:par. 65 (which becomes a period in the
                        Erdman/Stevenson edition), but the only point Blake supplies in this context
                        is the comma after “sun,” which not only separates “sun”
                        from “black” and “shining” but also intimates that these
                        adjectives should adhere with no further break to the “round it were
                        fiery tracks” following, a relation warranted by the blackness which
                        later rolls through the deep after coming from between the black and white
                        spiders who are revolving on the tracks. In effect, the comma which Blake
                        did supply is compromised by the semicolon he did not, and, again,
                        modernizing editors are led to accept a syntactical relationship opposed to
                        that which the poet not only provided, but might have meant to provide.
                        Comparable semicolons questionably resolving ambiguities appear in 
                        <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (M) a:22, where the semicolon after
                        “Cherubim” supposes that the “victims” are sacrificing
                        the Cherubim, a reading inferentially at cross purposes with M f:15, where
                        the “Females prepare the Victims.” The comma which Stevenson
                        supplies after “Sacrifice” seems preferable, if any point is
                        needed.</p>
          <p>M a:4’s “Woven” is followed by a semicolon in B, while E
                        places a period before it. A likely inference is that no punctuation would
                        best aid the reader when editors so sparing of their points and changes
                        differ so radically about the syntactical relation of the word. Again, even
                        tentative punctuation becomes a species of editorializing a meaning rather
                        than aiding the reader towards a correct understanding of Blake’s
                        intention here. M 20:56— both B and E suppose an apostrophe after
                        “Witnesses,” a crucial supposition, particularly since it denies
                        Blake the comma he apparently had placed here for a usual purpose in his
                        practice: to introduce a quoted (or implicitly quoted) statement. Taken with
                        the fact that Blake seldom provides possessive apostrophes, such practice
                        suggests that the mark should be read as the comma it looks like. It can
                        then introduce the lines following (57-58) which probably should be read as
                        the “cries of the Churches,” with or without the consequent
                        punctuation which B perhaps misleadingly supplies. Contiguity and an
                        understanding of Blake’s irony at this juncture will make the reading
                        of the point as a comma preferable to some, even to more than some if the
                        point is allowed to stand as and where Blake made it.</p>
          <p>M 3:25 and <hi rend="i">passim</hi>—Seven times in six plates Blake
                        admonishes: “Mark well my words! they are of your eternal
                        salvation.” There is almost no correlation among the points used in the
                        same place from one reiteration to another. Nor does there seem to be any
                        editorial consistency in either following or providing punctuation, with the
                        most notable instance of such discrepancy evident in the two places where
                        Blake does point the line the same 
<pb id="p14-152" n="152"/>
                        way by supplying nothing at all. But B puts an exclamation after
                        “salvation” in a:20, a period after “salvation” in 7:7.
                        Why? I doubt whether an acceptable rationale can be found, except one based
                        in the precedent found in Blake’s own utter lack of concern for what
                        points he used from context to context. But to that precedent there is no
                        end of consequences, even to abolishing altogether the need for any attempt
                        at providing such “aids” for the modern reader. What one does find
                        highlighted here is the previously noted limits of B’s bracketed
                        punctuation. Since he can only provide points where there are either periods
                        or no points at all, he must be content to let punctuation stand which he
                        probably would not prefer if his editorial principles had not bound him to a
                        species of syntactical inconsistency. Again, while it might have been better
                        to have left the <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> drafts as unpointed as Blake
                        wrote them, the points that are supplied should probably be those that Blake
                        used (or B supplied) in the etched versions. E.g., if B reads an exclamation
                        (it may well be a colon) after “Dream” (1) in the illuminated
                        “The Angel,” why not supply that inferable Blakean pointing in the
                        draft rather than supply a comma? The likely answer may well suggest the
                        bibliographical weakness of the principle behind it, or at least a
                        <corr type="emend">discrepancy</corr> between the effect of following the principle
                        and of following
                        Blake. The principle is to aid the modern reader according to his
                        expectations in a given context. But the given context for Blake ultimately
                        fulfilled <hi rend="i">his</hi> expectation by providing <hi rend="i">his</hi>
                        emphasis (or syntactical division), which the modern reader
                        must (and really does) accommodate. However, in fairness, I should note that
                        B generally does supply in the <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> the pointing he
                        either finds or provides in the etched texts of the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>
                        poems.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, 88—“And says” is followed by a
                        semicolon; in 93 “and said” is followed by a period. B can,
                        according to his principles, bring the period into line with modern
                        expectations by providing a colon to introduce what was said in 93, though
                        he cannot do that in 1. 88 because Blake has, with characteristic
                        inconsistency, introduced a comparable locution by a point other than a dot.
                        The incongruity is apparent in contiguous contexts, but since
                        “says” and “saids” etc. are followed by all manner of
                        pointing <hi rend="i">passim</hi>, why bother cleaning up an occasional spot
                        when the overall result only makes the mess left untouched all the more
                        conspicuous? <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 3:21 reads “That cause at length
                        mov’d Milton to this unexampled deed” in copy A, but, as B
                        notes, was mended in the copper to “What cause” for copies B-D. B
                        chooses to accept the original “That” over the copper emendation
                        and therefore supplies a period at the end of the clause, where Blake had
                        supplied nothing at all. E, whose preference in this instance seems
                        preferable to B’s, prefers the copper emendation and so concludes
                        with a question mark (unbracketed). Even if “That” is preferred,
                        it would seem that Blake’s no-punctuation at line’s end is
                        better than anything supplied. Perhaps a comma would aid the reader a bit;
                        the period supplied by B may obscure a connection between this line and what
                        follows which Blake may care to intimate.</p>
          <p>M 20:7, 9—The only discernible difference between the colon B reads in
                        7 and the semicolon he reads in 9 is that the first may seem to have a
                        slightly smaller lower dot (though in “B” even that distinction
                        seems missing). As a general rule, B implicitly accepts the fuller bottom
                        dot as the sign of the comma which makes a semicolon in such cases, though
                        this principle, relative at best, seems variably defined and applied from
                        context to context. Size differences between dots vary in different
                        contexts. And the alternative criteria of rhetorical suggestiveness and
                        modern desirability may tend to jaundice the eye somewhat so that it sees
                        what best fits the apparent needs of a given syntax. On occasion, these
                        inferable rules of thumb may contravene each other—e.g., the larger
                        dot in 11 (M 20) is at the top, but B nods in favor of a modern tendency to
                        place a semicolon before anti-thetical “but” clauses, perhaps
                        gaining the slimmest warrant from a nearly discernible directional signal
                        which may be protuding comma-wise from the base of the lower and smaller
                        dot. Likewise, B (as E) has both context and modern usage on his side when
                        he overlooks the relatively adequate comma potential observable even in copy
                        B (more so in A) to read the lower dot as forming a colon after
                        “remain,” 20. Both B and E regularly accept a colon whose upper
                        dot is a bit higher on the page, and so more widely separated from its mate
                        below, as an implicit vertical forming an exclamation mark, when the context
                        or their sense of Blake’s rather expansive use of such tonal emphases
                        aids at filling in the requisite part of the empty space between. E tends to
                        opt for the shriek mark more often than B when such options are available.
                        Witness M 20:29, where E’s exclamations are reduced to the colons
                        which B’s copytext (and copy A as well) more nearly portray.
                        Arguably, the “high colon” may indicate a faulty imprint which an
                        editor is justified in filling in. Arguments the other way are obvious
                        enough. Sometimes a slight teardrop effect becomes a vertical for
                        exclamatory purposes when the context cries for one to modern
                        ears—“Awake Albion awake!” (M 22:5)—however unclear
                        it is that Blake necessarily preferred exclamations to colons in such
                        cases—either in practice or in theory. The apt Blakean comment on a
                        good many of these and kindred inferences from the problematically intense
                        inane may be found in the happily unpunctuated ambiguity of “what we
                        hope we see.” Another fairly common version of the exclamation mark is
                        one in which the dot actually appears to be a comma. Most likely this simply
                        means that Blake was negligent (though he does tell us that, however absurd
                        he thinks nonsense about dots is, he knows how to make them), as he is in
                        reverse when he provides periods rather than apostrophes to indicate
                        elisions etc. M 12:27 provides an equivocal case in point, where a dot
                        provides E with “earth’s” and B with “earths,”
                        probably because the context does not require a possessive and the dot may
                        therefore be supposed an accident. In impressions where there is evidence
                        that the imprint of the point did not take, one may check other copies not
                        only to see whether high colons are properly read as exclamations because
                        the upper dot has in fact expanded to a vertical but even to see whether a
                        healthy, fully-rounded dot in the best copies has not been partially
                        eclipsed in its lower half so that a quarter-mooned comma tail appears in
                        inferior impressions.</p>
          <p>M 20:19—In keeping with a general policy of 
<pb id="p14-153" n="153"/>
                        not supplying any point at line’s end when the next line begins with
                        a coordinating conjunction, B has none after “permanent.” E not
                        only has a period here but provides it unbracketed, indicating that he had
                        seen it in his copytext. Neither copy A nor B has anything here, so, if
                        E’s reading is not a mistake, then another copy may provide what
                        these two do not. There are of course a great many such discrepancies. And
                        this may not be the best of many possible examples but it should serve to
                        indicate the need for establishing a best or consensus text, even to the
                        given point, and letting the reader know what the evidence and the reasoning
                        are that went into an editorial preference when (apparently) equally
                        definitive alternatives are available. Without belaboring another kind of
                        point which may be extraneous here, isn’t the time at hand when
                        computer calculations about Blake’s multitudinous
                        “copytexts” for a given work and the “vagaries” of his
                        pointing can be made, collated, and inferred from, even if the end result is
                        at best merely a higher degree of correlation between the point preferred by
                        the editor and the one which Blake most likely etched?</p>
          <p>“Earth’s Answer,” 7—the supplied semicolon arbitrates
                        an ambiguity by associating “Cold and Hoar” with “I,”
                        when it may well belong to “den” or “Jealousy.” In the
                        <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> draft, B supplies a comma, which may indicate
                        some lessening assurance about what the adjectives are meant to qualify.
                        “Does the sower?” (18) may suggest a heavy rhetorical emphasis by
                        intruding a (rationally) redundant question mark in the midst of a sentence.
                        It is possible—particularly if Blake etched his end-line points after
                        he etched the text—that this rather poorly formed point was
                        implicitly aborted when Blake realized he wanted it to go after
                        “night” below.</p>
          <p>M 22:36—B catches a dot after “Albion” which E misses; but E
                        notes one after “Watch-Fiends,” 40, which B misses or ignores.
                        Always, there is the question of alternative copy texts which may justify
                        opposed readings. The colon after “seems,” M 26:45 is so clearly
                        there in copies A and B that one is tempted to infer that another copytext,
                        lacking the point, eliminated it from E’s syntax.</p>
          <p>M 27:54-5—The clear dot after “Month” is apparently read (by
                        B—E sees a comma) as if it were over the “i” of
                        “invulnerable” below. It is really too far up and to the right to
                        do that service, given the available option. The clear dot (read as a comma
                        by both B and E) after “Year” provides a parallel by way of
                        confirmation. It would be tempting, though misleading, to suppose that Blake
                        provided periods here, not elsewhere in the series, to suggest the elision
                        of the verb. But Blake’s pointing of any given series is a mixed bag
                        of dots and commas throughout, with no apparent differentiating function,
                        rhetorical or normative. (See, e.g., 27:33-34; 28:49.) In M 9:37 positioning
                        suggests an opposite inference about a dot’s purpose. The period B
                        reads after “Palamabron” really (as E must infer) dots the first
                        “i” of “Elynittria” in 38. The problem is (as the second
                        “i” demonstrates) that Blake dots his i’s with about as
                        much consistency as he points his series.</p>
          <p>VDA 134—B’s copytext does not have the question mark he places
                        after “lust”; it may, both in that and other copies, have the
                        exclamation mark which E provides, but it looks most like what in context it
                        may best be read as—a colon. In M 19:50 the barest hint of a question
                        mark has allowed B and E to perceive it into place as the context may seem
                        to need it, though a colon, an exclamation, or a semicolon would be more the
                        computer’s view of the mark Blake made after “repentance.”
                        Often the best choice may well seem “None of the above,”
                        particularly when he has created an impossible hybrid by placing a comma
                        under a vertical (VDA 187 provides a good example, visible even in <hi rend="i">The
                        Illuminated Blake</hi>).</p>
          <p>M 24:15—At times B seems to make the choice Blake should have made. As
                        E notes, it is a semicolon at line’s end, but the context of colons
                        which make up this catalogue of parallels seems to justify B against the
                        strict demands of the point as Blake made it, however he meant it. And does
                        Blake mean the distinctions his editors rightly note in such cases? In M
                        17:46-59 <hi rend="i">passim</hi>, B and E often disagree on whether a point
                        is a colon or an exclamation mark. Here, as generally, B is less likely to
                        take advantage of a highly placed top dot or a slight projection from it
                        towards the vertical, whereas E, who may after all be more sympathetic to
                        the rhetorical demands of the sigla, is abundant with exclamations.</p>
          <p>M 17:55—Given “A,” E is preferable with a comma after
                        “fibres,” but “B” tends to justify B’s
                        period.</p>
          <p><corr type="emend">M 11:40</corr>—The apostrophe in “namd” which both B and E
                        apparently saw is not really there in copies A or B, though these copies do
                        show one over the “e” in “toned” (not recorded by B) in
                        11:47. Given the comparable accent to indicate a pronounced “-ed”
                        in “used,” one may wonder whether Blake wanted the extra syllable
                        pronounced where he did not so indicate. But a typical lack of consistency
                        in such matters may be inferred from the “shudder’d” of M
                        12:33 and the “shudderd” two lines later.</p>
          <p>M 14:21—B and E agree in not seeing a comma after
                        “everything,” perhaps because it is partly obscured by the
                        “E” of “Eternity” below, perhaps because it separates
                        subject and verb. Such pointing could have its rhetorical purpose. More
                        anomalous is the comma which E places after “loud,” 14:45, but no
                        copytext I’ve seen justifies it, nor does B confirm it.</p>
          <p>M 22:61—An atypical example of B preferring the exclamation mark, E
                        the period, in a context where they both felt some point should be supplied.
                        M 10:24 is more typical, where the colon B seems properly to see and place
                        after “Jehovah thunder’d above” becomes an exclamation for
                        E. Four lines above E agrees with B in seeing a colon after the same
                        locution. While “Ecce signum” may be too often the cry of the
                        blinkered textual fundamentalist, it may be at least an appropriate reminder
                        now and then leveled at an editor prone to reading the spaces between the
                        dots where, in Blake, contexts elsewhere seeming to demand an exclamatory
                        emphasis are low-keyed by a mere period or even an indifferent comma.</p>
          <p>M 6:47—Both B and E read a comma here, probably because they would
                        rather not break up the sentence 
<pb id="p14-154" n="154"/>
                        after “Truth,” but a speculative reader straining to justify
                        Blake’s perhaps unjustifiable practice may support the clear period
                        the poet put here by suggesting that its purpose is to establish a kind of
                        enclitic emphasis for “Truth” which a terminal
                        point—particularly if it is understood as having no <hi rend="i">syntactical</hi>
                        justification—may provide. The same inference
                        may be applied to “Lie” in the line following. Admittedly such an
                        inference will have a limited application and must be allowed even within
                        such limits in the face of the conflicting and more easily demonstrable
                        inference that Blake let his points fall into shape as arbitrarily as the
                        chips from his copperplate defined them into dots or commas, colons or
                        semicolons. In 27:49-51, 55-56, Blake demonstrates that he will, though
                        rarely, place periods at line’s end before the conjunction
                        “And” when it introduces a clause. B, who does not typically
                        supply points in such cases, changes all but one of these to semicolons.
                        But, while this may provide some (really unnecessary) aid and comfort to the
                        modern reader because it falls in more neatly with modern syntactical
                        groomings, may it not for that very reason dissipate a rhetorical intention
                        that Blake might have felt and conditioned Blake readers may infer? Again, I
                        do not mean this as a criticism of B on principle—we can remove his
                        italics and restore Blake’s periods as we go—but I do suggest
                        that where these changes or supplyings are not really necessary, where they
                        arbitrate ambiguities better left to the reader’s discrimination of
                        relationships, or where they may lead a reader away from a rhetorical effect
                        plausibly inferred, they represent a dubious editorial intrusion, because
                        they do, however tentatively, represent an editorial authority. The crucial
                        editorial judgment involved must decide whether suggested punctuation is not
                        misleading punctuation.</p>
          <p>VDA, 114, exemplifies the necessary contradiction often involved in trying to
                        read Blake’s points according to the way they look. The exclamation B
                        and E read after “O Urizen” seems more a colon in the British
                        Museum Print Room copies but would gain exclamation status (on the principle
                        of the high colon) in copy E were it not that the required dot at the bottom
                        appears as a perfectly tailed Blakean comma, much more to that point than
                        the one which makes up (for B) the bottom half of a semicolon at the end of
                        this line. One can argue on one hand that “O Urizen” is clearly
                        exclamatory in its tonal suggestiveness, but one must also note that Blake
                        will in comparable passages provide alternative forms of punctuation. Here,
                        a contextual argument could be made for the colon, though, again, Blake
                        could as well have used a semicolon in such a context, as B’s
                        copytext seems to indicate.</p>
          <p>VDA, 122, suggests the infinite because utterly idiosyncratic rhetorical
                        potential of Blake’s pointing: “Does he who contemns poverty,
                        and he who turns with abhorrence / From usury: feel the same passion or are
                        they moved alike?” Had the colon been a period B likely would have
                        removed it on principle. But one wonders—Could Blake have actually
                        meant his colon here, as his dot elsewhere, to indicate a slow-down mark
                        which would have emphasized the opposition he was setting up between the
                        actions and passions of two quite different kinds of people? Of course here
                        as often the point (whatever point) provides for the breathing pause the
                        spoken lines may require. Insofar as Blake may be supposed to provide that
                        kind of rhetorical aid, supplied and omitted pointings tend to withdraw
                        it.</p>
          <p>M 2, 11. 9-12 of the poem—“gold” is followed by a point with
                        a big lower dot which elsewhere B would probably read as a comma (to make a
                        semicolon), particularly since it projects a bit of comma tail as well. But
                        since, as B sees it, all else is colon through here, he no doubt properly
                        goes along with the drift of the context. Even the concluding exclamation
                        (after “fire”) is rhetorically apt (though perhaps no more than
                        the three preceding it would be), but its top dot has little (if any) more
                        tendency to a vertical than does the one after “unfold” above.
                        Indeed E sees an exclamation in both places.</p>
          <p>“On Anothers Sorrow,” 27. Why supply a semicolon when the context
                        demands, if anything, a period? But this seems another case of rhetorical
                        and rational pointing working at cross purposes. The penultimate stanza here
                        is meticulously effective and, one would like to hope, purposely pointed,
                        whether one accepts B’s periods or E’s commas as
                        Blake’s points after the parallel “Think not”’s of
                        29 and 31. It reads quite beautifully if the pauses of the original
                        punctuation are observed and B’s suggested omissions ignored. The
                        last stanza contains a dot indicating a pause after “joy,” which
                        carries with it some of the weight on the exclamation after
                        “O”—and then Blake rushes to the poem’s end without
                        a point to hinder him or the reader. The run-on passage is particularly
                        effective after the slow and balanced cadence of the previous stanza. And so
                        one may wish away the semicolon supplied to break up the flow in 34,
                        particularly since the modern reader could get along without it, on other
                        grounds, as easily as he does in comparable places where B does not provide
                        a point.</p>
          <p>M 23:20—Copy B has a clear dot after “where” which justifies
                        B. In copy A there is nary a dot to be seen, which justifies E, who records
                        none. Since there is also in copy B a dot below the dot transcribed by B we
                        could assume that either we are in this copy presented with a fallen colon
                        or, more likely, that both dots are inadvertent. In either case, the
                        literalist of the text (copy B version) would seem obliged to note both dots
                        as having justifiable reason for being there, or ignore both as kindred
                        accidents. That they are likely accidents can be inferred—and this is
                        the point—by appealing to other copies for arbitration. If the other
                        copies supply the single dot, receive it with B; if not, ignore it with
                        E—and with, I suppose, confirmation from our normative willingness to
                        deny a point in a context where none is needed. (Note, however, that both
                        copies A and B <hi rend="i">do</hi> provide a likely colon before
                        “where,” which E and B agree in ignoring.) In another view, one
                        may forage around enough in available copies to come up with a point which
                        may seem better justified by modern expectations than that which exists (or
                        does not exist) in an elected copy text. There may very well be in copy A
                        the comma which makes a comforting appositive out of “Seat of
                        Satan” (before “Seat”) in M 24:45 and so E is 
<pb id="p14-155" n="155"/>
                        justified. But in copy B there is none, so B is
                        justified in not transcribing it.</p>
          <p>As already suggested, it will not always do to let the majority of
                        impressions of a given poem stand as the workable consensus to abide by,
                        since it is often clear that only the minority—perhaps only
                        one—of the impressions have received the fully definitive stamp of
                        Blake’s copper or are free from obscuring coloration, splatters,
                        encroaching tendrils etc., which will at times indeed seem to be just the
                        point one may care to require in a given context. Even within the copy which
                        seems on balance the best available a few points will be found that are less
                        than definitive relative to their reproduction elsewhere. Out of a myriad of
                        instances, one may note that a presumptive dot in the A and B copies of
                        “Garden of Love,” 3, after “midst” may tail off into a
                        barely perceptive comma in copy I but evolves more clearly in copy N, which
                        then confirms B here in his choice of a copytext rendition that better shows
                        it as it no doubt was on the copper. Still, one cannot therefore abide in
                        any given set of impressions merely because some or even most will provide
                        less obscured and uncertain pointings, since often a given plate in a
                        relatively superior copy will come a cropper for reasons which must be
                        ascribed to the nature of Blake’s reproductive process and
                        techniques. One may suppose, for instance, that the many flyspecks
                        surrounding and even filling in the gap between the colon after
                        “regale” in “Little Vagabond,” 6, required B to confirm
                        the point by reference to a clearer copy than N. Indeed the extraneous
                        mottles and dots on this impression at times make the words themselves
                        nearly illegible (cf. 11. 5-9). Again, since there really is no such thing
                        as a text whose reliability in matters of pointing is necessarily preferable
                        to others extant, the editor must call his dots as he sees them with a
                        counterbalancing pair of principles variably abetted by other
                        considerations: on one hand, the consensus reading; on the other hand, the
                        best text—even the best impression—even the best production of
                        a single point in a given context, where that seems ascertainable.</p>
          <p>The rhetorical license that Blake noted in the quite arbitrary pointings of
                        the editions of Bacon, Swedenborg, and the Bible that he was familiar with
                        could have served as precedent for the rationally frustrating uniqueness of
                        his own practice. But, as often, he went beyond his precedents. It is, for
                        instance, quite possible that he meant to imply a specific rhetorical
                        emphasis when he placed a dot between subject and verb—“One
                        thought. fills immensity.” Should any letterpress edition even suggest
                        our omitting it? Or note the effect of the dots as slowdown marks in
                        “Cradle Song,” 13-16: 
						<q>
							Sweet moans. dovelike sighs.<lb/>
							Chase not slumber from thy eyes.<lb/>
							Sweet moans. sweeter smiles.<lb/>
							All the dovelike moans beguile.
						</q>
						This is the way B actually read the
                        text (putting aside his italics etc.), and it is a good example of his
                        providing the diplomatic version that E does not, because E is attracted to
                        commas in most such cases, though his eye may indeed see more than his heart
                        knows, as I’d think was likely the case here. There is generally a
                        textual integrity in B’s dottiness that may be preferred to
                        E’s well-meaning accommodation to a modern expectation for something
                        less terminal than the dot <hi rend="i">qua</hi> period implies for the
                        modern reader. As already suggested, perhaps the best editorial expedient is
                        to retain such dots with the reminder to the reader that in Blake they mean
                        “slow”—sometimes “dead slow”—but hardly
                        ever “stop period”; and that their recurrence in a given context
                        after each word (as sometimes happens) merely means that that procession of
                        words should be paced according to the measured emphasis that the
                        poet’s “cadences” thereby imply, whether the dots hint at a
                        comma or keep their roundness unprojected. In “Cradle Song” an
                        excellent comma after “mild,” 7, could serve to call into question
                        nearly all the others that a given editor might care to find elsewhere in
                        this context. On the other side of the question, one may note that the dot
                        after “eyes,” 14, has as much claim to being a comma as others so
                        designated by both B and E, here and elsewhere. But, since it may seem that
                        every dot has a comma inside awaiting the editor who needs it, it is perhaps
                        as well that editorial consensus compensate for editorial disagreement when
                        the syntax in question is a matter of indifference, <hi rend="i">if</hi> it
                        is here. In “Nurse’s Song” (<hi rend="i">Inn.</hi>), the
                        mark after “play,” 7, and “play,” 9, is the same, and
                        could perhaps have led B to provide Blake with a consistency in commas or
                        periods which he perhaps aimed at here, though consistency about such jots
                        and tittles was not one of Blake’s hobgoblins, as a collation of the
                        following lines suggests: 
						<q>
							And their sun does never shine.<lb/>
							And their fields are bleak and bare.<lb/>
							And their ways are fill’d with thorns.<lb/>
							(B sees no point here.)<lb/>
							It is eternal winter there.<lb/>
							(“Holy Thursday,” <hi rend="i">Exp.</hi> 9-12)<lb/>
							<lb/>
							And I wept both night and day<lb/>
							And he wip’d my tears away<lb/>
							And I wept both day and night<lb/>
							And hid from him my hearts delight<lb/>
							(“The Angel,” 5-9)
						</q>
						One may perhaps
                        argue for different rhetorical intentions in the two passages, but the
                        argument would have to gain most of its substance from the ingenuity of its
                        advocate, since Blake himself seems blissfully innocent of weight and
                        measure here and quite beyond the nets or needs of rationalization. And
                        discriminating rationale for the present arrangement of dots and no-dots
                        could, if the pointing were reversed, find an esthetic or rhetorical
                        application for the reader intent on binding Blake to a contrary set of
                        insights.</p>
          <p>Besides those already noted, the following substantive and/or typographical
                        errors should be corrected as indicated. M 27:14, <hi rend="i">for</hi>
                        “or the Artist” <hi rend="i">read</hi> “or as the
                        Artist”; M c:3, <hi rend="i">for</hi> “into Space” <hi rend="i">read</hi> “into the
                        Space”; M 31, <hi rend="i">after
                        1. 3 insert</hi> “Towards America: India rose up from his golden
                        bed:”; J 29:19, <hi rend="i">for</hi> “Susex” <hi rend="i">read</hi> “Sussex”; J
                        39:25, for “Atonements” <hi rend="i">read</hi> “Atonement”; J 45:31, <hi rend="i">for</hi>
                        “hand” <hi rend="i">read</hi> “hands”; J p. 524 should
                        be renumbered; <pb id="p14-156" n="156"/>
                        J 77 (top of 588) <hi rend="i">for</hi>
                        “Spirit &amp; Truth” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
                        “Spirit &amp; in Truth”; J 96:34, <hi rend="i">for</hi>
                        “rouze up: Eternal” <hi rend="i">read</hi> “rouze up: rouze
                        up: Eternal”; VDA 6:66, <hi rend="i">for</hi> “yet their” <hi rend="i">read</hi> “yet
                        are their”; VDA 6:73, <hi rend="i">for</hi> “and” <hi rend="i">read</hi> “&amp;”; MHH
                        5:par. 19, <hi rend="i">for</hi> “were cast” <hi rend="i">read</hi> “was cast”; MHH
                        9:58, <hi rend="i">for</hi> “best water” <hi rend="i">read</hi> “the best
                        water”.</p>
          <p>There are some other queries about substantives which may suggest a need for
                        either change or further comment. M 25:53 is aptly read “The Thor”
                        by B. Nor do I see any Blakean reason for not accepting “The” in
                        this reference to Thor and Odin as opposed to the Gods of Priam and/or
                        Apollo and Hercules. But since the reading has been seriously questioned by
                        editors whose scrupulosity B praises, we should perhaps have a word noting
                        their preference here. J 89:26 “flocks” is “Rocks” in E;
                        again, a significant disagreement deserves a note, perhaps a justification
                        of preference. Generally the alternatives “spake” and
                        “spoke” are either used indiscriminately by Blake or they are all
                        meant to be “spoke.” A word on “a” and “o” in
                        Blake would not be amiss, since his o’s very often look like
                        a’s when it is clear they cannot be. B generally does provide
                        comments on E’s recoveries from apparently blank spaces or illegible
                        blots and scribbles—often cogently, given the evidence adduced, e.g.,
                        MHH par. 20 (on “the Devil”). Blake’s caps are often hard
                        to discriminate from his lower case initial letters—B and E often
                        disagree about them—but when the context backs the look of the letter
                        (consider “Stars” for B’s “stars” M 22:24)
                        consistency is probably the best editorial policy, even if it is not often
                        Blake’s (the “Spoke” so capped by B in M 23:43 seems much
                        less deserving of the distinction). There is also much disagreement and
                        perhaps some inconsistency in reading the expanded spaces Blake sometimes
                        placed (purposely or not) between his lines. See, e.g., M 19:11, M 23:66, J
                        30:32, J 40:51. These are the kinds of errors and discordances which an
                        edition of this magnitude and complexity may seem inevitably to fall victim
                        to. It could make one wish that highly significant and ideally definitive
                        editions such as this one could receive the kind of widespread and critical
                        reviewing in page proofs that they will as inevitably receive once the book
                        has passed into the marketplace.</p>
          <p>Manuscript disagreements and apparent errors are often more difficult to
                        arbitrate because of the state of the mss, often chaotic, often palimpsestic
                        in appearance. <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> 49, 51 (1060B), “our” is
                        probably “your.” 51N has some erased lines at the top which E
                        recovers and B discounts as illegible. The recovery seems reasonable, given
                        the equipment and persistence we know E brings to such a task, and probably
                        should have been noted for the reader’s consideration. Both B and E
                        read “whitlors” for Keynes’ “whitloes” on 61N
                        (1039B). The OED lists no “whitlors” but it does note that
                        “whitloe” (a variant of “whitlow”) means a finger tumor,
                        which is very likely what Blake is ascribing to the poor painters he is
                        referring to. For comparable “-es” endings see the two
                        “theres” on this page (“alludes” on 79N is still
                        closer); nor did Blake typically make his “r” as this one would
                        have to be (see “Booksellers” and “Dealers” below, 61N).
                        Since “whitlors” also appears in the <hi rend="i">Concordance</hi>, it may be that a
                        typographical error was the original of
                        this reading. E’s “turnd on” seems preferable to B’s
                        “turned upon” 84N (1020B). Were it not that B’s
                        “night” of 67N (967B) looks very much like a definite
                        “might” at the start of this poem, both its loops and context
                        would make his reading preferable to E’s. In 99N, E’s
                        “opened” seems preferable to B’s “opend” (970B).
                        In 103N, E’s “whereer” (“Holy Thursday,” 13-14)
                        accommodates better to the number of cursive strokes available than does
                        B’s “wherever” (976), as it better accords with the metre
                        and with the etched version. B’s “flourishing” (105N, poem
                        40E), may be preferable to E’s “flaming,” but it looks to
                        me more like “flowery” written over “flowering,” with
                        the “hair” following perhaps mended from “head” (978B).
                        A few lines later, no question that the “The” B queries in his
                        footnote was deleted. However, in 106N, “his little coat” (B)
                        seems closer to Blake’s script than “the little coat” (E)
                        (981B). 114N’s “Dreaming o’er” (E) seems justified
                        by the “o’er” a bit later over B’s “Dreaming
                        of” (998). 115N, for E’s “compelld” I prefer
                        B’s “compeld” (1001B); 116N, for B’s
                        “Reformation of” I read “reformation by”; (1003B); 119N,
                        for B’s “are as follows” I see E’s “are as
                        follow” (1006B).</p>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, p. 3, 1. 12, “Individual” was
                        accidentally omitted before “[Man <hi rend="i">del</hi>]”. V 8:6:
                        B seems correctly to retain “fierce” and delete 
                        <corr type="emend">“bright,”</corr> a decision reversed by E, 
                        who nonetheless accepts a comparable—and
                        perhaps confirming—change in V 9:36. V 9:8 reads “Deep”
                        (B), not “dark” (E), though the cap is doubtful. V 23:10, it is
                        pretty clear that, as E records it, Blake meant to retain the words which B
                        deletes. V 25:13, “the” (E) is preferable to “this” (B),
                        as the other “The”’s in this insertion indicate.</p>
          <p>In the Watson “Marginalia,” 1405, B notes that Blake wrote
                        “Hipocrisy” in his Lavater notes, 1365, but there B transcribes
                        “Hypocrisy.” On the Watson titlepage verso, Blake seems actually
                        to have written “is is not so,” perhaps meaning “it is,”
                        as B transcribes it, but could be a scribal redundancy; “attacked by
                        Paine” should probably read “attackd,” as it does in the 
<hi rend="i">Concordance.</hi> The supplied “[are the . . . ]”
                        should probably be reduced to a supplied comma—as the context
                        indicates, Blake is being elliptical here as a matter of expediency and
                        rhetorical form. There seems no need to modernize “Fals[e]hood” so
                        (1406, 1408); the spelling without the “e” was both common and
                        Blakean. Since B caps “Is,” why not in consistency cap
                        “blush” after the next supplied question mark (1406)?
                        “Conscience . . . Locke,” at the bottom of p. 2, should probably
                        be followed by “If Conscience is not” etc. Blake had no space for
                        it at the bottom of p. 2, so put it at the top of p. 3 (1407-08). The capped
                        “ON ALL OCCASIONS ACT RIGHT” should be preceded by an asterisk,
                        indicating its specific relation to the asterisked comment following (1408).
                        “Princip[le] another” should appear so; i.e., “le” was
                        not written out (1408). “Can any man who writes ?ill so pretend”
                        may better indicate what Blake wrote in the comment at the top of 1415. The
                        “?ill” is written over the catchword “Let” and may in
                        fact be an aborted “illiberally.” The two paragraphs of
                        exasperated comments about the “Public RECORDS” (1418) are in a
                        scrawl rather larger and more hasty than the hand which fills most of these
                        margins, and so suggest a 
<pb id="p14-157" n="157"/>
<figure n="LavaterAphorisms169.14.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="654" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>( 169 )<lb/>
	<lb/>
	502.<lb/>
	The more there is of gradation<lb/>
	in virtue, the more dramatic the<lb/>
	energies of goodness and benevolence,<lb/>
	the more sublime their<lb/>
	character.<lb/>
	<lb/>
	503.<lb/>
	No wheedler loves.<lb/>
	no fumbler kisses<lb/>
	<lb/>
	504.<lb/>
	Great minds comprehend more<lb/>
	in a word, a look, the squeeze of<lb/>
	a hand, than vulgar men in day-long<lb/>
	conversation, or the most assiduous<lb/>
	correspondence.<lb/>
	<lb/>
	505.<lb/>
	The more one gives, or receives,<lb/>
	or sees, or comprehends, in little,<lb/>
	the</figTranscr>
	<head>J. K. Lavater.</head>
	<figDesc><hi rend="i">Aphorisms On Man</hi>, page 169. Reprinted with
                                permission from the Huntington Library.</figDesc>
</figure> 
                        different time of composition and state of mind. On 1420
                        (Blake’s p. 29) the same hand sets in with comparable vehemence on
                        the same subject. The hand recurs from Watson 35 ff. <hi rend="i">passim.</hi> I
                        mention this in passing as a possible aid to dating.
                        B’s supplied exclamation in “a Question [!] Downright
                        Plain” (1420) probably separates “Question” from the words
                        that modify it—another instance of misleading editorializing. For
                        “Does he cast them off,” 1423, read “does he not cast them
                        off.” In Lavater, Blake seems to have written “&amp;c,” as E
                        reads it, not “v” as B transcribes it (1374 and note). I tend to
                        side with E (as against B and Keynes) in supposing that the
                        “Admirable” on 1352 is not Blake’s, and I agree with him
                        altogether that “No fumbler kisses” (1374) is not in
                        Blake’s hand, so far as I’ve seen it: neither the slant nor
                        the double-s seems characteristic. While Keynes prints both annotations in
                        the Nonesuch edition B refers to, he excludes “No fumbler kisses”
                        and queries “Admirable” in his later Oxford editions.</p>
          <p>There are as well a few notes and queries about the printed Blake works.
                        Generally B accepts the changes made in various copies of <hi rend="i">Poetical
                        Sketches</hi>, though not the “his” for
                        “her,” “Song,” 16, 757, which nonetheless seems
                        justified by the context, as in his Notes B seems to allow. The
                        “ere” in <hi rend="i">King Edward the Third</hi>, Sc. [iii], 10,
                        1783, should probably be retained because it makes good sense in the context
                        and is not changed in any of the copies. Whatever sanction Blake’s
                        sometime omission of the apostrophe may provide to justify B’s
                        “e’er” seems overruled on both bibliographical and
                        interpretive grounds. In the “Descriptive Catalogue,” “How
                        should he? he who,” 827 note, should probably have been retained in the
                        body of the text for the rhetorical emphasis Blake probably meant to suggest
                        by it. B apparently assumes a printer’s error rather than
                        Blake’s copy for the semicolon he replaces with a comma on 832 (and
                        note). This semicolon could have had contemporary warrant and is certainly
                        no more anomalous than others B is forced, on principle, to retain in other
                        contexts. A comparable change is made on 851, though, in a rhetorical piece
                        such as this, the semicolon may be apt. Throughout B has a tendency to
                        supply the text with questionmarks which do not, at least in their
                        perfunctory and rational appearance, suggest Blake’s practice. The
                        questionmark provided on 845 could better have been an exclamation, while
                        the change from exclamation to questionmark on 848 heavily qualifies the
                        effect Blake seems to have aimed at with his introductory “0.” In
                        the “marginalia” to Thornton, Blake offers a suggestive aphorism
                        about his rhetorical practice which may well justify B in retaining in his
                        text disagreements in number which he will (as in the “Descriptive
                        Catalogue” errata list) elsewhere note: “The Greek &amp; Roman
                        Classics is the Antichrist I say Is &amp; not Are as the most expressive
                        &amp; correct too.” This clarified use of a rhetorical grammar should
                        probably be kept in mind by editors wending their way through the rational
                        solecisms of Blake’s syntax at large. The Thornton marginalia would
                        likely come into clearer perspective with closer study than it seems so far
                        to have received. In a brief glance at it, I note that “but [his] /
                        Satans / Will / who is” seems rather to be “but [his will who is]
                        / Satan’s who is . . . ” (1516). In the “French
                        Revolution,” the change of “war-living” to “war,
                        living” (or “war—living”) in line 283 really has no
                        justification and manages to dismantle an effective compound adjective in
                        the process.</p>
          <p>B’s ordering within and among the texts may have both its problems and
                        its merits. He must of course <corr type="emend">abrogate</corr> the page order of the
                        <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> in order to print “The Vision of the Last
                        Judgment,” the “Public Address,” and “The Everlasting
                        Gospel” integrated pretty much in the order Blake probably meant for
                        them. But individual pages within the <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> will
                        continue to provide grounds for a reconsideration of a given order. In this
                        version of “I saw a Monk of Charlemaine” Blake might have meant
                        the three stanzas on Voltaire and Gibbon to serve as a kind of integrating
                        refrain or chorus meant to appear at different parts of the poem rather than
                        as variants of each other best placed one after the other, as B has them.
                        The passages seem more to gloss reciprocally or progressively rather than to
                        replace each other, as B suggests (928 note); the 1. 7 change from 
<pb id="p14-158" n="158"/> 
                        “barons bold” to “Learning
                        rolld” would have a valid rhetorical rather than a possible esthetic
                        justification if such an inference were preferred. The marginal placing of
                        the passages may indicate that Blake intended them for distribution here and
                        there within the poem, but as B notes, there is no certain indicator of
                        where, and it may be that any editorial arbitration other than that
                        suggested by B would be a hazardous presumption. Still, it is worth noting
                        that contiguity alone was all the indication Blake relied on to place
                        comparable marginal inserts on pp. 54 and 98. B seems correct in reading the
                        line through “For the tear is an intellectual thing” as a
                        separation rather than deletion line. The lead-in catch phrase, “A tear
                        is an &amp;c,” seems to confirm the inference and the order. Another
                        positive use of a comparable phrase appears in the insertion of the
                        “Raphael Sublime” couplets (<hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> p. 39)
                        after “Raphael Sublime &amp;c” p. 1 “Public Address”
                        (1029). It might have been preferable if B had taken advantage of yet
                        another such cue, “Was Jesus Chaste or did he &amp;c” (p. 54), to
                        supply the appropriate passage from p. 48 where Blake apparently wanted it.
                        It would probably have aided the reader if B had been more forthcoming about
                        reorderings which may well be justified but are not obviously
                        so—e.g., the separation of “Commerce is so far” etc. (1037)
                        from the preceding part of its page (57), also concerned with Commerce, that
                        B places on 1034. Other problem pages whose ordering in B may deserve
                        rethinking include 62, 66, 67, 92.</p>
          <p>On p. 76, the context and the separating diagonal indicate that “Ishmael
                        is Mahomet” should be placed before, not after, the interpolated
                        “Abel kneels” etc. On p. 81, “at their head” should
                        probably come before “little infants,” which in fact the logic of
                        the caret and its insert suggests. “The Aged Woman is Britannica”
                        etc. should likely follow “began,” as the final recension of
                        Jerusalem etc. which is deleted in the margin. This does bring about the
                        interesting but not unblakean division of Jerusalem (as the bride of Albion)
                        into the Aged Woman and her daughter. That relatively characteristic anomaly
                        may be preferable to an ordering which would somehow place the Aged
                        Britannica, who is the aged wife, at her own head, since she is one of the
                        referents of “their” in “at their head” as B (and E)
                        receive it. I would also suggest, on the same page, that the internal logic
                        of the description would be tighter if “The Aged Figure . . . Oaks of
                        Albion” passage to the right of the emblem were placed <hi rend="i">after</hi> “coming
                        in the Clouds.” Blake first describes what
                        is above Noah, then what is around and beneath him, and finally adds the
                        description of the “Aged Figure” who is taking account of the
                        “various figures Risen into the Air.” The progression on p. 82
                        seems to support such an ordering. Blake wrote down the left side of the
                        emblem until he could write across the entire page. I.e., he did not go
                        first to the right of the emblem and then to the bottom of the page. B
                        provides more or less justifiable orderings in the illuminated works which
                        will at times make it a little harder to use his text with the 
<hi rend="i">Concordance</hi> and with references to the Erdman and Keynes editions.
                        Doubtless certain of his decisions will be queried—whether he has
                        rightly placed the conclusion of the Natural Religion plates, whether in
                        Vala he has correctly ordered 12:26-29—whether indeed a strictly
                        chronological ordering of the canon itself is preferable to, e.g., a
                        thematic approach such as E uses, or to what extent such an ordering can be
                        strict. Personally, I prefer <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> VIIb in context rather
                        than in an appendix, and so prefer B to E in this idea of order from both an
                        esthetic and bibliographical standpoint. At times, however, B’s
                        bibliographical assumptions do not seem cogent, even when his conclusions
                        may be warranted. E.g., in his discussion of the plate order for MHH (694) B
                        supposes that the order for copy G is only a temporary aberration from a
                        conventional order, used in all clearly authoritative copies other than G
                        and specifically reaffirmed by copy I which must have come after G because
                        of its 1825 watermark. But an 1815 watermark hardly precludes a post 1825
                        date for what appears on its paper and the fact that Blake numbered the
                        pages may seem to give his authority to the order when only one (perhaps
                        two) copies can be placed in opposition to it. I am not so much denying the
                        consensus likelihood of the order in copy I as I am questioning the
                        assumptions which attempt to establish the order beyond valid argument to
                        the contrary. If B’s conjecture that copies G and I were both colored
                        about 1827 is correct—because of their similarity—there may be
                        good reason in that alone to assign equal authority to the copy G ordering,
                        particularly if one also assumes that the G numbering was done at the same
                        time. The question then may be whether the G order is not actually
                        preferable because it represents what may very well be Blake’s
                        latest—not simply a late repetition of his earliest—thoughts
                        on ordering. One may then precede to the no doubt dubious but still, in its
                        degree, valid argument from internal evidence: Is there any reason inferable
                        from the text for Blake to have finally preferred the G order? Perhaps worth
                        pondering.</p>
          <p>As noted, the design reproductions are roughly comparable in quality to those
                        in <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi>, perhaps better on balance, worse
                        in a few obvious instances (e.g., MHH 1, 10, 16, 24, J 99, 100). One misses
                        the colors but must be pleased with a readable text pictorially supplemented
                        as Blake designed it to be. B himself provides a verbal supplement to the
                        designs which highlights what we can see well enough anyway but B sometimes
                        misses what may be less apparent or perhaps only apparent in a copy other
                        than the one which B chooses to reproduce and describe. There is nothing
                        here like the detailed rumination which E provides, partly at least because
                        interpretive analysis would not accord well with B’s editorial
                        principles. It is not always clear whether a given description applies to
                        the reproduction, to the copytext (they are not usually the same), or to a
                        representative text which may not be either. For instance, while the
                        copytext does depict a “Black boy” in “Chimney Sweep”
                            (<hi rend="i">Exp.</hi>), the boy in the reproduction is white-faced,
                        while in some variants (such as copy A) his hair looks like Tom
                        Dacre’s before it was shorn. As this last suggests, the space used
                        for merely describing what we can see may be—perhaps sometimes
                        is—better used to tell us all we need to know about significant
                        variants. The VDA reproductions and commentary make up a particularly
                        convenient case in point because B used the same copy (E) for the copytext
                        and the designs. While B does discriminate five figures 
<pb id="p14-159" n="159"/>
                        in plate 2’s rainbow (I can only find four), he does
                        not note the humanoid potential of the two rocks in the lower right. Nor,
                        under Variants, does he note that in copy O, apparently the most worked over
                        and clarified of the copies, the rocks not only take on the human form
                        distinguishable but provide a pictorial reprise of the Theotormon figure of
                        the frontispiece, his head buried in his arm. The other figure, bending over
                        at the waist with hair and arms hanging limply down, would then seem to be
                        Oothoon. Such appearances should be saved, even if they do not appear on
                        representative impressions, particularly since here they indicate the object
                        of the conjuror figure’s attentions. He is, in effect (isn’t
                        he?), converting the “Human Form Divine” into “Shapeless
                        Rocks.” At least the reader should be allowed the possibility of making
                        that inference. In plate 3, under verbal variants, B notes “Three
                        obscured words to the right of Albion” which should probably be
                        assigned instead to plate 2. B should have reported the variant of plate 4
                        in copy C which shows the spread-winged (or -armed) figure rising up behind
                        the woman dreaming on the cloud. Or, if he felt the variant form apocryphal,
                        he should have noted and explained such an inference. While copy E does
                        suggest the possibility that the woman in plate 8 is wearing a “long
                        skirt,” several other perhaps more representative copies suggest the
                        more likely possibility (given the text) that she is covered by bedclothes.
                        Nor does copy E show as clearly as copy O the plate 10 fourth figure that B
                        is uncertain about. Its fingers are well defined in copy O. Presumably this
                        copy—the Robinson copy—is one of the latest. Since, along with
                        another late copy (P), it contains the more clearly humanized and defined
                        figures, couldn’t a strong argument be made in favor of preferring it
                        as the basis for deciding on Blake’s latest and best pictorial
                        intentions in VDA? Retrospectively, it may indicate what Blake meant to
                        suggest by less obvious symbolic impressions in other copies. (I am myself
                        convinced that plate 7 of copy O defines the Contours of Theotormon’s
                        hair into a profile of Bromion’s head which looks up at Oothoon and
                        effectively illuminates her lament that none but Bromion can hear her
                        words.)</p>
          <p>The congenital ambiguity inherited from the originating copper and cloned
                        into the various impressions of a given work may at once defy and justify
                        editorial judgments. As already suggested, such ambiguity can be as much
                        compounded as resolved by the choice of copytext, partly because the elected
                        text may show plate to plate variations in quality that makes an overall
                        reliance on it at best a calculated risk. B states that he
                        “normally” chooses his “copy texts where the etched text is
                        clear, uncoloured, and not clarified by hand,” with specific priority
                        given to posthumous copies because they reflect the last state to which
                        Blake brought his coppers and can be seen “unaffected by colouring or
                        changes of mind in the process of printing or correcting.” Since 
                        <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> copy B is neither the latest nor an uncolored copy,
                        it is not clear why B preferred it, nor indeed is it clear, in substantive
                        matters at least, that he typically did prefer it when alternative copies
                        provided other readings.</p>
          <p>Generally speaking, B seems to opt for the unmended readings wherever they
                        may appear. Although in M 3:21, copies B-D contain the mended copper reading
                        “What” as Blake’s latest (some may feel best) choice, B
                        prefers “That” from copy A. Likewise, to have preferred his
                        copytext (and copies C and D) to copy A in M 24:60 would have eliminated a
                        line which to most readers might seem necessary. However, if the erasure of
                        the line is Blake’s, it would seem that his last intention was to
                        omit it. A comparable—or seeming—attempt in copy B at erasing
                        a grammatically unwarranted “s” in “sweets” M 31:46 goes
                        unheeded and unnoted, and, given Blake’s rhetorical indifference to
                        such matters, may confirm an apparent suspicion that other hands were at
                        work in mending Blake’s impressions to suit another sense of
                        propriety. Kindred mending might have changed M 23:66’s
                        “raving” to “?roaring” in copy B, another change in his
                        copytext which B notes but overrules. B also retains the clause which joins
                        M 4 and M 5 in copy B, though suggests that it might have been eliminated in
                        the copper for the latest printing in copy D. At times the crucial decision
                        may not be so much what Blake’s last intentions were but whether or
                        not they should be accepted as definitive. An ambiguous but well-known case
                        in point involves the restoration of certain words in J 3 which were in the
                        original copper but cannot be justified by an appeal to any copytext
                        impression. B places them in footnotes, along with predictable misgivings
                        about some of E’s recoveries in this context. It probably would have
                        benefited the common reader and would not have discomfited the scholar if
                        the deleted words which B accepts appeared (perhaps in italics) in the body
                        of the text, given the enabling if not identical precedent provided by the
                        inclusions in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> of material later deleted. Perhaps
                        this is the place to suggest that B’s recurrent unwillingness to be
                        convinced by E’s confidence or certainty about his many recoveries of
                        inferences about lost words will receive varying degrees of support from
                        those who follow the hunt through the texts which these editors have
                        scrutinized to see or not to see what Blake might have written. B’s
                        caution may seem to be the ideal complement to E’s sometimes
                        hazardous attempts at rescuing the apparently irretrievable from the outer
                        darkness in which Blake either accidentally or purposely left
                        it—particularly when he in turn supplements his caution by noting
                        E’s readings of what he finds illegible. The reader will thereby know
                        where the cruxes lie and the scholar may then attempt to resolve them when
                        in the presence of the originals containing them.</p>
          <p>A few other problems of copytext may be briefly noted. Given the grammatical
                        idiosyncracies of Blake and his possible precedents—and given his
                        insistence on the exact and exacting cadences of his line—the change
                        from an admittedly troublesome “Why have thou elevate” (J 34:10)
                        to a more easily justified “Why hast thou elevated[?st]” should
                        probably have been made in the footnotes, not in the body of the text. It
                        has no textual authority, and does not seem to correct a scribal (or
                        etching) error. As noted previously, discrepant and perhaps erroneous
                        pointing may result from the use of a copytext which, in a given instance,
                        is misleading. VDA, 60, does indeed have the dot after “hears” as
                        noted by B, but, from among the several copies I’ve seen, it appears
                        only in copy E, and may well be a splotch or anomaly peculiar to that
                        impression alone. 
                        <pb id="p14-160" n="160"/>
                        The inference is—and it
                        is elsewhere inferable as well—that something is not necessarily
                        better than nothing if it fails to gain representative support. VDA, 99,
                        concludes with a semicolon for E, nothing at all for B, and, in the British
                        Museum Print Room copies, a colon for me, one which I would diminish either
                        to a dot or comma using only the copy E copy-text that B apparently relies
                        on. But in this instance there is <hi rend="i">something</hi> there, though
                        B likely overlooked or ignored it because in his copytext he could
                        legitimately suppose that the miniscule and faded dot that imprinted from
                        the copper was in fact a part of the rather flaky smudginess which runs up
                        the margin just to the right of the text. A further inference: the copytext
                        here is neither best nor can it be easily seen as representative. The
                        indicated moral: other impressions must be checked and, where they clearly
                        provide better readings, preferred.</p>
          <p>VDA, 165, suggests the need to look around for a “best” text for a
                        given reading when there is some evidence that a specific or even consensus
                        copytext may be at fault. The word “sleep” ending this line is
                        followed by a readily discernible dot in copy E and so B accepts the point
                        as a period. The only copy I’ve checked which clearly justifies
                        E’s colon is copy O because it is only in that copy that the upper
                        dot comes through with any distinction. It is otherwise faded and smudged at
                        best. But since the “p” at the end of “sleep” likewise
                        suffers a noticeable attrition in other copies, the editor doggedly in
                        pursuit of the point Blake made might have been alerted to the need for
                        nosing about for a copy which rounded out a better “p.” In copy E
                        the “p” lacks its loop except in the merest impression, and a
                        comparable mereness barely ghosts in the upper dot of the colon which copy O
                        clearly defines. Admittedly, such pains may seem hardly worth the taking if
                        the instances are supposed isolated. But in the first place they are not,
                        and in the second place—if an editor supposes instead that
                        Blake’s pointing does matter in its minutest particular—or
                        even that it <hi rend="i">may</hi> matter-then he must draw very heavily on
                        his reserves of both patience and perspicuity to ferret it out at its best
                        or most likely. VDA, 107, suggests how infinite those reserves may have to
                        be. If one had decided that copy O’s clear colon in 167 gave its dots
                        a necessary priority over vacuity in other impressions—or if he had
                        only copy O to rely on—he would place a dot after the “And”
                        in 107, on the grounds that there is ample evidence that Blake’s
                        pointing does not abide rational questioning. But, fortunately, copies A and
                        B would be near at hand to provide here a void editorially preferable on
                        every logical ground. In the long run, the problems and the contradictory
                        solutions available for them probably exceed even a theoretic comprehension,
                        much more any set of workable editorial principles.</p>
          <p>A significant variant worth noting because it may affect decisions about the
                        relative dates of the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> copies appears in 1. 4 of
                        “The Lilly” in copy B. Whereas in copies A and T, e.g., the word
                        “bright” at the end of the line is etched in with a left-serifed
                        “g” in correspondence with the other g’s on the
                        impressions, in “B” an unserified “bright” has been
                        written into the text. If this is the only impression containing a variant
                        “g” of this sort, there may be grounds adduced for supposing that
                        it was also the first impression Blake made from the copper. He seems to
                        have rubbed out the foliage encroaching on the line in which he wanted
                        “bright” to appear in an initial attempt to get the space to
                        accommodate it. When he found out he could not do that to his esthetic
                        satisfaction, he put it instead in the position of a catchword below the
                        line. Since in other copies I have seen the marginal foliage is intact on
                        line with “beauty” (nearly touching it in most cases), it would
                        seem that they were made after the initial trial and error of “B”
                        had located the received positioning of “bright” under and to the
                        right of “beauty.” On another dating matter, it seems a perverse
                        reading of the evidence to suppose that a “clear postmark date of 28
                        August” 1799 on a Blake to Trusler letter “must” be a mistake
                        because it contradicts the written date of 23 August. If there is other
                        evidence to support this decision, we would seem to need it. Again, the
                        contradiction between an 18 October 1791 letter and the “7” which
                        makes up “the only really clear part of the postmark” might be
                        suggestively resolved by supposing that the writer (Reveley) misdated the
                        letter by one day. While the facts perhaps cannot be “reconciled”
                        definitively, a reader could be aided towards a likely inference if he were
                        told whether the legible “7” might have formed part of a
                        “17.” Or he could be kept from that speculation by being told
                        otherwise. Certain other problems of dating—particularly of possible
                        early drafts of early poems—must probably remain forever in the realm
                        of mere speculation, though it is difficult to believe that Blake wrote none
                        of the texts of his illuminated works much earlier than present dating
                            suggests.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See my “Thel, <hi rend="i">Thelyphthora</hi>, and the Daughters of Albion”
                            (forthcoming
                            in <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>), wherein I demonstrate the
                            derivation of Blake’s title (θηλ means “female”) from
                            a book advocating polygamy which was published in 1780-81.</note></p>
          <p>A few concluding queries. How likely is it that Blake meant to write
                        “o’er-fired” in <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, 29, when the word
                        has application only to ceramics (according to the OED), would seem to
                        contradict the sense of its context, and may well be of a piece with
                        non-words like “sendinding” (J 88) and “Chastitity” (J
                        94), which B rightly emends in the text? Admittedly, B’s inferable
                        principle in such a retention is in itself unobjectionable, but one may wish
                        that both rational and esthetic considerations had led him to place
                        “o‘erfir’d” in the footnote,
                        “o‘ertired” in the text. “Anglus” may, as B
                        suggests, refer to Robert Hunt (1051), but there is perhaps better
                        contextual evidence in the <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> for supposing that it
                        refers instead to the generic “taught” Englishman who is “so
                        used to Journeymens undecided bungling that [he] cannot bear the firmness of
                        a Masters Touch.” Is it possible to establish in a repeatable way the
                        precise measurements of the plates which B provides as a way of deciding
                        which ones appeared back to back on the same copper? I do not at all call
                        into question the brilliant work of this sort which went into B’s
                        classic essay on the masking of <hi rend="i">America</hi>, but do find my
                        own measurements (and Bindman’s) sufficiently at odds with B’s
                        to create some doubt whether millimeter accuracy is attainable on a level of
                        consensus. Is it perhaps more likely that the engimatic letters below the
                        text in MHH 6 are “MOH” (with a possible “H” inferable
                        as well from the blur following) rather than “WOH,” as B suggests
                        (79-80)? That rendition would have the relevance of abbreviating the
                        poem’s title. Finally, I note a proof-reading error, 684, where 
<pb id="p14-161" n="161"/>
                        <hi rend="i">Exp.</hi> 50 is accorded the roman letters which belong to
                        51.</p>
          <p>Many readers who ponder these volumes will be variously afflicted with a
                        certain sense of disappointment, tempered, however, with the recollection
                        that, in terms of the editorial purposes and assumptions set forth in his
                        introductory matter, Professor Bentley has fulfilled his promise, if not,
                        altogether, our hopes for a fully serviceable text and textual commentary on
                        Blake’s work. What is certain is that, in a multitude of ways, future
                        editors of reading texts and anthologies are bound to profit from the
                        immense labor which has gone into this edition. And its ultimate review and
                        evaluation will only be made by the next Blake editor who sets himself the
                        prodigious task of thoroughly retracing, in all its minute particulars, the
                        course of many years of devoted application that has led us this far along
                        the road to the establishment and refinement of the Blakean canon. A vast
                        number of these particulars will only come into view and focus because of
                        this edition—a fact that will continue to inspire the positive
                        assessments which it will continue to receive and which it so richly
                        deserves.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
