<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.3.hilton</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Maureen Quilligan, The Language of Allegory: Defining the Genre</title>
        <author n="Hilton">Nelson Hilton</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1980/1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980-81</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Stuart Curran</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Bo Lindberg</name>
              <name>Ann Bermingham Miller</name>
              <name>W.J.T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>E.B. Murray</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Hoyt Trowbridge</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980/1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-3-0006">
        <pb id="p14-135" n="135"/>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Maureen Quilligan. <hi rend="b">The Language of Allegory: Defining
                                the Genre.</hi> Ithaca and London: Cornell University Press, 1979.
                            305 pp. $15.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">Nelson</hi> <name><hi rend="b">Hilton</hi></name></docAuthor>.
          </byline>
          <p>Maureen Quilligan’s <hi rend="i">The Language of Allegory</hi> nowhere
                        mentions Blake, yet it should prove highly rewarding to those students
                        interested in Blake’s verbal art, and particularly to those pursuing
                        his murky distinction between “vision” and “allegory”
                            (<hi rend="i">VLJ</hi>, E 544).</p>
          <p>Quilligan’s thesis is that the defining characteristic of
                        non-mechanical allegories—what links them into a genre—is
                        “their very particular emphasis on language as their first focus and
                        ultimate subject” (p. 15), and her book unfolds the consequences and
                        operations of that focus through a theoretical framework (the book moves
                        from sections on “The Text” to “The Pretext,” “The
                        Context,” and “The Reader”) larded with discussions of
                        “allegories” as diverse as <hi rend="i">Piers Plowman</hi>,
                        Melville’s <hi rend="i">The Confidence Man</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The
                            Crying of Lot 49.</hi> For Quilligan, the kind of language which is the
                        subject (and object) of allegory displays three interrelated features: it is
                        polysemous, non-arbitrary, and—striking to read in a work of
                        contemporary literary criticism—it asks for a reader “willing to
                        entertain the possibility of making a religious response to the ineffability
                        invoked by [allegory’s] polysemous language” (p. 223).</p>
          <p>Emphasizing “the possibility of an otherness, a polysemy, inherent in
                        the very words of the page,” Quilligan proposes to reorient the idea of
                        allegory “away from out traditional insistence on allegory’s
                        distinction between word said and meaning meant, to the simultaneity of the
                        process of signifying multiple meaning” (p. 26). The allegory can then
                        be seen as a kind of extended pun, generating its narrative out of wordplay,
                        unfolding “as a series of punning commentaries, related to one another
                        on the most literal of verbal levels—the sounds of words” (p.
                        22; though here one must query, why not the graphic shapes of words as well?
                        sound is not the most literally <hi rend="i">literal</hi> of verbal levels).
                        A Blakean example might be “Of the primeval Priests assum’d
                        power” (<hi rend="i">BU</hi> 2.1), where you must wonder about prim and
                        proper evil priests and then the power they assumed or that you assume they
                        have—fit questions to open the book of your reason (among other
                        possibilities). Such a text—manifesting Quilligan’s suggestion
                        regarding the function of wordplay in allegory—addresses the
                        reader’s production of meaning and forces him “to become
                        self-conscious of his own reading” (pp. 21, 41). The end result of this
                        dynamic is to make the reader aware of his or her own interpretative acts,
                        to force the reader to reflect on how the text has been read, and in
                        reflecting on this operation to realize the choices he or she has made about
                        the text and, finally, the kinds of choices the reader makes in life (p.
                        253). The effect of the confused “Argument” (which means, <pb id="p14-136" n="136"/>
“literally,” “to make clear”)
                        of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> perhaps offers an
                        oblique example for Quilligan’s contention that “the effect of
                        wordplay is to make the reader self-conscious of reading by indicating the
                        primary importance of the verbal surface rather than the imagined action.
                        The narrative’s self-reflexiveness to its own verbal medium (not to
                        its action) by decentering the reader’s interest, unsettles the
                        focus, so the reader becomes more conscious of his own production of
                        meaning” (p. 254). “Rintrah roars &amp; shakes his fires in the
                        burdend air” seems as much about verbal (and graphic) media as about
                        any imagined action.</p>
          <p>The two remaining defining features of the language of allegory are expressed
                        in the contention that 
						<q> Allegories are not only always texts, predicated
                            on the existence of other previous, sacred texts, they are always
                            fundamentally about language and the ways in which language itself can
                            reveal to man his highest spiritual purpose within the cosmos. As such,
                            allegory always presupposes at least a potential sacralizing power in
                            language, and it is possible to write and to read allegory intelligently
                            only in those cultural contexts which grant to language a significance
                            beyond that belonging to a merely arbitrary system of signs. Allegory
                            will not exist as a viable genre without this “supra-realist”
                            attitude toward words; that is, its existence assumes an attitude in
                            which abstract nouns not only name universals that are real, but in
                            which the abstract names themselves are preceived to be as real and as
                            powerful as the things named. Language itself must be felt to have a
                            potency as solidly meaningful as physical fact before the allegorist can
                            begin; out of its magic phenomenality—out of language sensed in
                            terms of a nearly physical presence—the allegorist’s
                            narrative comes, peopled by words moving about an intricately reechoing
                            landscape of language. (p. 156) </q>
Quilligan’s belief that
                        “Allegory calls attention to the other—in a word, to God, or to
                        some sort of possible sacredness” should be related to her argument
                        that the Bible is the necessary “pretext”: “All allegories
                        incorporate the Bible into their texts . . . and its problematic
                        incorporation into the text becomes therefore a defining characteristic of
                        the genre” (p. 96). I confess some puzzlement here—it is as
                        though Quilligan wishes to characterize allegories as
                        “logocentric” exercises, deferring to “the word,”
                        “scripture,” “the book,” but chooses instead to localize
                        those signifieds as the Bible. This formulation is one of several that
                        cannot easily be applied to Blake, despite his belief in the Eternal Vision
                        contained in the Bible. Milton, Shakespeare, Paracelsus &amp; Behmen, the
                        American and French Revolutions are equally among Blake’s informing
                        pretexts; and these in turn are equally manifestations of imagination, the
                        pretext (or, preludium) of an imminent and immanent sacred power. Besides,
                        Blake’s early statement about creating a “Bible of Hell,”
                        and his later assertion that “that God from whom [all books are
                        given]” is again speaking through him, suggests that not the Bible
                        only, but all works of imagination are privileged. Quilligan herself seems
                        to admit this wider scope of allegory, recognizing that “since
                        allegories take as their province all the wisdom stored in the repository of
                        man’s language, they, of necessity, tend to an encyclopedic
                        sprawl” (p. 141).</p>
          <p>Quilligan’s remark concerning “those cultural contexts”
                        necessary for the intelligent reading and writing of allegory is also
                        unsatisfyingly vague. She refers to “those periods when language is
                        felt to be a numinous object” (p. 281); furthermore, allegory attempts
                        to place the reader in relation to self and to society as a whole
                        (“which is considered as well to be part of a cosmic play”), and
                        “this whole process relies on a public acceptance of the polysemous
                        potency of language to connect these (now, to us, disparate) realms”
                        (p. 192). This feels true as far as it goes, but one is driven to wonder:
                        when were those periods? what is the psycho-social-economic-spiritual matrix
                        behind the context she posits? Nineteenth-century New England was evidently
                        one of the periods—judging by the presence of examples from
                        Hawthorne, Emerson, and Melville (but who was reading <hi rend="i">The
                            Confidence Man</hi> “intelligently” when it was published?)
                        Examples from Nabokov and Pynchon, and quotations from Foucault suggest that
                        we are again entering one of the periods. Medieval and Renaissance England
                        of course. The correspondences get difficult to see. Obviously, the one
                        glaring example (since it offers no sample of real allegory) of an 
<hi rend="i">un</hi>privileged period is eighteenth-century and romantic
                        English literature. Given “the essential affinity of allegory to the
                        pivotal phenomenon of the pun” (p. 33), that period’s strictures
                        on the pun manifest its rejection of allegory. For Quilligan, that wide body
                        of literature serves only to make a negative point: “After Pope,
                        poetry’s main value lies in the intricate process by which words
                        uncreate darkness, bringing up from private recesses the previously
                        unacknowledged fundament of human experience. The privacy of the romantic
                        lyric, its devaluation of didactic purpose, along with the often-stated
                        romantic distaste for a mechanically conceived allegory, reveal what might,
                        in another context, be unlikely to be perceived as a generic fact about
                        allegory—that its purpose is always public, at the least,
                        ‘national’” (p. 191). Whatever else may be objected, one
                        sees vividly the liability of generalizing without taking account of the
                        Blakean particular (<hi rend="i">M</hi> 1, “Public Address,” <hi rend="i">inter
alia</hi>).</p>
          <p>Indeed, the issues raised by Blake’s “Sublime Allegory”
                        (letter, 7 July 1803) are, so to speak, <hi rend="i">isomorphous</hi> with
                        the questions suggested but not answered by Quilligan’s provocative
                        book. Or perhaps simply—although it manages to embrace <hi rend="i">The Crying of
Lot 49</hi>—Quilligan’s conception of
                        allegory would not include Blake; for all its emphasis on
                        “polysemy” Quilligan’s book seems to involve a conception
                        of the text curiously closed to “dissemination”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">1</ref> and even poetry (after Spenser). Quilligan notes
                        “allegory’s characteristic concern for process,” which
                        “can be spoken of only in terms of . . . language” (p. 221), yet
                        her reader feels in the end that despite the invocation of “the
                        sacred,” “language” is just another name for process to
                        facilitate the academic concern for defining a genre. <pb id="p14-137" n="137"/>
She
says that her interpretation “suggests that allegory
                        goes beyond mere literary categories” and that “The approach to
                        allegory I have been describing attempts to show how each work provides a
                        conscious portrait of the reader in the act of reading” (p. 241).
                        Portrait for whom? is the text merely a profound mirror in which the reader
                        sees his or her manipulations of the text? Or, what seems closer to the
                        almost mystical, unspoken vision of the book (and closer also to Blake), is
                        the “portrait” itself “conscious,” taking its life as
                        “a Representation of what Eternally Exists. Really &amp;
                        Unchangeably” (<hi rend="i">VLJ</hi>, E 544). For Blake, of course,
                        this is a description of “Vision &amp; Imagination” as opposed to
                        “Fable or Allegory . . . a totally distinct &amp; inferior kind of
                        poetry.” But it strikes this reviewer that Quilligan has in part
                        written about just such Vision, seen as “concern for process, for the
                        complicated exfoliation of interdependent psychic, intellectual, and
                        cultural revelations, which can all be spoken of only in terms of the force
                        that shapes them all: language” (p. 221). Ultimately, however,
                        “Process,” “language”—“going forth &amp;
                        returning wearied,” “the Words of Eternity”—seem in
                        Quilligan’s conception to be separate from some pre-existing
                        “sacred”: the genre she is limiting is marked by “a truly
                        allegorical concern for a sacred pretext” (p. 284). The ambiguity of
                        the last quotation would be appreciated by the Devil of <hi rend="i">The
                            Marriage</hi>, for whom “All Bibles or sacred codes. have been the
                        causes of . . . Errors.” For Blake, “language” itself,
                        “process” itself is sacred and holy, and the true perception of
                        such states, Vision: to defer with Quilligan to some earlier sacred is to
                        invoke “an allegorical abode where existence hath never come” (<hi rend="i">Eur</hi>
6.7). Read diabolically (allegorically?),
                        Quilligan’s book helps us to understand why “Allegory &amp;
                        Vision ought to be known as Two Distinct Things &amp; so called for the
                        Sake of Eternal Life.” <note id="n5"><hi rend="s">1</hi> The word is
                            glossed by Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak in the introduction to her
                            translation of Jacques Derrida, <hi rend="i">Of Grammatology</hi>:
                            “ . . . Derrida offers this version of textuality: A sowing that
                            does not produce plants, but is simply infinitely repeated. A semination
                            that is not insemination but dissemination, seed spilled in vain, an
                            emission that cannot return to its origin in the father [i.e. author].
                            Not an exact and controlled polysemy, but a proliferation of always
                            different, always postponed meanings” (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins
                            University Press, 1976; p. lxv).</note></p>
          <p>Lest I leave the reader with the impression that Quilligan wanted to write on
                        Vision but ended up trying to define allegory, let me repeat that <hi rend="i">The
Language of Allegory</hi> offers a great many inspired
                        moments and deserves close consideration by any reader interested, as all
                        readers of Blake must be, in “all-powerful Human Words!” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 24.1).
The last words here ought to be hers: 
<q> Perhaps
                            language cannot redeem language, so that poetry cannot redeem society;
                            fiction may only entertain. But all allegorists do aim at redemption;
                            and because they must work with language, they ultimately turn to the
                            paradox at the heart of their own assumptions about words and make the
                            final focus of their narratives not merely the social function of
                            language, but, in particular, the slippery tensions between literalness
                            and metaphor. They scrutinize language’s own problematic
                            polysemy. (p. 64) </q></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
