<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.3.gebentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">David Bindman, ed., assisted by Deirdre Toomey, 
The Complete Graphic Works of William Blake</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1980/1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980-81</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Stuart Curran</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Bo Lindberg</name>
              <name>Ann Bermingham Miller</name>
              <name>W.J.T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>E.B. Murray</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Hoyt Trowbridge</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980/1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
	<pb id="p14-161" n="161"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">GOD’S PLENTY</title>
            <title type="main">David Bindman, ed., assisted by Deirdre Toomey.
				<hi rend="b">The Complete Graphic Works of William Blake.</hi> London: 
				Thames and Hudson, 1978. New York: G. P. Putnam’s Sons, 1978. 494 pp., 
				765<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="p161u1" type="note">*</ref> 
				illus. £20, $45.00.</title>
          </head>
		  <note id="p161u1">* The titlepage numeration of
			“765 illustrations” is inaccurate, probably because of the
			intricate and inconsistent system of plate-numbers. The
			reproductions are numbered 1-21, 23-311, 314-88, 390-94, 396-655 (in
			the List of Plates the omitted designs are referred to as “not
			reproduced” or “missing”), but in addition there are
			38 variants (most, but not all, numbered with a suffix of a, b, or
			c) and 81 enlargements (most, but not all, ignored in the Notes to
			the Plates and the List of Plates). The correct total is 769, I
			believe.</note>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">G. E. </hi><name><hi rend="b">Bentley</hi></name>, 
<hi rend="b">Jr.</hi></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>T<hi rend="i">he Complete Graphic Works of William Blake</hi> is a remarkable
                        bargain and a great credit to Mr. David Bindman and to Thames &amp; Hudson.
                        It reproduces some 688 prints, mostly in full size, and it includes not only
                        all the subjects reproduced in Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Illuminated
                        Blake</hi> (1975), in Keynes’s <hi rend="i">Separate Plates</hi>
                        (1956) (except for the plates Blake engraved but did not design), and in
                        Easson and Essick’s <hi rend="i">William Blake Book Illustrator</hi>
                        Volume I (1972), but also The Small Book of Designs (reproduced nowhere
                        else, as far as I know), The Large Book of Designs (ibid.), the large color
                        prints, <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, Dante, and a number of incidental prints in
                        none of these collected publications. No book reproducing Blake’s
                        engraved designs is nearly so extensive.</p>
          <p>Further, the standards of production are high. The page size is large, 9
                        3/8″ × 13″, so that <hi rend="i">America</hi>, 
<pb id="p14-162" n="162"/>
		<hi rend="i">Europe, Jerusalem</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Job</hi> can be given
                        full size (some of the smaller prints are reproduced as many as eleven to a
                        page), and every print which is larger than this, such as the large color
                        prints, Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, and Dante, is
                        reproduced whole in reduced size and with a true-size detail. The quality of
                        the photographs and reproductions appears to be fine, and many variants are
                        reproduced. For example, there are three versions of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> pl. 1
                        and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> pl. 28 and four of
                        <hi rend="i">Job</hi> pl. 16. The plates are arranged straightforwardly
                        in chronological order, with variants gathered after the published version
                        of the work (e.g., <hi rend="i">America</hi>, pls. 1-18, a-c), and the text,
                        as is appropriate for a work aimed at a large audience, is matter of fact
                        and unpretentious. The brief “Introduction: Blake as a graphic
                        artist” (pp. 10-22) has the same merits and attitudes as Mr.
                        Bindman’s comprehensive <hi rend="i">Blake as an artist</hi> (1977),
                        and the succinct “Notes to the Plates” (pp. 465-88) are reliably
                        based upon standard Blake scholarship. This is a work which can be
                        recommended with enthusiasm to lovers and students of Blake.</p>
          <p>The copies reproduced come from widely separated collections, from Cambridge
                        to Canberra, but the great majority of groups of plates, such as those for
                        <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>, come from the British Museum Print
                        Room and Library (14), with three groups from the Fitzwilliam Museum
                        (Cambridge), two each from the Library of Congress, the Pierpont Morgan
                        Library, and the Huntington Library, and one each from Bodley, The
                        University of Glasgow, and Sir Geoffrey Keynes. The originals seem to have
                        been chosen for the convenience of the editor, who teaches at the University
                        of London and who made an admirable catalogue of the Fitzwilliam Blake
                        collection, rather than for the convenience of the scholar. Naturally
                        black-and-white plates on coated, cream-colored paper cannot indicate the
                        red, sepia, blue, green, and orange in which the originals of the works in
                        Illuminated Printing are printed, much less their subsequent coloring.
                        However, it would have been desirable to choose uncolored originals instead
                        of the watercolored copies of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (B), <hi rend="i">Songs of
                        Innocence</hi> (B), and <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                        Experience</hi> (B), for of course much of Blake’s delicate or
                        glorious coloring comes out simply muddy and distracting when reproduced in
                        black-and-white. Further, little effort seems to have been made to reproduce
                        copies of works in Illuminated Printing which have not appeared in facsimile
                        before. Some of the copies given here have been reproduced three or four
                        times, and only <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> (B), <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                        (A), <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> (B), and <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (B) appear
                        to be reproduced here for the first time. Such conventionality of choice
                        represents a missed opportunity, for scholars will of course turn to the
                        color facsimiles of the same copies rather than to these black-and-white
                        photographs.</p>
          <p>The generosity of the work is admirable. Far from shunning duplication merely
                        because a design has been reproduced on a previous page, all the 
                        <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> are repeated unchanged in the 
                        <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, the 
                        <hi rend="i">For Children</hi> plates are given again, with mostly 
                        minor alterations, in <hi rend="i">For the Sexes</hi>, and all the 
                        scenes in the Large and Small Books of Designs are of course reproduced 
                        elsewhere here. For the Blake student, here is God’s plenty.</p>
          <p>For the general reader, there are only a few defects of significance. One
                        such defect is the lack of a transcript of Blake’s texts, which are
                        here sometimes faint (<hi rend="i">Visions</hi>) or obscure (<hi rend="i">No
                            Natural Religion, Urizen, Songs</hi>)—but this of course would
                        have required another volume and a different kind of enterprise. (One might
                        as well ask for color reproductions at the same price.) Most of the texts
                        are plainly legible—ironically the clearest text is that for
                        Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>—and all can be read
                        with magnification and patience. More important is the lack of captions or
                        running-heads for the reproductions themselves. The reader opening at random
                        to the design numbered 519 must first determine whether this is a page
                        number (no) or a plate number (yes) and then look it up in the List of
                        Plates (p. 493) to discover that it is for <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> pl.
                        40. Yet more distracting is the lack of an index, which is inexcusable. If
                        one wants to discover, say, where “Our End is come” is reproduced,
                        one can find it only by trudging all through the List of Plates or the Notes
                        to the Plates; it is given as no. 81, 316, and 402. Plate captions and an
                        index are vital to a compendious work like this, and both editor and
                        publisher should have insisted upon them.</p>
          <p>For the general reader, then, <hi rend="i">The Complete Graphic Works of
                            William Blake</hi> is admirable value. What is there in it for the Blake
                        scholar who has ready access to the scholarship on which the book is based?
                        Well, for one thing, there are photographs of several copies of works in
                        Illuminated Printing which have apparently not been reproduced before. For
                        another, there are several designs which have not previously been reproduced
                        at all. One of these (no. 8), called “Charity” and distantly
                        related to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> pl. 46 (no. 525), was acquired by the
                        British Museum Print Room in 1958, and Mr. Bindman is cautiously (and
                        rightly, in my view) “inclined to accept it” as Blake’s (p.
                        467). Another (no. 185), “an experiment in colour-printing” called
                        “An estuary with figures in a boat,” is described even more
                        cautiously: “the attribution to Blake cannot be regarded as
                        certain” (p. 473), despite the mysterious inscription on it in an
                        unidentified hand: “By William Blake (Mr Stothard).” It is unlike
                        almost anything else Blake is known to have done, and the inscription is the
                        chief reason for associating it with him. Whether or not we accept the work
                        as Blake’s, the visual (or at least black-and white) evidence is now
                        before us on which to base a decision.</p>
          <p>How complete and comprehensive is the collection of <hi rend="i">Graphic
                            Works</hi> presented here? The first problem comes with the word
                        “Graphic,” which often means writing or drawing but here means
                        “contemporary engraved or etched or lithographed design or text”
                        (for some of the plates have no design). Mr. Bindman says, “I have set
                        out to reproduce every printed [i.e., contemporary engraved] design by Blake
                        as well as their major variants” (p. 7). Thus, we have Blake’s
                        engraving of his own designs and other engravers’ copies of
                        Blake’s designs, as in Burger’s <hi rend="i">Leonora</hi>,
                        Malkin’s <hi rend="i">A Father’s Memoir</hi>, and
                        Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>, and Mr. Bindman has generously
                        thrown in one or two of Blake’s engravings after the designs of other
                        men such as that for Bonnycastle’s <hi rend="i">Mensuration</hi>—“there is little
                        to 
<pb id="p14-163" n="163"/>
                        distinguish it from such work by Heath and others” (p. 467). The book
                        of course omits designs which Blake copied from elsewhere, such as those for
                        the Portland Vase in Darwin’s <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden</hi>, for
                        Gough’s <hi rend="i">Sepulchral Monuments, Vetusta Monumenta</hi>,
                        and Stedman’s <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi>, even though some of them
                        have important Blakean elements. It omits the plates after Blake’s
                        designs in Whitaker’s <hi rend="i">Seraph</hi> (1828) and in
                        Hamilton’s <hi rend="i">English School</hi> (1831), presumably
                        because they were made by other engravers after Blake died in 1827 and
                        because they were already reproduced in their earlier forms. There are,
                        however, a few plates which appear to belong here on Mr. Bindman’s
                        principles but which are missing. Blake’s first and third plates for
                        Gay’s <hi rend="i">Fables</hi> (1793) are significantly his own, for
                        they incorporate characteristic Blakean elements not in the designs he was
                        copying. The very small design of two old men planting trees in
                        Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> (1788) is probably
                        designed by Blake, though it is signed only “<hi rend="i">Blake
                        So</hi>” (see <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> [1977], pp. 594, 754), and
                        Varley’s <hi rend="i">Zodiacal Physiognomy</hi> (1828) has five
                        designs by Blake copied by Varley and engraved by Linnell, including two of
                        the “Ghost of a Flea”—and two more unpublished engravings
                        after Blake for it are in the collection of Sir Geoffrey Keynes. (Perhaps
                        the Varley plates were excluded because they were not made by Blake for the
                        purpose of being engraved and may be post-humous.) Another
                        “Complete” collection of contemporary printed copies of
                        Blake’s designs might legitimately omit a few of these designs and
                        include a few others.</p>
          <p>Similarly, the variant states of plates are, of course, far from complete.
                        The reproduction of <hi rend="i">America</hi> pl. 4 (no. 149) lacks the last
                        four lines of text, but there is no reproduction of the complete plate. The
                            <hi rend="i">America</hi> copperplate fragment is reproduced along with
                        a print from it (no. 164a), but the copperplate shows a number of details
                        not visible in the print, such as most of the last line of text. The
                        important proof variants of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> found in 
                        <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> are omitted, and there is no reproduction of the
                        important verbal and graphic variants in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> pl. 1
                        (“FIRST” omitted), pl. 6 (two figures omitted in copy D), pl. 15
                        (two figures added in G), pl. 24 (two figures omitted in D), and pl. 25 (a
                        line omitted in A).</p>
          <p>The attraction of this volume to the scholar is largely the same as for the
                        general reader: It collects in one place a vast number of fine reproductions
                        after contemporary engravings from Blake’s designs and does so
                        remarkably faithfully and inexpensively. With such riches before us, it is
                        ungenerous to complain. This is a work which all students and lovers of
                        Blake will wish to own.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
