<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.3.miller</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Andrew Wilton, Constable’s “English Landscape Scenery”</title>
        <author n="Miller">Ann Bermingham Miller</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1980/1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1980-81</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Stuart Curran</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Bo Lindberg</name>
              <name>Ann Bermingham Miller</name>
              <name>W.J.T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>E.B. Murray</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Hoyt Trowbridge</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1980/1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-3-0006">
        <pb id="p14-128" n="128"/>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Andrew Wilton. <hi rend="b">Constable’s ‘English
                                Landscape Scenery.’</hi> London: British Museum Publications
                            Ltd., 1980. 113 pp. £ 6.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">Ann Bermingham</hi> <name><hi rend="b">Miller</hi></name></docAuthor>.
          </byline>
          <p>In February 1829, after ten years as an Associate, John Constable was elected
                        to full membership in the Royal Academy by a margin of one vote. Other
                        reasons besides the narrowness of his election made it difficult for him to
                        enjoy the recognition that it officially conferred. He had lost his beloved
                        wife Maria a few months before, and his painting was popular neither with
                        critics nor collectors. Still smarting from his election seven months after
                        it, Constable planned a series of prints that would summarize, diffuse, and
                        defend the principles of his art. He hired an engraver, David Lucas, to
                        render in mezzotint several of his paintings and sketches. Lucas submitted
                        his proofs to Constable and revised his steel plates according to the
                        latter’s corrections, heightening and dramatizing the effects of
                        natural light. The series appeared from June 1830 to July 1832 (four issues
                        of four prints, and a fifth of six) under the title <hi rend="i">Various
                            Subjects of Landscape, Characteristic of English Scenery, From Pictures
                            Painted by John Constable, R. A.</hi> Although—or perhaps
                        because—the project, which he financed himself, was not a great
                        success, Constable published a second edition of the series in 1833, this
                        time with an expanded commentary and a new title, <hi rend="i">Various
                            subjects of Landscape, characteristic of English Scenery, principally
                            intended to mark the Phenomena of the Chiar’oscuro of
                            Nature.</hi></p>
          <p>All twenty-two mezzotints, along with eighteen other prints from the
                        Constable-Lucas collaboration, have been reproduced after forty years of
                        scholarly neglect in <hi rend="i">Constable’s</hi> “<hi rend="i">English Landscape
Scenery</hi>” by Andrew Wilton, who carefully
                        catalogues them and details their history and dates of issue. Mr. Wilton has
                        performed a valuable service, though one more valuable than he evidently
                        knows. His prefatory essay is strangely lacking in reasons why this little
                        known part of Constable’s work should be better known. Mr. Wilton
                        only finds in the prints further evidence of that “freedom from
                        mannerism, from preconceptions derived from the work of other artists”
                        that Constable’s work is traditionally supposed to demonstrate. Even
                        on its own sweepingly general terms, this commonplace can scarcely be
                        maintained. E. H. Gombrich has shown the considerable extent to which
                        Constable did work from preconceptions, and the Bicentenary Exhibition at
                        the Tate Gallery in 1976 amply demonstrated Constable’s debt to the
                        work of Claude, Gainsborough, Wilson, Girtin, Cozens, and even Turner. It is
                        not <hi rend="i">nature</hi> that determines the composition of
                        Constable’s work, so much as <hi rend="i">naturalism</hi>, that is,
                        an artistic rhetoric meant to convey the effect of nature. It is
                        particularly inappropriate to extol Constable’s freedom from
                        mannerism in the context of these mannered mezzotints, where such a rhetoric
                        appears at its most theatrical.</p>
          <p>All that motivates Mr. Wilton’s resurrection of <hi rend="i">English
                            Landscape Scenery</hi> seems to be an ideal of scholarly thoroughness.
                        In fact, the work has far more interesting claims to our attention. Born of
                        Constable’s anxiety to secure public understanding and acceptance of
                        his art, the series marks a 
<pb id="p14-129" n="129"/>
significant turning
                        point in his style, from the restrained naturalism of his early works to the
                        personal expressionism of his late ones. The shift, of course, is only the
                        most conspicuous version of a tension running throughout all
                        Constable’s work between objective representation and subjective
                        expression. Even the rhetorically restrained work of his early period makes
                        covert allusions to private reminiscences (of his boyhood, his
                        father’s business, his courtship). In the bolder, reverse strategy
                        taken in <hi rend="i">English Landscape Scenery</hi>, Constable identifies
                        the overt personal expressionism of the prints with an utterly empirical
                        study of nature. As the change of title indicates, together with the changes
                        of design asked from Lucas, the key to this identification is
                        Constable’s conception of chiaroscuro. As he asserts in his 1833
                        introduction, chiaroscuro is both a natural and an artistic means for giving
                        landscape its expression. As a result, “the Chiar’oscuro of
                        Nature” permits Constable to equate nature’s moods with his own.
                        At the same time as the inky shadows and glittering highlights evoke the
                        dramatic effects of natural light, they also imply an equally dramatic
                        emotional response to them. (Both dramas, unfortunately, are lost in the
                        British Museum’s muzzy reproductions.)</p>
          <p>Chiaroscuro is thus Constable’s anxious way to seduce the
                        uncomprehending public into collaborating in the meaning and purpose of his
                        art. We participate at once in nature and in the emotional life of an artist
                        deeply moved by nature. If art historians have neglected <hi rend="i">English
Landscape Scenery</hi>, the reason may be that the prints were
                        not executed by Constable himself. Yet insofar as they carry forward the
                        dramatic revelation of the uses of chiaroscuro, they are directly pertinent
                        to works that he did execute: those intensely tonal late masterpieces like
                        “The Valley Farm” (1835) that seem to aspire to no less than the
                        state of mezzotint.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
