<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.4.alexander</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">David Alexander and Richard T. Godfrey, Painters and Engraving: The Reproductive
Print from Hogarth to Wilkie</title>
        <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
              <name>Erik Frykman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>William Vaughan</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-4-0010">
        <pb id="p14-220" n="220"/>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">David Alexander and Richard T. Godfrey. <hi rend="b">Painters and
                                Engraving: The Reproductive Print from Hogarth to Wilkie.</hi> An
                            exhibition at the Yale Center for British Art, New Haven, Connecticut,
                            26 March through 22 June 1980. Exhibition and catalogue (73 pp., 14
                            illus.).</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Robert N.
                        <name>Essick</name>.</docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In about 1810, Blake called upon “Englishmen” to “rouze
                        yourselves from the fatal Slumber into which Booksellers &amp; Trading
                        Dealers have thrown you Under the artfully propagated pretence that a
                        Translation or a Copy of any kind can be as honourable to a Nation as An
                            Original.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n104"
type="note">1</ref> This appeal has
                        been so thoroughly answered by twentieth-century collectors, connoisseurs,
                        and curators as to overthrow completely the aesthetic of the last two
                        centuries which highly valued reproductive graphics. The triumph of original
                        printmaking has transformed our sense of what to value in prints and, less
                        happily, has tended to obscure the importance of copy engraving as the
                        predominant form of the craft throughout Blake’s lifetime. The recent
                        exhibition, <hi rend="i">Painters and Engraving</hi>, at the Yale Center for
                        British Art was a worthy and generally successful attempt to restore a more
                        balanced historical view and investigate—but not necessarily
                        advocate—the values of the reproductive print. <note id="n104"><hi rend="s">1</hi>
“Public Address” in David V. Erdman, ed.,
                                <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi> (Garden
                            City, New York: Doubleday, 1965), p. 565.</note></p>
          <p>The 150 works in the exhibition, including a few paintings accompanied by
                        their graphic translations, were displayed with appropriate restraint on the
                        third floor of the handsome new Yale Center. All the prints were fine, early
                        impressions and for the most part in excellent condition. Many of these
                        works were originally intended for the collector’s portfolio or
                        display in intimate domestic settings, and thus I had to compensate for the
                        public and institutional context of the exhibit by moving from print to
                        print and studying each at close range. Rich burr, mossy tints, and clean
                        strokes must be appreciated at a distance not to exceed twenty inches. A
                        scholarly exhibit of this type never draws the crowds swarming over the MOMA
                        Picasso fiesta on the same weekend I visited the Center. Left frequently
                        alone, except for an occasional guard who feared I was fogging up the
                        glazing, I could study the prints with considerable convenience. Three
                        visits of about two hours each made for a calm and decorous experience with
                        a proper eighteenth-century balance of delight and instruction.</p>
          <p>The exhibition had a narrow focus, for it dealt not with the full range of
                        reproductive printmaking in England from c. 1720 to c. 1830 (as the
                        sub-title implies), but rather with the specific field of prints copied
                        after paintings executed as finished works in their own right. Further,
                        almost all of the prints were based on eighteenth or early
                        nineteenth-century British paintings, and book illustrations were generally
                        excluded. This field was in turn divided into fourteen sections. Reciting
                        them is a bit tedious, but an efficient way of giving a sense of the
                        exhibit’s contents and an outline of the history of
                        eighteenth-century English copy engravings after paintings. <list type="ordered">
	<item><p><label>1.</label> Hogarth and His Predecessors (Le Blon, J. B.
                                    Jackson, Kirkall<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n105"
type="note">2</ref>) <note id="n105"><hi rend="s">2</hi> For each section I list only
                                        the more important printmakers presented, not all those
                                        exhibited.</note></p></item>
	<item><p><label>2.</label> The Mezzotint and Subject Painting 1735-1760
                                    (Faber, Houston, McArdell)</p></item>
	<item><p><label>3.</label> The Revival of Line 1740-1770 (Ravenet,
                                    Woollett)</p></item>
	<item><p><label>4.</label> The Irish Mezzotint Engravers in London
                                    1750-1775 
<pb id="p14-221" n="221"/> (Frye, Fisher, Watson,
                                    Dixon)</p></item>
	<item><p><label>5.</label> English Mezzotint Engravers 1760-1775
                                    (Spilsbury, Green, Earlom, Pether)</p></item>
	<item><p><label>6.</label> Benjamin West and the Market for Prints after
                                    History Paintings (Green and Woollett again, Hall, Strange)</p></item>
	<item><p><label>7.</label> Reynolds and the Great Age of the Portrait
                                    Mezzotint 1775-1785 (Watson, J. R. Smith, Sherwin)</p></item>
	<item><p><label>8.</label> An Expanding Print Market: The New Techniques
                                    of Stipple and Aquatint (Ryland, Bartolozzi, Knight,
                                    Schiavonetti)</p></item>
	<item><p><label>9.</label> The Painter as Print Maker: The Prints of
                                    George Stubbs and James Barry.</p></item>
	<item><p><label>10.</label> The Painter and the Search for the Best
                                    Selling Print 1775-1800 (Bartolozzi, Woollett &amp; Emes,
                                    Sharp)</p></item>
	<item><p><label>11.</label> The Widening Range of Mezzotint 1780-1810
                                    (Earlom, J. R. Smith, Ward)</p></item>
	<item><p><label>12.</label> The Ambitions of the Print Publishers (Heath,
                                    Skelton, Sharp, Tomkins, Anker Smith; and the publishers
                                    Macklin, Boydell, and Bowyer)</p></item>
	<item><p><label>13.</label> The English Print Trade and the French
                                    Revolutionary Wars (Orme, Bromley, Heath)</p></item>
	<item><p><label>14.</label> Conclusion: The Early Nineteenth Century
                                    (Raimbach, Cousins, John Martin, Lucas’ prints after
                                    Constable)</p></item>
</list> This list indicates the extent to which mezzotints, the chief means
                        for rendering oil paintings into repeatable images, dominated the exhibit.
                        All were highly competent and representative examples, but the long rows of
                        mezzotint portraits and genre scenes showed how regularity and the extreme
                        of high finish can grow into monotony. The more exciting mezzotints were
                        those after paintings with Caravaggesque light effects, such as Philip
                        Dawe’s plate of 1768 after Henry Robert Morland’s “The
                        Ballad Singer” (both painting and print exhibited) and the great plates
                        by Green, Earlom, and Pether after Wright of Derby’s “A
                        Philosopher Shewing an Experiment on the Air Pump,” “The
                        Blacksmith’s Shop,” and “The Farrier’s Shop.”
                        For one as lodged in Blake and his circle as I, it was a slight
                        disappointment not to find in the exhibit some of the striking mezzotints
                        after Fuseli, such as J. R. Smith’s “Belisane &amp; Percival
                        under the Enchantment of Urma” (1782) and “The Weird Sisters”
                        (1785).</p>
          <p>Although no works by or after Blake were in the show, it did offer an
                        excellent chance for experiencing at first-hand the context of styles and
                        techniques in which, and often against which, Blake pursued his own unique
                        course as a printmaker. Blake’s natural allies were Woollett and
                        Strange, the great practitioners of traditional line engraving who opposed
                        the newer schools of mezzotint, crayon manner, stipple, and aquatint. That
                        he attacked these two men, at least in his private <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> jottings
of c. 1810, and set his own career within an
                        older tradition of original graphics, shows the extent of his
                        dissatisfaction with the aesthetics and economics of the printmaking
                        industry represented in this exhibit. In his earlier years, Blake seems to
                        have been more willing to channel his talents into conventional copywork.
                        His major source of employment throughout his career was book illustration,
                        but some of his separate plates would have fitted comfortably into the Yale
                        exhibit. Blake’s two plates of 1782 after Watteau, “Morning
                        Amusement” and “Evening Amusement,” particularly the Keynes,
                        Butlin, McGill, and Essick impressions printed in sanguine or terra
                            cotta,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n106" type="note">3</ref>
are typical of the stipple
                        plates presented in section 8 of the exhibit. Ryland’s
                        “Maria” after Angelica Kauffmann (no. 76 in the exhibition
                        catalogue) and Bartolozzi’s “Presentation of King John of France
                        to Edward III” (no. 84) are very close to Blake’s work. If the
                        two extant productions (“Zephyrus and Flora” and
                        “Calisto,” both after Stothard) by the partnership of Blake and
                        Parker are representative of their intentions, then in 1784 the two former
                        apprentices of James Basire were attempting to produce and market prints
                        that met the contemporary demand for delicately stippled “fancy”
                        prints. A few years later, Blake even became involved in the highly popular
                        business of producing stipple prints after George Morland’s
                        picturesque views of country life. “The Industrious Cottager” and
                        “The Idle Laundress,” both originally published by J. R. Smith in
                        1788, are of the same genre as J. D. Soiron’s two plates after
                        Morland, “St. James’s Park” and “A Tea Garden” of
                        1790, exhibited at the Yale Center (nos. 85 and 86). Soiron’s plates,
                        like three extant impressions of Blake’s prints after 
                        Morland,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n107" type="note">4</ref> 
                        were printed in colors <hi rend="i">à la poupée</hi>—that is, with each color of ink
                        individually applied to the appropriate areas of the copperplate with a rag
                        dabber or stump brush and printed in one 
                        operation.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n108" type="note">5</ref> 
                        Blake’s own color printing of the illuminated
                        books appears to have been an extension of this technique to relief plates
                        and a substitution of opaque glue or gum-based pigments for colored inks.
                        <note id="n106"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Sir Geoffrey Keynes’
                            impression of “Morning Amusement” is reproduced in sanguine in
                            his <hi rend="i">Engravings by William Blake: The Separate Plates</hi>
                            (Dublin: Emery Walker, 1956), pl. 39.</note>
                        <note id="n107"><hi rend="s">4</hi> An impression of “The Idle
                            Laundress” color-printed in blue, brick red, brown, black, and
                            olive green is in the Keynes collection. A pair of these companion
                            prints color-printed in blue, green, brick red, and black was sold from
                            the A. E. Newton collection at Parke-Bernet, 17 April 1941, lot 154
                            ($150), and is now in the collection of Lucile Johnson Rosenbloom,
                            Pittsburgh.</note>
                        <note id="n108"><hi rend="s">5</hi> An exhibit at the Yale Center from 20
                            April through 25 June, 1978 dealt specifically with color printing. See
                            the informative catalogue by Joan M. Friedman, <hi rend="i">Color
                                Printing In England 1486-1870</hi> (New Haven: Yale Center for
                            British Art, 1978).</note></p>
          <p>The Yale exhibit included two important painter-printmakers, Barry and
                        Stubbs, whose work is legitimately a part of reproductive engraving, since
                        their prints were copied after paintings, but who are also in the tradition
                        of original graphics because the paintings they “copied” (and
                        frequently altered) were their own. Blake shared much with these artists who
                        also took singular approaches to the execution and publication of their
                        designs “without the intermediary of engraver and 
                        publisher.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n109" type="note">6</ref> 
                        In his early years Blake seems to have
                        had the intention of preparing a series of designs on subjects from British
                        history, and later on Biblical subjects, for eventual execution as
                        copperplate line engravings. From this resulted only the “Edward and
                        Elenor,” “Job,” and “Ezekiel” separate plates and
                        perhaps “The History of England, a small book of Engravings” known
                        only through their advertisement in the 1793 prospectus “To the
                    	Public.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n110" type="note">7</ref>
                        This pattern for an
                        artist-printmaker was established by Barry, whose “King Lear and
                        Cordelia” (nos. 102a and 102b in the exhibit) represents his energetic
                        approach to the copper. Prints on historical and literary subjects were the
                        <pb id="p14-222" n="222"/> 
                        most respected, having the same position in
                        graphics as the epic in the hierarchy of literary genres, and
                        eighteenth-century decorum called for their execution in traditional line
                        etching/engraving. Barry and Blake set their sights on this lofty field;
                        neither achieved the popular and financial successes of the painters West
                        and Reynolds or the copy engravers Woollett and Strange. Further, Barry
                        tended to experiment with inking and printing techniques to such an extent
                        that each impression is unique. This divergence from the uniform
                        repeatability sought by the established printmaking industry was carried to
                        an extreme in Blake’s relief etchings and color printed drawings.
                        <note id="n109"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Richard T. Godfrey in the catalogue
                            to the exhibition, p. 46.</note>
                        <note id="n110"><hi rend="s">7</hi> See Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">Poetry and
                            Prose of William Blake</hi>, p. 671.</note></p>
          <p>Given his explicit admiration for 
          				Barry,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n111" type="note">8</ref> 
          				the parallels between Blake’s career (or at least his
                        early intentions for it) and his predecessor’s are not surprising.
                        The associations between Blake and Stubbs come less readily to mind,
                        particularly given the differences in the subjects of their prints other
                        than large felines. The Yale exhibit, however, makes their general
                        relationship clearer. Godfrey tells us in the catalogue that “no prints
                        are less spontaneously executed than those of Stubbs, whose delight it was
                        to patiently rework and rethink for the graphic medium an image that he had
                        already defined in paint, perhaps decades before” (p. 46).
                        Blake’s career after 1804 shows this same tendency, for he returned
                        to his early plates to revitalize “Job,” “Ezekiel,”
                        “The Accusers,” “Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of
                        Albion,” and “Albion rose” with new cutting, burnishing, and
                        <corr type="emend">inscriptions.</corr> And Blake seems to have fiddled with “Chaucers Canterbury
                        Pilgrims” and <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi> into his last few
                        years.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n112" type="note">9</ref>
                        The great <hi rend="i">Job</hi> plates have a very high finish in their central panels,
                        display some of the minute flick and stipple work to create rich and varied
                        textures so typical of Stubbs’ plates, and are reworkings of designs
                        Blake executed almost twenty years earlier for Thomas Butts. Like Barry and
                        Blake, Stubbs also “manifested to a remarkable degree that natural
                        delight in purposeful technical 
                        experiment.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n113" type="note">10</ref> 
                        When viewed from this special perspective offered
                        by the Yale exhibit and catalogue, one might even begin to speak of the
                        “School of Barry, Blake, and Stubbs.” There are of course
                        significant differences among them, but all three artists struggled against
                        the modes of sensibility and production dominating late eighteenth-century
                        printmaking. Their works embody that unity of conception and execution so
                        much a part of Blake’s aesthetic and of our modern taste in graphics.
                        Certainly Blake’s major attempt at producing a large engraving after
                        one of his paintings, “Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims,” would have
                        fitted nicely into the Stubbs and Barry section of the Yale exhibition. It
                        is surprising that the organizers did not take advantage of available
                        resources to do this: across the street at the Yale University Art Gallery
                        they would have found Blake’s original copperplate of the
                        “Canterbury” and an impression of the rare third 
                        state.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n114" type="note">11</ref> 
                        The Center itself has a good
                        impression of the second state and, for contrast and context, a fascinating
                        etched proof (yet with inscriptions and an imprint, dated 1 August 1810,
                        indicating it was published) of the Schiavonetti-Heath plate after
                        Stothard’s “Canterbury Pilgrims” painting.
                        <note id="n111"><hi rend="s">8</hi> See the annotations to Reynolds (Erdman, pp.
                            626, 631, 640), the “Public Address” (Erdman, pp. 565, 570),
                            and the reference to “Barry, a Poem” on p. 61 of
                            Blake’s <hi rend="i">Notebook.</hi></note>
                        <note id="n112"><hi rend="s">9</hi> I have discussed all these revisions in
                            some detail and argued for their late date in <hi rend="i">William
                            Blake, Printmaker</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press,
                            1980).</note>
                        <note id="n113"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Godfrey in the exhibition catalogue, p.
                            47.</note>
                        <note id="n114"><hi rend="s">11</hi> The only other impressions of the third
                            state (as described in Keynes, <hi rend="i">Engravings by Blake: The
                            Separate Plates</hi>, pp. 46-47) I have been able to locate are in
                            the Huntington Library and the collection of Douglas Cleverdon,
                            London.</note></p>
          <p>A scholarly exhibition deserves a good catalogue to perpetuate its memory and
                        extend its impact beyond the lucky few who attended the show. Although the
                        physical appearance of the catalogue authored by Alexander and Godfrey is
                        not very promising, with few illustrations and typewriter typography, their
                        double-column text is packed with valuable information, some of it taken
                        from previously unpublished letters and engravers’ receipts. Although
                        not the focus of any one section of the catalogue, the class struggle
                        between engravers and painters—the latter always asserting their
                        superiority to the former yet desperately needing their talents—is
                        clearly documented. The conventional entries on individual works are
                        preceded by an introduction by Alexander, brief descriptions of printmaking
                        techniques by Godfrey, and a most informative overview by Alexander of how
                        eighteenth-century prints were published. The second of these sections
                        offers interesting material on the use of drypoint (hard to detect in
                        eighteenth-century plates because the burr was always removed before
                        printing) and on the sale of unfinished proofs, but also raises a few
                        doubts. Godfrey calls woodcut a “planographic process” (p. 8).
                        Surely it is relief; the first planographic technique was lithography, and
                        even that was a relief technique in its early history in England. Godfrey
                        also states that the etching ground was wax, the usual method of biting the
                        plate was to build a dike of wax around its edges and pour acid into the
                        shallow vessel formed thereby, and the most common mordant was dilute nitric
                        acid or the “Dutch Bath” of hydrochloric acid mixed with chlorate
                        of potash (p. 7). All three observations are subject to question. The
                        eighteenth-century etching manuals in French and English recommend the
                        “soft varnish” which indeed contained “virgin wax”
                        (i.e., purified beeswax) but also asphaltum and other 
                        substances.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n115" type="note">12</ref> 
                        Pure wax would be too soft and would
                        probably drip off the plate if one tried to smoke it with a candle. Blake
                        used the dike method for biting his relief plates; but the handbooks give
                        equal if not more attention to a slanted palette, with a trough at the
                        bottom, on which the plate was placed and acid poured over it, and to the
                        “Cochin Rocker”—an acid-filled tray in which the plate was
                        gently rocked back and forth to keep the acid moving and thereby prevent
                        bubbles that cause underbiting and lifting of the ground. To support his
                        reference to the dike method, Godfrey refers to item 9 in the exhibit, a
                        print from <hi rend="i">The Universal Magazine</hi> of October, 1748,
                        showing (among other printmaking activities) a copperplate resting in an
                        acid bath tended by a young boy with a feather to whisk away bubbles. This
                        scene is even more disconcerting to me than it should have been to Godfrey,
                        for I have never found an eighteenth-century description of etching that
                        recommends this procedure, now standard in an age without cheap apprentice
                        labor to pour acid or rock trays. Perhaps it is only a Cochin Rocker
                        temporarily at rest and the boy a lazy apprentice. Finally, the standard
                        mordant was probably Abraham Bosse’s so-called <hi rend="i">aquafortis</hi>, 
                        a mixture of vinegar, <corr type="emend">sal-ammoniac,</corr> sea salt, and
                        verdigris. Only Dossie (II, 146-50) objects noisily to this mordant and
                        writes that true <hi rend="i">aquafortis</hi> is nitric acid. None of the
                        manuals I have seen says anything of the Dutch Bath, although Bosse’s
                        formula has a similar combination of acids and salts and in my experience
                        bites copper in a 
                    <pb id="p14-223" n="223"/> 
                    	similarly gentle, non-bubbling
                        manner. But these technical matters seem to be subject to endless dispute,
                        and I suspect that neither Godfrey nor I have heard the end of it. 
                    <note id="n115"><hi rend="s">12</hi> See William Faithorne, <hi rend="i">The
                        Art of Graveing and Etching</hi> (London, 1662), section 19; and 
                        <hi rend="i">Sculptura Historico-Technica</hi>, Fourth Edition (London,
                        1770), pp. 82-83, for standard formulae. [Robert Dossie], <hi rend="i">The
                        Handmaid to the Arts</hi>, Second Edition (London, 1764), II,
                        83-89, offers eight different recipes, none of which is pure
                        wax.</note></p>
          <p>The catalogue, like the exhibition itself, is worthy of its institutional
                        sponsor. I hope that the Yale Center and its guardian angel, Mr. Paul
                        Mellon, will continue to serve scholars in specialized fields, such as
                        English copy engraving, where few other museums or libraries can afford to
                        labor. These efforts will surely add to Yale’s reputation as a center
                        for the study of British art and culture.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
