<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.4.mla</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">“Blake and the Eighteenth Century” at the 1980 MLA</title>
        <author n="Hilton">Nelson Hilton</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
              <name>Erik Frykman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>William Vaughan</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
	<pb id="p14-230" n="230"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-4-0011">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">“BLAKE AND THE EIGHTEENTH CENTURY” AT THE 1980
                                MLA</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>That the 1980 MLA Special Session on “Blake and the Eighteenth
                        Century” was probably the longest such meeting of the convention does
                        not alone explain the fact that the audience seemed to increase rather than
                        diminish in numbers during the presentation of the four papers and a
                        response. This was an eternity in love indeed with its temporal productions.
                        Leo Damrosch, Jr. spoke first on “Blake and the Recovery of the
                        Lyric,” arguing that Blake “recovers” the lyric through poems
                        “totally committed to meaning in its deepest sense” and that the
                        fullness of this commitment is what separates Blake most decisively from the
                        tentative lyric poetry of the eighteenth century. But at the same time, it
                        is this “total moral commitment to works of art that point beyond
                        themselves” that leads to Blake’s later work and its concern
                        with “the gap between what art claims and what it can perform.”
                        Jim Borck offered an illuminated discussion of “Blake and the
                        Topography of the Human Imagination,” and suggested that
                        “Blake’s interest in London corresponds to other contemporary
                        interests in anatomy texts and cartographic developments during his
                        life.” Blake “must transform the landscape from which his map has
                        been drawn, an external re-mapping which will cause distinctly new interior
                        maps to spring forth”—in particular, the London that Blake
                        “wishes to re-construct is an artistically remapped London based upon
                        anatomical details.” Jim’s illustrations pointed to
                        Vesalius’ <hi rend="i">Fabrica</hi>, an important anatomical text, as
                        a source for the poses of some Blake figures. In “UnLocking
                        Blake’s Crystal CabiNet,” Tom Vogler related some of the
                        significant details and the poetic argument of that poem to Blake’s
                        understanding and detestation of Lockean epistemology and metaphysics.
                        Referring to Barker’s famous Panorama of 1787 and to Bentham’s
                        proposed Panopticon, Tom characterized the speaker of the poem as one who
                        has entered “the tower of observation, or the Lockean stage of
                        self-reflection, in which he can see himself seeing, while we see him seeing
                        himself and describing what he sees.” Here, however, “the power of
                        observation does not unlock the epistemological prison but rather
                        constitutes it and expands it.” The speaker’s attempt to
                        “‘seize the inmost Form’ reveals that there is <hi rend="i">nothing</hi> there
that can be seized, perceived, or
                        comprehended by natural vision.” In his remarks on “Classical Line
                        and Romantic Identity,” Morris Eaves argued against the recent tendency
                        to use Blake’s favorite aesthetic opposition—line vs.
                        color—to align him with artistic <corr type="emend">neoclassicism</corr> and eighteenth-century
                        attitudes toward art. For Morris,
                        “Blake—characteristically—reestablishes Enlightenment
                        principles on romantic grounds. In the case of artistic line, he shears off
                        certain conventional associations (of line with reason and nature, for
                        instance), retains others (of line with intellect), and adds still others
                        (of line with imagination). The result is a thoroughly romantic cluster of
                        metaphors.” The Session closed with a response in the spirit of true
                        friendship from Stephen Carr; addressing each of the preceding papers,
                        Steve’s meta-critical effort attended to some characteristic problems
                        of placing Blake within standard categories and sequences of literary
                        history. “Reading Blake forces us to explore, to question, and in 
<pb id="p14-231" n="231"/>
some sense to deconstruct received categories and
                        methods of literary history and criticism . . . consequently a first stage
                        or gesture in approaching this topic is to subject ourselves to a much more
                        rigorous scrutiny than is usually the case.” As the four papers and the
                        response wonderfully demonstrate, we still have much to learn about Blake
                        and the eighteenth century.</p>
          <p>A petition urging the MLA to consider the creation of a Blake Discussion
                        Group was signed by forty-three members of the audience. The petition was
                        forwarded to the MLA, where it was promptly rejected.
                        <byline><docAuthor>NELSON <name>HILTON</name>,</docAuthor>
                        UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA.</byline></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
