<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.4.lentricchia</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Frank Lentricchia, After the New Criticism</title>
        <author n="Hilton">Nelson Hilton</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
              <name>Erik Frykman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>William Vaughan</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <pb id="p14-212" n="212"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-4-0010">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Frank Lentricchia. <hi rend="b">After the New Criticism.</hi>
                            Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1980. xiv + 384 pp.
                            $20.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Nelson <name>Hilton</name>.</docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Frank Lentricchia’s study of the last twenty odd years of literary
                        criticism in America, <hi rend="i">After the New Criticism</hi>, should be
                        of interest to any reader of Blake who has been idling “within a
                        structure of higher education where fortresslike walls isolate the various
                        areas of humane learning from one another” (pp. 135-36) and who would
                        like to get briefed on the decade’s coming title fight. The title, as
                        Humpty-Dumpty explains to Alice, concerns “who is to be master,”
                        or, if the reader prefers Obi Wan Kenobi, who is to possess “the
                        force”; and the contenders are the devouring empire of structuralist
                        and poststructuralist criticism, with its annihilating vision of the
                        subject, and Blake, with his prolific, self-annihilated subject. It will be
                        a fitting conclusion (i.e., synthesis into thesis) for a history which
                        begins with “The Place of Northrop Frye’s <hi rend="i">Anatomy
                            of Criticism</hi>,” or really even earlier, since Lentricchia
                        reports that readers of “<hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi> know that
                        that book had forecast the whole of [Frye’s] literary theory as well
                        as the furious rebirth of interest in a problematic writer,” and also
                        that, “Its general critical claims aside, the <hi rend="i">Anatomy</hi>
                        gave the Blake revivalists their proper poetics” (p. 4).
                        Lentricchia’s opening round is directed against the conception of art
                        in “apocalyptic humanism” which “reminds us (if ever we
                        needed reminding) of Frye’s Blakean commitments” (pp. 96, 23).
                        That conception surfaces again towards the end of the book, in a discussion
                        of Harold Bloom, where Lentricchia notes “the portentous (and
                        nostalgic) first sentence of <hi rend="i">The Visionary Company</hi>”
                        that when Blake died, “‘the firm belief in the autonomy of a
                        poet’s imagination died with him’” (p. 323). So one may
                        even read Blake into the origin or center (if one for the nonce believes in
                        such things) of Lentricchia’s history and enter the lists for his
                        name’s sake (<hi rend="i">In hoc signes</hi> . . . ).</p>
          <p>“The difficult term ‘history,’” Lentricchia tells us
                        in his Preface, “plays a decisive role” in his argument, which has
                        as one fundamental concern the exploration and critique of the “subtle
                        denial of history” he finds in “vast areas of contemporary
                        criticism.” The thrust of this concern appears in the titles of
                        chapters four and five—the book’s most significant sections,
                        and, according to the Preface, the ones which present the author’s
                        perspective most overtly—“uncovering History and the Reader:
                        Structuralism,” and “History or the Abyss:
                        Poststructuralism.” Lentricchia opposes “conceptions of a
                        ‘history’ which would generate itself as a unity and a
                        totality while resisting 
<pb id="p14-213" n="213"/>
forces of heterogeneity,
                        contradiction, fragmentation, and difference . . . which would deny
                        ‘histories’” (p. xiv). So it would seem we are offered a
                        “histories of criticism,” and indeed the first half of the
                        book—“A Critical Thematics, 1957-77”—also devotes
                        chapters to Frye, “Versions of Existentialism,” and “Versions
                        of Phenomenology.” There is, however, a consistent base perspective
                        worked up out of early Barthes, Jameson, Said, Foucault, and, ostensibly,
                        non-Yale-co-opted Derrida (Lentricchia claims “no originality” [p.
                        xi]) which continually directs us to acknowledge “worldly
                        determinates,” “the real state of sublunary nature,”
                        “historical life,” “ensnaring relations,” “enormous
                        constraints,” the “ineffaceable historicity of discourse”:
                        “the force that defines and appropriates tradition and knowledge and
                        encloses our cognitive reach within their boundaries” (pp. 10, 24, 26,
                        100, 143, 175, 154). We seem to glimpse this ground in the following
                        discussion of Heidegger’s existentialism, which, says Lentricchia,
                        “is an escape from the real implications of his master metaphor of the
                        world as <hi rend="i">workshop.</hi> For the metaphor demands that the world
                        be placed not in an existential context but within a frame of economic and
                        political power.” This statement could be pressed, to follow a common
                        Lentricchian strategy, to an apparent contradiction (ergo, the reader of the
                        book will understand, cognitive nullity): how can the world be placed within
                        one frame? and how do economic and political power dictate a situation where
                        metaphors make demands? As for Heidegger, his metaphoric failure is another
                        indication that his “philosophy is fundamentally nostalgic and
                        world-weary”—an improvement, at least, over Frye’s
                        “thoroughly despairing and alienated understanding of the possibilities
                        of historical life” (pp. 100, 26).</p>
          <p>Lentricchia offers a wonderful mine of summaries and recapitulations which in
                        themselves make his book useful and deserving of our thanks. But since 
<hi rend="i">After the New Criticism</hi> will stand or fall according to
                        the reader’s response to the conception of history that Lentricchia
                        urges not only for the practice of literary history, but for literary
                        criticism as well, that conception deserves further consideration. In
                        particular, a reader of this journal would want to ask, how would
                        Lentricchia benefit the study of Blake? We are told of “the powerful
                        constitutive forces of the historical process (political and economic
                        contexts, class differences, and so on)” that Culler’s idea of
                        the reader (in <hi rend="i">Structuralist Poetics</hi>) “somehow . . .
                        blocked out,” and we are offered for ratification Saussure’s
                        situation of “discourse, literary and otherwise, in its true home in
                        human history” and the <corr type="emend">concomitant</corr> “recognition of the
                        powerlessness of the individual subject, his passive and repressed status .
                        . . and . . . of the vast and frightening force of human collectives to
                        seize discourse for the ends of power” (pp. 111, 119-20). We are asked
                        to approve Lentricchia’s admiration for the early work of Barthes and
                        its conclusion that “‘literary history is possible only if it
                        becomes sociological’” but to reject the “intertextuality
                        or Writing” of the later Barthes as solipsistic fantasies of “a
                        seeker of pleasure in isolation from social, cognitive, and ethical
                        dimensions of selfhood” (p. 145). For the student of Blake, a
                        particularly moving and gripping example of the power of the Foucaultian
                        “discursive formation” to control what is “‘within the
                        truth’ (<hi rend="i">dans le vrai</hi>)” is offered by
                        Lentricchia’s remarks on Frost: 
						<q> . . . if one would not write
                            poetry in a void as did Robert Frost (when he achieved magazine
                            publication only five times between 1895 and 1912, a period during which
                            he wrote a number of poems later acclaimed), then one had better assent
                            to the rules of discursive policy by placing oneself within the confines
                            of those systems that determine biological or poetic truth for
                            one’s time. To refuse to conform is to accept a place, whether
                            one intends to or not, alongside society’s more dramatically
                            visible outcasts: the criminals, the insane, racial minorities, and the
                            indigent, who are brutally and unhesitatingy subjected to the power that
                            divides and silences. (p. 197) </q>
Well, Lentricchia would no doubt
                        reprove our presumption, but perhaps we should “commit ourselves to
                        this void, and see whether providence is here also” (<hi rend="i">MHH</hi>
17).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n100" type="note">1</ref> It is certainly a
                        wonderful irony (unintended or not) to read in this book, published by the
                        University of Chicago Press, that “to be critically <hi rend="i">dans
                            le vrai</hi> in 1980 is to speak under the imprimatur of certain
                        preferred presses and journals” (p. 198).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n101" type="note">2</ref> This sniping could be continued at length to show how
                        Lentricchia wishes to replace what we might call imagination with the
                        pre-pleasure-seeking Barthes’ conception of semiological systems
                        “put into operation, put into force <hi rend="i">by force</hi>”
                        (p. 132). But for all this, we might remember (as Lentricchia never does)
                        even the supremely privileged Derrida’s observation that “the
                        force of the work, the force of genius, the force, too, of that which
                        engenders in general . . . is the proper object of literary
                            criticism.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n102"
type="note">3</ref> Finally, on the
                        force of Lentricchia’s own historiography, we might note his remark
                        that Foucault’s “naked statement of his goals as a historian is
                        not evidence of what could be (and has been) termed old-fashioned
                        historicist naiveté, but of a passionate belief that genuine history
                        writing is not only possible, but is <hi rend="i">made possible</hi> by
                        Derrida’s revision of traditionalist thought in general and of
                        structuralism in particular” (p. 191, Lentricchia’s emphasis
                        again). Seeing as how Foucault is cited only in translation (indeed, <hi rend="i">The
History of Sexuality</hi> seems to have arrived just in
                        time to dominate the “Afterword”), Lentricchia was perhaps unaware
                        of Foucault’s “passionate” and stinging criticism of
                        Derrida and his “system” appended to the second edition of <hi rend="i">Histoire
de la folie</hi> (Paris: Gallimard, 1972). The
                        Derridean “revision of traditionalist thought” that Foucault sees
                        is “a petty pedagogy that has been powerfully determined by history,
                        which. . . . teaches the student that there is nothing outside the text. . .
                        . A pedagogy which . . . gives to the voice of the master-teacher that
                        unlimited sovereignty which authorizes its unending retelling of the
                            text.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n103" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n100"><hi rend="s">1</hi> On the question of Blake in the void,
                            see Morris Eaves, “Romantic Expressive Theory and Blake’s
                            Idea of the Audience,” <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi>, 95 (Oct. 1980),
                            784-801; on Blake and Foucault, see Daniel Stempel, “Blake,
                            Foucault, and the Classical Episteme,” forthcoming in 
<hi rend="i">PMLA.</hi></note>
	<note id="n101"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Doubly ironic (unintended or not)
                            because of Lentricchia’s fascination with the significance of
                            imprimatur: “[Joseph] Conrad’s perception will not explain
                            why the MLA granted its imprimatur to Culler” (i.e., the James
                            Russell Lowell Prize for <hi rend="i">Structuralist Poetics</hi>), or,
                            to realize that Poulet and phenomenology had caught on in the late
                            sixties, “we need only recall the imprimatur of the Harvard
                            University Press on Sarah Lawall’s exposition, <hi rend="i">Critics of
Consciousness</hi> (1968)” (pp. 104, 64).</note>
	<note id="n102"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Jacques Derrida, “Force and
                            Signification,” in <hi rend="i">Writing and Difference</hi>,
                            trans., intro., add. notes, Alan Bass (Chicago: Univ. of Chicago Press,
                            1978), p. 20.</note>
	<note id="n103"><hi rend="s">4</hi> The original reads, “ . . . je
                            dirai que c’est une petite pédagogie historiquement bien
                            determinée. . . . Pédagogie qui enseign à
                            l’élève qu’il n’y a rien hors du
                            texte. . . . Pédagogie qui . . . donne à la voix des
                            maîtres cette souveraineté sans limite qui lui permet
                            indéfiniment de redire le texte” (p. 602).</note></p>
          <p>“Structure, Sign, and Play in the Discourse of the Human
                        Sciences”—“an elegant attack on the traditionalist position
                        in general” (p. 160)—is the 
<pb id="p14-214" n="214"/>
most
                        cited of Derrida’s works in <hi rend="i">After the New
                            Criticism.</hi> As Lentricchia often reminds us, that warhorse (now
                        fourteen years old!) introduced “the structurality of structure”
                        and the concept of “the center . . . the creation of the ‘force
                        of desire.’ In something like an ultimate act of wish-fulfillment,
                        desire attempts to establish the center beyond fictive status as objective
                        reality.” Lentricchia adds, “The impact of Derrida on the
                        traditionalist position can be measured most precisely, I think, by his
                        singular success in stirring up that old unmasterable anxiety about the
                        center” (p. 165). Lentricchia rides these concepts far: through Sartre,
                        through Stevens, through “systems of last-ditch humanism” (p. 33),
                        but most effectively when he introduces a quotation from <hi rend="i">Anatomy of
Criticism</hi> to show “How uncannily Frye anticipates
                        and, then, crucially rejects” the future Derridean position:
                        “‘Criticism as knowledge . . . recognizes the fact that there
                            <hi rend="i">is</hi> a center of the order of words. Unless there is
                        such a center, there is nothing to prevent the analogies supplied by
                        convention and genre from being an endless series of free associations . . .
                        never creating a real structure’” (p. 14). Frye’s
                        conception of human desire, Lentricchia notes, “causes form or
                        structure to come into being while remaining itself unconditioned by
                        law”; it is “the sure ground, the guarantee of Frye’s
                        ultimate humanism” (p. 15). “Over and over,” Lentricchia
                        tells us that Frye tells us, “the literary universe is a representation
                        not of the way things are, but of the ways of human desire” (p. 19). It
                        would be inappropriate to ask Lentricchia what he would do with
                        Blake’s principle that “The desire of Man being Infinite the
                        possession is Infinite &amp; himself Infinite” (<hi rend="i">NNR</hi>b), but we can
remark the striking absence from <hi rend="i">After
                            the New Criticism</hi> of any concern for one who has for the last
                        decade presented desire in another perception to the American critical
                        scene, Jacques Lacan (mentioned only once, in passing).</p>
          <p>The second, ante-climactic part of <hi rend="i">After the New Criticism</hi>
                        is devoted to “The American Scene: Four Exemplary Careers.” The
                        “subjects” are “Murray Krieger’s Last
                        Romanticism,” “E. D. Hirsch: The Hermeneutics of Innocence,”
                        “Paul de Man: The Rhetoric of Authority,” and “Harold Bloom:
                        The Spirit of Revenge.” One may ponder the fact that two of these
                        critics grappled with Blake in books at the early state of their careers,
                        and a third is reported to have remarked that “Blake was a
                        deconstructor before deconstructionism.” Despite some reservations
                        about a “retrograde and anti-intellectual . . . desire . . . to be an
                        original theorist,” Lentricchia is most sympathetic to that revengeful
                        spirit, Harold Bloom. And early in his discussion it is remarkable to see
                        Lentricchia become fixated on the idea of “firm belief” which
                        appears in the opening line of <hi rend="i">The Visionary Company</hi>
                        (cited above, first paragraph). After quoting the line, Lentricchia carps,
                        “Yet . . . only a few sentences after speaking of Blake’s
                        ‘firm belief in the autonomy of a poet’s imagination,’
                        [Bloom] writes of skepticism and discontinuity” (p. 323). Nonetheless,
                        “Bloom’s vacillations aside, what is essential to his romantic
                        line is a full commitment to the mythopoetic imagination. It is a commitment
                        earned (Blake’s ‘firm belief’) only because it takes
                        irony into account and transcends it; a commitment with large extrapoetic
                        sources and implications” (p. 323). Lentricchia does not dwell on the
                        power of his own insight here, but begins the following paragraph with:
                        “Still, the notion of ‘firm belief’ is a redundant phrase
                        which may, and in this instance does, betray subversive perceptions”
                        (p. 324). The student of Blake realizes with a shock that because of
                        Bloom’s indirect reference Lentricchia evidently considers “firm
                        belief” to be one of Bloom’s “Blakean indulgences,” a
                        quality he merely “celebrates in Blake” (pp. 343, 325). It is an
                        intriguing comment on influence and anxiety that, through Bloom, Blake has
                        elicited such attention.</p>
          <p>There can, I think, be little doubt as to the absolute value of the work of
                        the two men Lentricchia urges that we “return to,” Derrida and
                        Foucault (in that order, it seems). And few will question
                        Lentricchia’s understanding of their sense that they, and we,
                        “are at the end of an era” (p. 208). Yet it is a curiously
                        “undecidable” phenomenon that, in America, the same
                        “discursive formation” that has published Lentricchia, prompted
                        this review, translated Foucault, and summoned Derrida to Yale and
                        California to lecture in English has also ever more strongly brought forward
                        the figure/presence/texts/study of William Blake.</p>
		<q> Then I asked: does a firm perswasion that a thing is so, make it so? He
                        replied. All poets believe that it does, &amp; in ages of imagination this
                        firm perswasion removed mountains; but many are not capable of a firm
                        perswasion of any thing. (<hi rend="i">MHH</hi> 12) </q>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
