<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.4.vaughan</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Andrew Wilton, British Watercolours 1750 to 1850</title>
        <author n="Vaughan">William Vaughan</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
              <name>Erik Frykman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>William Vaughan</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
	<pb id="p14-218" n="218"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-4-0010">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Andrew Wilton. <hi rend="b">British Watercolours 1750 to 1850.</hi>
                            Oxford: Phaidon, 1977. 208 pp., 170 plates (53 in color).
                            £12.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>William
                        <name>Vaughan</name>.</docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The rise of watercolor painting as an independent art form is intimately
                        connected with the character and fortunes of British art in the decades
                        around 1800. An impressive number of the finest painters of the
                        time—such as John Robert Cozens, Thomas Girtin and John Sell
                        Cotman—chose it as their principal medium. Many other major
                        artists—notably William Blake and J. M. W. Turner—used it
                        frequently and with great originality. In view of this it might be expected
                        that the subject would be given an important place in any study of British
                        Romantic art. Yet on the whole it has tended to be treated as a theme apart,
                        relegated to specialists, most of whom approach it from the viewpoint of the
                        connoisseur. Such commentaries have of course been invaluable in building up
                        our knowledge of the indentity of individual practitioners and for charting
                        the history of the organizations that grew up as the practice of watercolor
                        painting expanded. But they have tended to be less informative about the
                        broader context. There is little treatment of the question of why watercolor
                        should step from its modest position as an ancillary sketching medium (as
                        which it had been used by great masters of all countries since the middle
                        ages) to that of a method suitable for finished pictures. The change
                        involved the development of new attitudes to the study of natural effects,
                        spontaneity and the interest in local scenery, all of which are connected
                        with the emergent Romantic movement. There are social questions as well.
                        Watercolor was a favored medium of amateurs and drawings masters. Not all of
                        these were insignificant figures. John Ruskin is a distinguished example of
                        the former and John Sell Cotman of the latter. But more important than this
                        from a historical point of view is the fact that watercolorists were active
                        in social groups where oil painters had little purchase. Often they cut
                        quite a figure. Thackeray talks of “gay, smart, watercolour
                        painters”; and there are examples in contemporary novels of the impact
                        they could have in the homes of gentlemen.</p>
          <p>Andrew Wilton’s book—which covers the heyday of the British
                        watercolorists—is to some extent aware of these wider issues.
                        However, he is principally concerned with providing a clear and readable
                        account of the leading lights of the school. <pb id="p14-219" n="219"/>
The
                        book is based on a series of lectures, and the chapters appear to follow
                        these closely. Each is centered on a major artist (though incorporating
                        thumbnail sketches of associates) and each is of similar length. There is,
                        of course, nothing remiss in publishing lectures. Some of the most
                        attractive and memorable books have been formed in this way. Mr.
                        Wilton’s work has certainly retrained much of the engaging atmosphere
                        of a successful lecture series. But I cannot help wishing that he had made a
                        few more concessions to the more enduring format that his text has now
                        achieved. In particular an introduction would have been welcomed. As it is
                        we are plunged straight into the work of Paul Sandby, “the father of
                        English watercolour,” without any preliminaries. At the other end of
                        the book we emerge with Turner and a sharp vertiginous vista of abstractions
                        to come in the twentieth century. An epilogue or conclusion of some kind
                        would, I feel, have been preferable.</p>
          <p>Perhaps Mr. Wilton felt that such formalities could be dispensed with because
                        his perspective on the subject was essentially traditional. Certainly his
                        handling of this viewpoint is an accomplished one. His experiences as a
                        museum curator have been put to very good use in his description of the
                        techniques of individual painters—particularly those who produced
                        landscapes. The author is perhaps best known for the studies he has made
                        into the watercolors of Turner, and the essay in this book provides a fine
                        and concise summation of his views on this topic.</p>
          <p>Mr. Wilton is less at home when dealing with the figurative tradition, and
                        appears to avoid it where he can. We are not reminded of the attempts to
                        make watercolor a vehicle for history painting, although these—as can
                        be seen in the works of Joshua Cristall—were not always disgraceful.
                        When Bonington is discussed, more interest is shown in his landscapes than
                        in his historical sketches. Most of the figurative work
                        discussed—such as that by Rowlandson and John Frederick
                        Lewis—can be fitted into the general theme of the observation of
                        nature and interest in topography. There is only one who
                        cannot—William Blake.</p>
          <p>Blake is hardly likely to fit comfortably into any general survey of British
                        art of the Romantic era. Here he stands out, not only because his subject
                        matter is so radically different from that of the other watercolorists, but
                        also because his view of watercolor itself seems to be different. He
                        certainly used watercolor a lot—more, in fact, than any other
                        painting medium—but he is definitely not within the British
                        watercolor tradition. For him it was principally a designing medium, as it
                        had been for the great European masters before him. He produced many
                        beautiful works treated in a highly original manner, most notably the Dante
                        illustrations with their touches of pure color. But he would rather have
                        been at work on frescos, if circumstances had allowed. Despite this Wilton
                        tries to make watercolor the focus of his career, even going so far as to
                        characterize his color printing as “another manifestation of his
                        inventive use of watercolour.”</p>
          <p>Blake’s position does pinpoint a problem within the book as a
                        whole—the degree of commitment to watercolor as a medium felt by the
                        artists under discussion. Some made it their career, some used it
                        sporadically for convenience or as a means of making preparatory studies.
                        Wilton treats both categories equally without discussing the distinction.
                        Thus Constable—who was no enthusiastic watercolorist—is given
                        the same billing as such masters of the medium as Girtin, Cotman and Turner.
                        This also leads to the discussion of much material that seems extraneous to
                        the history of watercolor in the case of those artists for whom the
                        technique was not a ruling passion.</p>
          <p>There is, however, much that is attractive about the book. Apart from the
                        readability of the text, there is also the selection of plates. This is far
                        from being a simple rerun of classics—although some of the most
                        breathtaking examples (such as Girtin’s “White House”) have
                        properly been included. It brings to light many little known
                        gems—such as W. H. Hunt’s “Little Girl Reading.” The
                        biographies of the artists and notes on the plates are highly informative.
                        So much so, in fact, that it seems a shame that this section could not have
                        been extended, and a broader introduction provided by the main text.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
