<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.4.fischer</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Mary Lynn Johnson and John E. Grant, eds., Blake’s Poetry and Designs</title>
        <author n="Fischer">Michael Fischer</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
              <name>Erik Frykman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>William Vaughan</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-4-0010">
        <pb id="p14-215" n="215"/>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Mary Lynn Johnson and John E. Grant, eds. <hi rend="b">Blake’s
                                Poetry and Designs.</hi> New York and London: W. W. Norton, 1979.
                            xlviii + 618 pp., 113 illus. (32 color plates). $9.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Michael
                        <name>Fischer</name>.</docAuthor></byline>
          <p>After laying down rules for textbooks in “Choosing Textbooks for Blake
                        Courses: A Survey &amp; Checklist,” <hi rend="i">Blake
                        Newsletter</hi>, 10 (Summer, 1976), 9-26, Mary Lynn Johnson has decided to
                        play the game. The result—the Norton Critical Edition of Blake
                        (edited with John E. Grant)—is one of the best Blake textbooks in
                        print.</p>
          <p>The selections from Blake’s work are well-organized, accessible, and
                        generous, so generous, in fact, that it is easier to list what the editors
                        excerpt (<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>, the Notebook, <hi rend="i">The
                            Four Zoas, Jerusalem, A Descriptive Catalogue, A Vision of the Last
                            Judgment</hi>, the Marginalia, and the Letters) than what they include
                        in its entirety (virtually everything else of importance, including 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>). Thirty-two color plates from the illuminated
                        books let students know what they are missing when they concentrate on Blake
                        in print. Numerous monochrome reproductions interspersed throughout the text
                        are less spectacular but still helpful in indicating how Blake designed his
                        work. The prefaces and notes are also useful: their tone is sympathetic but
                        not canonical, their relation to the text about right. They seldom
                        overshadow or complicate the lines that they try to explain; they identify
                        terms and characters without allegorizing them. When the editors make
                        difficult editorial decisions—and with Blake’s punctuation
                        they of course must—they always explain their reasoning and refer us
                        to other sources, especially the editions of David Erdman and Geoffrey
                        Keynes. A chronology, maps of Britain, London, and the Holy Land, an
                        extensive bibliography, a list of key terms with page numbers pointing to
                        definitions and examples in the text, commentary by some of Blake’s
                        contemporaries (Coleridge, Robinson, and Lamb, among others), and several
                        essays by twentieth-century critics—these useful accessories complete
                        the volume. The critical essays, I should add, are adequate, if predictable,
                        including contributions by Northrop Frye, Jean Hagstrum, David Erdman, and
                        Harold Bloom, among others. T. S. Eliot’s “William Blake”
                        and Irene Tayler’s “The Woman Scaly,” however, come as
                        pleasant surprises. Eliot introduces a dissenting voice in what threatens to
                        be a chorus of unqualified approval; Tayler takes on one of the most
                        important and least understood issues in Blake—his treatment of the
                        sex roles and sexuality.</p>
          <p>No book is perfect, not even this one. While Blake’s Marginalia is a
                        welcome addition to a book of this kind, the editors’ omission of the
                        passages 
<pb id="p14-216" n="216"/>
to which he is reacting robs many of his
                        statements of their humor, force, and truth. A sentence like “Execution
                        is the Chariot of Genius” sounds like an odd exercise in
                        hyperbole—unless one has been reading Reynolds on execution and
                        genius. The editors rightly note that “Blake could have been a
                        masterful controversialist, or even a heckler,” but their presentation
                        of his annotations won’t allow students to discover why. Although the
                        critical essays do not ignore Blake’s drawings—in fact,
                        Hagstrum and Erdman devote a great deal of attention to them—they
                        nevertheless reflect the interests of the literary critics who write them.
                        An essay by an art historian might have placed Blake in art history and
                        revealed what attracts visual artists to his work. Even more importantly, a
                        fuller discussion of Blake’s methods as an engraver would have been
                        useful. Familiarity with these techniques allows us to see Blake’s
                        critical ideas as he saw them—as practical principles anchored in his
                        everyday life as an artist. Finally, many of the critical essays contain
                        page references to Keynes and Erdman which will force the student to get
                        another book or go digging through this one. When possible, the editors
                        should have correlated these references with citations to their own
                        edition.</p>
          <p>But these are minor problems. The highest tribute one can pay to a book like
                        this is to use it, and I plan to in the next undergraduate course I teach on
                        Blake. Or so I dare to hope, for declining enrollments in upper-level
                        literature classes have made such courses rare. Textbooks like this one are
                        consequently in danger of disappearing with small colleges, tenure-track
                        contracts, and other relics of an earlier day. In “Choosing
                        Textbooks” (1976), Johnson could write that “more and more people
                        are preparing to teach Blake for the first time, or teach more of Blake than
                        they did last year, to a growing audience of new readers.” Today some
                        of us are hoping to teach him one more time.</p>
          <p>Of course literature textbooks are still published but, I would suspect, at a
                        slower rate. And even many of those books that do see print reflect the
                        limited functions that they now serve. If tested by the needs of students,
                            <hi rend="i">The Oxford Anthology of English Literature: Romantic Poetry
                            and Prose</hi>, for example, would probably fail. Harold Bloom’s
                        introduction explains that “the major Romantic questers, whether we see
                        these as the poets themselves or as the quasi-autobiographical heroes of
                        their poems, are all engaged in the extraordinary enterprise of seeking to
                        re-beget their own selves, as though through the imagination a man might
                        hope to become his own father, or at least his own heroic precursor.”
                        The headnote to the section on Wordsworth similarly describes modern poetry
                        as “the poetry of the growing inner self.” Although that self
                        “was a Protestant creation,” “before Luther it was prefigured
                        in Catholic thinkers as diverse as the furious reformer Savonarola and the
                        meditative Thomas à Kempis, who wrote <hi rend="i">The Imitation of
                            Christ.</hi>” Blake, too, “was primarily an intellectual
                        revisionist, even as <corr type="emend">Nietzsche,</corr> Marx, Freud, in the longest perspective,
                        seem most important as revisionists of the European Enlightenment.”</p>
          <p>Whatever their other merits, I agree with Johnson that these statements seem
                        out of place in a textbook. Instead of enlightening students, Bloom’s
                        over-writing deepens their suspicion that they are missing out on some
                        mystery that no one will explain—some “extraordinary”
                        affair involving men trying to become their own fathers,
                        “daemonic” intellectual revisionists, and “furious”
                        fifteenth-century Italian monks (the strongest students have looked up
                        Savonarola in their Random House Dictionary). One can imagine the
                        frustration of these students when they confront so many unexplained terms
                        and names—or, more precisely, one has to imagine it because in the
                        absence of courses on Romanticism, <hi rend="i">The Oxford Anthology</hi>
                        never faces this kind of test. Isolation from a classroom audience may
                        explain why so few readers have objected to the book’s insularity.
                        These readers have become professional critics and the book another episode
                        in Bloom’s criticism.</p>
          <p>Constructed with the needs of non-specialists in mind, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Poetry and
Designs</hi> is a welcome exception to the
                        trend I have been describing. Either the marketplace is flexible enough to
                        allow the publication of seemingly obsolete books, or this kind of textbook
                        is not yet obsolete. I hope that both possibilities are true. In either
                        case, Grant and Johnson have made it easier (if not easy) for us to teach
                        Blake’s poetry and prose.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
