<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.4.gleckner</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">W. J. Linton’s Tailpieces in Gilchrist’s Life of William Blake</title>
        <author n="Gleckner">Robert F. Gleckner</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
              <name>Erik Frykman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>William Vaughan</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-4-0008">
        <pb id="p14-208" n="208"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">W. J. LINTON’S TAILPIECES IN GILCHRIST’S LIFE OF WILLIAM BLAKE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Robert F.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Gleckner</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>In his <hi rend="i">Bibliography of William Blake</hi> Sir Geoffrey Keynes made an
            attempt to identify all of Blake’s designs from which W. J. Linton made his wood
            engravings for the 1863 edition of Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William
              Blake, “Pictor Ignotus”</hi>: in Volume I four full-page cuts (three from the Job
            series and “Plague”) and fifty-six smaller cuts in the text; in Volume II seven small
            wood engravings in the text.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n90"
type="note">1</ref> Logically assuming
            from the Gilchrist titlepage statement, “Illustrated from Blake’s own works, in
            facsimile by W. J. Linton,” that all of these cuts (other than those “in
            photolithography” and the “few” Blake “original plates”) were based on, or engraved
            after, Blake originals, Keynes nevertheless lists ten in Volume I and three in Volume II
            as unidentified (he ignored the one on page 111 of Volume II)—all rather miniscule
            chapter tailpieces. In <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977) G.
            E. Bentley, Jr. makes no comment about Linton’s contributions to the 
              <hi rend="i">Life</hi>, and Robert Essick in his “Finding List of Reproductions of Blake’s
Art,”
              <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 5 (1971), 1-160, lists only Linton’s full-page
            cuts—properly so given the purpose of the list. <note id="n90"><hi rend="s">1</hi> (New
              York: The Grolier Club, 1921), pp. 328-31. Keynes erroneously lists a Linton cut on
              II, 1, and II, 2; they are on II, ix (unnumbered page), and II, 1, respectively. The
              frontispiece of Linnell’s 1827 portrait of Blake is apparently the only engraving not
              done by Linton: it is by C. H. Jeens.</note></p>
          <p>In my recent research toward an article on Linton and Blake (forthcoming in the 
              <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi>) I re-examined all of Linton’s
            contributions to Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi> and have managed to identify all but
            three of the tailpieces unidentified by Keynes. They form an interesting pattern, one
            that reflects certain problems Linton had with Dante Gabriel Rossetti over the inclusion
            in the Gilchrist of photolithographed reproductions of the Job designs. Of the thirteen
            tailpieces (fourteen including the one on page 111 of Volume II) the sources of which
            Keynes could not identify, nine are from the border design of Plate 12 of the Job series
            (see illus. 3): 
			<q> Volume I, page 11: the sixth figure from the top right of Job 12,
              reversed.<lb/>
 Volume I, page 42: figures at bottom right.<lb/>
 Volume I, page 118:
              figures at bottom left.<lb/>
 Volume I, page 126: figures at top center.<lb/>
 Linton
              added to, and changed, Blake’s stars, designing them in his own characteristically
              spiky manner (see illus. 1).<lb/>
 Volume I, page 233: fifth figure from top right,
              reversed, again with Linton’s spiky stars (see illus. 2).<lb/>
 Volume I, page 248:
              third figure from top left.<lb/>
 Volume II, page 97: third figure from bottom right,
              turned sideways.<lb/>
 Volume II, page 111: figure just above center right.<lb/>
 Volume
              II, page 116: figure at upper-right corner of main design box.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n91"
                type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n91"><hi rend="s">2</hi> None of these appears in the
                1880 edition of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life.</hi></note></q></p>
          <p>Elsewhere in Gilchrist we have Linton’s wood engravings of Job Plates 5, 8, and 14 (all
            full-page, the last excluding Blake’s border designs 
              <figure n="Gilchrist126.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="366">
              <head>1 Tailpiece from Gilchrist, Vol. I, p. 126, after <hi rend="i">Job</hi>
                12.</head>
            </figure>
            <figure n="Gilchrist233.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="365">
              <head>2 Tailpiece from Gilchrist, Vol. I, p. 233 after <hi rend="i">Job</hi>
                12.</head>
            </figure> except for the corner angels), the top half of the border design of Plate 18,
            and the circular part of the main boxed design of Plate 15. From Rossetti’s
            correspondence with Anne Gilchrist (who had taken over the editing of the 
              <hi rend="i">Life</hi> at the death of her husband) as the volumes were nearing completion, we
            learn that, despite their plans to include photolithographs of the entire Job series,
            Linton (who had been a part of the project as early as 1861<ref target="n92" type="note">3</ref>
and, one would presume, knew about the photolithography idea) went ahead and
            executed his own wood engravings of the entire series.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n93" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n92"><hi rend="s">3</hi> On 20 April 1861 Rossetti had written to
              Alexander Gilchrist to suggest a friend of his to work on the Blake illustrations: “I
              have been thinking that if you are still unprovided with a satisfactory copyist (or a
              sufficiency of such) for the Blakes,—Mrs. Edward [Burne] Jones would be very likely to
              succeed. This occurred to me shortly after seeing you the other day, but I did not see
              her till today, when I mentioned the matter to her. I hope I did not do wrong, but she
              is too intimate a friend to make it awkward for me if you and Linton cannot entertain
              the idea”—<hi rend="i">Letters of Dante Gabriel Rossetti</hi>, ed. Oswald Doughty and
              John R. Wahl (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1965), II, 396. This seems to suggest that
              Linton originally may have planned (or been hired) only to supervise (and/or execute a
              few of) the engravings for the <hi rend="i">Life.</hi> In any case, nothing seems to
              have come of the matter.</note>
	<note id="n93"><hi rend="s">4</hi> This is an
              assumption on my part. Rossetti’s words, in the letter to Mrs. Gilchrist quoted below,
              are “the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> Plates which he [Linton] copied.” It is possible, then,
              that these plates are the five I have already noted—though Linton’s pillaging of the
              border design of Plate 12 argues that he did more than five.</note></p>
          <p>It is not clear what led to this confusion, for in February 1863 Linton had written to
            Rossetti “about the illustrations” and Rossetti had even taken the trouble of visiting
            Linton to consult with 
<pb id="p14-209" n="209"/>
<figure n="bb421.1.14-13.ps" id="bb421.1.spb.14" work-copy="bb421.1" rend="db" width="786" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>12<lb/>
	For God speaketh once yea twice<lb/>
	&amp; Man percieveth it not<lb/>
	That he may withdraw Man from his purpose<lb/>
	&amp; hide Pride from Man<lb/>
	If there be with him an Interpreter One among a Thousand<lb/>
	In a Dream in a Vision of the Night<lb/>
	in deep Slumberings upon the bed<lb/>
	Then he openeth the ears of Men &amp; sealeth their instruction<lb/>
	then he is gracious unto him<lb/>
	&amp; saith Deliver him from going down to the Pit<lb/>
	I have found a Ransom<lb/>
	For his eyes are upon<lb/>
	the ways of Man &amp; he observeth<lb/>
	all his goings<lb/>
	I am Young &amp; ye are very Old wherefore I was afraid<lb/>
	Lo all these things worketh God oftentimes with Man to bring<lb/>
	back his Soul from the pit to be enlightened<lb/>
	with the light of the living<lb/>
	Look upon the heavens &amp; behold the clouds<lb/>
	which are higher<lb/>
	than thou<lb/>
	If thou sinnest. what<lb/>
	doest thou against him. or if thou be<lb/>
	righteous what givest thou unto him<lb/>
	WBlake invenit &amp; sculpt<lb/>
	London Published as the Act directs March 8: 1825 by WillmBlake N 3 Fountain Court Strand<lb/>
	Proof</figTranscr>
              <head>3 <hi rend="i">Job</hi> 12.</head>
            </figure>
<pb id="p14-210" n="210"/>
			him about them.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n94" type="note">5</ref>
            At about the same time Rossetti received from Mrs. Gilchrist the Job photolithographs
            which he said pleased him “much—being, though blurry, very full of colour, and not
            losing perhaps by reduction but getting concentrated in a pleasant way.”<ref
              target="n95" type="note">6</ref> Taken together, these letters suggest that the plan
            to photolithograph the Jobs was one of long-standing. The only problem with Linton
            involved a design he engraved for the titlepage, the original of which Rossetti
            apparently had not seen, for upon receiving it (or, more likely, a proof of it) from
            Mrs. Gilchrist he returned it to her for some “amendment,” saying he would venture “to
            write a word to Mr. Linton suggesting the removal of the cut, which surely is no
            facsimile from anything of Blake’s, but a sort of design by some one else.” Then, as if
            doubting his authority, he added a postscript to this letter: “Would you perhaps send
            the Titlepage on to Mr. Linton—to explain better what I mean.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n96"
              type="note">7</ref> But Rossetti, perhaps reinforced by Mrs. Gilchrist in a letter not
            extant, did nevertheless “advise” Linton to omit “that insane cut in the title
              page.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n97" type="note">8</ref> With all this
to-do there is no evidence
            in the letters of Rossetti or Mrs. Gilchrist to suggest any misunderstanding about the
            Job series. When Linton sent Rossetti the (apparently) final list of illustrations to
            the volumes, then, and included in it all his copies of the Jobs, Rossetti was in a
            quandary about what to do with them since the photolithographs were ready to go. He
            quickly wrote Mrs. Gilchrist: “I see he still includes the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> Plates
            which he copied, in spite of the photolithographs which might be considered to supersede
              them.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n98" type="note">9</ref> What finally
emerged is clearly a kind of
            compromise, Linton no doubt insisting that at least some of his Jobs be included even
            along with the full photolithographed set,<hi rend="s">10</hi> Rossetti urging Mrs.
            Gilchrist (in the letter just quoted) that “it seemed a pity to leave them out after the
            trouble and expense.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n99" type="note">10</ref>
Why all the rest of Linton’s
            Jobs that were included, piecemeal, as tailpieces turn out to be one, Plate 12, I cannot
            say. Perhaps that plate was, simply, one of his favorites; perhaps, even more simply, it
            was the only other one that he actually engraved. <note id="n94"><hi rend="s">5</hi>
              Letter from Rossetti to Mrs. Gilchrist, dated only “Feb. 1863,” in 
                <hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, II, 477. There is a hint, however, that there was some earlier
              difficulty over the Job project. On 13 December 1862 William Michael Rossetti, who was
              also very much a part of the Gilchrist <hi rend="i">Life</hi> enterprise, wrote to
              Mrs. Gilchrist: “I am truly sorry that so much anxiety to you has been involved in the
              Job affair”—<hi rend="i">Letters of William Michael Rossetti</hi>, ed. Clarence Gohdes
              and Paull F. Baum (Durham: Duke Univ. Press, 1934), p. 11. I can find no other
              reference to an apparent problem—though, of course, Linton <hi rend="i">may</hi> have
              been the cause. Dante Gabriel once said of him, “He keeps stomach-aches for you” even
              if he was the best engraver around—Oswald Doughty, <hi rend="i">Dante Gabriel
                Rossetti: A Victorian Romantic</hi> (New Haven: Yale Univ. Press, 1949), p.
              215.</note>
	<note id="n95"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Another letter of February 1863 from
              Rossetti to Mrs. Gilchrist, in <hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, II, 477.</note>	
              <note id="n96"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Letter from Rossetti to Mrs. Gilchrist, dated only “1863”
              but apparently later than those already cited, in <hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, II,
              482.</note>
	<note id="n97"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Letter of 1863 from Rossetti to Mrs.
              Gilchrist, in <hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, II, 483.</note>
	<note id="n98"><hi rend="s">9</hi><hi rend="i"> Letters</hi>, II, 489. This “list” was perhaps that from
which
              the “List of Illustrations” (Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life</hi>, I, xiii-xiv) was to be
              made, for earlier Rossetti had written to Mrs. Gilchrist that “Mr. Linton has sent me
              a list of the illustrations [n.b.: not <hi rend="i">his</hi>] which must come in
              somewhere. I will see with the Printer” (<hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, II, 488). I have
              been unable to learn whether the list has survived.</note>
	<note id="n99"><hi rend="s">10</hi> The listing of Linton’s Job plates in the “List of Illustrations”
following
              the contents pages of the <hi rend="i">Life</hi> is accompanied by the notation: “Two
              only the centres the same size as the originals [i.e. Job 5 and 14], and one reduced
              to show border [i.e. Job 8]. These Plates are given in duplicate in the Series
              rendered by Photolithography.” There is no notation accompanying the listing of
              Linton’s engravings of Job 15 and 18.</note></p>
          <p>Of the other five tailpieces Keynes could not identify, I can be certain of only one,
            that on page 269 of Volume I, which is the lower-left figure on the titlepage of 
              <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi> That on page 160 of Volume I (see
            illus 4) may be a version (reversed) of the reclining figure in the center of Plate 4 of
              <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, or possibly of the second figure from the bottom right of
            Job 12, or even more likely to my eye, the figure to the left of the word “Albion” on
            the titlepage of <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>—though I have no
            great confidence in these sources since all of the other tailpieces are exact replicas.
            For those on pages 304 and 367 of Volume I, and 24 of Volume II (see illus. 5, 6, 7), I
            cannot find even good analogues. Perhaps these last were taken from the excised
            titlepage design; or they are examples of Linton’s idea of a Blakean figure or design;
            or they are taken from other of Linton’s own voluminous work (the one on II, 24, for
            example, is strongly reminiscent of details in several of Linton’s wood engravings for
            Harriet Martineau’s <hi rend="i">A Description of the English Lakes</hi>, 1858). In any
            case, Linton’s entire role in the Gilchrist project, as well as his own fascinating
            Blake-like career, deserve considerably more scholarly and critical attention than they
            have been accorded to date.</p>
          <figure n="Gilchrist160.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="214">
            <head>4 From Gilchrist, Volume I, p. 160.</head>
          </figure>
          <figure n="Gilchrist304.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="805">
            <head>5, 6, 7 Unidentified tailpieces from Volume I, pp. 304, 367; Volume II, p.
              24.</head>
          </figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p14-211" n="211" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
