<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.4.frosch</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Simon Stuart, New Phoenix Wings: Reparation in Literature</title>
        <author n="Frosch">Thomas R. Frosch</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
              <name>Erik Frykman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>William Vaughan</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-4-0010">
        <pb id="p14-224" n="224"/>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Simon Stuart. <hi rend="b">New Phoenix Wings: Reparation in
                                Literature.</hi> London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, Ltd., 1980.
                            $23.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Thomas R.
                        <name>Frosch</name>.</docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The confrontation of psychoanalysis and literary Romanticism is a
                        particularly challenging and intriguing one. On the one hand, with its
                        interest in subjectivity, its attraction to memory, fantasy, and dream, its
                        intuitive grasp of unconscious process, its fascination with the primitive
                        and with extreme states of mind and feeling, and its commitment to the theme
                        of human desire and its vicissitudes, Romanticism would seem to demand
                        exactly the kind of illumination a psychoanalytic approach offers. On the
                        other hand, perhaps nothing is more effectively and meaningfully hostile to
                        the idealizations of Romanticism than the characteristic demythologizing
                        force of Freudian analysis; the psychoanalytic description of the neurotic
                        is often a telling negative portrayal of the Romantic hero. Indeed,
                        Freud’s work can easily be seen as both the culmination of a century
                        of Romanticism and a reaction against it. For the literary critic who finds
                        psychoanalytic models valid and compelling and who is at the same time
                        intellectually and emotionally sympathetic to Romanticism, the problem is to
                        bring Romanticism and psychoanalysis together in a way that respects both.
                        Such a project, exemplified in the work of Harold Bloom, Thomas Weiskel,
                        Richard Onorato, and others, seems to me the most important recent
                        development in Romantic studies.</p>
          <p>When it comes to Blake, the problem is especially difficult. First, Blake
                        offers an abundance of diverse Romantic attitudes; his characters include
                        both “good” and “bad” Romantics: the Sunflower, Thel,
                        Orc, Oothoon, Los, the Devil of <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>, the
                        poet’s own persona at different moments, even Urizen constitute
                        together a virtual encyclopedia of Romanticism. Blake’s poetic
                        universe is powered and pervaded by a general Romanticism, a desire for
                        paradise; and his on-going poetic adventure centers upon his attempts to
                        refine and shape that desire. It is easy for psychoanalysis to help Blake
                        criticize the negative Romanticism, but how is it to handle the positive?
                        Second, Blake’s own systematic charting of the psyche, precisely
                        because it has numerous points of similarity to Freud’s, is a
                        formidable defense against attempts to apply psychoanalytic models to his
                        work. And sure enough, most psychoanalytic references in Blake studies show
                        how Blake embodies or anticipates Freud’s theories, rather than how
                        psychoanalytic techniques of interpretation can open up an unconscious
                        dimension in Blake’s own words. A third difficulty is that Blake does
                        not lay himself bare, like Wordsworth, who virtually begs to be analyzed. As
                        compatible as Blake may be thematically with an ethic of subjectivity and
                        self-expression, poetically he belongs primarily to an older, more openly
                        literary tradition; he is a writer of calculated guises, of ironies and
                        dramatizations.</p>
          <p>Simon Stuart’s <hi rend="i">New Phoenix Wings</hi> is a psychoanalytic
                        study of literature that respects poetic idealization (customarily
                        identifying idealization with sentimentality and falsification, the author
                        writes, we tend “to pass over that area in which an idealised view can
                        penetrate an essential reality”) and that includes an extensive chapter
                        on Blake. Stuart’s approach is based on the striking and 
<pb id="p14-225" n="225"/>
controversial work of Melanie Klein, whose
                        theories have been highly influential in England, more so than in the United
                        States. Klein believed that infants in their first six months experience
                        toward the object that dominates their lives, the breast, not only positive
                        feelings but also intense feelings of aggression, and she identified these
                        sadistic impulses with the death-instinct. Culminating during the experience
                        of weaning, the aggression is expressed primarily in unconscious destructive
                        fantasies (the derivatives of which can be observed later) toward the
                        internalized image of the breast, as well as the internalized image of both
                        parents. Furthermore, in his fantasies of hatred and assault, the infant
                        fears that the object of his fury will retaliate in kind. This is the
                        paranoid-schizoid stage, schizoid because of the conflict between the
                        satisfying, pleasure-giving image of the breast and the frustrating, hostile
                        image of the breast. It is the persecuting inner object, rather than actual
                        parental discipline, that for Klein is the source of the Superego.</p>
          <p>Tormented by fears both of his own aggressive impulses and of the persecuting
                        enemy those impulses have created, the infant enters a stage of severe
                        depression, in which he is dominated by a sense of loss. But the depression
                        is countered by the growing realization that the external parents do not
                        behave like the internal fantasy parents, that despite his own aggression
                        and the sadism of the internal parents, the external ones still remain
                        loving. The infant is then moved to rebuild his inner world, which has been
                        shattered by sadism, and he passes into a stage of reparation, dominated by
                        fantasies of healing the damaged parents. This impulse of reparation, Stuart
                        emphasizes, is the source of art; to create is to recreate, to rebuild the
                        lost or fragmented internal object.</p>
          <p>Crucial to the process of reparation is a new ability to form symbols,
                        substitutes for what the infant has lost. In Klein’s treatment of
                        sublimation, when the image of the breast becomes over-whelmingly fraught
                        with conflict and anxiety, the infant forms a symbolic substitute for it;
                        the anxieties of the depressive stage thus drive the subject to sublimations
                        which, ideally, resolve the anxieties, leading to new interests and
                        activities. In this way, the death-instinct becomes the power behind the
                        creation of “life-enhancing, life-preserving activities.” The
                        alternative to reparation and symbol-formation is stultification,
                        pathological withdrawal, impotence of all types; “We must construct our
                        symbols,” writes Stuart, “or die.”</p>
          <p>Stuart examines these issues in the work of a mythopoeic poet, Blake; a
                        subjective, confessional poet, Wordsworth; a novelist, Dostoevsky; and a
                        dramatist, Shakespeare. But first he explores Kleinian patterns in less
                        sophisticated forms, in nursery rhymes and in compositions written by his
                        own sixth-form students. This chapter—for me, the best part of the
                        book—features an engaging discussion of his method of teaching
                        “Goosey, goosey gander.” From the innocence of children’s
                        literature, he moves to Blakean Innocence and Experience, juxtaposing
                        “A Little Boy Lost” to a student fantasia about a homosexual rape
                        on an altar by a father-priest, to show the Oedipal intricacies within
                        Blake’s theme of religious and social oppression. But where is the
                        reparation in this poem? It appears, Stuart claims, in the spectrum of
                        colors surrounding the poem on Blake’s illuminated plate, a
                        covenantal rainbow, which both recalls the lost oneness at the source of the
                        spectrum and also is emblematic of the restitution made by aesthetic form
                        itself. The latter point becomes a major theme in the book. Whereas comic
                        literature manifests reparation in both content and form, tragic literature
                        does so purely in form. For Freud, the formal properties of literature offer
                        a kind of forepleasure, which bribes us to accept the author’s
                        fantasy. For Bloom, concentrating on the writer, rather than the audience,
                        formal properties, as ratios of misreading, are aggressive transformations
                        of a prior text. For Stuart, we experience a feeling of reparation in our
                        appreciation of rhyme, meter, sound, and verbal patterning. Successful
                        poetry doesn’t incite us to fulfill the forbidden impulses it takes
                        as its subject matter but transports us to a state of Thomistic
                        contemplation of aesthetic wholeness and universal meaning. For Stuart,
                        formal elements embody the Ego’s ordering of “crude Id
                        impulses”; but he typically underplays the magical fantasy involved in
                        that ordering. Formal elements can often be seen as rooted in primal
                        experiences and impulses; the Thomistic stasis can be regarded as a
                        reincarnation of the infant’s experience of the good object; it may
                        also be that some need for obstacle, resistance, or counter-pressure enters
                        into the artist’s own experience of form: witness Frost and his
                        tennis net. In different ways, Vico, Buber, and Northrop Frye have pointed
                        out that magic, fantasy, and, in effect, Id impulses play a part in the
                        process of poetic structuring, as well as in the material to be structured.
                        In any event, Stuart does not convince me that “A Little Boy Lost”
                        is not, in the terms of Stephen Dedalus’ Thomistic aesthetic,
                        primarily a pornographic poem, one which is calculated to incite us to
                        outrage, one in which the function of aesthetic form is to sharpen the
                        point.</p>
          <p>Stuart’s major section on Blake begins with a reading of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> Night
VIIa as an account of the origins of the
                        creative imagination. The Night opens with the Oedipal entanglements of Orc
                        and Urizen, in which it becomes clear that no hope for redemption can any
                        longer be expected from the Id, hero of <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> but
                        now as crippled as the Superego that oppresses it. The world of Orc and
                        Urizen is the paranoid-schizoid world, ruled by the death-instinct. A way
                        out can be found only through Los, or the Ego, but only if the Ego accepts
                        the annihilation of its current, limited concept of itself as a wholly
                        conscious, rational entity by acknowledging its own “forgotten, denied,
                        split off, despised aspect,” and especially its envy and jealousy,
                        prime Kleinian effects in the early phases. The Spectre of Urthona, who both
                        represents the despised aspect and argues for its acceptance, receives a
                        more favorable presentation in Stuart than I have seen elsewhere. Once Los
                        is inwardly healed, he turns with Enitharmon to the reparative work of
                        creating “embodied semblances,” or symbols, <pb id="p14-226" n="226"/>
for the other
spectres of the fallen world; that is, Los and
                        Enitharmon become the good internalized parents cooperating in the process
                        of creation, rebuilding the world shattered by Orc and Urizen and by their
                        own depressive anxieties, and the world of symbols they build is Golgonooza.
                        In the vision of the Lamb of God clothed in Luvah’s robes of blood
                        that enteres the episode at the end and that Anne Mellor has attacked as a
                        conventional religious intrusion, Stuart sees an effective symbol of the
                        process of reparation, in which the dead spectres, the shattered pieces of
                        the world, are reborn; the Lamb is, in effect, a culminating symbol of the
                        process of symbol-formation itself.</p>
          <p>All this may sound somewhat formulaic, but it is much less so in
                        Stuart’s text than in my synopsis, and so far I find it a fine
                        reading. At this point, however, Stuart makes the claim that Blake himself
                        fails to achieve in the poetic form of VIIa the embodied semblance, the
                        process of giving structure to the broken, that in his narrative is
                        presented as the triumph of the life-instincts. Indeed, he relates
                        Blake’s epic style to the infant’s sense of omnipotence,
                        which, as a manic defense against depression, is an obstacle to true
                        reparation. In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, he concludes, Blakean form
                        becomes even looser and more narcissistic; and he similarly censures 
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> for its embodiment of a
                        world-view and a poetics dominated by mere magic and an exaggerated sense of
                        the worth of all the individual’s products. Blake is at his best, by
                        contrast, in the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, where he is writing in tight,
                        traditional forms, shaping his impulses in the terms of a larger, anterior
                        enterprise (he calls “A Little Boy Lost” a “great
                        poem”). This is a stunningly retrogressive point, and T. S.
                        Eliot’s strictures on Blake, as well as his general aesthetic, are
                        brought back to life to support it. Working with categories of Ernst Kris,
                        Stuart develops opposed concepts of the artist as craftsman and as magician,
                        the latter equated with the “bad artist” and the neurotic, and
                        writes that the presence of the Romantic, inspired, and prophetic Bard
                        “vitiates” many Blakean passages. At such times Blake lacks
                        “classical impersonality.”</p>
          <p>Stuart’s aesthetic categories and sympathies are remote from his
                        Blakean material. Organic form has its abuses and failures—so too
                        does classical or “traditional” form, as Blake was fond of
                        pointing out—and Blake did not entirely escape such failures; but I
                        doubt if Stuart’s argument will give much pause for reconsideration
                        to anyone who is convinced that Blake’s epic style was a conscious,
                        artful expansion of form accompanying and even necessitated by an expansion
                        and deepening of statement and vision. More important, Stuart’s sense
                        of tradition is limited, for the epic style is indeed quite traditional; it
                        belongs to a tradition of prophetic poetry, which has its own formal
                        features and which includes the Bible and <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>,
                        Blake’s favorite books. There are references in Stuart that imply a
                        partial acknowledgment that Blake’s epic style is traditional in its
                        own way; but if a psychology of art is truly required by its principles to
                        reject an entire tradition of style that writers themselves have found
                        useful throughout the history of literature, then the psychology needs to be
                        revised. We may accept that certain powerful and skillful works of art
                        exemplify narcissistic, omnipotent, and magical conceptions of the self and
                        the world—however, we then might question not whether such art is
                        therefore rendered invalid but, as Bloom has done, whether poetic excellence
                        is the same thing as the wisdom of daily life. Romantic magic and
                        imagination and the character of the Romantic poet-prophet require a cooler
                        psychological analysis than Stuart gives them.</p>
          <p>Stuart proceeds to analyze the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> as successful embodied
                        semblances. He reads the “Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> attractively as
a poem that represents the poetic
                        process in terms of conception (piping down the valleys wild), gestation
                        (from piping to singing to writing), and birth (the child, at first inside
                        the piper, with the cloud above his head as both a placenta and a
                        thought-bubble, vanishes when the song is externalized in a book).
                        Procreation and poetic process are identified with incarnation, since the
                        child, the song, the song’s subject (the lamb), Innocence, and, by
                        implication, Jesus are jointly conceived and brought into the world in the
                        poem. In “The Little Boy Lost” and “The Little Boy
                        Found,” dew and mire represent both the material world, into which, in
                        a Neoplatonic reading, the soul descends, and also the urine and feces of
                        the child’s assault against the parents. Losing involves destroying.
                        But the real parents, as opposed to the inner ones, continue to be ever nigh
                        and caring, and reparation is achieved. It would appear that since the new
                        father is a sublime one (God) the concept of reparation needs to be
                        supplemented here by the concept of Family Romance.</p>
          <p>“The Chimney Sweeper” of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> receives the
                        most provocative of these readings. The essence of the poem for Stuart is
                        not its social protest but its portrayal of the inner experience of
                        oppression. The shaving of Tom’s head is castration; cleaning
                        chimneys and sleeping in soot is an “anal diversion” opposed to
                        the genital strivings expressed in the dream of rising to the clouds. Tom
                        learns to endure temporarily an onslaught of the death-instinct without
                        being emotionally destroyed by it; his genital potency remains inviolate
                        despite the attacks on it. But a fuller reading would have to account for
                        the element of pathetic rationalization in the poem, as well as the fact
                        that the sweeps’ entering the chimneys implies active homosexuality,
                        not passive like the altar fantasia to which Stuart compares the poem. We
                        can expand upon Stuart’s reading as follows. First, the poem begins
                        with the death of the mother; that is, when the child is weaned, he enters a
                        state of persecution. The poem ends with the promise of phallic liberation;
                        in the meantime, the child under-goes a severe detainment at the anal stage.
                        Second, while cleaning other people’s chimneys might well be,
                        symbolically, the nadir of humiliation, it could also represent a
                        destructive homosexual assault against the father; latent aggression appears
                        within the portrayal of helpless suffering. Third, in Klein the child is
                        fascinated by the contents of the mother’s body, which in his
                        fantasies include other children, penises, and excreta (in the paired poem
                        the child himself is “a little black thing,” a piece of soot), and
                        the anus is frequently in the child’s fantasies the place of birth;
                        the sweeps thus enact 
<pb id="p14-227" n="227"/>
the epistomophilic and
                        destructive fantasy of entering the mother’s body, exploring it, and
                        robbing (liberating) its contents, while they also suffer the retaliatory
                        fantasy of being swallowed and destroyed by that body, assimilated to the
                        fragments of dirt within it, locked in coffins of black. But the liberation
                        of the sweeps, the resurrection of the dead, is also a bringing forth of
                        life from excrement, which Irvine Schiffer in <hi rend="i">The Trauma of
                            Time</hi> describes as one of the radical fantasies of the artistic
                        process. The poem thus gives us a comprehensive vision of psychic conflict
                        in the mode of anality; but it goes even further to merge psychology and
                        social criticism, suggesting how a concept of reparation can be exploited
                        and how symbol-formation, in the transcendent genital paradise, can be
                        overly drastic. If the child behaves well under the oppressive regime, he
                        will be rewarded after death. In this poem, the life-instinct, having
                        transformed the death-instinct, is then subtly co-opted by its
                        adversary.</p>
          <p>For Stuart, Innocence and Experience represent not childhood and maturity but
                        the idealized breast and the persecuting breast, “the two contrary
                        states of the human soul.” While the <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Innocence</hi> are set in the stage of depressive anxiety and typically
                        conclude in reparation, the <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>
                        paradoxically focus on the earlier paranoid-schizoid stage, which does not
                        contain the potentiality of reparation; here the life-instinct, with its
                        conversion of disintegration into beauty, is present in poetic form alone.
                        In “The Sunflower” Stuart sees the obverse of the successful
                        process of creation he discerns in “Piping down the valleys wild.”
                        He reconciles the apparently contradictory impulses dramatized in the poem
                        toward sexual fulfillment and transcendence by arguing that sexual desire is
                        treated in Blake as the “symbolic enactment of a quest which supersedes
                        it . . . erection [is the image] of resurrection.” He expands upon this
                        by reference to Donne’s “The Ecstasy,” in which, as Stuart
                        has it, a psychosexual reality appears behind the concepts of Platonic Ideal
                        and Christian Incarnation and in which soul and body find a saving
                        reciprocity; in Stuart’s reading, “as the physical uses the . .
                        . immaterial for physical ends, so the immaterial must use the physical for
                        ends transcending the physical.” “The Sunflower” records a
                        failure to understand the relation of the physical to the spiritual, a
                        failure, then, of symbol-formation, of incarnation. This is a good reading,
                        but to understand the uniquely Blakean treatment of the relationship between
                        the physical and the spiritual, one would have to take into account, first,
                        Blake’s theme that the visionary is not a separate realm from the
                        bodily (as in Plato and orthodox Christianity) but an expansion of the
                        bodily, and, second, a psychological, as opposed to thematic, analysis of
                        Blake’s deeply complex attitudes toward sexuality, woman, and
                        nature.</p>
          <p>Stuart’s Wordsworth chapter is clearer and smoother than his Blake
                        section, not only because the material is more readily amenable to his
                        approach but even more because his discussion here actually begins with a
                        psychological analysis of the poet’s text rather than with a concept
                        of the poet’s work (the transcendent Blake) to which a psychological
                        analysis is, in effect, adapted. Chiefly interested in the way Wordsworth
                        can “transform the substance of despair into creativity,” Stuart
                        asks how the poet can claim that such traumatic Oedipal episodes as the
                        stolen boat scene in <hi rend="i">The Prelude</hi>, Book I, ultimately
                        contribute to his growth and sense of well-being. Onorato’s answer
                        (still the best one for me) is that Wordsworth’s imagination is
                        driven by a need to deny traumatic effect, specifically that caused by his
                        parents’ deaths; but according to Stuart, Wordsworth’s
                        earliest experience, his pre-Oedipal innocence, his internalization of the
                        good parents, is so firm and positive that the later conflicts of Experience
                        can be not only survived but used to enriching effect. “So feeling
                        comes in aid / Of feeling . . . if but once we have been strong.” It is
                        in this way that looking back at the past restores us. What also helps
                        Wordsworth survive the depressive stage is his genius for symbol-formation.
                        In his treatment of the Spot of Time in which Wordsworth visits the
                        murderer’s gibbet, Stuart shows how anxiety drives the poet from
                        symbol to symbol in a series of sublimating equations—from the
                        visionary dreariness of the childhood landscape to the golden glow perceived
                        by the adult returning to the scene, for example, or from the letters of the
                        murderer’s name (torn bits of the mother’s body) to the girl
                        with the pitcher to “the loved one by my side.” The capacity to
                        fabricate embodied semblances in this way resolves the anxiety and leads to
                        authentic growth.</p>
          <p>Stuart also compares “Tintern Abbey” and the “Intimations
                        Ode” as, respectively, an unconvincing and a successful attempt to
                        resolve depressive anxiety over the loss of the good object. In
                        “Tintern Abbey” anxiety and aggression are magically denied; the
                        sense of persecution that emerges in other depressive passages—in,
                        for example, Wordsworth’s reflections on the Reign of
                        Terror—is smothered beneath “The still, sad music of
                        humanity.” In the Ode, however, the source of depression is faced: the
                        child perversely destroys his own happiness and integrity; we “provoke
                        . . . the inevitable yoke.” Such an acknowledgment validates the
                        poem’s movement from depression (the thought of grief, forgetfulness)
                        to reparation (the timely utterance, remembrance).</p>
          <p>In the final chapter it becomes apparent that Stuart’s ultimate
                        purpose is the forging of a synthesis of psychoanalysis, art, and religion,
                        and it is on the third term that he now concentrates. Apparently sharing the
                        yearning of Eliot for rites and symbols that are grounded in human reality
                        and psychologically developing that desire, he looks through Christian myth
                        and ritual to its pagan roots and, beyond, to the inner events of depressive
                        mourning for the lost object and restitution, “an eternal rhythm of
                        death and resurgence, impotence and potency, destruction and
                        reparation.” Both art and, in its symbolic rather than magical aspect,
                        religion embody “the struggle of the life-instincts to find forms to
                        celebrate their ever recurrent mourning of what is lost and rediscovery
                        thereby of new life.” He analyzes structures of rebirth in <hi rend="i">Crime and
Punishment</hi> (studying the relation between Raskolnikov
                        and Svidrigailov) and <hi rend="i">Much Ado About Nothing</hi>, adding, in
                        the latter case, a touch here 
<pb id="p14-228" n="228"/>
and there to
                        previous discussions of rebirth in Shakespearean comedy: Hero is the
                        destroyed and restored object; Don John manifests the infant’s
                        envious wish to spoil the power and greatness of the good object; the
                        renunciation of self-sufficiency and superiority that brings Beatrice and
                        Benedick together has its roots in the infant’s relinquishing of the
                        breast, a renunciation that is the basis of enriching sublimations. But the
                        center of the chapter remains the quest for an effective symbol, “a
                        hyper-verbal communication [that] may resort to words,” as the soul
                        does to the body in Donne, but that is finally a transcendent reality.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">New Phoenix Wings</hi> demonstrates that the important work of
                        Melanie Klein is worth the attention of students of literature; and Stuart
                        is not a mere mechanical adapter of her theories but a reader whose approach
                        to literature does show fineness and subtlety. His style, however, despite
                        some eloquent passages is too often an obstacle: for example,
                        “‘Introduction’ with ‘Earth’s
                        Answer’ <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, like Coleridge’s <hi rend="i">Dejection</hi>
or Wordsworth in <hi rend="i">The Prelude</hi>
                        I, records the disjunction of that bisexual process without the temporary
                        conjunction of which the record could not exist.” In his argument
                        Stuart does not, in my view, use psychoanalytic criticism to maximal effect,
                        tending to use it to open up a writer’s vision of humanity and to
                        demonstrate in general terms the Creative Process at work rather than to
                        open up our vision of the particular sensibility constituted by the
                        writer’s words. Did the creative process have precisely the same
                        meaning for both Blake and Shakespeare? Are the anxieties and the implicit
                        attitudes toward parental images revealed in their texts identical? Except
                        in the case of the openly subjective Wordsworth texts, I miss a sense of the
                        individual inflection of the universal process.</p>
          <p>It may be that different followers of Freud bear a special relationship to
                        different authors. Ferenczi seems close to Wordsworth, for example, and the
                        heretical Jung has been successfully used in conjunction with many writers
                        in the romance mode. In Klein, the handling of aggression and its conversion
                        into creativity is central. I would like to see Kleinian analyses of writers
                        as divergent as Pope—with his aggressive satire, his virtually
                        magical concern with form and craft, and perhaps his enemy-parents, Dulness
                        and Tibbald-Cibber—and Shelley—with his massive
                        transformations of aggression and his Prometheus devastating the world
                        through Jupiter and then rebuilding it. As for Blake, anger and aggression
                        certainly figure saliently in both his style and his poetic situations. But
                        because of Stuart’s bias against the epic work, <hi rend="i">New
                            Phoenix Wings</hi> doesn’t fully answer the question of
                        Klein’s relevance. What about the study of jealousy and the battle
                        against the death-instinct (Covering Cherub, Selfhood, Error, Satan) in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>? What about the bringing together of the parents
                        (Milton and Ololon, Albion and Jerusalem) that dominates both <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>? Here, far more than in the
                            <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, would come the test of Klein as a guide to
                        Blake. I am grateful to Stuart for provoking such questions, and I do think
                        his book makes a contribution to Blake studies. Still, it is important to
                        observe how psychoanalysis can be used merely to give formidable authority
                        to anterior aesthetic judgments. Here, surrounded by references to Eliot and
                        Donne and by a Thomistic concept of form, Blake is subsumed into a poetic
                        and religious tradition alien to his own, with predictable results in terms
                        of aesthetic evaluation. Stuart has brought Blake and psychoanalysis
                        together by taking him out of the Romantic, visionary line of English
                        literature; more than analyzing Blake’s Romanticism, he has
                        eliminated it.</p>
          <p>A broader issue is the exact nature of the voyage from impulse and experience
                        to symbol and art. In Freud, that voyage involves a sacrifice; this is
                        reaffirmed by Lacan. In Bloom, art is not a reparation for aggression, but
                        aggression itself is at the source of the creative process; and in Bloom,
                        too, denials and defenses are generators of the poetic imagination. Does
                        poetry start with a reparation for a catastrophe or with the catastrophe
                        itself? Throughout <hi rend="i">New Phoenix Wings</hi> Stuart stresses that
                        in reparation the internal parents are recreated and brought together in
                        sexual union; artistic creation involves an internally bisexual process, in
                        which male and female elements, father and mother, are married. We might say
                        that while in the paranoid-schizoid stage the infant suicidally destroys his
                        own creators, in reparation he recreates himself by affirming his origins;
                        he inwardly repeats his own creation. This is Coleridge’s Primary
                        Imagination, the “repetition in the finite mind of the eternal act of
                        creation in the infinite I AM.” <hi rend="i">New Phoenix Wings</hi> has
                        much to offer on this phase of the poetic process. What it lacks is a vivid
                        complementary account of the Secondary Imagination, which “dissolves,
                        diffuses, dissipates, in order to recreate,” in which aggression plays
                        a role and the subject seeks not to repeat his origins but to remake them,
                        even, in the most highly Romantic formulations, to be his own creator. For
                        such an account, we would have to pass from reparation to the Oedipus
                        Complex and the Family Romance.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
