<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.4.hilton</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake and the Mountains of the Mind</title>
        <author n="Hilton">Nelson Hilton</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
              <name>Erik Frykman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>William Vaughan</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <pb id="p14-196" n="196"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-4-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">BLAKE AND THE MOUNTAINS OF THE MIND</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">NELSON</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">HILTON</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>While the Romantics looked to nature’s mountains in the form of Mont
                    Blanc, the Jungfrau, or Skiddaw to find a visible externalization of their
                        psychology,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">1</ref>
Blake’s mountains
                    reflect an interior vision of the mountains of mythology and those, not far
                    distant, of the Bible. These befit a poet who saw his visions in the worlds of
                    thought and, from all accounts, never saw a genuine mountain (much less a Welsh
                    one) in his life. Mircea Eliade summarizes the mythological dimension: 
					<q>
                        Mountains are the nearest thing to the sky, and are thence endowed with a
                        twofold holiness: on the one hand they share in the spatial symbolism of
                        transcendence—they are ‘high,’
                        ‘vertical,’ ‘supreme,’ and so on—and on
                        the other, they are the especial domain of all hierophanies of atmosphere,
                        and therefore, the dwelling of the gods.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n44" type="note">2</ref></q>
Their symbolic and religious significance, he continues, “is
                    endless.” One can see the sacred quality stemming from the fact that
                    mountains penetrate the upper, pure regions of the atmosphere (aether) carried
                    on in seventeenth-century poetic diction, where standard non-negative epithets
                    are “cloud-touching, star-brushing.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n45" type="note">3</ref> For the ancient Greeks the upper air, source of meteors and other
                    meteorological events, was integrally related to mountains and “high
                        ground”—<hi rend="i">ta meteora</hi>; their conjunction offers
                    “a spot where one can pass from one cosmic zone to another” (Eliade,
                    p. 100). Blake writes of the “Atlantean hills” that “from their
                    bright summits you may pass to the Golden world” (<hi rend="i">Am</hi>
                    10.6, 7).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">4</ref> The
dwelling of Zeus—Dios,
                    God of the Bright Sky—was Mount Olympus, but “olympus” was to
                    be found all over mountainous Greece; the word itself is the pre-Greek term for
                    “mountain.” The Romans, though lacking mountains, nonetheless
                    dignified “their own poor little Capitol . . . with the title of
                        ‘Mons’”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">5</ref>
and the
                    cosmological zone of the female body receives the same dignity.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">1</hi> On the development of this trend, see
                        Marjorie Hope Nicolson, <hi rend="i">Mountain Gloom and Mountain Glory: The
                            Development of the Aesthetics of the Infinite</hi>, The Norton Library
                        (1959, rpt.; New York: W. W. Norton &amp; Co., 1963). We may note here that
                        “mountains” do, in fact, appear more frequently in Blake’s
                        imagery (161 times in the poetry) than in Wordsworth’s or
                        Shelley’s. This is, to be sure, hardly true of mount/mountain imagery
                        at large; one finds at once that Blake uses no adjectival combinations such
                        as “mountain gloom” or “glory.” But the
                        “mountains” themselves are more numerous, and more strange.</note>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Mircea Eliade, <hi rend="i">Patterns in
                            Comparative Religion</hi>, trans. Rosemary Sneed, Meridian Books
                        (New York: World Publishing, 1963), p. 199.</note>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Joshua Poole, <hi rend="i">English Parnassus;
                            or, A Help to English Poesie</hi>, cited in Nicolson, p. 35. Such
                        epithets show how mountains become quintessentially “sublime” or
                            <hi rend="i">sublimen</hi>, just “below the threshold” (of
                        heaven).</note>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">4</hi> References to Blake are from E: <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of
William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman, 3rd
                        ed. w/rev. (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1968). Cf. <hi rend="i">FZ</hi>,
                        II, 32.8ff., E 315: “a Golden World whose porches round the heavens /
                        And pillard hall &amp; rooms receivd the eternal wandering
                        stars.”</note>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Wilfrid Noyce, <hi rend="i">Scholar
                            Mountaineers, Pioneers of Parnassus</hi> (London: Dennis Dobson, 1950),
                        p. 11.</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Cf. Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Love’s
                            Labour’s Lost</hi>, V.i.75-77; Ahania urges Urizen in a Blakean
                        double-entendre “To arise to the mountain sport, / To the bliss of
                        eternal valleys” (<hi rend="i">BA</hi> 5.7-8). Mountains also represent
                        the woman’s bosom; see in particular Blake’s illustration no.
                        4 to Milton’s <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi>, “The Sunshine
                        Holiday.”</note></p>
        <p>In Mesopotamia, “temples were called the ‘mountain house,’ the
                    ‘house of the mountain of all lands,’ the ‘mountain of
                    storms,’ the ‘bound between sky and earth,’ and so
                        on.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">7</ref> The
association of <hi rend="i">meteora</hi>, high things, and centering, is again expressed in the
                    widespread belief of various cultures that their mountain lies directly under
                    the pole star, and so presents the <hi rend="i">Axis Mundi.</hi> In the Old
                    Testament one of the names of God, <hi rend="i">El-Shaddai</hi>, can be
                    translated as “the God of the Mountain, the God of the
                    ‘Height’ or (as the highest) an astral god,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n50" type="note">8</ref> and in the historical period of Israel, “mountain
                    house” became a common name for “temple.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n51" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Eliade, <hi rend="i">Patterns</hi>, p. 376;
                        cf. Thomas Fawcett, <hi rend="i">The Symbolic Language of Religion: An
                            Introductory Study</hi> (London: SCM Press, 1970), p. 153. According to
                        Richard J. Clifford, <hi rend="i">The Cosmic Mountain in Canaan and the Old
                            Testament</hi>, Harvard Semitic Monographs, vol. IV (Cambridge, Mass.:
                        Harvard Univ. Press, 1972), “ . . . many modern scholars seem
                        disinclined to use the concept of the <hi rend="i">Weltberg</hi> to describe
                        Mesopotamian speculation about the cosmic center. Nonetheless, there is a
                        cosmic center, where heaven and earth are united. The cosmic center appears
                        in some texts to be <corr type="emend">commemorated</corr> by a shrine or temple”
(p. 25).</note>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Ad de Vries, <hi rend="i">A Dictionary of
                            Imagery and Symbolism</hi> (Amsterdam: North-Holland Publishing, 1974),
                        s.v. “mountain.”</note>
	<note id="n51"><hi rend="s">9</hi> W. Foerster in Gerhard Kittel, ed., <hi rend="i">Theological Dictionary of
the New Testament</hi>, trans.
                        Geoffrey W. Bromiley, vol. V, (Grand Rapids, Mich.: Wm. B. Eerdmans, 1968),
                        s.v. “<hi rend="i">to oros.</hi>”</note></p>
        <p>The closeness of God and the mountain is typified by the theophanies at Sinai. As
                    houses of God, they are also places of sacrifice, high—Latin 
<hi rend="i">alta</hi>—altars; in Genesis 22:2 God tells Abraham to offer his
                    <corr type="emend">son “for</corr> a burnt offering upon one of the mountains which I
will tell thee
                    of.” So Los takes Orc “to the top of a mountain” (<hi rend="i">BU</hi> 20.21) to
chain him down. The New Testament made great use of the
                    Old Testament symbolism, and its repeated description of Jesus’ going <hi rend="i">eis
to oros</hi>, “up the mountain” or “into the
                    mountains,” assumes a formulaic dimension.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n52" type="note">10</ref> Little wonder that Blake should characterize the two Testaments by
                    their respective dominant mountains: 
					<q> Such is the Divine Written Law of Horeb
                        &amp; Sinai:<lb/>
 And such the Holy Gospel of Mount Olivet &amp;
                        Calvary<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 16.68-69) </q>
	<pb id="p14-197" n="197"/>
One mountain, however, serves to site and anchor both
                    Testaments: Mount Zion, “Beautiful for situation, the joy of the whole
                    earth” (Ps. 48:2), “the holy Mountain” (Zech. 8:3) of the Lord
                    and synonymous with its city, Jerusalem. So Paul reminds the Hebrews, “But
                    ye are come unto mount Sion, and unto the city of the living God, the heavenly
                    Jerusalem” (12:22). Tiny Mount Zion is to “tower over the other
                    mountains” (Clifford, p. 157; cf. Is. 2:4, Mic. 4:1). 
                    <note id="n52"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Cf. Mt. 5:1, 14:23, 15:29; Mk. 3:13, 6:46; Lk.
                            6:12, 9:28; Jn. 6:3, 6:15. Thomas Fawcett nicely summarizes this
                            important theme: 
						<q> In addition to being antitypical, many events in
                                Christ’s life are associated with the cosmic mountain. The
                                one in fact inevitably brought in the other by association. When
                                Jesus is made in Matthew’s gospel to give his new law from
                                the mount, there is both a fulfilment of the Sinai revelation in
                                view, and underlying this, the symbolism of the mountain as the
                                place of God’s disclosure to men. The motif appears on
                                several occasions. The narrative opens with a story of temptation in
                                which Christ formulates his message in confrontation with the Devil
                                and in reliance on the word of God, appropriately located on a
                                mountain. The moment of disclosure to the disciples of Jesus’
                                nature and mission takes place on the mount of Transfiguration. At
                                the summit of the mountain they see him converse with the saints of
                                the past. His crucifixion was later held to have taken place upon a
                                hill, and Calvary became the focal mountain for much Christian
                                theology, because at this moment above all it came to be held that
                                God had revealed himself to man. Finally the ascension is said to
                                have taken place on the mount of Olives in such a way that the
                                symbolism of the summit as the point of meeting between man and God
                                is clearly shown. His ascension from this point implies a summit in
                                which the two worlds of mythology are joined. </q>
                            (<hi rend="i">Symbolic Language</hi>, p. 227)
                    </note></p>
        <p>As Jerusalem is to Mount Zion, so she was and will be to Albion; which is to say
                    that Albion is—or rather, was and will be—a holy mountain.
                    Holinshed, who begins his <hi rend="i">Chronicles</hi> discussing the legend of
                    the ancient denomination of England, refers to speculation “whether
                    Britaine was called Albion of the word Alb, white, or Alp an hill.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53" type="note">11</ref> The name in fact is connected with the
                    root of Latin <hi rend="i">Alpis</hi>, Gaelic <hi rend="i">alp</hi>, and Irish
                        <hi rend="i">ailp</hi>, meaning mountain. Blake plays on this assonance and
                    etymological connection, imagining that Los’s “voice is heard from
                    Albion: the Alps &amp; Appenines / Listen” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 85.16-17).
                    As only high mountains tend to be white (with snow), the traditional association
                    of Albion with <hi rend="i">albus</hi> could also be seen to suggest that Albion
                    was once a high mountain, now islanded by the sea. This could be confirmed by
                    Albion’s white cliffs, a word Blake generally uses in its less common
                    sense of “a steep slope, a hill.” The cliffs are the sides of
                    Albion’s great mountain as it slips down below the surface of the sea:
                    “ . . . Albion the White Cliff of the Atlantic / The Mountain of Giants . . . ” 
                    (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 49.6-7). <note id="n53"><hi rend="s">11</hi><hi rend="i"> 
                    Holinshed’s Chronicles of England, Scotland, and Ireland</hi> in 6 vol. 
                    (London: J. Johnson et al., 1807-1808), I, 6.</note></p>
        <p>Mountains are necessarily related to the image of the ocean deluge. Thomas
                    Burnet’s mytho-poetic <hi rend="i">Sacred Theory of the Earth</hi> (1681)
                    argued that the weight of the floodwaters broke the crust of the paradisal
                    “mundane egg” into mountains.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54"
type="note">12</ref> In
                    a somewhat similar manner, when Eternity rolls apart in <hi rend="i">The Book of
                        Urizen</hi> what is left is “mountainous all around,” dominated by
                    “ruinous fragments of life / Hanging frowning cliffs &amp; all between /
                    An ocean of voidness unfathomable” (5.7, 9-11). Earlier cosmologies also
                    focused on the creation of “land” out of Chaos (if not
                    Eternity)—the deep, the Semitic <hi rend="i">Tehom.</hi> These traditions
                    imagined that the mountains were placed in <hi rend="i">Tehom</hi> to serve as
                    foundations of the world—they were the first dry land, like Mount Ararat
                    after the later flood. According to some rabbinical similes, “God’s
                    mountains reach down to the great Tehom” and “these mountains dominate
                    Tehom, lest it should rise and innundate the earth.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">13</ref> As foundations, the mountains are seen as the
                    “pillars of heaven” (Job 26:11, cf. 9:6). So in Albion/Jerusalem, 
					<q>
                        Pancrass &amp; Kentish-town repose<lb/>
 Among her golden pillars high:<lb/>
                        Among her golden arches which<lb/>
 Shine upon the starry sky.<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 27.9-12) </q>
The cosmological scope of this reference
                    is clear remembering that the “pillard hall &amp; arched roof of Albions
                    skies” receive “the eternal wandering stars” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi>, II, 25.16, 32.9;
E 310, 315).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">14</ref> Since the flood
represented the victory of Chaos, of Leviathan,
                    some rabbinical commentators held that the land of Israel was not submerged by
                    the Deluge, a belief which is paralleled in Islam. A. J. Wensinck comments: 
					<q>
                        Why the Sanctuary is not attained by the waters of the Deluge is clear:
                        Deluge is the reign of Tehom, of old a demonic power, familiar from the
                        creation stories. The Sanctuary is the type and representation of Kosmos and
                        of Paradise and as such a power diametrically opposed to Chaos; when the
                        Semites maintain that the Sanctuary was not reached by the Deluge, this is
                        not only due to the opinion that the Sanctuary is the highest place in the
                        world, but also to the conviction that Chaos cannot gain a complete victory
                        over Kosmos, for behind the latter is the creative power of the supreme
                        being.<lb/>
 (pp. 15-16) </q></p>
        <p>This conception offers several analogies to Blake’s images, from that of
                    the one sense through which man may “himself pass out” (<hi rend="i">Eur</hi> iii.5)
which remained after the other senses “whelm’d
                    in deluge” (<hi rend="i">Eur</hi> 10.10-11) over him, to the picture of
                    Albion as the mountain remaining when “the Atlantic Continent sunk round
                    Albions Cliffy shore / And the Sea pourd in amain” (<hi rend="i">J</hi>
                    32[36].40-41). The “sea of Time &amp; Space” is the principal deluge.
                    This may account for the frequent graphic depiction of an action taking place on
                    a location surrounded by water; it is an image of England, but it signifies also
                    imaginative vision, not yet drowned in Time and Space (or Realism or
                    Naturalism). So when Reuben sleeps “like one dead in the
                    valley”—the vale, or low-lying, submersible land—the notable
                    thing is that he is thus “Cut off from Albions mountains &amp; from all
                    the Earths summits” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 30[34].43,44). “Wild seas
                    &amp; Rocks” are to “close up Jerusalem away from / The Atlantic
                    <corr type="emend">Mountains</corr>” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 49.77-50.1). <hi rend="i">America</hi> tells
                    that 
					<q>
                    	On those vast shady hills between America &amp; Albions shore;<lb/>
                        Now barr’d out by the Atlantic sea: call’d Atlantean hills<lb/>
                        Because from their bright summits you may pass to the Golden world<lb/>
                        An ancient palace, archetype of mighty Emperies,<lb/>
                        Rears its immortal pinnacles. . . .<lb/>
                        (10.5-9)
					</q>
                    One critic has called this
                    passage “iconic” and remarked its “tantalizing quality of
                    meanings nearly communicated yet withheld.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n57" type="note">15</ref> Without entering the context of <hi rend="i">America</hi> or the
                    “suitability of invoking the myth of a lost, paradisal Atlantis as a symbol
                    of transcendent unity,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58"
type="note">16</ref> I would
                    simply emphasize that the mythic structure of the mountain sanctuary, temple,
                    palace is itself a “meaning communicated.” The reader is told
                    something about the situation, appearance, and function of the summit-structure
                    and it takes its place among Blake’s visionary locales—the
                    description engages our attention by calling up latent (and several times
                    removed) mythological associations. The Atlantic, one should remember, is named
                    not for Atlantis, but for the Titan Atlas, seen in classical times as Mount
                    Atlas, the pillar of heaven. Atlas, Blake believed, was the Greek name for
                    Albion, “Patri<hi rend="i">arch</hi> of the Atlantic” 
                    (<hi rend="i">DC</hi>, E 534; italics added). Blake viewed 
        <pb id="p14-198" n="198"/> 
        			his Hesperian situation quite personally, as evident in the 
        			dedicatory poem to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, which says that 
        			his “designs unchangd remain”: 
					<q> 
                    	For above Times troubled Fountains<lb/>
                    	On the Great Atlantic Mountains<lb/>
                    	In my Golden House on high<lb/>
                    	There they Shine Eternally<lb/>
                    	<lb/>
                    	(“The Caverns of the Grave,” 17-20)
					</q>
                    These
                    mountains rise out of the sea of time becoming the “infinite” and
                    “eternal” mountains, the site of paradise: “the Garden of Eden .
                    . . the golden mountains” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 28.2), “the mountain
                    palaces of Eden” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 41[46].3-4).</p>
        <p>The setting of Abraham’s sacrifice and Jesus’ crucifixion leads to
                    the very different image of Albion “slain upon his Mountains / And in his
                    Tent,” 
        <figure n="LeydenCalvary.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="658">
        	<head>1 Lucas van Leyden, “Calvary” (1517; 11 1/8 × 16 1/4
                            in.)</head>
            <figDesc>Courtesy of the British Museum.</figDesc>
        </figure> 
        			a formula which occurs three times (<hi rend="i">M</hi> 3.1-2; 19.20;
                    <hi rend="i">J</hi> 59.16). The Tent is the Sky (<hi rend="i">M</hi> 29.4),
                    and the plural mountains reach back to the common mythological idea of a central
                    tent-pole, axle-tree mountain, and four smaller poles making a square around it
                    (the sort depicted, in cross-section, dropping around plates 1 and 21 of 
<hi rend="i">Job</hi>). The image also evokes “mountainous Wales,”
                    where Albion’s ancient inhabitants fled originally to escape the Saxons,
                    there finally to be conquered by Norman Edward I, who, as retold by Gray, put to
                    death “all the Bards that fell into his hands”—the poetic being
                    of Albion.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">17</ref>
	<note id="n54"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Cf. Thomas Burnet, <hi rend="i">The Sacred
                            Theory of the Earth</hi>, intro. Basil Willey, Centaur Classics
                        (Carbondale, Ill.: Southern Illinois Univ. Press, 1965), Bk. K, ch. 5, p.
                        63.</note>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">13</hi> A. J. Wensinck, <hi rend="i">The Ideas of
                            the Western Semites Concerning The Navel of the Earth</hi>;
                        Verhandelingen der Koninklijke Akademie van Wetenschappen te Amsterdam,
                        Adeeling Le Herkunde, Nieuwe Reeks, Deel XVII, no. 1 (Amsterdam: Johannes
                        Müller, 1916), p. 2.</note>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Cf. Kittle, ed., <hi rend="i">Theological
                            Dictionary of the New Testament</hi>, s.v. <hi rend="i">stulos</hi>,
                        “pillar”: “The word <hi rend="i">stulos</hi> has cosmological
                        significance in some hymnal passages in the OT. . . . The primary thought
                        here is that the earth is a house which God has built” (vol. VII, p.
                        733). The mountains are the pillars of that house. Compare Christopher
                        Smart’s use of the image: “For he [God] hath fixed the earth
                        upon arches &amp; pillars, and the flames of hell flow under it.” 
(<hi rend="i">Jubilate Agno</hi>, ed. W. H. Bond [Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard
                        Univ. Press, 1954], p. 67).</note>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Vincent A. De Luca, “Ariston’s
                        Immortal Palace: Icon and Allegory in Blake’s Prophecies,” 
<hi rend="i">Criticism</hi>, 12 (Winter 1970), 5-6. For a recent and
                        suggestive reading, critical of the implications of the
                        “archetype,” see Deborah Dorfman, “‘King of
                        Beauty’ and ‘Golden World’ in Blake’s <hi rend="i">America</hi>: The Reader
and the Archetype,” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi>, 46 (Spring 1979), 122-35.</note>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">16</hi> De Luca, p. 6; note that nowhere in his work
                        does Blake ever specifically mention Atlantis.</note>
	<note id="n59"><hi rend="s">17</hi> According to Mallet, however, “the
                        ancient inhabitants of Britain have been dispossessed by the Saxons of the
                        greatest and most pleasant part of their island, and constrained to conceal
                        themselves among the mountains in Wales, where, to this day, they retain
                        their language, and preserve some traces of their ancient manners;” 
<hi rend="i">Northern Antiquities</hi>, trans. (London, 1770), I,
                    70.</note></p>
        <p>But from all indications, something happened earlier, something which
                    “separated the stars from the mountains: the mountains from Man” (<hi rend="i">J</hi>
17.31). Somewhere in the Druid past, Albion changed
                    “From willing sacrifice of self, to sacrifice of (miscall’d) Enemies
                    / For Atonement,” an action, like Abraham’s, located on the
                    mountains. Albion concludes his opening speech in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                    saying: 
					<q> By demonstration man alone can live, and not by faith.<lb/>
 My
                        mountains are my own, and I will keep them to myself:<lb/>
 The Malvern and
                        the Cheviot, the Wolds Plinlimmon &amp; Snowdon<lb/>
<pb id="p14-199" n="199"/>
Are mine. <hi rend="i">here</hi> will I build my
                        Laws of Moral Virtue!<lb/>
 Humanity shall be no more: but war &amp;
                        princedom &amp; victory!<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 4.28-32, my italics)
					</q>
					In less than ten lines, “Albions mountains run with blood, the cries
                    of war &amp; of tumult” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 5.6). These sacrifices in
                    turn react on their sites as 
					<q> . . all the mountains and hills shrink up like
                        a withering gourd<lb/>
 As the Senses of Men shrink together under the Knife
                        of flint<lb/>
 In the hands of Albions Daughters, among the Druid
                        Temples<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 66.82-84)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">18</ref>
	<note id="n60"><hi rend="s">18</hi> The mountains shrinking “like a
                            withering gourd” suggests God’s action on the gourd tree
                            sheltering Jonah; He “prepared a worm . . . and it smote the gourd
                            that it withered” (Jonah 4:7). One may think also of the comparison
                            of the earth to an apple, withering into mountainous ridges.</note></q>
Other of
Albion’s fallen mountains are listed in another catalogue:
                    “ . . . the Peak, Malvern &amp; Cheviot Reason in Cruelty / Penmaenmawr
                    &amp; Dhinas-bran Demonstrate in Unbelief” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 21.34-35).
                    The single appearance of “Dhinas-bran” may refer to “Dîn
                    Brëon, the <hi rend="i">Hill of Legislature</hi>,” which “was
                    the sacred mount, where . . . the ancient judges of the land, assembled, to
                    decide causes.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61"
type="note">19</ref>
	<note id="n61"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Davies, <hi rend="i">Myth and Rites of the
                            British Druids</hi> (London, 1809), p. 6. Damon suggests the obscure
                        “Dinas Bran,” a hill in north Wales topped by the ruins of an
                        ancient camp. Unconvinced himself, he adds, “Blake might really have
                        had in mind Dinas Penmaen, and ancient British fort which could hold twenty
                        thousand men. It was on the summit of Mount Penmaenmawr” (<hi rend="i">A Blake
Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols of William Blake</hi>, rpt.
                        [New York: Dutton, 1971], p. 103; cf. <hi rend="i">J</hi> 18.38 where Hand
                        and Hyle are “Building Castles in desolated places, and strong
                        Fortifications”). One argument against “Dhinas-Bran” as a
                        “camp” is that all the others are specific mountains or mountain
                        ranges; but this remains unsatisfying at best.</note></p>
        <p>Blake was evidently impressed by the description in Ezekiel of the sacrificial
            feast the Lord is to 
        <figure n="HograthIndustry.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="670">
			<head>2 Hograth, <hi rend="i">Industry and Idleness</hi>, pl. XI, “The
                            Idle ‘Prentice Executed at Tyburn” (1747; 10 1/2 × 13
                            1/4 in.).</head>
			<figDesc>Courtesy of the British Museum.</figDesc>
		</figure> 
					make of his enemies; all the beasts are invited to the “great
                    sacrifice upon the mountains of Israel, that ye may eat flesh and drink
                    blood;” there “ye shall eat fat till ye be full, and drink blood till
                    ye be drunken” (29:17, 19). In “the Song” sung at “The Feast
                    of Los and Enitharoom” Blake transfers the action to the mountains
                    themselves—which begin to emerge as solidified giant forms with Biblical
                    histories: 
					<q> [The Mountain <hi rend="i">del.</hi>] Ephraim calld out to [The
                        Mountain <hi rend="i">del.</hi>] Zion: Awake O Brother Mountain<lb/>
 Let us
                        refuse the Plow &amp; Spade, the heavy Roller &amp; spiked<lb/>
 Harrow.
                        burn all these Corn fields. throw down all these fences<lb/>
 Fattend on
                        Human blood and drunk with wine of life is better far<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi>, I, 14.7-10, E 304, 746) </q>
Clifford notes the suggestion
                    that “the feast on the mountain of the bodies of the enemy is a
                    transformation of the exchatological picture of the ‘joyous
                    feast’” as in Isaiah 25:6-8. “Possibly,” he concludes,
                    “the banquet for the victorious on the mountain and the slaughter-sacrifice
                    of the enemies are one and the same” (pp. 176-77). This duality seems
                    applicable to the Wedding Feast of Los and Enitharmon, since they begin, with
                    Urizen, “Rejoicing 
<pb id="p14-200" n="200"/>
in the Victory” (12.35,
                    E 303, cf. <hi rend="i">J</hi> 4.32 above). Blake’s intertwining vision
                    of the Fall on the mountains of Israel and England follows from his conception
                    of Druid practices and from hints in the Old Testament—unified in an
                    image of “moral” sacrifice on mountains (classical mountains, <hi rend="i">ora</hi>,
become m<hi rend="i">ora</hi>l emblems). His first use of
                    the negative power of Old Testament mountains is the figure and setting of
                    “har,” the Hebrew for “mountain,” in particular, “the
                    mountain” (<hi rend="i">hā-hār</hi>) where Moses received the
                    Law (cf. Clifford, p. 107ff.); as Blake would have read in Bryant: “Har and
                    Hor signify a mountain; ὄρος [oros] of the Greeks.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62" type="note">20</ref> So Tiriel first enters “the pleasant
                    gardens of Har” (<hi rend="i">Tir</hi> 2.10)—reminiscent of
                    “Eden the garden of God” located on “the holy mountain of
                    God” (Ez. 28:13-14)—and on his return, “the mountains of
                    Har” (7.19).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63"
type="note">21</ref><hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi> imagines “the old mountains . . .
                    like aged men, fading away” (9) which aptly suits “aged Har” (<hi rend="i">Tir</hi>
8.6). <note id="n62"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Jacob Bryant,
                            <hi rend="i">A New System or, An Analysis of Ancient Mythology</hi>,
                        etc., vol. I (London, 1774), p. 94. The Greek root appears in the word
                        “orology,” which the <hi rend="i">OED</hi> cites from 1781 as
                        “the science of mountains.”</note>
	<note id="n63"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Harold Bloom remarks, “As Har means
                        ‘mountain’ in Hebrew, the very phrase ‘vales of
                        Har’ is an irony” [?] (E 863); Damon interprets the name and
                        situation of Har as, “He who was a mountain now lives in a vale, cut
                        off from mankind” (<hi rend="i">Blake Dictionary</hi>, p.
                    174).</note></p>
        <p>The Book of Joshua offers the Druid-like image of the Israelites setting up
                    “a great stone . . . under an oak . . . by the sanctuary of the LORD”
                    (25.26) at Shechem, which lies between Mount Gerizim, appointed by the Lord for
                    a blessing, and Mount Ebal, appointed for a curse. Here, in the natural
                    amphitheater of the two mountainsides, Joshua divided the tribes of Israel
                    according to the words of Moses, and while one hears little of blessing, twelve
                    shouted verses beginning “Cursed be . . . ” (Jos. 27:11ff.) further
                    illustrate the nature of “barren mountains of Moral Virtue” (<hi rend="i">J</hi>
45[31].19-20; cf. 4.31, above). Jerusalem laments: “The
                    mountain of blessing is itself a curse &amp; an astonishment: / The hills of
                    Judea are fallen with me into the deepest hell” (<hi rend="i">J</hi>
                    79.7-8). A passage repeated in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> shows Tirzah binding down the Human Form crying:
<q> Bind
                        him down Sisters bind him down on Ebal. Mount of cursing:<lb/>
 Malah come
                        forth from Lebanon: &amp; Hoglah from Mount Sinai<lb/>
 . . . . . . . . . .
                        . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
 Weep not so Sisters! weep not so! our life
                        depends on this<lb/>
 Or mercy &amp; truth are fled away from Shechem &amp;
                        Mount Gilead<lb/>
 Unless my beloved is bound upon the Stems of
                        Vegetation<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 68.3-4, 7-9; <hi rend="i">FZ</hi>,
                        VIII, 105.47-48, 51-53, E 364) </q>
The “Stems of Vegetation,” a
                    revision of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>’ introduction to this passage
                    reveals, are the “stones” of the mountain altar: “binding on the
                    Stones [stems <hi rend="i">del.</hi>] / Their victims &amp; with knives
                    tormenting them” (105.28-29 and E 759). “Druid” monuments tend to
                    be associated with Salisbury Plain, but describing his picture “The Ancient
                    Britons,” Blake wrote, “Distant among the mountains, are Druid
                    Temples, similar to Stone Henge” (<hi rend="i">DC</hi>, E 536). Blake was
                    following good authority. Borlase’s <hi rend="i">Antiquities . . . of
                        Cornwall</hi>, for example, observed of the Druids that, “It was a
                    general custom to chuse for their places of worship woods which stood on the
                    tops of hills, and mountains, as more becoming the dignity and sublime offices
                    of their devotions, and of nearer neighbourhood (as they imagined) to the
                    habitations of their Gods.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64"
type="note">22</ref> Borlase
                    remarks the Old Testament parallels and describes “Karnbrê-hill,
                    which has all the evidences that can be desired of having been appropriated to
                    the use of the British Religion;” these are “rock-basons, circles,
                    stones erect, remains of Cromlêh’s, Karns, a grove of Oaks, a
                    cave, and an enclosure” (pp. 116, 120). Thomas Pennant, in his <hi rend="i">Journey to
Snowden</hi> (London, 1781), writes that his fellow-traveller
                    climbed a local hill “on whose summit was a circular coronet of rude
                    peppley stones . . . with an entrance to the east, or rising sun” (p.
                        63).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65" type="note">23</ref>
	<note id="n64"><hi rend="s">22</hi> William Borlase, <hi rend="i">Antiquities, Historical and Monumental, of
the County of Cornwall.
                                Consisting of Several Essays on the First Inhabitants,
                                Druid-Superstition, Customs, and Remains of the most Remote
                                Antiquity</hi> etc., 2nd ed. (London, 1769), p. 116. The practice
                            was not confined to England; John Toland believed that “Abundance
                            of such heaps remain still on the mountains in France, and on the
                            Alps;” <hi rend="i">A Critical History of the Celtic Religion</hi>
                            etc. (London, n.d. [1740?]), p. 102. The cross-cultural associations can
                            extend even further. In his <hi rend="i">Ode to Superstition</hi>
                            (1786), Samuel Rogers writes: 
<q> On yon hoar summit, mildly bright<lb/>
                                With purple ether’s liquid light<lb/>
 High o’er the
                                world, the white-rob’d Magi gaze<lb/>
 On dazzling bursts of
                                heav’nly fire. . . .<lb/>
 (II.3) </q>
A note adds:
                            “‘The Persians,’ says Herodotus, ‘reject the
                            use of temples, altars, and statues. The tops of the highest mountains
                            are the places chosen for sacrifices’” (<hi rend="i">The
                                Pleasures of Memory with other Poems</hi>, new &amp; enlarged ed.
                            [London, 1799], p. 118).
                    </note>
	<note id="n65"><hi rend="s">23</hi> The imaginative power which increasingly
                        associated mountain-tops and Druids is exemplified by a
                        mid-nineteenth-century climber’s description of the top of
                        “Glyder Fach”: “The scene before us, in fact, resembled the
                        ruins of some vast Druidical temple—a mountain
                        Stonehenge—which has been overthrown ages ago by some awful
                        convulsion of nature. Indeed, so strong was our impression that we were in
                        the midst of venerable Druidical remains, that it was some time ere we could
                        convince ourselves that what we saw was in reality a chaotic mass of stones
                        thrown into inconceivable convulsion” (John H. Cliffe, quoted in Edward
                        C. Pyatt, <hi rend="i">Mountains of Britain</hi> [London: B. T. Batsford,
                        1966], p. 67).</note></p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> shows “the Divine Vision like a Silent Sun”
						<q> . . . setting behind the Gardens of Kensington<lb/>
 On Tyburns River, in
                        clouds of blood, where was mild Zion Hills<lb/>
 Most ancient promontory, and
                        in the Sun, a Human Form appeared<lb/>
 (43[29].2-4) </q>
“Zion Hills
                    most ancient promontory” is a formula which appears twice elsewhere in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Plate 12 asks after the burying-place of Etinthus
                    and suggests in further questions, 
					<q> . . . near Tyburns fatal Tree? is
                        that<lb/>
 Mild Zion hills most ancient promontory; near mournful<lb/>
 Ever
                        weeping Paddington? is that Calvary and Golgotha?<lb/>
 (12.26-28)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66" type="note">24</ref>
	<note id="n66"><hi rend="s">24</hi> See also Michael J. Tolley,
                            “Jerusalem 12:25-29—Some Questions Answered,” <hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter</hi>, 4 (August 1970), 3-6; and David V.
                            Erdman, <hi rend="i">Prophet Against Empire</hi>, rev. ed., Anchor Books
                            (Garden City, N. Y.: Doubleday, 1969), pp. 474ff.</note></q>
This is glossed by
27.25ff where “ever-weeping Paddington” is
                    identified as “that mighty Ruin / Where Satan the <hi rend="i">first</hi>
                    victory won” (my italics), where also “the Druids” made
                    “Offerings of Human Life.” The general reference is to Tyburn,
                    London’s place of public hangings from as early as 1196 until 1783. By
                    the time they were discontinued, Blake was twenty-six and undoubtedly all too
                    aware of the eager crowds that appeared for each of the eight public
                    hanging-days—indeed, tradition made these public holidays for all
                        journeymen.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">25</ref>
A “Paddington
                    Fair” was a public execution, so called because Tyburn was less than a mile
                    from the village of Paddington,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68"
type="note">26</ref> in whose
                    parish it was eventually included. There is a visionary continuity joining the
                    Druid monuments, Calvary, and Tyburn: Druid human sacrifices “generally
                    consisted of such criminals as were convicted of theft, or any capital
                    crime” (Borlase, p. 121) and Calvary—as the crucifixion of two
                    thieves with Jesus suggests—was, like Tyburn, a site for the execution of
                    common criminals. <note id="n67"><hi rend="s">25</hi> George Rudé, 
<hi rend="i">Hanoverian London, 1714-1808</hi>, The History of London
                        (Berkeley and Los Angeles: University of California Press, 1971), p.
                        94.</note>
	<note id="n68"><hi rend="s">26</hi><hi rend="i"> 1811 Dictionary of the Vulgar Tongue. A Dictionary of
Buckish
                            Slang, University Wit, and Pickpocket Eloquence</hi>, fore. Robert
                        Cromie, rpt. from 1811 original (Chicago: Follett Publishing, n.d. [?1971]),
                        s.v.</note></p>
        <p>I am suggesting that the passage from plate 12 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                    quoted above answers itself: Mild Zion hills most ancient promontory <hi rend="i">is</hi>
Tyburn’s fatal Tree (“that” of 1.26). Not
                    because it had particular elevation (it is a mountain of the mind, a mounting of
                    the scaffold), but because it possessed all the attributes of Calvary,
                    succinctly re-summarized by Richard Cumberland in his long poem, <hi rend="i">Calvary; or
the Death of Christ</hi> (London, 1792): “Without the city
                    wall there was a mount / Call’d 
<pb id="p14-201" n="201"/>
CALVARY: The
                    common grave it was / Of malefactors” (VI. 440-42). According to one
                    authority the Tyburn gallows was in fact situated “on a small eminence at
                    the corner of Edgeware-Road,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69"
type="note">27</ref> which
                    road, together with Park Lane was as late as 1806 the western limit of
                    London’s urbanization and the location of one of its “gates,”
                    the Tyburn Turnpike.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70"
type="note">28</ref> Lucas van
                    Leyden’s engraving of <hi rend="i">Calvary</hi> shows just how small an
                    eminence can make a mount, or promontory (illus. 1), and Sterne probably
                    reflects the general conception when he has Tristram remark that an altar over
                    sixty feet high would have “been as high as mount <hi rend="i">Calvary</hi>
                    itself” (<hi rend="i">Tristram Shandy</hi>, VII, 5). Blake described his
                    residence at South Molton Street—just blocks down Oxford Street from the
                    old gallows—as located on “Calvarys foot / Where the Victims were
                    preparing for Sacrifice” (<hi rend="i">M</hi> 4.21-22). Significant also
                    was the very instrument of execution. Tyburn Tree was not a gibbet; rather,
                    “The scaffold consisted of three posts, ten or twelve feet high, held apart
                    by three connecting cross-bars at the top.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n71" type="note">29</ref> It was, in effect, a ruined version of a Druidic temple made of
                    trilithons—one of the far-fetched hypotheses about 
<figure n="milton.c.p4-a" id="milton.c.illbk.04" work-copy="milton.c" rend="db" width="723" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>3<lb/>
	Beneath the Plow of Rintrah &amp; the Harrow of the Almighty<lb/>
	In the hands of Palamabron. Where the Starry Mills of Satan<lb/>
	Are built beneath the Earth &amp; Waters of the Mundane Shell<lb/>
	Here the Three Classes of Men take their Sexual texture Woven<lb/>
	The Sexual is Threefold: the Human is Fourfold<lb/>
	If you account it Wisdom when you are angry to be silent. and<lb/>
	Not to shew it: I do not account that Wisdom but Folly.<lb/>
	Every Mans Wisdom is peculiar to his own Individiality<lb/>
	O Satan my youngest born, art thou not Prince of the Starry Hosts<lb/>
	And of the Wheels of Heaven. to turn the Mills day &amp; night?<lb/>
	Art thou not Newtons Pantocrator weaving the Woof of Locke<lb/>
	To Mortals thy Mills seem every thing &amp; the Harrow of Shaddai<lb/>
	A scheme of Human conduct invisible &amp; incomprehensible<lb/>
	Get to thy Labours at the Mills &amp; leave me to my wrath<lb/>
	Satan was going to reply. but Los roll’d his loud thunders.<lb/>
	Anger me not! thou canst not drive the Harrow in pitys paths.<lb/>
	Thy Work is Eternal Death, with Mills &amp; Ovens &amp; Cauldrons.<lb/>
	Trouble me no more, thou canst not have Eternal Life<lb/>
	So Los spoke! Satan trembling obey’d weeping along the way.<lb/>
	Mark well my words, they are of your eternal Salvation<lb/>
	Between South Molton Street &amp; Stratford Place: Calvarys foot<lb/>
	Where the Victims were preparing for Sacrifice their Cherubim<lb/>
	Around their loins pourd forth their arrows &amp; their bosoms beam<lb/>
	With all colours of precious stones, &amp; their inmost palaces<lb/>
	Resounded with preparation of animals wild &amp; tame<lb/>
	(Mark well my words! Corporeal Friends<lb/>
	are Spiritual Enemies)<lb/>
	Mocking Druidical Mathematical<lb/>
	Proportion of Length Bredth Highth<lb/>
	Displaying Naked Beauty! with Flute &amp;<lb/>
	Harp &amp; Song</figTranscr>
	<head>3 <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, copy C, pl. 3.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Rare Book Division, The New York Public Library,
                            Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations.</figDesc>
</figure> Stonehenge was that it had served as a monumental gallows. In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 80,
Vala attempts to “weave Jerusalem a
                    body” or “A Dragon form on Zion Hills most ancient promontory”:
                    the “form” is that of the Druidic “Dragon Temples” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 25.4,
47.6). <note id="n69"><hi rend="s">27</hi> John Timbs,
                            <hi rend="i">Curiosities of London</hi>, A New Edition (London, 1867),
                        p. 809.</note>
	<note id="n70"><hi rend="s">28</hi> See, for example, the map accompanying B.
                        Lambert, <hi rend="i">The History and Survey of London and Its Environs</hi>
                        (London, 1806), vol. IV.</note>
	<note id="n71"><hi rend="s">29</hi> Peter Linebaugh, “The Tyburn Riot
                        Against the Surgeons,” in <hi rend="i">Albion’s Fatal Tree:
                            Crime and Society in Eighteenth-Century England</hi>, Douglas Hay, Peter
                        Linebaugh, John G. Rule, E. P. Thompson, Cal Winslow (New York: Pantheon
                        Books/Random House, 1975), pp. 65-117, p. 66. The structure is visible, for
                        example, in Hogarth’s print, <hi rend="i">The Idle ’Prentice
                            Executed at Tyburn</hi>, Industry and Idleness, XI (illus.
                        2)—complete with a Calvary-like crowd of spectators. Timbs reports
                        that “The gallows subsequently consisted of two uprights and a
                        cross-beam” (p. 809)—an equally Druidic, if less impressive,
                        structure.</note></p>
        <p>These motifs are illustrated at the bottom of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, plate 4
                    (illus. 3); there a rock-skull emerges from the ground, overshadowed by three
                    trilithons on a mount, reminiscent of the three crosses on Calvary (note
                    Blake’s reference to Calvary on the same plate, quoted above), while on
                    the right the three seem to have joined into a threefold trilithon which
                    suggests a Druid form of the Tyburn gallows.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n72" type="note">30</ref> One might note also how directly above this structure a spindle or
                    body hangs on high from the end of the line held by one of Blake’s
                    spinner-Goddesses. The rock-skull identifies this scene as Calvary or Golgotha,
                    “which is, being interpreted, the place of a skull” (Mk. 15:22, inter
                    al.). This theme is further developed in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 28,
                    where Albion “sat by Tyburns brook, and underneath his heel shot up! / A
                    deadly Tree, he nam’d it Moral Virtue” (14-15)—the
                    “Tree” here joins the cross, Tyburn Tree (cf. <hi rend="i">OED</hi>,
                    s.v. “tree,” B. 4a,b), and the Tree of Good and Evil, complete with a
                    Serpentine form at its base.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73"
type="note">31</ref> Tyburn, then,
                    is Zion Hills promontory, “most ancient” because all things begin in
                    Albion and this is “‘the most ancient promontory’ of
                    sacrifice” (Erdman, <hi rend="i">Prophet</hi>, p. 475), “the summit of
                    the cosmic mountain and at the same time the place where Adam had been created
                    and buried. Thus the blood of the Saviour falls upon Adam’s skull, buried
                    precisely at the foot of the Cross, and redeems him”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">32</ref> (illus. 4). The use of the word “promontory,”
                    as Tolley notes, is singular—it serves perhaps to bring in several
                    associations. The promontory is a <hi rend="i">visionary</hi> scene (like the
                    Atlantic mountains of <hi rend="i">America</hi>), a “head-land”
                    offering a vista on the Sea of Time and Space (cf. <hi rend="i">3 Henry VI</hi>,
                    III. ii. 134-36); it is the sterile earth to which Hamlet equates it (II. ii.
                    311); and finally, it is the covering of the fallen mind: in <hi rend="i">Paradise
                    Lost</hi> the angelic host defeats the rebels and “on <corr type="emend">their</corr>
                    heads / Main Promontories flung” (6.653-54; cf. <hi rend="i">J.</hi> 71.55
                    cited below). Ultimately the most ancient promontory is the reader’s
                    skull (Golgotha/Golgonooza), “Once open to the heavens and elevated on the
                    human neck” (<hi rend="i">Eur</hi> 10.28), but now imagining and enclosing
                    all these mountains of and in the mind. 
                    <note id="n72"><hi rend="s">30</hi> Cf.
                        Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi>, Anchor Books (Garden City,
                        N. Y.: Doubleday, 1974), p. 220.</note>
                    <note id="n73"><hi rend="s">31</hi> Erdman astutely observes that “To
                        correspond to the serpent in the Garden of Eden the typography of Hyde Park
                        supplies the Serpentine River, which Blake in his deviousness never refers
                        to by its own name . . . ” (<hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against
                        Empire</hi>, rev. ed. [Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1969], p. 465);
                        one antiquary notes that the fatal tree was “opposite the head of the
                        Serpentine . . . itself being formed in the bed of the ancient stream, first
                        called Tybourn . . . ” (Timbs, p. 809).</note>
                    <note id="n74"><hi rend="s">32</hi> Mircea Eliade, <hi rend="i">Cosmos and
                            History: The Myth of the Eternal Return</hi>, trans. Willard R. Trask,
                        Harper Torchbooks, Bollingen Library (New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1959), p.
                        14; see also, George Every, <hi rend="i">Christian Mythology</hi> (London:
                        Hamlyn Publishing, 1970), “The place of the skull,” pp. 51ff.
                        Erdman writes (following Timbs), “It was recalled that after the
                        Restoration the bodies of Cromwell, Ireton, and Bradshaw had been
                        disinterred, hanged, and beheaded, and then reburied [under Tyburn
                        gallows]—another denial of the Resurrection” (<hi rend="i">Prophet</hi>, p.
                        474).</note></p>
        <p>Los, who is himself an ancient Briton, reaches back to the unfallen state of the
                    mountain imagery, praying “O Divine Saviour arise / Upon the Mountains of
                    Albion as in ancient time<supplied type="emend">”</supplied> 
                    (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 44[30].21-22). This image,
                    together with the evocation of “those feet in ancient time / . . . upon
                    Englands mountains green” (<hi rend="i">M</hi> 1), recalls the
                    twice-repeated Biblical praise, “How beautiful upon the mountains are the
                    feet of him that bringeth good tidings, that publisheth peace” (Is. 52:7,
                    Nah. 1:15). Considering the plate geology of relief etching, one could say that
                    Blake’s message also is published on the mountains. The finale of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> presents a vision of “the Sun in heavy clouds /
            <corr type="emend">Struggling</corr> to rise above the Mountains” (95.11-12): a struggle, perhaps,
                    because mountains are the “risings” of the earth, the objects of
                    increasing Romantic adoration. <pb id="p14-202" n="202"/>
<figure n="DurerCrucifixion.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="771" height="1000">
	<head>4 Albrecht Dürer, “Crucifixion,” from the <hi rend="i">Small Passion</hi> (1509-11; 127 × 97
mm.).</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the British Museum.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p14-203" n="203"/>
That Sun will rise over different mountains, the
                    natural ones being removed and cast into the sea by faith and “firm
                    perswasion” in imagination (<hi rend="i">MHH</hi> 12; cf. Mt. 21:21). Once
						<q> Jerusalem coverd the Atlantic Mountains &amp; the Erythrean,<lb/>
 From
                        bright Japan &amp; China to Hesperia France &amp; England.<lb/>
 Mount Zion
                        lifted his head in every Nation under heaven:<lb/>
 And the Mount of Olives
                        was beheld over the whole Earth<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 24.46-49) </q>
and
                    though at present “Jerusalem lies in ruins: / Above the Mountains of
                    Albion, above the head of Los” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 71.54-55), in the words
                    of Isaiah, “it shall come to pass in the last days, that the mountain of
                    the LORD’s house shall be established in the top of the mountains, and
                    shall be exalted above the hills; and all nations shall flow unto it”
                    (2:2).</p>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p14-204" n="204" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
