<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.4.bindman</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">The Dead Ardours Revisited</title>
        <author n="Bindman">David Bindman</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
              <name>Erik Frykman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>William Vaughan</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <pb id="p14-211" n="211"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-4-0009">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">DISCUSSION</hi>
          </title>
          <title type="section-subtitle">
            <hi rend="b">WITH INTELLECTUAL SPEARS &amp; LONG WINGED ARROWS OF THOUGHT</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">THE DEAD ARDOURS REVISITED</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>David <name>Bindman</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Before “The Dead Ardours Perry” enters the canon of Blake’s
                        writings [see David V. Erdman, “Leonora, Laodamia, and the Dead
                        Ardours,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 54, Fall 1980, pp. 96-98] and becomes
                        part of the intellectual heritage of the English-speaking peoples it might
                        be of interest for me to describe what I can make of the words on the
                        drawing with it in front of me. To begin with, the letters ‘W
                        B’ on the left are <hi rend="i">below</hi> the level of the disputed
                        text, therefore David Erdman’s assumption that they belong with it is
                        doubtful: more to the point, perhaps, is that the letters ‘W
                        B’ do not look as if they are in Blake’s hand, and they are
                        not in the same type of script as the other text. There can be no doubt
                        about the initial words ‘The dead’ nor, I believe, that they
                        are in Blake’s own formal script, but it is still not even clear how
                        many words follow. I agree with Erdman that ‘bad-doers’ does
                        not work but I would dispute it because there appear to be <hi rend="i">four</hi>
letters where he reads the ‘ard’ of
                        ‘ardours’; in fact I see a faint ‘b’ or another
                        letter with a long vertical stroke before his conjected ‘ard’.
                        That final ‘d’ is certain, the ‘ar’ at least
                        possible, in which case we are left with ‘bard’, which makes
                        sense but can only be regarded as a tentative suggestion. The four letters
                        read by Erdman as ‘ours’ may complete the word as he suggests
                        (in which case it would be unlikely to begin with ‘bard’);
                        there could be a hyphen between them and the previous word (as in
                        ‘bad-doers’), or they could form a separate word. What makes
                        it especially difficult is that they seem to have been gone over and altered
                        in pencil, most likely by Blake himself. As for the word read by Erdman as
                        ‘Perry’ it looks very much to me and to others who have looked
                        at it as if it begins with an elaborate ‘l’ and it could end
                        with a ‘g’ and not a ‘y’. I can make nothing of
                        the letters in between. I should also say that it seems very improbable that
                        Blake would have brought in the name of such an obscure engraver in this
                        way, in the same formal script as the title, even if there were other
                        evidence to connect it with the <hi rend="i">Leonora</hi> engravings.</p>
          <p>I am sorry to have thrown the question open again, but anyone who wants to
                        have another try is always welcome to look at the drawing in London. 
<hi rend="i">David V. Erdman’s response will appear in the summer
                            1981 issue. Eds.</hi></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
