<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.4.essick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake’s “Enoch” Lithograph</title>
        <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
              <name>Erik Frykman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>William Vaughan</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
    <pb id="p14-180" n="180"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-4-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">BLAKE’S “ENOCH” LITHOGRAPH</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">ROBERT N.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">ESSICK</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>Like many of Blake’s separate graphics, “Enoch” offers several
                    problems for those who wish to determine its exact medium, date, and the
                    circumstances surrounding its production. Even the subject of Blake’s
                    only known lithograph was not discovered until 1936.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> My purpose here is to review what we know about the techniques
                    Blake used to create “Enoch” and present some new information on its
                    relationship to the history of early lithography in England. 
<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Laurence Binyon and Geoffrey Keynes, introduction to
                            <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job by William Blake</hi> (New
                        York: Pierpont Morgan Library, 1935), p. 8 of the first fascicle. The
                        authors credit Joseph Wicksteed with the discovery that the inscription on
                        the book held by the central figure is “Enoch” in Hebrew; the
                        inscription on the tablet held by a floating figure on the right is
                        “And Enoch walked with God” (from Genesis V:24). Previous
                        authorities had believed that the design pictured “Job in
                        Prosperity,” the title given to it by A. G. B. Russell in <hi rend="i">The Engravings
of William Blake</hi> (Boston and New York: Houghton
                        Mifflin, 1912), p. 91. The error is understandable because the design is
                        closely connected with Blake’s development of a composition he also
                        used in his Job illustrations, culminating in the lower half of the central
                        design on pl. 2 of the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engravings. Apparently some
                        scholars have not been convinced by Wicksteed’s findings; S. Foster
                        Damon, for example, describes the print as “‘Job in
                        Prosperity’ . . . holding on his lap an open book labelled (in
                        Hebrew) ‘Enoch’.” See Damon, <hi rend="i">A Blake
                            Dictionary</hi> (Providence, R. I.: Brown University Press, 1965), p.
                        126.</note></p>
        <p>The pen and ink inscription (illus. 1) on the verso of an impression of
                    “Enoch” in the collection of Mr. Edward Croft-Murray (illus. 2) would
                    seem to offer a description of how the print was made. The handwriting is George
                    Cumberland’s, whose own involvement with graphic experiments, and in
                    particular with Blake’s plans to publish an account of his
                        inventions,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref>
lends some authority to the
                    inscription. Mr. Croft-Murray tells me that the print appeared in a
                    Sotheby’s auction in 1957 as part of a miscellaneous lot that included a
                    number of Italian engravings that were probably from Cumberland’s
                    extensive collection of such material. Cumberland probably acquired his
                    “Enoch” directly from Blake, and his description on its verso may very
                    well be based on Blake’s own account of how he made the print, as the
                    last two words of the note indicate. The inscription reads as follows: 
					<q> White
                        Lyas—is the Block / draw with Ink composed of asphaltum dissolved in
                        dry [?] / Linseed oil—add fine venetian Tripoli &amp; [?] Rotten
                        Stone Powder. / Let it dry. when dry saturate the stone with water and / Dab
                        it with the broad Dabber, and [<hi rend="i">deleted</hi>] coverd very thinly
                        with / best Printers Ink—and Print as a block—. / of
                            Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref></q>
If we assume the general accuracy of Cumberland’s account, the
                    “Block” or stone was white lias, a limestone from an area near Bath in
                    southwestern England, rather than the German Kellheim stone used by Alois
                    Senefelder in the lithographic process he invented in the mid-1790s.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> Instead of using lithographic chalk or ink,
                    Blake drew his design with a mixture of asphaltum and linseed oil which, if not
                    the acid resist he actually used in his copperplate relief etchings, must have
                    been a liquid with very similar physical properties. Besides the chemical
                    differences between this mixture and lithographic ink,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> Blake’s material was probably more glutinous and
                    would have to be heated so as to flow evenly from the brush or pen and harden
                    quickly upon contact with the cool stone. According to Cumberland’s note,
                    Blake added “Tripoli” and/or rotten stone, both fine polishing
                    compounds, to his resist, perhaps simply as a thickener or to increase the
                    receptivity of the resist to printing ink. At this point, the usual procedure in
                    early nineteenth-century lithography, at least as practiced in England, would
                    have required a lithographic etch, water wash, and gum-water treatment to
                    increase the stone’s ability to hold water and repel ink. The first of
                    these procedures actually reduced the surface of the stone wherever it was not
                    protected by the lithographic ink or chalk, which functioned like the ground or
                    acid resist in copperplate etching. Although he later realized that the proper
                    inking of the stone depended almost completely on the antipathy of the oily
                    printing ink to the water-soaked stone, Senefelder states in his <hi rend="i">Complete
Course</hi>, p. 10, that he etched his early stones to a depth of
                    “about a 10th part of a line, (or 1-120th part of an inch).” That this
                    practice was continued in early English lithography is indicated by Thomas
                    Fisher who notes, in the <hi rend="i">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi> of 
<pb id="p14-181" n="181"/>
1808, that “that part of the face of the stone
                    not actually covered with the ink is lowered about the thickness of half a line
                    [i.e., about 1/24 of an inch?].”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref> Thus,
                    “polyautography” (as early lithography was called) was a relief
                    process and not a true planographic technique like modern lithography. 
<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Letters between Cumberland and Blake of
                        1807-1808 and several entries in Cumberland’s journal indicate that
                        the two friends were discussing the publication of Blake’s “new
                        Mode of Engraving.” See Geoffrey Keynes, ed., <hi rend="i">The Letters
                            of William Blake</hi> (London: Rupert Hart-Davis, 1968), p. 134; and G.
                        E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press,
                        1969), pp. 187-88, 211 and n. 3, 212.</note>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> The inscription was first published on the
                        verso of a single sheet of “Additional items on exhibition, 
                        <corr type="emend">13 January–28 March 1971,”</corr> a supplement to 
                        <hi rend="i">William Blake: Catalogue of the Collection in the 
                        Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge</hi>, ed. David Bindman (Cambridge: 
                        Heffer and Sons, 1970). The text printed here is a new transcription 
                        from the original (see also illus. 1).</note>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See Senefelder, <hi rend="i">Complete Course
                            of Lithography</hi> (London: R. Ackermann, 1819), for a full description
                        of the process and its invention. The use of white lias for lithography was
                        first suggested in print by John Thomas Smith, <hi rend="i">Antiquities of
                            Westminster</hi> (London: J. T. Smith, 1807), p. 48. Charles Hullmandel,
                            <hi rend="i">The Art of Drawing on Stone</hi> (London: Hullmandel and R.
                        Ackermann, [1824]), p. 2, warns that “the white lias, of Bath . . . is
                        too soft and porous” for lithography. Michael Twyman, <hi rend="i">Lithography
1800-1850</hi> (London: Oxford University Press, 1970), p.
                        30, asserts that Blake subscribed to Smith’s <hi rend="i">Antiquities</hi>; but in
fact the “William Blake, Esq. Sunbury
                        House, Middlesex” in Smith’s List of Subscribers, p. 274, is not
                        the eponym of this journal.</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Senefelder, pp. 111-18, offers several
                        formulae for his “chemical ink.” Most require wax, soap, shellac,
                        and lampblack (for color). The “soft” ink “for transferring
                        Drawings or Writings from Paper on the Stone” (pp. 121-22) is a less
                        viscous variant of the chemical ink. For what we know of the acid resist
                        Blake used for his relief etchings, see Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake,
                            Printmaker</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1980), pp.
                        87-88.</note>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Senefelder, p. 10; Fisher, “The Process
                        of Polyautographic Printing,” <hi rend="i">Gentleman’s
                            Magazine</hi>, 78 (March 1808), 194.</note></p>
        <p>If Cumberland did not accidently leave these steps out of his description, then
                    Blake’s method required neither etching nor gumming-up and he added only
                    water to repel the printing ink from the uncovered surface of the stone. The
                    foreshortening of the conventional procedure may have been possible because
                    Blake’s asphaltum and linseed oil resist would itself raise the image
                    above the level of the stone. Asphaltum will solidify at a slightly higher level
                    than any smooth surface to which it is applied.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n7" type="note">7</ref> Finally, Blake inked the stone with a “broad Dabber,”
                    which must have been a large type-printer’s inking ball of the sort
                    generally used in early English lithography,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n8" type="note">8</ref>
                    and printed the stone “as a block”—that is, in relief like a
                    woodcut or one of Blake’s own copperplates for his illuminated books.
                        <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> I have found it quite easy to print from
                        varnish delineations on unetched surfaces; see Essick, <hi rend="i">William
                            Blake, Printmaker</hi>, pp. 110-11 and fig. 109. Printing from asphaltum
                        and linseed oil would be the same as long as the mixture were allowed to
                        harden thoroughly.</note>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Smith, <hi rend="i">Antiquities of
                            Westminster</hi>, p. 50.</note></p>
        <p>If we can trust Cumberland’s intriguing inscription, “Enoch” was
                    produced by a hybrid technique combining the stone and water elements of early
                    lithography with an acid resist very similar, perhaps even identical, to that
                    used by Blake in his own relief etchings. The awkward execution of some passages
                    in the design (note, for example, the two faces upper left) may be the result of
                    the experimental nature of the medium and Blake’s unfamiliarity with
                    working on a stone that was far more porous than his copperplates. It is even
                    possible that Cumberland played a role in the preparation of the stone; similar
                    types of gracelessness of line and stiffness in the figures appear in the
                    outline engravings (or perhaps simply drypoint sketches) he made for his 
<hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline</hi> (1796). It must be admitted, however, that
                    Blake’s own work, particularly drawings executed in the 1780s, is not
                    free from such features.</p>
        <p>A basically similar use of acid resist on a lithographic stone, but one that
                    required etching, is described by William Home Lizars in his “Account of a
                    New Style of Engraving on Copper in Alto Relievo” in <hi rend="i">The
                        Edinburgh Philosophical Journal</hi>, 2 (January-April 1820), 23. In a
                    letter dated January 1819, Cumberland wrote his son to “tell <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> a Mr
Sivewright [thanked by Lizars for assistance] of Edinburgh
                    has just claimed in Home Philosophical Journal of Last Month As his own
                    invention Blake’s Method—&amp; calls it Copper Blocks I
                        think.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> I
cannot find any
                    “Home Philosophical Journal,” and the relationship between
                    Cumberland’s letter and Lizars’ article (the former dated a year
                    before the publication of the latter)remains a mystery. But E. B.
                    Murray’s astute redating of one of Blake’s letters to Thomas
                        Butts<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> has
suggested to me the
                    possibility that Cumberland failed to change to the new year when he dated his
                    letter in January, and thus it may have actually been written late in the first
                    month of 1820 and does indeed refer to Lizars’ article. In any case, it
                    is quite possible that Blake knew of Lizars’ work, but the information
                    could not have reached him until long after he had produced “Enoch.”
                        <note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> British Library Add. MSS. 36501, ff.
                        360-61. Cumberland dated the letter “22 Jan 1819” in the upper
                        right corner of the first page. Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p.
                        214, incorrectly gives the date as “January 22nd, 1809.” In his
                        letter, Cumberland refers to the Sivewright-Lizars application of their
                        relief technique to copper (as in Blake’s illuminated books) and not
                        to stone (as in “Enoch”).</note>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Murray, “A Suggested Redating of a
                        Blake Letter to Thomas Butts,” <hi rend="i">Blake: An Illustrated
                            Quarterly</hi>, 13 (Winter 1979-80), 148-51.</note></p>
        <p>A. G. B. Russell, Laurence Binyon, and Sir Geoffrey Keynes have all associated
                    the execution of “Enoch” with the lithographic publishing endeavors of
                    Georg Jacob Vollweiler.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">11</ref> Late in 1800,
                    Senefelder came to England and patented his new process of polyautography.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> He brought with him Philipp André,
                    to whom Senefelder had taught the new process. When he returned to Germany after
                    a visit in England lasting about seven months, Senefelder sold the patent to
                    André, who stayed in London. In 1803, André issued <hi rend="i">Specimens of
Polyautography</hi> containing twelve lithographs by various
                    English artists, including Barry, Stothard, and Fuseli. When André left
                    London in 1805, Vollweiler took over as patentee. He reissued <hi rend="i">Specimens</hi>,
adding to it twenty-four new prints, with a title-page
                    dated 1806 but with some prints inscribed 1807 on the stone. Like the first
                    issue, Vollweiler’s publication attracted little notice, and he returned
                    to Germany in August 1807. His lithographic equipment passed into the hands of
                    D. Redman, who removed the business to Bath in 1813. <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi>
Russell, <hi rend="i">Engravings of Blake</hi>, p. 91; Binyon,
                            <hi rend="i">The Engraved Designs of William Blake</hi> (London: Ernest
                        Benn, 1926), pp. 21-22; Keynes, <hi rend="i">Engravings by William Blake:
                            The Separate Plates</hi> (Dublin: Emery Walker, 1956), pp. 43-44. None
                        of these authorities gives any specific reasons for believing that
                        Vollweiler had something to do with “Enoch.”</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> The historical facts recounted here are
                        taken from Senefelder’s <hi rend="i">Complete Course</hi>,
                        Twyman’s <hi rend="i">Lithography</hi>, pp. 26-40, and Felix H. Man,
                        “Lithography in England (1801-1810),” in <hi rend="i">Prints</hi>,
                        ed. Carl Zigrosser (New York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1962), pp.
                        97-130.</note></p>
        <p>But “Enoch” was not published as part of either issue of the <hi rend="i">Specimens.</hi><supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> The best
                    known impression of “Enoch” is the one in the British Museum,
                    Department of Prints and Drawings, bound into a volume containing many 
<hi rend="i">Specimens</hi> prints, but also containing a number of lithographs
                    not published in <hi rend="i">Specimens.</hi> No impression of “Enoch”
                    is mounted on paper with a brown aquatint border, as are all the prints actually
                    issued in the <hi rend="i">Specimens</hi>, 1803 and 1806. Indeed,
                    Cumberland’s description of Blake’s experimental procedures would
                    seem on the face of it to dissociate his work from the entire
                    Senefelder-André-Vollweiler enterprise. It seems improbable that the
                    inventor of lithography or his official successors in London would sponsor a
                    project that did not follow normal lithographic procedures on which they held
                    the patent. The special properties of Kellheim stone would logically have been
                    one of the keys to their secret, patented process, and the substitution of
                    another, locally obtainable stone something that the patentees would eschew.
                    This is the line of thinking I set forth in my previous comments on
                        “Enoch,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> but
some new
                    evidence I have come upon indicates a very different conclusion. Several
                    crucial, if not absolutely conclusive, pieces of evidence do link
                    “Enoch” to Vollweiler’s activities. <note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Fisher, 
<hi rend="i">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi>, p. 195,
                        lists the artists who contributed to the Vollweiler issue, and Blake is not
                        among them.</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> In <hi rend="i">William Blake,
                            Printmaker</hi>, pp. 161-63. While I am on the tedious subject of
                        correcting my own errors, let me point out that fig. 4 in 
<hi rend="i">Printmaker</hi>, a detail from “View of St Peter’s
                        Church” after Thyne O’Niell, was not engraved by Blake’s
                        master, James Basire (1730-1802), but by his son and successor of the same
                        name (1769-1822). My error was caused by a pencil inscription on the verso
                        of a trimmed impression in my collection indicating that the print was
                        produced c. 1775, and thus necessarily by the elder Basire. However,
                        Professor Christopher Heppner has very kindly pointed out to me that the
                        print appears on the <hi rend="i">Oxford Almanack</hi> of 1809. The whole
                        design, much reduced, is reproduced in Helen Mary Petter, <hi rend="i">The
                            Oxford Almanacks</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1974), p. 84, where it
                        is noted that the painting was commissioned from Hugh O’Neill (who
                        apparently also used the name “Thyne O’Niell”) in 1806.
                        Thus the plate must be by the younger Basire. My purpose in reproducing a
                        detail from it in <hi rend="i">Printmaker</hi> was to show typical features
                        of the senior Basire’s style, particularly twisted lines on rounded
                        forms and worm lines in landscapes, later used by Blake. The first technique
                        can be found in just about any arm or leg delineated by Blake’s
                        master; the worm lines appear in a number of his book
                        illustrations—see for example James Stuart and Nicholas Revett, <hi rend="i">The
Antiquities of Athens</hi>, vol. I (1762), pl. 1; <hi rend="i">Vetusta Monumenta</hi>, vol. II, pl. 24 (“View
of Richmond
                        Palace” dated 1765); Jacob Bryant, <hi rend="i">A New System, or, an
                            Analysis of Ancient Mythology</hi> (1774-76), vol. I, pls. 2, 3, 7, vol.
                        II, pl. 1 (lower left in the upper panel); <hi rend="i">Archaeologia</hi>,
                        vol. III (1775), pl. 17 facing p. 315; Richard Gough, <hi rend="i">Sepulchral
Monuments in Great Britain</hi> (1786), pl. 14 facing p. 42.
                        Some of these examples are very close to the worm lines in plates by the
                        younger Basire and by Blake, although both may have been directly influenced
                        by William Woollett’s practices. Woollett was famous for his use of
                        heavy worm lines, or “needling,” and was apparently much admired
                        by the senior Basire since he gave his son Richard the middle name of
                        Woollett (see <hi rend="i">Printmaker</hi>, pp. 199-200).</note></p>
        <p>Fisher, writing in the <hi rend="i">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi> in 1808 (see
                    my note 6), remarks that “M. Andre imported them [the lithographic stones]
                    from Germany, although his successor [Vollweiler] assured me that stone [i.e.,
                    white lias] of a nearly similar quality might be procured in the neighbourhood
                    of Bath, but not, he believed, in very large blocks” (pp. 193-94). This
                    statement does not prove that Vollweiler actually used white lias, but it does
                    indicate that he was amenable to its use and suggests that one of the reasons
                    his successor, Redman, moved to Bath may have been the availability of proper
                    stones in that area. According to Felix Man, “Vollweiler issued circulars
                    asking amateurs to try their hand in the new art, offering instructions and
                    materials, with 
        <pb id="p14-182" n="182"/>
		<figure n="CumberlandInscription.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="312">
			<head>1 Pen and ink inscription by George Cumberland on the verso of an
									impression of Blake’s “Enoch” lithograph (illus.
									2).</head>
			<figDesc>The mat covers a few letters on the far right.</figDesc>
		</figure>
		<figure n="ESXV.1.1B.SP" rend="file" width="958" height="674">
			<head>2 Blake’s “Enoch.”</head>
			<figDesc>Modified lithograph, 1806 or early 1807. 21.7 × 31 cm. The
									marks in the white space above the central figure are letters of the
									inscription (illus. 1) showing through from the verso. Collection of Mr.
									Edward Croft-Murray; reproduced with his permission.</figDesc>
		</figure>
		<pb id="p14-183" n="183"/> 
					the stone on loan at a moderate 
					price.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> 
					Thus, Vollweiler may have provided stones
                    to artists who, like Blake, had little contemporary fame and thus would not have
                    been asked to contribute to <hi rend="i">Specimens.</hi> And these artists of
                    little consequence would have been the very sort to be given the somewhat
                    inferior white lias rather than the imported, and probably much more precious,
                    Kellheim stones. <note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> “Lithography in
                        England” in <hi rend="i">Prints</hi>, p. 108. Man does not give the
                        source of his information or the whereabouts of copies of these
                        “circulars.”</note></p>
        <p>The papers on which three of the four extant impressions of “Enoch” are
                    printed suggest a further connection with Vollweiler. The print in the British
                    Museum is on the same type of buff colored wove paper, and both the image (21.7
                    × 31 cm.) and the sheet (22.6 × 31.9 cm.) are of about the same
                    size, as several of the <hi rend="i">Specimens</hi> prints, second issue, bound
                    with it. The chocolate brown wove paper on which the copies in the collections
                    of Sir Geoffrey Keynes and Raymond Lister are printed is similar in color and
                    texture to the stock used for the chalk manner lithographs in P. E.
                    Stroehling’s <hi rend="i">Original Sketches Drawn Upon Stone</hi>,
                    published by Vollweiler shortly before he left London, and for the prints in 
<hi rend="i">Twelve Views in Scotland, Delineated by a Lady</hi> [F. Waring] <hi rend="i">in the Polyautographic
Art of Drawing Upon Stone</hi>, published by
                    Rudolph Ackermann in 1803.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16"
type="note">16</ref> I know of no
                    other prints by Blake, executed in any medium, printed on these unusual types of
                    paper. Finally, a standard plate printing press of the early nineteenth century
                    could only have been adapted for lithographic printing with considerable
                    difficulty because of the thickness of the stone. In all probability, Blake
                    would have had to turn to someone with the requisite equipment to pull good
                    quality impressions from his stone. The only people in England so equipped until
                    1812 were André, Vollweiler, and Redman.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n17" type="note">17</ref> Thus, the preponderance of the evidence suggests that Blake
                    learned of lithography from Vollweiler, rented or borrowed the stone from him,
                    delineated “Enoch” in an acid resist similar to the liquid he had used
                    for years for his relief etchings, and returned the stone to Vollweiler for
                    printing. The first three of these steps could have occurred only in 1806 or
                    early 1807, after Vollweiler had taken over the London lithographic business
                    from André and before he departed for Germany. The printing could have
                    been done by Redman at a later time, but it would have been to the economic
                    advantage of all concerned to proof “Enoch” shortly after its
                    execution and remove Blake’s work from the stone so that it could be used
                    again for another drawing. <note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Five of the
                        Stroehling lithographs on brown paper are in the British Museum. In 1803,
                        Ackermann could only have learned of lithography from André, who very
                        probably also provided Ackermann with the stones and pulled the impressions.
                        For a reproduction of the Keynes’ impression of “Enoch” on
                        a brown background slightly lighter than the tone of the original paper, see
                        Keynes, <hi rend="i">Engravings by Blake: The Separate Plates</hi>, Pl.
                        26.</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> According to Twyman, p. 34. Mann, p. 112.
                        states that “Enoch” is “clearly recognizable as a Vollweiler
                        print,” but does not say why.</note></p>
        <p>Blake could not have learned about Senefelder’s inventions until a good
                    many years after he had developed his own methods of relief etching on copper.
                    Even the most sophisticated manipulations of relief etching and its integration
                    with white-line etching/engraving are displayed as early as 1793 in 
<hi rend="i">America.</hi> Yet Blake must have been very interested in whatever he could
                    learn about lithography from Vollweiler or other practitioners since early
                    polyautography was so similar, in its essential relief-etched characteristics,
                    to his own techniques. The plans to publish an account of Blake’s
                    inventions (see my note 2) may have been stimulated by his learning about rival
                    techniques such as Senefelder’s etching on stone and Lizars’
                    etching in relief on metal or stone. Blake might have learned something from
                    contacts with Vollweiler that he could apply to his own copperplate methods,
                    although there is no evidence for this in Blake’s relief etchings after
                    1806-1807. Senefelder had developed a method of transferring a text or design
                    written in lithographic ink from gummed paper to a stone,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref> and Vollweiler may have known about this technique.
                    This was most useful to artists who, unlike Blake, were not professional
                    engravers and thus were not proficient at writing or designing with right and
                    left reversed. I very much doubt that Blake needed to use a transfer technique;
                    if he did, he must have invented it independently some years before his contacts
                    with Vollweiler. Although lithography’s influence on the illuminated
                    books could only have been minimal and late, “Enoch” does provide a
                    unique point of indirect contact between William Blake and Alois Senefelder, two
                    of the greatest innovators in the graphic arts. <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> See
Senefelder, <hi rend="i">Complete Course</hi>, pp. 121-22,
                        169-71, 256-64.</note></p>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p14-184" n="184" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
