<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.4.turner</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">At The British Art Center: Turner &amp; Shakespeare</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
              <name>Erik Frykman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>William Vaughan</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <pb id="p14-229" n="229"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-4-0011">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">NEWSLETTER</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">AT THE BRITISH ART CENTER: TURNER &amp; SHAKESPEARE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>The following is a press release from Yale University: <hi rend="i">Turner
                            and the Sublime</hi>, a major loan exhibition exploring the relationship
                        of J. M. W. Turner (1775-1851) to theories of the sublime, will open at the
                        Yale Center for British Art on Wednesday, 11 February 1981.</p>
          <p>The sublime as an aesthetic concept has been discussed by numerous writers,
                        and Turner’s own interest in the theory, as propounded in the
                        eighteenth century by Edmund Burke and others, has often been noted. But
                        Turner, far from being bound by any theoretical conceptions, used these as
                        the starting point for a whole series of technical and artistic innovations.
                        In pursuit of the sublime, Turner made many very large watercolors which
                        emulated the grandeur and importance of oil paintings. Several of these,
                        together with their no less impressive full-scale preparatory studies, will
                        be included in this exhibition, some being shown for the first time. The
                        most significant of Turner’s paintings in the genre of the sublime
                        will be represented by fine impressions of prints, often engraved under the
                        close supervision of Turner himself.</p>
          <p>This exhibition, the first to examine a specific aspect of Turner’s
                        art, will include 123 watercolors, prints and drawings executed between 1793
                        and 1845. Of these works, sixty constitute an unprecedented loan from the
                        resources of the Turner Bequest, deposited in the British Museum in London;
                        in addition, a sizable number of works come from the Center’s own
                        holdings, and others from private collections.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Turner and the Sublime</hi> has already received considerable
                        attention at the Art Gallery of Ontario in Toronto where it opened on 1
                        November 1980. After closing in New Haven on 19 April 1981, it will travel
                        to the British Museum in London where it will be on view from 15 May through
                        20 September 1981.</p>
          <p>The 192-page catalogue accompanying the exhibition, published by British
                        Museum Publications and available at the Center’s Sales Desk,
                        includes 32 color plates and 108 black and white reproductions. Written by
                        Andrew Wilton, a leading authority on Turner watercolors and Curator of
                        Prints and Drawings through December 1980, the catalogue discusses
                        Turner’s training and early career in the light of traditional
                        attitudes to the sublime and considers the mature Turner’s use of
                        them for his own needs.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Shakespeare and British Art</hi>, an exhibition bringing
                        together for the first time the University’s extensive holdings of
                        Shakespearean art, will open at the Yale Center for British Art on Thursday,
                        23 April and remain on view through Sunday, 5 July 1981.</p>
          <p>William Shakespeare was one of the most important literary inspirations for
                        British artists in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. Nearly 1400
                        works based upon scenes or characters in his plays were shown at the Royal
                        Academy exhibitions between 1769 and 1900. One of the most significant
                        events in the development of an English School of history painting was
                        Josiah Boydell’s <hi rend="i">Shakespeare Gallery</hi>, a group of
                        paintings, illustrating the plays of Shakespeare, which were commissioned in
                        the last quarter of the eighteenth century and engraved for subscription.
                        Illustrated editions of Shakespeare’s works proliferated, especially
                        during the nineteenth century when over three hundred were in print.</p>
          <p>This exhibition surveys the literary and visual sources of Shakespearean
                        illustration, from the first illustrated edition of 1709 to Victorian
                        interpretations of this theme. It draws on the large collection of
                        Shakespearean material in the British Art Center, including a number of
                        paintings from the Boydell <hi rend="i">Shakspeare Gallery</hi> and others
                        of important eighteeth century actors in major roles, such as Benjamin
                        Wilson’s <hi rend="i">David Garrick and George Anne Bellamy as Romeo
                            and Juliet</hi> and Pieter Van Bleeck’s <hi rend="i">Mrs. Cibber
                            as Cordelia.</hi> Nearly thirty paintings and over 120 drawings and
                        prints from the Center’s collection will be on view. Among the
                        artists represented by important drawings and watercolors are Francis
                        Hayman, George Romney, Henry Fuseli, Richard Parkes Bonington, Francis Danby
                        and Frederic Lord Leighton. The Lewis Walpole Library in Farmington,
                        Connecticut will be lending five watercolor drawings by H. W. Bunbury as
                        well as fifteen engravings. Finally, a number of prints and rare,
                        illustrated editions of Shakespeare from the collections of Beinecke Rare
                        Book and Manuscript Library and Sterling Memorial Library will be on
                        display.</p>
          <p>The exhibition has been organized by Geoffrey Ashton, Librarian of the
                        Garrick Club and former resident fellow of the British Art Center, who is a
                        specialist in theatrical and Shakespearean art. It will be accompanied by a
                        catalogue with 110 illustrations and detailed entries on all 190 objects in
                        the exhibition.</p>
          <p>In conjunction with <hi rend="i">Shakespeare and British Art</hi>, the Center
                        will offer a range of special programs. On Friday, 24 April at 4 p.m., The
                        Lord Annan, Vice-Chancellor the the University of London, will deliver a
                        lecture, sponsored by the British Studies Program, entitled “How Should
                        We Produce Shakespeare?” On Saturday, 25 April from 10:30 a.m. to 4:30
                        p.m., there will be a symposium, <hi rend="i">Shakespeare in the Eighteenth
                            and Nineteenth Centuries.</hi> Topics under discussion will include: the
                        relationship of Shakespeare’s plays to visual depictions of them, the
                        importance of Shakespearean drama as a subject for art, and performances of
                        the bard’s works during the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. The
                        program will feature the following talks:</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>10:30 a.m.-12:30 p.m.</title>
            </head>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">The Coral Reef: Some Morning Thoughts on
                                        Shakespeare</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>—Maynard Mack, Sterling Professor Emeritus of English, Yale
                                University.</p>
            </div4>
            <pb id="p14-230" n="230"/>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Confrontation and Complexity in
                                        Shakespeare’s Scenes</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>—George Hunter, Professor of English, Yale University
                                University.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Acting Shakespeare</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>—Eugene Waith, Douglas Tracy Smith Professor of English
                                Literature, Yale University.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Boydell’s Shakespeare</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>—G. E. Bentley, Professor of English, University of
                                Toronto.</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>2:30-4:30 p.m.</title>
            </head>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Shakespeare and the Artist in the Nineteenth
                                        Century</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>—Geoffrey Ashton, Librarian, Garrick Club, London,
                                England.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Turner’s “Juliet and her
                                        Nurse”</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>—Ronald Paulson, Thomas E. Donnelly Professor of English, Yale
                                University.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Shakespearean Paintings and Nineteenth-Century Art
                                        Criticism</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>—Richard D. Altick, Professor of English, The Ohio State
                                University, Columbs.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Honor and Dejection: Holman Hunt’s Problem
                                        with a Problem Play</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>—Mark Roskill, Professor of Art History, University of
                                Massachusetts, Amherst.</p>
              <p>On Sunday, 26 April at 3 p.m., Ann Carter-Cox, a soprano who has
                                given solo recitals at Carnegie Hall, Town Hall and Abraham Goodman
                                House in New York and appeared regularly at the Medieval Faires held
                                at the Cloisters each summer, will perform at the Center.
                                Accompanying herself on the lute and dulcimer, she will sing songs
                                of medieval and Renaissance England, including lyrics from
                                Shakespeare’s plays. The following Sunday (3 May), also at 3
                                p.m., students in the Yale School of Drama will present scenes from
                                Shakespeare as performed in the eighteenth and nineteenth
                                centuries.</p>
              <p>As part of the Center’s “Art in Context” series
                                Tuesdays at 12:30 p.m., Judith Colton, Associate Professor of the
                                History of Art, will present an informal lecture on the oil painting
                                by Adrien Carpentiers entitled “Roubiliac Modeling his Monument
                                to Shakespeare” on 21 April, and Patrick Noon, Acting Curator
                                of Prints and Drawings, will discuss “The Reconciliation of the
                                Montagues and the Capulets,” a watercolor by Frederic Lord
                                Leighton, on 21 April.</p>
              <p>Gallery talks by members of the Department of Academic Programs are
                                scheduled for the following Thursdays at 2 p.m.: 23 and 30 April; 7
                                and 21 May; 4, 18 and 25 June. Special tours of the exhibition may
                                be arranged by contacting Teri Edelstein at 203/436-3013.</p>
              <p>A summer film series, featuring Shakespearean films made in the
                                United States, Great Britain, and Germany displaying a variety of
                                cinematic techniques and concepts, is scheduled for the following
                                Saturdays at 2:30 p.m.: 13 June—<hi rend="i">Macbeth</hi>; 27
                                    June—<hi rend="i">A Midsummer Night’s Dream</hi>;
                                18 July—<hi rend="i">Othello</hi>; 1 August—<hi rend="i">Romeo and
Juliet</hi>; 15 August—<hi rend="i">Hamlet.</hi> All programs are open to the public without
                                charge.</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
