<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.4.frykman</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Göran Malmqvist, ed. and trans., En Ö på Månen</title>
        <author n="Frykman">Erik Frykman</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
              <name>Erik Frykman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>William Vaughan</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-4-0010">
        <pb id="p14-217" n="217"/>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Göran Malmqvist, ed. and trans. <hi rend="b">En Ö
                                på Månen.</hi> Uppsala: Brombergs bokförlag,
                            1979. Facsimile of the manuscript, transcription, Swedish translation,
                            14 reproductions. $14.50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Erik <name>Frykman</name>.</docAuthor></byline>
          <p>As author of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> and as
                        visionary artist Blake has had a fair amount of attention in Sweden, and
                        individual short poems have been translated. As visionary poet he is less
                        well known outside academic circles, and even <hi rend="i">intra muros</hi>
                        he is certainly not a familiar name to most students. In these days of
                        soaring book prices and some diffidence on the part of publishers it is
                        pleasing that a comparatively small but enterprising firm, Messrs. Bromberq
                        of Uppsala, should have ventured to bring out, beautifully produced, a
                        Swedish translation with parallel English text of <hi rend="i">An Island in
                            the Moon.</hi> In a country with the firmest of beliefs in
                        specialization, it is equally pleasing that the translator-editor is not an
                        Eng. Lit. man but a professor of sinology. Göran Malmqvist of the
                        University of Stockholm is widely known not only as a scholar but also as an
                        assiduous translator of Chinese verse and prose. As these things will
                        sometimes happen, his interest in Blake is said to have been aroused during
                        a visit to Peking.</p>
          <p>For this volume—which includes some well-chosen black-and-white
                        illustrations—Professor Malmqvist provides a lengthy introduction
                        where, with obvious zest and an entirely convincing knowledge of the period
                        concerned and of Blake scholarship, he outlines the intellectual and social
                        background of Blake’s burlesque. It is to be regretted that he did
                        not take time—or perhaps was not granted the space—to say a
                        little more about Blake as poet and artist, the more so since <hi rend="i">An Island
in the Moon</hi> provides more than one early glimpse into
                        Blake’s firmly held tenets and, of course, presents not only the
                        waywardly burlesque songs but also three of the <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Innocence.</hi> How one wishes that the volume could also have contained
                        the text and translation of, for instance, <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
                            Heaven and Hell</hi>; the Swedish reading public would then have had
                        more of an introduction to Blake’s thought and genius. However, there
                        is every reason to be grateful to Professor Malmqvist, the more so because
                        as translator of an often intriguing text he succeeds excellently, even with
                        those difficult, bafflingly allusive songs.</p>
          <p>He offers an independent, conjectural interpretation of the enigmatic word
                        “wickly” (in Chapter 5) which he translates as if it were a
                        deliberate corruption of “videlicet.” It has much to say for his
                        skill as translator that the only passage that leaves him resourceless is
                        Blake’s elaborate pre-Joycean pun, “An Easy of Huming
                        Understanding, by John Lockye, Gent.”</p>
          <p>A mock-serious appendix by the translator is one large joke at the expense of
                        the government-imposed 
<pb id="p14-218" n="218"/>
leveling-down tendencies
                        in the Swedish educational system of these latter days. However, as a Swede
                        one feels a slight consolation after having listened to a lecture at the
                        recent I.A.U.P.E. conference in Aberdeen, where Professor George S. Rousseau
                        of UCLA gave his somber view on the lack of interest taken in
                        eighteenth-century literature by American university students. Some of his
                        colleagues from both sides of the Atlantic chimed in, but all showed
                        determination to do something about it. The academic world everywhere is in
                        sore need of daring enthusiasts; Göran Malmqvist is certainly one of
                        them.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
