<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>14.4.paley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">John Trivett Nettleship and His “Blake Drawings”</title>
        <author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">14.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Thomas R. Frosch</name>
              <name>Erik Frykman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>William Vaughan</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_14">
    <body>
      <pb id="p14-185" n="185"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-14-4-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">JOHN TRIVETT NETTLESHIP AND HIS “BLAKE DRAWINGS”</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">MORTON D.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">PALEY</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>When J. T. Nettleship died in 1902, he was a successful artist who had specialized in
          wild animal subjects. According to <hi rend="i">The Magazine of Art</hi>, “He took as his
          models the animals which have not come under human domination, the larger beasts of prey,
          fierce and untameable; and he sought habitually to realise all their strenuous energy and
            ferocity.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">1</ref> From 1874
until 1901 he exhibited
          regularly at the Royal Academy as well as at the New Gallery and the Grosvenor
            Gallery.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">2</ref> He also
published two books: 
            <hi rend="i">Essays on Robert Browning’s Poetry</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n21" type="note">3</ref> and 
            <hi rend="i">George Morland and the Evolution from Him of Some Later Landscape
            Painters.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">4</ref> His
daughter Ida had married
          Augustus John. To his contemporaries Nettleship could appear at the same time to be “our
          later Landseer” and “a lord of Bohemia.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23"
type="note">5</ref> Yet in the
          early 1870s, at the beginning of his career, Nettleship had created works of a much
          different kind than those which made his reputation. “It is to be regretted that none of
          the designs conceived in this period was ever properly finished,” wrote James Sutherland
          Cotton, who had known Nettleship. “They included Biblical scenes, such as ‘Jacob wrestling
          with the Angel,’ and ‘A Sower went forth to sow,’ which have been deservedly compared with
          the work of William Blake.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24"
type="note">6</ref> Nettleship’s early work
          was indeed heavily influenced by Blake, and when he came to frequent the Rossetti circle,
          he brought his “Blake drawings” (as they came to be known in the Nettleship family) with
          him. <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Anon., “J. T. Nettleship, Animal Painter,<corr
type="emend">”</corr> 
              <hi rend="i">The Magazine of Art</hi>, 1903, p. 75.</note>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">2</hi> See Algernon Graves, <hi rend="i">Dictionary of Artists</hi> (New York:
Burt
            Franklin, 1970 [reprint of 1901]); <hi rend="i">The Magazine of Art</hi>, 1903, p. 77.
            77.</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">3</hi> London: Macmillan and Co.,
            1868.</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">4</hi> London: Seeley &amp; Co.,
            1898.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">5</hi> “Sigma” [Julian Osgood Field], 
              <hi rend="i">Personalia</hi> (Edinburgh and London: William Blackwood &amp; Sons, 1903),
            p. 215; <hi rend="i">The Art Journal</hi>, 1907, p. 251.</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi
              rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> DNB</hi>, Supplement 1901-11 (1927), s.v.</note></p>
        <p>According to William Michael Rossetti, Nettleship may have been introduced to the
          Rossettis by mutual friends—John Payne or Arthur O’Shaughnessy, both poets. “As he had not
          from the first been destined for the pictorial profession,” wrote Rossetti of Nettleship,
          “he was older than most beginners, twenty-seven. He was an intellectual young man, full of
          abstract conceptions: such a subject as ‘God Creating Evil’ had no terrors for him—or I
          should rather say, not any such terrors as dissuaded him from designing it.”<ref
            target="n25" type="note">7</ref> Nettleship studied painting at the Slade school, but
          the influence of Blake may have come to him through “The Brotherhood,” a group that
          included John Butler Yeats and Edwin Ellis.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26"
type="note">8</ref> In this
          circle Nettleship would also have met O’Shaughnessy, whose <hi rend="i">Epic of Women</hi>
          he illustrated in 1870. At any rate, by the time Nettleship met Dante Gabriel Rossetti, he
          had already acquired a Blakean pictorial vocabulary. According to Gale Pedrick, he
          produced “sketches of a Blake-like kind [which] amazed and delighted Rossetti with their
          audacity of treatment.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">9</ref>
Until recently it was
          difficult to assess the impact upon Rossetti and, later, upon W. B. Yeats of Nettleship’s
          “Blake drawings,” as they were the property of the Nettleship family. Now in the
          collection of the University of Reading, their importance as early examples of the
          influence of Blake’s art can at last be appreciated.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n28" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">7</hi><hi rend="i"> Some Reminiscences of William
              Michael Rossetti</hi> (London: Brown, Langham, 1906), II, 326.</note>	
              <note id="n26"><hi rend="s">8</hi> As suggested to me by Professor Ian Fletcher, who first
called
            the Nettleship drawings to my attention and to whom I an grateful for his valuable
            assistance and encouragement.</note>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">9</hi><hi rend="i"> Life
              with Rossetti</hi> (London: Macdonald, 1964), p. 103.</note>
	<note id="n28"><hi
              rend="s">10</hi> I wish to thank Dr. J. A. Edwards, Archivist of the University of
            Reading, for enabling me to see this material.</note></p>
        <p>Nettleship’s early drawings are varied in style as in subject matter. Some are obviously
          indebted to Blake, while others are more conventionally Victorian. Among the former are a
          series involving naked human figures and a huge serpent, reminiscent of Blake’s Los,
          Enitharmon, child Orc and Orc 
        <pb id="p14-186" n="186"/>
        <figure n="WrightPayne27.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="568">
            <head>1 “God with eyes turned inward upon his own glory.”</head>
            <figDesc>Photographic reproduction, from Thomas Wright’s <hi rend="i">Life of
                Payne.</hi> Appendix I, no. 27. [Thomas Wright, <hi rend="i">The Life of John
                Payne.</hi> London. T. Fisher Unwin. 1919. Rep. facing p. 30.]</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <figure n="WrightPayne9.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="554">
            <head>2 Pencil drawing.</head>
            <figDesc>Appendix I, no. 9.</figDesc>
        </figure> 
          serpent. This family group appears in nos. 4, 6, and 9 in the checklist appended
          to this article (see Appendix I), while some members of the group appear in nos. 5, 8, and
          16. Although the components of the designs are derived from Blake, Nettleship has not
          imitated any single design in them. In this way he is similar to 
          David Scott,<ref target="n29" type="note">11</ref> who also used a Blakean vocabulary to create
heroic
          scenes with their own distinctive feeling. Some other “Blake drawings” 
        <figure n="WrightPayne16.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="284">
            <head>3 Pencil drawing.</head>
            <figDesc>Appendix I, no. 16.</figDesc>
        </figure> 
          are closer to specific sources. The diving figure of no. 11 strongly resembles
          that of plate 14 in <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>, save that the artist has changed
          the position of the head after first drawing it in an attitude more similar to Urizen’s.
          “God with eyes turned inward upon his own glory” strongly suggests the Urizenic head of
            <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> plate 22 and elsewhere. On the whole, however, it is not the
          imitation of Blake that makes these drawings interesting but rather Nettleship’s
          assimilation of Blake’s style with his own. <note id="n29"><hi rend="s">11</hi> On Scott,
            see David Irwin, “David Scott: Illustrations of Mysticism and the Supernatural,” 
              <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 15 (1976), 461-68.</note></p>
        <p>At about the same time that he executed the “Blake Drawings,” Nettleship did five
          illustrations for Arthur W. E. O’Shaughnessy’s <hi rend="i">Epic of Women and Other
            Poems</hi>, the poet’s first book, published by the enterprising John Camden Hotten<ref
            target="n30" type="note">12</ref> in 1870. In these designs the influence of Blake,
          though apparent, is further subordinated to Nettleship’s own manner. The title page shows
          a male nude in the foreground, reclining in a garden-like setting and staring over the sea
          to the rising sun. A titanic nude male wearing a chaplet of stars leans down pointing from
          the top of the picture; a female figure on the left with a chain fastened to her waist
          raises her arms, hands clasped, upward. None of these figures is copied from Blake, but
          the effect of the whole suggests the illustrations to <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi>
          Two female figures in other designs recall Oothoon in 
<pb id="p14-187" n="187"/>
<figure n="EpicofWomenTitlePage.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="674">
            <head>4 Title page for <hi rend="i">Epic of Women</hi> by <corr type="emend">Arthur W. E.
              O’Shaughnessy.</corr></head>
            <figDesc>London: John Camden Hotten, 1870. The Huntington Library.</figDesc>
          </figure><hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi> One of these appears at the
          end of “A Neglected Harp,” chained round the waist to the harp and manacled by the right
          ankle. She is almost a reversed-position version of Oothoon in <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>
          4, hovering in a flame-like wave while chained by the left ankle. The nude at the end of
          “A Troth for Eternity” resembles Oothoon in <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> 3, but Nettleship,
          in accord with O’Shaughnessy’s poem, has replaced Blake’s eagle with a dagger. For the
          poem called “Exile,” Nettleship repeated the male figure of the title page foreground, and
          for “Bisclavet” he drew a strikingly original design showing a sea of androgynous-looking
          figures with strangely accentuated lips. <hi rend="i">Epic of Women</hi>, according to
          both Richard Garnett and Edmund Gosse,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
type="note">13</ref> was well
          received, and these pictures could have meant the beginning of a promising career as a
          book illustrator for Nettleship. Indeed, according to Thomas Wright, Nettleship produced a
          drawing for <corr type="emend">O’Shaughnessy’s</corr> next book of verse, but his new publisher objected on the
          ground of indecency, saying “The British public has to be studied.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
            type="note">14</ref> In any event, O’Shaughnessy’s <hi rend="i">Lays of France</hi>
          (London: Ellis and Green, 1872) was published without illustration. 
              <note id="n30"><hi rend="s">12</hi> On Hotten, see my article “John Camden Hotten, A. C.
Swinburne, and
            the Blake Facsimiles of 1868,” <hi rend="i">Bulletin</hi> of the New York Public
            Library, 79 (1976), 259-96.</note>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">13</hi> See Garnett, 
              <hi rend="i">DNB</hi>, XLII, 309; Gosse, <hi rend="i">Silhouettes</hi> (London: William
            Heinemann, 1925), pp. 173-79. <hi rend="i">Epic of Women</hi> went into a second edition
            in 1871, and Hotten reprinted laudatory excerpts from eight periodical reviews in the
            end papers.</note>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">14</hi><hi rend="i"> The Life of John
              Payne</hi> (London: T. Fisher Unwin, 1919), p. 44.</note></p>
        <p>Nettleship did illustrate, or partly illustrate one more book in the 1870s—<hi
rend="i">Emblems</hi> by Alice Cholmondeley, “Revised by J. J. Nettleship” [sic] and edited by
          Reginald Cholmondeley (London: Smith, <figure n="NeglectedHarp.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="659">
            <head>5 Illustration for “A Neglected Harp” in <hi rend="i">Epic of Women.</hi></head>
            <figDesc>The Huntington Library.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <figure n="TrothforEternity.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="190">
            <head>6 Illustration for “A Troth for Eternity” in <hi rend="i">Epic of
              Women.</hi></head>
            <figDesc>The Huntington Library.</figDesc>
          </figure>
<pb id="p14-188" n="188"/>
          <figure n="EllisPencil.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="419">
            <head>7 E. J. Ellis, pencil drawing.</head>
            <figDesc>Study for a design published in <hi rend="i">Seen in Three Days.</hi> Appendix
              I, no. 1.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <figure n="CholmondeleyEmblems.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="704">
            <head>8 Autotype related to Mrs. Cholmondeley’s <hi rend="i">Emblems.</hi></head>
            <figDesc>Appendix I, no. 24.</figDesc>
          </figure> Elder &amp; Co., 1875). It is hard to know what is meant by “revised”: some of
          the pictures are in the style of the “Blake drawings” while others could conceivably have
          been designed by Mrs. Cholmondeley.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33"
type="note">15</ref> The plates bear
          no signatures, though some are marked S E &amp; Co in their lower right hand corners.
          There are short inscriptions on most of them, as noted in Appendix II. Some of the 
            <hi rend="i">Emblems</hi> are imaginatively conceived, but most of them convey an impression
          of listlessness, almost of stasis. There are glimpses of the interest in animals that had
          already begun to dominate Nettleship’s art, but these subjects are treated without
          imaginative force. Nevertheless, Nettleship’s animal pictures were bringing him the
          popular recognition that had been denied the “Blake drawings.” Of these Thomas Wright
          says, “With all his endeavours success seemed unattainable.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">15</hi> I have been able to learn little of Mrs.
            Cholmondeley. She was not the Alice Cholmondeley (whose actual Christian name was Mary)
            who wrote under that name more than a generation later.</note>
	<note id="n34"><hi
              rend="s">16</hi><hi rend="i"> Life of John Payne</hi>, p. 21.</note></p>
        <p>William Butler Yeats was introduced to Nettleship by Yeats’ father some time in the
          period 1887-91. Yeats had previously been so impressed by one of the animal paintings that
          he had written a poem entitled “On Mr. Nettleship’s Picture at the Royal Hibernian
          Academy”: 
		<q> Yonder the sickle of the moon sails on,<lb/>
 But here the Lioness licks her
            soft cub<lb/>
 Tender and fearless on her funeral pyre;<lb/>
 Above, saliva dropping from
            his jaws,<lb/>
 The Lion, the world’s great solitary, bends<lb/>
 Lowly the head of his
            magnificence<lb/>
 And roars, mad with the touch of the unknown,<lb/>
 Not as he shakes
            the forest; but a cry<lb/>
 Low, long and musical. A dew-drop hung<lb/>
 Bright on a grass
            blade’s under side, might hear,<lb/>
 Nor tremble to its fall. The fire sweeps round<lb/>
            Re-shining in his eyes. So ever moves<lb/>
 The flaming circle of the outer Law,<lb/>
 Nor
            heeds the old, dim protest and the cry<lb/>
 The orb of the most inner living heart<lb/>
            Gives forth. He, the Eternal, works His will.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35"
type="note">17</ref>	
              <note id="n35"><hi rend="s">17</hi> First published in the <hi rend="i">Dublin University
                Review</hi> for April 1886, p. 3. MS version cited here from <hi rend="i">The
                Variorum Edition of the Poems</hi> of W. B. Yeats, ed. P. Allt and R. K. Alspach
              (New York: Macmillan, 1957), pp. 688-89. Reprinted by permission.</note></q>
Yeats did
          not reprint this poem, and it is easy to see why: it is too conventionally rhetorical, the
          analogy of the lion’s eye to the circle of the outer law and to the orb of the living
          heart is too obviously contrived, and the last line seems produced by the will to end with
          an emphatic flourish. Yeats was to change his mind, too, about the quality of Nettleship’s
          animal paintings—by the time he met the artist, Yeats considered him “once inventor of
          imaginative designs and now a painter of melodramatic lions.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">18</ref> Yeats tells of how he was impressed by the courage and
asceticism of
          Nettleship, by then a reformed alcoholic who incessantly drank cocoa. 
              <note id="n36"><hi rend="s">18</hi> “Four Years/1887-1891,” <hi rend="i">The Dial</hi>, 71
(1921),
            81.</note></p>
		<q> He thought [Yeats writes] that any weakness, even a weakness of the body, had the
          character of sin and while at breakfast with his brother, with whom he shared a room on
          the third floor of a corner house, he said that his nerves were out of order. Presently,
          he left the table and got out through the window and on to the stone ledge that ran along
          the wall under the window-sills. He sidled along the ledge, and turning the corner with
          it, got in at a different window and returned to the table. ‘My nerves,’ he said, ‘are
          better than I thought.’<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">19</ref>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">19</hi> “Four Years,” p. 83.</note></q>
        <pb id="p14-189" n="189"/>
        <p>Nettleship, responding to the young poet’s admiration, showed Yeats some of his early
          drawings. Yeats responded enthusiastically: 
		<q> . . . They, though often badly drawn,
            fulfilled my hopes. Something of Blake they certainly did show, but had in place of
            Blake’s joyous intellectual energy a Saturnian passion and melancholy. God Creating
            Evil, the death-like head with a woman and a tiger coming from the forehead which
            Rossetti—or was it Browning?—had described as ‘the most sublime design of ancient or
            modern art’ had been lost, but there was another version of the same thought, and other
            designs never published or exhibited. They rise before me even now in meditation,
            especially a blind Titian-like ghost floating with groping hands above the
              tree-tops.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">20</ref>
	<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">20</hi>
              “Four Years,” pp. 81-82.</note></q>
These pictures stimulated Yeats to write his first
          piece of art criticism. It is not clear what became of this essay. In <hi rend="i">The
            Dial</hi> Yeats says it was rejected by an editor “lifting what I considered an
          obsequious caw in the Huxley, Tyndall, Carolus Duran rookery.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39"
            type="note">21</ref> Yet in his letters to Kathleen Tynan Yeats gives a different
          account. On 28 February 1890 he writes of his work at hand: “Then comes an article on
          Nettleship’s designs for the <hi rend="i">Art Review</hi>—great designs never published
          before—and later an article on Blake and his anti-materialistic Art, for somewhere”; but
          on 1 July 1890 he reports “I am working on Blake and such things. The <hi rend="i">Art
            Review</hi> has come to an end and so unhappily my article on Nettleship’s designs is
            useless.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">22</ref> Like the
original “God Creating Evil,”
          Yeats’s essay on Nettleship appears to have been lost. <note id="n39"><hi rend="s">21</hi>
            “Four Years,” p. 82.</note>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">22</hi><hi rend="i"> The Letters
              of W. B. Yeats</hi>, ed. Allan Wade (London: Rupert Hart-Davis, 1954), pp. 150,
            154.</note></p>
        <p>Yeats made on effort to re-enlist Nettleship in the service of visionary art. He
          commissioned the artist to draw the frontispiece for the first edition of <hi rend="i">The
            Countess Kathleen and Various Legends and Lyrics</hi>, published by T. Fisher Unwin in
          1892. The resulting picture of Cuchillin fighting the waves was so lacking in conviction
          that Yeats was not encouraged to make a second attempt “to restore one old friend of my
          father’s to the practice of his youth.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41"
type="note">23</ref> England’s
          second Landseer returned to his animal painting. “Nettleship,” concluded Yeats, “had found
          his simplifying image, but in his painting had turned away from it. . . . ”<ref
            target="n42" type="note">24</ref>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">23</hi> “Four Years,” p.
            80.</note>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">24</hi> “Four Years,” p. 83.</note></p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">APPENDIX I: Nettleship’s “Blake Drawings” at the University of
                Reading</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>All are pencil drawings unless otherwise indicated.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/1. 26 × 19 cm. This drawing is actually by E. J. Ellis, apparently a study for
            a design published in Ellis’ <hi rend="i">Seen in Three Days</hi> (London: sold by
            Bernard Quaritch, 1893). In the published version the male figure has been changed to an
            old man with great wings and a long white beard. Both versions are obviously indebted to
            Blake’s designs for Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi></p>
          <figure n="PencilDrawing7.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="356">
            <head>9 Pencil drawing.</head>
            <figDesc>Appendix I, no. 7.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <figure n="PencilDrawing11.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="700">
            <head>10 Pencil drawing.</head>
            <figDesc>Appendix I, no. 11.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p14-190" n="190"/>
          <figure n="Autotype18.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="352">
            <head>11 Autotype (untitled).</head>
            <figDesc>Appendix I, no. 18.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <figure n="MadnessSepia.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="357">
            <head>12 “Madness” Sepia colored autotype, dated 1870.</head>
            <figDesc>Appendix I, no. 24.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p14-191" n="191"/>
          <figure n="CholmondeleyEmblemsAutotype.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="420">
            <head>13 Autotype for <hi rend="i">Emblems</hi> by Alice Cholmondeley.</head>
            <figDesc>(London: Smith, Elder &amp; Co., 1875).</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <figure n="CholmondeleyEmblemsAutotype2.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="430">
            <head>14 Autotype for <hi rend="i">Emblems</hi> by Alice Cholmondeley.</head>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p14-192" n="192"/>
          <figure n="CholmondeleyEmblemsAutotype3.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="791">
            <head>15 Autotype for <hi rend="i">Emblems</hi> by Alice Cholmondeley.</head>
          </figure>
          <p>MS 7/27/2r and 2v. Pencil, India ink, water color. 13 × 17 cm. Both are drawings of a
            large feline, possibly a lioness.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/3r. Pencil, pen, and ink. 25 × 18 cm. An 
            <figure n="CholmondeleyEmblemsAutotype4.14.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="844">
              <head>16 Autotype for <hi rend="i">Emblems</hi> by Alice Cholmondeley.</head>
            </figure> angel with huge wings dancing with a young woman.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/3v. Two faintly sketched figures, one male, one female.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/4. 25 × 36 cm. A male figure is about to kill a supine figure with a sword. At
            the lower right is the head (and knees?) of a woman whose hair rises to twine about the
            swordsman’s wrists and thighs.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/6. 36 × 26 cm. The “family group.” The man, awkwardly holding a sword in his
            right hand, severs the head of a giant serpent. The woman and the boy support the man on
            either side.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/7. 26 × 36 cm. A powerful male figure bound down as it were by the stems of
            vegetation.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/8r. 26 × 36 cm. A man drawing a sword and a boy with a knife on a
            staircase.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/8v. A man and a boy, sketchily drawn.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/9. 26 × 36 cm. The “family group.” Man 
<pb id="p14-193" n="193"/>
struggles
            with gigantic serpent, woman and (faintly sketched) boy look on. Crescent moon at
            right.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/10r. 26 × 36 cm. An old man sits hunched in a throne-like chair. A young woman
            sits at his left. Behind him is a portrait of a mother and child.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/10v. A lioness and parts of another.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/11. Pencil and ink. 35 × 26 cm. A powerful male nude descending. Cf. 
              <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>, plate 14.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/12. Pencil and ink with water color wash. 16 × 9 cm. An upside-down figure
            falls from the starry sky.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/13. Sepia ink drawing. 11 × 14 cm. A kneeling nude male clasps his head with
            his right hand and a helmet on the ground with his left.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/14. Etching. 14 × 10 cm. A huge man wearing a cape embraces a skeletal woman
            while holding a goblet high in his right hand. A leopard stands in the foreground.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/15r. Pencil and ink. A sailor is about to throw a bound man overboard. A woman
            wearing a crucifix, possibly a nun, looks on.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/15v. A pensive-looking girl in a long dress.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/16. 35 × 25 cm. Two male figures, supine woman, serpent. It isn’t clear whether
            the standing male is about to stab the fallen one or to rescue him from the serpent.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/17r. 20 × 26 cm. Inscribed “Polyphemus watching Galatea.” The bearded,
            mountain-like Polyphemus stretches his arms imploringly.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/17v. Sketch of a nude woman with her left arm about a child.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/18. Autotype. Sheet 25 × 32 cm; design area 17 × 24 cm. A naked man is towed
            through the air by a larval female. This design does not appear in Mrs. Cholmondeley’s
              <hi rend="i">Emblems.</hi></p>
          <p>MS 7/27/19. Sepia colored autotype reproduction. 23 × 28 cm. Inscribed at the top
            “Madness” and signed in the lower left hand corner: “Made in the Summer of 1870 / J. T.
            Nettleship.” Ms. note at the bottom reads as follows: 
			<q> The prostrate figure
              symbolizes a man who near the summit of his career has been struck down by madness;
              hands as of Earth-spirits come out of the ground, lift the circlet from his head, and
              begin to draw him in, as worms suck in a straw. The male figures behind him (right of
              the design) symbolize his past acts; they stab themselves. The female figures
              symbolize the emotions; they wait. The figures behind him, up to the hill top (left of
              the design) symbolize his future achievements; they throw away crown and stars which
              were to be his rewards. Every face in the drawing is bowed and hidden, for shame’s
              sake. <hi rend="u">x</hi> The design embodies the <hi rend="i">prospective</hi> fear,
              in any sane mind, that madness must mean an annihilation of all individuality, of all
              the results of past effort or love, and of all future hopes of achievement. But the
              earth-spirits, while they take the man to themselves, out of sight,, perhaps renew
              him, but not as the same unity.<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="s">x</hi> The figure next in front
              of the prostrate man gives back to the male figure just behind him some pledge that
              had been given to the future, some unfinished work—useless now. The embodiment of past
              acts and emotions makes them as it were friends and lovers of the man, identified with
              his aims.<lb/>
<lb/>
 J. T. Nettleship<lb/>
 22 April 1890<hi rend="s">x</hi></q></p>
          <p>MS 7/27/20. Autotype. Sheet 25 × 31 cm. ; design area 16 ½ × 24 cm. A sower, following
            a butterfly, scatters his seed, which is devoured by geese following him. This is
            identical, save in size, with the much smaller version in <hi rend="i">Emblems.</hi> The
            same is true of nos. 21 and 22 below. All three lack inscriptions here. In 
              <hi rend="i">Emblems</hi> this one bears the legend “SOWING WILD OATS.”</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/21. Autotype. Sheet 25 ½ × 33 cm. ; design area 16 ½ × 24 cm. A naked child
            addresses a serpent with an ear trumpet. The corresponding plate in 
              <hi rend="i">Emblems</hi> bears the printed legend “THE DEAF ADDER—WITH AN EAR
TRUMPET.”</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/22. Autotype. Sheet size 25 ½ × 31 ½ cm. ; design area 17 × 24 cm. A naked man
            with a sickle in a rural landscape. Legend in <hi rend="i">Emblems</hi> only: “REAPING
            WILD OATS.”</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/23r. Autotype. Sheet 26 × 32 cm. ; design area 16 ½ × 24 cm. A huge human
            skeleton and a naked woman in the recess of an overhanging rock. The skeleton points
            left, and the woman seems about to crawl out in that direction. Not in 
              <hi rend="i">Emblems.</hi></p>
          <p>MS 7/27/23v. Pencil drawing of an almost supine nude woman. Possibly a study for the
            lower figure in no. 25 below.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/24. Autotype. 17 × 20 cm. From <hi rend="i">Emblems</hi>, with printed text:
            “FIRST PLEASURE, NEXT AMBITION’S CROWN / LAST DEATH ITSELF IS TRAMPLED DOWN.” See illus.
            7.</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/25 (2 copies). Autotype. Sheet size 31 × 25 cm. ; design area 23 ½ × 16 ½ cm. A
            male figure descends through the sky to a bound woman. The corresponding, smaller plate
            in <hi rend="i">Emblems</hi> bears the legend: “A FALLING STAR / THE LOST PLEIAD.”</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/26. Autotype. Sheet size 25 ½ × 32 cm. ; design area 17 × 24 cm. A naked giant
            extends a sword over a gorge. A long procession of small figures goes from the left to
            the center. The first ones walk over the sword as over a bridge, while others swim in
            the water and are pursued by demonic-looking creatures. The corresponding, smaller plate
            in <hi rend="i">Emblems</hi> is legended: “THE BRIDGE IS STEEP, THE 
              <pb id="p14-194" n="194"/>
RIVER DEEP / FEW CAN THEIR FOOTING KEEP.”</p>
          <p>MS 7/27/27. Photographic reproduction of “God with Eyes Turned Inward Upon His Own
            Glory.” From Thomas Wright’s <hi rend="i">Life of Payne.</hi> See illus. 1.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title><hi rend="b">APPENDIX II: </hi><hi rend="i">Emblems</hi> by Alice
              Cholmondeley</title>
          </head>
          <list type="ordered">
            <item>
              <p><label>1.</label> THE BRIDGE IS STEEP, THE RIVER DEEP / FEW CAN THEIR FOOTING KEEP.
                See Appendix I, no. 26.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p><label>2.</label> FIRST HEAVEN, NEXT AMBITION’S CROWN / LAST DEATH ITSELF IS
                TRAMPLED DOWN. See Appendix I, no. 24.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p><label>3.</label> THE LAMP OF TRUTH. The lamp is phallic.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p><label>4.</label> A FALLING STAR / THE LOST PLEIAD. See Appendix I, no. 25.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p><label>5.</label> LA CRUCHE CASSÉE. THE PITCHER THAT WENT TO THE WELL TOO OFTEN. A
                Rossetti-ish lady and Landseer-ish lions.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p><label>6.</label> THE LOST WAY, ALL ASTRAY / THE SPHINX AS GUIDE. A male nude
                lacking the energy of his Blakean counterparts. A doggie-like, leashed sphinx,
                rather ludicrous than enigmatic.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p><label>7.</label> SOWING WILD OATS. See Appendix I, no. 20.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p><label>8.</label> REAPING WILD OATS. The grotesque figure with his sickle may owe
                something to Despair with his flaying knife in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The House of
                  Death.</hi> See Appendix I, no. 22.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p><label>9.</label> THE DEAF ADDER—WITH AN EAR TRUMPET. See Appendix I, no. 21.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p><label>10.</label> No text. Two billing swans and their reflections.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p><label>11.</label> L’ANIMA IN MASCHERA. / MISREPRESENTED. The death-like figure
                with the scythe is conventional, but the lightly draped lady on her swan-throne
                seems distinctive of Nettleship, as does the artist who paints her.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p><label>12.</label> A CRESCENT LIFE IN ITS ECLIPSE / IN THE EARTH’S SHADOW SLIPS.
                Serpent and crescent moon—cf. Blake’s “Narcissa” engraving for Young’s 
                  <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi></p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p><label>13.</label> HIGHER, NOT NIGHER, WE ASPIRE. A literalized version of “I want
                I want” in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Gates of Paradise.</hi></p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p><label>14.</label> PLUCKING DAISIES (FROM GOETHE’S “FAUST”) / “ER LIEBT MICH—ER
                LIEBT MICH NICHT.” A nude woman holds a daisy on a country road.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p><label>15.</label> No text. A diminutive, naked child leaps from a frying pan (held
                by a girl) into the fire.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p><label>16.</label> THROUGH ANGEL’S ARMS, BENEATH / THEIR WINGS, YOU PASS THE GATES
                OF DEATH. The joining of the angels’ wings to form a Gothic arch which is a
                passageway to death makes a link to Blake probable.</p>
            </item>
            <item>
              <p><label>17.</label> A FAREWELL. A lady’s hand waves a handkerchief to a departing
                horseman.</p>
            </item>
          </list>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
