<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>15.1.page</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Donald H. Reiman, ed., The Garland Facsimiles of the Poetry of James Montgomery</title>
                <author n="Page">Judy Page</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1981</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1981</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">15.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Review Editor</resp>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Production Office</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Susan Corban</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>Pam Blair</name>
                            <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
                            <name>Wendy Jones</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <name>James Warwick</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>Martin K. Nurmi</name>
                            <name>Judith Page</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>Henry Summerfield</name>
                            <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1981"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_15">
        <body>
            <pb id="p15-28" n="28"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-15-1-0008">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
				  <head>
					<title type="main"><hi rend="b">ROMANTIC CONTEXT: POETRY</hi><lb/>
					Significant Minor Poetry 1789-1830<lb/>
					Printed in photo-facsimile in 128 volumes<lb/>
            		<hi rend="b">Selected and Arranged by Donald H. Reiman</hi></title>
				  </head>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title type="main" rend="main"><hi rend="b">The Garland Facsimiles of the Poetry of
                                    James Montgomery</hi></title>
                        </head>
                        <head>
                            <title type="main">James Montgomery. Prison
                                Amusements and the Wanderer of Switzerland, Greenland and Abdallah,
                                Verses to the Memory of the Late Richard Reynolds/The World Before
                                the Flood, The Chimney Sweeper’s Friend.</title>
                        </head>
                        <byline>
                            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
                            <docAuthor>
                                <hi rend="b">Judy</hi>
                                <name>
                                    <hi rend="b">Page</hi>
                                </name>
                            </docAuthor>
                        </byline>
                        <p>If you were asked to name the significant minor writers of the Romantic
                            period, you would probably think of Southey or Crabbe or even John Clare
                            before James Montgomery. And yet, in his day Montgomery was known in
                            England and America as a poet, essayist, and humanitarian. His popular
                                <hi rend="i">Wanderer of Switzerland</hi>, a tribute to the fight
                            against French tyranny, inspired Byron to claim that it was “worth a
                            thousand ‘Lyrical Ballads’ and at least fifty ‘degraded epics.’”<ref
                                target="n85" type="note">1</ref> Although Byron’s enthusiasm was
                            extravagant, the historical and social range of Montgomery’s work and
                            his relationship to the major English Romantics make him interesting to
                            modern critics. <note id="n85"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See Byron’s notes to
                                    <hi rend="i">English Bards and Scotch Reviewers</hi> in 
                                    <hi rend="i">Byron: Poetical Works</hi>, ed. Frederick Page, rev.
                                ed. John Jump (New York: Oxford Univ. Press, 1970), p.
                            866.</note></p>
                        <p>The Garland Publishing Company’s five-volume facsimile edition allows us
                            to view Montgomery’s works in their original form, with the poet’s
                            prefaces and dedications, as well as with illustrations by contemporary
                                engravers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86"
type="note">2</ref> While British and
                            American collections of Montgomery are available in most university
                            libraries, the originals are rare. Furthermore, with facsimiles, we can
                            appreciate the poems as books that, like the <hi rend="i">Songs of
                                Innocence and of Experience</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Lyrical
                                Ballads</hi>, were designed to have a certain impact on an audience.
                                <note id="n86"><hi rend="s">2</hi> The volumes are part of a Garland
                                Series, Significant Minor Poetry, 1789-1831, ed. Donald H. Reiman.
                                All quotations from Montgomery’s poetry refer to this edition and
                                will be cited by line or page.</note></p>
                        <p>The Garland reproductions do not necessarily represent the poems that
                            Montgomery thought to be his best and collected in his 
                                <hi rend="i">Poetical Works of James Montgomery</hi> (1836). Nor do the
volumes
                            include the works for which Montgomery is best remembered today, the
                            Christian hymns and imitations of psalms.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n87" type="note">3</ref> They emphasize instead Montgomery’s relationship to the
                            themes and commitments of the English Romantics: <hi rend="i">Prison
                                Amusements</hi> are written when Montgomery is imprisoned for libel
                            during the repressive 1790s; <hi rend="i">The Wanderer of
                                Switzerland</hi> reflects disillusionment with the course of the
                            French Revolution; <hi rend="i">The West Indies</hi> celebrates the
                            abolition of the slave trade in England in 1807; and <hi rend="i">The
                                World Before the Flood</hi> is Montgomery’s self-consciously
                            Miltonic poem. <note id="n87"><hi rend="s">3</hi> The 
                                    <hi rend="i">Greenland</hi> volume does contain some religious poems, but
                                neither Montgomery’s <hi rend="i">Christian Psalmist</hi> nor his
                                    <hi rend="i">Songs of Zion</hi> is reprinted.</note></p>
                        <p>Donald H. Reiman’s editorial choices generally make sense from this
                            perspective, although I wonder why the <hi rend="i">Verses to the Memory
                                of the Late Richard Reynolds</hi> (1816) were reproduced with 
                                <hi rend="i">The World Before the Flood</hi> (1813), since the poems
                            offer nothing but sincere praise for a pious Quaker from Bristol.
                            Perhaps instead of these <hi rend="i">Verses</hi>, the series could have
                            included <hi rend="i">Pelican Island</hi> (1827), Montgomery’s last long
                            poem and his only venture in blank verse. Also, the facsimiles,
                            necessarily without modern editorial comments, would be more useful with
                            new, separate introductions covering the material in each volume,
                            instead of Reiman’s general essay.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n88" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n88"><hi rend="s">4</hi> I depend on John Holland
                                and James Everett’s seven-volume <hi rend="i">Memoirs of the Life
                                    and Writings of James Montgomery</hi> (London: Longman, Brown,
                                Green, and Longmans, 1854) for Montgomery’s letters, speeches, and
                                editorials, as well as for anecdotes, comments, and letters by
                                others concerning Montgomery. I refer to this work by volume as 
                                    <hi rend="i">Memoirs.</hi></note></p>
                        <p>Montgomery was born in Scotland in 1771, the son of Moravian
                            missionaries. When he was six years old, his parents left for the West
                            Indies after placing him in the Moravian School at Fulneck near 
                                <pb id="p15-29" n="29"/>
                            <figure n="JamesMontgomery.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="568">
                            	<figTranscr>Engraved by H. Adlard from a Painting by John Jackson, RA.<lb/>
                            	<lb/>
                            	James Montgomery.<lb/>
                            	AGED 55.<lb/>
                            	<lb/>
                            	LONDON: LONGMAN BROWN GREEN &amp; LONGMAN’S</figTranscr>
                                <head>Portrait of Montgomery from Vol IV of Holland &amp; Everett’s
                                        <hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi> from The Boston Public
                                    Library.</head>
                            </figure> Leeds. He excelled for a while, but became more dedicated to
                            poetry than to the required curriculum. After leaving Fulneck, trying
                            several jobs, and unsuccessfully peddling his poems in London,
                            Montgomery was hired as a clerk on the <hi rend="i">Sheffield
                                Register</hi> by the editor Joseph Gales. When Gales fled to America
                            in 1794 under the threat of political imprisonment, Montgomery took over
                            the paper, now the <hi rend="i">Sheffield Iris</hi>, and remained editor
                            until 1825. During these years and until his death in 1854, Montgomery
                            published several volumes of poetry, reviewed other poetry in the 
                                <hi rend="i">Eclectic Review</hi>, lectured on <hi rend="i">belles
                                lettres</hi> and literary history in London, and participated in the
                            workaday world of Sheffield.</p>
                        <p>Such is the bare outline of Montgomery’s life. But Montgomery, like
                            Wordsworth, would no doubt have directed us to look for his life in his
                            works. The Garland facsimiles invite us to view the works
                            chronologically from <hi rend="i">Prison Amusements</hi> in the 1790s
                            through <hi rend="i">The Chimney Sweeper’s Friend and Climbing Boy’s
                                Album</hi>, published in 1824 a year before his retirement from the
                                <hi rend="i">Iris.</hi></p>
                        <p>The first volume includes both <hi rend="i">Prison Amusements</hi> and
                                <hi rend="i">The Wanderer of Switzerland</hi>, the former published
                            in 1797 in London under the pseudonym Paul Positive as 
                                <hi rend="i">Prison Amusements, and Other Trifles: Principally written during
                                Nine Months of Confinement in the Castle of York.</hi> Montgomery
                            found himself in York Castle twice as a result of his position as editor
                            at a time when charges of libel and sedition were regularly leveled. But
                            Montgomery was not a Radical; the motto of the <hi rend="i">Iris</hi>
                            read “Ours are the plans of fair, delightful Peace, / Unwarped by party
                            rage, to live like brothers” (<hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi>, I, 175).
                            Montgomery warned that the staff of the <hi rend="i">Iris</hi> “Have not
                            scrupled to declare themselves <hi rend="i">friends</hi> to the cause of
                                <hi rend="i">Peace</hi> and <hi rend="i">Reform</hi>, however such a
                            declaration may be likely to expose them in the present times of 
                                <hi rend="i">alarm</hi> to obnoxious epithets and unjust and ungenerous
                            reproaches. . . . they scorn the imputations which would represent every
                            reformer as a Jacobin, and every advocate for peace as an enemy to his
                            King and country” (<hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi>, I, 177).</p>
                        <p>Although Montgomery commented bravely on politics in the 
                                <hi rend="i">Iris</hi>, his <hi rend="i">Prison Amusements</hi> deal neither
                            with the political climate nor with the events leading up to his
                            imprisonment. They are simply about passing the time in prison. In the
                            lyrics and verse epistles in the volume, Montgomery uses conventional
                            imagery and allegorical plot structures featuring free-spirited robins
                            and captive nightingales. Because his treatment of his situation is
                            superficial and his allegorical pose suggests a distance incompatible
                            with often inflated language, the poems remain trifles. Their occasion
                            may be curious and revealing, but the texts are limp.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="i">The Wanderer of Switzerland and other Poems</hi>, published
                            in London and printed by Montgomery in 1806, has more life. Montgomery
                            wrote <hi rend="i">The Wanderer</hi> in a ballad meter and structured it
                            as a dialogue between a Swiss patriot forced to flee his homeland after
                            the French invasion and a hospitable Shepherd living “beyond the
                            frontiers.” The theme of natural liberty against political tyranny and
                            what Daniel Parken of the <hi rend="i">Eclectic Review</hi> termed
                            Montgomery’s “warmth of sentiment” (<hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi>, II, 84)
                            attracted British readers. But even the sympathetic Parken noted that
                            the metrical style and debate structure were monotonous in a long,
                            six-part poem, and that Montgomery’s expression was not “brilliant” 
                                (<hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi>, II, 84). In the <hi rend="i">Edinburgh
                                Review</hi>, Francis Jeffrey was typically less charitable, charging
                            that “Mr. Montgomery has the merit of smooth versification, blameless
                            morality, and a sort of sickly affectation of delicacy and fine
                            feelings, which is apt to impose on the amiable part of the young and
                            the illiterate” (<hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi>, II, 133).</p>
                        <p>Perhaps Montgomery himself best explains both the popularity of 
                                <hi rend="i">The Wanderer</hi> and its failings in a comment written
                            years later: “the original plan of a dramatic narrative for a poem of
                            any length beyond a ballad was radically wrong, and nothing perhaps but
                            a little novelty (now gone by) and the peculiar interest of the
                            subject—at once romantic and familiar to our earliest feelings and
                            pre-possessions in favour of liberty, simplicity, the pastoral life, and
                            the innocence of olden times—could have secured to such a piece any
                            measure of popularity” (<hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi>, III, 221). The form
                            of <hi rend="i">The Wanderer</hi> does seem wrong because the regularity
                            of ballad rhythms is not complemented by a  <corr type="emend">sparse,</corr> fast-paced narrative
                            of events—the style of the traditional folk ballad debates, of many of
                            the <hi rend="i">Lyrical Ballads</hi>, and of Montgomery’s own “Vigil of
                            St. Mark.” <pb id="p15-30" n="30"/>
Furthermore, despite the debate
                            structure, the poem lacks dramatic development.</p>
                        <p>In “The Vigil of St. Mark” (published with <hi rend="i">The
                            Wanderer</hi>, pp. 137-46) Montgomery fuses ballad rhythms with
                            structural compression. This poem is based on a legend, which Keats used
                            in his fragmentary “Eve of St. Mark,” that on this eve the ghosts of all
                            the people who will die in the coming year walk in a gloomy procession.
                            In Montgomery’s poem, a nobleman named Edmund sees his love Ella in such
                            a procession while he is away from home; he arrives home to discover
                            Ella’s funeral procession, a scene described in eerie flashes of action
                            and a quick rhythm: 
<q> ‘Twas evening: all the air was balm,<lb/>
 The
                                heavens serenely clear;<lb/>
 When the soft magic of a psalm<lb/>
                                Came pensive o’er his ear.<lb/>
<lb/>
 Then sunk his heart; a strange
                                surmise<lb/>
 Made all his blood run cold:<lb/>
 He flew,—a funeral
                                met his eyes;<lb/>
 He paused,—a death-bell roll’d. </q>
The poem
                            then concludes with a vision of Edmund walking with Ella’s ghost on each
                            eve of St. Mark. Montgomery compresses the narrative but suggests action
                            by showing the result of events, their emotional impact.</p>
                        <p>There are other good poems in the volume, such as “The Common Lot,” but
                            many of the pieces share the same weakness: Montgomery presents a
                            situation as allegorical or metaphorical and then explains it, making it
                            so fixed and brittle that it loses whatever imaginative freedom it had.
                            In “The Snow-Drop” (pp. 154-60), for example, the narrator discovers a
                            snowdrop on a walk and welcomes it as a harbinger of spring. But then
                            the power of the metaphor is explained away: 
<q> There is a Winter in my
                                soul,<lb/>
 The Winter of despair;<lb/>
 O when shall Spring its rage
                                controul?<lb/>
 When shall the SNOW-DROP blossom there? </q></p>
                        <p>Despite its poetic weaknesses, <hi rend="i">The Wanderer of Switzerland
                                and other Poems</hi> established Montgomery as more than the editor
                            of the <hi rend="i">Iris.</hi> In response to this popularity, Robert
                            Bowyer of Pall Mall asked Montgomery to write a poem celebrating the
                            parliamentary bill outlawing the slave trade in England. Bowyer wanted
                            to publish a volume of several poems accompanied by engravings which
                            would illustrate selected passages. Long devoted to abolition and
                            remembering his parents who died helping slaves in the West Indies,
                            Montgomery wrote <hi rend="i">The West Indies</hi>, a poem which traces
                            the history of the slave trade from the days of Columbus to the present.
                            Besides Montgomery’s poems and engravings by Raimbach, Scriven, and
                            Worthington from illustrations by Smirke, the volume includes shorter
                            poems by James Grahame and Elizabeth Benger, as well as prose sketches
                            of the activities of Granville Sharpe, Thomas Clarkson, and William
                            Wilberforce. Bowyer’s idea was to produce a magnificent volume founded
                            on the principle of making the sister arts “allies” in the cause of
                            freedom. But the distance between 
                                <figure n="PoemsAbolition.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="750" height="430"/>
                            <pb id="p15-31" n="31"/>
conception and execution was great, and the
                            relationship of poetry to illustration has nothing of the imaginative
                            tension of Blake’s illustrated poems. When the book was finally
                            published in 1809 after many printing delays and problems with the
                            engravers, it did not sell quickly, although Montgomery’s later, less
                            expensive edition of <hi rend="i">The West Indies</hi> had a wider
                            circulation.</p>
                        <p>The narrative of <hi rend="i">The West Indies</hi> wanders the globe as
                            Montgomery progresses through the history of the slave trade, showing
                            the degeneration that profiteering in human lives brought on master and
                            slave alike, the one a “tether’d tyrant of one narrow span; The bloated
                            vampire of a living man” (Part III, 11. 235-36) and the other “dead in
                            spirit” and “toil degraded” (Part IV, 1. 59). The poem ends cheerfully
                            with a vision of the entire world renovated from slavery to freedom as a
                            result of British leadership and the establishment of the “church of
                            God” (1. 266) in the wilderness. Choosing to ignore the ambiguities
                            surrounding the slavery debates, Montgomery confidently sees the freedom
                            of all men and women leading to the millenium: 
<q> —All hail!—the age of
                                crime and suffering ends;<lb/>
 The reign of righteousness from
                                heaven descends;<lb/>
 Vengeance for ever sheathes the afflicting
                                sword;<lb/>
 Death is destroy’d, and Paradise restor’d;<lb/>
 Man,
                                rising from the ruins of his fall,<lb/>
 Is one with GOD, and GOD is
                                All in All.<lb/>
 (11. 279-84) </q></p>
                        <p>Although sincere and passionate, <hi rend="i">The West Indies</hi> often
                            lapses into long sermons on the plight of slaves. Montgomery is too
                            eager for the poem to succeed as social history and rhetoric: he even
                            provides his own footnotes on such works as Clarkson’s 
                                <hi rend="i">History of the Abolition</hi>, Captain Stedman’s 
                                <hi rend="i">Narrative of a Five Years’ Expedition</hi> (which Blake
                            illustrated), and Mungo Parke’s <hi rend="i">Travels.</hi> Furthermore,
                            the poem suffers from typical formal ailments; Montgomery’s heroic
                            couplets are tiring and his explanations of conventional imagery
                            annoying: “Bondage is winter, darkness, death, despair / Freedom the
                            sun, the sea, the mountains, and the air” (Part I, 155-56).</p>
                        <p>In <hi rend="i">The West Indies</hi>, which Romantically begins with the
                            origins of history and ends with the “New Creation,” Montgomery planned
                            a poem on a grand scale. Like his greater contemporaries, he also wanted
                            to write an epic poem; he judged his lesser pieces the way Keats more
                            wrongly judged his shorter works: as trifles. Even as a schoolboy
                            Montgomery tried to write epics—one based on Genesis and Milton and the
                            other on the achievements of Alfred the Great. With the example of
                            Milton always before him, Montgomery longed to write of things yet
                            unattempted in prose or rhyme, even though he sensed early in his career
                            that he might never succeed.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n89"
type="note">5</ref>	
                                <note id="n89"><hi rend="s">5</hi> During his second imprisonment in York
                                Castle, Montgomery wrote to his friend Joseph Aston of Manchester:
                                “I determined to rival—nay outshine—every bard of ancient or modern
                                times! I have shed many a tear in reading some of the sublimest
                                passages in our own poets, to think that I could not equal them. I
                                planned and began at least a dozen epic poems . . . ” 
                                    (<hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi>, I, 258-59).</note></p>
                        <p><hi rend="i">The World Before the Flood</hi>, the major poem in the next
                            Garland volume, represents Montgomery’s attempt on a Biblical theme.
                            Inspired by the eleventh book of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>,
                            Montgomery set out to write an account of the struggle between the
                            Patriarchs of God and the Giants of the Earth descended from Cain.
                            Montgomery borrows liberally from <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>,
                            often, it seems, relying on the 
                                <figure n="ChimneySweepersFriend.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="750" height="431"/>
                            <pb id="p15-32" n="32"/>
associations that readers would have with
                            Milton’s imagery and scenes. For instance, when Montgomery wants to
                            underscore the moral and theological confusion of the assembly of
                            Giants, he reminds us of the discord of Pandemonium: 
<q> A shout of
                                horrible applause, that rent<lb/>
 The echoing hills and answering
                                firmament,<lb/>
 Burst from the Giants,—where in barbarous
                                state,<lb/>
 Flush’d with new wine, around their king they sate;<lb/>
                                A Chieftan each, who, on his brazen car,<lb/>
 Had led a host of
                                meaner men to war.<lb/>
 (Canto 8, p. 146) </q>
Montgomery wants to
                            give the Giants reality by using the Miltonic context, just as Milton
                            brings the Fallen Angels to life by identifying them with the pagan
                            gods.</p>
                        <p>In letters written at the time, Montgomery claimed that he was inspired
                            by Milton’s Enoch, one of the Just Men in <hi rend="i">Paradise
                                Lost</hi>, a man like Abdiel and the poet-hero Milton, who resists
                            the temptations of cheap glory. But the focus in <hi rend="i">The World
                                Before the Flood</hi>, as far as there is a center in this
                            loosely-constructed poem, is on Javan, the prodigal poet who returned to
                            the land of the Patriarchs after succumbing to temptations of fame and
                            glory. Montgomery was more attracted to the greater humanity of the
                            flawed poet than to the rock-like Just Man. Like Wordsworth, he was
                            moved by the human misery of the eleventh book, and like Keats, he
                            wanted to see more deeply into the human heart than Milton had.</p>
                        <p>Montgomery does make the tensions in Javan’s heart seem real, but the
                            character probably interests us more because we view him as a Romantic
                            type, such as Byron’s Cain, than because of the sustained power of
                            Montgomery’s creation. Byron, in fact, may have drawn on Montgomery’s
                            Javan and Zillah for his characters in <hi rend="i">Cain</hi>, although
                            Montgomery creates an orthodox and hopeful fiction. Montgomery’s
                            characters enjoy fellowship because they have first established their
                            faith in a God whom Byron’s Cain sees as an unacceptable tyrant and whom
                            Byron sees as a product of man’s alienation from his own humanity.</p>
                        <p>The two major interests in <hi rend="i">The World Before the Flood</hi>,
                            the story of Javan’s return and the fate of the Patriarchs who are
                            threatened by the hostile Giants, are not tightly interwoven. Nor is
                            Montgomery’s narrative skillful. The long stories of the history of the
                            race, including the last days of Adam and Eve, do not have dramatic
                            propriety; the storytelling is not structured so that hearing a story
                            changes the way a character looks at the world, as the Bard’s Song
                            inspires Milton in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> or the Wanderer’s
                            tale affects the poet in <hi rend="i">The Ruined Cottage.</hi> Javan has
                            already returned to the flock, at least emotionally, when the poem
                            begins; he doesn’t need to be moved to action by a story. Furthermore,
                            heroic couplets do not give Montgomery enough freedom for the extended
                            periods that add power and variety to long narrative verse.</p>
                        <p>In the years that he was working on <hi rend="i">The World Before the
                                Flood</hi>, Montgomery considered himself an outcast. After
                            abandoning the Moravian religion of his youth, he lost direct contact
                            with church members, and, while he always considered himself a
                            Christian, he was troubled by restlessness and doubt. At the same time,
                            he yearned for fellowship with other Christians, for the communion and
                            community so central to the Moravian Brethren.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n90"
                                type="note">6</ref> Perhaps we can see this yearning in the
                            character of Javan, who gives up what Milton calls “renown on Earth”
                                (<hi rend="i">PL</hi>, XI, 698) and returns to his native land. In
                            any event, in the year following the publication of <hi rend="i">The
                                World Before the Flood</hi>, Montgomery officially returned to the
                            Moravian faith and remained an active member for the rest of his life.
                                <note id="n90"><hi rend="s">6</hi> In <hi rend="i">The Making of the
                                    English Working Class</hi> (New York: Pantheon Books, 1964), p.
                                47, E. P. Thompson notes the strong communitarian tradition in the
                                Moravian Brotherhood.</note></p>
                        <p>If <hi rend="i">The World Before the Flood</hi> is the story of the
                            prodigal’s return to his faith, Montgomery’s next long poem, 
                                <hi rend="i">Greenland</hi>, is a tribute to the faithful, the Moravian
                            missionaries who were risking their lives in an inhospitable land.
                            Greenland—the poem and the country—had been on Montgomery’s mind for
                            years before he finally published the poem as a fragment in 1819. The
                            first three cantos sketch the history of the Moravian church and the
                            first voyage to Greenland in 1733; the fourth and fifth cantos refer to
                            the lost Norwegian colonies of the tenth through fifteenth centuries.
                            The projected cantos were to have dealt with “that moral revolution,
                            which the gospel has wrought among these people, by reclaiming them,
                            almost universally, from idolatry and barbarism” (Montgomery’s Preface,
                            p. vi). Although Montgomery’s reasons for not completing 
                                <hi rend="i">Greenland</hi> are unclear, this sketch should indicate the
                            difficulty of using such material with no central plot or character. The
                            most likely assumption is that Montgomery wanted to publish the
                            unfinished poem in order to bolster his campaign in the 
                                <hi rend="i">Iris</hi> to save the missions, and simply never returned to it.
As
                            if to strengthen the impact of the poem as propaganda, the completed
                            cantos have long, detailed footnotes and appendices on the Moravians,
                            information that the reader of 1819 or today could gather more
                            efficiently from a history text. Such frequent and minute interruptions
                            destroy the rhythmical momentum of long narrative poetry.</p>
                        <p>Despite these faults, <hi rend="i">Greenland</hi> does contain
                            imaginative descriptive passages: 
<q> On rustling pinions, like an
                                unseen bird,<lb/>
 Among the yards, a stirring breeze is heard;<lb/>
                                The conscious vessel wakes as from a trance,<lb/>
 Her colours float,
                                the filling sails advance;<lb/>
 While from her prow the murmuring
                                surge recedes:<lb/>
 —So the swan, startled from her nest of
                                reeds,<lb/>
 Swells into beauty, and with a curving chest,<lb/>
                                Cleaves the blue lake, with motions soft as rest.<lb/>
 (Canto III,
                                pp. 47-48) </q>
What is most striking about Montgomery’s imagery is
                            the apparent influence of Shelley. Throughout 
                                <hi rend="i">Greenland</hi> Montgomery describes atmospheres full of energy
and
                            movement: rushing meteors, powerful glaciers, expanding vapours,
                            crashing mountain ice, winds yelling like demons. The imagery of
                            Montgomery’s earlier poetry was more static and conventional; but in 
                                <hi rend="i">Greenland</hi> his images reflect the harsh and unyielding
                            power of the natural world. Like Shelley in “Mont Blanc” (published in
                            1817 at 
<pb id="p15-33" n="33"/>
                            <figure n="ChimneySweeperWall.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="356"/> the end of
the
                                <hi rend="i">History of a Six Weeks’ Tour</hi>), Montgomery invokes
                            geological time as well as human history.</p>
                        <p>But unlike Shelley, Montgomery did not abhor didactic poetry. He wrote
                                <hi rend="i">Greenland</hi> as veiled propaganda, and even more to
                            the point, he edited <hi rend="i">The Chimney Sweeper’s Friend and
                                Climbing Boy’s Album</hi> for the “direct enforcement of
                                reform.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n91"
type="note">7</ref> This volume combines
                            actual accounts of abuses with selected poetry, all designed to prove
                            what Montgomery states in the Preface: 
<q> This book will exhibit such
                                testimonies concerning the subject, in all its bearings, as ought to
                                satisfy the most supercilious, obdurate, and prejudiced, that such
                                an employment is inhuman, unnecessary, and altogether unjustifiable.
                                The barbarity of the practice cannot be denied:—nor can it be
                                mitigated, for it is next to impossible to teach a child this trade
                                at all, without the infliction of such cruelties upon his person, as
                                would subject a master in any <hi rend="i">other</hi> business to
                                the discipline of Bridewell, were he to exercise the like on 
                                    <hi rend="i">his</hi> apprentices. Nor can any necessity, except
                                that which is the tyrant’s pleas, be proved in support of it. There
                                are <hi rend="i">machines in use</hi>, with which ninety-nine
                                chimneys out of a hundred might be swept . . . (vi-vii) </q>
                            Montgomery proposes that the legislature “prohibit the masters from
                            taking any more children as climbers” (vii) and replace human beings
                            with machines. His central contrast recurs throughout the volume:
                            Parliament passed a bill outlawing the trade in Negroes but it allows
                            the trade in British children. 
                            <note id="n91"><hi rend="s">7</hi> I am 
                            <corr type="emend">referring</corr> to Shelley’s argument in 
                            the Preface to <hi rend="i">Prometheus Unbound</hi> that 
                            “nothing can be <corr type="emend">equally</corr> well 
                            expressed in prose that is not tedious and supererogatory 
                            in verse<supplied type="emend">”</supplied> 
                            (<corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">Shelley: Poetical Works</hi>,</corr> 
                            ed. Thomas Hutchinson [London: Oxford Univ. Press, 1968], p. 207).</note></p>
                        <p><hi rend="i">The Chimney Sweeper’s Friend</hi> consists of pleas,
                            testimonies, case histories, “true” stories, medical reports, legal
                            resolutions, and petitions; the <hi rend="i">Climbing Boy’s Album</hi>
                            contains mostly poems (with the exception of brief prose fictions and a
                            dramatic sketch) illustrating the misery of the “profession.” For the
                                <hi rend="i">Album</hi> Montgomery solicited works from all over the
                            kingdom, getting many responses—mostly from sincere souls rather than
                            literary talents. Some declined to contribute on the grounds that a poem
                            on such a subject would be neither useful nor poetical: Walter Scott
                            responded with instructions (printed in Montgomery’s general preface)
                            for constructing chimney vents so that very little soot accumulates, and
                            what does accumulate can be cleaned with a machine; Joanna Baillie said
                            that such a collection of poems “is just the way to have the whole
                            matter considered by the sober pot-boilers over the whole Kingdom as a
                            fanciful and visionary thing. I wish, with all my heart, that
                            threshing-machines and cotton-mills had first been recommended to monied
                            men by poets” (<hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi>, IV, 61). Nevertheless,
                            Montgomery felt that the two-part miscellany, which included three
                            engravings by Cruickshank, would attract readers in support of the
                            cause. And, hoping to interest the King more deeply in the plight of
                            climbing boys, Montgomery dedicated the volume to George IV.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="i">The Chimney Sweeper’s Friend</hi> includes graphic and
                            gruesome details of such miseries as chimney sweeper’s cancer (of the
                            scrotum), permanently deformed limbs, and stunted and crooked growth.
                            The picture is grim: children as young as four or five sold to a master,
                            unwashed for as long as six months, and starved so they would not grow
                            and thrive. Masters were known to stick pins in children’s feet or to
                            light fires under them so that they would climb narrow chimneys; the
                            instances of children dragged senseless out of chimneys either dead or
                            soon to die occurred frequently. The massive evidence against using
                            children is complemented by the testimony of George Smart, who invented
                            and had been using a machine for cleaning chimneys since 1803. But
                            repeated testimony proves that while machines existed, slavery was more
                            profitable and some Englishmen had more reverence for their chimneys
                            than for the children who swept them.</p>
                        <pb id="p15-34" n="34"/>
                        <p>Beyond testaments to physical injustices, the selections include subtle
                            personal observation. In an introductory address written by a Mrs. Ann
                            Alexander of York for a pamphlet on the subject, the writer pleads as a
                            mother to mothers: 
<q> Could we have endured the idea, that those who
                                had been nursed at our bosoms, with all a mother’s tenderness; those
                                who had repaid the toils of maternal solicitude with the sweet
                                smiles and endearing actions of unconscious innocence; should, at
                                the early age from five to seven years, when probably their natural
                                or acquired dread of darkness was in full operation, be forced into
                                the rough and obscure recesses of a chimney, in the manner described
                                in this pamphlet? (p. 86) </q>
Such a detail as the child’s fear of
                            darkness adds poignancy to the evident physical dangers of sweeping.
                            Mrs. Alexander consistently calls attention to the emotional deprivation
                            of the children: “As climbing boys are brought up under those who had
                            their feelings of tenderness early blunted by their disgusting
                            profession, and, who, probably have received little, if any, education
                            themselves; what means of improvement can we therefore suppose such
                            masters will provide for their apprentices?” (p. 88). This kind of life
                            blunts the feelings and affections associated with a child’s
                            development, so that he becomes deformed mentally as well as physically.
                            He is deprived of the natural bonds which connect children to a
                            responsive world.</p>
                        <p>The theme of mental and emotional deprivation runs through the pieces in
                            the <hi rend="i">Climbing Boy’s Album.</hi> Many of the fictions are
                            based on actual accounts of children either stolen from parents or sold
                            by them to master sweeps. “The Lay of the Last Chimney Sweeper” (pp.
                            369-77), dated optimistically in the year 1827, tells the story of a
                            child who for a time enjoyed a healthy, free childhood in his native
                            glen; but when his father’s death brought hard times, his mother made
                            her way into the city and was tricked and tempted into bartering her
                            boy. 
<q> A sooty man, of mien austere,<lb/>
 Pursued her steps
                                behind:<lb/>
 Stern were his features and severe,<lb/>
 And yet his
                                words were kind.<lb/>
<lb/>
 Her boy should learn his trade, he
                                said,<lb/>
 Nor would he aught withhold;<lb/>
 He’d lodge him, clothe
                                him, give him bread;—<lb/>
 He show’d the tempting gold. </q>
The lay
                            typically contrasts natural love and country freedom with the corruption
                            of the city. The chimney sweep becomes the outcast from society, marked
                            by soot and deprived of fellowship.</p>
						<q> When too, upon the village green, among the lads I stand,<lb/>
 No
                            friendly voice my presence hails, I press no friendly hand;<lb/>
 I fain
                            would mingle in their sports, but, ah! my brow doth wear<lb/>
 A mark
                            that bids that noisy crew my converse to beware.<lb/>
 (“A Ballad of the
                            House-Tops,” p. 360) </q>
                        <p>Readers of this journal will be interested to find Blake’s “Chimney
                            Sweeper” from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> in the 
                            <hi rend="i">Album</hi>, with the explanation that Charles Lamb sent the poem
along
                            in lieu of his own contribution. As far as I can tell, Blake and
                            Montgomery had no direct contact, although Montgomery was familiar with
                            some of Blake’s illustrations and owned a copy of the illustrations to
                            Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi><ref target="n92" type="note">8</ref> It
happens, too, that the copy of <hi rend="i">The Chimney
                                Sweeper’s Friend and Climbing Boy’s Album</hi> used by Garland (from
                            Yale’s Beinecke Library) contains on the back leaf a handwritten note
                            that quotes Gilchrist’s comments on a strange alteration that Lamb made
                            in the text: 
						<q> In Gilchrist’s Life of Blake it is written:—“One poem,
                                ‘The Chimney Sweeper,’ still calls for special notice. . . . This, I
                                may add, was extracted 35 years later in a curious little volume
                                (1824) of James Montgomery’s editing, as a friend of the then
                                unprotected Climbing Boys. It was entitled “The C.S. ’s F. &amp; C.
                                B. ’s A,” a miscellany of verse and prose, original and borrowed,
                                with illustrations by R. C. Charles Lamb, one of the living authors
                                applied to by the kind-hearted Sheffield poet, while declining the
                                task of rhyming on such a subject, sent a copy from the “Songs of
                                Innocence”, communicating it as “from a very rare and curious little
                                work.” At line 5, “Little Tom Dacre” is transformed by a sly blunder
                                of Lamb’s into “Little Tom Toddy.” ” </q>
                            Lamb’s intentions in changing the name (whatever they might 
                            have been) are not as significant as his choice of the more 
                            ambiguous song from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> than the angry 
                            one from <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, in which the sweeper’s 
                            parents have gone to Church “to
                            praise God &amp; his Priest &amp; King / Who make up a heaven of our
                            misery.” This choice is more politic in a volume dedicated to the
                            current king and courting his support for the cause. 
                                    <note id="n92"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Holland and Everett say that Montgomery
sold his
                                copy because “several of the plates were hardly of such a nature as
                                to render the book proper to lie on a parlour table for general
                                inspection,” and regretted the sale when “the death of the artist
                                soon afterwards rendered the work both scarce and proportionately
                                valuable” (<hi rend="i">Memoirs</hi>, I, 38).</note></p>
                        <figure n="SongsOfZion.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="510">
                        	<figTranscr>MONTGOMERY’S POETICAL WORKS.<lb/>
                        	________<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	This Day are published, in foolscap 8vo. Price 5s.<lb/>
                        	SONGS OF ZION,<lb/>
                        	BEING IMITATIONS OF PSALMS,<lb/>
                        	By J. MONTGOMERY.<lb/>
                        	Printed for Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme, Brown, and Green.<lb/>
                        	Of whom may be had, by the same Author,<lb/>
                        	GREENLAND, and other Poems, 2d Edit. 8s. bds.<lb/>
                        	The WORLD before the FLOOD, 6th Edit. 9s.<lb/>
                        	The WEST INDIES, and other Poems, 6th Edit. 6s.<lb/>
                        	The WANDERER of SWITZERLAND, 9th Edit. 6s.<lb/>
                        	Or the above in the 3 vols. with uniform titles, 1l. 13s. bds.<lb/>
                        	Also, VERSES to the MEMORY of R. REYNOLDS, 2s.<lb/>
                        	POLYHYMNIA; or Select Airs of celebrated Foreign Composers,<lb/>
                        	adapted to English Words, written expressly for this<lb/>
                        	Work, Price 6s.<lb/>
                        	________<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	This day is published, in 2 vols. foolscap 8vo. 12s. bds.<lb/>
                        	PROSE, by a POET.<lb/>
                        	CONTENTS:— Pen, Ink, and Paper; Morna; Old Women; Life<lb/>
                        	of a Flower, by itself; Juvenile Delinquency; an Old English<lb/>
                        	Year; the Moon and Stars, a Fable; Common Place; a Six Miles’<lb/>
                        	Tour; a Tale without a Name; a Modest Confession; the Acorn,<lb/>
                        	an Apologue; a Dialogue of the Alphabet; a Scene not to be<lb/>
                        	found in any Play; Mutability; Extracts from my Journal at<lb/>
                        	Scarborough; the Voyage of the Blind; an Apocryphal Chapter<lb/>
                        	in the History of England; a Forenoon at Harrogate; an African<lb/>
                        	Valley; the Last Day; Postscript.<lb/>
                        	Printed for Longman, Hurst, Rees, Orme, Brown, and Green.<lb/>
                        	 ________<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	The STATE LOTTERY, a Dream. By SAMUEL<lb/>
                        	ROBERTS. Also THOUGHTS ON WHEELS, a Poem.<lb/>
                        	By J. MONTGOMERY. One Vol. 8vo. 7s. boards.</figTranscr>
                        </figure>
                        <pb id="p15-35" n="35"/>
                        <figure n="NoteChimneySweeper.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="681">
                        	<figTranscr>Note.<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	In Gilchrist’s Life of Blake it is written:—<lb/>
                        	“One poem, ‘The Chimney Sweeper,’ still calls <lb/>
                        	for special notice. . . . This, I may add, <lb/>
                        	was extracted 35 years later in a curious <lb/>
                        	little volume (1824) of James Montgomery’s <lb/>
                        	editing, as a friend of the then unprotected <lb/>
                        	Climbing Boys. It was entitled “The C.S. ’s F. <lb/>
                        	&amp; C. B. ’s A,” a miscellany of verse and prose, <lb/>
                        	original and borrowed, with illustrations by <lb/>
                        	R. C. Charles Lamb, one of the living authors <lb/>
                        	applied to by the kind-hearted Sheffield <lb/>
                        	poet, while declining the task of rhyming <lb/>
                        	on such a subject, sent a copy from the <lb/>
                        	“Songs of Innocence”, communicating it as <lb/>
                        	“from a very rare and curious little work.” <lb/>
                        	At line 5, “Little Tom Dacre” is transformed <lb/>
                        	by a sly blunder of Lamb’s into “Little Tom Toddy.” ”<lb/>
                        	<lb/>
                        	T.H.</figTranscr>
                        </figure>
                        <p><hi rend="i">The Chimney Sweeper’s Friend and Climbing Boy’s Album</hi>
                            reminds us of Montgomery’s commitment to both journalism and poetry,
                            since some of the selections were first printed in the 
                                <hi rend="i">Iris.</hi> This dual commitment set him apart from many of his
                            greater contemporaries. His work as an editor stole time from poetic
                            composition, and even when he finally gave up the editorship of the 
                                <hi rend="i">Iris</hi>, he wrote essays, lectured, and participated
                            actively in religious and secular affairs. Blake and Wordsworth, Shelley
                            and Keats, put poetry first, since they considered it the most powerful
                            means of reform: the poet could hammer away tyranny, sharpen the
                            discriminating powers of the mind, legislate quietly over the world.
                            Perhaps Montgomery sensed that his poetry alone could not have exerted a
                            major influence on the spirit of the age.</p>
                        <p>Montgomery failed because his poetry of sincerity lacks formal discipline
                            and depth of thought. His poems often lapse into a rhetorical and
                            preachy style that cannot rest in imaginative uncertainties; nor does he
                            create his own sustained, coherent poetic system. The faults of much of
                            his poetry resemble those named by Jeffrey in his review of 
                                <hi rend="i">The Excursion</hi> (<hi rend="i">Edinburgh Review</hi> [24] Nov.
                            1814): prolix and long-winded ideas without discipline. Overwhelmed by
                            the sentiments of <hi rend="i">The Wanderer of Switzerland</hi>, Byron
                            claimed in <hi rend="i">English Bards and Scotch Reviewers</hi> that
                            Montgomery’s works “might have bloomed at last” (420) if they had not
                            been “nipped in the bud” by the “Caledonian gales” (422) of the 
                                <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Review.</hi> We do not have to agree with Byron
                            to be grateful for the return of Montgomery’s works in the shape of the
                            Garland facsimiles.</p>
                    </div3>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
