<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.1.erdman</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">Let the Dead Ardours Live!</title>
        <author n="Erdman">David V. Erdman</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <name>James Warwick</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Martin K. Nurmi</name>
              <name>Judith Page</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Henry Summerfield</name>
              <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
      <pb id="p15-58" n="58"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-1-0009">
        <head>
          <title type="section"><hi rend="b">DISCUSSION</hi></title>
          <title type="section-subtitle"><hi rend="b">WITH INTELLECTUAL SPEARS &amp; LONG WINGED ARROWS OF
THOUGHT</hi></title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">LET THE DEAD ARDOURS LIVE!</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">David V.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Erdman</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Perhaps it is well to have further discussion of the inscription on
                        Blake’s sketch: see David Bindman, “The Dead Ardours
                        Revisited,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 56, Spring 1981, p. 211,
                        querying my “Leonora, Laodamia, and the Dead Ardours,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 54,
Fall 1980, pp. 96-98. Bindman and I have both
                        examined the original sketch, in his collection, while the photograph of it
                            <hi rend="i">as reproduced</hi> in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 54 has given
                        people a wretchedly faint image to examine. Here, with better reproductive
                        results be it hoped, is a re-photographing on high-contrast paper, giving
                        much sharper definition.</p>
          <p>“There can be no doubt about the initial words ‘The
                        dead’,” Bindman agrees, adding: “nor, I
                        believe, that they are in Blake’s own formal script, but it is
                        still not even clear how many words follow.” He also questions
                        whether Blake was the one who put his initials in the far left and whether
                        “Perry” can possibly be the word crowded in at the end of
                        the inscription—though he apparently takes it to be in
                        Blake’s hand: to Bindman it seems “very improbable that
                        Blake would have brought in the name of such an obscure engraver in this
                        way, in the same formal script as the title, even if there were other
                        evidence to connect it with the <hi rend="i">Leonora</hi>
                        engravings.”</p>
          <figure n="BlakeSketch.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="312">
            <figTranscr>W B. The dead ardours Perry</figTranscr>
            <head>W B. The dead ardours Perry</head>
            <figDesc>David Bindman Collection.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>I find it hard to conceive of anything that would more powerfully connect
                        this design with the design which Blake made and Perry etched for 
<hi rend="i">Leonora</hi> (see plate 380 in Bindman’s <hi rend="i">Complete Graphic Works of Blake</hi>) than
the striking
                        resemblances between the “dead” somethings in this sketch
                        and the “Forms” “of Death” (according to
                        line 2 of its inscription) in that plate that was etched and published. To
                        Blake, Perry need not have been “an obscure engraver” even
                        though he was a bad one and we may suppose that Blake disliked, not his
                        obscurity, but his ugly transformation of Blake’s faces and
                        bodies with his stippling deconstruction.</p>
          <p>That the word I have read as “Perry” might rather be a word
                        integral to the caption, as Bindman implies, seems to be ruled out by the
                        nature of the caption as a mock-up or layout, something I alluded to before
                        but have now given closer attention to, thanks to the questioning.
                        Lettering, in a design plan, is not inscribed but positioned. Bindman makes
                        no note of the letters “VOLUME” which have been partly cut
                        off but are visible in the upper left portion of the sketch. It will be left
                        to a lettering engraver to inscribe that half-title. And even the caption
                        itself, far from being all in “Blake’s own formal
                        script,” is approximately formal only in the opening
                        “The” and the second and third “d”. The
                        smaller letters are only roughly indicated, to lay out the spacing, if later
                        revised a bit for legibility. In short, this is not a finished inscription
                        but a mock-up for an engraver to follow in his own style. In the three
                        stipple engravings actually used in <hi rend="i">Leonora</hi> it seems
                        evident that the identifying phrases “Blake inv:” and
                        “Perry sc:” in the corners of the plates were not
                        inscribed by Blake: quite possibly they were not inscribed by Perry either
                        but by a specializing lettering engraver.</p>
          <pb id="p15-59" n="59"/>
          <p>Thanks to David Bindman’s query, I can now see that the
                        “P” of “Perry” is rather more like the
                        “P” as engraved in the published plates than it is like
                        Blake’s—though, <hi rend="i">pace</hi>
                        Bindman’s other viewers of the original sketch, nothing like a
                        formal “L” can be seen here. The letter is a formal
                        “P” in the style of copperplate hand employed by Blake
                        (see “O Prince” for a flourished example, in <hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 38:15) as well
as in that of the lettering engraver.</p>
          <p>Why should “Perry” be crowded up so against the last word
                        of the caption, and too close for a properly flourishing
                        “P”? And why “W.B.” put off toward the
                        left edge? I take it that although the caption itself had to be carefully
                        spaced and its style indicated, the placing of the names would depend on the
                        final shaping of the plate. They were simply jotted here, by Perry or by
                        some foreman, as reminders. If the design were used as a vignette under
                        “SECOND VOLUME” (to guess at a number) it might float as a
                        cloud above blank space and the names be tucked inconspicuously under the
                        corners of the cloud: compare Bindman, plates 381 and 382.</p>
          <p>As for the caption itself, however, infrared photography yields no trace of
                        any letter where Bindman hesitantly conjectures (and abandons) a
                        “b” for “bard.” But
                        “ardours” stands out even more clearly than
                        “dead”; the pencil mending Bindman mentions I take to be
                        Blake’s turning the sketch into setting-copy, so to speak. If the
                        New Mexico printer doesn’t now betray us, I think no one need
                        worry further about this transcription. David Bindman, however, has
                        generously invited the curious to consult the original.</p>
          <p>And what next? Perhaps someone working in publishing history will discover
                        what aborted Volume these ardours were intended to adorn.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
