<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.1.summerfield</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake and the Names Divine</title>
        <author n="Summerfield">H. Summerfield</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <name>James Warwick</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Martin K. Nurmi</name>
              <name>Judith Page</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Henry Summerfield</name>
              <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
      <pb id="p15-14" n="14"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-1-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">BLAKE AND THE NAMES DIVINE</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">H.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">SUMMERFIELD</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>In his later works, William Blake occasionally fails to maintain his usual sharp
                    distinction between the God who brought about the fall into matter and uttered
                    the Ten Commandments and the Divine Humanity who manifests as Jesus and is
                    immanent in each individual. What, for example, are we to make of the couplets
                    on plate 3 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, which announce that he who spoke on
                    Sinai inspires the epic, or of the Prologue to <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The
                        Gates of Paradise</hi>, which informs us that Jehovah, having written the
                    Decalogue, repents and inters it under His Mercy Seat?</p>
        <p>Some commentators have recognized the problem which arises from such passages as
                    these. Sloss and Wallis complain that “Throughout the later writings
                    confusion arises from Blake’s use of the terms God, Jehovah, and
                    Jehovah Elohim”; Milton Percival, discussing Blake’s
                    treatment of the Incarnation, regrets that “The divine names are not
                    clearly differentiated from one another”; and Kathleen Raine confesses
                    that Blake does not always employ the name Jehovah consistently. Harold Bloom
                    tackles the problem by distinguishing between a “humanizing”
                    and a “Urizenic” Jehovah but does not specify the relations
                    between them. Probing more deeply, Jean Hagstrum sees Christian love
                    transforming Jehovah the tyrant into Christ-Jehovah the compassionate Father,
                    yet we are left to wonder about Jehovah’s origin and about his
                    pre-Christian forgiveness of Cain in <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel.</hi> Anne
                    Mellor’s suggestion that Jesus the Imagination absorbs the reasoner
                    Jehovah, reconciling his law and energetic wrath with love and mercy, faces the
                    same objections and makes a puzzle of Jesus’ abundant energy in
                    “The Everlasting Gospel.” Bo Lindberg locates the
                    inconsistency in Jehovah Himself, claiming that he favors his sons Satan and
                    Jesus alternately but overlooking the fact that it is Adam, not Jesus, who is
                    Satan’s brother in Blake’s myth. Finally, Thomas
                    Altizer’s argument that Blake’s God and Satan have an
                    underlying identity depends heavily on what he admits is “a single
                    symbolic image,” namely the Seven Eyes of God, and, as Ronald Grimes
                    points out, he blurs the distinctions between God, Satan, and Urizen.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">1</hi> D. J. Sloss and J. P. R. Wallis, ed., <hi rend="i">The Prophetic Writings
of William Blake</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon
                        Press, 1926), II, 185-86; Milton O. Percival, <hi rend="i">William
                            Blake’s Circle of Destiny</hi> (1938; rpt. New York: Octagon
                        Books, 1964), p. 141; Kathleen Raine, <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi>
                        (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1968), II, 315, n. 53; Harold Bloom,
                            <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse: A Study in Poetic
                            Argument</hi> (New York: Doubleday, 1963), p. 367; Jean H. Hagstrum, 
<hi rend="i">William Blake: Poet and Painter</hi> (Chicago: University of
                        Chicago Press, 1964), pp. 117, 128; Anne Kostelanetz Mellor, <hi rend="i">Blake’s
Human Form Divine</hi> (Berkeley: University of
                        California Press, 1974), pp. 244-47; Bo Lindberg, <hi rend="i">William
                            Blake’s Illustrations to the Book of Job</hi> (Abo, Finland:
                        Abo Akademi, 1973), pp. 82-88; Thomas J. J. Altizer, <hi rend="i">The New
                            Apocalypse: The Radical Christian Vision of William Blake</hi> (n.p.:
                        Michigan State University Press, 1967), pp. 136-38; Ronald L. Grimes, <hi rend="i">The
Divine Imagination: William Blake’s Major
                            Prophetic Visions</hi> (Metuchen, N. J.: Scare-crow Press, 1972), pp.
                        154-55; 161, n. 67. For the brotherhood of Adam and Satan see the
                        Laocoön engraving—David V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of
William Blake</hi>, 4th printing, rev. (New
                        York: Doubleday, 1970), pl. 3 and p. 270, or <hi rend="i">Blake, Complete
                            Writings with variant readings</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes, rev. (London:
                        Oxford University Press, 1972), p. 775. These two editions are henceforward
                        referred to as E and K respectively, the letter being followed by a page
                        number. Quotations are taken from the former, indications of textual
                        variation being omitted. For quotations from <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate and line numbers are also
                        given.</note></p>
        <p>The question at issue should not be confused with two related but distinct
                    problems—the conundrum of who created the cosmos and the puzzle posed
                    by certain statements in Blake’s annotations to Watson’s
                        <hi rend="i">Apology for the Bible.</hi> It has long been recognized<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">2</ref> that from <hi rend="i">The Book of
                        Urizen</hi> (1794) onwards Creation has two aspects in Blake’s
                    system. On the one hand it is “Error” (E555/K617), a
                    degenerate state into which a portion of Eternity falls in a process described
                    in the first chapter of Genesis; on the other hand it is “an act of
                    Mercy” (E553/K614), a limitation imposed on the Fall to make redemption
                    possible. Thus Blake can denounce Creation (the Fall) as the work of the
                        Devil,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">3</ref> yet
praise Creation (the
                    limitation of the Fall) as the achievement of Los, Jehovah, and Jesus.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">2</hi> See, for example, P. Berger, <hi rend="i">William Blake: Poet and
Mystic</hi>, trans. Daniel H. Conner (London:
                        Chapman and Hall, 1914), pp. 103-09, 117-23; S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">William
Blake: His Philosophy and Symbols</hi> (1924; rpt. Gloucester,
                        Mass.: Peter Smith, 1958), pp. 194, 476; Northrop Frye, <hi rend="i">Fearful
                            Symmetry: A Study of William Blake</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University
                        Press, 1947), pp. 135, 138; J. G. Davies, <hi rend="i">The Theology of
                            William Blake</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1948), p. 97, n. 3; and
                        Peter F. Fisher, <hi rend="i">The Valley of Vision</hi> (Toronto: University
                        of Toronto Press, 1961), pp. 245-46.</note>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Annotations to Bacon’s <hi rend="i">Essays</hi> (E615/K403) and G. E.
Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969), p. 318.</note>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">4</hi><hi rend="i"> Jerusalem</hi> 73:16-28 (E226/K713); <hi rend="i">ibid.</hi>
                        49:52-55 (E197/K680); <hi rend="i">ibid.</hi>, pl. 77—11. 21-22
                        of the blank verse (E230/K718).</note></p>
        <p>Once, in 1798, Blake goes beyond the defense of nature as a merciful limitation
                    on the Fall. In annotating Bishop Watson’s <hi rend="i">An Apology
                        for the Bible</hi>, a riposte to Thomas Paine’s Deist tract <hi rend="i">The Age of
Reason</hi>, Blake states that the Bible tells him that
                    God created nature perfect and that its imperfections 
<pb id="p15-15" n="15"/>
                    result from Adam’s sin; he also endorses the sixth commandment when
                    he condemns Joshua for breaking it, and contrasts lethal
                    “Natural” disasters favorably with Joshua’s
                    “Unnatural” carnage describing the Lisbon earthquake as
                    “the Natural result of Sin” (E604/K388). In these notes Blake
                    is attempting to defend Paine at his weakest against Watson at his strongest,
                    for the Bishop is attacking the Deist claim—already refuted by
                        Hume<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">5</ref>—that a
flawless
                    creation reflects the perfection of its Maker. Blake, as Mark Roberts has
                    pointed out,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">6</ref>
takes refuge in the
                    traditional Christian doctrine of the Fall. In his anxiety to vindicate Paine,
                    he retreats from the position which he otherwise maintains early and late<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">7</ref> that the God of the first chapter of
                    Genesis is a corrupted spirit and he assesses even post-Adamic, fallen nature
                    with its destructive qualities as less morally deplorable than are wicked
                        men.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">8</ref> Towards
the end of his
                    annotations, Blake momentarily steps out of his role as a defender of Paine and
                    exclaims, “The Bishop never saw the Everlasting Gospel any more than
                    Tom Paine” (E608/K394). The phrase “the Everlasting
                    Gospel” (from Revelation xiv.6) was, as A. L. Morton notes,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">9</ref> a term used by seventeenth-century English
                    antinomian sects to denote their doctrine, and Blake appropriates it for his own
                    version of Christianity, which is closely related to theirs but equally alien to
                    the orthodox and the Deists of his age. <note id="n27"><hi rend="s">5</hi> David
                        Hume, <hi rend="i">Dialogues Concerning Natural Religion</hi> (1779), Part
                        X. The Lisbon earthquake undermined the faith of the most illustrious
                        Deist—Voltaire.</note>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> The Tradition of Romantic Morality</hi> (London: Macmillan,
                        1973), pp. 114-16. Cf. also Frye, <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi>, p.
                        131.</note>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">7</hi> He is identified, for example, with Urizen in
                            <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> (1794)
                        (25:39-42—E82/K236), with the Elohim as opposed to Jehovah in
                        conversation with Robinson (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p.
                        545), and as the maker of the Natural Man in the chapter headings of the
                        fragmentary illuminated manuscript of Genesis (E667/K933—dated
                        1826-27 by Keynes).</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">8</hi> It is just possible, however, that, as
                        Bernard Blackstone implies—<hi rend="i">English Blake</hi>
                        (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1949), p. 361, n. 1—the
                        poet is here identifying “the heaven and the earth” of the
                        first verse of the Bible with that which existed prior to any fall,
                        “the Eternal Creation flowing from the Divine Humanity in
                        Jesus” (E543/K444), the Nature that shrunk before the shrunken eyes
                        of Har and Heva (E66/K246).</note>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">9</hi><hi rend="i"> The Everlasting Gospel: A study in the sources of William
                            Blake</hi> (London: Lawrence and Wishart, 1958), pp. 37-40.</note></p>
        <p>The distinction between the accusing, lawgiving God and the Divine Humanity (or
                    Poetic Genius) is essential to Blake’s Christianity from the early
                    1790s onwards. In <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> (c.
                    1790-1793), he identifies Jehovah, the Poetic Genius, with Energy, and Satan,
                    the Accuser of the Book of Job, with Reason. Although emotionally Blake leans
                    very heavily towards Energy, he admits that “Reason and Energy . . .
                    are necessary to Human existence” (E34/K149), for he is adapting
                    Boehme’s notion of a division of the primal unity into two Principles
                    as the basis of creation and also the source of evil. According to Boehme (in
                    Blake’s time known as Behmen), the two Principles can be represented
                    as Wrath, Fire, or the Power of God and as Love, Light, or the Heart of God, and
                    they are identical with the Father and Son of the Christian
                    Trinity—“The Father,” states Boehme, “is
                    the eternal Power, or Virtue, and the Son is the Heart and 
                    Light. . . . ” When separated from the Light or Love, the Fire or Wrath becomes the
                    flames of Hell, yet on that Fire the existence of every created thing depends.
                    Without the Fire, Boehme asks, 
					<q> where would be the Mobility, Kingdom, Power,
                        and Glory? Therefore we have often said, The Anger is the Root of Life; and
                        if it be without the Light, then it is not God, but Hell Fire; but if the
                        Light shines therein, it becomes Paradise and Fulness of Joy. </q>
Either of
                    these Principles is incomplete without the other: 
					<q> Indeed <hi rend="i">All</hi> is from
one Eternal Original, but it severizes itself into a
                            <hi rend="i">twofold</hi> Source; a Similitude whereof we have in the
                        Fire, and Light; where the Fire is painful and <hi rend="i">consuming</hi>,
                        and the Light meek and giving; and yet the one were a Nothing without the
                            other.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">10</hi><hi rend="i"> The Three Principles of the Divine Essence</hi> iv. 7 and
                            xxv. 70, and <hi rend="i">Mysterium Magnum</hi> vii. 15, in <hi rend="i">The Works
of Jacob Behmen, The Teutonic Theosopher</hi> (London,
                            1764-81, I, 21, 274, and III, 30.</note></q>
Blake was acquainted with Boehme’s
work many years before he
                    embodied in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> a distortion of
                    his doctrine, making the primal division between God and Satan instead of
                    between Father and Son; many years afterwards he remained Boehme’s
                    ardent admirer.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">11</ref>
His treatment in later
                    life of the lawgiving and redemptive aspects of the biblical God and his use of
                    the names Jehovah and Jesus show signs of Boehme’s influence, but he
                    had by then come to follow Boehme in associating the First and Second Principles
                    with the Father and the Son. <note id="n33"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Letter to
                        Flaxman, 12 Sept. 1800 (E680/K799) and Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Records</hi>, p. 313. For <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>, see n. 38
                        below.</note></p>
        <p><hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> is a bravely anti-dualistic
                    work, but a year or two after finishing it Blake adopts a semi-Gnostic dualism
                    making the egregious and tragic Urizen his demiurge.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">12</ref> At this point his interest in the Trinity, evident in
                        <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>, seems to lapse to reappear during the
                    lengthy period, beginning not later than 1797, in which he composes 
<hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, later renamed <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n35" type="note">13</ref> In this epic, he makes Urizen share the blame for the
                    Fall with Luvah, Vala, and Man himself. Later, in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and
                        <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Urizen (an individual) fades into the
                    background being displaced respectively by Satan (a state) and the Spectre of
                    Albion (who is also Satan), in whom the forces that work against a return to the
                    prelapsarian unity are focused: in these poems Satan—the Accuser as
                    distinct from the Miltonic rebel—confronts the Trinity. 
<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Only semi-Gnostic because Los voluntarily
                        descends with Urizen to ensure that the material universe will not be wholly
                        maleficent. Cf. Stuart Curran, “Blake and the Gnostic Hyle: A
                        Double Negative,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, IV (Spring
                        1972), 117-33; and W. J. T. Mitchell, <hi rend="i">Blake’s
                            Composite Art: A Study of the Illuminated Poetry</hi> (Princeton:
                        Princeton University Press, 1978), pp. 131, 136.</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">13</hi> The title-page is dated 1797. For a
                        discussion of Blake’s conception of the Trinity, see Frye, <hi rend="i">Fearful
Symmetry</hi>, pp. 52-53.</note></p>
        <p>The earliest sign that Blake is recovering his interest in the Trinity is a
                    reference to the Holy Spirit (E604/K387) in his annotations, dated 1798, to
                    Watson’s <hi rend="i">Apology for the
                    Bible</hi>—annotations which, with their allusions to
                    Blake’s professing himself a Christian, to the Everlasting Gospel,
                    and to the forgiveness of sins—adumbrate much in his later work. A
                    second mention of the Third Person occurs at the end of his letter of 30 January
                    1803 to James Blake (E696/K822), and in a late or relatively late addition to
                    Night VIIA of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> Enitharmon laments, “Such
                    is our state nor will the Son of God redeem us but destroy”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">14</ref> (E355/K331). In 1807, Blake represented
                    all three Persons of the Trinity in his painting <hi rend="i">The Fall of
                        Man.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">15</ref>
His many subsequent
                    allusions need not be detailed. <note id="n36"><hi rend="s">14</hi> The line is
                        not included in H. M. Margoliouth’s reconstruction of the earlier
                        version of the epic—<hi rend="i">William Blake’s</hi>
                        Vala: <hi rend="i">Blake’s Numbered Text</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon
                        Press, 1956).</note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Reproduced as pl. 49 in Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>
(Oxford: Phaidon, 1978). The Holy Spirit
                        above Christ’s head is somewhat faint.</note></p>
        <p>In Blake’s fully developed myth, as in Boehme, the primal division is
                    not the gulf between God and the Accuser but a separation within the Godhead
                    Itself. The perfect harmony among the Eternals, who are at once a multitude and
                    a single being,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">16</ref>
does not always prevail
                    even between the Father and the Son, and there are signs that each can be
                    imperfect when sundered from the other. <note id="n38"><hi rend="s">16</hi>
                            Cf., for example, <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night the First:
<q>
                                Then those in Great Eternity met in the Council of God<lb/>
 As one
                                Man for contracting their Exalted Senses<lb/>
 They behold Multitude
                                or Expanding they behold as one<lb/>
 As One Man all the Universal
                                family &amp; that one Man<lb/>
 They call Jesus the Christ
                                &amp; they in him &amp; he in them<lb/>
 Live in Perfect
                                harmony . . . (E306/K277) </q>
It is part of Albion’s
                            error to declare on the brink of his fall, “We are not One: we
                            are Many” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 4:23;
                        E145/K622).
                    </note></p>
        <p>There is abundant evidence, both visual and textual, that Blake in his later
                    phase conceives of the Father divorced from the Son as possessing cruel,
                    tyrannical, and destructive attributes. To begin with the paintings, on the left
                    (the sinister side) of the Father at the top of the <hi rend="i">Epitome of
                        James Hervey’s “Meditations among the
                        Tombs,”</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39"
type="note">17</ref> a late work, he
                    inscribes the text—non-biblical though related to Deuteronomy iv.24
                    and Hebrews xii.29—“God out of Christ is a Consuming
                    Fire.” In <hi rend="i">Christ the Mediator</hi> (c. 1799-1800),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">18</ref> a pale glow round the 
<pb id="p15-16" n="16"/>
<figure n="BUT641.1.1.WC" rend="file" width="799" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>INRI<lb/>
                            <lb/>
                            1807 WBlake inv</figTranscr>
	<head>1 Blake, <hi rend="i">The Fall of Man</hi> (1807).</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Victoria and Albert Museum.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p15-17" n="17"/>
head of Jesus makes a Boehmean contrast with the dark
                    flames radiating from the Father, and the latter holds the scepter of worldly
                    power which Satan bears in <hi rend="i">The Great Red Dragon and the Beast from
                        the Sea</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Number of the Beast is 666</hi> (both c.
                        1805).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">19</ref>
Between the fourth and fifth of
                    the Huntington set of Blake’s illustrations to <hi rend="i">Paradise
                        Lost</hi> 1807),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42"
type="note">20</ref> the Father undergoes
                    a change. In the fourth painting, <hi rend="i">Christ Offers to Redeem Man</hi>,
                    the Father, who embraces the Son, is wingless and, judging from the vacant space
                    on the left of his right hand and forearm, beardless; light radiates from the
                    place where the heads of the Father and Son meet and, like the light in 
<hi rend="i">Jacob’s Ladder</hi> (c. 1805),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43"
type="note">21</ref> it progressively darkens as it travels down the picture
                    away from the eternal realm. In the fifth painting, <hi rend="i">Satan’s and Raphael’s
Entries into Paradise</hi>, the
                    Father, now cut off from the Son, has become a winged, bearded, Urizenic god
                    hovering over Raphael.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44"
type="note">22</ref> The sky again grows
                    gradually darker towards the bottom, but though there is still radiance from the
                    Father it is much paler than in the previous illustration and, except for a
                    narrow area immediately above his head, it is streaked with dull yellow-green
                    stripes. This winged figure descends from the image of Urizen which Blake
                    incorporated in 1791 (before he had named the god) in his engraving <hi rend="i">The
Fertilization of Egypt</hi> based on a rough sketch by Fuseli.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n45" type="note">23</ref> It has a successor in the drooping deity
                    who presides over Blake’s ninety-seventh illustration to <hi rend="i">The Divine
Comedy</hi> (1824-1827).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">24</ref> A
                    comparable contrast may be present within a single painting, <hi rend="i">The
                        Fall of Man</hi> (1807),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47"
type="note">25</ref> where
                    Death—seated in the cave between Sin and Hell, the figures being
                    identifiable from Blake’s description (E662/K441) and from one of his
                    paintings of <hi rend="i">Satan, Sin and Death</hi> (c. 1808)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">26</ref>—could well be a degenerate form of the
                    Father above. The latter has spiky hair like that of the deity in plate 2 of
                    Blake’s <hi rend="i">Illustrations of The Book of Job</hi>
                    (1825)—spikes which, as Bo Lindberg has noticed,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n49" type="note">27</ref> turn out to have been a sign of the bearer’s
                    Satanic character as they develop into the hideous projections from the
                    Devil’s head in plate 11. If the Father has indeed fallen to become
                    Death, he has acquired in his descent stylized wings and an iron crown, and his
                    beard has shrunk, but his hands and outstretched arms retain their pose (the
                    Urizenic pose of their counterparts in <hi rend="i">The Fertilization of
                        Egypt</hi>), his left foot remains a little in front of his right, and his
                    head still inclines to one side—now his right instead of his left. In
                    the complex pattern of the painting, the Father is separated from the Son, the
                    rebel from the heavenly angels, mankind from Paradise, and Paradise from the
                    earth. <note id="n39"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Reproduced and described in Martin
                        Butlin, <hi rend="i">William Blake: a complete catalogue of the works in the
                            Tate Gallery</hi>, rev. (London: Tate Gallery, 1971), pp. 54-55. Morton
                        D. Paley, in <hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination: A Study of the
                            Development of Blake’s Thought</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press,
                        1970), states that the Father here represents Boehme’s First
                        Principle (p. 44). Cf. also Mellor, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Human
                            Form Divine</hi>, p. 244.</note>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Reproduced as color pl. VIII in Geoffrey
                        Keynes, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the
                            Bible</hi> (London: Trianon Press, 1957) and in black and white as pl.
                        34b of Anthony Blunt, <hi rend="i">The Art of William Blake</hi> (New York:
                        Columbia University Press, 1959). For description and analysis, see Blunt,
                        pp. 66-67; Mellor, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Human Form Divine</hi>,
                        p. 249; and David Bindman, <hi rend="i">Blake as an artist</hi> (Oxford:
                        Phaidon, 1977), pp. 124-25.</note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Reproduced as pl. 124 of Bindman, <hi rend="i">Blake as an artist</hi>,
and facing p. 89 of Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, 2nd impression, rev. (London: Tate
Gallery,
                        1978). Cf. also the scepter of the Virgin in <hi rend="i">The Queen of
                            Heaven in Glory</hi> (1824-27), reproduced as pl. 99 of Albert S. Roe,
                            <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations to the Divine Comedy</hi>
                        (1953; rpt. Westport, Conn.: Greenwood Press, 1977).</note>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Reproduced as pls. IV and V of C. H. Collins
                        Baker, <hi rend="i">Catalogue of William Blake’s Drawings and
                            Paintings in the Huntington Library</hi>, 2nd ed. (San Marino, Cal.:
                        Huntington Library, 1969). My remarks are based on an examination of the
                        originals.</note>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Reproduced in color as pl. 17 of William
                        Vaughan, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (London: Thames and Hudson, 1977).
                        I have also examined the original in the British Museum.</note>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Jean Hagstrum (<hi rend="i">Poet and
                            Painter</hi>, p. 126) notes that in the fourth design Christ hides the
                        face of the Father but does not mention the latter’s reappearance
                        in the next illustration. Nor does David Bindman, who sees in <hi rend="i">Christ
Offers to Redeem Man</hi> the wrathful Father in despair (<hi rend="i">Blake as an artist</hi>, pp. 188-89).
The hovering figure is
                        identified by Baker as “the Eternal Father” (<hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi>, p. 18),
by Marcia R. Pointon as “the
                        Almighty” (<hi rend="i">Milton &amp; English Art</hi>
                        [Manchester: Manchester University Press, 1970], p. 147), and by Edward J.
                        Rose as Milton’s God the Father, an “Aged
                        Presence” who “tries to pervert Messiah by sending him to
                        rout the rebel angels” (“Blake’s Illustrations
                        for <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost, L’Allegro</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi>:
A Thematic Reading,” <hi rend="i">Hartford
                            Studies in Literature</hi>, 2 [1970], 40-67).</note>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">23</hi> See Blunt, <hi rend="i">Art of William
                            Blake</hi>, p. 41 and pl. 21; Albert S. Roe, “‘The
                        Thunder of Egypt,’” in <hi rend="i">William Blake:
                            Essays for S. Foster Damon</hi>, ed. Alvin H. Rosenfeld (Providence:
                        Brown University Press, 1969), pp. 158-95; and John Beer, “Blake,
                        Coleridge, and Wordsworth: Some Cross-currents and Parallels
                        1789-1805,” in <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays in honour of Sir
                            Geoffrey Keynes</hi>, ed. Morton D. Paley and Michael Phillips (Oxford:
                        Clarendon Press, 1973), pp. 231-59.</note>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Reproduced as pl. 97 of Roe, <hi rend="i">Illustrations to the Divine
Comedy.</hi></note>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">25</hi> See n. 15 above. I have inspected the
                        original in the Victoria and Albert Museum, London, on which it is clear
                        that Death’s feet are not shackled as seems possible from the
                        reproduction.</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Reproduced as pl. 82 of Kathleen Raine, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>
(New York: Praeger, 1971).</note>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">27</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake’s Illustrations to Job</hi>, pp. 82-83,
                        204.</note></p>
        <p>Verbal references to the degeneration of the Father when He is cut off from the
                    Son are also plentiful. A famous passage in “A Vision of the Last
                    Judgment” caustically declares: 
					<q> Thinking as I do that the Creator
                        of this World is a very Cruel Being &amp; being a Worshipper of Christ
                        I cannot help saying the Son O how unlike the Father First God Almighty
                        comes with a Thump on the Head Then Jesus Christ comes with a balm to heal
                        it (E555/K617) </q>
The repentant God of the Prologue to <hi rend="i">For
                        the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n50" type="note">28</ref>
                    now falls into place—he writes the Law after he has degenerated, but,
                    reunited with the Son in the Christian dispensation, he repents. Similarly, we
                    need no longer be surprised that the lawgiving God should be identified with the
                    true God, Blake’s inspirer, in plate 3 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">28</hi> For commentary on this Prologue, see Emily
                        S. Hamblen, <hi rend="i">On the Minor Prophecies of William Blake</hi>
                        (London: Dent, 1930), p. 372; George Wingfield Digby, <hi rend="i">Symbol
                            and Image in William Blake</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1957), pp.
                        14-19; William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi>, ed. Geoffrey
                        Keynes (London: Trianon Press, 1968), I, 8; John Beer, <hi rend="i">Blake’s
Visionary Universe</hi> (Manchester: Manchester
                        University Press, 1969), pp. 36-38; Mellor, <hi rend="i">Blake’s
                            Human Form Divine</hi>, p. 227.</note></p>
        <p>The names Elohim, Jehovah, and Jesus appear in the list of the Seven Eyes of God
                    which is given in each of Blake’s three epics (E366, 106, 202/K351,
                    494, 686). It is widely agreed that the Eyes—Lucifer, Molech, Elohim,
                    Shaddai, Pa(c)had, Jehovah, and Jesus—constitute seven historical
                    (and religious) periods.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51"
type="note">29</ref> Though they seem
                    to be individuals from the viewpoint of the Eternals who commission them as
                    guardians of the fallen world, they turn out in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (32:10;
                    E130/K521) to be states from mankind’s standpoint and to be subject
                    to corruption.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">30</ref>
The first six shrink from
            the self-sacrifice necessary to redeem the fallen, the self-sacrifice 
<figure n="BUT770.1.1.WC" rend="file" width="686" height="1000">
	<head>2 Blake, <hi rend="i">Epitome of James Hervey’s
                “Meditations among the Tombs.”</hi></head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Tate Gallery.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p15-18" n="18"/>
<figure n="but529.1.3.wc" id="but529.1.wc.03" work-copy="but529.1" rend="db" width="818" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>180<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
	<head>3 Blake, <hi rend="i">Christ Offers to Redeem Man</hi> (1807), fourth
                            illus. of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Huntington Library.</figDesc>
</figure> which only Jesus, the seventh, will consummate. The third and sixth
                    Eyes are Elohim and Jehovah, “Elohim” being a Hebrew plural
                    rendered as “God” in the Authorized Version and
                    “Jehovah” a faulty transliteration of the sacred name piously
                    rendered as “the Lord.” Blake frequently employs
                    “Elohim”—the only name used for God from Genesis
                    i.1 to Genesis ii.3—for the “Cruel Being” who is
                    “the Creator of this World,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53"
type="note">31</ref> and in Night the Eighth of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, where
                    he first appears as the third Eye, he creates Adam to endure the sacrificial
                    death he himself shuns (E366/K351). In <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, however, Adam,
                    conceived as the Limit of Contraction, is defined or fashioned by “The
                    Divine hand” before Elohim descends (13:18-23; E106/K494). In 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, “Los who is of the Elohim” is
                    Adam’s maker (73:24-28; E226/K713). The fourth and fifth Eyes bear
                    the names Shaddai (Almighty) and Pa(c)had (Terror), which also denote the Hebrew
                    God, and indeed Thomas Altizer’s observation that the first six are
                    antithetical to the 
                    seventh<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">32</ref> 
                    suggests that
                    all six may be aspects of the Father. Jehovah, the last of these six, becomes
                    “leprous,” which recalls not only the Urizen of the earlier
                    <hi rend="i">America</hi> (16:3, 11; E56/K203) but Jesus’ threat
            		in “The Everlasting Gospel” to 
<figure n="but529.1.4.wc" id="but529.1.wc.04" work-copy="but529.1" rend="db" width="815" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>WBlake 1807</figTranscr>
	<head>4 Blake, <hi rend="i">Satan’s and Raphael’s Entries into Paradise</hi> 
	(1807), fifth illus. of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Huntington Library.</figDesc>
</figure> 
					the Angel of the Divine Presence, who had written the Law at Sinai:
					<q> 
						My Presence I will take from thee<lb/>
						A Cold Leper thou shalt be 
						(E513/K754)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">33</ref>
					</q>
					Jehovah’s leprosy is a consequence of his separation from
                    Christ, and one of his names when he is in this state is the Angel of the Divine
                    Presence, which in Blake always denotes a corrupt 
                    being:<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">34</ref> 
                    he is the God who covers Adam’s and Eve’s nakedness in the painting 
                    <hi rend="i">The Angel of the Divine Presence Clothing Adam and Eve 
                    with Coats of Skins</hi> 
                    (1803),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">35</ref> 
                    the spiky-haired deity in plate 2 of <hi rend="i">Illustrations of The Book of Job</hi> 
                    (1825), where he is named in Hebrew “King Jehovah,” and the central figure in the
                    Laocoön engraving (c. 1820), where the Hebrew above identifies him as
                    “the Angel of Jehovah” and the Hebrew below as
                    “Jah” (an abbreviation for “Jehovah”), the
                    father of Satan and 
                    Adam.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">36</ref> 
                    (The English phrase “The Angel of the Divine Presence” appears on both 
                    <hi rend="i">Job</hi> pl. 2 and the Laocoön plate.) In “A
                    Vision of the Last Judgment,” Blake claims that people often refer to
                    this Angel—who became the patron spirit of the Britain of the fallen
                    world with her oak groves—when they speak of “Jehovah
                    Elohim,” this being the name translated as “the Lord
                    God” in the Authorized Version 
                    (E549/K610).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">37</ref>
	<note id="n51"><hi rend="s">29</hi> E.g. Damon, <hi rend="i">Philosophy and
                            Symbols</hi>, pp. 388-89; Percival, <hi rend="i">Circle of Destiny</hi>,
                        pp. 242-50; Frye, <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi>, pp. 128-34; Hazard
                        Adams, <hi rend="i">William Blake: A Reading of the Shorter Poems</hi>
                        (Seattle: University of Washington Press, 1963), p. 63; Paley, <hi rend="i">Energy and
Imagination</hi>, pp. 135-41. Edward Rose persuasively
                        suggests that in Eternity the seven are simultaneous or
                        coexistent—“Illustrations to <hi rend="i">Paradise
                            Lost</hi>,” p. 54, n. 8. John Adlard—“A
                        ‘Triumphing Joyfulness’: Blake[,] Boehme and the
                        Tradition,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, I (Spring 1969),
                        109-22—associates the Eyes with the Kabbala’s ten
                        Sephiroth and Boehme’s Seven Spirits of God; Kathleen
                            Raine—<hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi>, II,
                        210-13—identifies them with seven fallen Sephiroth.</note>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">30</hi> Cf. Damon, <hi rend="i">Philosophy and
                            Symbols</hi>, p. 424; Raine, <hi rend="i">loc. cit.</hi>; and John
                        Howard, <hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi> Milton: <hi rend="i">A Study in
                            the Selfhood</hi> (Cranbury, N. J.: Associated University Presses,
                        1976), pp. 45-46, 83, 93-95, and 181-82.</note>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">31</hi> From the passage quoted above. Cf. also the
                        references to the Elohim in the prose introduction, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, pl.
27 (E170/K649), and in Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Records</hi>, p. 545.</note>
	<note id="n54"><hi rend="s">32</hi><hi rend="i"> New Apocalypse</hi>, p. 137.</note>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">33</hi> Emily S. Hamblen—<hi rend="i">Minor Prophecies</hi>, p. 386—expounds
this passage, and
                        Michael J. Tolley—“Blake’s
                        ‘Edens Flood’ Again,” <hi rend="i">Notes
                            and Queries</hi> 213 (January 1968), 11-19—notes its
                        apparent inconsistency with the favorable references to the Holy Spirit
                        present at Creation which precede and follow it. See also Tolley,
                        “William Blake’s Use of the Bible in a Section of
                        ‘The Everlasting Gospel,’” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>, 207 (May 1962),
171-76.</note>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">34</hi> For this Angel see Damon, <hi rend="i">Philosophy and Symbols</hi>, p.
296, and <hi rend="i">A Blake
                            Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols of William Blake</hi> (Providence, R.
                        I.: Brown University Press, 1965), p. 23; Tolley,
                        “Blake’s Use of the Bible,” p. 174, and
                        “Blake’s ‘Edens Flood’
                        Again,” pp. 13-17; Northrop Frye, “Blake’s
                        Reading of the Book of Job,” in <hi rend="i">Essays for Damon</hi>,
                        pp. 221-34; Lindberg, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations to
                            Job</hi>, pp. 203-04; and Jenijoy La Belle, “Words Graven with
                        an Iron Pen: The Marginal Texts in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi>” in 
<hi rend="i">The Visionary Hand: Essays for the Study
                            of William Blake’s Art and Aesthetics</hi>, ed. Robert N.
                        Essick (Los Angeles: Hennessey and Ingalls, 1973), pp. 527-50.</note>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">35</hi> Bindman, <hi rend="i">Blake as an
                            artist</hi>, pl. 112 and p. 138.</note>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">36</hi> See n. 1 above. Irene Tayler, in
                        “Blake’s Laocoön,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 10 (Winter 1976-77),
72-81, argues that
                        Laocoön is a prophet corrupted by giving his allegiance to the
                        war and dominion of the Covenant of Priam instead of to the forgiveness of
                        sins of the Covenant of Jehovah; yet she mentions that he is himself
                        identified with Jehovah. His being the Father in a degenerate form resolves
                        the contradiction.</note>
	<note id="n59"><hi rend="s">37</hi> The verse which Blake cites here as alluding
                        to this spirit—Exodus xiv. 19—actually speaks of
                        “the angel of Elohim.”</note></p>
        <p>References to imperfection in the Son separated from the Father are rarer than
                    aspersions on the Father separated from the Son, but however much Blake, like
                    Boehme, leans emotionally towards the Son, as he leaned towards Energy in <hi rend="i">The
Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, they do occur. In
                    conversation with Crabb Robinson, Blake stated that Christ was 
<pb id="p15-19" n="19"/>
wrong to attack the Government and to allow himself to be
                    crucified. On being asked how error was consistent with Christ’s
                    divinity he replied, “He was not then become the father,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">38</ref> indicating that the separation of the
                    Persons had led to a temporary lapse from perfection. On a later occasion, he
                    told Robinson that Christ was wrong to expel the money-changers from the Temple,
                    that he “took much after his Mother And in so far he was one of the
                    worst of men,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">39</ref>
and in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> Los says of him, “by his Maternal Birth he
                    is that Evil-One” (90:35; E247/K736). It is part of Christ’s
                    sacrifice to assume from his mother the corruption of the Natural Man, which he
                    must then put off before he can again become one with the Father. The point is
                    repeated in “The Everlasting Gospel”: 
					<q> He took on Sin in
                        the Virgins Womb<lb/>
 And put it off on the Cross &amp; Tomb<lb/>
                        (E515/K749) </q>
In this poem Jesus, though dear to Blake, is not flawless.
                    The Father, Himself vindictive in His separation from the Son (“Gods
                    Mercy &amp; Long Suffering / Is but the Sinner to Judgment to
                    bring” [E512/K753]),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62"
type="note">40</ref> rebukes
                    Jesus for his degrading humility: 
					<q> And when he Humbled himself to God<lb/>
                        Then descended the Cruel Rod<lb/>
 If thou humblest thyself thou humblest
                        me<lb/>
 Thou also dwellst in Eternity<lb/>
 (E511/K752) </q>
<figure n="BookofJob.p2.Tate.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="763" height="1000">
	<head>5 Blake, <hi rend="i">Illustrations for The Book of Job</hi> (1825),
                            plate 2.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Tate Gallery.</figDesc>
</figure> When God goes on to command “Thou on the Cross for them [i.e.
                    sinners] shalt pray,” Jesus indignantly refuses and confesses to past
                    error: 
					<q> I never will Pray for the World<lb/>
 Once [I] did so when I prayd in
                        the Garden<lb/>
 I wishd to take with me a Bodily Pardon<lb/>
 (E512/K753)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63" type="note">41</ref></q>
Even the Jesus who,
as the seventh Eye of God, “Died willing
                    beneath Tirzah &amp; Rahab” (E366/K351), though glorious in
                    self-sacrifice, is not perfect, for the Seven Eyes have to unite with each other
                    and with the Eighth, the sleeping Humanity, to become “One Man Jesus
                    the Saviour” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 42:11; E142/K534)—the
                    fullness of the Divine Humanity Itself.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n64" type="note">42</ref>
	<note id="n60"><hi rend="s">38</hi> Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p.
                        311. This statement may be anticipated by the Devil’s declaration
                        on pl. 6 of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell:</hi>
                        “Know that after Christs death, he became Jehovah”
                        (E35/K150). If so, the Son there represents reason, the Father
                        energy—cf. Martin K. Nurmi, <hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi>
                        Marriage of Heaven and Hell: <hi rend="i">A Critical Study</hi> (Kent, Ohio:
                        Kent State University, 1957), pp. 36-37; John Beer, <hi rend="i">Blake’s
Humanism</hi> (Manchester: Manchester University
                        Press, 1968), p. 25; William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
                            Hell</hi>, ed. Clark Emery (Coral Gables: University of Miami Press,
                        1963), pp. 52-54; and Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr., <hi rend="i">Angel of
                            Apocalypse: Blake’s Idea of Milton</hi> (Madison: University
                        of Wisconsin Press, 1975), pp. 211-12. But all three Persons of the Trinity
                        are probably forms of energy, and Satan, the Accuser of the Book of Job,
                        their rational contrary: Harold Bloom—<hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse</hi>, p.
81—sees the Son as
                        “human desire” and the Father as “Desire removed
                        from all encumbrances.” The fact that Milton’s Satan is
                        Messiah from the biblical viewpoint and that Jesus acts “from
                        impulse. not from rules” (E42/K158) supports this view.</note>
	<note id="n61"><hi rend="s">39</hi> Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p.
                        548. For this aspect of the incarnate Jesus, cf. Jean H. Hagstrum,
                        “Christ’s Body,” in <hi rend="i">Essays in
                            honour of Keynes</hi>, pp. 129-56.</note>
	<note id="n62"><hi rend="s">40</hi> Margaret Bottrall, in <hi rend="i">The
                            Divine Image: A Study of Blake’s Interpretation of
                            Christianity</hi> (Rome: Edizioni di Storia e Letteratura, 1950), pp.
                        21-26, 89-90, and Kathleen Raine, in <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi>,
                        II, 235 and 313, n. 14, offer explanations of this vindictiveness.</note>
	<note id="n63"><hi rend="s">41</hi> Hazard Adams finds unresolved confusion
                        in this passage (<hi rend="i">Shorter Poems</hi>, p. 197). Cf. also
                        Raine, <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi>, II, 313-14. A few lines
                        earlier Jesus displays a wrath which might be thought more
                        characteristic of the Father; however it is not here contended that
                        Blake’s Father and Son embody precisely the qualities of
                        Boehme’s First and Second Principles, but that, like those
                        Principles, each is incomplete and therefore imperfect without the
                        other. For Jesus’ character in the poem, see Jean Hall,
                        “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Everlasting
                            Gospel</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 4 (1971),
                        61-72.</note>
	<note id="n64"><hi rend="s">42</hi> Sloss and Wallis observe—<hi rend="i">Prophetic Writings</hi>, I,
280-81—that
                        “Jesus is normally the Divine Humanity and not merely one of its
                        agents.” Harold Bloom notes—<hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse</hi>, p. 441, n.
6—that in
                        having all seven Eyes comprehended in Jesus, Blake is following a hint in
                        Revelation v.6. Cf. also Damon, <hi rend="i">Philosophy and Symbols</hi>, p.
                        368.</note></p>
        <p>Blake uses “the Names Divine / Of Jesus &amp; Jehovah”
                    (E266/K771) in two ways. Sometimes—as in the Prologue to <hi rend="i">The Gates of
Paradise</hi>, the <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi>, and
                    the second Job engraving—“Jehovah” denotes the
                    Father separated to a greater or lesser extent from the Son. More often, this
                    sacred name is reserved for the Divine Humanity, who can manifest as Father,
                    Son, or Holy Spirit, but in whom the Father and Son 
<figure n="BookofJob.p17.Tate.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="765" height="1000">
	<head>6 Blake, <hi rend="i">Illustrations for The Book of Job</hi> (1825),
                            plate 17.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Tate Gallery.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p15-20" n="20"/>
are contained. (Since the Holy Spirit, according to the
                    Western tradition, proceeds from the Father and the Son, there is no question of
                    its becoming cut off or incomplete.) It is Jehovah the Divine Humanity whose
                    Covenant is the forgiveness of sins,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65"
type="note">43</ref> whose
                    Spirit is the Divine Mercy,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66"
type="note">44</ref> whose visions
                    inspire the poet,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67"
type="note">45</ref> and who, as the Father,
                    “maketh his sun to rise on the evil and on the good, and sendeth rain
                    on the just and on the unjust.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68"
type="note">46</ref>
                    In the fragmentary illuminated manuscript of the early chapters of Genesis that
                    Blake prepared in his last years, he tries to distinguish the fierce, fallen
                    Elohim from the merciful Jehovah. He inserts each of these names once, and only
                    once, in the King James text, making the serpent promise Eve “ye shall
                    be as Gods (Elohim)” (iii.5) and making Eve acknowledge after
                    Cain’s birth, “I have gotten a man from Jehovah”
                    (iv.1). Jehovah also appears, standing opposite Christ, on both versions of the
                    title-page preceding the text, where the Holy Ghost strides over their heads
                    emphasizing the balance between them. However, some of the drawings (often
                    indistinct) which punctuate the text show the Elohim—the Father
                    separated from the Son and often accompanied by two angels—creating
                    first the universe and then, probably, Adam, from whom he splits off Eve. The
                    final sketch seems to depict Jehovah, the Divine Humanity, kissing the brow of
                    Cain, over whose birth He presided and on whom He now places, as
                    Blake’s chapter heading tells us, the mark of forgiveness.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69" type="note">47</ref>
	<note id="n65"><hi rend="s">43</hi><hi rend="i"> Jerusalem</hi> 61:24-25 and 98:23, 45 (E210, 255/K694-95,
745,
                        746); “The Everlasting Gospel,” prose (E792/K757); <hi rend="i">The Ghost of
Abel</hi> 2:22-24 (E270/K781).</note>
	<note id="n66"><hi rend="s">44</hi> Annotations to Wordsworth’s <hi rend="i">The Excursion</hi>,
E656/K784.</note>
	<note id="n67"><hi rend="s">45</hi> The subtitle and dedication of <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi>
(E268/K779).</note>
	<note id="n68"><hi rend="s">46</hi> Matthew v.45, alluded to in
                        Blake’s inscriptions on his illustrations to Dante
                        (E669/K785).</note>
	<note id="n69"><hi rend="s">47</hi> My statements are based on an examination of
                        the MS., which is in the Huntington Library, San Marino, Calif. For the
                        chapter headings, see E667/K933. The title-pages are reproduced as pls.
                        XXXII and XXXIII of Baker, <hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi>, and the two
                        following pages in <hi rend="i">Blake: An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 11
                        (Spring 1978), 242-43. For the balance between the Father and the Son, cf.
                        Piloo Nanavutty, “A Title-page in Blake’s Illustrated
                        Genesis Manuscript,” <hi rend="i">Journal of the Warburg and
                            Courtauld Institutes</hi>, 10 (1947), 114-22. See also Damon, 
<hi rend="i">Philosophy and Symbols</hi>, pp. 220-21, and <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi>, p. 151; John E. Grant,
rev. of <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> by Damon, <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi>, 45
                        (July 1966), 533-35; and n. 9 to Grant, “Envisioning the First <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi>,” in <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman
                        and John E. Grant (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1970),
                        304-35.</note></p>
        <p>Occasionally, as in “The Everlasting Gospel,” Blake employs the
                    name Jesus for the Son severed from the Father, but usually he indicates by it
                    the Divine Humanity, in whom all the Persons are in fact comprehended. Thus
                    Blake’s rendering of the Lord’s Prayer can begin
                    “Jesus our Father who art in thy Heavns call’d by thy Name
                    the Holy Ghost” (E658/K788), and in plate 3 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> he speaks of
“Jesus our Lord, who is the God of
                    Fire and Lord of Love” (E144/K621) showing that in this Jesus, as
                    Morton Paley observes, Boehme’s First and Second Principles
                        coalesce.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70" type="note">48</ref>
Marrying word and image,
                    Blake uses the quotations from John x and xiv in the lower margin of his
                    seventeenth illustration to Job to show that within the Father who appears in
                    this and the four preceding plates the Son also is present. In the Rosenwald
                    drawing of the Last Judgment (c. 1810), some of the divisions represented in 
<hi rend="i">The Fall of Man</hi> are healed: at the top of the design human
                    beings, as Blake tells us (E552/K613), are again in Paradise, and the Father is
                    reunited with the Son in the person of Jesus sitting on Jehovah’s
                        throne.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71" type="note">49</ref> In
conceiving the Godhead
                    thus, Blake is following Swedenborg, who condemned conventional Trinitarianism
                    as tritheistic and held that the three Persons were all present in Christ, whom
                    he regarded as the incarnation of Jehovah.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n72" type="note">50</ref>
	<note id="n70"><hi rend="s">48</hi><hi rend="i"> Energy and Imagination</hi>, pp. 257-58. Damon finds here
                        “the synthesis of Moses and Jesus” (<hi rend="i">Philosophy and Symbols</hi>, p.
434), while Jean H. Hagstrum contrasts
                        this combination of wrath and love with the division of wrath from pity on
                        pl. 54 of the poem (“‘The Wrath of the Lamb’:
                        A Study of William Blake’s Conversions,” in <hi rend="i">From Sensibility to
Romanticism: Essays Presented to Frederick A.
                            Pottle</hi>, ed. Frederick W. Hilles and Harold Bloom (New York: Oxford
                        University Press, 1965), pp. 311-30.</note>
	<note id="n71"><hi rend="s">49</hi> Reproduced Damon, <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi>, illus. I. Anne Mellor
makes the same observation about
                        the Jesus in the 1808 Petworth painting of the Last Judgment (<hi rend="i">Blake’s
Human Form Divine</hi>, p. 223). The device can be
                        traced back to the Pollok House version of 1806.</note>
	<note id="n72"><hi rend="s">50</hi> See, for example, <hi rend="i">The True
                            Christian Religion</hi>, 170, and <hi rend="i">The Doctrine of the New
                            Jerusalem Concerning the Lord</hi>, 30-31. J. G. Davies (<hi rend="i">Theology of
Blake</hi>, p. 37), Margaret Bottrall (<hi rend="i">Divine
                            Image</hi>, pp. 44-45), and Kathleen Raine (<hi rend="i">Blake and
                            Tradition</hi>, II, 202) make some of these points. Morton D.
                        Paley—“‘A New Heaven is Begun’:
                        William Blake and Swedenborgianism,” <hi rend="i">Blake: An
                            Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 13 (Fall 1979), 64-90—observes
                        that Blake’s interest in Swedenborg seems to have revived around
                        1800, which is about the time that he showed a renewed awareness of the
                        Trinity.</note></p>
        <p>Being a poet and artist, Blake thinks primarily in images and is less concerned
                    with strict consistency than is a philosopher. Nevertheless, when he is first
                    overwhelmed by the horrors of Experience he begins a long search for a coherent
                    solution to the problem of evil. Passing through non-dualism and a
                    quasi-Gnosticism, he reaches his final position about 1800. Confronted with an
                    apparent contradiction at the heart of this position, a grossly inconsistent use
                    of the name Jehovah, critics have tended to be evasive or perfunctory. However,
                    an investigation of the problem reveals that Blake develops a daring theology
                    rooted in Boehme to enable him to sustain with equal fervor a passionate
                    devotion to the Trinitarian God of Christianity and an unremitting protest
                    against the life-denying cruelty of the moral law and the created universe.</p>
        <pb id="p15-21-22" n="21-22" rend="hidden"/>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
