<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.1.worrall</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">The Marlborough College Production of The Ghost of Abel</title>
        <author n="Worrall">David Worrall</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <name>James Warwick</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Martin K. Nurmi</name>
              <name>Judith Page</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Henry Summerfield</name>
              <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-1-0008">
        <div2>
          <pb id="p15-56" n="56"/>
          <div3>
            <figure n="GhostOfAbel.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="393"></figure>
            <head>
              <title type="main"><hi rend="b">The Ghost of Abel</hi>, a play produced by
                                Marlborough College for the Edinburgh Festival Fringe. Directed by
                                Michael Davis. 25-30 August 1980.</title>
            </head>
            <byline>
              <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
              <docAuthor>
                <hi rend="b">David</hi>
                <name>
                  <hi rend="b">Worrall</hi>
                </name>
              </docAuthor>
            </byline>
            <p>From Aardvark to Z Theatre Company, in music, dance, mime and drama,
                            there were over 330 shows, including 180 premieres, on offer at the 1980
                            Edinburgh Festival Fringe. Listed in the Fringe program between a revue
                            called <hi rend="i">West Ham v. Hearts</hi> and a play named <hi rend="i">The
Human Puppet Theatre</hi>, the eye was arrested by the
                            detail that Marlborough College’s production of
                            Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi> would be playing
                            three shows a day during the second week of the Festival, sponsored by
                            the prestigious and enterprising Richard Demarco Gallery.</p>
            <p>The Edinburgh Fringe is a unique jewel in the cultural life of Britain.
                            For three weeks in late summer a bewildering mixture of professional and
                            amateur groups from both sides of the Atlantic compete to fill
                            excruciatingly uncomfortable seats hastily installed in countless church
                            halls, schools, <pb id="p15-57" n="57"/>
youth centers, at least one
                            enlightened nightclub, the odd marquee and perhaps even a few
                            “legitimate” theatres. Audiences can be tiny even at
                            the very low prices charged and Fringegoers can be as choosy as they
                            please. If Prickly Heat University’s production of
                            Genet’s juvenilia proves to be less than definitive, it can
                            be consoling to know that Add Hock Th. Co. will be opening at the other
                            end of the street in ten minutes’ time.</p>
            <p>Not that more philosophical tastes are neglected. <hi rend="i">The Ghost
                                of Abel</hi>, produced by one of Britain’s leading
                            independent schools, under the direction of Michael Davis, proved an
                            engaging and demanding event that crammed much into its half-hour
                            playing time. Rather than leaving Blake crying in the wilderness to a
                            passing audience perhaps unfamiliar with English romanticism (or even
                            Cain and Abel), it had been decided to present Blake’s drama
                            as the last statement in a gradually unfolding Christian myth beginning
                            with Genesis 4 and then proceeding to <hi rend="i">The Ghost of
                                Abel</hi> via extracts from Coleridge’s <hi rend="i">The
                                Wanderings of Cain</hi> and Byron’s <hi rend="i">Cain: A
                                Mystery.</hi></p>
            <p>Marlborough College was not the only company operating from St.
                            Francis’ Hall, and its show was sandwiched between two other
                            groups performing almost immediately before and after. Such a quick
                            change around must have been difficult for everyone. A church-hall
                            accommodating a succession of performances cannot offer much in the way
                            of normal theatrical facilities and Michael Davis was wise to opt for
                            simple uniform of jeans and kaftans for his cast.</p>
            <p>The play began with a semi-ritualistic enactment of the Cain and Abel
                            section of Genesis with each verse spoken by a different actor. In this
                            scene, and at times throughout the play, a seated chorus of onlookers
                            was used to good effect in echoing the stylized facial and grouping
                            characteristics of the Job designs. Indeed, one could have wished that
                            the nettle of the language of stylized gesture had been grasped more
                            firmly and confidently by the company, because it is a mode of
                            expression that seems particularly well suited to swiftly moving
                            epigrammatic language.</p>
            <p>Coleridge’s <hi rend="i">The Wanderings of Cain</hi> does not
                            adapt easily to the stage, even in abridgement, but Cain’s
                            subtle edging towards repentance is quite close to Blake’s
                            lines on the forgiveness of sins which concluded this episode.
                            Furthermore, the Coleridge piece was dramatically relevant because it
                            introduces Abel’s ghost, which is not present in
                            Byron’s play. Byron’s <hi rend="i">Cain: A
                                Mystery</hi> was a successful third movement not merely because it
                            directly gave rise to <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi> but also
                            because it contains promisingly dramatic writing. Adam’s
                            “Eve! let not his, / Thy natural grief, lead to
                            impiety” sounded eminently mealy-mouthed in contrast to
                            Eve’s almost shrewish “His will! . . . . May all the
                            curses / Of life be on him!” These are appropriate colleagues
                            for Los and Enitharmon in their weaker moments and suitable precursors
                            for elements in Blake’s Adam and Eve. The skillfully cut <hi rend="i">Cain: A
Mystery</hi> ended with Cain in painful
                            self-knowledge addressing Abel’s corpse and providing a cue
                            for <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi>: “Now for the
                            wilderness!”</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi> was heralded by choice Blake epigrams
                            and part of the preface to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> The slightly
                            augmented title, “A Revelation In The Vision of Elohim Jehovah
                            Seen by William Blake, Dedicated to Lord Byron in the
                            Wilderness,” made a convincingly firm curtain opener and even
                            Blake’s “stage” directions sounded well. In
                            this strenuous evening one was driving four-handed with the Bible,
                            Coleridge, Byron and Blake, but the easy syntax of <hi rend="i">The
                                Ghost of Abel</hi> came across with exceptional clarity, as did the
                            movements of the actors. A line of standing figures became first a grave
                            and then a row of flames from which Satan emerged. One caught fleeting
                            echoes of the illuminated books in the stances and positions of the
                            players.</p>
            <p>Marlborough College ended by following Blake’s invitation to
                            “Sing,” and it was here that I had my only
                            reservations. Blake’s “Peace, Brotherhood and
                            Love” has a grand simplicity of message that makes it suitable
                            for the refrain of a song, as Michael Davis correctly recognized, but
                            one felt that they too easily translated it into a Sixties-type pop
                            culture hymn. However, this may have been a sensible arrangement for a
                            cast in its mid-teens and without benefit of musical accompaniment.</p>
            <p>Was this a successful theatrical experiment? The answer must be yes. The
                            Bible stories are the stuff of the oldest traditions of English drama
                            and seeing Coleridge’s, Byron’s and
                            Blake’s interpretations of the same story together in the
                            space of half an hour was a valuable experience. The virtue of Michael
                            Davis’ production was that it set all three in vivid context.
                            One may now ask others with bigger and better resources to try and do
                            likewise in this surprising and largely untrodden area of
                            romanticism.</p>
            <figure n="GhostofAbelplay.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="287"></figure>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
