<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.1.paley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">A Victorian Blake Facsimile</title>
        <author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <name>James Warwick</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Martin K. Nurmi</name>
              <name>Judith Page</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Henry Summerfield</name>
              <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
      <pb id="p15-24" n="24"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-1-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">A VICTORIAN BLAKE FACSIMILE</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">MORTON D.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">PALEY</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p><hi rend="i">Works of William Blake</hi>, bearing no publisher’s
                    imprint and dated 1876 on its title page, has posed a minor conundrum in Blake
                    scholarship. The title page announces it as “Reproduced in Facsimile
                    From the Original Editions. One hundred copies printed For private
                    circulation.” It is a facsimile of very poor quality, yet it made
                    available for the first time complete reproductions of <hi rend="i">Songs of
                        Innocence and of Experience, The Book of Thel, Visions of the Daughters of
                        Albion, America, Europe, The Book of Urizen</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Song
                        of Los.</hi> These were not to appear in facsimile again until William
                    Muir’s considerably better productions of 1884-90.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73" type="note">1</ref> Thus <hi rend="i">Works</hi> has some historical
                    importance as a pioneering albeit seriously flawed project, but the
                    circumstances of its publication have never been made clear up to now. In the
                    Keynes <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi> it is assigned to the publisher F. S.
                        Ellis,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">2</ref> while
the Bentley <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> gives no publisher for <hi rend="i">Works</hi> under the
                    main entry and assigns the facsimiles to John Pearson in individual entries for
                    each illuminated book.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75"
type="note">3</ref> In “A
                    Supplement to <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>” (<hi rend="i">Blake/An
                        Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 11 [1977-78], 148), Professor Bentley suggests
                    that “The sponsor, who is not identified in the book, may be Andrew
                    Chatto.” It now can be shown that the publisher was definitely Chatto
                    and Windus, that the actual date of publication was 1878, and that <hi rend="i">Works</hi>
was probably the abortive result of an ambitious plan for a
                    complete Blake facsimile originally conceived by John Camden Hotten. 
<note id="n73"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi rend="i"> The Edition of the Works of William Blake</hi> (Edmonton: The
                        Blake Press).</note>
	<note id="n74"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">A Bibliography
                            of William Blake</hi> (New York: Grolier Club, 1921), pp. 293-94.</note>
	<note id="n75"><hi rend="s">3</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Books</hi> (Oxford: The Clarendon Press, 1977), pp. 501, 102, 159, 126,
                        181, 426, 473. Professor Bentley now agrees that <hi rend="i">Works</hi>
                        should be attributed to Chatto and Windus and the 1877 <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> to
John Pearson, and has kindly given me the benefit of
                        his criticism in the preparation of this note. I am also indebted to
                        Professor Robert N. Essick for invaluable information.</note></p>
        <p>In 1868 John Camden Hotten published the first complete facsimile of one of
                    Blake’s illuminated books, <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
                        Hell.</hi> As I have shown elsewhere, this was intended as the first volume
                    in a series which Hotten announced as “facsimile copies (exact as to
                    paper, printing—the water-colour drawings being filled in by an
                    artist) of the ORIGINAL EDITIONS of the books written and illustrated by William
                        Blake.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76" type="note">4</ref>
This plan was
                    evidently set back by the sudden death in 1868 of Hotten’s artist,
                    Henry John Bellars. It appears that Hotten had difficulty in finding another
                    facsimilist of Bellars’ skill, for on 8 September 1870 Hotten wrote
                    to the printers Banks &amp; Co.: “I may ask if you have an artist
                    who can successfully reduce Cruikshank’s etchings &amp; draw on
                    stone (or engrave), the printing to be done in colours like the plates to <hi rend="i">Tom
and Jerry.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77" type="note">5</ref>
                    When Hotten died in 1873 at the age of forty, no further Blake facsimiles had
                    been issued. <note id="n76"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See my article “John
                        Camden Hotten, A. C. Swinburne, and the Blake Facsimiles of 1868,”
                            <hi rend="i">Bulletin</hi> of the New York Public Library, 79 (1976),
                        259-96. The quotation is from an excerpt from a sale catalogue in a copy of
                        the Hotten <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> facsimile in the collection of Robert
                        N. Essick.</note>
	<note id="n77"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Quotations from the letters of John Camden
                        Hotten and of Andrew Chatto are from the copies in the Letter Books of
                        Chatto and Windus, to whom I am grateful for permission to use
                    them.</note></p>
        <p>After Hotten’s death, a chestful of drawings after Blake, some of
                    which may have been studies by Bellars for the projected facsimile, was found in
                    Hotten’s cellar. These drawings were bought by the New York dealer J.
                    W. Bouton and offered for sale as genuine Blakes, laying the ground for the
                    story of the “John Camden Hotten forgeries.” Meanwhile
                    Hotten’s business was acquired by his former publishing associate
                    Andrew Chatto, who was joined in partnership by W. E. Windus. The plan for an
                    extensive Blake facsimile was not abandoned, and in the following year
                    considerable progress was made on it. On 17 September 1874 Chatto wrote to
                    William Michael Rossetti, who had assisted Hotten with his Blake projects: 
					<q>
                        Dear Sir<lb/>
<lb/>
 I send herewith sample proofs of facsimiles of six more
                        of W<hi rend="s">m</hi> Blake’s works. When carefully coloured by
                        hand they will look wonderfully like the originals<lb/>
<lb/>
 Printed on
                        paper the present size the whole of Blakes works might be contained in 2
                        volumes, but I think it will be desirable to strike off a few copies to be
                        sold separately on paper the approximate size of the originals.<lb/>
 Yours
                        very faithfully,<lb/>
 Andrew Chatto </q>
Chatto must have found, however,
          that the time required was longer than had been anticipated, for 
<pb id="p15-25" n="25"/>
<figure n="America.p13.1876Works.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="704" height="1000">
	<head>1 <hi rend="i">America</hi>, plate 13.</head>
	<figDesc>From 1876 <hi rend="i">Works.</hi> By permission of The Huntington
                            Library, San Marino, California.</figDesc>
</figure> his ledger shows that on 17 November 1877, he ordered one hundred sets
                    of “Blake reproductions” to be printed by Banks and that on 26
                    January 1878, 103 printed sets were dispatched to the binder Sotheran.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78" type="note">6</ref> That this was a lithographic reproduction
                    in indicated by the ledger notation “Illustrations: / Stone Bonds <hi rend="i">rubbed
off.</hi>” (Possibly the lithographic stones had
                    previously been used for printing bonds. The word could equally be
                    “bands,” but this makes no sense). The costs were
                    £100—a surprisingly large sum, especially in view of the poor
                    quality of the work—paid to an unnamed artist, £37/10 for
                    printing and £21 for binding. The disposition of stock is not indicated, an
                    unusual feature in these meticulously kept ledger books. 
<note id="n78"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Ledger 3, p. 185. The Huntington Library copy of <hi rend="i">Works</hi> bears the stamp of
the binder Bone, who also worked
                        extensively for Hotten and for Chatto. It may be that Sotheran farmed out
                        some of the binding to Bone.</note></p>
        <p>In their list for 1877, Chatto and Windus advertised the facsimile as follows: 
		<q><hi
rend="i">Blake’s Works</hi><lb/>
<lb/>
 A series of
                        Reproductions in Facsimile of the Works of William Blake, including the
                        “Songs of Innocence and Experience” [sic], “The
                        Book of Thel,” “America,” “The Vision of
                        the Daughters of Albion,” [sic] “The Marriage of Heaven
                        and Hell,” “Europe, a Prophecy,”
                        “Jerusalem,” “Milton,”
                        “Urizen,” “the Song of Los,”
                        &amp;c. [<hi rend="i">in preparation</hi>]<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n79" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n79"><hi rend="s">7</hi> From an unpaginated list appended to <hi rend="i">Choice Humourous
Works</hi> by Mark Twain (London: Chatto
                            and Windus, 1877).</note></q>
This is a considerably broader list of titles than
was actually published:
                    the inclusion of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> would
                    have almost doubled the number of pages, necessitating the two volume
                    publication that Chatto had envisaged in 1874. The actual contents are correctly
                    indicated, though there are some mistakes as to titles and dates of publication,
                    in J. W. Bouton’s catalogue no. 56 (undated, but probably published
                    c. 1881): 
					<q> Works of <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi><lb/>
<lb/>
 A reproduction
                        of the Original issues of the works of this remarkable Artist, comprising
                        “Songs of Innocence and Experience,” 55 leaves (1789);
                        “Book of Thel,” 8 leaves, 1789; “America, a
                        Prophecy,” 18 leaves, 1793; “The First Book of
                        Urizen,” 26 leaves, 1794; “The Song of Los,” 8
                        leaves (1794). Carefully printed on heavy plate paper in the original
                        colors. 1 vol. folio, <hi rend="i">hf. roxb., morocco, gilt top, uncut.</hi>
                        $22.50.<lb/>
<lb/>
*⁎*“One hundred copies printed for private
                        circulation”<lb/>
 Reprinted in facsimile from the excessively rare
                        Original Editions. 1789-94. Printed on one side only.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n80"><hi rend="s">8</hi> The readings should of course be
                            “Songs of Innocence and <hi rend="i">of</hi>
                            Experience” and “Visions of the Daughters of
                            Albion.” The latter was published in 1793, not 1789; <hi rend="i">The Book of
Thel</hi> bears the publication date 1789 and
                            not 1794; and <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> was published in 1795
                            not 1794. For some reason <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>, the sole
                            known copy of which had been sold to the British Museum in 1866, was not
                            part of the plan. Neither was <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, the
                            sole known copy of which was then in the collection of Lord Houghton.
                            The first facsimiles of these two books were published by E. J. Ellis
                            and W. B. Yeats in volume III of <hi rend="i">The Works of William
                                Blake, Poetic, Symbolic and Critical</hi> (London: B. Quaritch,
                            1893).</note></q>
Apparently the advertisement was issued before Bouton had seen a
copy of
                        <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, since the facsimile is <hi rend="i">not</hi>
                    “in the original colors,” though Chatto had intended that it
                    be. When Bouton advertised <hi rend="i">Works of William Blake</hi> in his
                    catalogue 63 (c. 1885), the wording was almost identical with that of catalogue
                    56, but mention of color was omitted.</p>
        <p>With this information in mind, we are in a position to reconstruct the
                    circumstances leading to the publication of <hi rend="i">Works.</hi> The
                    facsimile scheme was initiated by John Camden Hotten and taken over after
                    Hotten’s death by his successor Andrew Chatto. Some proofs were ready
                    in September 1874. Publication was anticipated for 1876, for a letterpress title
                    page bearing that date was printed. (The absence of a publisher’s
                    imprint is not inconsistent with the practice of the time: neither
                    Hotten’s 1868 <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> nor Pearson’s
                    1877 <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> bears one.) The plan was to issue a
                    hand-colored facsimile, and some colored proofs may have been prepared, but
                    possibly owing to the poor quality of the facsimile work, the book was issued
                    uncolored and reduced in its scope. <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
                        Hell</hi>, still available in Hotten’s edition, was left out, and
                    so were Blake’s two longest illuminated books, <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> The collection was published
                    in a single volume in 1878.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Works by William Blake</hi> comprises facsimiles of six of
                    Blake’s illuminated works, as follows:</p>
        <p>1. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, 55 leaves 
<pb id="p15-26" n="26"/>
<figure n="FreehandDetail.p18.F.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="956" height="1000">
	<head>3 Freehand drawing of an enlarged detail from plate 18, copy F.</head>
	<figDesc>In the original the cloth is colored pink.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="Europe.p17.1876Works.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="722" height="1000">
	<head>2 <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, plate 17.</head>
	<figDesc>From 1876 <hi rend="i">Works</hi> (where it is numbered 15). By
                            permission of the Huntington Library, San Marino, California.</figDesc>
</figure> (including the rejected “A Divine Image”). The
                    foliation corresponds to that of no known original copy: no <hi rend="i">Songs
                        of Innocence</hi> ends in “Laughing Song,” and in <hi rend="i">Works</hi> the
“Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> comes not at the beginning but after seventeen
                    other poems! The inclusion of “A Divine Image,” makes it
                    likely that the original used was, as Bentley (<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p.
                    426) suggests, copy a, which had been sold to the British Museum by B. M.
                    Pickering in 1864. “Laughing Song,” missing from copy a, could
                    have been supplied from copy T, in the British Museum since 1856. However, Dr.
                    David Bindman informs me that copy BB, recently sold in London, also contains
                    “A Divine Image.” This copy must therefore be considered an
                    alternative source. Its location was unknown from 1830 on.</p>
        <p>2. <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, 8 leaves. Copy D, in the British Museum
                    Print Room since 1856, had already been used for the reproduction of the 
<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> title page in A. C. Swinburne’s <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, published by Hotten in
1868. Presumably copy D was also
                    used for <hi rend="i">Works.</hi></p>
        <p>3. <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, 11 leaves. Two copies, A
                    and B, were in the British Museum Print Room. Presumably one of these was used.
                    According to Bentley (<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 473), it was B.</p>
        <p>4. <hi rend="i">America</hi>, 18 leaves. The clue to identification here is the
                    number of tails on the serpent in plate 13. In the various original copies, the
                    serpent has either three tails or one. The serpent of <hi rend="i">Works</hi>
                    has three, and so must derive from one of the following copies: E, F, G, I, K,
                    or L. Bentley (<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 102) suggests that copy F,
                    acquired by the British Museum in 1859, was the one used.</p>
        <p>5. <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, 17 leaves. In <hi rend="i">Works</hi> the
                    “Ancient of Days” frontispiece is placed after the title page
                    by mistake. Page 3, found only in copies H and K, is not present. A very likely
                    source is copy D (as Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 181, suggests);
                    this had also been acquired by the British Museum in 1859. There is, however,
                    one other possibility—copy F. In plate 18 (numbered 15 in <hi rend="i">Works</hi>) of
the facsimile a garment obscures the penis of the
                    male figure. This may well be a concession to Victorian prudery, but it may be
                    significant that the penis is similarly obscured in copy F. (Owing to the
                    fragility of the original, it has not been possible to obtain a 
<pb id="p15-27" n="27"/>
photograph, but I have made a freehand drawing of this detail.) In
                    the other copies, the male figure is nude, though as Bentley (<hi rend="i">Blake
                        Books</hi>, p. 156) notes, “In copy D there are lines on the
                    man’s left hip as if to represent cloth, but the cloth is not
                    colored.” Copy F was acquired in 1866 by B. M. Pickering. Pickering
                    later sold it to an unknown collector whose monogram was D W J. It is now in the
                    Berg Collection of the New York Public Library.</p>
        <p>As we have seen, it is virtually certain that the records in the Chatto and
                    Windus ledger entry headed “Blake reproductions” refer to the
                    “1876” <hi rend="i">Works.</hi> One other hypothesis
                    concerning these records should be mentioned here. <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>
                    assigns the facsimile of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> hitherto attributed to John
                    Pearson to Chatto and Windus on the basis of this same ledger entry.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81" type="note">9</ref> However, it seems incontrovertible that
                    John Pearson did in fact produce the photolithographic black-and-white facsimile
                    of copy D of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in 1877. Two reliable sources indicate
                    this. John Muir, in a prospectus included with his facsimile of <hi rend="i">The
                        Song of Los</hi> (1890), asserts that he has not published a 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> because Pearson has already done so. As Pearson acted as the
                    distributor of Muir’s first four Blake facsimiles in 1884,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82" type="note">10</ref> Muir was surely in a position to know who
          had published <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in 1877. Furthermore, E. W. 
<figure n="WilliamMuir.ad.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="694" height="1000">
	<head>4 William Muir’s advertisement for <hi rend="i">The Edition
                                of the Works of William Blake.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>By permission of the Library of Congress.</figDesc>
</figure> Hooper, who bought Pearson’s original copy (now in the
                    Harvard University Library), wrote: “Blake’s
                    ‘Jerusalem’ was reproduced by John Pearson, book-seller of
                    London. A Copy of this reproduction is in the Boston Public Library. I have
                    compared the reproduction carefully page by page with my original hand tinted
                    copy (which I bought from John Pearson) &amp; find it was taken from my
                        copy.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83" type="note">11</ref>
There was no reason
                    for Pearson, a reputable dealer and collector with a special interest in
                        Blake,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84" type="note">12</ref> to
misrepresent the origin of
                    the <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> facsimile. It should therefore be restored to
                    his credit as publisher, and the Chatto and Windus ledger entry must be taken to
                    refer to the “1876” <hi rend="i">Works.</hi>
	<note id="n81"><hi rend="s">9</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Books</hi>, p. 264. Professor Bentley agrees that this
                        hypothesis should now be withdrawn, and in “A Supplement to <hi rend="i">Blake
Books</hi>,<supplied type="emend">”</supplied> p. 148, he identifies Pearson as the
                        publisher.</note>
	<note id="n82"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Pearson issued a prospectus in that year,
                        but after Pearson’s retirement from business in 1885, Bernard
                        Quaritch became Muir’s agent.</note>
	<note id="n83"><hi rend="s">11</hi> From a note by Hooper on a card accompanying
                        copy D of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in the Harvard University
                        Library.</note>
	<note id="n84"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Pearson owned the former Flaxman copy of <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence</hi>, copy D, from which Muir’s
                        facsimile was produced in 1884. He also owned a copy of <hi rend="i">Poetical
Sketches</hi> and a rather dubious-sounding water color showing
                        “a number of Nude figures being led captive by a Devil, and others
                        following; the great head of a marine monster, in the mouth of which are
                        several figures, etc.”—<hi rend="i">Catalogue of the
                            Valuable and Interesting Library formed during the past 40 years by Mr.
                            John Pearson (Sold in consequence of declining health). The Third
                            Portion. Sotheby, Wilkinson, and Hodge. Tues. 7 Nov. 1916 and following
                            Day</hi> (nos. 40, 41, 42).</note></p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
