<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.1.essick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">New Information on Blake’s Illuminated Books</title>
        <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <name>James Warwick</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Martin K. Nurmi</name>
              <name>Judith Page</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Henry Summerfield</name>
              <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
      <pb id="p15-4" n="4"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-1-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">NEW INFORMATION ON BLAKE’S ILLUMINATED BOOKS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">ROBERT N.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">ESSICK</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>One of the special pleasures of studying William Blake’s prints is the
                    way new treasures keep turning up.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n0"
type="note">*</ref>
	<note id="n0">EDITORS’ NOTE: COPY h OF THE
                        SONGS OF INNOCENCE AND OF EXPERIENCE HAS RECENTLY RE-EMERGED. FOR MORE
                        INFORMATION SEE THE NEWS SECTION OF THIS ISSUE.</note> The following is a brief report
on several of
                    his illuminated books and single leaves therefrom that have come to light in
                    recent months, supplemented by a discussion of some previously recorded
                    impressions with unusual characteristics deserving more attention than they have
                    received in the past.</p>
        <p>On 13 January 1830, Sotheby’s in London offered at auction a small
                    volume listed in the catalogue as lot 41 and described as
                    “Blake’s Phantasies, Songs of Innocence and of Experience,
                    on 55 PLATES, <hi rend="i">brown calf, elegant, very rare.</hi>”
                    According to an annotated copy of the catalogue in the British Museum Print
                    Room, the vendor was Robert Balmanno (1780-1865), the great Stothard collector
                    who apparently also owned copy U of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and
                    other works by Blake. Lot 41 was sold to “Glynn” for the
                    munificent sum of one pound. Nothing further was known of this volume to either
                    Keynes and Wolf in 1953 or Bentley in 1977, in whose bibliographies it is listed
                    as untraced copy BB of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                        Experience.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1"
type="note">1</ref> After an absence of 150
                    years, the book reappeared to public view in the spring of 1980 and was offered
                    at auction once again at Sotheby’s, this time in their
                    Hodgson’s Rooms on Chancery Lane, on 1 May 1980, as lot 100.
                    According to a pencil note on the title-page, the volume was “Bought of
                    Blake May 1816,” probably by Balmanno or someone acting for him. The
                    auction catalogue further indicates that, after Glynn’s purchase in
                    1830, the book passed to John Wild, whose initials are written “over
                    the small partly erased library stamp in the lower margin of the general title,
                    and who inserted his bookplate.” Wild’s library passed to
                    his cousin and the book remained in the cousin’s family until its
                    sale from “The Property of a Lady” on 1 May. The volume
                    fetched £16,000 from Andrew Edmunds, the London printdealer, who sold it
                    shortly after the auction to the Oxfordshire bookdealer Colin Franklin. He sold
                    it by August 1980 to the New York bookdealer Justin G. Schiller, in whose
                    private collection the volume now resides. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi>
                        Geoffrey Keynes and Edwin Wolf 2nd, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
                            Illuminated Books: A Census</hi> (New York: Grolier Club, 1953), p. 66;
                        G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press,
                        1977), p. 425. All plate number and copy designations in this essay follow
                            <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi> See also Bentley, “A Supplement
                        to <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake: An
                            Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 11 (Winter 1977-78), 138-44.</note></p>
        <p>I have not seen this copy of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                        Experience</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref> but its extraordinary
                    importance deserves preliminary notice in this journal. The information
                    presented here is based on the auction catalogue and descriptions of the book
                    supplied by Donald Heald, who inspected the book for me prior to the auction,
                    and Andrew Edmunds. There can be no doubt that the volume now owned by Mr.
                    Schiller is copy BB. It is bound in early nineteenth-century brown calf, the
                    spine elaborately decorated in gilt tooling and stamped
                    “Blake’s Phantasies.” These features explain the
                    description of the binding and odd title given the book in the 1830 auction
                    catalogue. At the inner margin of the general title-page are fragments of blue
                    paper—probably remnants of the original wrapper in which Blake or
                    Mrs. Blake bound the book. The 55 plates (the usual 54 plus pl. b, “A
                    Divine Image”) on 55 leaves are printed in black ink with the delicacy
                    and maculated textures typical of Blake’s inking. The leaves (wove
                    paper, apparently without watermark) measure about 18.3 × 11.8 cm.
                    Many plates contain thinly inked areas that have been carefully painted over in
                    black, perhaps diluted India ink. This hand work suggests that the 
<pb id="p15-5" n="5"/>
book was not simply left uncolored but was specifically
                    prepared for sale as a copy in black. Three plates, however, have some hand
                    coloring (see illus. 1). Unlike the black tinting in thinly printed relief
                    areas, the light washes in etched whites on these plates are not applied with
                    much skill and may have been added by someone other than Blake. The plates are
                    numbered consecutively in gray ink just above the upper right corner. The form
                    of these numbers is very similar to those in copy T of <hi rend="i">Songs of
                        Innocence and of Experience</hi>; they were in all probability written by
                    Blake. <note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Mr. Schiller tells me, in a letter of 7
                        July 1980, that exclusive rights to inspect and describe the volume have
                        been granted to one individual (not me) until August 1982. There is,
                        however, a brief report, without reproductions from copy BB, by Sir Geoffrey
                        Keynes in <hi rend="i">The Book Collector</hi>, 30 (Spring 1980), 39-42. Sir
                        Geoffrey records the following sequence for the plates: 1-4, 6-7, 11, 25,
                        18, 19, 15, 16-17, 22-23, 20-21, 9-10, 12, 8, 27, 24, 5, 13, 14, 26, 54,
                        28-33, b, 38, 46, 51, 45, 47, 41, 39, 52, 43, 53, 37, 50, 42, 44, 49, 34-36,
                        40, 48. The plate offsets correspond to this sequence.</note></p>
        <p>Blake generally issued complete copies of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> in 54
                    plates. Only three early copies (B-D) contain the tailpiece (pl. a) without
                    text, and these lack “To Tirzah.” Before the rediscovery of
                    copy BB, “A Divine Image” (pl. b) was known only through the
                    posthumous impressions in copies a, c, and n of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and
                    a loose impression in Sir Geoffrey Keynes’ collection.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> The impression of “A Divine
                    Image” (illus. 2) in copy BB is thus of considerable importance. It is
                    the only impression undoubtedly printed by Blake and included by him in a copy
                    of the <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi> It is also significant that the poem is included
                    as plate 35 in the volume, and thus is an integral part of the book rather than
                    a supplementary plate at the end. The presence of “A Divine
                    Image” <figure n="Shepherd.Songsie.BB.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="655">
	<head>1 “The Shepherd” from <hi rend="i">Songs of
                                Innocence and of Experience</hi> copy BB.</head>
	<figDesc>Relief etching, 11.1 × 6.9 cm., partly hand tinted.
                            Photograph courtesy of Sotheby Parke Bernet &amp; Co.; reproduced
                            with their permission.</figDesc>
</figure> makes copy BB the most complete copy known of <hi rend="i">Songs of
                        Innocence and of Experience</hi> printed by Blake, lacking only the early,
                    rejected tailpiece but including complete texts of all the poems of the
                    anthology. It certainly deserves more thorough bibliographic and chalcographic
                    study than the cursory description given here. <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi>
                        The Keynes impression, reproduced as pl. 3 in the Keynes and Wolf 
<hi rend="i">Census</hi>, is in gray with the upper border surrounding the
                        text wiped free of ink (except for residual smudges). Such cleaning of the
                        borders is typical of Blake’s pre-1800 impressions of relief
                        etchings, but is also found in a few posthumous impressions. This impression
                        is poorly printed, but it may be an early working proof pulled by
                        Blake.</note></p>
        <p>Posthumous impressions of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>
                    are far less beautiful and interesting than copies printed by Blake.
                    Nevertheless, they were printed from the original copperplates and thus deserve
                    description and study. A previously unrecorded 
<figure n="DivineImage.Songsie.BB.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="654">
	<head>2 “A Divine Image” from <hi rend="i">Songs of
                                Innocence and of Experience</hi> copy BB.</head>
	<figDesc>Relief etching, 11.2 × 7 cm., partly hand tinted in
                            black. Photograph courtesy of Sotheby Parke Bernet &amp; Co.;
                            reproduced with their permission.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p15-6" n="6"/>
            <figure n="Europe.c.p4.secondproofstate.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="686">
	<head>3 <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, copy c, pl. 4.</head>
	<figDesc>Relief and white-line etching, second (proof) state, 23.6
                            × 17.1 cm. Achenbach Foundation for Graphic Arts, San
                            Francisco.</figDesc>
</figure> posthumous copy has been acquired recently by the astute collector Mr.
                    Arthur E. Vershbow of Boston.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
type="note">4</ref> The volume
                    consists of 42 leaves of white wove paper, 18.3 × 12.6 cm., bearing
                    on their rectos only pls. 1-14, 16-29, 33-36, 38-43, 46, 49, 52, and 53 of the
                        <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> in that order. These are printed in dark gray ink
                    and bound in full green morocco, covers tooled in gilt and blind, raised bands
                    with gilt <hi rend="i">fleur-de-lis</hi> design on the spine, stamped in gilt on
                    the spine BLAKE. | [rule] | SONGS | OF | INNOCENCE | &amp; | EXPERIENCE.
                    The front endpapers are marbled, followed by a blank fly-leaf showing a foolscap
                    watermark. The same binding papers are repeated at the end, except that the
                    blank fly-leaf is without watermark. The plates are numbered consecutively in
                    pencil, top right. As in other posthumous copies, most of the plates are heavily
                    inked and printed, although the borders of some are very lightly inked. The
                    white-line work on the title-page to <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> is badly
                    clogged with ink; the frontispiece to <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> and
                    “The Lamb” contain some foul inking of etched whites. The
                    first plate of “The Ecchoing Green” is very heavily inked, the
                    second rather lightly inked. That this is a posthumous copy is confirmed by the
                    fact that it is printed on J WHATMAN 1831 and 1832 paper, as indicated by the
                    following watermark fragments: 
					<q> leaf 7: TMAN | 31<lb/>
 leaf 10: J WHA | 18<lb/>
                        <figure n="Europe.c.p9.thirdpublishedstate.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="681">
	<head>4 <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, copy c, pl. 9.</head>
	<figDesc>Relief and white-line etching, third (published) state, 23.7
                                × 17.1 cm. Achenbach Foundation for Graphic Arts, San
                                Francisco.</figDesc>
</figure> leaf 30: TMAN | 31<lb/>
 leaf 34: ATMAN | 32 </q>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> The Vershbow collection also includes a copy
                        of the 1813 quarto edition of Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The
                            Grave</hi> with Schiavonetti’s plates after
                        Blake’s designs hand colored. A recent acquisition is
                        Blake’s original pencil and wash drawing for the fourth wood
                        engraving (young shepherd left, old shepherd right, figure with a staff
                        running to the right in the background) in Thornton’s edition of
                            <hi rend="i">The Pastorals of Virgil</hi>, 1821. This drawing, formerly
                        in the collection of Mrs. Mathew Baird, is reproduced in Geoffrey Keynes,
                        ed., <hi rend="i">Pencil Drawings by William Blake</hi> (London: Nonesuch
                        Press, 1927), pl. 50 no. 3. I am indebted to Mr. Vershbow for allowing me
                        access to, and permission to describe works in, his collection.</note></p>
        <p>This volume was acquired at an unknown time, probably in the 1920s, by Mrs.
                    George Madison (Alice) Millard of Pasadena, California. A note by her describing
                    the book is still preserved with it. Mrs. Millard, the proprietor of the Little
                    Museum of La Miniatura through which also passed copy N of <hi rend="i">Songs of
                        Innocence</hi>, sold the book for $100 to Mrs. John Hudson Poole (nee
                    Caroline Boing) of Pasadena, who died in 1931. It passed by inheritance to her
                    husband, in whose house the book remained until his death in 1955 when his book
                    collection was packed and stored by his heirs. They placed the Blake
                        collection<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> for
sale with the San
                    Francisco bookdealer Bernard Rosenthal, who sold the posthumous copy of the 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> to Mr. Vershbow late in 1979.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> The collection included standard items, such
                        as reference works, a copy of Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>
                        (1808), and a set of the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engravings, but nothing else
                        of importance.</note>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> I previously noted this sale, and incorrectly
                        described the volume as containing 43 plates, in “Blake in the
                        Marketplace 1978-1979,” <hi rend="i">Blake: An Illustrated
                            Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 7.</note></p>
        <p>In the mid-nineteenth ce * ry, George A. Smith collected and bound together a
                    large, miscellaneous group of plates from Blake’s illuminated books,
                    some separate plates, the manuscript “Order” of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, and the
                    manuscript of Allan Cunningham’s
                    Life of Blake. The contents and complex history of this collection are spelled
                    out in Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, pp. 337-41. Three plates from
                    this group, untraced since their sale from George C. Smith’s
                    collection at Parke Bernet, New York, on 2 November 1938, have now surfaced in
                    public collections.</p>
        <pb id="p15-7" n="7"/>
          <figure n="Europe.c.p15.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="656">
          <head>5 <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, copy c, pl. 15.</head>
          <figDesc>Relief etching, partly color printed, 23.4 × 17.2 cm.
                        Houghton Library, Harvard University.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <p>Lot 30 in the 1938 auction, containing five plates from <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
                    copy c, was sold to the dealer Gannon for $140. <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>,
                    p. 341, records that three of these are now at New York University and that the
                    remaining two, pls. 4 and 9, are untraced. These plates, printed on the recto
                    and verso of a single sheet, were acquired by T. E. Hanley, whose widow, Tullah
                    Hanley, gave them in recent years to the Achenbach Foundation for Graphic Arts,
                    M. H. de Young Memorial Museum, San Francisco.</p>
        <p>Both plates now in the Achenbach Collection are printed in olive 
                    green<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> 
                    on a sheet of unwatermarked wove paper, 33 × 24.8 cm. 
                    Neither has any hand tinting. The ragged left edge of the
                    paper was probably created by its removal from the bound collection described
                    above. The recto, bearing pl. 4 (illus. 3), is numbered 23 in pencil upper
                    right. Most of the leaves in the original bound collection were numbered upper
                    right in ink; this pencil number may have been added by B. B. Macgeorge, who
                    acquired the depleted collection by 1906. Written in ink below the image is
                        “<hi rend="u">Murder</hi>. (the Assassin awaiting his
                    victim).” Below this title and slightly to the left is written
                    “The two plates on the leaf are from ‘Europe,’
                    published by W. Blake, at Lambeth, in 1794.” In pencil lower right is
                    “see back.” The plate is in the second state of three,
                    containing the white-line work in the ruts on the road, on the
                    traveller’s legs and lower stomach, and on the straps 
<figure n="milton.philprf.P13" rend="file" width="703" height="1000">
	<head>6 <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, pl. 13.</head>
	<figDesc>White-line etching, 15.9 × 11.1 cm., second state,
                            printed in three colors. Philadelphia Museum of Art.</figDesc>
</figure> 
                    over his chest, but before the addition of further white lines on the
                    traveller’s pack, its straps, his right upper arm and shoulder, and
                    his upper stomach. The only recorded impressions of the first state are in proof
                    copy b (Pierpont Morgan Library) and in the collection of Leonard Baskin; the
                    only other second state impressions are in proof copies a (British Museum) and
                    b.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> 
                    The impression of pl. 9 (illus. 4) on
                    the verso is in the last of three states. There are slight pencil marks below
                    the image on the right; a partly erased brown ink 
<pb id="p15-8" n="8"/>
                    inscription below the design reads “Famine [followed by an illegible
                    word] to eat the child for food.” This title is based on George
                    Cumberland’s inscription on the same plate in copy D of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
                    (British Museum). 
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> The 1938
                        auction catalogue, lot 30 nos. 3 and 4, describes the plates as
                        “printed in gray.” I take this to be a simple
                        error.</note>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> I take this information from Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p.
143, except that Bentley does not note
                        that pl. 4 in copy a is in the second state.</note></p>
        <p>An impression of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> pl. 15 was also included in George A.
                    Smith’s bound collection. This was sold with four other prints from
                        <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> in lot 32 in the 1938 George C. Smith auction ($160
                    to E. Weyhe Inc.) and is listed as untraced in Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake
                        Books</hi>, p. 341. The print was acquired by Mr. and Mrs. Philip Hofer,
                    probably directly from Weyhe, and given by Mrs. Frances Hofer in 1979 to the
                    Houghton Library, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts (illus. 5). The
                    unwatermarked wove sheet, 31.3 × 22.6 cm., bears stab holes along the
                    left margin, “36” in ink top right (George A.
                    Smith’s original foliation), “24” in pencil top
                    left (Macgeorge foliation?), “PX” in pencil bottom left (a
                    bookdealer’s coded price?), and “Europe page 10.”
                    in pencil below the left corner of the image. A pen and ink framing line extends
                    along all four sides of the plate mark; a second frame in the same ink is 4 mm.
                    from the image. The basic printing color is brown, but the text (except for a
                    few words in lines 5 through 9) has been gone over with a pen in black ink. Much
                    of the design is poorly printed and the spider webs, insects, leaves at the
                    bottom, and outlines of the figure lower right have also been worked over in
                    black ink. The dark areas at the bottom are color printed in
                    green—rather patchy on the right, but thick and heavy in the lower
                    left corner. The impression appears to be an experimental pull, perhaps rejected
                    because of the poor inking and color printing. However, Blake (or someone else?)
                    spent a good deal of time with pen &amp; ink trying to salvage the print.
                    If this work was indeed done by Blake, perhaps he intended to hand color the
                    design further and transform it into an impression of sufficient quality to use
                    in a copy of <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi></p>
        <p>Mrs. Hofer has also given the Houghton Library a copy of <hi rend="i">Little Tom
                        the Sailor.</hi> It is printed in dull black ink on a wove sheet 49.9
                    × 17 cm., cut close on the right with the loss of a fraction of the
                    image. The dark areas in the designs may have been hand tinted with India ink.
                    This example, at one time in the Graham Robertson collection, is included as no.
                    5 in Keynes’ list of 
                    copies.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 2nd
                        ed. rev. (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971), p. 108.</note></p>
        <p>While there are a good many unbound and now widely scattered proofs of the <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
plates, separate impressions from <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> are extremely rare: Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake
Books</hi>, p.
                    305, records only a single impression of pl. 38 in the collection of Mrs. Ramsey
                    Harvey. I recently came upon an unrecorded impression of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, pl. 13
                    (illus. 6), at the Philadelphia Museum of Art, which
                    received the print as a gift from Carl Zigrosser in 1975. On the back of the
                    unwatermarked wove sheet, 21.2 × 15.4 cm., Zigrosser has written the
                    following: “Milton Descending etching by William Blake trial proof
                    printed in two colors [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>; see below] #358
                    Binyon’s Engraved Designs of W. Blake [followed by a reference to
                    Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and quotation of lines 13, 21-23
                    from pl. 12] This print was purchased by Alexander W Drake, former art editor of
                    The Century, from Gilchrists [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] in the 1890’s.
                    Sessler purchased it from Drake’s widow, living in Stockbridge Mass
                    and I purchased it from Sesslers.” This is very probably the print
                    described by W. M. Rossetti, in his list of Blake’s engravings in
                    Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, as a
                    “Figure, with a glory, standing before a rising or setting sun or
                    globe.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref>
                    Apparently Rossetti
                    did not realize that the plate was executed for one of the illuminated books. He
                    does not indicate as much, but the print was probably then (1863) in the
                    collection of Mrs. Gilchrist, from whom it passed to her son, Herbert H.
                    Gilchrist, and then by sale in the 1890s to Alexander W. Drake. 
<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi> (London
                        and Cambridge: Macmillan, 1863), II, 258. The description is repeated in the
                        1880 ed., II, 280.</note></p>
        <p>There is no reason to question Zigrosser’s provenance for this
                    impression, although Sessler’s purchase and sales records, 1919-1975,
                    contain no record of the 
                    print.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> 
                    Zigrosser did purchase an unidentified “Blake print . . . framed in
                    gold” from Sessler’s for $60 on 3 November 1951; but this
                    was acquired from “Nicholson,” not Drake, and is probably the
                    intaglio impression of the experimental relief and white-line etching, sometimes
                    entitled “Let Him look up in the Heavens and laugh in the bright
                    air,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref>
                    which Zigrosser gave to
                    Lessing J. Rosenwald in June 1961, and which is now in the National Gallery of
                    Art, Washington. 
                    <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Sessler’s
                        records of (most?) Blake materials that have passed through the Philadelphia
                        shop have been assembled and copied for me by Michael Young of the
                        University of Pennsylvania.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> See Keynes, <hi rend="i">Engravings by
                            William Blake: The Separate Plates</hi> (Dublin: Emery Walker, 1956),
                        pp. 38-39 and pl. 24.</note></p>
        <p>I do not believe that it has been noticed previously that this plate exists in
                    two states. In comparison to the impressions in copies A, B (illus. 7), and C of
                        <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, the Philadelphia example shows fewer relief
                    plateaus between white-line cross-hatchings just below the figure’s
                    left breast, apparently the result of more tool work in this area. The clearest
                    difference, however, and one that can not be explained simply as inking and
                    printing variations, is the boldly scratched white lines below and to the left
                    of the man’s right foot, clearly visible in the Philadelphia
                    impression but not in copies A, B, and 
                    C.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref>
                    This same second state with additional white-line work also appears in copy D of
                    the illuminated book (illus. 8). Thus, the second state was executed rather late
                    in the production of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, sometime between c. 1808 when
                    copies A-C were printed and 1815 (or later) when copy D was 
                    printed.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> For a reproduction of the plate in copy A,
                        see David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> (Garden City,
                        New York: Anchor, 1974), p. 232. For copy C, see Kathleen Raine, <hi rend="i">Blake
                        and Tradition</hi> (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press,
                        1968), II, 249, fig. 184.</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Copies A-C are on Whatman paper watermarked
                        1808; copy D is watermarked RUSE &amp; TURNERS | 1815. See the
                        discussion of printing history in Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p.
                        309.</note></p>
        <p>The figure and his immediate surroundings are lightly printed in reddish-brown.
                    The dark areas above (see illus. 6) are heavily inked and printed in blue-green;
                    the dark ground below the figure is in black. There is a small spot of olive
                    green—perhaps simply a thin droplet of the blue-green in the
                    sky—on the man’s torso just above his left hip. The
                    thickly printed colors show the dendritic reticulations of Blake’s
                    color printing, c. 1794-1796. I suspect, however, that these are not opaque gum-
                    or glue-based pigments, but thick ink, perhaps partly dried even before its
                    uneven application to the plate. Yet it is surprising to find that Blake
                    continued to experiment, well into the nineteenth century, with opaque coloring
                    techniques and reticulated textures so characteristic of his work of the
                    mid-1790s.</p>
        <p>Professor G. E. Bentley, Jr., was another recent visitor to the Philadelphia
                    Museum of Art. That rich 
<pb id="p15-9" n="9"/>
                    collection has yielded further
                    treasures to a most assiduous prospector, and he has asked me to record his
                    discovery of a previously unrecorded posthumous impression of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                    pl. 99 in this article. I am delighted to comply, and offer
                    the following information on the print in Professor Bentley’s
                    standard format for supplementing <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi></p>
        <p>BINDING: Loose; inventory number: 19 75-26-21. Verso inscribed (probably by Carl
                    Zigrosser, who gave it to the Museum) “McGeorge [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>]
                    Coll.” The rest of the inscription is not useful. This indicates that
                    it came with the miscellaneous group of prints &amp;c. with the Order of
                    the <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi></p>
        <p>LEAF SIZE: 15.7 × 23.0 (irregular), remargined to 16.2 ×
                    23.1 cm.</p>
        <p>WATERMARK: 1830 (cut off above).</p>
        <p>PRINTING COLOUR: Brown.</p>
        <p>ONE LEAF, printed on one side only.</p>
        <p>OFFSET: None.</p>
        <p>NUMBER: “99” (or “91”?) scratched on the
                    copper in the top right corner.</p>
        <p>COLOURING: None.</p>
        <p>VARIANTS: There are horizontal streaks on the plate. The lines from the
                    substratum of design show very clearly, especially in the irrelevant
                    cross-hatching on and at the level of the heads.</p>
        <p>In the summer 1980 issue of this journal (see note 6), I listed the sale of three
                    plates from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>
                    (“The Ecchoing Green,” second plate, “The Little
                    Black Boy,” second plate, and “Holy Thursday” from
                        <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>), for many years in the collection of Dr. Bent
                    E. Juel-Jensen, to Colin Franklin and then to Zeitlin &amp; Ver Brugge, the
                    Los Angeles book and print dealer. These were returned to Colin Franklin, who
                    has now sold them to Raymond M. Wapner of Roosevelt Island, 
                    New York.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Mr. Wapner is a partner of the New York
                        bookdealer Justin G. Schiller, with whose permission I record the ownership
                        of these plates.</note></p>
        <p>While these plates were in Los Angeles, I was able to inspect them carefully.
                    They are the only known relief etchings printed by Blake on laid India paper.
                    The light inking of the designs and borders, combined with darker inking of the
                    text, is typical 
<figure n="milton.b.p13" id="milton.b.illbk.13" work-copy="milton.b" rend="db" width="703" height="1000">
  <figTranscr>13</figTranscr>
  <head>7 <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, copy B, pl. 13.</head>
  <figDesc>White-line etching, 16 × 11.1 cm., first state, hand
				colored. Huntington Library, San Marino, California.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="milton.d.p16-13" id="milton.d.illbk.16" work-copy="milton.d" rend="db" width="687" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>16</figTranscr>
	<head>8 <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, copy D, pl. 13 (16 in this copy).</head>
	<figDesc>White-line etching, 16 × 11.1 cm., second state, hand
                            colored. Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, The Library of
                            Congress.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p15-10" n="10"/>
<figure n="urizen.beineckeprf.P1" rend="file" width="758" height="1000">
	<head>9 <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi>, copy H, pl. 1.</head>
	<figDesc>Relief etching, 14.9 × 10.3 cm., on wove sheet 18.9
                            × 13.9 cm., mounted. Text ink printed in golden brown; design
                            color printed in red, brown, gray, green, black, and blue. Beinecke
                            Library, Yale University.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="urizen.beineckeprf.P4" rend="file" width="760" height="1000">
	<head>10 <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi>, copy H, pl. 4.</head>
	<figDesc>Relief etching, 13.6 × 10.1 cm., on wove sheet 17.5
                            × 12.5 cm., mounted. Text ink printed in green; design color
                            printed in brown and green. Figure hand tinted with pink. Beinecke
                            Library, Yale University.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="urizen.beineckeprf2.P25" rend="file" width="761" height="1000">
	<head>11 <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi>, copy H, pl. 25.</head>
	<figDesc>Relief etching, 14.8 × 10.4 cm., on wove sheet 18
                            × 11.6 cm., mounted. Text ink printed in olive green; design
                            color printed in gray, rose, rust red, blue, and several shades of
                            brown. Perhaps some hand tinting in yellow. Beinecke Library, Yale
                            University.</figDesc>
</figure> 
<pb id="p15-11" n="11"/> 
					of Blake’s best
                    nineteenth-century relief printing of plates intended for hand coloring. The
                    cadmium orange ink is similar to the ink in copies U (on paper watermarked
                    1815), Z, and AA (both printed c. 1825) of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and
                        of Experience.</hi> The coloring of the text area in the second plate of
                    “The Little Black Boy” and the ink framing lines (blue, rather
                    than the usual red) are typical of late copies of the <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi>
                    The India paper also bespeaks a late date of printing. None of
                    Blake’s original graphics on laid India were unquestionably printed
                    until the 1820s. As I have suggested 
                    elsewhere,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> 
                    Linnell’s influence may have prompted the use of such
                    paper, for he favored laid India even for unfinished proofs. 
<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> See my <hi rend="i">William Blake, Printmaker</hi>
                        (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1980), p. 220. Linnell’s
                        preference for laid India may perhaps be explained by the need for a paper
                        smooth and hard enough to take an accurate impression of the dense patterns
                        of fine lines and flick work on his engraved portraits.</note></p>
        <p>The inking and printing of the plates clearly point to Blake’s hand,
                    but I am much less certain about the incomplete hand coloring. The washes on all
                    three impressions are thin, even, and applied to fairly broad areas with some
                    disregard for printed outlines. These features can be found in
                    Blake’s hand coloring of the early 1790s, but by the nineteenth
                    century he had developed a far more sophisticated style with greater delicacy
                    and precision in the application of colors. The best examples show fine brush
                    work, similar to the technique of miniature painting, and subtle blending at the
                    borders between colors—yet without any violation of outlines.
                    Christ’s gown on the second plate of “The Little Black
                    Boy” is colored a bright scarlet found in no other impression.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> None of these three plates contains any of
                    the drawing with pen and ink (or sometimes even pencil) so typical of
                    Blake’s work. It may be unfair to compare the coloring of these
                    plates to finished examples in complete copies of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>,
                    but my doubts persist nonetheless. 
                    <note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> At least
                        according to the color notes in Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p.
                        391.</note></p>
        <p>Proof impressions of Blake’s relief etchings with incomplete inking or
                    coloring are rarely as beautiful as finished examples, but they can provide
                    interesting information about his graphic processes. Even recorded impressions
                    of this type in well-catalogued public collections deserve more careful study.
                    Wandering through that enormous repository of information, Bentley’s
                    <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, one can all too easily overlook the special
                    qualities of odd proofs and unfinished pulls. Although New Haven, Connecticut,
                    is more famous for theoretical speculation than chalcographic treasures, the
                    city’s leading university offers several opportunities to study
                    unusual impressions of plates from Blake’s illuminated books.</p>
        <p>In 1970, Charles J. Rosenbloom bequeathed to the Beinecke Library, Yale
                    University, impressions of pls. 1, 4, and 25 of <hi rend="i">The First Book of
                    Urizen.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref>
                    All three (illus. 9-11)
                    are richly color printed without subsequent hand coloring or pen and ink work
                    except for a small amount of hand tinting in pink on the figure in pl. 4 and
                    perhaps some yellow applied by hand to pl. 25. As such, they show how expert
                    Blake was at handling a difficult medium and keeping the pigments from spreading
                    so chaotically that all definition of forms is lost. The title-page (illus. 9)
                    shows great technical control on the figure; unlike the heavily colored 
<figure n="ahania.beineckeprf2.P1" rend="file" width="763" height="1000">
	<head>12 <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, copy Bb, pl. 1.</head>
	<figDesc>Intaglio etching, 13.6 × 9.8 cm. on wove sheet 14.4
                            × 10.6 cm. Color printed from the surface (of the intaglio
                            plate?) in gray and dark green. Beinecke Library, Yale
                            University.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="ahania.beineckeprf.P1" rend="file" width="733" height="1000">
	<head>13 <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, copy Bb, pl. 1.</head>
	<figDesc>Intaglio etching, 13.6 × 9.8 cm. on wove sheet 29.7
                            × 21.7 cm. Color printed from the surface of a plate or piece
                            of paper in purple, green, rust red, and brown. Beinecke Library, Yale
                            University.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p15-12" n="12"/>
<figure n="songsie.colorprint.P5" rend="file" width="795" height="925">
	<figTranscr/>
	<head>14 “The Shepherd,” design only on wove paper, 7.5
                            × 6.4 cm.</head>
	<figDesc>Color printed in red, blue, green, dark brown, golden brown, and
                            flesh tones with additional hand tinting and pen and ink work. Yale
                            Center for British Art.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="songsie.colorprint.P22" rend="file" width="828" height="567">
	<figTranscr/>
	<head>15 “Spring,” design only on wove paper, 4.5
                            × 6.8 cm.</head>
	<figDesc>Color printed in red, green, dark brown, golden brown, and flesh
                            tones with additional hand tinting and pen and ink work. Blue wash in
                            sky. Yale Center for British Art.</figDesc>
</figure> 
                    tree on the left, he was printed so as to produce reticulated textures
                    yet leave white areas (eyes, for example) for later development on the print.
                    Plate 25 (illus. 11) clearly demonstrates that Blake was able to color print
                    from etched areas (upper right, and the figure lower left) as well as relief
                    plateaus.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref>
                    The extreme shallowness of
                    the etching, particularly in <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi>,
                    combined with the thickness of Blake’s color medium, permitted this
                    type of proto-planographic printing. The etching of the design provided little
                    more than a guide for the hand painting of the copperplate. 
<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, pp. 168, 341,
                        records these prints as still in Rosenbloom’s collection and does
                        not note their special features. Their bequest to Yale is noted in
                        Bentley’s “Supplement” (see footnote 1). They
                        are designated as copy H by Bentley. The three plates were once part of the
                        large collection of prints bound by George A. Smith with the
                        “Order” of the <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi> They were acquired
                        by Rosenbloom at the George C. Smith auction, Parke Bernet, 2 November 1938,
                        lot 34 ($250 to Sessler’s for Rosenbloom).</note>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> There is a similar color printed proof of
                        pl. 25, without hand tinting or drawing, in Sir Geoffrey Keynes’
                        collection.</note></p>
        <p>The Beinecke Library also owns two impressions of the title-page for <hi rend="i">The Book of
Ahania</hi> and one of pl. 4 from the same illuminated book.
                    The first two (illus. 12, 13) constitute a rare set of progress proofs. The two
                    illuminated books etched in intaglio, <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, do not lend themselves to color printing
                    from the surface of the copperplates. The pressure necessary for good intaglio
                    printing is far too great for color printing from surfaces. The title-page to
                        <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> (copy A, British Museum) shows that the
                    design must have been color printed or blotted with a separate plate or piece of
                    paper rather than the copperplate bearing the etched text.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> The exceptionally light printing of the text in the
                    first Beinecke proof (illus. 12) suggests that Blake may have been trying, at
                    least in this one case, to print simultaneously from the intaglio lines and the
                    surface of the plate in two colors. The results are not promising. The second
                    proof (illus. 13) is much better as an intaglio impression and the four-color
                    printing of the design area is more even with fewer streaks and uncovered spots.
                    It seems unlikely that work of this quality could have been produced in one run
                    through the press. Thus these two proofs may record Blake’s progress
                    from single to double printing for his intaglio, color printed
                    books—a progress that led to a technical division between printing
                    texts and printing designs with important consequences. In this same period
                    during the mid-1790s, Blake’s color printing began to develop
                    independent of his work as a poet, most successfully in the great 1795 color
                    printed drawings, and finally evolved into the so-called
                    “tempera” paintings of 1799-1800. <note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> See Essick, 
<hi rend="i">William Blake, Printmaker</hi>, p. 130
                        and fig. 118.</note></p>
        <p>In “Blake in the Marketplace, 1976-77,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21"
type="note">21</ref> I recorded the sale at auction of impressions of the
                    designs without text of “The Shepherd” and
                    “Spring” from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> These two
                    prints (illus. 14, 15) were acquired in 1978 by the Yale Center for British Art,
                    New Haven. They are not incomplete or working proofs, but highly finished color
                    prints of great beauty. They are two of only three known color printed designs
                    from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>: in copies of <hi rend="i">Songs of
                        Innocence and of Experience</hi> containing color printing, such work is
                    confined to the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> plates alone. The Yale Center
                    prints are cut close to the designs, and thus it is possible that the plates
                    were originally printed with the texts and cut apart by someone other than
                    Blake. I suspect, however, that both were printed as designs only with the texts
                    masked. If so, then these prints are similar to Blake’s work in the
                    “Large” and “Small” Books of Design.
                    “The Shepherd” and “Spring” now at the Yale
                    Center may have been produced for the conjectural copy B of the Small Book of
                    Designs or 
<pb id="p15-13" n="13"/>
some similar collection of color printed
                        miniatures.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref>
Like the other prints
                    described here, they testify to Blake’s life-long commitment to
                    innovation in the graphic arts. But far more than the others, these two small
                    prints demonstrate the excellence of his best work. <note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi><hi
rend="i"> Blake: An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 12 (1978), 31.</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> See G. E. Bentley, Jr., “Dr. James
                        Curry as a Patron of Blake,” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>,
                        27 (1980), 71-73, for new information on a possible purchaser of
                        Blake’s color prints besides Ozias Humphry.</note></p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
