<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.1.doerrbecker</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Fuseli, the Swiss, and the British: Some Recent Publications</title>
        <author n="Dörrbecker">Detlef W. Dörrbecker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <name>James Warwick</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Martin K. Nurmi</name>
              <name>Judith Page</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Henry Summerfield</name>
              <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-1-0008">
        <div2>
          <pb id="p15-53" n="53"/>
          <div3>
            <figure n="Fuseli.Swiss.British.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" type="reviewed-cover" width="400" height="551">
            	<figTranscr>Wickstead</figTranscr>
            </figure>
            <head>
              <title type="main" rend="main"><hi rend="b">Fuseli, The Swiss, And The British:</hi> Some Recent
                                Publications.</title>
            </head>
            <byline>
              <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
              <docAuthor>
                <hi rend="b">Detlef W.</hi>
                <name>
                  <hi rend="b">Dörrbecker</hi>
                </name>
              </docAuthor>
            </byline>
            <p>Johann Heinrich Füssli has been repatriated. Posthumously the
                            Swiss painter who, under the name of Henry Fuseli, became Professor of
                            Painting and Keeper of the London Royal Academy is now accepted as one
                            of the major figures of eighteenth-century Continental 
                            art,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n140" type="note">1</ref> 
                            and many of his most celebrated
                            works have, during the past seventy years or so, found their way
                            “back” into Swiss, German, and Italian collections.
                            Also, much of the scholarly work on Fuseli has been published on the
                            Continent, and now two aspects of his work which are not readily
                            available to the museum public, his poetry and his drawings, seem on the
                            verge of gaining the recognition they deserve. <note id="n140"><hi rend="s">1</hi>
                            Thus, the first modern monograph, Arnold
                                Federmann’s <hi rend="i">Johann Heinrich
                                    Füssli: Dichter und Maler 1741-1825</hi> (Zurich and
                                Leipzig: Orell Füssli, 1927) was published as vol. 1 of a
                                series entitled “Monographien zur Schweizer
                                Kunst;” similarly, the <hi rend="i">catalogue
                                    raisonné</hi> is vol. 1 of the
                                “Oeuvrekataloge Schweizer Künstler,”
                                published for the Swiss Institute for Art Research (Gert Schiff, 
<hi rend="i">Johann Heinrich Füssli 1741-1825</hi>, 2
                                vols. [Zurich: Berichthaus, and Munich: Prestel, 1973]). Recently
                                Herbert von Einem discussed Fuseli in his book on <hi rend="i">Deutsche
Malerei des Klassizismus und der Romantik 1760 bis
                                    1840</hi> (Munich: C. H. Beck, 1978).—It was in Rome
                                and in England that Fuseli developed from a gifted amateur into a
                                professional artist. Still, there might be a kernel of truth in
                                Pevsner’s hint that Fuseli’s
                                “Swiss-ness” may explain the basic discrepancies
                                between his and Flaxman’s style (see <hi rend="i">The
                                    Englishness of English Art</hi>, London: Architectural Press,
                                1956, pp. 126f.). Thus, I do not mean to ridicule, in a precipitant
                                way, what has been termed the “national character”
                                in art. Together with all milieu and social theory of art this
                                complex of questions undoubtedly belongs to the realm of unsolved
                                problems in post-war art history. The painter’s own
                                feelings for Switzerland obviously remained unsettled, which is
                                hardly surprising with an emigrant. (Compare, e.g., the satirical
                                drawing Schiff no. 568 and the poem on “Schweizerlands
                                Künstler.”). In any case, it appears to be an
                                irresponsible—though probably
                                unconscious—chauvinism when Fuseli’s art is
                                “claimed” for the annals of this or that nation as
                                long as we know so little about the complex interplay of personal
                                style, national character and the
                                “internationalism” (Rosenblum) of late
                                eighteenth-century art.</note></p>
            <p>Professor Schiff’s pioneering analysis of the British
              Museum’s <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">Roman Sketchbook</hi>,</corr> which prepared
                            the way for the 1958-59 exhibition of the then little-known 
<hi rend="i">Zeichnungen von Johann Heinrich Füssli</hi> in Zurich,
                            and Eudo C. Mason’s rare edition of some of the
                            painter’s poems,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n141"
type="note">2</ref> have
                            been followed more recently by a number of important books and
                            exhibition catalogues. Some of these are briefly described in the
                            following notes, leaving, however, the <hi rend="i">chef
                                d’oeuvre</hi> of all Fuseli scholarship to the present
                            day, Gert Schiff’s monumental <hi rend="i">catalogue
                                raisonné</hi>, for separate discussion later. 
<note id="n141"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Gert Schiff, <hi rend="i">Zeichnungen
                                    J. H. Füsslis aus seiner römischen Zeit:
                                    Mit einem beschreibenden Katalog seines Römischen
                                    Albums im Britischen Museum, London</hi> (unpublished Ph. D.
                                thesis, University of Cologne, 1957); Gert Schiff, <hi rend="i">Zeichnungen
von Johann Heinrich Füssli 1741-1825:
                                    Unbekannte und neugedeutete Blätter aus Sammlungen in
                                    Grossbritannien, Nordirland, Schweden und der Schweiz</hi>
                                (Zurich: Fretz &amp; Wasmuth, 1959 [Schweizerisches Institut
                                für Kunstwissenschaft, “Kleine
                                Schriften,” vol. 2]); and Eudo C. Mason, ed., 
<hi rend="i">Unveröffentlichte Gedichte von Johann Heinrich
                                    Füssli</hi> (Zurich: Kunstgesellschaft, 1951
                                [“Neujahrsblatt der Zürcher
                                Kunstgesellschaft”]).</note></p>
            <p>As a poet Fuseli indeed has to be considered in the context of
                            German-language literature. The relation between painting and poetry in
                            his <hi rend="i">oeuvre</hi> differs considerably from that in
                            Blake’s, where the terminology of the “sister
                            arts” and a “composite art” seems more
                            legitimate. The <hi rend="i">Sämtliche Gedichte</hi> do not
                            follow the concept of <hi rend="i">ut pictura poesis</hi> at all; on the
                            contrary, with few exceptions they are quite abstract and non-visual,
                            written in the manner and under the marked influence of Friedrich
                            Gottlieb Klopstock.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n142"
type="note">3</ref> Guthke points
                            out what the reader of Fuseli’s poetry feels from the
                            beginning: the author favored the classical ode; his stanzas are alcaic
                            or asclepiadeic; he makes use of hexameters or distichs—all
                            rather complex poetic devices employed with an extensive <corr type="emend">knowledge</corr> of
                            antique traditions. These suit much of his subject matter, which is full
                            of learned allusions and sometimes close to an allegorical
                            hide-and-seek. <note id="n142"><hi rend="s">3</hi> See
                                Guthke’s “Nachwort,” in Johann Heinrich
                                Füssli, <hi rend="i">Sämtliche Gedichte</hi>,
                                ed. Martin Bircher and Karl S. Guthke (Zurich: Orell
                                Füssli, 1973 [“Nobile Turegum:
                                Zürcher Drucke des 16. bis 19. Jahrhunderts”]),
                                p. 107; (DM 32, c. $19.00). In addition, Mason showed how close
                                Fuseli’s poems often are to Horace (see Mason 1951, p.
                                28).</note></p>
            <p>Many of these verses are addressed to Fuseli’s friends in
                            Switzerland; then there are the odes on patience, “auf den
                            Portwein,” and “an das Vaterland.” Other
                            groups are devoted to the <hi rend="i">Nibelungen</hi> saga and Germanic
                            history, the anti-slavery campaign and the American War of Independence,
                            or the author’s theory of art. That Fuseli’s
                            finest achievement as a poet is one of his few love poems,
                            “Nannas Auge,” has long been accepted. Though Fuseli
                            has been identified as one of the major exponents of the
                            Storm-and-Stress movement, Guthke justly emphasizes that his poetry is
                            far from being impeccable. Often 
<pb id="p15-54" n="54"/>
there are
                            signs of rhetorical over-working, a fault that Fuseli recognized and
                            criticized himself.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n143"
type="note">4</ref> Judging the
                            quality of his literary work, however, we ought to remember that what we
                            have of his later poetry is in most cases known from working drafts
                            only, and Mason’s earlier hypothesis, that many of the poems
                            might have reached a maturer state in the lost fair copies, still seems
                                valid.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n144"
type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n143"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See Bircher &amp; Guthke 1973,
                                p. 110.</note>
	<note id="n144"><hi rend="s">5</hi> See Mason 1951, p. 12.</note></p>
            <p>The majority of the forty-six poems, printed here in an often tentative
                            chronological sequence, were written early in Fuseli’s
                            career, and only two of them in English. If seen in the context of
                            contemporary German and English literature, all of them bear witness to
                            the stylistic conservatism of their author. The mature work of Goethe
                            and Schiller, of Hölderlin and Kleist, of the German and
                            British Romantics made no mark. The odes bear an especially strong
                            resemblance to Klopstock’s “Hermann und
                            Thusnelda”—which Fuseli deliberately remodelled in
                            about 1760—while the prose poem “Klagen” is
                            somewhat reminiscent of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
                                Thoughts.</hi> Another group reflects Fuseli’s admiration
                            for his countryman Rousseau,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n145"
type="note">6</ref> and
                            throughout he shows a critical awareness of the decaying feudal
                            structures of European society, as seen through his own republicanism.
                            The cult of artistic creativity that is apparent in “Die Gaben
                            Gottes,” the attack on colonialism and slavery and his
                            “prophecy” of the American Revolution in
                            “Chincona” and “Colombo” are
                            close—but close in subject matter only—to
                            Blake’s works of the early 1790s. Though Fuseli’s
                            poetry clearly suggests that his friendship with the engraver grew out
                            of a number of political and artistic ideas that they shared, I cannot
                            see any direct <hi rend="i">poetic</hi> influence of the one on the
                            other of the two men. [Mis-]reading the <hi rend="i">Gedichte</hi> as
                            prose essays, however, we find Fuseli’s “Erste [und
                            Zweite] Ode über die Kunst” of the early 1770s
                            foreshadowing Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>
                            in its praise of Michelangelo and outline at the expense of Titian,
                            Correggio, and coloring. (Though Raphael, too, was one of
                            Fuseli’s effeminate demons!) Fuseli’s exclamation
                            “Hölle, sei mir gegrüsset!”
                            appears to echo Blake’s <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, and any
                            Blake scholar will feel at home with the attacks on kings and priests
                            that are launched repeatedly. <note id="n145"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Cf.
                                Johann Heinrich Füssli, <hi rend="i">Remarks on the
                                    Writings and Conduct of J. J. Rousseau—Bemerkungen
                                    über J. J. Rousseaus Schriften und Verhalten</hi>,
                                ed. Eudo C. Mason (Zurich: Fretz &amp; Wasmuth, 1962
                                [Schweizerisches Institut für Kunstwissenschaft,
                                “Kleine Schriften,” vol. 4]).</note></p>
            <p>Guthke’s “Nachwort” supplies the reader with
                            yet another short biography of Fuseli which, though there is nothing new
                            in it, is necessary to an understanding of the various auto-biographical
                            pieces. Rather more important is the analysis of the obvious
                            discrepancies between Fuseli’s poetic and pictorial <hi rend="i">oeuvres</hi>,
and Guthke is also helpful with respect to
                            the formal development of Fuseli’s poetry in its historical
                            context. Mason’s introduction to the edition of 1951,
                            however, is not superseded by Guthke and Bircher. In my opinion it
                            remains the most detailed and balanced account of Fuseli’s
                            poetic achievement that has been published to the present day.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n146" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n146"><hi rend="s">7</hi> See Mason 1951, pp. 7-45. The
                                opinions here are by no means identical with the same
                                author’s rather rash verdicts in <hi rend="i">The Mind of
                                    Henry Fuseli</hi> (London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul,
                                1951), pp. 26-29, a book that was in print when the editor first
                                learned about the Fuseli poems in the
                                “North-Konvolut” (see Mason 1951, p.
                            21n2).</note></p>
            <p>Though the title promises <hi rend="i">Sämtliche
                            Gedichte</hi>, the edition is <hi rend="i">not</hi> complete. Thus, for
                            unknown reasons the lyrical fragments among Fuseli’s letters,
                            which are known from Federmann’s book,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n147" type="note">8</ref> have been left out. Also, I am not entirely
                            comfortable with the editorial principles employed in this first, and
                            probably for a long time to come the only, collection of
                            Fuseli’s poetry that is available to a wide public. Too much
                            may have been left to the uncontrollable “Ermessen des
                                Herausgebers”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n148"
type="note">9</ref> and the
                            extent of Bircher’s “modernizing” can be
                            only estimated by comparing the facsimile reproductions of the
                            manuscripts with the edited versions.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n149" type="note">10</ref> This may be justified by the attempt to achieve
                            “eine lesbare . . . Textform;” I doubt, however, that
                            the same text can meet with the demands of a “wissenschaftlich
                            zuverlässige Textform.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n150"
type="note">11</ref> In any case, the incompleteness in the
                            apparatus of variants will be regretted in the long run, especially by
                            those scholars who cannot easily consult the original manuscripts in
                            Appledore (Ashford, Kent), Berlin, and Zurich. And yet, if Bircher and
                            Guthke’s edition is measured against what we had before,
                            these criticisms shrink to their proper proportions. While Fuseli may be
                            only a minor Swiss poet, the publication of this handsome little
                            volume—about the size of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>—should
nevertheless be welcomed
                            for the insight it makes possible into the painter’s feelings
                            as well as his ideas.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n151"
type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n147"><hi rend="s">8</hi> See Federmann 1927, pp. 115f., 120,
                                133, 135, 136, 141, 145.</note>
	<note id="n148"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Bircher, “Zum
                                Text,” in Bircher &amp; Guthke 1973, p. 120.</note>
	<note id="n149"><hi rend="s">10</hi> E.g., in the second Lavater ode I
                                count upwards of forty “modernizations,” including
                                one misreading, in a poem of not more than twenty-two lines. See
                                Bircher &amp; Guthke 1973, p. 90 and the opposite page for a
                                reproduction of Fuseli’s autograph.</note>
	<note id="n150"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Bircher, “Zum
                                Text,” in Bircher &amp; Guthke 1973, p. 119.</note>
	<note id="n151"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Finally, interested readers should
                                be aware that only 1000 copies were printed, and those six years
                                ago.</note></p>
            <p>Whereas the 1977 Milan catalogue of some forty-five of
                            Fuseli’s <hi rend="i">disegni e dipinti</hi> gives little
                            relevant information beyond a number of new owner-ships,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n152" type="note">13</ref> Yvonne
                            Boerlin-Brodbeck’s work on the Basle collection of
                            Fuseli’s drawings deserves more attention. Cleaning and
                            restoration of this group, combined with the author’s
                            scrutiny on watermarks and the like, has yielded a number of interesting
                            new results.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n153"
type="note">14</ref> Almost eighty works
                            from what probably is the finest Fuseli collection in our day, the
                            Kunsthaus Zurich, were on show at Geneva in 1978, and, more recently, an
                            exhibition comprising not only the “painter in ordinary to the
                            devil” but also his circle in Rome, was held at the Yale Center
                            for British Art.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n154"
type="note">15</ref> Yet another
                            exhibition, concentrating on the Auckland Fuselis, travelled to various
                            cities in Australia and New Zealand from April to November 1979. The
                            Auckland drawings did not come to scholarly light until 1963; they were
                            then published in Peter Tomory’s important catalogue of 1967.
                            The booklet accompanying their latest showing is a slightly revised and
                            considerably enlarged version, prepared by the same author. This time,
                            Fuseli’s designs were put into proper perspective: the 100
                            items on show included work by such artists as Barry, Blake, John Brown,
                            Jefferys, Mortimer, Romney, and Alexander Runciman, forming, according
                            to Tomory, a <hi rend="i">Poetical Circle</hi> around the British-Swiss
                                master.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n155"
type="note">16</ref> For Blake
                            enthusiasts, Tomory’s new hypothesis that the engraver
                            William Blake may have been the original owner of the Auckland Fuseli
                            collection should certainly add to the attractiveness of the catalogue.
                            Prof. Tomory argues that the album may have passed through
                            Linnell’s hands and then into the possession of Albin Martin,
                            the former owner of the much disputed New Zealand set of copies from
                            Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n156" type="note">17</ref>
	<note id="n152"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Lamberto Vitali, <hi rend="i">Johann Heinrich Füssli: disegni e
dipinti</hi>,
                                exhb. cat. <corr type="emend">Museo Poldi Pezzoli</corr> (Milan: Electa, 1977, c. $14.00). The
                                catalogue also contains a brief essay by Gert Schiff on
                                “Füssli in Italia,” pp. [7]-12.</note>
	<note id="n153"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Yvonne Boerlin-Brodbeck, <hi rend="i">Zeichnungen des 18. Jahrhunderts
aus dem Basler
                                    Kupferstichkabinett</hi> (Basle: Kunstmuseum, 1978), nos.
                                72-103, pp. 44-52; (c. $10.00).</note>
	<note id="n154"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Dagmar Hnikova, <hi rend="i">Johann
                                    Heinrich Füssli 1741-1825</hi> (Geneva:
                                Musée Rath, 1978; c. $9.00); as far as I can see, the
                                entries in this 50-page leaflet are drawn entirely from the
                                information supplied in Schiff 1973. When writing this note, my copy
                                of the Yale catalogue, prepared by Nancy L. Pressly ($11.50) had not
                                arrived in Germany; it will duly be recorded, however, in next
                                year’s “Checklist.”</note>
	<note id="n155"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Peter A. Tomory, <hi rend="i">The
                                    Poetical Circle: Fuseli and the British</hi> (Florence: Centro
                                Di, for the Australian Gallery Directors’ Council, 1979
                                [“Centro Di cat. 108”]; c. $15.00), being the
                                second, revised and enlarged edition of <hi rend="i">A Collection of
                                    Drawings by Henry Fuseli, R. A.</hi> (Auckland, N. Z.: City Art
                                Gallery, 1967), which has been reviewed by Michael J. Tolley in 
<hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter 11</hi>, 3 (Winter 1969),
                                51-52.</note>
	<note id="n156"><hi rend="s">17</hi> See Tomory 1979, p. 15.</note></p>
            <p>Besides the Milan catalogue, another Italian effort in Fuseli studies
                            ought to be mentioned. <hi rend="i">L’opera completa di
                                Füssli</hi> has many merits.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n157" type="note">18</ref> First, the 64 full-page illustrations in quarto
                            format represent the largest group of color plates from
                            Fuseli’s <hi rend="i">oeuvre</hi> published to the present
                            day; and the modest price of the book makes us put up with the fact that
                            some of them are rather marred, and 
<pb id="p15-55" n="55"/>
that they
                            often show a beastly tinge of red which of course is absent from the
                            original oils and watercolors. Then there is a competent
                            “elenco cronologico e iconografico di tutti i dipinti di
                            Füssli o a lui attribuiti,” compiled by Paola Viotto
                            under the guidance of Gert Schiff. This “catalogo delle [318]
                            opere” is illustrated with tiny black-and-white reproductions
                            of the paintings. Complete with an appendix (a descriptive and fully
                            illustrated list of 122 important Fuseli drawings), an
                            “itinerario di un’avventura critica,” a
                            select bibliography, a timetable, a thematic index, and an introductory
                            essay by Gert Schiff on “il classicista
                            ‘malgré lui,’” this makes up a
                            fine and most useful compendium. Side by side, the London catalogue of
                                1975<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n158"
type="note">19</ref> and this volume from the
                            “Classici dell’Arte” series constitute, as
                            it were, an abbreviated version of the monumental <hi rend="i">catalogue
                                raisonné.</hi>
	<note id="n157"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Gert Schiff and Paola Viotto, <hi rend="i">L’opera completa di
Füssli</hi>
                                (Milan: Rizzoli, 1977 [“Classici
                                dell’Arte,” vol. 91, n.s. vol. 6]; Italian Lire
                                3000. / c. $4.50 paperback edition, Lire 8000. / c. $10.50
                                hardcover.</note>
	<note id="n158"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Gert Schiff, et al., <hi rend="i">Henry Fuseli 1741-1825</hi> (London:
Tate Gallery Publications
                                Department, 1975).</note></p>
            <p>In spite of the warnings of Anthony Blunt and others,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n159" type="note">20</ref> both Blake and Fuseli scholars, where dealing
                            with the relation between the two artists, have all too often been
                            preoccupied with establishing dubious priorities in the use of this or
                            that motif. It is to be hoped that the wealth of materials published by
                            now, including some listed in this announcement, will help in tackling
                            more ingenious questions. Thus, the similarities in subject matter may
                            be weighed against the basic differences in personal style; Fuseli, the
                            outsider inside the academic system may confront Blake, the outsider
                            outside all systems but his own; Fuseli, as a representative of the 
<hi rend="i">Cinquecento</hi> tradition may be set against Blake, the
                            “creator as destroyer.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n160"
type="note">21</ref> I can think of no Fuseli painting which would be mistaken
                            as a Blake—in the present state of research it seems to be
                            worthwhile to accept the challenge and to ask why. What is needed now is
                            a comparistic investigation of the formal constituents of a number of
                            iconographically similar works by both artists. I should think that we
                            all have had enough of the narrow-minded and partial quarrels between
                            Fuselians and Blakeans, which often appear to be as irrelevant as they
                            are subjective, characterized by a mutual ignorance of the results of
                            the literature in the neighboring field of studies.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n161" type="note">22</ref> The latter, at least, need not be, and in the
                            future we may try not to 
<q> [Rear Priorities] with pedantic rage<lb/>
                                And [strew] with [Truisms] the unmeaning page,<lb/>
 Till Sense with
                                Nonsense, Truth with Falsehood toss’t<lb/>
 On
                                Fancy’s wave, [sink] in Confusion lost.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n162" type="note">23</ref></q>
	<note id="n159"><hi rend="s">20</hi> See Anthony F. Blunt, <hi rend="i">The Art of William Blake</hi> (New
York and London: Columbia
                                University Press, 1959), p. 41.</note>
	<note id="n160"><hi rend="s">21</hi> This, of course, is not to say that
                                there is no “Tradition” or
                                “Antiquity” in Blake’s work; he made
                                use of them, however, in a radically non-affirmative way. To
                                simplify matters: where the Swiss-born painter draws on artistic and
                                intellectual traditions, he does so as an
                                “imitator” (understood according to the definition
                                in his own first Academy lecture); Blake’s strengths and
                                weaknesses, on the other hand, originate in a method of
                                “Copying” based on
                                “Inspiration,” not “Mnemosyne.”
                                See Ralph N. Wornum, ed., <hi rend="i">Lectures by the Royal
                                    Academicians: Barry, Opie, and Fuseli</hi> (London: Henry G.
                                Bohn, 1848), p. 348, and Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
                                1.</note>
	<note id="n161"><hi rend="s">22</hi> The game was started contemporarily
                                by Stothard, and among its devotees we find Gilchrist, Federmann,
                                Albert S. Roe, Gert Schiff, and all too many others.</note>
	<note id="n162"><hi rend="s">23</hi> Fuseli’s
                                “Dunciad of Painting,” in Bircher &amp;
                                Guthke 1973, p. 81.</note></p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p15-56" n="56" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
