<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>15.1.hilton</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Donald H. Reiman, ed., The Garland Facsimiles of the Poetry of Erasmus Darwin</title>
                <author n="Hilton">Nelson Hilton</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Summer 1981</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1981</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">15.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Review Editor</resp>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Production Office</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Susan Corban</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>Pam Blair</name>
                            <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
                            <name>Wendy Jones</name>
                            <name>Kris Lackey</name>
                            <name>James Warwick</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>Martin K. Nurmi</name>
                            <name>Judith Page</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>Henry Summerfield</name>
                            <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1981"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_15">
        <body>
            <pb id="p15-28" n="28"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-15-1-0008">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
				  <head>
					<title type="main"><hi rend="b">ROMANTIC CONTEXT: POETRY</hi><lb/>
					Significant Minor Poetry 1789-1830<lb/>
					Printed in photo-facsimile in 128 volumes<lb/>
            		<hi rend="b">Selected and Arranged by Donald H. Reiman</hi></title>
				  </head>
                    <pb id="p15-36" n="36"/>
                    <div3>
                        <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
                        <head>
                            <title type="main" rend="main"><hi rend="b">The Spectre of Darwin</hi></title>
                        </head>
                        <head>
                            <title type="main">Erasmus Darwin. The Botanic Garden (in 2 Vols.), The Golden Age/The
                                Temple of Nature.</title>
                        </head>
                        <byline>
                            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
                            <docAuthor>
                                <hi rend="b">Nelson</hi>
                                <name>
                                    <hi rend="b">Hilton</hi>
                                </name>
                            </docAuthor>
                        </byline>
						<q> “ . . . couplets of shooting stars, lightning, the aurora borealis,
                            fires at the earth’s centre, animal incubation, volcanic mountains,
                            calcined shells, glow worms, fire-flies, steam-engines, water engines,
                            and ‘flying chariots.’”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n93"
type="note">1</ref>	
                                <note id="n93"><hi rend="s">1</hi> James V. Logan’s summary of some
                                passages in <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi> (<hi rend="i">The
                                    Poetry and Aesthetics of Erasmus Darwin</hi>, Princeton Studies
                                in English 15 [Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1936], p.
                                117).</note></q>
                        <p>To consider Erasmus Darwin and Blake is to join the widening discussion
                            over Blake’s knowledge and use of Science, and the debate over the
                            sources of his information. This discussion has thus far found its most
                            extreme formulation in Donald Ault’s important book, 
                                <hi rend="i">Visionary Physics.</hi> Ault’s book, it must be said, leaves
some
                            incredulous readers with the impression that Blake compassed the 
                                <hi rend="i">Principia</hi>—and while that may be true, it is important
                            for accepting Blake’s active use of scientific ideas to realize that
                            they were available through various and more popular sources. If, for
                            example, one stands the scientifically acute Swedenborg on his head, as
                            he did Newton, one ends up with a kind of basic Newtonianism again: core
                            ideas can be disseminated through unlikely texts. Erasmus Darwin is
                            similarly important for Blake studies—turned on his head, considered in
                            the light of what he was attempting rather than the way it was realized,
                            one could argue that Darwin is the English poet contemporary with Blake
                            who most shares Blake’s breadth of vision and his aim of ushering in the
                            reign of “sweet science” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> finis).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n94"
                                type="note">2</ref> Whether or not Blake actually works from some of
                            Darwin’s images is not the real issue here; what is important is that
                            Darwin represents a conduit of the latest scientific information easily
                            available to Blake: “there is no better way,” writes one historian of
                            the period, “of ascertaining the state of science in 1789-90, or a more
                            agreeable one, than by consulting Darwin’s poems and his voluminous
                                notes.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n95"
type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n94"><hi
                                    rend="s">2</hi> Students of Darwin, who usually delight in
                                showing his considerable presence in the imaginations of the
                                Romantics, have been at an imaginative loss in dealing with Blake.
                                For Desmond King-Hele, “Blake detested the technology celebrated in
                                    <hi rend="i">The Economy of Vegetation</hi>, and was probably
                                none too pleased that his superb engravings contributed to the
                                poem’s success” (<hi rend="i">Doctor of Revolution: The Life and
                                    Genius of Erasmus Darwin</hi> [London: Faber &amp; Faber, 1977],
                                p. 306); Donald M. Hassler finds that Blake “did not use [like
                                Shelley] science as a rhetorical foundation for his Platonism. . . .
                                Blake had no reason to be indebted to Darwin and, in fact,
                                deliberately stayed away from Darwin more than did any other
                                Romantic” (<hi rend="i">Erasmus Darwin</hi>, Twayne’s English
                                Authors Series [New York: Twayne Publishers, 1973], p.
                                127).</note>
	<note id="n95"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Francis D.
                                Klingender, <hi rend="i">Art and the Industrial Revolution</hi>,
                                ed., rev. Arthur Elton (New York: Augustus M. Kelley, 1968), p.
                                39.</note></p>
                        <p>We can assume that Blake read <hi rend="i">The Loves of the Plants</hi>
                                (<hi rend="i">LP</hi>), as did nearly everyone else in 1789. It was
                            published by Joseph Johnson (as were Darwin’s succeeding works) though
                            an arrangement which Fuseli evidently helped to bring about.<ref
                                target="n96" type="note">4</ref> Two years later, Blake undoubtedly
                            had read the succeeding volume, <hi rend="i">The Economy of
                                Vegetation</hi> (<hi rend="i">EV</hi>, dated 1791, probably
                            published May 1792), since he engraved and in part designed several
                            plates for the first edition (another followed in a later edition).
                            These two titles represent, respectively, Part II (already in a third
                            edition) and Part I of <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi>, the order
                            of publication reflecting an astute marketing decision since the more
                            “scientific” Part I proved less spectacularly popular than the sexual
                            double-entendres of <hi rend="i">The Loves of the Plants.</hi> Given
                            this history, it seems probable that Blake also read parts of 
                                <hi rend="i">Zoonomia</hi> (Z; 1794-96), the most significant of
                            Darwin’s mammoth prose works. Almost forgotten today, 
                                <hi rend="i">Zoonomia</hi> enjoyed wide republication and influence,<ref
                                target="n97" type="note">5</ref> being commonly linked with such
                            better remembered radical works as <hi rend="i">Political Justice</hi>
                            and <hi rend="i">The Age of Reason.</hi> Primarily as the result of a
                            concerted reactionary attack,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n98"
type="note">6</ref>
                            Darwin’s reputation collapsed and his posthumous poem, <hi rend="i">The
                                Temple of Nature</hi> (<hi rend="i">TN</hi>, 1802),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n99"
                                type="note">7</ref> met with little success. However, 
                                <pb id="p15-37" n="37"/>
as the most interesting and satisfying of
                            Darwin’s poems, and one again illustrated by Fuseli, it seems likely to
                            have attracted Blake’s attention. <note id="n96"><hi rend="s">4</hi>
                                Fuseli acted as the initial go-between for Darwin and Johnson
                                (King-Hele, p. 162), and Darwin effusively praises the “nightmare .
                                . . mark’d by FUSSELI’S poetic eye” (<hi rend="i">The Loves of the
                                    Plants</hi>, III.51ff.).</note>
	<note id="n97"><hi rend="s">5</hi> King-Hele reports that “The <hi rend="i">European
                                    Magazine</hi> quoted the opinion that <hi rend="i">Zoonomia</hi>
                                ‘bids fair to do for Medicine what Sir Isaac Newton’s 
                                    <hi rend="i">Principia</hi> has done for Natural Philosophy,’ and the 
                                    <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi> thought it ‘one of the most
                                important productions of the age’” (p. 241).</note>	
                                    <note id="n98"><hi rend="s">6</hi> See Norton Garfinkle, “Science and
Religion
                                in England, 1790-1800: The Critical Response to the Work of Erasmus
                                Darwin,” <hi rend="i">Journal of the History of Ideas</hi>, 16 (June
                                1955), 376-88. The most effective attack was a sustained parody
                                appearing in the first issues of <hi rend="i">The Anti-Jacobin
                                    Review</hi> (1798); entitled “The Loves of the Triangles,” it is
                                thought to have been authored by George Canning and two
                                collaborators.</note>
	<note id="n99"><hi rend="s">7</hi> The poem is
                                so named only on the title page, reflecting a last-minute change from
                                the announced pre-publication title (then subtitle), 
                                    <hi rend="i">The Origin of Society.</hi></note></p>
                        <p>Like Hayley, Darwin is little read today—poetically he seems to merit
                            regard mostly as a quintessential example of the diction against which
                            the “Preface” to <hi rend="i">Lyrical Ballads</hi> exclaims.<ref
                                target="n100" type="note">8</ref> But as encyclopedias—and all three
                            poems, with their indexes, their very extensive Notes, and still more
                            extensive Additional Notes force that comparison—they are fascinating.
                            And for the poet who, as W. J. T. Mitchell reminds us, delights in
                            encyclopedic form, Darwin would represent a benighted but sincere
                            fellow-traveller, some of whose entries were worth studying. And with
                            respect to the present viability of Blake’s science-based imagery, it is
                            significant that Darwin was in fact one of the most knowledgable
                            scientific intellects of the age,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n101" type="note">9</ref>
                            making reference to the latest theoretical and experimental work in his
                            poems and notes (for example, the <hi rend="i">OED</hi> says the 
                                <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi> offers the first English appearance
                            of “hydrogen”). Given such an accurate state-of-the-sciences, perhaps
                            the Poetic Genius could extrapolate future developments (“What is now
                            proved was once, only imagin’d”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n102" type="note">10</ref>.
                            This discussion will offer some examples of how Blake 
                                <hi rend="i">could</hi> have built on images and concepts supplied by
                            Darwin—images and concepts available elsewhere, to a regular reader of
                                <hi rend="i">Philosophical Transactions</hi> for instance, but most
                            accessible to us, and possibly to Blake, in their strange poetic and
                            annotated guise. <note id="n100"><hi rend="s">8</hi> According to
                                Coleridge, “Dr. Darwin laboured to make his style fine and gaudy, by
                                accumulating and applying all the sonorous and handsome-looking
                                words in our language. This is not poetry . . . .” (Hassler, p.
                                100). James Logan concludes that Darwin offers “a supreme example of
                                bad taste in ornate language” (p. 141).</note>
	<note id="n101"><hi
                                    rend="s">9</hi> Many quotations could be introduced here;
                                Coleridge again, before he soured on Darwin, wrote of “ . . . Dr.
                                Darwin, the everything, except the Christian! Dr. Darwin possesses,
                                perhaps, a greater range of knowledge than any other man in Europe,
                                and is the most inventive of philosophical men. He thinks in a 
                                    <hi rend="i">new</hi> train on all subjects except religion”;
                                King-Hele writes, “Though I may be biased, I regard Erasmus Darwin
                                as the greatest Englishman of the eighteenth century” (King-Hele,
                                pp. 260, 323). In addition to his own writing Darwin translated
                                Linnaeus, founded the famous “Lunar Society,” was so noted a doctor
                                that he was requested to become the Royal Physician, and was Charles
                                Darwin’s grandfather.</note>
	<note id="n102"><hi rend="s">10</hi><hi
                                    rend="i"> MHH</hi> 8; Blake citations are taken from David V.
                                Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William
                                Blake</hi>, 3rd printing rev. (Garden City, N. Y.: Doubleday,
                                1968).</note></p>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="b">I. PARENT POWER</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>The “beginning” of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> may offer a place
                                to start looking at Blake’s “use” of Darwin. After the prayerful and
                                oracular declarations, the poem announces, “Begin with Tharmas
                                Parent power. darkning in the West” (4.5). We begin with Tharmas,
                                evidently, because of an action—his darkning—and an attribution,
                                “Parent power.” To begin this way is then to begin at the beginning,
                                but also to defer the question of origin: not the parent, but the
                                power of parenting or generating is at stake. This suggests a
                                curious reflection of a favorite, almost formulaic expression of
                                Darwin’s which appears first in the famous “Of Generation” section
                                in <hi rend="i">Zoonomia</hi> and then twice in <hi rend="i">The
                                    Temple of Nature.</hi> In <hi rend="i">Zoonomia</hi> Darwin
                                notes that Hume “places the powers of generation much above those of
                                our boasted reason; and adds, that reason can only make a machine .
                                . . but the power of generation makes the maker.” Darwin goes on to
                                support Hume’s conclusion “that the world itself might have been
                                generated rather than created, . . . increasing by the activity of
                                its inherent principles rather than by a sudden evolution of the
                                whole by the Almighty fiat.” Darwin then stops to interject, “—What
                                a magnificent idea of the infinite power of THE GREAT ARCHITECT! THE
                                CAUSE OF CAUSES! PARENT OF PARENTS! ENS ENTIUM!”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n103"
                                    type="note">11</ref> In <hi rend="i">The Temple of Nature</hi>
                                nearly the same words characterize the source of “the immutable laws
                                impressed on matter,” the “amazing powers . . . originally impressed
                                on matter and spirit by the great Parent of Parents! Cause of
                                Causes! Ens Entium!”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n104"
type="note">12</ref> “Enion O
                                Enion” says the Parent power in its next line, and we are reminded
                                of one posited derivation for the name of the “Aged Mother.” 
                                    <note id="n103"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Erasmus Darwin, 
                                        <hi rend="i">Zoonomia; or The Laws of Organic Life</hi>, vol. I
(London:
                                    J. Johnson, 1794), p. 509.</note>
	<note id="n104"><hi rend="s">12</hi><hi rend="i"> TN</hi> IV. 453n.; cf. Add. Note VIII.
                                    Darwin is cited from the Scholar Press Facsimiles of 
                                        <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Temple
                                        of Nature</hi> published by the Scholar Press (Menston,
                                    Yorkshire) in 1973 with introductory notes by Desmond King-Hele;
                                    these reprint the first editions of each work or part (so
                                    creating a facsimile of <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi>
                                    which was never offered to the public—although many subscribers
                                    to the first edition of <hi rend="i">The Loves of the
                                        Plants</hi> undoubtedly bound up their own after purchasing
                                        <hi rend="i">The Economy of Vegetation</hi>).</note></p>
                            <p>Also relevant in this context is Darwin’s notion of the origin of
                                life from a primordial muscular fibre; this argument is detailed in
                                    <hi rend="i">The Temple of Nature</hi>, which tells that
                                “Imperious Man” “Arose from rudiments of form and sense, / An
                                embryon point, or microscopic ens!” (I.313-14). A note explains
                                “that all vegetables and animals arose from such a small beginning,
                                as a living point or living fibre.” Fibre is, one remembers, one of
                                Blake’s pervasive thematic conceptions: Tharmas asks Enion why
                                “every little fibre” of his soul is to be examined, and soon after
                                that the Parent power falls—“he sunk down.” Directly following: 
<q>
                                    His spectre issuing from his feet in flames of fire<lb/>
 In
                                    gnawing pain drawn out by her lovd fingers every nerve<lb/>
 She
                                    counted. every vein &amp; lacteal threading them. . . .
                                    (5.15-17) </q>
Here the syntax indicates that his spectre
                                consists—in part—of the fibres of nerve, vein, and lacteal which
                                Enion weaves into “a form of vegetation”: “She drew the Spectre
                                forth from Tharmas in her shining loom / Of vegetation” (6.1-2).
                                Blake would not have been the first to connect the primordial fibre
                                (line) and the Parent power—shortly after <hi rend="i">Zoonomia</hi>
                                was published, Richard Edgeworth wrote the author to say that the
                                attempted deistic cover-up did not deceive him: “Your Ens Entium is
                                the same as your living filament—your God of God!” (cited in
                                King-Hele, p. 251). For Blake also they are the same: “this Spectre
                                of Tharmas / Is Eternal Death;” the present embodiment, perhaps, of
                                the Darwinian powers of life that “seize, digest, secrete,—dispense
                                / The bliss of Being to the vital Ens” (<hi rend="i">TN</hi>
                                I.149-50, cf. 446). The creation of the circle of Destiny, the Ulro,
                                the system of generation is Blake’s beginning, the darkning of the
                                Parent power which underlies Darwin’s spurious homage to an apparent
                                “Parent of Parents” and governs his self-confident vision of
                                comprehensible, ultimate Nature.</p>
                            <p>A further example may serve to characterize the spectral presence of
                                Darwin. In Canto III of <hi rend="i">The Temple of Nature</hi>: 
<q>
                                    “The GIANT FORM on Nature’s centre stands,<lb/>
                                    And waves in ether his unnumber’d hands;<lb/>
                                    Whirls the bright planets in their silver spheres,<lb/>
                                    And the vast sun round other systems steers;<lb/>
                                    Till the last trump amid the thunder’s roar<lb/>
                                    Sound the dread Sentence “TIME SHALL BE NO MORE!”<lb/>
                                    (385-90)
                                </q>
                                Where in “Night the First” Blake reached back to begin before
                                Darwin’s beginning, in “Night the Ninth” his ending commences where
                                Darwin’s leaves off: 
<q> Los his vegetable hands<lb/>
                                Outstretchd his right hand branching out in fibrous Strength<lb/>
                                Siezd the Sun. His left hand like dark roots coverd the moon<lb/>
                                And tore them down cracking the heavens from immense to immense<lb/>
                            <pb id="p15-38" n="38"/> 
                            	Then fell the fire of Eternity with loud &amp; shrill<lb/>
                            	Sound of loud Trumpet thundering    (117.6-11) </q>
                                This first in a series of incomplete revelations
                                shows Los, Blake’s “giant form,” trying to engineer a Darwinian
                                apocalypse—his vegetable hands representing the admittedly grand
                                extension of a vegetable imagination (“Thus all the suns, and the
                                planets, which circle round them, may again sink into one central
                                chaos; and may again by explosions produce a new world; which in
                                process of time may resemble the present one, and at length undergo
                                the same catastrophe! these great events may be the result of the
                                immutable laws impressed on matter by the Great Cause of Causes,
                                Parent of Parents, Ens Entium!” [<hi rend="i">TN</hi> IV. 453n.]).
                                Los’ dramatic action, after all, comes from being “Terrified at Non
                                Existence / For such they deemd the death of the body.” Natural
                                Religion or Deistic Science seizes, <hi rend="i">orders</hi> the
                                heavens out of a fear of Non-Existence, the state of “the Spirit”
                                (cf. 117.3-4).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n105"
type="note">13</ref>	
                                        <note id="n105"><hi rend="s">13</hi> If these illustrations do have
any
                                    relevance they would necessarily posit a post-1802 date for the
                                    composition of the two passages from <hi rend="i">The Four
                                        Zoas.</hi></note></p>
                            <p>These tentative illustrations of “influence” (or perhaps simply,
                                “relevant overtone coloring”) suggest two aspects of Darwin’s
                                spectral presence in Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n106" type="note">14</ref>
                                First, that Blake was an appreciative and attentive reader of
                                Darwin; and second, that this very closeness made Darwin all the
                                more suspect for him, and so only “spectrally” present. For Darwin
                                had done—successfully, in the popular eye—what Blake wanted to do.
                                With a somewhat analogous scope of vision<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n107"
                                    type="note">15</ref> and a somewhat analogous sense of the
                                epistemic break reflected by the “scientific method,” Darwin created
                                a system all the more troubling to Blake’s imagination.<ref
                                    target="n108" type="note">16</ref> Where Darwin hoped “to inlist
                                Imagination under the banner of Science” (<hi rend="i">BG</hi>,
                                Advertisement), Blake strives for the reverse, under the banner of
                                “Sweet Science.” <note id="n106"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Compare
                                    Logan’s description of the presence of Lucretius in Darwin:
                                    “ghostlike, the influence . . . is more pervasive than factual
                                    and detailed” (p. 121).</note>
	<note id="n107"><hi rend="s">15</hi> In this respect Darwin represents the culmination
                                    of a history of “visionary”-scientific didactic poetry which
                                    includes Black-more’s <hi rend="i">Creation</hi>, Brooke’s 
                                        <hi rend="i">Universal Beauty</hi>, and a host of others. There
                                    is a volume to be written on this tradition and its relation to
                                    Blake.</note>
	<note id="n108"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Logan
                                    accurately notes that “Permeating <hi rend="i">The Botanic
                                        Garden</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Temple of Nature</hi> is a
                                    deep exhilaration, perhaps unconsciously transmitted into his
                                    work. It derives from his delight in the order and unity of
                                    nature, and his intense realization of a wonder newly born into
                                    the world, the infant science. The generation of poets that
                                    followed . . . failed to perceive that Darwin was a modern
                                    prophet, not inspired perhaps, but nevertheless a seer . . . .
                                    the first English poet to interpret modern science” (p.
                                    147).</note></p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="b">II. GEOPHYSICS</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>The power and appeal of Darwin at his best are evident in the
                                following lines from <hi rend="i">The Economy of Vegetation</hi>,
                                about which Walpole wrote a friend in May 1792, “the twelve verses
                                that by miracle describe and comprehend the creation of the universe
                                out of chaos, are in my opinion the most sublime passage in any
                                author. . . . ”:<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n109"
type="note">17</ref>
<q> 
                                	“—LET THERE BE LIGHT!” proclaim’d the ALMIGHTY LORD,<lb/>
                                	Astonish’d Chaos heard the potent word;—<lb/>
                                	Through all his realms the kindling Ether runs,<lb/>
                                	And the mass starts into a million suns;<lb/>
                                	Earths round each sun with quick explosions burst,<lb/>
                                	And second planets issue from the first;<lb/>
                                	Bend, as they journey with projectile force,<lb/>
                                	In bright ellipses their reluctant course;<lb/>
                                	Orbs wheel in orbs, round centres centres roll,<lb/>
                                	And form, selfbalanced, one revolving Whole.<lb/>
                                	—Onward they move amid their bright abode,<lb/>
                                    Space without bound, THE BOSOM OF THEIR GOD!<lb/>
                                    (I.103-14)
                                </q>
                                The Miltonic description, “self-balanced”—Characteristically
                                expanded to refer to an entire stellar system rather than just the
                                Earth—perhaps enters into Blake’s various usages of the image, but
                                far more significant is Darwin’s idea of planets born by explosions:
                                a note adds, “If these innumerable and immense 
                                    <hi rend="i">suns</hi> thus <hi rend="i">rising</hi> out of Chaos are
                                supposed to have thrown out their attendant planets by new
                                explosions, as they ascended; and those their respective satellites,
                                filling in a moment the immensity of space with light and motion, a
                                grander idea cannot be conceived by the mind of man” (italics
                                added). <note id="n109"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Walpole also wrote of
                                    the poem, it “is so deep, that I cannot read six lines together
                                    and know what they are about, till I have studied them in the
                                    long notes” (<hi rend="i">The Letters of Horace Walpole</hi>,
                                    ed. Mrs. Paget Toynbee [Oxford, 1905], XV, 110).</note></p>
                            <p>But three years later, Chapter I of <hi rend="i">The Book of
                                    Urizen</hi> opens with “Lo, a shadow of horror is risen / In
                                Eternity! . . . . Times on times he divided.” The grander idea in
                                the mind of Blake was first suggested in David Worrall’s important
                                and detailed discussion of Blake’s adaption of Darwin’s geophysical
                                speculations—the second section of his “William Blake and Erasmus
                                Darwin’s <hi rend="i">Botanic Garden</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n110"
                                    type="note">18</ref> is essential reading for any student of
                                Blake. Darwin’s idea of cosmogenic explosions involves volcanos and
                                earthquakes: “We can have no idea of a natural power, which could
                                project a Sun out of Chaos, except by comparing it to the explosions
                                or earthquakes owing to the sudden evolution of aqueous or of other
                                more elastic vapours; of the power of which under immeasurable
                                degrees of heat, and compression, we are yet ignorant” 
                                    (<hi rend="i">EV</hi> I.105n.). A note on “Solar Volcanos” suggests
that
                                “cavities are made in the sun’s body by a process similar to our
                                Earthquakes” (<hi rend="i">EV</hi> Add. N. XV), and,
                                correspondingly, as the earth’s volcanos show its center to consist
                                of “a large mass of burning lava . . . . a second sun,”<ref
                                    target="n111" type="note">19</ref> “the first earthquakes, which
                                produced immense changes in the globe, must have been occasioned by
                                central fires” (<hi rend="i">EV</hi> Add. N. VI). So in 
                                    <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi>, already beginning Blake’s
                                correspondence between head and (astronomical) orb, the King of
                                France appears with “his forehead . . . in affliction, / Like the
                                central fire” (79-80). A striking instance of geophysical dynamic
                                was the creation of the moon: 
<q> And Earth’s hugh sphere exploding
                                    burst in twain.—<lb/>
 GNOMES! how you gazed! when from her
                                    wounded side<lb/>
 Where now the South-Sea heaves its waste of
                                    tide,<lb/>
 Rose on swift wheels the MOON’S refulgent car<lb/>
                                    Circling the solar orb, a sister-star<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">EV</hi>
                                    II.76-80) </q>
Blake refers to this image several times, first,
                                as Worrall observes, in <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi> when
                                Aumont “compares and dates man’s first <hi rend="i">enslavement</hi>
                                to changes in the heavens” [italics added]: “the terrible sun clos’d
                                in an orb, and the moon / Rent from the nations” (211-12). In 
                                    <hi rend="i">American</hi> the “close hall of counsel”—the skull is
                                one referent (cf. <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> 10.25ff.)—was “built when
                                the moon shot forth, / In that dread night when Urizen call’d the
                                stars round his feet.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n112"
type="note">20</ref> One of
                                the most intriguing developments occurs in <hi rend="i">The Book of
                                    Urizen</hi>, where Darwin’s cosmological dynamic seems to inform
                                both Urizen, “rent from [the] side” of Los, “By earthquakes riv’n,
                                belching sullen fires” (6.4, 10.4); and Los, “His bosom earthquak’d
                                with sighs” (13.49) and then dividing to produce the first female
                                form—all on a stage of the Void, “the endless Abyss of space” 
                                    <pb id="p15-39" n="39"/> (15.10). As R. E. Simmons first noted,
                                these passages—which result in Urizen as a “clod of clay” and the
                                globe of blood or incipient female “Wand’ring wide on the bosom of
                                night”—suggest “a geophysical theory of the origin of the earth as a
                                chunk of matter thrown off by the sun.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n113"
                                    type="note">21</ref> The developing analogy can be pressed even
                                further, for, as Darwin illustrates, gravity was commonly imaged as
                                a chain: “Chain’d to one centre whirl’d the kindred spheres” 
                                    (<hi rend="i">EV</hi> II.91). So, directly after being rent from the
                                side of Los (/sol), Urizen is chained up—in “chains of the mind” to
                                be sure, but also gravity (that serious matter). This points to the
                                ontological relation between present existence, enslaved, and
                                “creation,” for in Eternity “Earth was not: nor globes of
                                attraction” (<hi rend="i">BU</hi> 3.36). “Creation” was the fall
                                from energy/imagination into matter and its accompanying systems of
                                gravity and space-time, a conception which has roots in Swedenborg’s
                                science-based fantasy of the “spiritual” universe mirrored by our
                                tangible one. The important point, as Worrall concludes, is that
                                “After <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi>, Darwin’s geophysical
                                speculations are quickly absorbed into the expanding synthesis of
                                Albion’s Angel, Urizen, and Los, where the scientific version of the
                                relations of chaos, sun, and earth are freely interchanged” (p.
                                417); this opens the way to one key analogy guiding the cosmology of
                                Blake’s “cosmic” myth, an analogy which should somewhat refocus our
                                sense of Blake’s concerns. Los is, on <hi rend="i">one</hi> level,
                                the actual sun; Urizen the Earth; Enitharmon the moon.<ref
                                    target="n114" type="note">22</ref> The most far-reaching
                                concrete analogies are set up and then spiritualized, so that Los
                                includes the total imagistic potential of the sun and so forth.
                                    <note id="n110"><hi rend="s">18</hi><hi rend="i"> Bulletin of
                                        the New York Public Library</hi>, 78 (Summer 1975),
                                    397-417.</note>
	<note id="n111"><hi rend="s">19</hi> David Erdman
                                    suggests that Luvah’s name is related to “lava” via Darwin 
                                        (<hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire</hi>, rev. [Garden
                                    City, N. Y.: Doubleday, 1969], p. 334).</note>	
                                        <note id="n112"><hi rend="s">20</hi> The same night, evidently, that
the
                                    stars threw down their spears/spheres/tears.</note>	
                                    <note id="n113"><hi rend="s">21</hi> “<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>: The
                                    Symmetry of Fear,” in <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms
                                        Dramatic</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1969),
                                    pp. 146-73, p. 153.</note>
	<note id="n114"><hi rend="s">22</hi>
                                    Like Ahania: 
<q> . . . a faint shadow wandring<lb/>
 In chaos and
                                        circling dark Urizen,<lb/>
 As the moon anguishd circles the
                                        earth; (<hi rend="i">BA</hi> 2.38-40) </q></note></p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="b">III. BIOGENETICS</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>Another recent critic finds Darwin behind the “biogenetic creation”
                                in <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.</hi> Unfortunately, D. C.
                                    Leonard<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n115"
type="note">23</ref> uses relevant
                                quotations to support forced relations. Darwin, to repeat, is
                                spectrally present in Blake—his importance lies in the compendium of
                                scientific imagery he offered rather than in massive direct
                                influence. Consider, for example, as Leonard does, Darwin’s
                                memorable lines on embryonic development as exemplified in the
                                crocodile. The passage itself, significantly, is introduced to
                                establish a comparison with seed development, the subject of
                                preceeding lines. To suggest the less specific but more pervasive
                                nature of Darwin’s “influence” on Blake, we must look at the
                                movement of these eighty-some lines as a whole, for their real (and
                                Blakean) burden is a vision of interpenetrating, interacting
                                correspondences. <note id="n115"><hi rend="s">23</hi> “Erasmus
                                    Darwin and William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century
                                        Life</hi>, 4 (March 1978), 79-81.</note></p>
                            <p>The Botanic Muse opens the subject by addressing her 
                            	“Sylphs,”<ref target="n116" type="note">24</ref>
								<q> 
									“SYLPHS! as you hover on ethereal wing,<lb/>
									Brood the green children of parturient Spring!—<lb/>
									Where in their bursting cells my Embryons rest,<lb/>
									I charge you guard the vegetable nest;<lb/>
									Count with nice eye the myriad SEEDS, that swell<lb/>
									Each vaulted womb of husk, or pod, or shell;<lb/>
									Feed with sweet juices, clothe with downy hair,<lb/>
									Or hang, inshrined, their little orbs in air.” 
								</q>
								The little orbs hanging in air suggest stars
                                and, indeed, the following four lines make the comparison explicit:
								<q> 
									“So, late decry’d by HERSCHEL’S piercing sight,<lb/>
									Hang the bright squadrons of the twinkling Night;<lb/>
									Ten thousand marshall’d stars, a silver zone,<lb/>
									Effuse their bended lustres round her throne;”<lb/>
									(<hi rend="i">EV</hi> IV.351-62)
								</q>
                                Here, then, we see stars as vegetable seeds or pods, hanging in
                                a tracery of vegetation, perhaps like those in Blake’s first
                                illustration to <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso.</hi> The star-seed-orbs
                                as “husk, or pod, or shell” suggests how <hi rend="i">The Four
                                    Zoas</hi> can imagine “the stars threshd from their husks”
                                    (134.1);<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n117"
type="note">25</ref> while the “sweet
                                juices” feeding the seeds suggest an analogy to some stellar,
                                etherial nutrient. The comparison of seeds to stars leads to a
                                digression: 
<q> 
                                	Flowers of the sky! ye too to age must yield,<lb/>
                                    Frail as your silken sisters of the field!<lb/>
                                    Star after star from Heaven’s high arch shall rush,<lb/>
                                    Suns sink on suns, and systems systems crush,<lb/>
                                    Headlong, extinct, to one dark centre fall,<lb/>
                                    And Death and Night and Chaos mingle all!<lb/>
                                    —Till o’er the wreck, emerging from the storm,<lb/>
                                    Immortal NATURE lifts her changeful form,<lb/>
                                    Mounts from her funeral pyre on wings of flame,<lb/>
                                    And soars and shines, another and the same.<lb/>
                                    (IV.371-80)
                                </q>
                                A note refers us to Herschel’s
                                conclusion “that the nebulae or constellations of fixed stars are
                                approaching each other, and must finally coalesce in one mass.” The
                                “Flame” of Nature’s wings reappears as the lines following return to
                                the discussion of seeds: 
<q>
                                	“Lo! on each SEED within its slender rind,<lb/>
                                	Life’s golden threads in endless circles wind;<lb/>
                                    Maze within maze the lucid webs are roll’d,<lb/>
                                    And, as they burst, the living flame unfold.<lb/>
                                    The pulpy acorn, ere it swells, contains<lb/>
                                    The Oak’s vast branches in its milky veins;<lb/>
                                    Each ravel’d bud, fine film, and fibre-line<lb/>
                                    Traced with nice pencil on the small design.”<lb/>
                                    (IV.381-88)
                                </q>
                                The “living flame” is vegetation, an image frequent enough in
                                Blake’s illustrations. More than that, it reflects organic energy,
                                the vital power that haunts Darwin—it is but a shift of focus to see
                                this power as spiritual or mental flames. The image of “Life’s
                                golden threads . . . Maze within maze” picks up an earlier image of
                                the body’s circulatory system, which “O’er . . . tissued membrane
                                spreads / In living net-work all its branching threads; / Maze
                                within maze;” just as, in turn, “So shoot the Spider-broods at breezy
                                dawn / Their glittering net-work o’er the autumnal lawn” 
                                    (<hi rend="i">EV</hi> III.531-33, 555-56). The discussion of seeds
                                culminates in a picture of Earth, “the mighty ball”: 
<q> And the
                                    GREAT SEED evolves, disclosing ALL:<lb/>
 LIFE 
                                        <hi rend="i">buds</hi> or <hi rend="i">breathes</hi> from Indus to the
                                    Poles,<lb/>
 And the vast surface kindles, as it rolls!<lb/> 
                                        (<hi rend="i">EV</hi> IV.406-8) </q>
	<pb id="p15-40" n="40"/>
It
                                is not far to the “globe of life blood,” the seed of Nature, the
                                first “female form” (<hi rend="i">BU</hi> 18.1, 7). These sorts of
                                associations help to gloss some of the multi-dimensions of creation
                                in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>:
<q> . . . A Web dark &amp; cold,
                                    throughout all<lb/>
 The tormented element stretch’d<lb/>
 From
                                    the sorrows of Urizens soul<lb/>
 And the Web is a Female in
                                    embrio.<lb/>
 None could break the Web, no wings of fire.<lb/>
                                    (25.15-19) </q>
Nature’s “wings of flame” cannot break the net
                                of its own laws. Dampened by the melancholy of natural abstraction,
                                these flames of nature or natural inspiration are merely “another
                                and the same,” or, as Blake saw the process, “the Ashes of Mystery”
                                animating again, “as of old so now anew began / Babylon again in
                                Infancy Calld Natural Religion” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> VIII,
                                111.22-24). <note id="n116"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Darwin stated at
                                    the outset of the poem that the Sylphs, together with the
                                    Gnomes, Nymphs, and Salamanders of Rosicrucian doctrine, afford
                                    “proper machinery for a philosophic poem; as it is probable that
                                    they were originally the names of hieroglyphic figures of the
                                    Elements, or of Genii presiding over their operations. The
                                    Fairies of more modern days seem to have been derived from them.
                                    . . .” Klingender’s observation that “Darwin’s nymphs reveal a
                                    graceful charm and a mischievous propensity for unexpected
                                    metamorphoses into machinery, plants or elemental forces of
                                    nature” (p. 37), suggests that they are not entirely unrelated
                                    to Blake’s “mighty ones”—or to his Genii, Gnomes, Nymphs, and
                                    Fairies for that matter.</note>
	<note id="n117"><hi rend="s">25</hi> I discuss this further in “Spears, Spheres, and
                                    Spiritual Tears: Blake’s Poetry as <hi rend="i">The Tyger</hi>,
                                    11. 17-20,” forthcoming in <hi rend="i">Philological
                                        Quarterly.</hi></note></p>
                            <p>Darwin’s discussion of seeds now moves to the conclusion which
                                interested D. C. Leonard: 
<q> While in bright veins the silvery Sap
                                    ascends,<lb/>
 And refluent blood in milky eddies bends;<lb/>
                                    While, spread in air, the leaves respiring play,<lb/>
 Or drink
                                    the golden quintessence of day.<lb/>
 —So from his shell on
                                    Delta’s shower-less isle<lb/>
 Burst into life the Monster of the
                                    Nile;<lb/>
 First in translucent lymph with cobweb-threads<lb/>
                                    The Brain’s fine floating tissue swells, and spreads;<lb/>
 Nerve
                                    after nerve the glistening spine descends,<lb/>
 The red Heart
                                    dances, the Aorta bends;<lb/>
 Through each new gland the purple
                                    current glides,<lb/>
 New veins meandering drink the refluent
                                    tides;<lb/>
 (IV.419-30) </q>
Leonard’s analogy to the first four
                                lines of “the Monster’s” creation (<hi rend="i">BU</hi>
                                    10.19-23)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n118"
type="note">26</ref> seems too
                                ground-less to bear repeating; nonetheless, every reader will
                                probably sense something Blake-like at work. Here again, what seem
                                to reverberate are words and minute images, rather than larger
                                patterns or trains of images (Blake metonymizes rather than
                                metaphorizes Darwin). Through the use of “cobweb-threads” and
                                “tissue,” Darwin’s image of the brain recalls the seed and its
                                “lucid webs” and the body’s “tissued membrane” with its “living
                                net-work” similar to that made by the Spider. So <hi rend="i">The
                                    Book of Urizen</hi>’s development of Urizen’s “spiders web,” the
                                “Female in embrio,” is not altogether without precedent: 
<q> 8. So
                                    twisted the cords, &amp; so knotted<lb/>
 The meshes: twisted
                                    like to the human brain<lb/>
 9. And all calld it, The Net of
                                    Religion.<lb/>
 (25.20-22) </q>
The brain, 
                                    <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> says, “is the Seat / Of Satan in its Webs”
                                (20.37-38). Darwin’s description of “the glistening spine descends”
                                is for Leonard a picture of Urizen 
<q> In a horrible dreamful
                                    slumber;<lb/>
 Like the linked infernal chain;<lb/>
 A vast Spine
                                    writh’d in torment<lb/>
 (10.35-37) </q>
This association serves
                                to remind us that Blake’s vision has a far greater (and more
                                compressed) complexity than Darwin’s: Urizen’s “geophysical” chain
                                of gravity is doubled by a “biogenetic” spine; both are,
                                inferentially, serpentine or worm-like, and both the result of
                                “horrible dreamful slumber”—as was, perhaps, Darwin’s entire vision
                                for Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n119"
type="note">27</ref> Drawing on Albert
                                S. Roe’s discussion of “The Fertilization of Egypt,”<ref
                                    target="n120" type="note">28</ref> which Blake engraved and in
                                part designed for <hi rend="i">The Economy of Vegetation</hi>,
                                Leonard confidently asserts the identity of this “Monster of the
                                Nile” [crocodile] with Darwin’s Nile River God and hence Blake’s
                                “Egyptian Monster, Urizen.” <note id="n118"><hi rend="s">26</hi><q>
                                        3. The eternal mind bounded began to roll<lb/>
 Eddies of
                                        wrath ceaseless round &amp; round<lb/>
 And the sulphureous
                                        foam surgeing thick<lb/>
 Settled, a lake, bright, &amp;
                                        shining clear:<lb/>
 White as the snow on the mountains cold.
                                    </q></note>
	<note id="n119"><hi rend="s">27</hi> Hassler notes
                                    that Darwin “is not troubled with trying to discover one central
                                    myth—not troubled because he basically understands, I think,
                                    that there is no such final unity” (p. 28)—for Blake also “a
                                    Perfect Unity Cannot Exist,” but everything hinges on whether or
                                    not one wishes to pursue the qualification, “but from the
                                    Universal Brotherhood of Eden” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi>
                                    3).</note>
	<note id="n120"><hi rend="s">28</hi> See “The Thunder
                                    of Egypt,” in Alvin H. Rosenfeld, ed., <hi rend="i">William
                                        Blake: Essays for S. Foster Damon</hi> (Providence, R. I.:
                                    Brown University Press, 1969), pp. 158-95.</note></p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="b">IV. LIVING LINES</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>Leonard also reminds us of the central importance and wide
                                applicability of Darwin’s proposal “that all warm-blooded animals
                                have arisen from one living filament, which THE FIRST GREAT CAUSE
                                endued with animality” (<hi rend="i">Z</hi> 39.4, p. 505), relating
                                it to the “fibrous” branching of the globe of life blood, whose
                                “fibres or filaments” Leonard sees as “the life roots of creation.”
                                More interesting, though equally lacking in credible support, is
                                Leonard’s intuitive analogy linking Orc in his initial, simple, form
                                of a worm to Darwin’s primordial filament. 
<q> . . . Enitharmon,
                                    sick,<lb/>
 Felt a Worm within her womb.<lb/>
<lb/>
 4. Yet
                                    helpless it lay like a Worm<lb/>
 In the trembling womb<lb/>
 To
                                    be moulded into existence<lb/>
<lb/>
 5. All day the worm lay on
                                    her bosom<lb/>
 All night within her womb<lb/>
 The worm lay till
                                    it grew to a serpent<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">BU</hi> 19.19-26) </q>
                                This may be seen, in part, as a description of the penis in the
                                vagina and also, evidently, as the male seed (already known to
                                consist of worm-like forms<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n121" type="note">29</ref>).
                                Leonard and also Carmen S. Kreiter<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n122" type="note">30</ref> develop the idea that the worm’s change to “Many forms
                                of fish, bird &amp; beast” which “Brought forth an Infant form”
                                suggests embryonic “evolutionary” recapitulation. Of equal interest
                                is the development of “the worm” into Blake’s general silk-worm
                                imagery, and the obliquely related idea of some form of “line” at
                                the source of creation. This idea might be summarized as follows:
<q>
                                    (chain = spine = serpent/worm = fibre) = line<lb/>
                                    (= speech/writing [lines of text])
                                    </q>
							<note id="n121"><hi rend="s">29</hi> See 
									<corr type="emend">Albrecht</corr> von Haller, <hi rend="i">First Lines of
                                        Physiology</hi>, trans. William Cullen, The Sources of
                                    Science No. 32, 2 vols. in 1 (1786; fac. rpt. New York and
                                    London: Johnson Reprint, 1966), Sect. 882.</note>
                            <note id="n122"><hi rend="s">30</hi> “Evolution and William Blake,” 
                                        <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 4 (Winter 1965),
                                    110-18.</note></p>
                            <p>For Darwin, the idea of the first filament/fibre/line seems to have
                                accompanied some sort of imaginative revelation, since while lines
                                pass unremarked in <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi>, after the
                                discussions of fibres in <hi rend="i">Zoonomia</hi> they come to
                                prominence in <hi rend="i">The Temple of Nature.</hi> A reference to
                                spiders in the earlier work evokes a tag from Pope while hinting, as
                                mentioned above, at an analogy between the spider’s “glittering
                                net-work” and the body’s “living net-work”:<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n123"
                                    type="note">31</ref>
<q>
                                	So shoot the Spider-broods at breezy dawn<lb/>
                                	Their glittering net-work o’er the autumnal lawn;<lb/>
                                    From blade to blade connect with cordage fine<lb/>
                            <pb id="p15-41" n="41"/> 
                            		The unbending grass, and live along the line;<lb/>
                                    (<hi rend="i">EV</hi> III.555-58) 
 								</q>
 								The branching
                                threads become living lineaments of art in a revision of the formula
                                as it appears in <hi rend="i">The Temple of Nature</hi>, a passage
                                which might remind the reader of Los’s sculpted halls 
                                (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 16.61ff.): 
<q>
                                	Unnumber’d ailes connect unnumber’d halls,<lb/>
                                	And sacred symbols crowd the pictur’d walls;<lb/>
                                    With pencil rude forgotten days design,<lb/>
                                    And arts, or empires, live in every line.<lb/>
                                    (I.85-88)
                                </q>
 								But the real
                                burden of <hi rend="i">The Temple of Nature</hi>—versifying what had
                                already been worked out at length in 
                                <hi rend="i">Zoonomia</hi>—appears in passages such as the following: 
<q>
                                    ATTRACTION next, as earth or air subsides,<lb/>
                                    The ponderous atoms from the light divides,<lb/>
                                    Approaching parts with quick embrace combines,<lb/>
                                    Swells into spheres, and lengthens into lines.<lb/>
                                    Last, as fine goads the gluten-threads excite,<lb/>
                                    Cords grapple cords, and webs with webs unite:<lb/>
                                    And quick CONTRACTION with etheral flame<lb/>
                                    Lights into life the fibre-woven frame.—<lb/>
                                    Hence without parent by spontaneous birth<lb/>
                                    Rise the first specks of animated earth;<lb/>
                                    From Nature’s womb the plat or insect swims,<lb/>
                                    And buds or breathes, with microscopic limbs.<lb/>
                                    (I.239-53)
                                </q>
 								Given lines, the whole fabric/tissue/text of creation follows, woven in
                                the looms of nature; so <hi rend="i">The Loves of the Plants</hi>
                                tells of the “Inventress of the Woof, fair LINA” (II.67)—cotton’s
                                appropriate Latin name—in whose loom is worked “the fibre-line”
                                (II.78; lines become linen). Among the primal microscopic forms of
                                life are “Self-moving lines” (<hi rend="i">TN</hi> I.286), while in
                                seeds, “The Reproductions of the living Ens” commence as “the living
                                fibre shoots” and “new embryon fibrils . . . form the living line”
                                    (<hi rend="i">EV</hi> II.63, 65, 79-80). Out of such
                                reproductive techniques “heaven born STORGE weaves the social
                                    chain;”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n124"
type="note">32</ref> and “soft
                                affections live along the line,” for “Birth after birth the line
                                unchanging runs / And fathers live transmitted in their sons” 
                                    (<hi rend="i">TN</hi> II.92, 94, 107-08). Darwin’s note on
                                “Imagination’s power” over reproduction says, “It is not to be
                                understood, that the first living fibres, are produced by
                                imagination, with any similarity of form to the future animal, but
                                with appetencies or propensities, which shall produce . . .
                                corresponding with the imagination of the father” (II.118n.). For
                                Blake, imagination is the father of all reproduction, the creator
                                (not reproducer) of the line which (as for Darwin) is only
                                “tinctured” in the loom/womb textile machinery of the mother: 
<q>
                                    And first he drew a line upon the walls of shining heaven<lb/>
                                    And Enitharmon tincturd it with beams of blushing love<lb/>
                                    It remaind permanent a lovely form inspird divinely human<lb/>
                                    Dividing into just proportions Los unwearied labourd<lb/>
                                    The immortal lines upon the heavens<lb/>
                                    (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> VIIa 90.35-39)
                                </q>
                                This offers a more encompassing vision of
                                Darwin’s “chemic arts” which “disclosed in pictured lines, / Liv’d
                                to mankind” (<hi rend="i">EV</hi> I.367-68); Darwin’s line is
                                finally the agent and expression of imitation (artistic or
                                “genetic”) rather than 
                                imagination.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n125"
type="note">33</ref>
                                <note id="n123"><hi rend="s">31</hi> George Poulet
                                    offers some important remarks on this theme in <hi rend="i">The
                                        Metamorphoses of the Circle</hi>, trans. Carley Dawson and
                                    Elliott Coleman (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press,
                                    1966), pp. 55 ff.</note>
                                <note id="n124"><hi rend="s">32</hi> A
                                    note adds that “the Greek word Storgè is used for the affection
                                    of parents to children” (Add. N. IX), offering another possible
                                    source for Blake’s unique description of “Love of Parent
                                    Storgous Appetite” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> V, 61.10).</note>
                                <note id="n125"><hi rend="s">33</hi> James Logan writes: “It must be
                                    admitted that [Darwin] narrowed down the mental process called
                                    imagination to more precise terms than any one who went before
                                    him. But in doing so, he greatly limited the scope of
                                    imagination; . . . Imagination . . . according to Darwin, is a
                                    state in which our ideas are evoked by mere sensation, by the
                                    emotions of pleasure and pain; it is best designated by the word
                                    revery” (p. 54).</note></p>
                            <p><hi rend="i">The Temple of Nature</hi> also presents the living-line
                                or fibre as the basic unit of animation because of its power of
                                contraction. A note to the lengthy passage quoted above says that
                                “The power of contraction, which exists in organized bodies and
                                distinguishes life from inanimation, appears to consist of an
                                ethereal fluid which resides in the brain and nerves of living
                                bodies, and is expended in the act of shortening their fibres”
                                (I.245n.). A power of expansion, which Darwin nowhere posits
                                (expansion being the result of another contraction), was already
                                part of Blake’s conception of Eternity: “The will of the Immortal
                                expanded / Or contracted his all flexible senses” 
                                (<hi rend="i">BU</hi> 3.37-38). Eternity, evidently, is non-linear: the pure
                                state, perhaps, of the “etherial fluid” or “spirit of animation”
                                (<hi rend="i">Z</hi>, p. 
                                30).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n126"
type="note">34</ref> 
                                Given the heritage of Locke and Newton (in the
                                “Questions” appended to <hi rend="i">The Opticks</hi>), and
                                particularly Hartley (who greatly influences Darwin), our textured
                                universe of lines and fibres testifies to the impossibility of
                                Edenic perception; for Darwin, indeed, “The word 
                                <hi rend="i">idea</hi> . . . is defined as a contraction, or motion, or
                                configuration, of the fibres” (<hi rend="i">Z</hi>, p. 11). The
                                lines of thought, in turn, become chains, “links of the chain of
                                fibrous actions” (<hi rend="i">TN</hi> Add. N. VII): 
<q>
                                	Last in thick swarms ASSOCIATIONS spring,<lb/>
                                	Thoughts join to thoughts, to motions motions cling;<lb/>
                                	Whence in long trains of catenation flow<lb/>
                                	Imagined joy, and voluntary woe.<lb/>
                                    (<hi rend="i">TN</hi> I.277-80) 
                                </q>
                                Individual words
                                reflect “In parted links the long ideal trains” and are,
                                furthermore, “Chain’d down in characters” to give “to sight the
                                evanescent sound” (<hi rend="i">TN</hi> III.398, IV.266, 268).
                                Darwin himself realizes one now much-discussed consequence of this
                                imprisonment: “the acquirement of different languages in their
                                infancy may affect the modes of thinking and reasoning of whole
                                nations, or of different classes of society; as the words of them do
                                not accurately suggest the same ideas, or parts of ideal trains; a
                                circumstance which has not been sufficiently analysed” 
                                (<hi rend="i">TN</hi> IV.398n.). 
                                <note id="n126"><hi rend="s">34</hi> Darwin
                                    continues, “The circumstances attending the exertion of the
                                    power of ATTRACTION constitute the laws of motion of inanimate
                                    matter”—Eternity precedes the constitution of these laws (“Earth
                                    was not: nor globes of attraction”).</note></p>
                            <p>The silk-worm occupies an interesting position in this universe of
                                lines: a kind of “living line,” it cocoons itself with self-produced
                                line, only to burst its “well-woven house of silk” 
                                (<hi rend="i">TN</hi> Add. N. IX) after transformation. Darwin’s images also
                                serve to remind us that “worm” was a standard term for “silk-worm,”
                                a convention which has ramifications for Blake’s references: 
<q>
                                	The Silk-Worm broods in countless tribes above<lb/>
                                	Crop the green treasure, uninform’d of love;<lb/>
                                	Erewhile the changeful worm with circling head<lb/>
                                	Weaves the nice curtains of his silken bed;<lb/>
                                	Web within web involves his larva form,<lb/>
                                	Alike secured from sunshine and from storm;<lb/>
                                	For twelve long days He dreams of blossom’d 
                            <pb id="p15-42" n="42"/> 
                            		groves,<lb/>
                                    Untasted honey, and ideal loves;<lb/>
                                    Wakes from his trance, alarm’d with young Desire,<lb/>
                                    Finds his new sex, and feels ecstatic fire;<lb/>
                                    (<hi rend="i">TN</hi> II.295-304)
                                </q>
                                The rationale for this is “sexual reproduction only which seems to have
                                been the chef-d’oeuvre, or capital work of 
                                nature;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n127"
type="note">35</ref> 
                                as appears by the wonderful transformation
                                of leaf-eating caterpillars into honey-eating moths and butterflyes,
                                apparently for the sole purpose of the formation of sexual organs,
                                as in the silk-worm, which takes no food after its transformation,
                                but propagates its species and dies” (<hi rend="i">TN</hi> Add. N.
                                VIII). The silk-worm’s change raises in particular the question of
                                instinct: 
<q>
                                	Conscious of change the Silkworm-Nymphs begin<lb/>
                                    Attach’d to leaves their gluten-threads to spin;<lb/>
                                    Then round and round they weave with circling heads<lb/>
                                    Sphere within Sphere, and form their silken beds.<lb/>
                                    —Say, did these fine volitions first commence<lb/>
                                    From clear ideas of the tangent sense;<lb/>
                                    From sires to sons by imitation caught,<lb/>
                                    Or in dumb language by tradition taught?<lb/>
                                    Or did they rise in some primeval site<lb/>
                                    Of larva gnat, or microscopic mite;<lb/>
                                    (<hi rend="i">TN</hi> III.419-28).
                                </q>
                                No answer is suggested
                                here, but Darwin’s discussion of the Portland Vase in 
                                <hi rend="i">The Economy of Vegetation</hi> pointed the way to an analogy
                                that might have interested Blake. Instinct, the “dumb language,” and
                                the “spirit of imagination” exist outside the immediate organization
                                of lines to effect the transformation of line into expanded plenum:
                                each parted linear link of word is also like a worm, waiting for its
                                wings. <note id="n127"><hi rend="s">35</hi> This same argument in
                                    Darwin’s <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">Phytologia</hi>,</corr> or “a theory of
                                    vegetation” (Dublin, 1800), adds “ . . . and much pleasure is
                                    afforded” (cited by Hassler, p. 76).</note></p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="b">V. THE PORTLAND VASE</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>The famous Barberini Vase, which had been brought to England eighteen
                                months previously, was acquired by the Duke of Portland in June
                                1786. A few days later it was loaned to Josiah Wedgwood, who had
                                long desired to create some copies of it. Wedgwood was another close
                                friend of Darwin’s: their families were to be linked by marriage,
                                and Wedgwood’s remarkable industrial pottery, “Etruria,” was so
                                named by Darwin because he thought that Wedgwood had rediscovered a
                                kind of ceramic painting previously known only to the ancient
                                Etruscans. Darwin no doubt studied the original and in 1790 was sent
                                the first copy for approval. Against this background it is no
                                surprise to see a slight reference to the vase in <hi rend="i">The
                                    Economy of Vegetation</hi>— 
<q> Or bid Mortality rejoice and
                                    mourn<lb/>
 O’er the fine forms in Portland’s mystic urn<lb/>
                                    (II.319-20) </q>
—occasion several different views of the vase
                                (illus. 1-4) and a lengthy “Additional Note” whose explanation of
                                the scenes on the vase “is still regarded as the best.”<ref
                                    target="n128" type="note">36</ref> The views were evidently
                                copied and engraved by Blake, who—judging from Johnson’s letter to
                                Darwin of 23 July 1791—was for a time entrusted with the vase
                                    itself.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n129"
type="note">37</ref> Darwin’s remarks
                                would in any event have interested any student of Bryant and the
                                other mythologists, for, according to Darwin, the vase “represents
                                what in antient times engaged the attention of philosophers, poets,
                                and heros, I mean a part of the Eleusinian mysteries” (Add. N.
                                XXII). Darwin’s deep interest in these matters emerges more strongly
                                in the “Preface” to <hi rend="i">The Temple of Nature</hi> where he
                                writes that “in the mysteries the philosophy of the works of Nature
                                . . . are believed to have been taught by allegoric scenery . . .
                                which gave rise to the machinery of this poem.” The scenes on the
                                vase he describes as “the first part of this scenery,” representing
                                “Death, and the destruction of all things.” In <hi rend="i">The
                                    Economy of Vegetation</hi>, Darwin sees the central figure, a
                                female in a dying attitude (represented by the inverted torch in her
                                hand, “an antient emblem of extinguished life”), as “an hieroglyphic
                                of the Eleusinian emblem of MORTAL LIFE, that is, the lethu, or
                                death, mentioned by Virgil amongst the terrible things exhibited at
                                the beginning of the mysteries.” Another figure, “The MANES or GHOST
                                appears lingering and fearful, and wishes to drag after him a part
                                of his mortal garment, which however adheres to the side of the
                                portal through which he has passed.” Such images 
                                    <figure n="PortlandVase.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="668" height="1000">
                                    <head>1 The Portland Vase.</head>
                                    <figDesc>Courtesy of Robert Essick.</figDesc>
                                </figure>
<pb id="p15-43" n="43"/>
<figure n="FirstCompartment.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="686" height="466">
                                    <head>2 The First Compartment.</head>
                                    <figDesc>Courtesy of Robert Essick.</figDesc>
                                </figure>
<figure n="SecondCompartment.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="686" height="476">
                                    <head>3 The Second Compartment.</head>
                                    <figDesc>Courtesy of Robert Essick.</figDesc>
                                </figure>
<figure n="HandlesBottomVase.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="689" height="467">
                                    <head>4 The Handles and Bottom of the Vase.</head>
                                    <figDesc>Courtesy of Robert Essick.</figDesc>
                                </figure> perhaps helped to point Blake toward his later use of
                                body-as-garment. And while there are many sources, conscious and
                                not, for Blake’s varied and multivalent serpent images, the
                                following passage must have occasioned some interest: “A little
                                lower down in the group the manes or ghost is received by a
                                beautiful female, a symbol of IMMORTAL LIFE. This is evinced by her
                                fondling between her knees a large and playful serpent, which from
                                its annually renewing its external skin has from great antiquity . .
                                . been esteemed an emblem of renovated youth.” This may suggest
                                another interpretation for the mysterious design in 
                                    <hi rend="i">America</hi>, pl. 14, where a would-be scholar prays to a
                                seated woman with a fondled serpent between her spread knees. The
                                “death-preaching sibyl” seen by David Erdman is an academic
                                projection—the serpent at the bottom of the plate ejaculates those
                                same flames from which the student, as Orc or “renovated youth” in
                                the design of pl. 10, could emerge. So also the serpent of pl. 11
                                ridden by children and reined by a young girl could offer extremely
                                positive associations: in the text of pl. 15, the female spirits
                                “glowing with the lusts of youth . . . feel the nerves of youth
                                renew. and desires of ancient times.” As the same design of the
                                ridden serpent appears at the end of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, these
                                same associations may affect the interpretation and dating of that
                                final plate, already generally considered as a later addition to the
                                poem. <note id="n128"><hi rend="s">36</hi> King-Hele, p. 202; he
                                    cites W. Mankowitz, <hi rend="i">The Portland Vase and the
                                        Wedgwood Copies</hi> (London: Deutsch, 1952). Before Darwin
                                    the vase had been discussed and reproduced in Montfaucon’s 
                                        <hi rend="i">L’Antiquité Expliquée</hi> (1719).</note>	
                                    <note id="n129"><hi rend="s">37</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., 
                                        <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1969); for Blake
there
                                    would have been the added pleasure of having his engravings used
                                    rather than some existing ones by Bartolozzi. The engravings are
                                    dated Dec. 1, 1791.</note></p>
                            <p>But the most interesting explanation comes towards the close of the
                                note; it offers information available elsewhere, but in succinct and
                                memorable form summarizes an emblem essential for considering, 
                                    <hi rend="i">inter alia</hi>, the title page of 
                                    <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>:
<q> The Psyche of the AEgyptians was one of
                                    their most favorite emblems, and represented the soul, or a
                                    future life; it was originally no other than the aurelia, or
                                    butterfly, but in after times was represented by a lovely female
                                    child with the beautiful wings of that insect. The aurelia,
                                    after its first stage as an eruca or caterpillar, lies for a
                                    season in a manner dead, and is inclosed in a sort of coffin, in
                                    this state of darkness it remains all the winter, but at the
                                    return of spring it bursts its bonds and comes out with a new
                                    life, and in the most beautiful attire. The AEgyptians thought
                                    this a very proper picture of the soul of man, and of the
                                    immortality to which it aspired. But as this was all owing to
                                    divine Love, of which EROS was an emblem, we find this person
                                    frequently introduced as a concomitant of the soul in general of
                                    Psyche. (Bryant’s Mythol. Vol. II. p. 386). </q>
This rich
                                description could serve to gloss many of Blake’s images which point
                                to the cocoon or chrysalis stage of <corr type="emend">lepidopteral</corr> metamorphosis: the
                                couch of death, covering veil, golden bed.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n130"
                                    type="note">38</ref> “In Eden [Beulah, del.] Females sleep the
                                winter in soft silken veils / Woven by their own hands to hide them
                                in the darksom grave” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> I 5.1-2). The female
                                forms weave their veils “in sweet raptured trance” of sexual
                                organization, the “dreams of bliss” of the sleepers of
                                Beulah—reminding us that in the Blakean <hi rend="i">aufhebung</hi>
                                of the image Darwin’s aurelia becomes Blake’s human larva. Time
                                itself is a cocoon: <pb id="p15-44" n="44"/> “every Moment has a
                                Couch of gold for soft repose” (<hi rend="i">M</hi> 28.45ff). The
                                sleeping (time=sleeping) “for a season in a manner dead” is only
                                prologue to the main event which interested Blake, pupation or
                                “bursting”: “Graves . . . bursting with their births of immortality”
                                    (<hi rend="i">VLJ</hi>, E 543). Such references assume a
                                formulaic dimension, emphasizing—curiously—the “bottom” of the
                                grave/couch/cocoon, as when multitudes of warlike sons “Burst the
                                bottoms of the Graves &amp; Funeral Arks of Beulah” 
                                    (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 89.6, et al.). This bursting consistently represents
a
                                kind of de-evolution or birth (as <hi rend="i">descent</hi>, perhaps)
                                into cruel “male forms without female counterparts or Emanations”
                                    (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> VIIa 85.19). The dynamic is perhaps
                                similar to that of “The Crystal Cabinet”—the bursting of which
                                suggests that the cabinet is in part a chrysalis—where the male gets
                                wrapped up in Beulah-love, but by intellectually striving to seize
                                its inmost form breaks the intended pattern of his development and
                                falls back to the weeping babe stage. For all Blake’s emphasis on
                                mental fight and individual exertion, there is a contrasting faith
                                in a kind of spiritual “genetic programming,” a saving “inmost
                                form”—“this was all owing to divine Love,” to use Darwin’s words.
                                But Blake reverses Darwin’s conception of emblem and actuality.
                                    <note id="n130"><hi rend="s">38</hi> “Gold” enters the
                                    association through “chrysalis” (from Greek 
                                        <hi rend="i">chrusos</hi>, gold) and the aureate possibilities of
                                    “aurelia.”</note></p>
                        </div4>
                        <div4>
                            <head>
                                <title>
                                    <hi rend="b">VI. ODDS AND SEXUAL ENDS</hi>
                                </title>
                            </head>
                            <p>The idea of “emblem,” evident in Darwin’s interest in the Portland
                                Vase, appears more directly in a footnote which Albert S. Roe also
                                finds “suggestive 
                                <figure n="TheTornado.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="505">
                                    <head>5 “The Tornado.”</head>
                                    <figDesc>Courtesy of Robert Essick.</figDesc>
                                </figure> 
                                with reference to Blake.” Commenting on “the holy Halo” in
                                the first canto of <hi rend="i">The Economy of Vegetation</hi>,
                                Darwin writes: 
                                <q> I believe it is not known with certainty at what
                                    time the painters first introduced the luminous circle round the
                                    head to import a Saint or holy person. It is now become a
                                    symbolic language of painting, and it is much to be wished that
                                    this kind of hieroglyphic character was more frequent in that
                                    art; as it is much wanted to render historic pictures both more
                                    intelligible, and more sublime; and why should not painting as
                                    well as poetry express itself in a metaphor, or in indistinct
                                    allegory? A truly great modern painter lately endeavored to
                                    enlarge the sphere of pictorial language, by putting a demon
                                    behind the pillow of a wicked man on his death bed. Which
                                    unfortunately the cold criticism of the present day has
                                    depreciated; and thus barred perhaps the only road to further
                                    improvement in this science.<lb/>
                                    (<hi rend="i">EV</hi> I.
                                    358n.)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n131" type="note">39</ref>	
                                            <note id="n131"><hi rend="s">39</hi> Roe identifies the painting
                                        referred to as Reynold’s “Death of Cardinal Beaufort” (“The
                                        Thunder of Egypt,” p. 166).</note></q>
                                <figure n="TOCTempleOfNature.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="686" height="864">
                                    <head>6 Table of Contents for <hi rend="i">The Temple of
                                            Nature</hi>, Canto IV, “Of Good and Evil.”</head>
                                    <figDesc>Repr. from Scholar Press facsimile.</figDesc>
                                </figure>
                                <pb id="p15-45" n="45"/> 
                                Darwin’s off-hand characterization
                                of painting as a science which can improve through experiments in
                                expression would probably have elicited Blake’s 
                                interest:<ref target="n132" type="note">40</ref> 
                                the serpents of <hi rend="i">America</hi>, for example, seem to 
                                offer a “kind of hieroglyphic character” in their part of that 
                                work’s metaphor or  “indistinct allegory.” 
                                <note id="n132"><hi rend="s">40</hi> There
                                    is, indeed, some special pleading in Darwin’s argument; for as
                                    Logan notes, no one can write a poem on scientific processes and
                                    be pictorial without being abstract except through allegory,
                                    personification, and simile: “Everything must be interpreted
                                    through symbols, if fantastic none the less concrete. If no
                                    concrete symbol can be found, then the abstraction must be
                                    addressed directly, hailed by name and importuned, and thus
                                    dragged bodily before the mind of the reader” (pp. 138-39). For
                                    example, “an illicit love affair is used as an allegory for the
                                    chemical reaction of nitric acid with oxygen to produce what is
                                    probably a nitrate salt. During the course of this reaction, a
                                    reddish vapor is given off and heat escapes; and Darwin likens
                                    this result to Mars’ seduction of Venus and to Vulcan’s ensuing
                                    anger, which ties them together with a net, that, the chemical
                                    bond” (Hassler, p. 56). For Blake, such limited symbols must
                                    ultimately be subsumed to apparent confusions of text—that is,
                                    the whole text itself is the only adequate “symbol.”</note></p>
                            <p>Striking also is Darwin’s spectre-like conception of 
                            <q>
                            	The Demon, Jealousy, [who] with Gorgon frown<lb/>
                            	Blasts the sweet flowers of Pleasure not his own,<lb/>
                            	Rolls his wild eyes, and through the shuddering grove<lb/>
                            	Pursues the steps of unsuspecting Love<lb/>
                            	(<hi rend="i">TN</hi> II.307-10)<ref target="n133" type="note">41</ref>
                            	<note id="n133"><hi rend="s">41</hi>
                                        Compare the Blakean spectre which “hunts [the] footsteps” of
                                        the Emanation (<hi rend="i">M</hi> 32.4-5).</note>
                            </q>
                                For Darwin, Jealousy is sexual strife, and so an expression of vital
                                energy—here he is not far from a foreshadowing of natural selection.
                                He notes that the horns of stags “have therefore been formed for the
                                purpose of combatting other stags for the exclusive possession of
                                the females, who are observed, like the ladies in the times of
                                chivalry, to attend the car of the victor” (<hi rend="i">TN</hi>
                                II.321n.). So Darwin concludes this theme with a reference to the
                                “Knight on Knight, recorded in romance” who looked to the admiring
                                eyes of the female bands, “Bow’d to the Beauty, and receiv’d her
                                smiles” (<hi rend="i">TN</hi> II.333). Faint reward indeed, but
                                perhaps remembered by Blake in the dark conception of Vala-centered
                                strife through <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Chapter 3:
                                <q> This is no warbling brook, nor shadow of a mirtle tree:<lb/>
                                	But blood and wounds and dismal cries, and shadows of the oaks:<lb/>
                                	And hearts laid open to the light, by the broad grizly sword:<lb/>
                                    And bowels hid in hammerd steel rip’d quivering on the ground.<lb/>
                                    Call forth thy smiles of soft deceit: call forth thy cloudy tears:<lb/>
                                    We hear thy sighs in trumpets shrill when morn shall blood renew.<lb/>
                                    (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 65.50-55)
                                </q>
                                Given “the importance of the sexual love which Darwin believes to be
                                the most highly developed kind of love” (Hassler, p. 84), it is not
                                surprising that Darwin turns from sexual strife to the domestic
                                “triumph of despotic LOVE”; even “the enamour’d Flowers”:
                                <q> 
                                	<corr type="emend">Breathe</corr> their soft sighs from each enchanted grove,<lb/>
                                	And hail THE DEITIES OF SEXUAL LOVE.<lb/>
                                	(<hi rend="i">TN</hi> II.409-10)
                                </q>
                                But for Blake such deification is woven to dreams, and “Sexes
                                must vanish &amp; cease / To be, when Albion arises from his dread
                                repose” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 92.13-14). This may serve as Blake’s
                                final response to what must have been the most compelling aspect of
                                Darwin’s 
                                vision<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n134" type="note">42</ref>—a 
                                positive delight in sexual organization that had troubled Blake as far back
                                as <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel.</hi><ref target="n135" type="note">43</ref>
	<note id="n134"><hi rend="s">42</hi> Hassler notes that
                                    “Darwin uses various techniques throughout his verse to make his
                                    characters as sensuous and as ‘sexual’ as possible” (p.
                                    83).</note>
	<note id="n135"><hi rend="s">43</hi> David Erdman
                                    characterizes <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> as “pictorially
                                    and metaphorically . . . a curious counterpart” of 
                                        <hi rend="i">The Loves of the Plants</hi>; “some of Blake’s
flowers and
                                    their human forms seem to derive from Darwin’s text, notes, and
                                    illustrations. . . . Darwin’s emphasis on sexual encounter and
                                    aggressive masculinity seems particularly relevant” 
                                        (<hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> [Garden City, N. Y.:
                                    Doubleday, 1974], p. 33).</note></p>
                            <p>Darwin’s vision of the sexual universe reaches heights of modern
                                fascination in his discussion in verse and footnote concerning
                                curved forms, or “IDEAL BEAUTY.” “If the wide eye the wavy lawns
                                explores,” or “Hills, whose green sides with soft protuberance rise,
                                / Or the blue concave of the vaulted skies,”—anytime the eye sees
                                lines which reflect “the nice curves, which swell the female
                                breast”: 
<q> The countless joys the tender Mother pours<lb/>
 Round
                                    the soft cradle of our infant hours,<lb/>
 In lively trains of
                                    unextinct delight<lb/>
 Rise in our bosoms 
                                        <hi rend="i">recognized by sight</hi>;<lb/>
 Fond Fancy’s eye recalls the
                                    form divine,<lb/>
 And TASTE sits smiling upon Beauty’s
                                    shrine.<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">TN</hi> III.227-32) </q>
Darwin’s
                                attraction to this idea is evident in the catalogue of poetic
                                paraphrases he finds for women’s breasts: “velvet orbs,” “milky
                                fount,” “the Paphian shrine,” “pearly orbs,” “salubrious fount,”
                                “the perfect form.” Indeed, considering the opening request in 
                                    <hi rend="i">The Temple of Nature</hi> that the “mystic veil
                                withdraw” from the Goddess in order to “Charm after charm . . .
                                display / And give the GODDESS to adoring day!” and the echoing
                                closing image of the poem, it is not too much to say that for Darwin
                                the female bosom equals “TRUTH DIVINE!”: Urania (the reader’s
                                guide), 
<q> Thrice to the GODDESS bows with solemn pause,<lb/>
 With
                                    trembling awe the mystic veil withdraws,<lb/>
 And, meekly
                                    kneeling on the gorgeous shrine,<lb/>
 Lifts her ecstatic eyes to
                                    TRUTH DIVINE!<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">TN</hi> I.168-70, IV.521-24)
                                </q>
Concerning “wavy lawns,” Darwin offers a long and detailed
                                footnote (taken verbatim from <hi rend="i">Zoonomia</hi> XIV.6) to
                                support his contention that when we see any object of vision which
                                bears any similitude to the form of the female bosom, “if the object
                                be not too large, we experience an attraction to embrace it with our
                                arms, and to salute it with our lips, as we did in our early infancy
                                the bosom of our mother.” This may suggest an additional link
                                between “beauty”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n136"
type="note">44</ref> and
                                “Beulah”—as in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 30.10-11, “Beulah to its
                                Inhabitants appears within each district / As the beloved infant in
                                his mothers bosom round incircled.” 
                                        <note id="n136"><hi rend="s">44</hi> In connection with Darwin’s
“breast-esthetic,”
                                    Logan observes: “Here we have the whole foundation of Darwin’s
                                    theory of poetry and art. Beauty is frankly sensuous; it arises
                                    from those things, belonging to nature which have given us
                                    pleasure through our different senses. . . . It is a much
                                    cleverer, and certainly more modern, explanation of the delight
                                    that we receive from curving lines than Hogarth’s ‘wanton chase’
                                    theory” (p. 62).</note></p>
                            <p>The third edition of <hi rend="i">The Economy of Vegetation</hi>
                                (1795) included a new illustration, engraved by Blake, of “The
                                Tornado” (illus. 5). A Note, as usual, contains the meat of the
                                discussion; this one follows a note on the “Maelstrom” which labels
                                that phenomenon “an extensive vortex, or eddy,” testifying to the
                                general linguistic equivalence between
                                vortex-eddy-whirlpool-(tornado) which would have informed Blake’s
                                reading. Darwin tells us that two major winds meeting in contrary
                                directions cannot be supposed to balance each other, and as a result
                                “a rotatory motion will be produced as they ascend like water
                                falling through a hole [sic], and an horizontal or spiral eddy is
                                the consequence; these eddies are more or less rapid, and are called
                                Tornadoes in their most violent state” (<hi rend="i">EV</hi> Add. N.
                                XXXIII). This violent eddy “has not only its progressive velocity,
                                but its circular one also, <pb id="p15-46" n="46"/>
which thus lifts
                                up or overturns every thing within its spiral whirl.” This offers a
                                potentially significant lesson in Blakean psycho-physics: expressed
                                more simply, “The surface of contact between two currents curls over
                                to form a vortex”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n137"
type="note">45</ref>—perhaps
                                even the surface of contact between “currents of creation,” or even,
                                contrary ideas. Blake’s engraving is striking in comparison with
                                others done about this time—as a Tornado, or spiral eddy, the
                                various coiled serpents represent the circular velocity of the
                                vortex. The left-hand figure in plate 6 of <hi rend="i">The Book of
                                    Urizen</hi> suggests, in particular, the inverse, inverted image
                                of “The <corr type="emend">Tornado.”</corr> <note id="n137"><hi rend="s">45</hi> Theodor
                                    Schwenk, <hi rend="i">Sensitive Chaos: The Creation of Flowing
                                        Forms in Water and Air</hi>, trans. Olive Whicher and
                                    Johanna Wrigley (New York: Schocken Books, 1976), p.
                                47.</note></p>
                            <p>But there are other pleasures to reading Darwin aside from reading-in
                                Blake. One can only feel great admiration for the man, and for the
                                growing power of experimental science, after pondering Darwin’s note
                                that the larynx is “something like the trumpet stop of an organ, as
                                may be observed by blowing through the wind-pipe of a dead goose”
                                    (<hi rend="i">TN</hi> Add. N. XV). And there is a certain charm
                                in Darwin’s style, when taken in small doses: 
<q> [the NEREID’s]
                                    playful Sea-horse woos her soft commands,<lb/>
 Turns his quick
                                    ears, his webbed claws expands,<lb/>
 His watery way with waving
                                    volutes wins,<lb/>
 Or listening librates on unmoving fins.<lb/>
                                        (<hi rend="i">EV</hi> III.227-80) </q>
And there are
                                haunting lapses—as in the verses on the “electric kiss” 
                                    (<hi rend="i">EV</hi> I. 349-56), or the story of the plague-diseased
                                Aegle and her lover Thyrsis, who “clasps the bright Infection in his
                                arms” (<hi rend="i">EV</hi> IV. 106). And there is still the
                                pleasure of “archeological” discovery; who knows?—someone may yet
                                vindicate Richard Edgeworth’s belief that “in future times some
                                critic will arise who shall re-discover <hi rend="i">The Botanic
                                    Garden</hi> and build his fame upon this discovery. . . . It
                                will shine out again to the admiration of posterity” (cited in
                                Logan, p. 94). But anyone, surely, can safely take the pleasure of
                                reading Darwin once.</p>
                            <p>Darwin’s poetical works are now available in facsimile as part of the
                                Garland “Romantic Context” series, with a serviceable introduction
                                by Donald H. Rieman.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n138"
type="note">46</ref>
                                Unfortunately, these are not as successful as the facsimile editions
                                published by the Scholar Press in 1973—most importantly with regard
                                to the illustrations, which in the Garland edition look like bad
                                xeroxes, with the names of artist and engraver sometimes cropped
                                off. The Garland series chooses, curiously, to reproduce the second
                                edition of <hi rend="i">The Loves of the Plants.</hi> This opens the
                                way to some interesting comparisons<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n139" type="note">47</ref> for the student having access to both reprints or to
                                other later editions, but offers a slightly less successful text for
                                the single-copy reader. The Garland <hi rend="i">Temple of
                                    Nature</hi> also includes <hi rend="i">The Golden Age</hi>, a
                                parodic epistle in verse issued under Darwin’s name; the fact that
                                one university bibliographer once accepted the attribution hardly
                                justifies its inclusion, which only serves to make one the more
                                regret the exclusion of the truly damaging parody, “The Loves of the
                                Triangles.” Still, every undergraduate library should now include
                                Darwin, and for those that do not, the Garland edition would be the
                                easiest solution. <note id="n138"><hi rend="s">46</hi> Erasmus
                                    Darwin, <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi>, intro. Donald H.
                                    Reiman, A Garland Series: Romantic Context: Poetry; Significant
                                    Minor Poetry 1789-1830, selected and arranged by Donald H.
                                    Reiman, in two vols. (New York and London: Garland Publishing,
                                    1978); and in the same series, Erasmus Darwin, <hi rend="i">The
                                        Golden Age</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Temple of Nature</hi>,
                                    intro. Donald H. Reiman.</note>
	<note id="n139"><hi rend="s">47</hi> For example, in the first edition:
									<q>
									So NINON pruned her wither’d charms, and won<lb/>
									With harlot-smiles her gay unconscious son;—(I.125-26)
									</q>
									and in the second edition: 
									<q>
									So, in her wane of beauty, NINON won<lb/>
									With fatal smiles her gay unconscious son.—(I. 125-26).
									</q>
                                    The second edition drops the wonderful sequence about the Polish
                                    salt mines and their underground cities (first ed. IV.309-26).
                                </note></p>
							<pb id="p15-47-48" n="47-48" rend="hidden"/>
                        </div4>
                    </div3>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
