<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.1.wittreich</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Donald H. Reiman, ed., The Garland Facsimiles of the Poetry of William Hayley</title>
        <author n="Wittreich">Joseph Wittreich</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <name>James Warwick</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Martin K. Nurmi</name>
              <name>Judith Page</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Henry Summerfield</name>
              <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
      <pb id="p15-28" n="28"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-1-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main"><hi rend="b">ROMANTIC CONTEXT: POETRY</hi><lb/>
            Significant Minor Poetry 1789-1830<lb/>
            Printed in photo-facsimile in 128 volumes<lb/>
            <hi rend="b">Selected and Arranged by Donald H. Reiman</hi></title>
          </head>
          <pb id="p15-48" n="48"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title type="main" rend="main"><hi rend="b">“Far yet extend that biographic page!”: 
              Some Thoughts on Donald Reiman’s Hayley</hi></title>
            </head>
            <head>
              <title type="main">William Hayley. Ode to Mr. Wright and Other Poems, 
              The Eulogies of Howard/Ballads/Poems on Serious and Sacred Subjects,
              A Poetical Epistle to an Eminent Painter and Other Poems, An Essay
              on Sculpture.</title>
            </head>
            <byline>
              <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
              <docAuthor>
                <hi rend="b">Joseph</hi>
                <name>
                  <hi rend="b">Wittreich</hi>
                </name>
              </docAuthor>
            </byline>
            <figure n="WilliamHayley.15.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="505">
              <head>Hull: William Hayley, 1800 (Mansell Collection)</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Students who learn from their mentors only that Blake left Felpham in a
                            snit, that thereupon he “immortalized [Hayley] as a fool not to
                            be endured,” and so conclude, “no one much cares what
                            Hayley said,” are unlikely to be affected by, much less
                            interested in, historical judgments of Blake’s
                            patron—are indeed apt to be impatient with them and
                            unappreciative of an effort, such as Donald Reiman’s, to
                            situate Hayley in a “Romantic Context.” They may even
                            be suspicious, if not wholly contemptuous, of an enterprise that would
                            publish four volumes of Hayley’s verse under the caption,
                                “<hi rend="i">Significant</hi> Minor Poetry” (my
                            italics). This poetry is not by current standards, much less by the
                            standards of Hayley’s more astute contemporaries, good. It
                            is, in the most generous terms, an achievement of the left hand, yet
                            offers its own rewards, even to the most recalcitrant Blakeans,
                            presuming they are able to cast off prejudice long enough to ask the
                            right questions. Why Blake left Felpham we know. Why he went to Felpham
                            in the first place and what he and Hayley talked about, off and on for
                            three years, are matters of interest that these four volumes might fuel.
                            They do not answer such questions, to be sure, but set forth clues for
                            answering them; they might even inspire a more enterprising student to
                            heed the Hayleyan plea—“extend that biographic
                            page!”—and, in the process, to adjudicate between
                            widely discrepant assessments of Hayley’s place in literary
                            history and of the role he might have played in Blake’s life
                            and art, even in the formation of an aesthetic that underlies it.</p>
            <pb id="p15-49" n="49"/>
            <p>The simple allegorizing of Hayle into Hayley, invented in our century and
                            popularized by Blake’s editors, is analogous to the
                            allegorizing of Prometheus against which Hayley himself registered a
                            protest in <hi rend="i">An Essay on Sculpture</hi>; it would seem,
                            moreover, to run counter to Blake’s own preference for a
                            visionary over an allegorical mode of poetry and to become increasingly
                            more dubious as one weighs the judgments of history against those
                            imposed upon Hayley by the Blake cult. Against its generally hostile
                            evaluations are the more temperate estimates of literary historians and
                            critical theorists (such as H. T. Swedenberg and Northrop Frye) and of
                            reviewers and poets roughly contemporary with Hayley, yet not nearly so
                            rough in their appraisal of him (such as Southey, Coleridge, and even
                            Byron). There are finally the highly laudatory remarks about Hayley that
                            come from Miltonists of the late eighteenth and early nineteenth
                            centuries: the editor of the <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> printed by
                            C. Whittingham in 1799 draws upon Hayley for his epigraph and admits he
                            is chiefly indebted to Hayley; and Charles Dunster, in his 1800 edition
                            of <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>, portrays Hayley as the
                            age’s best knower of Milton. Perhaps the truth about Hayley,
                            especially about Blake’s regard and disregard of him, is too
                            complicated to be fairly represented by a single spokesman and thus is
                            to be approached through a variety of perspectives that in their very
                            contrariness lead one closer to that truth. As Samuel Palmer might say
                            in this instance: “Truth . . . seems . . . to stand at a fixed
                            centre between its two antagonists, Fact and Phantasm.”</p>
            <p>Reiman’s Introduction, not tailored to individual volumes but
                            expediently (for the publisher) reprinted four times, formulates the
                            paradox of Hayley’s once being among “the most
                            respected poets, as well as the most popular . . . in England”
                            (p. v) and now being scarcely remembered except by Blakeans, and then
                            usually scornfully. The praise bestowed upon this poet by the popular
                            culture, which contributed to his being offered the Laureateship in
                            1790, was an anathema to most of the major Romantic poets who even if
                            they judged Hayley unworthy of that honor (so Hayley also judged
                            himself!) could accept, albeit grudgingly, Southey’s estimate
                            of him quoted in the <hi rend="i">Dictionary of National Biography</hi>:
                            “everything about that man is good except his poetry.”
                            Like his fellow Romantics, Blake probably judged Hayley to be a
                            rhymester not a poet, but, again like them, may have found something,
                            both in his prose writings and in conversation, to redeem Hayley. Even
                            if Blake was as jealous in his independence, as petty in his
                            relationships, and as stingy in his praise, as some critics make him out
                            to be, he might have concurred in the following sentiment so long, that
                            is, that he did not know its author was Leigh Hunt: “two things
                            must be remembered to his honour, . . . he has been the quickest of our
                            late writers to point out the great superiority of the Italian school
                            over the French; and . . . has been among the first . . . in hailing the
                            dawn of our native poetry.” To be remembered too, though not
                            always to his honor, is Hayley’s relationship with Blake, a
                            three-year encounter, which, having for so long been caricatured, needs
                            now to be humanized and then re-viewed along the lines that Reiman
                            proposes: “His work on plates for a number of
                            Hayley’s titles suggests that a study [of them] . . . in the
                            light of Blake’s ideas is likely to point to the origin of
                            details (perhaps parodying Hayley’s ideas) in
                            Blake’s own writings after 1803” (pp. xii-xiii). In
                            this way the blankness of the historical record regarding the extent of
                            their agreements and disagreements might be filled in with plausible
                            speculation that remains faithful to the principles of both men.</p>
            <p>What did Blake and Hayley talk about? Why might Blake have felt
                            intellectually in his debt despite deep, even irreconcilable,
                            differences? Hayley’s poetry, along with the accompanying
                            notes, provides some ground for conjecture. They talked about Milton
                            certainly (in <hi rend="i">An Essay on Sculpture</hi>, 1800, Hayley
                            calls him “The hallow’d Homer of the Christian
                            world” [II. 170]); and they probably talked about the whole
                            epic tradition of which Milton was England’s mighty exemplar,
                            of Sidney and Spenser perhaps, and of Dante and Tasso. Hayley thought
                            Dante’s poetry, especially the Ugolino episode, might provide
                            a new subject matter for painters and, in <hi rend="i">An Essay on Epic
                                Poetry</hi>, 1782, offered the first sustained English translation
                            for the <hi rend="i">Commedia</hi>—a rendering in <hi rend="i">terza rima</hi>
of the first three cantos of the Inferno.
                            As early as <hi rend="i">A Poetical Epistle to an Eminent Painter</hi>,
                            1778, addressed to George Romney, Hayley urged, “Let
                            Milton’s self” lead the artist to portray
                            “the scenes that blaze in his immortal song,” singling
                            out his Michael and especially his Satan who is “more sublimely
                            true” than that of Raphael, Guido, and West—a Satan
                            who has not yet lost his original brightness as he awakens his legions
                            or, still earlier, as he is “falling from the Realms of Bliss,
                            / Hurl’d in the Combustion to the deep Abyss” (II.
                            451-74, Notes, p. 76). Allusions to Milton elsewhere in
                            Hayley’s poetry reveal a mind captivated by the episode of
                            Ithuriel’s spear. Romney picked up such hints, and Blake may
                            have responded to them as well. In <hi rend="i">An Essay on
                                Sculpture</hi> Hayley returns to Milton, this time to celebrate him
                            with Tasso as one who “Imbib’d the fervour of
                            sublime design” (I. 133); with Michelangelo as one who,
                            achieving a perfection that no precepts teach, “close[d] / A
                            life of labour in divine repose, / In that calm vale of years”
                            (I. 157-60); and with Newton as an example of men in whom
                            “ceaseless toil” produced “pure
                            minds” and who “to glory climb’d”
                            (I.230-38). Here again Hayley urges sculptors “To quicken
                            marble with Miltonic fire” (II.194) and, later, praises the
                            industry and genius of Fuseli’s Milton Gallery. Here too he
                            will praise <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> for containing
                            “the sublimest censure of the national conduct of
                            Rome” (Notes, p. 306) and, in <hi rend="i">An Elegy on the
                                Death of Sir William Jones</hi>, 1795, the “local
                            exactitude” of Milton’s descriptions (Notes, p. 25).
                            But in <hi rend="i">An Essay on History</hi>, 1780, he had already
                            complained of the “Danger of dwelling on the distant and minute
                            parts of a subject really interesting,” observing
                            Milton’s “Failure . . . in this particular”
                            (III, Argument). There are poems like <hi rend="i">The Eulogies of
                                Howard</hi> that through an epigraph, “to tell of deeds /
                            Above heroic,” will establish a Miltonic context or that
                            through a subtitle, “A Vision,” will invoke a
                            tradition of which, in comparison with Blake, Hayley has but a
                            diminished awareness.</p>
            <p>Subjects raised by Hayley’s poetry might also have provided
                            topics for conversation: Michelangelo and Raphael; John Howard, the
                            prison reformer; <pb id="p15-50" n="50"/>
Newton, religionist and
                            scientist; Cowper, Romney, Reynolds, Flaxman, and Fuseli; William Jones,
                            Thomas Maurice, and their Asiatic researches; Bishop Lowth and his
                            lectures on the bardic poetry of the Hebrews. Individual phrases,
                            however puerile their contexts, might have captured Blake’s
                            attention—“mental eyes,” “mental
                            vision,” “optics of the mind,” “a
                            mental mist,” “unfetter’d forms,”
                            “art divine,” “living forms,”
                            “vast design,” “radiant
                            structure”—perhaps even an entire line like this one
                            from <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>: “I see thee riding in the sun,
                            / Upon the Eagle’s back” (III). Certain of
                            Hayley’s ideas, however inadequate their poetic embodiment,
                            might similarly have provided occasions for conversation: “the
                            removal of . . . galling fetters” from mankind; “Jesus
                            enthron’d in every human heart”; “boundless
                            vision . . . uncrampt by time and space”; “the bard,
                            to rhymes no more confin’d”;
                            “Adam’s race redeem’d from woe . . .
                            [and] Paradise to man restored.” Blake would have entered his
                            demurrals, of course; and Hayley may have been patronizing, or worse, in
                            receiving them. But if our renewed consideration of their relationship
                            were to suggest a more human and civilized dimension, a modulation of
                            rancor into guarded respect, we might sense that Blake came to feel with
                            Hayley that an appropriate tribute to such respect is to realize another
                            man’s ideas, even if realizing them means sometimes altering
                            so as to improve upon them.</p>
            <p>If Blake had read Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Felpham</hi>, 1814, he
                            might have cast himself into the role assigned to Cowper, that of a
                            Miltonic bard laboring to unfetter the human mind. Blake might even have
                            imagined himself accomplishing what Hayley says his son—had
                            he lived—would have accomplished: “Confederate
                            arts” joining “to see / Their English Michael Angelo
                            in thee” (p. 22). The extent to which Blake came to Felpham as
                            a surrogate son who disappointed, and was disappointed in, his father
                            needs exploring. With Hayley’s conception of the arts and of
                            artistic objectives as they are set forth in <hi rend="i">An Essay on
                                Sculpture</hi> Blake could not help but have agreed. He would have
                            joined Hayley in resisting those “mental tyrants” in
                            their effort “To limit England in the sphere of Art”
                            (II. 165-66); with Hayley he would also have belittled “foreign
                            Theorists, with System blind, / Prescrib [ing] false limits to the
                            British mind” as Hayley puts it in <hi rend="i">A Poetical
                                Epistle</hi> (II. 15-16). He would have agreed with Hayley that
                            through the arts a nation makes bold advances to ideal life, that the
                            arts, while they reveal the “destin’d
                            havoc” of the world, are also heralds of a purer day
                            (IV.578-86). He would probably have found Hayley’s
                            analogizing of the young artist to “A young Prometheus in a
                            vulture’s clasp” (VI.20) pointedly relevant, even
                            ironically apt, to his own situation of which the very man who hoped
                            that young artists would not be tyrannized by engravers and who, in <hi rend="i">A
Poetical Epistle</hi>, allowed as how fashion
                            “fetters the creative hand” (I.53-56) now seemed so
                            remarkably insensitive. It remains one of the ironies of literary
                            history that Hayley who chastized others for confounding, depressing,
                            dampening the genius of young poets seems to have done just that, at
                            least for a time, with Blake.</p>
            <p>Hayley must have seemed a strangely divided personality to Blake, as he
                            did to other of the Romantic poets. Yet all of them, including Blake,
                            would be expected to see art, along with Hayley in <hi rend="i">An Essay
                                on Sculpture</hi>, as emerging, still emerging, from darkness and
                            “shin[ing] through Oppression’s storm” (IV,
                            22-23),—as being a projection of that history, at once epical
                            and tragical, which it would alter. The very alignment that Hayley, in
                                <hi rend="i">An Essay on History</hi>, perceives between history and
                            art, the former lending a dramatic center to the latter, must have fired
                            Blake’s interest in, impelled his scrutiny of both history
                            and art, the former not chronicled but mythologized however, and the
                            latter raised to the key of prophecy and vision. In the very act of
                            identifying Hayley with Hyle, some of Blake’s critics have
                            scandalized a relationship that begs to be psychologized; moreover, they
                            have Newtonized a vision whose ultimate goal is to save us from single
                            vision and Newton’s sleep. Blake’s poetry is not,
                            in the words of <hi rend="i">An Essay on Sculpture</hi>, “mere
                            allegory” (Notes, p. 188). If Donald Reiman’s Hayley
                            helps to redeem us from the simple equation, Hyle = Hayley, it will have
                            performed a valuable service for Blakeans; and in the very act of
                            setting Hayley within a Romantic context Reiman has brought us one step
                            nearer capturing the spirit of an age that is as much the age of Hayley
                            and Hunt as of Southey and Shelley, of Byron and Blake.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
