<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.1.songs</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">Songs Copy h</title>
        <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <name>James Warwick</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Martin K. Nurmi</name>
              <name>Judith Page</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Henry Summerfield</name>
              <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
      <pb id="p15-59" n="59"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-1-0010">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">SONGS COPY h</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Another copy of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> has
                        re-emerged on the auction market after a disappearance of over sixty years.
                        At an unknown time, the great bibliophile H. Buxton Forman acquired at least
                        ninety-eight posthumous impressions of the <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi> These he
                        had mounted on linen stubs and bound in three volumes in dark maroon levant
                        morocco, Jansen style, with elaborately gilt dentelles. Each is stamped on
                        the tail of the front paste-down end-paper “BOUND BY RIVIERE
                        &amp; SON FOR H. BUXTON FORMAN” and each bears
                        Forman’s bookplate on the inside front cover. One volume,
                        designated as g<hi rend="s">1</hi> in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> and
                        containing 23 plates, is now at Princeton; another (g<hi rend="s">2</hi>),
                        with 18 plates, is in the Rosenwald Collection of the Library of Congress.
                        The third and largest volume (h), containing 57 plates on 57 leaves,
                        disappeared after its sale to the bookdealer A. S. W. Rosenbach at the
                        Buxton Forman auction at Anderson Galleries in New York on 15 March 1920,
                        lot 53 ($90). This volume, not previously described in any detail, has now
                        come to light at Christie’s New York auction of 22 May 1981, lot
                        36, with “A Divine Image” and “The Sick
                        Rose” reproduced in the catalogue. It is now in my collection.</p>
          <p>The 57 plates in copy h are in the sequence given below and show fragments
                        (cut by the edges of the sheets) of J WHATMAN 1831 and 1832 watermarks as
                        indicated. Unless otherwise noted, the ink is gray, ranging from very light
                        to almost black. Plates: 1, 1 (a light red-brown terra cotta ink, hereafter
                        designated simply as “brown”; watermark J WH/18), 3
                        (ATMAN/31), 2 (J WH/18), 4, 6 (ATMAN/31), 7, 8, 5, 25, 9, 10 (J WH/18), 22,
                        23, 16, 17, 24 (brown; J WHA/18), 19 (brown), 11 (ATMAN/31), 12 (ATMAN/31),
                        18 (brown), 20, 21, 26 (brown), 27, 13 14, 28 (brown, with a few spots of
                        gray), 29, 30 (brown), 31 (brown), 38, 40 (brown; J WH/18), 42, 34, 35 (J
                        WH/18), 36 (brown, 
                        <pb id="p15-60" n="60"/>
                        with dark brown ink or paint
                        stains on the lower right corner of the leaf), 32 (brown; J WHA/18), 45
                        (brown; TMAN/31), 33, 49 (brown), 41 (brown), 39 (TMAN/32), 52 (brown), 52
                        (J WH/1), 54 (brown), 43 (brown; ATMAN/31), 44 (brown; TMAN/31), 50 (brown),
                        48 (brown), 53 (J WH/1), 53 (brown), 46 (brown), 51 (brown), 37 (brown), 47
                        (brown), b (dark reddish brown—clearly a different ink than the
                        other brown; ATMAN/832). Plate 15, “Laughing Song,” is
                        lacking; it is not included in any of the three volumes bound up for
                        Forman.</p>
          <p>The leaves measure approximately 28 × 19.5 cm., except that the
                        first leaf and the 45th (bearing “To Tirzah” in gray) are
                        short at the bottom, only 24.1 and 24.3 cm. high respectively. This is the
                        approximate leaf size in copies g<hi rend="s">1</hi> and g<hi rend="s">2</hi>. These
                        two smaller leaves are a slightly thicker wove paper than
                        all the rest. Each leaf is numbered in pencil consecutively, 1 through 57,
                        below the lower left corner of the plate. Other pencil inscriptions are
                        “KSNS/200<supplied type="emend">”</supplied> (clearly a bookdealer’s notation)
                        on the verso
                        of the front free endpaper, “2” below the plate on the
                        first leaf, “Gilchrist calls this ‘Christian
                        Forbearance’ II. 65 1863” below “A Poison
                        Tree” on the 41st leaf, and “20” on the verso of
                        the last leaf (bearing “A Divine Image” on its recto).</p>
          <p>Three plates are partly hand colored in water colors. Plate 38,
                        “Nurse’s Song” in <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>,
                        is awkwardly painted in green, rose red, blue, and yellow, with the title
                        gone over in gold. The pale blue, green, and yellow washed on plate 40,
                        “The Fly,” are more skillfully applied. Plate 45,
                        “The Little Vagabond,” has been touched with blue and
                        olive green in a few spots.</p>
          <p>The vendor of copy h at Christie’s auction was Charlton M. Theus,
                        Jr. According to his letter to me of 11 June 1981, Mr. Theus acquired the
                        book <hi rend="i">c.</hi> 1946 from Mr. Reid, a bookseller of Chesterton,
                        South Carolina. I have not been able to learn anything of the
                        book’s whereabouts between 1920 and 1946.</p>
          <p>Like all posthumous copies of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> I have seen, copy h
                        contains a good many poorly inked and printed impressions. Some plates were
                        printed with such great pressure that they have been embossed into the
                        paper. But copy h has one distinctive characteristic. With its three
                        duplicate plates (1, 52, 53) and inclusion of only the sixth known
                        impression of “A Divine Image,” it has more plates than
                        any other copy of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience.</hi>
                        <byline><docAuthor>ROBERT N. <name>ESSICK</name>,</docAuthor> UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, RIVERSIDE.</byline></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
