<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.1.nurmi</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Kathleen Raine, Blake and the New Age</title>
        <author n="Nurmi">Martin K. Nurmi</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Pam Blair</name>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>Kris Lackey</name>
              <name>James Warwick</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Martin K. Nurmi</name>
              <name>Judith Page</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Henry Summerfield</name>
              <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-1-0008">
        <div2>
          <pb id="p15-51" n="51"/>
          <div3>
            <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
            <head>
              <title type="main">Kathleen Raine. <hi rend="b">Blake and the New Age.</hi> London:
                                George Allen &amp; Unwin, 1979. Pp. 179 × + viii.
                                $17.95.</title>
            </head>
            <byline>
              <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
              <docAuthor>
                <hi rend="b">Martin K.</hi>
                <name>
                  <hi rend="b">Nurmi</hi>
                </name>
              </docAuthor>
            </byline>
            <p>This book is a collection of essays all but two of which were delivered
                            as lectures during the past decade or so. The essays are:
                            “England’s Prophet”;
                            “‘Everthing that Lives is Holy’”; 
                            “Blake’s Christianity”; 
                            “Blake’s Last Judgement”; 
                            “Taylor, Blake and the English Romantic Movement”; 
                            “Blake, Wordsworth and Nature”;
                            “Innocence and Experience”; and 
                            “Berkeley, Blake and the New Age.” 
                            The book is intended, says the Preface,
                            “not for the academic, but for the common reader and especially
                            for those in search of what Blake himself claims to have possessed,
                            spiritual knowledge,<supplied type="emend">”</supplied> and all the essays are
                            said to be “studies
                            of Blake’s thought as it has an immediate bearing on changes
                            taking place at the present time” (vii).</p>
            <p>Raine sees the new age that Blake called for in the Preface to <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> as the
            				“change of premises”
                            going on in the last part of the nineteenth century and the first half
                            of the twentieth that will replace materialism and restore mind as the
                            first principle of the universe. She does not deal with these changes or
                            with the direct relevance of Blake’s thought to them except
                            very generally, almost incidentally. And, as readers of Miss
                            Raine’s <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi> would know,
                            Blake’s thought is conceived of less as ideas developed by
                            himself than as spiritual knowledge received and transformed from the
                            esoteric tradition of the west, especially from Plotinus and Plato
                            through their contemporary interpreter and translator, Thomas
                            Taylor.</p>
            <p>Blake’s originality is vigorously denied in this book:
                            “Blake was not an original thinker, and the arrows he loosed
                            with such force from his bow of burning gold, though tipped with his own
                            fire, were seldom of his own making” (p. 151). And “At
                            the risk of shocking those lovers of Blake who see in him a visionary of
                            absolute originality, I must say that with better knowledge of
                            Blake’s own deep studies it seems to me that his most
                            remarkable gift was that of imaginatively assimilating the ideas of his
                            chosen teachers” (p. 115). While no one I think during the past
                            three decades at least would claim for Blake “absolute
                            originality,” taking away as much of it as these statements do
                            is to take away too much of the reason for being interested in him at
                            all.</p>
            <p>In addition to what is called here “the Platonic
                            tradition,” among Blake’s immediate teachers are not
                            only Thomas Taylor but also Swedenborg and Berkeley—who again
                            share in the Platonic tradition as conceived here. Returning in the last
                            essay of the book to the theme of the New Age, Raine writes: 
                            <q> 
                            	It was Blake who proclaimed the new age; not on his own authority but 
                            	upon that of Emanuel Swedenborg . . . When in his 
                            	<hi rend="i">Marriage of</hi>
	<pb id="p15-52" n="52"/>
								<hi rend="i">Heaven and Hell</hi> Blake announced ‘a new
                                heaven is begun’, the prophecy is
                                Swedenborg’s; and the new vision of the age
                                is—allowing for common sources within a
                                tradition—Berkeley’s philosophy. (p. 151)
                            </q>
                            Though recognizing that such a sweeping statement may “well be
                            challenged” and may need definition and limits, the only limits
                            set by Raine consist of her saying that in the Platonic tradition
                            “it is not always possible to say which particular writer is
                            the source of some common idea” (p. 151). There is no
                            indication that a reader looking into <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
                            Heaven and Hell</hi> would there find Swedenborg very vigorously and
                            unambiguously attacked, though it is true that Blake did owe more to
                            Swedenborg than his treatment of him in <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>
                            would suggest. In the discussion that follows there are many suggestive
                            parallels between Berkeley and Blake drawn piecemeal from a variety of
                            works. But if, as was suggested, the new vision announced in <hi rend="i">The
                            Marriage</hi> was based on Berkeley’s
                            philosophy, there are only four incidental references to <hi rend="i">The
                            Marriage</hi> to show for it, and no mention of
                            Blake’s idea of the Contraries, one of the central themes of
                            the new vision.</p>
            <p>Thomas Taylor is mentioned throughout the essays, but the strongest
                            claims for his importance not only to Blake but to the Romantic movement
                            as a whole come in the fifth essay, where Raine asserts that, though no
                            “great flowering of the arts could ever have one cause, . . .
                            the most powerful source of inspiration of the Romantic Movement was a
                            revival of the Platonic philosophy” through the translations
                            and commentaries of Thomas Taylor. There is a good deal of useful
                            information here about Taylor and the extent to which he was known in
                            his time. But the view of Romanticism we get is limited to literary
                            Romanticism and that only in England. Romanticism was indeed a
                            “great flowering of the arts”—not only
                            literature—and of politics, etc., in numerous languages and
                            cultures, in which influences of the Platonic tradition or, much less,
                            Taylor do not always seem to appear.</p>
            <p>It seems to me very unfortunate that Raine feels she must deny
                            Blake’s originality as much as she does. Blake is certainly
                            not the completely culturally isolated phenomenon he was thought to be
                            by some many years ago, and he has some roots in the esoteric tradition
                            as well as many other places. But if he was not as original as once
                            thought—and probably no one ever was—he was
                            fiercely independent; and it is very difficult to imagine his being as
                            derivative as he is said here to be. It seems to me that
                            Blake’s sources may be more profitably studied if we
                            don’t deny the affective impression we all had on first
                            looking into him, of an enormously fresh and original poet and artist
                            with depths of meaning only to be guessed at, rather than a visionary
                            transmitter of ideas merely assimilated from Platonic
                            tradition—and from Swedenborg and Berkeley. In considering
                            his debt to the Platonic tradition and to Plato himself as made
                            available in his time by Thomas Taylor, there is the stubborn fact that
                            Blake in all his works has few kind words to say about Plato.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
