<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.2.davidson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">The Music of the Ancients</title>
        <author n="Davidson">Peter Davidson</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>James Warwick</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Peter Davidson</name>
              <name>Detlef Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Anthony J. Harding</name>
              <name>David Sten Herrstrom</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>James A. Winn</name>
              <name>Michael C. Young</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
	<pb id="p15-98" n="98"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-2-0010">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">THE MUSIC OF THE ANCIENTS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Peter</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Davidson</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>When one reads that the occupations of Samuel Palmer and his friends at Shoreham were
“literature, and art, and ancient music,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37"
type="note">1</ref> curiosity is aroused by the last of these activities, as it is the one about which the
least is known. <note id="n37"><hi rend="s">1</hi> A. H. Palmer, <hi rend="i">The Life and Letters of Samuel
Palmer</hi>, 1892, p. 53.</note></p>
          <p>From his youth, Palmer was both a singer and a violinist<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n38" type="note">2</ref> and Francis Finch had considerable skill as a pianist and counter-tenor.
Thus, it is not remarkable to discover that the Ancients passed their evenings with such contemporary songs as
Moore’s <hi rend="i">Irish Melodies</hi> (Finch’s rendition of “The Minstrel Boy” was especially
remembered)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">3</ref>, although the vision of
Palmer and Calvert walking through Shoreham to Palmer’s singing of “The British Grenadiers” places a
heavier demand upon the imagination. (Presumably Palmer sang the older version of the tune, with a rising
phrase and a turn for the words “none that can compare”).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n40" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Raymond Lister, <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer, a Biography</hi>, 1974, p.
28.</note>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Eliza Finch, <hi rend="i">Memorials of the Late Francis Oliver Finch</hi>,
1865, pp. 331, 356.</note>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">4</hi> A. H. Palmer, p. 28n.</note></p>
          <p>Another musical enterprise of the Ancients has been recorded:
<q>
But the favourite haunt was a wild lane near Shoreham in Kent, flanked on either side with great old beech
trees; it was hedged in by their spreading roots in the wildest contortions. Some years before it had been the
scene of a murder, and while in its pristine wildness and grandeur it was most admirably adapted as the
theatre for the enactment of some of the scenes of witchcraft so popular among the Tableaux vivans. They all
knew the Macbeth music by heart, and many a night made the ‘black lane’ ring with it.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Finch, p. 45.</note></q></p>
          <p>A. H. Palmer confirms that the Macbeth music in question was that published first in 1770,
claiming to be Boyce’s revision of the score which Matthew Locke composed for D’Avenant’s version of the
play.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">6</ref> This music, which held the
stage until 1875, was in fact composed in 1702 by Richard Leveridge.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n43" type="note">7</ref> The following melodramatic lines would seem to suit the occasion upon which
Palmer and his friends performed them:
<q>
Crimes foll’wing crimes on horror wait<lb/>
The worst of creatures faster propagate<lb/>
Many more murders must this one ensure<lb/>
As if in death were propagation too<lb/>
He shall he will he must spill much more blood<lb/>
And become worse to make his title good.
</q>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">6</hi> A. H. Palmer, p. 42.</note>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Roger Fiske, <hi rend="i">English Theatre Music in the Eighteenth
Century</hi> (Oxford, 1973), pp. 26-27.</note></p>
          <p>When we try to identify the “ancient music” which provided a more thoughtful contrast to
“Locke” and Tom Moore, we might do well to remember that, in the early nineteenth Century, the phrase
“ancient music” would have suggested the “Concerts of Ancient Music” given under Royal patronage. The
definition of “Ancient” in this context was “no music less than twenty years old,” but the repertory
was primarily Handelian, although works by the older English composers were also performed. In the light of
this it is interesting to find this reference in a letter of 5 June 1836 from Palmer to Richmond:
<q>
Then vow you’ll not stand it; but get out your Handel;<lb/>
and a kind friend will call in and give you some scandal.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44"
type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">8</hi><hi rend="i"> The Letters of Samuel Palmer</hi>, ed. Raymond Lister
(Oxford, 1974) I, 77.</note></q></p>
          <p>There is one firm clue concerning the musical repertory of “The Ancients.” In his memorial
essay on Francis Finch, Palmer writes,
<q>
The writer has felt more pleasure in sitting by his pianoforte, listening to fragements of of Tallis, Croft,
or Purcell . . . than from many displays of concerted music.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n45" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Finch, pp. 355-56.</note></q>
Given this, we may attempt to discover the extent to which music by these composers would have been available
in the 1820s.</p>
          <p>At this point, it should be noted that, apart from a few pieces printed in such collections as
Stafford Smith’s <hi rend="i">Musica Antiqua</hi>, Palmer and his friends would have had no access to
Dowland, Campion and the earlier English composers whose printed works have a poor rate of survival and whose
notation would have presented considerable difficulties.</p>
          <p>A surprising quantity of Purcell’s vocal music would have been obtainable; a “third
edition” formed from unsold sheets of earlier editions of <hi rend="i">Orpheus Britannicus</hi> had appeared
in 1721. <hi rend="i">A Collection of Songs</hi>, taken from <hi rend="i">Orpheus Britannicus</hi>, was
published by John Johnson in the 1790s. Benjamin Goodison published at the same time several volumes of a
proposed “complete” edition.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">10</ref>
Purcell could also be found in Clarke’s 1809 collection or Corfe’s 1805 <hi rend="i">Beauties of
Purcell</hi>, which contains a generous selection from the operas, stage music and songs. In view of
Palmer’s admiration for Dryden, and of the Ancients’ common vision of the pastoral landscape,
            <pb id="p15-99" n="99"/>
<figure n="Leveridge.Macbeth.music.15.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="603">
	<head>Pages from (title page of) Leveridge’s music for <hi rend="i">Macbeth.</hi></head>
</figure>
we might suppose that this song from <hi rend="i">King Arthur</hi> would have found favor:
<q>
For folded flocks and Fruitful Plains<lb/>
The Shepherd’s and the Farmer’s gains<lb/>
Fair Britain all the world outvies<lb/>
And Pan as in Arcadia reigns<lb/>
Where pleasure mixt with profit lyes.
</q>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">10</hi> For this and other information, I am indebted to Dr. Richard Luckett and
Mr. Richard Andrewes, both of the University of Cambridge.</note></p>
          <p>Croft’s <hi rend="i">Musica Sacra</hi> was published in 1724. It seems unlikely, judging from
the complexity of the part writing, that the Ancients would have sung the choral anthems and, while the
accomplished Finch would have been able to sing the vocal line of any of the solo anthems, there would have
been no instrument available for the accompaniment. Especially in view of the fact that thirty 
<hi rend="i">Select Anthems</hi> by Croft, with convenient pianoforte/organ accompaniments, were published in
1847, it seems likely that Finch sang these pieces to Palmer after they had left Shoreham.</p>
          <p>Chants and hymn tunes attributed to all three composers make frequent appearances in contemporary
hymn and anthem books, and these are the form in which Tallis would have been easily available to Palmer’s
friends. (The vogue which Tallis enjoyed in the 1840s would not have started by then, although Tallis’ full
services were in print and in use in the early nineteenth century.)</p>
          <p>Boyce’s <hi rend="i">Cathedral Music</hi>, with Arnold’s continuation, does, however, provide
three comparatively easy pieces: “I call and cry,” “Hear the voice and prayer” and “All people that
on earth do dwell.” There is one piece of which we may be sure, as it recurs in many collections, and that
is Tallis’ <hi rend="i">Canon</hi>, which was used throughout the period as an evening hymn.</p>
          <p>The idea of the evening hymn is strong, in Palmer’s world. There is the painting 
<hi rend="i">Coming from Evening Church</hi>; there is his statement that
<q>
The smaller glories of Heaven might be tried—hymns sung amongst the hills of Paradise at eventide<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">11</ref></q>
and there is also the poem,
<q>
With pipe and rural chaunt along,<lb/>
The Shepherds wind their homeward way,<lb/>
And with melodious even song,<lb/>
Lull to soft rest the weary day . . .
</q>
	<pb id="p15-100" n="100"/>
<figure n="EveningHymn.15.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="418" height="400">
	<figTranscr>EVENING HYMN. L.M.<lb/>
	Glory to thee, my God, this night, For<lb/>
	all the blessings of the light; Keep me O keep me<lb/>
	King of Kings, under thy own Almighty wings.</figTranscr>
	<head>The <hi rend="i">Evening Hymn</hi> in a contemporary hymnbook.</head>
</figure>
<q>
For I though base believe that Thou for me<lb/>
Hast better things prepared than village gardens be:<lb/>
<lb/>
By streams of life, and th’ever blooming tree,<lb/>
To walk, and sing with antique saints, and see<lb/>
Bliss above all, dear Lord thy face eternally.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48"
type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">11</hi> A. H. Palmer, p. 13.</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Lister, pp. 70-71.</note></q></p>
          <p>Thus we might imagine the Ancients singing: Finch leading the round with his alto voice,
Palmer’s baritone,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">13</ref> then Calvert
and the others joining with the words,
<q>
Glory to Thee my God this night<lb/>
For all the blessings of the light<lb/>
Keep me o keep me King of Kings<lb/>
Beneath thy own almighty wings.
</q>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">13</hi> In the notes of A. H. Palmer, communicated by Mr. Raymond
Lister.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
