<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.2.minnick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="checklist">Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Recent Scholarship</title>
        <author n="Minnick">Thomas L. Minnick</author>
        <author n="Dörrbecker">Detlef W. Dörrbecker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>James Warwick</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Peter Davidson</name>
              <name>Detlef Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Anthony J. Harding</name>
              <name>David Sten Herrstrom</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>James A. Winn</name>
              <name>Michael C. Young</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
      <pb id="p15-83" n="83"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-2-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">BLAKE AND HIS CIRCLE: A CHECKLIST OF RECENT SCHOLARSHIP</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline><docAuthor><hi rend="b">THOMAS L. </hi><name><hi rend="b">MINNICK</hi></name></docAuthor> WITH
THE ASSISTANCE OF <docAuthor><hi rend="b">DETLEF W. </hi><name><hi
rend="b">DÖRRBECKER</hi></name></docAuthor></byline>
        <p>This year’s issue of our annual checklist includes two modifications that we hope will increase
its value to those who consult it. First, we have numbered the entries and added an index, since the
organization that we adopted last year multiplies the number of sections and therefore the number of alphabets
in which a reader may have to look to find a favorite author. Second, we have adopted the convention of
including an asterisk (*) after items that at least one of us has not personally examined. (We have abandoned
the use of the asterisk or any other symbol to indicate retrospective items.)</p>
        <p>As always, it is a pleasure to record our gratitude to those who sent along offprints of their
articles, notes, and reviews that we might not otherwise have located. Mr. Ray Thompson of Columbus, Ohio,
helpfully reported on some items. And a special word of thanks is due to Professor G. E. Bentley, Jr., for his
continuing advice and support.</p>
        <p>T. L. M.</p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">PART I</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">WILLIAM BLAKE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">EDITIONS, TRANSLATIONS, FACSIMILES, REPRODUCTIONS</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>1 Blake, William. “Brief an Dr. Trusler [and] Anmerkungen zu Sir Joshua Reynolds’
‘Abhandlungen.’” Pp. 25-38 in <hi rend="i">Englische Literaturtheorie des 19. Jahrhunderts: Texte von
Blake bis Yeats</hi>, ed. Hans-Heinrich Rudnick (Stuttgart: Philipp Reclam Jun., 1979).</p>
            <p>2 Blake, William. <hi rend="i">Oeuvres de William Blake</hi>, vol. 3, trans. and ed. Pierre
Leyris. Paris: Aubier-Flammarion, 1980. [The third volume of Leyris’ ambitious French edition of Blake’s
writings contains annotated translations of the <hi rend="i">Religion</hi> tracts, <hi rend="i">Tiriel, Thel,
The French Revolution</hi>, the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, the <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
Albion</hi>,
<pb id="p15-84" n="84"/>
	<hi rend="i">America, Urizen, Europe, The Song</hi> (and) <hi rend="i">Book of Los</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">Ahania</hi>; there also is an introductory essay by Leyris and Jacques Blondel.]</p>
            <p>3 Blake, William. “[Poems/Gedichte].” Pp. 31-61 in <hi rend="i">Gedichte der englischen
Romantik; Englisch/Deutsch</hi>, ed. Raimund Borgmeier (Stuttgart: Philipp Reclam Jun., 1980). [Nineteen of
Blake’s poems are reprinted here side by side with the editor’s prose translations.]</p>
            <p>4 Erdman, David V., coordinating ed., with John E. Grant, Edward J. Rose, and Michael J.
Tolley, eds. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Designs for Edward Young’s “Night Thoughts”: A Complete
Edition.</hi> 2 vols. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1980. [Vols. 1 and 2 contain the Introduction and the plates.
Vols. 3 and 4, “now in preparation,” will contain the commentary.]</p>
            <p>5 Keynes, Sir Geoffrey L., ed. <hi rend="i">The Letters of William Blake, with Related
Documents</hi>, 3rd ed., rev. and enl. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1980.</p>
            <p>6 Klonsky, Milton. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Dante.</hi> New York, N.Y.: Harmony Books, 1980.
Reviewed by Tom Phillips, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 13
February 1981, p. 169.</p>
            <p>7 Malmqvist, Göran, ed. and trans. <hi rend="i">William Blake: En <corr type="emend">Ö</corr>
På Månen.</hi> Uppsala: Brombergs Bokförlag, 1979. [This edition and translation of <hi rend="i">An Island
in the Moon</hi> includes a facsimile of Blake’s manuscript.] Reviewed by Erik Frykman, 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 217-18.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">BIBLIOGRAPHIES, BIBLIOGRAPHICAL ESSAYS, EXHIBITION CATALOGUES</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>8 Alexander, David, and Richard T. Godfrey. <hi rend="i">Painters and Engraving: The
Reproductive Print from Hogarth to Wilkie.</hi> An exhibition at the Yale Center for British Art, New Haven,
Connecticut, 26 March through 22 June 1980. And catalogue. Reviewed by Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 220-23.</p>
            <p>9 Dodd, Phillip, Andrew Lincoln, and J. R. Watson, “The Nineteenth Century: Romantic
Period,” pp. 256-79 in James Redmond, <hi rend="i">et al.</hi>, eds., <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in
English Studies, Volume 58 (1977)</hi> (London: For the English Association by John Murray, 1979). [Blake
items are discussed on pp. 257-60.]</p>
            <p>10 Hofmann, Werner, ed. <hi rend="i">Goya: Das Zeitalter der Revolutionen 1789-1830</hi> [exhb.
cat.]. Munich: Prestel, for the Kunsthalle Hamburg, 1980 [“Kunst um 1800”]. [Drawings and paintings by
such artists as Romney, Fuseli, Flaxman, and Blake, among others, served to demonstrate the European context
of Goya’s art.]</p>
            <p>11* Lambourne, Lionel. <hi rend="i">British Watercolours in the Victoria and Albert Museum: An
Illustrated Summary catalogue.</hi> London: HMSO, 1980.</p>
            <p>12 Minnick, Thomas L., with the assistance of Detlef W. Dörrbecker and Kazumitsu Watarai.
“Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Recent Scholarship.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 85-94.</p>
            <p>13 Modern Language Association of America. “Blake.” Pp. 106-108 in <hi rend="i">1979 MLA
International Bibliography of Books and Articles on the Modern Languages and Literatures</hi>, vol. 1. New
York, N.Y.: MLA, 1980.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">CRITICAL STUDIES</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>14 Ackland, Michael. “Blake’s Problematic Touchstones to Experience: ‘Introduction,’
‘Earth’s Answer,’ and the Lyca Poems,” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 19 (1980), 3-17.</p>
            <p>15* Adams, Hazard. <hi rend="i">William Blake: A Reading of the Shorter Poems.</hi> [1963;
rpt.] Folcroft, Penns.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1980.</p>
            <p>16* Ansari, Asloob A. <hi rend="i">Arrows of Intellect.</hi> [1965; rpt.]. Folcroft, Penns.:
Folcroft Library Editions, 1976.</p>
            <p>17 Austin, Deborah. “Threefold Blake’s Divine Vision, Intention, and Myth.” Pp. 79-96 in
Marjorie W. McCune, Tucker Orbison, and Philip M. Withim, eds., <hi rend="i">The Bindings of Proteus:
Perspectives on Myth and the Literary Process</hi> (Cranbury, N. J.: Bucknell University Press, 1980).</p>
            <p>18* Bahan, Maung. <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Mysticism.</hi> [1924; rpt.] Folcroft,
Penns.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1974.</p>
            <p>19* BaHan, Maung. <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Mysticism.</hi> [1924; rpt.] Darby, Penns.:
Arden Library, 1978.</p>
            <p>20 Bain, Iain, and David Chambers. “Printing Blake’s Engravings for Thornton’s 
<hi rend="i">Virgil.</hi>” <hi rend="i">The Private Library</hi>, 3rd series, 1 (1978), 171-77.</p>
            <p>21 Baine, Rodney M. “Bromion’s ‘Jealous Dolphins’.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 206-07.</p>
            <p>22 Bateson, F. W. “Myth—A Dispensable Critical Term.” Pp. 98-109 in Marjorie W. McCune,
Tucker Orbison, and Philip M. Withim, eds., <hi rend="i">The Bindings of Proteus: Perspectives on Myth and the
Literary Process</hi> (Cranbury, N.J.: Bucknell University Press, 1980). [Bateson uses “A Poison Tree” as
a test case for his argument that English literary criticism can do without the term “myth.”]</p>
            <p>23 Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Blake’s Trial Documents.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 37-39.</p>
            <p>24 Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Dr. James Curry as a Patron of Blake.” <hi rend="i">Notes and
Queries</hi>, n.s. 27 (1980), 71-73.</p>
            <p>25 Bentley, G. E., Jr. “William Blake’s Techniques of Engraving and Printing.” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi>, 34 (1981), 241-53.</p>
            <p>26 Bergmann, Elizabeth Wagner. “Yeats’s Poetry and the Pre-Raphaelite Tradition: From
Painting to Sculpture.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 41 (1981), 4029-A. Diss.,
University of Michigan, 1980. [Chapter One includes discussion of Blake as, in Yeats’s view, the ancestor of
Rossetti, Morris, Burne-Jones, <hi rend="i">et cie.</hi>]</p>
            <p>27 Bindman, David. “The Dead Ardours Revisited.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 211. [A reply to David Erdman, q.v.]</p>
            <p>28 Blunt, Anthony F. <hi rend="i">The Art of William Blake.</hi> [1959; rpt.] New York, N.Y.
[etc.]: Harper and Row, 1974 [“Icon Editions”].</p>
            <p>29* Bogan, Jim. “The Emanation in Blake’s ‘Jerusalem’.” <hi rend="i">Publications of
the Missouri Philological Association</hi>, 4 (1979), 83-89.</p>
            <p>30* Bronowski, Jacob. <hi rend="i">William Blake: A Man Without a Mask.</hi> [?1943-44; rpt.]
New York, N.Y.: Gordon Press, 1976.</p>
            <pb id="p15-85" n="85"/>
            <p>31* Bruce, Harold L. <hi rend="i">William Blake in This World.</hi> [1925; rpt.] Darby, Penns.:
Arden Library, 1978.</p>
            <p>32* Burdett, Osbert. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> [1926; rpt.] New York, N.Y.: Haskell
House, 1974 [“Studies in Blake,” no. 3].</p>
            <p>33 Buxton, John. <hi rend="i">The Grecian Taste. Literature in the Age of Neo-Classicism
1740-1820.</hi> London and Basingstoke: Macmillan, 1978. [Discusses neoclassical strains from Shaftesbury
through Akenside, Collins, Goldsmith, Blake (pp. 85-104), Landor, Peacock, and Shelley.]</p>
            <p>34 Carr, Stephen Leo. “William Blake’s Print-Making Process in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi>, 47 (1980), 520-541.</p>
            <p>35* Chesterton, Gilbert K. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> [1910; rpt.] Havertown and
Philadelphia, Penns.: Richard West, 1973.</p>
            <p>36 Cooper, Andrew M. “Blake’s Escape from Mythology: Self-mastery in 
<hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 20 (1981), 85-110.</p>
            <p>37 Cox, Stephen D. “Berkeley, Blake, and the Apocalypse of Pynchon’s <hi rend="i">The
Crying of Lot 49</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Essays in Literature</hi>, 7 (1980), 91-99.</p>
            <p>38 Crehan, Stewart. “Blake’s ‘Tyger’ and the ‘Tygerish Multitude.’” 
<hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi>, 6 (1980), [150] 151-60.</p>
            <p>39 Damrosch, Leopold, Jr. <hi rend="i">Symbol and Truth in Blake’s Myth.</hi> Princeton,
N.J.: Princeton University Press, 1980. [Also published in the “Limited Paperback Editions/LPE.”]</p>
            <p>40 Davis, Patricia Elizabeth. “William Blake’s New Typology and the Revaluation of Prophecy
in the Eighteenth Century.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 40 (1980),
6288-A-6289-A. Diss., Emory University, 1979. [After an introductory review and analysis of post-Reformation
attitudes toward prophecy, Davis analyzes <hi rend="i">Europe, Milton</hi>, and the <hi rend="i">Illustrations
to the Book of Job.</hi>]</p>
            <p>41 Deck, Raymond H. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> Finally Arrive in
America.” <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi>, n.s. 31 (1980), 183-92.</p>
            <p>42 Dembo, Pamela. “William Blake and Rabindranath Tagore.” <hi rend="i">Unisa</hi>
[University of South Africa] <hi rend="i">English Studies</hi>, 14 (1976), 52-55.</p>
            <p>43* Dickinson, Kate L. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Anticipation of the Individualistic
Revolution.</hi> [1915; rpt.] Darby, Penns.: Arden Library, 1980.</p>
            <p>44 Dilworth, Thomas. “Blake’s Argument with Newberry in ‘Laughing Song.’” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 36-37.</p>
            <p>45 Dobai, Johannes. “William Blake als Kunsttheoretiker,” pp. 198-231 in Gerhard Charles
Rump, ed., <hi rend="i">Kunst und Kunsttheorie des XVIII. Jahrhunderts in England: Studien zum Wandel
ästhetischer Anschauungen 1650-1830—Art and Art Theory in Eighteenth Century England: Studies in the Change
of Aesthetic Concepts 1650-1830</hi> (Hildesheim: Gerstenber Verlag, 1979).</p>
            <p>46. Dunbar, Pamela. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Poetry of Milton.</hi>
Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1980. Reviewed by Michael Mason, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times
Literary Supplement</hi>, 13 February 1981, p. 169.</p>
            <p>47 Eaves, Morris. “Romantic Expressive Theory and Blake’s Idea of the Audience.” 
<hi rend="i">PMLA</hi>, 95 (1980), 784-801. [See Welch, Dennis M., for a reply.]</p>
            <p>48 Eaves, Morris. Reply to Welch, Dennis M., <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi>, 96 (1981), 274-75.</p>
            <p>49* Edwards, Gavin. “Mind-Forg’d Manacles: A Contribution to the Discussion of Blake’s
‘London.’” <hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi>, 5 (1979), 87-105.</p>
            <p>50 El-Hage, George Nicolas. “William Blake and Kahlil Gibran: Poets of Prophetic Vision.”
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 41 (1981), 4024-A., Diss., State University of New
York at Binghamton, 1981. [Includes discussion of Gibran’s knowledge of Blake, perhaps through Rodin; a
comparison of Gibran’s prophet, AlMustafa, and Blake’s Los; a section on Blake and Gibran on imagination
and nature; and a final chapter on Blake and Gibran as poets of the Bible.]</p>
            <p>51 Erdman, David V. “Leonora, Laodamia, and the Dead Ardours.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 96-98.</p>
            <p>52 Essick, Robert N. “Blake’s ‘Enoch’ Lithograph.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 180-84.</p>
            <p>53 Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Printmaker.</hi> Princeton, N.J.: Princeton
University Press, 1980. $50.00. Reviewed by Michael Mason, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times
Literary Supplement</hi>, 13 February 1981, p. 169.</p>
            <p>54 Essick, Robert N., with the assistance of Thomas V. Lange. “Blake in the Marketplace,
1978-79.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 4-21.</p>
            <p>55* Fairchild, B. H., Jr. “Songs of Innocence and Experience: The Blakean Vision of George
Lucas.” <hi rend="i">Literature/Film Quarterly</hi>, 7 (1979), 112-19.</p>
            <p>56* Fairchild, B. H., Jr. <hi rend="i">Such Holy Song: Music as Idea, Form, and Image in the
Poetry of William Blake.</hi> Kent, Ohio: Kent State University Press, 1980.</p>
            <p>57 Fishman, Sylvia Barack. “The Watered Garden and the Bride of God: Patterns of Biblical
Imagery in Poems of Spenser, Milton, and Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 41
(1980), 1063-A. Diss., Washington University, 1980. [Traces “two major patterns of biblical allusion —the
cosmic marital metaphor and the moral pastoral” from the Song of Solomon through <hi rend="i">The Faerie
Queene</hi> and <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> to <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion,
Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>]</p>
            <p>58 Fiske, Irving. <hi rend="i">Bernard Shaw’s Debt to William Blake.</hi> [1951; rpt.]
Hancock, Ver.: Vermont Creative Center, 1979. [“An exact photographic facsimile of the original edition,”
with a brief biography of the author added by his daughter, Ladybelle Fiske.]</p>
            <p>59* Gaunt, William. <hi rend="i">Arrows of Desire.</hi> [1956; rpt.] Norwood, Penns.: Norwood
Editions, 1980.</p>
            <p>60 George, Diana Hume. <hi rend="i">Blake and Freud.</hi> Ithaca and London: Cornell University
Press, 1980. $15.00.</p>
            <p>61* George, Diana H. “Malignant Fires and the Chain of Jealousy: Blake’s Treatment of
Oedipal Conflict.” <hi rend="i">University of Hartford Studies in Literature</hi>, 11 (1979), 197-211.</p>
            <p>62 Glazer, Myra. “Blake’s Little Black Boys: On the Dynamics of Blake’s Composite Art.”
<hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1980), 220-36.</p>
            <p>63 Gleckner, Robert F. “Blake, Bickerstaff, and Eighteenth-Century Theater,” 
<hi rend="i">Essays in Literature</hi>, 7 (1980), 247-53.</p>
            <p>64 Gleckner, Robert F. “W. J. Linton’s Tailpieces in Gilchrist’s Life of William
Blake.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 208-211.</p>
            <pb id="p15-86" n="86"/>
            <p>65 Gmuca, Jacqueline Laura. “A Preference for the Acorn, not the Oak: A Study of Yeats’s
Romanticism through the Use of Imagery.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 41 (1981),
4040-A-4041-A. Diss., Kent State University, 1980. [The appendix discusses Yeats’s assessments of Keats,
Shelley, and Blake, from each of whom, Gmuca argues, Yeats drew an image central to his work. The final
chapter and epilogue incorporate discussion of Blake’s Christ as important to Yeats.]</p>
            <p>66 Hagstrum, Jean H. “Eros and Psyche: Some Versions of Romantic Love and Delicacy.” 
<hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry</hi>, 3 (1977), 521-542. [Discusses Apuleian concepts in the work of Canova, Romney,
and in <hi rend="i">Thel.</hi>]</p>
            <p>67 Hibbard, David Otis. “Blake’s Metaphorical Transforming Vision and the Problem of the
One and the Many.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 41 (1980), 1610-A. Diss., Kent
State University, 1980. [Hibbard argues that Blake’s fourfold vision provides the key to his visionary
solution to the traditional problem of the One and the many. This study includes a comparison of Blake’s
vision and Martin Buber’s I-thou relation, Owen Barfield’s doctrine of visionary participation, the
Christian Trinity, and Paul’s notion of membership in the Body of Christ.]</p>
            <p>68 Hilton, Nelson. “Blake and the Mountains of the Mind.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 196-204.</p>
            <p>69 Hilton, Nelson. “Blake in the Chains of Being,” <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth
Century</hi>, 21 (1980), 212-35.</p>
            <p>70* Hodgart, Patricia, and Theodore Redpath, eds. <hi rend="i">Romantic Perspectives: The Work
of Crabbe, Blake, Wordsworth, and Coleridge As Seen by Their Contemporaries and by Themselves.</hi> [1964;
rpt.] Darby, Penns.: Arden Library, 1979.</p>
            <p>71 Hoeveler, Diane Long. “Blake’s Erotic Apocalypse: The Androgynous Ideal in
‘Jerusalem.’” <hi rend="i">Essays in Literature</hi>, 6 (1979), 29-41.</p>
            <p>72 Lange, Thomas V. “Blake in American Almanacs.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 94-96.</p>
            <p>73 La Belle, Jenijoy. “Michelangelo’s Sistine Frescoes and Blake’s 1795 Color-Printed
Drawings: A Study in Structural Relationships.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980),
66-84.</p>
            <p>74 Lefebvre, Mark Stephen. “William Blake’s Concept of his Function as a Poet in
Society.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 41 (1980), 2123-A. Diss., Kansas State
University, 1980. [Argues that Blake’s concept of the social role of the poet-prophet “developed from a
naive faith in the simple statement of truth to a firm belief in the permanency of art and its ability to
eventually make itself felt on the human consciousness.”]</p>
            <p>75 Levinson, Marjorie. “‘The Book of Thel’ by William Blake: A Critical Reading.” 
<hi rend="i">ELH</hi>, 47 (1980), 287-303.</p>
            <p>76* Levitt, Annette S. “The ‘Miltonic’ Progression of Gulley Jimson.” 
<hi rend="i">Mosaic</hi>, 11 (1977), 77-91. [Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> as a model for Joyce Cary?]</p>
            <p>77 Lister, Raymond. “A Letter from Benjamin Disraeli to Anne Gilchrist.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 99.</p>
            <p>78* MacDonald, Greville. <hi rend="i">The Sanity of William Blake.</hi> [1920; rpt.] Folcroft,
Penns.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1975.</p>
            <p>79 Maeda, Yoshihiko. “[In Japanese] Notes on the Iconography and Style of William Blake’s
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> Designs.” <hi rend="i">Eibeibungaku, Rikkyo Daigaku Bungakubu Eibeibungaku
Kenkyushitsu</hi> [<hi rend="i">English and American Literature, The Rikkyo Review, The Department of
Literature of Rikkyo University</hi>], 41 (1981), 21-58.</p>
            <p>80 Maeda, Yoshihiko. “[In Japanese] William Blake’s Coloring of the <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> Designs and the Colored Copy F in Sir John Soane’s Museum.” <hi rend="i">Rikkyo Daigaku
Kenkyuhohoku</hi> [<hi rend="i">St. Paul’s Review. The Department of General Education</hi>], 40 (1981),
15-37.</p>
            <p>81* Malmqvist, N. Göran D. “William Blake i Kina.” <hi rend="i">Artes</hi>, 3 (1979),
108-15.</p>
            <p>82 Mann, Paul Jay. “A Preface to William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 41 (1980), 2123-A-2124-A. Diss., University of California,
Santa Cruz, 1980. [Mann begins with a consideration of the “status of the manuscript and the nature of
manuscripts in general” and, rather than “dismissing the manuscript’s apparent inability to manifest
objective unity, the first chapter explores the manuscript as a representation of the fallen world.” Chapter
Two investigates several theories of reading “in the light of the apocalyptic project of <hi rend="i">The
Four Zoas</hi>, in order to reveal more clearly the reader’s role in the production of meaning.” The third
and final chapter “explores the nature of prophecy” and takes the Four Zoas and Albion as “paradigms”
of reading.]</p>
            <p>83* McClellan, Jane. “Auden’s Creative Relationship to Blake, Coleridge, and Wordsworth.”
<hi rend="i">North Dakota Quarterly</hi>, 47 (1979), no. 1, 41-54.</p>
            <p>84 McClenahan, Catherine Louise. “Creation Unfinished: Text and Structure in William
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 41 (1980),
2616-A. Diss., The University of Wisconsin—Milwaukee, 1979. [“This close reading of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> explores two propositions. First, the poem’s basic structure is a spiral, shaped by
parallels and contrasts, and proceeding by dialectic. . . . Second, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is designed to
be read as what Roland Barthes calls a ‘text’: a form generated only by reader and work together.”]</p>
            <p>85* Morton, Arthur L. <hi rend="i">The Everlasting Gospel.</hi> [1958; rpt.] Darby, Penns.:
Arden Library, 1978.</p>
            <p>86 Paley, Morton D. “John Trivett Nettleship and his ‘Blake Drawings.’” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 185-94.</p>
            <p>87 Pease, Donald. “Blake, Whitman, and Modernism: A Poetics of Pure Possibility.” 
<hi rend="i">PMLA</hi>, 96 (1981), 64-85.</p>
            <p>88 Pechey, Graham. “‘The Marriage of Heaven and Hell:’ A Text and Its Conjuncture.” 
<hi rend="i">Oxford Literary Review</hi>, 3 (1979), no. 3, 52-76.</p>
            <p>89* Pierce, Hazel. “William Blake’s Illuminated Printing.” <hi rend="i">Platte Valley
Review</hi>, 1 (1973), 51-56.</p>
            <p>90* Preston, Kerrison. <hi rend="i">Blake and Rossetti.</hi> [1944; rpt.] Belfast, Maine:
Porter, 1978.</p>
            <p>91* Price, Steve. “From What Does Blake’s Thel Flee?” <hi rend="i">Publications of the
Missouri Philological Association</hi>, 4 (1979), 39-45.</p>
            <pb id="p15-87" n="87"/>
            <p>92 Punter, David. “Blake and the Shapes of London.” <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi>, 23 (1981),
1-23.</p>
            <p>93 Quadri Iovine, Marcella. “La poesia del desiderio: ‘Ah! Sunflower’ di W. Blake.” 
<hi rend="i">Annali Istituto Universitario Orientale: anglistica</hi>, 22 (1979), 139-54.</p>
            <p>94 Read, Dennis M. “Cromek’s Provincial Advertisements for Blake’s ‘Grave.’” 
<hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>, n.s. 27 (1980), 73-76.</p>
            <p>95 Read, Dennis M. “A New Blake Engraving: Gilchrist and the Cromek Connection.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 60-64.</p>
            <p>96 Reisner, Mary E. “Effigies of Power: Pitt and Fox as Canterbury Pilgrims.” 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 12 (1978-1979), 481-503. [The essay attempts to trace “the
descent, on the basis of astonishing resemblance, of Blake’s Pardoner and Summoner in 
<hi rend="i">Chaucer’s Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> from satirical portraits of William Pitt the Younger and Charles
James Fox”; there are 5 illus.]</p>
            <p>97* Roe, Albert S. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations to the Divine Comedy.</hi> [1953; rpt.]
Westport, Conn.: Greenwood, 1977.</p>
            <p>98 Rose, Edward J. “Blake and Dürer.” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi>, 16
(1980), 166-76.</p>
            <p>99 Rose, Edward J. “Blake’s Human Root: Symbol, Myth, and Design.” <hi rend="i">Studies
in English Literature 1500-1900</hi>, 20 (1980), 575-86. [Pp. 587-90 reproduce four of the <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> watercolors.]</p>
            <p>100* Rudd, Margaret E. <hi rend="i">Organiz’d Innocence: The Story of Blake’s Prophetic
Books.</hi> [1956; rpt.] Folcroft, Penns.: Folcroft Library Editions, 1977.</p>
            <p>101 Sanzo, Eileen. “Blake and the Spaces of Paradise.” <hi rend="i">the nassau review</hi>,
4 (1980), 19-23.</p>
            <p>102 Schleifer, Ronald. “Simile, Metaphor, and Vision: Blake’s Narration of Prophecy in
‘America.’” <hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature 1500-1900</hi>, 19 (1979), 569-588.</p>
            <p>103* Schotz, Myra Glazer. “‘For the Sexes’: Blake’s Hermaphrodite in ‘Lady
Chatterly’s Lover.’” <hi rend="i">Bucknell Review</hi>, 24 (1978), 17-26.</p>
            <p>104 Soupault, Philippe. “William Blake.” [1927; rpt.] Pp. 83-131 in <hi rend="i">Ėcrits
sur la peinture</hi> (Paris: Lachenal &amp; Ritter, 1980).</p>
            <p>105 Stempel, Daniel. “Blake, Foucault, and the Classical Episteme.” <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi>,
96 (1981), 388-407.</p>
            <p>106 Storch, Margaret. “The Very Image of Our Conceptions: Blake’s Allegory and the Role of
the Creative Poet.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi>, 83 (1980), 262-79.</p>
            <p>107 Strickland, Edward. “John Dennis and Blake’s Guinea Sun.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 36.</p>
            <p>108 Tannenbaum, Leslie W. “Transformations of Michelangelo in William Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1980), 19-50.</p>
            <p>109 Taylor, Ronald Clayton. “Semantic Structures and the Temporal Modes of Blake’s
Prophetic Verse.” <hi rend="i">Language and Style</hi>, 12 (1979), 26-49.</p>
            <p>110 Thorpe, James. <hi rend="i">Gifts of Genius: Treasures of the Huntington Library.</hi> San
Marino: The Huntington Library, 1980. $10.00. [Pp. 107-30 are “William Blake: The Power of the
Imagination,” originally published, as were the other seven sections of this book, as a pamphlet.]</p>
            <p>111 Todd, Ruthven. “‘Poisonous Blues,’ and Other Pigments.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 31-34.</p>
            <p>112 Vaughan, Frank Andrew. “Blake’s Illustrations to the Poetry of Thomas Gray: A Movement
toward Eternity.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 41 (1981), 4049-A. Diss.,
University of California at Riverside, 1980. [Vaughan argues that each series of designs within the set of 116
designs Blake made for Gray’s poems “is an independent portion of a movement which first explores the
reasons for the fall, next articulates the errors of Generation, and, finally, announces the qualities of mind
necessary for a reascension. . . . ”]</p>
            <p>113 Waggoner, Hyatt H. “Visionary Poetry, Learning to See.” <hi rend="i">The Sewanee
Review</hi>, 89 (1981), 228-47. [Blake is discussed throughout.]</p>
            <p>114 Warner, Nicholas O. “Blake’s Moon-Ark Symbolism.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 44-59.</p>
            <p>115 Welburn, Andrew J. “Blake’s Cosmos: Sources and Transformations.” 
<hi rend="i">JEGP</hi>, 80 (1981), 39-53.</p>
            <p>116 Welch, Dennis M. Reply to Eaves, “Romantic Expressive Theory and Blake’s Idea of the
Audience” (<hi rend="i">q.v.</hi>), <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi>, 96 (1981), 273-74.</p>
            <p>117* Wright, Thomas. <hi rend="i">Blake for Babes.</hi> [1923; rpt.] Darby, Penns.: Arden
Library, 1978.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">PART II</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">BLAKE’S CIRCLE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>William Cowper</title>
            </head>
            <p>118 Dawson, P. M. S. “Cowper and the Russian Ice Palace.” <hi rend="i">Review of English
Studies</hi>, n.s. 31 (1980), 440-43.</p>
            <p>119 Feingold, Richard. <hi rend="i">Nature and Society: Later Eighteenth-Century Uses of the
Pastoral and Georgic.</hi> New Brunswick, N.J.: Rutgers University Press, 1978. [Pp. 121-54 are chapter four,
“William Cowper: State, Society, and Countryside”; and pp. 155-92 are chapter five, “Art Divorced from
Nature: <hi rend="i">The Task</hi> and Bucolic Tradition.”]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Erasmus Darwin</title>
            </head>
            <p>120 Hassler, Donald M. “Byron and Erasmus Darwin,” <hi rend="i">Ball State University
Farum</hi>, 20 (1979), 75-80.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>John Flaxman</title>
            </head>
            <p>121 Eddy, Linda R. “‘Achilles Contending with the Rivers’: Flaxman Translates Homer.”
<hi rend="i">The Stanford Museum</hi>, 6-7 (1976-77), 10-17.</p>
            <p>122 Flaxman, Vivien. “‘The Flight of Satan from Paradise’ and ‘Adam and Eve’: John
Flaxman’s Last Works?” <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 122 (1980), 687-90.</p>
            <p>123 Hofmann, Werner. “L’Artista, servitore di due padroni: tra arte e industria—è
l’arte ad esser tradita?” <hi rend="i">Bolaffiarte</hi>, 54 (1979), 52-56.</p>
            <p>124 Irwin, David. <hi rend="i">John Flaxman 1755-1826: Sculptor, Illustrator, Designer.</hi>
London: Studio Vista/Christie’s, 1979. [With Bindman’s exhibition handbook, for a long time to come this
will probably be the standard monograph on the artist.]</p>
            <pb id="p15-88" n="88"/>
            <p>See also item 10, Hofmann, Werner, ed.; and item 153, Byron, Arthur, <hi rend="i">et
al.</hi></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Henry Fuseli</title>
            </head>
            <p>125* Garlick, Kenneth J. <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Master Drawings from the
Ashmolean.</hi> [exhb. cat.] Oxford: International Exhibitions Foundation, 1979. [Fuseli was among the artists
represented in this traveling exhibition.]</p>
            <p>126 Hock, Erich. “Klopstocks Ode ‘Verhängnisse’ und ihre Umdichtung durch Johann
Heinrich Füssli.” <hi rend="i">Euphorion</hi>, 73 (1979), 219-226. [Fuseli’s so-called “Gaben Gottes”
ode was modeled after Klopstock’s poem.]</p>
            <p>127 Leisi, Ernst. “Zu einer Studie J. H. Füsslis.” Pp. 45-48 in 
<hi rend="i">Aufsätze</hi> (Heidelberg: Carl Winter Universitätsverlag, 1978). [A rpt. of an essay first
published in the <hi rend="i">Neue Zürcher Zeitung</hi>, 22 March 1959.]</p>
            <p>128 Muschg, Walter. “Heinrich Füssli.” Pp. 238-59 in <hi rend="i">Pamphlet und Bekenntnis:
Aufsätze und Reden</hi>, ed. Peter André Bloch, with the assistance of Elli Muschg-Zollikofer (Olten and
Freiburg i. Br.: Walter, 1968). [A rpt. of Muschg’s preface in his 1942 edition of Fuseli’s letters.]</p>
            <p>129* Pressly, Nancy L. <hi rend="i">The Fuseli Circle in Rome. Early Romantic Art of the
1770s.</hi> New Haven: Yale Center for British Art, 1979. $10.00.</p>
            <p>130 Ravenhall, Mary Dennis. “Illustrations of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> in England.”
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 41 (1980), 442-A. Diss., University of Illinois at
Urbana-Champaign, 1980. [Ravenhall “seeks to identify changing interpretations of Milton’s Christian
epic” by comparing illustrations to <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi> Artists studied include de Medina,
Aldrich, Lens, Cheron, Hayman, Richter, Westall, Burney, Fuseli, and Hamilton. Ravenhall does not mention
Blake in her abstract.]</p>
            <p>131 Starobinski, Jean. “Johann Heinrich Füssli.” Pp. 96-107 in <hi rend="i">1789: Les
emblèmes de la raison</hi> (Paris: Flammarion, 1973). [An Italian edition was published by the Istituto
Editoriale Italiano at Milan.] See also item 10, Hofmann, Werner, ed.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>William Hamilton</title>
            </head>
            <p>132 Campbell, Anne. “A Scrapbook of Drawings by William Hamilton.” <hi rend="i">Huntington
Library Quarterly</hi>, 43 (1980), 327-34. See also item 130, Ravenhall, Mary Dennis.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>William Hayley</title>
            </head>
            <p>133* Hayley, William. <hi rend="i">An Essay on Sculpture, in a Series of Epistles to John
Flaxman</hi>, ed. Donald H. Reiman. [1800: rpt. with Blake’s engravings.] New York: Garland, 1978.
[“Romantic Context,” vol. 61.]</p>
            <p>134* Hayley, William. <hi rend="i">The Eulogies of Howard, a Vision.</hi> [1791; rpt., bound
with Hayley’s] <hi rend="i">Ballads, Founded on Anecdotes Relating to Animals</hi> [1805; rpt. with
Blake’s engravings], and <hi rend="i">Poems on Serious and Sacred Subjects</hi> [1818; rpt.], ed. Donald H.
Reiman. New York, N.Y.: Garland, 1978 [“Romantic Context,” vol. 60].</p>
            <p>135* Hayley, William. <hi rend="i">Ode, Inscribed to John Howard.</hi> [1780; rpt., bound with
Hayley’s] <hi rend="i">Essay on Painting</hi> [1781; rpt.], <hi rend="i">Triumphs of Temper</hi> [1781;
rpt.], and <hi rend="i">Essay on Epic Poetry</hi> [1782; rpt.], ed. Donald H. Reiman. New York, N.Y.: Garland,
1979 [“Romantic Context,” vol. 58].</p>
            <p>136* Hayley, William. <hi rend="i">Ode to Mr. Wright of Derby.</hi> [1783; rpt., bound with
Hayley’s] <hi rend="i">Occasional Stanzas</hi> [1788; rpt.], <hi rend="i">Elegy on the Death of the
Honourable Sir William Jones</hi> [1795; rpt.], <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi> [1800; rpt. with
Blake’s designs], <hi rend="i">Triumphs of Music</hi> [1804; rpt.], <hi rend="i">Stanzas of an English
Friend to the Patriots of Spain</hi> [1808; rpt.], and <hi rend="i">Ode to a Friend</hi> [1783; rpt.], ed.
Donald H. Reiman. New York, N.Y.: Garland, 1979 [“Romantic Context,” vol. 59].</p>
            <p>137* Hayley, William. <hi rend="i">A Poetical Epistle to an Eminent Painter.</hi> [1778; rpt.,
bound with Hayley’s] <hi rend="i">An Elegy</hi> [ . . . ] <hi rend="i">Addressed to the Right Reverend
Robert Lowth</hi> [1779; rpt.], <hi rend="i">Epistle to Admiral Keppel</hi> [1779; rpt.], 
<hi rend="i">Epistle</hi> [ . . . ] <hi rend="i">on the Death of John Thornton, Esq.</hi> [1780; rpt.], and 
<hi rend="i">Essay on History</hi> [1780; rpt.], ed. Donald H. Reiman. New York, N.Y.: Garland, 1978 [“Romantic
Context,” vol. 57].</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Thomas Holcroft</title>
            </head>
            <p>138 Piorkowski, Joan Lucille. “‘Revolutionary’ Sentiment: A Reappraisal of the Fiction of
Robert Bage, Charlotte Smith, and Thomas Holcroft.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>,
41 (1980), 2127-A. Diss., Temple University, 1980. [Basing her argument on a reading of selected
novels—including Bage’s <hi rend="i">Man As He Is</hi> and <hi rend="i">Hermsprong; or Man As He Is
Not</hi>, Smith’s <hi rend="i">The Old Manor House</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Young Philosopher</hi>, and
Holcroft’s <hi rend="i">Anna St. Ives</hi> and <hi rend="i">Hugh Trevor</hi>, Piorkowski discusses the
revolutionary subject matter of these novelists, their interest in the craft of fiction, and the way their
work develops the tradition of the novel of sentiment.]</p>
            <p>139 Rosenblum, Joseph. “An Addition to the Holcroft Canon.” <hi rend="i">Restoration &amp;
Eighteenth Century Theatre Research</hi>, 15 (1976), 44-45. [Attributes to Holcroft a letter which appeared in
the October, 1781 issue of <hi rend="i">The Town and Country Magazine.</hi>]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Friedrich Klopstock</title>
            </head>
            <p>140 Thayer, Terence K. “From <hi rend="i">Topos to Mythos</hi>: The Poet as Immortalizer in
Klopstock’s Works.” <hi rend="i">JEGP</hi>, 80 (1981), 157-75.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>John Caspar Lavater</title>
            </head>
            <p>141* Graham, John. <hi rend="i">Lavater’s Essay on Physiognomy: A Study in the History of
Ideas.</hi> Bern, Frankfurt, and Las Vegas: Peter Lang, 1979. SFr. 26.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Samuel Palmer</title>
            </head>
            <p>142* Whittingham, Selby, and Evelyn Joll. <hi rend="i">English Watercolours and Drawings from
the Manchester City Art Gallery.</hi> [exhb. cat.] London: Thomas Agnew and Sons, 1977. [Palmer included among
the artists represented.]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>George Romney</title>
            </head>
            <p>143* Cubbon, A. M. “The Romney Portraits of the Taubman Family.” <hi rend="i">Journal of
the Manx Museum</hi>,
<pb id="p15-89" n="89"/>
7 (1976), 232-34.</p>
            <p>See also item 10, Hofmann, Werner, ed.; item 66, Hagstrum, Jean H.; and item 171, Nelke, Laura,
and Richard W. Hutton.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Thomas Stothard</title>
            </head>
            <p>144 [Baskett and Day]. <hi rend="i">An Exhibition of Drawings and Book Illustrations by Thomas
Stothard R. A. (1755-1834).</hi> s.l. [London: Baskett and Day], s.d. [1980]. [A 4pp. sales catalogue.]</p>
            <p>145 Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Coleridge, Stothard, and the First Illustration of
‘Christabel.’” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 20 (1981), 111-16.</p>
            <p>See also item 171, Nelke, Laura, and Richard W. Hutton.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Edward Young</title>
            </head>
            <p>146 Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (London: R. Edwards,
1797): A New Unillustrated State.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 34-35.</p>
            <p>147 Fox, Jeffrey Reid. “Critical, Annotated Edition of Edward Young’s <hi rend="i">The
Complaint: Or, Night-Thoughts on Life, Death, and Immortality—Night the First.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 41 (1980), Diss., The Ohio State University, 1980. [“The
present edition has two purposes. The foremost . . . is to provide readers of the poem with a reliable text.
No new editions of <hi rend="i">Night-Thoughts</hi> have been published in the last hundred years, and the
most readily available texts are so corrupt, that close analyses . . . are extremely risky. . . . The second
purpose is to provide the reader with a solid understanding of the poem by brushing away the myths that have
grown up around it. . . . ”]</p>
            <p>148 Odell, D. W. “The Argument of Young’s <hi rend="i">Conjectures on Original
Composition.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Studies in Philology</hi>, 78 (1981), 87-106.</p>
            <p>See also item 4, Erdman, David V., coordinating ed.; and items 79 and 80, Maeda, Yoshihiko.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">PART III</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">WORKS OF RELATED INTEREST</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>149 Abrams, Ann Uhry. “Politics, Prints, and John Singleton Copley’s ‘Watson and the
Shark.’” <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi>, 61 (1979), 265-76.</p>
          <p>150* Alberts, Robert C. <hi rend="i">Benjamin West: A Biography.</hi> Boston, Mass.: Houghton
Mifflin, 1978.</p>
          <p>151 Auden, Wystan Hugh. <hi rend="i">The Prolific and the Devourer. Antaeus</hi>, no. 42 (Summer,
1981). [This book of aphorisms and reflections written by Auden in 1939 makes up this entire issue of 
<hi rend="i">Antaeus</hi> and is printed in full for the first time. Allusions to Blake appear throughout,
including in the title.]</p>
          <p>152 Byrd, Max. <hi rend="i">London Transformed: Images of the City in the Eighteenth
Century.</hi> New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1978. [Postscript includes discussion of Blake.]
Reviewed by Andre Parraux, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi>, 75 (1980), 851-52.</p>
          <p>153* Byron, Arthur, <hi rend="i">et al. Josiah Wedgwood: ‘The Arts and Sciences
United’—Correspondence, Experiment Books, and the Ceramic Products.</hi> [exhb. cat.] London: Science
Museum, 1978. [Some mention of Wedgwood as a patron of Flaxman.]</p>
          <p>154 Carr, Gerald L. “Benjamin West’s Altar Paintings for St. Marylebone Church.” 
<hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi>, 62 (1980), 293-303.</p>
          <p>155 Denham, Robert D., ed. <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye on Culture and Literature.</hi> Chicago:
University of Chicago Press, 1978. Cloth, $13.00; paper, $5.50. Reviewed by Lauriat Lane, Jr., 
<hi rend="i">English Studies in Canada</hi>, 7 (1981), 123-28.</p>
          <p>156 Farnsworth, Rodney. “Permanence and Change: Water Images and Symbols in Western European
Poetry and Painting, 1770-1840.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 41 (1980), 1050-A.
[This study, “the first interdisciplinary study of the water cycle and its four quarters (springs, rivers,
seas, clouds/rain),” focuses on Romantic poetry and painting in Germany (Goethe, Lenau, Caspar David
Friedrich, Joseph Anton Koch), England (Byron, Shelley, Constable, Turner), and France (Rousseau, Victor Hugo,
Philippe-Jacques de Loutherbourg).]</p>
          <p>157 Faulkner, Peter. <hi rend="i">Robert Bage.</hi> Boston: G. K. Hall, 1979. $10.50. [Twayne’s
English Authors Series.]</p>
          <p>158* Field, Richard S. “The Monotype: A Majority Opinion?” <hi rend="i">Print Collector’s
Newsletter</hi>, 9 (1978), 141-42. [Focuses on the technical processes of monotyping, with references to
Blake.]</p>
          <p>159 Finholt, Richard. “Northrop Frye’s Theory of Countervailing Tendencies: A New Look at the
Mode and Myth Essays.” <hi rend="i">Genre</hi>, 13 (1980), 203-57.</p>
          <p>160* Finley, Gerald. <hi rend="i">Landscapes of Memory: Turner as Illustrator to Scott.</hi>
London: The Scolar Press, 1980. £30.00</p>
          <p>161 Frye, Roland Mushat. <hi rend="i">Milton’s Imagery and the Visual Arts: Iconographic
Tradition in the Epic Poems.</hi> Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1978. Reviewed by John Steadman, 
<hi rend="i">Comparative Literature</hi>, 33 (1981), 100-03.</p>
          <p>162 Garlick, Kenneth J., and Angus D. Macintyre, eds. <hi rend="i">The Diary of Joseph
Farington</hi>, vols. 5 and 6 (August 1801 to December 1804). New Haven, Conn. and London: Yale University
Press, for the Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art, 1979. [“Studies in British Art.”]</p>
          <p>163* Gettings, Fred. <hi rend="i">The Hidden Art: A Study of Occult Symbolism in Art.</hi>
London: Studio Vista, 1978. [Includes discussions of Blake.]</p>
          <p>164 Higonnet, Margaret R. “Bachelard and the Romantic Imagination.” <hi rend="i">Comparative
Literature</hi>, 33 (1981), 18-37. [Mentions Blake as one of Bachelard’s Romantic sources.]</p>
          <p>165* Kircher, Gerda Franziska. <hi rend="i">Die Truchsessen-Galerie: Ein Beitrag zur Geschichte
des deutschen Kunstsammelns um 1800.</hi> Frankfurt am Main, Bern, and Las Vegas: Peter Lang, 1979.
[“Galerie: Beiträge zur Kunstgeschichte,” vol. 2.]</p>
          <p>166 Lankheit, Klaus. “Ein Skizzenbuch des Pietro Benvenuti mit Themen aus Shakespeare.” 
<hi rend="i">Mitteilungen des Kunsthistorischen Institutes in Florenz</hi>, 23 (1979), 357-76. [A set of Italian
copies after the 1803 edition of Boydell’s Shakespeare Gallery, executed c.
<pb id="p15-90" n="90"/>
1809.]</p>
          <p>167 Larsson, Roger Barnett. “The Beautiful, the Sublime and the Picturesque in
Eighteenth-Century Musical Thought in Britain.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 41
(1980), 14-A. Diss., State University of New York at Buffalo, 1980. [Reviews the musical and nonmusical
literature of the eighteenth century on the aesthetic categories of the beautiful, the sublime, and the
picturesque.]</p>
          <p>168* Locke, Don. <hi rend="i">A Fantasy of Reason: The Life and Thought of William Godwin.</hi>
London, Henley, and Boston, Mass.: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1980.</p>
          <p>169* Mankowitz, Wolf. <hi rend="i">Wedgwood</hi>, 3rd ed. London: Barrie and Jenkins, 1980.</p>
          <p>170 Mellor, Anne K. <hi rend="i">English Romantic Irony.</hi> Cambridge, Mass. and London:
Harvard University Press, 1980. $15.00.</p>
          <p>171* Nelke, Laura, and Richard W. Hutton. <hi rend="i">Alderman Boydell’s Shakespeare
Gallery.</hi> [exhb. cat.] Chicago, Ill.: University of Chicago, David and Alfred Smart Gallery, 1978. [On
show were engravings after the paintings of Romney, Opie, Northcote, Stothard, and Barry, amongst others.]</p>
          <p>172 Netterville, Harvey Eli. “Kathleen Raine: The Heart in Flower.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation
Abstracts International</hi>, 41 (1981), 3120-A. Diss., The Florida State University, 1980. [“An
introduction to the criticism, autobiography, and poetry of the distinguished modern British poet, Kathleen
Raine.”]</p>
          <p>173* Pacey, Philip. <hi rend="i">A Sense of What Is Real: The Arts and Existential Man.</hi>
London: Brentham, 1977. [Blake, alongside C. D. Friedrich and Edvard Munch, serving as an example for the
affinities between existential thought and the arts.]</p>
          <p>174 Paley, Morton D. “John Camden Hotten and the First British Editions of Walt Whitman—‘A
Nice Milky Cocoa-nut.’” <hi rend="i">Publishing History</hi>, 6 (1979), 5-35.</p>
          <p>175 Paschall, Douglas. “Continuity in Northrop Frye’s Criticism.” <hi rend="i">Sewanee
Review</hi>, 88 (1980), 121-25.</p>
          <p>176 Rozenberg, Paul. “Romantisme ou barbarie: le romantisme anglais, une utopie du sujet.”
<hi rend="i">Littérature</hi>, no. 40, December 1980, 95-114. [Blake mentioned throughout.]</p>
          <p>177 Spivey, Ted R., ed. <hi rend="i">W. B. Yeats: The Occult And Philosophical Backgrounds.
Studies in the Literary Imagination</hi>, 14 (1981), whole issue. [This issue includes nine essays on
Yeats’s sources, with references to Blake throughout.]</p>
          <p>178 Stafford, Barbara Maria. “Beauty of the Invisible: Winckelmann and the Aesthetics of
Imperceptibility.” <hi rend="i">Zeitschrift für Kunstgeschichte</hi>, 43 (1980), 65-78.</p>
          <p>179 Starobinski, Jean. “Der Sonnenmythos der Revolution.” <hi rend="i">Süddeutsche
Zeitung</hi>, 9-10 March 1974 (“Beilage” for no. 58). [Mentions Blake’s use of revolutionary 
<hi rend="i">sol</hi> imagery.]</p>
          <p>180 Stockard, Olivia Tate. “‘Poetic Picture, Painted Poetry’: A Study of Restoration
Advice-to-a-Painter Poems.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International.</hi> 41 (1980, 684-A. Diss.,
New York University, 1980). [“The Restoration Advices to Painters are infrequently studied. . . . Graphic
caricature was rare when the Advices flourished in the 1660’s, and the form seems to have satisfied a need
to expose distortions in the political art of the period. This fortuitous concurrence of form and historical
moment accounts for the painter poem’s extreme but short-lived popularity.”]</p>
          <p>181 Wagner, Monika. <hi rend="i">Die Industrielandschaft in der englischen Malerei und Grafik
1770-1830.</hi> Frankfurt am Main, Bern, and Las Vegas: Peter Lang, 1979. [“Kunstwissenschaftliche
Studien,” vol. 8.]</p>
          <p>182* Woodman, Ross G. “Milton’s Urania and Her Romantic Descendants.” 
<hi rend="i">University of Toronto Quarterly</hi>, 48 (1979), 189-208.</p>
          <p>183* Young, Howard T. <hi rend="i">The Line in the Margin: Juan Roman Jimenez and His Readings in
Blake, Shelley, and Yeats.</hi> Madison, Wisc., and London: University of Wisconsin Press, 1980.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">PART IV</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">REVIEWS OF WORKS CITED</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">IN PREVIOUS CHECKLISTS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>184 Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi> Reviewed by Stuart Curran, 
<hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi>, 75 (1980), 367-70.</p>
          <p>185 Bentley, G. E., Jr., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings.</hi> Reviewed by
Jean-Jacques Mayoux, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi>, 33 (1980), 466-67; by Désirée Hirst, 
<hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi>, n.s. 31 (1980), 475-77; and by E.B. Murray, <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 148-161.</p>
          <p>186 Bindman, David, ed. <hi rend="i">John Flaxman.</hi> [exhb. cat.] Reviewed by Judy Egerton,
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 22-30.</p>
          <p>187 Bindman, David, <hi rend="i">et al. John Flaxman: Mythologie und Industrie</hi>, exhb. cat.
Hamburger Kunsthalle. Reviewed by Herbert Albrecht, <hi rend="i">Rheinischer Merkur</hi>, 4 May 1979; by
Edouard Beaucamp, <hi rend="i">Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung</hi>, 12 May 1979; by Ursula Bode, 
<hi rend="i">Hannoversche Allgemeine Zeitung</hi>, 25 May 1979; by Erika Brenken, <hi rend="i">Rheinische
Post</hi>, 24 April 1979 (also published in the <hi rend="i">Neuss-Grevenbroicher Zeitung</hi>); by Barbara
Dieterich, <hi rend="i">Generalanzeiger</hi> (Bonn), 5 May 1979 (also published in the 
<hi rend="i">Nordwest-Zeitung</hi> [Oldenburg]); by Peter Engel, <hi rend="i">Flensburger Tageblatt</hi>, 21 April
1979 (the same article published in the <hi rend="i">Westdeutsche Allgemeine Zeitung</hi> and a number of
other papers); by Günter Engelhard, <hi rend="i">Deutsche Zeitung</hi>, 27 April 1979; by Uwe Eppendorf, 
<hi rend="i">Münstersche Zeitung</hi>, 26 April 1979 (also published in the <hi rend="i">Holsteinischer
Courier</hi>, 30 April 1979); by Hans Theodor Flemming, <hi rend="i">Die Welt</hi>, 21 April 1979; by Rolf
Gaska, <hi rend="i">Kieler Nachrichten</hi>, 21 April 1979; by Geno Hartlaub, <hi rend="i">Deutsches
Allgemeines Sonntagsblatt</hi>, 3 June 1979; by Paul Theodor Hoffmann, <hi rend="i">Hamburger Abendblatt</hi>,
21 April 1979; by Pierre Mazars, <hi rend="i">Le Figaro</hi>, 27 May 1979; by Renate Riechert, 
<hi rend="i">Porzellan und Glas</hi>, no. 6 (1979); by Doris Schmidt, <hi rend="i">Süddeutsche Zeitung</hi>,
28-29 April 1979; by Gisela Schütte, <hi rend="i">Die Welt</hi>, 26 January 1979 [on the projected exhb.]; by
Joachim Schyle, <hi rend="i">Kölner Stadtanzeiger</hi>, 16 May 1979; by Klaus Thiele-Dohrmann, 
<hi rend="i">Tagesanzeiger</hi> (Zurich), 7 May
<pb id="p15-91" n="91"/>
1979; by Herbert H. Wagner, <hi rend="i">Cannstätter Zeitung</hi>, 17 May 1979 (also published in the 
<hi rend="i">Esslinger Zeitung</hi>, in the Düsseldorf <hi rend="i">Handelsblatt</hi>, 18 May 1979, and in
various other papers); by A. zum Winkel, <hi rend="i">Ostholsteiner Anzeiger</hi>, 28 April 1979; in the 
<hi rend="i">Neue Zürcher Zeitung</hi>, 4 May 1979; in <hi rend="i">Der Spiegel</hi>, 16 April 1979.</p>
          <p>188 Bindman, David, ed., assisted by Deirdre Toomey. <hi rend="i">The Complete Graphic Works of
William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14
(1981), 161-63.</p>
          <p>189 Briganti, Giuliano. <hi rend="i">I pittori dell’imaginario.</hi> Reviewed by Anna Ottani
Cavina, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 122 (1980), 195-96.</p>
          <p>190 Brisman, Leslie. <hi rend="i">Romantic Origins.</hi> Reviewed by Stuart Peterfreund, 
<hi rend="i">Poetics Today</hi>, 2 (1980), 218-25.</p>
          <p>191 Bronowski, Jacob. <hi rend="i">The Visionary Eye.</hi> [Collected Essays]. Reviewed by
Catherine Lord, <hi rend="i">Journal of Aesthetics and Art Criticism</hi>, 38 (1979), 204-05.</p>
          <p>192 Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> [exhb. cat.] Reviewed by Fenella Crichton,
<hi rend="i">Pantheon</hi>, 36 (1978), 284; by Theodore Crombie, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 107 (1978), 329; by
Vivien Lowenstein, <hi rend="i">Arts Review</hi>, 30 (1978), 151-52; by Christopher Neve, <hi rend="i">Country
Life</hi>, 163 (1978), 902-03; by William Vaughan, <hi rend="i">Connoisseur</hi>, 198 (1978), 86.</p>
          <p>193 Carey, Frances A., <hi rend="i">et al. Le Gothique retrouvé.</hi> [exhb. cat.] Reviewed by
Xenia Muratova, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 122 (1980), 84-87.</p>
          <p>194 Damon, S. Foster. <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary</hi>, with a new index by Morris Eaves.
Reviewed by John E. Grant, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 131-35.</p>
          <p>195 Denham, Robert D. <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye and Critical Method.</hi> Reviewed by Frederick
W. Conner, <hi rend="i">Journal of Aesthetics and Art Criticism</hi>, 38 (1979), 97-98.</p>
          <p>196 Einem, Herbert von. <hi rend="i">Deutsche Malerei des Klassizismus und der Romantik, 1760 bis
1840.</hi> Reviewed by William Vaughan, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 122 (1980), 701.</p>
          <p>197 Easson, Kay Parkhurst, and Roger R. Easson, eds. <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.</hi>
Reviewed by Stuart Curran, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 138-43.</p>
          <p>198 Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Relief Inventions.</hi> Reviewed by David
Bindman, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 106-07.</p>
          <p>199 Essick, Robert N., and Donald Pearce, eds. <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time.</hi> Reviewed by
Zachary Leader, <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 19 (1980), 419-433; and by W. J. T. Mitchell, 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 116-120.</p>
          <p>200 Gage, John, ed. <hi rend="i">Zwei Jahrhunderte Englische Malerei.</hi> [exhb. cat.] Reviewed
by Graham Dry, <hi rend="i">Barlington Magazine</hi>, 122 (1980), 87-88 (see <hi rend="i">ib.</hi>, 221, for a
review of the symposium held in connection with the exhibition by the same author); by Hans Joachim Müller,
<hi rend="i">Die Zeit</hi>, 30 November 1979; by Eberhard Straub, <hi rend="i">Frankfurter Allgemeine
Zeitung</hi>, 1 December 1979 [and, no doubt, in many other German newspapers].</p>
          <p>201 Gallant, Christine. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Assimilation of Chaos.</hi> Reviewed by Anne
K. Mellor, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi>, 78 (1979), 442-44.</p>
          <p>202 Garlick, Kenneth J., and Angus D. Macintyre, eds. <hi rend="i">The Diary of Joseph
Farington</hi>, vols. 1 and 2. Reviewed by Robert R. Wark, <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi>, 62 (1980), 495-96;
by Ellis K. Waterhouse, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>, n.s., 27 (1980), 451-52. Vols. 5 and 6: Reviewed
by L. H., <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 122 (1980), 353.</p>
          <p>203 Godfrey, Richard T. <hi rend="i">Printmaking in Britain.</hi> Reviewed by Judy Egerton, 
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 122 (1980), 133; and by Andrew Wilton, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 102-04.</p>
          <p>204 Gillham, D. G. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by Pamela Dembo, 
<hi rend="i">Unisa</hi> [University of South Africa] <hi rend="i">English Studies</hi>, 11 (1973), 56-58.</p>
          <p>205 Harrison, J. C. F. <hi rend="i">The Second Coming, Popular Millenarianism 1780-1850.</hi>
Reviewed by Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 104-05.</p>
          <p>206 Hartman, Jørgen Birkedahl. <hi rend="i">Antike Motive bei Thorvaldsen.</hi> Reviewed by
Nicholas Penny, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 123 (1981), 41.</p>
          <p>207 Hofmann, Werner, ed. <hi rend="i">Goya: Das Zeitalter der Revolutionen 1789-1830.</hi> [exhb.
cat.] Reviewed by Nigel Glendinning, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 123 (1981), 54-57; and by Ekkehard
Mai, <hi rend="i">Pantheon</hi>, 39 (1981), 9-11.</p>
          <p>208 Jackson, Wallace. <hi rend="i">The Probable and the Marvelous: Blake, Wordsworth, and the
Eighteenth-Century Critical Tradition.</hi> Reviewed by Hoyt Trowbridge, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 143-45; by Jacques Blondel, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi>, 33 (1980), 215; by
William Edinger, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi>, 78 (1980), 189-91; by Joseph A. Wittreich, Jr., 
<hi rend="i">Modern Language Quarterly</hi>, 40 (1979), 312-317; by P. M. S. Dawson, <hi rend="i">Review of
English Studies</hi>, n. s. 31 (1980), 112-13; and by Stuart M. Tave, in <hi rend="i">The Yearbook of English
Studies</hi> [“Literature and Its Audience,” II] (London: Modern Humanities Research Association, 1981),
pp. 290-93.</p>
          <p>209 James, David E. <hi rend="i">Written Within and Without: A Study of Blake’s Milton.</hi>
Reviewed by Désirée Hirst, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi>, n.s. 31 (1980), 475-77.</p>
          <p>210 Johnson, Mary Lynn, and John E. Grant, eds. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Poetry and Designs.</hi>
Reviewed by Michael Fischer, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 215-16.</p>
          <p>211 King-Hele, Desmond. <hi rend="i">Doctor of Revolution: The Life and Genius of Erasmus
Darwin.</hi> Reviewed by Graham Cullum, <hi rend="i">AUMLA</hi>, 51 (1979), 95-97.</p>
          <p>212 Kroeber, Karl, and William Walling, eds. <hi rend="i">Images of Romanticism: Verbal and
Visual Affinities.</hi> Reviewed by Jacques Blondel, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi>, 33 (1980), 85-86; by
Kenneth Garlick, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>, n.s. 27 (1980), 452-453; by W. J. T. Mitchell, 
<hi rend="i">Criticism</hi>, 21 (1979), 376-79; by Raymond L. Wilson, <hi rend="i">Journal of Aesthetics and Art
Criticism</hi>, 38 (1979), 219.</p>
          <p>213 Lentricchia, Frank. <hi rend="i">After the New Criticism.</hi> Reviewed by Nelson Hilton, 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 212-14.</p>
          <p>214 Lindsay, Jack. <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Life and Work.</hi> Reviewed by Bo Ossian
Lindberg, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 164-74.</p>
          <p>215 Mitchell, W. J. T. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art.</hi> Reviewed by Elaine Kreizman,
<hi rend="i">Modern Language Notes</hi>, 94 (1979), 1250-57.</p>
          <p>216 Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by
<pb id="p15-92" n="92"/>
Anne K. Mellor, <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 18 (1979), 155-57.</p>
          <p>217 Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> 1978 (German edition). Reviewed by Victor
H. Elbern, <hi rend="i">Das Münster</hi>, 32 (1979), 349-50.</p>
          <p>218 Phillips, Michael C., ed. <hi rend="i">Interpreting Blake.</hi> Reviewed by David Simpson,
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 121-127; Zachary Leader, <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi>, 19 (1980), 419-33; Edward Larrissy, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>, n.s. 27 (1980),
450-51; Désirée Hirst, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi>, n.s. 31 (1980), 475-77; and by Pamela
Dembo Van Schaik, <hi rend="i">Unisa</hi> [University of South Africa] <hi rend="i">English Studies</hi>, 18
(1980), 26.</p>
          <p>219 Quilligan, Maureen. <hi rend="i">The Language of Allegory: Defining the Genre.</hi> Reviewed
by Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 135-37.</p>
          <p>220 Raine, Kathleen J. <hi rend="i">Blake and Antiquity.</hi> Reviewed by L. M. Finlay, 
<hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>, n.s., 27 (1980), 251-52.</p>
          <p>221 Schiff, Gert. <hi rend="i">Johann Heinrich Füssli 1741-1825.</hi> Reviewed by D. H.
Weinglass, <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi>, 62 (1980), 665-69.</p>
          <p>222 Schwinning, Heiner. <hi rend="i">Dichtung und Radikalismus in der Epoche 1780-1806: Studien
zu Blake, Wordsworth und Burns.</hi> Reviewed by Horst Höhne, <hi rend="i">Zeitschrift für Anglistik und
Amerikanistik</hi>, 28 (1980), 364-66.</p>
          <p>223 Stuart, Simon. <hi rend="i">New Phoenix Wings: Reparation in Literature.</hi> Reviewed by
Thomas R. Frosch, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 224-28; and by Pamela Dembo Van
Schaik, <hi rend="i">Unisa</hi> [University of South Africa] <hi rend="i">English Studies</hi>, 18 (1980),
57.</p>
          <p>224 Todd, Janet M., ed. <hi rend="i">A Wollstonecraft Anthology.</hi> Reviewed by Alicia
Ostriker, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 129-31.</p>
          <p>225 Tyson, Gerald P. <hi rend="i">Joseph Johnson: A Liberal Publisher.</hi> Reviewed by G. E.
Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 145-47; and by James H. Averill,
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 20 (1981), 129-31.</p>
          <p>226 Vaughan, William. <hi rend="i">German Romanticism and English Art.</hi> Reviewed by Leonee
Ormond, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 122 (1980), 776.</p>
          <p>227 Weiskel, Thomas. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Sublime.</hi> Reviewed by Stuart S. Peterfreund,
<hi rend="i">Comparative Literature</hi>, 32 (1980), 221-24; and by Richard Gravil, <hi rend="i">Modern
Language Review</hi>, 74 (1979), 664-66.</p>
          <p>228 Wilkie, Brian, and Mary Lynn Johnson. <hi rend="i">Blake’s “Four Zoas”: The Design of a
Dream.</hi> Reviewed by John D. Kilgore, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Quarterly</hi>, 40 (1979), 309-312; by
Zachary Leader, <hi rend="i">Essays in Criticism</hi>, 30 (1980), 243-47; and by Victoria Myers, 
<hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi>, 58 (1979), 245-47.</p>
          <p>229 Wilson, Mona. <hi rend="i">The Life of William Blake</hi>, ed. Sir Geoffrey Keynes, 3rd ed.
Reviewed by Pamela Dembo, <hi rend="i">Unisa</hi> [University of South Africa] <hi rend="i">English
Studies</hi>, 10 (1972), 82.</p>
          <p>230 Wilton, Andrew. <hi rend="i">British Watercolours 1750-1850.</hi> Reviewed by William
Vaughan, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 218-19.</p>
          <p>231 Wilton, Andrew. <hi rend="i">Constable’s “English Landscape Scenery.”</hi> Reviewed by
Ann Bermingham Miller, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1981), 128-29.</p>
          <p>232 Wittreich, Joseph A., Jr. <hi rend="i">Angel of Apocalypse: Blake’s Idea of Milton.</hi>
Reviewed by H. B. de Groot, <hi rend="i">English Studies</hi>, 60 (1979), 670-72.</p>
          <p>233 Wittreich, Joseph Anthony, Jr. <hi rend="i">Visionary Poetics: Milton’s Tradition and His
Legacy.</hi> Reviewed by Leonard Trawick, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 100-02;
by Archie Burnett, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>, n.s. 27 (1980), 368-69; by William E. Cain, 
<hi rend="i">Criticism</hi>, 21 (1979), 366-68; by Don Norford, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Quarterly</hi>, 40
(1979), 292-306; and in <hi rend="i">Virginia Quarterly Review</hi>, 56 (1980), 56.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">INDEX TO AUTHORS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Abrams, Ann Uhry, 149</p>
          <p>Ackland, Michael, 14</p>
          <p>Adams, Hazard, 15</p>
          <p>Alberts, Robert C., 150</p>
          <p>Albrecht, Herbert, 187</p>
          <p>Alexander, David, 8</p>
          <p>Ansari, Asloob A., 16</p>
          <p>Auden, Wystan Hugh, 151</p>
          <p>Austin, Deborah, 17</p>
          <p>Averill, James H., 225</p>
          <p>BaHan, Maung, 18, 19</p>
          <p>Bain, Iain, 20</p>
          <p>Baine, Rodney M., 21</p>
          <p>Bateson, F. W., 22</p>
          <p>Beaucamp, Edouard, 187</p>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr., 23, 24, 25, 145, 146, 184, 185, 188, 225</p>
          <p>Bergmann, Elizabeth Wagner, 26</p>
          <p>Bindman, David, 27, 186, 187, 188, 198</p>
          <p>Blondel, Jacques, 2, 208, 212</p>
          <p>Blunt, Anthony F., 28</p>
          <p>Bode, Ursula, 187</p>
          <p>Bogan, Jim, 29</p>
          <p>Borgmeier, Raimund, 3</p>
          <p>Brenken, Erika, 187</p>
          <p>Briganti, Giuliano, 189</p>
          <p>Brisman, Leslie, 190</p>
          <p>Bronowski, Jacob, 30, 191</p>
          <p>Bruce, Harold L., 31</p>
          <p>Burdett, Osbert, 32</p>
          <p>Burnett, Archie, 233</p>
          <p>Butlin, Martin, 192</p>
          <p>Buxton, John, 33</p>
          <p>Byrd, Max, 152</p>
          <p>Byron, Arthur, 153</p>
          <p>Campbell, Anne, 132</p>
          <p>Carey, Frances A., 193</p>
          <p>Carr, Gerald L., 154</p>
          <p>Carr, Stephen Leo, 34</p>
          <p>Cavina, Anna Ottani, 189</p>
          <p>Chambers, David, 20</p>
          <p>Chesterton, Gilbert K., 35</p>
          <p>Conner, Frederick W., 195</p>
          <p>Cooper, Andrew M., 36</p>
          <p>Cox, Stephen D., 37</p>
          <p>Crehan, Stewart, 38</p>
          <p>Crichton, Fenella, 192</p>
          <p>Crombie, Theodore, 192</p>
          <p>Cubbon, A. M., 143</p>
          <p>Cullum, Graham, 211</p>
          <p>Curran, Stuart, 184, 197</p>
          <p>Damon, S. Foster, 194</p>
          <p>Damrosch, Leopold, Jr., 39</p>
          <p>Davis, Patricia Elizabeth, 40</p>
          <p>Dawson, P. M. S., 118, 208</p>
          <p>Deck, Raymond H., 41</p>
          <p>Dembo, Pamela, 42, 204, 229 (<hi rend="i">see also</hi> Pamela Dembo Van Schaik)</p>
          <p>Denham, Robert D., 155, 195</p>
          <p>Dickinson, Kate L., 43</p>
          <p>Dieterich, Barbara, 187</p>
          <p>Dilworth, Thomas, 44</p>
          <p>Dobai, Johannes, 45</p>
          <p>Dodd, Phillip, 9</p>
          <p>Dry, Graham, 200</p>
          <p>Dörrbecker, Detlef W., 12</p>
          <p>Dunbar, Pamela, 46</p>
          <p>Easson, Kay Parkhurst, 197</p>
          <p>Easson, Roger R., 197</p>
          <p>Eaves, Morris, 47, 48, 194</p>
          <p>Eddy, Linda R., 121</p>
          <p>Edinger, William, 208</p>
          <p>Edwards, Gavin, 49</p>
          <p>Egerton, Judy, 186, 203</p>
          <p>Einem, Herbert von, 196</p>
          <p>Elbern, Victor H., 217</p>
          <p>El-Hage, George Nicolas, 50</p>
          <p>Engel, Peter, 187</p>
          <p>Engelhard, Günter, 187</p>
          <p>Eppendorf, Uwe, 187</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V., 4, 51</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N., 8, 52, 53, 54, 198, 199</p>
          <p>Fairchild, B. H., Jr., 55, 56</p>
          <p>Farnsworth, Rodney, 156</p>
          <p>Faulkner, Peter, 157</p>
          <p>Feingold, Richard, 119</p>
          <p>Field, Richard S., 158</p>
          <p>Finholt, Richard, 159</p>
          <p>Finlay, L. M., 220</p>
          <p>Finley, Gerald, 160</p>
          <p>Fischer, Michael, 210</p>
          <p>Fishman, Sylvia Barack, 57</p>
          <p>Fiske, Irving, 58</p>
          <p>Flaxman, Vivien, 122</p>
          <p>Flemming, Hans Theodor, 187</p>
          <p>Fox, Jeffrey Reid, 147</p>
          <p>Frosch, Thomas R., 223</p>
          <p>Frye, Roland Mushat, 161</p>
          <p>Frykman, Erik, 7</p>
          <p>Gage, John, 200</p>
          <p>Gallant, Christine, 201</p>
          <p>Garlick, Kenneth J., 125, 162, 202, 212</p>
          <p>Gaska, Rolf, 187</p>
          <p>Gaunt, William, 59</p>
          <p>George, Diana Hume, 60, 61</p>
          <p>Gettings, Fred, 163</p>
          <p>Gillham, D. G., 204</p>
          <p>Glazer, Myra, 62 (<hi rend="i">see also</hi> Myra Glazer Schotz)</p>
          <p>Gleckner, Robert F., 63, 64</p>
          <p>Glendinning, Nigel, 207</p>
          <p>Gmuca, Jacqueline Laura, 65</p>
          <p>Godfrey, Richard T., 8, 203</p>
          <pb id="p15-93" n="93"/>
          <p>Graham, John, 141</p>
          <p>Grant, John E., 4, 194, 210</p>
          <p>Gravil, Richard, 227</p>
          <p>Groot, H. B. de, 232</p>
          <p>Hagstrum, Jean H., 66</p>
          <p>Harrison, J. C. F., 205</p>
          <p>Hartlaub, Geno, 187</p>
          <p>Hartman, Jørgen Birkedahl, 206</p>
          <p>Hassler, Donald M., 120</p>
          <p>Hibbard, David Otis, 67</p>
          <p>Higonnet, Margaret R., 164</p>
          <p>Hilton, Nelson, 68, 69, 213, 219</p>
          <p>Hirst, Désirée, 185, 209, 218</p>
          <p>Hock, Erich, 126</p>
          <p>Hodgart, Patricia, 70</p>
          <p>Hoeveler, Diane Long, 71</p>
          <p>Hoffmann, Paul Theodor, 187</p>
          <p>Hofmann, Werner, 10, 123, 207</p>
          <p>Höhne, Horst, 222</p>
          <p>Hutton, Richard W., 171</p>
          <p>Irwin, David, 124</p>
          <p>Jackson, Wallace, 208</p>
          <p>James, David E., 209</p>
          <p>Johnson, Mary Lynn, 210, 228</p>
          <p>Joll, Evelyn, 142</p>
          <p>Keynes, Sir Geoffrey L., 5, 229</p>
          <p>Kilgore, John D., 228</p>
          <p>King-Hele, Desmond, 211</p>
          <p>Kircher, Gerda Franziska, 165</p>
          <p>Klonsky, Milton, 6</p>
          <p>Kreizman, Elaine, 215</p>
          <p>Kroeber, Karl, 212</p>
          <p>La Belle, Jenijoy, 73</p>
          <p>Lambourne, Lionel, 11</p>
          <p>Lane, Lauriat, Jr., 155</p>
          <p>Lange, Thomas V., 54, 72</p>
          <p>Lankheit, Klaus, 166</p>
          <p>Larrissy, Edward, 218</p>
          <p>Larsson, Roger Barnett, 167</p>
          <p>Leader, Zachary, 199, 218, 228</p>
          <p>Lefebvre, Mark Stephen, 74</p>
          <p>Leisi, Ernst, 127</p>
          <p>Lentricchia, Frank, 213</p>
          <p>Levinson, Marjorie, 75</p>
          <p>Levitt, Annette S., 76</p>
          <p>Leyris, Pierre, 2</p>
          <p>Lincoln, Andrew, 9</p>
          <p>Lindberg, Bo Ossian, 214</p>
          <p>Lindsay, Jack, 214</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond, 77</p>
          <p>Locke, Don, 168</p>
          <p>Lord, Catherine, 191</p>
          <p>Lowenstein, Vivien, 192</p>
          <p>MacDonald, Greville, 78</p>
          <p>Macintyre, Angus D., 162, 202</p>
          <p>Maeda, Yoshihiko, 79, 80</p>
          <p>Mai, Ekkehard, 207</p>
          <p>Malmqvist, Göran, 7, 81</p>
          <p>Mankowitz, Wolf, 169</p>
          <p>Mann, Paul Jay, 82</p>
          <p>Mason, Michael, 46, 53</p>
          <p>Mayoux, Jean-Jacques, 185</p>
          <p>Mazars, Pierre, 187</p>
          <p>McClellan, Jane, 83</p>
          <p>McClenahan, Catherine Louise, 84.</p>
          <p>McCune, Marjorie W., 17, 22</p>
          <p>Mellor, Anne K., 170, 201, 216</p>
          <p>Miller, Ann Bermingham, 231</p>
          <p>Minnick, Thomas L., 12</p>
          <p>Mitchell, W. J. T., 199, 212, 215</p>
          <p>Morton, Arthur L., 85</p>
          <p>Muller, Hans Joachim, 200</p>
          <p>Muratova, Xenia, 193</p>
          <p>Muschg, Walter, 128</p>
          <p>Myers, Victoria, 228</p>
          <p>Nelke, Laura, 171</p>
          <p>Netterville, Harvey Eli, 172</p>
          <p>Neve, Christopher, 192</p>
          <p>Norford, Don, 233</p>
          <p>Odell, D. W., 148</p>
          <p>Orbison, Tucker, 17, 22</p>
          <p>Ormond, Leonee, 226</p>
          <p>Ostriker, Alicia, 224</p>
          <p>Pacey, Philip, 173</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D., 86, 174, 205, 216, 217</p>
          <p>Parraux, Andre, 152</p>
          <p>Paschall, Douglas, 175</p>
          <p>Pearce, Donald, 199</p>
          <p>Pease, Donald, 87</p>
          <p>Pechey, Graham, 88</p>
          <p>Penny, Nicholas, 206</p>
          <p>Peterfreund, Stuart, 190, 227</p>
          <p>Phillips, Michael, 218</p>
          <p>Phillips, Tom, 6</p>
          <p>Pierce, Hazel, 89</p>
          <p>Piorkowski, Joan Lucille, 138</p>
          <p>Pressly, Nancy, 129</p>
          <p>Preston, Kerrison, 90</p>
          <p>Price, Steve, 91</p>
          <p>Punter, David, 92</p>
          <p>Quadri Iovine, Marcella, 93</p>
          <p>Quilligan, Maureen, 219</p>
          <p>Raine, Kathleen J., 220</p>
          <p>Ravenhall, Mary Dennis, 130</p>
          <p>Read, Dennis M., 94, 95</p>
          <p>Redmond, James, 9</p>
          <p>Redpath, Theodore, 70</p>
          <p>Reiman, Donald H., 133, 134, 135, 136, 137</p>
          <p>Reisner, Mary E., 96</p>
          <p>Riechert, Renate, 187</p>
          <p>Roe, Albert S., 97</p>
          <p>Rose, Edward J., 4, 98, 99</p>
          <p>Rosenblum, Joseph, 139</p>
          <p>Rozenberg, Paul, 176</p>
          <p>Rudd, Margaret E., 100</p>
          <p>Rudnick, Hans-Heinrich, 1</p>
          <p>Rump, Gerhard Charles, 45</p>
          <p>Sanzo, Eileen, 101</p>
          <p>Schiff, Gert, 221</p>
          <p><corr type="emend">Schleifer,</corr> Ronald, 102</p>
          <p>Schmidt, Doris, 187</p>
          <p>Schotz, Myra Glazer, 103 (<hi rend="i">see also</hi> Myra Glazer)</p>
          <p>Schütte, Gisela, 187</p>
          <p>Schwinning, Heiner, 222</p>
          <p>Schyle, Joachim, 187</p>
          <p>Simpson, David, 218</p>
          <p>Soupault, Philippe, 104</p>
          <p>Spivey, Ted R., 177</p>
          <p>Stafford, Barbara Maria, 178</p>
          <p>Starobinski, Jean, 131, 179</p>
          <p>Steadman, John, 161</p>
          <p>Stempel, Daniel, 105</p>
          <p>Stockard, Olivia Tate, 180</p>
          <p>Storch, Margaret, 106</p>
          <p>Straub, Eberhard, 200</p>
          <p>Strickland, Edward, 107</p>
          <p>Stuart, Simon, 223</p>
          <p>Tannenbaum, Leslie W., 108</p>
          <p>Tave, Stuart M., 208</p>
          <p>Taylor, Ronald Clayton, 109</p>
          <p>Thayer, Terence K., 140</p>
          <p><corr type="emend">Thiele-Dohrmann, Klaus,</corr> 187</p>
          <p>Thorpe, James, 110</p>
          <p>Todd, Janet M., 224</p>
          <p>Todd, Ruthven, 111</p>
          <p>Tolley, Michael J., 4</p>
          <p>Trawick, Leonard, 233</p>
          <p>Trowbridge, Hoyt, 208</p>
          <p>Tyson, Gerald P., 225</p>
          <p>Van Schaik, Pamela Dembo, 218, 223 (<hi rend="i">see also</hi> Pamela Dembo)</p>
          <p>Vaughan, Frank Andrew, 112</p>
          <p>Vaughan, William, 192, 196, 226, 230</p>
          <p>Waggoner, Hyatt H., 113</p>
          <p>Wagner, Herbert H., 187</p>
          <p>Wagner, Monika, 181</p>
          <p>Walling, William, 212</p>
          <p>Wark, Robert R., 202</p>
          <p>Warner, Nicholas O., 114</p>
          <p>Watarai, Kazumitsu, 12</p>
          <p>Waterhouse, Ellis K., 202</p>
          <p>Watson, J. R., 9</p>
          <p>Weinglass, D. H., 221</p>
          <p>Weiskel, Thomas, 227</p>
          <p>Welburn, Andrew J., 115</p>
          <p>Welch, Dennis M., 47, 48, 116</p>
          <p>Whittingham, Shelby, 142</p>
          <p>Wilkie, Brian, 228</p>
          <p>Wilson, Mona, 229</p>
          <p>Wilson, Raymond, 212</p>
          <p>Wilton, Andrew, 203, 230, 231</p>
          <p>Winkel, A. zum, 187</p>
          <p>Withim, Philip M., 17, 22</p>
          <p>Wittreich, Joseph A., Jr., 208, 232, 233</p>
          <p>Woodman, Ross G., 182</p>
          <p>Wright, Thomas, 117</p>
          <p>Young, Howard T., 183</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
