<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.2.harding</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Mike Westbrook, Bright As Fire, a recording  of jazz settings of Blake</title>
        <author n="Harding">Anthony J. Harding</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>James Warwick</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Peter Davidson</name>
              <name>Detlef Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Anthony J. Harding</name>
              <name>David Sten Herrstrom</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>James A. Winn</name>
              <name>Michael C. Young</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-2-0009">
        <pb id="p15-97" n="97"/>
        <div2>
          <figure n="WestbrookBlake.15.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="297">
          	<figTranscr>THE WESTBROOK<lb/>
          	BLAKE<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	BRIGHT AS FIRE<lb/>
          	Settings of William Blake<lb/>
          	MIKE WESTBROOK<lb/>
          	Phil Minton  Kate Westbrook<lb/>
          	Alan Wakeman  Chris Biscoe<lb/>
          	Dave Barry</figTranscr>
          </figure>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Mike Westbrook. <hi rend="b">Bright As Fire</hi>, a recording of jazz settings
of Blake. London: Original Records. Released and distributed in the U.S.A. and Canada by Europa Records,
Orlando, Florida. $8.98.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">Anthony J. </hi><name><hi rend="b">Harding</hi></name>.</docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Blake died singing: but there have been few attempts to celebrate his genius musically, by
comparison with the large number of illustrated commentaries and facsimile editions now available. Mike
Westbrook’s <hi rend="i">Bright as Fire</hi> is a new album of jazz settings of Blake’s poetry, and it
earns its title with Blakean vigor and a rare Blakean sense of satirical fun.</p>
          <p>The first two tracks each open with a piano solo, hymnlike and slightly portentous in the manner
of Alan Price, but the lines from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (Plate 27:19-34, 103-06, and Plate 86:1-10) are
delivered by Phil Minton with ecstatic conviction. Despite the inevitable children’s choir, the Blake we
hear is no grade-school saint but a full-blooded proletarian artist. Alan Sinclair’s tuba in “The fields
from Islington to Marybone” makes Track 1 rather bass-heavy, but “I see thy Form” is good, with an
inspired trumpet entry at “From thy white shoulders.”</p>
          <p>Track 3, a powerful setting of “London,” opens with ghastly screams on saxophone and
clarinet. A lonely lament on saxophone (which is used throughout rather as Vaughan Williams used it in 
<hi rend="i">Job: A Masque for Dancing</hi>, suggesting the whining hypocrisy of Job’s comforters) then
introduces the song itself, delivered in tones of bitter despair by Kate Westbrook, whose voice has the
riveting huskiness of Lotte Lenya’s—it is worth noting that Mike Westbrook’s band came to Blake by way
of Brecht and Kurt Weill. Further lamentations on saxophone, gradually gibbering into incoherence, conclude
the track, the most original on the album. After the intensity of “London,” “A Poison Tree” is played
for sheer fun as a diabolic tango. Alan Wakeman’s tenor sax growls menacingly; Kate Westbrook’s hoydenish
diction is just right for the exaggerated malice of this poem. The tango rhythm accelerates to a contemptuous
closing flourish.</p>
          <p>“Holy Thursday” (the one from <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>) is the longest track on the
album. The poem itself is sung to a simple accompaniment of piano and cello, but there is a long and highly
inventive jazz epilogue. Clarinet, bass and drums are joined by saxophones and tenor horn, playing lamenting,
wailing chords, then the trumpet stutters mockingly, caricaturing the smug “philanthropy” affected by the
“wise guardians of the poor.” Chris Biscoe’s saxophone imitates a pathetic, leaden-footed dance to the
choppy accompaniment of cello and bass.</p>
          <p>This mood of hopelessness is dispelled by the opening of the last setting, based on an extract
from <hi rend="i">America</hi> and one from <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> It begins with a Hebraic-sounding
summons on tenor horn; Phil Minton sings, unaccompanied for the first four lines, “Let the slave, grinding
at the mill, run out into the street . . . .” His reassuringly cockney voice is joined (at “his chains are
loose”) by the band, which crescendoes to a startling and effective key-change at “The Sun has left his
blackness.” The great affirmation, “For everything that lives is holy,” is the climax of this last
track; but before the final fade-out there is an impassioned reading (by Mike Westbrook) of “What is the
price of Experience?” from <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, with ostinato accompaniment by piano, horn and
saxophones.</p>
          <pb id="p15-98" n="98"/>
          <p>Adrian Mitchell chose the texts, and his emphasis on <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> and the
prophetic books reflects what is usually thought of as modern taste in Blake. The music was originally
composed at Adrian Mitchell’s request for his <hi rend="i">Tyger</hi> (1971), “a stage show in celebration
of the life and works of William Blake,” and Mitchell writes that what had impressed him about Mike
Westbrook’s music was its combination of “earthiness and fire.” These qualities, with much bold and
inventive musicianship, are strongly apparent in this valuable addition to Blake discography.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
