<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.2.butlin</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">A Newly Discovered Watermark and a Visionary’s Way with His Dates</title>
        <author n="Butlin">Martin Butlin</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>James Warwick</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Peter Davidson</name>
              <name>Detlef Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Anthony J. Harding</name>
              <name>David Sten Herrstrom</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>James A. Winn</name>
              <name>Michael C. Young</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
	<pb id="p15-101" n="101"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-2-0010">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">A NEWLY DISCOVERED WATERMARK AND A<gap type="emend"/> 
              VISIONARY’S WAY WITH HIS DATES</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Martin</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Butlin</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Recent conservation treatment at the Tate Gallery has revealed that the Gallery’s large color
print of “Newton,” signed and dated by Blake in his own hand “1795 WB inv [in monogram]”, is
watermarked “JWhatman/1804”.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">1</ref> The
watermark, in the margin of the actual design, was only found when the fine canvas on which the print had been
mounted was removed.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">2</ref> Eight of the
other large color prints in the Tate Gallery, also from the collection of Thomas Butts, were similarly mounted
on canvas though “Pity” was lifted from its canvas preparatory to being lent to an exhibition in
1980.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">3</ref> It is expected that others will
be similarly treated in due course, when further watermarks may be discovered; “Hecate” is already known
to be watermarked “1794/JWhatman” but was not dated by Blake. <note id="n55"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Martin
Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>, 1981, I, 166-67 no. 306, repr. II, pl.
394 in color. All the large color prints, together with related drawings, are catalogued in Butlin, I, 156-77,
introd. and nos. 289-329, and repr. in vol. II.</note>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">2</hi> I am indebted to Kasia Szeleynski of the Tate Gallery’s conservation
department for informing me of this discovery and discussing it with me. An inscription on the back of the
print, previously covered by the canvas, reads “No. 22 Page 203”; this refers to William Rossetti’s
listing in the 1863 edition of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, which means that the
paper must have been mounted on the canvas after that date.</note>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Butlin 310; exh. <hi rend="i">The Painterly Print</hi>, Metropolitan
Museum, New York, and Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, October 1980-March 1981 (17, repr.). The exhibition also
included the small color-printed try-out in the British Museum (Butlin 313; 16, repr.) and the version in the
Metropolitan Museum (Butlin 311; 18, repr. in color); the version in the Yale Center (Butlin 312) was repr. as
fig. 50.</note></p>
          <p>The first documentary record of any of the twelve designs is the inclusion of eight in an account
between Blake and Thomas Butts of 3 March 1806, apparently as having been delivered, four at a time, on 5 July
and 7 September 1805; “Newton” was apparently delivered on the latter date. All the works delivered in
1805 are in fact dated “1795”, with the possible exception of the copy of “Christ Appearing to the
Apostles” now in the Yale University Art Gallery, the only print from these eight not in the Tate Gallery.
Nine prints from the Butts collection (seven of those listed in the account, including “Newton,” together
with two titles not listed in any account) were sold by Butts’s grandson, Captain F. J. Butts, to W. Graham
Robertson in 1905 or 1906 and were presented by him to the Tate Gallery in 1939.</p>
          <p>A number of cases of what may be called conceptual, mythical or even wishful pre-datings by Blake
are already known. There are several examples of the later state of an engraving bearing the date of the first
state.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">4</ref> It is also highly likely that
the version of “The Penance of Jane Shore” that Blake claimed in the catalogue of his exhibition in 1809
had been “done above Thirty Years ago” was not the small, immature example from his series of watercolors
of subjects from English history now in a British private collection—that version is easily reconcilable
with a date of c. 1779—but the larger, more finished and more accomplished version in the Tate Gallery that
seems to date from about 1793.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">5</ref> But
what, in the case of this print of “Newton,” is the original to which the date “1795” applies? Many
people, including myself, have supposed that Blake printed more than one example of each color print at one
time, by a sort of monotype process, finishing each print in pen and watercolor on demand at a later
date.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">6</ref> This would mean that the two
known versions of “Newton,” like the (up to three) known versions of the other prints in the series,
<pb id="p15-102" n="102"/>
would both have been printed in 1795 and that this copy of “Newton” would have been finished in 1805 for
delivery to Thomas Butts; this would of course have been reconcilable with a date, for the finishing only, of
1804 or later. But in no way can the first printing have been done in 1795 on paper watermarked 1804. It is
known that paper manufacturers occasionally post-dated their watermarks by a year or so; a watercolor by
Joshua Cristall in the Tate Gallery, on paper watermarked 1808, is signed and dated “J. Cristall 1807”,
apparently when the work was executed, in a space carefully left uncolored.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">7</ref> But for a manufacturer to post-date his paper by as much as
nine years is inconceivable, and in fact the previous batch of Whatman paper was dated 1794, only a year
before the date given by Blake with his signature.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62"
type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">4</hi> For example, “Joseph of Arimathea among the Rocks of Albion,”
“Albion Rose,” “Job” and “Ezekiel”; see Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake,
Printmaker</hi>, 1980, pp. 29, 64-67, 70, 178-86, 257.</note>
	<note id="n59"><hi rend="s">5</hi> See Butlin, I, 23-24 nos. 67 and 69.</note>
	<note id="n60"><hi rend="s">6</hi> The fullest discussion of the technique of the large color prints is in
Essick, pp. 125-35.</note>
	<note id="n61"><hi rend="s">7</hi> See <hi rend="i">The Tate Gallery 1972-4</hi>, 1975, p. 52, repr., where
the contrary is argued.</note>
	<note id="n62"><hi rend="s">8</hi> See the tables of watermarks in Butlin, I, 627, and G. E. Bentley, Jr.,
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, 1977, p. 72; until the discovery of the watermark on the Tate Gallery’s
“Newton” no “JWhatman/1804” watermarks were known on any of the works included in my catalogue. For
Whatman paper see also Essick, p. 105.</note></p>
          <p>The Butts prints are not only the first series for which there is any evidence; they also seem to
have been the first set to have been sold to a patron. Blake offered another set of twelve prints to Dawson
Turner in a letter of 9 June 1818 but these, and other examples, seem to have remained unsold at his death.
One possibility could be that Blake printed one set in 1795 but that when he came to do the set for Butts he
chose not to finish his existing prints but to start again from the beginning with new impressions. Frederick
Tatham, who was not born until 1805, stated that Blake re-painted “his outline on the millboard when he
wanted to take another print.” But to re-do the color printing after a period of nine years, with the
original thick, gummy colors all dried up on whatever form of plate Blake used, whether millboard (Tatham
stated that Blake used “a common thick millboard”) or metal, would seem to be a very perverse way of
setting about things. If in fact the prints were color printed from metal plates it is possible that an
outline was etched onto the plate in 1795 but that nothing else was done at that date. This is supported by
the appearance of “God Judging Adam” in which Blake seems first to have printed a monochrome outline
before overprinting it with his usual tacky color-printing medium. Or, in view of the fact that there are
certain preliminary drawings, including one for the “Newton,” and even a small-scale preliminary color
print of “Pity,” perhaps it is to these that Blake’s 1795 date applies, meaning that at least he had the
idea and had made the first experiments in that year. Or, he may have actually begun printing the series of
twelve designs in 1795 with the whole scheme in his mind but not completed it until he was able to sell a
series to Butts in 1805. It is significant that three of the titles owned by Butts but not included in the
1805 accounts, “Satan Exulting over Eve,” “Pity” and “Hecate,” were signed in a different way from
the others, with the single word “Blake” actually incised into the pigments. The 1794 watermark of
“Hecate” allows for this work to have been executed in 1795, while “Pity” does not have a watermark;
it is difficult however to be certain about the copy of “Satan Exulting over Eve” now in the collection of
John Craxton, though no watermark is visible from the front of the work.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63" type="note">9</ref> Further explanations are no doubt possible. 
<note id="n63"><hi rend="s">9</hi> For a discussion of possible implications of the way in which the color prints
are signed, though not in fact of the group with the incised “Blake,” see my article “Cataloguing
William Blake” in Robert N. Essick and Donald Pearce, eds., <hi rend="i">Blake in his Time</hi>, 1978, pp.
84-85.</note></p>
          <figure n="but306.1.1.cpd" id="but306.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="737">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
            1795 WB</figTranscr>
            <head>“Newton,” color print finished in pen and watercolor, 46 × 60 cm.</head>
            <figDesc>Tate Gallery, London.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>Whatever the exact solution, both as to the techniques used by Blake and the stages in which he
applied each process, there are far wider implications in this new discovery. It has been generally assumed,
at least recently, that Blake’s use of color printing was confined largely to the years 1794, 1795 and
1796.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64" type="note">10</ref> This is based partly on the
evidence of the large color prints but also on that of the illuminated books and the designs from them that
were issued separately in color-printed versions. But it is now clear that Blake was still using color
printing in at least one print executed as late as 1804-05. This also has implications for the theory that a
revolution in Blake’s style took place as a result of his experiences during his stay at Felpham from 1800
to 1803, in which he came to concentrate far more on clear outlines and balanced forms than in his earlier
works. It is one thing to postulate a color print basically executed in 1795 and then more closely defined
with pen outlines and clear color washes on being sold to Thomas Butts in 1805; it is quite another to see
Blake re-using, as late as 1804-05, a technique the most dominant feature of which was its blotting and
blurring. <note id="n64"><hi rend="s">10</hi> See Essick, pp. 147-51.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p15-103" n="103" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
