<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.2.labelle</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake’s Insanity: An Unrecorded Early Reference</title>
        <author n="La Belle">Jenijoy La Belle</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1981</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <name>James Warwick</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Peter Davidson</name>
              <name>Detlef Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Anthony J. Harding</name>
              <name>David Sten Herrstrom</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>James A. Winn</name>
              <name>Michael C. Young</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1981"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
	<pb id="p15-100" n="100"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-2-0010">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">BLAKE’S INSANITY: AN UNRECORDED EARLY REFERENCE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Jenijoy</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">La Belle</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Published references to William Blake prior to the appearance of Alexander Gilchrist’s 
<hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi> in 1863 are uncommon, generally brief, all too often inaccurate—but still worthy
of notice as curious bits of Blakeana. G. E. Bentley, Jr., in his monumental <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>,
attempts to list “all works published before 1863 which refer to Blake at all, except catalogues,” as he
states in his Introduction.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">1</ref> A
previously unnoticed reference appears in Thomas John Gullick and John Timbs, <hi rend="i">Painting Popularly
Explained</hi>, first published in London in 1859 by “Kent and Co. (late Bogue), Fleet Street.” A two-page
overview of “The Rise of Modern Water-Colour Painting” appears towards the end of this 318-page discussion
of painting techniques. There (pp. 302-04), the authors note the early masters of the British school of
watercolorists, including Paul Sandby, John Cozens, and Thomas Girtin. The section concludes with the
following two sentences:
<q>
[Joseph Mallord William] Turner is even greater in water-colours than in oil; but several other eminent oil
painters have distinguished themselves also in water-colour painting. The following are some of the principal
deceased masters of this branch of art, viz., [William] Blake, and [Richard] Dadd (who both died insane),
[Thomas] Rowlandson (the caricaturist), [George Fennel] Robson, [George] Barrett, [John] Varley, Samuel Prout,
[Peter] Dewint, and Copley Fielding.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51"
type="note">2</ref></q>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977, p. 10. Selections from brief references to
Blake, 1831-62, are reprinted in Bentley, ed., <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Critical Heritage</hi> (London
and Boston: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1975), pp. 220-69.</note>
	<note id="n51"><hi rend="s">2</hi> P. 304. Blake’s name does not appear in the highly selective index.
Timbs later wrote a sketch of Blake’s life, based mostly on Gilchrist, in his <hi rend="i">English
Eccentrics and Eccentricities</hi> (London: Chatto and Windus, 1875), pp. 339-50.</note></p>
          <p>It is surprising to find Blake included in an 1859 list of “principal deceased masters” in
water-color; his appearance here suggests that Blake’s
<pb id="p15-101" n="101"/>
artistic reputation was being quietly resurrected shortly before the publication of Gilchrist’s biography.
But the most remarkable feature of the passage is the symmetry of its errors: Blake was dead, but did not die
insane; Dadd was insane, but did not die until 1886.</p>
          <p>Gullick and Timbs very probably lifted some of their misinformation from <hi rend="i">A Handbook
to the Water Colours, Drawings, and Engravings, in the</hi> [Manchester] <hi rend="i">Art Treasures
Exhibition, Being a Reprint of Critical Notices Originally Published in “The Manchester Guardian”</hi>
(London, 1857).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">3</ref> In this work, pp.
12-13, the anonymous author compares Blake and Dadd and asserts that “both were mad . . . 
[<hi rend="i">but</hi>] Blake’s fancies were lovely, rather than terrible.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">3</hi> First noted in connection with Blake in Suzanne R. Hoover, “Fifty
Additions to Blake Bibliography: Further Data for the Study of His Reputation in the Nineteenth Century,”
<hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 5 (Winter, 1971-72), 169. See also Bentley, ed., <hi rend="i">Blake: The
Critical Heritage</hi>, p. 258; Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 660 no. A563. The original
“Notices” in the <hi rend="i">Manchester Guardian</hi> have not been traced. On p. 297 of their book,
Gullick and Timbs refer to the <hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi> (different from the <hi rend="i">Handbook</hi>) of
the 1857 Manchester exhibition and on p. 303 they refer to the <hi rend="i">Handbook</hi>, the authorship of
which they attribute to “Mr. Tom Taylor.”</note>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">4</hi> P. 12; quoted from Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p.
660.</note></p>
          <p>The statement—premature by a mere twenty-seven years—that Dadd was deceased may have resulted
from a misreading of other published statements. The <hi rend="i">Art-Union</hi> of October 1843 took note of
Dadd’s insanity, his murder of his father in August 1843, and his subsequent confinement. The journal
apostrophizes the unfortunate man as follows: “The late Richard Dadd. Alas! . . . for, although the grave
has not actually closed over him, he must be classed among the dead.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">5</ref> Perhaps Gullick and Timbs misconstrued this (or some other)
elegy for Dadd’s psychological demise, and this prompted them to list him, along with Blake, among the
principal, insane, and deceased British masters of watercolor. <note id="n54"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Vol. 5, p.
267; quoted from Patricia Allderidge, <hi rend="i">The Late Richard Dadd</hi>, exhibition catalogue (London:
The Tate Gallery, 1974), p. 9. Allderidge notes the reference to Dadd in <hi rend="i">Painting Popularly
Explained</hi>, but does not record its authors or the reference to Blake.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
