<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.3.ferber</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Mars and the Planets Three in America</title>
        <author n="Ferber">Michael Ferber</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1981/1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981·82</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>George Hartley</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <resp>Typist</resp>
              <name>Denise Warren</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Greg Crossan</name>
              <name>Detlef Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Bo Ossian Lindberg</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Joseph S. Salemi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1981/1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
	<pb id="p15-136" n="136"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">MARS AND THE PLANETS THREE IN AMERICA</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Michael</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Ferber</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>We are still very far from understanding the passage about Mars in plate 5 of 
<hi rend="i">America</hi>, despite the recent proposal, put forth by Rodney M. and Mary R. Baine in 
<hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi>, 13 (1975), 14-18, that Swedenborg is behind it. I have been puzzling for
several years over the Swedenborg quotations they offer, but I cannot see their bearing, however interesting
they may be in themselves, on the meaning of the <hi rend="i">America</hi> passage. The idea that the spirits
of Mars are the best spirits, the notion that Mars represents a balance of intellect and emotions, and the
other odd Swedenborgian speculations seem at best only vaguely relevant and at worst quite contrary to the
tenor of the rest of the poem. They come up first against our inevitable association of Mars with warfare, an
association Blake gives no suggestion we should break. As the Baines admit, moreover, Swedenborg cannot
account for “the planets three.” Even, finally, if we somehow knew that Swedenborg’s <hi rend="i">Earths
in our Solar System</hi> were the “source,” we would still be faced with the problem, worse than the one
we had before, of how its meanings fit together with the rest of the poem.</p>
          <p>In any case, I have a few tentative suggestions about the passage. I cannot make it all cohere,
but the connections I offer are the sort of thing we ought to do to it; someone with a fresher eye will
doubtless recast these suggestions to make better sense of the passage.</p>
          <p>When the wrathful Prince of Albion arises dragon-like at midnight, he “flam’d red meteors”
(3:14-16); this alone would make him resemble the red planet with its terrible wandering comets (5:2-3). When
Albion’s Angel sees the terrible Orc rising over the Atlantic, Orc first seems a comet and then seems the
red planet Mars which once enclosed such terrible comets in its sphere. At that time “the planets three”
flew round the crimson disk. I take it that Blake is not distinguishing comets from planets, except for the
planet red itself; the terrible comets are “wandering,” after all, and “wanderer” is what
<pb id="p15-137" n="137"/>
“planet” means. To be enclosed in Mars’s sphere, as the comets are, and to fly round the disk, as the
three planets do, are the same thing, for “sphere” probably has something of its older cosmological
meaning as one of the concentric transparent globes around the earth; it can mean “orb” or “orbit” but
probably not “disk.” So we have the suggestion that Orc was once one of these three planets revolving
about Mars.</p>
          <p>But then the Sun becomes a problem. It too seems to have been orbiting Mars, either as one of the
three or, as I think, a fourth planet-comet, before it was “rent” from the red sphere. Two lines later a
voice comes forth and gives the great speech on plate 6 beginning “The morning comes.” Isn’t this speech
about the arrival of the sun from its orbit about Mars? True, the song the redeemed captives sing begins
“The Sun has left his blackness,” not “redness,” but from an earthly vantage the former age seemed
black, a dark age of Empire dominated by warfare, or Mars, which of course is only visible at night. Since Orc
presides over this dawn, we may associate him with the Sun, once of Mars’s sphere. Now he seems, to
Albion’s Angel or Prince, to be Mars, because he rises warlike against him, but it is the wrathful Prince
himself who is the original Mars. It is he who “burns in his nightly tent” before he rises at midnight
flaming the red meteors like comets (3:1, 3:14-16).</p>
          <p>When Orc the Sun (and son) leaves Mars the wrathful Prince, Orc presumably takes the three
planets with him, or threatens to. Who are they? Since Orc-America is wandering out of the British Empire, we
should look to see who else may be drawn into orbit around him. I think Blake tells us: it is “Ireland and
Scotland and Wales” (15:13), who made up the original Empire. (A less likely threesome is “France Spain
&amp; Italy” (16:16), but they seem to be little empires themselves.) The “burning winds” of
revolutionary fervor driven by Orc and the fierce Americans cause the Guardians of the three original colonies
to forsake their frontiers (abandon the original Empire) and “deform their ancient heavens” (15:11-15).
“Ancient heavens,” which brings back the astronomical theme, is a phrase we have met before, when the
frightened Angel of Albion addresses Orc: “Ah rebel form that rent the ancient / Heavens” (9:14-15). And
“rent” we have met once before this, when “the Sun was rent from thy red sphere.” The connections seem
clear enough. America is the new center, the new sun, for the satellite nations that once revolved around
warlike, imperial England, but in erupting out of England’s sphere of influence America has taken on the
features of its father, at least from the father’s point of view.</p>
          <p>We need resort to no arcane source to map things thus far, but a few reminders of the common
tradition may help fill in the map. The “Archetype of mighty Emperies” may be the ancient palace of
Ariston (10:8), but the prototype of mighty Emperies is certainly Rome, which worshipped Mars and waged almost
constant war. Rome even set its calendar by Mars, beginning each year on March first: “now the times are
return’d upon thee” (9:19). Of course Rome learned from Greece, and especially Troy, to follow after
“the detestable Gods of Priam” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 14:15); Mars, as Ares, took Priam’s side in the
Trojan War. In his first appearance in western literature, in fact, Ares arrives on the plain of Troy with
three companions about him, Phobos, Deimos, and Eris, or Fear, Terror, and Strife (<hi rend="i">Iliad</hi>
4.439-41). Britain, founded by a son of a royal Trojan who founded Rome, became, in John of Gaunt’s words,
“this seat of Mars” (<hi rend="i">Richard II</hi>, II, i, 41), and Gaunt should know, having fought beside
the Black Prince, whom Blake portrays in his <hi rend="i">King Edward the Third</hi> as insatiably
battle-hungry: “It is my sin to love the noise of war” (3:232).</p>
          <p>Whether the passage in <hi rend="i">America</hi> 5 can be brought into line with other
astronomical passages in Blake I am not sure. In cancelled plate b of <hi rend="i">America</hi> itself there
are some difficult lines about a comparable eruption, but they bring in the stars and the moon as well. The
cancelled lines seem less susceptible of a political reading than the Mars section, and may be about the
altering of perceptions when reason subjugates the stars and creates a theory of a heliocentric system
governed by laws of gravity. Whatever the lines mean, Blake did cancel them.</p>
          <p>I think Blake did not care very much about astronomy or astrology or cosmological speculations of
the Swedenborgian sort. All of his astronomical passages seem to be functions of his phenomenology of
consciousness or his political and historical myth. The Mars passage has an <hi rend="i">ad hoc</hi> character
that tempts one to seek a source, but that character is due to its nonce role as a political allegory.
Whatever the details of this allegory, the language of stars and planets has been the common vehicle since
ancient times of discourse about political events, as the phrase “sphere of influence” should doubly
remind us. In Blake’s day “revolution” still had more to do with “revolving” than with
“revolting,” and the vast wheels of blood over the Atlantic (4:6) may alert us to the cyclical paradigm
that governed most of Blake’s thinking about political change. The American colonists themselves were happy
to evoke ancient astronomical terms for their revolution. The “Novus Ordo Saeclorum” on the back of our
dollar bill hearkens to the theory of the <hi rend="i">apocatastasis</hi> or cosmic renewal in Virgil’s
Fourth Eclogue, and with each new state we add a new star to the blue firmament of our flag.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
