<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.3.lange</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">A Rediscovered Colored Copy of Young’s Night Thoughts</title>
        <author n="Lange">Thomas V. Lange</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1981/1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981·82</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>George Hartley</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <resp>Typist</resp>
              <name>Denise Warren</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Greg Crossan</name>
              <name>Detlef Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Bo Ossian Lindberg</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Joseph S. Salemi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1981/1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
	<pb id="p15-134" n="134"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">A REDISCOVERED COLORED COPY OF YOUNG’S NIGHT THOUGHTS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Thomas V.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Lange</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>In their exhaustive research, the editors of <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Designs for Edward
Young’s Night Thoughts</hi> (1980)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">1</ref>
were able to add four “new” copies to the two earlier censuses of colored copies of the engraved
work,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">2</ref> and they state, “At present
twenty-three coloured copies are believed to exist, all but one of which have recently been studied by one or
more of the editors of the present edition.” Somewhat later in their commentary they continue, “Still
untraced is the well-attested Gaisford-Macgeorge copy, called G in the Bentley census and last located in
1926.” The editors obscure this “well-attested” copy, since they choose to omit all mention of it from
their census of colored copies. The only physical description appears in footnote 81, some forty pages after
the census. <note id="n59"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake’s Designs for Edward Young’s
“Night Thoughts,”</hi> edited with commentary by John E. Grant, Edward J. Rose, Michael J. Tolley,
co-ordinating editor David V. Erdman (Oxford Univ. Press, 1980).</note>
	<note id="n60"><hi rend="s">2</hi> W. E. Moss, “The Coloured Copies of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 2 (1968), 19-23; G. E. Bentley, Jr., “A Census of
Coloured Copies of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797),” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 2
(1968), 41-45.</note></p>
          <p>While engaged in research quite unrelated to Blake for the Lutheran Church in America, I
discovered this untraced colored copy of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> in a disused closet, among the books
bequeathed to the Church by Mrs. William T. Tonner in 1971. Upon her death, a portion of Mrs. Tonner’s
distinguished Blake collection passed to the Lutheran Church, including one of the two recorded impressions of
the color-print “Newton” (Butlin 307), an early state of the copper engraving, “The Canterbury
Pilgrims,” and a drawing, “Moses striking the rock” (Butlin 445). The remainder of the Tonner Blake
collection was given to the Philadelphia Museum of Art, and was described by Martin Butlin in the Museum’s
<hi rend="i">Bulletin.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">3</ref> Hereafter
I will refer to the Gaisford-Macgeorge copy as the Tonner-Lutheran Church copy. 
<note id="n61"><hi rend="s">3</hi> “The Blake Collection of Mrs. William F. Tonner,” Philadelphia Museum of Art 
<hi rend="i">Bulletin</hi>, 67 (July-September 1972), 5-31.</note></p>
          <p>The purpose of this brief note is to describe this newly discovered copy of <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi>, and to correct and update the provenance information. The following entry follows the format
used by the editors of the recently published edition of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>:</p>
          <p>I-12A (Moss-Bentley G). White Death.</p>
          <p>Bound in three-quarter red-brown morocco over greenish-blue marbled paper by Riviere, marbled
end-papers. The spine is tooled in the style of Roger Payne. Top edge gilt, others uncut. Lacks the
Explanation of the Engravings, which is, however, supplied in 19th century type-facsimile. Watermarks on
twelve leaves. 16-¾ × 12-¾ inches. (42.5 × 32.8 cm.). Grotesque color on p. 10 (6E), p. 31 (18E), p. 35
(20E). No JC monogram.</p>
          <p>1) Acquired by Thomas Gaisford (1779-1855) of Offington, Worthing. He added his engraved
bookplate
            <pb id="p15-135" n="135"/>
<figure n="BB515.SecondNight.15.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="766" height="1000">
	<head>Engraved title-page to the second Night.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Lutheran Church in America.</figDesc>
</figure>
and the volume was sold with his library at Sotheby’s, 23 April 1890, lot 192, for £40.10.0 to Quaritch
for;</p>
          <p>2) Bernard Buchanan Macgeorge and listed in his privately-printed library catalogues of 1892 (p.
9—not listed as colored) and 1906 (p. 14—as colored); sold with his library at Sotheby’s, 1 July 1924,
lot 118, for £125 to Quaritch;</p>
          <p>3) Offered by Quaritch in their catalogue 388 (October 1924), item 326, and again in their
catalogue 401 (May 1926), item 218, for £175;</p>
          <p>4) Sold to Cortlandt F. Bishop, who added his red leather bookplate; sold at the Bishop sale at
American Art Association, Anderson Galleries (part III, 14-15 November 1938), to Charles Sessler for $325;</p>
          <p>5) Sold in December 1938 to Florence Foerderer Tonner for $357.50; she added her distinctive
bookplate and bequeathed the volume in 1971 to</p>
          <p>6) The Lutheran Church in America.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62"
type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n62"><hi rend="s">4</hi> I am grateful to Mr. Donald Trued, Lutheran Church in America (New York),
for permission to publish this note. Inquiries concerning this volume should be addressed to him at 231
Madison Avenue, New York, NY 10016.</note></p>
          <p>Certain details of the provenance and physical description do not exactly correspond to those
published by Bentley and Moss, neither of whom ever examined the actual volume. The most obvious of these
differences is the absence of the Explanation leaf. As late as the Bishop sale, and when the volume was sold
by Sessler to Mrs. Tonner, the accompanying bibliographical descriptions noted, “Laid in at the end is the
scarce leaf of ‘Explanation of the Engravings,’” and pencilled in an unidentified hand on the front
binder’s blank is the statement, “At the end is Blake’s explanation of the Engravings, often wanting.”
The leaf included in the Tonner-Lutheran Church copy is, however, a curious and apparently unrecorded
facsimile printed from type and loosely inserted in the volume, the source of which has not been
traced.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63" type="note">3</ref> The text of this leaf is a
column-for-column and page-for-page reprint of the original, is printed on both sides of the sheet (as the
original), but is in a much-reduced format: 11-1/4 × 8-5/8 inches. There are no stubs in the volume (other
than modern binder’s stubs) to suggest that the original leaf of Explanation was ever present. Nor are there
marks at any point to indicate where the facsimile leaf was “laid in at the end,” but modern stains from
pressure-sensitive tape show that the leaf was crudely stuck facing the titlepage some time after the Bishop
sale, since the catalogue entry for that sale was taped below the facsimile, and has left identical stains.
<note id="n63"><hi rend="s">5</hi> It is possible that this leaf was printed to complete this copy of the
book, and that it is not therefore otherwise recorded.</note></p>
          <p>Three further bits of penciled notes have not yet been identified; they may belong to the
above-mentioned owners, or may indicate still further owners. On the verso of the front free endpaper is the
notation “Cat/3759”; on the front binder’s blank is the price code “puuacy” and beneath that can be
seen the erased price “1200.00”; and on the final free endpaper is written “c9901.” None of these
notations is in Quaritch’s form; the volume also lacks that firm’s usual collation note. Sessler’s cost
code, written by Mabel Zahn but now erased, can also be clearly read.</p>
          <p>This newly-located copy of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> is textually complete with all
engravings colored and printed in their correct locations. Neither “JC” monograms nor any other notes
appear on the plates. The coloring of this copy of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> has been compared with
that of copy I-13 (New York Public Library, Print Room of the Art, Prints, and Photographs Division), and has
been found to be reasonably consistent. The only notable difference (other than predictable variations in
intensity) is found on the figure of Death on the titlepage to the Second Night. In the NYPL and in other
copies, the long flowing beard and shoulder are clearly visible; in this newly discovered copy that figure has
been overpainted with a black hood and cloak, obscuring both hair and shoulder. Copies I-8 and I-11 seem to
have this same feature. The engraving of this plate is, as usual, in the later state with added work.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n64"><hi rend="s">6</hi> It is perhaps worth mentioning that plates very from copy to copy in the
presence or absence of engraved imprint lines, a point mentioned by Easson and Essick.
Grant-Rose-Tolley-Erdman are right to suggest that uncolored copies exist in which the engraved titlepage to
the Second Night appears in the earlier state; one such copy was presented to The Pierpont Morgan Library by
Miss Louise Crane in memory of her mother, Mrs. W. Murray Crane, and I have examined two further copies in
private collections.</note></p>
          <p>The question of placing the Tonner-Lutheran Church copy of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
correctly in the census prepared by Grant, Rose, Tolley, and Erdman, is somewhat problematical since those
editors are themselves inconsistent and somewhat arbitrary in their arrangement. They note, “There is no
indication as to whether [this newly-discovered copy] is a White or Green Death copy. If it is of the former
type and should prove not to have been tinted by Blake, it will fit well enough as copy I-16, yet
<pb id="p15-136" n="136"/>
stand somewhat apart since it uniquely contains the ‘Explanations’ sheet unbound, whereas all other
coloured copies that include this sheet have it bound in one of three positions.” Now that it is recognized
that this copy does <hi rend="i">not</hi> contain the Explanation leaf, it cannot be located as copy I-16.
Even if it <hi rend="i">did</hi> contain this leaf it would not, according to the editorial criteria presented
on pp. 60-62, be appropriately placed as copy I-16 since the surrounding copies, I-13 through I-15, are all
seriously imperfect in one regard or another.</p>
          <p>Copies I-2 through I-14 have been arranged together by Grant-Rose-Tolley-Erdman, since all those
copies contain what the editors have optimistically labeled “grotesque colouring” or “grotesque
painting”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65" type="note">7</ref>; within this group copies
I-2 through I-7 are arranged together since they contain the leaf of Explanation bound after p. 95. These
copies are further arranged “according to the earliness of provenance that can be established with some
certainty.” Copies I-8 to I-10 have the Explanation leaf bound after the Advertisement, and copies I-11 and
I-12 lack the Explanation leaf entirely. Copies I-13 through I-15 also lack that leaf, and are further
deficient in lacking either text or colored engravings. The newly-discovered copy of <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> cannot be placed as copy I-16 since that would put it in the midst of seriously defective
copies. Since it contains “grotesque colouring,” lacks the Explanation leaf, and has demonstrable
provenance closest to copy I-12, this new copy can best be located as copy I-12A. It must be pointed out that
the editors of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> are inconsistent in the arrangement by earliness of
provenance, and one might at the same time question the wisdom of organizing a census in part on such slight
grounds as the binder’s location of the Explanation leaf. <note id="n65"><hi rend="s">7</hi> The explanation
of this phenomenon will be discussed in a future article in <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly.</hi></note></p>
          <p>It may well be that this colored copy of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> has escaped the notice
of Blake bibliographers since it appeared in the Bishop sale under Young’s name at the very end of the last
catalogue volume, and was not mentioned under the general Blake heading. When one considers the prices fetched
by other Blake works at that sale, it seems that this copy of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> might well have
brought more if catalogued with the other Blakeana earlier in the sale.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
