<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.3.dorrbecker</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Innocence Lost &amp; Found: An Untraced Copy Traced</title>
        <author n="Dörrbecker">Detlef W. Dörrbecker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1981/1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1981·82</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>George Hartley</name>
              <name>Wendy Jones</name>
              <resp>Typist</resp>
              <name>Denise Warren</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Greg Crossan</name>
              <name>Detlef Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Bo Ossian Lindberg</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Joseph S. Salemi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1981/1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
      <pb id="p15-125" n="125"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">INNOCENCE LOST &amp; FOUND: AN UNTRACED COPY TRACED</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">DETLEF W.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">DÖRRBECKER</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>The year 1980 has already been described with numerous epithets. For those interested in
          the graphic work of William Blake it has been a year of unexpected rediscoveries. This is
          especially true of Blake’s best known work in illuminated printing, the <hi rend="i">Songs
            of Innocence and of Experience.</hi></p>
        <p>Some time in Spring 1980, Copy BB of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> reappeared in a sale at
            Sotheby’s,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">1</ref> and in
autumn a series of coincidences
          led me to the Wallraf-Richartz-Museum (WRM), Cologne, where in the collection of Dr.
          Walter Neuerburg I found a fragmented copy of the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>
          which has never been available to the scholarly or non-scholarly public before.<ref
            target="n35" type="note">2</ref> The following description of what I believe to be 
            <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, Copy Y, attempts to supply a few new details about
          this particular copy and thus to supplement G. E. Bentley, Jr. ’s bibliographical notes on
          entry no. 139 in his <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi><ref target="n36" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See Robert N. Essick’s article with “New
            Information on Blake’s Illuminated Books.”, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
              Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1981), 4-13.</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">2</hi> The private
            collection of Dr. Walter and Marlis Neuerburg, which since 1978 has been on permanent
            loan at the Wallraf-Richartz-Museum, covers European printmaking from Goya to the Brücke
            masters. Among many other English illustrated books of this period it also includes a
            proof copy of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Illustrations to the Book of Job.</hi> A preliminary
            review of the holdings of the collection is given by Barbara Catoir, “Panorama der
            europäischen Graphik: Die Sammlung Neuerburg im Kölner Wallraf-Richartz-Museum/Von der
            Dauerleihgabe zum Besitz?”, <hi rend="i">Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung</hi>, 22 July
            1980, p. 19. —I am much indebted to Dr. Neuerburg for his <hi rend="i">imprimatur</hi>;
            at the same time, I would like to thank Dr. Hella Robels, curator of prints and drawings
            at the WRM, and her staff for organizational help. Neither the “rediscovery” nor this
            publication of the <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> series at Cologne would have been
            possible without Horst Meller of the Dept. of English at the University of Heidelberg
            and Robert N. Essick, who both played a vital part in the series of coincidences
            mentioned above. The reproductions were supplied by the Rheinisches Bildarchiv, Cologne
            (where prints can be ordered, quoting their negative nos. 180629-180643).</note>	
            <note id="n36"><hi rend="s">3</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford:
            Clarendon Press, 1977), pp. 364-432. My paramount indebtedness to this work will be
            evident throughout the following pages.</note></p>
        <p>The private collector’s typewritten catalogue<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n37" type="note">4</ref>
          mistakenly assumes that the fifteen handcolored prints which are now preserved at the
          Cologne museum once formed “Seiten 3-17 [ . . . ] der kombinierten Ausgabe aus den beiden
          Titeln ‘Songs of Innocence, 1789’ und ‘Songs of Experience, 1794’.” Since all the designs,
          however, belong to the <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> series, and since the authentic
          foliation leaves no room for the combined titlepage of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>—which
          in most cases was numbered as page 1 by Blake—I think it is much more likely that this
          copy in its original integrity consisted of the <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> plates only.
          Yet Dr. Neuerburg was correct when he stated that this copy was still missing from the
          Keynes and Wolf <hi rend="i">Census</hi>, and that the year 1802 is the approximate 
            <hi rend="i">terminus post quem</hi> for its execution. <note id="n37"><hi rend="s">4</hi>
            The xeroxed TS of the catalogue is available at the WRM Prints Dept.; it lists the set
            from <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> as inv. nos. 1561-1575.</note></p>
        <p>The Cologne copy consists of fifteen plates, printed on fifteen leaves with relatively
          wide margins. The leaves have been foliated consecutively 3-17 by Blake in the upper right
          corners, just outside the framing lines of the designs.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n38" type="note">5</ref> Their arrangement coincides with the “standard order” of plates 4-18 as
          established in Bentley’s <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, which of course corresponds with
          Blake’s own <hi rend="i">late</hi> order.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39"
type="note">6</ref>	
            <note id="n38"><hi rend="s">5</hi> As in other copies of the illuminated books which are
            generally assumed to have been numbered by Blake himself, the foliation of the Neuerburg
            copy has been executed in ink. The color of the ink is of the same light gray which was
            employed for the single framing lines in most of the plates. The numbers themselves I
            have compared with those in facsimiles of the <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>, the “Pickering
            Manuscript” of post-1803, and copies of the illuminated books where the hand has been
            accepted as Blake’s own. Since the character of the script in the Cologne copy of 
              <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> strongly resembles that in the other examples, I see no reason
            to doubt the authenticity of the present pagination.</note>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">6</hi> See Bentley 1977, pp. 375-76; according to the Keynes &amp; Wolf ordering
of
              <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, the Cologne copy shows the following sequence of plates:
            3. 15. 10-11. 8. 29-30. 9. 13. 20-21. 28. 18-19. 12.</note></p>
        <p>Two of the leaves show a distinct, though fragmentary, watermark. Plate 7 as well as
          plate 16 have “BUTTA” in the lower right corner of the sheet and in both the original
          watermark certainly read “BUTTANSHAW” before the leaves were cut down to their present
          size. Buttanshaw wove paper without at least portions of a date has not been recorded
          otherwise in Blake’s oeuvre.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
type="note">7</ref> Buttanshaw paper with
          the first two digits of a date, “18[ ],” was employed by the artist for his euphoric
          letter to John Flaxman of 19 October 1801. The same make, and three digits of a date,
          “180[ ],” appear to be visible in three of the leaves of Copy O of 
            <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (University of Texas), whereas only two copies of the combined 
            <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (P in an anonymous private collection in Britain, and Q in the
          collection of Mrs. Dennis of New York, N.Y.) seem to have preserved both the name and date
          intact: “BUTTANSHAW / 1802.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41"
type="note">8</ref> Obviously, Blake made
          use of Buttanshaw paper during a comparatively short period of time. The Buttanshaw
          watermark in the present copy of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> thus points to the Felpham
          period and the years immediately following (up to c. 1807) for an approximate date of the
          printing. <note id="n40"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Bentley’s entry under the respective heading
            in his table of watermarks, “<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (3 pls.),” refers to the three
            plates in <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (Y), i.e. our copy (see Bentley 1977, p. 71;
            Professor Bentley agreed to this correction in correspondence). The watermark fragments
            of the Neuerburg copy both appear in the lower right corner of the sheet, and it seems
            likely that with the edge of the paper not just half of the maker’s name (to the right)
            but also a date—which originally may have been visible below—has been trimmed off. At
            the same time I ought to point out that Bentley’s source for the description of 
              <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> Copy Y (see below) mentioned the Buttanshaw watermark for
            plates 6, 15-16 (see Bentley 1977, p. 366); I cannot find any sufficient explanation for
            this discrepancy, but I hope that the remaining evidence will prove to be strong enough
            to confirm my identification of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (Y) with the fifteen prints
            at Cologne.</note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">8</hi><hi rend="i"> Ibid.</hi>, pp. 71,
            366, 368.</note></p>
        <p>Two other facts seem to support 1801-02 as the <hi rend="i">terminus post quem</hi> for
          the production of the Cologne 
<pb id="p15-126" n="126"/>
copy: unlike the early copies,
          the plates were (1) printed on one side of the leaves only, and (2) foliated by the
          artist. At the same time, however, the arrangement of the designs as confirmed by the
          autograph pagination in this case poses a new problem. While Blake “began numbering his
          copies” of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> from “at least
          1806,” the sequence of the fifteen plates at the WRM is that of the late, post-1818 copies
          of the combined edition.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">9</hi><hi rend="i"> Ibid.</hi>, p. 383. An interpretation of the plate numbers in
the
            Cologne copy that concludes that the sequence here chosen by the poet-printer actually
            anticipated the order of the late copies in full, must remain hypothetical. The
            Neuerburg copy is a fragment, and the order of plates 4-18 does not necessarily imply
            that the sequence of the remaining <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> pages, now lacking from
            it, must also have been the same as in the late copies. In this context it is of
            particular importance that plates 2-27 (with plates 53 and 54 interpolated) in Copy S of
              <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>—with an 1808 Whatman watermark—really are in the same
            order as in the late copies and in the fragmented Copy Y (<hi rend="i">ibid.</hi>, p.
            377). Thus, the existing evidence certainly makes the Cologne copy and 
              <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (S) the most likely candidates to testify for a much earlier date of
            the so-called “standard order.”</note></p>
        <p>The contradiction between the extrinsic evidence of the watermarks and the plate order
          might be explained if we assume that the copy with which our fragment once belonged had
          been printed (and colored) by about 1802-06, but was foliated, bound, and sold at a much
          later date (or, very simply, by assuming that the pagination was not the work of the
          artist himself). In this situation, intrinsic evidence that only stylistic analyses of the
          coloring can supply becomes crucial. A close comparison of the Cologne copy, especially
          with the other “Buttanshaw copies,” may yield the decisive clue; unfortunately, however, I
          have never seen <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (0) and <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (P-Q), and
          therefore cannot offer more than a few cursory remarks on the use of color in the present
          example.</p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>THE COLOGNE COPY OF <hi rend="i">INNOCENCE</hi>, PLATE BY PLATE</title>
          </head>
          <p><hi rend="i">Note</hi>: The printing color is a pale, somewhat sepialike brown, unless
            stated otherwise. All the strengthening of outlines has been executed with pen and gray
            or black ink. Generally, this pen work and the coloring follow closely the etched lines
            of the designs. There is no colorprinting, of course, and the following glosses all
            apply to watercolor washes which have been added to the printed design by hand. Blake’s
            foliation, running from 3 to 17, is to be found in the upper right corners of each page
            and has been written with grayish ink. In the measurements height precedes width.</p>
          <p>Pl. 4: “Introduction.” Leaf-size 20.1 × 14.5 cm. At three sides the design is
            surrounded by a light blue wash; at the bottom, however, there is no indication of “the
            water clear” (as, e.g., in Copies T and Z of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>), but a simple
            horizontal strip of brown color from which the Tree-of-Jesse foliage shoots up into the
            margins. These vines are colored green and yellow, and, from the tiny panels they
            enclose, streaks of rose color are drawn horizontally into the area of the text. On both
            sides the figures in the third vignette from the bottom, as well as the foliage itself,
            have been strengthened with pen and ink.</p>
          <p>Pl. 5 (illus. 1): “The Shepherd.” Leaf-size 20.1 × 14.0 cm. Elaborately colored, with
            much modulation of the various hues, creating a completely convincing image of an
            Arcadian sunset. Behind the ochre colored flock extends a line of bushes in varied tones
            of green; the hill in the background is of a saturated dark blue. Above, pink washes
            have been laid over some gray shading. Behind the text panel the sky has been tinted
            with a light blue which also reappears at the top of the design where it has been
            applied in a darker pigmentation. The plant twining up the trunk of the tree in other
            copies has been partly eliminated by a brown watercolor wash except for its lower
            portion; there it shows three red calyxes. The Shepherd’s clothes are of a light brown.
            His face and hair, some of the folds of his gown, his crook, and the foremost of his
            sheep have all been reworked with the pen. Necessitated by poor inking and/or printing
            the text of 11. 1-4 had occasionally to be strengthened too.</p>
          <p>Pl. 6: “The Ecchoing Green,” I. Leaf-size 19.8 × 14.0 cm. Behind the green and yellow
            foliage of the central tree (which seems to cast light, not shadow, on the scene below)
            and the group of playing children, the sky is a mixture of pink and bright blue. These
            hues return in the foreground where they dominate, slightly more saturated and in an
            a-b-a-b-like rhythm the colors of the various costumes. The ground is divided into areas
            of lime-green and warm orange which is composed—in an almost “divisionist” manner—of red
            and yellow washes. The outlines of the tree and of most of the figures have been
            strengthened with pen and ink. Bright yellow, blue, and pink washes (i.e. the classic
            trias of primary colors) have been used to structure the lower half of the page. The
            title line, having been thinly inked, had to be painted over (with dark brown
            watercolor).</p>
          <p>Pl. 7: “The Ecchoing Green,” II. Leaf-size 20.9 × 14.7 cm. The group of figures is set
            against a blue background which changes first to pink, and then to yellow, with some
            orange added in the upper part of the design. As in many other copies, the two
            grape-plucking figures are clothed in pink and blue dress. Below them, the man wears a
            gray-green overcoat, and the surrounding figures are clad in dresses of pink, yellow,
            and orange. Some of the contours and faces of the figures have been worked over with pen
            and ink. The large vine has a brown stem and green leaves (which, with Blake, is not a
            matter-of-fact).</p>
          <p>Pl. 8: “The Lamb.” Leaf-size 20.5 × 14.3 cm., printed in a somewhat darker brown than
            the rest of the plates. All in all, the coloring here is more subdued; there are
            yellowish greens for the fore-ground and the tree’s foliage in mid-distance, a warm
            quality of yellow for the upper and rose color for the lower portion of the sky. The
            same hue of pink has also been employed for the child’s skin. The outlines of the
            child’s arms, its hands, and the central lamb have all been reworked with the pen, and
            the child’s right hand even shows some <hi rend="i">pentimenti.</hi></p>
          <p>Pl. 9: “The Little Black Boy,” I. Leaf-size 20.6 × 14.2 cm., printed in brown. The
            mother and child are the usual dark brown; the mother’s skirt, though partly shaded, is
            of the same color in a brighter, nougat-like mixture. The foliage of the tree, printed
            in brown, has been enriched by yellow and green washes. These contrast with the blue and
            reddish tints which have been employed for the sky. The orb of the sun on the horizon of
            the green hills does not at all act as a source of light (here then, the sun itself
            appears to be “bereav’d of light”). Its dull yellowish-brown color seems to belie the
            luminosity of both the sky in the design, and the bright yellow, pink, and blue washes
            which streak 
<pb id="p15-127" n="127"/>
horizontally across the text panel. The contours
            of the tree to the left and the mother’s right arm have been hastily re-worked with
            pen.</p>
          <p>Pl. 10 (illus. 2): “The Little Black Boy,” II. Leaf-size 20.7 × 13.7 cm. The whole of
            the page seems to be bathed in a silvery light; this light, of course, emanates from the
            paper which has been covered with particularly delicate layers of paint. The Christ-like
            shepherd’s garment, the skin of the English boy, and the flock of sheep have all been
            treated with only a few gray washes; in a more saturated, darker pigmentation the same
            gray has been used for the black boy and the tree. The water in the immediate foreground
            is of a steel-like blue-gray. The landscape scenery makes a colorful contrast with this
            almost monochrome center of the picture; there is green, yellow, and bright cinnabar in
            the foreground, green and blue (with an inlaid strip of red) in the background hills and
            foliage. For the sky, the primary colors have again been employed in their most luminous
            state; the halo-like sun emanates rose colored rays into the blue (right), bright
            gray-blue (area of the text), and orange-yellow “atmosphere.” Pen work is to be seen on
            the outlines of the three figures, strengthening especially the shepherd’s profile, and
            on the branches of the arching tree.</p>
          <p>Pl. 11: “The Blossom.” Leaf-size 20.8 × 14.4 cm., printed in dark blue. The blossoming
            plant is colored carmine red and blue, with some brown near the right-hand border of the
            design. The six children have pink skin and light brown wings; the wings of the central
            maiden are blue. A warm quality of yellow, tending distinctly towards orange to the
            right of the second stanza, has been washed in for a background. No additional outlining
            with the pen, but some of the text (the title, 11. 4-6, and especially 11. 11-12) has
            been strengthened with watercolor in beige.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43"
type="note">10</ref>	
              <note id="n43"><hi rend="s">10</hi> In the left margin of this sheet the fragment of a lower
              case roman letter, probably a “d.” is visible. At first glance it looks as if printed,
              but in fact it appears to be the only surviving part of an ink inscription which was
              cut off when the leaves were prepared for binding.</note></p>
          <p>Pl. 12: “The Chimney Sweeper.” Leaf-size 21.3 × 14.8 cm. The printed design leaves
            little room for coloring in this case. There are some blue (11. 1-12, 20-24 [to the left
            of the page]), bright salmon and carmine red (11. 15-20), and yellow (11. 20-24 [washed
            in from the right]) lanciform washes between the lines of the text. The flourishes
            between the stanzas and the background of the design at the bottom of the page are of a
            pale yellowish green; also, some brown is interspersed, which has been used for the
            trunk of the tree to the right as well. The long-robed figure, the child rising from the
              <figure n="s-inn.Y.P2-5" rend="file" width="630" height="1000">
              <head>1 “The Shepherd,” <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, Copy Y.</head>
              <figDesc>Relief etching, hand-colored with additional pen and ink work. Neuerburg
                Collection at the Wallraf-Richartz-Museum, Cologne.</figDesc>
            </figure>
<figure n="s-inn.Y.P4-10" rend="file" width="643" height="1000">
              <head>2 “The Little Black Boy,” plate 2, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, Copy
                Y.</head>
              <figDesc>Relief etching, hand-colored with additional pen and ink work. Neuerburg
                Collection at the WRM, Cologne.</figDesc>
            </figure>
<pb id="p15-128" n="128"/>
dark brown earth, nine of the ten dancing and
            running children, and the title line at the top of the page have been firmly outlined in
            pen.</p>
          <p>Pl. 13: “The Little Boy lost.” Leaf-size 20.3 × 14.4 cm.; the lettering of the text has
            been re-worked with pen and gray ink, thus considerably darkening the original pale
            brown of the printing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">11</ref>
As in most other copies,
            the design is dominated by a strong chiaroscuro contrast between the dark, in this case
            blue-gray, background on one side, the uncolored and only lightly shaded dress of the
            boy, and the bright yellow and red of the will-o’-the-wisp-like gleam on the other. The
            same pink which has been used on the boy’s face and bare forearms serves to set off the
            text from the ground. The floating angels are colored yellow, so that together with the
            blue washes at the bottom of the page and between the stanzas the trias of primary
            colors is present once more in the lower portion of this page. The outlines and drapery
            of the boy as well as those of the three angels to the right of the text, and the
            contours of the tree have been worked over with the pen. 
                <note id="n44"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Blake’s reason for doing this must have been the weak
legibility of the
              text in this impression of plate 13, not the decision <hi rend="i">to color</hi> the
              words themselves (as, e.g., in the late Copy H of the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> at
              the Fitzwilliam Museum). I could detect no textual variants caused by this reworking
              except the commas after the “fathers” in 11. 1 and 3, at the end of 1. 4, and after
              “deep” in 1. 7, and the colon at the end of 1. 8, which found no consideration in the
              “strengthened version.”</note></p>
          <p>Pl. 14 (illus. 3): “The Little Boy found.” Leaf-size 20.7 × 14.5 cm. The text panel has
            been treated in much the same way as in the preceding page, with the addition of some
            blue-green for the twining plants that surround the two stanzas of the poem. The setting
            of the scene with its dark brown tree trunks, brownish green bushes, and marine blue sky
            is sombre but nevertheless colorful. Thus, patches of red, creating the effect of
            reflected sunset light, have been introduced on the branches of the tree to the right.
            The two figures, however, have been left almost uncolored, with only a few gray washes
            to indicate light, shade, and relief of their white robes. The adult figure does not
            have the disc-like halo of the late copies, though when washing in the blue sky, the
            artist left uncolored an oval circlet above the head. The faces and hands of both
            figures show some pink flesh-color; the boy’s hair is a dark blonde, and the brim of his
            hat is dark gray. The pen has been used to define more clearly the faces and the
            outlines of the figures (including the angel to the right of the text), as well as the
            contours of the three trees.</p>
          <p>Pl. 15: “Laughing Song.” Leaf-size 20.6 × 14.8 cm., printed in a darker brown than most
            of the other plates in this copy. Again, the text panel shows the primary colors: from
            the left a bright blue, from the right a luminous red, and at the bottom a warm quality
            of yellow has been washed in. There the birds with their red bodies and blue wings take
            up once more the colors of the upper part of the text area, and of the dresses of the
            figures in the design above. The same three colors, with the addition of some green and
            orange-red, are arranged round the white of the uncolored table-cloth. The dress of the
            woman on the left, sitting in front of the table, is mainly of a bright blue, but has
            been sprinkled with pinkish red. Her male pendant at the right (facing the table in this
            copy) is dressed in blue, and two of the women behind the table wear pinkish red gowns.
            The central figure, seen from the back, is colored orange-red and thus corresponds with
            the autumn-like splendor of the tree’s yellow, orange, and even red foliage. Only a few
            details like the shoulders of the man with arms upraised and the chair at the right have
            been strengthened in pen and ink.</p>
          <p>Pl. 16: “A Cradle Song,” I. Leaf-size 20.7 × 14.8 cm. The flourishing branches are
            either brown (i.e. the printing color), or a lusterless green; the tiny figures have not
            been hand-colored. The text is set off against yellow, blue, and rose colored washes
            which run down the margins (at the left: yellow; at the upper right: blue, and at the
            lower right: pinkish red); these have also been extended horizontally between the lines
            of the text. To the left of the title and of the fourth stanza a few of the plant
            ornaments have been worked over with pen and ink.</p>
          <p>Pl. 17 (illus. 4): “A Cradle Song,” II. Leaf-size 20.8 × 14.3 cm. The plant-like
            flourishes above, below, and between the two remaining stanzas on this page have been
            colored green, modulating towards yellow; they, as well as the woman carrying a child to
            the left of 11. 26-28, have been given stronger outlines with the pen. The design below
            is composed of only three different hues: the floor, chair, and cradle, as well as the
            mother’s hair, are colored a light brown; the curtain is blue and vividly structured by
            the printed lineament in pale brown; at the left—behind the woman’s back—it is covered
            with dark gray-blue shading; finally, the woman’s dress is tinted with the bright
            pinkish carmine red that has been observed so often in this copy. The faces of mother
            and child, the outlines and drapery folds of the woman’s dress, the chair, and even some
            of the folds in the curtain have all been forcefully strengthened with pen and black
            ink.</p>
          <p>Pl. 18: “The Divine Image.” Leaf-size 20.0 × 13.6 cm., printed in blue-gray. Text and
            design have been equally set off against washes of pink (left margin and top left),
            bright blue (top right), yellow and orange (lower right-hand portion), the latter two
            gaining in intensity near the “raising” scene with the haloed Christ-like figure.
            Yellow, cinnabar red, and the orange which is the product when these two are applied on
            top of each other, are the colors of the flaming plant. The figures have been touched
            with pink for their carnations. There is no additional pen work on this design.</p>
          <p>It should be evident from these glosses that the Cologne copy of <hi rend="i">Songs of
              Innocence</hi> is characterized by a particularly luminous transparency of all the
            various hues of watercolor that have been employed in its hand-coloring. The combined
            use of the three primary colors (often together with green as the fourth), or at least
            two of them in weak saturation, is an essential aspect of the formal unity of the
            complete set. Also, the extensive use of pen and ink on the figures and other important
            details belongs with the characteristic qualities of this copy. Throughout, the basic
            rule of traditional color perspective has been observed; wherever the printed design
            allowed for it, “warm” colors and especially reds have been employed in the fore-ground
            whereas dark blue tones have been reserved for the background, and the brighter blues
            mostly for the “distant” sky.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45"
type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n45"><hi
                rend="s">12</hi> Copy P of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (now at Yale) was printed on
              different makes of paper, which, however, are dated 1802 and 1804. The copy was given
              by Malkin to one of his friends in 1805, and thus it was evidently produced at about
              the same time when Blake probably also executed the present copy (see Bentley 1977,
              pp. 366, 409). The sequence of plates in Copy P differs largely from that of the
              Cologne fragment, yet the coloring of the two copies may have a lot in common. David
              Bindman in <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist</hi> (Oxford: Phaidon, 1977), p. 59,
              described Copy P as follows: “ . . . the outlines are firmly outlined in pen . . . The
              predominant color note is a cerulean blue, which acts illusionistically, usually over
              the whole page, giving the suggestion that the text is floating in the sky. The
              effects of luminosity are correspondingly more subtle.”</note></p>
          <pb id="p15-129" n="129"/>
          <p>Though the following paraphernalia certainly give no clue for either the dating and the
            early history of the Neuerburg copy, or for an estimation of its aesthetic value, a
            bibliographical account would be incomplete without it. So let me briefly mention that
            the leaves have apparently been trimmed offhand; their slightly varying sizes, which
            range from 19.8 to 21.3 cm. in height, and 13.6 to 14.8 cm. in width, indicate that a
            pair of scissors instead of a chopper was probably used for cutting them to their
            present size.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">13</ref> Whereas
today the prints are mounted
            separately with perspex guard sheets, they were originally stabbed with three holes in
            preparation for binding.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">14</ref>
These stitch-holes are
            about 5.0 to 6.0 cm. from the top of the pages, and about 3.0 cm. apart from each other;
            they have been closed in the course of the restoration of the prints (see below), but
            are still visible on close examination. <note id="n46"><hi rend="s">13</hi> This becomes
              even more evident when the leaves are measured at all four sides. In most cases the
              measurements provided above, which have been taken at the left and bottom edges of the
              paper, do not exactly match those of the opposite sides. For plate 8, e.g., I noted
              20.4 (left) × 14.6 (bottom) cm., and 20.6 (right) × 14.1 (top) cm.</note>	
              <note id="n47"><hi rend="s">14</hi> The original (?paper) covers or any other remains of a
              former binding have not been preserved with the prints.</note></p>
          <p>As regards the history and identification of the Cologne copy, only a few details are
            known. On 12 March 1962, “a gentleman” sold an incomplete copy of 
              <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> for £1000 through Sotheby’s to “Fairbrother.” This copy had
not been
            recorded before, and it was described in the respective Sotheby catalogue under lot
              151.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">15</ref>
“Fairbrother,” 
            <figure n="s-inn.RY.P12-14" rend="file" width="612" height="1000">
              <head>3 “The Little Boy found,” <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, Copy Y.</head>
              <figDesc>Relief etching, hand-colored with additional pen and ink work. Neuerburg
                Collection at the WRM, Cologne.</figDesc>
            </figure> according to Bentley was the pseudonym of the art dealer Nicolas Rauch of
            Geneva, whose “sale records [—unfortunately—] were not preserved after his death by his
              successor.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">16</ref> Thus,
shortly after the illuminated
            book had made its first appearance on the art market, we lost track of 
              <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, Copy Y, once again. The description in the sales catalogue
            was detailed enough, however, to allow for future identification. The data supplied by
            the catalogue—and since then incorporated into <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>—included
            the number of plates and their contents, watermarks, foliation details, approximate
            leaf-sizes, and printing color. With the help of Bentley’s superb tables it is easy to
            find that these details all suit the Cologne copy, which, in 
              <figure n="SINNCopyYCradleSong.15.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="394">
              <head>4 “A Cradle Song,” plate 2, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, Copy Y.</head>
              <figDesc>Relief etching, hand-colored with additional pen and ink work. Neuerburg
                Collection at the WRM, Cologne.</figDesc>
            </figure>
<pb id="p15-130" n="130"/>
turn, cannot be identified with any other of the
            untraced copies of either the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> or the combined 
              <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience.</hi>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">15</hi>
              I have not been able to obtain a copy of this particular sales catalogue from a German
              library. The sale was probably devoted exclusively to books, since there is also no
              copy of a Sotheby’s catalogue with this date in the Dept. of Prints and Drawings of
              the British Museum. I did not go any further; I have relied entirely on Bentley’s
              account of the first surfacing of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (Y); see Bentley 1977,
              p. 412.</note>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">16</hi><hi rend="i"> Ibid.</hi>, p. 412, n.
              1.</note></p>
          <p>Obviously, Dr. Walter Neuerburg bought Copy Y from Rauch (who may well have acted on
            behalf of the distinguished German collector) or some intermediary agent soon after the
            sale at Sotheby’s was over. This is confirmed by the correspondence between the
            collector and Mr. and Mrs. Kästner of Wolfenbüttel which is still preserved with the
            prints at the WRM. The first of these letters is dated 6 April 1962, and it refers to
            the projected restoration of Blake’s newly acquired prints. This restoration had been
            brought to a successful end by 19 May 1962.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50"
type="note">17</ref> The
            present owner himself, however, was reluctant to supply me with further information
            about the provenance of his treasure; yet he was kind enough to tell me that—“all in
            all”—the reconstruction of the last stages in the history of his copy, as offered here,
            is correct.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">18</ref>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">17</hi> The
              restoration was executed by Mrs. Anita Kästner, who has done expert work for the
              Herzog-August-Bibliothek at Wolfenbüttel. From her report—which is still inserted in
              the respective box at the WRM—and from the prints themselves one gets the impression
              that she treated the fragment of Blake’s illuminated book with all the care and
              knowledge that are required for a difficult job like this. From her correspondence
              with the owner it is clear that Mrs. Kästner knew beforehand how much special care
              must be taken with both the fragile printing relief and the delicate layers of paint.
              Consequently her restoration concentrated on cleaning the paper in the margins,
              leaving the actual printing surface unaffected.</note>
	<note id="n51"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Each of the fifteen leaves has been blind stamped with a collector’s
mark
              (showing the Neuerburg coat of arms) in the lower right corner of the sheets. This
              mark is basically the same as the one described for Heinrich Neuerburg, the present
              owner’s father, under no. 1344a in Frits Lugt’s <hi rend="i">Lee Marques de
                collections de dessins et d’estampes</hi>, supplement [i.e. vol. 2] (La Haye:
              Martinus Nijhoff, 1956), p. 190.</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, Copy BB, and <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, Copy Y, have been
            merely <hi rend="i">re</hi>-discovered. And yet, the first of Blake’s illuminated books
            ever to appear in a collection on the Continent, outside of the English-speaking world,
            may raise hopes for more and even bigger surprises in the future. I do not expect the
            “Ancient Britons,” or the painted version of the “Last Judgement” stored away on the
            backstairs of some provincial museum on the Continent. But the unexpected finding at
            Cologne certainly highlights another “work needed” in the field of Blake studies which
            is missing from Gerald Bentley’s list. Our knowledge of the entire 
              <hi rend="i">corpus</hi> of the graphic work of William Blake will be limited in an almost
            inexcusable way until a thorough investigation into the holdings of at least the major
            public collections in France, Germany, Italy, and the Scandinavian countries has been
              undertaken.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">19</ref>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">19</hi>
              This attempt at bibliographic exactness and its amateur author have profitted
              enormously from the help of three friends who <hi rend="i">are</hi> professionals in
              the field. Wihtout the questions and suggestions of G. E. Bentley, Jr., Robert N.
              Essick, and Sir Geoffrey Keynes my description would have lacked much relevant
              information. Those flaws in the argument which certainly remain, however, are entirely
              my own.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p15-131" n="131" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
