<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.4.gleckner</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake’s Swans</title>
        <author n="Gleckner">Robert F. Gleckner</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>George Hartley</name>
              <name>Cathy Christman</name>
              <resp>Typist</resp>
              <name>Denise Warren</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Hazard Adams</name>
              <name>James Bogan</name>
              <name>Gavin Edwards</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Randel Helms</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Janice Lyle</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Gerda Norvig</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
      <pb id="p15-164" n="164"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-4-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">BLAKE’S SWANS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">ROBERT F.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">GLECKNER</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>The swan is as rare a bird in Blake’s works as he said London print shops
                    were in his youth<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">1</ref>—though their
                    appearances, in text and design, span almost his entire working career from 
<hi rend="i">There Is No Natural Religion</hi> through <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Critical interpretations of
them have been sparse and, even
                    if one cannot expect consensus, they are unusually varied: the Female Will,
                    chariot of inspiration, a pen, the river Severn, arsenic, the soul, desire, the
                    body (or Generation), Blake himself as poet-painter.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">2</ref> By far the most elaborate of these interpretations is
                    Erdman’s commentary in <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> on plate
                    11 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, which is the only one to really try to come
                    to grips with that puzzling design by seeing it as a sublime allegory of
                    Blake’s marriage of copper-plate etching (of text and design) and the
                    printing and coloring of that design on paper. Since the <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plate
is especially complex, let me leave it aside for a
                    moment to deal with some “simoler” swans. <note id="n32"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi
rend="i"> The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman
                        (Garden City: Doubleday, 1965), p. 679, hereafter cited in text and notes as
                        E plus the page number.</note>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Successively S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Philosophy
and Symbols</hi> (New York: Peter Smith,
                        1947; orig. ed. 1924), p. 469; David Bindman, <hi rend="i">Blake as an
                            Artist</hi> (Oxford: Phaidon, 1977), p. 182; Erdman, <hi rend="i">The
                            Illuminated Blake</hi> (Garden City: Anchor/ Doubleday, 1974), p. 149,
                        hereafter cited in text and notes as <hi rend="i">IB</hi> plus the page
                        number; Bindman, 1oc. cit.; W. H. Stevenson, ed., <hi rend="i">The Poeme of
                            William Blake</hi> (London and New York: Longman/W. W. Norton, 1972), p.
                        646n.; Kathleen Raine, <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi> (Princeton:
                        Princeton University Press, 1968), I, 177; Erdman, <hi rend="i">IB</hi>, 54;
                        Joseph Wicksteed, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Jerusalem</hi>
                        (Trianon Press, n.d.), p. 217; Erdman, <hi rend="i">IB</hi>, 54, 290. There
                        are others as well. Interestingly Damon does not index the swan in <hi rend="i">A
Blake Dictionary</hi> (Providence: Brown University Press,
                        1965).</note></p>
        <p>According to the Blake concordance there are only two swans in his writings,
                    neither apparently remarkable enough to elicit any comment except from Kathleen
                    Raine who, in glossing the “bright swan” of <hi rend="i">Visions of
                        the Daughters of Albion</hi> (plate 3), identifies the whole scene as
                    Plotinian, the swan as “Plato’s emblem of the soul,” here
                    dipping “its wing in the ‘red earth’ of the natural body,
                    which is the ever-flowing river of generated life.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">3</ref> Although it is certainly possible that Blake was aware
                    of this Neoplatonic interpretation of the <hi rend="i">Phaedo</hi>,
                    Raine’s gloss on the <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> passage (3:18-19; E 46)
                    commits precisely the same error that so frustrates Oothoon in
                    Theotormon’s reaction to her rape and “defilement” by Bromion.
                    Her invoking of the swan here is not to corroborate such simplistic body-soul
                    dichotomizing but to counteract it. The swan is but one of three parallel
                    images, the others being fruit and lamb. As the worm feeds on the sweetest
                    fruit, she argues, so is the “new wash’d lamb ting’d with the
                    village smoke” and “the bright swan / By the red earth” of the
                    river of life (that is, by the red clay of Esau-Edom in Genesis 25:25-30). But
                    unlike these, she says, “How can I be defild when I reflect thy image
                    pure?” Adopting Theotormon’s mistaken orientation, she turns it
                    against itself: unlike the swan “I bathe <hi rend="i">my</hi> wings. / And
                    I am white and pure”—Blake’s grammatical construction here
                    denying a cause and effect relationship. She <hi rend="i">is</hi> sullied to
                    Theotormon’s morally jaundiced eye but to hers, bathing in “our
                    immortal river” leaves no residue of “generation’s” slow
                    stain. The seed of Oothoon’s conception, perhaps even the seed of
                    Blake’s entire conception in the <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>, is in <hi rend="i">The
Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>: “As the catterpiller
                    chooses the fairest leaves to lay her eggs on, so the priest lays his curse on
                    the fairest joys”; but “The soul of sweet delight, can never be
                    defil’d”—by village smoke, red earth, or hypocritical moral
                    and religious judgement.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35"
type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake and Tradition</hi>, I, 177. In the 
<hi rend="i">Phaedo</hi> Socrates, talking to Simmias of immortality, mentions swans
                        as sacred to Apollo and as having the gift of prophecy, but he does not
                        specifically identify the swan with the soul.</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Orc reiterates Blake’s point, even
                            more powerfully, in <hi rend="i">America</hi>, plate 8:
<q> That stony
                                law I stamp to dust: and scatter religion abroad<lb/>
 To the four
                                winds as a torn book, &amp; none shall gather the leaves;<lb/>
 But
                                they shall rot on desart sands, &amp; consume in bottomless
                                deeps;<lb/>
 To make the desarts blossom, &amp; the deeps shrink to
                                their fountains,<lb/>
 And to renew the fiery joy, and burst the
                                stony roof.<lb/>
 That pale religious letchery, seeking
                                Virginity,<lb/>
 May find it in a harlot, and in coarse-clad
                                honesty<lb/>
 The undefil’d tho’ ravish’d in her
                                cradle night and morn:<lb/>
 For every thing that lives is holy, life
                                delights in life;<lb/>
 Because the soul of sweet delight can never
                                be defil’d.<lb/>
 (5-14) </q></note></p>
        <p>Oothoon’s swan, then, is not the Platonic soul but rather an image of her
                    eternal imaginative individuality, her fundamental and divine (“pure”)
                    humanness in its “eternal joy” (8:8). In Raine’s footnote to
                    her Plotinian interpretation, however, she superimposes upon it an allusion to
                    Plato that does lead us in a direction pertinent to virtually all of
                    Blake’s swan images, even as it leads us further and further away from
                        <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>: “The soul of
                    Orpheus,” she reminds us, “enters the body of a swan, in the myth in
                    the tenth book of the <hi rend="i">Republic</hi> (620A); but this is usually
                    understood in a symbolic sense, the swan being the emblem of the poet.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">5</ref> While the Orpheus-swan connection in the 
<hi rend="i">Republic</hi> is clear, there is 
<pb id="p15-165" n="165"/>
no
                    evidence so far as I know that that connection evolved into an iconographical
                    (or even mythological) tradition. Nevertheless, the fact that Orpheus was an
                    especial favorite of Apollo’s (some said even his son) validates the swan
                    association in that the bird was sacred to him. As Robert J. Clements points
                    out, the most popular symbol of the poet in the Renaissance was the swan, its
                    consistent linkage to Apollo according it prophetic powers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">6</ref> Blake’s intimate knowledge of Renaissance emblem
                    literature is now generally accepted,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38"
type="note">7</ref> and
                    Cesare Ripa (<hi rend="i">Iconologia</hi>, 1593), Geoffrey Whitney (<hi rend="i">Choice of
Emblemes</hi>, 1586), and Alciati (<hi rend="i">Emblemata</hi>,
                    1551; it went through over 150 editions before 1621 and Clements calls it
                    “the bible of emblem books” [p. 785])—as well as any number of
                    their imitators—all identify the swan with Apollo, the poet, poesy,
                    prophecy. <note id="n36"><hi rend="s">5</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake and Tradition</hi>, I,
410-11. While, as almost all
                        critics note, Plato is clearly the source of Shelley’s
                        “Enchanted Boat” lyric, with its swan, in <hi rend="i">Prometheus
                            Unbound</hi>, the application of his imagery to Blake is justifiable
                        only if one is indifferent to Blake’s unalterable opposition to the
                        ideas that inform Plato’s conception. Besides, Raine ignores
                        Plato’s explanation of Orpheus’s metamorphosis: his soul
                        “chose” the swan because of hatred for womankind (since women had
                        killed and dismembered him) and because therefore he did not wish to be
                        conceived and born of woman. Cf. Wither’s emblem of Ganymede astride
                        Jupiter’s eagle as the soul mounting to heaven (<hi rend="i">A
                            Collection of Embleme 1635</hi>, ed. John Horden [Yorkshire: Scolar
                        Press, 1968], p. 156). Piloo Nanavutty in “Blake and Emblem
                        Literature,” <hi rend="i">Journal of the Warburg &amp; Courtauld
                            Institutes</hi>, 15 (1952), p. 260, identifies <hi rend="i">America
                            11</hi> with this myth.</note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">6</hi> “Iconography on the Nature and
                        Inspiration of Poetry in Renaissance Emblem Literature,” <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi>, 70
(1955), 784. Clements notes that Cicero, in the <hi rend="i">Tusculanae Disputationes</hi>, says that swans
were gifted with
                        powers of divination. The information in the rest of this paragraph is from
                        Clements. See also J. Rendel Harris, “Apollo’s Swans,” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of
the John Rylands Library</hi>, 9 (1925),
                        372-416.</note>
	<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">7</hi> See, e.g., Nanavutty’s essay cited
                        above, pp. 258-61; Mary Lynn Johnson, “Emblem and Symbol in
                        Blake,” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi>, 37 (1974),
                        151-70; and Judith Wardle, “‘For Hatching ripe’: Blake
                        and the Educational Uses of Emblem and Illustrated Literature,” 
<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi>, 81 (1978), 324-48,
                        esp. her “Appendix.”</note></p>
        <p>The only other instance of a swan in Blake’s writings seems to argue
                    further for his awareness of this tradition, even if not for a specific textual
                    or emblem source. In <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> Urizen, fallen and
                    “shut up in the deep dens of Urthona,” spills out his “Woes”
                    in a lament for the lost Eden: 
					<q> My fountains once the haunt of Swans now
                        breed the scaly tortoise<lb/>
 The houses of my harpers are become a haunt of
                        crows<lb/>
 The gardens of wisdom are become a field of horrid graves<lb/>
                        And on the bones I drop my tears &amp; water them in vain (Night V, E 336)
					</q>
					The fact that Urizen is associated in the remainder of this Night with
                    Apollo and the chariot of the sun solidifies the allusion, Blake of course
                    transforming both the Apollo and Orpheus myths (which he knew probably from
                    Ovid) into the fall of all Art. Though the fallen prophet’s tonque (or
                    the voice of wisdom) remains eloquent, 
					<q> in vain the voice<lb/>
 Of Urizen in
                        vain the Eloquent tongue. A Rock a Cloud a Mountain<lb/>
 Were now not Vocal
                        as in Climes of happy Eternity<lb/>
 Where the lamb replies to the infant
                        voice &amp; the lion to the man of years<lb/>
 Giving them sweet
                        instructions Where the Cloud the River &amp; the Field<lb/>
 Talk with the
                        husbandman &amp; shepherd. . . .<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi>, Night
                        VI, E 341) </q>
More impressive evidence of Blake’s knowledge of the
                    swan of emblem literature, however, is in the most regal of all his graphic
                    swans, that adorning the titlepage of his illustrations to Gray’s poems.
                    The caption is “The Pindarick Genius recieving his Lyre,” the latter
                    descending from the sky to the youthful poet who is riding the swan with so
                    loose a rein that he virtually gives it its head. Blake, of course, may be
                    merely echoing here Pindar’s common characterization as the “Theban
                        Swan,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">8</ref> for
he has indicated
                    elsewhere that he was reasonably familiar, if not with Pindar’s poetry
                    directly, with his reputation and the legends and stories about him. 
<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Gray himself, however, whose steady praise of
                        Pindar and his own writing of “Pindarics” Blake obviously knew
                        well, describes Pindar as the “Theban Eagle . . . / Sailing with
                        supreme dominion / Thro’ the azure deep of air” (“The
                        Progress of Poesy,” 1. 115—subtitled “Pindaric” with
                        an epigraph from Pindar). Gray’s note to the passage simply says that
                        “Pindar compares himself to that bird.” The swan epithet belongs
                        to the family of Mantuan Swan and Swan of Avon, though it was Cowley who
                        attached the swan to Pindar (noted by Roger Lonsdale, <hi rend="i">The Poems
                            of Thomas Gray, William Collins, Oliver Goldsmith</hi> [London: Longman,
                        1969], p. 176). That attachment is echoed by Denham in his “On Mr.
                        Abraham Cowley.” Irene Tayler, in <hi rend="i">Blake’s
                            Illustrations to the Poems of Gray</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University
                        Press, 1971), identifies the swan of Blake’s titlepage to Gray as
                        “Apollo’s bird” (p. 22).</note></p>
        <p>In <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi>, for example, Suction asks at one
                    point “if Pindar was not a better Poet than Ghiotto was a Painter” (E
                    444), but the question is never answered in the ensuing squabble over whether
                    Plutarch, who quotes Pindar but says little about him, was prejudiced against
                    Italians. There is little evidence in the context that Blake knew much more
                    about Plutarch than that he wrote “lives”—though it’s
                    interesting at least to recall, in connection with the poet-prophet idea, the
                    comic discussion in Chapter 3 of <hi rend="i">An Island</hi> of
                    “Phebus,” who was, among other things according to Obtuse Angle, the
                    “God of . . . Painting, Perspective . . . Phraseology . . . Mythology . . .
                    in short every art &amp; science adorn’d him as beads round his
                    neck.” He also “understood Engraving”—though in the course
                    of the insane conversation he ultimately is confused with Pharoah.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">9</ref> Blake’s only other mention of Pindar
                    by name is in an inscription on one of his pencil drawings: “Corinna the
                    Rival of Pindar Corinna the Graecian Poetess.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n41" type="note">10</ref> The allusion here is to the story that Pindar in his youth was
                    defeated in a poetical contest by Corinna, who then advised him to use more
                    mythology in his poems; when he did so she ungraciously criticized his using it
                    too profusely. The suggestiveness of this Pindar-lyre-swan-genius association
                    (occurring as it does about 1797 when Flaxman commissioned the Gray series for a
                    gift to his wife)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42"
type="note">11</ref> is strengthened by the
                    earlier appearance in <hi rend="i">America</hi> of a comparable swan (plate 11),
                    like the Gray swan being ridden with gentle—though not quite so
                    gentle—rein. Erdman describes this one as hastening “from
                    Albion’s fires . . . to safer homes inland” (<hi rend="i">IB</hi>,
                    149), though such action seems hardly to demonstrate prophetic power or
                    fortitude. (If indeed the swan-rider is fleeing “the British bombardment of
                    coastal towns” as Erdman claims, we might wonder why he heads East instead
                    of West, as the fleeing family in plate 3 does.) Yet Erdman does identify the
                    rider as an Orc-Los “image,” as Samuel Adams (that is,
                    “Boston’s Angel” who speaks the prophetic words of plate 11),
                    Tom Paine, and “the poet himself in disguise . . . like Horace.” While
                    his additional idea of this being a “pen swan” may not be as
                    far-fetched as it sounds on the surface, Erdman’s Horatian reference is
                    most unfortunate. Horace did prophesy his poetic immortality in the context of
                    feeling himself turning into a swan (surely echoing Socrates), but it is hard to
                    imagine any poet who would serve less well as a prophetic model, or indeed any
                    kind of poetic model, for Blake. The fact is, of course, that Horace is alluding
                    to the very tradition Blake himself is making use of. Erdman is right: the rider
                    is the poet, prophet, Blake—riding Eastward toward the advancing
                    “dragon form” of “Albion’s wrathful Prince” (<hi rend="i">America</hi> 3:14-15).
<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">9</hi> E 442-43.
                        Earlier Blake invokes Apollo with his “rays of light” and
                        “truth’s beams” in his <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>
                        poem, “An Imitation of Spencer.”</note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">10</hi> See <hi rend="i">Pencil Drawings of William
                            Blake</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes (London, 1927), p. 45. The Corinna
                        episode was among the most commonly retailed of Pindar anecdotes.</note>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Mary K. Woodworth, <hi rend="i">Notes &amp;
                            Queries</hi>, 215 (n.s. 17) (1970), 312-13.</note></p>
        <p>As attractive as all this may be, one may still wonder about the swan’s
                    being bridled, however gently.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43"
type="note">12</ref> If indeed
                    its rider here is Orc-like, as his origins in the fiery figure of plate 10
                    suggest, what we have in the total icon is poesy or prophecy being pressed by
                    its rider into the violent action of bloody battle and the final loosing of
                    plagues, “fierce disease and lust” (16:21) on England, a holocaust
                    totally out of keeping with Apollo, Orpheus, the “Pindarick Genius,”
                    poetry, and prophecy as Blake understood them. It is instead 
<pb id="p15-166" n="166"/>
prophecy perverted to war-song, one of the things he saw happening
                    in Gray as well. Is this why the rider looks back, doubletaking his own violent
                    image as well as the lost Eden of Atlantis on the previous plate? And is this
                    why, as it seems to me, the swan strains at the rein? The contrasting view is
                    seen in the serpent figure at the bottom of the page, which Erdman properly sees
                    as smilingly attentive to its riders, so limply reined as to be free (note the
                    limp arm of the rein-holder as distinct from the sharply tensed wrist of the
                        swan-rider),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">13</ref>
its tail spiralling off
                    into infinity-eternity, its riders “in long drawn arches sitting”
                    feeling “the nerves of youth renew” (15:24-25). These riders, we
                    should note, reverse (and hence annihilate) time through the true prophecy of
                    the serpent, Blake moving us from the youthful rein-holder back to child back to
                    infant back to the prophetic coils of the snake’s tail, repeating almost
                    exactly the curlicue soaring upward from the “P” of
                    “Prophecy” on plate 3,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45"
type="note">14</ref> growing
                    “vitally upward in endless communication that expands into words and
                    poetry” (<hi rend="i">IB</hi>, 143). Erdman himself seems to sense
                    something of the falseness of the Orc-prophecy and the dawning of Los-like
                    vision in his commentary on the “Preludium”: “The poem beginning
                    on Plate 3 presents a potentially cyclic revolution of rise and fall, rebellion
                    and enslavement, threatening a perpetual dull round”;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">15</ref> and also in his interpretation of the “Finis”
                    design at the foot of plate 16, corroborating my reading of the serpent-swan
                    opposition on plate 11: “Coiling among thorny but blossoming red roses, his
                    head another rosebud, he directs his tongue in the proper prophetic position . .
                    . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">12</hi> In commenting on Blake’s water-color
                        drawing of “Fiery Pegasus,” however, Robert Essick says that this
                        “emblem of inspiration . . . must be organized by a more restrained
                        vision. The reins will become the bound and outward circumference of
                        creative energy without destroying it” (“<hi rend="i">Preludium</hi>: Meditations
on a Fiery Pegasus,” in <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, ed. Essick and Donald Pearce [Bloomington and
                        London: Indiana University Press, 1978], pp. 9-10). I’m not so sure
                        of that. Prince Hal’s vaulting into the saddle, “turning and
                        winding” Pegasus, and “witch[ing] the world with noble
                        horsemanship”—the passage from <hi rend="i">Henry IV, Part
                            I</hi> that Blake is illustrating—seems hardly an appropriate
                        paradigm of the prophetic poet; more like Pope’s <hi rend="i">Essay
                            on Criticism.</hi> Is this why Blake does not have the flying
                        poet-prophet (?) bridle Pegasus at all but has him fly with (or as)
                        Pegasus?</note>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">13</hi> One might compare this limp rein with the
                        even limper one of the strange phallus-cloud-borne figure atop plate 1 of
                            <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (<hi rend="i">IB</hi>, 129),
where the rein is attached, appropriately, to the
                        “V” of “Visions,” the other vertical of the
                        “V” terminating in a serpentine prophetic trumpet.</note>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">14</hi> In the cancelled variant of this plate (<hi rend="i">IB</hi>, 392) that
curlicue is absent.</note>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">15</hi><hi rend="i"> IB</hi>, 139. The bridled swan, like Essick’s
                        potentially (or necessarily) bridled Pegasus, has its counterpart in the
                        Gray titlepage, which may, then, be a satiric rather than complimentary
                        portrait. In fact, the poet of the title-page may be seen as an idealized
                        portrait of Blake himself (the Gray of plate 2 is at least reminiscent of
                        Gray’s profile, and in any case is most unlike the face of the
                        “Genius”). Tayler, in <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations to
                            . . . Gray</hi>, takes no note of the differences but does certify plate
                        2 as “strikingly similar to Gray’s as it had appeared in the
                        Basire engraving done while Blake was Basire’s apprentice, and also
                        to Blake’s later pencil sketch, ‘The poet, Gray’”
                        (p. 22). My suggestion is lent credence by the final plate of the series,
                        “Gray himself, guided by his visionary illustrator,” as Tayler
                        puts it (p. 146). Here Gray and Blake look alike.</note>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">16</hi><hi rend="i"> IB</hi>, 155. In Ovid as elsewhere Venus’s chariot is
                        drawn by winged swans (<hi rend="i">Metamorphoses</hi>, X), making an
                        association of serpent, rose, and swan in Blake at least tantalizing. In
                        Edward A. Armstrong’s <hi rend="i">The Folklore of Birds</hi> (New
                        York: Dover, 1970; orig. ed. 1958), there is an engraving (after an
                        unidentified Roman work) of Apollo in a swan-drawn chariot (p. 51) and one
                        of a vase or wine-jar design of Adonis and Aphrodite riding in a chariot
                        drawn by two swans (p. 45). For other less-than-sanguine readings of 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> see Robert E. Simmons, “<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>: The Symmetry of Fear”; Michael J.
Tolley, “<hi rend="i">Europe</hi>: ‘to those ychain’d in
                        sleep’”; and Erdman’s longer version of his <hi rend="i">IB</hi> commentary,
“<hi rend="i">America</hi>: New
                        Expanses”—all in <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms
                            Dramatic</hi>, ed. Erdman and John E. Grant (Princeton: Princeton
                        University Press, 1970). The latest “pessimistic” reading of 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> is Minna Doskow’s “William
                        Blake’s <hi rend="i">America</hi>: The Story of a Revolution
                        Betrayed,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 8 (1979),
                    167-186.</note></p>
        <p><hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> indexes a number of other etched swans in
                    the early works—up through <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
                        Hell</hi> (though I find none in “The Ecchoing Green” or on plate
                    8 of <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> as indexed), none of them incontrovertible
                    except those in <hi rend="i">There Is No Natural Religion</hi> and “The
                    Little Boy lost.” While it is possible that in the former (plate 8a) the
                    boy approaches the swan because it “might be ridden” (<hi rend="i">IB</hi>, 29), the
text suggests it as the visible expression of the
                    increasingly unlimited desires of the reaching child. If “More! More! is
                    the cry of a mistaken soul” and “less than All cannot satisfy
                    man” (<hi rend="i">No Natural Religion</hi>, 7b), the child as he stands is
                    no better off than the reachers of <hi rend="i">No Natural Religion</hi>, 7b;
                    but as the numerically comparable plate 7a vividly suggests, that
                    “All” is the imagination that produces “the spiritual music
                    rising from the pipe of the musician” (<hi rend="i">IB</hi>, 29). In plate
                    8a, then, the swan <hi rend="i">will</hi> rise and fly freely (not, I think,
                    reined) as the Renaissance’s Poesia or Blakean prophecy in precisely the
                    same way as the mind-forged-manacled man of <hi rend="i">No Natural
                        Religion</hi> 8b rises from the morass in plate 9b. It is quite possible, of
                    course, that such a “retrospective” reading of this earliest of all
                    Blake’s swans, from the perspective of <hi rend="i">America</hi> and the
                    Gray illustrations, is an over-reading, but the nature of the prophetic tracts,
                    along with the earlier allusions to “Phebus” and Pindar in <hi rend="i">An Island in
the Moon</hi> at least allow the possibility. In this
                    light Erdman must be correct about “The Little Boy lost” plate in
                    saying that the swan there, also floating behind (or in) the “y” of
                    “Boy” in the title, is a “fitter object for boy with outstretched
                    arms [precisely, one might add, in the same striding position as the <hi rend="i">No
Natural Religion</hi> boy—though he moves <hi rend="i">toward</hi> the swan and is, importantly, unclad] to
pursue . . . ”
                        (<hi rend="i">IB</hi>, 54). And “The Little Boy lost” is, of
                    course, also a poem about erroneous perception. In both cases, then, it seems
                    proper to identify the swans, not with desire itself, but rather with the
                    prophetic, visionary, imaginative perception and art that is the product of
                    desire, and the child as the incipient poet who will not ride the swan but, like
                    Orpheus or Pindar, become it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48"
type="note">17</ref>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">17</hi> In <hi rend="i">IB</hi> Erdman indexes a
                        number of other possible swans in the <hi rend="i">Songs, The Marriage</hi>,
                        and <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, some of these, at least, suggesting a
                        confusion in his mind (or eye) between his bird of paradise (the
                        imagination, often accompanying the birds of the five senses) and swans.
                        Perhaps Blake’s lack of discrimination, or etched definition, here is
                        intentional? In any case, it is probably safe to say that flying swans are
                        “better” than floating ones.</note></p>
        <p>I pass over <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 71 here as a clear anti-swan image,
                    bat-winged and not only firmly planted (apparently on the ground) but even
                    grovelling ridiculously and “fatuously kissing or nibbling at the
                    toes” of the Leda-like Vala (<hi rend="i">IB</hi>, 350). If she puts on his
                    knowledge with his power (both of which seem calculatedly absent in
                    Blake’s satiric portrait of the spectrous swan), both will eventuate in
                    the maze of error, prophecy become labyrinthine mystery, emanating from the
                    Vala-like figure’s head. But we cannot pass over the most troublesome of
                    all Blake’s swans, the one in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 11.</p>
        <p>Most recently David Bindman, obviously unhappy with the Erdman reading I shall
                    turn to in a moment, advanced two other interpretations of plate 11
                    (Ovid’s King Cygnus legend and the swan as the River Severn), only to
                    argue persuasively against both.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49"
type="note">18</ref> I am less
                    sceptical about Erdman’s elaborate allegory of the swan as both singing
                    and etching the plate with its beak, complemented by the swimming-flying figure
                    at the bottom of the plate producing “infinite illumination”:
                    “Like the serpent of Hell [in plate 15 of <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>],
                    the serpent-necked swan projects lineation. Like the eagle, the feather-finned
                    skimmer adorns the surface with living colors (needing the spectral fins while
                    the colors are wet, the feathers for rising from illustration to
                        Illumination).”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50"
type="note">19</ref> Given the text of
                    the plate, there seems to me little doubt that Erdman is on the right track,
                    however much one may balk at his wrapping up all of the plate’s minute
                    particulars so tidily. Even so, I still have some problems with his reading.
                    While the design, as he notes, is one of only ten white-line etchings in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, the text is in Blake’s usual relief etching,
                    the contrary processes married. It doesn’t really matter, then, which
                    process the swan is engaged in. What is to the point are its bubbles (acid),
                    eating into the plate, and swimming-flying through it, corroding apparent
                    surfaces away to reveal the infinite that was hid. Part of the
                    “infinite” is the text itself, which we note is under water, that is,
                    within the plate on which the swan-prophet-graver sits. The rest of the infinite
                    is the text humanized, still streaming the acidic bubbles on wrists, neck, and
                    hair (or head-dress).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51"
type="note">20</ref> At the same time,
                    although Blake repeats in this lower design the lines of the water above to
                    remind us that the swimmer is within the plate, not merely “on” it,
                    the figure is also clearly flying, arms outstretched in a familiar Blakean
                    gesture of airy freedom. In a sense, then, this is the swan, now fully humanized
                    and in full flight, no longer merely floating (or planted) in the materials of
                    the artifice but assuming total mythographic status as poet-prophet-artist as
                    well 
<pb id="p15-167" n="167"/>
as poem-prophecy-art. The entire plate is thus
                    the Erin of the text, not merely the swimmer-flyer as Erdman suggests: “And
                    the Spaces of Erin reach’d from the starry heighth, to the starry
                    depth,” the spaces that are the enabling agency for the process that will
                    eventuate in the immediately following plates (12ff). It is, to borrow Angus
                    Fletcher’s terms, the prophetic moment, space and time (Los’s
                    “pulsations of time, &amp; extensions of space” during and in which
                    he performs his “sublime Labours”—<hi rend="i">J</hi>, 11:2 and
                    10:65). That the moment does not last the text tells us, as well as the parody
                    of this visionary creative activity that is imaged in the margin of plate
                    12—for “Around Golgonooza lies the land of death eternal; a Land /
                    Of pain and misery and despair and ever brooding melancholy” (13:30-31).
                    But the moment’s augury is too powerful to be denied: the embrace of
                    plate 99 will come. <note id="n49"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Bindman, <hi rend="i">Blake as an
Artist</hi>, p. 182. Erdman mentions Cygnus also, gingerly;
                        see <hi rend="i">IB</hi>, 290. Yeats predictably invokes
                        “Leda-Swan” (<hi rend="i">The Works of William Blake</hi>, ed.
                        Yeats and E. J. Ellis [London: Quaritch, 1893], II, 357).</note>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">19</hi><hi rend="i"> IB</hi>, 291. Erdman’s yoking of swan and eagle, albeit
                        qualified by his reference to the serpent, interestingly parallels
                        Gray’s “confusion” of Pindar as swan and eagle (see my note
                        8).</note>
	<note id="n51"><hi rend="s">20</hi> It would be nice, if perhaps foolish (though
                        his detailed recall of his own past work is astonishing), to think that
                        Blake here remembered a part of the “Phebus” passage in <hi rend="i">An Island in
the Moon</hi>: “ . . . in short every art
                        &amp; science adorn’d him [Apollo] as beads around his neck” (E
                        442). Is it possible that Blake knew any of the myths of swan-maidens, which
                        appear all over Europe and in Ireland (not, so far as I know, in England),
                        and which involve, among other characteristics in common, a magical necklace
                        as not merely a talisman of swan-womanhood but the agency of the
                        transformation? See Anna Louise Frey, <hi rend="i">The Swan-Knight
                            Legend</hi>, in <hi rend="i">Contributions to Education Published under
                            the Direction of George Peabody College for Teachers</hi>, No. 103
                        (Nashville, 1931). Ripa has an interesting Indian with headdress and beads
                        in his “America” emblem (<hi rend="i">Baroque and Rococo Pictorial
                            Imagery</hi>, ed. Edward A. Maser [New York: Dover, 1971], No. 105). In
                        any case, Aradobo and Obtuse Angle ignorantly confuse Phebus and Pharaoh,
                        and if Mrs. Sigtagatist chides them all for “making use of the names in
                        the Bible” (E 443), Blake did not hesitate to put the classical sun-god
                        in the Bible and, in the true Christian tradition, Christianize him into
                        Jesus Christ, the imagination, the archetypal Artist.</note></p>
        <p>Even if we accept the view of plate 11 that I have advanced, or some compromise
                    between it and Erdman’s, the sexes of both swan and swimmer-flyer, as
                    well as the Indian appearance of the latter still nag (on the Indian see my note
                    20). The safest answer is the one Erdman gives: “In their present
                    appearance both figures are androgynous, possibly nearer Eternity than Beulah,
                    possibly nearer Ulro” (<hi rend="i">IB</hi>, 291). Possibly. Damon sees
                    both as female, the swan “the Female Will,” the lower figure
                    “Inspiration (an Emanation),” and Yeats suggests “Leda-Swan”
                    for the one, “Vala, or America, as Oothoon, taking ‘her impetuous
                    course’ o’er Theotormon’s reign” for the other.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">21</ref> If indeed <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 71
                    recalls the Zeus-Leda myth, as it certainly seems to, can we arbitrarily ignore
                    that myth on plate 11 and invoke Horace and King Cygnus instead? I think not. I
                    have already indicated that Horace is a most unlikely and 
<corr type="emend">unapropos</corr> allusion,
                    and none of the three Cygnus stories told by Ovid has the remotest connection
                    with anything on this plate—not to mention, as Bindman reminds us, that
                    Cygnus was “indubitably male.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53"
type="note">22</ref>
                    If a simple spectre-emanation contrariety were all that Blake wanted, he surely
                    would have made that clearer. What, then, does the Ledean swan have to do with
                    the Orphic swan? <note id="n52"><hi rend="s">21</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake: His
Philosophy and Symbols</hi>, p. 469; Ellis
                        and Yeats, II, 357. In his admirable <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite
                            Art</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1978), W. J. T.
                        Mitchell argues a similar opposition between the two figures, the
                        “prophetic swan-woman versus the fashionable goldfish-woman” (p.
                        200), part of a pattern he sees throughout <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> of
                        contrasting female images, one “the naked, sexually liberated guide . .
                        . who leads humanity to the realm of imagination and forgiveness . . . and
                        the heavily clothed Vala-sibyl who keeps her subjects’ minds . . . on
                        mundane matters” (p. 199). Mitchell seems to have in mind
                        Blake’s goldfish in his designs to Gray, and it is certainly true
                        that plate 4 of “Ode on the Death of a Favourite Cat” includes two
                        figures reminiscent at least of the swimmer-flyer of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 11. I
see less thematic and iconic connection here,
                        though, than in Gray’s lines on the “Theban Eagle” Pindar
                        in “The Progress of Poesy” where he “sails” with
                        “supreme dominion / Thro’ the azure deep of air.” In any
                        case, given the entire text and design, I cannot regard the two figures in
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 11 as opposed to each other.</note>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">22</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake as an Artist</hi>, p. 182.</note></p>
        <p>Let us go back to Cygnus for a moment. There is an interesting connection between
                    the Leda-Swan story and Cygnus in that both have reference to the Trojan War. In
                    Book XII of the <hi rend="i">Metamorphoses</hi> Achilles, in the height of the
                    battle for Troy, seeks out Cygnus, who unknown to Achilles, has been made
                    invulnerable to spear and sword by his father Neptune. Achilles finally corners
                    him, however, pressing him against a rock, then throws him down and, kneeling on
                    his ribs, strangles Cygnus with the thongs of his own helmet. It is at that
                    moment that Neptune transforms Cygnus into a swan. As I indicated earlier, it
                    seems ridiculous to associate <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 11 with this bloody
                    story, but the collocation of Leda (who, we should recall, became Nemesis after
                    her rape), Zeus-swan, the Trojan War, Achilles, and Cygnus-swan is difficult to
                    ignore entirely. However circuitous a route this is into Blake’s
                    conception on plate 11 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, that plate does
                    immediately precede the building of Golgonooza (as opposed to the destruction of
                    Troy), the “realizing” of true prophecy as opposed to the bloody
                    realization of “all human history flowing from” the false prophecy
                    inherent in Leda’s rape.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54"
type="note">23</ref> Although
                    the union of Zeus and Leda would seem to be especially apropos in light of
                    Blake’s woman-swan, then, its applicability, if any, must lie in his
                    transformation of Bromion-like tyranny and its consequent vengeful
                    destructiveness into the productive union of divine and human as the
                    artist-builder. Blake was not unacquainted with Homer, as we know. His antipathy
                    to the “Classics . . . that Desolate Europe with Wars” erupts angrily
                    in the 1820 etching “On Homer’s Poetry &amp; On Virgil”: 
					<q>
                        Sacred Truth has pronounced that Greece &amp; Rome as Babylon &amp; Egypt:
                        so far from being parents of Arts &amp; Sciences as they pretend: were
                        destroyers of all Art. Homer Virgil &amp; Ovid confirm this opinion. . .
                        .<lb/>
 Rome &amp; Greece swept Art into their maw &amp; destroyd it. . . .
                        Grecian is Mathematic Form Gothic is Living Form. . . .<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">24</ref></q>
Such living form is what the swan of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 11
                    creates, the product of a “redeemed” Leda-Swan / Los-Enitharmon being
                    not war but the corrosive spirit that burns away the apparent surfaces of
                    history to reveal the infinite “Nature of Eternal Things . . . All
                    Springing from the Divine Humanity” (<hi rend="i">A Vision of the Last
                        Judgment</hi>, E 551); for 
						<q> All things acted on Earth are seen in the
                        bright Sculptures of<lb/>
 Los’s Halls &amp; every Age renews its
                        powers from these Works<lb/>
 With every pathetic story possible to happen
                        from Hate or<lb/>
 Wayward Love &amp; every sorrow &amp; distress is carved
                        here<lb/>
 Every Affinity of Parents Marriages &amp; Friendships are
                        here<lb/>
 In all their various combinations wrought with wondrous Art<lb/>
                        All that can happen to Man in his pilgrimage of seventy years<lb/>
 Such is
                        the Divine Written Law of Horeb &amp; Sinai:<lb/>
 And such the Holy Gospel
                        of Mount Olivet &amp; Calvary (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 16:61-69) </q>
                    With no mention of Leda anywhere in Blake’s works, however, we may still
                    rest discontented with this sort of Blakean transformation of the
                    “classics” and the “detestable Gods of Priam” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
14:15)—though it is worth recalling here that in such
                    influential emblem books as Ripa’s <hi rend="i">Iconologia</hi> and
                    Christophorus Giarda’s <hi rend="i">Icones symbolicae</hi>, Poesy (or
                    Poesia) is almost always a female figure, holding a lyre in one hand and a
                    plectrum in the other, with a white swan attendant.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">25</ref>
	<note id="n54"><hi rend="s">23</hi> Raine, II, 306.</note>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">24</hi> E 267. Such sentiments are found in Blake as
                        early as <hi rend="i">King Edward the Third</hi>; see especially its sixth
                        scene (E 428-30). We should also recall his condemnation of Jupiter as
                        “the enemy of conjugal love . . . an iron-hearted tyrant, the ruiner of
                        ancient Greece,” a “spectrous Fiend,” and “the ruin of
                        my labours” (letter to Hayley, 23 October 1804, E 702); also <hi rend="i">The
Laocoön</hi> plate and the half-dozen references in
                        his works to the “Gods of Priam.”</note>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">25</hi> Clements, “Iconography . . . ,” p.
                        782. According to A. and B. Rees’s <hi rend="i">Celtic Heritage</hi>
                        (1961), “swan” was frequently used in both Irish and Greek
                        literature as a metaphor for “girl” (noted in the very beautiful
                        book, <hi rend="i">The Swans</hi>, ed. Peter Scott [Boston: Houghton
                        Mifflin, 1972], p. 155; see also the entire essay, “The Swan in
                        Mythology and Art” by Mary Evans and Andrew Dawnay, included in this
                        book).</note></p>
        <p>One final suggestion about Blake’s swans, one that may have some bearing,
                    particularly, on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 11: Spenser’s <hi rend="i">Ruines of
Time</hi>—which I have already suggested Blake knew
                        well<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">26</ref> and
which includes allusions to
                    “fair Ledaes warlick twinnes” (1.386), Orpheus and Eurydice
                    (11.391-92), and the immortality of art, which laments the ruin of
                    “Verlame,” and which is an elegy on the death of
                    Sidney—concludes with six verbal emblems, the first two of which may have
                    some relationship to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 11. The first of these is
                    Sidney as a swan floating 
<pb id="p15-168" n="168"/>
down the Thames and sweetly
                    singing “the prophecie / Of his owne death in dolefull Elegie,” after
                    which 
					<q> With loftie flight aboue the earth he bounded,<lb/>
 And out of sight
                        to highest heauen mounted:<lb/>
 Where now he is become an heauenly
                        signe.<lb/>
 (11.599-602) </q>
Similarly constellated is the Orphean harp of
                    the second emblem: 
					<q> Whilest thus I looked, loe adowne the <hi rend="i">Lee</hi>,<lb/>
 I sawe an Harpe stroong all with silver twyne,<lb/>
 And
                        made of golde and costlie yuorie,<lb/>
 Swimming, that whilome seemed to haue
                        been<lb/>
 The harpe, on which <hi rend="i">Dan Orpheus</hi> was seene<lb/>
                        Wylde beasts and forrests after him to lead,<lb/>
 But was th’Harpe of
                            <hi rend="i">Philisides</hi> now dead.<lb/>
<lb/>
 At length out of the
                        Riuer it was reard<lb/>
 And borne aboue the cloudes to be diuin’d. .
                        . .<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">27</ref>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">26</hi> “Blake’s ‘I Saw a Chapel
                            All of Gold,’” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi>, 15
                            (1979), 37-47.</note>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">27</hi> L1. 603-11. Ovid has the waters of
                            Hebrus receive Orpheus’ dismembered head and lyre and, as both
                            floated down midstream, “The lyre uttered a plaintive melody and
                            the lifeless tongue made a piteous murmur” (<hi rend="i">The
                                “Metamorphoses” of Ovid</hi>, trans. Mary M. Innes
                            [Baltimore: Penguin, 1955], Book XI, p. 247).</note></q>
Even if the swan here is
indubitably as male as Cygnus (was Blake
                    conflating the indubitably female swans of the <hi rend="i">Prothalamion</hi>
                    with this one?), the context of <hi rend="i">The Ruines of Time</hi> is
                    marvellously apt—for, as we know, “The Ruins of Time builds Mansions
                    in Eternity” (E 678), precisely what swan-flyer-swimmer, Los-Enitharmon,
                    Sidney-swan, Orpheus-harp, and Blake all demonstrate in their own respective
                    ways. In his youth Blake, imitating Spenser, called upon these detestable gods
                    of Priam—Apollo, Mercury, Jove, and Pallas Athena—but it did not
                    take him long to recognize that pantheon’s dead-endedness and to take
                    flight, in his own transmutation of part of that pantheon, as a swan. 
                </p>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p15-169" n="169" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
