<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.4.bogan</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake’s Jupiter Olympius in Rees’ Cyclopaedia</title>
        <author n="Bogan">James Bogan</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>George Hartley</name>
              <name>Cathy Christman</name>
              <resp>Typist</resp>
              <name>Denise Warren</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Hazard Adams</name>
              <name>James Bogan</name>
              <name>Gavin Edwards</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Randel Helms</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Janice Lyle</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Gerda Norvig</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
      <pb id="p15-156" n="156"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-4-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">BLAKE’S JUPITER OLYMPIUS IN REES’ CYCLOPAEDIA</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">JAMES</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">BOGAN</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>From 1804 until 1820 Blake worked on his illustrated epic poem 
            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> During those same years Abraham Rees, a learned divine, was in charge
          of compiling <hi rend="i">The Cyclopaedia; Or, Universal Dictionary of Arts, Sciences, and
            Literature.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> A major
English encyclopedia was
          needed in “this period of illumination and general enquiry,” as Rees stated in the
          Prospectus directed “To the Public.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref> The thirty-nine
          volume <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia</hi> was to surpass the Edinburgh-based 
            <hi rend="i">Brittannica</hi>, which was in its ten-volume fifth edition.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3"
            type="note">3</ref> As for the compendious work of the French Encyclopedists, the
          following notice from the “Domestic Occurrences” columns of <hi rend="i">Gentleman’s
            Magazine</hi> indicates the feelings of the encyclopaedia-buying public: “The Earl of
          Exeter expunged from his large and well-selected library, and burnt, the works of
          Voltaire, Rousseau, Bolingbroke, Raynal, and that grand arsenal of impiety, the French
            Encyclopedia.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi>
            London: Longmans, 1819.</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> “Dr. Rees’ New
            Cyclopaedia” (London, 1801). Copy courtesy of the University of Reading Library
            Archives.</note>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Robert Collison, 
              <hi rend="i">Encyclopedias</hi> (New York: Hafner, 1964), p. 141.</note>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> (August, 1798), LXVII, 718.</note></p>
        <p>Rees was assisted in his worthy project for the edification of “intelligent and esteemed
            subscribers”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> by
“EMINENT PROFESSIONAL GENTLEMEN” and
          “THE MOST DISTINGUISHED ARTISTS.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref> The contributors
          were mainly Londoners, many of them drawn from the ranks of the Royal Academy and Royal
          Society and several of whom played significant roles in Blake’s life. Sir Humphrey Davy
          was called on to provide the articles on Chemistry. John Bonny-castle, a friend of Henry
          Fuseli, wrote some of the Astronomy sections. The musicologist, Sir Charles Burney, did
          not refrain from including a facsimile of a hand-written score from Rousseau—his
          counterpart for the <hi rend="i">Encyclopedie.</hi> Major Moor, whose illustrated 
            <hi rend="i">Hindu Pantheon</hi> Blake was familiar with, wrote on Indian Mythology. Mr.
          Mushett was the authority on blast furnaces, yet he mentions not a word about the
          blacksmith Los. Benjamin Malkin, a friend and sometime employer of Blake, wrote a few of
          the biographical articles for which the <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia</hi> was specially
            noted.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> The articles on
painting were prepared by
          Thomas Phillips, who once had Blake sit for the portrait included in the illustrations to
          Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi> Blake’s old friend John Flaxman contributed articles
          on “Beauty,” “Basso Relievo,” “Armour,” and a book-length treatise on “Sculpture,”
which
          was an extensive amplification of his “Lectures” at the Royal Academy. Among the engravers
          who made plates for the <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia</hi> were Wilson Lowry, James Parker,
          Blake’s one-time business partner, and Robert Cromek, his nemesis in the publishing world.
            <note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> “Preface,” <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia</hi> (London:
            Longmans, 1819), I, viii.</note>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> <hi rend="i">
              Ibid.</hi>, title page.</note>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Alexander Gordon,
            “Rees, Abraham,” DNB (1896).</note></p>
        <p>Blake himself was to join in the work on Rees’ <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia</hi> with this
          “eminent” and “distinguished” company of men. At a time when Blake was living in poverty
          and obscurity, John Flaxman steered an occasional job his way. They were not always very
          satisfactory opportunities for one of the geniuses of the age, but engraving a “butter
          boat” for Josiah Wedgwood’s catalogue did out some food in the larder and porter on the
            table.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> In 1815 Flaxman
enlisted Blake to do the
          engravings for his “Sculpture” article, and also for “Armour,” “Basso Relievo,” and
“Gem
            Engraving.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> The four
plates of the engravings for
          “Sculpture” include the old standards of Greek statuary: the Apollo Belvedere, the Medici
          Venus, the Knidian Aphrodite of Praxiteles, the Hercules Farnese, Jupiter Olympius the
          Athena Parthenos of Phidias, the Laocoön, and 
<pb id="p15-157" n="157"/>
others (illus.
          1). Also represented is a statue of Durga drawn from Moor’s <hi rend="i">Hindu
            Pantheon</hi>, an Etruscan Patera, a colossal statue at Thebes, a droll Chinese statue,
          and two examples of Persian sculpture from Persepolis. The plates in Rees are mere
          copywork, with perhaps one exception, the Jupiter Olympius, which stands out among the
          collection of gods, goddesses, and heroes. This stipple engraving of Jupiter is more
          concentrated, inventive, and minutely detailed than the rest, including the Laocoön which
          is certainly fainter by comparison.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n8"><hi
              rend="s">8</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon
            Press, 1969), p. 240.</note>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., 
              <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1978), #489.</note>	
              <note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> The two most extensive treatments of Blake’s use of
sculpture
            are to be found in Stephen Larrabee’s <hi rend="i">English Bards and Grecian
              Marbles</hi> (New York: Columbia University Press, 1943) pp. 99-119, and Morton
            Paley’s “‘Wonderful Originals’—Blake and Ancient Sculpture” in <hi rend="i">Blake in
His
              Time</hi>, ed. Robert Essick and Donald Pearce (Bloomington: Indiana University Press,
            1978), pp. 170-97.</note></p>
        <p>Before treating Blake’s representation of the Jupiter Olympius, some background on the
          statue itself and its place in the history of art will provide a context for Blake’s work.
          Phidias’ statue of Zeus in the Temple at Elis, the site of the Olympic games, was one of
          the seven wonders of the ancient world. Strabo reports that when asked “after what model
          he was going to make the likeness of Zeus, [Phidias] replied that he was going to make it
          after the likeness set forth by Homer in these words: ‘Cronion spake, and nodded assent
          with dark brows, and then the ambrosial locks flowed streaming from the lord’s immortal
          head, and he caused great Olympus to quake’ (<hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> I. 528)” 
            (<hi rend="i">Geography</hi> viii. 3.30). John Flaxman describes the statue this way in his
            <hi rend="i">Lectures</hi>:
<q> But the great work of this chief of sculptors, the
            astonishment and praise of after ages, was the Jupiter at Elis, sitting on his throne,
            his left hand holding a scepter, his right extending victory to the Olympian conquerors,
            his head crowned with olive, and his pallium decorated with birds, beasts, and flowers.
            The four corners of the throne were dancing victories, each supported by a sphinx,
            tearing a Theban youth. At the back of the throne, above his head, were the three hours
            or seasons on one side, and on the other the three graces. On the bar between the legs
            of the throne, and the panels or spaces between them were represented many stories. . .
            . On the base the battle of Theseus with the Amazons; on the pedestal, an assembly of
            the gods, the sun and moon in their cars, and the birth of Venus. The height of the work
            was sixty feet. The statue was ivory, enriched with the radiance of golden ornaments and
            precious stones.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> (illus.
2) 
                <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> The account is based on Pausanias’ 
<hi rend="i">Description of
                Greece</hi> (v. 11.1-9). John Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Lectures on Sculpture</hi>
              (London, 1838), pp. 89-90.</note></q></p>
        <p>Prodigies were associated with the statue from the beginning. In his 
            <hi rend="i">Description of Greece</hi>, Pausanias relates “that the god himself evinced his
          approbation of the art of Phidias; for, as soon as the statue was finished, Phidias prayed
          to Jupiter, and entreated him to signify if the work was pleasing to his divinity; and
          immediately after he prayed, they say, that part of the pavement was struck by 
          <figure n="BB489.1.4.COM" rend="file" width="350" height="468">
            <head>1 Rees <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia.</hi></head>
            <figDesc>“Sculpture,” Plate I.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <figure n="BB489.1.4.COM.detail-jupiter" rend="file" width="350" height="568">
            <head>2 “Jupiter Olympius.”</head>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p15-158" n="158"/> 
          lightning.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> Martin
          Robertson notes that “the floor in front was paved with black marble and there was a
          reflecting pool of oil that not only served to preserve the ivory but to cast light up on
          and reflect the figure.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref>
The seated figure filled
          the space, his lofty head almost touching the ceiling. Imagine the effect on a suppliant
          when the towering statue doubled in an eerie light! The effect was to induce a state of
          religious awe attested to by Dio Chrysostom, for one: 
		<q> O best and noblest of artists,
            how charming and pleasing a  <corr type="emend">spectacle</corr> you have wrought, and a vision of infinite delight
            for the benefit of all men, both Greeks and barbarians, who have ever come here, as they
            have come in great throngs and time after time, no one will gainsay . . . . Whoever is
            sore distressed in soul, having in the course of his life drained the cup of many
            misfortunes and griefs, nor ever winning sweet sleep—even this man, methinks, if he
            stood before this image, would forget all the terrors and hardships that fall to our
            human lot. Such a wondrous vision did you devise and fashion, one in very truth a<lb/>
            “Charmer of grief and anger, that from men All the remembrance of their ills could
            loose!”<lb/>
 So great the radiance and so great the charm with which your art has
            clothed it.<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">Discourses</hi> XII; 51-52) </q>
	<note id="n12"><hi
              rend="s">12</hi> Pausanias, <hi rend="i">The Description of Greece</hi>, trans. Thomas
            Taylor (London, 1824), I, 29.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> <hi rend="i">A
              History of Greek Art</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1975), I,
            317.</note></p>
        <p>The statue itself had a curious history. For six centuries it remained at Elis, revered
          by Greeks, Romans, and barbarians alike, such was its universal power. Caligula attempted
          to have the statue carried off to Rome to adorn the imperial city, but Suetonius reports
          that the statue “suddenly uttered such a peal of laughter that the scaffoldings collapsed
          and the workmen took to their heels” (<hi rend="i">The Lives of the Caesars</hi>, IV, 57).
          The Emperor Theodosius was more successful in plundering the temple. In 373 A. D. he
          abolished the Olympic Games and profaned the temple of Zeus when he had the
          chryselephantine statue expropriated to New Rome (Constantinople).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
            type="note">14</ref> There it joined in captivity the Knidian Aphrodite of Praxiteles,
          the Eros of Mindos by Lysippus, and many other masterpieces by Greek artists. A quote from
          Blake’s “On Virgil” makes apt comment here: “A war-like State never can produce Art. It
          will Rob &amp; Plunder &amp; accumulate into one place &amp; Translate &amp; Copy &amp;
          Buy &amp; Sell &amp; Criticise, but not Make.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n15" type="note">15</ref> The
          fire at the library of Alexandria was one of the seven catastrophes of the ancient world;
          another was the great fire at Constantinople in 475, which destroyed the Palace of Lausos.
          Thousands of works of art were irrevocably lost in the disaster, including the Zeus and
          other works by Phidias, Praxiteles, and Lysippus.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n16" type="note">16</ref> No
          detailed copies of the Zeus remained, though dim one-dimensional likenesses on coins and
          some gem engravings do survive.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">17</ref>
	<note id="n14"><hi
              rend="s">14</hi> Enno Fraxius, <hi rend="i">A History of the Byzantine Empire</hi>
            (New York: Funk &amp; Wagnalls, 1967), p. 43.</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake: Complete Writings</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes (London:
            Oxford University Press, 1974), p. 798. Subsequent references to this edition appear in
            the text.</note>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Georgius Cedrenus, 
              <hi rend="i">Historiarun Compendium</hi>, 322C, Vol. I, p. 564 (<hi rend="i">Corpus Scriptorum
              Historiae Byzantinae</hi>, Vol. 34).</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> See G.
            M. A. Richter, <hi rend="i">The Sculpture and Sculptors of the Greeks</hi> (New Haven
            and London: Yale Univ. Press, 1970), figs. 647-53.</note></p>
        <p>In Blake’s era Phidias and his Olympian Zeus were highly esteemed. Winckelmann in his 
            <hi rend="i">Reflexions on the Painting and Sculpture of the Greeks</hi>, translated by
          Fuseli, gives the highest place to Phidias: “The Zeus of Phidias was the standard of
          sublimity, the symbol of the omnipresent Deity, like Homer’s Eris, he stood upon the
          earth, and reached heaven.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">18</ref> In Joseph Spence’s 
            <hi rend="i">Polymetis</hi> (1747) is this passage on the Jupiter: “The superiority of
          Jupiter . . . was in that air of majesty which the ancient artists endeavoured to express
          in his countenance. If some of the nobler statues of Jupiter, as that of Jupiter Olympus
          made by Phidias, in particular, had remained to our times; we might see this more strongly
          at present; for that was reckoned the master-piece of the greatest statuary that ever was;
          and those who beheld it are said to have been astonished at the greatness of ideas in
            it.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref> The desire to
have had a glimpse of the
          original is clear. <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> (London, 1765), p. 148.</note>	
            <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Spence, p. 51.</note></p>
        <p>Though Blake took exception to the uninspired opinions of his patron William Hayley, he
          would not have quarreled with the gentleman’s estimation of Phidias. Hayley had finished
          his <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi> just before Blake came to work for him in 1800.
          In lock-step heroic couplets he describes how he is taken “in vision” to see the Zeus;
          then he addressed Phidias: 
		<q> All vouch thy fame, though not in speech—<lb/>
 Thine, the
            prime glory pagan minds could reach—<lb/>
 Thine, to have form’d, in superstition’s
            hour,<lb/>
 The noblest semblance of celestial power!<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20"
type="note">20</ref>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Hayley, p. 55.</note></q>
Blake himself
          thought Phidias ranked with Homer and Socrates (<hi rend="i">Anno Watson</hi>, K 388).</p>
        <p>In 1800 John Flaxman was the “Happy son of the immortal Phidias” to Blake (Letters, K
          807). Flaxman’s thoughts on his spiritual father are giver in the “Sculpture” article in
          Rees’ <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia</hi>: “Superior genius, in addition to a knowledge of
          painting, which he practiced before sculpture, gave a grandeur to his compositions, a
          grace to his groups, a softness to flesh, and a flow to draperies, unknown to his
          predecessors . . . . The discourse of contemporary philosophers on mental and personal
          perfection assisted him in selecting and combining ideas, which stamped his work with the
          sublime and beautiful of Homer’s verse. . . . The great work of the great master, the
          astonishment and praise of after ages, was the Jupiter at Elis.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21"
            type="note">21</ref> From ancient commentary to Blake’s own friends the preeminence and
          power of Phidias were celebrated, and in 1815 Blake got the chance to turn praise into a
          picture. <note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Abraham Rees, <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia</hi>
            (London: Longmans, 1819), XXXII, not paginated.</note></p>
        <p>The Olympian Jupiter was one of the statues to be engraved for the Sculpture plates in
          Rees’ <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia.</hi> Blake engraved the plate, but it is not entirely
          clear whether it was Blake, Flaxman, or the two together who worked out the design of the
          picture. Spence outlines the problem facing the artist: “It is a great pity that we have
          no better figures of Jupiter . . . they fall short even of the idea one can form of a
          Jupiter in one’s own mind, by the help of ancient poets, and infinitely short of the
          celebrated Jupiter made by Phidias.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
type="note">22</ref> Here was a
          chance to create a likeness of Jupiter and in a way “to renew the lost Art of the Greeks,”
          a one-time ambition of Blake (Letters, K 792). <note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Spence,
            p. 46.</note></p>
        <pb id="p15-159" n="159"/>
        <figure n="SpenceJupiter.15.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="486">
          <head>3 “Jupiter,” from Joseph Spence, <hi rend="i">Polymetis.</hi></head>
        </figure>
        <p>In addition to the imaginative powers of the designer, there were other sources for the
          engraving: traditional representations of Jupiter, the Hellenistic statue of Jupiter in
          Marbury Hall, and a literary description in the writings of Pausanias. The engraving in
          the <hi rend="i">Polymetis</hi> exemplifies the standard iconography associated with
          Jupiter (illus. 3). In the Marbury Hall Zeus we have a likely model for the basic
          attitudes of the Jupiter in Rees (illus 4). The torso, beard, and especially the pallium
          are similar, though the body is more symmetrically arranged in Blake.</p>
        <p>For the fine detail in the engraving, we are directed to “See Pausanias,” whose 
            <hi rend="i">Description of Greece</hi> contains a minutely detailed verbal portrait of the
          famed statue. The engraving follows almost verbatim the description, of which Flaxman
          quotes the relevant sections in his Sculpture article. In giving Pausanias’ account I have
          added a [Y]-yes- and an [N]-no-to indicate whether the engraving follows the description.
          As the picture is black and white/two-dimensional, some qualities of the sculpture do not
          apply: “The god is seated upon his throne [Y], made of gold and ivory, a crown of olive
          branch on his head [Y], in his right hand bearing a Victory [Y], also of ivory and gold;
          she bears a fillet, and is crowned [Y-but the olive crown is in her right hand]; the left
          hand of the <figure n="MarburyZeus.15.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="257" height="493">
            <head>4 Marbury Hall Zeus, courtesy of the J. Paul Getty Museum, Malibu,
              California.</head>
          </figure> god holds a sceptre of various coloured metals [Y]; an eagle of gold sitting
          upon the sceptre [Y]; his garment is of gold, and on his garment are wrought animals and
          flowers, particularly the lily [N<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23"
type="note">23</ref>]; his sandals are
          of gold; the throne is variously ornamented with gold and gems, and also ivory and ebony:
          on it animals are painted in their proper colours, and sculptured with great labour [These
          pictures on the sides and back of the work are not shown in the frontal view of the
          engraving]. Four victories, as in the dance, are on the hinder feet on the throne, two on
          each side [Y-two of the four are brought forward]; and on the front the children of the
          Thebans taken away by the sphynx [Y] . . . . [Pausanias goes on to describe numerous
          scenes that surround the statue but are not included in the engraving]. Upon the throne,
          above the head of the god, Phidias carved the Graces and the Hours [Y]. 
            <pb id="p15-160" n="160"/>
Three of them large; these are called daughters of Jove. [Three of
these
          Graces form the outer ring of the halo-arch over Jupiter’s head. Two, though there should
          be three, cherubs make the inner ring].” It is evident that the engraving is based on this
          description, but as to the character and expression of the Jupiter there is more to say.
            <note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> This detail is followed in Flaxman’s designs to the
              <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi>, (London, 1805), plate 5.</note></p>
        <p>A quote from Homer that Phidias did not note as a source of his inspiration still
          felicitously describes this Jupiter: “He, whose all-conscious Eyes the World behold, / Th’
          Eternal Thunderer, sate thron’d in Gold” (<hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> VIII, 550-51).<ref
            target="n24" type="note">24</ref> The face radiates omniscience and the symmetrical
          features indicate harmony. The heroic torso, firmly-set feet, and symbols of power all
          combine to picture majesty of character. Even the beard contributes to the effect. Spence
          comments on this point: “What is nobler than the long beard in Michaelangelo’s Moses? A
          full beard surely may give majesty as well as a long one, and you see, in effect, how much
          it gives . . . . to the heads of the Greek Jupiters . . . . A full beard still carries the
          idea of majesty with it, all over the East; which it may possibly have had ever since the
          times of the patriarchal government there. The Grecians had a share of the oriental notion
          of it.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref> Power inhabits
the Jupiter from the head,
          with its flame-like laurel wreath, to the feet where the redoubtable Sphinxes are
          stationed like obedient guards. <note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Alexander Pope’s
            translation.</note>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi> Spence, p. 52.</note></p>
        <figure n="BB489.1.4.COM.detail-pedestal" rend="file" width="600" height="208"/>
        <figure n="pedestal-key.15.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="216">
          <figTranscr>1 9 10 11 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 12 13
          (NEILL FLEEMAN SCULPSIT)</figTranscr>
          <head>5 “Jupiter Olympius” pedestal and key to pedestal as follows: (1) Sun, (2) Juno, (3)
            Jupiter, (4-5-6) The Three Graces, (7) Hermes, (8) Vesta, (9) Love (Cupid), (10) Venus,
            (11) Persuasion, (12) Moon, (13) Neptune.</head>
        </figure>
        <p>Still there is not much sign of the wrathful, terrible thunderer in this picture. Spence
          explains how the benevolent aspect befits this deity: 
		<q> Among the different characters
            of Jupiter, I think I have mentioned to you those of the Mild and of the Terrible
            Jupiter . . . Mild Jupiter’s face has a mixture of dignity and ease in it. That serene
            and sweeter kind of majesty . . . The statues of the Terrible Jupiter were represented
            in every particular differently from those of the Mild Jupiters. These were generally of
            black marble, as those were of white. The one is sitting with an air of tranquility; the
            other, is standing and more or less disturbed. The face of one, is pacific and serene;
            of the other angry or clouded. On the heads of one, the hair is regular and composed; in
            the other, it is so discomposed that it falls half-way down the forehead.<ref
              target="n26" type="note">26</ref>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> <hi rend="i">
                Ibid.</hi></note></q>
	<pb id="p15-161" n="161"/>
The “Terrible Jupiters” have distant
          cousins in the truculent demons that guard the gates of many Hindu and Buddhist temples;
          but in this engraving we are certainly presented with a “Mild Jupiter.”</p>
        <p>The combination of strength and benevolence evident in the statue is further explicated
          from the glosses of Thomas Taylor: “‘Jupiter is seen holding a sceptre, and [winged]
          victory.’ Jupiter is every where called by Homer . . . ‘the father of gods and men, ruler
          and king, and the supreme of rulers . . . ’ On account, therefore, of his 
            <hi rend="i">commanding</hi> or <hi rend="i">ruling</hi> characteristic, he is very properly
          represented with a sceptre, which is certainly an obvious symbol of command. The symbol of
          victory likewise justly belongs to him, on account of his all-subduing power, which
          vanquishes all mundane opposition, and causes the war of the universe to terminate in
            peace.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref> Hayley
declaimed the virtues of the
          peace-bestower in his <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>:
<q> Lo, in calm pomp, with
            Art’s profusion bright<lb/>
 Whose blended glories fascinate the sight,<lb/>
 Sits the
            dread power! Around his awful head<lb/>
 The sacred foliage of the olive spread,<lb/>
            Declares that in his sovereign mind alone<lb/>
 Peace ever shines, and has forever
              shone.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">28</ref>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">28</hi>
              Hayley, p. 53.</note></q>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> In the commentary to
            Pausanias, III, 193.</note></p>
        <p>The divine nature of the subject is emphasized by the arrangement of Graces and Seasons
          about Jupiter’s head. The halo-effect of the attending Graces and Seasons is 
            <hi rend="i">not</hi> accounted for in Pausanias; in fact he mentions that they are disposed to
the
          right and left of Jupiter’s head. Haloes around the heads of pagan gods are found
          elsewhere in eighteenth and nineteenth century art,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n29" type="note">29</ref>
          but the effect in this picture certainly contributes to the portrayal of Jupiter as a
          Prince of Peace. This Jupiter is neither a despotic Greek god nor a tyrannical Urizen.
          Blake himself says forthrightly: “Consider that the Venus, the Minerva, the Jupiter, the
          Apollo . . . are all of them representations of spiritual existences, of Gods immortal to
          the mortal perishing organ of sight; and yet they are embodied and organized in solid
          marble” (<hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, K 576). A representation of celestial
          power has here been embodied and organized in dots of ink. 
              <note id="n29"><hi rend="s">29</hi> Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi>, plate 9, and 
<hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi>,
            plate 1, are two examples, the styles of which contrast with the halo in
          Rees.</note></p>
        <p>On the base of the Jupiter statue is a picture of a bas-relief in such minute detail as
          to call for a magnifying glass (illus. 5). The Lilliputian beings outlined in dots are a
          company of Olympian gods that appear more the size of fairies. Once again the artist has
          stayed close to the description in Pausanias, which allows us to identify the characters:
          “Upon the base of the throne, which great mass was wrought in gold, are other ornaments
          relating 
          <figure n="BlakeReesDrawing.15.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="424">
            <head>6 Blake’s drawing for Rees’ sculpture plate, courtesy of the Lessing J. Rosenwald
              Collection in the Library of Congress.</head>
          </figure>
          <figure n="FlaxmanJupiter.15.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="296" height="472">
            <head>7 “Jupiter Olympus” by John Flaxman.</head>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p15-162" n="162"/>
          to the god. The rising Sun in his chariot [1], and Jupiter [3]
          and Juno [2], and by them the Graces [4,5,6]; these lead Hermes [7], and Hermes Vesta [8].
          Cupid [9] also from the sea receiving Venus [10], who was crowned by Persuasion [11].
          Apollo was with Diana [Apollo is subsumed in the rising Sun and Diana with the Moon-12],
          and Minerva with Hercules [neither pictured]; and on the lowest part of all was Neptune,
          [13-Blake’s image here is in the attitude of the Capitoline Neptune], and the Moon [12] in
          her chariot urging on her horses.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30"
type="note">30</ref> A noteworthy
          improvisation from the description is the Sun driving his chariot led by a team of
          vigorous horses, while the Moon’s team grazes, thereby emphasizing the active/passive
          contraries of day and night. Hermes’ costume could almost make him a medieval jester.
          Besides being the guide of souls to the underworld, he is also the patron of tricksters.
            <note id="n30"><hi rend="s">30</hi><hi rend="i"> Cyclopaedia</hi>, “Sculpture,” not
            paginated.</note></p>
        <p>Finally there is the matter of who designed the “Jupiter Olympius” engraving. There is no
          identification of the designer on the plate itself. When Flaxman designed the “Basso
          Relievo” plate in 1804, he was credited with it and James Parker with the engraving.
          “Blake del[iniavit] et sc[ulpsit],” in Rees’ Plate III with the Laocoön tells us Blake
          drew the picture and engraved it. On Rees’ Plate I with the Jupiter simply appears “Blake
          sc.” He engraved the plate, but the designer is not mentioned. Blake did make a rather
          finished preliminary drawing of the whole page that Frederick Tatham described as
          “exquisite” (illus. 6).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
type="note">31</ref> Blake’s drawing of the page
          is not conclusive proof that he designed it, for he may have been working from a prior
          drawing by Flaxman. Still, the existence of the drawing makes it likely that he had a hand
          in the design, and two differences between the drawing and the final engraving itself make
          it even more likely: (1) In the bas-relief on the base Neptune is moved from the left
          foreground to the right. (2) The Moon-goddess is moved closer to Vesta and her right arm
          is raised. Blake probably made these changes as he understood the need to balance the
          groupings more effectively. <note id="n31"><hi rend="s">31</hi> With the Greek quotation
            translated, the text in Tatham’s hand reads: “The Glory round the Head of this superb
            Jove is composed of figures. That noble God-like head puts us in mind of these sublime
            lines from Homer. ‘Cronion spake and nodded assent with dark brows, and then the
            ambrosial locks flowed streaming from the lord’s immortal head, and he caused great
            Olympus to quake’ [<hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> I.528]. This exquisite Drawing is by William
            Blake-made &amp; afterwards Engraved for the Encyclopaedia for which Flaxman wrote the
            article on Sculpture. Frederick Tatham.” In Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings
              and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (New Haven and London: Yale Univ. Press, 1981),
            this drawing is 678A recto, pl. 896A; the verso is reproduced as pl. 897.</note></p>
        <p>If a design was provided it would most probably have been by Flaxman. When his 
            <hi rend="i">Lectures</hi> were published in 1838, <corr type="emend">sculpture</corr> plates from
his drawings were
          included. While there is a basic similarity in the two engravings of Jupiter, Flaxman’s
          picture of “Jupiter Olympus at Elis” (illus. 7) differs <hi rend="i">markedly</hi> from
          the Rees Jupiter: (1) The expression of the face and drawing of hair and beard are clearly
          different. (2) The eagle, sphinxes, and victims are more detailed. (3) There is no halo
          effect of Graces and Seasons. (4) The statue is placed in a temple setting with roof and
          walls. (5) The design of the bas-relief differs by being quite vague, and the Moon is
          driving a chariot pulled by two active horses. while Flaxman could have done another
          drawing, this Flaxman design was <hi rend="i">not</hi> the basis of the Rees
          engraving.</p>
        <p>The mild Jupiter that dwells in the dusty precincts of an outmoded household
          encyclopaedia reveals many elements of Greek religion and thought. Although Blake’s
          attitude towards the Greeks shifted from admiration to distrust between 1800 and 1815, his
          deft execution of the Jupiter Olympius engraving belies a dogmatic dismissal of Greek
          tradition. This miniature colossus invites contemplation by any who would like a glimpse
          of one of the sculptural wonders of the Golden Age.</p>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p15-163" n="163" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
