<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.4.norvig</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Milton Klonsky, William Blake: The Seer and His Visions</title>
        <author n="Norvig">Gerda S. Norvig</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>George Hartley</name>
              <name>Cathy Christman</name>
              <resp>Typist</resp>
              <name>Denise Warren</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Hazard Adams</name>
              <name>James Bogan</name>
              <name>Gavin Edwards</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Randel Helms</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Janice Lyle</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Gerda Norvig</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-4-0008">
        <pb id="p15-184" n="184"/>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Milton Klonsky. <hi rend="b">William Blake: The Seer and His
                                Visions.</hi> New York: Harmony Books, 1977. 142 pp. $12.95 cloth,
                            $7.95 paper.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Gerda S. <name>Norvig</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>One of the striking ironies of Blake scholarship over the last ten or fifteen
                        years is that so much of it unwittingly contradicts by the example of its
                        own style and method just the values in Blake’s vision it claims to
                        honor and expound. Perhaps this is a paradox that cannot be solved, however,
                        since clearly there is something in the very nature of the Blakean
                        enterprise that stubbornly mocks all efforts to write plainly about it,
                        something which seems equally to invite and to resist the sort of rational
                        discourse demanded of critical commentary.</p>
          <p>All of us have felt the dilemma. All of us have noted that the moment we try
                        to pin down our responses to the dynamics of Blake’s art, we find
                        ourselves falling into one of the postures of limited vision the work we are
                        looking at itself satirizes. No matter what tack we take—whether we
                        opt for interpretation or descriptive analysis, deconstruction or literary
                        historicism, cool objectivity or impressionistic enthusiasm—the
                        critic in us risks becoming a parody of the flexible pilgrim-reader Blake
                        ultimately addresses.</p>
          <p>No doubt this is all to the good and should be considered a necessary step in
                        the rite of reading orchestrated by Blake. For both the challenge and the
                        impossibility of finding an unearthly, Archimedian leverage point from which
                        to move the Blakean world is of course testimony to the remarkably vital
                        inclusiveness of this artist’s greater aesthetic. Still, it is useful
                        to recognize and beware the fact that like a warring Zoa, a “mistaken
                        Demon of heaven,” each of our critical approaches tends to create a
                        fixed and one-sided universe out of the Blakean material, thereby
                        distorting—often obliterating—the truly transformative
                        dimensions that characterize Blake’s best work.</p>
          <p>In the text accompanying the beautiful reproductions that make up the core of
                            <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Seer and his Visions</hi>, Milton
                        Klonsky tries bravely though unsuccessfully to avoid these common pitfalls
                        of the critical act. His strategy is to take many contradictory stances,
                        settling for no one coherent approach as he shifts uneasily among three of
                        the more extreme styles of Blake commentary: personal effusion, pedantic
                        source analysis, and the mechanical cross-referencing of familiar Blakean
                        motifs. He begins his twenty-four page introduction with a gentle poke at
                        the insular reader who has neither particularized nor personalized the
                        message of perceptual renovation that Blake’s texts carry. This
                        well-taken caveat, however, turns out to serve not as a way into Blake but
                        as a prelude to a trite and tedious account of Klonsky’s own
                        visionary experience while on a one-time LSD trip in the 1960s. Throughout
                        the description of his psychedelic conversion, itself sounding like an
                        unconscious parody of the fall of Tharmas, Klonsky loosely appropriates
                        mottos from <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>,
                        “Auguries of Innocence,” and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> to
                        substantiate his 
<pb id="p15-185" n="185"/>
touching and naive claim that he
                        has responded to Blake with an affinity of feeling Blake himself would have
                        approved of. And it is true that Klonsky does come to the artist’s
                        work in a spirit of congeniality, eager to “Enter into”
                        Blake’s symbols and to “make a Friend &amp; Companion” of
                        those “Images of wonder” as Blake recommends.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75" type="note">1</ref> However, like many others affected by the drug
                        culture who have flocked to Blake because of a vague spiritual longing and a
                        taste for hallucinogenic imagery, Klonsky too often ignores the harder part
                        of Blake’s advice to the spectator, that we should approach visionary
                        forms not just imagistically and emotionally but also “on the Fiery
                        Chariot of . . . Contemplative Thought” (<hi rend="i">VLJ</hi>, E 550).
                            <note id="n75"><hi rend="s">1</hi> “A Vision of the Last
                            Judgment,” <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>,
                            ed. David V. Erdman (New York, 1970), p. 550.</note></p>
          <p>The key word here is “contemplative.” For although Klonsky’s
                        text is full of little bypaths into arcane fields of thought, none of these
                        rarefied excurses is sufficiently grounded, contemplated or developed in its
                        own right, and few are demonstrably related to the Blakean themes, purposes,
                        instances they are supposed to illuminate. Instead the author presents a
                        patchwork of allusive lore and occult references from sources outside Blake,
                        while the thread of argument that would tie all these bits of learning
                        together is most often either frayed or forgotten.</p>
          <p>An example is Klonsky’s skewed and summary disquisition on the
                        esoteric system of the Hebrew <hi rend="i">Zohar</hi>, especially its
                        mystical teaching about the seventy “facets” and the six hundred
                        thousand “entrances” of the words of scripture. Here he justifies
                        a paragraph-long aside on Cabbalistic numerology by declaring (without any
                        proven or even claimed basis in fact) that Blake was acquainted
                        “perhaps at first hand” with that “most famous version of the
                        Cabbala.” He then hints in a round-about way that there is a causal
                        link between the Zoharian symbolism and Blake’s view of significant
                        form—an intriguing notion were it to be either elaborated or
                        substantiated. The entire burden of proof for such a link, however, is made
                        to rest on the shaky ground of a single quotation from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
describing the many angles of the grain of sand hidden
                        from Satan’s watchfiends. Evidently these angles, each a “lovely
                        heaven” in Blake’s words, are to be seen by us as equivalent to
                        the seventy facets of the holy words of scripture. Yet how so, and if so to
                        what end, is unfortunately not explained. Nevertheless we might accept the
                        analogy of Cabbalistic “facets” to Blakean “angles” if
                        the comparison were offered as a merely curious parallel. But Klonsky, by
                        innuendo and—as is his wont—equivocal phrasing, implies much
                        more. He implies that Blake both intended the reference and expected it to
                        be taken as a criticism of the Jewish source, for Klonsky writes that
                        “in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> the Cabbalistic vision of the
                        multiplicity of possible entrances into the infinite was refracted by Blake
                        and revealed in its ‘minute particularity.’”</p>
          <p>Here many readers of his book may pause to note that “refracting the
                        infinite” through clear exposition of “minute particularity”
                        is certainly not one of Klonsky’s own strong points. Indeed by mixing
                        and matching ideas lifted out of context, Klonsky regularly tries to force
                        untenable connections as he juggles the niceties of both metaphor and fact.
                        His habit is either to cloud the issue by providing an excess of information
                        so that his frequently dubious tenets are virtually lost in a sea of
                        incongruous data, or, when he does hit on a fruitful analogy (for instance
                        the comparison between Blake’s fourfold system of vision and the
                        traditional fourfold method of biblical interpretation), he makes the
                        opposite error, generalizing without supplying the descriptive detail or
                        conceptual framework that would lend his notion substance, validity,
                        credence.</p>
          <p>But it is not only the content of Klonsky’s prose that is affected by
                        this disquieting carelessness and lack of critical proportion. The style,
                        too, often suffers from such idiosyncrasies as a self-indulgent penchant for
                        punning and a cuteness of diction which almost always threatens clarity. For
                        example, when Klonsky speaks of one of Blake’s witty rejoinders to
                        Crabb Robinson, he calls it “a neat thrust, most likely inspired by
                        some spirit on the spot—jabbing this pointed detail like a bare
                        bodkin into his solidly planted and down-to-earth metaphysical
                        fundament.” Another time Klonsky designates what he asserts is a
                        <corr type="emend">personification</corr> of an already hypostatized idea, “a
hypertrophe of a
                        trope as ’twere.” And his trick of playing on words by
                        fragmenting them syllabically (“with-in,”
                        “immediatively,” “into-it-tively,” “ir-and/or
                        suprarational”) only adds to the rather jarring, schizophrenic effect
                        of the tone he adopts throughout.</p>
          <p>What is at stake here, though, is not just a matter of voice. Fundamentally,
                        Klonsky’s commentary gets into trouble because it is the product of a
                        sorely divided outlook, a conflicted allegiance that gratuitously pits
                        intellect against vision and vision against intellect in an unconscious and
                        often underhanded manner destined to misrepresent Blake’s own
                        strongly integrated aesthetic. First of all, by misappropriating
                        Blake’s anti-rationalism and regarding it as a license for him to
                        eschew the precision of both analytical thought and truth to factual detail,
                        Klonsky commits a shocking array of reportorial sins hard to pass over or
                        forgive in the aggregate. For from the smallest inaccuracies of scholarship
                        and editing (such as crediting Marianne Moore rather than Yeats with the
                        invention of the phrase “literalist of the imagination” as applied
                        to Blake, or giving Morton D. Paley a new middle initial) to the more
                        egregious errors of analysis that plague Klonsky’s explications of
                        Blake’s key views on cause and effect, on the relationship between
                        artistic execution and imagination, and on the nature of spiritual
                        sensation, this author erects a sort of “allegorical abode where
                        existence hath never come” (<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> 6.7) and calls it
                        Blake’s world. One of Klonsky’s favorite devices for leaping
                        over the evidences of historical research and passing off private surmise as
                        probable fact is his liberal use of phrases like “Blake <hi rend="i">must have</hi>
known . . . ” or “he was <hi rend="i">undoubtedly</hi> familiar with . . . ” (italics mine). The
                        “must have” construction is the most prevalent: I counted twelve
                        uses of it in the introductory essay alone, five of which are the means of
                        conveying false information, while the rest are simply minor fudgings that
                        only slightly mislead.</p>
          <pb id="p15-186" n="186"/>
          <p>But while Klonsky is impatient of both scholarly tact and intellectual rigor
                        in this way, his mistrust of the restraints of academic argument does not
                        represent a considered position. Indeed, he seems just as uncomfortable with
                        the compensatory virtues of his “amateur enthusiasm,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76" type="note">2</ref> and we therefore often find him
                        curiously <corr type="emend">withholding</corr> the sympathy we might well expect him to show for modes
                        of imagining that dispense with logical structures. He regularly adopts an
                        excessively cynical tone, for example, when speaking of Blake’s view
                        of the spirit world, as if embarrassed by the products of Blake’s
                        eidetic imagination even though in theory he hotly defends the psychological
                        and perceptual processes such envisionings entail. So of Blake’s
                        encounter with psychic images Klonsky says, “he also—or so he
                        claimed—saw visions and spoke face to face with spooks . . . and what
                        can we make of <hi rend="i">that</hi>?” Further on he remarks, archly,
                        that “whatever else [Blake’s] spirits had going for them, they
                        weren’t very good at business.” And later still, when Klonsky is
                        ostensibly clearing Blake (yet again) of the old charge of insanity, he
                        writes: “No doubt, among the heterogeneous swarms of spirits attending
                        him he must have had (and who hasn’t?) one or two or several spirits,
                        with a bit too much white around the eyeball . . . .” In a similar
                        fashion Klonsky several times attributes to the subtly controlled, allusive
                        method of Blake’s expressive technique a wild and woolly mentality
                        more accurately descriptive of Klonsky’s own thought process. Thus
                        while analyzing what he evidently believes is the chaotic formal principle
                        of <hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, Klonsky declares that:
<q> One
                            idea in <hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalogue</hi> suggests another,
                            sometimes only distantly or even metaphorically related, which
                            immediately raises its voice above it, and then, in turn, may be drowned
                            out by a following idea, before the first can be heard again. Written in
                            the ejaculatory style of his marginalia, but now across the whole page
                            of everything he believes and knows, it is as though the conclamant and
                            sometimes discordant voices of all his attendant spirits were
                            alternately haranguing, explaining, protesting, denouncing, scolding,
                            cajoling, lecturing, pleading and prophesying. </q>
	<note id="n76"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Cf. John Hollander, “Talkies,”
                                <hi rend="i">The New York Review of Books</hi>, Dec. 8, 1977, 50-54,
                            p. 51. This is a review of Klonsky’s <hi rend="i">Speaking
                                Pictures</hi> and D. J. Gordon’s <hi rend="i">The Renaissance
                                Imagination.</hi></note></p>
          <p>Unhappily many of the problems of the introduction are carried through in the
                        explanations of the splendid visuals which are the main allure of this book.
                        One wants to cry out, after the essay so titled by John E. Grant, “you
                        can’t write about Blake’s pictures like that!”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77" type="note">3</ref> You cannot, that is, say that the six
                        birds painted in the sky of the title page of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
                            Heaven and Hell</hi> are five in number simply because you want to
                        identify them with the five senses, nor can you name one of those six birds
                        an “eagle,” when it is really a bird of paradise, just to be able
                        to compare it to that other eagle Blake calls “a portion of
                        genius” in one of the proverbs of Hell. Or again, in Blake’s
                        tempera “Satan Smiting Job with Sore Boils” you cannot claim that
                        the three darts in the hand of Satan are actually four darts, and you cannot
                        call the substance Satan is emptying out of the vial in that same picture
                        “venereal disease” because you want to interpret Job’s
                        affliction as sexual. <note id="n77"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake
Studies</hi>, 1 (Spring 1969), 193-205.</note></p>
          <p>But these and other difficulties that crop up in the descriptive commentary
                        do not seriously detract from the special value of the book’s 107
                        pages of illustrations. Considered as an anthology of Blake’s
                        pictorial art, the 135 separate pictures exhibited here show a satisfying
                        range of methods, kinds and iconographic concerns, and they are displayed in
                        clear, large-format reproductions, 43 of which are printed in (mostly very
                        good) color. Some of these offerings are familiar favorites, others make
                        available for the first time in an inexpensive edition glossy colored
                        versions of such striking watercolors as “The Arlington Court
                        Picture,” “The Ghost of Samuel Appearing to Saul,” two of the
                        full-page illustrations for the illuminated <hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi>, a
                        pair of lesser known designs from the “L’Allegro” sequence
                        and three well chosen drawings from the second set of Blake’s
                        “Comus” illustrations.</p>
          <p>Perhaps the best feature of the collection, however, is not the range of
                        pictures but the aesthetically pleasing, gently instructive way designs are
                        juxtaposed on the page to make valuable graphic points about the
                        relationship of significant themes and pictorial ideas in Blake’s
                        work. One case in point is the two page spread, pages 72-73, which pairs
                        “The Woman Taken in Adultery” with “The Blasphemer”
                        (commonly called “The Stoning of Achan”). Both paintings
                        illustrate scriptural passages that treat the motif of punishment for sin by
                        stoning, the “Woman Taken in Adultery” representing
                        Christ’s New Testament critique, in John 8, of the Old Testament law
                        which is being shown at work on the opposite page in the painting of
                        “The Blasphemer” from Leviticus 24. Another case: on the
                        page-spread just preceding, two more of Blake’s biblical
                        illustrations, “Bathsheba” and “Lot and His Daughters,”
                        are matched, but this time the connection between them remains primarily
                        compositional. The representation of Bathsheba shows her upright in the
                        center of the canvas, her arms around two young children who stand on either
                        side of her as she is being observed by David, while the design of “Lot
                        and His Daughters” depicts a drunken, half-reclining Lot flanked by 
<hi rend="i">his</hi> two children as they prepare to seduce him. The
                        general plot of illicit eroticism ties the two subjects together, but it is
                        the similarity of the compositions that draws our attention to the vaguely
                        cognate themes.</p>
          <p>A final example, more subtle yet possibly even more effective, is the
                        antiphonal facing of a <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> engraving on page 96
                        with Blake’s design for the titlepage of Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> on
page 97. Here the two prints maintain a symmetrical,
                        formal balance largely on the grounds of their topological identity. For
                        both designs feature two figures about to join each other on the vertical
                        axis in an ascending-descending relationship, and both sets of figures are
                        placed on the outer edges of their plates (one on the left, the other on the
                        right) with a middle space reserved for text. We note the visual mirroring,
                        and only secondarily does it occur to us that the <hi rend="i">subjects</hi>, also,
are related reflexively. For the <hi rend="i">Night
                            Thoughts</hi> illustration depicts a young nude woman personifying
                        “sense” (in accord with the appropriate lines of Young’s
                        poem) who runs “savagely” to celebrate the powers remaining 
<pb id="p15-187" n="187"/>
to her in the fading daylight while the ghastly
                        figure of descending night is about to smother her with his bell-shaped
                        pall; and the contrary situation is portrayed in the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>
                        design where a beautiful nude man, an angelic messenger, dives downward,
                        blowing his bell-shaped trumpet, to waken the shrouded, ghoulish skeleton
                        below and rouse him from the sleep of corporeal death in the grave. The
                        pictures thus comment upon each other like type and antitype. Thanks to the
                        inventiveness of Gene Conner and Murray Schwartz, layout and production
                        editors, this kind of interplay is a general feature of <hi rend="i">William
                            Blake: The Seer and his Visions</hi>, a feature the thoughtful reader
                        cannot help but learn from and enjoy.</p>
          <p>Because of such felicities, this handsomely produced book is a valuable
                        volume indeed. It will be accessible to many because of its reasonable
                        price, and so long as its owner or borrower reads the pictures and skims the
                        text, rather than vice versa, it will make an excellent introduction to
                        Blake’s art.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
