<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.4.hilton</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Leopold Damrosch, Jr., Symbol and Truth in Blake’s Myth</title>
        <author n="Hilton">Nelson Hilton</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>George Hartley</name>
              <name>Cathy Christman</name>
              <resp>Typist</resp>
              <name>Denise Warren</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Hazard Adams</name>
              <name>James Bogan</name>
              <name>Gavin Edwards</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Randel Helms</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Janice Lyle</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Gerda Norvig</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
	<pb id="p15-192" n="192"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-4-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Leopold Damrosch, Jr. <hi rend="b">Symbol and Truth in Blake’s
                                Myth.</hi> Princeton, New Jersey: Princeton Univ. Press, 1980. xiv +
                            395 pp. $25.00 cloth, $9.50 paper.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Nelson <name>Hilton</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>After two books on Samuel Johnson, Leopold Damrosch, Jr. has now burst
                        forward unheralded to present <hi rend="i">Symbol and Truth in
                            Blake’s Myth.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78"
type="note">1</ref> It is a
                        weighty tome which will be read by every serious student of Blake over the
                        next few years; the observations on “sex,” “fatherhood,”
                        and the “spectre” if thought before have never been so well
                        expressed. Having stated my belief that the book should be widely read, I
                        hope I may be forgiven for taking the remaining space to wrestle in true
                        friendship with a gloriously Urizenic text. Let me begin with this
                        misreading: “As human beings if not as literary critics, we surely owe
                        [Damrosch] Blake the obligation of testing his [criticism] myth against our
                        experience of [Blake] truth, which is no more than doing what he constantly
                        begs us to do [unsure]. . . . But as critics we must go further and try to
                        understand why [Damrosch’s criticism] <pb id="p15-193" n="193"/>
                        Blake’s myth takes the unsatisfying form that it does. To do so will
                        reveal his final ambivalence . . . ” (239-40). <note id="n78"><hi rend="s">1</hi> In
the most recent of the preceding books, <hi rend="i">The Uses of Johnson’s Criticism</hi> (1976),
                            Damrosch still held to the vision of “Blake, the champion of minute
                            particulars.”</note></p>
          <p>Return to the title, the awkward indefiniteness of which is immediately
                        apparent as one pauses to run through its equally compelling permutations.
                        The rationale for the second term, “truth,” is that “As a
                        prophet Blake claims to announce the truth, and I have entitled this study
                            <hi rend="i">Symbol and Truth</hi> because I think it important to
                        consider how his poems might be perceived as true by modern readers”
                        (9). The language is curious only until we realize that it is standard
                        Academese: distancing and subject/self-effacing (how <hi rend="i">perhaps</hi>
“perceived” not by Damrosch but nameless
                        “modern readers”; reporting, non-judgmentally, Blake’s
                        “claims”) in the midst of its very self-assertion (“because I
                        think it important”). As it will turn out in the final consideration,
                        “If Blake deliberately cuts himself off from the phenomenology of lived
                        experience, and if the modern reader cannot join him in that exclusion, why
                        should one read him?” (368). Disregarding the two “particularly
                        compelling” academic reasons, I would suggest that the true modern
                        reader does join in that exclusion—the young Blake readers of the new
                        age, who believe as well in imaginary numbers, the genetic code, black
                        holes, and floating keeps in computer programs, are indeed moving ever
                        further from the phenomenology of Damrosch’s nostalgic, Wordsworthian
                        “lived experience” (we are told, regretfully, that “There can
                        be no Wordsworthian solitary reaper in Blake . . . and no Michael . . . ”; 
                        that, “In the end . . . Blake cannot come to terms with
                        [Wordsworth’s image of] ‘ . . . the very world which is the
                        world / Of all of us” [366-67, 368]).</p>
          <p>The first word of this book’s title, “symbol,” is its most
                        important and problematic one; significantly (or symbolically?) enough, it
                        never appears in Blake’s text in any form. Damrosch, however, is
                        concerned with “the issues” raised by Blake, and central to this
                        focus is Blake’s “exposure of the problem of symbolism,”
                        “his exploration of the possibilities and limits of the symbol”
                        (7, 368). One is left with the impression that this also is
                        Damrosch’s vision of his own achievement. The obvious question,
                        “What is a symbol?”, would quickly propel us beyond Damrosch and
                        into the deep space of contemporary poetics; but since the concept of
                        “symbol” appears on nearly every page, it is essential to try to
                        understand what Damrosch means by it. “Symbols are not simple
                        signs”—they are “‘dense with meaning’”
                        and so “any simple translation of symbol into ‘meaning’
                        reduces it once more to a sign” (67, 68, 65).</p>
          <p>Damrosch argues that “The symbol for Blake is more than a magnetic field
                        of emotional charges or a cognitive system within which experience can be
                        organized. It is our best and subtlest means of insight into reality. The
                        sun looks like a disk but is human” (69). “But in Blake’s
                        theory,” says Damrosch, “owing to his suspicion of the fallen
                        world, symbols are vitiated by their fallen status, for example in the
                        various versions of the sun.” “Therefore,” this argument
                        continues, the symbols “point to, or participate in a reality which is
                        more vivid and immediate than they are, <hi rend="i">so long as</hi> we can
                        achieve an apocalyptic breakthrough and ascend into vision on the fiery
                        chariot of the imagination” (362). Heady stuff.</p>
          <p>By “vision,” Blake “means a mode of perception that sees
                        through symbols rather than with them” (302).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79" type="note">2</ref> “All thinking,” by way of evident contrast
                        to vision, is of a “symbolic character” (256). “We therefore
                        have slippery and ambiguous symbols pointing to a more vivid and organized
                        reality ‘within’” (362). This “reality,”
                        Damrosch has to argue implicitly, is itself symbolic or hypothetical, since
                        “Blake openly defies the reality principle” by means of his
                        “wish fulfillment on a cosmic scale that . . . chooses to deny
                        essential facts of human experience” (163, 70). This ostensibly
                        meta-symbolic and transcendent Blakean reality depends finally on “an
                        act of faith—which the reader must postulate even if he does not
                        share”—since “Invariably we are brought back to the
                        necessity of the divine” (69, 314). We read Blake, then (now), “to
                        know what it would be like to believe in man’s spiritual power”
                        (368). These opinions resonate movingly with the author’s most
                        telling statement in the book: “I myself (to speak frankly) have no
                        religious belief” (246). Reading in Damrosch’s concluding
                        paragraph that the entire exercise “would have a merely antiquarian
                        function if Blake did not possess the power of a religious vision”
                        (371), one cannot resist wondering, “Did he put on his knowledge with
                        his power?” <note id="n79"><hi rend="s">2</hi> To assert the reality of
                            vision, Damrosch cites several mescaline experiences (none his own) and
                            concludes, “I have thought this documentation important—and
                            it could be multiplied many times over—because it should compel
                            [!] a recognition that Blake’s visions were actual experiences,
                            not merely poetic metaphors” (49).</note></p>
          <p>Let us return to “the issue” of “<corr type="emend">unsatisfying</corr> form” and
                        “final ambivalence”: “The purpose of [Damrosch’s
                        criticism] Blake’s myth is far from being merely descriptive. It is
                        prescriptive . . . ” (150). Hence such dicta as “the invention of
                        states represents a decisive change in Blake’s myth, and I think an
                        unfortunate one”; “I propose to establish an intellectual context
                        that will show not only what Blake seems to mean, but also why he finds it
                        so hard to mean what he wants”; “his representations of Female
                        Will would have been less tendentious if he had made more of the symbolism
                        of Lilith”; “Blake’s real mistake, if I may bluntly call it
                        that, was to give in to the dualist impulse and to dismiss sexuality to
                        Beulah” (154, 176, 219, 234).</p>
          <p>Let me make clear what I think is going on. To talk about “symbols”
                        is to posit the existence of “another” text, of latent meanings,
                        and thus the concomitant necessity (since “A symbolic language has to
                        be interpreted” [116]) of an interpreter, a wise guardian of the text
                        and context. <hi rend="i">Cui bono</hi>? Recognizing that “To say what
                        a given symbol means in Blake’s work is impossible except in an
                        extended essay on its various specific meanings” (107), Damrosch has
                        projected instead a royal road of interpreting the nature of Blakean
                        symbolization. His book is “a study in philosophical
                        interpretation” which is, anyway, “logically prior to
                        commentary”; it is, indeed, a “metacommentary” (4, 5). Like
                        its title, the book’s chapters offer abstract categories such as
                        “The Truth of Symbols,” “God and Man.” Early on,
                        Damrosch cites Blake’s reported remark, “‘I can look at a
                        knot in a piece of wood till I am frightened at it,’” and finds
                        the implication that “a fixity of gaze would compel the object to yield
                        up its hidden 
<pb id="p15-194" n="194"/>
meaning” (42). Perhaps we hear
                        an abstracted echo of this when we read, later, that our author “will
                        explore some philosophical reasons for the knottiest problems in
                        Blake’s myth,” the meanings that “baffle
                        interpretation,” that “give trouble because they cannot be
                        coherently reconciled” (113-14). Appropriately enough, he fixes his
                        gaze longest—for over a fifth of the book—on “The Problem
                        of Dualism” (every Blakean symbol “has a dual significance”
                        [290]) and there, most “compellingly,” on “Sex.” One
                        hopes that these fine discussions were as therapeutic for Damrosch as he
                        holds Blake’s myth to have been for its creator (152, 311).</p>
          <p>Damrosch’s concern “with contexts rather than sources” (6)
                        is at times misguided. Context, again, is something the (meta-) commentator
                            decides<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80"
type="note">3</ref>—but it is time that
                        we start discovering “intertext” rather than projecting context,
                        which is to say, it is time we started producing the text rather than
                        abstracting its “meaning.” For example, Damrosch quotes
                        Blake’s description that “the Plowman of Chaucer is Hercules in
                        his supreme eternal state, divested of his spectrous shadow, which is the
                        Miller . . . ,” and observes that “In mythological terms, [the
                        two] combine to make up Hercules, whom the ancient mythographers failed to
                        recognize as a divided being.” They “did not understand that their
                        Hercules was a composite being. Blake’s myth exists not to confirm
                        traditional intuitions but to make new sense of them” (82). Well and
                        good—but a little more concern for source/intertext would not be
                        amiss. In the underworld of the <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> we see Hercules,
                        in the translation of Pope that Blake was possibly reading with Hayley at
                        the time, “A tow’ring spectre of gigantic mold, / A shadowy
                        form” (11.742-43). One fascinating aspect of Hercules is that
                        “high in heav’n’s abodes / Himself resides, a God among
                        the Gods,” whereas “here” ghosts surround “his
                        shade” (743-44, 747). Pope observes in a note to the passage that it
                        offers “full evidence of the partition of the human composition into
                        three parts: The body is buried in the earth; the image or ειδολον descends
                        into the regions of the departed; and the soul, or the divine part of man,
                        is receiv’d into heaven.” Needless to say this conception of a
                        divided or composite being suggests <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> as well. 
<note id="n80"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Or decides can’t be decided:
                            “the visionary episodes . . . are the ultimate context of his
                            myth” (44).</note></p>
          <p>Again, Damrosch’s emphasis on analogous context can distract us from a
                        more interesting textuality. He relates that, according to Hans Jonas, in
                        the “Gnostic philosophy of Valentinus, ‘matter would appear to
                        be a function rather than a substance on its own, a state of the
                        “affection” of the absolute being, and the solidified external
                        expression of that state. . . . This substance, then, psychical as well as
                        material, is nothing else than a self-estranged and sunken form of the
                        Spirit solidified . . . ’” (168). Damrosch adds, “Every
                        word of this description can be applied to Blake, not because he
                        ‘was’ a Gnostic but because the Gnostic form of Neoplatonism
                        arrived at similar answers by an analogous route.” But perhaps
                        Blake’s is not an arbitrary dualism severing the spiritual and the
                        material, “defining one half of the duality out of existence.”
                        Perhaps it represents, in part, an attempt to incorporate contemporary
                        “scientific reality.” As Blake would have read in the <hi rend="i">Principia</hi>,
“The vapors which arise from the sun . . . may
                        meet at last with, and fall into, the atmospheres of the planets by their
                        gravity, and there be condensed and turned into water and humid spirits; and
                        from thence, by a slow heat, pass gradually into the form of salts, and
                        sulphurs, and tinctures, and mud, and clay, and sand, and stones, and coral,
                        and other terrestrial substances.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n81" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n81"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Florian Cajori, ed. <hi rend="i">Sir
                                Isaac Newton’s Mathematical Principles of Natural Philosophy
                                and His System of the World</hi>, trans. Andrew Motte [1729]
                            (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1934), p. 542; see also 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 12.2, p. 84.</note></p>
          <p>The importance of science or “scientific myth” as a
                        context/intertext persists throughout Blake’s work. “The final
                        vision of the Zoas,” notes Damrosch, “conversing in visionary
                        forms dramatic, represents them as ‘going forward irresistable from
                        Eternity to Eternity’ [<hi rend="i">J</hi> 98.27], a phrase which we
                        have seen in Boehme and which probably derives from biblical locutions like
                        ‘from everlasting to everlasting’” (341). But again, this
                        is in part Blake’s revision of Newton’s “living,
                        intelligent, and powerful Being” whose duration reaches “from
                        eternity to eternity.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82"
type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n82"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Cajori, p. 545; this is from the
                            “General Scholium,” <hi rend="i">essential</hi> reading for
                            any student of Blake; note that Newton’s God “constitutes
                            duration and space,” while the Zoas are “Creating Space,
                            Creating Time” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 98.13).</note></p>
          <p>“In his positive vein,” writes Damrosch, “Blake describes art
                        as organized vision that transforms appearances.” He cites the
                        beautiful passage in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, “‘Thou seest the
                        gorgeous clothd flies that dance &amp; sport in summer,’” and
                        finds that “their random swarming [becomes] an intricate dance.”
                        But, he would remind us, “the vision of the dancing flies is
                        Los’s conceit, a work of imagination which is only a temporary
                        transformation of the fallen world.” The dance-message of bees is a
                        world of delight closed to this critic.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n83" type="note">6</ref>
                        So too, for him, “The lark [in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>] is not
                        significant in itself, as an actual bird, but as a symbol of prophetic
                        inspiration, which is made clear a little later in the image of a relay of
                        larks as heavenly messengers. ‘To Immortals, the Lark is a mighty
                        Angel’” (86). Are we not Immortals, for a lark? Remarkable
                        symbol, to lead “the Choir of Day! trill, trill, trill, trill”
                            (<hi rend="i">M</hi> 31.31). <note id="n83"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Cf.
                            “With what sense does the bee form cells?” (<hi rend="i">VDA</hi> 3.4); on
“bee” as one usual signified of
                            “fly,” see OED. This example is generated retrospectively, but
                            then, “What is now proved was once, only
                            imagin’d.”</note></p>
          <p>For me, the most difficult aspect of this book concerns the author’s
                        conception of Blake’s language. A practitioner of “philosophical
                        interpretation,” Damrosch approvingly cites <corr type="emend">Wittgenstein:</corr>
                        “‘Philosophy is a battle against the bewitchment of our
                        intelligence by means of language.’ So is Blake’s
                        poetry,” he adds (358). To which I answer, forgetting who said it,
                        “Poetry is too important to be left to philosophers!” The crucial
                        term here, even more difficult than Damrosch’s “symbol,” is
                            <hi rend="i">word.</hi> While recognizing that “Blake exhibits an
                        almost Joycean awareness of the manipulability of words,” Damrosch
                        knows that “behind the words he sees a divine vision to which they
                        point, and has little interest in words for their own sake” (73). Words
                        are opake bricks in “‘the stubborn structure’ of the
                        Language”—a quotation to which Damrosch continually returns.
                        Language is one more of those “barriers to vision” (like images,
                        phenomena, symbols [42, 69, 302]), that we must learn to see through (73,
                        328): “how could the structure not be stubborn? Syntax is tyrannical,
                        forcing us to think along its lines, and every individual word is haunted by
                        associations that the user cannot escape” (326). Blake’s
                        liberties with syntax and normal association are for Damrosch only further
                        indications of Blake’s “determination to make us break through
                        language” (326).</p>
          <pb id="p15-195" n="195"/>
          <p>Discussing <hi rend="i">Adam Naming the Beasts</hi>, Damrosch proposes that
                        “in the very act of <hi rend="i">naming</hi>, in choosing human symbols
                        with which to represent experience, man has committed himself to the
                        Fall” (90). But is the word, in its practical and conceptual reality, a
                        human symbol? Damrosch neglects to acknowledge that both <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> end with <hi rend="i">onomastic</hi> “visions” (“I heard it namd,”
                        “I heard the Name,” <hi rend="i">M</hi> 42.15, <hi rend="i">J</hi>
                        99.5). Perceiving that there is something particular about Blake’s
                        relation to the word, Damrosch admits that “in Eternity . . . words
                        become truly creative as in the symbolism of the first chapter of
                        John’s gospel . . . rather than a stubborn structure” (327). So,
                        “When Albion awakens he is heard ‘speaking the Words of Eternity
                        in Human Forms,’” and these “Words are not signs but living
                        beings. . . . And conversation must therefore be more than language as we
                        know it, the stubborn structure of Los” (346). Curiously enough, these
                        living words which Damrosch would confine to Blake’s Eternity have
                        escaped to his own text twelve pages on: “Blake’s words will not
                        stay on the page as objects of aesthetic contemplation; they invade the
                        reader’s mind and attempt to transform his world” (358).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84" type="note">7</ref> These are indeed the agents of a <hi rend="i">stubborn</hi>
structure (let us consult the OED):
                        “refusing obedience, unyielding, untameable, difficult to
                            subdue.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n85"
type="note">8</ref> Blake’s genius
                        is that he recognizes this divine, transcendental, Orcian energy in the
                        word. Where Damrosch sees his “slippery and ambiguous symbols pointing
                        to a more vivid and organized reality ‘within,’” one
                        might instead see definite and polysemous words pointing to the vivid and
                        organized reality within their structure: a vision of telos we could call
                        imagination/the word/Jesus. Why, after all, does language exist? Why do we
                        yield up the question of its origins? And here also I must dissent from the
                        author’s view that “Blake’s dream of visionary truth is
                        fundamentally incompatible with modern theories of intertextuality,
                        indeterminacy, and deconstructive license” (355). The Book of
                        Revelation is indeed “a very different model from the speculations of
                        Jacques Derrida,” but such contemporary explorations show us in words
                        and texts the vortex long foretold.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n86" type="note">9</ref>
                        Barthes’ “galaxy of signifiers” adjoins Blake’s
                        Eternity. <note id="n84"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Perhaps he didn’t mean
                            this, or perhaps it’s just one of those Blakean incoherences, for
                            we read a few pages later that “It is crucially significant that
                            the words are engraved . . . so that instead of allowing them to pass
                            into our minds as if they spoke themselves inside our heads, we are
                            forced—or would be if we used Blake’s original
                            texts—to see them as objects put there by a human artist”
                            (363).</note>
	<note id="n85"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Damrosch seemingly prefers the judgment
                            of Johnson’s <hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> that “In all its
                            uses it commonly implies something of bad quality.” Considering the
                            description in the preceding verse, “English, the rough
                            basement,” “stubborn” may be pointing toward a stylistic
                            description of the mother tongue as “Harsh; rough; rugged”
                            (Johnson). Yet the terms “basement” and
                            “structure”—appearing only here in Blake’s
                            poetry—certainly suggest something like Heidegger’s vision
                            that “Language is the house of Being. Man dwells in this house.
                            Those who think [<hi rend="i">die Denkenden</hi>] and those who create
                            poetry [<hi rend="i">die Dichtenden</hi>] are the custodians of the
                            dwelling.”</note>
	<note id="n86"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Cf. the description of <hi rend="i">Beatrice Addressing Dante from the
Car</hi>: “a deadening book
                            of memory or law . . . emerges in smoke from the vortex”
                            (186).</note></p>
          <p>Consider another example of “Blakean symbolism, which continually
                        disturbs our imaginations with its aggressive strangeness. After Satan
                        seizes the harrow of Palamabron and reduces his servants to drunken
                        confusion, ‘Los took off his left sandal placing it on his head, /
                        Signal of solemn mourning.’ This is a symbolic action that demands a
                        gloss, not a ‘natural representation’” (94). Damrosch
                        does not offer that gloss (this being a metacommentary, one supposes), but
                        goes on to ask, typically, “Would an exemplar of the poet in Wordsworth
                        put a sandal on his head?” I suggest that this is not so much a
                        symbolic act as a linguistic one—an act whose “symbolism”
                        is its praxis, which is “more than language as we know it, the stubborn
                        structure of Los.”</p>
          <p>We need first to remember the surrounding text: the servants of the mill riot
						<q> With ecchoing confusion, tho’ the Sun was risen on high.<lb/>
                            Then Los took off his left sandal placing it on his head,<lb/>
 Signal of
                            solemn mourning<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">M</hi> 8. 10-12) </q>
“Ecchoing
                        confusion” here indicates the manner in which the words that follow are
                        to be understood. Thus “Sun” becomes the “sandal” which
                        is in turn the “signal of solemn mourning.” This is another
                        version of what appears in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as “that Signal
                        of the Morning which was told us in the Beginning” (<hi rend="i">J</hi>
                        93. 26),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n87" type="note">10</ref> the
beginning in which was
                        the living word, the <hi rend="i">logon zooās</hi> (λογον ζοης) of
                        Golgonooza. As the Sun was risen “<hi rend="i">on high</hi>,” so
                        Los places the sandal “<hi rend="i">on his</hi> head.” The sandal
                        is the signal which the servants behold, and its rising initiates the
                        mourning, the awareness of loss. What will later be the sandal of the
                        vegetable world, the vehicle, the signifier, is here seen as the
                        intellectual sun-head, the sign itself. The passage discloses a mode of
                        productivity distinct from the odd picture (“symbol”) offered by
                        the narrative; indeed, the description seems to be intentionally
                        “unfortunate” (Stevenson’s annotation) in order to draw
                        attention to the process of literal transformation at work. Thus in this
                        passage <hi rend="i">s</hi>u<hi rend="i">n</hi> becomes ri<hi rend="i">s</hi>e<hi
rend="i">n</hi>, becomes Los or sol anagrammatically, and
                        then becomes <hi rend="i">s</hi>a<hi rend="i">n</hi>da<hi rend="i">l</hi>
                        becomes <hi rend="i">s</hi>ig<hi rend="i">n</hi>a<hi rend="i">l</hi> becomes
                            <hi rend="i">s</hi>o<hi rend="i">l</hi>/em<hi rend="i">n</hi>—and
                        all ending with mourning. The underlying theme, in word and letter 
(<hi rend="i">o</hi>’s occur here at twice Blake’s average
                        rate, as randomly sampled), is the sun; this should not surprise Damrosch,
                        who offers a section on “Symbolic Knowing: The Example of the
                        Sun.” This theme may be called the “hypogram,” the term
                        introduced by Saussure in his strange investigation of Latin verse to
                        characterize “the inducing word”: the word or small group of words
                        which he supposed “led, by way of phonetic paraphrase, to the
                        elaboration of the poem” (Starobinski). Saussure hoped to discover a
                        law of poetic composition, and while such a conception is incredible, it
                        does seem that in the passage at hand the Poetic Genius (not to be
                        identified with the conscious poet) writes from a pre-text concerning the
                        sun. The effect of such literal play parallels that which Maureen Quilligan
                        posits for wordplay in allegory: it makes the reader “self-conscious of
                        reading by indicating the primary importance of the verbal surface rather
                        than the imagined action.” Such expanded considerations make the reader
                        more conscious of the various paths to the production of meaning: the simple
                        but serious realization that there is more at work than meets the everyday
                        sleepy eye (or ear) is enough: the glimmering indication that there are
                        worlds of delight closed by our common sense, our expectation, our symbolic
                            projections,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n88"
type="note">11</ref> awakens another sense
                        for that delight, the sense that “Reason or the ratio of all we have
                        already known is not the same that it shall be when we know more” 
(<hi rend="i">NNRb</hi>): a sense of process, of our passing presence in the
                        exfoliation of the word. S-u-n perhaps serves in such a generating position
                        in the passage since—to use a Swedenborgian intertext—the Lord
                        is the Word, which is the spiritual sun, which is the only real existence
                        and the conjunction between man and itself: the Poetic Genius centers on the
                        word “sun” as another name for the word and for itself. 
<note id="n87"><hi rend="s">10</hi> This points to the important Blakean
                            homonym morning/mourning which I will not discuss except to observe that
                            it helps to explain the contradiction in seeing that “every morning
                                <hi rend="i">is</hi> a completed desire” even though “the
                            recurrence of spring, even in the gladness of its songs, is a symptom of
                            the cyclical prison of the fallen world” (53, 86).</note>
	<note id="n88"><hi rend="s">11</hi> “‘The Eye altering alters
                            all’ occurs in a poem that describes the imprisoning cycle of the
                            fallen world,” says Damrosch (27)—but it doesn’t so
                            much describe as <hi rend="i">inscribe</hi>: do we naively believe that
                            “all is done as <hi rend="i">I</hi> have told”?</note></p>
          <p>Damrosch “must reject Frye’s suggestion that the key to
                        Blake’s thought is the synonymity of 
<pb id="p15-196" n="196"/>
                        ‘form’ and ‘image.’” Projecting unbindable
                        duality everywhere, he explains, “On the contrary, form belongs to the
                        eternal realm and image to the sensory”; and from this “We see how
                        profoundly Blake needed a religious assurance of union with the one central
                        Form” (44). But Frye’s “synonymity” is precisely the
                        energy or space embodied in the word, which joins form and image and is
                        discontinuous with the world. At the beginning of <hi rend="i">The Four
                            Zoas</hi> Blake directs us to John 1:14, quoting the last part in Greek:
                        “And the Word was made flesh, and dwelt among us.” And the reason,
                        according to the other reference to John, is “That they all may be one.
                        . . . ” Albion, if one will. It is language, the medium of
                        communication and communion, in which we are one; it is the word which is
                        the true subject. As Los “built” the stubborn structure, so
                            “<hi rend="i">the words</hi> of man to man. . . . build the
                        Universe stupendous: Mental forms Creating” (<hi rend="i">M</hi> 30.
                        18-20, my italics). Where Damrosch sees us “confined to a world in
                        which the word is woven into the garment of the Shadowy Female” (328),
                        we can change the metaphysics and see the word weaving textuality, hear
                        “the voice of the shuttle.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n89"
type="note">12</ref>
                        The rich ambiguity Damrosch is wont to find in Blake appears revealingly in
                        his own comment on a quotation from Eliade: “‘The myth is
                        supposed to happen . . . in a non-temporal time, in an instant without
                        duration, as certain mystics and philosophers conceived of eternity.’
                        In a word, as Blake conceived of it” (353). <note id="n89"><hi rend="s">12</hi>
“Los answerd swift as the shuttle of gold” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 92.13).</note></p>
          <p>This book, like all of its sort but more than some, is an exercise in
                        academic power. It does not wear its learning lightly—a footnote to
                        Pascal detains us with the information that “Pascal’s term 
<hi rend="i">jetée</hi> is strikingly anticipatory of
                        Heidegger’s <hi rend="i">geworfen</hi>” (233); a note on <hi rend="i">The
Recluse</hi> tells that “Both the thought and the
                        meditative music—filled with anticipatory echoes of Stevens’
                            <hi rend="i">Sunday Morning</hi>— are radically un-Blakean”
                        (87). We are told with astonishment that “the Blakean phrase
                        ‘prolific energy’ appears—of all places;—in
                        Burke’s <hi rend="i">Reflections on the Revolution in
                        France</hi>” (148), when there is no such phrase in Blake; the 
<hi rend="i">Merkabah</hi> is introduced without any explanation for the
                        unlearned (240); “an electrical circuit plugged in to itself”
                        appears as the impossible image of “an internal economy of perpetual
                        stability” (239); we learn that “the problem of the divine is
                        ubiquitous,” but also that “Cruelty is ubiquitous” (244,
                        252). We hear too often that “It has been said . . . ,” “In
                        other words . . . ,” “It is easy to see . . . ,” “No
                        doubt . . . ” (e.g. 96, 97, 103, 252), and also, usually with a
                        negative tone, what “Blakeans” think. “A true acceptance of
                        opposites demands a skeptical temperament and a commitment to things as they
                        are” (242), says the same author who warns against dangers in “The
                        zeal to domesticate [Blake] for English Literature” (308). We see
                        Damrosch’s zeal for things as they are in his “denial” of
                        opposing flights of fancy (see 105, 239).</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Symbol and Truth in Blake’s Myth</hi> is, then, a
                        forceful and at times seductive attempt to inscribe Blake with the
                        traditional issues of subject-oriented philosophy. I would rather wish,
                        “loving the greatest men best,” our continual effort to subject
                        ourselves to Blake. For myself, I deny that “In learning Blake’s
                        grammar we learn how to use his vocabulary; when we fail, it is either
                        because we have not understood imaginatively enough or because he has not
                        shown us what he means” (81). We fail because we do not pay due
                        attention to the “Litteral Expression”: “Mark well my words . . . ”</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
