<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.4.lyle</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">David Irwin, John Flaxman 1755-1826: Sculptor, Illustrator, Designer</title>
        <author n="Lyle">Janice Lyle</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>George Hartley</name>
              <name>Cathy Christman</name>
              <resp>Typist</resp>
              <name>Denise Warren</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Hazard Adams</name>
              <name>James Bogan</name>
              <name>Gavin Edwards</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Randel Helms</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Janice Lyle</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Gerda Norvig</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
      <pb id="p15-176" n="176"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-4-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">David Irwin. <hi rend="b">John Flaxman 1755-1826, Sculptor,
                                Illustrator, Designer.</hi> London: Studio Vista/Christie’s,
                            1979. New York: Rizzoli International Publications, Inc., 1980. xviii +
                            249 pp., 282 illus. $55.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Janice <name>Lyle</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Until recently the only full-length monograph on John Flaxman available to
                        scholars was the limited edition of W. G. Constable’s biography
                        published in 1927. However, 1979 saw Flaxman’s full re-emergence as
                        an artistic personality. The re-evaluation of his importance reached its
                        peak with the major Flaxman exhibitions held in Hamburg, Copenhagen, and
                        London accompanied by an extensive catalogue edited by David Bindman, the
                        numerous reviews of these exhibitions, and the publication of David
                        Irwin’s monograph, <hi rend="i">John Flaxman 1755-1826 Sculptor
                            Illustrator Designer.</hi> Thus, John Flaxman, whose art Irwin promoted
                        as early as 1959 (see “Reviving Interest in Flaxman,” 
<hi rend="i">Connoisseur</hi>, 144 [1959], 104-05), is now the subject of much
                        modern attention.</p>
          <p>In the Preface of his book, the first full-scale appraisal of
                        Flaxman’s life and work, Irwin states: 
						<q> My aim has been a
                            comprehensive examination of all aspects of Flaxman’s career
                            between the covers of one book. Different areas of his work are
                            interdependent, thus making separate studies by their very nature
                            incomplete. I have not traced his influence abroad, nor included his
                            influence on Victorian artists. I have tried, however, to discuss as
                            many of Flaxman’s works as possible, short of producing a <hi rend="i">catalogue
raisonné.</hi></q></p>
          <p>Irwin has been quite successful in the task he set for himself. He has
                        assembled and collated information from widely diverse and often
                        hard-to-find sources into a logical, cogent—if at times
                        dry—exposition of Flaxman’s development. Undoubtedly, the
                        book’s greatest contribution to scholarship is its presentation of
                        factual information in an organized format.</p>
          <p>Technically the book is excellent. It is well-designed and offers 282
                        illustrations, all black-and-white (a fact which is less distressing with
                        Flaxman’s work than with that of most artists, as the majority of his
                        drawings are pen-and-ink while his sculpture is uncolored marble). The
                        illustrations are located either on or near the page of the discussion, and
                        there are notably few errors in corresponding plate numbers.</p>
          <p>The format is basically thematic, although the progression of
                        Flaxman’s interests allows the author to place the ten chapters in a
                        generally chronological sequence: (I) Early Career; (II) Artist and
                        Industry: Wedgwood; (III) To Italy; (IV) Sculptures in Italy; (V)
                        Illustrations; (VI) Sculptor of Tombs: after 1794; (VII) Sculpture: Secular
                        Commissions; (VIII) Portraits; (IX) Royal Plate and Other Metalwork; (X)
                        Professor of Sculpture; Epilogue: Victorian Taste. Notes, bibliography,
                        index of works and general index follow.</p>
          <pb id="p15-177" n="177"/>
          <p>The outstanding feature of Irwin’s study is his presentation within a
                        single volume of the entire range of Flaxman’s activities. Besides
                        lecturing at the Royal Academy, Flaxman was a prolific sculptor of tombs and
                        monuments, an influential illustrator of important literary works, and a
                        recognized designer of pottery and silver. Irwin’s greatest
                        contribution to our understanding of Flaxman’s work is his chapter on
                        Flaxman’s interest in Italian Trecento and Quattrocento art. The care
                        with which Irwin cites only those frescoes that Flaxman could have seen in
                        the 1790s is a credit to his thorough art-historical methodology. In
                        addition, he incorporates an excellent selection of photographs to
                        demonstrate the Italian sources for Flaxman’s art. The
                        author’s discussion of the close relationship between John Flaxman
                        and William Young Ottley offers valuable insights into a relationship which
                        has received too little attention. In this context, Ottley’s
                        dedication of his volume, <hi rend="i">A Series of plates engraved after the
                            paintings and sculptures of the most eminent masters of the early
                            Florentine school</hi>, 1826, to John Flaxman deserves further study.
                        Certainly Ottley’s admiration for Flaxman is evident in his drawing
                        style. Many Ottley drawings, made in preparation for the volume on
                        Florentine art and also based on Flaxman’s engraved designs to Dante,
                        Homer, and Aeschylus, are stylistically so close to Flaxman that they have
                        been incorrectly catalogued as Flaxman drawings.</p>
          <p>Despite the importance of this instructive research on Flaxman, some minor
                        criticisms are necessary. In many instances, the author seems to have
                        unnecessarily limited his aims and viewpoint. All too often he confines
                        himself to a mere recitation of events and description of works.
                        Flaxman’s interaction with other artists of the period is seldom
                        discussed, and the artistic theories prevalent at the time are not explored
                        in relationship to Flaxman. Indeed, Irwin fails to make critical judgments
                        about Flaxman’s place in the art world of 1800. One example is his
                        discussion of Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Triumphal Arch surmounted by
                            Britannia</hi> where no mention is made of French visionary architects
                        like Boullée and Ledoux. These architects conceived projects of
                        enormous proportions that undoubtedly furnished precedents for
                        Flaxman’s design.</p>
          <p>Symptomatic of the limitations of Irwin’s methodology is the
                        comparison of Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Achilles Shield</hi> and Thomas
                        Stothard’s <hi rend="i">Triumph of Bacchus and Ariadne: Sideboard
                            Dish</hi> which appear as consecutive illustrations in Chapter X. Irwin
                        writes: 
						<q> The Shield of Achilles was displayed prominently at the
                            coronation banquet in July 1821. The royal collection already possessed
                            a large sideboard dish illustrating the theme of the <hi rend="i">Triumph of
Bacchus and Ariadne</hi>, which had been designed by
                            Stothard, and also made for Rundell’s, in 1814 (Plate 271). The
                            composition of this dish and the shield are in some respects similar,
                            and it is possible that Flaxman influenced his fellow artist. The
                            similarities may however have been prescribed in the commisions [sic].
                            Both works have a central motif of a chariot flanked by several figures,
                            but whereas Flaxman’s represent constellations, Stothard’s
                            are putti; Flaxman’s chariot is pulled by horses,
                            Stothard’s by centaurs.<lb/>
 (pp. 194-95) </q>
John
                        Flaxman’s refinement of composition, his ability to design complex
                        figural groups which remain clear and distinct, and his sensitive use of
                        three-dimensional qualities contrast sharply with Stothard’s
                        overly-elaborate compositional elements and less well-proportioned figures.
                        The author’s exposition of these important differences would
                        certainly clarify the positive aspects of Flaxman’s style and his
                        sensibility in design. 
						<q> In Chapter IV Irwin notes that<lb/>
<lb/>
                            Flaxman’s volumes [of illustrations to Homer, Aeschylus and
                            Dante] were therefore published either without any quotations at all or
                            with only a minimal number of lines under each plate. This novel form of
                            publication undoubtedly contributed to their contemporary visual impact
                            and their far-reaching influence.<lb/>
 (pp. 68-69) </q>
This “novel
                        form of publication” is significant and deserves elaboration. The
                        history of book illustration offers some prototypes for this format, such as
                        Stothard’s <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> series of
                        1788-91. A broader view of context and influence would have added to the
                        scholarly insights in this volume.</p>
          <p>Blake scholars will be disappointed by the paucity of references to the
                        object of their interest. For example, Flaxman’s drawings for the <hi rend="i">Book
of Enoch</hi> (one of which appears as figure 140) display
                        many correspondences with Blake’s drawings of the same subject, while
                        the similarities between Flaxman’s drawing for William
                        Collins’ sculptural monument (figure 77) and Blake’s
                        illustrations for <hi rend="i">America</hi> will be obvious to Blake
                        scholars; Irwin’s reticence on these points is regretable. The
                        discussion of Flaxman’s designs for Homer, Aeschylus, and Dante
                        rightly stresses the importance of symmetry in these works. Flaxman’s
                        illustrations, produced in Italy during the early 1790s, rely on a
                        simplification or distillation of each form, a positioning of those forms in
                        a perpendicular or parallel relationship to each other, and a division of
                        the abstract spaceless ground into geometric segments. It is likely that
                        upon Flaxman’s return from Italy in 1794, these engravings had an
                        important stylistic impact on Blake. That the period 1794-1795 was traumatic
                        for Blake has often been noted in reference to his poetry and his political
                        beliefs. The French Revolution, the execution of Louis XVI, the Reign of
                        Terror, and the repressive measures instituted by the English government all
                        contributed to the disillusionment of Blake and other radicals of the
                        period. This disillusionment caused Blake to alter not only his political
                        and philosophical attitudes, but his poetic and artistic methods as well.
                        Flaxman’s designs are more abstract and refined than Blake’s,
                        but Blake was capable of translating the compositional elements of
                        Flaxman’s engravings into the powerful images of the 1795 series of
                        color-printed drawings. As Blake is now the most popular 
<pb id="p15-178" n="178"/>
and well-known artist of this period, it is unfortunate that
                        such specific correlations in style, technique, and theory between the two
                        close friends are not included in Irwin’s study.</p>
          <p>The only really distressing aspect of the book is Irwin’s attitude
                        toward references. Footnotes in the volume most often cite contemporary
                        sources or the manuscripts and drawings themselves. This approach ignores
                        the more recent critical commentary on individual Flaxman works. Thus, when
                        Irwin refers to Goya’s use of Flaxman’s Dante designs, he does
                        not cite Sarah Symmons’ excellent article, “John Flaxman and
                        Francisco Goya: Infernos Transcribed” (<hi rend="i">Burlington
                            Magazine</hi>, 113 [Sept. 1971], 508-12), nor does he specifically
                        credit Robert Wark with the cogent analysis of Flaxman’s drawing
                        style in <hi rend="i">Drawings by John Flaxman in the Huntington
                            Collection</hi>, 1970. In his discussion of deathbed scenes he does not
                        refer to Robert Rosenblum’s seminal work on the topic in 
<hi rend="i">Transformations in Late Eighteenth Century Art</hi>, 1967, a book whose
                        footnotes have provided the stimulus for numerous dissertations.
                        Irwin’s exploration of Flaxman’s publication of Hesiod does
                        not direct the reader to G. E. Bentley, Jr., “Blake’s
                        Hesiod” (<hi rend="i">Library</hi>, 20 [1965], 315-320); and although
                        he does cite Bentley’s <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, the awkward
                        format of the footnotes requires one to go from Chapter V, footnote 30, back
                        to Chapter I, footnote 7, to discover to which work by Bentley Irwin is
                        referring.</p>
          <p>The problems in citation may appear trivial, but a volume with pretentions to
                        offering a thorough discussion, short of a <hi rend="i">catalogue
                            raisonné</hi>, of the works of a single Neoclassic artist is
                        definitely more than a coffee-table book. As such, one expects a
                        thoroughness in the footnotes that will provide valuable research
                        assistance. (It is possible that the reservations noted in this review may
                        be partly the result of the delay between completion of Irwin’s
                        manuscript and publication.) Undoubtedly, Irwin’s book will be the
                        primary Flaxman reference for many years to come. The catalogue edited by
                        David Bindman (<hi rend="i">John Flaxman, R. A.</hi>, London: Thames and
                        Hudson Ltd., 1979) will better serve scholars interested in the broader
                        questions slighted by Irwin, such as Flaxman’s place within the
                        context of his contemporary art scene and the exploration of his
                        international influence. Irwin’s book, however, has the virtue of
                        providing a comprehensive life of Flaxman with the traditional biographical
                        elements and a straightforward exposition of his major works. Taken
                        together, these two recent volumes should promote a more informed
                        appreciation of John Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">oeuvre</hi> and furnish
                        the basis for further, more detailed studies of his career and
                        influence.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
