<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.4.edwards</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">David Simpson, Irony and Authority in Romantic Poetry</title>
        <author n="Edwards">Gavin Edwards</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>George Hartley</name>
              <name>Cathy Christman</name>
              <resp>Typist</resp>
              <name>Denise Warren</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Hazard Adams</name>
              <name>James Bogan</name>
              <name>Gavin Edwards</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Randel Helms</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Janice Lyle</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Gerda Norvig</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-4-0008">
        <pb id="p15-179" n="179"/>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">David Simpson. <hi rend="b">Irony and Authority in Romantic
                                Poetry.</hi> Totawa, New Jersey: Rowan and Littlefield, 1979. 267
                            pp. $22.50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Gavin <name>Edwards</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The novelty of what David Simpson is doing in this book about irony in
                        Romantic poetry is indicated by the fact that Byron gets only one brief
                        mention in it. Correlatively, Simpson aims to unseat established views of
                        Romantic poetry as personal expression or as poetry of experience (though
                        lines of communication are kept open with both views). Instead, the work of
                        Keats, Blake, Wordsworth, Coleridge, and Shelley, and approximately
                        contemporary tendencies in philosophy and aesthetics (notably the work of
                        Hegel) are described as ironic, but not in a sense which most readers will
                        be familiar with. But then “defamiliarisation” is what the book is
                        all about.</p>
          <p>Most of us think of irony as, with various provisos and sophistications,
                        “saying one thing and meaning another.” David Simpson is talking
                        about a more radically unsettling practice, a practice named in a German
                        theoretical tradition and invoked in some recent North American criticism
                        (notably, and relevently, by Paul de Man in “The Rhetoric of
                        Temporality”). According to the notion of irony with which most of us
                        are more familiar, the <hi rend="i">meaning</hi> of what is said, the real
                        position of its author, can be deduced <hi rend="i">from</hi> what is said.
                        The reader knows where he stands because he knows where the author stands: a
                        reciprocal identification established via the material through which they
                        communicate. Romantic irony on the other hand insistently disturbs or even
                        subverts these relationships, drawing attention to the processes of
                        identification and interpretation themselves. Language, if it can still be
                        talked about as a “medium” at all, becomes “a medium which
                        takes us by the arm and shakes us into activity, rather than one which
                        vanishes in reverence to the prior clarity of the message it embodies”
                        (p. 56). Romantic irony forces us to construct meaning for ourselves in what
                        is therefore a “performative” activity: an activity, that is to
                        say, which involves making meanings as much as responding to and describing
                        them. All such attributions of meaning, interpretations, are therefore, by
                        definition, themselves put into question. The link between the question of
                        irony and the question of authority is evident: Simpson avoids the pun on
                        authors and authority, but perhaps a reviewer may be allowed it.</p>
          <p>He quote Shelley on the primary task of philosophy: 
		<q> Philosophy, impatient
                            as it may be to build, has much work yet remaining, as pioneer for the
                            overgrowth of ages. It makes one step towards this object; it destroys
                            error, and the roots of error. It leaves, what it is too often the duty
                            of the reformer in political and ethical questions to leave, a vacancy.
                            It reduces the mind to that freedom in which it would have acted, but
                            for the misuse of words and signs, the instruments of its own
                                creation.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67"
type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n67"><hi rend="s">1</hi> P. 30, quoted from <hi rend="i">The
                                    Complete Works of Shelley</hi>, ed. Ingpen and Peck, (rpt., New
                                York and London: Gordian Press and Ernest Benn Ltd., 1965), VI,
                                195.</note></q>
	<pb id="p15-180" n="180"/>
What is identified, in the poetry and the
                        philosophy, is this work of deconstruction; and reconstruction, except that
                        such reconstruction is never more than provisional, itself always subject to
                        further deconstruction. David Simpson moreover shares the principles he
                        finds at work in Romantic writing. That he does so is, as he is well aware,
                        itself unsettling. He is aware of the questioning which must attend
                        continually on his own critical discourse; aware that it cannot exclude
                        itself from the paradoxes of that “hermeneutic circle” to which it
                        refers. A book of this kind is bound to be difficult, and this is certainly
                        a difficult book. Its success needs to be judged by its ability to go on
                        thinking clearly when what has to be thought clearly is the impossibility of
                        thinking clearly, or at any rate without doubleness. By this criterion the
                        book is, most of the time, an outstanding success.</p>
          <p>The book’s descriptions of its own procedures necessarily resemble the
                        poetic procedures to which it refers. Thus “we shall find ourselves
                        constantly laying and unlaying the same bricks, in a process marked by
                        repetition rather than clearly defined progress” (p. 24). The book
                        begins with detailed readings of <hi rend="i">Ode on a Grecian Urn</hi> and
                            <hi rend="i">La Belle Dame Sans Merci.</hi> Thereafter individual
                        chapters are devoted to specific issues—the image of childhood,
                        theories and practices of language, the relation between author and
                        narrator, metaphor, irony—which are at the same time reapproaches to
                        a single chameleon problematic. Some poems are discussed, or referred to,
                        repeatedly; so one way of grasping the drift and force of the argument, in
                        the context of the present review, is to describe some of these
                        readings.</p>
          <p>In Wordsworth’s <hi rend="i">The Thorn</hi>, Simpson argues, we may
                        eventually decide that no real facts are available to us that are
                        uncontaminated by the gossip of the community in which Martha Ray lives or
                        by the “old sea captain” who is identified by Wordsworth,
                        elsewhere, as the “loquatious narrator” of the poem. Even the
                        description of the moss upon the little hill at the beginning of the poem
						<q> As if by hand of lady fair<lb/>
 The work had woven been;<lb/>
 And
                            cups, the darlings of the eye,<lb/>
 So deep in their vermillion
                            dye<lb/>
<lb/>
 introduces under the cover of “observation” the
                            primary images and metaphors of the human drama to which all this is
                            supposed to be but a preface (p. 104). </q>
The insidious thing about
                        such figurative language in the poem 
						<q> is that it is just ambiguous enough
                            to make the casual reader think that he is making genuine connections
                            and finding things for himself; whereas all the time he is simply
                            falling into the trap laid by an unconsciously cunning narrator. (p.
                            105) </q>
So the poem must encourage the <hi rend="i">un</hi>casual
                        reader to get “beyond, in our own voices, the sorts of misprision which
                        the old sea-captain inflicts on the landscape, and on the human beings who
                        are dragged into it.” (p. 105). But this is impossible; by definition
                        since the contamination is complete and no other source of information is
                        available. A commitment to “things in themselves” is both posited
                        and put out of reach. In this respect the poem, and our experience as
                        readers of it, dramatizes what Simpson calls Wordsworth’s
                        “uncontrollable epistemological predicament.” After all, <hi rend="i">The Lyrical
Ballads</hi> are about situations wherein “the
                        feeling therein developed gives importance to the action and situation and
                        not the action and situation to the feeling.” And this is, as Simpson
                        says, “a positive manifesto as much as a crime” (p. 107). In which
                        case the would-be open minded narrator of the poem can indeed be seen as an
                        emblem of the poet Wordsworth himself. So that poet and narrator, whom we
                        have to separate, also come together again. And Simpson connects this,
                        through a discussion of certain developments in eighteenth-century
                        philosophy, with a widespread instability in “the very vocabulary and
                        concept of distinction” (p. 122). The mind’s relation to the
                        world, to itself, and to its possible “parts” is uncontrollably
                        shifting: “Each is present, or absent, simultaneously with the
                        other” (p. 123).</p>
          <p>What happens to names, the practice of naming, is a central instance of this
                        complex instability. And some of the most interesting remarks on
                        Blake’s work appear in the context of Simpson’s discussion of
                        how, for the Romantics, the “disruption of the stability of objects and
                        names . . . unsettles the subject whose tools they are” (p. 70).
                        “Blake’s undertaking begins, notoriously, with the proper name
                        itself” (p. 76). In speculating on the etymology of “Urizen”
                        Simpson argues that the “list of homophonal substitutions which can be
                        made into this name seems almost infinite” (p. 76). His own suggested
                        substitutions are, he insists, 
						<q> not matters for scholarly proof, perhaps,
                            and what I have suggested will no doubt be accorded various degrees of
                            probability by different readers. But this could be exactly the point.
                            In the fallen world which Urizen, and our reason, represent, dominated
                            as it is by intentional projections and inflections of the self into the
                            world (a process which Blake the artist does not consider himself immune
                            from), is not this fronting of the altering eye the most important
                            meaning of all? (p. 77) </q>
Naming is also the theme of
                        Simpson’s discussion of <hi rend="i">Infant Joy.</hi> He rejects the
                        notion that the <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> poems are spoken by Innocence
                        and that we therefore need to slough off adult sophistication in order to
                        read them properly. Some, at least, can be read as spoken by dramatically
                        presented adult narrators implicitly conditioned by the properties of
                        experience. <hi rend="i">Infant Joy</hi> is a case in point. It is usually
                        read as “a celebration of maternal love, a loving dialogue between
                        adult and infant” (p. 52), and “the flower containing the group of
                        figures” in the illustration “is usually deemed to be opening,
                        with the limp flower yet to open.” But Simpson points out that
                        “this latter flower could as well have gone through its cycle already,
                        and the open flower could be in the process of closing” (p. 53), a
                        reading which of course gives a very different significance 
<pb id="p15-181" n="181"/>
to the family relationships going on in the open flower. And
                        in the poem the speaker 
						<q> turns (that is, paraphrases the infant into
                            turning) the description of a state—“I happy
                            am”—into a proper noun—“Joy is my
                            name”—society’s gesture of appropriation and
                            admission, and, of course, of signification. (p. 53) </q>
Sweet joy
                            be<hi rend="i">falls</hi> the helpless infant. But we are not offered a
                        simple reversal of the standard positive reading: 
						<q> I do not mean to imply
                            that my reading is the authoritative one, and it is not simply modesty
                            which makes me say so. For we can pass on beyond it, to a higher level
                            of consciousness and self-consciousness. The benediction again comes to
                            seem positive, and the smile again holds a degree of promise, when we
                            recall or realise that the fall is a necessary fall, and that there is
                            no innocence except as it is discovered or constructed. (p. 54) </q>
A
                        discovery and construction which applies of course both to our relationship
                        to the text and to the other kinds of relationship to which the text
                        refers.</p>
          <p>The image of the child has a crucial role to play in this reading of
                        Romanticism, as of course it has in other readings. But for Simpson it is
                        very much the <hi rend="i">image</hi> of the child which is at stake.
                        Childhood reproaches us with “the errors of acquired folly” as
                        Blake put it. And the child, who is therefore an agent of deconstruction is
                        also the Romantic ironist <hi rend="i">par excellence</hi>: he is never
                        reachable except as the receding image which the adult consciousness has of
                        him. The child disrupts institutions and personalities outside himself by
                        being conceived as their “other” but by the same token “is
                        himself denied the level of metacommentary, the stable identity which would
                        enable him to replace in any absolute way the authority which he
                        challenges” (p. 33).</p>
          <p>Clearly Simpson commits himself to the view that there was something which
                        can be called Romanticism. A commitment of this kind needs to accomplish two
                        things, I think, in particular. It needs to show that the writers so
                        designated are linked by their differences as well as by their similarities.
                        And it needs to show that what is said of them cannot really be said of
                        other writers.</p>
          <p>On the first count the book is impressively successful. At least so far as
                        the poetry is concerned; I am less competent to judge the philosophical
                        texts, though there certainly seems to be a close analogy between what the
                        poetry is doing and what the philosophical texts are saying (and sometimes
                        doing). As for the poetry it is already clear that, for instance, Blake is
                        more extreme and more self-possessed in his engagement with issues that
                        Wordsworth also addresses. Blake, that is to say, is more thoroughgoing,
                        enthusiastic, and explicit in his subversion of self-possession.</p>
          <p>The chapter on metaphor is perhaps the most difficult part of the book, and I
                        am not sure that its various elements are ever effectively coordinated.
                        Nevertheless it is in this chapter that I get the strongest sense of writers
                        who are linked by their differences. Simpson sets out to show that
                        Shelley’s commitment to metaphor as the <hi rend="i">sine qua
                            non</hi> of poetry is consistent with a deep scepticism about metaphor
                        on the part of Wordsworth, Coleridge and Blake. The figurative language of
                        the old sea-captain is evidence of the dangers involved in metaphor for
                        Wordsworth. We may be deceived into believing that relationships made by the
                        mind and through language are already present in the real world as facts
                        which the mind and language then respond to. In other words a danger of
                        reification is built into metaphor, “both of [consciousness] and of the
                        elements of its world, reciprocally” (p. 160). We are tempted to deny
                        the performative character of our activities as minds in relation to the
                        world, as authors or readers in relation to texts.</p>
          <p>The hostility to metaphor is most explicit in Coleridge’s criticism
                        and theory, as part of his campaign against our tendency to be convinced by
                        “impressive images in juxtaposition.” Wordsworth’s
                        ambivalence on this issue will already be evident from the ambivalent
                        relationship between “author” and “narrator” of <hi rend="i">The Thorn.</hi>
Blake prefers analogy to metaphor because it
                        brings out, what metaphor tends to conceal, the <hi rend="i">activity</hi>
                        of making connections. And Simpson suggests that for Blake the uncreative
                        activity of creation (as it is evoked for instance in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> when
“Thought changed the infinite to a serpent”)
                        is “exactly the metaphorical process, which shuts up the infinite
                        revolutions” (p. 159). In a similar way one could say that the passage
                        from joy to Joy in <hi rend="i">Infant Joy</hi> imposes on the child a name
                        that is then said to be proper to it.</p>
          <p>The central place given to metaphor in poetic creation by Shelley is a
                        different response to the same kind of insight. “The reification
                        through metaphor which Wordsworth fears so much is countered by Shelley with
                        an oversupply of metaphor which prevents us ever coming to a <hi rend="i">stop</hi> in
the production of meanings” (p. 161).
                        Shelley’s metaphors tend to “interfere” with one another;
                        “each single relation develops out of and turns into another.” And
                        correlatively “the subject which is accustomed to the
                        ‘outering’ gesture as a means of establishing its identity
                        will also be in a state of becoming, the ethical corollary of which is love,
                        where all things ‘meet and mingle’” (p. 163). As Shelley
                        said, “Veil after veil may be withdrawn, and the inmost naked beauty of
                        the meaning never exposed.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68"
type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n68"><hi rend="s">2</hi> P. 163, quoting <hi rend="i">The Complete
                                Works of Shelley</hi>, VII, 131.</note></p>
          <p>In its attempt to show that things are true of these writers which are not
                        really true of previous writers the book is I think less successful. In
                        effect Simpson presents a kind of “modernization theory” which
                        claims that there is a direct link between the spirit of our age and the
                        spirit of the Romantic age and a pretty clear historical break between
                        Augustan and Romantic discourse. 
						<q> Augustan discourse was usually content
                            to insinuate the unquestioned verification of the perceiving subject by
                            never describing it, never suggesting that it might be responsible for
                            what it sees. It exists as an unspoken 
<pb id="p15-182" n="182"/>
but
                            implicitly central presence from which, and not through which, the
                            landscape is organised, and the precision-crafted gallery of general
                            specificities, visual and psychological, which it conveys, are deployed
                            through the rhymed couplet. Romanticism, on the other hand, seems
                            fundamentally committed to a model of ‘reciprocal
                            causality’, wherein the self and object are articulated
                            coinstantaneously, and poetic description, with its implication in and
                            dramatisation of temporality, must then tend to provide an unsettled
                            rhetoric out of which this synthetic moment emerges
                            ‘negatively’, if at all, from a context of surrounding
                            qualifications and blunted approaches. (pp. 138-39) </q>
This is a
                        helpful formulation. And it is unfair to criticize a book about one mode of
                        discourse for not offering equally nuanced and complex analysis of other
                        modes with which it is contrasted. But there is a particular problem when
                        the modes of discourse involved are the Augustan and the Romantic. There is
                        frequently in such cases, as I think there is here, a suspiciously perfect
                        co-incidence between the description and what is described: we have a
                        composed and generalized description of a composed and generalizing
                        discourse and a complex, paradoxical, and very detailed description of a
                        complex and paradoxical discourse. David Simpson is acutely conscious of the
                        paradox involved, from a hermeneutic perspective, in offering to establish
                        an historical origin for that perspective; acutely conscious of the
                        probability of finding just what he is looking for. But this
                        self-consciousness would be more convincing if some attempt had been made to
                        analyze a few non-Romantic literary texts with the kind of concentration and
                        deconstructive intent he brings so effectively to Romantic ones. He does
                        comment on a few lines of Cowper and Crabbe; but since I disagree with what
                        he says about the lines of Crabbe, I don’t know whether this just
                        means that Crabbe has been put on the wrong side of the line or that the
                        line doesn’t really exist in the way Simpson suggests. I suspect that
                        the most resolutely composed Augustan poems can (and should) be discomposed.
                        They can be read as ironic in the Simpson sense, even if secretly or
                        reluctantly so. But this does not simply mean that the Augustan/Romantic
                        distinction should be drawn less sharply. It needs somehow to be
                        redrawn.</p>
          <p>There could be no better indication of the distinction between the two
                        concepts of irony than the distinction between <hi rend="i">A Tale of a
                            Tub</hi> and Leavis’ notable essay <hi rend="i">The Irony of
                            Swift.</hi> Leavis’ blindness, in my view, to an important
                        dimension of Swift’s practice coincides precisely with his use of the
                        familiar notion of irony and the kind of meaning which it requires of a
                        text. Now I don’t simply want to set up Swift as disproof of what
                        Simpson says about Augustan discourse; he says, after all, that it was
                        “usually” as he describes it. The problem is rather that Swift
                        remains, despite his “romantic” irony quite definitely <hi rend="i">not</hi> a
Romantic writer. And I can’t at the moment
                        see how, with David Simpson’s terms, that relationship of difference
                        and similarity is to be described. (A difference and similarity written into
                        the curious conclusion of Leavis’ own essay: “We shall not think
                        Swift remarkable for intelligence if we think of Blake.”)</p>
          <p>David Simpson’s historical placing of the Romantic poets raises
                        another problem, though in this case one that he is certainly aware of. In
                        all this talk about “the reader” for instance 
						<q> How . . . is the
                            reader of 1798 to be distinguished from the reader of 1978? The answer
                            is another question: ‘which reader of 1798, and for which reader
                            of 1978?’ (p. xi) </q>
Simpson quite fairly leaves that question
                        to us. And this reader is immediately reminded of Wordsworth in <hi rend="i">Simon
Lee</hi> addressing 
<q> My gentle reader, I perceive<lb/>
 How
                            patiently you’ve waited,<lb/>
 And I’m afraid that you
                            expect<lb/>
 Some tale will be related. </q>
Wordsworth, a gentleman
                        writing about “an old huntsman,” draws the attention of his
                        readers of 1798 to their status as, in all probability, gentlefolk; and to
                        the doubtful moral claims which that title silently endows them with in its
                        association of gentility with gentleness. Now this is an unsettling of
                        relationships which suggests that Wordsworth is very well aware of the
                        historical context of the crisis of intersubjective verification as Kelvin
                        Everest has described it in <hi rend="i">Coleridge’s Secret
                            Ministry.</hi> It is instructive to read Simpson in conjunction with
                        Everest, who describes “a shift in the poet’s sense of audience,
                        his sense of the authority which his values carry”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69" type="note">3</ref> but who sees it in the context of a general
                        “cultural dislocation that took place in England in the 1790s, a
                        dislocation that issued not only in the clearer manifestation of class
                        conflicts developing with the industrial revolution, but in the separation
                        of the creative intellect from its accustomed audience.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70" type="note">4</ref> So that the poets are “isolated by
                        class from the common people, and by principle from their social and
                        intellectual fellows.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71"
type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n69"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Kelvin Everest, <hi rend="i">Coleridge’s Secret Ministry, the Context of
the Conversation
                                Poems, 1795-1798</hi> (Sussex and New York: The Harvester Press and
                            Barnes and Noble, 1979), p. 172.</note>
	<note id="n70"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Everest, p. 108.</note>
	<note id="n71"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Everest, p. 113.</note></p>
          <p>This cultural disclocation may be defined as a disclocation, across the whole
                        range of social life, in the processes of signification. The processes
                        through which identities are constructed became increasingly visible and
                        problematic, and this may of course be cause for both hope and fear. Thus
                        many of the poems with which Simpson deals bear directly upon other
                        discursive activities which are themselves in effect
                        “performative”: a child is christened in <hi rend="i">Infant
                            Joy</hi>, Martha Ray is gossipped into isolation in <hi rend="i">The
                            Thorn.</hi> Tom Paine identifies the reifying tendency of metaphor in a
                        way that closely parallels the positions of Wordsworth and Blake. He
                        identifies Burke’s metaphorical language as an integral part of the
                        costume-drama of aristocratic society which works, as theatre works, by the
                        willing suspension of disbelief on the part of the popular audience:
                        “In England the right of war and peace is said to reside in a 
<hi rend="i">metaphor</hi>, shown at the Tower for sixpence or a shilling
                            apiece.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72"
type="note">6</ref> And “Titles are
                        like circles drawn by the magician’s wand, to contract the sphere of
                        man’s felicity. He lives immured within the Bastille of a word, and
                        surveys at a distance the envied life of man.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73" type="note">7</ref> And in this context of naming and what to do about
                        it, the history of the word “Jacobin” in England is very
                        interesting. It was 
<pb id="p15-183" n="183"/>
applied to diverse reformers
                        (including Wordsworth and Coleridge of course) by <hi rend="i">anti</hi>-Jacobins so
as to reflect the Revolution in France onto English
                        society in a way that suited their own interests; John Thelwall for one felt
                        that the only defence against this naming was to accept it as a badge of
                        honor because “it is fixed upon us, as a stigma, by our
                            enemies.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74"
type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n72"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Tom Paine, <hi rend="i">The Rights of
                                Man</hi>, ed. Collins (London: Penguin, 1969), p. 99.</note>
	<note id="n73"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Paine, p. 102.</note>
	<note id="n74"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Quoted in Carl B. Cone, <hi rend="i">The
                                English Jacobins</hi> (New York: Charles Scribner’s Sons,
                            1968), p. iii.</note></p>
          <p>If the processes of human identification were peculiarly visible and
                        problematic, the task—then or now—of deciding what was <hi rend="i">really</hi>
going on must be a peculiarly difficult one, must
                        involve from the start questions of metaphor, of narrative, of
                        characterization. The question of whether there was really a promise/threat
                        of Revolution in England is in <hi rend="i">some</hi> respects like the
                        question of what really happened to Martha Ray.</p>
          <p>David Simpson’s reading of Romantic poetry leads out naturally and
                        fruitfully, in my view, into these wider contexts. On the other hand the way
                        in which he himself refers to the social and political context might
                        discourage some readers from going in that direction. For instance: 
						<q> . .
                            . I have not given carefully constructed accounts of the reaction to the
                            French Revolution, or a properly documented consideration of the reviews
                            and the reviewers. Let me stress that I do not think these things
                            unimportant; it is simply that one can only write one book at a time. It
                            may well be for example, that the rather esoteric explorations of
                            self-focussing revolutions which these writers offer have much to do
                            with the repressive legislation and draconian censorship introduced
                            during the Revolutionary and Napoleonic Wars. The ethical reservations
                            which they project about their own tendencies towards authority,
                            combined with the high sense of urgency about passing on these
                            reservations, may after all be part of a sophisticated self-protection,
                            producing a version of “revolution” which is permissible
                            precisely because personal, because unorganised in the social sense.
                            (pp. xi-xii) </q>
This is a very interesting speculation, which needs to
                        be followed up. And it is certainly true that, for instance, Paine’s
                        critique of metaphor is not insistently self-reflexive; it is linked to a
                        confident commitment to the notion of a literal language of communication
                        and the authority of his own statement. But the way in which Simpson
                        formulates his speculations is open to criticism. His book talks a lot about
                            <hi rend="i">The Prelude</hi> but, as he admits, doesn’t talk
                        about the French Revolution. And this does seem to involve an assumption
                        that the French Revolution doesn’t exist in the poem in quite the
                        same way as, for instance, Mont Blanc does; that “the reaction to the
                        French Revolution” is different in kind, less “personal,”
                        than the reaction to Mont Blanc. Therefore, in so far as “self,”
                        in the phrase “self-focussing revolutions,” refers to the self of
                        the person as well as the self of the revolutions I think that
                        Simpson’s distinction between personal and social revolutions is
                        misconceived. The speculative distinction David Simpson draws between
                        Revolution and revolution is subtly prescribed in the circle which his own
                        discourse draws around the practice of writing and reading poetry.</p>
          <p>It is important to make these criticisms because of the use to which this
                        book could be put, particularly in the current climate of criticism and
                        theory in North America which seems inhospitable to questions of social and
                        political context. That David Simpson’s own readings are not closed
                        in that respect is evident from his recent study of <hi rend="i">The
                            Ecchoing Green</hi> in this journal. And his book does at least address
                        itself, as we have seen, to a question that needs to be put to any
                        deconstruction criticism: just how figurative is its own vocabulary of
                        anti-authoritarian subversion? It must also be said, to sceptical 
<hi rend="i">British</hi> readers, that Simpson’s book is a splendid
                        vindication of theoretically informed and explicit textual analysis.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
