<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.4.punter</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Betty T. Bennett, ed., British War Poetry in the Age of
Romanticism: 1793-1815</title>
        <author n="Punter">David Punter</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>George Hartley</name>
              <name>Cathy Christman</name>
              <resp>Typist</resp>
              <name>Denise Warren</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Hazard Adams</name>
              <name>James Bogan</name>
              <name>Gavin Edwards</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Randel Helms</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Janice Lyle</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Gerda Norvig</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-4-0008">
        <pb id="p15-189" n="189"/>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main" rend="main"><hi rend="b">WAR AND THE USES OF MYTH</hi></title>
            <title type="main">Betty T. Bennett, ed. <hi rend="b">British War Poetry in the Age of
Romanticism:
                                1793-1815.</hi> New York and London: Garland Publishing Inc., 1976
                            (Romantic Context: Poetry 1789-1830. Series: Vol. I). xii + 528 pp.
                            $47.00 library binding.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>David <name>Punter</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>It is still so easy, despite the efforts not only of historians but also of
                        literary critics, David Erdman and other Blake scholars in their forefront,
                        to forget the point which Betty Bennett usefully underlines in her
                        introduction to this collection: that for most British people, the major
                        constituent of experience in the years between 1793 and 1815 was war. In
                        fact, such is the regularity with which the Revolutionary and Napoleonic
                        Wars are treated as experiences peripheral to British culture that behind
                        this blurring of memory there begins to loom the shadow of a more deliberate
                        evasion, and an evasion of greater dimensions than those characteristic of a
                        national criticism which has traditionally preferred its historical context
                        to be presented severely diluted and preferably bent into the service of
                        moral instruction. The reasons for this evasion are complex, and some of
                        them bear a particular relation to the present: this is not an economic or
                        political phase in which inter-European warfare presents itself as a
                        privileged object of attention, nor is it one, indeed, in which military
                        history as such can be happily seen as free from political partiality. But
                        most of the reasons have a longer socio-psychological pedigree than that,
                        and the materials presented in this collection of war poetry can help us
                        towards an understanding of them; it can also help us towards a deepened
                        understanding of Blake’s literary practice by providing a
                        constellation of popular writing within which to situate his acts of
                        mysterious demystification.</p>
          <p>In referring to the experience of war, I do not mean merely to effect a
                        simple contentual connection. War, certainly, produces its own hierarchies
                        of signification, and it is the wars of the romantic age which provide, for
                        instance, a shape for those connections between aggression and commerce
                        which Blake makes so powerfully, and which, as this collection among others
                        reveals, were a habitual feature of the popular discourse of the time. But
                        those hierarchies are themselves dependent on deeper arrangements of social
                        life. In economic terms, the seemingly interminable years of conflict with
                        the French can fairly be seen as an era of interrupted potential, of hanging
                        on the brink. The exploitation of the colonies, and the steady progress of
                        commercial success attendant on that exploitation, did not cease to proceed,
                        but they progressed under uneasy conditions, constantly dependent on the
                        next phase of commercial sabre-rattling, the next round of Orders in
                        Council; and thus the war effort becomes increasingly seen as something to
                        be undertaken in order for something else to begin, as an increasingly 
<pb id="p15-190" n="190"/>
burdensome impediment to the birth of a new age.
                        And, for instance, without this element within the popular imagination, this
                        prolonged “labor” which is both the production of munitions and
                        also the delayed attempt to give birth to a mythically stable Britain of the
                        future, all those difficult births which punctuate the Prophetic Books would
                        have been less bloody, and their place within the formal structures of the
                        poems less prominent.</p>
          <p>And equally, without the thunder of firearms, however empirically absent from
                        the English mainland, the thunderings of Orc and Urizen would seem parts of
                        a quite different vocabulary: the foregrounding of war as a fact of the
                        social life of the age is the essential prerequisite for historically
                        relevant and operable definitions of hyperbole, of clarity and opacity, and
                        even of volume. In the discourse of the time, the clamor of the guns is
                        important in many ways. For the Tories, it contains a double danger: that
                        hearing it might spark a corresponding rebellious clamor at home, and/or
                        that continental furor might obscure the sounds of unrest when they occur.
                        Against the first, there is always the weapon of repression of
                        communication, the setting up of resistances which will prevent the rapid
                        electric flow of revolutionary thought; against the second, the quieter
                        resource of spying, the ear which Pitt had always to keep uncomfortably
                        close to the ground, however grand an international posture he sought to
                        assume.</p>
          <p>In this context, as Bennett hints, the search for a plainer “language of
                        men” which constitutes one strand of English romanticism becomes
                        perceptibly a part of a wider set of social demands riddled through and
                        through with the political. Some of the major romantics may find their way
                        to pockets of silence, may be able to test subtle tuning-forks on the
                        mountains and the winds, but for the most part this collection (rightly, I
                        believe, eschewing the handful of productions which have come to dominate
                        the literary landscape of the period) shows us not soliloquy or refinement
                        of sensibility but stentorian bellowing, the endless repetition of image and
                        abstraction. The bellowing, the condensation of argument into ritual cries
                        of “liberty,” “freedom,” “justice,” at first
                        appears to come from the mostly anonymous poets themselves and from the
                        newspaper editors; but as Bennett points out in an unashamedly derivative
                        but nonetheless very handy run-down of the politics of the press, even the
                        powerful editors are for the most part puppets, and the voices come from
                        over their shoulders, direct from the politicians. Under these
                        circumstances, freedom of speech is a dangerous risk, and one with which
                        neither Tory nor Whig felt happy. Too much was at stake; from a
                        psychological perspective, what seems to have been in the air was the
                        unpredictable outcome of a massive social ambivalence, itself the product of
                        conflict of allegiance between economic and national groupings. Ambivalence
                        and evasion here go hand in hand, for what the popular poetry reveals is a
                        set of contradictions which cannot be handled except by displacement, by the
                        shifting of historical, geographical, and social contexts.</p>
          <p>Yet in some ways this is too simple: certainly the politicians manipulated,
                        and certainly editors were under no misapprehension about their national
                        responsibilities. Yet it would clearly be hopelessly optimistic to argue
                        that therefore some hypothetical variety of “free” or even radical
                        poetry, some poetry which could see through chauvinism to
                        chauvinism’s economic and psychological functions, was suppressed,
                        except in the rarest instances. The operations of hegemony are more
                        all-embracing than that; and what is evidenced by the war poetry of
                        1793-1815, I would suggest, is an intense fear resulting in an equally
                        intense network of collusions. It is a familiar point that those poets of
                        the period who had some claim to be called working-class, here represented
                        especially by Cunningham and Bloomfield, tended towards formal and
                        ideological traditionalism; but it is more generally true that, as Bennett
                        puts it, “poets who supported the war as well as those who opposed it
                        use the same terms.” Beneath differences of party politics we see the
                        emergence and consolidation of a unified vocabulary, as if the tension of
                        prolonged outward conflict were too great to permit inner discord. The
                        relation between warfare and national unity is close indeed, and it
                        generates an enormous power to absorb contradiction and produce it as
                        confirmation. When Britain can be referred to, as it is in
                        “Britain’s Genius Triumphant” (1807), as
                        “freedom-fost’ring” and “coop’d up” in two
                        successive lines, what we need to wonder about is the power of the
                        individual voice to survive under the pressure of fear, a fear increasingly
                        seen as related to invasion but actually concealing a more deeply-laid fear
                        of change and the destruction of stability. And the strategies by means of
                        which this fear is displaced supply us with keys to the underlying myth
                        against which the collusions are supposed to offer protection: it is a myth
                        of imminent sexual violation, as, clearly, Blake was well aware at the
                        time.</p>
          <p>There is of course, and especially in the early years of the war, a terror of
                        chaos, well exemplified in “The Farmer and Labourer” (1794):
                        “confusion whelms all forms, all properties; / And chaos reigns among
                        the sons of men, / Till God’s avenging arm restores fair Peace
                        again.” The most important shapes for disorder are those we also find
                        in the Gothic, both Gothic fiction and the more immediately relevant
                        nationalistic and military Gothic represented by Macpherson’s 
<hi rend="i">Ossian</hi> and, in Bennett’s collection, by his many
                        imitators. But this discourse of chaos and order is usually unspecific,
                        lacking in vitality; it is in the imagery of a rousing song like “Stop
                        to a Stride,” from <hi rend="i">The Gentleman’s Magazine</hi>
                        (1803), which has Napoleon raping each European country in turn, that
                        greater concreteness is invested. The political implications of a stance
                        which claims that first France herself, then “poor Switzerland”
                        and so on, have fallen victim to a violent sexual assault are manifold.
                        Primarily, it enables a consensus to be achieved around the difficult issue
                        of how to treat the French as, on the one hand, savage aggressors and, on
                        the other, the victims of a pseudo-egalitarian conspiracy. This is done by
                        separating out masculine and feminine characteristics, often along the lines
                        suggested by Burke’s potent image of the French queen. In a 1794
                        “Ode” from the <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi>, the male French
                        are conjured away completely, so that the stalwart British can perform the
                        ideologically 
<pb id="p15-191" n="191"/>
necessary function of protecting
                        French virgins (presumably also virgin minds, free from the taint of
                        Jacobinism) from damage. Frederick Atkinson’s “The
                        Emigrée” (1799) is typical of a genre in which French womanhood
                        is conveniently reduced to penury and orphanage, British commerce being
                        therefore her only means of survival. Helen Maria Williams, in her “Ode
                        to Peace” of 1801, appears to entertain hopes that all might come right
                        yet with a marriage between France and England, but for the most part so
                        benign a solution to the quandary seems very distant.</p>
          <p>This attempt to depotentiate the French, perhaps to remove an anxiety and an
                        envy that they, the old enemy, have managed to effect by revolution a
                        significant penetration of the historical fabric, becomes the key to the
                        dominant formal device of the collection, which, despite Wordsworth, is
                        personification. Real battles between real people are, subtly and not so
                        subtly, transmuted into battles of the giants, in which “Freedom”
                        and “Terror,” “Liberty” and “Slaughter,”
                        “Peace” and “Rapine” are made to take on the agential
                        role in relation to historical action. A particularly revealing example
                        occurs in Scott’s “Bonaparte” (1811), where, after a first
                        verse in which the poet waxes rude about Napoleon’s low birth in a
                        “suburb hovel,” and as we are apparently about to close in on the
                        picture, we learn that “before that Leader strode a shadowy form, / Her
                        limbs like mist, her torch like meteor show’d.” This shadow
                        turns out, conventionally, to be “Ambition”; what is significant,
                        however, is her function as the “mist” which obscures real
                        historical connection. In “Peace more Desirable than War” (1793),
                        we find another use for personification when “Science,”
                        “Justice,” “Virtue” and so forth are followed in the
                        same mode by “George,” who can thus be conveniently translated to
                        a higher realm by a more than human process, providing a model of
                        “super-natural” sanction.</p>
          <p>And there are other devices which we could list, all of which help to obscure
                        agency: transmutation into animals, gods or devils, condensation into heroic
                        figures, and more intricate linguistic processes, mostly to do with
                        passivization and the suppression of the subject. The process which Blake
                        describes in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, where he
                        provides so insightful an account of the social purposes of religion, can be
                        extended—indeed, should be extended—into the formation of
                        social myth, and it is clearly such a formation which is happening here,
                        especially if we accept that a major function of myth is to naturalize
                        contradiction. As a comment on the book, however, this is simply to say that
                        overall it is what it set out to be, a mine of information, and no more. The
                        introduction is a model of decorum, in which the minimal historical and
                        social facts are stated lucidly but without recourse to speculation. The
                        footnotes provide, as well as literary references, a sketchy narrative of
                        the principal events of the wars; indeed, such is the author’s zeal
                        that many of them appear twice, a habit which may well have been caught from
                        the emphatic style of the poetry itself.</p>
          <p>But perhaps historical narrative cannot really be so simple. The confident
                        celebrations of old English beef and pudding begin eventually to seem thin,
                        slightly desperate, like the skin of a system of ideas and control from
                        which the substance is gradually leaking. Yet the pressure exerted to
                        maintain the carapace is enormous; and here we get a glimpse of the forces
                        of cultural solidarity which drove Blake to such lengths. The principal
                        effort of poetry in these years, judging by this copious evidence, seems not
                        at all to have been to achieve direct communication with the hypothesized
                        “people,” but rather to generate a connection between simplicity
                        of structure and abstract opacity of image, whereby the representation of
                        physical action could be turned into schematized mental conflict by a series
                        of increasingly minimal gestures. Vaunting abstractions are permitted to
                        “do things” to each other; individuals generally figure not as
                        actors but as patients, sufferers, sad and distant seamen, weeping widows.
                        And thus, of course, the hierarchy of the State is produced as the formal
                        limitation of poetry: while outwardly professing them to be made of oak, the
                        poets portray the “people” as cowering beneath the feet of mighty,
                        semi-invisible contestants, “Giant Forms” par excellence.</p>
          <p>The relation which Blake’s poetry bears, then, to this body of
                        work—and Bennett and I would agree, I think, in referring to it <hi rend="i">as</hi>
a homogeneous body of work, although the nature of our
                        evidence would be different—is a complicated one. The root of that
                        relation lies in the fact that it is, in this poetry, Jacobin and
                        anti-Jacobin alike, always the French who are portrayed as desirous. The
                        English are firm and steadfast; or at least, they are perpetually about to
                        be called upon to be firm and steadfast. Towards the untoward events across
                        the Channel, policy permits a number of attitudes, from noisy cheering on of
                        our troops from the sidelines to averting the eyes and calling on the moral
                        virtues to save us from pollution. It also, on occasion, permits some rather
                        patchy satire. What, however, is inconceivable is that the British could
                        have outward-going desires, except the negative one of stopping the French;
                        and this despite the facts of colonization. The prevalent ideology clearly
                        did not allow connections between French and British imperialism, and thus
                        two separate streams of imagery are generated: the French commit assault,
                        the British protect and nurture their colonies like offspring or, perhaps
                        better, distant nieces. And it is interesting that when Blake tries to put
                        this severed world together, in <hi rend="i">America, Europe</hi> and <hi rend="i">The
Song of Los</hi>, he too finds it very difficult. There is
                        plenty of desire in America, and there is a set of economic truths applied
                        to Asia, but Europe remains the most puzzling of geographies, an apparent
                        fairyland where, nonetheless, the displaced sense of threat is a palpable
                        absence. The land fit for Englishmen to live in, a concern dear to the
                        hearts of many of these poets, is one-dimensional: it is a still point, at
                        which change can be forever avoided.</p>
          <p>In this particular context, Blake’s achievement is to continue to
                        wrestle with the exclusion of desire, and with the function of that
                        exclusion as a political device. There were poems being written in the last
                        decade of the eighteenth century whose professed purpose was to apply a
                        succession of 
<pb id="p15-192" n="192"/>
proverbs, neatly and in order, to
                        scenes from the wars; under such circumstances, the “Proverbs of
                        Hell” seem all the more challenging. But, of course, myth is not
                        genuinely susceptible to opposition, nor even can it be destroyed or
                        modified by the construction of counter-myths; since its realm is
                        contradiction, it is capable of remaining unaffected by intellectual
                        weapons, modifying its contours only in a complex and variable relation with
                        changes in the underlying reality. A poem of 1813 entitled “National
                        Discord” is interesting in this context; the poet regrets the
                        contemporary lack of a “Thracian Lyrist . . . gifted with skill / To
                        humble the Tiger to crouch at his will,” and bemoans the collapse of
                        the world into discord rather than the harmony which, of course, once
                        prevailed: 
						<q> the Genius of bright intuition is fled;<lb/>
 And harmony
                            passed from the heart to the head;<lb/>
 No rapt inspiration now succours
                            the brave!<lb/>
 No sounds of the lyre are effectual to save!<lb/>
<lb/>
                            The reign is establish’d of Discord; delight<lb/>
 Exults in
                            narration of siege and of flight;<lb/>
 Where losses confuse in the
                            flames spreading-far,<lb/>
 And distresses in pageants and tumults of
                            war. </q>
This, I believe, well illustrates ambivalence in contemporary
                        attitudes to the war; the assumed preoccupation of poets with the martial is
                        criticized, while at the same time the key terms “delight” and
                        “exults” are attached precisely to this condemned narration. For
                        “condemned narration,” we could substitute “Bible of
                        Hell,” and we would thus be enriching our sense of the relations
                        between Blakean narrative and history, while at the same time starting to
                        think in quite a Blakean way first about the specific shapes, the particular
                        inclusions and exclusions, which psychic energy can be made to assume by the
                        pressure of historical circumstance and then about the ideological
                        collusions which seek to protect people both from the threat of change and,
                        at the same time and inextricably, from the risk of taking on their own
                        power.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
