<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>15.4.adams</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Kathleen Raine, From Blake to A Vision</title>
        <author n="Adams">Hazard Adams</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">15.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>George Hartley</name>
              <name>Cathy Christman</name>
              <resp>Typist</resp>
              <name>Denise Warren</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Hazard Adams</name>
              <name>James Bogan</name>
              <name>Gavin Edwards</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Randel Helms</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Janice Lyle</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Gerda Norvig</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_15">
    <body>
	<pb id="p15-187" n="187"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-15-4-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Kathleen Raine. <hi rend="b">From Blake to A Vision.</hi> Dublin: The
                            Dolmen Press. Atlantic Highlands, New Jersey: Humanities Press, 1979
                            (New Yeats Papers XVII). 64 pp. £4.50, $11.75 paper.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Hazard <name>Adams</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Kathleen Raine’s line on Blake is familiar to us: He was an adept of
                        the “Perennial Philosophy,” which holds that consciousness is the
                        ground of reality. In this monograph she asserts that Yeats is
                        Blake’s “greatest disciple” and “the claims he made,
                        the beliefs he held on the reversal of premises which would characterize the
                        New Age, are the same as Blake’s.” When I hear this sort of
                        remark I must confess that I am inclined to stop reading; I want immediately
                        to make a list of all the important differences that I am convinced are
                        going to be glossed over in the discourse that follows. But the writer is
                        Kathleen Raine, and like many earlier quirky scholars of Blake, she is
                        usually informative even when she mounts into her particular pulpit and
                        tells us (in the tone I imagine a True Pythoness would use) that we must all
                        now hear occult Truth. This is a Truth that links the speaker in a chain of
                        adepts back to Plato, who of course was himself a neoplatonist.</p>
          <pb id="p15-188" n="188"/>
          <p>Raine declares Swedenborg to be a major influence on both Blake and Yeats.
                        This is not news. It would be if Raine were to declare that Blake does not
                        attack Swedenborg. She doesn’t, but she also fails to mention that he
                        does and that he tends to use Swedenborg very eccentrically indeed. Raine
                        declares Blake to be a diagrammatist like Yeats and all the diagrams of both
                        to be Jungian mandalas. S. Foster Damon’s diagram of Blake’s
                        city of Jerusalem is presented, along with Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vision of the Last
Judgment</hi> and the famous plate 36 of <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> But it is <hi rend="i">not</hi> said that
Damon
                        might better <hi rend="i">not</hi> have diagrammed Jerusalem, which as far
                        as I can see is constructed to be a trap for diagrammatists, as is just
                        about all of <hi rend="i">A Vision.</hi> Plate 36 stands out as the 
<hi rend="i">only</hi> diagram Blake included in all of his illuminated
                        works and surviving manuscripts. Of course, if one equates every mandala
                        discovered in Blake with a diagram, one finds diagrams everywhere, as does
                        Raine when she declares <hi rend="i">A Vision of the Last Judgment</hi> a
                        mandala and claims Blake to have described many mandalas. The nice thing
                        about mandalas is that they are ubiquitous, once one learns alertness.</p>
          <p>The title of this monograph can be taken literally. Raine spends some time on
                        its “to” (the space between Blake and <hi rend="i">A Vision</hi>),
                        which turns out to be the Ellis-Yeats <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> of 1893. In
                        the vast commentary in that work Yeats (and Ellis) introduced occultism into
                        the interpretation of Blake and made for the most part a tasteless mess of
                        it to go along with their butchering of Blake’s text. This occultism
                        has been inconvenient for most of us, but not for Raine. It is certainly the
                        occultist aspect of Yeats’s interpretation that is constantly getting
                        him into trouble. For example, Yeats “relates Blake’s quaternity
                        to the four ‘worlds’ of the Cabala and other systems” (p.
                        16). This is typical of where Raine thinks Yeats goes right, but I believe
                        him to be going rather consistently wrong here. Raine can accept much of
                        Yeats’s reading of Blake because her own interpretive level is so
                        lofty and abstract that she rarely feels she must stoop to details of the
                        text and never to questions of tone. Basically, however, the problem is that
                        not enough attention is paid to the way in which the whole of any of
                        Blake’s works controls how much we should read into any given part.
                        Unfortunately, at Raine’s level the “wisdom” of Swedenborg,
                        Blake, Yeats, and Jung is all one. These four are “among those who have
                        . . . attempted what must, sooner or later, be attempted if indeed a
                        ‘New Age’ and a change of the premises of our culture is
                        approaching.”</p>
          <p>There are too many unsupported dogmatisms in this monograph. Many years ago I
                        wrote what I think was the first serious American essay on Raine’s
                        poetry. It was a quite favorable account (I do not regret it), and I treated
                        her poetic voices as those of enchantress and medium. But neither of these
                        voices is the proper one for criticism. Luckily one can take my complaint,
                        put it to the side, and profit from parts of this text, for there are some
                        good things here though they are presented in a rather disorganized way.
                        Raine sees certain important shifts of emphasis from Blake to Yeats and
                        notices certain of Yeats’s misreadings. But must Blake’s
                        twenty-seven churches (correctly traced back to Swedenborg) be so simply
                        related to Yeats’s twenty-eight lunar phases, without so much as a
                        word that twenty-seven is not twenty-eight? Is Yeats’s little
                        dialogue in <hi rend="i">Vacillation</hi> really a dialogue with his master
                        Blake? Isn’t there, though not a “rotation” of Urizen and
                        Luvah, at least a cyclicity? Yeats got this all wrong because of his
                        astrologizing of Blake. Is Yeats’s mask really to be identified with
                        Tharmas quite so easily, as Raine does? Is there no time in Blake’s
                        eternity, or is eternity in Blake’s time? Or is it better to look
                        rather more closely and consider that there may be more than one time in
                        Blake? The most interesting part of the monograph is toward the end where
                        Raine discusses the influence of “The Mental Traveller” on <hi rend="i">A
Vision</hi> and various poems. Here, however, not as much as
                        she implies is new. She calls Blake’s poem a detailed examination of
                        his symbol of Canaan. That seems promising, but she goes on to utter over
                        several pages the following equation: Canaan = Mundane Shell or Egg = the
                        world of biblical history = space and time = the twenty-seven churches = the
                        covering cherub = the womb = the serpent = the center = the mills = the
                        wheels = dens = Newton’s universe = Milton’s chaos and ancient
                        night = Dante’s Purgatory = “under the hill.” This is, of
                        course, roughly so in the way Joyce later also made everybody everybody
                        else. But since all of these things are roughly the fallen world, the
                        revelation that the poem is about Canaan tells us nothing that hasn’t
                        been well known to readers of the poem for a long time under some other term
                        in the equation.</p>
          <p>Incidentally, in the process of observing Blake’s metaphorical chain,
                        Raine calls Satan the “lost traveller” of one of Blake’s
                        late short poems. But if we look at the syntax we discover that Satan is not
                        the traveller but “the lost traveller’s dream under the
                        hill.” Of course, where everybody is everybody else, this ultimately
                        makes no difference. Or does it? The whole basis of Blake’s thought
                        turns on the principle of identity and the paradox in that word. Fully read,
                        it indicates that everything has an identity of its own, but is identical to
                        other things as well. Raine’s occultism negates the first meaning and
                        presses for the second. This is the point at issue here. Was Blake an
                        occultist who would suppress individual identity or the “minute
                        particular,” which Raine seems to confuse with the conscious ego, or is
                        he a visionary poet who insists on both sides of the paradox at once? For
                        that matter, in the end which was Yeats?</p>
          <p>The monograph has numerous illustrations from occult texts, Blake, and <hi rend="i">A
Vision.</hi> Some are not discussed. That’s all right.
                        Most of them are mandalas.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
