<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.1.essick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Martin Butlin, The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</title>
        <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>George Hartley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
      <pb id="p16-22" n="22"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-1-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Martin Butlin. <hi rend="b">The Paintings and Drawings of William
                Blake.</hi> Two Volumes. New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1981.
              $300.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Robert N.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Essick</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>We have waited a long time for a complete and authoritative catalogue raisonné of
            Blake’s paintings and drawings. William Michael Rossetti made the first attempt,
            published in the second volume of Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William
              Blake</hi>, 1863. A revised version appeared in the 1880 <hi rend="i">Life</hi>, but
            it too is seriously flawed by Rossetti’s errors, paucity of basic information on sizes,
            media, and provenances, and an inability to control a tendency toward evaluative and
            impressionistic descriptions. Yet Rossetti’s lists are distinguished by having been
            compiled at a time when many works, including some now lost, were still in the
            possession of original purchasers or their immediate descendants.</p>
          <p>Archibald G. B. Russell was the next to begin a complete catalogue. According to a
            handsome broadside prospectus,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12"
type="note">1</ref> Methuen intended to
            publish Russell’s volume in 1905. He planned to include “an analysis of Blake’s art and
            the media employed by him,” and the two sample entries show that the catalogue would
            have been a considerable improvement over Rossetti’s work. Nothing seems to have come of
            Russell’s ambitious plans, although he did write the catalogues for the important Blake
            exhibitions at the National Gallery of British Art (now Tate Gallery) in 1913 and the
            Manchester Whitworth Institute (now Whitworth Art Gallery) in 1914, as well as a
            handlist of the W. Graham Robertson collection.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n13" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">1</hi> A copy in my collection bears a handwritten
              note to a potential purchaser dated 17 September 1904. The prospective title was 
                <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake, a Critical Study with a
                Catalogue Raisonné of His Works and Forty Plates in Photogravure and
              Colour.</hi></note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">2</hi> The last was published in the
                <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 37 (1920), 27-39.</note></p>
          <p>In the world of academic art history, a catalogue raisonné is generally considered the
            most important scholarly work on an artist, the foundation and impetus for all other
            types of studies. By the late 1920s, Blake enthusiasts must have considered a new
            catalogue of his drawings and paintings a primary requisite in the field. By the next
            decade, Ruthven Todd, with the encouragement and assistance of Geoffrey Keynes, began a
            major effort to meet this need. Todd worked on his catalogue for at least a dozen years,
            and he produced several lengthy drafts. His labors were well advanced by 1942, for in
            July of that year he presented to Graham Robertson a seventy-five page typescript album
            of Blake’s works in Robertson’s collection based — as Todd states in a letter
            accompanying the album—on his “big catalogue.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n14" type="note">3</ref> This
            larger work may have been the typescript of 231 pages, now among Todd’s papers at the
            University of Leeds, containing annotations by Keynes datable up to 1946. But the final,
            longest version of Todd’s work is a typescript of 553 pages, including indices and
            numerous handwritten additions by the author datable to at least 1947.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15"
              type="note">4</ref> Sometime between 1966 and 1968, 
              <ref target="n16" type="note">5</ref> Todd presented this catalogue to Lessing J. Rosenwald, who
in turn gave it to
            the Library of Congress. The project apparently ended there, still some distance from
            publication, although xerox copies of the LC typescript have become something of an
            underground classic among Blakeans. <note id="n14"><hi rend="s">3</hi> The album and
              letter are now in my collection. Robertson may have used some of Todd’s information
              when the collector wrote his holograph catalogue (also in my possession) of his
              Blakes. This was posthumously published as <hi rend="i">The Blake Collection of W.
                Graham Robertson</hi>, ed. Kerrison Preston (London: Faber and Faber,
              1952).</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">4</hi> The annotations include references to
              the 1947 Blake exhibition at the Galerie René Drouin, Paris, but there is no mention
              of the great Robertson auction two years later.</note>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Among the Todd papers at Leeds is a letter of 25 February 1966 to Todd
from
              Rosenwald in which Rosenwald states his willingness to receive the “Blake
              bibliography” (i.e., catalogue?). In a letter to Rosenwald of 26 December 1968, Todd
              notes that his draft catalogue was then at the National Gallery of Art, Washington. I
              have not surveyed the Todd papers for other references to the catalogue; my comments
              here are based on a typescript handlist of the collection at Leeds.</note></p>
          <pb id="p16-23" n="23"/>
          <p>Martin Butlin has at last succeeded where other scholars and their publishers had
            failed. His work was originally sponsored by the Blake Trust under the guidance of its
            chairman, Sir Geoffrey Keynes. Although Butlin made use of both typescripts of Todd’s
            catalogue, he spent more than ten years checking all of Todd’s information, bringing it
            up to date, and personally inspecting almost every drawing and painting attributed to
            Blake. A nearly finished version of his work was partially printed in galley proof by
            the Trianon Press, which intended to publish the catalogue in a handsome format with a
            limited number of high-quality illustrations. The death in 1977 of the Trianon’s
            director and moving spirit, Arnold Fawcus, brought an end to the direct involvement of
            that press. Yale University Press in London took over and, with the financial assistance
            of Paul Mellon and the Yale Center for British Art, published the two-volume catalogue
            reviewed here. It is most appropriately dedicated to Arnold Fawcus and the members of
            the Blake Trust who did not live to see its completion.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> is an extraordinary work
            of scholarship. We have at one stroke moved from having no catalogue raisonné of Blake’s
            art to having one of the finest ever written on any artist. In the study of Blake’s
            drawings and paintings, Butlin’s work will have the same historical importance as
            Keynes’ bibliography and edition of the 1920s have had in the study of Blake’s writings.
            Serious students of Blake’s art will have to use this catalogue continually as their
            basic reference tool; those who do not attend to the facts Butlin sets forth will be
            doing themselves (and Blake) a disservice. Let me also recommend to the subscribers of
            this journal that they read the catalogue word for word, cover to cover. I cannot expect
            most Blakeans to relish the details of provenances as fervently as I, but soaking in so
            many minute particulars on size, media, pentimenti, signatures, dating, and history has
            been for me an incomparable educational experience.</p>
          <p>Butlin covers all of the drawings and paintings that can reasonably be attributed to
            Blake, plus color printed etchings and engravings which one can reasonably assume were
            originally printed by Blake as separate impressions. All these works are organized into
            twenty-nine roughly chronological sections, followed by a list of forty-nine
            miscellaneous untraced works, catalogues of works by Blake’s wife and brother, and a
            table of watermarks. The information in each entry is set forth in the same form as
            Butlin’s catalogue of the Blakes at the Tate Gallery.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n17" type="note">6</ref> There is no need for me to summarize that format here; suffice it to say that
            everything is clear, precise, straightforward, and thorough. The volume of text (vol. I)
            concludes with an index to subjects and titles and a general index that includes the
            names of all owners, past and present. The only improvement I can suggest for the latter
            is that the long lists of entry numbers following “Christie, Manson &amp; Woods Ltd.”
            and “Sotheby, Parke Bernet and Co.” could have been usefully divided according to the
            dates of the auctions recorded therein. <note id="n17"><hi rend="s">6</hi> William
              Blake, <hi rend="i">A Complete Catalogue of the Works in the Tate Gallery</hi>, rev.
              ed. (London: Tate Gallery, 1971).</note></p>
          <p>One of the more remarkable features of this remarkable book is the second volume,
            containing 1,194 illustrations (the publisher advertises only 1,158). Except for seven
            series of drawings, reproduced elsewhere in recent years, and a few slight verso
            sketches, <hi rend="i">every extant drawing and painting is reproduced.</hi> Butlin has
            provided both a catalogue and, in a sense, an “edition” of Blake’s images. This
            pictorial edition can be completed with the addition of the following reproductions of
            series of works: 
			<q><hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> illustrations. All extant reproduced in G.
              E. Bentley, Jr., ed., <hi rend="i">William Blake: Tiriel</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon
              Press, 1967).<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Notebook.</hi> David V. Erdman and Donald
              K. Moore, eds., <hi rend="i">The Notebook of William Blake</hi>, 2nd ed. (New York:
              Readex Books, 1977).<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> illustrations. John E.
              Grant, Edward J. Rose, Michael J. Tolley, eds., co-ordinating editor David V. Erdman,
                <hi rend="i">Blake’s Designs for Edward Young’s “Night Thoughts</hi>,” 2 vols.
              (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1980).<lb/>
<lb/>
 Illustrations to Gray’s 
                <hi rend="i">Poems.</hi> Irene Tayler, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations to the Poems of
                Gray</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1971). Complete color facsimiles
              in Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Watercolour Designs for the Poems of
                Thomas Gray</hi> (Paris: Trianon Press for the Blake Trust, 1972).<lb/>
<lb/>
                <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> Manuscript. G. E. Bentley, Jr., ed., <hi rend="i">William
                Blake: Vala, or the Four Zoas</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1963). David Erdman and
              Cettina Magno are currently preparing a new reproduction of the complete
                manuscript.<lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="i">The Blake-Varley Sketchbook.</hi> Martin Butlin,
              ed., <hi rend="i">The Blake-Varley Sketchbook of 1819</hi> (London: Heinemann,
              1969).<lb/>
<lb/>
 Illustrations to <hi rend="i">The Divine Comedy.</hi> Albert S. Roe,
                <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations to the Divine Comedy</hi> (Princeton: Princeton
              University Press, 1953). Also available in portfolios issued in 1922 and 1968, and in
              Milton Klonsky, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Dante</hi> (New York: Harmony Books, 1980). </q>
            Thus a library containing a mere eight titles can now provide reproductiosn of almost
            every extant drawing and painting by Blake, his wife, and his brother. To this
            collection we need to add only one further volume, David Bindman’s <hi rend="i">The
              Complete Graphic Works of William Blake</hi> (London: Thames and Hudson, 1978), to
            cover all images invented by Blake. The only <hi rend="i">lacunae</hi> remaining are
            some images executed but not invented by him<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">7</ref> and
            the many hand colored or color printed copies of the illuminated books that have not yet
            been reproduced. The doors of perception are now almost fully open. 
                <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Most of the reproductive book illustrations to c. 1796 are
              reproduced in Roger R. Easson and Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake: Book
                Illustrator</hi>, Vol. II (Memphis, Tenn.: American Blake Foundation, 1979). All the
              separate copy plates will be reproduced in a new catalogue of the separate plates to
              be published by Princeton University Press.</note></p>
          <pb id="p16-24" n="24"/>
          <p>Butlin and his publisher have generously included 251 color plates. These have been
            judiciously selected and include the early series illustrating the story of Joseph, all
            five versions of “Pestilence,” the six water colors in the extra-illustrated second
            folio of Shakespeare (British Museum), all eight series of illustrations to Milton’s
            poems, and the Butts set of Job water colors (Pierpont Morgan Library). With so many
            color reproductions it is not too surprising that the quality is uneven. Many plates
            look lovely, with rich and presumably true tones, but some that I have compared against
            the originals in the Huntington Library fall short of adequate. In the 
              <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> series of twelve designs, the warm browns and cool greens and
            grays of the originals have uniformly turned a gelid steel-blue. Perhaps someone is
            already busy writing an article, based on these reproductions, interpreting Blake’s
            changes between the icy conception of hell (and Eden?) in the Thomas-Huntington set of
            1807 and the warmer climes pictured in the Butts set of the next year. Oddly enough, the
            “Satan, Sin and Death” from the Butts group, detached from its companions and now with
            the Huntington series, has much better color fidelity. The fault seems to have been not
            with the ektachrome transparencies but with Yale’s printing of them, as I can testify is
            the case with the sickly green reproduction of the version of “Pestilence” in my
            collection. The blue shift also infects the Huntington series illustrating 
              <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and <hi rend="i">On the Morning of Christ’s Nativity</hi>, although
less
            seriously than in the <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> water colors. I do not decry the
            presence of the color plates, but one must certainly be careful when using them. Those
            who need guaranteed accuracy in their color perceptions must still visit the
            originals.</p>
          <p>A reviewer could legitimately cease at this point, rounding off his efforts with a
            final display of congratulatory adjectives and a prophecy of the book’s undoubted
            authority and utility for years to come. I intend, however, to take a leisurely tour of
            the entire catalogue, pausing along the way to point out curious features and
            interesting prospects. I have more than one excuse for taking this approach. By at least
            noting all thirty-two sections of the catalogue, I hope to indicate something of its
            scope, as well as provide an outline of Blake’s artistic career. There are many
            discoveries recorded by Butlin, easily overlooked among the great mass of information he
            presents, and simply to highlight and summarize these will serve a purpose. Although
            remarkably few for a text of 694 pages, there are some typos and simple errors of fact
            that deserve correction in a work of such surpassing importance. In some cases I offer
            counter-arguments to Butlin’s interpretations and attributions—not because his line of
            thinking is weak, but because there is another side to the issue that deserves
            exploration. My more extended annotations to the catalogue are often idiosyncratic and
            never definitive. They may, however, indicate some ways Butlin’s great work can
            stimulate thought, both concrete and speculative, and provide the foundation for future
            studies of Blake the artist. At the very least, the following will show that there is
            room enough in this catalogue for all of us to ride our hobbyhorses.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">I. Blake’s Apprenticeship: Westminster Abbey, 1772-1779</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Most readers will probably be surprised to learn that at least forty-eight drawings
              have survived from Blake’s apprentice years. Almost all of these were prepared in
              connection with James Basire and the Society of Antiquaries. They demonstrate Blake’s
              early involvement with medieval history and art and the exacting trade of accurately
              reproducing architectural and sculptural antiquities. Blake’s later development of a
              pictorial aesthetic centered on line and precision has its practical antecedents in
              these early projects.</p>
            <p>The work for Basire falls into three groups. Two drawings record the opening of the
              tomb of Edward I at Westminster Abbey on 2 May 1774 under the direction of Sir Joseph
              Ayloffe. At a slightly later date, Blake made at least nine drawings for plates in
              Ayloffe’s <hi rend="i">Account of Some Ancient Monuments in Westminster Abbey</hi>
              (1780). There are also replicas of seven of the Ayloffe drawings, apparently made for
              Richard Gough because they are now with his collection at the Bodleian Library. Butlin
              also attributes these to Blake (#12-18),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
type="note">8</ref> although
              one cannot rule out the possibility that they were executed by another hand at a later
              date. Butlin states that Ayloffe’s <hi rend="i">Account</hi> was “reissued in the
              second volume of <hi rend="i">Vetusta Monumenta</hi> in 1789.” I have never seen a
              copy of Ayloffe’s essay other than as part of the <hi rend="i">Vetusta</hi>, a work
              published in parts and bound by purchasers in various formats with general title
              pages. Some copies containing Ayloffe’s <hi rend="i">Account</hi> are dated 1789 on
              the general title page, but others are undated. It is not at all certain that copies
              of Ayloffe’s work bound in the <hi rend="i">Vetusta</hi> represent a “reissue.” All
              copies of his <hi rend="i">Account</hi> may have been printed in 1780, the date on its
              title page. <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">8</hi> I will use this form of reference to
                Butlin’s entry numbers thoughout the remainder of this review. These numbers may
                take on the same authority long since awarded to Keynes’ letter designations for the
                illuminated books.</note></p>
            <p>The third and largest group of apprentice drawings (#19-47) were prepared for
              engraving in Gough’s <hi rend="i">Sepulchral Monuments</hi>, not published until 1786.
              Butlin adds several works to Keynes’ list of drawings in the Bodleian for both Ayloffe
              and Gough, and corrects two captions in <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> in which three
              of the Ayloffe originals in the Society of Antiquaries are labeled as the Bodleian
                replicas.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">9</ref> As it does
so often, Butlin’s
              catalogue has clarified and completed the factual basis for work by other scholars.
                <note id="n20"><hi rend="s">9</hi> See “The Engraver’s Apprentice,” pp. 14-30 and
                pls. 5 and 8 in Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 2nd ed. (Oxford: Clarendon
                Press, 1971).</note></p>
            <p>Butlin’s attributions give additional support to the belief that the plates in
              Gough’s <hi rend="i">Sepulchral Monuments</hi> picturing tombs and statues in
              Westminster Abbey, signed by Basire as delineator and engraver, are indeed based on
              drawings by Blake. The catalogue of twenty-nine drawings engraved on twenty-two plates
              in Gough adds two plates to Bentley’s list<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n21" type="note">10</ref> of
              twenty (four very tentative) and accords with the list in Easson &amp; Essick with but
              one exception. Butlin does not attribute the drawing of “Eleanor Dutchess of Glocester
              1399” (Gough plate LX; no. 19 in Easson &amp; Essick) to Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
                type="note">11</ref> Even though it is signed “Basire. del,” like the other Gough
              drawings in the Bodleian, Butlin does not include it because it “seems to be different
              in style from the other works associated with Blake” (p. 6). It certainly 
                <pb id="p16-25" n="25"/>
is in a different style, as is the engraving, but this might be
              explained by the fact that Eleanor’s monument is a floor slab inlaid in lines of
              brass, whereas the other monuments Blake drew are three-dimensional sculptures or
              bas-reliefs in stone. The artist may simply be adopting his style to suit his subject
              and the accuracy required of archaeological illustration—an early example of the
              “appropriate execution” Blake commended years later in the <hi rend="i">Public
                Address.</hi> Further, if the drawing is by some other apprentice or journeyman
              employed by Basire, he must have sent two employees to Westminster Abbey. This seems
              unlikely, particularly if Malkin is right about Blake’s having been sent to the Abbey
              in order to separate him from contentious workers in Basire’s shop.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23"
                type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">10</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., 
                  <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977), pp. 567-68.</note>	
                <note id="n22"><hi rend="s">11</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake: Book Illustrator</hi>, II,
                55-63.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Benjamin Heath Malkin, 
                  <hi rend="i">A Father’s Memoirs of his Child</hi> (London: Longman, Hurst, Rees, and Orme,
                1806), pp. xix-xx.</note></p>
            <p>The following are comments on individual works listed by Butlin’s entry numbers. I
              will append such lists to most of the following discussions of Butlin’s chronological
              sections.</p>
            <p>#3, “Countess Aveline, Side View of Her Tomb” (Society of Antiquaries, London). As
              Butlin indicates, the “J Basire” signature on this and most of Blake’s other drawings
              executed for his master has the first two letters in monogram, sharing a common
              vertical. Others bear the JB initials alone, similarly joined. Is this the immediate
              predecessor to Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> monogram? In Basire’s version,
              the top loop of the B continues to the left, arching slightly over the J. Blake’s
              circular extension of the lower loop of the B in his monogram may be a modification
              and magnification of his master’s distinctive signature.</p>
            <p>It would have been helpful, and have accorded perfectly with Butlin’s usual practice,
              to have included cross-references here and for #4, 5, 7-10 to the replica drawings in
              the Bodleian (#12-18).</p>
            <p>#38, “Queen Philippa, Side View of Her Tomb” (Bodleian Library). The reference should
              be to Gough’s <hi rend="i">Sepulchral Monuments</hi> plate 48, not plate “42.”</p>
            <p>#50, “Figure from Michelangelo’s ‘Last Judgment’” (Huntington Library). Butlin
              expresses considerable doubt about the attribution of this oil painting (illus. 1) to
              Blake, but includes it nonetheless. I have no doubt that this is <hi rend="i">not</hi>
              by Blake. As Butlin states, the “style and technique” of the painting are “completely
              uncharacteristic” of Blake’s work in the same early period. The total absence of drawn
              outlines in ink or paint clearly distinguishes it from the Gough and Ayloffe drawings,
              also of the 1770s, and the designs for English history (#51-70) of c. 1779. Indeed, it
              is hard to imagine how a copy of one of Michelangelo’s figures could be less like
              Blake’s style as either a careful copyist or an inventor of original compositions. The
              bold signature and date lower right on this oil (“W. Blake 1776”) are, as Butlin
              states, “sufficiently unlike Blake’s usual forms to be inadequate evidence for his
              authorship.” According to the Huntington’s catalogue of its Blake collection, the
              library’s founder acquired the painting “in New York, 1916.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24"
                type="note">13</ref> I suspect that this means only c. 1916 and that the purchase
              was made while Huntington was residing in New York, but not necessarily from a New
              York dealer. On 20 February of the next year, Huntington purchased from Rosenbach of
              Philadelphia the <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> illustrations and a portfolio of drawings
              with bold Blake signatures for $17,200 the lot.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n25" type="note">14</ref>
              None of the latter group is by Blake. That the signatures are intentional forgeries is
              confirmed by the signature of Henry Pierce Bone (English artist, 1779-1855) on one
              drawing—not quite completely rubbed off and painted over. One drawing has a date of
              “17—,” trimmed off by the edge of the sheet, as well as the signature. No two
              signatures in this collection are identical, but all area of the same general
              character and to my eye seem to have been made by the same hand. The inscription on
              this painting after Michelangelo fits comfortably into this family of fakes. 
                <note id="n24"><hi rend="s">13</hi> C. H. Collins Baker, <hi rend="i">Catalogue of William
                  Blake’s Drawings and Paintings in the Huntington Library</hi>, rev. by R. R. Wark
                (San Marino: Huntington Library, 1963), p. 53. I have not been able to locate any
                further information on the acquisition of the painting or documents supporting the
                catalogue statement.</note>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">14</hi> According to a note
                kept with the <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> water colors. Butlin, #527, states that these
                were purchased in 1916 for $29,000 (apparently the price at which Rosenbach offered
                the drawings in his 1916 catalogue no. 18, item 17).</note></p>
            <figure n="Michelangelo.LastJudgment.16.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="804">
              <head>1 “Figure from Michelangelo’s ‘Last Judgment.’”</head>
              <figDesc>Oil on paper, 51.7 × 31.9 cm. Inscribed “W. Blake 1776” lower right and
                “William Blake. Study for the Last Judgment Signed and dated 1776. from Mr. Flaxmans
                collection” on verso. Butlin #50. Huntington Library.</figDesc>
            </figure>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p16-26" n="26"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">II. Illustrations to English History, c. 1779 and c. 1793</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>David Bindman has already discussed Blake’s early series of illustrations to English
              history in some detail and has at least noted works in the later groups.<ref
                target="n26" type="note">15</ref> Yet the coordinated information that Butlin
              presents on sizes, media, and datings allows one to see, more clearly than ever
              before, Blake’s long involvement with these historical subjects and his attempts to
              develop them into a significant series of illustrations. They comprise one of his most
              important artistic projects from c. 1779 to at least 1793. Almost all the compositions
              fall into five groups, as listed below in chronological order.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27"
                type="note">16</ref> The same subjects do not necessarily reappear in successive
              groups. <note id="n26"><hi rend="s">15</hi> “Blake’s ‘Gothicised Imagination’ and the
                History of England,” pp. 29-49 in <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays in Honour of
                  Sir Geoffrey Keynes</hi>, ed. Morton D. Paley and Michael Phillips (Oxford:
                Clarendon Press, 1973). See also Bindman’s <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist</hi>
                (Oxford: Phaidon, 1977), pp. 22-27. <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist</hi> generally
                holds up very well when matched against Butlin’s detailed information on the works
                surveyed by Bindman.</note>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Groups a and b are
                intermixed by Butlin; c and d are engravings and therefore not catalogued by
                him.</note></p>
            <p>a. The small drawings of c. 1779 (#51-53, 54[?],<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n28" type="note">17</ref> 57, 60, 61[?], 62, 64, 65[?], 67, perhaps 184 and 197A—see below for a
              discussion of the last). <note id="n28"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Entry numbers followed by
                a question mark indicate untraced works which have an uncertain relationship to the
                group.</note></p>
            <p>b. The large drawings of c. 1793, showing a strong neoclassical influence. These
              compositions began as outline pencil drawings of about 30 × 45 cm.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29"
                type="note">18</ref> (#56, 58, 68); at least a few were developed into carefully
              executed water colors of about 20 × 28 cm. (#55, 69) or 32 × 50 cm. (#59, 63 [the
              untraced but presumably necessary preliminary drawing for the engraving “Edward &amp;
              Elenor”], 66). Butlin’s comparatively late dating of these works lends further
              credence to a late dating of the large “Edward &amp; Elenor” engraving and, by
              inference, of the first state of the “Job” and “Ezekiel” separate plates.<ref
                target="n30" type="note">19</ref>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">18</hi> The
                measurements I give for groups are approximate averages. Individual compositions may
                vary considerably from these averages, but not by so much as to suggest another
                group.</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">19</hi> See Essick, <hi rend="i">William
                  Blake, Printmaker</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1981), pp. 64-68,
                186, 219-20; Figs. 60, 61.</note></p>
            <p>c. “The History of England, a small book of Engravings” advertised by Blake in his
              prospectus “To The Public” of 10 October 1793. No copy has ever been traced or
              described. Several drawings in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>, and a list of
              subjects on page 116, may relate to this set of plates. It is of course possible that
              the “book” was never engraved, although every other work listed by title and price in
              the 1793 prospectus was published.</p>
            <p>d. A projected series of large plates on “the History of England” mentioned as being
              in preparation in the 1793 prospectus. Blake may have intended to base these on the
              1793 watercolors (group b, above), but only “Edward &amp; Elenor” is known.</p>
            <p>e. A group of compositions on the themes of war and plague (#184-97), all listed by
              Butlin in the fourth section of his catalogue. These probably began with #184,
              “Pestilence,” of c. 1779-1780, the style and size (13.8 × 18.6 cm.) of which strongly
              suggest that it was one of the series (a, above) of small illustrations to English
              history. This design became detached from the historical series and was developed
              independently through at least four further versions (#185, 190, 192, 193),
              culminating in the “Pestilence” of c. 1805 (Boston Museum of Fine Arts). To this
              subject Blake added three companions, “Fire,” “War,” and “Famine,” in 1805
(#194-96).
              Another design, “A Breach in a City,” developed through three drawings (#188, 189,
              191), seems to be part of this group and culminates in the “War” of 1805 (#195). An
              interesting borrowing of motifs from this group is the use of the bellman and man
              supporting a slumping woman, lower left in the first two “Pestilence” compositions, on
              plate 10 of <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi> The “Pestilence” and “Breach in a City” subjects
              began as members of a historical group, evolved into independent works in more than
              one medium, and then were rejoined in their final versions.</p>
            <p>As is so typical of Blake’s habits as artist and poet, what began as an interest in
              specific historical subjects grew into a concern with universal categories of human
              experience and consciousness: not the London plague of 1665, but pestilence in all
              times and places; not the fire of 1666, but fire as metaphor for a host of conditions
              and processes. All these subjects and themes find their most complex treatment in the
              illuminated books, although they are not the only progeny of Blake’s early interest in
              historical compositions.</p>
            <p>Comments on individual entries follow.</p>
            <p>#51, “The Landing of Brutus in England,” and #52, “A Landing in Britain” (both Robert
              H. Taylor Collection). Butlin points out the “frieze-like” relationship between these
              two drawings. Although all the other history designs of c. 1779 are self-contained,
              perhaps Blake was thinking of his compositions as wall decorations in a large room
              with some designs arranged as a frieze. James Barry had begun his paintings for the
              Society of Arts in 1777, and some of these are greatly elongated in an enormous
              frieze, while others have more conventional height-width ratios.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
                type="note">20</ref> Perhaps Barry’s vast undertaking fired the imagination of his
              ambitious young admirer. Years later, Blake continued to dream of such projects,
              describing in an advertisement to his 1809 exhibition “The Invention of a portable
              Fresco” suitable for decorating “Westminster Hall, or the walls of any other great
              Building.” <note id="n31"><hi rend="s">20</hi> See William L. Pressly, 
                  <hi rend="i">The Life and Art of James Barry</hi> (New Haven and London: Yale University
                Press, 1981), pp. 86-122.</note></p>
            <p>#59, “The Ordeal of Queen Emma” (Private Collection, Great Britain). The reference
              should be to Plate 177, not “176.”</p>
            <p>#60, “The Death of Earl Goodwin” (British Museum). The reference should be to Plate
              178, not “177.”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">III. Miscellaneous Early Works, Mainly in Pen and Wash, c.
                  1775-1790</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Every catalogue needs omnibus sections to hold everything from the singular
              masterpiece to the detritus of an artist’s career. Butlin requires only four. The
              variety of styles exhibited by the works in this first miscellaneous section reveal
              Blake’s reactions to the cross-currents of influences affecting most of his
              contemporaries in the 1780s, that remarkable decade in the history of English art when
              not only Blake but Stothard, Romney, and Flaxman were searching for their own styles.
              The presences of Mortimer and Barry are felt in these drawings; certainly Stothard is
              there, perhaps Romney; and the shifts between rococo energy and sweetness and
              neoclassical idealism and restraint are clearly present. The variety of subjects and
              styles offers 
<pb id="p16-27" n="27"/>
many ways of grouping these works. But let me
              reduce the possible categories to a mere nine as a way of indicating the range and
              something of the structure of Blake’s endeavors, 1775-1790.</p>
            <p>a. Academic studies taken from the life or sculptured or engraved models (#71-73).
              These include the recto-verso sketches later developed into “Albion rose,” and
              probably reflect Blake’s brief attendance in the Royal Academy school. To this small
              group we can add the carefully executed copies (c. 1785) of Adamo Ghisi’s engravings
              after Michelangelo’s Sistine frescoes (#167-70).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n32" type="note">21</ref>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">21</hi> See Jenijoy La Belle, “Blake’s Visions
                and Re-visions of Michelangelo,” in <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, ed. Robert
                N. Essick and Donald Pearce (Bloomington &amp; London: Indiana University Press,
                1978), pp. 13-22.</note></p>
            <p>b. A large group of biblical subjects, including Saul and Samuel (#74-75, 117),
              Abraham and Isaac (#108-109), Moses and the Ten Commandents (#111-115), Manoah (#116),
              and Saul and David (#118-119A). The collection is far too diverse to be called a
              series or even an interrelated group; they could well be independent compositions not
              executed with any overall scheme or ultimate purpose in mind. Yet some may be part of
              a long, multifaceted development of several series of Bible illustrations loosely
              paralleling the pictures of English history. The graphic renderings, finished and
              projected, of biblical and historical subjects are grouped together in Blake’s
              prelusive comments in his 1793 prospectus. Important subgroups in the biblical works
              are the three finished water colors of the story of Joseph (#155-57, exhibited in
              1785) and their extant preliminary sketches (#158 and 159 recto and verso), the Job
              and Ezekiel drawings (#162-66) leading to the large separate plates, and six versions
              of a “Good Farmer” composition (#120-25; see illus. 2-4). This last group shows
              Blake’s way of meditating on paper, working up and reworking the same composition over
              a period of about five years. Butlin is particularly good at briefly indicating
              erasures and the successive changes from one version to the next.</p>
            <p>c. Seven Shakespeare heads (#84; illus. 5-6). Butlin dates these c. 1780, but they
              look somewhat more accomplished than other works of that period and show hints of the
              neoclassicism of the Joseph series (see b, above) exhibited in 1785. I would suggest
              c. 1783. See also comments on #84.7, below.</p>
            <p>d. A narrative group on murder, exile, and reunion (#85-88 rectos, versos of 85 and
              86, perhaps 90 and 91). Some motifs, particularly the position of the figures’ heads
              and the tendril designs on the curtain in #85 recto, the general style, and the
              apparent subjects of this group<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33"
type="note">22</ref> suggest that it
              represents a preliminary form of a series similar to the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>
              drawings. Butlin dates all but #90 to c. 1785-90, but their style suggests that they
              are prior to the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> designs of c. 1789. Was there a (now lost)
              poem that this group illustrated? Arguments by analogy—i.e., the drawings are like the
                <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> illustrations, and thus there may have been a poem like 
                <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>—take us close to the realm of pure speculation. Yet the query
              is the very sort that Butlin’s disciplined, factual catalogue often stimulates in its
              reader’s imagination. <note id="n33"><hi rend="s">22</hi> #85-88 and their related
                verso sketches have been discussed by Michael Tolley, “Some Blake Puzzles—Old and
                New,” and John E. Grant, “Addenda and Some Solutions to Tolley’s Blake Puzzles,” 
                  <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 3 (1971), 107-35.</note></p>
            <p>e. A group picturing Satan confronting various allies and adversaries, very probably
              based on <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> (#101-105). #106, “Death Shaking the 
              <figure n="BUT122.1.1r.WD" rend="file" width="958" height="685">
                <head>2 “The Good Farmer.”</head>
                <figDesc>Pen and wash over pencil, 33.6 × 47.3 cm., c. 1780-1785. Butlin #122 recto.
                  Essick Collection.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <figure n="but122.1.1v.pid" id="but122v.1.penink.01" work-copy="pid" rend="db" width="958" height="680">
				<figTranscr>The good Farmer giving his fields <lb/>
				 in Famine<lb/>
				 both sides.</figTranscr>
                <head>3 Verso of illus. 2, a further development of the same subject.</head>
                <figDesc>Butlin #122 verso.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <figure n="BUT123.1.1r.WD" rend="file" width="958" height="684">
                <head>4 “The Good Farmer.”</head>
                <figDesc>Pen and wash, 26.7 × 37.5 cm., c. 1780-1785. Butlin #123 recto, developed
                  from #122 verso (illus. 3). Tate Gallery.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <pb id="p16-28" n="28"/>
              <figure n="BUT84.1.1.WC" rend="file" width="958" height="772">
                <head>5 Shakespeare Heads.</head>
                <figDesc>Pen and water color, ovals, each approximately 5.7 × 9.5 cm., c. 1780 (?).
                  Butlin #84. Juliet asleep</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <figure n="BUT84.1.6.WC" rend="file" width="958" height="744">
                <head>Macbeth and his Lady</head>
              </figure>
              <figure n="BUT84.1.7.WC" rend="file" width="958" height="740">
                <head>Prospero and Miranda (or Lear and Cordelia?)</head>
              </figure>
              <figure n="BUT84.1.3.WC" rend="file" width="958" height="800">
                <head>Othello and Desdemona.</head>
                <figDesc>Boston Museum of Fine Arts.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <figure n="BUT84.1.4.WC" rend="file" width="958" height="754">
                <head>6 Shakespeare Heads (see caption to illus. 5).</head>
                <figDesc>Cordelia and Lear</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <figure n="BUT84.1.5.WC" rend="file" width="958" height="788">
                <head>Lear</head>
              </figure>
              <figure n="BUT84.1.2.WC" rend="file" width="958" height="758">
                <head>Falstaff and Prince Hal.</head>
                <figDesc>Boston Museum of Fine Arts.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <figure n="BUT135.1.1.WD" rend="file" width="958" height="664">
                <head>7 “The Spirit of a Just Man Newly Departed Appearing to his Mourning
                  Family.”</head>
                <figDesc>Pen and gray wash, 33 × 48.8 cm., c. 1780-1785. Butlin #135. Royal
                  Collection, Windsor.</figDesc>
              </figure> 
              Dart—Milton” (untraced) may be related. These seem to be Blake’s first
              pictorial attempts at Miltonic subjects.</p>
            <p>f. A group dealing with death and burial (#135-39, the last two untraced). This
              includes #136, “The Counsellor, King, Warrior, Mother and Child,” later developed into
              one of the illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> published in
              1808. #135, “The Spirit of a Just Man Newly Departed Appearing to his Mourning Family”
              (illus. 7) was the basis for an emblem sketch on p. 61 of Blake’s 
                <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>, used in turn for plate 13 of <hi rend="i">The Gates of
Paradise</hi>
              (illus. 8). Butlin’s cross-references, notes, and illustrations allow one to trace,
              more efficiently and thoroughly than ever before, many such histories of Blake’s
              compositions and motifs.</p>
            <p>g. Illustrations to <hi rend="i">Robinson Crusoe</hi>, c. 1780-1785 (#140 recto,
              141). This is the only group that may have had some connection with a commercial
              commission, although that seems unlikely even when Blake is illustrating an enormously
              popular text. Stothard’s <hi rend="i">Robinson Crusoe</hi> illustrations of 1781 were
              published in <hi rend="i">The Novelist’s Magazine</hi>, a series for which Blake began
              engraving plates no later than 1782. Stothard also produced a fine series of
              illustrations for an edition of <hi rend="i">Robinson Crusoe</hi> published in 1790 by
              John Stockdale, who employed Blake to engrave plates for his 1793 edition of Gay’s 
                <hi rend="i">Fables.</hi> Perhaps Stothard’s work prompted Blake to try his hand at
              novel illustration. At the very least, his friend’s designs exemplify the context of
              commercial book illustration in which—or against which—Blake worked. That these two
              drawings are awkward and amateurish will not inhibit our fascination with them. Just
              what was the great man up to ?</p>
            <pb id="p16-29" n="29"/>
            <figure n="gates-child.B.p13.16.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="569">
              <head>8 <hi rend="i">For Children: The Gates of Paradise</hi>, copy B, plate
                13.</head>
              <figDesc>Intaglio etching, 8.1 × 7.2 cm., 1793. British Museum.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="BUT204.1.1.PD" rend="file" width="814" height="1000">
                <head>9 “How I Pity,” perhaps a rejected design for <hi rend="i">The Gates of
                    Paradise.</hi></head>
                <figDesc>Pencil, 5.5 × 6.5 cm., c. 1793. Butlin #204. British Museum.</figDesc>
            </figure> 
            <p>Rossetti (Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>, 1863, II, 235) lists among
              Blake’s “works in colour” a “Robinson Crusoe” design with “a visionary effect of
              colour, like a transparency.” Butlin very tentatively identifies this description with
              #140 recto, but could Rossetti possibly describe this monochrome pen and indian ink
              sketch in such glowing terms and declare it “fine”? It seems likely that Rossetti is
              referring to yet a third <hi rend="i">Crusoe</hi> design, as Rodney M. Baine has
              suggested (“Blake and Defoe,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 6 [1972],
              51-53).</p>
            <p>h. The <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> illustrations (#198-200), grouped together in
              Butlin’s fifth section. Although this series was very probably intended for
              conventional intaglio etching/engraving, if intended for publication at all, these
              carefully executed monochrome drawings are Blake’s first known attempts at
              illustrating his own poetry. They are among the most accomplished works of his first
              thirty-five years. The invention, c. 1789, of “Illuminated Printing” (as Blake called
              his new medium in the 1793 prospectus) seems to have put a sudden end to such
              high-finish visual/verbal projects. It is difficult to overestimate the impact on
              Blake’s art of what was, at its inception, a merely technical innovation that must
              have seemed to his contemporaries as little more than a crude descent down the
              hierarchy of graphic media and genres.</p>
            <p>i. The emblem series in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> (#201) and other drawings
              related to <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi> (#202-214; see illus. 9). All the
                <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> drawings, whether emblems in the series first described
              by Erdman<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">23</ref> or
preliminaries for other designs,
              are gathered in Butlin’s sixth section. This section 
              also includes some little-known drawings (illus. 10) of uncertain subject
              with only a distant relationship to the <hi rend="i">Notebook.</hi>
              <note id="n34"><hi rend="s">23</hi> In his facsimile edition of the 
              	<hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>, first published in 1973.</note></p>
            <p>Comments on individual entries in sections III through VI follow.</p>
            <p>#80, “Two Sketches of a Swordsman Standing over his Defeated Opponent” (National
              Gallery of Art). Butlin suggests that this sheet of recto-verso sketches once belonged
              to Mrs. William Dobinson, great-granddaughter of Thomas Chevalier, and comments that
              the only Blake work definitely known to have been owned by her is copy a of 
                <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi> However, she also owned the
              second-state impressions of the “Job” and “Ezekiel” separate plates now in Keynes’
              collection. According to Butlin’s provenance information, Mrs. Dobinson (or another
              “great-granddaughter” of Chevalier?) also owned #802, “Drawings from a Sketchbook”
              (Keynes Collection).</p>
            <p>#84.7, “Prospero and Miranda” (Boston Museum of Fine Arts; illus. 5, bottom left).
              This Shakespeare design has usually been titled “Lear and Cordelia,” as has the
              etching/engraving of the image executed c. 1806-1808 by Thomas Butts, father and
                son.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">24</ref> Butlin offers
his retitling because “the
              types and hairstyles differ from No. 84.4” (“Cordelia and the Sleeping Lear,” illus.
              6, top left). In #84.7, both figures are well-dressed and neatly groomed. If the
              design does illustrate <hi rend="i">Lear</hi>, it is probably based on an early scene
              in the play when Lear is accusing Cordelia of pridefulness and banishes her. Note that
              his gesture is very similar to one of Job’s accusatory friends in the separate plate,
              the 
<pb id="p16-30" n="30"/>
earliest drawing for which (Butlin #162, illus. 11) also
              dates from the early to mid-1780s. Alternatively, the design could picture a much
              later scene when, with renewed composure, Lear says to Cordelia, “come, come, let’s
              away to prison” (V, iii, 8). But in #84.4, and Lear in #84.5 (illus. 6, top right),
              the characters are pictured during or just after they have undergone experiences that
              would dishevel and disconcert the best of us. The differences in expression and
              coiffure between #84.7 and the two scenes definitely from <hi rend="i">Lear</hi> may
              record the changes wrought in the same father and daughter. Butlin’s new title is not
              completely convincing. <note id="n35"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Butlin states that there
                are five known proofs and that each represents “a different state.” Actually there
                are seven traced impressions in a total of four states.</note></p>
            <p>#103, “Warring Angels: Michael Contending with Satan” (untraced since 1949). The
              medium is pencil and pen, not just pen.</p>
            <p>#133 recto, “A Crouching Woman,” possibly later used for <hi rend="i">The Gates of
                Paradise</hi> (Pierpont Morgan Library). I suspect that her left hand rests on a
              mound of earth, not a “tortoise” as Butlin intriguingly describes it.</p>
            <p>#163 recto, “The Complaint of Job,” and verso, “Standing Figure” (untraced since
              1928). This drawing of an important subject was last recorded in a Sotheby’s auction,
              17 December 1928, lot 138 from the collection of Miss Brenda G. Warr (£115 to Maggs).
              This auction catalogue gives the following description of the recto, not described by
              Butlin: <figure n="BUT211.Frolic.16.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="391">
                <head>10 “Frolic” (?).</head>
                <figDesc>Pencil, 14.4 × 18.4 cm., c. 1793. Butlin #211, where it is stated that the
                  owner has suggested that this may be a subject from British history, perhaps
                  “Boadicea inspiring the Britons against the Romans,” one of the subjects listed in
                  Blake’s <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>, p. 116. Collection of George Goyder.</figDesc>
              </figure> “Job is seated on the left, depicting grief in face and gesture; his wife,
              in the centre, is seated beside him, hands clasped on knees, her head turned towards
              him; the three friends kneel in a group to the right; trees are faintly outlined on
              the dark background.” This description suggests that the drawing is intermediate
              between #162 (illus. 11), which lacks any background trees, and the finished
              preliminary (#164, see below) for the separate plate.</p>
            <p>This drawing is only the most important of numerous lost works by Blake to have
              passed through Maggs Bros. Ltd., the venerable book dealer of Berkeley Square. Mr.
              Bryan Maggs has kindly searched for me through the company records and the fabled
              “Maggs basement,” but has turned up nothing of importance.</p>
            <p>#164, “The Complaint of Job” (Fine Art Museums of San Francisco), and #166, “The
              Death of Ezekiel’s Wife” (Philadelphia Museum of Art). Butlin dates these beautiful
              companion drawings, like their far less skillful preliminaries, to c. 1785. Perhaps
              they were executed closer to their publication as prints in 1793. Both show the
              close-focus, almost claustrophobic sense of space also exploited for its emotional
              intensity by Barry. The face of Job’s wife in #164 is similar in outline and
              expression to, but even more accomplished in execution than, the standing woman in
              #189, “A Breach in a City” (Carnegie Institute, Pittsburgh), dated by Butlin to c.
              1790-1795. Blake may have begun, in about 1790, to execute finished preliminaries—some
              if not all based on earlier, cruder drawings—for his projected series of historical
              and biblical prints advertised in his 1793 prospectus.</p>
            <p>#172, “Sketch for Engraving of Michelangelo after Fuseli, on a Drawing by Fuseli”
              (Essick Collection). Butlin dates Blake’s pencil sketch on Fuseli’s ink drawing to c.
              1788 even though the plate for which the drawing is the preliminary was not published
              until 1801 in Fuseli’s <hi rend="i">Lectures on Painting.</hi> Butlin’s argument for
              this dating—that the plate in the <hi rend="i">Lectures</hi> is very close in
              “technique” to the frontispiece by Blake after Fuseli in Lavater’s 
                <figure n="BUT162.1.1.WD" rend="file" width="958" height="658">
                <head>11 “Job, his Wife and Friends.”</head>
                <figDesc>Pen and gray wash, 31.1 × 45.1 cm., c. 1785. Butlin #162 recto. Tate
                  Gallery.</figDesc>
              </figure>
<pb id="p16-31" n="31"/>
	<hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi>, 1788—is not very
              convincing. There is, however, a better reason for the c. 1788 date. The portrait of
              Michelangelo bears on its verso a pencil sketch by Fuseli very similar to—perhaps even
              a preliminary version of—the drawing for the Lavater frontispiece. It seems most
              unlikely that Fuseli would retain this piece of paper until c. 1801 and then use it
              for his Michelangelo portrait which Schiff has similarly dated to 1785-1790.<ref
                target="n36" type="note">25</ref> Blake owned both of these drawings by Fuseli until
              late in his life. <note id="n36"><hi rend="s">25</hi> Gert Schiff, <hi rend="i">Johann
                  Heinrich Füssli</hi> (Zurich: Verlag Berichthaus, 1973), I. 511. The rectos and
                versos of Fuseli’s drawings and the plates by Blake based on them are reproduced in
                  <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 5 (1971-1972), 173-76. In the accompanying
                article Ruthven Todd speculates interestingly on the history of Fuseli’s
                Michelangelo and <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> drawings.</note></p>
            <p>#175, “Figures from a Greek Vase, after D’Hancarville: A Bacchic Mystery” (British
              Museum). Butlin states that “the small tripod above the main figures shows that this
              is a place of oracles; the skull between one of the attendants’ feet, one of
              sacrifice.” Neither the tripod nor the skull appear in Butlin’s reproduction, Plate
              217, and it is not clear which are the main figures and which the attendants.</p>
            <p>#179A, “A Male Nude with an Urn, Copy from the Antique?” (estate of Theodore
              Besterman). The Blake signature looks right; the ink drawing, at first glance, looks
              very wrong. I do not find Butlin’s comparison with #82 recto, “Three Figures Under a
              Yoke with Two Children” (British Museum) to be very helpful. The three figures are
              generalized and rigid forms typical of Blake’s work, in spite of the wash background;
              the figure in #179A is carefully modeled with hatching and wash used for tonal
              effects. A more telling comparison is with the planographic transfer print, perhaps
              “Charity,” in the British Museum.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37"
type="note">26</ref> The hatching,
              and even the posture of the central figure, are remarkably similar. See also #201. 35,
              below. <note id="n37"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Reproduced in Bindman, 
                  <hi rend="i">Complete Graphic Works of Blake</hi>, pl. 8; Essick, <hi rend="i">Blake,
                  Printmaker</hi>, Fig. 122.</note></p>
            <p>#197A, “Searching Among the Dead on a Battlefield” (Private Collection, Great
              Britain). Bindman includes this drawing in his list of the series of small English
              history designs, c. 1779 (see section II, a, above), and gives it the title “The
              Finding of the Body of Harold.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38"
type="note">27</ref> Although
              Bindman’s identification of the subject is far from certain, the drawing does seem to
              be part of the history series or very closely related to it. The size is about the
              same; and the gestures, underdrawing, and handling of washes are very similar to #51,
              “The Landing of Brutus in England.” <note id="n38"><hi rend="s">27</hi> <hi rend="i">
                  Blake: Essays in Honour of Keynes</hi>, ed. Paley and Phillips, p. 35.</note></p>
            <p>#201.35, “Emblem 16” in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>, p. 35 (British Library).
              Neither Butlin nor any other Blake scholar has noted that this sketch is the basis, in
              reverse, for the “Charity” planographic print (see note 26). In the sketch, the
              central figure’s head leans to the left (right in the print) toward two children, one
              of whom holds the adult figure’s hand as in the print. The pair of children on the
              right embrace, as do the pair on the left in the print. The only motifs in the drawing
              not repeated in the print are the slight suggestions of a gown on the adult and the
              cloud beneath the five figures. These parallels between sketch and print comprise one
              of the major reasons for attributing the latter to Blake.</p>
            <p>#204, “How I Pity” (British Museum; illus. 9). The inscribed title, size, and
              emblematic character of this pencil sketch make it possible that this is “an unused
              design for <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi>,” as Butlin states. But as Joseph
              Viscomi has kindly pointed out to me, the design was used as the headpiece of plate 3
              of <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> with some modifications in the figures’ positions
              and the projection of the net or web into the background rather than covering the
              lower figures. These enmeshed figures in the sketch are also similar to the praying
              victim in plate 15 of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, lower right.</p>
            <p>#214, “Various Personifications, a Death Bed and other Drawings” (Houghton Library,
              Harvard). The attribution of this recto-verso sheet of sketches has had a checkered
              career in recent years. In the first edition (1973) of his <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>
              facsimile, Erdman reproduced the sketches and attributed them to Blake in their
              captions, pp. 86-87. But in an “erratum,” p. 105, and again in his second edition of
              1977, Erdman attributes the sheet of studies to Dante Gabriel Rossetti, noting in the
              first edition that the “detail figures must have been copied from Blake’s 
                <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> watercolours.” Butlin vigorously disputes this,
reattributing
              the sheet to Blake and dismissing most of Erdman’s comparisons to the 
                <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs which, Butlin claims, were “almost certainly
unknown to
              Rossetti as early as 1863, when his brother listed this sheet of drawings in his
              catalogue in Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake.</hi>” Butlin compares
              these studies to the similar group of small sketches on pages 74 and 75 of Blake’s 
                <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>; a more telling comparison, at least from a stylistic point
              of view, is with #226 recto, “Sketches for <hi rend="i">America</hi> and other Books,”
              c. 1793 (collection of Charles A. Ryskamp). #595 recto and verso, “Nude Studies”
              (British private collection), is also similar in some respects, although more
              carefully detailed in the interior modeling of the figures. This is dated by Butlin c.
              1810; its provenance, like that of #214, leads back to W. M. Rossetti. Apparently #595
              was the sheet of “various studies of the figure” lent by W. M. Rossetti to the
              Burlington Fine Arts Club Blake exhibition in 1876, item 155; and also the “Nude
              Studies” included by him in his Blake catalogue in the second volume of Gilchrist’s
                <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi> (1863), p. 252, no. 148. It seems unlikely that
              Rossetti would have misattributed several of his brother’s sketches to Blake, and thus
              the similarities between #595 and #214 support Butlin’s attribution of the latter to
              Blake.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">VII. Drawings for the Earlier Illuminated Books and Other Similar
                  Sketches, c. 1789-1795</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The size of this section, thirty-one entries in all, might suggest that there are a
              good many drawings for the designs in the illuminated books, with others unrecorded
              and now lost. But many of the entries are for works in the “Similar Sketches” category
              rather than directly related to the illuminated books, six are for works untraced
              since no later than 1912 (and some of these may be colored prints rather than
              drawings), one is not by Blake (see #243A, below), and all others are working sketches
                <pb id="p16-32" n="32"/>
rather than finished preliminaries of the sort that were
              conventionally made in preparation for intaglio etchings or engravings. Scholars
              working on the illuminated books must henceforth take these sketches into account, but
              there is nothing in Butlin’s catalogue to disprove the supposition that Blake composed
              the final versions of his relief-etched designs directly on the copper. The relief
              etching medium allows for this kind of direct composition: Blake could easily draw on
              the plate in pencil or chalk and continue to make significant revisions even after he
              had applied acid-resist—just as long as he had not applied any acid.</p>
            <p>#218, “Sketches for <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>: Thel and The Clod of Clay,
              and Thel Fleeing from the House of Clay” (Miss Ann Caro, London; illus. 12). This is
              one of only two extant drawings for a published illuminated book that is clearly a
              mock-up for one or more entire pages, complete with horizontal lines to indicate the
              position of the text.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">28</ref>
W. Graham Robertson and
              Bindman have discussed this fascinating drawing,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n40" type="note">29</ref>
              but interpreters of the illuminated books have not given it the attention it deserves.
              Just below the headpiece on the left is the roman numeral III, which corresponds to
              plate 6 in the published book (illus. 13). The sketch on the right must therefore be a
              preliminary version of plate 7 (illus. 14). It illustrates the end of Chapter III
              which would have appeared immediately above it: 
			<q> Queen of the vales, the matron
                Clay answerd; I heard thy sighs.<lb/>
 And all thy moans flew o’er my roof. but I
                have call’d them down:<lb/>
 Wilt thou O Queen enter my house. ‘tis given thee to
                enter,<lb/>
 And to return; fear nothing. enter with thy virgin feet. </q>
Thel
              stands in front of the matron Clay’s house, arms outstretched. Her “moans” fly above.
              That Blake drew these two plates side by side on one sheet suggests that he was
              thinking of the pictorial relationship between facing pages even though no extant copy
              of the book is printed recto-verso. <note id="n39"><hi rend="s">28</hi> The only other
                drawing of this sort is #223A recto, perhaps a first idea for the title page to 
                  <hi rend="i">America</hi> (British Museum). #239 verso, “Sketch for a Border”
                (National Gallery of Art), also seems to be a mock-up with lines indicating a text,
                but it does not relate to any known illuminated book page. For a direct preliminary
                for a white-line etching in an illuminated book, see comments on #566,
                below.</note>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">29</hi> See Robertson’s edition of
                Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi> (New York: Dodd, Mead, 1907), p. 495 no.
                12 (where the drawing is first recorded and the sketch on the right is identified as
                “the House of Clay”); <hi rend="i">Blake Collection of Robertson</hi>, ed. Preston,
                p. 199; Bindman, <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist</hi>, pp. 63-64. [A discussion by
                G. E. Bentley, Jr., of the Thel sketch will appear in a forthcoming issue of BLAKE.
                Eds.]</note></p>
            <p>At some point between sketching these pages and etching the plates, Blake made some
              significant changes. The design that stands as the headpiece to plate 6 in the sketch
              was shifted one position later in the book, becoming the tailpiece to plate 7. Blake
              drew this design on the copper with right and left in the same direction as in the
              sketch, thereby reversing it in impressions from the plate (note that the positions of
              the matron Clay and the infant Worm are reversed in illus. 14). If the shift in
              position continued for the tailpiece in the sketch, then it would become the headpiece
              to Chapter IV on plate 8 where it could still illustrate the end of Chapter III. And
              perhaps Blake did execute a final plate with this design, for the only known etched
              version of Chapter IV on plate 8—the only chapter without a headpiece—has long been
              suspected to be a late addition, perhaps a replacement for an earlier conclusion to
              the poem. The new headpiece to Chapter III on plate 6 (illus. 13) illustrates the
              opening lines of that chapter. Thel’s gesture in the etched version of plate 6 echoes
              her appearance in the sketched version of the Chapter III tailpiece; the Cloud is the
              same type of soaring personification as those above the house of Clay. If Blake did
              not shift the sketched tailpiece to the next plate but rejected it altogether, he may
              have simply borrowed these motifs from it to construct the substitute headpiece on
              plate 6.</p>
            <p>Butlin does not note that this <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> drawing is on laid paper with a
              large crown and Britannia watermark cut in half by the lower edge of the sheet.</p>
            <p>#229, “Los Supporting the Sun” (National Gallery of Art). Butlin does not note in his
              provenance information that this drawing was once owned by Willis Vickery and sold
              from his collection at the American Art Association-Anderson Galleries, New York, 1
              March 1933, lot 23 ($70). Lot 24 in this sale is also a pencil drawing attributed to
              Blake, described as representing “a woman in classical robe and headdress kneeling in
              lament over the semi-draped figure of a man relaxed in death. Supporting figures in
              mere outline appear. . . . The signature, ‘<hi rend="i">W. Blake</hi>,’ is partly
              erased. Size, 6 ¼ by 9 ½ inches.” I cannot identify this work as any of the drawings
              in Butlin’s catalogue.</p>
            <p>#243A, “A Serpent” (Malcolm Frazier, Medfield, Massachusetts). Butlin refers to
              Bindman’s doubts about attributing this water color to Blake. Indeed, the attribution
              is so doubtful that I see no reason to include the work in the catalogue. It pictures
              a real, biological snake, not one of Blake’s symbolic serpents.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">VIII. Illustrations to Mary Wollstonecraft and Shakespeare, and Other
                  Works, c. 1790-1795</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>#255, “Los and Orc” (Tate Gallery). Based on the evident significance of the scene in
              this water color, Butlin comments interestingly that “in this case the theme [the
              conflict of Los and Orc] appears first in a visual form, not in poetry.” If he is
              right in this instance, “Los and Orc” exemplifies the way in which an artist “thinks”
              with hand and eye. This process of composition, purely pictorial at its inception, can
              take place prior to—or simultaneous with—the verbal conceptualization of meaning. The
              interplay of forms, whether consciously borrowed from another artist or “invented,”
              grows in complexity and significance as the artist works up a design. Traditional
              meanings come readymade with certain motifs and <hi rend="i">pathos formulae</hi>; as
              these are pictorially integrated with other elements in the composition, new themes
              arise. From these can evolve stories, such as the one about Los, Enitharmon, and Orc
              prefigured by this drawing. As designs are modified, even if the changes are motivated
              by purely compositional concerns, the themes and stories they embody can be revised
              thereby. The literary background and bias of most Blake scholars lead them to assume
              that concept or story precedes pictorial image. As Butlin suggests, the priority of
              word to picture cannot be assumed in every case.</p>
            <p>#257, “The Good and Evil Angels” (Cecil Higgins Museum, Bedford), and #258, “God
              Judging Adam” <pb id="p16-33" n="33"/> (collection of George Goyder). These two water
              colors of 1793-1794 and 1790-1793, respectively, provide the necessary context for
              understanding the stylistic developments exemplified by the great 1795 color printed
              drawings (see comments on section X, below). The color prints show Blake’s somewhat
              sudden tendency toward schematization, a flattened (and in that sense neoclassical)
              sense of pictorial space, and an impulse toward the minute particulars of surface that
              have little to do with naturalistic detail. In contrast to these two earlier drawings,
              the color prints of the same subjects are immeasurably more powerful, elemental, and
              psychologically disturbing. Neither the change in medium, from pen and water color
              drawing to color printing with subsequent pen and water color finishing, nor the
              impact of relief etching, with its intrinsic flattening and anti-naturalistic
              limitations, can completely account for the power of the large 1795 color printed
              drawings.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">IX. Separate Designs from the Illuminated Books, etc., c.
                  1794-1796</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>#261.8, “<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, Plate 5,” color print from the dispersed copy B of
                <hi rend="i">A Small Book of Designs</hi> (Beinecke Library, Yale University).
              Butlin is incorrect in his statement that “the colour-printing 
              <figure n="BUT218.1.1r.PD" rend="file" width="958" height="679">
	<figTranscr>III<lb/>
	<lb/>
	By William Blake<lb/>
	attested by<lb/>
	Frederick Tatham</figTranscr>
                <head>12 “Sketch for <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>: Thel and the Clod of Clay,
                  and Thel Fleeing from the House of Clay.”</head>
                <figDesc>Pencil on sheet 22.4 × 31.7 cm., c. 1789. Butlin #218. Collection of Miss
                  Ann Caro, London.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <figure n="thel.o.p5-6" id="thel.o.illbk.05" work-copy="thel.o" rend="db" width="712" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>5<lb/>
	4<lb/>
	III.<lb/>
	Then Thel astonish’d view’d the Worm upon its dewy bed.<lb/>
	Art thou a Worm? image of weakness. art thou but a Worm?<lb/>
	I see thee like an infant wrapped in the Lillys leaf:<lb/>
	Ah weep not little voice, thou can’st not speak, but thou can’st weep;<lb/>
	Is this a Worm? I see thee lay helpless &amp; naked: weeping;<lb/>
	And none to answer, none to cherish thee with mothers smiles.<lb/>
	The Clod of Clay heard the Worms voice, &amp; raisd her pitying head;<lb/>
	She bowd over the weeping infant, and her life exhal’d<lb/>
	In milky fondness. then on Thel she fix’d her humble eyes.<lb/>
	O beauty of the vales of Har. we live not for ourselves.<lb/>
	Thou seest me the meanest thing, and so I am indeed;<lb/>
	My bosom of itself is cold. and of itself is dark,<lb/>
	But</figTranscr>
                <head>13 <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, copy O, plate 6 (numbered 5 in this
                  copy).</head>
                <figDesc>Relief etching, hand colored, 15.3 × 10.8 cm., 1789. Rosenwald Collection,
                  Library of Congress.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <figure n="thel.o.p6-7" id="thel.o.illbk.06" work-copy="thel.o" rend="db" width="713" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>6<lb/>
	5<lb/>
	But he that loves the lowly, pours his oil upon my head,<lb/>
	And kisses me, and binds his nuptial bands around my breast.<lb/>
	And says; Thou mother of my children, I have loved thee.<lb/>
	And I have given thee a crown that none can take away<lb/>
	But how this is sweet maid, I know not, and I cannot know.<lb/>
	I ponder, and I cannot ponder; yet I live and love.<lb/>
	The daughter of beauty wip’d her pitying tears with her white veil,<lb/>
	And said. Alas! I knew not this. and therefore did I weep:<lb/>
	That God would love a Worm I knew. and punish the evil foot<lb/>
	That wilful, bruis’d its helpless form: but that he cherish’d it<lb/>
	With milk and oil, I never knew; and therefore did I weep.<lb/>
	And I complaind in the mild air, because I fade away.<lb/>
	And lay me down in thy cold bed, and leave my shining lot.<lb/>
	Queen of the vales. the matron Clay answerd; I heard thy sighs.<lb/>
	And all thy moans flew o’er my roof. but I have call’d them down:<lb/>
	Wilt thou O Queen enter my house. ’tis given thee to enter.<lb/>
	And to return; fear nothing. enter with thy virgin feet.<lb/>
	IV</figTranscr>
                <head>14 <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, copy O, plate 7 (numbered 6 in this
                  copy).</head>
                <figDesc>Relief etching, hand colored, 15.4 × 10.6 cm., 1789. Rosenwald Collection,
                  Library of Congress.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <pb id="p16-34" n="34"/> 
              reduces the width of Urizen’s arms, following the
              modelling lines of the etching rather than the lower outlines.” This reduction does
              occur, however, in the two other separate, color printed impressions, #260.21 
              (<hi rend="i">A Small Book of Designs</hi>, copy A; British Museum) and #278 (University
              of Texas). The arm thickness and very similar patterns of color printing in the
              British Museum and Texas impressions strongly suggest that they were printed one after
              the other: #260.21 was probably printed first, with little (if any) addition of more
              opaque colors to the plate before the second pull. The Yale impression is printed in
              different colors and patterns and is not part of this #260.21-#278 sequence of
              pulls.</p>
            <p>#261.10, “<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, Plate 10,” color print from the dispersed copy B
              of <hi rend="i">A Small Book of Designs</hi> (Pierpont Morgan Library). Butlin briefly
              quotes a reference to a version of this design and to #446, “The Blasphemer” (Tate
              Gallery), appearing in <hi rend="i">The Critic</hi>, Vol. 22 no. 510 (14 April 1860),
              467. I do not believe that this unsigned, commendatory review, published before the
              appearance of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>, has been previously noted.
              It appears in a section of the journal titled “Art and Artists” on p. 465; the
              exhibition review itself is titled “Water-Colour Drawings at South Kensington.” After
              discussion of works by A. E. and J. Chalon, John Varley, and Thomas Hood the poet, the
              review ends with the following, only a small part of which is reprinted by Butlin. 
			<q>
                There are also three drawings by that wonderful man William Blake. One is (we
                suppose) “The High Priests Stoning a Prophet” [#446]; the uplifted arms of the
                former have all that imaginative suggestiveness and direct appeal to the imagination
                characteristic of this painter. The other frame contains two scraps from Blake’s
                wild illustrated Books. One is an enigmatic male figure sinking in the waves [a
                version of #261.10]; the other is the first page of “The Songs of Innocence” (the
                Echoing Green [Butlin suggests the separate impression of the first plate of “The
                Ecchoing Green” at Harvard]), and has all the <hi rend="i">riant</hi> melody of
                colour and charming fancy peculiar to that unique book. It would be well to get the
                whole of the coloured “Songs of Innocence and Experience” (any of the copies which
                are printed only on one side of the leaf), and to frame the entire series. No money
                could be better spent in this Department [of the South Kensington Museum] than by
                showing the English world that it has had one really imaginative and spiritual
                artist, of whom it knows nothing. </q>
The author shows some familiarity with 
                <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>—note his distinction between
              copies printed recto-verso and those on rectos only—and an appreciation of Blake’s
              art, both rare qualities in 1860.</p>
            <p>#262.3, <corr type="emend">“<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>,</corr> Plate 21,” color print from
<hi rend="i">A Large
                Book of Designs</hi> copy A (British Museum). Butlin comments that this design
              showing Los, Orc, and Enitharmon “is related to Flaxman’s engraving of the blacksmith
              god Hesphaestus [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] (or Vulcan) chaining Prometheus 
                (<hi rend="i">Compositions for the Tragedies of Aeschylus</hi>, 1793, pls. 3 and 4).” As
Bindman
              has pointed out, <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> plate 21 recalls “the common Renaissance
              subject of <hi rend="i">Venus, Vulcan and Cupid at the Forge.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41"
                type="note">30</ref> Flaxman, however, does not picture that subject but only
              Prometheus chained, and the visual similarities between his two designs and Blake’s
              are very slight. <note id="n41"><hi rend="s">30</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake as an
                  Artist</hi>, p. 93.</note></p>
            <p>#287, “Lucifer and the Pope in Hell,” color print (Huntington Library). This is an
              intaglio etching/ engraving color printed from the surface of the plate—not, as Butlin
              has it, a “colour-printed relief etching.” Butlin’s provenance information stops with
              the purchase of the print by Sabin in 1914. Sessler’s records indicate that they
              acquired it from Robson in July 1923 for $407 and sold it to Henry E. Huntington in
              August 1923 (no price recorded, but perhaps part of a lot including #748 for
              $2,500).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">X. The Large Color Prints, c. 1795</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Two pieces of information, one mentioned in passing in this catalogue and the other
              discovered by Butlin after its publication, require us to rethink our basic ideas
              about how and when the large color prints were produced. In his entry on #295, “God
              Judging Adam” (Metropolitan Museum, New York), he writes that “among the flames on the
              lower right-hand side are what appear to be the forms of capital letters, seen upside
              down and at a diagonal, suggesting that an engraved plate bearing such letters was
              deliberately or accidentally involved in the printing of this pull.” Butlin noted this
              feature of the print in his 1978 Tate exhibition catalogue,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42"
                type="note">31</ref> but no one seems to have published further on the discovery.
              The letters, or at least uncolored surfaces of the paper that look like fragments of
              letters printed in blind, are indeed present, 7.1 cm. from the bottom edge of the
              print and 8.9 cm. from the right edge. It is very difficult to see, much less
              identify, these marks unless one knows just where to look. To my eye, the letters are
              not necessarily “upside down,” but are in reverse. There are two rows of letters, the
              top containing at least the letter N, the bottom perhaps ON. In size, blind printing,
              and configuration, these look very much like the lettering of a platemaker’s mark of
              the sort present in blind in some impressions of <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>
              and <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43"
type="note">32</ref> Indeed, the three
              barely visible letters on “God Judging Adam” may have been made by the third and
              fourth lines of the same platemaker’s mark stamped into the back of the copperplate of
              “Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims” (HARRIS / N<hi rend="s">o</hi> 31 / SHOE LANE / LONDON)
              or the firm’s mark on the back of the Job title page plate (G. HARRIS / N<hi rend="s">o</hi>
31 / SHOE LANE / LONDON).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">33</ref>	
                <note id="n42"><hi rend="s">31</hi> Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>
                (London: Tate Gallery, 1978), p. 60.</note>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">32</hi> See
                Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, pp. 145, 225, 381-82 n. 4.</note>	
                <note id="n44"><hi rend="s">33</hi> This is highly speculative. It is difficult to
                determine the exact outlines of the letters in “God Judging Adam,” and my rather
                crude attempts at making comparative measurements have proven unsuccessful. The
                sizes of the letters of a platemaker’s mark vary according to the force with which
                the punch bearing the letters is struck into the copper, but appropriately scaled
                photo-transparencies might offer some firm answers.</note></p>
            <p>Modern scholars have generally accepted Frederick Tatham’s statement that the 1795
              color prints were stamped from “thick millboard” or “paste-board.” Butlin, p. 156,
              quotes Tatham’s account; and although he questions other parts of Tatham’s
              description, he does not directly challenge the millboard theory. Clearly, the
              evidence for a platemaker’s mark in the Metropolitan Museum version of “God Judging
              Adam” opens that theory to question. There are, however, other possibilities than the
                <pb id="p16-35" n="35"/>
obvious one that “God Judging Adam,” and perhaps other
              color printed drawings, were stamped from a metal plate. Butlin allows that a plate
              may have been “accidentally involved in the printing of this pull.” Odd accidents do
              occur in print studios, although it is hard to explain how this one could have
              happened. If a plate was purposely included in the print’s production, it need not
              have been the primary printing surface. Blake may have used the back of a small
              copperplate to blot colors already painted or printed on the paper in order to
              increase their reticulations for whatever aesthetic reasons he had in mind. This
              would, in effect, allow for revisions in surface structure after the initial
              printing.</p>
            <p>Another possibility has been suggested to me in correspondence by Sue Welsh Reed,
              Assistant Curator of Prints at the Boston Museum of Fine Arts. Mrs. Reed, who has
              written perceptively on the early history of monotype printing, 
                <ref target="n45" type="note">34</ref> has investigated the letters in “God Judging Adam”
with
              considerable care. She proposes that Blake may have been using mill-board bearing an
              indented manufacturer’s stamp, as in the “Bristol board” of the nineteenth century or
              some Strathmore papers of today. Such a stamp, if not filled with colors, would leave
              letters in blind similar to those produced by a platemaker’s mark. In these examples
              the stamp is usually closer to the edge of the board or sheet than in “God Judging
              Adam”—assuming that the printing board was at least as large as the printed paper—but
              the situation may have been different in the eighteenth century. Mrs. Reed has also
              studied the forms of the letters with the aid of a detailed transparency and concluded
              that the letter T precedes ON in the second line. If she is correct, then we can rule
              out the G. HARRIS platemaker’s mark. <note id="n45"><hi rend="s">34</hi> See Reed,
                “Monotypes in the Seventeenth and Eighteenth Centuries,” pp. 3-8 in <hi rend="i">The
                  Painterly Print: Monotypes from the Seventeenth to the Twentieth Century</hi> (New
                York: Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1980). Mrs. Reed did not learn of the letters in
                “God Judging Adam” until after her work in this volume had been
              published.</note></p>
            <p>Certainly this whole matter requires more investigation. A. H. Shorter’s 
                <hi rend="i">Paper Mills and Paper Makers in England 1495-1800</hi> (Hilversum, 1957) includes
              some names of papermakers that <hi rend="i">might</hi> have used a blind stamp with
              the requisite letters, but provides no evidence even for the existence of such stamps.
              If any reader of this quarterly knows of an expert in eighteenth-century millboard
              makers’ stamps, I would be delighted to know his or her name and address.</p>
            <p>The second, more recent discovery concerning the 1795 color printed drawings has much
              more extensive implications. As Butlin has recently reported in this journal,<ref
                target="n46" type="note">35</ref> the Tate Gallery impression of “Newton” is on
              paper watermarked 1804. Let me try to recover from this bombshell and add a few
              speculations to Butlin’s remarkably restrained article. While the 1804 watermark
              overturns most of what has been believed about the dating of the 1795 
                [<hi rend="i">sic?</hi>] color printed drawings, it does confirm the long-held suspicion that
the
              dates on Blake’s prints (of all types) record the year of “invention”—not execution or
              publication unless specifically inscribed as such. Thus the inscription on the
              intaglio etching/engraving “Albion rose,” “<hi rend="i">WB inv 1780</hi>,” means
              exactly that and nothing more. Blake invented the design in that year, a process that
              may have included composition in some medium, but the date gives no clue as to the
              date of execution (<hi rend="i">sculpsit</hi>) in the copper or printing.<ref
                target="n47" type="note">36</ref>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">35</hi> “A Newly
                Discovered Watermark and a Visionary’s Way with His Dates,” <hi rend="i">Blake: An
                  Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (Fall 1981), 101-03.</note>
	<note id="n47"><hi
                  rend="s">36</hi> The seminal article on Blake’s etched and engraved dates is David
                V. Erdman, “The Dating of William Blake’s Engravings,” <hi rend="i">Philological
                  Quarterly</hi>, 31 (1952), 337-43; reprinted, with a new postscript by the author,
                in <hi rend="i">The Visionary Hand</hi>, ed. Robert N. Essick (Hennessey &amp;
                Ingalls, 1973), pp. 161-71. Building on Erdman’s findings, I proposed the rule of
                thumb that “Blake’s imprint date of engraving (<hi rend="i">sculpsit</hi> as
                distinct from <hi rend="i">invenit</hi>) incised in the plate records the
                publication of the first state” of a plate (<hi rend="i">Blake, Printmaker</hi>, p.
                65). Neither of these studies addresses the problem of Blake’s hand written dates on
                planographic prints.</note></p>
            <p>I have suggested elsewhere that the color printed drawings sold to Thomas Butts in
              1805 were not finished in pen and water colors until shortly before the sale.<ref
                target="n48" type="note">37</ref> We now have incontrovertible evidence that Blake
              also <hi rend="i">printed</hi> at least one version of “Newton” in 1804 or 1805 when
              he sold it to Butts. The inscribed date on this Tate impression, “1795 WB inv,” refers
              only to the “invention” of the design, just as with the similar inscription on “Albion
              rose.” The other color printed drawings with inscribed dates either contain the “inv”
              abbreviation or have the year alone. <note id="n48"><hi rend="s">37</hi> <hi rend="i">
                  Blake, Printmaker</hi>, p. 132. Butlin, p. 156, makes much the same
              point.</note></p>
            <p>Blake’s technique of color printing required a fairly thick application of paint the
              millboard (or copperplate?), and this glue or gum based medium must be immediately
              printed before it dries. The progressive decrease in the amount of color printing in
              the three impressions of some color printed drawings indicates that they were printed
              in succession from the millboard or plate before the initial application of paint had
              dried. This seemed to be good evidence that, if any one impression had been pulled in
              1795, all had been. Butlin’s discovery throws into doubt all these seemingly
              reasonable assumptions. We are left with at least two alternative explanations.<ref
                target="n49" type="note">38</ref>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">38</hi> Both
                alternatives are briefly suggested by Butlin in his note on the 1804
                watermark.</note></p>
            <p>1. Blake could reuse his millboards or copperplates for the color printed drawings
              after the first application of paint had dried on them. Perhaps Blake could clean the
              paint from his printing board or plate, leaving only the outline for future use. This
              would have been fairly easy if the printing surfaces were metal and outlines of the
              designs had been very lightly scratched into them. If indeed this was Blake’s method,
              then a successive decrease among impressions in the amount of printed colors does not
              necessarily indicate a single press run.</p>
            <p>2. Blake may not have printed <hi rend="i">any</hi> color printed drawings in 1795.
              The inscribed dates indicate only the year Blake invented the designs, carrying their
              execution no further than drawings. These could have been made on the millboards or
              copperplates themselves but not colored up and printed until much later. This
              seemingly bizarre hypothesis at least has the advantage of not controverting the
              evidence that all impressions of at least some of the color printed drawings were
              pulled in one press run.</p>
            <p>As Butlin indicates at the end of his article in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, the
              discovery of the 1804 watermark affects more than just theories about Blake’s color
              printing techniques. Our understanding of Blake’s artistic development, his
              experimentation with and abandonment of various media, from c. 1794 to c. 1805 has
              hinged on the belief that he did all his color printing, both planographic and from
              relief etched plates, c. 1794-1796. We now know that a major example of planographic
              color printing was executed in 1804 or 1805. To this we can also add the post-1804
              plate from <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> at the Philadelphia Museum of Art, printed with
              the reticulated impasto effects of Blake’s size-colors even if the medium was thick
                ink.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">39</ref> If more color
printed works should
              emerge, definitely datable post-1803, we will be forced to modify our picture of
              Blake’s development out of the Burkean sublime of color printing and into the 
                <pb id="p16-36" n="36"/>
<figure n="but296.1.1.cpd" id="but296.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="784">
	<figTranscr/>
                <head>15 “God Judging Adam.”</head>
                <figDesc>Color printed drawing finished (by another hand?) in pen and water colors,
                  42.3 × 51.7 cm., c. 1795. Butlin #296. Philadelphia Museum of Art.</figDesc>
              </figure>
<figure n="but311.1.1.cpd" id="but311.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="774">
	<figTranscr>WBlake<lb/>
	inv.</figTranscr>
                <head>16 “Pity.”</head>
                <figDesc>Color printed drawing finished in pen and water colors, 42.1 × 52.8 cm., c.
                  1795. Butlin #311. Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York.</figDesc>
              </figure> unobscured lines and illumination of his nineteenth-century drawings and
              handcolored prints. Even our sense of Blake’s psychological history and the evolution
              of his most important aesthetic concepts could be shaken by a major redating of the
              color prints. <note id="n50"><hi rend="s">39</hi> See <hi rend="i">Blake: An
                  Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (Summer 1981), cover, p. 8, and illus.
              6.</note></p>
            <p>I do not believe that there is sufficient cause for a complete reassessment quite
              yet. It is of course possible that only the Tate version of “Newton” was printed in
              1804 or 1805 in response to Butts’ order for a set of the color printed drawings. Yet
              even if the 1804-1805 “Newton” is an anomaly, we have learned from Butlin’s remarkable
              discovery to distrust our tendency to shape careers into neatly periodized narratives,
              or to extrapolate rigid doctrines about an artist’s practice from his verbal
              statements. Once again we are reminded that Blake was a craftsman, an inveterate
              tinkerer, and if he needed to do a bit of color printing he would not be stopped by
              his theories, much less ours.</p>
            <p>Comments on individual entries follow.</p>
            <p>#296, “God Judging Adam” (Philadelphia Museum of Art; illus. 15). Butlin enlists the
              opinions of Andrew Wilton and David Bindman to question the authenticity of the
              handcoloring on this color printed drawing. I too very much doubt that it is by Blake.
              The colors have a higher tonality than any other color printed drawing I have seen,
              and they were applied in broad, thin washes totally uncharacteristic of Blake’s work.
              The contrast with Blake’s own handcoloring is particularly striking if one compares
              this impression to the carefully layered, almost stippled coloring in the prints sold
              to Butts. One odd feature of this Philadelphia version is the eyelashes added to the
              frontmost horse that give him an almost comic air. The color printing, however, seems
              perfectly genuine. The outlines of the major forms seem to have been printed in black
              or gray with the few additional colors limited almost entirely to areas surrounding
              the men and horses. If we could eliminate the questionable overpainting, we would have
              a print looking very similar to a monochrome pull of a relief etching. The provenance
              of this print indicates that it was still in Blake’s possession at his death. I
              suspect that he kept it as an unfinished experimental impression printed in only a few
              dark colors and that a later hand finished it in pen &amp; ink and bright water
              colors.</p>
            <p>#298, “Lamech and his Two Wives” (Essick Collection). Butlin notes that this example
              has “little actual colour-printing” and “was covered with varnish, but it has now been
              largely removed.” There is a good deal of color printing in the abstract and somber
              background and foreground landscape, but very little on the figures. The print still
              looks varnished to me; if any varnish was removed it must have been before 1974.</p>
            <p>#311, “Pity” (Metropolitan Museum of Art; illus. 16). Several large areas of the
              print not overpainted show horizontal striations. The colors rise in sharp ridges with
              thinly printed valleys between, almost as though a fine comb had been drawn through
              the size-colors before they had dried. In illus. 16 this odd effect is most clearly
              visible below the horse’s extended foreleg and in the prone woman’s hair and on the
              ground below. The horizontal lines also appear in these areas in the Yale Center
              impression (#312) but are almost completely obscured by the overpainting in the Tate
              impression (#310)— or perhaps by the thickness of the medium itself in what is
              probably the first pull from the millboard or plate. These markings might have been
              caused by the surface structure of the printing surface, such as the ridges in some
              modern cardboards. It seems unlikely that they were produced by the wire lines 
                <pb id="p16-37" n="37"/>
of laid paper because there is no evidence of chain lines;
              these surely would have left their mark if the wire lines did. The more one looks at
              the color printed drawings, the more the mysteries multiply.</p>
            <p>#317, “Hecate” (National Gallery of Scotland). The reference should be to plate 415,
              not “417.”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XI. The Great Book Illustrations, c. 1795-1807</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>This 116-page section covers the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> and Gray
              illustrations and the drawings in the <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> manuscript. For the
              first group, Butlin does not record most of the dashes before lines of Young’s text
              indicated in the captions, and usually visible in the reproductions, in the Clarendon
                edition.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">40</ref> See also
comments on #330.241 and
              #330.299, below. <note id="n51"><hi rend="s">40</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake’s
                  Designs for Edward Young’s Night Thoughts</hi>, ed. Grant, et al. I have not
                compared these reproductions or the information in their captions against the
                original water colors in the British Museum.</note></p>
            <p>#330.55 (<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> water color 55, British Museum). “Line 318
              is also starred” should read “Line 334 . . . .”</p>
            <p>#330.64. Butlin comments on the contrast between the “Urizenic old man” in this
              design and the mother and children on the right. He does not consider the sinister
              implications in the woman’s appearance, emphasized in the etching/engraving but
              already present in the water color. The vegetation might, in the context of 
                <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, indicate exuberant expression. In 
                <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, however, we are directed toward Blake’s concepts of fallen
              nature. The woman (mother? nurse?) is old, with harsh and haggard features, and her
              head is covered with a veil or scarf. We are led away from any suggestions of the
              gently supportive mothers and nurses of Innocence and toward the figures of Tirzah and
              Vala. The children are therefore dominated by Urizenic abstraction and generation.
              These are not opposites of good and evil, but two faces of a single error. (My caveat
              here is not meant to dismiss Butlin’s extremely brief but often penetrating
              interpretations of the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs.)</p>
            <p>#330.97. The small figure kneeling at the upper left corner of the text panel aims a
              single arrow (not Butlin’s “arrows”) at the man below.</p>
            <p>#330.196. Butlin states that the figure leaning over a precipice is “watched by a
              sheepdog.” The dog’s eyes are closed, or simply not drawn in. The point would seem to
              be not watchfulness but a failure to perceive danger and the alienation of man from
              natural, and supposedly alert, companions.</p>
            <p>#330.221. Butlin writes of a never-before-described “pencil sketch, perhaps a more
              robust version of the same girl [in the water color], running over on to the blank
              text-page.” No such figure is visible in the reproduction in the Clarendon
              edition.</p>
            <p>#330.224. Butlin: “Also marked in pencil at lines 47 and 49.” Clarendon edition: line
              37 marked with a cross in the right margin; line 49 marked with a cross in the left
              margin. The Clarendon reproduction suggests that Butlin’s “47” is a simple error for
              37.</p>
            <p>#330.228. Butlin: “An old man ploughing.” Perhaps middle-aged, overworked, worried,
              and with hints of gray in his Orc-like curly locks—but <hi rend="i">not</hi> old.</p>
            <p>#330.241. The caption in the Clarendon edition fails to note the cross before line
              381. Butlin’s reference to it is confirmed by its presence in the Clarendon
              reproduction.</p>
            <p>#330.264. The date ascribed to <hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi> should be c.
              1788, not “1780.”</p>
            <p>#330.299. Butlin states that line 532 “is starred,” and “also line 538.” The
              Clarendon edition neither notes nor pictures the latter.</p>
            <p>#330.310. Is the figure unquestionably a “man”? He/she wears a scarf over his/her
              head like several women, but no (other?) men, in the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
              designs.</p>
            <p>#330.348. The page is given an incorrect entry number, “330.340.”</p>
            <p>#330.475. The figure is not, as Butlin describes him, “supporting a segment of the
              zodiacal circle” pictured in the background. As the starred line (“What More than 
                <hi rend="i">Atlantean</hi> Shoulder props / The incumbent Load?”) indicates, the figure
              is Atlas. He carries on his shoulder the earth bearing the clearly delineated
              continents of Europe, Africa, and the western third of Asia.</p>
            <p>#330.489. There is only one angel (not Butlin’s “angels”) above the three struggling
              figures.</p>
            <p>#330.498. Only two, not all “three figures” (Butlin), are writing on a scroll.</p>
            <p>#330A. Butlin lists in this entry the drawings on three proofs of the 
                <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> engravings in a “private collection” (i.e., collection of
              Philip Hofer). He writes that the early proof of the title page to Night the First in
              this group contains the title “written in pencil and wash.” The title is in pencil
              alone; the wash is confined to the giant figure to the right of the text panel.</p>
            <p>#337, <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> (British Library).
              Butlin writes that his descriptions of these drawings are “based particularly on
              Margoliouth’s and Grant’s identifications,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n52" type="note">41</ref> but
              also “tentatively go beyond their suggestions in some cases.” Among the most
              interesting of these additions to his predecessors are Butlin’s comments on the
              relevance of the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> proofs to the texts they bear and on
              the formal, and in some cases iconographic, relationships between these 
                <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs and contiguous <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> drawings.
Butlin
              also argues, p. 290, that the large drawing of Christ on page 116 of the manuscript,
              the verso of a <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> proof, was first executed as a design
              for <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi> He constructs a line of compositional
              development that implies that the drawings of Christ on pages 16<ref target="n53"
                type="note">42</ref> and 58 also began as working sketches for the frontispiece to
              the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> water colors (#330.1). The point is an important
              one: if true, then Blake made use of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> drawings (as
              well as proofs of the etching/engravings) in his <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> illustrated
              manuscript. Butlin’s argument also 
<pb id="p16-38" n="38"/>
means that the
              frontispiece to the Young designs was a late addition to the series (as has been
              suggested by the editors of the Clarendon Clarendon <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>,
              I, 12), composed after the proofs of the etching/engravings on pages 70 and 73 of the
              1797 edition (bearing pages 58 and 116 of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> on their versos) had
              been pulled. <note id="n52"><hi rend="s">41</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake’s
                  Vala</hi>, ed. H. M. Margoliouth (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1956); John E. Grant,
                “Visions in <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>: A Consideration of Some Pictures in the
                Manuscript,” pp. 141-202 in <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory</hi>, ed. Stuart
                Curran and Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr. (Madison: University of Wiscons in Press,
                1973).</note>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">42</hi> The erased drawing of the risen
                Christ on page 16, described by Butlin, is not visible in the reproduction in
                Bentley’s facsimile edition of the manuscript.</note></p>
            <p>As Butlin tells us, the editors of the Clarendon <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
              believe (p. 38 and n. 56) that the drawing on <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> page 116 was
              composed as an illustration to that poem and follows rather than precedes the similar
              portravals of Christ in the first <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> design, finished
              recto and preliminary verso. Yet, Butlin’s argument is intriguing and as convincing as
              such speculation can ever be. One piece of circumstantial evidence supporting his case
              is the fact that the <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> text is written over the drawings of
              Christ on pages 16 and 58, and crowded into the upper margin on page 116. In all three
              examples, the drawings were very probably executed before the text. This also seems to
              be the case with the text above and below the large drawing on page 86, a verso of a
                <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> proof.</p>
            <p>Another interesting contribution to the investigation of this frustratingly complex
              manuscript is Butlin’s brief comment on the sequence of composition of the two
              versions of Night VII. He suggests (p. 285) that Blake may have first drawn the large
              figure on page 76 (the last page of Night VI and perhaps a kind of frontispiece to
              Night VII) as a male and later converted him to a female. This suggests that Night
              VIIa was written first because “that seems to be the more male oriented” of the two
              versions. Even an argument as speculative as this one may be helpful when wrestling
              with <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></p>
            <p>#337.87-90, <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, two leaves cut from an impression of
              Blake’s etching/engraving “Edward &amp; Elenor.” Butlin comments that “the text on
              pages 87 and 90 was presumably written consecutively on the back of the engraving
              which was then cut in half and trimmed to insert the pages into the manuscript.” This
              is an interesting theory, but the only evidence for it, as Butlin notes, is that “the
              text on page 90 is abnormally close to the left-hand edge of the paper.” This suggests
              that Blake had a wider margin on the left when he began writing. Yet I doubt that
              Blake wrote pages 87 and 90 before cutting “Edward &amp; Elenor” in half; working on
              the full sheet would simply have been very awkward and have served no purpose
              practical or artistic. Subsequent trimming to conform to the size of the other
              manuscript leaves accounts for the narrow left margin on page 90 and the missing 4.6
              cm. wide central strip from “Edward &amp; Elenor” along the outer margins of pages 88
              and 89.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XII. Miscellaneous Designs, c. 1795-1800</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>#341, “Malevolence” (Philadelphia Museum of Art). To Butlin’s provenance information
              I can add, from Sessler’s records, that they purchased the drawing for $6000 and sold
              it to Mrs. Tonner in November 1954 for $6500.</p>
            <p>#342, “Churchyard Spectres Frightening a Schoolboy” (Imogen Dennis Collection,
              Oxfordshire; illus. 17). Butlin follows Rossetti in giving this drawing a title that
              associates it with an oft-illustrated passage in Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>, but
              he then argues against such a connection and dates the drawing c. 1795-1800 (i.e., at
              least five years before the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> commission). The passage in
              question is as follows: 
			<q> Oft in the lone church-yard at night I’ve seen,<lb/>
 By
                glimpse of moon-shine, chequ’ring through the trees,<lb/>
 The school-boy, with his
                satchel in his hand,<lb/>
 Whistling aloud to bear his courage up,<lb/>
 And lightly
                tripping o’er the long flat stones<lb/>
 (With nettles skirted, and with moss
                o’ergrown)<lb/>
 That tell in homely phrase who lie below.<lb/>
 Sudden he starts! and
                hears, or thinks he hears,<lb/>
 The sound of something purring at his heels.<lb/>
                Full fast he flies, and dares not look behind him,<lb/>
 Till out of breath he
                overtakes his fellows;<lb/>
 Who gather round, and wonder at the tale<lb/>
 Of horrid
                apparition, tall and ghastly,<lb/>
 That walks at dead of night, or takes his
                stand<lb/>
 O’er some new open’d grave; and, strange to tell,<lb/>
 Evanishes at
                crowing of the cock!<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">43</ref>
	<note id="n54"><hi
                    rend="s">43</hi> Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (London: R. H.
                  Cromek, 1808), pp. 3-4. The scene is illustrated, without any “spectres,” in the
                  frontispiece (signed “Dodd de. Sparrow sculpt.”) to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>,
                  ed. G. Wright (London, 1785); in the unsigned title page vignette of 
                    <hi rend="i">Roach’s Beauties of the Poets of Great Britain</hi> (London, 1794), vol. I;
and
                  in the frontispiece (signed “F. Seymour del. &amp; sc.”) to <hi rend="i">The Grave
                    A Poem by Robert Blair to which is Added An Elegy Written in a Country
                    Church-Yard by Mr. Gray</hi> (Philadelphia, 1787). In his edition, Wright states
                  (p. 10) that “the above description [of the schoolboy] has met with universal
                  approbation, and is doubtless one of the most natural and pleasing pictures
                  throughout the whole poem.” Clearly, any artist setting out to illustrate Blair in
                  1805 would be led to consider this subject if he were at all familiar with its
                  critical and illustrative reputation.</note></q></p>
            <p>Butlin does not offer an alternative subject or purpose for the drawing, but claims
              that there is “no justification” in Blair’s poem “for the figure in the doorway on the
              right, who looks like a school-master holding a birch,” that “the boy is holding a
              doll rather than a satchel,” and that the style of the water color “suggests a date in
              the later 1790s.” Blair writes, in the passage quoted above, of “something purring” at
              the boy’s heels and also of his tale of a “horrid apparition, tall and ghastly.” These
              might be taken by an illustrator as two different figures, both figments of the boy’s
              imagination at different times. Thus there is some justification for the noticeably
              “tall” figure on the right (illus. 17). That he is represented as “a schoolmaster
              holding a birch,” to use Butlin’s phrase, is altogether appropriate as the product of
              a schoolboy’s frightened fancy. But even if there were no textual rationale for the
              figure in the doorway, we could not for that reason dissociate the drawing from the
                <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> illustrations because plates 3, 5, 7-11 among Blake’s
              published designs for that poem contain prominent figures not mentioned in the
              text.</p>
            <p>The loose style of the drawing can be accounted for by its unfinished state and by
              the fact that it illustrates a passage in Blair much lighter in tone than others. A
              broad, caricature-like style is thus appropriate. The stylistic similarities between
              this drawing and some of Blake’s comic illustrations to Gray’s poems, such as the
              ninth design for “A Long Story,” are I believe the result of parallels in genre and
              tone, not precise chronology. The dimensions of the drawing correspond to the
              published <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> designs and to the only extant finished wash drawing
              in the series, the rejected “Death Pursuing the Soul through the Avenues of Life”
              (#635). Finally, the object held by the boy looks to my eyes like Blair’s “satchel”
              with a tassel dangling from its lower corner—not Butlin’s “doll.”</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p16-39" n="39"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XIII. Works Done at the Instigation of William Hayley, c.
                  1800-1805</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Blake scholars have frequently treated the years 1800 to 1805 as a traumatic period
              in Blake’s life and as a watershed in his career as artist and poet. Butlin has now
              provided a complete, illustrated accounting of the drawings and paintings that Blake
              produced for Hayley during this time. They show a considerable falling off in his
              artistic achievement, particularly when he (or Hayley?) forced his powerful, but in
              some ways narrow, talents into pictorial genres on the circumference of his vision.
              Miniature portraiture (#347, 353-54, 376-78), interior decoration (#343. 1-18), and
              vaguely topographical landscape (#369-75) may have instructed Blake in techniques he
              made use of in later masterpieces, but they are hardly his 
              <hi rend="i">métier.</hi></p>
            <figure n="BUT342.1.1.WC" rend="file" width="652" height="1000">
              <head>17 “Churchyard Spectres Frightening a Schoolboy.”</head>
              <figDesc>Pen and water color over pencil, 17.9 × 11.6 cm., dated by Butlin c.
                1795-1800 but perhaps an 1805 illustration to Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi>
                Butlin #342. Imogen Dennis Collection.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Whatever the limitations of Hayley’s character and need to protect and dominate
              disturbed geniuses like Romney and Cowper, we cannot lay all of Blake’s difficulties
              at his patron’s doorstep. From about 1802 to at least 1809, Blake seems to have
              suffered sporadically from what we would now call, using current rather than Blakean
              myths of mental states, a manic-depressive syndrome. This “disease” can sometimes
              progress into a schizophrenic state with delusive visions and directive voices, and a
              paranoia that focuses on well-intentioned friends. We should be dissuaded from
              attaching the schizophrenia label to Blake at this period of his life because of the
              considerable evidence indicating that he had visions—and believed in their superiority
              to conventional “reality”—from his youth to the last day of his life. Thus the
              1800-1805 period does not mark the sudden emergence of supposedly pathological
              phenomena. Blake’s central difficulty seems to have been not visions and voices, but
              self-doubt. Hayley’s real threat was not that he forced Blake to perform commercial
              tasks but that he made Blake suspect the importance of his vision.</p>
            <p>As a consequence of this jolt to Blake’s conception of his being, he began to harden
              his self-definition as an alienated genius and to withdraw from relationships
              threatening his isolation. After the partial break with Hayley, Cromek and Hunt were
              less the objects than the catalysts for Blake’s most significant acts of rejection.
              His sense of unrecognized talent shifts toward a paranoid discovery of jealousy in
              such erstwhile friends as Hayley, Flaxman, and Stothard. Yet these unrewarding but
              perhaps psychically necessary adjustments are less consequential than the fact of
              Blake’s self-rescue from doubt and despondency. We should not ignore the possibility
              that his return to a Christ-centered theology may have been part of this psychological
              salvation, much as Wordsworth and Coleridge were led to embrace traditional Christian
              structures after the failure of pantheism and its secular analogue, the French
              Revolution. The anatomy and cost of Blake’s restoration of faith in his vision have
              yet to be explored in detail. Butlin’s catalogue now gives us the pictorial foundation
              for the study of these mental heroics, much as Keynes, Erdman, and Bentley have
              provided the verbal documents.</p>
            <p>Two minute particulars follow.</p>
            <p>#343. 17, “Cowper,” one of eighteen Heads of Poets (City of Manchester Art
              Galleries). Butlin follows Rossetti in describing the wreath around the portrait as
              “lilies of the valley.” This seems clearly wrong to me; the wreath looks very similar
              to the bay or laurel pictured in the Dante, Chaucer, and Dryden portraits. Butlin
              describes Spenser’s wreath as “olive,” but it too looks like bay or laurel.</p>
            <p>#345, “Thomas Alphonso Hayley” (Yale Center for British Art). This half-length
              portrait was at one time bound up with the manuscript of Cunningham’s life of Blake
              and other Blakeana. Besides the dealer catalogues, listed by Butlin, in which this
              collection appeared, Quaritch also offered it in his advertising flyer dated May 1885,
              “William Blake’s Original Drawings.” This four-page flyer also offered a group of
              drawings from Tatham’s collection, <pb id="p16-40" n="40"/>
a group of important
              biblical water colors from the Butts collection, the Boston Museum 
                <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> series (#528), and nine of the twelve <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>
              illustrations (#536) executed for Butts.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XIV. Illustrations to the Bible Painted for Thomas Butts, c.
                  1799-1809</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>This group of 118 extant temperas and water colors includes some of Blake’s greatest
              works. While a few individual biblical paintings have received critical attention, the
              group as a whole remains largely unexplored. Butlin’s gathering of facts and
              illustrations will very probably stimulate, and provide the foundation for, a good
              many studies of these widely dispersed works. Some of these future essays (and books?)
              will no doubt propose various organizational schemes for the whole collection or
              subsets of it. The fact that they all take their subjects from the same book, a book
              with the richest tradition of interpretation in European culture, permits a vast
              proliferation of contrasts, comparisons, and groupings. Just as it is virtually
              impossible to select at random two or more passages in the Bible between which a
              clever exegete cannot find some relationship, so it is with any grouping of Blake’s
              biblical subjects. The true believer creates patterns to discover the immanence of God
              in the text; the Blake interpreter creates patterns to discover the immanence of the
              artist’s mind in the pictures. Neither ever fails in the search. If we pursue the
              hermeneutics of such studies far enough we may be led to that dangerous borderland
              between semiotics and the mathematics of finite sets. Or we are led to Wallace Stevens
              and order as the <hi rend="i">telos</hi> of desire:
<q> But to impose is not<lb/>
 To
                discover. To discover an order as of<lb/>
 A season, to discover summer and know
                it,<lb/>
 To discover winter and know it well, to find,<lb/>
 Not to impose, not to
                have reasoned at all,<lb/>
 Out of nothing to have come on major weather,<lb/>
 It is
                possible, possible, possible. It must Be possible.<lb/>
 (“Notes toward a Supreme
                Fiction”) </q></p>
            <p>Butlin’s catalogue offers appropriate restraint to the more fanciful cluster builders
              and pattern searchers. Parallels in media, dimensions, form of signature and other
              physical characteristics can tell us a great deal about which thematic groupings are
              most probable. Authoritative dating provides a diachronic structure against which we
              can test the synchronic structures of the iconographer, much as the labors of Los
              restrain the conquests of Urizen. Even the most convincing pattern of symbolic meaning
              is suspect if it violates the physical and chronological facts. We should also keep in
              mind the possibility that the structure of the group was less affected by an
              iconographic program than by such practical exigencies as available canvas sizes or
              the remaining wall or cabinet space in Butts’ home.</p>
            <p>Butlin subdivides the biblical subjects according to medium: tempera paintings
              (#379-432, including thirty-one traced and twenty-four untraced works<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55"
                type="note">44</ref>) and water color drawings (#433-526, including eighty-seven
              traced and six untraced works). Each group is arranged according to the order in the
              Bible of the passages illustrated, thereby forming two pictorial Blake Bibles. Within
              each group are subgroups determined by size, dating, and to some extent subject. The
              most significant of these groupings are defined by all three criteria. The temperas,
              all painted c. 1799-1803, fall into two groups according to size: those with
              dimensions of about 27 × 38 cm. (for typical examples see illus. 19-21), and a set of
              five works measuring about 32 × 50 cm. The latter were all executed c. 1799-1800 in
              thick, dark colors and take their subjects from the life of Christ: #410, “The Christ
              Child Asleep on a Cross”; #415, “The Baptism of Christ”; #416, “The Miracle of the
              Loaves and Fishes”; #422, “Christ’s Entry into Jerusalem”; #424, “The Last
                Supper.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">45</ref> The
structural independence of the
              large temperas from the small is underscored by the appearance of one subject, “The
              Christ Child Asleep on a Cross,” in both groups (#410, 411). Finally, among the
              smaller temperas there is a subset of the four Apostles (#396-99, “St. Mark” and “St.
              John” untraced) executed with the canvas turned to a vertical major 
              axis.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">46</ref> 
              #387, “Moses Indignant at the Golden Calf,” is the
              only other tempera, large or small, with a vertical format, although it is hard to see
              how it would fit into the series of Apostles. <note id="n55"><hi rend="s">44</hi>
                Calculating the number of works according to catalogue numbers does not work because
                there are “A” entries (i.e., #425A) and other adjustments.</note>
	<note id="n56"><hi
                  rend="s">45</hi> Butlin fails to include #410 in his list of the large temperas,
                p. 318. Neither Butlin or any other scholar I know of has previously argued for the
                independence and integrity of the large temperas as a group.</note>	
                  <note id="n57"><hi rend="s">46</hi> The dimensions of the two untraced works are not known,
but
                it is reasonably safe to assume that they corresponded to the extant Apostles. This
                group was first described as such by Bindman, <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist</hi>,
                p. 125.</note></p>
            <p>The biblical water colors offer a considerable challenge to those looking for subsets
              or a program organizing the whole collection. The patron may have had a good deal to
              say about the selection of subjects: in a letter of 22 November 1802, Blake asked
              Butts “what subject you choose to be painted on the remaining Canvas which I brought
              down with me” to Felpham.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58"
type="note">47</ref> Such influences do not
              necessarily exclude a program, but they do complicate the issue. The chronology of
              execution and sale to Butts delineates three style periods—1800, 1803, and 1805 (see
              Butlin, p. 335, and comments on #491, below)—but these do not seem to correspond
              directly to groupings by subjects or readily apparent themes. Butlin states simply his
              answer to the question of format: “Though the watercolours differ in size they seem to
              have been intended as a unified series, perhaps embodying Blake’s own commentary on
              their texts” (p. 336). Any illustration by Blake inevitably embodies his own
              commentary on the text, but we cannot decide on the basis of that observation whether
              these illustrations are independent works, each a separate interpretation of a
              specific text, or a “unified series” that we are to interpret as an interrelated
              entity with its own intentional structure. <note id="n58"><hi rend="s">47</hi><hi
                  rend="i"> The Letters of William Blake</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes, Third Edition
                (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1980), p. 43.</note></p>
            <p>We are on firmer ground when constructing subgroups among the biblical water colors
              on the basis of the physical and chronological facts that Butlin places at our finger
              tips. I list below some of these clusters.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59"
type="note">48</ref>	
                <note id="n59"><hi rend="s">48</hi> Subsets a (the three main pairs), b, c, and d (#519-22
                and “possibly” #518) are noted by Butlin, pp. 336, 360-61, 369. Bindman, 
                  <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist</hi>, pp. 131, 164-65, notes subsets b and c (which he
                apparently joins together) and d (#519-22, excluding #518). My purpose here is less
                to contribute new details about these groupings than to summarize the current state
                of research.</note></p>
            <p>a. At least three pairs formed by parallels in subject and composition. These are
              #453, “Samson Breaking his Bonds,” and #455, “Samson Subdued,” both c. 1800-1803;<ref
                target="n60" type="note">49</ref> #488, “Mary Magdalene Washing 
                <pb id="p16-41" n="41"/>
Christ’s Feet,” and #489, “Christ in the House of Martha and
Mary,” C.
              1803-1805; and #511, “The Death of St. Joseph,” and #512, “The Death of the Virgin,”
              both inscribed “1803.” The similarities in compositional format and coloring indicate
              that these pairs—unlike groupings based solely on interpretive insights—were probably
              intentional. Other pairings are possible, but far less certain—e.g., #466, “By the
              Waters of Babylon,” and #472, “The Repose of the Holy Family in Egypt,” both of 1806.
              It is not surprising, and perhaps not very significant, that #509, “St. Paul Shaking
              off the Viper,” and #510, “St. Paul and the Viper,” are similarly constructed because
              they picture immediately successive events in the same location. 
                  <note id="n60"><hi rend="s">49</hi> The untraced #454, “Samson and the Philistines,” may
mean that
                this is a group of three, not two.</note></p>
            <p>b. A group picturing the Crucifixion and Entombment, begun in 1800 and completed no
              later than 1803. Butlin, p. 360, includes in this group #494, “Christ Crucified
              Between the Two Thieves”; #495, “The Soldiers Casting Lots for Christ’s Garment”; and
              #499, “Sealing the Stone and Setting a Watch.” These three each measure about 40 × 32
              cm., but I would tentatively add, for reasons of style and subject, two slightly
              smaller works: #491, “Judas Betrays Him” (36.6 × 30.1 cm.); and #496, “Christ Nailed
              to the Cross: The Third Hour” (33.2 × 34.6 cm.). Butlin dates the Judas c. 1803-1805,
              but I would date it no later than 1803 because, like all the members of this group, it
              exhibits Fuseli’s influence in its exaggerated gestures and almost caricature-like
              faces.</p>
            <p>c. A group, executed c. 1805, picturing the Crucifixion, Entombment, and
              Resurrection. Butlin, pp. 336 and 361, includes the following because of their similar
              sizes, formats, and “near-monochromatic colouring”: #497, “The Crucifixion: ‘Behold
              thy Mother’”; #498, “The Entombment” (illus. 18); #500, “Christ in the Sepulchre,
              Guarded by Angels”; #501, “The Angel Rolling the Stone away from the Sepulchre”; #502,
              “The Resurrection”; #504, “The Magdalene at the Sepulchre.” To these six Butlin
              tentatively adds #487, “The Raising of Lazarus” (a typological prefiguration of
              #502?); and #505, “The Ascension.” The latter is much more brightly colored than the
              others, as is appropriate for its subject; this coloring and the prominent use of pen
              and pencil outlining suggest a slightly earlier date, c. 1803-1805. #498, 500-502, and
              504 are strongly linked because they all picture Christ’s tomb from a low perspective,
              contain an arched doorway as a central background motif, and have a highly symmetrical
              arrangement of figures (see illus. 18).</p>
            <p>d. Beasts from the Book of Revelation, all c. 1803-1805, all similar in size and
              format, and all signed with the WB monogram. This group consists of #519, “The Great
              Red Dragon and the Woman Clothed with the Sun” (Brooklyn Museum); #520, the same
              subject in the National Gallery of Art; #521, “The Great Red Dragon and the Beast from
              the Sea” (National Gallery of Art); and #522, “The Number of the Beast is 666”
              (Rosenbach Museum, Philadelphia). I would tentatively add #518, “And the Angel which I
              saw Lifted up his Hand to Heaven,” executed c. 1805 perhaps as a contrary exemplar to
              the four beasts. Early preludes to this group of five are #517, “Death on a Pale
              Horse” (with coloring similar to #518), and #524, “He Cast him into the Bottomless
              Pit” (often called “Michael Binding the Dragon”), both c. 1800. One might even include
              #523, “The Whore of Babylon” (1809) as a late addition to the apocalyptic company.</p>
            <p>The chronology of composition of the eight water colors in the last subdivision (d)
              offers a clue to how such groups, when not simply the productions of interpreters,
              evolved over a number of years. Blake began with two compositionally distinct and
              independent works, #517 and #524, possibly without any thought of creating a series of
              illustrations to Revelation. In about 1803 he returned, at his own or Butts’ behest,
              to the subject, producing #519 and #521. Shortly thereafter he expanded the pair to a
              quartet with the addition of #520 and #522. Blake then drew #518 as a balance to the
              family of horrid creatures, both an addition to the group and a release from it. Some
              four years later, he returned to the apocalyptic beasts for #523, clearly distinct in
              color and format from the earlier cluster. Our sense, and possibly Blake’s, of a
              planned series comes <hi rend="i">after</hi> the initial compositions, becomes
              definite in the middle period with the purposefully interrelated #519-22, and then
              dissipates as compositions on related subjects lead toward new styles and meanings.
              There is no program prior to composition. It grows organically in the course of, and
              as a consequence of, work with pencil, paint, and paper. It does not end neatly and
              suddenly, but extends its influence through later works.</p>
            <p>The foregoing scenario contains a good deal of speculation, but at least it accords
              with Blake’s theories of composition. He seems to have put into practice in such cases
              his insistence on the unity of conception and execution, thought and deed, mind and
              hand. I hope we can give additional authority to those interpretations informed by a
              sense of Blake’s conceptual/compositional processes.</p>
            <p>Comments on individual entries follow.</p>
            <p>#381, “Lot and his Daughters” (Huntington Library; illus. 19). Recent observation
              with ultraviolet illumination has shown that much of the background and landscape on
              the right in this tempera have been repainted. The lines (visible in Butlin’s
              reproduction and in illus. 19) forming a rectangle, well within the outer edges of the
              image and framing the figures, seem to be the result of an earlier matting, perhaps to
              cover once-damaged areas. These lines are not directly related to overpainting or
              other repair efforts. The extensive restorations to this tempera are hardly unique;
              most of those painted c. 1799-1800 are in bad shape and have been restored at least
              once—in some cases as many as three times. A case in point is #394, “Job and his
              Daughters” (National Gallery of Art), which looks at first glance to be in fair
              condition today but was described by W. M. Rossetti as “fearfully dilapidated” in the
              1863 edition of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of Blake.</hi> Someone has done a lot of
              work on it in the last 118 years.</p>
            <p>#387, “Moses Indignant at the Golden Calf” (Ian Phillips Collection). The plate
              reference should be to 487, not “407.”</p>
            <pb id="p16-42" n="42"/>
            <figure n="but498.1.1.wc" id="but498.1.wc.01" work-copy="biblicalwc" rend="db" width="747" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
              <head>18 “The Entombment.”</head>
              <figDesc>Pen and water color, 41.7 × 31 cm., c. 1805. Butlin #498. Tate
                Gallery.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="but381.1.1.pt" id="but381.1.pt.01" work-copy="biblicaltemperas" rend="db" width="958" height="673">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
              <head>19 “Lot and his Daughters.”</head>
              <figDesc>Pen and tempera on canvas, 26.3 × 37.8 cm., c. 1799-1800. Butlin #381.
                Huntington Library.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>#401, “The Nativity” (Philadelphia Museum of Art). Sessler’s records indicate that
              the firm purchased this tempera in April 1938 from Wells for $4050 and sold it in
              December to Mrs. Tonner for $4500.</p>
            <p>#422, “Christ’s Entry into Jerusalem.” Butlin locates this work at “Pollock House,
              Corporation of Glasgow.” Hilary Macartney of the Glasgow Museums &amp; Art Galleries
              informs me that the Corporation of Glasgow was replaced by the Glasgow District
              Council in 1974. The same correction pertains to #427, 639, 653, 667, and 668. Ms.
              Macartney also tells me that neither this tempera nor any other Blakes (#639, 653,
              667, 668) from the Stirling-Maxwell Collection were given “in lieu of death duties,”
              as Butlin claims.</p>
            <p>#426, “The Body of Christ Borne to the Tomb” (Tate Gallery; illus. 20). Butlin
              quotes, with apparent approval, Bindman’s claim that Joseph of Arimathea is
              “prominent” in this tempera and in #427, “The Entombment” (Pollock House, Glasgow;
              illus. 21).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">50</ref> If present
in the latter, he must be
              the central figure holding an incense jar. There are two patriarchal figures in #426,
              but Joseph is probably the figure third from the right with the same very long beard
              and jar pictured in #427. Further, his walking stick is an appropriate prophecy of his
              legendary sermon, pictured in Blake’s relief color print “Joseph of Arimathea
              Preaching to Inhabitants of Britain,” during which his staff turned into a thorn tree.
              However, in his entry on #427, Butlin identifies the central figure as Nicodemus
              arriving “with myrrh and aloes.” Neither the Gospels nor the apocryphal Book of
              Nicodemus offers a definitive textual answer; in John XIX:38-39, both are present at
              Christ’s tomb. On the visual evidence alone, one is tempted to claim that the two
              longbeards in #426 and 427 <hi rend="i">must</hi> be the same man. Yet if we turn to
              the water color of “The Entombment” (Butlin #489; illus. 18), we find two aged twins
              on the left, one of whom is probably Nicodemus and the other Joseph of Arimathea. But
              which is which? Clearly, we cannot be certain that two figures in different works are
              the same character just because they look very similar, or even identical. Butlin’s
              inconsistency in calling the old man in #427 both Joseph and Nicodemus points to a
              general problem in interpreting Blake’s designs. Who said Blake’s old men all look
              alike? <note id="n61"><hi rend="s">50</hi> Bindman, <hi rend="i">Blake as an
                  Artist</hi>, p. 124.</note></p>
            <figure n="but426.1.1.pt" id="but426.1.pt.01" work-copy="biblicaltemperas" rend="db" width="958" height="689">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
              <head>20 “The Body of Christ Borne to the Tomb.”</head>
              <figDesc>Tempera on canvas, 26.7 × 37.8 cm., c. 1799-1800. Butlin #426. Tate
                Gallery.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p16-43" n="43"/>
            <p>#445, “Moses Striking the Rock” (Lutheran Church in America, Philadelphia). According
              to their records, Sessler’s purchased the drawing from Angew’s in December 1964 for
              $7000 and sold it to Mrs. Tonner for $7700.</p>
            <p>#458, “The Ghost of Samuel Appearing to Saul” (National Gallery of Art; illus. 22).
              Early reproductions and descriptions, as well as a few extant examples, indicate that
              at least some of the biblical water colors executed for Butts were mounted on large
              sheets inscribed in a fine copperplate-type hand with the appropriate texts. I know of
              no evidence that these works were ever bound, but the careful mounting and inscribing
              indicate that they were probably intended to be kept together in an album or portfolio
              to form an illustrated selection of biblical passages. The physical arrangement of
              central design and surrounding text foreshadows the format of the Job engravings.</p>
            <p>“The Ghost of Samuel Appearing to Saul” is one of the few water colors that have not
              had the inscriptions removed. It is reproduced with this review in full illus. 22—I
              believe for the first time.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62"
type="note">51</ref> The inscription just
              below the right corner of the design, “1<hi rend="s">st</hi> Samuel 28<hi rend="s">th</hi> ch:
12<hi rend="s">th</hi> to 21,” records the passage illustrated, but not
              all the quoted and paraphrased lines. “And Saul said . . . ” above the image is from 1
              Samuel 28:7, with the initial “Then” of the King James version changed to “And.” The
              first sentence below the design (“And 
              <figure n="BUT427.1.1.PT" rend="file" width="958" height="670">
                <head>21 “The Entombment.”</head>
                <figDesc>Pen and tempera on canvas, 26.5 × 38 cm., c. 1799-1800. Butlin #427.
                  Glasgow Museums and Art Galleries, Stirling Maxwell Collection, Pollok
                  House.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <figure n="but458.1.1.wc" id="but458.1.wc.01" work-copy="biblicalwc" rend="db" width="958" height="898">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
                <head>22 “The Ghost of Samuel Appearing to Saul,” complete with original inscribed
                  mount.</head>
                <figDesc>Pen and water color, 32 × 34.4 cm. on paper 54 × 44 cm., c. 1800. Butlin
                  #458. National Gallery of Art, Washington.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <figure n="but462.1.1.wc" id="but462.1.wc.01" work-copy="biblicalwc" rend="db" width="839" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>WB</figTranscr>
                <head>23 “David Delivered out of Many Waters.”</head>
                <figDesc>Pen and water color, 41.5 × 34.8 cm., c. 1805. Butlin #462. Tate
                  Gallery.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <pb id="p16-44" n="44"/> 
              Saul said to the woman, bring me up Samuel.”) is a
              modification of verse 11, “Then said the woman, Whom shall I bring up unto thee? And
              he said, Bring me up Samuel.” The next sentence (“And when the woman . . . ”) is taken
              from verse 12, with further modifications (“The woman spake” changed to “spake”). The
              remaining inscriptions follow the Bible through verse 19, with a few clauses elided
              and new ones compounded from remaining phrases. None of the changes creates any
              substantive additions or subtractions. <note id="n62"><hi rend="s">51</hi> The A. E.
                Newton auction catalogue, Parke-Bernet, 16 April 1941, p. 46, contains a
                reproduction that vaguely records only the inscriptions below the design.</note></p>
            <p>Butlin (pp. 335-36) offers two possible scribes as the author of the mount
              inscriptions: Mrs. Blake (as Graham Robertson suggested), or a member of the Butts
              family prior to 1852. If the former, I doubt that she would have modified the biblical
              text, in ways exemplified by #458, without specific directions to do so from her
              husband. If the latter, we must believe, on the basis of these examples alone, that
              Thomas Butts or some member of his family was a skilled calligrapher. We should also
              consider the possibility that Blake himself executed the <corr type="emend">inscriptions</corr>. Although it is
              always difficult to attribute a formal, stylized hand, the inscriptions on “The Ghost
              of Samuel” are not incompatible with the most elegant copperplate lettering in the 
                <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> manuscript. These biblical inscriptions have generally been
              ignored in the past, but certainly future studies of the biblical water colors must
              take them into account.</p>
            <p>#462, “David Delivered out of Many Waters” (Tate Gallery; illus. 23). One of the
              organizational hypotheses worth testing in the biblical water colors is the presence
              of a typological format, both within individual works and between New and Old
              Testament subjects. This composition, with a cruciform gesture reflected between David
              and Christ, offers clear evidence of Blake’s use of the figural tradition. It is easy
              to read other Old Testament illustrations typologically if one attends to the subjects
              alone. What we need to find are <hi rend="i">compositional</hi> parallels, like the
              one within “David Delivered,” that indicate specific figural relationships among the
              Old and New Testament designs. I have yet to find a clear pattern of such
              parallels.</p>
            <p>#481, “The Parable of the Wise and Foolish Virgins.” The “Private Collection” in
              which Butlin locates this version of the composition is that of Philip Hofer,
              Cambridge, Mass., who is named as the owner in the Philadelphia (1939) and National
              Gallery of Art (1957) exhibition catalogues.</p>
            <p>#524, “He Cast Him into the Bottomless Pit,” often called “Michael Binding the
              Dragon” (Fogg Art Museum). The reference should be to Plate 585, not “524.”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XV. Illustrations to Milton’s Poems, c. 1801-1820</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Butlin brings these much-studied illustrations together in proper chronological order
              of composition and reproduces all of them in color. It is especially helpful to have
              the three <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> series—those for Rev. Thomas, Butts, and
              Linnell—sorted out once and for all. Perhaps the most obvious facts are the most
              important to keep in mind when studying the complex iconography of the Milton designs:
              the number of images, their range and diversity, and the considerable length of time
              over which they were executed. To the central group of ninety compositions catalogued
              in this section we can add seven early works (#101-106, 259) and a few later ones
              (#781A, perhaps untraced #835-39) with Miltonic subjects, several sketches in Blake’s
                <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>, and a few designs in <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> Butlin’s
              brief comparisons of motifs and compositional formats between early and later series
              of illustrations to the same poem will be particularly valuable to future
              interpreters.</p>
            <p>#532, sketch for “Satan Watching the Endearments of Adam and Eve” (Keynes
              Collection). The reference should be to Plate 724, not “714.”</p>
            <p>#543.1, “Mirth” in the <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> illustrations (Pierpont Morgan
              Library). Butlin writes that Jean Hagstrum has related this composition “to Golzius’
              ‘Sun God’ engraving.” Hagstrum’s reference is not to this water color but to #543.3,
              “The Sun at his Eastern Gate.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63"
type="note">52</ref>
	<note id="n63"><hi
                  rend="s">52</hi> Hagstrum, <hi rend="i">William Blake Poet and Painter</hi>
                (Chicago: Chicago University Press, 1964), pp. 46, 50.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XVI. Illustrations to Shakespeare, c. 1806-1825</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Like Fuseli, Blake was much attracted to Queen Katharine’s dream in 
                <hi rend="i">Henry VIII</hi>, executing four treatments of the subject (#247, 547.3, 548,
549).
              The last two, executed in 1807 and 1825, are clearly superior to Blake’s other
              Shakespearean efforts. These indicate not only his growth as an artist, but also how
              much his interests centered on scenes of transmundane insight. These evoked his
              artistic talents far more successfully than earthbound passages in Shakespeare’s
              plays.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XVII. Illustrations to the Book of Job, c. 1805-1826</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Perhaps some of us have become used to thinking of the Job designs as productions of
              Blake’s final years because of the late date of the engravings. Such chronological
              distortions are corrected by Butlin’s setting out the four main series and twelve
              independent works—a total of seventy-four images—in proper order. He provides a most
              convincing argument for dating all but two compositions (see comments on #550. 17, 20,
              below) in the Butts series to c. 1805-1806, contemporary with the 
                <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> illustrations. The progressive development of all the Job designs
casts
              further doubt on the authenticity of the “New Zealand” set, now in Paul Mellon’s
              collection. That series follows the last state of the engravings for those plates,
              such as 16, in which there are design changes in successive proof states. Thus the New
              Zealand set did not play a role in the development of the designs culminating in the
              engravings. They must have been executed after the completion of the engraved series.
              Butlin is right in excluding the 
<pb id="p16-45" n="45"/>
New Zealand set from the
              canon and attributing it to Linnell, who may have been assisted by members of his
              family or his students.</p>
            <p>#550.17, “The Vision of Christ,” and #550.20, “Job and his Daughters,” in the Butts
              set of water colors (Pierpont Morgan Library). Butlin offers good reasons for
              believing that these are late additions, perhaps left unfinished at Blake’s death and
              completed by Mrs. Blake. Lindberg’s theory<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n64" type="note">53</ref> that
              they were executed at the same time as the rest of the series and were finished by
              Butts does not account for the differences in paper, basic conception of the figures,
              or the resemblances between their style and Blake’s late works. Thus the Butts set was
              originally conceived as a series of nineteen designs, and these two subjects were
              first introduced in the Linnell set of 1821.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n65" type="note">54</ref> We
              know that Blake borrowed the Butts set back from its owner in September 1821 so that
              Linnell could make tracings of them for a new set.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n66" type="note">55</ref> Apparently Butts learned at some point of the two new designs and
              commissioned versions to and to his set. There is no evidence supporting Gilchrist’s
              contention that the relationship between Blake and Butts “grew cool” in the 1820s;
              indeed, Gilchrist’s own statement that “one of the last, if not the very last, works
              bought by Mr. Butts of Blake, was the original series of twenty-one watercolour
              drawings or <hi rend="i">Inventions</hi> from the <hi rend="i">Book of Job</hi>,”<ref
                target="n67" type="note">56</ref> may be a slightly confused reference to the late
              acquisition of these two designs. The possibility of contact between Butts and Mrs.
              Blake after her husband’s death is suggested by Butts’ acquisition of posthumous copy
              I of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>
	<note id="n64"><hi rend="s">53</hi> Bo Lindberg, 
                  <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Book of Job</hi> (Åbo, Finland: Åbo
                Akademi, 1973), pp. 19, 325, 345.</note>
	<note id="n65"><hi rend="s">54</hi> Butlin
                first presented these arguments in “Cataloguing William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Blake
                  in his Time</hi>, ed. Essick and Pearce, pp. 86-87.</note>
	<note id="n66"><hi
                  rend="s">55</hi> Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon
                Press, 1969), p. 274.</note>
	<note id="n67"><hi rend="s">56</hi><hi rend="i"> Life of
                  William Blake</hi> (London: Macmillan, 1863), I, 282.</note></p>
            <p>#551.6, “Satan Smiting Job with Boils” in the Linnell set of water colors (Fogg Art
              Museum). Butlin is very good at pointing out Linnell’s “misunderstandings” when he
              traced the outlines from the Butts set. For example, in this composition Job’s right
              hand, not pictured in Butts’ version, has been added. Butlin, however, does not
              comment on the fact that we can still see the landscape background drawn right through
              the hand, suggesting that it was added after the original tracing. The right hand
              appears in all later versions—the reduced drawings, the engravings, and the tempera
              (#807) of c. 1826. Perhaps Blake, when finishing the outlines, introduced this new
              feature. Alternatively, Linnell could have returned to the drawing after seeing the
              later versions to make his water color set compatible with them.</p>
            <p>#553, “Every Man also Gave him a Piece of Money, Alternative Composition,” located by
              Butlin in a private British collection but recently acquired and exhibited by the Tate
              Gallery. This delicate drawing (illus. 24) is an interesting but rejected variant
              executed before the engravings, c. 1821-1823. Both water color sets have a very
              different composition, with a horizontal major axis, representing this event. In this
              drawing, and again in the reduced sketches (#557.43) for the engravings, Blake changed
              to a vertical format and created a design that would be a reflective contrary to plate
              5. The thematic contrasts between giving and receiving, between outer charity
              according to the law and inner humility according to the spirit, would thereby be
              strengthened. But Blake returned to the horizontal design of the water colors,
              creating a juxta position of plates 19 and 4 because of their similar positioning of
              Job and his wife beneath a tree and before stone columns. The emphasis is now on the
              contrasts between receiving destructive news in the midst of Job’s pride and receiving
              lifegiving sustenance in the midst of Job’s humility. Butlin suggests (p. 432) that
              Blake returned to his first version because “the vision of God [in the alternative
              composition] is so similar to that in plate 20.” An even closer parallel is with God
              in plate 13; Blake may have felt that three similar representations was one too
              many.</p>
            <p>#557, “Sketchbook Containing Twenty-Seven Drawings for the Engraved Illustrations to
              the Book of Job Together with Other Drawings” (Fitzwilliam Museum). In his
              introductory comments on these reduced drawings, p. 426, Butlin notes that Linnell’s
              comment that “the Borders [on the Job plates] were an afterthought and designed as
              well as engraved upon the copper without a previous drawing”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68"
                type="note">57</ref> is a “slight exaggeration, particularly as there also exists a
              set of trial proofs [in the National Gallery of Art, Washington] with sketches for the
              borders.” Linnell’s statement is correct when properly understood within the context
              of graphic procedures that would normally have required fairly detailed, full-size
              preliminary drawings of any images engraved on the copper. Butlin claims that pages 7,
              9, and 11 of the Fitzwilliam sketchbook contain “indications suggesting the borders”;
              but the first and second of these show at most a few squiggles resembling lines of
              text rather than pictures, and the last bears vague indications of a border completely
              unlike the one in the engraving of plate 3. Among the early proofs with border
              sketches, only those of plates 1, 2, and 10 bear even a slight resemblance to the
              engraved versions. The development of the border decorations appears to have begun
              with the reduced sketches, with an emphasis on texts rather than designs. Next, Blake
              used some very early proofs (#559.1-6) of the engravings to sketch out possible border
              compositions. Linnell’s statement that there was no “previous drawing” (i.e., a direct
              preliminary) is not contradicted by these alternative first-thought sketches. By
              “designed . . . upon the copper” he simply means that the final drawings were made on
              the copper in pencil or chalk around the central panels, already developed to a fairly
              high level of finish. In that sense, the framing designs were indeed an
              “afterthought.” The border drawings were then scratched into the copper in drypoint,
              fragments of which can still be seen as light shadow lines next to letters and lines
              on some early impressions. Finally, these lightly incised outlines were worked over
              with the graver. <note id="n68"><hi rend="s">57</hi> Linnell’s letter of 27 September
                1844 to Charles Wentworth Dilke, now in Keynes’ collection (see Bentley, 
                  <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, pp. 326-27).</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XVIII. Drawings and Separate Designs Related to 
                    <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, c. 1804-1820</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>#566, Sketch for <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plate 26, “Hand Appearing to Jerusalem”
              (British Museum). Butlin usually notes the presence of glue spots, indicating that a
              drawing may have been fixed face down to another sheet for transfer, but he overlooks
              their clear presence on 
              <pb id="p16-46" n="46"/>
              <figure n="BUT553.1.1r.WC" rend="file" width="790" height="1000">
                <head>24 “Every Man also Gave him a Piece of Money,” an alternative design for Job
                  plate 19.</head>
                <figDesc>Pencil and water color, 22.6 × 17.7 cm., c. 1821-1823. Butlin #553. Tate
                  Gallery.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <figure n="BUT591.1.1.PD" rend="file" width="700" height="831">
                <head>25 A standing figure and two drawings of a face.</head>
                <figDesc>black and red chalk, 20 × 16.5 cm., c. 1805-1810 (?) and c. 1825 (?).
                  Butlin #591. Essick Collection.</figDesc>
              </figure> 
              the four corners of this pencil sketch. Joseph Viscomi has kindly pointed
              out to me the presence of a plate mark around the image on three sides just outside
              the glue spots. This plate mark measures 16.4 cm. high, exactly the same as the height
              of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plate 26. There is no clear plate mark on the left side
              of the drawing, but this is because the sheet has been trimmed to 21 cm. from the
              right plate mark, reducing it to less than the 22.5 cm. width of plate 26. This
              trimming has also cut off Hand’s extended fingers on the far left. In other respects
              the drawing matches the plate in general outlines and proportions, although it lacks
              details on the figures and there is no text. As Butlin points out, the image is “not
              in reverse”—exactly the case if the drawing had been placed face down on the plate to
              reverse it on the copper. Impressions taken from the plate will of course be reversed
              again, changing right and left back to their original position in the drawing. Blake
              describes just such a transfer technique in his <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> memorandum
              “To Engrave on Pewter.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69"
type="note">58</ref> The use of transfer for
              white-line plates does <hi rend="i">not</hi> indicate that Blake used a similar method
              to prepare his black-line relief etchings of designs or texts. Although often combined
              on the same plate, the two media are very different in both appearance and method of
              execution. <note id="n69"><hi rend="s">58</hi><hi rend="i"> The Poetry and Prose of
                  William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman (Garden City, New York: Doubleday, 1965),
                p. 672.</note></p>
            <p>Viscomi’s important discovery of a plate mark on this sketch and his interpretation
              of its significance provide very strong evidence for Blake’s use of transfer for the
              white-line relief etching on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plate 26. Viscomi has also
              suggested in conversation that Blake used the same technique for all his white-line
              plates. The pencil sketch for the white-line headpiece to <hi rend="i">Little Tom the
                Sailor</hi> (#359 recto) would seem to be a similar drawing prepared for transfer,
              but in its present state it lacks glue spots and a plate mark. The printed headpiece
              measures 11.1 × 16.1 cm., just within the 11.6 × 16.5 cm. size of the drawing. Thus
              there should be some remaining evidence of transfer if the drawing had been used for
              that purpose.</p>
            <p>#578, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plate 51 (Keynes Collection), and #579, 
                <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plate 51 (National Gallery of Victoria, Melbourne). Butlin
              describes each of these separate impressions as a “line engraving printed in relief.”
              This may be a little misleading because “line engraving” is generally taken to be an
              intaglio medium. Further, the plate is basically an etching, although some tool work
              may have been added. The best term for the technique is “white-line relief
              etching.”</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p16-47" n="47"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XIX. Miscellaneous Drawings, c. 1805-1820</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>#591, “A Standing Figure and Two Drawings of a Face” (Essick Collection; illus. 25).
              In his provenance information, Butlin does not include the fact that Paul Grinke sold
              this drawing to Quaritch, or placed it on consignment with that firm, before I
              purchased it in October 1970. The proof of the frontispiece to Bürger’s 
                <hi rend="i">Leonora</hi> on the verso bears pencil indications for further work which was
added
              to the plate in the published state. These markings may have been made by Blake. On
              the recto above the “Blake” inscription (lower right, not by Blake) are indistinct
              traces of two lines of partially erased letters. Butlin suggests that both the heads
              were executed at a later time than the standing figure, but the same black chalk or
              soft lead pencil seems to have been used for both the figure and the head lower left.
              He also suggests that the figure is “just possibly Satan arousing his legions,” but
              does not note the slight indications of an alternative right arm position just above
              the horizontal (see illus. 25). This arm position brings the sketch closer to Satan’s
              posture in “Satan Calling up his Legions” in the Huntington series of 
                <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> illustrations (#529.1) and in the tempera of “Satan Calling
up
              his Legions” (#662). The dating of all three works makes it possible that this awkward
              little sketch records an early stage in the development of the main figure in the two
              finished compositions.</p>
            <p>#598-601, a group of four sheets of pencil studies bearing six related designs. Five
              of these studies are reproduced here, illus. 26-30. Butlin groups these compositions
              together “for the first time” (p. 444), dating them all c. 1805 and suggesting that
              “all are perhaps related to Blake’s commission to illustrate Blair’s 
                <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>” (p. 450). All these sketches of about the same size are on unused
              sheets from Hayley’s 1802 <hi rend="i">Ballads.</hi> They form an interrelated group
              or series well worth study. The dominant motif is a devilish-looking fellow, somewhat
              similar to the figure on p. 75 of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>, standing in
              various attitudes of amazement or fright before a gothic church (#598, 599 recto, 600
              verso; see illus. 26, 27, 30). On the back of #599, Blake sketched out other sorts of
              figures against a similar background (illus. 28), and continued to work out this type
              of composition in #601. On the recto of #600 he tried an even more elaborate design
              (illus. 29), apparently of a resurrection scene. Slight hints of a church facade and
              portal remain, but the soaring and embracing figures would seem to be contraries to
              the devilish or desperate characters in the other sketches.</p>
            <p>Butlin’s proposal that the group is related to the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>
              illustrations can be supported through a comparison with #636, “The Gambols of the
              Ghosts” (Yale Center for British Art; illus. 31). Although the textual basis for this
              elaborate composition is slight, it may well be the “Gambols of the Ghosts according
              with their affections previous to the final Judgment” mentioned by Flaxman in his
              letter to Hayley of 18 October 1805 describing <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> illustrations
              that Blake was then preparing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70"
type="note">59</ref> Besides the
              general similarities in tone and apparent themes between this <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>
              design and the series discussed here, one can also point out similar motifs such as
              the church door and facade on the left with humbled figures before it (illus. 28),
              heads with their bodies seemingly buried in the ground (illus. 28), soaring and
              twisting figures (illus. 29), and the flying character, just above those entering the
              church, who may be holding a whip (#601, not reproduced here). Another link to the 
                <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> designs is suggested by #624 verso, “The Ascension of the
              Beatified Soul” (illus. 32). This too is on <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> paper and has
              the same vertical format, scale, and portal motif as the #598-601 series. Butlin
              tentatively dates this sketch c. 1807, but I see no reason why it could not have been
              drawn a year or two earlier. On the recto is a preliminary sketch for “The Death of
              the Strong Wicked Man” among the published <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> illustrations.
              Butlin suggests that the verso drawing (illus. 32) may have been “done in connection
              with the Dedication” to the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>, but his cryptically brief “cf.
              also Nos. . . . 598-601” hints at a connection with that series. It may well be part
              of the group, following #600 (illus. 29) as an appropriate conclusion to a pictorial
              tale of fright, despair, death, resurrection, and ascension. 
                  <note id="n70"><hi rend="s">59</hi> Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p.
166.</note></p>
            <p>The circumstantial and thematic associations between this series and the 
                <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> designs imply a chronology of composition beginning with Cromek’s
              commission. After the “Gambols of the Ghosts” was rejected, for whatever reasons,
              Blake may have decided to develop it, and other Graveyard motifs, into a series of
              compositions. Blake may even have created his oddly devilish but apparently frightened
              figure (illus. 26, 27, 30) out of Blair’s description of the schoolboy in “The lone
              church-yard” who runs from an imagined presence “purring at his heels” (see discussion
              of #342, above). Since the lucrative job of executing his <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>
              designs had been taken away from Blake, he may have begun this series as a way of
              salvaging something for himself from the project. It might have been developed into an
              important series of finished water colors or prints, but we have no evidence that it
              ever progressed beyond these first thoughts in pencil.</p>
            <p>#607 verso, “Upper Part of a Nude Demon” (George Goyder Collection). The reference
              should be to Plate 48, not “50.”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XX. Illustrations to Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, c.
                  1805-1807</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Butlin’s complete listing of all the extant <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> designs deepens
              one’s bewilderment over why none of the finished preliminary drawings have survived.
              Cromek must have passed them on to Schiavonetti and his journeymen for rendering in
              copper, and presumably they were returned to the publisher. After that, one cannot
              even speculate on their destiny. Among the rejected designs, only one (#635; see
              comments below) is a finished wash drawing of the sort normally prepared as the
              immediate preliminary for an engraving, although #633, “A Widow Embracing her
              Husband’s Grave,” comes close.</p>
            <pb id="p16-48" n="48"/>
            <figure n="BUT598.16.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="811">
              <head>26 “The Devil Outside a Church.”</head>
              <figDesc>Pencil, 27.1 × 13 cm., c. 1805. Butlin #598. Collection of George Goyder,
                Suffolk.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="BUT599.recto.16.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="812">
              <head>27 Two sketches for “The Devil Outside a Church.”</head>
              <figDesc>Pencil, 27.2 × 12.7 cm., c. 1805. Butlin #599 recto. Collection of George
                Goyder, Suffolk.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="BUT599.verso.16.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="737">
              <head>28 A woman and child before a church with other figures passing by.</head>
              <figDesc>Pencil, 27.2 × 12.7 cm., c. 1805. Butlin #599 verso. Collection of George
                Goyder, Suffolk.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="BUT600.1.1r.PD" rend="file" width="619" height="1000">
              <head>29 “A Resurrection Scene.”</head>
              <figDesc>Pencil, 21 × 13.5 cm., c. 1805. Butlin #600 recto. National Gallery of Art,
                Washington.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p16-49" n="49"/>
            <figure n="BUT600.1.1v.PD" rend="file" width="602" height="1000">
              <head>30 “The Devil Outside a Church.”</head>
              <figDesc>Pencil, 21 × 13.5 cm., c. 1805. Butlin #600 verso. National Gallery of Art,
                Washington.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>A few corrections and comments on individual entries follow.</p>
            <p>Page 455, second line. The proof of “Death’s Door” engraved by Schiavonetti is dated
                <hi rend="i">Feby 1<hi rend="s">st</hi> 1806</hi>, not “12 February 1806.”</p>
            <p>#616, “Second Alternative Design for Title-Page: A Spirit Rising from the Tomb”
              (Huntington Library). Inscribed “A Series of Designs: Illustrative of The Grave. a
              Poem by Robert Blair. Invented &amp; Drawn by William Blake 1806.” In his provenance
              information, Butlin records the possible sale of this drawing from the collection of
              Frederick Tatham at Sotheby’s, 29 April 1862, in lot 159 with seven other works (7<hi
                rend="i">s.</hi> to Smith). This lot contained a work described in the sale
              catalogue as “Spirit rising from the Tomb”—a title that could fit several drawings by
                Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71" type="note">60</ref> Dennis M.
Read has recently discovered,
              and very kindly allowed me to record here, that this drawing was still in the
              possession of Thomas H. Cromek, Robert H. Cromek’s son, as late as 1865.<ref
                target="n72" type="note">61</ref> According to Read, T. H. Cromek wrote his
              manuscript “Memorials of R. H. Cromek” in that year. He states therein that “The
              original design for the Frontispiece [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>?], still in my possession,
              was suppressed, and one much finer substituted. It is a pen outline, slightly shaded
              with Indian ink, and blue, and represents a soul rising from the tomb, on which Blake
              has written, very neatly, this title:—‘A Series of Designs illustrative of The Grave—a
              Poem by Robert Blair Invented &amp; Drawn by William Blake 1806.’” The concluding
              quotation makes it absolutely certain that Cromek is referring to #616. It is unlikely
              that the drawing was intended as a “frontispiece” or title page for the 
                <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> illustrations published in R. H. Cromek’s 1808 edition. The ratio of
              height to width is inappropriate for a folio or quarto volume, and the inscription
              “Invented &amp; Drawn” suggests that this title-page was created for a series of
              drawings, not engravings. <note id="n71"><hi rend="s">60</hi> Martin Butlin generously
                supplied me with a photostat of this part of the auction catalogue.</note>	
                <note id="n72"><hi rend="s">61</hi> Dr. Read (not “Reid,” the spelling used by Butlin on
                p. 464, #635) is currently writing a book on R. H. Cromek. He has gained access to,
                and carefully studied, the paper of T. H. Cromek still in the possession of Cromek’s
                descendants. See Read, “A New Blake Engraving: Gilchrist and the Cromek Connection,”
                  <hi rend="i">Blake: An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (1980), 60-64.</note></p>
            <p>The correction of provenance is not merely a pedant’s fine-tuning. The inscribed date
              of 1806 might suggest that this drawing—like the similarly dated #613, a title page
              design showing a resurrection scene (British Museum)—was executed as part of an
              independent project. After he learned of Cromek’s perfidy by late 1805, Blake may have
              attempted to assemble a collection of <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> drawings as a way of
              rescuing something of his own from an otherwise thoroughly depressing situation.<ref
                target="n73" type="note">62</ref> But such speculations must be dismissed if Cromek
              commissioned and acquired the drawing. His son’s ownership of it in 1865 argues
              strongly that he did. We know that Cromek was exhibiting “the original Drawings” for
              the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> illustrations in Birmingham in July 1806.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74"
                type="note">63</ref> This drawing may have been prepared expressly as a title page
              for a portfolio of drawings Cromek carried about with him to advertise his forthcoming
              publication, although it seems a bit misleading to include a design not part of the
              group selected for engraving. <note id="n73"><hi rend="s">62</hi> This rationale is
                very tentatively proposed in Robert N. Essick and Morton D. Paley, 
                  <hi rend="i">Robert Blair’s The Grave Illustrated by William Blake</hi> (London: Scolar
Press,
                1982). See also comments on the #598-601 series, above.</note>
	<note id="n74"><hi
                  rend="s">63</hi><hi rend="i"> Birmingham Gazette</hi> and Birmingham 
                  <hi rend="i">Commercial Herald</hi>, 28 July 1806. See Geoffrey Keynes, “Blake in the
                Provinces,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 9 (1975), 41-42.</note></p>
            <p>#626, “Death of a Voluptuary” (untraced since 1863). Butlin traces this India ink
              drawing through the collections of Frederick Tatham and F. T. Palgrave, but loses its
              track after W. M. Rossetti’s 1863 
<pb id="p16-50" n="50"/>
description in Gilchrist’s
                <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>, II, 241: “Interesting as being a close parallel in
              design, but not in character, to that of ‘The Soul hovering over the Body,’ engraved
              in the ‘Grave’; not at all like the engraved ‘Death of the Strong Wicked Man.’ The
              dead voluptuary is crowned with vine-leaves; his soul, a female figure expressive of
              coarse passions, contemplates him with repulsion. Scratchy and rather ugly in
              execution.” The same, or a very similar, drawing was described by S. Foster Damon in
              1924: “Mr. Gabriel Wells [a New York dealer] owns a hansome ink sketch of the 
                <hi rend="i">Death of the Voluptuary</hi>, which was never engraved for this series
              [i.e., the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> illustrations]. The youth, naked and crowned with
              vines, lies on the ground; above him his Emanation hovers with uplifted hands. On the
              back of the sheet is a pencil-sketch, also marked ‘Blair’s Grave’: it represents Jesus
              intervening between Achilles and Agamemnon, before a crowd of warriors (Christian
              Forbearance quelling Pagan Pride).”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75"
type="note">64</ref> The
              intriguing verso sketch is not catalogued by Butlin. 
                  <note id="n75"><hi rend="s">64</hi> Damon, <hi rend="i">William Blake his Philosophy and
Symbols</hi>
                (London: Constable, 1924), p. 217 n. 4.</note></p>
            <p>#635, “Death Pursuing the Soul through the Avenues of Life” (Essick Collection). In
              his provenance information, Butlin states that “Harvey” had this drawing “by 1863.”
              Dennis Read, however, has discovered that T. H. Cromek still had it in his possession
              in May or June 1863 when he mentioned it in his manuscript “Recollections of
              Conversations with Mr. John Pye.” Read believes that Cromek did not dispose of the
              drawing until 1866 at the earliest. Butlin also proposes that “Death Pursuing” was in
              the George A. Smith sale at Christie’s, 16 July 1880, lot 119 (£1.15<hi rend="i">s.</hi> to
Dowdeswell). Lot 119 is described in the auction catalogue as a “Sketch
              in Indian ink—supposed to be a composition to represent the same sentiment as that in
              ‘The Grave,’ called, ‘The Soul visiting the Recesses of the Grave.’” “Death
Pursuing”
              is highly finished in sepia washes, not sketched in ink, and it seems odd to describe
              either the falling woman or Urizenic male pictured in it as a visiting soul. However,
              the auction catalogue description accords well with Rossetti’s description (Gilchrist,
                <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>, 1863, II, 241) of Butlin’s #630: “A young Man
              entering Death’s Door. . . . <hi rend="i">Indian ink.</hi> Probably a preparatory
              version of ‘The Soul exploring the Recesses of the Grave.’” I suspect that Smith
              acquired #630, not #635, at some time after 1870, when it was owned by A. H. Bright,
              and sold it in 1880. Alas, #630 is now untraced.</p>
            <p>#635 was exhibited in 1976 at California State University, Northridge, California—not
              “Northridge, New York.”</p>
            <p>#637, “An Allegory of Human Life” (untraced since 1863). Butlin groups this with the
                <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> illustrations, apparently because Rossetti (Gilchrist, 
                <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>, 1863, II, 251) suggests that “there is probably some
              relation between” this composition and #636, “The Gambols of the Ghosts.” However,
              Rossetti stars his entry for #637 to indicate considerable size, states that it is “a
              different composition, and to a considerable extent a different idea, from” #636, and
              goes on to describe it as containing “a great number of figures, highly finished,
              representing various aspects of the soul 
              <figure n="but636.1.1.wd" id="but636.1.wd.01" work-copy="gravewd" rend="db" width="692" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>Blake</figTranscr>
                <head>31 “The Gambols of the Ghosts.”</head>
                <figDesc>Pencil and wash, 46 × 31.6 cm., c. 1805 (?). Butlin #636. Yale Center for
                  British Art, New Haven.</figDesc>
              </figure> 
              and of life. The whole may be compared to a glorified Masonic broadsheet.”
              Perhaps #637 would fit more appropriately in Butlin’s section on the Last Judgment
              designs in company with #641, “The Fall of Man,” or in his section of late temperas
              along with #673, “An Allegory of the Spiritual Condition of Man.” Like both of these,
              #637 was originally sold to Butts.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XXI. The Last Judgment, 1806-1827</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>This brief section of five and a half pages includes some of Blake’s greatest
              compositions on a theme of immense importance to his thought and art from 
              <pb id="p16-51" n="51"/>
              <figure n="BUT624v.1.1.PD" rend="file" width="531" height="1000">
                <head>32 “The Ascension of the Beatified Soul.”</head>
                <figDesc>Pencil, 27.8 × 14.3 cm., dated by Butlin “c. 1807 (?)” but perhaps 1805.
                  Butlin #624 verso. Victoria and Albert Museum.</figDesc>
              </figure> 
              about 1805 to the end of his life. #643, “The Last Judgment,” a pencil
              sketch in the collection of George Churchill, London, is I believe reproduced for the
              first time. It is interesting to note that the great pen and pencil drawing of the
              Last Judgment in the National Gallery of Art (#645) is dated by Butlin c. 1809, and
              thus it and its preliminaries (#643, 644) follow rather than precede the finished
              water colors of 1806 (#639) and 1808 (#642). #645 may therefore by a direct
              preliminary for the lost tempera (#648) which, according to Rossetti, measured “seven
              feet by five feet” (Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>, 1880, II, 223).</p>
            <p>#646, “The Last Judgment—Tracing” (estate of Gregory Bateson, California). Butlin
              comments that this tracing is “not without life and possibly by Blake.” But a
              comparison with #645, on which it is based, shows a considerable difference in
              strength of line. I should think a fence sitting phrase like “possibly but not
              probably by Blake” would be more appropriate. This work cannot be traced with
              confidence prior to the 1880s.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XXII. Blake’s Exhibition, 1809</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>#653, “Sir Jeffery Chaucer and the Nine and Twenty Pilgrims on their Journey to
              Canterbury” (Pollok House, Glasgow). There should be a reference to Plate 587, a color
              reproduction of a detail from the tempera, as well as the reference to Plate 878.
              Butlin states that there is a handcolored impression of the engraving “ex David McC.
              McKell, sold Parke-Bernet 24 April 1945 (39).” This is a little misleading. This
              second state impression, partially and very lightly tinted with water colors, was sold
              from the collection of Frank J. Hogan at Parke-Bernet in the 1945 sale that Butlin
              records. It was acquired in the same year by McKell, from whom it passed to his son,
              Dr. David McKell. The print is now in the collection of a descendant of Dr. McKell’s
              in central California. The pencil inscription on it states that it was given to Tatham
              by Mrs. Blake, not “Mr. Blake” as Butlin writes. The other hand colored example, now
              in Keynes’ collection, is, like the McKell print, a second state impression.</p>
            <p>There are several different accounts of Cromek’s involvement in Blake’s work on the
              painting and engraving of Chaucer’s pilgrims. Butlin cites the version that Linnell
              wrote in a copy of J. T. Smith’s <hi rend="i">Nollekens and his Times</hi>, and states
              that Cromek “commissioned the painting from Blake.” Linnell’s actual words are,
              “Cromec [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] according to Blake employed or engaged him to finish
              the frescoes as he called it of the Canterbury Pilgrims. . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76"
                type="note">65</ref> The word “finish” in this statement is crucial. If Cromek
              “commissioned” the painting as Butlin states, then the idea for such a work may have
              been Cromek’s, as is claimed in the “Biographical Sketch of Robert Hartley Cromek” in
              the 1813 edition of Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi><ref target="n77" type="note">66</ref> His
hiring of Stothard to execute a similar Canterbury design would then
              be only the withdrawal of a commission from one artist and its bestowal on
              another—perhaps a tricky maneuver, but potentially defensible. Blake apparently
              claimed that Cromek stole the <hi rend="i">idea</hi> of a pilgrims panorama from him,
              not merely that he took a commission elsewhere. J. T. Smith says that Blake showed
              Cromek “the designs sketched out for a fresco picture” without prior prompting or
              commission, and Gilchrist states that Cromek saw “a pencil drawing” (perhaps #654?) of
              the pilgrims at Blake’s house.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78"
type="note">67</ref> The preponderance
              of the “evidence”—if one can bestow that term on these secondhand accounts—indicates
              that Blake conceived of the composition and Cromek commissioned, if he commissioned
              anything, the finishing of the design and/or its engraving. 
                  <note id="n76"><hi rend="s">65</hi> Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 464 n.
                1.</note>
	<note id="n77"><hi rend="s">66</hi> Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The
                  Grave</hi> (London: R. Ackermann, 1813), p. xlviii. This anonymous account
                probably reflects Cromek’s, or Mrs. Cromek’s, own defense of his
                actions.</note>
	<note id="n78"><hi rend="s">67</hi> Smith, <hi rend="i">Nollekens and
                  his Times</hi> (London: Henry Colburn, 1828), II, 467; Gilchrist, 
                  <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>, 1863, I, 203. Allan Cunningham’s account refers to
Blake’s
                claim that Cromek had “commissioned him to paint the Pilgrimage,” but Cunningham
                makes no statement relevant to the priority of conception. See Cunningham, 
                  <hi rend="i">The Lives of the Most Eminent British Painters, Sculptors, and
                  Architects</hi>, 2nd ed. (London: John Murray, 1830), II, 163.</note></p>
            <p>Butlin states that Schiavonetti’s engraving of Stothard’s “Pilgrimage to Canterbury”
              appeared “before Blake’s, in about November 1809.” This follows a comment made in that
              month (according to Bentley) by George Cumberland, Jr.: “have you seen the etching of
              Mr Stothards Pilgrims it is finished.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79"
type="note">68</ref> However,
              the plate was left unfinished when Schiavonetti died on 7 June 1810, and an unfinished
              etched proof at the Yale Center for British Art is dated in the imprint 1 August
              1810—only four months before the date on Blake’s plate. The plate of Stothard’s
              design, finished by Heath, was not published until 1 October 1817. George Cumberland,
              Jr. must have been referring only to 
<pb id="p16-52" n="52"/>
the preliminary etching
              of the plate, if his statement is at all accurate. The only direct evidence for the
              appearance of the print points to a date of August 1810, not Butlin’s “about November
              1809.” #654, “The Canterbury Pilgrims: Sketch for the Engraving” (Merlin Cunliffe,
              Armadale, Australia; illus. 33). Butlin states that this pencil drawing “is close to
              the engraving except that the group of figures on the extreme left is omitted and the
              background only barely indicated.” If this journal is up to its usual high standards
              in reproduction, a careful look at illus. 33 will show that the group on the extreme
              left is present and that the background, particularly the Tabard Inn, is more than
              just “barely indicated.” <note id="n79"><hi rend="s">68</hi> Bentley, 
                  <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 220.</note></p>
            <p>Gilchrist (<hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>, 1863, I, 225) tells an interesting story
              about a drawing of the Canterbury Pilgrims. He states that the “original design” for
              either the painting or the print “hung over a door in [Blake’s] sitting-room.” When
              taken down it was “nearly effaced,” which Blake believed to have been caused by “some
              malignant spell.” When told of this, Flaxman “mildly expostulated, ‘Why! my dear sir!
              as if, after having left a pencil drawing so long exposed to air and dust, you could
              have expected otherwise!’” This is one of Gilchrist’s mini-dramas that cannot be
              accepted without question, but he might be referring to #654, the only extant pencil
              drawing of the composition. His account explains the rubbed, faded, and somewhat
              tattered condition of this drawing. The seven spots in a row (not mentioned by Butlin)
              just below the top edge suggest that the drawing was either hung on these marks or
              stuck face down to the copperplate for direct transfer.</p>
            <p>#659, “The Goats, an Experiment Picture” (untraced since 1809). Butlin quotes Blake’s
              comment in his <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> that he took this unusual
              subject “from the Missionary Voyage.” Blake is very probably referring to James
              Wilson, <hi rend="i">A Missionary Voyage to the Southern Pacific Ocean</hi>, 1799,
              which contains, pp. 129-30, a scene very similar to Blake’s description of his
                painting.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80" type="note">69</ref>
	<note id="n80"><hi rend="s">69</hi>
                Pointed out in <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi>, ed. G. E. Bentley, Jr.
                (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1978), II, 855 n.</note></p>
            <figure n="BUT654.1.PD.BM" rend="file" width="958" height="355">
              <head>33 “The Canterbury Pilgrims: Sketch for the Engraving.”</head>
              <figDesc>Pencil, 35.4 × 95.8 cm., c. 1809-1810. Butlin #654. The Hon. Merlin Cunliffe,
                Armadale, Victoria, Australia. Photograph courtesy of the National Gallery of
                Victoria; reproduced with the owner’s permission.</figDesc>
            </figure>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XXIII. Tempera Paintings and Other Works, c. 1810-1825</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>#667, “Adam Naming the Beasts” (Pollock House, Glasgow; illus. 34). According to
              Hilary Macartney, Assistant Keeper, Glasgow Museums and Art Galleries, the painting is
              not “relined,” as Butlin describes it.</p>
            <p>#667-670, “Adam Naming the Beasts,” “Eve Naming the Birds,” “The Virgin and Child in
              Egypt,” and “Christ Blessing” (illus. 34-37). Several scholars have pointed out that
              these four temperas of c. 1810, all of similar size and format, are an interrelated
              group. They can bear a closer examination.</p>
            <p>The two males (illus. 34, 37), Old Adam and New, are clearly juxtaposed. The first is
              surrounded by images of the natural world, particularly the oak. Adam’s impending fall
              is foreshadowed by the bare trees in the background and by the serpent. Christ is
              framed by olive or laurel leaves<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81"
type="note">70</ref> emblemizing his
              triumph over the pyramid of death in the right background. Adam raises his right hand
              to point to the spiritual world above, and hence detached from, him; Christ raises his
              right hand to bless us in the spirit of prophecy he has made manifest in this world.
                <note id="n81"><hi rend="s">70</hi> I am unable to identify the foliage with any
                horticultural precision. Both olive and laurel would be appropriate as emblems of
                Christ’s victory or plenitude. The leaves and fruit are similar to those surrounding
                the portraits of Dante, Spenser, Dryden, and Cowper in the “Heads of the Poets”
                series (#343.4, 9, 12, 17). These are identified by Butlin as bay, olive, bay or
                laurel, and “lilies of the valley” respectively. The last is an error—see comments
                on #343.17, above. Bay is simply another name for laurel; the “olive” in #343.9
                looks very much like the bay or laurel in the other portraits.</note></p>
            <p>Similar parallels and contrasts link the female portraits (illus. 35, 36). Their hand
              gestures are not identical and the precise meanings of these gestures are not
              altogether clear, but both would seem to be presenting the other beings in each
              design. The bird above Eve’s right hand shows upward flight and may thereby symbolize
              transcendence. The Virgin’s child is the very image of incarnation. Christ will, as
              the palm to his right reminds us, overcome the sin and death of the natural world in
              which Eve is situated, a world that has now solidified into the Egyptian tyranny
              suggested by the landscape background in #669. The animals and birds of Adam and Eve
              have been replaced by the Sphinx above the Virgin’s left shoulder, a union of man and
              beast that satanically parodies Christ’s union of man and God.</p>
            <pb id="p16-53" n="53"/>
            <p>Each woman is also linked to her male companion. In the first pair, the natural
              female was created out of the male; in the second, the divine male was born of the
              female. As with the transcendence/incarnation pattern, the male/female relationships
              form a mirror-image structure—each homologous to, but the reverse of, the other. The
              portrayals of the Virgin and of Christ blessing are linked further through the
              date-bearing palm and pyramids in the first and the fruitful trees and single pyramid
              in the second.</p>
            <p>We can of course arrange these four paintings in the chronological sequence of the
              events portrayed (as Butlin does in his catalogue entries) to form a pictorial
              narrative. But the group is far more than a sequential series. The form of the whole
              is spatial as well as temporal and depends upon multiple interconnections among all
              members of the group to generate meanings. I remain skeptical about discovering
              similar patterns in the biblical water colors Blake executed for Butts. If there is
              such a program, however, its complexity must be enormous because the number of
              possible interconnections of the type found in this cluster (#667-70) rises
              exponentially with the number of images.</p>
            <p>Butlin does not question Rossetti’s titles, “Adam Naming the Beasts” and “Eve Naming
              the Birds.” In neither case is it certain that the act of naming is pictured. Butlin
              compares the former to the general frontispiece of Hayley’s 1802 
              <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (illus. 38) and implies that they have 
              the same subject. The compositions are clearly related, and Adam 
              gestures in the engraving with his left hand in a way almost 
              identical to Eve in #668. In both portrayals of Adam, he may only
              be sitting among the animals and not naming them, as has been 
              suggested for the <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> 
              frontispiece.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82" type="note">71</ref>
              <note id="n82"><hi rend="s">71</hi> See Nancy Smith’s entry in 
                <hi rend="i">William Blake in the Art of his Time</hi>, catalogue of an 
                exhibition at the University of California, Santa Barbara, 
                24 February-28 March 1976, pp. 27-28. The inscribed text
                from Cowper’s <hi rend="i">The Task</hi> makes no mention of naming the 
                animals; and Hayley, in a letter to John Johnson of 16 May 1802, calls 
                the plate “adam, . . . surrounded [by] animals” (Bentley, 
                <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 95).</note></p>
            <p>#674, “The Virgin and Child” or “Black Madonna.” In the catalogue text, the owner is
              given as “Mr. and Mrs. Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia,” but in the caption to Plate
              963 the work is located at the “Yale Center for British Art.” The painting has 
              <figure n="BUT667.1.1.PT" rend="file" width="830" height="1000">
                <head>34 “Adam Naming the Beasts.”</head>
                <figDesc>Pen and tempera on fine linen, 75 × 62.2 cm., 1810. Butlin #667. Glasgow
                  Museums and Art Galleries, Stirling Maxwell Collection, Pollok House.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <figure n="BUT668.1.1.PT" rend="file" width="838" height="1000">
                <head>35 “Eve Naming the Birds.”</head>
                <figDesc>Pen and tempera on linen, relined, 73 × 61.5 cm., c. 1810. Butlin #668.
                  Glasgow Museums and Art Galleries, Stirling Maxwell Collection, Pollok
                  House.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <figure n="BUT669.1.1.PT" rend="file" width="816" height="1000">
                <head>36 “The Virgin and Child in Egypt.”</head>
                <figDesc>Tempera, 76.2 × 63.5 cm., 1810. Butlin #669. Victoria and Albert
                  Museum.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <pb id="p16-54" n="54"/>
              <figure n="BUT670.1.1.PT" rend="file" width="828" height="1000">
                <head>37 “Christ Blessing.”</head>
                <figDesc>Tempera, 75 × 62 cm., c. 1810. Butlin #670. Fogg Art Museum, Harvard
                  University, bequest of Grenville L. Winthrop.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <figure n="bb466.2.1.com" id="bb466.2.comb.01" work-copy="bb466.2" rend="db" width="821" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>Their strength, or speed, or vigilance, were giv’n<lb/>
	In aid of our defects. In some are found<lb/>
	Such teachable and apprehensive parts,<lb/>
	That man’s attainments in his own concerns<lb/>
	Match’d with th’ expertness of the brutes in theirs<lb/>
	Are oft times vanquish’d and thrown far behind.<lb/>
	Cowpers Task<lb/>
	Book VI.<lb/>
	Blake d &amp; s<lb/>
	Publishd June 1. 1802 by W Blake Felpham</figTranscr>
                <head>38 Frontispiece (Adam among the beasts) to William Hayley, 
                    <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads</hi>, 1802.</head>
                <figDesc>Designed and executed by Blake. Etching/engraving, 15.9 × 13.1 cm. Essick
                  Collection.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <figure n="BUT678.16.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="422">
                <head>39 Drawings from bas reliefs, a sphinx, and Jupiter for Abraham Rees, 
                    <hi rend="i">The Cyclopaedia.</hi></head>
                <figDesc>Pencil, sheet 31.7 × 28.3 cm., c. 1807. Butlin #678. Collection of Albert
                  S. Roe.</figDesc>
              </figure> recently been exhibited at the Yale Center, which now has at least physical
              possession, if not legal ownership.</p>
            <p>Butlin presents good arguments for dating this rather damaged and apparently restored
              tempera somewhat earlier than the inscribed date of 1825. The general composition,
              torso of the child, and the Virgin’s hand gestures are very similar to #669, “The
              Virgin and Child in Egypt” (illus. 36) of 1810, and the impasto effects and dark
              tonality of the painting link it to works of c. 1809. Butlin writes that “the date
              ‘1825’ may, therefore, be either a mistaken restoration or a post-dating by Blake
              himself on a work of c. 1810-20.” We should all be used to Blake’s habit of apparent
              predating, in order to record the conception rather than execution of a work, but this
              would be the only example of postdating. Such a practice would open a most
              discomfiting can of worms. I trust that the inscribed date is the work of a mistaken
              restorer who, when he reinforced the gold on the inscription, changed Blake’s date
              (1815 perhaps, with a curved “1”?) to 1825.</p>
            <p>#678, “Drawings from Bas Reliefs, a Sphinx, and Another Figure, for Rees’s
              Cyclopaedia” (collection of Albert S. Roe; illus. 39). The three preparatory sketches
              on this sheet offer the chance for a little speculation about Blake’s work for Rees.
              The lower panel is a preliminary for the bas relief of Zethus, Antiope, and Amphion
              engraved by Blake lower left on “Plate IV” of “Basso Relievo,” plates volume II of
              Rees’s <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia</hi> (illus. 40). Lower right is a sketch for
              “Hercules and Apollo contending for the Tripod from the Villa Albani,” engraved on
              plate II of “Basso Relievo” signed “Bond sculp.” William Bond, who engraved after
              Reynolds and Westall and was a governor of the Society of Engravers founded in 1803,
              very probably executed this plate, perhaps in part after this or another drawing by
              Blake. We should—very tentatively—add plate II to the list of “Plates Engraved After
              Drawings by Blake.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83" type="note">72</ref>
In this case, as with the
              wood engraving of “The Giant Polypheme, from a Famous Picture by N. Poussin” in
              Thornton’s <hi rend="i">Pastorals of Virgil</hi> (1821), Blake did not “invent” the
              design but was only a middle-man between the original artist and the engraver. 
              <note id="n83"><hi rend="s">72</hi> I first suggested that Blake had “something to do with
                the execution of” plates I and II in a review of Bentley’s <hi rend="i">Blake
                  Books</hi> in <hi rend="i">Blake: An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 11 (Winter
                1977-1978), 194. Could William Bond the engraver have anything to do with Blake’s
                “William Bond” in the Pickering Manuscript of c. 1803?</note></p>
            <p>The images at the top of the drawing (illus. 39) correspond to “An Egyptian
              Hieroglyphical Sphinx” and “Jupiter with the thunder and trident, a Greek gem of the
              oldest style”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84" type="note">73</ref> 
              (Butlin’s “another figure” in his
              descriptive title) engraved on “Plate I” of “Basso Relievo” (illus. 41). This plate is
              unsigned, although there are lines and dots, lower right, that may be fragments of an
              engraver’s signature. As with “Plate II,” it is possible that part of the plate was
              based on a drawing by Blake. The full plate pictures Egyptian, Persian, and Greek
              artifacts, and Blake engraved works of all three types in his four signed plates of
              “Sculpture” in <hi rend="i">The Cyclopaedia.</hi> Some of these sculptures, like the
              Hindu basso relievo right center in illus. 41, are located in the British Museum.
                <note id="n84"><hi rend="s">73</hi> According to the description of the plate in 
                <hi rend="i">The Cyclopaedia</hi>, text volume III, end of the entry on “Basso
                Relievo” (no pagination). Blake engraved two antique gems for Hayley’s 1802 
                <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>, executed a plate on “Gem Engraving” in the “Miscellany”
                section of Rees’s <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia</hi>, and refers to antique gems
                approvingly in his annotations to Reynolds (c. 1808) and in his “Laocoön” separate
                plate (c. 1820).</note></p>
            <p>Could Blake have also engraved “Basso Relievo Plate I” (illus. 41)? The attribution
              of commercial, highly conventional, and unsigned copy plates is 
            <pb id="p16-55" n="55"/> 
              always an uncertain business. Yet, plate I contains one feature linking it to
              Blake’s basso relievo plate IV (illus. 40) found in no other engraver’s work in 
              <hi rend="i">The Cyclopaedia.</hi> Squiggle lines composed of stipple dots are used as
              background shading behind Zeus (center left) and on the steps beneath four Persians
              (bottom design) on plate I. These same types of lines appear on plate IV, most
              noticeably on the left side and base of the altar center left and on the top, left
              side, and base of the altar lower right. Blake also used this type of dotted line in
              all four of his “Sculpture” plates in <hi rend="i">The Cyclopaedia.</hi> This hardly
              provides evidence for a clear attribution, but it does contribute to the suspicion
              that Blake drew the images for, and perhaps even engraved, more plates for 
              <hi rend="i">The Cyclopaedia</hi> than the inscribed signatures indicate.</p>
            <p>I trust that the foregoing paragraphs sufficiently demonstrate my claim that Butlin’s
              monumental catalogue offers many opportunities for everyone to ride a favorite Blake
              hobbyhorse.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XXIV. Portrait Drawings, c. 1800-1825</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>#687, “James Barry” (Keynes Collection). Butlin follows Keynes in dating this crude,
              simple drawing to c. 1800. Might it not have been drawn many years earlier? Blake was
              very probably attracted to Barry as early as his apprentice years. The drawing bears
              no resemblance to the visionary heads filling the next section of the catalogue.</p>
            <p>#688, “John Linnell” (National Gallery of Art). In this entry, Butlin comments that
              “Linnell met Blake in 1818, seeking advice about engraving his drawing 
              <figure n="BB489.1.2.COM" rend="file" width="750" height="1000">
                <head>40 “Basso Relievo Plate IV” from Abraham Rees, <hi rend="i">The
                    Cyclopaedia</hi>, plates volume II, 1820.</head>
                <figDesc>Etching/engraving signed “Blake sc.” lower right; dated 11 November 1818 in
                  the imprint (trimmed off in the impression reproduced here). 24.3 × 18 cm.
                  Huntington Library.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <figure n="BassoRelievo.Plate1.16.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="474">
                <head>41 “Basso Relievo Plate I” from Abraham Rees, <hi rend="i">The
                    Cyclopaedia</hi>, plates volume II, 1820.</head>
                <figDesc>Etching/engraving, unsigned; dated 1 December 1807 in the imprint. 21.7 ×
                  14.4 cm. Huntington Library.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <pb id="p16-56" n="56"/>
              <corr type="emend" rend="plain">
              <figure n="BUT692-121-corrected-reversed.16.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="266">
                <head>42 John Varley, “Zodiacal Figures and Counting for Geomancy, with a Head [of
                  Blake?] Looking Down.”</head>
                <figDesc><corr type="emend">Page 121 from the <hi rend="i">Blake-Varley Sketchbook</hi>, c.
1819.
                  Pencil, sheet 15.5 × 20.5 cm. Butlin #692.121. Untraced since 1971.</corr></figDesc>
              </figure>
              </corr>
              <figure n="K24.1.1.RM" rend="file" width="784" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>Portrait of<lb/>
                Wm. Blake 1820.<lb/>
                <lb/>
                J. L. fecit</figTranscr>
                <head>43 John Linnell, Portrait of Blake.</head>
                <figDesc>Pencil, sheet 20.1 × 15.5 cm., inscribed 1820. Fitzwilliam Museum,
                  Cambridge.</figDesc>
              </figure> 
              of James Upton (see Essick, <hi rend="i">Printmaker</hi>, 1980, pp. 221-2).”
              Gilchrist (<hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>, 1863, I, 244) similarly states that
              Linnell asked Blake to “help him over engravings then in hand, from portraits of his
              own,” but there is nothing in either Butlin’s cited source or in the primary visual
              and verbal documents to support such a claim. According to Linnell’s journal entry of
              24 June 1818, he hired Blake to “begin the engraving” of the Upton 
              plate.<ref target="n85" type="note">74</ref> To employ a professional 
              engraver for the purpose of “Laying 
              in”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86" type="note">75</ref> 
              a portrait on the copper does not imply that the artist sought advice from 
              the journeyman. By 1818, Linnell was already a superb engraver, as 
              demonstrated by his 1813 portrait plate of the Baptist preacher John Martin. 
              Indeed, if any advice was given it was probably in the opposite direction. 
              Both Gilchrist and A. T. Story claim that Blake received efficacious advice
              from Linnell;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n87" type="note">76</ref> 
              the development of Blake’s intaglio engraving techniques after 1818 
              supports that claim. 
              <note id="n85"><hi rend="s">74</hi> Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 256.</note>
              <note id="n86"><hi rend="s">75</hi> The words are used by Blake in his receipt of 19
                September 1818 (see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 581).</note>
              <note id="n87"><hi rend="s">76</hi> Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>, 1863, I,
                285; Alfred T. Story, <hi rend="i">The Life of John Linnell</hi> (London: Richard
                Bentley, 1892), I, 224-25. Story, I, 158-59, denies Gilchrist’s claim that Linnell
                sought Blake’s advice on portrait engraving.</note></p>
            <p>#691, “Two Theatrical Portraits: Cooke and Kemble” (untraced since 1854). Butlin
              suggests that these may not have been by Blake. I suspect that they have something to
              do with the toy theatre prints that have sometimes been wrongly attributed to our
              Blake. One of these, signed “Blake fect.,” pictures “Mr. H. Kemble, as
              Massaniello.”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XXV. The “Visionary Heads,” c. 1819-1825</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>#692.121, “Varley: Zodiacal Figures and Counting for Geomancy, with a Head Looking
              Down,” from the 
                <figure n="Tracing.afterBlake.EgyptianTaskmaster.16.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="405">
                <head>44 Tracing or copy, perhaps by Adam White, after Blake’s “The Egyptian
                  Taskmaster.”</head>
                <figDesc>Pencil on thin paper, 10 × 7 cm., after 1854 (?). Essick
                  Collection.</figDesc>
              </figure>
<pb id="p16-57" n="57"/>
	<hi rend="i">Blake-Varley Sketchbook</hi> (untraced
              since 1971; illus. 42). Butlin comments that “certain of Varley’s Zodiacal and other
              drawings are drawn over an unfinished sketch of a head seen from above, quite high in
              quality but presumably by Varley also.” At least this one example is very probably a
              portrait of Blake, heretofore unidentified as such (illus. 42, just above the center
              of the sheet). The high forehead, arch of the eyebrow, and “snub nose”<ref
                target="n88" type="note">77</ref> are most characteristic. Varley may have made this
              quick but skillful sketch to capture Blake, with head bowed and eyes closed, in the
              midst of conjuring up one of the visionary heads. The portrait is similar—in point of
              view, closed eyes, and even knitted brow just above the eyes and nose—to Linnell’s
              well-known pencil drawing of Blake inscribed “1820” (illus. 43). Might Linnell’s
              sketch also record a visionary meditation? <note id="n88"><hi rend="s">77</hi> As
                Blake characterizes his nose in “The Everlasting Gospel” (c. 1818) in his 
                  <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>, p. 33.</note></p>
            <p>#696, “The Egyptian Taskmaster Killed by Moses, and Saul, King of Israel” (collection
              of George Howard). Butlin traces this sheet bearing two visionary heads through the
              collections of John Varley, Albert Varley, and Alfred Aspland, from whose collection
              it was sold in 1885. A tracing of the Taskmaster alone, probably made by John Varley,
              is listed as #696A. Butlin gives no provenance for the tracing until its acquisition,
              apparently in the 1830s or early 1840s, by William Hawkins. There is also a reduced
              copy of the Taskmaster, formerly owned by Ruthven Todd and now in my collection
              (illus. 44). This drawings, or at least the inscriptions, may be the work of Adam
              White, who owned several visionary heads or counterproofs of them. White inscribed
              #740, a counterproof of Wat Tyler, in a hand very like the “Taskmaster”
              inscriptions.</p>
            <p>Lower right on the “Taskmaster” (illus. 44) is written “Traced from an original of
              Blake’s belonging to M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Lowrie.” The drawing is about fifteen
              percent smaller than Butlin’s dimensions (approx. 12 × 9 cm.) for both Blake’s
              original and Varley’s tracing. Further, the original is located in the possession of
                “M<hi rend="s">r</hi> Lowrie”—probably Joseph Wilson Lowry, son of Wilson Lowry the
              engraver and John Varley’s brother-in-law, who also owned two visionary heads (#711,
              740) he gave to Adam White in 1854. The inscription lower left (illus. 44) follows the
              wording on Blake’s drawing not found on Varley’s tracing, a fact that supports Lowry’s
              ownership of the original. Thus it seems likely that after the original left Albert
              Varley’s collection and before it entered Aspland’s it passed through the hands of J.
              W. Lowry.</p>
            <p>#707, “Achilles” (untraced since 1942). Butlin quotes descriptions of this drawing
              written by Rossetti and Graham Robertson. Ruthven Todd has also described the drawing.
              He notes “a faint pencil circle, perhaps intended to represent a coin” lower right on
              the sheet.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n89" type="note">78</ref>
	<note id="n89"><hi rend="s">78</hi>
                Todd’s typescript catalogue of Robertson’s collection, p. 54 (see n. 3); repeated in
                Todd’s typescript catalogue of Blake’s drawings and paintings, p. 392 of the Library
                of Congress version.</note></p>
            <p>#722, “Canute, Replica (?)” (Huntington Library). Butlin’s provenance information
              stops with Parsons in March 1918. According to their records, Sessler’s acquired the
              drawing from Parsons in December 1922 for $33.17 and sold it to “Lentz” in the same
              month for $75.</p>
            <p>#729, “Richard Coeur de Lion” (Joseph Holland Collection). A few additional details
              on provenance from Sessler’s records: purchased for Moncure Biddle by Sessler’s in the
              1938 auction recorded by Butlin. Taken back by Sessler’s on consignment in February
              1957 at $250 and sold to Holland in March 1957.</p>
            <p>#748, “Old Parr When Young” (Huntington Library). Butlin’s provenance information
              lacks the acquisition of the drawing by Sessler’s (according to their records) in June
              1920 for $150 from Parsons. Sessler’s sold it to Huntington in September 1923 as part
              of a lot costing $2,500.</p>
            <p>#750, “The Ghost of a Flea” (Tate Gallery). The reference should be to Plate 966, not
              “960.”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XXVI. Late Drawings and Water Colors, c. 1820-1827</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>#769, “Twenty Drawings for Thornton’s Virgil” (dispersed). Butlin notes that #769.2,
              “Thenot and Colinet Converse Seated Beneath Two Trees,” was “recut (repr. 
              <hi rend="i">Athenaeum</hi> 21 January 1843, p. 165, and Keynes 1971, pl. 35) but Blake’s
              original engraving retained” in Thornton’s Virgil of 1821. This implication that the
              recut version printed (not “repr.”) in the <hi rend="i">Athenaeum</hi> was executed
              before the 1821 printing of Blake’s cuts follows Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of
                Blake</hi>, 1863, I, 274: “One of the designs engraved by Blake was re-cut among the
              engravers”—apparently meaning the engravers who made three other cuts after Blake,
              printed in 1821. The earliest record of the journeyman recut of #769.2 is its
              publication in the 1843 <hi rend="i">Athenaeum</hi>, where it is simply stated that
              “side by side [with Blake’s cut] we have printed a copy of an engraver’s improved
              version of the same subject.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n90"
type="note">79</ref> Thus it is likely
              that the recut was made specifically for the sake of the comparison made in the
              periodical. This possibility is increased by the fact that the recut is the reverse of
              Blake’s cut and the drawing for it, whereas the three journeymen cuts in the 1821
              Virgil are in the same direction as Blake’s drawings. There would have been no reason
              for these engravers to reverse just one cut; but a later copyist, working from Blake’s
              cut rather than the drawing, would have found it easier to copy the design directly on
              a wood block, thereby reversing it in impressions. At the very least, there is no
              evidence supporting Gilchrist’s story about an 1821 recut of #769.2. 
              <note id="n90"><hi rend="s">79</hi> Unsigned review by Henry Cole of an edition of Goldsmith’s
                  <hi rend="i">Vicar of Wakefield</hi>, illustrated by William Mulready, in 
                  <hi rend="i">The Athenaeum</hi>, no. 795 (21 January 1843), 65.</note></p>
            <p>#769.3, “Colinet and Thenot, with Shepherd’s Crooks, Leaning Against Trees.” This
              drawing for the Virgil wood engravings, listed by Butlin as untraced, was acquired in
              the fall of 1980 by Arthur E. Vershbow of Boston from Goodspeed’s Book Shop.</p>
            <p>#769.4, “Unused Design: Colinet and Thenot Stand Together Conversing, Their Sheep
              Behind” (Pierpont Morgan Library). In the caption to Plate 1001, the reference should
              be to this catalogue entry, not “767.4.”</p>
            <p>#774, “Moses Placed in the Ark of the Bulrushes” (Huntington Library). Butlin, in his
              provenance information, gives no owner between Robson in 1918 and Huntington.
              According to their records, 
            <pb id="p16-58" n="58"/>
            <figure n="BUT790.1.1r.PD" rend="file" width="852" height="1000">
                <head>45 “Two Figures Confront Each Other Over a Body.”</head>
                <figDesc>Pencil, sheet 18.7 × 15.9 cm., c. 1820-1825 (or earlier?). Butlin #790
                  recto. British Museum.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="BUT792.1.1.PD" rend="file" width="625" height="1000">
                <head>46 “The Three Tabernacles/The Lamb of God.”</head>
                <figDesc>Pencil, sheet 15.1 × 9.3 cm., c. 1820-1825. Butlin #792. Keynes
                  Collection.</figDesc>
            </figure> 
              Sessler’s acquired this water color from Robson in July 1920 for $726 and
              sold it, with twelve letters from Charles Lamb to S. T. Coleridge, to Huntington in
              November 1920 for $7,000.</p>
            <p>#785, “Timon” (Beinecke Library, Yale). Butlin, in his provenance information, lists
              this drawing in a Sotheby’s sale in 1893, followed by its acquisition by “Heath,”
              followed by its sale through Quaritch to Marsden J. Perry in “1890.” This last,
              contradictory date is apparently an error. The drawing was formerly bound, as Butlin
              notes, in copy Q of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> According to John Sampson,
              Perry purchased this volume “in 1900 from Quaritch.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n91" type="note">80</ref> If this is correct, and if Butlin is correct in placing #785 in an 1893
              auction already bound in the book, then Perry did not acquire the drawing until 1900.
                <note id="n91"><hi rend="s">80</hi><hi rend="i"> The Poetical Works of William
                  Blake</hi>, ed. Sampson (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1905), p. 73. Bentley, 
                  <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 410, cites Sampson for this part of the book’s
                history.</note></p>
            <figure n="BUT793.1.1.PD" rend="file" width="617" height="1000">
              <head>47 “The Church Yard.”</head>
              <figDesc>Pencil, sheet 15 × 9.2 cm., c. 1820-1825. Butlin #793 recto. Keynes
                Collection.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p16-59" n="59"/>
            <p>#790 recto, “Two Figures Confront Each Other Over a Body” (British Museum). Butlin
              reports various speculations about the subject of this sketch 
              (<corr type="emend">illus.</corr> 45) but he does not note its association 
              with the design beneath the text on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 
              plate 69. In this relief etching, two women dance before a bound
              male. One woman holds a knife and both have objects tied to their forearms and ankles.
              These decorations have been identified by Erdman as scalps and flayed hands.<ref
                target="n92" type="note">81</ref> This pencil sketch seems to represent a similar
              orgy of sacrifice involving two women and a fallen, tortured, or slain male. The
              central figure holds a knife and has her limbs decorated exactly as in the 
                <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> design. On this same woman’s breast, and perhaps hanging
              from her neck, is an object that looks rather like the flayed face held by the woman
              on the left in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plate 69. These clear associations with
              <figure n="BUT794.1.1.PD" rend="file" width="621" height="1000">
                <head>48 “Death.”</head>
                <figDesc>Pencil, sheet 15.1 × 9.3 cm., c. 1820-1825. Butlin #794. Keynes
                  Collection.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <figure n="BUT795.1.1.PD" rend="file" width="619" height="1000">
                <head>49 “Mirth.”</head>
                <figDesc>Pencil, sheet 15.2 × 9.3 cm., c. 1820-1825. Butlin #795. Keynes
                  Collection.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <figure n="BUT796.1.1.PD" rend="file" width="621" height="1000">
                <head>50 “Hope.”</head>
                <figDesc>Pencil, sheet 15.1 × 9.3 cm., c. 1820-1825. Butlin #796. Keynes
                  Collection.</figDesc>
              </figure>
              <pb id="p16-60" n="60"/> 
              the illuminated book suggest a date somewhat earlier
              than Butlin’s “<hi rend="i">c.</hi> 1820-5(?)” and contemporary with other drawings
              for <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> that he groups together in section XVIII, dated c.
              1804-1820. On the verso of #790 is a slight sketch of a naked and apparently airborne
              man basically similar to the figure right of the first eight lines of text on plate 19
              of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and close to a mirror image of the figure in the upper
              right margin of plate 83. <note id="n92"><hi rend="s">81</hi><hi rend="i"> The
                  Illuminated Blake</hi>, annotated by David V. Erdman (Garden City, New York:
                Anchor Press/Doubleday, 1974), p. 348.</note></p>
            <p>#792-796, a group of five compositions inscribed “The Three Tabernacles/The Lamb of
              God,” “The Church Yard,” “Death,” “Mirth,” and “Hope” (all Keynes Collection;
              reproduced here, illus. 46-50). W. Graham Robertson, who once owned these five
              sketches, was the first to suggest that “they seem to form a series.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n93"
                type="note">82</ref> All are on the same size paper and bear title inscriptions in
              similar calligraphy. Another member of the group may be #797, inscribed “Affection
              &amp; Love” (Beinecke Library, Yale University). The sheet bearing this pencil sketch
              is about 3.7 cm. shorter than the others, but the design and inscription are
              compatible with them. <note id="n93"><hi rend="s">82</hi> Volume II, p. 152, of
                Robertson’s manuscript catalogue of his collection. See <hi rend="i">The Blake
                  Collection of Robertson</hi>, ed. Preston, p. 217.</note></p>
            <p>This group has yet to receive any interpretive analysis. It constitutes an
              interesting attempt to compose an emblematic series rather like the <hi rend="i">Gates
                of Paradise</hi> of 1793. It also shows, at least in the “Church Yard” composition
              and use of airborne figures, the influence of Blake’s work on the 
                <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> illustrations out of which he also developed a group of drawings
              described earlier, #598-601. “Mirth” recalls Blake’s portrayal of the personification
              of Mirth in Milton’s <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi>, drawn and subsequently engraved c.
              1816-1820. Perhaps Blake began these preliminary sketches for a new series of emblems
              but abandoned them in favor of revising his 1793 <hi rend="i">Gates</hi> into 
                <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi>, usually dated c. 1818 but
              perhaps begun a few years later. Like that revised series of etching/engravings, this
              group of drawings recognizes the truths of this life (“Death”), but it also gives us
              hope for salvation and transcendence through both Christ (“The Lamb of God”) and good
              works (“Affection &amp; Love”).</p>
            <p>#796, “Hope” (Keynes Collection; illus. 50). The reference should be to Plate 1042,
              not “1041.”</p>
            <p>#797, “Affection and Love” (Beinecke Library, Yale University). The reference should
              be to Plate 1041, not “1042.”</p>
            <p>#798, “The Crucifixion” (Tate Gallery). Butlin notes the “nervous line” in this
              pencil sketch of c. 1825-1827. Do we see here the effects of Blake’s growing illness
              and the “shivering fit[s]”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n94"
type="note">83</ref> it caused? We also
              see evidence of an unsteady hand in #800 (“‘Return Alpheus’ from Milton’s
‘Lycidas’”),
              #801 (“Lady Torrens and Family, after John Linnell”), and #827 (the <hi rend="i">Book
                of Enoch</hi> illustrations). <note id="n94"><hi rend="s">83</hi> See Blake’s
                letters to Linnell of 1825, 31 March 1826, and 19 May 1826 (<hi rend="i">Letters of
                  Blake</hi>, ed. Keynes, pp. 156, 159-60).</note></p>
            <p>#802A, “A Vision of Hercules, Drawing in a Sketchbook” (untraced since 1920). In the
              1920 auction catalogue in which this sketchbook appeared, it is stated that the
              sketchbook also contained an extract from Cennino Cennini’s <hi rend="i">Treatise on
                Painting</hi> in Blake’s hand. This offers additional evidence for Blake’s ownership
              of, or at least familiarity with, Cennini’s book. Butlin suggests that #802A may have
              originally been part of the same notebook as #802, “Drawings from a Sketchbook”
              (Keynes Collection). These include two studies for George Richmond’s “Abel” which, as
              Anne Gilchrist noted, was executed as a “<hi rend="i">gesso</hi> water colour, worked
              in Blake’s favourite ‘fresco’ medium.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n95" type="note">84</ref> Blake
              took a particular interest in Cennini’s formulae for a glue-based medium;<ref
                target="n96" type="note">85</ref> he may have both quoted the appropriate section on
              this “fresco” medium (as he called his own glue-based paint) and “made a careful
                correction-drawing”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n97"
type="note">86</ref> of Richmond’s picture in
              the same sketchbook. Both were, in effect, directions to the young artist. 
                <note id="n95"><hi rend="s">84</hi><hi rend="i"> Anne Gilchrist her Life and
                Writings</hi>, ed. Herbert Harlakenden Gilchrist (London: T. Fisher Unwin, 1887), p.
                261.</note>
	<note id="n96"><hi rend="s">85</hi> See Linnell’s letter to Anne
                Gilchrist of 10 December 1862 (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 684) and
                W. M. Rossetti in Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>, 1863, I, 369.
                Cennini’s formulae are briefly described by Bo Ossian Lindberg, <hi rend="i">Blake:
                  An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 14 (Winter 1980-81), 173 n. 41.</note>	
                <note id="n97"><hi rend="s">86</hi><hi rend="i"> Anne Gilchrist her Life and
                Writings</hi>, p. 261.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XXVII. Late Paintings in Tempera, c. 1821-1826</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>This group of nine final tempera (or, more accurately, “distemper”) paintings
              demonstrates Blake’s mastery of a most delicate and intractable medium. He learned to
              apply the (altered?) medium less thickly, and perhaps with better preparation of the
              canvas, than in his earlier examples. Perhaps Blake’s reading of Guiseppe Tambroni’s
              1821 edition of Cennini’s <hi rend="i">Trattato della Pittura</hi> (see note 85)
              caused him to alter his practice slightly. Whatever the exact cause, the late temperas
              have survived in far better condition than the earlier attempts. They are also lighter
              in tone, as though Blake had slowly exorcised the Venetian and Flemish demons of
              darkness and decay infecting his painting techniques. Given his insistence on the
              unity of conception and execution, he must have felt that these technical spectres
              were also disrupting his thoughts. When considered from this perspective, we can see
              that Blake’s ideas about Rubens, Rembrandt, and Correggio were not only critical
              statements on historical personages but also personifications of his own difficulties
              as an artist. #805 and 806, “Count Ugolino and His Sons in Prison” and “The Body of
              Abel Found by Adam and Eve,” show the same stipple-like brushstrokes characterizing
              Blake’s portrait miniatures and some of his most beautiful water colors. By combining
              his experiences in several media, Blake finally learned how to exploit the intrinsic
              properties of an opaque, glue-based medium rather than being an unconscious slave to
              the impasto techniques of oil painting.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XXVIII. Illustrations to Dante’s <hi rend="i">Divine Comedy</hi>,
                  1824-1827</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Butlin carefully records the cryptic series of numbers on the versos of the Dante
              designs, also appearing on one of the Enoch drawings (#827.3). He also describes, and
              in the more important cases reproduces, some sketches for the Dante designs not
              previously noticed. Twenty-three such sketches appear on the versos of the large
              drawings.</p>
            <p>In his letter of 25 April 1827 to Linnell, Blake mentioned that, “as to Ugolino,
                &amp;<hi rend="s">c</hi>, I never supposed that I should sell them; my Wife alone is
              answerable for their having Existed in any finish’d State.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n98"
                type="note">87</ref> Just what was Mrs. Blake’s direct or 
<pb id="p16-61" n="61"/>
              indirect contribution to the Ugolino tempera (#805) or to the Dante water colors?
                <note id="n98"><hi rend="s">87</hi><hi rend="i"> Letters of Blake</hi>, ed. Keynes,
                p. 170.</note></p>
            <p>#812.18 verso, “Sketch for ‘The Six-Footed Serpent Attacking Agnolo Brunelleschi’”
              (Fogg Art Museum, Harvard). The plate reference is to 1055, but in fact this verso
              sketch is not reproduced. Plate 1055 pictures #812.51 verso.</p>
            <p>#812.39 verso, “Slight Sketch for ‘Cacus’” (National Gallery of Victoria, Melbourne).
              The reference should be to Plate 1054, not “1053.”</p>
            <p>812.43 verso, “Sketch of Rocks” (Fogg Art Museum, Harvard). The reference should be
              to Plate 1053, not “1054.”</p>
            <p>#814 recto and verso, “Sketch for ‘Minos’” and “Copy of Michelangelo’s
‘Adam’”
              (George Hooper Collection). Neither of the sketches looks like Blake’s work,
              particularly because of their soft chalk lines and shading. The recto follows #812.9,
              “Minos” among the Dante illustrations, very closely. Perhaps Linnell, who made a
              number of copies of Blake’s designs, or a member of his family copied Blake’s drawing.
              Linnell of course owned the Dante illustrations and #814 probably came from his
              collection. The careful copy of Michelangelo’s Adam on the verso may relate to
              Linnell’s graphic reproductions of the Sistine frescoes. He engraved facsimiles of six
              old engravings of single figures by Michelangelo in 1828 and reproduced the full
              “Creation of Adam” panel as a mezzotint dated February 1833. I doubt both Butlin’s
              attribution of these recto-verso drawings to Blake and his comment that the head of
              Adam “in the copy bears a remarkable likeness to Blake himself.”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XXIX. Last Works: Illustrations to the Book of Enoch, Genesis and 
                    <hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>, c. 1824-1827</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>All the works gathered in this section were very probably left unfinished at Blake’s
              death. The Bunyan illustrations have some water colors added by another hand; Butlin’s
              descriptions of these additions and their attribution to someone other than Blake
              (Mrs. Blake? Tatham?) are completely convincing even when checked against color
              reproductions that tend to mask differences in brush work and textures. Anyone
              interpreting the Bunyan series must surely take into account their joint
              authorship.</p>
            <p>Even if one discounts the poor coloring on some of the <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s
                Progress</hi> designs, they still show a considerable falling off in quality when
              compared to other late works, particularly the Job plates and the Dante water colors.
              For example, #829.6, “Christian Drawn Out of the Slough by Help,” is a complete botch.
              The attempt at perspective in the background road is pathetic and the figure of
              Christian is completely unconvincing. A few designs, however, show Blake still in
              command of his art.</p>
            <p>#829.20, “Christian with the Shield of Faith, Taking Leave of His Companions,” was
              detached from the group early on and escaped the attentions of the blundering
              colorist. It shows what Blake may have wanted for the whole series, although it is
              hard to see how some of the designs could ever be improved sufficiently. We may still
              appreciate these water colors as a pictorial commentary on Bunyan’s text, but in
              purely pictorial terms they are Blake’s least successful illustrative series.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XXX. Miscellaneous Untraced Works</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>This group of forty-nine items, plus the untraced but at least tentatively datable
              works listed throughout the catalogue, form a daunting collection of losses and
              mysteries. A particularly intriguing item is #846, described by Palmer in 1855 as “a
              finished picture from the <hi rend="i">Metamorphoses</hi>, after Giulio Romano.” As
              Butlin notes, this might be #803, “The Sea of Time and Space” (National Trust,
              Arlington Court). But I can find nothing in Ovid that #803 could illustrate.</p>
            <p>#849, “Egypt” (untraced since 1863). Described by Rossetti (Gilchrist, 
                <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>, 1863, II, 252) as “a naked, standing male figure.” Might
this
              work have some connection with Blake’s engraving after Fuseli, “Fertilization of
              Egypt,” published in Erasmus Darwin’s <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi> in 1791?
              Blake’s finished wash drawing of the design (#173) is not otherwise listed by
              Rossetti. His description of #849 generally fits this back view of Anubis straddling
              the Nile.</p>
            <p>#868, “A Nude Woman” (untraced since 1910). Butlin traces this drawing to the
              collection of Thomas Butts. When sold at Sotheby’s, 22 March 1910, the drawing was
              described as “a small water-colour” and grouped in lot 447 with impressions of plates
              engraved by Butts, father and son. I suspect that this drawing is also by Butts. It
              may be either the “Venus Anadyomene” wash drawing on a sheet 11.5 × 7.6 cm. now at
              McGill University, Montreal; or the untraced variant of the same figure reproduced in
                <hi rend="i">The Connoisseur</hi>, 19 (September-December, 1907), 96. The latter has
              been described by Bentley as an engraving,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n99"
type="note">88</ref> but
              its inscription (“Venus Anadyomene Inv. et pinx T Butts 1807”) and the quality of line
              and shading visible in the reproduction suggest that it is another water color
              drawing. <note id="n99"><hi rend="s">88</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi>, p. 176.
                The McGill Drawing has been attributed to Butts, with the assumption that it is a
                preliminary for the “engraving” described by Bentley, in Christopher Heppner, “Notes
                on Some Items in the Blake Collection at McGill with a Few Speculations Around
                William Roscoe,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 10 (1977), 101.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XXXI. Drawings Attributed to Robert Blake, 1767-1787</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>R1, “Robert Blake’s Sketchbook” (Huntington Library). Butlin cites Bindman’s
              justifiable doubts about Robert’s authorship of these sketches, much less William’s
              (as has sometimes been claimed). Among Robert’s other drawings, only the heads on R11
              verso, “Academy Studies of Profile and Part-Profile Heads” (British Museum) look
              anything like the work in this sketchbook.</p>
            <p>R4, “A Druid Grove” (Keynes Collection). The plate reference should be to 176, not
              “179.”</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p16-62" n="62"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">XXXII. Works Attributed to Catherine Blake, 1762-1831</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The first two entries in this section, “Agnes” and “Head ‘Taken from Something She
              Saw in the Fire,’” show a Blake-like talent for haunting images. The originals, both
              in Keynes’ collection, are far more impressive than any reproductions yet
              published.</p>
            <p>In his Introduction, p. xii, Butlin expresses the hope that future discoveries of
              drawings and paintings by Blake will “be published <hi rend="i">Blake: An Illustrated
                Quarterly</hi>; long may it thrive!” Let me offer a final celebration of Butlin’s
              masterful catalogue by accepting that open invitation.</p>
            <p>A second-state impression of Blake’s white-line metal cut, “The Man Sweeping the
              Interpreter’s Parlour,” on a sheet of unwatermarked wove paper 12.2 × 19 cm., was sold
              anonymously at Christie’s, 3 December 1980, lot 161. This print, now in my collection,
              bears on its verso a pencil sketch of a standing figure (illus. 51), no doubt executed
              by Blake. The paper is trimmed into the figure at the top, suggesting that the drawing
              was made when the 
              sheet was somewhat larger. Martin Butlin has suggested in correspondence
              that the style dates the drawing to the 1790s. The modeling on the body is similar to
              figures in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> manuscript, particularly the giant nude on
              page 66. If this dating is correct, then the drawing was executed before the print was
              pulled because the second state of “The Man Sweeping” was almost certainly executed in
              the 1820s. The subject may be Samson pulling down the pillars of the temple (Judges
              16:25-30). Note the slit-like eyes, perhaps indicating Samson’s blindness, and the
              disappearance of his arms behind what I take to be breaking pillars. The same subject
              is pictured in Blake’s final <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> water color. Although
              Samson’s posture is very different, the columns break in the middle much as they do in
              this rough little sketch.</p>
            <p>Martin Butlin—long may he thrive!</p>
              <figure n="BUTWBA6.1.1.PD" rend="file" width="958" height="784">
                <head>51 Standing figure, perhaps Samson pulling down the pillars of the
                  temple.</head>
                <figDesc>Pencil, sheet 12.2 × 19 cm., c. 1796 (?). Essick Collection.</figDesc>
              </figure> 
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p16-63-65" n="63-65" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
