<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.1.johnson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Observations on Blake’s Paintings and Drawings (Based on Butlin’s Catalogue
Raisonné)</title>
        <author n="Johnson">Mary Lynn Johnson</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Wayne Erickson</name>
              <name>George Hartley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
      <pb id="p16-4" n="4"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-1-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">OBSERVATIONS ON BLAKE’S PAINTINGS AND DRAWINGS (BASED ON BUTLIN’S CATALOGUE
RAISONNÉ)</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">MARY LYNN</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">JOHNSON</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>Martin Butlin’s two-volume plates-and-catalogue set, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of
William Blake</hi> (1981), provides what hundreds of research trips cannot offer, the opportunity to compare
works by Blake in widely scattered collections, executed in different media, during different periods. Since I
have been in correspondence with Butlin about some of the interpretations of Blake’s pictures that his book
has suggested to me and have received his acquiescence on most points, I would like to summarize my proposals
for the scrutiny of the Blake community, assuming that others who are eagerly studying our new resource are
also making discoveries that ought to be shared now rather than held for fuller development in specialized
articles. For the sake of simplicity, I shall present my proposed identifications of subjects, notations of
recurrent motifs, and observations of analogues in the order of Butlin’s catalogue numbers (followed in
parentheses by his plate numbers) in <hi rend="i">Paintings and Drawings.</hi></p>
        <p>cat. 86r (pl. 92) <hi rend="i">An Old Man Appearing on a Cloud to a Young Nude Couple.</hi> The
nude couple—minus the old man in the cloud—appears on plate 5 of <hi rend="i">All Religions Are
One</hi>;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> the connection between this
plate and the preliminary sketch on cat. 85v was observed in John E. Grant, “Addenda and Some Solutions to
Tolley’s Blake Puzzles,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 3 (1971), 135. The reclining male nude is also
anticipated in three sketches on cat. 81 (also pl. 81), though his position is reversed and his legs are more
nearly horizontal. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Reproduced in David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">The
Illuminated Blake</hi> (Garden City, N. Y.: Doubleday/Anchor, 1974), p. 25.</note></p>
        <p>cat. 110 (pl. 113) <hi rend="i">Lot and the Angels</hi> (?). The two prominent vessels on the table
and the exotic design of the low chairs suggest that this couple is Philemon and Baucis, elderly Phrygians who
shared their meager provisions with the disguised gods Hermes and Zeus, for which they were rewarded by the
perpetual replenishment of their cruse of oil (or in some versions their jug of wine). Admittedly, the female
appearance of their solitary guest argues against this interpretation.</p>
        <p>cat. 115r (pl. 125) <hi rend="i">Moses Staying the Plague</hi> (?). This appears to illustrate
Ezekiel’s prophetic act in the Valley of Dry Bones, at the moment when the bones become flesh: “So I
prophesied as he commanded me, and the breath came into them, and they lived, and stood up upon their feet, an
exceeding great army” (Ezekiel 37:10). The prophet’s commanding cruciform gesture and the unblemished
bodies of the men (some of whom arise out of the dry earth) fit the text in Ezekiel better than that of
Numbers 16:46-50, in which Aaron is supposed to be burning incense and standing between the dead and the
living (a congregation of men, women, and children—not men only as in this drawing). Butlin points out that
the dimensions of <hi rend="i">Moses Staying the Plague</hi> (?) are close to those of the work by this name
exhibited in 1876 by the Burlington Fine Arts Club; perhaps the work was mistitled even then. David
Bindman’s title, <hi rend="i">The Second Vision of Ezekiel</hi>, in <hi rend="i">Blake as An Artist</hi>
(Oxford; Phaidon, 1977), p. 17, seems right except for number: first, the Wheels (1-2); second, the
Abominations, the Man
<pb id="p16-5" n="5"/>
with the Inkhorn, and again the Wheels (8-11); third, the Dry Bones (37); and finally, the Temple (40-44,
47).</p>
        <p>cat. 147 (pl. 161) <hi rend="i">A Young Woman Reclining on a Couch, Writing in a Book.</hi></p>
        <p>cat. 148r (pl. 162) <hi rend="i">Group of Men Seated in a Circle.</hi> Although these pictures are
not clearly related in provenance, size, and media, the subjects reappear together in some small pencil
designs, enclosed in frames as if for a page layout, on cat. 212r (pl. 244) and, upside down, on cat. 212v
(pl. 245) and cat. 213v (pl. 246). The woman, reclining and writing (or reading), appears underneath a group
of standing men in cat. 212r and 212v; in 213v the men are seated, and the indistinct figure underneath is
also seated, reading or writing. Perhaps the woman is writing a visionary interpretation of a historical event
the men are planning. cat. 147 is in “Pen and grey wash over pencil,” cat. 148 in a compatible “Pen and
indian ink over pencil.” The unevenness of the top right edge of cat. 147 indicates that this sheet has been
damaged; even now, the drawings are close in size and may originally have been still closer. Their provenances
are not mutually exclusive or incompatible; as there is no record of cat. 148 until 1876, it may also have
been in the Tatham collection.</p>
        <p>cat. 154v (pl. 168) <hi rend="i">A Warrior in Armour Kneeling before a Bearded Elder.</hi> In
composition this sketch anticipates cat. 459 (pl. 540), <hi rend="i">David Pardoning Absalom</hi> (cat. 459,
pl. 540), one of the biblical watercolors executed for Butts in the 1800-05 series. Though Butlin dates the
sketch c. 1780, the interval of more than twenty years would not necessarily have deterred Blake from
returning in a wholly new style, even with a different subject, to a composition he liked. The interval
between the newly recognized Blake pen drawing, <hi rend="i">Goliath Cursing David</hi> (cat. 119A-r, pl.
133), c. 1780-85, and the watercolor version of the same subject in the biblical series for Butts (cat. 457,
pl. 525), c. 1803-05, is equally long—though, as we shall see, the later Goliath reveals a remarkable
development in Blake’s iconography of giantism.</p>
        <p>cat. 220 (pl. 251) <hi rend="i">Two Figures in a Decorative Border.</hi> The central figure may
well be Psyche, lifting her lamp or torch to observe the sleeping Cupid. The horse-like “tail” area that
gave rise to Butlin’s speculation that she may be a female centaur is actually the bowed head, knee, and
upper arm of a different, larger-scale (and probably unrelated), mourning female, in profile facing right. She
resembles the chief female mourner in <hi rend="i">The Death of Ezekiel’s Wife</hi> (cat. 166, pl. 203) and
the rightmost figure in <hi rend="i">The Mourners</hi> (cat. 153, pl. 169).</p>
        <p>The “Psyche” composition resembles the central fan design of cat. 223Av (pl. 256).</p>
        <p>cat. 222 (pl. 252) “<hi rend="i">Is All Joy Forbidden.</hi>”</p>
        <p>cat. 224 (pl. 257) <hi rend="i">Los, Orc, and Enitharmon</hi> (?).</p>
        <p>cat. 238 (pl. 276) <hi rend="i">A Woman Standing Before Two Massive Seated Figures.</hi> These
three sketches are similar in style, dimensions, paper stock, and theme. All imply conflicts between parents
and their adolescent children. In all three a book is shown, apparently as a source for or reinforcement of
the parent’s blighting authority. The tiny flying mother and child at the upper left of “<hi rend="i">Is
All Joy Forbidden,”</hi> perhaps depicting in contrast the nurturing of joy, appear in reverse on the
half-title of <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> (<hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi>, p. 35). In 
<hi rend="i">Los, Orc, and Enitharmon</hi> (?), the pose of the adolescent son, his curly hair identifying him as
an Orc figure, resembles—though from a back view—that of the curly-haired woman also tied by her wrists in
one of Blake’s engravings for Stedman’s <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi>, “Flagellation of a Female Samboe
Slave.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> On the basis of this
analogy, it is probable that the object in the hand of the father figure is a thonged whip rather than
compasses. The third sketch recapitulates the tensions of “A Little Girl Lost” of <hi rend="i">Songs of
Experience</hi>: the position of the Ona figure’s hands suggests that she has been caught in a sexual
indiscretion; the buried face of the father figure and the open book beside him are also strongly reminiscent
of the father’s response in “A Little Girl Lost.” In all three sketches the denial or repression of the
vital force in the maturing children causes the suffering of both parents and children; in all three the
mother, if present at all, is only a passive witness or mourner; in all three a nude adolescent is in conflict
with a gowned parent. <note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Captn. J. G. Stedman, <hi rend="i">A Narrative of a
Five Years’ Expedition, Against the Revolted Negroes of Surinam</hi> . . . (London: J. Johnson &amp; J.
Edwards, 1796), I, opposite 326; rpt. Barre, Mass.: Imprint Society, 1971, I, opposite 181.</note></p>
        <p>cat. 231v (pl. 266) <hi rend="i">Esther Appealing to King Ahasuerus against Haman.</hi> When in
conversation with Sir Geoffrey Keynes I suggested this subject for the sketch, I could not see the lines of
“Haman’s” broad-brimmed hat, sharply visible in the photographic reproduction. Now, noting the
resemblance in composition between this sketch and that of an earlier drawing, <hi rend="i">The Keys of
Calais</hi> (cat. 64, pl. 56), I suspect that “Haman” is a later version of a burgher of Calais pointing
to his benefactress, Queen Philippa. There may be a clue in the hairstyle of the queen: three or four separate
braids or curls hanging down her back, down to her waist, is perhaps more suggestive of medieval Europe than
of biblical Persia.</p>
        <p>cat. 239v (pl.280) <hi rend="i">Sketch for a Border.</hi> Judging from the two flowerlike spirits
at the bottom, this may be a draft for the title page of <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel.</hi></p>
        <p>cat. 251 (pl. 301) <hi rend="i">An Incantation.</hi> Despite the 
<corr type="emend">Anubis-like</corr> appearance of the head, this appears to be a prototype of <hi rend="i">Noah
and the Rainbow</hi> (cat. 437, pl. 514). The wavy lines of the arch in the pencil sketch are pehaps related
to pentimenti in the Noah watercolor which suggest cherubs’ faces and wings like those in the rainbows over
the deathbeds of Joseph and Mary (cats. 511-12, pls. 610-11). The curved supports for the altar in cat. 251,
however, resemble those in <hi rend="i">The Sacrifice of Jephthah’s Daughter</hi> (cat. 452, pl. 522), and
the same general composition is used in <hi rend="i">Job’s Sacrifice</hi> (cat. 551-18, pl. 750) and its
preliminary sketch (cat. 557-41, pl. 778).</p>
        <p>cat. 392 (pl. 499) <hi rend="i">The Judgement of Solomon.</hi> The symmetrical placement of angelic
wings behind Solomon probably alludes to the Mercy Seat (Exodus 24: 17-30; Hebrews 9:5), also underlying 
<hi rend="i">Christ in the Sepulchre, Guarded by Angels</hi> (cat. 500, pl. 603), as its inscription indicates.
(It was Darrell Figgis
<pb id="p16-6" n="6"/>
who first observed that this picture in turn is related to the Beulah-vision of angelic guardianship of Albion
in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Night VIII.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3"
type="note">3</ref>) This positive allusion suggests that the apparent risk of human sacrifice in Solomon’s
pronouncement is in reality an occasion for forgiveness. <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> See 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, 99: 7-10, <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V.
Erdman (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1965), p. 357, and Darrell Figgis, <hi rend="i">The Paintings of William
Blake</hi> (London: Ernest Benn, [1925]), p. 66.</note></p>
        <p>cat. 436 (pl. 513) <hi rend="i">The Angel of the Divine Presence Clothing Adam and Eve with Coats
of Skins.</hi></p>
        <p>cat. 457 (pl. 525) <hi rend="i">Goliath Cursing David.</hi> My suggestion in a conversation with
Sir Geoffrey Keynes—accepted by Butlin in his commentary on cat. 436—that the six toes of the Angel of the
Divine Presence, like the six toes of Goliath, indicate membership in the Giant Brood, can be further
supported. The description of Goliath’s son who was slain by David’s armies is slightly clearer in 1
Chronicles 20:6 than in the corresponding passage in 2 Samuel 21:20: “And yet again there was war at Gath,
where was a man of great stature, whose fingers and toes were four and twenty, six on each hand, and six on
each foot: and he also was the son of the giant.” In isolation from this passage and from the water color
picture of Goliath, the extra digit of the Angel who towers above Adam and Eve might appear to be an
insignificant accident. But the Goliath of this same water color series for Butts has not only six toes on his
right foot (those on the left foot are too far in the background to be counted) but also six fingers on each
hand! Since these extra digits do not appear in the pen drawing, <hi rend="i">Goliath Cursing David</hi> (cat.
119Ar, pl. 133), I suppose that Blake came upon the biblical description of Goliath’s son only as he was
working on the watercolors for Butts, and that he adopted it as a distinctive feature of the race of giants,
whose origin he traced to the Angel of the Divine Presence. The six-toed left foot of the Angel contrasts with
the normal feet of the human-sized divine being who brings Eve to Adam in the companion picture, cat. 435r
(pl. 512); this contrast suggests that the two scenes take place before and after the Fall. Only after Adam
and Eve experience themselves as fallen and <corr type="emend">diminished</corr> do they experience the Divine
Presence as a forbidding giant who clothes them in skins but also blocks their return to Eden.</p>
        <p>cat. 523 (pl. 584) <hi rend="i">The Whore of Babylon.</hi> Does the inscription “W Blake inv
&amp; del 1809” mean that Blake intended to engrave this design? The earlier biblical water colors are not
signed “inv &amp; del.”</p>
        <p>cat. 604 (pl. 845) <hi rend="i">The Dove Brooding over the Face of the Waters</hi> (?). This may be
a pencil sketch for <hi rend="i">The Creation of Light</hi>, one of the lost water colors in the biblical
series for Butts.</p>
        <p>cat. 705 (pl. 920) “<hi rend="i">Joseph and Mary, and the Room they were Seen in.</hi>” Despite
Linnell’s title and the size of the female in relation to the two male figures in the tiny sketch of the
whole room, I suspect that the enlarged figures depict Jesus (with the hand of Joseph visible on his left arm)
and Mary. The face of Mary in the enlarged sketch is that of a woman; traditionally, of course, and in all of
Blake’s paintings and drawing of the Holy Family, Joseph is considerably older than Mary.</p>
        <p>cat. 833 (pl. 1125) <hi rend="i">A Seated Man Spurning a Standing Woman, perhaps for “The
Pilgrim’s Progress.”</hi> The pose of the seated man, in every detail, resembles that of Hagen in
Fuseli’s <hi rend="i">Kriemhild, Accompanied by Two Hun Servants, Shows the Imprisoned Hagen the Ring of the
Nibelungen</hi>, reproduced as figure 13 in Butlin’s catalogue of the 1978 Blake exhibition at the Tate
Gallery.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> Butlin dates the pencil
sketch 1824-27(?), and the Fuseli picture is dated 1807; the drawing appears to be in an earlier style than
the other <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> sketches. <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Martin Butlin,
<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (London: Tate Gallery, 1978), p. 89.</note></p>
        <p>One further note: the inscription by Tatham on <hi rend="i">Charon, Copy from the Antique</hi> (?),
cat. 178r (pl. 218), states that the figure was “copied from something else not designed by him.” I know
of one other copy of the head, by an unknown artist of the period, which may be after the same original. This
was a large finished pencil drawing which I saw in 1977 at the gallery of Rafael Valls, the London art dealer,
and photographed with his permission. The head, eyes, beard, staff, and general expression are too similar to
be coincidental. The appearance of a wave makes Butlin rightly suspicious of the traditional identification,
since the figure appears to be wading rather than propelling a ferry. The angle of the head, the pole, and the
billowing of the cape do, however, recall the Charon of Romney’s “Psyche Being Rowed across the Styx,”
reproduced as figure 121 to accompany Jean H. Hagstrum’s “Romney and Blake: Gifts of Grace and
Terror.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Jean Hagstrum, “Romney and Blake: Gifts of Grace and Terror,” in 
<hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, ed. Robert N. Essick and Donald Pearce (Bloomington and London: Indiana
University Press, 1978), 201-12. In Blake’s <hi rend="i">Charon</hi> the small pair of parallel lines
running diagonally from an area near “Charon’s” left hand to an area <corr type="emend">almost</corr> as
far down as the wave could be part of the ferry’s rigging; the boat itself might be obscured by the raging
waves. There appear to be two knots on the object I am calling a rope; the upper knot is very
faint.</note></p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
