<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.2.dorrbecker</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">John E. Grant, Edward J. Rose, and Michael J. Tolley, eds., 
David V. Erdman, co-ordinating ed., William Blake’s Designs for Edward Young’s 
‘Night Thoughts’: A Complete Edition</title>
        <author n="Dörrbecker">Detlef W. Dörrbecker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Krzysztof Z. Cieszkowski</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Christina Shuttleworth Kraus</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Judith W. Page</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Thomas A. Vogler</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-2-0010">
        <pb id="p16-130" n="130"/>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">John E. Grant, Edward J. Rose, and Michael J. Tolley, eds., David V. Erdman,
       co-ordinating ed. <hi rend="b">William Blake’s Designs for Edward Young’s
        ‘Night Thoughts’: A Complete Edition.</hi> Two Volumes. Oxford: Clarendon
       Press, 1980. $365/£150 the set.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Detlef W.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Dörrbecker</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Life, Death, and Immortality</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>“Young was fortunate. He seems almost the only poet who has had his mere metaphors
       illustrated and made corporeal.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41"
type="note">1</ref> —Blake
       enthusiasts are fond of the idea that Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> are
       remembered today mostly on account of their having been illustrated by their worshipped hero.
       It is to be questioned, however, whether Blake himself would be remembered today had he left
       behind nothing but this particular series of watercolors and engravings which, with respect
       to quantity, is his largest. <note id="n41"><hi rend="s">1</hi> [Edward Bulwer-Lytton],
        “Conversation with an Ambitious Student in Ill Health,” <hi rend="i">New Monthly
         Magazine</hi>, 29 (1830), 519; here quoted from the reprint in G. E. Bentley, Jr., ed., 
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969), p. 402.</note></p>
            <p>Few of Blake’s nineteenth-century commentators had direct access to the 537
       watercolor drawings, and thus could only judge the artist’s <hi rend="i">Night
        Thoughts</hi> designs (<hi rend="i">NT</hi>) from the forty-three engravings in
       Edwards’ edition of 1797. These were criticized as being “somewhat
       uninteresting.” “In Blake’s conceptions it is a hit or a miss,” and,
       Gilchrist continues, “the miss is a wide one,” especially if it comes to the
       illustrations for Young’s poem. “There is a monotony of subject, of treatment, of
       handling the graver even. . . . There is little or no individuality in his faces, if more in
       his forms. Typical forms and faces, abstract impersonations, are used to express his meaning.
       Everything,—figures, landscape, costume, accessory,—is reduced to its elemental
       shape, its simplest guise. . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42"
type="note">2</ref> Thus the <hi rend="i">NT</hi> designs prompted one of the harshest critiques of Blake’s
artistic
       output in Gilchrist’s biography. Nowadays, few would subscribe to the normative
       aesthetics which loom large behind such nineteenth-century views; and yet, even the most
       cautious value judgments, based on a critical and intimate knowledge of Blake’s entire
       work as a visual artist and taking only his own creative possibilities as a standard, will
       necessarily have to admit certain deficiencies—of which monotonous reduplication
       isn’t the least—that prevent the <hi rend="i">NT</hi> watercolors from ranking
       high among Blake’s masterpieces.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43"
type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William
         Blake</hi>, vol. 1 (London and Cambridge: Macmillan, 1863), pp. 140, 143, and 141; 2nd ed.
        (London: Macmillan, 1880 [which in vol. 2 adds Shields’ important descriptions of the
         <hi rend="i">NT</hi> water colors]), pp. 137, 140; 4th ed., ed. Ruthven Todd (London and
        New York: J. M. Dent and E. P. Dutton, 1942), pp. 117, 120, and 117-18. Whereas Gilchrist
        also had many things to say in favor of the designs, William Bell Scott simply found them
        “so completely inferior [to the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> illustrations] that they had no
        attractions.” See the <hi rend="i">Autobiographical Notes of the Life of William Bell
         Scott</hi>, ed. W. Minto, vol. 1 (London, 1892), p. 21, here quoted from <hi rend="i">Blake
         Records</hi>, p. 193.</note>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Bindman’s discussion of the series in his <hi rend="i">Blake as an
Artist</hi> (Oxford: Phaidon, 1977), pp. 109-12, represents an attempt
        to weigh fairly Blake’s achievement against the “staleness and repetition”
        which are considered as an “inevitable” effect of the very nature of
        Edwards’s commission.</note></p>
            <p>This and the sheer number of the designs may explain why the <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
       illustrations had to wait for reproduction longer than any other of Blake’s works. The
       need for a complete edition of these watercolors which represent approximately a fifth of the
       artist’s surviving designs, was first advocated in Hershel Margoliouth’s
       pioneering article of 1954: “How can the large company of students of Blake function
       adequately when [by 1954] 457 drawings, most of his work for a year and a half of the prime
       of his life, have never been 
       reproduced?”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">4</ref> Little
       happened, and in 1969 Morton Paley still had to complain that the <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
       designs “have remained the least known as well as the largest of Blake’s sets of
       designs,” for which “no detailed consideration of their symbolism, thematic
       structure, and meaning has yet been 
       published.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">5</ref>
       Then, in the same year, readers of the second edition of Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Prophet
        Against Empire</hi> were informed that “only in the late 1960’s did extensive
       scholarly study of the Blake water colors begin, as Clarendon Press undertook to publish a
       multi-volume edition of the whole series (with commentary by John Grant, Michael Tolley, and
<pb id="p16-131" n="131"/>
       Edward Rose).”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">6</ref> 
       Research for this edition had started as early as 1963-1964 (see p. x), but even
       the photographic reproductions, now under review, had to wait for their publication yet
       another ten years following Erdman’s announcement. It is only natural if with this
       elapse of time the highest possible expectations were raised. <note id="n44"><hi rend="s">4</hi>
Hershel M. Margoliouth, “Blake’s Drawings for Young’s
        ‘Night Thoughts’,” <hi rend="i">The Review of English Studies</hi>, n.s.
        5 (1954), 54.</note>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Morton D. Paley, “Blake’s ‘Night
        Thoughts’: An Exploration of the Fallen World,” in <hi rend="i">William Blake:
         Essays for S. Foster Damon</hi>, ed. Alvin H. Rosenfeld (Providence, R. I.: Brown
        University Press, 1969), p. 133.</note>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">6</hi> David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against
         Empire</hi>, 2nd rev. ed. (Garden City, N. Y.: Doubleday, 1969), p. 287, n. 14. Other early
        announcements of the <hi rend="i">NT</hi> edition include the same author’s
        “Blake 1757-1827,” in <hi rend="i">English Poetry: Select Bibliographical
         Guides</hi>, ed. A. E. Dyson (London: Oxford University Press, 1971), p. 147, and John E.
        Grant, “Envisioning the First ‘Night Thoughts’,” in <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms
Dramatic</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman and John E. Grant
        (Princeton, N. J.: Princeton University Press, 1970), p. 304, n. 2.</note></p>
            <p>These great expectations, I am afraid, are not fulfilled by the two enormous folio-sized
       volumes now published. Besides a foreword by Erdman who acted as coordinating editor, the
       first volume contains an introduction of some eighty pages, a bibliographic checklist of
       previous studies of the <hi rend="i">NT</hi> illustrations, and reproductions 1-263. These
       are followed in the second volume by reproductions from <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 264-537, and
       thus the modern edition exactly reflects the arrangement of the original water colors which
       were bound accordingly in two volumes for their first owner, the book dealer and publisher
       Richard Edwards. To the 537 halftone reproductions are added in the second volume a selection
       of seventy-eight designs which are reproduced in color, as well as eight specimen color
       plates from colored copies of the engravings; also reproduced are sixty-two proofs and the
       1797 edition in its entirety (vii+95+[2]pp.).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Monochrome Plates</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>I take it for granted that, with a total of 801 plates (including figures in the text,
       which are all connected with Blake’s <hi rend="i">NT</hi>), and presenting for the
       first time all the known materials related to one of Blake’s major commissions,
       including the reproductions of virtually hundreds of designs which have hitherto not been
       accessible except to students at the British Museum Print Room, the importance and value of
       such an edition is self-evident to anyone who is seriously interested in Blake’s work.
       This is merely the quantitative aspect, however. The reproductions being the <hi rend="i">raison
d’être</hi> and, no doubt, the reason for so high a retail price of
       these volumes, it is their quality which has to be considered first.</p>
            <p>Each of the 537 monochrome plates measures c. 29.5 × 22.7 cm.; this still means a
       reduction by approximately 30% from the originals (c. 42 × 32.5 cm.). The latter were
       executed on Whatman drawing paper which supplied the water colorist with an almost absolute,
       though unbleached, white for his ground. Its effect might have been imitated in the
       reproductions if a similar make of printing paper as, e.g., that used for the plates in
       Keynes’ <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, had been decided upon.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">7</ref> Alas, it was not, and the choice of a somewhat creamy, toned
paper for
       the printing of the pictures marks the second step away from the originals. The consequences
       of this decision for a printing paper which adds to the reproductions a color of its own are
       felt most strongly where the color plates are concerned. The black and white reproductions,
       however, may seem satisfactory at first sight. Only when compared with the originals or even
       with the results that were achieved in the 1927 facsimile does it become evident how much
       detail is lost in them.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">8</ref>
Equally important is the fact
       that there is no uniformity of tonal values in the monochrome reproductions.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">9</ref> Similar if not identical washes of a bright blue which in the
       watercolors have been employed to indicate the sunlit sky, reproduce as a faint
       gray—that is, just as one would expect—in the majority of the plates (see e.g.
       reprod. from <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 7, 11, 17, 21, etc.). Then there are instances, however,
       where a similar cerulean blue or a light gray wash in the original design becomes, in the
       reproduction, approaching night or sometimes even a complete darkness (see e.g. reprod. from
        <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 146, 154, 169, 175, 207, 227, 236, 238, 242, etc.). What is reproduced
       by equally compact areas in the halftone screen is thus not necessarily in keeping with areas
       of corresponding brightness or darkness in the watercolors. In general, the contrast between
       light and dark areas is much stronger in the black and white reproductions than in the
       designs themselves, and much detail gets lost together with Blake’s richer modulation
       of colors.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">10</ref> This certainly
need not be. The ten years
       this publication has been in preparation surely would have allowed for the production of a
       more homogeneous set of photographs and its adequate printing. Apart from these
       strictures—and especially if compared with the color plates—the monochrome
       reproductions of <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 1-537 serve their major purpose well enough. They will
       act as a valuable aid to memory for all those who have seen the originals, and—as a
       “simile” of the “figures, landscape, costume,
       accessory” of Blake’s designs—they will allow for iconographic
       research as well as, say, for a study of recurrent motifs among Blake’s figures. 
<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">7</hi> See Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 2nd enl.
        ed. (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1971). It needs no stressing, I suppose, that the use of
        glossy coated paper would have produced even worse results; also, the choice of paper may
        well have been dictated by the economics of modern book production outside the control of
        the editors.</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">8</hi> In the Clarendon edition one almost has to know beforehand
        about, for example, the presence of the frightened and the sleeping warrior in the
        resurrection scene of <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 264; otherwise one will be at pains to interpret
        the fragmentary traces of their outlines in the monochrome reproduction. The same design in
        Geoffrey Keynes, ed., <hi rend="i">William Blake: Illustrations to Young’s
         ‘Night Thoughts’</hi> (Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, for the
        Fogg Museum of Art, 1927) has all the detail reproduced to perfection. Yet of course the
        Fogg publication as well as the set of five plates from the <hi rend="i">NT</hi> water
        colors included in Keynes’ <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> (pls. 15-19) were
        reproduced by the collotype process, a printing technique which progress has by now almost
        put beyond price for publishers and their customers.</note>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">9</hi> I take it for granted that the editors did not attempt to
        create an independent work of art, but wanted to supply us with the most reliable
        “copy” that is possible; consequently I hope that no one will refer me to what
        Blake had to say about uniformity and “intermeasurability,” or to Morris
        Eaves’ excellent article on the “Artistic Machine” (<hi rend="i">PMLA</hi>,
        92 [1977], 903-27).</note>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">10</hi> The example of <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 264 has been quoted
        above; for further evidence I may refer to Lorenzo-Belshazzar’s left arm in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 60,
which in the reproduction is almost lost from sight under heavy
        blackish shading; this, as well as the upper part of the warning spirit’s left arm,
        are shaded with a gray wash but are perfectly clear in the original water color. Because of
        this kind of unreliability the reproductions—if not checked against the
        originals—may easily lend themselves to over-interpretation. <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 154
        illustrates the lines “Till One [i.e. Death] calls Him, who varies not his Call, / But
        holds him [i.e. Earth’s happiest Man] fast, in Chains of Darkness bound.” Blake
        shows the Urizenic figure of Death, crouching behind his chained victim. On the basis of the
        reproduction one might feel tempted to describe the setting of this scene as a cave, similar
        to those in <hi rend="i">Gates</hi> 3, or <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> 9—the watercolor,
        however, simply has unmodulated gray washes for a background screen which do not indicate
        any sort of measurable space or recession at all.</note></p>
            <p>It is this main section of the edition which also comes closest to keeping up with its
       claim to be “a necessary response to the wide and increasing modern interest
       in all of Blake’s works and to the exacting inclusiveness of a critical scholarship
       which demands easy access and frequent reference to the artist’s entire <hi rend="i">oeuvre</hi>”
(p. vii). And indeed, as regards “easy
       access,” the Clarendon edition has one real advantage even over the originals
       at the British Museum. The latter are mounted in an annoying and disadvantageous manner
       between heavy perspex screens which, however, proved to be necessary for their protection.
       Also, it takes approximately a week to go through the whole series box by box at the Print
       Room, and this does not allow for careful examination of more than a small portion of the
       watercolors. Usually students are asked to have only one box on their table at a time, and in
       consequence it becomes extremely wearisome to both staff and visitor if one wants to compare
       a design from Night VIII with another from Night II, and so on. For a wide range of possible
       questions such comparison has been enormously facilitated by the publication of the 
<hi rend="i">Complete Edition.</hi></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Color Plates</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>In the same large format as the monochrome plates, almost 15% of the watercolors are
       reproduced for a second time in “full colour.” For all those
       who once had a chance to study the originals, this will be the most disappointing part of the
       present publication. Many readers are likely to disagree with me if I say that ten
       high-quality color plates, equal to those in Keynes’s 1927 edition, would have 
<pb id="p16-132" n="132"/>
done more for our understanding of Blake’s coloring in the <hi rend="i">NT</hi> series than such a
“large proportion of full-colour
       plates” (p. vii) of a more than questionable standard. It is indeed much
       easier to demonstrate the range of possibilities in color composition that Blake made use of
       in this series by a large number of examples. But what—except misleading—are
       all these examples good for if only a small portion of the seventy-eight color reproductions
       gives at least a fair impression of what the originals look like? And yet this is an idle
       question. We will have to work with the edition as it is, and all that is to be done <hi rend="i">post
festum</hi> is to list the major discrepancies between the original designs
       and their reproductions. This may serve as a warning and—at best—as a
       corrective for those who are forced to base their judgment on what is to be gleaned from the
       present publication.</p>
            <p>Technically speaking, Blake’s <hi rend="i">NT</hi> designs are basically pen and ink
       drawings which have been tinted with watercolors. These are merely added to outline drawings,
       indicating once more that color is certainly not at the structural and conceptual center of
       Blake’s artistic work. Yet secondary importance remains importance still, and it is
       evident even from such miserable reproductions that the coloring is essential for elucidating
       the idea which is captured in the drawing.</p>
            <p>The range of colors used by Blake for his <hi rend="i">NT</hi> illustrations is in itself
       restricted. First there is a dominance of bright blues, yellows and greens for the early
       Nights. Though rose color is frequently employed, genuine red is relatively rare except for
       being used in the carnation. From Night VII onwards, Blake’s palette darkens
       considerably; there are stronger contrasts between light and dark areas in the designs which
       now also include much larger quantities of red.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51"
type="note">11</ref> Parts
       of the picture area are often left untouched so that the white of the paper may figure as
       clouds in a sky background or may represent light. Due to the toned paper employed for their
       printing, this white has mostly been lost in the color reproductions. There it is often
       transferred into a smudgy pink or ochre, giving the impression of heavy foxing or of some
       strange underpainting which is alien to the originals (see reprod. from <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
       151). Blake’s gray and black here tend to reproduce as a dark and dense brown, or are
       changed to a pale or a dark umber (see reprod. from <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 78, 125, 156, 166,
       284, 324, 344, 410, 415, 446, 466). Gray may even be deformed into a dark mauve (see reprod.
       from <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 34). The flesh colors, male and female, either lose most of their
       vivid aspects (see reprod. from <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 6, 156, etc.), or, to the contrary, show
       too much of pink (see reprod. from <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 117). The brilliance and intensity of
       the varied hues of green have suffered most; they are lost almost completely in the
       reproduction from <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 30, they are much darkened in the reproduction from
        <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 111, or they are boiled down and reduced to a common denominator as in
       the reproductions from <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 6, 24, 36, 78, 143, 158, 234, 296, 430, and 442.
       Brown—though of subordinate importance, if present at all in the
       watercolors—often gains dominance in the reproductions (for examples of the
       introduction of brown which is absent from the original design and for a brownish overall
       tinge akin to a nineteenth-century gallery varnish, see reprod. from <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 17,
       68, 312, 338, 378, 410, 446). The bright, translucent washes of blue and yellow are strongly
       affected by the color of the “ground,” the creamy tinge of the
       printing paper; they lose much of their brilliance and depth, and in some places in the
       reproductions yellow or blue are omitted altogether (see especially reprod. from <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
34, 91, 143, 345, 408). Yellow may reproduce as an almost golden brown, as beige or
       ochre (see reprod. from <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 111 and 284); that the more specific and often
       used quality of lemon loses its tendency towards bright green, but may gain a tendency
       towards yolk of egg, gold, or orange is to be seen in other examples (see reprod. from 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 6, 135, 170, 203, 287, 408). Blake’s reds, ranging from carmine and
       cinnabar to salmon color, participate in the general loss of intensity and variety of hues
       which sadly characterizes the color plates. They reproduce too dark and dense, and they are
       thus brought close to a reddish brown which is lacking from the originals (see reprod. from
        <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 107, 125, 156, 345). <note id="n51"><hi rend="s">11</hi> On p. 10 of
        the introduction the editors observe that there “are no great differences in style from
        Night the First to Night the Ninth; the increasing frequency of stronger hues in the later
        Nights seems calculatedly dramatic.”</note></p>
            <p>If just one color comes off wrong from a reproduction, this causes a distortion in the
       whole of the color composition which is unmendable. So in the end we are left with only a
       small porportion of full-color plates that actually meet with the requirements of a critical
       scholarship. (For the few good ones see reprod. from <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 87, 164, 170 [good
       for the greens], 339, 352, 361, 471.) And it is no real consolation that the remaining plates
       in the second volume are those which are the most satisfactory. At approximately 70% of the
       original size they reproduce the proofs, the finished engravings, and the complete text of
       the printed edition of 1797. The originals in this case being in a monochrome medium
       themselves, the reproduction must have caused comparatively few problems for the printer.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Introductory Essay</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Until the publication of the volumes of commentary, the scholarly apparatus of the 
<hi rend="i">Complete Edition</hi> of Blake’s <hi rend="i">NT</hi> illustrations is
       limited to the captions, a foreword, and an introductory essay. The captions identify the
       watercolors by their standardized numbers (<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 1-537).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">12</ref> They also cite the page number for the respective Night, and
the
       numbers of the lines which were illustrated by Blake. A set of symbols serves to distinguish
       the markings of lines, and if a design has been engraved for the 1797 edition, a reference to
       the engraving is included as well. Erdman’s foreword, dated August 1977, is
       interesting mostly as an advertisement for the forthcoming volumes of commentary. Readers are
       told that the “purpose and uses of a commentary will be made manifest when it
       appears,” and are asked (in 1977, or in 1980?) their “patience
       for another year or two” (p. vii). There can be no arguing about that. The
       coordinating editor’s claim, however, “that commentary is even more
       necessary for the apparently simple pictures than for those where difficulty and irony
       insistently confront us” (p. viii), is a paradox which in due time will have
       to be put to the proof. <note id="n52"><hi rend="s">12</hi> This system of identification has
        been in general use from the late 1960s onwards; it now has also been adopted for the brief
        entries for each design in Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William
         Blake</hi>, vol. 1 (New Haven, Conn. and London: Yale University Press, for the Paul Mellon
        Center for Studies in British Art, 1981), no. 330, pp. 178-253. The system for numbering the
        water colors and the engravings, each by a series straight through from <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
        1 to <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 537, and from 1E to 43E, and their combined use in references like
         <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 1(31E), or 31E(<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 1) respectively, is explained on
        p. xv.</note></p>
            <pb id="p16-133" n="133"/>
            <p>Finally, there is the introduction which—apart from offering a valid and useful
       compilation of all the external sources and data connected with Blake’s <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
project—makes an independent contribution to our knowledge of the history
       and development of these designs. In the first of the five chapters of this essay, the
       editors describe the “Occasion” which led to the production of the watercolors.
       They deal with the neglect of Young’s poem and Blake’s illustrations in
       twentieth-century scholarship, and claim that today Young may be rehabilitated if only read
       through these illuminations of his poetry (see p. 3). Then, quoting from the Farington Diary,
       Ann Flaxman’s letters, the Prospectus, and the Advertisement for the 1797 edition, the
       outward circumstances of Edwards’s commission are described.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n53" type="note">13</ref> Though there is some truly Blakean bias, and even some twisting of the
        evidence,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">14</ref> these pages are on
the whole a sound
       recapitulation of all that is presently known about the history of the production of the
       watercolors, and of Blake’s relations with Edwards. For the first time, the editors
       offer a balanced account of the publisher’s role and his “personal enthusiasm for
       the project” (p. 5). Richard Edwards emerges almost triumphantly as a sort of
       anti-Cromek, and this view is more convincing to me than Bentley’s earlier stance, who
       could see in the Advertisement nothing but “a strange piece of puffing.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">15</ref>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">13</hi> No new documentary evidence seems to have surfaced; thus,
        these pages had to repeat the information which was previously available from Sir Geoffrey
        Keynes’s authoritative essay in his <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, pp. 50-58, and
        from Bentley’s <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, passim. The letters from Ann Flaxman,
        however, previously believed to have been written some time in 1797, are now convincingly
        predated c. “16 March 1796” (see p. 4 and p. 85, n. 4).</note>
	<note id="n54"><hi rend="s">14</hi> The motive here seems to be simply to put Blake in the
        most favorable light when, e.g., Farington is scorned as “an unsuccessful
        painter,” just because he “was an unsympathetic witness” (p. 4) who did not
        appreciate Blake’s work. As secretary to the Royal Academy Farington was socially
        much more successful than Blake himself, and some arguments concerning Farington’s
        paintings are required to justify such a rash verdict which—in any case—will
        remain an unnecessary idiosyncrasy and rather out of place in this context. Also, we cannot
        know whether or not “Farington made nonsense of what must have been an effort by Fuseli
        to explain what was [positively] special about Blake’s use of imagination” (p.
        4). It <hi rend="i">must</hi> not; after all, Fuseli on the very same occasion is reported
        saying that “Blake has something of madness abt. him.” This sentence, however, is
        not quoted by Grant, Rose, and Tolley. See <hi rend="i">The Diary of Joseph Farington</hi>,
        ed. Kenneth Garlick and Angus D. Macintyre, vol. 2 (New Haven, Conn. and London: Yale
        University Press, for the Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art, 1978), p. 589.
        There is another “probable” conjecture concerning Fuseli on p. 9, and again, the
        editors’ evidence is somewhat shallow.</note>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 57. See also
        p. 87, n. 13 in the present publication, where Bentley’s reading of Edward’s
        text is correctly criticized as being “rather selective.”</note></p>
            <p>As regards the “Reception of the Engraved Edition,” it remains conjectural
       whether or not it really “had a considerable sale” (p. 7). The authors themselves
       think it “probable” that the print run was limited to no more than 200 copies, and
       even if these were actually sold within the next ten years, it is rather an exaggeration to
       say the sale had been “considerable.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56"
type="note">16</ref> The
       following pages are occupied by an account of the history and ownerships of the watercolors
       from the time of their completion onwards (pp. 7-8). The editors’ sources for these
       paragraphs have been printed previously in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> and
       Keynes’s <hi rend="i">Blake Studies.</hi>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">16</hi> I ought to point out, however, that the first printing of
        Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Hesiod</hi> in 1817 had also been limited to 200 copies only,
        and that eighteen of these were still unsold in 1838. See G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">The Early
Engravings of Flaxman’s Classical Designs: A Bibliographical Study</hi>
        (New York: NYPL, 1964), pp. 54-56.</note></p>
            <p>Though including sections on the “Completion of the Series” and “A
       Frontispiece for Each Volume,” the chapter on the “Preparation and Production”
       of the 537 watercolors is merely 3 1/2 pages long (pp. 10-13). These contain information on
       the Whatman drawing paper which was employed by the artist, on the inlaying and framing of
       the pages of Young’s text, on the masking of the latter before application of the
       colors, on the markings of lines which were to serve as a starting point for the
       illustrations, on Blake’s processes from underdrawing to coloring, and on the 
<hi rend="i">pentimenti</hi> and the problem of the preliminary sketches. Grant, Rose, and
       Tolley assume the possibility that at least some of the water colors were finished “only
       while [Blake was] making the plates,” and that “he may easily be supposed to have
       given the final touches to some of them [i.e. the water color designs] only in order to
       perfect them as a complete series” (p. 11) even after any view of publishing a sequel to
       the 1797 edition of Nights I-IV had ceased to exist. This I believe to be particularly
       important because previously the <hi rend="i">NT</hi> water colors have often been considered
       as mere preparatory drawings for the engravings. For their first owner, however, they may
       well have held the status of an independent and self-sufficient work of art. The engravings
       then, which were to publish only a selection of the entire series of designs (be it 150, or
       even 200 plates), would have to be placed rather with the large reproductive engravings after
       the paintings from Boydell’s Shakespeare Gallery, or those initially planned by Fuseli
       for his Milton Gallery,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">17</ref> than
to be considered the sole
       and <hi rend="i">prima causa</hi> for Blake’s sequence of the 537 water colors. There
       was of course a strong economic interest behind all the Gallery schemes of the day. The point
       I want to make, however, is that this economic interest in the 1790s was ideologically linked
       with the idea of establishing a British school of history painting, and that both Blake and
       Edwards may have thought of the <hi rend="i">NT</hi> designs as their personal contribution
       to its realization. To prepare a series of engravings, pencil drawings or monochrome wash
       drawings would have been completely sufficient, and there certainly would have been no need
       for mounting the pages of a precious copy of Young’s <hi rend="i">NT</hi> which later
       was said to have been the author’s own (see pp. 8 and 9). The careful outlining and
       coloring of these designs then may well accord to an additional, or rather the first part of
       Edwards’ commission, comparable only to that from Flaxman for the similar Gray
        series.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">18</ref> This view is also
corroborated by what the
       authors have to report about the reception of the watercolors which in “any event . . .
       indicates considerable respect on Edwards’s part for both the poetry of Young, and the
       drawings of Blake” (p. 11).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">19</ref>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">17</hi> For Fuseli’s plan to have his Milton paintings
        published in a series of engravings which were to be executed by Sharpe and Bartolozzi, see
        Gert Schiff, <hi rend="i">Johann Heinrich Füsslis Milton-Galerie</hi> (Zurich and
        Stuttgart: Fretz &amp; Wasmuth, 1963), pp. 12-13.</note>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">18</hi> The water colors for Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi>
        and Dante illustrations are no counter-evidence. Though both eventually resulted in a series
        of engravings, it has to be remembered that the first set of paintings for <hi rend="i">Job</hi> had
been executed without any view toward their publication, and that the Dante
        watercolors differ markedly from the <hi rend="i">NT</hi> designs in both their often
        sketchlike style of drawing and their often unfinished coloring.</note>
	<note id="n59"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Though David Erdman describes the series as a “vast
        gallery of illuminative art” (p. vii), and though the editors seem to be aware of some
        sort of connection between the <hi rend="i">NT</hi> designs and the various Shakespeare and
        Milton galleries (see p. 7), they prefer the view that the “decision to prepare the
        watercolours as a self-sufficient <hi rend="i">opus</hi>” (p. 12) was an afterthought
        and dates from a later period than the original commission.</note></p>
            <p>Speculations about the designing and the function of <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 1 (31E) and about
       Edwards’ printing schedule (pp. 12-13) lead on to the next section. This is devoted to
       the “Engravings,” and here we learn about the difficulties with correct positioning
       of the plates and overprinting of the text panels in the 1797 edition (pp. 13-14), problems
       which in a few cases even made a “cropping of figures” unavoidable, “as in 3E
        (<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 14), for example” (p. 14). The penciled page numbers on some of
       the so-called “private proofs” from the collection of Philip Hofer are interpreted
       as an unsuccessful attempt to cope with those problems caused by “the tight economy of
       space required by the printed pages of text” (p. 14). Then, the often complicated
       development of the forty-three designs that were engraved for the edition of 1797 is
       presented in a “Table of Engraved Designs” (pp. 17-35). With the private proofs
       included which “only now [have been] made available for study” (p. 15), this
       account of all the variant states supplements and up-dates Easson and Essick’s
       bibliographical notes for the same set of engravings.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n60" type="note">20</ref>
       The publication of the Hofer private proofs with their remarques certainly adds a new facet
       to what we know about Blake as print maker, and it is only in a few cases that the usefulness
       of this “Table” may be lessened by some minor descriptive errors.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">21</ref>
	<note id="n60"><hi rend="s">20</hi> See Roger R. Easson and Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake:
Book Illustrator</hi>, vol. 1 (Normal, Ill.: American Blake Foundation,
        1972), pp. 15-27. Professors Rose, Tolley, and Grant also relied largely on Easson and
        Essick’s account of the printing process (see pp. 88, n. 29 and 89, n. 43); with
        respect to the size of the printing paper the information G. E. Bentley, Jr.,
        “Young’s ‘Night Thoughts’ (London: R. Edwards, 1797): A New
        Unillustrated State,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, 14 (1980), 35, will now have to be taken
        into consideration.</note>
	<note id="n61"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Thus, I see simply parallel lines, but no
        “cross-hatching in the shadow below Death’s toes” (p. 19) in 4E; and it is
        certainly wrong to describe the king “under the outstretched foot of Death” in 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 20 as having been “decapitated” (p. 19). In the watercolor the
        figure’s head is merely seen foreshortened and from below so that only the outline of
        the king’s chin shows; much the same contour is employed for a second time in <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
20 for the head of the other king who is seen from above. Obviously, Blake
        made use of the device of counter-, or mirror-images, a practice well known from
        Quattrocento paintings (see, e.g., the archers in the 1475 San Sebastiano altarpiece at the
        National Gallery in London [inv. no. 292], which is traditionally attributed to Antonio and
        Piero del Pollaiuolo). Blake’s departure from his water color design in the final
        engraving (5E) does not “reflect an inclination toward less provocative designs”
        (p. 13), but rather an attempt to make his image more easily recognizable in all its
        details. The editors’ fantastic interpretation of the water color proves that he was
        right in this decision.</note></p>
            <p>The chapter on “The Frontispieces” (<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 1 and 264) opens with a
       consideration of “the symbolic dramatic effect achieved by the placing of the vision of
       the Rising Christ in the fourth title-page of the engraved edition” (p. 35). Then, the
       title pages supplied for each of the four Nights in the 1797 edition are discussed as a
       sequence of designs, one relating to the others. From the following interpretation of the
       function of <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 1 and <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 264 
<pb id="p16-134" n="134"/>
we
       can get a foretaste of what is to be expected from the commentary. “One of the purposes
       of our commentary will be to make explicit some of the tensions of interpretation and
       contradiction that play in the reader-viewer’s response to Young’s
       ‘parson’d’ pages and Blake’s visionary pictures. Practically
       speaking, the question will generally be how and in what ways the designs, singly and
       cumulatively, manage simultaneously (or with lapses) to be faithful to the text of Young and
       true to the poetic and prophetic genius of Blake” (p. 39). This question has a venerable
       tradition in the history of Blake scholarship; it was much the same sort of question
        which—<hi rend="i">grosso modo</hi>—was central in Wicksteed’s studies
       of the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> illustrations, in Roe’s interpretations of Blake’s
       Dante, and in many of the more recent studies of Blake’s response to Milton.
       Ultimately, it might be traced back to Blake himself, notably to his <hi rend="i">Milton: A
        Poem</hi> (where, however, it resulted in poetry, not criticism). The task which Professors
       Rose, Tolley, and Grant have set themselves, will certainly require a method to proceed with
       the utmost caution against over-interpretation, and it is to be hoped that they will remain
       aware of their own warning against the dangers of mere “theorizing about . . . intended
       symbolism[s]” (p. 17). The present writer, however, already feels at a loss if he is
       supposed to judge the critical value of euphoria—as in the following statements about
       the resurrection scene in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 264: “Instead of fixing the reader with
       the direct eye of Truth [a reference to <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 156 (43E)], his [i.e.
       Christ’s] upcast eyes direct the viewer to the above which is within, the home of
       intelligible meaning. The overcast is opened, not by effort, but by an explosion that is a
       celebration. The outstretched hands that need no longer push the clouds apart [as in 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 1 (31E)], by the piercing light that replaces darkness in all directions;
       opened and made one. The hands simultaneously display to doubters the proof that Jesus 
<hi rend="i">is</hi> the human family; as he suffered for all, he can offer the infinite expanse
       to all, and even prepare to offer the handclasp of Friendship. Blake never quite depicts this
       moment of fraternity . . . ” (pp. 38-39). Such free flow of pseudo-Blakean associations
       (or should I say “illuminations”?)—which, if only translated into less
       ecstatic phrasing, are truisms as relevant for a painting of the resurrection by, for
       example, Sebastiano Ricci as for Blake’s <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 264—must be
       controlled by a more modest inspection of those levels of pictorial meaning which are closer
       to the graphic surface of the illustrations and closer to the eye of their beholder.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62" type="note">22</ref>
	<note id="n62"><hi rend="s">22</hi> One such modest consideration—which in fact I
        expect from Tolley’s future comments on the watercolor—would have been a
        reference to the typological connection between the self-sacrifice of Samson in the Old and
        of Christ in the New Testament while discussing the final design (<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 537)
        in the context of the Christologic frontispieces (<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 1 and <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
264). This would seem more relevant to an understanding of Blake’s meaning
        than the aperçu phrase about Samson’s broken pillars which “can now
        represent the conventional fame on which Blake [involuntarily!] turned his back” (p.
        39).</note></p>
            <p>In general, it seems problematic to me, for instance, to “explain” a design in
        <hi rend="i">NT</hi> by reference to some similarity in the artist’s much later
       illuminations in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Blake was certainly convinced that the full
       meaning of one of his pictures was to be discovered without reference to his other
       productions (outside a given series), much less to those which had not yet been executed. His
       claim to unity in a (single) work of art ought to be taken seriously when attempting an
       interpretation, and it does assign to all comparisons a rather limited significance.
       Blake’s pictorial language is based—and this is especially true of the <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
designs<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63" type="note">23</ref>—on a restricted
       “alphabet” of human postures. These, however, allow for an almost unlimited number
       of combinations. While we can see that one and the same gesture is used throughout
       Blake’s <hi rend="i">oeuvre</hi>, and often with the most contradictory implications,
       it is the combinations which count for an adequate understanding because only they determine
       the meaning of the otherwise isolated letters of this alphabet. A comparison, then, which
       takes into account just one element of a picture, for example the gesture of the outspread
       arms, remains arbitrary and inconclusive—it leads nowhere.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n64" type="note">24</ref>
	<note id="n63"><hi rend="s">23</hi> See the introductory quotation from Gilchrist’s
         <hi rend="i">Life</hi>, which, I think, is not without some justification.</note>
	<note id="n64"><hi rend="s">24</hi> For an example, see pp. 90, n. 58 and 47 (fig. 8) where
         <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 264 is compared with the last plate in <hi rend="i">All Religions are
         One</hi>, probably just because the latter design is considered as an early appearance of
        the motif of the outspread arms in Blake’s <hi rend="i">oeuvre.</hi></note></p>
            <p>Pages 39-51 describe and reproduce eleven “drawings” which “at least bear a
       closer resemblance to particular <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs than they do to
       other finished Blake pictures” (p. 39). The watercolor copy of <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 11,
       painted on a printed leaf of vellum (Henry E. Huntington Library; fig. 1, p. 41), is now no
       longer ascribed to Blake, and much doubt is cast on the authenticity of the drawing of
       “Timon” which is related to <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 115 (Yale University Library; fig.
       5, pp. 43-45).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65" type="note">25</ref> The faint
iconographic connection
       between the emblem drawing on page 42 of the <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> and <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 26 is
described as the relation between a “basic design” and its
       “considerable amplification” (p. 41; fig. 2). With this drawing included, it is
       surprising that no mention is made, for example, of the resemblance between the design for
        <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 61 and the emblem drawing on page 17 of the <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>,
       both representing the encounter of a youthful traveler with Death, who is waiting for
       him—once as a shrouded skeleton, and then as the usual white-bearded figure in 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi>—in a doorway. Figure 3 reproduces the fifth plate from “Series
       a” of <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion.</hi> Though one may be surprised to
       find a relief etching among what is said to be a group of “Drawings,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66" type="note">26</ref> no one will fail to recognize its connection with 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 27 (7E). But readers will probably wonder why, for example, the similar
       connection between the second plate of “The Little Black Boy” and <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 378 is
omitted from this list. Next comes a labored interpretation of the supposed
       symbolic content of the amalgamation of the two superimposed pencil drawings on the sheet
       which is reproduced as figure 4 (Victoria and Albert Museum). This shows the back-view of a
       figure with arms raised at acute angles which has been drawn over a faint, yet more elaborate
       drawing of a seated female looking to the right. The latter bears some resemblance to
       “Night” in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 103, and the figure seen from behind is connected
       by the editors with Christ as he appears in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 127. The distinct stylistic
       differences between the first and rather finished drawing—which appears to be a 
<hi rend="i">pentimento</hi> that Blake did not care to erase before using the same sheet of
       paper for the second time—and the rough sketch which he drew over it at an apparently
       much faster speed are passed over without mentioning. It is of course difficult to calculate
       the lapse of time between the first and the re-use of the paper; it should have been noted,
       however, that stylistically the superimposed figure is much closer to the design on the verso
       of the sheet (“An Angel Taking a Huge Stride among the Stars”) than to the
       underlying drawing of “Night.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67"
type="note">27</ref> This might
       have warned against an interpretation which to me appears to be a misconstruction of
       Blake’s workshop practice. If the authors say that this combination of the two
       “states” of the drawing suggests “that 
<pb id="p16-135" n="135"/>
the first
       picture was meant to be blocked out” (p. 42) by the second, if they elaborate on this
       fascinating, but rather too brainy idea by asserting that “Christ in the second drawing
       would be intervening to stop Night from telling all she has learned” (p. 43), they are
       guilty of exactly that sort of “theorizing about [the] intended symbolism” (p. 17)
       which they had promised to refrain from.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68"
type="note">28</ref>
	<note id="n65"><hi rend="s">25</hi> Martin Butlin, too, “finds it very difficult to see
        Blake’s hand” in both these works; see Butlin, vol. 1, nos. 334 and 785, pp.
        254-55 and 542-43.</note>
	<note id="n66"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Another relief etching is reproduced as fig. 8: plate 10
        from <hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi>, which is said to be the model for <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
264; see note 24, above.</note>
	<note id="n67"><hi rend="s">27</hi> See Butlin, vol. 1, no. 820r&amp;v, pp. 591-92.</note>
	<note id="n68"><hi rend="s">28</hi> An unerased <hi rend="i">pentimento</hi> is by definition
        a phenomenon which indicates that the respective drawing is <hi rend="i">not</hi> a
        finished, self-contained work of art; on the contrary, such drawings document various stages
        in the development of one or possibly various <hi rend="i">concetti</hi> all at a time. The
        authors allot symbolic weight to what appears to me an accidental concurrence of sketches,
        and it becomes clear at this point how much Blake studies would profit from a consideration
        of such stimulating new approaches toward descriptive and terminological precision and a
        critical understanding of the act of drawing as Alexander Perrig’s <hi rend="i">Michelangelo Studien
I: Michelangelo und die Zeichnungswissenschaft—Ein
         methodologischer Versuch</hi> (Frankfurt am Main and Bern: Peter &amp; Herbert Lang, 1976
        [“Kunstwissenschaftliche Studien,” vol. 1]).</note></p>
            <p>The discussion of the “Timon” drawing at Yale (fig. 5) is interesting mostly for
       the “rule” it serves to establish; “as a rule Blake’s successive
       versions of a subject are superior, in invention at least, to their predecessors” (p.
        45).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69" type="note">29</ref> But what about the
exceptions to the rule? To
       give just one example, one may say that Blake’s “Nebuchadnezzar” in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
Heaven and Hell</hi> is—if isolated from its context in the
       illuminated book—inferior to its successor, the large color print of c. 1795; so far
       the editors’ rule is easily verified. And yet, if one looks at <hi rend="i">NT</hi>
       299, the third version of the same subject, I cannot accept the idea that “in invention
       at least” this has to be considered the superior treatment. Again, when comparing 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 117 (32E) with the so-called “Nimrod” drawing (Nelson
       Gallery/Atkins Museum of Fine Arts; fig. 6), the editors’ criteria for artistic
       quality prove to be disputable. There certainly ought to be some definition of
       “progression” (p. 46) in art, and a design ought first to be properly described
       before one assigns to it a higher or a lower rank.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70"
type="note">30</ref>
       Otherwise we will end up with possibly inspired but nonetheless apodictical statements which
       are useless for the “critical scholarship” that this publication is supposed to
       facilitate. The authors’ zeal for their “rule” must underlie their
       comparison of <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 196 to a related drawing from the Cleveland Museum of Art
       (fig. 7). The arguments which are supplied for judging the water color the
       “superior” design border on the ridiculous. How can the lack of detail and
       precision in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 196 be seriously understood as a gain over the pencil
       drawing “in visual and symbolic statement” (p. 47)? Professors Rose, Grant, Tolley
       observe for themselves that <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 196 is a mirror-image of the drawing, and
       though they offer no explanation for this reversal they rema in in the affirmative about its
       being “most evidently a preliminary drawing” (p. 47). Their statement about the
       artist’s “broadening [of] the symbolic application” in the watercolor by
       means of what is called “small revisions” (p. 47) seems a mystification of
       Blake’s art and of his methods of designing, quite contrary to what he had to say
       about them himself. The Cleveland drawing is definitely superior to <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 196
       in delineation and modeling, and it is certainly the more convincing, though less 
<hi rend="i">outré</hi>, variant of the subject. But regardless whether one accepts this
       view of the drawing’s superiority over <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 196, or prefers to think
       of it as the preliminary and, “in consequence,” the inferior design, this cannot
       supply a decisive clue for the exact dating of the drawing as the authors believe. 
<note id="n69"><hi rend="s">29</hi> In passing it ought to be mentioned that Blake claimed the
        unity of vision and execution for his works; this unity is not respected by the authors who
        are, it seems, ready to isolate what they call “invention” from the execution of a
        design.</note>
	<note id="n70"><hi rend="s">30</hi> The “mighty hunter” in Blake’s “Let
        Loose the Dogs of War” is said to be “looking back . . . to cheer on his
        untethered single reserve dog” (p. 45). Indeed, the figure is looking back, but
        definitely not downwards at the second dog which appears in the lower right corner of the
        design—the cheering is clearly directed at someone whom we cannot see because he is
        not represented in the drawing as we now have it. Following the direction of the crowned
        hunter’s line of sight one will find, however, that the drawing appears to have been
        trimmed before mounting at least at the right margin where today the edge of the paper is
        cutting through Nimrod’s left foot and through the second of the bloodhounds. By
        means of the false description of the direction of the hunter’s cheering the actual
        incompleteness of the design is in effect converted into a self-sufficient image. The
        consequences of a possible later trimming and the necessity for a reconstruction of the
        original composition thus pass unnoticed because of the rash and prejudiced manner in which
        the editors discharged their duty of examining closely what is actually to be seen on the
        material surface of the drawing.</note></p>
            <p>The chapter ends with a consideration of some early sketches—including the four
       versions of “The Warring Angels”—which were employed for the composition of
        <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 372, 452, and 510 (see figs. 9-11). Though some speculations about
       “Blake’s conjectural repertoire portfolio” (p. 50, see also pp. 48 and 51)
       are brought forward with ever-growing confidence in its former existence, the overall result
       of this search for “Preliminary and Related Drawings” is a negative one. Even if
       all the designs that are represented in this listing are accepted as preparatory for designs
       among the <hi rend="i">NT</hi> watercolors, their quantitative disproportion would still
       confirm what the editors let us know beforehand: “Almost no evidence survives of
       preliminary sketches or drawings; yet he [i.e. Blake] may well have made and discarded
       many” (p. 10). Of course we cannot know how many of Blake’s preparatory sketches
       have been lost; however, the numerous erasures and corrections in the underdrawing of the
       water colors and, in fact, the very weakness of the drawing itself which is to be seen rather
       often even in the finished designs (see, e.g., the legs of the spinning-wheel table in 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 294) seem to indicate that he did not invest the same amount of work in the
       conception and execution of this enormous and—due to the fixed format and the
       repetition of much subject matter in the poem itself—necessarily tiresome series as he
       did in his best work.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71" type="note">31</ref>
	<note id="n71"><hi rend="s">31</hi> The chapter on the preliminary designs is followed by a
        discussion of two “Derivative or Possibly Derivative Designs” which had been
        mentioned in Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life.</hi> Both are justly dismissed as bearing
        no, or only a “dubious,” relationship with the <hi rend="i">NT</hi> series (see
        pp. 51-52).</note></p>
            <p>The remaining pages of the introduction are entirely concerned with the intricacies of the
       colored version of the engravings and include a new census of twenty-two of the known
        examples.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72" type="note">32</ref> Based on a
first-hand examination of all
       these colored copies, this account supersedes the earlier compilations of Moss and
        Bentley.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73" type="note">33</ref> Whereas in c. 1942
Moss still devoted much
       speculation to the identity of the colorists (preferably Blake or his wife), Grant, Rose, and
       Tolley set this straight by pointing out that any statement “as to when or by whom a
       particular copy was coloured must be regarded as inferential rather than factual” (p.
       53), though they do not exclude the possibility that Blake colored one or more model
        copies.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">34</ref> The authors describe
and distinguish three
       basic schemes or “types” of coloring (see p. 53), with fifteen copies belonging to
       the first, six to the second, and just one copy to the third type (which—until further
       copies with similar coloring happen to turn up—cannot be considered as a proper
       “type,” but rather has to be regarded as a unique exception<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n75" type="note">35</ref>). The most important distinction between the three groups is that the
       figure of Death in plate 1E wears a white robe in copies of type I, a green robe in copies of
       type II, and a gray robe in the type-III copy. A further subdivision of the second group is
       based not on a particular difference in coloring, but on the observation that, for two of the
       copies, an earlier state of plate 11E, and, for the four remaining copies in this group as
       well as all the other colored copies, a later state has been used. There is, in any case,
       “a caution against assuming that the family characteristics [of the three types] are
       self evident” (p. 54). A list of thirteen “Major Variations” follows (pp.
       54-55), and three of these—the two states of plate 11, the J C ligature which the
       editors have discovered in several of the colored copies, and the so-called
       “grotesque” coloring of some of the designs in the first group—are discussed
       at length on the succeeding pages. All the empirical information presented in this section is
       new, yet so far these observations rather serve to introduce “further complication”
       (p. 57) than to clarify the matter. This, of course, is 
<pb id="p16-136" n="136"/>
not to be
       blamed on the editors, who deserve our admiration for their close scrutiny of the copies.
        <note id="n72"><hi rend="s">32</hi> On p. 53 twenty-three copies are said to be known while
        the census lists only twenty-two of them. This discrepancy is due to the then untraced
        Gaisford copy (Moss-Bentley, Copy G); see also note 38, below.</note>
	<note id="n73"><hi rend="s">33</hi> See W. E. Moss, “The Coloured Copies of
        Blake’s ‘Night Thoughts’,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 2
        (1968), 19-23; G. E. Bentley, Jr., “A Census of Coloured Copies of Young’s
        ‘Night Thoughts’ (1797),” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 2 (1968),
        41-45; G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977),
        no. 515, pp. 642-46, with another copy (T) added in Bentley’s “Supplement to
        ‘Blake Books’,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, 11 (1977-78), 150.</note>
	<note id="n74"><hi rend="s">34</hi> “If one were to suppose that quality of colour were
        the surest evidence of Blake’s own responsibility for the tinting of a particular
        copy,” (p. 55) Professors Grant, Rose, and Tolley would vote for their Copies I-1,
        I-15, and IIB-1 as the most likely candidates (see pp. 54, 60-61, and the color specimen in
        vol. 2). In the case of Copy IIB-1 (Moss-Bentley, Copy B) this means that they agree with
        Moss’s connoisseur belief which is said to have been based on “faith [rather]
        than evidence” (p. 61), and, in a different context, is quoted as providing “a
        clear example of the limitations of impressionistic scholarship” (p. 4)! Yet another
        paragraph does at least allow for “the possibility that Blake himself had no
        responsibility for any of these [coloring] schemes” (p. 60).</note>
	<note id="n75"><hi rend="s">35</hi> “Type III, is quite likely to have been done by some
        possessor of an uncolored copy for his own enjoyment, or as a forgery” (p. 60; see also
        p. 62).</note></p>
            <p>The “Need for a New Census” of the colored copies, its coding system, and the
       reasons for the particular sequence of copies which is chosen here are explained on pages
       60-62. The identification of each copy by the combination of roman and arabic numerals is
       meant as a source of information in itself.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76"
type="note">36</ref> The three
       “types” of coloring are referred to by the roman numerals I-III, and while the
       capital letters A and B mark the subdivision of type II, the arabic numerals attempt to group
       various copies according to some other characteristics they have in common.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77" type="note">37</ref> This system has certain advantages over the alphabetization
of copies
       which is so well known from the bibliographies of Sir Geoffrey Keynes and G. E. Bentley, Jr.
       A designation like “IIB-3” will translate to the initiated as “Green Death
       type of coloring: plate 11 in final state: Explanation sheet following front matter,”
       whereas “Copy H” carries none of these data. I am afraid, however, that when more
       copies come to light and need to be fitted in, this advantage of the new coding system will
       soon be lost. For example, there simply is no room for another copy of the White Death type,
       with the explanations following page [96] in the copy’s proper place, that is between
       Copy I-7 (which is the last of the White Death group with the explanations bound at the end
       of the book) and Copy I-8 (which is the first copy of the same group that has the
       explanations following the advertisement). The introduction of capital letters following the
       arabic numerals will be necessary in this case, and beside the growing complicatedness of the
       copy designation there is a limit to even that sort of rationalization (imagine a sequence
       like I-6, I-6A, I-6B, I-6AA, etc.). So in ten years’ time all this fuss about a new
       system of copy identifications will probably appear as much ado about nothing. 
<note id="n76"><hi rend="s">36</hi> This coding system is reminiscent of Nancy Bogen’s census in
        her edition of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> (in which Professor Erdman also took a hand). Whereas
        for Bogen the roman numerals served to designate various stages of textual revision, they
        are here employed to differentiate between the three coloring schemes. See William Blake,
         <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, A Facsimile and a Critical Text, ed. Nancy W. Bogen
        (Providence, R. I. and New York: Brown University Press and NYPL, 1971), pp. 53-55.</note>
	<note id="n77"><hi rend="s">37</hi> Thus, copies with the Explanation sheet bound between the
        Advertisement and 1E follow those where it is bound at the end of the book; the
        “earliness of provenance that could be established” (p. 61) serves as another
        criterion for the grouping.</note></p>
            <p>While the two untraced copies from Bentley’s list (Copies G and T) are excluded from
       the new census—which is keyed to color schemes and does not allow for the insertion of
       copies which are not available for inspection—four previously unknown colored copies
       of the edition of 1797 have here been fully documented for the first time (Copies I-7, I-10,
       I-15, III-1).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78" type="note">38</ref> To establish
the provenances of some of
       the copies must have been extremely difficult. This is illustrated by the fact that no less
       than three copies (I-7, I-12, I-14) are said to have belonged, at one time or the other, to
       just one collector, A. Edward Newton.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79"
type="note">39</ref> Though—in
       the authors’ own words—“there are likely to be errors” (p. 62) in the
       lists of ownerships which they provide, they have dealt admirably with this task. Also, the
       minute descriptions of the bindings, page sizes, and collations which are supplied for each
       copy leave nothing to be desired. Like the table of engraved designs, this census is another
       piece of competent work. <note id="n78"><hi rend="s">38</hi> Most probably, however, one will
        have to identify Bentley’s untraced Copy T with Copy I-7 of the new census. The
        latter was “<hi rend="i">perhaps</hi> acquired by A. Edward Newton” (p. 65) before
        it passed through the hands of Mrs. George E. Edmunds to the Detroit Institute of Arts in
        January 1927, and Copy T is “untraced” since it was sold from the library of A.
        Edward Newton in May 1926. Bentley quotes the sale catalogue as stating that in this copy
        the “text has been ruled throughout” (Anderson Galleries, 29 May 1926, lot 25; see
        Bentley, suppl. 1977-78, p. 150). This is in keeping with the “most distinctive
        feature” of the Detroit copy, viz. “that the text on all the pages has been
        framed, not very neatly, in single or double lines of unpleasing violet ink . . . . Titles
        are single, double or triple overlined and underlined” (p. 65). For references to the
        Moss-Bentley Copy G see pp. 53, 61, and 92, n. 81, in the present edition; this copy has now
        been located in the collection of the Lutheran Church in America by Thomas V. Lange, and has
        been placed as copy I-12A in the 1980 census (see “A Rediscovered Colored Copy of
        Young’s ‘Night Thoughts,’” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, 15
        [1981-1982], 134-36).</note>
	<note id="n79"><hi rend="s">39</hi> Today, there are three copies, one of each type of
        coloring, at Harvard, and with two copies each the Paul Mellon collection, the Rosenwald
        collection, and the <corr type="emend">Pierpont Morgan Library</corr> also provide the opportunity to study different
        copies side by side (see p. 62).</note></p>
            <p>At the end of the introductory essay readers will find a “Checklist of Studies and
       Reproductions” with short commentaries for many of the ninety-six entries (pp. 72-84). A
       classed bibliography like this, arranged chronologically, is useful primarily because it
       reflects something of the history of the reception of the <hi rend="i">NT</hi> illustrations
       in Blake criticism. This checklist, like all such lists, does not really include
       “every” relevant “published study” as the compilers claim (see p. 72).
       But just the same the list certainly does facilitate research on Blake’s <hi rend="i">NT</hi>, as I
have found myself when preparing this review.</p>
            <p>At this point, and before an attempt is made to sum up the results, a word on book
       production may be in order. A large format type face which is as legible as it is well
       designed has been employed for the printing of the text, and the lavish layout of the
       introduction leaves those beautiful wide margins to which we are no longer accustomed. The
       disastrous effect of the creamy paper for pictorial printing has been noted above, but the
       same paper is excellent for the text. Misprints are few, and only the binding of these
       volumes might not have been designed for such heavy stuff.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n80" type="note">40</ref> Clarendon Press has possibly been the most active and important publisher
for
       Blake books in recent years, and it hardly needs to be mentioned that they have produced
       books which show both “the full elaboration of colour-printing” and the
       “accuracy [of] fine-screen offset lithography” in plain black and white.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81" type="note">41</ref> All the same it is to be regreted that the results
       achieved in the quality of reproduction for the first complete edition of William
       Blake’s <hi rend="i">NT</hi> will not figure as a page of glory in the annals of this
       distinguished firm. <note id="n80"><hi rend="s">40</hi> After only a few days of (careful)
         use my copy showed cracking in the front joints. The following typographical errors ought
         to be corrected: 
		<q> p. 4, l. 31: read 24 June, instead of 23 June;<lb/>
 p. 11, l. 19 and
          passim: read Table of Engraved Designs, instead of Table of Designs;<lb/>
 p. 30, l. 37:
          read Fig. 6, instead of Fig. 7;<lb/>
 p. 31, l. 11: read 33. <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 119,
          instead of 33. 119;<lb/>
 p. 63, l. 2: while Richard Edwards was born in 1768, his and his
          elder brothers’ father, William Edwards, probably was not born in the same
          year;<lb/>
 p. 73, l. 14 (2): read pp. 401-2, instead of pp. 401-3;<lb/>
 p. 73, l. 17 (3):
          read i. 139-44, instead of i. 139-40;<lb/>
 p. 79, l. 13 (43): my copy of Lister’s
          biography gives 1968, not 1969 as the year of publication;<lb/>
 p. 87, n. 20: even from
          the reproduction it is evident that the transcription must read “WA White/28 March 19
          [ ]/of M.J. Perry,” not just “M.P.”;<lb/>
 p. 90, n. 55: read 1516, instead
          of 1616; Grünewald was a contemporary of Raphael and Dürer, not Rubens or
          Rembrandt. </q></note>
	<note id="n81"><hi rend="s">41</hi> Nicolas Barker, <hi rend="i">The Oxford University Press
         and the Spread of Learning 1478-1978: An Illustrated History</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press,
        1978), p. 56.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Complaint</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The introductory essay, as a whole, does not really introduce the reader to the 537
       watercolors which—thus at least I suspected—are its designated object. Instead,
       the essay rather serves to trace the development of the forty-three engravings for
       Young’s <hi rend="i">NT.</hi> Though the basic information on the outward
       circumstances of the production of the water color designs, on their subsequent history, and
       on their preservation is all there, a curious disproportion caused most of the text to be
       occupied with bibliographic material relating to the engraved version of the designs.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82" type="note">42</ref> Though no doubt much is added here to our
knowledge, it is
       a bit of a disappointment if, after all these years of study on the editors’ side, and
       after all these years of waiting on the side of their Blakean audience, we are still left
       with the more important questions concerning the iconology, style, and aesthetic 
<corr type="emend">achievement</corr>
       of this series of illustrations. By the time the commentary appears in print, all this may
       eventually be forgotten, and yet I maintain that much of what has now been published unter
       the misleading title of an introduction would have made a splendid appendix. It offers
       answers to the sort of chalcographic questions which the student of the water color designs
       and the general reader are likely to ask not in the first but in the last place. 
<note id="n82"><hi rend="s">42</hi> Whereas there are only about twenty-one pages concerning the
        water colors and the supposedly preparatory drawings, some forty-five pages deal exclusively
        with the printed version and its colored copies.</note></p>
            <p>That this edition will nevertheless become a tool of major importance for the study of
       Blake’s art and its symbolic meaning is beyond doubt, and I hope that the very
       copiousness of my notes on both text and plates of the <hi rend="i">Complete Edition</hi>
       will convey 
<pb id="p16-137" n="137"/>
something of this importance. At the same time I
       firmly believe that an irretrievable chance has been wasted as regards the overall quality,
       the potential usefulness, and the reliability of this tool. The editors deserve our gratitude
       for finally making available to a larger public these riches which were formerly hidden away
       in the unwieldy boxes at the British Museum Print Room. Yet gratitude is mingled with
       resentment for the editors’ and publisher’s sheer carelessness. As has been
       demonstrated above, it is hard to believe that any serious and responsible attempt has been
       made to properly check the proofs of the reproductions against the originals while seeing
       these volumes through the press.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83"
type="note">43</ref> Even today their
       production has been very costly; it is self-evident that in all likelihood a publication
       project of this scope for the <hi rend="i">NT</hi> series will not likely be possible again
       for at least half a century. During this time Blake scholars will have to work with this
       edition or none at all, and I cannot do otherwise than blame those who did not see to it that
       libraries and prospective private buyers get the very best that is to be achieved with modern
       printing techniques. More than 180 years after the initial publication of Edward’s
       selection from the complete series, Blake’s illustrations for Edward Young’s
        <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> remain ill-fated, and this to an extent they certainly do
       not deserve.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84" type="note">44</ref>
	<note id="n83"><hi rend="s">43</hi> It is not that I expected a Trianon Press facsimile of so
        large a number of designs, not even at $365. How much closer one can get to the original
        colors with the ordinary offset processes and at a moderate price is to be seen in various
        cheap volumes with reproductions from Blake’s work such as the Dover <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>,
the OUP <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, and
        especially the sixteen color plates in the 1972 Gray exhibition handbook. See William Blake,
         <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (New York, N. Y.: Dover Publications, 1971); <hi rend="i">Songs
of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes (London: Oxford
        University Press, 1970); <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, ed. Geoffrey
        Keynes (London and New York: Oxford University Press, 1975); and Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">William
Blake’s Water-Colour Designs for the Poems of Thomas Gray</hi>
        (London: Methuen, 1972). The plates for three of these books have of course been printed by
        Trianon Press, but in six-, seven- and eight-color offset, without the stencil coloring by
        hand which is known from the genuine facsimiles produced for the Blake Trust.</note>
	<note id="n84"><hi rend="s">44</hi> Many years ago, when this journal was still known as the
         <hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi>, one of the editors of the book now under review entered a
        discussion with the following “intellectual spears”: “Dialogue is difficult,
        even with disputants who are thoroughly conversant with the issues and evidence, if their
        overriding concern is to vindicate themselves rather than to correct error whatever its
        origin. Strenuous encounter magnifies the danger, but mildness is no more reliable guarantee
        against indulgence in selfhood. Correspondents of the <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>
        must believe that a number of essential truths in Blake’s art can be identified and
        that assertions about them can be evaluated. When the question at issue has a markedly
        empirical dimension a scholar must be prepared to lay out all his evidence for inspection.
        Most Blakeists would agree with these principles, at least in theory.” (John E. Grant,
        “Mother of Invention, Father in Drag, or Observations on the Methodology that Brought
        About these Deplorable Conditions and What Then is to be Done,” <hi rend="i">Blake
         Newsletter</hi>, 2 [1968], 29). My review of the <hi rend="i">Complete Edition</hi> of
        Blake’s <hi rend="i">NT</hi> illustrations is controversial, but I have tried to
        adhere to Grant’s principles and to lay out the evidence as far as even a long review
        article allows for that. And I surely hope that readers will find I have done so not merely
        in theory, but in practice.</note></p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p16-138-139" n="138-139" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
