<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.2.page</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">T. V. F. Brogan, English Versification, 1570-1980: A Reference Guide with a
Global Appendix</title>
        <author n="Page">Judith W. Page</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Krzysztof Z. Cieszkowski</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Christina Shuttleworth Kraus</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Judith W. Page</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Thomas A. Vogler</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-2-0010">
        <pb id="p16-125" n="125"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">T. V. F. Brogan. <hi rend="b">English Versification, 1570-1980: A Reference
Guide with
        a Global Appendix.</hi> Baltimore: The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1981. 794 pp.
       $47.50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Judith W.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Page</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>T V. F. Brogan’s <hi rend="i">English Versification, 1570-1980</hi> is a welcome
      reference guide that will help students and researchers plow through the overgrown field of
      versification, defined here as the study of the rhythmical elements and structures of poetry.
      In this thick volume, Brogan organizes works on English versification according to theoretical
      subjects such as sound, syntax, and meter. In addition to the clearly outlined table of
      contents, a global appendix, indexes arranged by poet and author, and generous
      cross-references make the guide readily accessible for research into any component of verse
      theory, from particular studies of Blake to general studies of the role of syntax in
      versification.</p>
          <p>The book is valuable not only because of the author’s painstaking efforts of
      organization and consolidation, but also because of his firm grasp of the history of
      versification and of the theoretical importance of linguistics in the field. In his general
      introduction, in the introductions to various subjects, and in the evaluative descriptions of
      many of the works cited, Brogan recognizes and confronts the historical problems of
      versification: imprecise thinking and confused terminology. According to Brogan, this
      theoretical confusion developed because theorists before the twentieth century did not
      understand the place of language in versification. But this understanding is essential, since
      the increased patterning of verse organizes language on a higher level: “Verse-patterning
      is contrived out of—superimposed upon yet also generated inductively from—the
      only available elements, the natural phonological features of each particular language”
      (xix). Brogan’s emphasis on a sound linguistic basis for verse theory informs his
      judgments of particular entries and, in my opinion, gives credence to his evaluations.</p>
          <p>As far as I can tell, too, Brogan includes and fairly evaluates all of the major works in
      versification, from the earliest theorists through the generative metrists of the 1970s. In
      his evaluation of T. S. Omond’s <hi rend="i">English Metrists</hi> (Oxford, 1921),
      Brogan restates the need for a modern evaluative bibliography for versification. Brogan also
      rightly identifies the weakness of George Saintsbury’s influential <hi rend="i">History
       of English Prosody</hi> (3 vols., London, 1906-10) as a complete lack of a consistent theory,
      which makes the book “one of the most extravagant irrelevancies in criticism” even
      though it is “a great monolith of wide and informed reading” (p. 10). Brogan
      outlines major works and schools in modern English verse theory, including those of the
      structural linguists Seymour Chatman and Roger Fowler and the generative metrists Morris
      Halle, S. Jay Keyser, and Paul Kiparsky. He sees Marina Tarlinskaja’s <hi rend="i">English Verse:
Theory and History</hi> (The Hague, 1976) as “the most extensive and the
      most important study of English verse-structure produced in this century” (p. 282),
      because Tarlinskaja is comprehensive (dealing with verse from the thirteenth to the nineteenth
      centuries) and thorough (with the aid of a computer inventory of 100,000 lines).</p>
          <p>The major Romantic poets and their interpreters are well represented in <hi rend="i">English
       Versification.</hi> For instance, Brogan summarizes Wordsworth’s comments on meter in
      the 1800 Preface to <hi rend="i">Lyrical Ballads</hi> and Coleridge’s
      “answer” to them in Chapter 18 of the <hi rend="i">Biographia.</hi> In his comments
      on Wordsworth, Brogan could have been more thorough, though. Wordsworth deserves more credit
      as a forward-looking theorist, aware of the psychological effects of meter, not just meter as
      a “mild narcotic” (p. 163) but also meter as a means by which the poet can heighten
      and intensify emotion. In his entry under W. J. B. Owen’s “The Theory of
      Meter” from <hi rend="i">Wordsworth as Critic</hi> (Toronto, 1969), Brogan quotes and
      seems to accept at face value Owen’s comments that “‘the prose parts of
      Wordsworth’s blank verse, especially, appear to gain no advantage from being in
      meter’” (p. 157). Such a questionable statement at least needs to be read
      alongside Wordsworth’s own assertion 
<pb id="p16-126" n="126"/>
in the Preface
      “that of two descriptions either of passions, manners, or characters, each of them
      equally well executed, the one in prose and the other in verse, the verse will be read a
      hundred times where the prose is read once.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36"
type="note">1</ref> The
      pleasure provided by the meter (in blank verse, the rhymthmical repetition of the iambic
      pattern) may thus interact with and intensify the poetry. <note id="n36"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi
rend="i"> The Prose Works of William Wordsworth</hi>, ed. W. J. B. Owen and Jane
       Worthington Smyser (Oxford: Clarendon, 1974), I, 150.</note></p>
          <p>Blake presents us with more questions than does Wordsworth. His comments on versification
      consist of a few aphorisms, with nothing as systematic even as the paragraphs from the
      Preface. And whereas Wordsworth works within the tradition of accentual-syllabic verse,
      Blake’s poetry does not flow easily into this mainstream. <hi rend="i">English
       Versification</hi> will be useful to the student who wants to investigate the principles
      behind or follow through on hunches about Blake’s versification. Suppose that someone
      has been working on the idea that the rhythmical principle of Blake’s prophecies is
      based on syntactical patterns. Brogan’s descriptions and evaluations of studies written
      on the role of syntax in versification under the category “Syntax and Grammar”
      should direct that person to relevant readings. Another useful category for the Blake
      researcher would be “Visual (Typographic) Structures.” Although many of the entries
      deal with modern “concrete poetry” and Renaissance “pattern poetry,”
      insights into both of these could enhance the study of Blake’s composite art.</p>
          <p>Furthermore, a researcher can turn to the index and immediately find a listing of works
      specifically on Blake’s versification or works in which Blake may be mentioned. From
      these entries, the researcher can piece together a historical survey of the writings and
      determine what kinds of things have been written. Brogan summarizes and evaluates some of the
      works, including Alicia Ostriker’s <hi rend="i">Vision and Verse in William Blake</hi>
      (Madison, 1965), the only book-length study of Blake’s versification. Brogan sees
      Ostriker’s book as a “groundbreaking survey” (p. 349) but claims that it is
      methodologically faulty; he rightly implies that the “concrete foundation” (p. 349)
      will have to include a more precise theoretical structure. Other Blake entries include studies
      that mention or begin to investigate the influence of music and the visual arts on
      Blake’s metrical styles. But the big question remains: what principle is behind the
      rhythmical structures of Blake’s poetry? Quantities, syntax, stress, all of the above,
      none of the above? This question and its answers will have to be based on an understanding of
      the history and theory of English versification.</p>
          <p>Brogan’s <hi rend="i">English Versification</hi> can help to strengthen this basis.
      Brogan succeeds in his intentions of offering a single view of the field, of sketching its
      historical contour, and, potentially, of generating new ideas and works about versification in
      the future. Anyone interested in the verse structures of Blake’s—or any
      poet’s—“sweet forms” should hurry to this worthy guide.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
