<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.2.labelle</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">R. J. Shroyer, ed., Johann Caspar Lavater, Aphorisms on Man (1788)</title>
        <author n="La Belle">Jenijoy La Belle</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Krzysztof Z. Cieszkowski</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Christina Shuttleworth Kraus</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Judith W. Page</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Thomas A. Vogler</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
	<pb id="p16-126" n="126"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-2-0010">
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Johann Caspar Lavater. <hi rend="b">Aphorisms on Man (1788). A Facsimile</hi>
       Reproduction of William Blake’s Copy of the First English Edition with an Introduction
       by R. J. Shroyer. Delmar, New York: Scholars’ Facsimiles &amp; Reprints, 1980. xxxiii
       + 227 pp. (With one illus.). $22.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Jenijoy</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">La Belle</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The business of making facsimiles of Blake’s illuminated books has a long and
      fascinating history, beginning with John Camden Hotten’s edition of <hi rend="i">The
       Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> in 1868 and culminating in recent years with the splendid
      work of the William Blake Trust. There are of course many beautiful copies of the illuminated
      books still awaiting appropriate replication, but we seem to have reached a point in Blake
      studies where the reproduction of Blake’s pictorially less impressive works can also
      find an audience. Thanks to R. J. Shroyer and Scholars’ Facsimiles &amp; Reprints, a
      reproduction of the copy of Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man</hi> annotated by
      Blake is now available. Since there are at least three typographic editions of the
       annotations,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">1</ref> the audience for
such a work must 
<pb id="p16-127" n="127"/>
be fairly limited. Yet, in the pages of this journal, it is
difficult
      to decry such a publication. A facsimile edition certainly recommends itself to dedicated
      Blake scholars. <note id="n37"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Complete Writings</hi>, ed.
Geoffrey Keynes (London: Oxford Univ. Press,
       1966), pp. 65-88; <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V.
       Erdman (Garden City, New York: Doubleday, 1965), pp. 572-90; <hi rend="i">William
        Blake’s Writings</hi>, ed. G. E. Bentley, Jr. (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1978), II,
       1350-87. A new edition of Erdman’s text is forthcoming, one which has been carefully
       collated in galley proof against the original volume in the Huntington Library.</note></p>
          <p>Blake apparently annotated his copy of the <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> shortly after its
      publication in 1788. Although the typographic editions of these annotations all reprint the
      parts of Lavater’s text most essential for understanding Blake’s commentary, the
      entire 643 aphorisms have not been reprinted for over a hundred years, and they have never
      before been printed in full in conjunction with Blake’s marginalia. Scholars have long
      recognized the significance of Blake’s responses to Lavater at a crucial early point in
      the development of Blake’s ideas on man, society, and God. The directness and brevity
      of the annotations help to make them capsule distillations of concepts we find more
      expansively and complexly woven through the fabric of Blake’s poetry. For anyone eager
      to produce a facsimile edition of one of Blake’s annotated books, surely
      Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> is a good first choice.</p>
          <p>Shroyer’s twenty-eight page introduction is the best part of this book. He does a
      good job of presenting, in a surprisingly lively manner, essential information about Lavater,
      Henry Fuseli (the translator of the aphorisms and a close friend of their author), and
      bibliographical details concerning the editions of the book and Blake’s annotations.
      These materials are just what is wanted in an introduction to a facsimile edition. Although
      Shroyer’s discussion of Lavater’s work on physiognomy is a bit tangential to
      this edition, it contributes to the historical context in which Shroyer sets the aphorisms.
      The introduction remains strong when it moves into such detailed matters as the question of
      Fuseli’s possible rewritings of Lavater’s work. Fuseli made his translation from
      a now lost manuscript and included some sixty-five aphorisms, by Shroyer’s count, that
      have no “close matches” with the German editions of the <hi rend="i">Regeln</hi> of
      1787 and 1788. Shroyer offers a convincing explanation of how this came about, based on the
      fair assumption that Lavater himself (having caught what Shroyer calls “gnomic
      fever”) revised his maxims between the writing of the manuscript he sent to England and
      the publication of the German editions. One of the strengths of the introduction is that
      Shroyer is concerned with Lavater’s works in their own right before he plunges into
      Blake’s annotations.</p>
          <p>In the last few pages of his introduction, Shroyer surveys some of Blake’s more
      significant annotations to Lavater and points out the basic concepts they embody.
      Blake’s long concluding comment is quoted, including seven or eight words thoroughly
      deleted with circular pen strokes in the original. Shroyer’s transcription of this
      deleted passage is identical to Erdman’s text: “&amp; they converse with the
      spirit of God.” Bentley’s reconstruction, “&amp; thus are either good or
       Evil,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">2</ref> makes a completely
different conclusion to
      the passage. The only evidence I can see in the original at the Huntington Library for either
      reading is the pattern of ascenders and descenders not obscured by Blake’s deletion
      lines. These fragmentary pieces of evidence tend to give more support to Bentley’s
      reading than to Erdman’s. I suspect, however, that we will never be sure of any
      reading, unless computer-enhanced photography can give us a definitive answer. 
<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i"> Poetry and Prose of Blake</hi>, ed. Erdman, p. 590; <hi rend="i">Blake’s
        Writings</hi>, ed. Bentley, II, 1386.</note></p>
          <p>Shroyer comments sensibly on the structural and thematic relationships between the Lavater
      annotations and Blake’s other writings of the late 1780s and early 1790s. He also makes
      an interesting suggestion (p. xxiii) that there is a more than accidental similarity between
      the frontispiece that Blake engraved after Fuseli’s design for the English edition of
      the <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> and the frontispiece to <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi>
      The remarks on Lavater’s presence in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>
      and Blake’s later poems are less compelling and too brief to be convincing. Shroyer
      emphasizes Lavater’s membership with Swedenborg in the party of repressive moralizers
      scorned by Blake; but we need more evidence for this than Shroyer has room to provide, and
      surely Blake’s possible criticisms of Lavater must be balanced by the numerous
      indications, provided throughout the annotations, of Blake’s sympathies with
      Lavater’s energetic humanism.</p>
          <p>After such a promising introduction, the facsimile itself is a distinct
      disappointment—or, rather, an indistinct disappointment because of the soft-focus
      fuzziness it gives to Blake’s fine and clear penmanship.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n39" type="note">3</ref> Blake’s copy of the aphorisms is reproduced slightly larger than the
      original. The photographic process used was apparently one of those that register only black
      or white, converting any middle tones in one direction or the other. As a result, a disturbing
      number of Blake’s pen strokes are lost or fragmented into vague rows of dots and
      dashes. The problem here is not merely aesthetic, but textual. <note id="n39"><hi rend="s">3</hi> All
comments on the accuracy of the facsimile are based on a comparison between it
       and the original volume in the Huntington Library.</note></p>
          <p>In his introduction Shroyer notes that neither the Keynes nor the Erdman edition is
      “wholly satisfactory” in its rendering of Blake’s underlinings of
      Lavater’s text. He then claims that “this facsimile . . . should go a long way
      toward alerting the student to such problems and suggesting some answers” (p. xvii).
      Unfortunately, this facsimile creates a good many problems and solves few. Indeed, one must
      use the Keynes, Erdman, or Bentley text as a constant guide while attempting to read
      Shroyer’s reproductions. For example, in aphorism no. 3 Blake’s underlining of
      the penultimate line is signalled only by a few easily overlooked dots; the underlining of the
      last line here (and in no. 424) is not indicated at all. In the original, the pen strokes are
      fine but unmistakably clear. Blake’s X next to aphorism no. 21 is reduced to a large T
      and makes it seem as though it were the first letter of the non word, “Tuneasy.” The
      X next to the end of no. 619 disappears altogether. Blake wrote two large exclamation points
      following aphorism no. 157. In the facsimile, these become four widely spaced dots that look
      like nothing more than accidental flyspecks. And at the end of no. 309, Blake’s
      question mark becomes a colon. The vertical line in pencil next to no. 285 does not appear at
      all in the facsimile, and the long pencil note on no. 532 is illegible. The word
      “Admirable!” written vertically next to aphorism no. 20 reproduces fairly well, but
      nowhere does Shroyer point out that it is 
<pb id="p16-128" n="128"/>
written in pencil. Nor
      does he identify other annotations in pencil or in a light brown ink quite distinct from the
      black ink of the majority of the annotations. Blake’s editors have attributed some of
      these annotations to a hand other than Blake’s, and surely this is a matter Shroyer
      should have taken up in his introduction. He cannot be held responsible for his
      publisher’s failures in reproducing the original, but even if he had expected high
      quality photographic work he should have realized the necessity for identifying different inks
      and different hands.</p>
          <p>Another difficulty not overcome by the publisher is the presence of annotations very close
      to the spine of the book. Apparently the volume could not be opened wide enough to expose such
      annotations completely to the camera. As a result, it seems as though Blake wrote
      “ellent” next to aphorism no. 40; in the original, “Excellent” is clear
      and fully present. The lengthy annotations in the inner margins of aphorisms nos. 248, 342,
      532, 533, and 605 are converted to odd bits and pieces. Once again, the reader must return to
      typographic texts in order to make sense of the facsimile.</p>
          <p>Professor Shroyer has indicated in correspondence<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n40" type="note">4</ref> that
      the <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man</hi> is the first volume in a proposed series of facsimiles
      of Blake’s annotated books. Future volumes will have full transcriptions of the
      annotations. These transcriptions, if accompanied by appropriate notes on such matters as
      differences in ink, should go a long way toward solving some of the problems burdening the 
<hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> facsimile. One can only hope that a solid scholar like Shroyer will
      be better served by his publisher in prospective volumes, and that we can use them with full
      confidence in their accuracy and completeness. As Blake wrote, “He who would do good to
      another, must do it in Minute Particulars.” <note id="n40"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Letter
       from R. J. Shroyer to Nelson Hilton, 6 May 1981.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
