<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.2.reiman</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The Derivation and Meaning of “Ololon”</title>
        <author n="Reiman">Donald H. Reiman</author>
        <author n="Kraus">Christina Shuttleworth Kraus</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Krzysztof Z. Cieszkowski</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Christina Shuttleworth Kraus</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Judith W. Page</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Thomas A. Vogler</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
      <pb id="p16-82" n="82"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-2-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">THE DERIVATION AND MEANING OF “OLOLON”</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">DONALD H.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">REIMAN</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
          <hi rend="b">AND</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">CHRISTINA SHUTTLEWORTH</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">KRAUS</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>Northrop Frye suggested that the name Ololon in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> derives from
     “ululation,” a word Blake himself uses in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">1</ref> In both English and Latin (from which the English words come
     directly), <hi rend="i">ululate</hi> means to howl, wail, or lament, and <hi rend="i">ululation</hi>
either a howl, wail, or cry of lamentation, or the action of howling or
     wailing (<hi rend="i">OED</hi>; Lewis &amp; Short, <hi rend="i">A Latin Dictionary</hi>).
      <note id="n10"><hi rend="s">1</hi> <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University
Press, 1947), p. 143; cf.
       <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> 4:62.</note></p>
        <p>Frye’s etymology has gone generally unchallenged, though two scholars mention (in
     passing) what is clearly the single, direct origin of the name. Peter F. Fisher remarks simply
     that Ololon was “a name probably derived from a Greek word (ὀλολύζειν) which signified the
     crying of women to the gods.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">2</ref>
Harold Bloom also notes
                    that Ololon is from ὀλολύζειν, but he misinterprets the Greek and follows Frye
in discussing
     “the lamentation of women to the gods.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12"
type="note">3</ref> Grief
                    and mourning, however, may not be the aspects of ὀλολύζειν that Blake wished to
suggest. As defined
                    in Liddell and Scott’s <hi rend="i">Greek-English Lexicon</hi> (1961), the verb
ὀλολύζειν,
                    with the related words ὀλολυγών and ὀλολυγαῖος, applies to “women
crying aloud to the gods in
     prayer or thanksgiving,” to “the cries of goddesses,” and to “women crying
     to the gods . . . mostly in sign of joy.” A survey of classical uses of the word from
     Homer (e.g., <hi rend="i">Od.</hi> 22.411, <hi rend="i">Il.</hi> 6.301) to Aristophanes (e.g.,
      <hi rend="i">Birds</hi> 222, <hi rend="i">Knights</hi> 1327) and the tragedians indicates not
     only that the word has jubilant connotations, but that it was sometimes used in specific
     opposition to a cry of lament. This is particularly evident in a scene from Euripides’
      <hi rend="i">Medea</hi>, in which a messenger describes Creusa’s death from poison and
     her handmaiden’s reaction to it. The servant initially thinks it a portent from the
     gods: 
	<q>καί τις γεραιὰ προσπόλων, δόξασά που<lb/>
         ἢ Πανὸς ὀργὰς ἢ τινὸς θεῶν μολεῖν,<lb/>
         ἀνωλόλυξε . . .<lb/>
<lb/>
 An aged woman servant who, I take it, thought This was some
      seizure of Pan or another god, Cried out, “God bless us” . . . </q>
But, as she
          realizes what is happening, she howls in terror: 
		<q><corr type="emend">εἶτ᾽</corr>
ἀντίμολπον ἧκεν ὀλολυγῆς μέγαν<lb/>
                        κωκυτόν. . . .<lb/>
<lb/>
 Then she raised a
      different cry from that “God bless us,”<lb/>
 A huge shriek . . . <ref target="n13" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Translation by Rex Warner, in <hi rend="i">The Complete
        Greek Tragedies</hi>, eds. David Grene and Richmond Lattimore (Chicago: University of
       Chicago Press, 1959), III, 99.</note></q>
Her second cry, a κωκυτός, <hi rend="i">is</hi> a wail
of grief (the hellish river Cocytus
                    takes its name therefrom), and Euripides is careful to stress, with his
ἀντίμολπον . . . ὀλολυγῆς
     (“sounding different from ululation”), the change in the nature of the outburst.
      <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">2</hi> <hi rend="i">The Valley of Vision: Blake as Prophet and
Revolutionary</hi> (Toronto:
      University of Toronto Press, 1961), p. 248. Northrop Frye in his “Editor’s
      Preface” calls attention to Fisher’s great command of languages.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">3</hi> <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse: A Study in Poetic Argument</hi>
(Ithaca: Cornell
      University Press, 1970), p. 332.</note></p>
        <p>There is a secondary meaning of ὀλολύζειν which may have influenced Blake in the choice
of a name
     for his character. Johannes Scapula’s sixteenth-century <hi rend="i">Lexicon
      Graeco-Latinum</hi>, the standard Greek lexicon of Blake’s day (used, for example, by
     Shelley and members of his circle in their Greek studies), gives, along with the earlier
     meanings of the verb, the Aristotelian definition of ὀλολυγών: <hi rend="i">Ululatus: et
      peculiariter is quem mares ranae edunt, cum foeminas ad coitum vocant</hi> (I. 1816:
     “out-cry: and particularly that which male frogs emit when they 
<pb id="p16-83" n="83"/>
     call the females to coitus”).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">5</ref>
Although this is a
     technical term which applies to the male of the species—in contrast to the literary
     ὀλολύζειν, which is an exclusively female activity<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n15" type="note">6</ref>—it
     is possible that Blake read Scapula and chose to incorporate sexual connotations into his
     Ololon, perhaps overlooking the masculine emphasis that appears only in <hi rend="i">mares</hi>
                    of the Latin definition. Ὀλολυγών, which transliterates as 
<hi rend="i">ololugōn</hi>, is
     the form of the word closest to the name Blake selects: he need only drop the penultimate
     syllable to arrive at “Ololon.” <note id="n14"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Cf. Aristotle, 
<hi rend="i">Historia Animalium</hi> 536<hi rend="s">a</hi>11, and Aelianus, <hi rend="i">De
       Natura Animalium</hi>, 9.13.</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Cf. Aeschylus, <hi rend="i">Agamemnon</hi>, 594-95: καὶ
γυναικείῳ νόμῳ / ὀλολυγμὸν ἄλλος ἄλλοθεν κατὰ πτόλιν
ἔλασκον ευφημοῦντες (“and throughout all the quarters of the city, in woman’s wont,
they raised
      a shout of gladsome praise”; trans. H. Weir-Smith, Loeb Classical Library edition of
      Aeschylus [Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1963], II, 53).</note></p>
        <p>Although Blake did not enjoy a formal education, he did study foreign languages and
     literatures. His library certainly contained books in French and Italian, and Frederick Tatham
     maintained that Blake also owned Hebrew, Latin, and Greek texts.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n16" type="note">7</ref> In 1803, Blake wrote to his brother James that the Greek lessons which he was
taking
     from William Hayley were progressing well: “I go on Merrily with my Greek &amp; Latin; am
     very sorry that I did not begin to learn languages early in life as I find it very Easy . . . .
     I read Greek as fluently as an Oxford scholar &amp; the Testament is my chief master:
     astonishing indeed is the English Translation, it is almost word for word. . . .”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">8</ref> Blake’s own estimation of his fluency may be
taken
     with a grain of salt (the two men apparently confined their studies to the New Testament and to
     collating Cowper’s Homer<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">9</ref>), but
one may assume that
     the poet had a working knowledge of classical Greek and doubtless made use of a Greek
     lexicon—in all likelihood Scapula’s. He could, therefore, have been aware of the
     range of meaning and the subtle ramifications thereof that the word ὀλολύζειν suggests for the
     character he creates. <note id="n16"><hi rend="s">7</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., and Martin K.
      Nurmi, <hi rend="i">A Blake Bibliography</hi> (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press,
      1964), pp. 195-212. The Tatham letter of 8 June 1864 is printed in Geoffrey Keynes’s
      “Blake’s Library” (<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 6 November
      1959, p. 648).</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Blake to James Blake, 30 January 1803; in Geoffrey Keynes,
      ed., <hi rend="i">The Letters of William Blake</hi> (Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University
      Press, 1968), pp. 65-66.</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William
      Blake</hi>, ed. Ruthven Todd (London: J. M. Dent &amp; Sons Ltd., 1942), p. 146, quotes a
      letter dated 8 Nov. 1801 from Hayley to the Rev. John Johnson describing how he and Blake
      “read every evening that copy of [Cowper’s] Iliad . . . comparing it with the
      first edition and with the Greek as we proceed.”</note></p>
        <p>How appropriate, then, is this derivation of “Ololon” for the Blakean character and
     for <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> as a whole? Susan Fox’s study of the poem, <hi rend="i">Poetic Form in
Blake’s “Milton”</hi> (Princeton University Press, 1976)
     provides insight into Ololon’s nature and into her relations with the poet-character
      Milton.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">10</ref> Accepting Fox’s
outline of the structure
     and action of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, we suggest that there are additional nuances in the
     poem when one takes into account the Greek derivation and meanings of the name
     “Ololon.” <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">10</hi> See also John Howard, <hi rend="i">Blake’s
“Milton”: A Study in the Selfhood</hi> (Rutherford, N. J.:
      Fairleigh Dickinson University Press, 1976), and Kay Parkhurst Easson and Roger R. Easson in
      their Shambhala edition of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (1978).</note></p>
        <p>When Ololon first appears in Book I (Plate 21),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n20" type="note">11</ref> it is
     as a “sweet River, of milk &amp; liquid pearl” (21:15). At this point, Ololon is the
     lifegiving river of Eden—unconscious and undifferentiated sexuality—its qualities
     of “milk and liquid pearl” suggesting a union of the milk of women’s breasts
     and the pearly semen of the male.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21"
type="note">12</ref> But a crucial change in
     the status of Ololon takes place in Plate 21. On the “mild banks” of the river Ololon
     “dwelt those who Milton drove / Down into Ulro” (both grammar and context demand that
     we read “those . . . who” as the subject of “drove” and “Milton”
     as the object, driven “Down into Ulro”). As Ololon will ultimately be revealed to
     Blake-in-Felpham as human history (“the Woof of Six Thousand Years,” 42:15), we can
     infer from the varied descriptions of Ololon on Plate 21 that the river represents the flow of
     historical process, while “those” who dwell on its “mild banks” are
     individual historical figures and societies. In Eden, where all contraries are united, these
     embody both the potentialities and the past realizations of the historical process. Among them,
     therefore, are both the beings and forces who conditioned the historical John Milton in his
     failure to fulfill his potentiality (hence driving him to Ulro) and all unrealized
     potentialities in the idea of “Milton” awaiting redemption through incarnation:
     “they wept” and “The mountains” (identified as “the river’s
     living banks,” that is, the limiting parameters of historical necessity)
     “wail’d!” at the fate of Milton. Each dawn “the Family / Of Eden heard
     the lamentation” though “the clarions of day” soon “drowned the
     lamentations / And when night came . . . all refused to lament” (21:23-26). But the
     lamentation at dawn suffices to begin “Providence,” which Blake saw as the ambiguous
     intrusion of Eternity into Time.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Text and plate and line numbers are from <hi rend="i">The
       Poems of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman, commentary by Harold Bloom (Garden City, N.
      J.: Doubleday &amp; Co., Inc., 1968).</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Compare Shelley’s <hi rend="i">Epipsychidion</hi>, lines 568-72:
<q>
the wells<lb/>
 Which boil under our being’s
        inmost cells,<lb/>
 The fountains of our deepest life, shall be<lb/>
 Confused in
        passion’s golden purity,<lb/>
 As mountain-springs under the morning Sun. </q>
(As the
       note in the Norton Critical Edition of <hi rend="i">Shelley’s Poetry and Prose</hi>
       (p. 387) points out, the explicit sexual images here are accompanied by an allusion to the
       myth of Alpheus and Arethusa.) See also Fox, <hi rend="i">Poetic Form</hi>, p. 216, fn.
       16.
                    </note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">13</hi> For a suggestion of some of the complexities, see S. Foster
      Damon, <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary</hi> (Providence: Brown University Press, 1965), pp.
      335-36.</note></p>
        <p>When the laments reach “the Family Divine” and “the Cloud of Milton”
     stretches “over Europe,” the Four Zoas unite into the figure of “One Man”
     weeping over Ololon (21:39). Ololon then begins to “feel Pity” for Milton (21:54) and
     thereby breaks the unconscious unity of its self-contained Edenic state, incarnating through a
     series of transformations, beginning with a metamorphosis from river into the
     “Clouds” which accompany the manifestation of “One Man even Jesus”
     (21:58-60).</p>
        <p>In Book the Second, this composite group of clouds descends to Beulah, the “place where
     Contrarieties are equally True” (30:1). Their “descent” is not a qualitative
     one: as Fox notes, Beulah is not a lesser, but simply a different state from Eden.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">14</ref> Unlike the Edenic world of sexual union
between contraries,
     Beulah is incapable of accepting the potential stress of conflict between opposing essences. It
     is a world of protected, infantile sexuality and maternal love: “Beulah to its inhabitants
     appears . . . / As the beloved infant in his mother’s bosom round incircled”
     (30:10-11). As Ololon passes through this place, the inhabitants of Beulah lament, fearing the
     impending struggle of the final judgment as “they saw the Lord coming / In the Clouds of
     Ololon with Power &amp; Great Glory” (31:15-16). As the Clouds of Ololon pass through
     this moony world, they begin to lament with Beulah. The river of sexual union destabilizes and
     dissolves as it drifts through the half-realized realm of childish innocence<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">15</ref>—its contraries are separated, and Ololon, now split into
     distinguishable “Sons &amp; Daughters” (30:4), laments in a world in which mature
     sexual love is frustrated: “Men are sick with Love!” (31:62). <note id="n23"><hi rend="s">14</hi>
Fox, <hi rend="i">Poetic Form</hi>, pp. 9-10, 128 ff.</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Compare Shelley’s use of the hydrogen cycle in <hi rend="i">Prometheus
Unbound</hi>, II.ii.70-82.</note></p>
        <p>As “the Divine Voice was heard in the Songs of Beulah” (33:1 ff.), there comes a
     change in the quality of union from a “mild and gentle” state to a period of jealousy
     and strife: “now thou art terrible / In jealousy &amp; unlovely in my sight, because thou
     hast cruelly / Cut off my loves in fury till I have no love left for thee” (33:5-7). Yet a
     temporary answer to this pain of division <hi rend="i">is</hi> offered: the “Songs of
     Beulah in the Lamentations of Ololon” end with a promise of a renewal of self-effacing
     trust, “When the Sixfold Female” (the Emanations representing Milton’s wives
     and daughters) shall “relent” and “give / Her maidens to her 
<pb id="p16-84" n="84"/>
husband:
delighting in his delight” (33:14-18); “then &amp; then alone
     begins the happy Female joy, / As it is done in Beulah” (33:19-20). In the
     infantile/maternal state of Beulah, the female’s abnegation of self takes the form of
     nourishing the male by providing him with whatever he desires, “delighting in his
     delight.”</p>
        <p>This self-effacement, however, does not solve the problem posed by historic Milton’s
     descent to “Eternal Death.” Ololon must continue to journey until the potentialities
     inherent in the eternal idea of Milton reunite with the figure fixed by history, rejoining
     Milton’s aggressive maleness with the principle of selfless union hitherto possible to
     maleness only in the Edenic realm of potentiality. To that end, Ololon continues its descent
     into the generated world of the “Mundane Shell.” Reaching “rocky Albion,”
     it takes on a final incarnation in Blake’s own garden as “a Virgin of twelve
     years” (36:17).</p>
        <p>Ololon, now embodied as an unthreatening female Emanation, meets her ideal Spectre,
     “Milton,” now embodied in William Blake. After admitting to him that she has fostered
     false natural religion in her previous incarnations, she hears “Milton” declare the
     need for mutual annihilation and replies once again “in clouds of despair” (41:29).
     Then, the virgin “with a shriek” separates into six parts, splits “Away from
     Ololon” (i.e., the Eden potentiality), and flees “into the depths / of
     Milton’s Shadow” (42:3-6). The explosive chemistry of the union of Spectre and
     Emanation produces the vision of “One Man Jesus the Saviour,” wrapped in a garment
     “named the Woof of Six Thousand Years” (42:11, 15): in short, the union of the Divine
     Image of Man, clothed in the matrix of human history. This final action, occurring in the world
     of generation and yet not fully partaking of it, restores to Ololon the ideal unity of
     sexuality that had been its original nature in Eden. Now, however, its wholeness results not
     from complacent, unthinking acceptance of its potentiality but from self-conscious choice in
     the realm of actuality.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Milton</hi> is, among many other things, the story of a journey from a
     pre-sexual state through childhood/motherhood to the full awareness of adult sexual maturity.
     The union of male and female in the original river Ololon and the similar union in the final
     plate of the poem are both manifestations of a perfect fusion of contraries; only the last
     combination, however, which takes place within the Mundane Shell, redeems William Blake and,
     through him, mankind, existent within the Mundane Shell.</p>
        <p>If “Ololon” means, as we maintain, a cry of joy or a cry to the gods, then the
     “lamentations” attributed to manifestations of Ololon throughout the poem have a
     multiple significance. First, they are, even in the depths of despair, cries to the
     gods—i.e., to the powers of self-knowledge and self-sacrifice that will eventually
     destroy false natural religion and enable Ololon to recombine with Milton in a mutual
      redemption.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">16</ref> Secondly, on a
linguistic plane,
     Ololon’s journey represents a passage from meaning through nonsense to full meaning
     again. While in her river state, “Ololon” is both a cry to the Divine within humanity
     and an expression of sexuality. When she at last rediscovers her true nature, in the garden at
     Felpham, she is once again this combination of sexuality and joy. Her lamentations of
     Milton’s fate in Eden and in Beulah are, like her incarnation in Beulah in the form of
     clouds, incomplete. They do not represent Ololon’s true nature—until the female
     potentialities in her can be united with Milton, neither is she whole in any sense, nor has the
     full significance of her name unfolded. Finally, the fact that those lamentations that begin in
     Eden are replaced by the rejoicing implicit in Ololon’s name only within the Mundane
     Shell demonstrates again that Blake’s ideal state lies within the quotidian world of
     full human experience—not in some external heaven or realm of forms. 
<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Cf. the trusting cry of the despairing Trojan women in <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> 6, as they
plead with Athena: αἱ δ ὀλολυγῇ πᾶσαι Ἀθήνῃ χεῖρας ἀνέσχον (6.301:
“all the women, in a cry [<hi rend="i">ololugē</hi>] to Athena, lifted up their hands . . .
”).</note></p>
        <p>The etymology of “Ololon” reinforces the idea that the names Blake
     “coins” are neither arbitrary nor merely onomatopoeic, but have traditional
     historical or linguistic bases. And despite the uncompromising condemnation of the classics in
     the Preface to <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (later suppressed), the classical antecedents of
     “Ololon” indicate that Blake was at least interested enough in ancient secular
     literature to pursue the implications of a few words therefrom—more, perhaps, than have
     thus far been identified.</p>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p16-85" n="85" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
