<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.2.vogler</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Diana Hume George, Blake and Freud</title>
        <author n="Vogler">Thomas A. Vogler</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Krzysztof Z. Cieszkowski</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Christina Shuttleworth Kraus</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Judith W. Page</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Thomas A. Vogler</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
      <pb id="p16-121" n="121"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-2-0010">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Diana Hume George. <hi rend="b">Blake and Freud.</hi> Ithaca: Cornell
University Press,
       1980. $15.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Thomas A.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Vogler</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>There are several general issues in the basic conception of Diana Hume George’s book
      on Blake and Freud that are timely, significant, and promising, even though the book itself
      falls far short of fulfilling its promise. It is proposed as “a contribution to
      psychoanalytic theory and criticism” (17-18) in the form of an intertextual engagement
      between Freud and Blake, antagonists in a synchronic field of discourse. It is thus in
      different ways both a Blakean and a Freudian project, well worth the undertaking.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">1</ref> More conspicuously than most poets, Blake
situated his work
      among other texts which he cited, engaged in battle, parodied and attempted to transform or
      correct, so producing an intertextual construct constantly aware of the semiotic processes
      which both made the project possible and at the same time tried to inscribe it in the
      already-written code of the competing Urizenic system. Thus to read Freud—“as
      Blake read Milton, and with similar purposes” (69)—as the author whose works
      “constitute the <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> of the twentieth century” (66) could
      be a most fruitful way to engage the too-long-deferred relationships between these two
      authors, to go beyond the Jungians who have had their archetypal ways with Blake’s
      texts for so long, and to expand our growing awareness of the artistic and poetic dimensions
      of Freud’s contribution to literature. <note id="n26"><hi rend="s">1</hi> The only
       other comparable work I have come across in this area is Morris Dickstein’s study of
       the “influence” of Freud on Blake, which concentrates mainly on the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence
and of Experience</hi>: “The Price of Experience: Blake’s
       Reading of Freud,” in <hi rend="i">The Literary Freud: Mechanisms of Defense and the
        Poetic Will</hi>, Vol. 4 of the Psychiatry and the Humanities Series, ed. J. H. Smith (New
       Haven: Yale University Press, 1980).</note></p>
          <p>If there is anything distinctive about the discourse we call literature, and in that
      discourse especially true of Blake, it is that <hi rend="i">how</hi> something is said (or
      written) is given as much attention as <hi rend="i">what</hi> is said. Freud too followed this
      same emphasis, which led him to the discovery of a pervasive rhetorical or narrative dimension
      in the psyche and its productions. Certain aspects of his investigations have led in recent
      years to a series of refinements—for better or worse—on his discoveries, in
      which the unconscious can be interpreted as having a structure like that of language, or can
      be understood as being a modality of writing, or a manifestation of universal laws of
      tropology. In all these cases of what, for reductive convenience, we might call “French
      Freud,” there is an attempt to follow Freud’s insight that paying attention to the
      mode of exposition or representation (<hi rend="i">Darstellung</hi>) was the best way to
      obtain clues for interpreting the basic nature of the unconscious.</p>
          <p>For George, however—who in spite of her interest in the “major
      revisionists” (18) of Freud, is curiously unaware of or indifferent to French
      Freud—the unconscious exists as a realm of freedom and a source of energy which artists
      can conveniently tap to enable them to overcome the constraints of the reality principle.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">2</ref> Unlike ordinary people, artists have
“special
      gifts” which allow them “access to the unconscious” (49) where they can
      “cathect energy freely and intensely through the displacement and condensation processes.
      . . . While ordinary men and women live in the world of consciousness . . . the artist has
      retained the ability to reconcile paradox . . . to be certain and assert . . . and to escape
      time” (51). The artist “passes freely between and among pleasure and pain, reality
      and fantasy, time and timelessness” (52), and “The reality principle is thereby
      subject to, because created by, the artist” (63). <note id="n27"><hi rend="s">2</hi> The
       only French author cited in the whole study is Bataille, whose “somewhat wiggy
       theses” are described as “valuable to the psychoanalytic critic”
      (239).</note></p>
          <pb id="p16-122" n="122"/>
          <p>According to George, this “theory of art . . . lay buried in Freud’s major
      works” (52), which means that “Psychoanalysis contains the seed of hope and vision
      of which Blake’s system was the harvest a century before” (60). But Freud failed
      to nourish his seed of hope, which therefore “remained latent, that is, unwritten”
      (66). Freud denied himself “the prophetic and prescriptive voice” (147) and instead
      “whispered his manifesto . . . because he dared not shout it, perhaps not even to
      himself” (138). It is only when he is “freed of his mistakes” by George (70)
      that he can be heard to stop muttering and begin shouting what he really means (69-70).
      Presumably it is George’s insight into the “fourth dimension of imaginative
      liberty” as a “redemptive overlay on other ways of thinking, interacting, and being
      in the world” (76) which sharpens her hearing in this manner. Blake, on the other hand,
      was early able “to reverberate the themes” in a manner loud and clear,
      “prophetic and prescriptive” (147). 
	<q> Blake’s own solution was expressed
       numerous times throughout his career in language that remained almost identical throughout
       several decades, from its first expression in <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
        Albion</hi> to its final expression in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> It consists of a fantasy
       of free love so radical that it still sounds peculiarly shocking in our time. (142) </q>
What
      follows this assertion is a lenghty quotation from what George calls the “visionary
      poet-prophet of <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>” (127), the Oothoon who expresses
      “Blake’s own solution” and “Blake’s ideal” (142).</p>
          <p>George’s acknowledgement of Freud in this context is thus rather like Freud’s
      basic approach to literature; he never tired of admiring it for having anticipated what he
      took to be the truths of psychoanalysis. But chiefly, perhaps, Freud discovered and
      appreciated what he took to be the mode of production of truth in the literary text, in which
      the truth is deferred because the literary theme does not offer itself directly to the reader
      as such. In this respect, literature was seen to share the most general characteristic of the
      unconscious, that of a modality or economy of indirect representation. For Freud the great
      universal opening for interpretation was the insight that discourse itself can always be read
      as a symptom of something else, as a practice of representation in which the relationship of
      conscious subjects to the discourse they produce is always eccentric. In such a view the
      ultimate Truth is of less concern than the process of signification or meaning 
(<hi rend="i">Deutung</hi>) as it is available to our understanding through the observation of its
      practice of representation. The problematic relationship between subjects and their writing
      practices constitutes a working area where subjects can learn both about themselves and about
      the nature of language and its functioning by observing that practice closely. As Freud says,
	<q> There is often something in the material itself which takes charge of one and diverts one
       from first intentions. Even such a trivial achievement as the arrangement of a well-known
       piece of material is not entirely subject to an author’s own choice; it takes what
       line it likes and all one can do is ask oneself after the event (<hi rend="i">nachträglich</hi>) why
it has happened in this way and no other.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28"
type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> The Standard Edition of The Complete Psychological Works of
Sigmund Freud</hi>
        (S.E.), ed. James Strachey <hi rend="i">et al.</hi>, 24 vols. (London: Hogarth Press,
        1953-1974), XVI, 379.</note></q></p>
          <p>There is thus in Freud a profound and pervasive economy of deferral which constitutes both
      the practice of the unconscious and the psyche in general, and becomes the basic and necessary
      modality of meaning (<hi rend="i">Deutung</hi>) and the governing principle of art itself,
      which must wait to be “completed” by interpretation. In this view the
      “Truth” of the Oedipus complex is less important for our understanding of meaning
      than is attention to the process of deferral which informs the structure and texture of the
      tragedy as an interpretable text: 
	<q> The action of the play consists in nothing other than
       the process of revealing, with cunning delays and ever-mounting excitement—a process
       that can be likened to the work of a psycho-analysis—that Oedipus himself is the
       murderer of Laius, but further that he is the son of the murdered man and of Jocasta.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">4</hi> S. E., IV, 261-62.</note></q></p>
          <p>This description of the “process” of the tragedy is an apt and knowing
      self-description of Freud’s own characteristic mode of exposition, in which belatedness
       (<hi rend="i">Nachträglichkeit</hi>) is chosen over the illusion of a truth
      immediately available and transparent to the author—a process in which postponement of
      comprehension, of final interpretations and truths, is both justified by and made necessary by
      the nature of meaning itself. Wherever we read in Freud, we find this profound and formal
      sense of process which governs science, art and life, and which must also govern the manner in
      which we interpret and talk about them. 
	<q> We bring expectations with us into the work, but
       they must be forcibly held back. By observation, now at one point and now at another, we come
       upon something new. . . . We put forward conjectures, we construct hypotheses, which we
       withdraw if they are not confirmed, we need much patience and readiness for any eventuality,
       we renounce early convictions so as not to be led by them into overlooking unexpected
       factors. . . .<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">5</hi> S. E., XXII, 174.</note></q>
Freud’s voice here (as at the end of 
<hi rend="i">Beyond the Pleasure
       Principle</hi>) is not unlike that of Los in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, urging
      his Sons to “be patient yet a little” in order to avoid the “fury
      premature” that results in “Martyrdoms &amp; Wars.”</p>
          <p>I find it necessary to make these by now rather familiar observations on Freud in order to
      characterize George’s book adequately as a pursuit of Truth (“I pursue this truth.
      . . . ” [p. 27]) which in its haste to reach the appointed end belies the promise of its
      beginnings. George is consistently patronizing of Freud, whom she sees as Blake’s
      “Idiot Questioner” who “publishes doubt &amp; calls it knowledge; whose
      Science is Despair” (178). But her most persistent criticism of him is that he failed his
      promise, by not adopting the role of “prophetic and prescriptive” utterance and
      shouting the Truth of his discoveries.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
type="note">6</ref> In this she has
      not only a remarkably naive and prescriptive view of the author-function, 
      <pb id="p16-123" n="123"/> 
      but one which is very much like what Freud was guarding himself against as a
      violation of his whole theory of interpretation, and rather like what Blake reveals as the
      temptation of Milton to found a new religion with a pre-emptive doctrine and discourse of
      Truth. Foucault has shrewdly observed that what he calls the “author-function” is a
      more complicated construct, that it does not develop “spontaneously as the attribution of
      a discourse to an individual,” but is rather the result of a “complex operation
      which constructs a certain rational being that we call ‘author,’” and that
      the author-function “is not defined by the spontaneous attribution of a discourse to its
      producer, but rather by a series of specific and complex operations” which do not
      “refer purely and simply to a real individual.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">7</ref>
      Foucault further isolates a particular author-function which I would like to appeal to in this
      context, citing Freud and Marx as exemplars: <hi rend="i">viz</hi>, authors who are not just
      the “authors” of their own works, but authors who define the possibilities of
      producing other works, including the rules that govern those works. Such authors can be seen
      as “founders of discursivity” in Foucault’s terminology, in that they define
      or initiate a discursive practice or a field of discursivity. The task they leave for
      subsequent practitioners of discourse is thus either extremely simple (to continue within the
      conspicuous limits of the founding discourse) or extremely difficult: to struggle at the
      necessary task of transforming the discursive practice itself, while the power of that
      practice continues to define the possibilities of what can be said as nothing more than
      variable functions of the originating discursivity itself. The point to be made from this is
      that the field of discursivity founded by Freud, and his own discursive practice, are both
      thoroughly and directly counter to prophecy and prescription, and to the author-function that
      George would have had him assume—contrary not as mere matters of style and temperament,
      but as the essential dimension of sound interpretive practice itself. <note id="n31"><hi rend="s">6</hi>
I find it hard to avoid here the image of Mr. Huffcap (who “would kick
       the bottom of the Pulpit out, with Passion, would tear off the sleeve of his Gown. &amp; set
       his wig on fire &amp; throw it at the people hed cry &amp; stamp &amp; kick &amp; sweat
       and all for the good of their souls”) or of Quid (“I will fall into such a passion
       Ill hollow and stamp &amp; frighten all the People there &amp; show them what truth
       is”) in <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi> (E 443, 456).</note>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">7</hi> “What is an Author,” in <hi rend="i">Textual
        Strategies: Perspectives in Post-Structuralist Criticism</hi>, ed. J. V. Harari (Ithaca:
       Cornell University Press, 1979), pp. 150, 153.</note></p>
          <p>What then of George’s assumption that the Truth is immediately available to Blake,
      for whom Milton’s “three major mistakes” turn out to be “relatively
      minor but debilitating” and can readily be cured, producing a Milton who is a “giant
      striding the mountains of Blake’s imaginative universe, afire with sexual and
      intellectual energy” (69)? For George the “readings” that Blake’s poems
      “invite are as theological as they are poetic” (147). She discovers Blake’s
      “theological” Truth in a process of reading that ignores distinctions of voice and
      dramatic context and “hears” Blake’s voice as the voice of Truth speaking
      through Oothoon, through the voice of the Devil—wherever the longed-for message can be
      found. Freud was too old and too sick to be up to the job (220), but Blake, who “knew
      everything about everything” (17) and seemingly had no difficulties or self-doubts, was
      easily able to complete the job begun and botched by Freud, the job of discovering and
      announcing the Truth. The Truth, of course, is that art as a realm of freedom can structure or
      restructure reality according to polymorphously perverse desire, realizing total sexual
      fulfillment. Genital sex, which chains us to reproduction, can be transcended by an indulgence
      in the full range of sexual acts, and the joys of sex will turn out to be intellectual (not
      “natural,” for “nature” is evil for Blake, and a stumbling-block for
      Freud) as we all, like Ololon, are “consumed and fulfilled in the orgasmic fires of
      intellect” (181). Freed from genitality, sexuality becomes “expressive of what Blake
      thought the highest in humankind—liberty, inspiration, imaginative freedom, art”
       (180).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Cf. Leopold Damrosch’s remark: “The solution is
       constantly announced by Blakeans: abolish secrecy, improve sensual enjoyment, dispense with
       jealousy and indulge in Oothoon’s ‘lovely copulation.’ But
       Blake’s closest affinity with Freud lies in his deep appreciation of the difficulty of
       doing this” (<hi rend="i">Symbol and Truth in Blake’s Myth</hi> [Princeton:
       Princeton University Press, 1980], p. 216).</note></p>
          <p>If this new and revolutionary truth sounds familiar, it is because the Freud in these pages
      is the “American Freud” of Marcuse, N. O. Brown, and the early Reich (before his
      “increasingly narrow and eventually monomaniac focus” [19]). These are
      George’s “major revisionists” (18) of Freud, operating within a liberated
      discursivity that in her view is properly prophetic and prescriptive. Like Blake, they have
      transcended Freud’s failure to envision “art as a way out of the closed
      system” or to embrace “art as an escape from determinism” (220, 228). We are
      thus left with a pathetic view of Freud as a sick, old Jew dying of throat cancer in
      Nazi-occupied Vienna, not realizing that if he had chosen to be a “prophet” rather
      than an “analyst” he could have escaped the determinism of his environment. We
      should “understand Freud’s pessimism, and love him for the modicum of hope and
      vision he retained,” but to avoid his fate we should embrace art and live in Jerusalem.
      We should become “Blakers” (17) and do what “Blake says” (78); to
      “restore ourselves to mythic stature . . . why not poetically, mythically, imagine an
      unfallen and expansive body that corresponds to our own” (78)? In Blake’s
      “Program” (80) any “adjustment to external reality and capitulation to natural
      limitation” are simply “a waste of time” (80). After all, Blake “knew
      exactly what he was doing” (106), and he “made it perfectly clear” (82).</p>
          <p>There is little in this intertextual venture that had not already been mapped by Blake in
      his anatomy of discourse in <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, where
      Oothoon shouts “Love! Love! Love! happy happy Love! free as the mountain wind!” and
      Theotormon does not listen. But Oothoon does not listen to Theotormon either, and there is no
      power in her rapturous rhetoric to change him. To equate the voice of Blake with Oothoon alone
      is to continue to misread this most misread of all Blake’s works, and to trivialize the
      energetic exertion of his talent in the continued quest for a poetic form that could change,
      rather than reinforce, the pattern of voices that “impose” on each other without
      ever constituting a discourse that could be called a conversation. Without suggesting that
      they are right in any ultimate sense, I would still urge that the French Freudians have been
      paying Freud more respectful attention than George, who basically uses a limited view of Freud
      as a straw man to set off a transcendent genius in Blake who “knew everything about
      everything.”</p>
          <p>I do think that George is right, in her notion that Blake and Freud are profound
      antagonists. But in spite of her proclamation of anticipatory victory for Blake, the battle is
      never fairly engaged, and the power of Freud’s views on the limits of the possibility
      of discourse cannot be overthrown by proclamation. George does at least recognize that
      “Freud’s choice of words was the linguistic 
<pb id="p16-124" n="124"/>
      representation of his own and his culture’s processes of symbol formation” (217).
      But she engages with the problem as if it were one of “diction” (217) and
      “terminology” (219) on the simple level of the choice of words.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">9</ref> The work of Laplanche and Pontalis, even after their eight
years of
      research, has probably only begun to show the labyrinthine interconnections of concepts,
      extensions, connotations and implications of Freud’s terminology for the conceptual
      organization and practice of psychoanalysis and interpretation.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n35" type="note">10</ref> The practice of discourse cannot be freed from the processes of
representation and
      available meanings that are inscribed in the very structure of linguistic and cultural codes
      by a simple avoidance of “conventional terminology” (227) and “diction,”
      as George seems for the most part to suggest. <note id="n34"><hi rend="s">9</hi> It is
       interesting that, although Freud’s “use of terminology is problematic”
       (219), his main utility is seen as a purveyor of terminology: “Blake needs Freud to
       clarify Blake’s contributions to psychology in accessible terms” (25).</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Jean Laplanche and J.-B. Pontalis, <hi rend="i">The
        Language of Psycho-Analysis</hi>, trans. Donald Nicholson-Smith (New York: W. W. Norton,
       1973).</note></p>
          <p>The end of <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> is relevant here:
<q> 8. So Fuzon
       call’d all together<lb/>
 The remaining children of Urizen:<lb/>
 And they left the
       pendulous earth:<lb/>
 They called it Egypt &amp; left it. </q>
To <hi rend="i">call</hi> it
      Egypt and leave it is not to enter the promised land of fully liberated discourse, but to
      enter a linguistic desert of doubt and despair, where the already-inscribed code constantly
      offers itself as the only path. This is why Los’s task in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
      is described as building “the stubborn structure of the Language, acting
      against/Albion’s melancholy, who must else have been a Dumb despair” (E 181).
      There is one extended moment, in Chapter 6, where George seems to realize and articulate the
      essence of the basic problems which she elsewhere glides over: 
	<q> Blake’s problems
       with portrayals of sexuality and of women, as I see it, are problems of symbol formation that
       express themselves in the limitations of language. . . . Blake’s vision of the human
       was constantly rendered problematic by language. He had to try to speak the literally
       unspeakable. Language and art were his tools for reunification of the Human Form Divine, but
       the images available to him to communicate his vision of the eternal were necessarily drawn
       from the repository of the material and natural world. That world—its images and
       therefore its language—was sexual. Blake wished to portray everything as human, and
       humans in this world are sexual beings. He was thus compelled to express ultimately
       genderless human forms in gendered terms. . . . To accomplish this task, he turned in every
       direction; most of all, to the sexes. Here, where he tried hardest to heal, he was constantly
       confronted with the wound. Sometimes, ironically, he deepened the wound.<lb/>
 (199-200) </q>
      This passage alone is worth almost the whole of the rest of the book, and I hope that it
      indicates the future direction of George’s efforts.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
