<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.2.minnick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="checklist">Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Recent Scholarship</title>
        <author n="Minnick">Thomas L. Minnick</author>
        <author n="Dörrbecker">Detlef W. Dörrbecker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Krzysztof Z. Cieszkowski</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Christina Shuttleworth Kraus</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Judith W. Page</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Thomas A. Vogler</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
      <pb id="p16-111" n="111"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-2-0009">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">BLAKE AND HIS CIRCLE: A CHECKLIST OF RECENT SCHOLARSHIP</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">THOMAS L.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">MINNICK</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
          <hi rend="b">AND</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">DETLEF W.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">DÖRRBECKER</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>This issue of our annual checklist of Blake Scholarship is the first in recent years to
     include no major changes in format or authorship. The general categories of the checklist
     remain the same, and we have retained the practice of numbering entries and concluding with an
     index of authors. An asterisk after an entry number indicates an item that we have not
     personally examined.</p>
        <p>As always, it is a pleasure to record our gratitude to authors who sent notice of their
     recent publications and occasionally, offprints.</p>
        <p>T. L. M.</p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">PART I</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">WILLIAM BLAKE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">EDITIONS, TRANSLATIONS, FACSIMILES, REPRODUCTIONS</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>1* Blake, William. <hi rend="i">Libri profetici</hi>, ed. and trsl. R. Sanesi. Milan:
       Guanda, 1980.</p>
            <p>2* Blake, William. <hi rend="i">Il matrimonio tra il cielo e l’inferno</hi>, trsl.
       P. Manetti. Florence: Nuovedizioni Vallecchi, 1979.</p>
            <p>3 Blake, William. <hi rend="i">Poesie</hi>, trsl. and ed. Giacomo Conserva, introd. by
       Sergio Perosa. Rome: Newton Compton, 1976; 2nd ed., 1980 [“Paperbacks poeti,” vol.
       45].</p>
            <p>4 Blake, William. <hi rend="i">Poetry of William Blake.</hi> Winterport, Maine:
       Borrower’s Press, 1978. Reviewed by G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake/An
        Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982), 148.</p>
            <p>5 Blake, William. <hi rend="i">Visioni</hi>, trsl. Giuseppe Ungaretti, with an introduction
       by Aldo Tagliaferri. [2nd ed.] Milan: Arnoldo Mondadori, 1980 [“Oscar poesia e
       teatro,” vol. 15.] [First published in 1965, Ungaretti’s bi-lingual edition
       contains selections from Blake’s poetry ranging from the “Abbozzi poetici”
       to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>; there are 100 pp. of commentary by Mario Diaconi.]</p>
            <p>6 Essick, Robert N., and Morton D. Paley, eds. <hi rend="i">Robert Blair’s The
        Grave.</hi> London: The Scolar Press, 1982. £45.00. Reviewed by Raymond Lister, <hi rend="i">The</hi>
[London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 11 June 1982, p.
       645.</p>
            <p>7 Stuart, James, and Nicholas Revett. <hi rend="i">The Antiquities of Athens</hi>, 3 vols.
       (1762-1794). New York, N.Y.: Arno Press, 1980. [In this reprint, the original folio format
       has been reduced to quarto; all four of Blake’s plates are reproduced in vol. 3.]</p>
            <p>8 Wright, John W., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
        ‘‘Urizen’’ Plate Designs: A Graphic Essay in Facsimile of His
        Copper Plates for ‘‘The First Book of Urizen.’’</hi> Ann Arbor,
       Mich.: [printed privately], 1980. [In his introductory essay Wright attempts to prove
       that—and to interpret why—Blake made use of portions of the copperplates which
       he had etched originally for “The Approach of Doom” when he colorprinted plates 14
       and 27 of <hi rend="i">Urizen.</hi>]</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p16-112" n="112"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">BIBLIOGRAPHIES, BIBLIOGRAPHICAL ESSAYS, EXHIBITION CATALOGUES</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>9 Andrews, Keith. <hi rend="i">Drawings from the Bequest of W. F. Watson 1881-1981.</hi>
       Edinburgh: National Gallery of Scotland, 1981. [No. 4 in this catalogue is Blake’s
       “God Writing Upon the Tablets of the Covenant”; the watercolor is also reproduced
       in color on the front cover.]</p>
            <p>10 Bennett, Shelley M. <hi rend="i">Prints by the Blake Followers</hi>, exhb. cat. San
       Marino, Calif.: Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery, 1981.</p>
            <p>11 Butlin, Martin. - <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols.
       New Haven, Conn. and London: Yale University Press, for the Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in
       British Art, 1981 [“Studies in British Art”].</p>
            <p>12 Czymmek, Goetz. <hi rend="i">Druckgraphik von William Blake aus der Sammlung
        Neuerburg</hi>, exhb. cat. Cologne: Graphische Sammlung des Wallraf-Richartz-Museums, 1982.
       [Only Copy Y of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> and a proof set of the <hi rend="i">Job</hi>
       engravings were on show.]</p>
            <p>13 DeLuca, V. A. “How We Are Reading Blake: A Review of Some Recent Criticism.”
        <hi rend="i">University of Toronto Quarterly</hi>, 50 (1980-1981), 238-247.</p>
            <p>14 Minnick, Thomas L., with the assistance of Detlef W. Dörrbecker. “Blake and
       His Circle: A Checklist of Recent Scholarship.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
        Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1981), 83-93.</p>
            <p>15 Modern Language Association of America. “Blake.” Pp. 121-122 in <hi rend="i">1980 MLA
International Bibliography of Books and Articles on the Modern Languages and
        Literatures</hi>, vol. 1. New York: MLA, 1981.</p>
            <p>16 “William Blake to David Hockney: A Private Collection of British Prints.”
       Exhibition at the Ashmolean Museum, Spring of 1982. Reviewed by Celina Fox, <hi rend="i">The</hi>
[London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 26 February 1982, p.
       215.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">CRITICAL STUDIES</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>17 Ackland, Michael. “Blake’s System and the Critics.” <hi rend="i">AUMLA:
                Journal of the Australasian <corr type="emend">Universities Language and Literature Association,</corr></hi> 54 (1980),
       149-170.</p>
            <p>18 Ackland, Michael. “Blakean Sources in John Gardner’s <hi rend="i">Grendel.” Critique:
Studies in Modern Fiction</hi>, 23 (1981), 57-66.</p>
            <p>19* Alkjaer, Niels. <hi rend="i">William Blake og andre essays.</hi> Copenhagen: printed
       for the author, 1974.</p>
            <p>20 Allentuck, Marcia R. “Ruskin and Blake Again: Unpublished Sources not in
       Bentley.” <hi rend="i">The Papers of the Bibliographical Society of America</hi>, 75
       (1981), 447-448. [Quotes from two ALS by Ruskin in the Victoria and Albert Museum.]</p>
            <p>21* Aubrey, Bryan. “‘Visions of Torment’: Blake, Böhme and
       ‘The Book of Urizen’.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Mystical Literature</hi>, 1
       (1980), 120-153.</p>
            <p>22 Bandy, Melanie. <hi rend="i">Mind Forg’d Manacles: Evil in the Poetry of Blake
        and Shelley.</hi> University, Ala.: University of Alabama Press, 1981. $19.95.</p>
            <p>23 Banerjee, Tilak. “Pope’s Epic and the Hebraic Tradition from Thomson to
       Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 42 (1982), 3143-A.
       Diss., York University, 1981. [“This dissertation relates the features of the major long
       poems of the eighteenth century to developments in the history of ideas. Part I deals with
       Pope’s renowned translations of Homer. Part II deals with the prophetical counter
       tradition, focussing on Thomson’s <hi rend="i">The Seasons</hi>, Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi>, and Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>”]</p>
            <p>24 Beal, Ann Dickinson. “‘Can Such an Eye Judge of the Stars’: A Study
       of Star Imagery in William Blake’s Poetry.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
        International</hi> 42 (1982), 3606-A. Diss., The University of North Carolina at Greensboro,
       1981. [In Blake’s work, “ . . . the images of the stars are shaped to fit the
       different genres and purposes of song, political prophecy, and epic, but . . . their
       visionary meaning remains essentially the same throughout Blake’s works. What is more,
       this visionary meaning is a key to the prophetic language of the poetry.”]</p>
            <p>25 Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Comment upon the Illustrated Eighteenth-Century Chaucer.”
        <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi>, 78 (1980), 398.</p>
            <p>26 Bentley, G. E., Jr. “A Portrait of Milton Engraved by William Blake ‘When
       Three Years of Age’? A Speculation by Samuel Palmer.” <hi rend="i">University of
        Toronto Quarterly</hi>, 51 (1981), 28-35.</p>
            <p>27 Bidney, Martin. “Structures of Perception in Blake and Whitman: Creative
       Contraries, Cosmic Body, Fourfold Vision.” <hi rend="i">ESQ</hi>: <hi rend="i">A Journal
        of the American Renaissance</hi>, 28 (1982), 36-47.</p>
            <p>28 Billigheimer, Rachel Victoria. “Wheels of Eternity: Circle Symbolism in the Works
       of W. B. Yeats and W. Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 42
       (1982), 3143-A. Diss., York University (Canada), 1980. [“This thesis explores circle
       symbolism in the work of W. B. Yeats and traces its relationship to circle imagery in the
       work of William Blake.”]</p>
            <p>29 Bogan, James J. “Apocalypse Now: William Blake and the Conversion of the
       Jews.” <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi>, 19 (1981), 116-120.</p>
            <p>30 Bogan, James. “Blake’s City of Golgonooza in ‘Jerusalem’:
       Metaphor and Mandala.” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1981), 85-98.</p>
            <p>31 Bogan, James. “Blake’s Jupiter Olympus in Rees’ <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982),
       156-163.</p>
            <p>32* Bogan, James. “From Hackwork to Prophetic Vision: William Blake’s
       Delineation of the Laocoon Group.” <hi rend="i">Publications of the Arkansas
        Philological Association</hi>, 6, no. 1 (1980), 33-51.</p>
            <p>33 Böker, Uwe. “Die Anfänge der europäischen
       Blake-Rezeption.” <hi rend="i">Arcadia: Zeitschrift für vergleichende
        Literaturwissenschaft</hi>, 16 (1981), 266-283.</p>
            <p>34 Bottrall, Margaret. “A Lecture on William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of
        Innocence and Experience</hi>” (sic). The Critical Forum. London: Norwich Tapes, Ltd.,
       1978. Reviewed by Paul Mann, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982),
       197.</p>
            <p>35 Bracher, Frederick Mark. “Blake’s Metaphysics.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
International</hi>, 42 (1982), 3162-A. Diss., Vanderbilt University,
       1981. [“In <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> Blake presents the sequential emergence
       of four principles—differentiation (Urizen), entelechy (Los), ecstasis
       (Pity/Enitharmon), and eros (Orc)—as successive attempts to overcome the non-being of
       the flux of possibilities constituting Eternity. . . . In <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> Blake
       outlines the manner in which Orc 
<pb id="p16-113" n="113"/>
might be freed and finite
       existence achieve infinity.”]</p>
            <p>36 Butlin, Martin. “A New Acquisition for the Tate and a New Addition to the Blake
       Catalogue.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982), 132.</p>
            <p>37 Butlin, Martin. “A Newly Discovered Watermark and a Visionary’s Way with His
       Dates.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1981), 101-103.</p>
            <p>38 Carr, Stephen Leo. “Visionary Syntax: Nontyrannical Coherence in Blake’s
       Visual Art.” <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi>, 22
       (1981), 222-248.</p>
            <p>39 Corti, Claudia. <hi rend="i">Il primo Blake: testo e sistema.</hi> Ravenna: A. Longo
       Editore, 1980 [“Il portico biblioteca di lettere ed arti”; vol. 70, sezione:
       letteratura straniera].</p>
            <p>40 Cox, Stephen D. “Adventures of ‘A Little Boy Lost’: Blake and the
       Process of Interpretation.” <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi>, 23 (1981), 301-316.</p>
            <p>41 Cribb, J. J. L1. “Yeats, Blake and ‘The Countess Kathleen’.” <hi rend="i">Irish
University Review</hi>, 11 (1981), 165-178.</p>
            <p>42 Crossan, Greg. “Blake’s Maiden Queen in ‘The Angel’.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982), 133-134.</p>
            <p>43* Culler, Jonathan. “Prolegomena to a Theory of Reading.” Pp. 46-66 in <hi rend="i">The
Reader and the Text: Essays on Audience and Interpretation</hi>, ed. Susan R.
       Suleiman and Inge Crosman. Princeton, N. J.: Princeton University Press, 1980. [Illustrates
       his theory with a reading of Blake.]</p>
            <p>44 Davidson, Peter. “The Music of the Ancients.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
        Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1981), 98-100.</p>
            <p>45* Dickstein, Morris. “The Price of Experience: Blake’s Reading of
       Freud.” Pp. 67-111 in <hi rend="i">The Literary Freud: Mechanisms of Defense and the
        Poetic Will</hi>, ed. Joseph H. Smith. New Haven, Conn. and London: Yale University Press,
       1980 [“Psychiatry and the Humanities,” vol. 4].</p>
            <p>46. Dörrbecker, Detlef W. “Innocence Lost &amp; Found: An Untraced Copy
       Traced.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982), 125-131.</p>
            <p>47 Doskow, Minna. “The Shape of Limitation: A Visual Pattern in the Illuminated Works
       of William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1981), 121-160.</p>
            <p>48 Downes, Margaret Josephine. “‘Conversing with Paradise’: A Study of
       Blake’s Art.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 42 (1981),
       2683-A. Diss., Florida State University, 1981. [“Just how the pastoral would
       imaginatively transform the world, and how Blake in his artistic vision perceives the
       emergence of the apocalypse out of our fallen state, are remarkably similar issues. This
       dissertation presents a more thorough analysis of pastoral elements and aims in
       Blake’s poetry than has been written to date.”]</p>
            <p>49 Ellis, James. “Wallace Stegner’s Art of Literary Allusion: ‘The
       Marriage of Heaven and Hell’ and ‘Faust’ in ‘Maiden in a
       Tower.’” <hi rend="i">Studies in Short Fiction</hi>, 17 (1980), 105-111.</p>
            <p>50 Erdman, David V. “A Book to Eat.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
        Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982), 170-175.</p>
            <p>51 Erdman, David V. “Let the Dead Ardours Live!” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
        Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1981), 58-59.</p>
            <p>52 Essick, Robert N. “New Information on Blake’s Illuminated Books.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1981), 4-13.</p>
            <p>53 Essick, Robert N. “<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> Copy h.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
        Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1981), 59-60.</p>
            <p>54 Essick, Robert N., and Michael C. Young. “Blake’s ‘Canterbury’
       Print: The Posthumous Pilgrimage of the Copperplate.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
        Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1981), 78-82.</p>
            <p>55 Ferber, Michael. “Blake’s ‘Thel’ and the Bride of
       Christ.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 9 (1980), 45-56.</p>
            <p>56 Ferber, Michael. “‘London’ and Its Politics.” <hi rend="i">ELH:
        A Journal of English Literary History</hi>, 48 (1981), 310-338.</p>
            <p>57 Ferber, Michael. “Mars and the Planets Three in America.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982), 136-137.</p>
            <p>58* Flor, João Almeida. “Para uma Imagem de William Blake na Cultura
       Oitocentista.” <hi rend="i">Brotéria</hi>, 110 (1980), 48-54.</p>
            <p>59 Franson, J. Karl. “A Renaissance Source for Blake’s
       ‘Tyger’.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>, n.s., 27 (1980),
       413-415.</p>
            <p>60* Frye, Northrop. <hi rend="i">Agghiaccante simmetria</hi>, trsl. Carla Plevano Pezzini
       and Francesca Valente. Milan: Longanesi, 1976. [The Italian Version of <hi rend="i">Fearful
        Symmetry</hi>, 1947.]</p>
            <p>61* Frye, Northrop. <hi rend="i">Favole d’identità: Studi di mitologia
        poetica.</hi> Torino: Einàudi, 1973 [“La ricerca letteraria: serie
       critica”; vol. 19]. [<hi rend="i">Fables of Identity</hi> in an Italian
       translation.]</p>
            <p>62 Furia, Philip. “Pound and Blake on Hell.” <hi rend="i">Paideuma: A Journal
        Devoted to Ezra Pound Scholarship</hi>, 10 (1981), 599-604.</p>
            <p>63 Givone, Sergio. <hi rend="i">William Blake: arte e religione.</hi> Milan: U. Mursia,
       1978 [“Saggi di estetica e di poetica”; vol. 20].</p>
            <p>64 Glazer, Myra. “Sex and the Psyche: William Blake and D. H. Lawrence.” 
<hi rend="i">Hebrew University Studies in Literature</hi>, 9 (1981), 196-229.</p>
            <p>65 Glazer-Schotz, Myra, and Gerda Norvig. “Blake’s Book of Changes: On Viewing
       Three Copies of the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake
Studies</hi>, 9 (1980), 100-121.</p>
            <p>66 Gleckner, Robert F. “Antithetical Structure in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Poetical
        Sketches.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 20 (1981), 143-162.</p>
            <p>67 Gleckner, Robert F. “Blake’s Swans.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
        Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982), 164-169.</p>
            <p>68 Glen, Heather. “The Poet in Society: Blake and Wordsworth on London.” 
<hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi>, [2], whole no. 3 (1976), 2-28. [See also entry 117,
       below.]</p>
            <p>69 Griffin, Paul Francis. “Toward a Literary History of the Subject: A Reading of
       Rousseau’s <hi rend="i">Confessions</hi> and Blake’s Visionary Epics.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation
Abstracts International</hi>, 42 (1981), 2121-A. Diss., University of
       Wisconsin-Madison, 1981. [“This study contends that a reassessment of the idea of the
       human subject is necessary if contemporary literary theory and interpretive practice are to
       take into account developments in Continental thought such as semiotics which have supplanted
       the traditional notion of the individual as an autonomous subject with a consideration of
       those material forces such as language and culture which inform our understanding of human
       subjective experience. . . . The fourth chapter outlines Blake’s evocation of 
<hi rend="i">apocalypse</hi> or the transformation of the world 
<pb id="p16-114" n="114"/>
as
       the strategy which organizes his poetry, and chapter five treats <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and
        <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>”]</p>
            <p>70* Hatherly, Ana. “Simbolismo e Imaginacão em Blake.” <hi rend="i">Colóquio/Letras</hi>,
54 (1980), 14-32.</p>
            <p>71 Helms, Randel. “Another Source for Blake’s Orc.” 
<corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">Blake/An
        Illustratred Quarterly</hi></corr>, 15 (1982), 198-199.</p>
            <p>72 Helms, Randel. “The Genesis of ‘The Everlasting Gospel.’” <hi rend="i">Blake
Studies</hi>, 9 (1980), 122-160.</p>
            <p>73 Heppner, Christopher. “Blake and the Novelists.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
        Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982), 198.</p>
            <p>74 Herrstrom, David Sten. “Blake’s Transformations of Ezekiel’s Cherubim
       Vision in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
       Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1981), 64-77.</p>
            <p>75 Hilton, Nelson. “Spears, Spheres, and Spiritual Tears: Blake’s Poetry as
       ‘The Tyger,’ 11. 17-20.” <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi>, 59
       (1980), 515-529.</p>
            <p>76* Hiromoto, Kaysuya. “A Comparison of the Chastity of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> with
       the Free Love of Blake.” <hi rend="i">Milton Center of Japan News</hi>, 4 (1980),
       5-6.</p>
            <p>76A Hood, Margaret Anne. “The Voice of Song: A Prosodic and Phonological Approach to
       William Blake.” M. A. thesis [typescript], Univ. of Adelaide, South Australia, 1982.
       [Examines early poems and prophetic passages designated by Blake as “song.”]</p>
            <p>77 Kauvar, Elaine M. “Landscape of the Mind: Blake’s Garden Symbolism.”
        <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 9 (1980), 57-73.</p>
            <p>78 Keynes, Geoffrey L. “‘Blake’s Own’ Copy of <hi rend="i">Songs
        of Innocence and of Experience.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi>, 29 (1980),
       203-207.</p>
            <p>79 Keynes, Geoffrey L. “An Undescribed Copy of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of
        Innocence and of Experience.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi>, 30 (1981),
       39-42.</p>
            <p>80 Keynes, Geoffrey L. “‘To the Nightingale’: Perhaps an Unrecognized
       Poem by William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi>, 30 (1981), 335-345. [The
       Nightingale poem, known from an etching by George Cumberland and dated c. 1784, is
       tentatively ascribed to Blake by Sir Geoffrey and a number of other scholars who were
       consulted by him. The essay supplies many arguments both in favor of and contradicting the
       attribution, and admits that in the end the authenticity of the poem “must rest on
       critical opinion.”]</p>
            <p>81 Kirk, Eugene. “Blake’s Menippean ‘Island’.” <hi rend="i">Philological
Quarterly</hi>, 59 (1980), 194-215.</p>
            <p>82 La Belle, Jenijoy. “Blake’s Insanity: An Unrecorded Early Reference.”
        <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1981), 100-101.</p>
            <p>83 La Belle, Jenijoy. “William Blake, Theodore Roethke, and Mother Goose: The Unholy
       Trinity.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 9 (1980), 74-86.</p>
            <p>84 Lange, Thomas V. “A Rediscovered Colored Copy of Young’s Night
       Thoughts.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982), 134-136.</p>
            <p>85 Lattin, Vernon E. “Blake’s Thel and Oothoon: Sexual Awakening in the
       Eighteenth Century.” <hi rend="i">The Literary Criterion</hi>, 16 (1981), 11-24.</p>
            <p>86 Leader, Zachary. <hi rend="i">Reading Blake’s “Songs”.</hi> Boston,
       Mass., London, and Henley-on-Thames: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1981.</p>
            <p>87 Luck, Marianna Mendillo. “Blake’s Urizen.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation
        Abstracts International</hi>, 42 (1981), 713-A. Diss., University of Connecticut, 1981.
       [“This is a psychological study of Urizen’s character in William Blake’s
        <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (1793) and <hi rend="i">The Book of
        Urizen</hi> (1794). These poems are viewed as dramas in which Urizen alternately assumes the
       roles of repressive father-figure and rebellious son . . . Urizen’s character is also
       examined in terms of the symbolism of the title-page and subsequent designs of <hi rend="i">The Book of
Urizen.</hi> . . . ”]</p>
            <p>88 Mathews, Lawrence. “Jesus as Saviour in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">English Studies in Canada</hi>, 6 (1980), 154-175.</p>
            <p>89 Mathews, Lawrence. “‘The Value of the Saviour’s Blood’: The
       Idea of Atonement in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Wascana
        Review</hi>, 15 (1980), 72-86.</p>
            <p>90 Matlin, David. “Kideta: A Study of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 42 (1981),
       228-A. Diss., State University of New York at Buffalo, 1981. [“I have entitled this
       essay <hi rend="i">Kideta</hi> because it is in the Hidatsa language at once the same word
       for sexual passion and the moment when the unknown must occur in the hunt and upon this word
       the meaning and use of this essay is poised.”]</p>
            <p>91* McCarthy, Shaun. “Riddle Patterns and William Blake’s ‘The
       Tyger’.” <hi rend="i">Journal of English</hi>, 8 (1980), 1-11.</p>
            <p>92* McGinnis, Wayne D. “Welty’s ‘Death of a Travelling Salesman’
       and William Blake Once Again.” <hi rend="i">Notes on Mississippi Writers</hi>, 11
       (1979), 52-54.</p>
            <p>93 Meller, Horst. “Die frühe romantische Dichtung in England: Die Geburt einer
       Romantik aus dem Geiste der Revolution.” Pp. 189-214 in <hi rend="i">Neues Handbuch der
        Literaturwissenschaft</hi>, vol. 15: Europäische Romantik II, ed. Klaus Heitmann.
       Wiesbaden: Akademische Verlagsgesellschaft Athenaion, 1982. [Pp. 194-200 are devoted to a
       chapter on “William Blake und die Vielgestaltigkeit des Revolutions-Mythos.”]</p>
            <p>94* Mewton, Robert. “Biblical Prophet or Deluded Visionary? William Blake and a Double
       Error.” Pp. 107-126 in <hi rend="i">L’Erreur dans la littérature et la
        pensée anglaises</hi>, Aix-en-Provence 1980 [“Actes du Centre Aixoises de
       Recherches Anglaises”].</p>
            <p>95 Mills, Alice. “The Spectral Bat in Blake’s Illustrations to 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 9 (1980), 87-99.</p>
            <p>96 Murray, E. B. “Thel, <hi rend="i">Thelyphthora</hi>, and the Daughters of
       Albion.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 20 (1981), 275-297.</p>
            <p>97* Noshiro, Shoho. <hi rend="i">William Blake—sono shogai to hin no subete.</hi>
       Tokyo: Hokuseido, 1979. [“Blake’s Life and Works.”]</p>
            <p>98 Ortiz, Anna Louise. “The Seer’s Progress: Transcendence and Social Vision in
       the Poetry of William Blake and Arthur Rimbaud.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
        International</hi>, 41 (1981), 5092-A. Diss., University of California, Los Angeles, 1980.
       [“ . . . when the Millenia did not follow revolution, and with civilization still
       waiting to be saved, Blake and Rimbaud tested their visions against the cities of men,
       believing that the city was the new arena where the battle against rationalism would be won
       or lost. It is this confrontation with the city, with all of the city’s intimations of
       Western Civilization, which shaped the post-revolutionary poetry of William Blake and Arthur
       Rimbaud.”]</p>
            <p>99 Pagliaro, Harold E. “Blake’s ‘Self-annihilation’: Aspects of
       its Function in the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, with a Glance at its History.” 
<hi rend="i">English</hi>, 30 (1981), 117-146.</p>
            <pb id="p16-115" n="115"/>
            <p>100 Paley, Morton D. “A Victorian Blake Facsimile.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
        Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1981), 24-27.</p>
            <p>101 Peterfreund, Stuart. “Blake and Newton: Argument as Art, Argument as
       Science.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Eighteenth-Century Culture</hi>, 10 (1981),
       205-226.</p>
            <p>102 Praz, Mario. “Teogonie di Blake.” Pp. 104-106 in <hi rend="i">Perseo e la
        Medusa: Dal Romanticismo all’ Avanguardi.</hi> Milan: Arnoldo Mondadori, 1979
       [“Saggi”; vol. 119). [A reprint of Praz’s article which was first published
       in 1976.]</p>
            <p>103 Punter, David. “Blake, Marxism and Dialectic.” <hi rend="i">Literature and
        History</hi>, [3], whole no. 6 (1977), 219-242.</p>
            <p>104* Quadri Iovine, Marcella. “<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>:
       Appunti sul demonismo in William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Lettore di Provincia</hi>, 39
       (1979), 61-70.</p>
            <p>105 Raine, Kathleen J. <hi rend="i">The Human Face of God: William Blake and the Book of
        Job.</hi> London: Thames and Hudson, 1982.</p>
            <p>106* Raine, Kathleen J. <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, trsl. T. Trini. Milan: Mazzotta,
       1980. [An Italian edition of Miss Raine’s book in “The World of Art Library”
       (1970).]</p>
            <p>107 Read, Dennis M. “‘An Eminent but Neglected Genius’: An Early
       Frederick Tatham Letter About William Blake.” <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi>,
       19 (1981), 29-33.</p>
            <p>108 Read, Dennis M. “The Context of Blake’s ‘Public Address’:
       Cromek and the Chalcographic Society.” <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi>, 60
       (1981), 69-86.</p>
            <p>109 Riede, David G. “The Symbolism of the Loins in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature 1500-1600</hi>, 21 (1981),
       547-563.</p>
            <p>110 Rivero, Albert J. “Typology, History, and Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">JEGP</hi>, 81 (1982), 30-46.</p>
            <p>111 Salemi, Joseph S. “Emblematic Tradition in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Gates
        of Paradise.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982),
       108-124.</p>
            <p>112* Sánchez, Aquilino. “William Blake and the Emblematic Tradition.” <hi rend="i">Anuario
del Departamento de Inglés</hi>, 1979, 121.</p>
            <p>113 Sellner, Albert. “Die Vermählung von Himmel und Hölle: Rekurs auf
       die spirituelle Tradition Europas am Beispiel William Blakes.” Pp. 202-233 in <hi rend="i">Die
Rückkehr des Imaginären: Märchen, Magie, Mystik, Mythos,
        Anfänge einer anderen Politik</hi> [ed. Christiane Thurn and Herbert Röttgen].
       Munich: Trikont-dianus Buchverlag, 1981.</p>
            <p>114 Simpson, David. <hi rend="i">Irony and Authority in Romantic Poetry.</hi> Totawa, New
       Jersey: Rowan and Littlefield, 1977. $22.50. Reviewed by Gavin Edwards, <hi rend="i">Blake/An
        Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982), 179-183.</p>
            <p>115 Singh, Charu Sheel. “The Concept of Nature in the Bhagavadgita and William
       Blake’s Pickering-Manuscript Poems.” <hi rend="i">Indian Journal of English
        Studies</hi>, 20, n.s. 1 (1980), 23-30.</p>
            <p>116* Skipp, Francis E. “Eliot’s Prufrock and Blake’s Lithe Lady.”
        <hi rend="i">Notes on Modern American Literature</hi>, 4 (1980), item 23.</p>
            <p>117 Smith, Stan. “Some Responses to Heather Glen’s ‘The Poet in Society:
       Blake and Wordsworth on London.’” <hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi>, [2],
       whole no. 4 (1976), 94-98. [See also entry 68, above.]</p>
            <p>118 Soubly, Diane M. “The Sun and Stars Nearer Roll: Jungian Individuation and the
       Archetypal Feminine in the Epics of William Blake and James Joyce.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation
Abstracts International</hi>, 42 (1981), 716-A. Diss., Wayne State University,
       1981. [“Carl Jung, William Blake, and James Joyce detail the psychic progress of
       individual and collective humanity, even though Joyce disavows any debt to this
       psychoanalytic contemporary, and even though Blake intuits psychic configurations some two
       centuries before the advent of depth psychology.”]</p>
            <p>119 Starling, Roy. “The Ellis and Yeats Edition of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>:
Text and Commentary.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
        International</hi>, 42 (1981), 2691-A. Diss., Florida State University, 1981. [“Ellis
       and Yeats were the first editors and commentators of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, and this study
       provides textual apparatus which shows the immense difficulties they encountered and the
       numerous changes they made as they attempted to derive a readable text from a ‘heap of
       unsorted and unnumbered’ manuscript leaves.”]</p>
            <p>120 Storch, Margaret. “Blake and Women: ‘Nature’s Cruel
       Holiness.’” <hi rend="i">American Imago</hi>, 38 (1981), 221ff.</p>
            <p>121 Summerfield, Henry. “Blake and the Names Divine.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
        Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1981), 14-22.</p>
            <p>122 Summerfield, Henry. “Blake’s ‘Pity’: An Interpretation.”
        <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1981), 34-38.</p>
            <p>123 Sutton, Dorothy Moseley. “Soul Clap Its Hands and Sing: Yeats’s Debt to
       Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 42 (1982), 3157-A.
       Diss., University of Kentucky, 1981. [“Yeats did not deliberately set out to imitate
       Blake, but he recognized his kinship with the earlier poet, and he gained self-confidence and
       courage from that recognition. The <hi rend="i">joie de vivre</hi>, the energy and exuberance
       that permeates much of Blake’s work became one of the most outstanding characteristics
       of Yeats’s work as well. Both poets had their darker side, but ultimately they are
       poets of affirmation. . . .”]</p>
            <p>124 Tannenbaum, Leslie W. <hi rend="i">Biblical Tradition in Blake’s Early
        Prophecies: The Great Code of Art.</hi> Princeton, N. J.: Princeton University Press, 1982.
       $25.00.</p>
            <p>125 Tingle, William Nicholas. “Romantic Thought: Education and Alienation.” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 41 (1981), 4395-A-4396-A. Diss.,
       University of California, Santa Barbara, 1980. [“The purpose of this study . . . is to
       trace the alterations in the concept of education as it moves from the Enlightenment to the
       period of late Romanticism. The chief writers discussed are Rousseau, Fichte, Schiller,
       Schelling, Blake, Wordsworth, Coleridge, and Shelley.”]</p>
            <p>126 Vaughan, Frank A. “Blake’s Illustrations to Gray’s ‘The
       Bard.’” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1981), 211-237.</p>
            <p>127 Wardle, Judith. “William Blake’s Iconography of Joy: Angels, Birds,
       Butterflies and Related Motifs from <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> to The Pickering
       Manuscript.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 9 (1980), 5-44.</p>
            <p>128 Waxler, Robert P. “The Virgin Mantle Displaced: Blake’s Early
       Attempt.” <hi rend="i">Modern Language Studies</hi>, 12 (1982), 45-53.</p>
            <p>129* Weathers, Winston. “The Construction of William Blake’s ‘The
       Tyger.’” Pp. 289-298 in <hi rend="i">Style and</hi>
	<pb id="p16-116" n="116"/>
	<hi rend="i">Text: Studies Presented to Nils Erik Enkvist</hi>, ed. Håkan Ringblom, et
       al. Stockholm: Språkförlaget Skriptor, 1975.</p>
            <p>130 Werner, Bette Charlene. “Milton’s Sixfold Emanation Redeemed in the Designs
       of Blake: William Blake’s Illustrations to Six Poems by John Milton.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation
Abstracts International</hi>, 42 (1981), 2693-A. Diss., University of
       Toledo, 1981. [“In illustrations for <hi rend="i">Comus, Paradise Lost</hi>, the
       Nativity Ode, <hi rend="i">L’Allegro, Il Penseroso</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Paradise
        Regained</hi>, Blake casts off what he perceives as error to highlight areas of eternal
       verity. His interpretations become more affirmative in successive treatments of the same
       poems and in subsequent series of illustrations.”]</p>
            <p>131* Williams, Porter, Jr. “The Influence of Mrs. Barbauld’s <hi rend="i">Hymms
        in Prose for Children</hi> upon Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
        Experience.</hi>” Pp. 131-146 in <hi rend="i">A Fair Day in the Affections: Literary
        Essays in Honor of Robert B. White, Jr.</hi>, ed. Jack M. Durant and M. Thomas Hester.
       Raleigh: Winston, 1980.</p>
            <p>132 Zalitis, Emma Elfrida Dimza. “Stock, Bud, and Flowers: A Comparative Study of
       Mysticism in Böhme, Blake, and Coleridge.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
        International</hi>, 42 (1982), 3591-A. Diss., Purdue University, 1981. [“Chapter Three
       analyzes Jacob Böhme, his thematology and style, and compares his work to William
       Blake’s visionary poetry, including <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>
       and <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel.</hi> Blake’s dialectic of good and evil operates in
       the broad tradition of dialectical ontology identified, at least thematically, with
       Böhme. Blake often resorts, also, to the same image motifs as Böhme.”]</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">PART II<lb/>
<lb/>
 BLAKE’S CIRCLE</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>James Barry</title>
            </head>
            <p>133 Pressly, William L. <hi rend="i">The Life and Art of James Barry.</hi> New Haven, Conn.
       and London: Yale University Press, for the Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art,
       1981 [“Studies in British Art”]. Reviewed by Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">The</hi>
       [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 30 October 1981, pp. 1251-1252; and by
       Robert R. Wark, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 124 (1982), 159-160.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Robert Blair</title>
            </head>
            <p>See item 6, Essick and Paley.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>William Cowper</title>
            </head>
            <p>134 Baird, John D., and Charles Ryskamp, eds. <hi rend="i">The Poems of William Cowper.
        Vol. I: 1748-1782.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1980. $74.00. Reviewed by Donald H. Reiman,
        <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982), 149-151; by Norma
       Dalrymple-Champneys, <hi rend="i">Notes &amp; Queries</hi>, n.s. 29 (1982), 83-84; and by
       Patricia Meyer Spacks, <hi rend="i">JEGP</hi>, 81 (1982), 264-267.</p>
            <p>135 Griffin, Dustin. “Cowper, Milton, and the Recovery of Paradise.” <hi rend="i">Essays in
Criticism</hi>, 31 (1981), 15-26.</p>
            <p>136 King, James, and Charles Ryskamp, eds. <hi rend="i">The Letters and Prose Writings of
        William Cowper. Vol. I: “Adelphi” and Letters, 1750-1781.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon
       Press, 1979. $58.00. Reviewed by Donald H. Reiman, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
        Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982), 149-151; by Norma Dalrymple-Champneys, <hi rend="i">Notes &amp;
        Queries</hi>, n.s. 28 (1981), 82-84; and by Patricia Meyer Spacks, <hi rend="i">JEGP</hi>,
       81 (1982), 264-267.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>George Cumberland</title>
            </head>
            <p>See item 80, Keynes.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Richard Cumberland</title>
            </head>
            <p>137 Campbell, Thomas Joseph. “Richard Cumberland’s <hi rend="i">The Wheel of
        Fortune:</hi> A Critical Edition.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
        International</hi>, 42 (1982), 3608-A. Diss., University of Oregon, 1981. [“This
       dissertation presents Richard Cumberland’s 1795 sentimental comedy <hi rend="i">The
        Wheel of Fortune</hi> in a critical edition based on a fresh collation of all editions
       published during Cumberland’s lifetime (six in London, two in Dublin), the existing
       Larpent MS (from the Huntington Library), and the Kemble promptbook copy. . . .”]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>John Flaxman</title>
            </head>
            <p>138 Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Flaxman in Italy: A Letter Reflecting the ‘Anni
       Mirabiles,’ 1792-93.” <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi>, 63 (1981), 658-664.</p>
            <p>139 Fowler, Harriet Whittemore. “John Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Knight of the
        Blazing Cross.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 42 (1982),
       1353-A. Diss., Cornell University, 1981. [“John Flaxman wrote his allegory, <hi rend="i">The Knight
of the Blazing Cross</hi>, in 1796 as a birthday present for his wife, Ann
       Denham Flaxman. . . . The poem is not only a very personal expression of the artist but also
       reflects important eighteenth-century concerns that are not apparent in Flaxman’s more
       neoclassical works. . . . Most significantly, the poem may be seen as an expression of
       Flaxman’s Swedenborgian ideas.”]</p>
            <p>140 Krueger, Ingeborg. “John Flaxmans Umrisse zu Homer und die Homer-Buchillustration
       im 19. und 20. Jahrhundert.” <hi rend="i">Gutenberg-Jahrbuch 1974</hi>, pp. 247-268.</p>
            <p>141 Symmons, Sarah. “J. A. D. Ingres: The Apotheos is of Flaxman.” <hi rend="i">Burlington
Magazine</hi>, 121 (1979), 721-725.</p>
            <p>See also item 171, Hennig.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Henry Fuseli</title>
            </head>
            <p>142 Bedoni, Simonetta. “La donna nei disegni di J. H. Füssli.” 
<hi rend="i">Commonità</hi>, 30, no. 176 (1976), 294-377.</p>
            <p>143 Dörrbecker, Detlef W. “Fuseli, The Swiss, And The British: Some Recent
       Publications.” [Review essay.] <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15
       (1981), 53-56.</p>
            <p>144 Iser, Ursula. “Henry malt Magdalena: Aus dem Manuskript eines Romans.” 
<hi rend="i">Neue Zürcher Zeitung</hi>, 24 December 1981, 29-30. [The chapter on Fuseli
       from a forthcoming biographical novel on Magdalena Schweizer-Hess.]</p>
            <p>145* Knowles, John. <hi rend="i">The Life and Writings of Henry Fuseli.</hi> [1831; rpt.] 3
       vols., with a new introduction by David H. Weinglass. Millwood, N. Y.: Kraus, 1982
       [forthcoming].</p>
            <p>146 Mayoux, Jean-Jacques. “De Füssli à Fuseli: <pb id="p16-117" n="117"/>
Itineraire
d’une thematique.” <hi rend="i">Critique</hi>, 32 (1976),
       1243-1268.</p>
            <p>147 Starobinski, Jean. “Johann Heinrich Füssli.” Pp. 97-107 in <hi rend="i">1789: Die
Embleme der Vernunft</hi>, trsl. Gundula Göbel, ed. Friedrich A.
       Kittler. Paderborn, Munich, Vienna, and Zurich: Ferdinand Schöningh, 1981
       [“Uni-Taschenbücher”; vol. 1150].</p>
            <p>148* Weinglass, David H., ed. <hi rend="i">The Collected English Letters of Henry
        Fuseli.</hi> Millwood, N. Y.: Kraus, 1982. [Contains 606 letters by and to Fuseli dating
       from 1759 onwards.]</p>
            <p>Gavin Hamilton</p>
            <p>149 Errington, Lindsay. “Gavin Hamilton’s Sentimental Iliad.” <hi rend="i">Burlington
Magazine</hi>, 120 (1978), 11-13.</p>
            <p>150 Hulton, Serena Q. “‘A Historical Painter’: Gavin Hamilton in
       1755.” <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 120 (1978), 25-27.</p>
            <p>151* Tomory, Peter A. “Three Oaths for Gavin Hamilton.” <hi rend="i">Australian
        Journal of Art</hi>, 1 (1978), 59-64.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>John Linnell</title>
            </head>
            <p>152* Crouan, Katharine, ed. <hi rend="i">John Linnell: A Centennial Exhibition</hi>, exhb.
       cat. Cambridge: Fitzwilliam Museum, 1982 [forthcoming].</p>
            <p>153 Payne, Christiana. “John Linnell and Samuel Palmer in the 1820s.” 
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 124 (1982), 131-136.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Samuel Palmer</title>
            </head>
            <p>See items 26, Bentley, and 153, Payne.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>George Richmond</title>
            </head>
            <p>154 Lister, Raymond G. <hi rend="i">George Richmond (1809-1896): A Critical Biography.</hi>
       London: Robin Garton, 1981. [The first edition consists of 1000 copies only.]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>George Romney</title>
            </head>
            <p>155* Dixon, Yvonne R. <hi rend="i">The Drawings of George Romney in the Folger Shakespeare
        Library.</hi> Ann Arbor, Mich. and London: University Microfilms, 1981. [Xerox of a
       University of Maryland dissertation, 1977.]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Thomas Stothard</title>
            </head>
            <p>156 Finlay, N. “Thomas Stothard’s Illustrations of Thomson’s <hi rend="i">Seasons</hi>
for the Royal Engagement Pocket Atlas.” <hi rend="i">Princeton
        University Library Chronicle</hi>, 42 (1981), 165-177.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Edward Young</title>
            </head>
            <p>157 Phillips, Patricia. “Richardson, Young and the <hi rend="i">Conjectures.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Studia Neophilologica</hi>, 53 (1981), 107-112.</p>
            <p>158 Weisheimer, Joel. “Conjectures on Unoriginal Composition.” <hi rend="i">The
        Eighteenth Century</hi>, 22 (1981), 58-73.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">PART III</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">WORKS OF RELATED INTEREST</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>159 Bennett, Betty T., ed. <hi rend="i">British War Poetry in the Age of Romanticism:
       1793-1815.</hi> New York and London: Garland Publishing Inc., 1976. $47.00. Reviewed by David
      Punter, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982), 189-192.</p>
          <p>160 Brown, Catherine, ed. “S. Foster Damon (1893-1971): Selections from His Personal
      Journal.” <hi rend="i">Books at Brown</hi>, 28 (1981), 1-57.</p>
          <p>161 Cave, Kathryn, ed. <hi rend="i">The Diary of Joseph Farington</hi>, vols. 7 and 8
      (January 1805 to December 1807). New Haven, Conn. and London: Yale University Press, for the
      Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art, 1982 [“Studies in British Art”].</p>
          <p>162* <hi rend="i">Circa 1800: The Beginnings of Modern Printmaking, 1775-1835</hi>, exhb.
      cat. New Brunswick, N. J.: Rutgers University Art Gallery, 1981.</p>
          <p>163* Dillenberger, John. <hi rend="i">Benjamin West: The Context of His Life’s Work,
       with Particular Attention to Paintings with Religious Subject Matter</hi> [including a
      corrected version of early 19th-century lists of West’s paintings]. San Antonio, Texas:
      Trinity University Press, 1977. Reviewed by Allen Staley, <hi rend="i">Burlington
       Magazine</hi>, 123 (1981), 307-309.</p>
          <p>164* Eichner-Dixon, Peter. <hi rend="i">Studien zum Verhältnis von Dichtung und
       Malerei im englischen Neoklassizismus des 18. Jahrhunderts.</hi> Frankfurt am Main, Bern, and
      Las Vegas: Peter Lang, 1981 [“Europäische Hochschulschriften: European University
      Studies”; ser. XIV, vol. 93].</p>
          <p>165 Engell, James. <hi rend="i">The Creative Imagination: Enlightenment to Romanticism.</hi>
      Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1981. $16.00. Reviewed by Lilian R. Furst, 
<hi rend="i">JEGP</hi>, 81 (1982), 268-270; and by Robert Beum, <hi rend="i">The Sewanee
       Review</hi>, 90 (1982), xxxix-xli.</p>
          <p>166 <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi>, a play. Directed by Michael Davis. Reviewed by
      David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1981), 56-57.</p>
          <p>167* Gottlieb, Erika. <hi rend="i">Lost Angels of a Ruined Paradise: Themes of Cosmic Strife
       in Romantic Tragedy.</hi> Victoria, B. C.: Sono Nis Press, 1981.</p>
          <p>168 Güse, Ernst-G. <hi rend="i">Lehmbruck und Italien: Zeichnung, Graphik,
       Plastik</hi>, exhb. cat. Duisburg: Wilhelm-Lehmbruck-Museum, 1978 [“Studio”; vol.
      4]. [Pp. 13-14 contain a brief comparison between one of Lehmbruck’s etchings and the
      “Whirlwind” plate from Blake’s Dante series.]</p>
          <p>169* Hamel, Christopher de, and Richard A. Linenthal, eds. <hi rend="i">Fine Books and Book
       Collecting.</hi> Leamington Spa, Warwicks.: James Hall, 1981. [A <hi rend="i">Festschrift</hi> for the
antiquarian bookseller Alan Thomas, containing an essay on a Blake
      leaf by Raymond Lister which had been bought from Thomas.]</p>
          <p>170 Haskell, Francis, and Nicholas Penny. <hi rend="i">Taste and the Antique: The Lure of
       Classical Sculpture 1500-1900.</hi> New Haven, Conn. and London: Yale University Press,
      1981.</p>
          <p>171 Hennig, John. “Goethes Kenntnis britischer Künstler.” <hi rend="i">Zeitschrift für
Kunstgeschichte</hi>, 44 (1981), 171-180. [For Goethe and Flaxman see
      especially pp. 174-175.]</p>
          <p>172 Hume, Robert D., ed., <hi rend="i">The London Theatre World, 1660-1800.</hi> Carbondale
      and Edwardsville: Southern Illinois University Press, 1980. $18.50.</p>
          <p>173 Kahin, Sharon McFarlan. “Eighteenth Century British Primitivism.” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 42 (1981), 1354-A-1355-A. Diss., Cornell
      University, 1981.</p>
          <p>174 Keynes, Geoffrey L. <hi rend="i">The Gates of Memory.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press,
      1981. [Sir Geoffrey’s 
<pb id="p16-118" n="118"/>
autobiography must needs contain
      numerous references to his seventy years’ work as a bibliographer and editor of Blake;
      there are also chapters on the “discovery” of the poet-printer and on the formation
      of the Blake Trust, plus a reprint of Keynes’s “Religio bibliographici,”
      which relates many interesting facts about the compilation of the 1921 
<hi rend="i">Bibliography.</hi>]</p>
          <p>175* Paulson, Ronald. “Burke’s Sublime and the Representation of
      Revolution.” Pp. 241-269 in <hi rend="i">Culture and Politics: From Puritanism to the
       Enlightenment</hi>, ed. Perez Zagorin. Berkeley, CA, etc.: University of California Press,
      1980.</p>
          <p>176 Pechey, Graham. “The London Motif in Some Eighteenth-Century Contexts: A Semiotic
      Study.” <hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi>, [2], whole no. 4 (1976), 2-29.</p>
          <p>177* Raine, Kathleen J. <hi rend="i">Inner Journey of the Poet.</hi> London: George Allen
      and Unwin, 1981. [A volume of Miss Raine’s criticism, including, of course, discussions
      of Blake.]</p>
          <p>178 Rosemergy, Janet Mary Cramer. “Kathleen Raine, Poet of Eden: Her Poetry and
      Criticism.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 42 (1982), 3995-A.
      Diss., University of Michigan, 1981.</p>
          <p>179 Taube, Otto von. “Die Liebe des William Blake.” Pp. 248-256 in <hi rend="i">Ausgewählte
Werke.</hi> Hamburg: Friedrich Wittig, 1959. [This short story is
      connected with the author’s Blake translation of 1907.]</p>
          <p>180 Taube, Otto von. <hi rend="i">Stationen auf dem Wege: Erinnerungen an meine Werdezeit
       vor 1914.</hi> Heidelberg: Lothar Stiehm, 1968 [“Generation der Zeitwende: Schriften der
      Rudolf Alexander Schröder-Gesellschaft”; vol. 2]. [There is some account of this
      German poet’s work as a translator of Blake’s writings at the beginning of our
      century on pp. 23, 33, 41, 54-55, 60, 65, 77, 136-7, and 160 of this volume of memoirs.]</p>
          <p>181* Westbrook, Mike. <hi rend="i">Bright as Fire</hi> [a recording of jazz settings of
      Blake]. Reviewed by Anthony J. Harding, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15
      (1981), 97-98.</p>
          <p>182 Wittreich, Joseph A., Jr. “‘The Illustrious Dead’: Milton’s
      Legacy and Romantic Prophecy.” <hi rend="i">Milton and the Romantics</hi>, 4 (1980),
      17-32.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">PART IV</hi>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">REVIEWS OF WORKS CITED</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">IN PREVIOUS CHECKLISTS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>183 Bindman, David, ed. <hi rend="i">John Flaxman, R. A.</hi> Reviewed by Andrew Wilton, 
<hi rend="i">Master Drawings</hi>, 19 (1981), 48-49.</p>
          <p>184 Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake.</hi> Reviewed
      by Michael Ferber, <hi rend="i">Yale Review</hi>, 71, no. 2 (1982), ix-xiii.</p>
          <p>185 Damrosch, Leopold, Jr. <hi rend="i">Symbol and Truth in Blake’s Myth.</hi>
      Reviewed by Morris Eaves, <hi rend="i">JEGP</hi>, 81 (1982), 438-441; by Nelson Hilton, 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982), 192-196; by Stuart Curran, <hi rend="i">Modern
Language Quarterly</hi>, 42 (1981), 303-305; and by Michael Ackland, <hi rend="i">Southern Review</hi>, 14
(1981), 302-307.</p>
          <p>186 Dobai, Johannes. <hi rend="i">Die Kunstliteratur des Klassizismus und der Romantik in
       England</hi>, 3 vols. 1974-1977. Reviewed by Bernhard Fabian, <hi rend="i">Kunstchronik</hi>,
      34 (1981), 227-235; by Gerhard Charles Rump and Christian Wolsdorff, <hi rend="i">Journal of
       the Society of Architectural Historians</hi>, 35 (1976), 73 [on vol. 1]; by Gerhard Charles
      Rump, <hi rend="i">Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians</hi>, 35 (1976), 143-144
      [on vol. 2], and 37 (1978), 307-308 [on vol. 3]; the same reviews by Rump and Wolsdorff were
      also published in <hi rend="i">British Society for Eighteenth Century Studies/Newsletter</hi>,
      9 (1976), 38-42 [on vols. 1-2], and 21 (1979), 81-84 [on vol. 3].</p>
          <p>187 Dunbar, Pamela. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Poetry of
       Milton.</hi> Reviewed by Marcia R. Pointon, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 123
      (1981), 313-314; by J. Karl Franson, <hi rend="i">Milton Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1981),
      99-101.</p>
          <p>188 Einem, Herbert von. <hi rend="i">Deutsche Malerei des Klassizismus und der Romantik,
       1760 bis 1840.</hi> Reviewed by Thomas Pelzel, <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi>, 63 (1981),
      688-690.</p>
          <p>189 Erdman, David V., John E. Grant, Edward J. Rose, and Michael Tolley, eds., 
<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Designs for Edward Young’s Night Thoughts.</hi> Reviewed by
      Karen Mulhallen, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 12 (1981), 157-161; by David Bindman,
       <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 123 (1981), 312-313; and by Jean H. Hagstrum, 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 15 (1982), 339-344.</p>
          <p>190 Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">William Blake, Printmaker.</hi> Reviewed by David
      Alexander, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 123 (1981), 311-312; by Leopold Damrosch,
      Jr., <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 20 (1981), 544-545; and by Bo Ossian Lindberg,
       <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982), 140-148.</p>
          <p>191 Fairchild, B. H. <hi rend="i">Such Holy Song: Music as Idea, Form, and Image in the
       Poetry of William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by James A. Winn, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
       Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1981), 94-96; Stuart Peterfreund, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 12
      (1981), 167-169; and by Martha Winburn England, <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 20
      (1981), 545-549.</p>
          <p>192 Gallant, Christine. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Assimilation of Chaos.</hi> Reviewed by
      Stephen D. Cox, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 15 (1981-1982), 205-209.</p>
          <p>193 George, Diana Hume. <hi rend="i">Blake and Freud.</hi> Reviewed by Michael Ackland, 
<hi rend="i">Southern Review</hi>, 14 (1981), 302-307; by Brian Wilkie, <hi rend="i">Journal of
       English and Germanic Philology</hi>, 81 (1982), 115-118; and by Alicia Ostriker, 
<hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 12 (1981), 161-164.</p>
          <p>194 Haskell, Francis, and Nicholas Penny. <hi rend="i">Taste and the Antique.</hi> Reviewed
      by Alex Potts, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 123 (1981), 618-619; by Michele H.
      Bogart, <hi rend="i">The Georgia Review</hi>, 36 (1982), 208-212.</p>
          <p>195 Honour, Hugh. <hi rend="i">Romanticism.</hi> Reviewed by Karl Kroeber, <hi rend="i">Studies
in Romanticism</hi>, 20 (1981), 268-270; and by Lorenz Eitner, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 123
(1981), 368-369.</p>
          <p>196 Irwin, David. <hi rend="i">John Flaxman 1755-1826, Sculptor, Illustrator, Designer.</hi>
      Reviewed by Janice Lyle, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982),
      176-178.</p>
          <p>197 de Jackson, J. R., <hi rend="i">Poetry of the Romantic Period.</hi> Reviewed by E. B.
      Murray, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi>, 33 (1982), 209-213; and by E. D. 
<pb id="p16-119" n="119"/>
Mackerness, <hi rend="i">Notes &amp; Queries</hi>, n.s. 28 (1981),
      438-440.</p>
          <p>198 Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. <hi rend="i">The Letters of William Blake with Related
       Documents.</hi> 3rd ed. Reviewed by G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
       Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982), 138-139.</p>
          <p>199 Kircher, Gerda Franziska. <hi rend="i">Die Truchsessen-Galerie.</hi> Reviewed by Jan
      Lauts, <hi rend="i">Zeitschrift für Geschichte des Oberrheins</hi>, 128, n.s. 89
      (1980), 590-592.</p>
          <p>200 Klonsky, Milton. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Seer and His Visions.</hi> Reviewed by
      Gerda S. Norvig, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982), 184-187.</p>
          <p>201 Leader, Zachary. <hi rend="i">Reading Blake’s
       ‘‘Songs.’’</hi> Reviewed by Susan Matthews, <hi rend="i">English</hi>, 30 (1981), 296-302.</p>
          <p>202 Mellor, Anne K., <hi rend="i">English Romantic Irony.</hi> Reviewed by L. J. Swingle,
       <hi rend="i">Modern Language Quarterly</hi>, 42 (1981), 99-104; and by Stuart M. Tave, 
<hi rend="i">Philosophy and Rhetoric</hi>, 15 (1982), 145-147.</p>
          <p>203* Powell, Nicolas. <hi rend="i">Fuseli: The Nightmare.</hi> Reviewed by Gerhard Charles
      Rump, <hi rend="i">British Society for Eighteenth-Century Studies/Newsletter</hi>, 4 (1974),
      10.</p>
          <p>204 Raine, Kathleen J. <hi rend="i">Blake and Antiquity.</hi> Reviewed by Jean-Jacques
      Mayoux, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi>, 34 (1981), 346-348.</p>
          <p>205 Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">Blake and the New Age.</hi> Reviewed by Martin K. Nurmi,
       <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1981), 51-52; and by Christine Gallant,
       <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 12 (1981), 164-167.</p>
          <p>206 Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">From Blake to A Vision.</hi> Reviewed by Hazard Adams, 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1982), 187-188.</p>
          <p>207 Reiman, Donald H., ed. The Garland Facsimiles of Works by Erasmus Darwin. Reviewed by
      Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1981), 36-48.</p>
          <p>208 Reiman, Donald H., ed. The Garland Facsimiles of the Poetry of James Montgomery.
      Reviewed by Judy Page, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1981), 28-35.</p>
          <p>209 Reiman, Donald H., ed. The Garland Facsimiles of Works by William Hayley. Reviewed by
      Joseph Wittreich, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (1981), 48-50.</p>
          <p>210 Stafford, Barbara Maria. <hi rend="i">Symbol and Myth: Humbert de Superville’s
       Essay on Absolute Signs in Art.</hi> Reviewed by F. David Martin, <hi rend="i">Journal of
       Aesthetics and Art Criticism</hi>, 40 (1981), 233-234.</p>
          <p>211 Tyson, Gerald P. <hi rend="i">Joseph Johnson: A Liberal Publisher.</hi> Reviewed by
      Frank H. Ellis, <hi rend="i">The Review of English Studies</hi>, 33 (1982), 88-90; and by R.
      J. Roberts, <hi rend="i">Notes &amp; Queries</hi>, n.s. 28 (1981), 84-85.</p>
          <p>212 Vaughan, William. <hi rend="i">German Romanticism and English Art.</hi> Reviewed by
      Ekkehard Mai, <hi rend="i">Pantheon</hi>, 39 (1981), 188-192.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">INDEX TO AUTHORS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Ackland, Michael 17, 18, 185, 193</p>
          <p>Adams, Hazard 206</p>
          <p>Alexander, David, 190</p>
          <p>Alkjaer, Niels 19</p>
          <p>Allentuck, Marcia R. 20</p>
          <p>Andrews, Keith 9</p>
          <p>Aubrey, Bryan 21</p>
          <p>Baird, John D. 134</p>
          <p>Bandy, Melanie 22</p>
          <p>Banerjee, Tilak 23</p>
          <p>Beal, Ann Dickinson 24</p>
          <p>Bedoni, Simonetta 142</p>
          <p>Bennett, Betty J. 159</p>
          <p>Bennett, Shelley M. 10</p>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. 4, 25, 26, 138, 198</p>
          <p>Beum, Robert 165</p>
          <p>Bidney, Martin 27</p>
          <p>Billigheimer, Rachel Victoria 28</p>
          <p>Bindman, David 183, 189</p>
          <p>Bogan, James 30, 31, 32</p>
          <p>Bogart, Michele A. 194</p>
          <p>Böker, Uwe 33</p>
          <p>Bottrall, Margaret 34</p>
          <p>Bracher, Frederick Mark 35</p>
          <p>Brown, Catherine 160</p>
          <p>Butlin, Martin 11, 36, 37, 184</p>
          <p>Campbell, Thomas Joseph 137</p>
          <p>Carr, Stephen Leo 38</p>
          <p>Cave, Kathryn 161</p>
          <p>Corti, Claudia 39</p>
          <p>Cox, Stephen D. 40, 192</p>
          <p>Cribb, J. J. L1. 41</p>
          <p>Crosman, Inge 43</p>
          <p>Crossan, Greg 42</p>
          <p>Crouan, Katharine 152</p>
          <p>Culler, Jonathan 43</p>
          <p>Curran, Stuart 185</p>
          <p>Czymmek, Goetz 12</p>
          <p>Dalrymple-Champneys, Norma 134, 136</p>
          <p>Damrosch, Leopold, Jr. 185, 190</p>
          <p>Davidson, Peter 44</p>
          <p>Davis, Michael 166</p>
          <p>DeLuca, V. A. 13</p>
          <p>Diaconi, Mario 5</p>
          <p>Dickstein, Morris 45</p>
          <p>Dillenberger, John 163</p>
          <p>Dixon, Yvonne R. 155</p>
          <p>Dobai, Johannes 186</p>
          <p>Dörrbecker, Detlef W. 14, 46 143</p>
          <p>Doskow, Minna 47</p>
          <p>Downes, Margaret J. 48</p>
          <p>Dunbar, Pamela 187</p>
          <p>Durant, Jack M. 131</p>
          <p>Eaves, Morris 185</p>
          <p>Edwards, Gavin 114</p>
          <p>Eichner-Dixon, Peter 164</p>
          <p>Einem, Herbert von 188</p>
          <p>Eitner, Lorenz 195</p>
          <p>Ellis, Frank H. 211</p>
          <p>Ellis, James 49</p>
          <p>Engell, James 165</p>
          <p>England, Martha Winburn 191</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V. 50, 51, 189</p>
          <p>Errington, Lindsay 149</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N. 6, 52, 53, 54, 190</p>
          <p>Fabian, Bernhard 186</p>
          <p>Fairchild, B. H. 191</p>
          <p>Ferber, Michael 55, 56, 57, 184</p>
          <p>Finlay, N. 156</p>
          <p>Flor, João Almeida 58</p>
          <p>Fowler, Harriet Whittemore 139</p>
          <p>Fox, Celina 16</p>
          <p>Franson, J. Karl 59, 187</p>
          <p>Frye, Northrop 60, 61</p>
          <p>Furia, Philip 62</p>
          <p>Furst, Lilian R. 165</p>
          <p>Gallant, Christine 192, 205</p>
          <p>George, Diana Hume 193</p>
          <p>Givone, Sergio 63</p>
          <p>Glazer, Myra 64</p>
          <p>Glazer-Schotz, Myra 65</p>
          <p>Gleckner, Robert F. 66, 67</p>
          <p>Glen, Heather 68</p>
          <p>Göbel, Gundula 147</p>
          <p>Gottlieb, Erika 167</p>
          <p>Grant, John E. 189</p>
          <p>Griffin, Dustin 135</p>
          <p>Griffin, Paul Francis 69</p>
          <p>Güse, Ernst-G. 168</p>
          <p>Hagstrum, Jean H. 189</p>
          <p>Hamel, Christopher de 169</p>
          <p>Harding, Anthony J. 181</p>
          <p>Haskell, Francis 170, 194</p>
          <p>Hatherly, Ana 70</p>
          <p>Heitmann, Klaus 93</p>
          <p>Helms, Randel 71, 72</p>
          <p>Hennig, John 171</p>
          <p>Heppner, Christopher 73</p>
          <p>Herrstrom, David Sten 74</p>
          <p>Hester, M. Thomas 131</p>
          <p>Hilton, Nelson 75, 185, 207</p>
          <p>Hiromoto, Katsuya 76</p>
          <p>Honour, Hugh 195</p>
          <p>Hood, Margaret Anne 76A</p>
          <p>Hulton, Serena Q. 150</p>
          <p>Hume, Robert D. 172</p>
          <p>Irwin, David 196</p>
          <p>Iser, Ursula 144</p>
          <p>de Jackson, J. R. 197</p>
          <p>Lauts, Jan 199</p>
          <p>Lyle, Janice 196</p>
          <p>Kahin, Sharon McFarlan 173</p>
          <p>Kauvar, Elaine M. 77</p>
          <p>Keynes, Geoffrey L. 78, 79, 80, 174, 198</p>
          <p>King, James 136</p>
          <p>Kircher, Gerda Franziska 199</p>
          <p>Kirk, Eugene 81</p>
          <p>Kittler, Friedrich A. 147</p>
          <p>Klonsky, Milton 200</p>
          <p>Knowles, John 145</p>
          <p><corr type="emend">Kroeber, Karl</corr> 195</p>
          <p>Krueger, Ingeborg 140</p>
          <p>La Belle, Jenijoy 82, 83</p>
          <p>Lange, Thomas V. 84</p>
          <p>Lattin, Vernon E. 85</p>
          <p>Leader, Zachary 86, 201</p>
          <p>Lindberg, Bo Ossian 190</p>
          <p>Linenthal, Richard A. 169</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond G, 154, 169</p>
          <p>Luck, Marianna Mendillo 87</p>
          <p>Mackerness, E. D. 197</p>
          <p>Mai, Ekkehard 212</p>
          <p>Manetti, P. 2</p>
          <p>Mann, Paul 34</p>
          <p>Martin, F. David 210</p>
          <p>Mathews, Lawrence 88, 89</p>
          <p>Matthews, Susan 201</p>
          <p>Matlin, David 90</p>
          <p>Mayoux, Jean-Jacques 146, 204</p>
          <p>McCarthy, Shaun 91</p>
          <p>McGinnis, Wayne D. 92</p>
          <p>Meller, Horst 93</p>
          <p>Mellor, Anne K. 202</p>
          <p>Mewton, Robert 94</p>
          <p>Mills, Alice 95</p>
          <p>Minnick, Thomas L. 14</p>
          <p>Mulhallen, Karen 189</p>
          <p>Murray, E. B. 96, 197</p>
          <p>Norvig, Gerda 65, 200</p>
          <p>Noshiro, Shoho 97</p>
          <p>Nurmi, Martin K. 205</p>
          <p>Ortiz, Anna Louise 98</p>
          <p>Ostriker, Alicia 193</p>
          <p>Page, Judy 208</p>
          <p>Pagliaro, Harold E. 99</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D. 6, 100</p>
          <p>Paulson, Ronald 175</p>
          <p>Payne, Christiana 153</p>
          <p>Pechey, Graham 176</p>
          <p>Pelzel, Thomas 188</p>
          <p>Penny, Nicholas 170, 194</p>
          <p>Peterfreund, Stuart 101, 191</p>
          <p>Phillips, Patricia 157</p>
          <p>Pointon, Marcia R. 187</p>
          <p>Potts, Alex 194</p>
          <p>Powell, Nicolas 203</p>
          <p>Praz, Mario 102</p>
          <p>Pressly, William L. 133</p>
          <p>Punter, David 103, 159</p>
          <p>Quadri Iovine, Marcella 104</p>
          <p>Raine, Kathleen J. 105, 106, 177, 204, 205, 206</p>
          <p>Read, Dennis M. 107, 108</p>
          <p>Reiman, Donald H. 134, 136, 207, 208, 209</p>
          <p>Reynolds, Graham 133</p>
          <p>Riede, David G. 109</p>
          <pb id="p16-120" n="120"/>
          <p>Ringblom, Håkan 129</p>
          <p>Rivero, Albert J. 110</p>
          <p>Roberts, R. J. 211</p>
          <p>Rose, Edward J. 189</p>
          <p>Rosemergy, Janet Mary Cramer 178</p>
          <p>Röttgen, Herbert 113</p>
          <p>Rump, Gerhard Charles 186, 203</p>
          <p>Ryskamp, Charles 134, 136</p>
          <p>Salemi, Joseph S. 111</p>
          <p>Sánchez, Auilino 112</p>
          <p>Sanesi, R. 1</p>
          <p>Sellner, Albert 113</p>
          <p>Simpson, David 114</p>
          <p>Singh, Charu Sheel 115</p>
          <p>Skipp, Francis E. 116</p>
          <p>Smith, Joseph H. 45</p>
          <p>Smith, Stan 117</p>
          <p>Soubly, Diane M. 118</p>
          <p>Spacks, Patricia Meyer 134, 136</p>
          <p>Stafford, Barbara Maria 210</p>
          <p>Staley, Allen 163</p>
          <p>Starling, Roy 119</p>
          <p>Starobinski, Jean 147</p>
          <p>Storch, Margaret 120</p>
          <p>Suleiman, Susan R. 43</p>
          <p>Summerfield, Henry 121, 122</p>
          <p>Sutton, Dorothy Moseley 123</p>
          <p>Swingle, L. J. 202</p>
          <p>Symmons, Sarah 141</p>
          <p>Tagliaferri, Aldo 5</p>
          <p>Tannenbaum, Leslie W. 124</p>
          <p>Taube, Otto von 179, 180</p>
          <p>Tave, Stuart M. 202</p>
          <p>Thurn, Christiane 113</p>
          <p>Tingle, William Nicholas 125</p>
          <p>Tolley, Michael 189</p>
          <p>Tomory, Peter A. 151</p>
          <p>Tyson, Gerald P. 211</p>
          <p>Ungaretti, Giuseppi 5</p>
          <p>Vaughan, Frank A. 126</p>
          <p>Vaughan, William 212</p>
          <p>Wardle, Judith 127</p>
          <p>Wark, Robert R. 133</p>
          <p>Waxler, Robert P. 128</p>
          <p>Weathers, Winston 129</p>
          <p>Weinglass, David H. 145, 148</p>
          <p>Weisheimer, Joel 158</p>
          <p>Werner, Bette Charlene, 130</p>
          <p>Westbrook, Mike 181</p>
          <p>Wilkie, Brian 193</p>
          <p>Williams, Porter, Jr. 131</p>
          <p>Wilton, Andrew 183</p>
          <p>Winn, James A. 191</p>
          <p>Wittreich, Joseph A., Jr. 182, 209</p>
          <p>Wolsdorff, Christian 186</p>
          <p>Worrall, David 166</p>
          <p>Wright, John W. 8</p>
          <p>Young, Michael C. 54</p>
          <p>Zagorin, Perez 175</p>
          <p>Zalitis, Emma Elfrida Dimza 132</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
