<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.2.johnson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The Norton Critical Edition of Blake: Addenda and Corrigenda</title>
        <author n="Johnson">Mary Lynn Johnson</author>
        <author n="Grant">John E. Grant</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Krzysztof Z. Cieszkowski</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Christina Shuttleworth Kraus</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Judith W. Page</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Thomas A. Vogler</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
      <pb id="p16-107" n="107"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-2-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">THE NORTON CRITICAL EDITION OF BLAKE: ADDENDA AND CORRIGENDA</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">MARY LYNN</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">JOHNSON</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
          <hi rend="b">AND</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">JOHN E.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">GRANT</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>Both internally and externally, the recent second printing of <hi rend="i">Blake’s
      Poetry and Designs</hi> displays noteworthy improvements. In the first printing the heavy
     color plates failed to adhere to the “Perfect Binding,” the trade name for a process
     which has also caused problems in other paperback illustrated books, such as <hi rend="i">The
      Oxford Anthology of English Literature</hi>; in our second printing, however, the binder
     forced the glue further up between pages, and thick and thin pages now appear to be holding
     together. Though this is of course not a new edition, the corrected printing includes important
     additions, such as the excerpt from the letter to Butts on allegory (p. 478), and changes, such
     as the new reading of a crucial phrase in the first Preface to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (p.
     312). Our original proposal to W. W. Norton had contained full texts of <hi rend="i">The Four
      Zoas</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, but to come within the publisher’s estimated
     price limit of $3.95, we had to trim the total length to 600 pages, including pictures,
     selections from the prose, and the critical essays required by the series format. Sadly, during
     the three years the book was in process of publication, the actual price went up to
     $9.95—still the price of the second printing—and there is obviously now little
     hope that full texts of the longer works will ever be restored in a new edition. Our
     corrections in this printing do not extend to the Bibliography, because the printing was
     carried out before we had submitted our new material; we shall nevertheless indicate the
     changes we had hoped to make in that section. The following list includes substantial changes;
     asterisks (*) indicate further corrections which do <hi rend="i">not</hi> appear in the new
     printing. We would appreciate hearing from readers who discover errors we have overlooked.</p>
        <p>p. xi. <hi rend="i">Add</hi> “To Thomas Butts, April 25, 1803 [*<hi rend="i">should
      be</hi> July 6, 1803] . . . 478”</p>
        <p>*p. xxix. Under “1779” <hi rend="i">add</hi> “Met Flaxman, sculptor” and
     delete Flaxman from the 1780 entry.</p>
        <p>p. xxxvii. For entries under 1820 and 1821, Blake’s “Times,” <hi rend="i">substitute</hi> new
entries: 1820 (January 29) Death of George III. Prince Regent becomes
     George IV (coronation June, 1821). Keats’s last volume of poems. Shelley’s <hi rend="i">Prometheus
Unbound.</hi> Southey’s <hi rend="i">A Vision of Judgment.</hi>
     1821 Death of Keats in Italy. Shelley’s <hi rend="i">Adonais.</hi> Byron’s <hi rend="i">Cain, Don
Juan</hi> III-IV.</p>
        <p>*p. xlii. “The Holy Land” map: The southern boundary of the Northern Kingdom should
     be the river Kanah; the letters “NOR” extend too far south. In the inset, Golgotha
     should be outside the city walls.</p>
        <p>p. xliii, line 13 from bottom. <hi rend="i">For</hi> “enlongated” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
“elongated.”</p>
        <p>p. xlv. Before the final paragraph, <hi rend="i">insert</hi> a new paragraph:
<q> Assuming
      that the reader will develop a tolerance for Blake’s irregularities while working
      through this text, we have altered Blake’s punctuation more in the earlier poems, less
      in the later ones. </q></p>
        <p>p. 17. <hi rend="i">Add</hi> a new sentence to the last line:
<q> For some early drafts, see
      pp. 176-181. </q></p>
        <p>*p. 21. The lopped-off design, omitting the boy who 
<pb id="p16-108" n="108"/>
hands the
     grapes to the girl, unfortunately could not be corrected in this reprinting.</p>
        <p>p. 40, footnote 7. <hi rend="i">Add</hi>: “cf. <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
     15:8.”</p>
        <p>p. 43, footnote 8. <hi rend="i">Add</hi>: “cf. ‘Earth’s
     Answer.’”</p>
        <p>pp. 45-46. The last two stanzas of “The Little Girl Found” should be on p. 45, the
     design on p. 46.</p>
        <p>p. 47. Both stanzas of “The Sick Rose” should appear on this page.</p>
        <p>p. 48, last line of footnote. <hi rend="i">For</hi> “ther” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
     “their.”</p>
        <p>p. 49, add to footnote. “See drafts of this poem, pp. 178-180.”</p>
        <p>*p. 53, add to footnote 2. “See E. P. Thompson in <hi rend="i">Interpreting Blake</hi>,
     ed. Michael Phillips (1978).”</p>
        <p>p. 54. Keyed to title, “Infant Sorrow,” a new footnote 7: “See draft, pp.
     180-182.” Subsequent footnotes are renumbered.</p>
        <p>p. 69, line 25. <hi rend="i">For</hi> “of” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
     “on.”</p>
        <p>p. 82, line 8. <hi rend="i">For</hi> “Swendenborg’s” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
     “Swedenborg’s.”</p>
        <p>*p. 87. <hi rend="i">Correct</hi> “But the following Contraries to these are:” 
<hi rend="i">to</hi> “But the following Contraries to these are True:”</p>
        <p>p. 88. “A Memorable Fancy,” line 2: <hi rend="i">For</hi> “enjoyment” 
<hi rend="i">read</hi> “enjoyments.”</p>
        <p>p. 88, last line of plate 6. After “rock” <hi rend="i">correct</hi> comma to
     semicolon.</p>
        <p>p. 101, footnote 1. <hi rend="i">For</hi> the first sentence of this footnote, 
<hi rend="i">substitute</hi> a new sentence: “At the beginning of this Memorable Fancy the Devil has
     appeared in this flame.”</p>
        <p>*p. 103, second paragraph, line 7 from bottom. <hi rend="i">Delete</hi> “of”;
     phrase should read “the antagonists Orc and Urizen.”</p>
        <p>p. 104. Before the final paragraph, <hi rend="i">insert</hi> a new paragraph:
<q><hi
rend="i">America</hi> is the first of the “Lambeth books,” works produced while
      the Blakes lived in the Hercules buildings, Lambeth, on the south side of the Thames (see
      map). <hi rend="i">America, Europe, The Song of Los, Urizen, Ahania</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The
       Book of Los</hi> make up a distinct sub-group in Blake’s canon, sharing common themes
      and images of the fallen human condition; each of these has the word “Lambeth” on
      its title page. </q></p>
        <p>p. 121, line 2 (<hi rend="i">America</hi> 16:17). <hi rend="i">Insert</hi> comma after
     “Albion”; <hi rend="i">delete</hi> comma after “Guardians.”</p>
        <p>p. 121, line 3 (16:18). <hi rend="i">Delete</hi> comma after “plagues.”</p>
        <p>p. 121, line 4 (16:19). <hi rend="i">For</hi> colon after “heaven,” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
comma.</p>
        <p>p. 121, line 6 (16:21). <hi rend="i">For</hi> period after “Orc,” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
colon.</p>
        <p>p. 121, footnote 3. <hi rend="i">For</hi> “Vames” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
     “James.”</p>
        <p>*p. 124, footnote 4. <hi rend="i">For</hi> “Fairly” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
     “Fairy.”</p>
        <p>p. 127, plate 5, line 6. <hi rend="i">For</hi> “worm” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
     “worms.”</p>
        <p>p. 127, footnote 3. The second sentence of this footnote <hi rend="i">should read</hi>:
     “Rintrah’s bride Ocalython personifies sexual jealousy and Palamabron’s
     queen Elynittria personifies chastity . . . .”</p>
        <p>p. 143, plate 3, line 25 (stanza 5). <hi rend="i">Delete</hi> “up.”</p>
        <p>p. 143, plate 3, line 29 (stanza 6). <hi rend="i">For</hi> “army” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
“array.”</p>
        <p>p. 144, plate 4, line 1 (stanza 3). <hi rend="i">Delete</hi> colon after
     “desarts.”</p>
        <p>p. 144, plate 4, line 6 (stanza 4). <hi rend="i">Change</hi> period to comma after
     “solitude.”</p>
        <p>p. 144, plate 4, line 17 (stanza 5). <hi rend="i">Change</hi> semicolon to comma after
     “was”; <hi rend="i">insert</hi> period after “womb.”</p>
        <p>p. 145, plate 4, line 46 (stanza 2). <hi rend="i">Delete</hi> comma after
     “blood.”</p>
        <p>p. 145, last line (stanza 4). <hi rend="i">Insert</hi> “the” after “o’er” 
        and before “dark.”</p>
        <p>p. 146, plate 5, line 28 (stanza 7). <hi rend="i">Delete</hi> comma after “roof.”
     (*And after “around.”)</p>
        <p>*p. 147, plate 8, line 2 (stanza 1). <hi rend="i">Insert</hi> “t” in
     “hurtling.”</p>
        <p>p. 148, plate 10, line 18 (stanza 2). <hi rend="i">Insert</hi> comma after
     “links.”</p>
        <p>p. 151, plate 13, line 21 (stanza 1). <hi rend="i">Change</hi> colon to period after
     “hand.”</p>
        <p>p. 151, plate 13, line 36 (stanza 4). <hi rend="i">Insert</hi> period after
     “region.”</p>
        <p>p. 152, plate 15, line 2. <hi rend="i">Delete</hi> hyphen in “death image.”</p>
        <p>*p. 155, plate 20, line 41 (stanza 8). <hi rend="i">Capitalize</hi> first letter in
     “Fruits.”</p>
        <p>p. 155, plate 20, line 44 (stanza 9). <hi rend="i">For</hi> “Form” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
“From.”</p>
        <p>p. 156, first line in stanza 5. <hi rend="i">Change</hi> semicolon to colon after
     “death” and close the space separating this line from the remainder of stanza 5.</p>
        <p>p. 160, line 5 from bottom. <hi rend="i">For</hi> “early in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">read</hi> “<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> 24:17.”</p>
        <p>p. 178, line 3. <hi rend="i">For</hi> “Hand or eye” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
     “hand &amp; eye.”</p>
        <pb id="p16-109" n="109"/>
        <p>*p. 202, “The Mental Traveller,” line 8. Add new footnote 1, keyed to this line:
     “Cf. Psalms 126:5, ‘They that sow in tears shall reap in joy.’”
     Renumber subsequent footnotes.</p>
        <p>*p. 223, footnote 3, line 2 from bottom. <hi rend="i">Add</hi> comma after
     “counterparts.”</p>
        <p>p. 232, MS page 123, line 20. <hi rend="i">For</hi> “piered” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
     “piercd.” (*And restore “20” line-number.)</p>
        <p>*p. 244, footnote 7. <hi rend="i">For</hi> “suburbs” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
     “villages.”</p>
        <p>p. 264, plate 19, line 5. <hi rend="i">For</hi> “Armon” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
     “Arnon.”</p>
        <p>p. 272, line 2 from bottom. <hi rend="i">For</hi> “Wesley” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
     “Westley.”</p>
        <p>p. 297, plate 36, line 22. <hi rend="i">Change</hi> period to semicolon after
     “whirlwind.”</p>
        <p>p. 306, plate 42, line 37. <hi rend="i">Change</hi> period to comma after
     “prepar’d.”</p>
        <p>p. 312, line 6. <hi rend="i">For</hi> “entrusted” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
     “acknowledge” (*the “c” in this word was omitted in the corrected
     printing); <hi rend="i">for</hi> “Writing” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
     “Deities.”</p>
        <p>p. 312, footnote 4. <hi rend="i">Delete</hi> old footnote and <hi rend="i">substitute</hi>
     new one: 
	<q> In published texts Erdman conjectured “entrusted” for the first
      “acknowledge” and “Writing” for “Deities”; this new reading by
      Erdman derives from an unpublished suggestion by Michael J. Tolley. </q></p>
        <p>p. 340, plate 62, line 17. <hi rend="i">Change</hi> period to semicolon after
     “weak.”</p>
        <p>*p. 359, line 7 of second paragraph. <hi rend="i">Insert</hi> semicolon before
     “the.”</p>
        <p>p. 361, at end of footnote 3. <hi rend="i">Add</hi>: “See also Leslie Tannenbaum, 
<hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi> 72 (1975).”</p>
        <p>*p. 367, part 4, line 77. <hi rend="i">For</hi> “Sprit” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
     “Spirit.”</p>
        <p>p. 369, part 5, line 38. <hi rend="i">Insert</hi> period after “Hipocricy.”</p>
        <p>p. 369, part 5, line 39. <hi rend="i">Change</hi> semicolon to comma after
     “way.”</p>
        <p>*p. 384, note 3. <hi rend="i">Delete</hi> footnote and <hi rend="i">substitute</hi> new one:
	<q> Paraphrased from the opening lines of <hi rend="i">Urania</hi> (1630) by the self-styled
      Water Poet, John Taylor (1583-1653), sailor and pamphleteer. </q></p>
        <p>*p. 417, lines 5-7. <hi rend="i">Delete</hi> sentence (“Since . . . oration”) and
      <hi rend="i">substitute</hi> new one:
<q> For information on the Chalcographic Society, see
      Dennis Read, <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> (forthcoming). </q></p>
        <p>*p. 456. After “To Thomas Butts, January 10, 1802” <hi rend="i">add</hi>, in
     brackets, “[i.e., 1803].”</p>
        <p>*p. 476, footnote 8. <hi rend="i">Change</hi> period to semicolon and <hi rend="i">add</hi>
     “his wife was a semi-professional engraver acquainted with others in Blake’s
     circle.”</p>
        <p>p. 478. <hi rend="i">Add</hi> the following excerpt from Blake’s letter to Butts of
     April 25, 1803 [*<hi rend="i">should be</hi> July 6, 1803]:
<q> Thus I hope that all our three
      years’ trouble Ends in Good Luck at last &amp; shall be forgot by my affections &amp;
      only remember’d by my Understanding; to be a Memento in time to come, &amp; to speak
      to future generations by a Sublime Allegory, which is now perfectly completed into a Grand
      Poem. I may praise it, since I dare not pretend to be any other than the Secretary; the
      Authors are in Eternity. I consider it as the Grandest Poem that this World contains. Allegory
      address’d to the Intellectual powers, while it is altogether hidden from the Corporeal
      Understanding, is my definition of the Most Sublime Poetry; it is also somewhat in the same
      manner defined by Plato. This Poem shall, by Divine Assistance, be progressively Printed
      &amp; Ornamented with Prints &amp; given to the Public. </q></p>
        <p>p. 498, line 3. <hi rend="i">Insert</hi> quotation mark before “<hi rend="i">Irving</hi>”; 
<hi rend="i">delete</hi> quotation mark before “He.”
      <hi rend="i">Repunctuate</hi> last four lines of this excerpt as follows:
<q>
      —‘You never saw the spiritual Sun—I have.—I saw him on Primrose
      Hill.—He said “Do you take me for the Greek Apollo?” “No!” I said.
      “That” (pointing to the Sky) “That is the Greek Apollo—He is
      Satan.”’ </q></p>
        <p>*pp. 602-607: Changes we intended to make in the Bibliography take into account the following
     rules of thumb: (1) specialized studies are mentioned only in headnotes and footnotes; (2) only
     the most comprehensive recent treatments of major subjects are included (these in turn refer to
     important earlier studies); (3) essays included in the books listed under “VI. Collections
     of Essays” do not reappear under “VII. Selected Essays”; (4) extensive resetting
     of type is not possible in a corrected printing.</p>
        <p>We hesitate to mention “forthcoming” works because we were wrong about the dates of
     the Butlin catalogue and the Clarendon edition of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, delayed in
     publication; thus in making corrections we would produce the anomaly of listing 1980-81 books
     in our 1979 edition. We will nevertheless venture to include in our wished-for corrections
     several other recent books but will not attempt to add articles published after 1979. One
     stellar book we had hoped to include now appears to have been cancelled by Scolar Press before
     publication: Sir Geoffrey Keynes’s edition of Copy W of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence
      and of Experience</hi>, announced in <hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi> 29 (1980); such are the
     perils of trying to keep a bibliography current for a future date of publication.</p>
        <pb id="p16-110" n="110"/>
        <p>*p. 602, last line. After “British Museum Collection” <hi rend="i">insert</hi>
     “by P. Morgan, edited by G. E. Bentley, Jr.”</p>
        <p>*p. 603, line 1. After “Library of Congress” <hi rend="i">insert</hi> “by Ruth
     Fine Lehrer.”</p>
        <p>*p. 603, lines 7-8. <hi rend="i">Delete</hi> final sentence of this paragraph and 
<hi rend="i">substitute</hi> a new sentence: “Martin Butlin’s <hi rend="i">The
      Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (New Haven and London: Yale Univ. Press, 1981) is
     a complete catalogue raisonné.”</p>
        <p>*p. 603, mid-page. <hi rend="i">For</hi> “Facsimilies” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
     “Facsimiles.”</p>
        <p>*p. 603, under “Facsimiles of Manuscripts,” in the correct alphabetical position:
<q><hi
rend="i">Tiriel: Facsimile and Transcript of the Manuscript, Reproduction of the Drawings
       and a Commentary on the Poem</hi>, by G. E. Bentley, Jr. Oxford: Clarendon, 1967. </q></p>
        <p>*p. 603, line 3 from bottom. After “<hi rend="i">Book of Thel</hi>” <hi rend="i">insert</hi>
“edited by Nancy Bogen.”</p>
        <p>*p. 604, lines 1-2. <hi rend="i">Delete</hi> “six more illuminated books are scheduled
     for publication in 1979.”</p>
        <p>*p. 604, line 5. <hi rend="i">Add</hi> “and <hi rend="i">Blake’s Grave</hi> by S.
     Foster Damon (Providence: Brown Univ. Press, 1963); a full edition of this work, with
     commentary by Robert N. Essick and Morton D. Paley, appeared in 1982.<supplied
type="emend">”</supplied></p>
        <p>*p. 604, under “II. Art: Collections and Commentaries,” <hi rend="i">add</hi> all
     the following:</p>
        <p>Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">William Blake 1757-1827.</hi> Munich: Prestal Verlag and
     Hamburger Kunsthalle, 1975.</p>
        <p>Dunbar, Pamela. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Poetry of
      Milton.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon, 1980.</p>
        <p>(under Erdman) <hi rend="i">For</hi> “1979” <hi rend="i">read</hi>
     “1980.”</p>
        <p>Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">William Blake Printmaker.</hi> Princeton: Princeton Univ.
     Press, 1980.</p>
        <p>Klonsky, Milton. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations to Dante.</hi> New York: Harmony
     Books, 1980.</p>
        <p>Mongan, Elizabeth and Wolf, Edwin II. <hi rend="i">William Blake 1757-1827.</hi>
     Philadelphia: Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1939.</p>
        <p>Russell, A. G. B. <hi rend="i">The Engravings of William Blake.</hi> Boston: Houghton
     Mifflin, 1912; rpt. New York: Benjamin Blom, 1968.</p>
        <p>*p. 605, under “IV. Biographies”:</p>
        <p>Keynes, Geoffrey. <hi rend="i">The Complete Portraiture of William and Catherine Blake.</hi>
     Paris and London: Trianon Press, 1977.</p>
        <p>*p. 605, under “V. Books of Criticism”:</p>
        <p>Damrosch, Leopold, Jr. <hi rend="i">Symbol and Truth in Blake’s Myth.</hi> Princeton:
     Princeton Univ. Press, 1980.</p>
        <p>George, Diana Hume. <hi rend="i">Blake and Freud.</hi> Ithaca: Cornell Univ. Press, 1980.</p>
        <p>*p. 606, under “VI. Collections of Essays”:</p>
        <p>Phillips, Michael, ed. <hi rend="i">Interpreting Blake.</hi> Cambridge: Cambridge Univ.
     Press, 1978.</p>
        <p>*p. 607, under “VII. Selected Essays”:</p>
        <p>Pechey, Graham. “The London Motif in Some Eighteenth-Century Contexts: A Semiotic
     Study.” <hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi>, 1:4 (1976), 2-28.</p>
        <p>A postscript: The first printing has been recalled by the publisher and should no longer be
     stocked in bookstores. Anyone whose duly purchased copy of the first printing fell apart may
     receive a new book by writing Mr. James L. Mairs, W. W. Norton &amp; Company, Inc., 500 Fifth
     Ave., New York, N.Y. 10036, and enclosing the first two pages (false title and title page) of
     the defective copy. Complimentary copies, excluding desk copies, cannot be replaced.</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
