<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.2.cieszkowski</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Joëlle Abitbol, trans., William Blake, The Everlasting Gospel/L’évangile éternel</title>
        <author n="Cieszkowski">Krzysztof Z. Cieszkowski</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Krzysztof Z. Cieszkowski</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Christina Shuttleworth Kraus</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Judith W. Page</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Thomas A. Vogler</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
	<pb id="p16-128" n="128"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-2-0010">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Blake. <hi rend="b">The Everlasting Gospel/L’évangile
        éternel</hi>, trans. by Joëlle Abitbol [text and French translation]. Paris:
       Editions Vrac, 1981. 45 pp., illus.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Krzysztof Z.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Cieszkowski</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Everlasting Gospel</hi> exists in manuscript form scattered
      through the pages of the <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> in the Department of Manuscripts in the
      British Museum, and in part in the Rosenbach MS; it is usually dated c. 1818. A full treatment
      of the work and the bibliographical and interpretational problems it raises can be found in
      Randel Helms’s essay <hi rend="i">The Genesis of “The Everlasting
       Gospel”</hi> in <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 9 (1980), 122-60.</p>
          <p>Joëlle Abitbol and Samuel Tastet’s edition prints the text and Mme.
      Abitbol’s French translation in parallel; it constitutes “Volume I” of a
      series entitled <hi rend="i">Double Same/Double Mème.</hi> Despite the inscription of
      the verso of the title-page, “c Editions G. Keynes—1957,” the text used
      adheres to the conjecturally chronological arrangement printed by Bentley; but its adherence
      is limited: Abitbol and Tastet eschew Blake’s capitalization and a fair 
<pb id="p16-129" n="129"/>
proportion of his punctuation, and the passages used are selected
      according to no obvious procedure (there is no mention of the fact that the text is
      selective). The text takes seven of the eleven or twelve sections and rearranges them
      according to no immediately apparent plan, labeling them I-VII; in Keynes’s
      nomenclature, the order of the edition is: Supplementary passage 2, Supplementary passage l,
      i, a,d,e,b,f; in Bentley’s nomenclature (following the Rosenbach MS and attempting a
      chronological realignment), the order is b,c,d,e,j,f,i,l. In any case, there are three
      sections missing, including the short prose passage at the beginning, and one of the two
      “Was Jesus Humble?” passages (p. 52 in the <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>).</p>
          <p>The text and illustrations are printed in an unattractive ochre-colored ink, and italics are
      used for quotations; the French text is aligned to the right-hand margin, which makes reading
      difficult. The translation does not attempt to reproduce Blake’s irregular four-foot
      iambic line, and so loses the headlong momentum of the invective of the poem; it also does not
      attempt the paired rhymes of the original, although rhyming couplets seem to occasionally slip
      into the French translation as if by chance (e.g., lines 3-4, 5-6 of the first section). The
      final two-line section is particularly inadequately translated: “Je suis certain que
      Jésus ne ferait pas cela, / A un Anglais ou à un Juif” distorts the meaning
      of “I am sure this Jesus will not do, / Either for Englishman or Jew”—the
      addition of “cela” loses the idiomatic sense of the line and introduces all sorts of
      new (and unwanted) meanings.</p>
          <p>The editors of this text include a quotation from Revelation 14:6, “and I saw another
      angel fly in the midst of Heaven, having the everlasting gospel to preach unto them that dwell
      on the earth . . . ”; this may be the source of Blake’s title for what is
      admittedly a very fragmentary and obscure work, but it need not necessarily be so, and has no
      further referential connection with the poem. Its inclusion adds nothing more than an
      additional disruptive perspective.</p>
          <p>Blake’s pen and watercolor drawing <hi rend="i">The Blasphemer</hi> (Tate Gallery
      5195; Butlin 446, dated c. 1800) is reproduced on the cover of the publication; on the back it
      is reproduced in reverse (probably to highlight the title of the series), an unattractive
      proceeding under any circumstances; coarse-grained ochre reproductions of details from the
      watercolor appear inside the text, again with a laterally-reversed copy of the image on the
      facing page. <hi rend="i">The Blasphemer</hi> is usually taken to represent the stoning to
      death of the Israelite woman’s son who blasphemed the name of the Lord, Leviticus 24:23
      (Butlin 446), although William Rossetti retitled it <hi rend="i">The Stoning of Achan</hi>,
      after Joshua 7:1, 18-25; the relationship of this subject (or these subjects) to the text in
      question is problematical if not dubious—Blake’s poem is a headlong invective
      against a particularly milk-and-water conception of Christ, and the stoning of a tied, tensed
      figure by fierce-eyed elders bears little relation to this. Among the bibliographical data of
      the edition, “Gravure de couverture de William Blake” is translated as “Design
      cover of William Blake”—as if attempting to establish a connection.</p>
          <p>This is a most unattractive edition of a Blake work, and also a wasted opportunity; such
      publication of a single work draws the attention to a fragment of Blake’s oeuvre which
      it inevitably loses when buried amid the bulk of a complete edition, and it is a pity that the
      work could not have been done with greater care and greater accuracy and attention to
      detail.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
