<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.2.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Ruthven Todd’s Blake Papers at Leeds</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1982</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Krzysztof Z. Cieszkowski</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Christina Shuttleworth Kraus</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Judith W. Page</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Thomas A. Vogler</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
      <pb id="p16-72" n="72"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-2-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">RUTHVEN TODD’S BLAKE PAPERS AT LEEDS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor><hi rend="b">G. E. </hi><name><hi rend="b">BENTLEY</hi></name>, 
<hi rend="b">JR.</hi></docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>In 1978, the books and papers of Ruthven Campbell Todd relating to William Blake were given
     by his son Dr. F. C. C. Todd to the Brotherton Library of the University of Leeds. The
     Brotherton Library, named after Lord Brotherton who paid for its construction, is the main
     library of the University for the humanities and social sciences. It is nobly housed and is
     especially rich in English literature of the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.</p>
        <p>What follows is primarily a catalogue of Ruthven Todd’s papers relating to William
     Blake presented to the Brotherton Library, but it is both more and less than that. It is less
     in that some of the Papers from Todd seem to have no connection with Blake<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> or are merely printed works without annotation,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> and consequently they are dealt with only in
footnotes here. It is more in
     that it includes a) some works related to Blake in the Library which did not come from Ruthven
     Todd, and b) some works in the Todd collection which are not about Blake but which are about
     his contemporaries. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> 314 <hi rend="i">Begins</hi>
       “different from the engravings . . . ” (n.d.—refers to <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> [Feb. 1972]), MS
(pencil), 1 f., perhaps related to Todd’s
       “Imaginary Indians in Europe,” <hi rend="i">Art in America</hi>, LX (1972),
       40-47.
                        <p>326 A group photograph taken in 1936 at the opening of the Surrealist Exhibition at
       Burlington Galleries (London), including Ruthven Todd (second from left, back row).</p>
	<p>327 Miscellaneous press cuttings from books in Todd’s collection, 3 ff.</p>
	<p>328 An appreciation of the work of Angela von Neumann (c. 1970) in four undated MS drafts
       with MS amendments <hi rend="i">beginning</hi> i “Permission to share a private
       world”; ii “Permit to share a private world,” 2 ff.; iii “Permission to
       accept a private world”, 2 ff.; iv “Permission to accept a private world”, 2
       ff.</p>
	<p>329 <hi rend="i">Begins</hi> “By the time one is in one’s sixty-second
       year” [1976], MS.</p></note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> The catalogue here also omits most of Todd’s
       miscellaneous collection of printed works about Blake including
                        <p>306 <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> index to No. 1-4 [1969], TS (carbon), 5
pp.</p>
	<p>325 <hi rend="i">A Descriptive Hand-List of a Loan Exhibition of Books and Works of Art by
        William Blake</hi> . . . Chiefly from the Collection of Mr. Lessing J. Rosenwald, Assembled
       by Mrs. George M. Millard (Pasadena [California], 1936), TS, 8 ff.</p>
	<p>323 Arts &amp; Crafts Exhibition organized by <hi rend="i">The Bognor Post</hi> . . .
       11-15 January 1927: The William Blake Centenary section [a scrap-book of newspaper cuttings]
       (1926-27), 16 ff. Title on front board: “The Man Who Lived at Felpham”; half-title:
       “Blake Centenary Commemoration”; the exhibition and scrapbook were arranged by G.
       P. Baker, whose printed monogram is mounted on f. 15<hi rend="s">r</hi>; autograph of Ruthven
       Todd on f. 1<hi rend="s">r</hi>.</p>
	<p>295-297 Three albums, entitled on the spines “William Blake Papers I[-III]”,
       containing photocopies of miscellaneous critical papers on Blake:</p>
	<p>Vol. I: ii, 244 [2] pp. (dated on f. 1: “25 de agosto de 1968”), TS contents on
       p. i</p>
	<p>Vol. II: vi, 244 pp., MS and TS contents on pp. i and iii (n.d.)</p>
	<p>Vol. III: ii, 111 [383] pp., no contents list (n.d.) For Vol. IV, see below.</p></note></p>
        <p>This catalogue is organized round Ruthven Todd’s Blake publications in chronological
     order of date of publication.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref>
Each entry begins with the
     earliest version of the work and concludes with the published version or, if it was revised 
<hi rend="i">after</hi> publication, with the revisions. At the conclusion of the list of
     publications are a number of entries related to Blake but not published, also arranged in
     chronological order. <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> There appears to be nothing relating
       to a number of Todd’s works on Blake, especially the earlier ones:
                        <p>“William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 5 April 1941, p.
       172 [a request for letters for a new edition of Gilchrist] with Geoffrey Keynes,
       “William Blake’s Catalogue: A New Discovery,” <hi rend="i">TLS</hi>, 12
       Sept. 1942, p. 456 [revised and reprinted in Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> (1949;
       1971)—discovery of the flyer to his “Exhibition of Paintings in Fresco”]</p>
	<p>“‘The Pilgrim’s Progress,’” <hi rend="i">TLS</hi>, 31 Jan.
       1942, p. 55 [on the sale of the drawings]</p>
	<p>“The Two Blakes,” <hi rend="i">TLS</hi>, 10 Feb. 1945, p. 72 [the signatures of
       both W. S. Blake the writing-engraver and William Blake the poet appear on a testimonial of
       1797]</p>
	<p>Foreword to Albion Facsimile No. 1 of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
        Experience</hi> [facsimile of copy b] (London + N.Y., 1947; [Folcroft, Pennsylvania], 1969),
       which also appears in <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> [facsimile of copy b] (N. Y.
       [?1947])</p>
	<p>Foreword to Albion Facsimile No. 2 of <hi rend="i">America</hi> (N.Y., 1947; n.d.)</p>
	<p>Introduction (pp. 7-13) to William Blake, <hi rend="i">Poems</hi> (London, 1949) Crown
       Classics</p>
	<p>“Fuseli and Blake: Companions in Mystery,” <hi rend="i">Art News</hi> LII (Feb.
       1954), 26, 57-58 [about the interchange of ideas between them]</p>
	<p>“William Blake,” a poem in his <hi rend="i">Garland for the Winter Solstice:</hi>
       Selected Poems (London: Dent, 1961), p. 26</p>
	<p>Introduction (pp. 11-21) and Notes (pp. 157-159) to <hi rend="i">Blake:</hi> Selected Poems
       (1960; 1963; 1964; 1966; 1967; 1969; 1970; 1971; 1973) The Laurel Poetry Series</p>
	<p>“Miro in New York: A Reminiscence,” <hi rend="i">Malahat Review</hi>, No. 1 (Jan.
       1967), 77-92, reprinted as a 15-page booklet (Brookville, N.Y., 1967) [details about
       Todd’s experiments with Blake’s method of relief etching (pp. 81-88) not
       recorded elsewhere—for more details, see S. W. Hayter, <hi rend="i">New Ways of
        Gravure</hi> (N.Y., 1949), 85, 143-144, 207]</p>
	<p>“An Accidental Scholar,” <hi rend="i">London Magazine</hi>, N.S., VII (Jan.
       1969), 42-51 [about his editions of Gilchrist in 1942 and 1945]</p>
	<p>“The Bohn Catalogue and James Vine,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, IV, 4
       (Spring 1971), 149 [correction of a misprint in the Keynes &amp; Wolf 
<hi rend="i">Census</hi>]</p></note></p>
        <p>The Todd Blake manuscripts have been catalogued anonymously by Miss Jean Radford and Mr. P.
     S. Morrish, sub-librarian (MSS and Special Collections) of the Brotherton Library, in 
<hi rend="i">University of Leeds The Library MS. 470 Blake letters and papers of Ruthven
     Todd</hi>, Handlist 49 [1981], on which the following list is based. I have, however, with Mr.
     Morrish’s consent, taken a number of liberties with the list. For one thing, I have
     omitted Nos. 1-291, which are letters of 1927-78 from Blake scholars and collectors such as C.
     H. C. Baker, G. E. Bentley, Jr., David Bindman, Martin Butlin, Morris Eaves, D. V. Erdman, R.
     N. Essick, Sir Geoffrey Keynes, T. L. Minnick, W. E. Moss, M. D. Paley, Leslie Parris, Kerrison
     Preston, Kathleen Raine, Lessing J. Rosenwald, Mark Schorer, and R. R. Wark.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> This is the section of the list to which access is restricted,
at least
     until A. D. 2011. (Written applications from <hi rend="i">bona fide</hi> Blake scholars for a
     dispensation to consult specific items may be considered by the Librarian and the
     representatives of Ruthven Todd.) <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> The bulk of Todd’s
      private papers are at the National Library of Scotland; large selections of poetry MSS are in
      the State University of New York at Buffalo; correspondence is in the Huntington Library,
      National Library of Scotland, New York Public Library, University of California (Berkeley),
      University of Texas, etc.</note></p>
        <p>For another, I have added further information from a personal inspection of the Todd
     manuscripts and from other sources.</p>
        <p>And for another, I have reorganized the material. However, each entry is preceded by the
     Handlist 49 entry number.</p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Ruthven Todd’s Life</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Two statements by Ruthven Todd in these papers may be sufficient to establish a biographical
      context for these manuscripts. The first is in an application to the Chapelbrook Foundation on
      15 June 1968 for support in preparing the new edition of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life
       of William Blake</hi>: 
	<q> I don’t know what I should say about myself. Fifty-four
       yesterday, born in Edinburgh, art-student, farm-laborer, editor, <pb id="p16-73" n="73"/>
       moved to London, worked as tutor and publisher’s reader, reviewer and other jobs. War
       years was in Civil Defence [<hi rend="i">as a conscientious objector to military
       service</hi>], and then worked in a bookstore before (bombed out) moving to Essex. To U.S.A.
       January 1947. Lived mostly in New York (apart from short semester in Iowa City) till 1954.
       Lived on Martha’s Vineyard till 1960. Came to Mallorca to spend summer as guest of
       Robert Graves. Got ill and spent return money. Have now got a cottage home. Have written
       several books of poems, novels (not really good enough), essays on art and science, and
       edited books on painting and selections from poets. Much more could be said, but I think that
       may serve.<lb/>
 [<hi rend="i">No. 44</hi>] </q>
And in a latter to the distinguished Blake
      collector George Goyder he wrote on 6 February 1970: 
	<q> I dropped out of the Blake world into
       a strange world of alcoholism, and only pulled myself out of that some six years ago.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> No. 136; this is the ribbon copy, perhaps never sent or
        sent only in modified form.</note></q>
More details may be found in a moving obituary by M. in the 
<hi rend="i">Majorca Daily
       Bulletin</hi>, in Julian Symons, “Ruthven Todd 1914-1978: Some Details for a
      Portrait,” <hi rend="i">London Magazine</hi> (April-May 1979), 62-80,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> and especially in his autobiography which has been edited by
his Majorcan
      friend Robert Latona and excerpts from which will appear in <hi rend="i">Malahat Review</hi>
      in January and April 1982. One particularly intriguing piece of information provided by Symons
      is that Symons’ 
	<q> first crime story, <hi rend="i">The Immaterial Murder Case</hi>, .
       . . was meant to be a collaboration, but Ruthven never did any writing. I wrote it, made him
       the murderer, and put the typescript in a drawer for several years.<lb/>
 [<hi rend="i">P.
        65</hi>] </q>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> No. 333. Some more information may be found in “Todd
       Collection,” <hi rend="i">Blake: An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, XII, 4 (Spring 1979),
       274 [it is going to Leeds] and [his son] Francis Christopher Crew Todd, <hi rend="i">Ruthven
        Todd (1914-1978)</hi>: a preliminary finding-list [Revised] (1980), mimeographed, 58 pp.
       (no. 334-336, three versions).</note></p>
          <p>As a young man, Todd became fascinated by Blake and collected works by and about him as
      assiduously as his very slender means permitted. He once had an extensive library of Blake and
      Flaxman, and the Flaxmans in particular were quite important. The bibliography section of
      Todd’s copy of his edition of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William
       Blake</hi> (1942), below, is annotated: 
	<q> All items underlined in red were in my library at
       Tilty Mill House nr. Dunmow, at the end of 1946 (dotted lines show that I owned only the
       plates). It was a pretty good library as libraries go and like all good libraries it went.
       The rest of my Blake collection [<hi rend="i">of scholarship</hi>] is also now scattered.
	</q>
	According to this marked list, among works with Blake’s engravings he once had
      Allen, <hi rend="i">History of England</hi> (1797) and <hi rend="i">Roman History</hi> (1798),
      Ariosto, <hi rend="i">Orlando Furioso</hi> (1783), Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (1808;
      1813), Boydell, <hi rend="i">Graphic Illustrations of the Dramatic Works of Shakspeare</hi>
      ([1803]), Burger, <hi rend="i">Leonora</hi> (1796), Cumberland, <hi rend="i">Thoughts on
       Outline</hi> (1796) and <hi rend="i">Outlines from the Antients</hi> (1829), Darwin, 
<hi rend="i">Botanic Garden</hi> (1791; 1795; 1799), Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> (1805),
      Fuseli, <hi rend="i">Lectures on Painting</hi> (1801), Gay, <hi rend="i">Fables</hi> (1793),
      Hayley, <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi> (1800), <hi rend="i">Essay on Sculpture</hi>
      (1800), <hi rend="i">Designs</hi> (1802), <hi rend="i">Life . . . of William Cowper</hi>
      (1803-4), <hi rend="i">Triumphs of Temper</hi> (1803), <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805), and
       <hi rend="i">Life of George Romney</hi> (1809), Henry, <hi rend="i">Memoirs of Albert de
       Haller</hi> (1783), Hoare, <hi rend="i">Academic Correspondence</hi> (1803), Hunter, 
<hi rend="i">Historical Journal of . . . Port Jackson</hi> (1793), Lavater, <hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> (1789),
Malkin, <hi rend="i">A Father’s Memoirs</hi> (1806), Mora, <hi rend="i">Meditaciones Poeticas</hi> (1826),
<hi rend="i">Remember Me!</hi> (1825),
      Shakspeare, <hi rend="i">Plays</hi> (1805), Stedman, <hi rend="i">Surinam</hi> (1796), <hi rend="i">The
Wit’s Magazine</hi> (1784), Mary Wollstonecraft, <hi rend="i">Original
       Stories</hi> (1791), and Young, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797). Notice that in the
      thirty some years after these were lost, apparently only one was recovered or replaced.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Ruthven Todd’s Blake Work</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Most of Ruthven Todd’s accomplishments were in poetry and fiction, but he made a
      major contribution to Blake scholarship. From his earliest published work on Blake (1941) to
      his latest (1980), he showed an extraordinary skill in finding new facts and relating them
      illuminatingly to Blake’s work, in areas as diverse as the two engravers named William
      Blake, to his pigments, to the discovery of his advertisement for his “Exhibition of
      Paintings in Fresco.” Todd’s earliest and his greatest Blake enterprise was his
      revised edition of Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> which,
      from its first publication in 1863, was recognized as being of central importance for Blake
      studies: 
	<q> Its effect was thunderous. Never has an important [<hi rend="i">English</hi>]
       literary reputation been posthumously established so instantaneously and effectively.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Books</hi> (1977), 25.</note></q>
Gilchrist’s
biography was repeatedly reprinted, in 1880, 1906, 1907, 1922, and
      1928 and proved its lasting value.</p>
          <p>There were, however, a number of serious defects to the work. For one thing, the collection
      of Blake’s writings in Volume II, edited by D. G. Rossetti and a syndicate of the
      Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood, was seriously incomplete and inaccurate, though it displayed to
      the public far more of Blake’s work than had previously been popularly available. For
      another, Gilchrist’s transcriptions of Blake’s letters in his biography were
      often merely approximate and usually at one or two removes from the manuscripts. And for a
      third, Gilchrist was alarmed by footnotes and systematically omitted identification of the
      sources of his information. All these factors made the work difficult to depend upon, but,
      because Gilchrist had talked to many of Blake’s young disciples such as John Linnell
      and Frederick Tatham and Samuel Palmer, his book cannot be ignored. Ruthven Todd approached
      these problems boldly and solved them successfully. First, he simply omitted
      Gilchrist’s Volume II with its incomplete and inaccurate writings, reproductions, and
      catalogues of Blake. Second, he corrected the texts of Blake’s letters and poems in
      Gilchrist’s biography (except where Gilchrist is the only authority for them, of
      course). Thirdly, and most laboriously, he sought out systematically the factual bases for
      Gilchrist’s 
<pb id="p16-74" n="74"/>
conclusions and anecdotes and displayed them in
      meticulous notes to the biography. Todd’s edition appeared in a modest Everyman edition
      in January 1942, was promptly recognized as a major work of scholarship, and a new edition
      appeared in 1945 with somewhat expanded notes. With its handsome prints from the Virgil
      electrotypes, it was attractive as well as useful, and it is certainly the cheapest and
      probably the best biography of Blake which has appeared.</p>
          <p>For the next forty years, Ruthven Todd collected materials for a new edition of his
      Gilchrist. After the war, he went to the United States of North America, partly to experiment
      with methods of recreating color-printing as Blake practiced it. He also wrote the Blake
      section (1945) of his <hi rend="i">Tracks in the Snow</hi>, a little, cancelled book on Blake
      (1947), an essay on Blake’s illuminated printing (1948), introductions to facsimiles of
       <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (1947) and <hi rend="i">America</hi>
      (1947), and trifling, popularizing essays on Blake for an exhibition in Hong Kong (1949) and a
      collection of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Poems</hi> (1949). Thereafter, except for a brief
            note on Blake and Fuseli (1954), a short poem 
<figure n="BotanicalDrawings.illus1.16.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="718">
	<head>Illus. 1-6 are botanical drawings and notes of 1965-66 in Majorca by Ruthven Todd, from
        a notebook belonging to his son Dr. C.C. Todd, by whose permission and generosity they are
        here reproduced.</head>
</figure> 
      on Blake (1961), and a slight edition of <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1960), he produced
      nothing on Blake until his announcement of “Gilchrist Redivivus” (1968). Thereafter,
      there was a flow of correspondence and notes about Blake, focusing on Gilchrist.</p>
          <p>He had a large correspondence with Blake scholars and collectors—he wrote to many
      scholars with queries and advice, and he wrote at enormous length. One might receive three
      ten-page, single-spaced, densely argued letters in a month—and then hear nothing for a
      year or more. These letters were often mini-essays, and generous and admiring editors made
      more than one into published articles—such as the posthumous one of 1980. Much of
      Ruthven Todd’s best work on Blake was in stimulating others through this private
      correspondence.</p>
          <p>Besides his surprisingly extensive Blake publications and correspondence, Ruthven Todd
      worked on at least four books on Blake which he did not live to finish. One is the catalogue
      raisonné of Blake’s art (298.1 below) on which Sir Geoffrey Keynes also worked
      and which was a basis for Martin Butlin’s great <hi rend="i">Paintings and Drawings of
       William Blake</hi>, 2 vols. (1981). Another is the Phoenix House book on <hi rend="i">William
       Blake</hi> of 1947 (No. 300 below) which was cancelled after it reached galley proof stage.
      Another was to be called <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Commercial Engraver.</hi></p>
          <figure n="BotanicalDrawings.illus2.16.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="722">
          	<figTranscr>2 de octubre de 1965<lb/>
			Under carob tree, in moss.<lb/>
			<lb/>
			2 de octubre de 1965.<lb/>
			Under Quercus ilex. Spores tawny.<lb/>
			<lb/>
			Dimonde, 3 de<lb/>
			octubre de 1965.<lb/>
			Yesterday afternoon<lb/>
			I went for a walk along<lb/>
			the road toward Lluch. I<lb/>
			walked about fo[ur] kilometers<lb/>
			and, having heard the noise<lb/>
			of running water, I took off<lb/>
			into the woods, mostly ilex, on my<lb/>
			walk back. There I found this<lb/>
			fine specimen of the mushroom<lb/>
			I had found under the rose<lb/>
			bush on the day before, and<lb/>
			the other mushroom which<lb/>
			I have drawn on this page.<lb/>
			In addition I encountered<lb/>
			a lot of shelf-mushrooms, of<lb/>
			which I collected three specimens<lb/>
			when I will try to draw today.<lb/>
			I could have collected more, but I<lb/>
			had no basket with me, and had<lb/>
			to make do with two handkerchiefs<lb/>
			knotted together as a collecting<lb/>
			case. Furthermore, I know that I<lb/>
			can only draw at a  certain speed<lb/>
			and so I had to content myself<lb/>
			with only two mushrooms which<lb/>
			might wilt fast, choosing the less<lb/>
			perishable shelf-mushrooms which, I knew, would survive through the night for<lb/>
			drawing today, along with such background material as the carob leaves and<lb/>
			the broken helix shell. Apart from the fact that this paper tends to be a little<lb/>
			too absorbent for tinta china used with an ordinary pen (I am writing with a<lb/>
			German Rapidograph), I am coming to the conclusion that the pen and black<lb/>
			ink make the stresses too strong. If I do go to Zurich about the middle of this<lb/>
			month I will see what I can find in the way of extra colored pencils. I hope<lb/>
			<lb/>
			sketches</figTranscr>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p16-75" n="75"/>
          <p>Most important was his new edition of Gilchrist For this work, he made extensive additions
      to a copy of his 1942 edition, which he subsequently lost in Iowa and then recovered years
      later. In the interval, in 1968 he had a copy of the 1945 edition taken a part and mounted on
      large leaves in three volumes, and these he annotated extensively and often differently than
      in the for-a-time-lost copy. At the same time he was corresponding vigorously with scholars
      and making tentative arrangements with the Clarendon Press to publish the new edition. The
      work he did was detailed and valuable, and much of it is new and fascinating. For instance, he
      quotes a “Cutting, dated 9.vi.1920 from Catalogue” (not further identified) of a
      “MS. Petition in favour of Wm. Carey being appointed Keeper of Paintings, etc. signed by
      Jas Northcote, Hy. Fuseli, Jas. Ward, Maria Cosway, Wm. Blake, Rd. Westall, Geo. Clint, John
      Constable, and other artists of the period, 1 p. folio” (1942, p. 221)—this must
      be the original of the <hi rend="i">printed</hi> document of December 1820 quoted in <hi rend="i">Blake
      Records</hi> (1969), 269. He also quotes an unpublished letter from Samuel
      Palmer to George Richmond of March 1879 in which Palmer speculates about a portrait of Milton
      etched by Blake “when three years of 
      age.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Gilchrist (1942), p. 17—see “A Portrait of
       Milton Engraved by William Blake ‘When Three Years of Age’?—A
       Speculation by Samuel Palmer,” <hi rend="i">University of Toronto Quarterly</hi>, LI
       (1981), 28-35.</note></p>
          <p>These fascinating materials for a new edition of Gilchrist are very extensive and very
            incomplete. They deserve to be brought into order and up to date 
<figure n="BotanicalDrawings.illus3.16.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="657">
	<figTranscr>Galilea, Mallorca. 1 de Mayo de 1966. This book has been on my<lb/>
shelves for a couple of months, but I have not used it until now.<lb/>
There are several reasons for my holding back. I have been a<lb/>
little intimidated both by its size and its quality. I have been a <lb/>
bit busy so far as drawing is concerned and, frankly, it is only now,<lb/>
after nearly six years in Mallorca, that I have organized my living<lb/>
quarters so that I can set up for both drawing and writing. I cannot<lb/>
hope to keep the book on a regular basis, as I did during those<lb/>
summers on Martha’s Vineyard fifteen or so<lb/>
years ago, but I mean to try to do something<lb/>
in it without rest gaps, such as there have <lb/>
been in my drawing. I have made rather<lb/>
a late start this year, as, after two dry<lb/>
a winter, such plants as these are are<lb/>
drying up quickly. However, I suppose I<lb/>
will find enough to occupy me. One thing<lb/>
is certain and that is that my colors will<lb/>
be more truthful than those of the photographs<lb/>
in Polunin &amp; Huxley, Flowers of the Mediterranean.<lb/>
Their wild pea may give some indication, but the<lb/>
salsify is a complete traves[t]y. This may be because it<lb/>
is only open during the<lb/>
early hours of the morning,<lb/>
but I would think that there<lb/>
must be color film capable of<lb/>
dealing with that light. There is,<lb/>
I feel, some irony in James giving me<lb/>
the book now, when I worry about my<lb/>
eyesight and wonder whether it will last<lb/>
out. Anyhow, I am certain that this is the<lb/>
last book of this size which I will take. I<lb/>
can only hope that my eye-sight will last<lb/>
out so that I can fill it. This being Sunday<lb/>
the pension swarms with people who [are]<lb/>
enjoying a really lovely day. There<lb/>
has been very little rain during<lb/>
the past winter and this is a<lb/>
real disaster for the Mallorcans<lb/>
who still try to live by<lb/>
farming rather than<lb/>
by battening on the <lb/>
foreigners. All the<lb/>
fields are dry,<lb/>
and so are the<lb/>
cisterns. I,<lb/>
being in this<lb/>
mountain college, and being<lb/>
aware of the people, hear<lb/>
the complaints while I<lb/>
doubt whether those who<lb/>
hot in Palma, those<lb/>
who are strangers, can<lb/>
have the least idea of<lb/>
the really serious drought.<lb/>
For the third time in my life I am again trying to set up some kind<lb/>
of a library to which I can refer when I want to identify the plants<lb/>
and mushrooms which I encounter in my wanderings. I have<lb/>
the Flora analítica de España, which is now out of print,<lb/>
and the Polunin &amp; Huxley which, with all its faults, is the<lb/>
best book in English we are likely to get for some time. I do<lb/>
wish that Polunin &amp; Huxley had had the sense to try to make<lb/>
their book more interesting, as Geoffrey Grigson’s The Englishman’s Flora is on the <lb/>
out, but of salsify they only say that “The cylindrical top roots are eaten as a vegetable.”<lb/>
There is no mention of the fact that it is also called oyster plant from an imagined resemblance<lb/>
in the taste, one which I do not notice. Dealing with Tra[go]pogon pratensis, Grigson<lb/>
mentions that that is known as Joseph’s Flower. “The beard [which gives it the name<lb/>
of Goat’s Beard] is the long silky pappus. ‘Joseph’s Flower’, because Joseph, the husband<lb/>
of the Virgin, is always shown bearded in pictures of the Nativity.” Surely Polunin<lb/>
&amp; Huxley could have found something of interest. They are orientated toward the<lb/>
eastern Mediterranean and so they failed to notice that, as in English, the common<lb/>
name for salsify in Spain is Barba cabruna which leads back to Grigson, “It was<lb/>
called Goat’s Beard by William Turner in 1548 as a translation of the shop name barba<lb/>
hirci, which goes back to the tra[go]pogon in Theophrastus and Dioscorides.” I want<lb/>
this to point out what it cured. As any drawing, of a typical plant from below the<lb/>
pension, shows, the leaves are not particularly leek-like, in spite of the specific name.</figTranscr>
</figure> 
      and published. I
      have agreed to serve as midwife if a publisher can be found—Ruthven Todd wanted the
      work to be very extensively illustrated and very inexpensive—but thus far no publisher
      has shown interest in it. Meanwhile there is a great store-house of biographical information
      about Blake among the Ruthven Todd Papers at Leeds.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Catalogue</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Symbols</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Brotherton</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>= The work is in the Brotherton Library but not among the Todd MSS (MS 470)</p>
              <p>f. (ff.) = folio (folios)</p>
              <p>MS = Manuscript</p>
              <p>n.d. = not dated</p>
              <p>TS = Typescript</p>
              <p>298 = The entry number among the Todd MSS</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Published Works</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>1942</p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Brotherton</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">The Life of William Blake</hi>, ed. W. Graham Robertson
        (1907), Todd’s copy marked on the endpaper and flyleaves “Working Copy No 1
        Ruthven Todd 1940 Annotated and 
<figure n="BotanicalDrawings.illus4.16.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="705">
	<figTranscr>29 de mayo de 1966. This month has been spent in trying to do too many things at the same time. I have<lb/>
not only been trying to write both Bead and Other / Friends and Places, but also to catch up with a large<lb/>
backlog of letters, writing and necessary reading. In addition I have been doing drawings in this<lb/>
book and then either repeating them, or using fresh specimens for largish separate drawings<lb/>
for sale, either privately or for my exhibition. The book serves as my draft book in which I<lb/>
explore the construction and complexities of each plant before doing the more finished work.<lb/>
Beside doing the drawings of the Mallorca flora, I have also started on the immense job<lb/>
of transfering all my drawing from Martha’s Vineyard to black and white. This was started by<lb/>
a letter from Nelson Coon telling me that the Dukes County Historical<lb/>
Society is going to publish A Check List of the Flora<lb/>
of Martha’s Vineyard and asking me to do the illustrations.<lb/>
I have only the 1952 volume of my journal and the smaller<lb/>
book which Carolyn Kizer gave me in Seattle. From these I<lb/>
can get some eighty-five drawings. I have written George<lb/>
Gosthall (and I have also done what I can to bring pressure upon<lb/>
him) asking for the others. If I get these there should be upward<lb/>
of three hundred drawings. Since I have now decided to<lb/>
make as much money as I can from all drawings not<lb/>
done in my sketchbooks, I have decided that the Dukes<lb/>
County Historical Society cannot possibly afford to buy<lb/>
the whole series. So I am going to make all the drawings,<lb/>
and then have vellum boxes, holding, say, fifty drawings<lb/>
in each. I will number the drawings in accordance with<lb/>
Asa Gray’s Flora, arrange them in the boxes with<lb/>
an index and then, probably, put the whole series<lb/>
up for sale at Sotheby’s, either in London or else<lb/>
in New York, according to which ever the firm<lb/>
advises. All I can do is hope that in this way<lb/>
I can earn enough money to buy a piece of <lb/>
land and have a house built. I have now got<lb/>
to a stage in which I need a house, both as a<lb/>
center from which I can operate and also as a<lb/>
place in which to work. If I had the rest of my<lb/>
Vineyard and journals and felt free of all pressures I<lb/>
think I could do all the pen and ink drawings in<lb/>
about a couple of months of hard, concentrated work.<lb/>
The day before yesterday a fluorescent desk-lamp, which<lb/>
I had ordered from Gilet, finally arrived. 3 de junio<lb/>
Feeling rather depressed. I have been trying to work my way<lb/>
out of it, without too much success. Today, I have finished<lb/>
separate drawings of Anacamptis, Ophrys &amp; Synnema, as<lb/>
well as Antirrhinum orontium in this Book. Although I<lb/>
realize that I need large subjects for my exhibition,<lb/>
I must also do small ones for my own benefit. I know<lb/>
I am too old to attempt to cover the flora of Mallorca,<lb/>
but, with luck, I can hope to make this book cover quite<lb/>
a large selection. One thing is that I must go out each<lb/>
morning and collect such plants as [are] close by noon or one<lb/>
in the afternoon. Quite a lot of what I had done here is<lb/>
now over for this year: the Wild Pea, Salsify, Star of Bethlehem<lb/>
and Gladiolus, while both the Crown Daisy and Corn Poppy are<lb/>
almost over. I now have nine drawings done on large sheets.<lb/>
The fluorescent light makes quite a bit of difference to my eyesight,<lb/>
and I hope it will help me. Finding that Winsor &amp; Newton<lb/>
still have a small stock of Whatman HP, I have ordered two<lb/>
quires and also a few Series 12, Sable brushes. I should get them<lb/>
within a week two. I am financing the large drawings with money<lb/>
from Tony and Linda Lewis, who have bought four drawings, two of<lb/>
mushrooms and an iris and a Butterfly Orchid, at £10 each. This<lb/>
arrangement of two drawings to a  page is monstrous; I must break it<lb/>
up. The best way will be to do a lot of small drawings and also occasional<lb/>
drawings filling a complete page. I wish my eyes would improve.<lb/>
I find that they are pretty tired by the time I have done four or<lb/>
so drawings and I also find that I do not work as quickly as I<lb/>
used to do, when making the Vineyard sketchbooks. If I am to<lb/>
get twenty or thirty drawings by the end of this month, I will<lb/>
have to work steadily and waste no time. Even on days when<lb/>
I have to go to Palma, I must try to do a drawing, either in this<lb/>
Book or on the sheets. I wish I could work myself out of this horrible<lb/>
depression. I recognize the reasons for it, but that does not help. All I can<lb/>
do is plod away and hope that somehow things will sort themselves out, in<lb/>
my favor. This, I fear, is a vain hope, but I have nothing else to which I can hold.</figTranscr>
</figure>
<pb id="p16-76" n="76"/>
Corrected”, with his address at 41 Mansionhouse Road,
        Edinburgh. The notes are in the margins; some pages have many corrections, many have
        none.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Brotherton</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Ibid. (1906 [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>]) in gatherings, apparently without additions, among
        the Todd books. Each of these volumes was doubtless preparatory to Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of
William Blake</hi>, ed. Ruthven Todd (1942); it was expanded in the 1945
        edition.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Brotherton</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, ed. Ruthven Todd (1942
        [marked by Todd “Published January 29, 1942”]), interleaved and annotated. This is
        apparently the copy which was lost or stolen, turned up in Iowa, and was returned to
         Todd.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> The extensive
marginalia often duplicate those in
        the COMPLETELY REVISED 1945 edition (below), but sometimes it does not, and some of it is
        intriguing. Associated with it are letters about the copyright of Gilchrist and his
        understanding with the Clarendon Press about it. <note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi>
          Another copy of Gilchrist (1942) annotated by Ruthven Todd, mostly with notes on the
          location of pictures mentioned by Gilchrist, is in the possession of his friend Mr. Robert
          S. Latona of Mallorca.
                                    <p>I am grateful for many and unfailing kindnesses from Mr. Cox (librarian
of the
          Brotherton Library), from Mr. Morrish (compiler of the Todd checklist for the Brotherton
          Library), and from Mr. Latona.</p></note></p>
              <p>Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, ed. Ruthven Todd (1942,
        1945), the leaves separated, pasted by a Mallorcan girl on Spanish legal-size paper,
        interleaved, and bound in three albums, the copyright page emended to read “COMPLETELY
        REVISED, 1968”, each volume dated “6 de julio de 1968”, copiously annotated
        by Todd:</p>
              <p>292 Vol..I, with preliminaries and pp. 1-134.</p>
              <figure n="BotanicalDrawings.illus5.16.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="713"/>
              <p>293 Vol. II, with pp. 135-302; at the end is a TS letter to Todd from Morchard Bishop
        [Oliver Stoner] (30 Aug 1968) containing various emendations for pp. 123-400.</p>
              <p>294 Vol. III, with pp. 303-366, 402, 401, 403-406 and index; also pasted in is a revised
        TS bibliography by Todd, 13 ff.</p>
              <p>304 Papers about a proposed revision of his edition of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of
William Blake</hi> (c. 1968).</p>
              <list type="ordered">
                <item>
                  <p><label>i</label> “A Modest Proposal” (n.d.), TS, 1 f.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>ii</label> “A Modest Proposal” (n.d.), TS (carbon), 5 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>iii</label> Photocopy of ii, with MS amendments (n.d.).</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>iv</label><hi rend="i">Begins</hi> “When, last fall . . . ” [1968] TS
(carbon), 7 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>v</label> “Pictures mentioned by Gilchrist with their owners in 1944”
          (n.d.), TS, 2 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>vi</label> “List of names, for index, for checking . . . ” (n.d.) TS
          with MS additions, 10 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>vii</label> “Papers and books I should have—listed 29 August
          1968” (1968), TS, 5 ff.</p>
                </item>
              </list>
              <p>305 “Outline and material for a version of ‘A Bibliographical check-list for
        William Blake’” (latest date in the bibliography is 1969 [f. 18]), TS, 30
        ff.</p>
              <p>1945</p>
              <p>“William Blake and the Eighteenth-Century Mythologists.” Pp. 68-75 of <hi rend="i">New
Road</hi>: Directions in <figure n="BotanicalDrawings.illus6.16.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="710"/>
<pb id="p16-77" n="77"/>
European Art and Literature. Ed. Fred Marnau. (1945). B. Pp. 29-60
        of Todd’s <hi rend="i">Tracks in the Snow</hi>: Studies in English Science and Art.
        (London, 1946) C. (N.Y., 1947) D. (Folcroft, Pennsylvania, 1975) E. (Norwood, <corr type="emend">Pennsylvania,</corr>
        1976) F. (1977) G. (N.Y., 1977) [A study of Blake’s indebtedness to currents of
        thought among contemporary antiquarians.]</p>
              <p>The 1975-77 printings here are apparently unauthorized. Todd worked on a new edition for
        Dover publications in 1971-74.</p>
              <p>318</p>
              <list type="ordered">
                <item>
                  <p><label>i</label> Draft index, TS with MS alterations, 37 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>ii</label> Another version, TS with MS alterations, 20 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>iii</label> A third version, TS (carbon) with MS alterations, 47 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>iv</label> List of plates, TS (carbon), 3 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>v</label> Seventeen glossy black-and-white photographs, being some of the plates
          listed in iv above.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>vi</label> Miscellaneous fragments, MS and TS, 13 ff.</p>
                </item>
              </list>
              <p>According to information received at Leeds from Dover Publications in July 1980, this
        project was first mooted in 1966, but most of their correspondence with Todd about it was
        between 1971 and 1974; the project was never formally cancelled, but Todd’s death
        intervened.</p>
              <p>1948</p>
              <p>“The Techniques of William Blake’s Illuminated Painting [<hi rend="i">i.e.</hi>,
Printing].” <hi rend="i">Print</hi>, VI (1948), 53-65. B. <hi rend="i">Print Collector’s Quarterly</hi>,
XXIX (Nov. 1948), 25-36.</p>
              <p>319</p>
              <list type="ordered">
                <item>
                  <p><label>i</label> Photocopy of 1948 edition annotated by R. N. Essick and of TS new
          footnotes by Todd [1972], 20 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>ii</label> Photocopy of version revised and reprinted in <hi rend="i">The
           Visionary Hand</hi>, ed. R. N. Essick (1973), 19-44, on 26 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>iii</label> Another copy of ii.</p>
                </item>
              </list>
              <p>1949</p>
              <p>299 “Aspects of the Life and Work of William Blake.” (Latest date in the
        bibliography is 1945) TS (duplicated), 7 ff. Published as “Aspects of the Life and Work
        of William Blake” in <hi rend="i">The Life and Work of William Blake Poet-Painter.</hi>
        [Exhibition in Hong Kong in 1949.]</p>
              <p>1968</p>
              <p>“Gilchrist Redivivus.” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, I, 1 (Autumn 1968),
        95-97. [Todd’s plan for a new edition.]</p>
              <p>302 Galley proof.</p>
              <p>303</p>
              <list type="ordered">
                <item>
                  <p><label>i</label> “Blake’s Dante Plates.” TS draft of a letter to the
          Editor, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 5 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>ii</label> Photocopy of the letter as printed in <hi rend="i">TLS</hi>, 29 Aug.
          1968, p. 928, 2 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>iii</label> TS draft of a further letter to the Editor, <hi rend="i">TLS</hi>, 18
          Sept. 1968, 1 f.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>iv</label> TS draft of a new version for <hi rend="i">Book Collecting &amp;
           Library Monthly</hi>, 10 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>v</label> Carbon copy of iv, with amendments, 10 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>vi</label> TS (carbon copy) second draft of iv, 11 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>vii</label> Photocopy of vi, 11 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>viii</label> Page-proof of the version which appeared in <hi rend="i">Book
           Collecting &amp; Library Monthly</hi>, No. 6 (1968), 164-171, 12 ff. [A cleaning of
          Blake’s Dante copperplates has made possible a printing of 25 new sets
          “considerably superior to the earlier [<hi rend="i">contemporary</hi>]
          ones.”]</p>
                </item>
              </list>
              <p>310 “Blake’s Copy of Dante.” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, IV, 2
        (1970), 49-50 (photocopy). [Where is Blake’s copy of Dante?]</p>
              <p>1970</p>
              <p>308 “Traditional pigments available prior to 1800” (1970), TS. Attached to it
        are rough notes by Todd on the same subject, in connection with a letter from Dr. Rosamond
        Drusilla Harley of 29 Jan. 1970 (No. 132).</p>
              <p>309 “Review of R. D. Harley, <hi rend="i">Artists’ Pigments</hi><supplied
type="emend">”</supplied> (1970) in <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, IV, 1 (1970), 28-30 (photocopy), 2
ff.</p>
              <p>1971</p>
              <p>330 Papers [before 1972] relating to his <hi rend="i">William Blake The Artist</hi>
        (1971).</p>
              <list type="ordered">
                <item>
                  <p><label>i</label> Draft introduction, partly autobiographical (n.d.), MS.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>ii</label> Another draft of an introduction, partly autobiographical (n.d.), TS,
          6 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>iii</label> “Draft and working copy of a chronology of William Blake”
          (n.d.), TS with MS additions, 8 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>iv</label> “Supplementary material, to be embodied in the chronology”
          (n.d.), TS with MS notes, 8 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>v</label> “A Chronology of the life of William Blake” (n.d.), TS, 2
          ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>vi</label> Further notes on the chronology of William Blake (n.d.), MS (pencil),
          2 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>vii</label> Folder containing a full draft (n.d.), TS with MS amendments (the
          list of proposed illustrations is a photocopy of TS), 75 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>viii</label> Two yellow ring binders containing photocopy of TS draft with MS
          amendments (n.d.), 64 + 49 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>ix</label> A red spring-back binder containing photocopy of TS draft (n.d.), 115
          ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>x</label> Galley proofs, extensively marked (n.d.), 19 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>xi</label> Galley proofs, with only a few marks (n.d.), 20 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>xii</label> A folder containing 117 glossy black-and-white photographs for
          illustrations, mostly marked for printer’s block-maker.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>xiii</label> Photocopy of editorial in <hi rend="i">The Private Library</hi>, 2nd
          Series, IV, 4 (1971), 153, 155, referring to <hi rend="i">William Blake The
          Artist.</hi></p>
                </item>
              </list>
              <p>311 “Two Blake Prints and Two Fuseli Drawings with some possibly pertinent
        speculations.” (1971)</p>
              <list type="ordered">
                <item>
                  <p><label>i</label> TS preliminary notes, much amended (n.d.), 7 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <pb id="p16-78" n="78"/>
                <item>
                  <p><label>ii</label> TS draft, incomplete (n.d.), 3 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>iii</label> TS draft, another version, incomplete (4 July 1971), 7 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>iv</label> TS draft, another version, incomplete (28 June-4 July 1971), 4 ff.
          Alterations to the text suggest that this is subsequent to iii.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>v</label> TS draft, another version with a supplementary note (n.d.), 18 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>vi</label> TS (carbon) draft, another version (n.d.), 21 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>vii</label> TS final version (n.d.), 2 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>viii</label> A folder containing 14 photographic prints of illustrations for the
          article, 5 being marked for the press.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>ix</label> As printed in <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, V, 3 (Winter
          1971-72), 173-181. [Fuseli’s drawings for the frontispiece to Lavater’s 
<hi rend="i">Aphorisms</hi> and for the last plate to his own <hi rend="i">Lectures</hi>
          belong to Ernest Seligmann.]</p>
                </item>
              </list>
              <p>1972</p>
              <p>317</p>
              <p>i Photocopy of “A Recollection of George Richmond by his Grandson.” <hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter</hi>, VI, 1 (Summer 1972 [i.e., Feb. 1973]), 24. [“When Blake died,
        George closed his eyes: ‘to keep the vision in’.”)</p>
              <p>315 “A Note on Stothard’s drawing of the ‘Battle of
        Ai[n]’.” (1972)</p>
              <list type="ordered">
                <item>
                  <p><label>i</label> TS draft much amended in pencil (April 1972), 2 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>ii</label> TS draft, another version (May 1972), 6 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>iii</label> An envelope of 5 photographic prints, 3 marked for the press. This
          was published as “Stothard (Thomas) <hi rend="i">The Battle of Ai.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Paul
Grinke Catalogue Five</hi> [London, 1972], pp. 17-19. [In Blake’s
          published engraving in Kimpton’s <hi rend="i">History of the Holy Bible</hi>
          (?1781), showing the warriors fighting left-handed, the sky seems to have “been left
          unfinished”; the more finished but unsigned and unpublished pull (in the Rosenwald
          Collection) “is undoubtedly also by Blake”—it is more finished, is
          right-handed, and corresponds in this respect to Stothard’s newly discovered
          drawing, offered for sale here.]</p>
                </item>
              </list>
              <p>1973</p>
              <p>317</p>
              <p>ii Photocopy of “The Rev. Dr. John Trusler (1735-1820),” <hi rend="i">Blake
         Newsletter</hi>, VI, 3 (Winter 1972-73 [i.e., Nov. 1973]), 71. [His interest in “a
        script type” was like Blake’s.]</p>
              <p>1976</p>
              <p>320 “The Identity of ‘Hereford’ in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>”
        (1972-75)</p>
              <list type="ordered">
                <item>
                  <p><label>i</label> Miscellaneous notes (n.d.), TS, 4 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>ii</label> First revision (“March 21, 1972: 8 p.m.”), TS with MS
          alterations, 10 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>iii</label> Another version (n.d.), TS with MS alterations, 14 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>iv</label> Photocopy of iii (n.d.), 12 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>v</label> Another version (n.d.), TS (photocopy), 7 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>vi</label> Final draft (n.d.), TS with some MS alterations, 10 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>vii</label> Three glossy black-and-white photographs prepared for the
          printer.<lb/>
<lb/>
 It was published as “The Identity of ‘Hereford’ in
           <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> with Observations on Welsh Matters,” <hi rend="i">Blake
           Studies</hi>, VI, 2 [1976], 139-151. [A rambling defence of the case for identifying him
          as Thomas Johnes.]</p>
                </item>
              </list>
              <p>1977</p>
              <p>321 “A Tentative Note on the Economics of ‘The Canterbury
        Pilgrims’.” (1977)</p>
              <list type="ordered">
                <item>
                  <p><label>i</label> TS draft with MS alterations (n.d.), 4 ff.</p>
                </item>
                <item>
                  <p><label>ii</label> As published in <hi rend="i">Blake: An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, XI,
          1 (Summer [June] 1977), 30-31. [Estimates of the costs of copper, printing, etc.]</p>
                </item>
              </list>
              <p>1980</p>
              <p>322</p>
              <p>i Notes on pigments (on verso of a price list of Windsor &amp; Newton Ltd. dated 31 Dec.
        69), MS (pencil), perhaps connected with “‘Poisonous Blues’ and Other
        Pigments,” <hi rend="i">Blake: An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, XIV, 1 (Summer 1980),
        31-34. [Prussian blue is <hi rend="i">not</hi> poisonous, as has been alleged; Blake was
        probably referring to nitric acid.]</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Unpublished Works</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>1946</p>
            <p>298. 1 Draft Catalogue of the Drawings and Paintings of William Blake (contains matter
       datable up to 1946 [f. 110]), TS and MS, 231 ff.; the MS annotations are probably in the hand
       of Geoffrey Keynes. [There is a typescript (1942) of the catalogue in the Library of Congress
       (pressmark: NC 1115. B72T6). The work was completely revised by Martin Butlin, whose great
       catalogue raisonné was published as <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William
        Blake</hi>, 2 vols. (1981).]</p>
            <p>1947</p>
            <p>300 <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>[: The Vision of Reality <hi rend="i">del</hi>] [A
       Mental Prince <hi rend="i">del</hi>] (London: Phoenix House, 1947), TS preliminaries (32
       plates described but not reproduced), appendices, and index, 35 ff., and 29 galley proofs of
       the text (c. 33,000 words).</p>
            <p>Recently I was asked by Ruthven Todd’s son Christopher to look at the work to judge
       whether it is worth publishing today, thirty-five years after its printing.</p>
            <p>The book is aimed at a popular rather than a scholarly audience. 
			<q> This short account of
        the life and works of William Blake . . . is primarily concerned with 
<pb id="p16-79" n="79"/>
Blake
as an artist [<hi rend="i">but</hi>] considerable attention has had to be devoted
        to his philosophy and mythology in order to present an understandable picture of the man
        whom I believe to be one of the greatest of Englishmen.<lb/>
<lb/>
 [<hi rend="i">Prefatory
         Note</hi>] </q>
Its alternative, deleted sub-titles indicate the wider context: The Vision
       of Reality; A Mental Prince. It consists of ten chapters: Orientation; Childhood and Youth;
       Poetic Genius; Experience and Expression; The Enemy of Oil; Felpham; With a Different Face
       [about Cromek and Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> designs]; The Grand Style of Art
       Restored [dealing with Blake’s 1809 exhibition]; “I am Hid”; His Own Eternal
       House. There is also a typescript Dedication to B. C., Prefatory Note, Contents, Notes on the
       [32] Illustrations, a note on The Location of Blake’s Pictures, Bibliography of Books
       by and About Blake, and an Index.</p>
            <p>The book is sensible and useful but not very original or interesting, and it is now
       seriously outdated. Much of it is quotation from Blake—The Proverbs of Hell are here
       in full, for instance—but there are no notes or specific indications of sources,
       though Todd does cite scholars such as M. O. Percival and Anthony Blunt. The Prefatory Note
       gives thanks to “my friends Geoffrey Grigson, Geoffrey Keynes, W. E. Moss, and W. Graham
       Robertson for unpublished information and material”, and some facts and documents quoted
       here were otherwise unknown in 1947. He quotes, for example, from John Linnell’s
       (still) unpublished autobiography about Blake, and he relates that 
	<q> Mr Graham Robertson .
        . . told me that when, nearly fifty years ago, he first visited Captain Butts, the grandson
        of Blake’s benefactor . . . , he found pictures painted on copper hanging against hot
        water pipes, a treatment no picture, unless it was one of George Stubbs’ enamels,
        could have been expected to survive. </q>
Had Ruthven Todd’s <hi rend="i">William
        Blake</hi> been published in 1947, it would have brought him some money and extended William
       Blake’s fame, but it would not have made a permanent addition to our understanding and
       appreciation of Blake. It was a competent money-spinner which suffers little disservice from
       being known only through this notice.</p>
            <p>There is no reference to the book in the Phoenix House archives now in Reading University
       Library, as I am informed by Michael Bott, Assistant Archivist there. The galleys bear
       corrections by the house editor but apparently none by Todd—perhaps he never returned
       the proofs.</p>
            <p>n.d.</p>
            <p>322</p>
            <list type="ordered">
              <item>
                <p><label>ii</label> Notes on Linnell (n.d.), MS (pencil), 1 f.</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <p><label>iii</label> Fragment on <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (n.d.), MS (pencil), 1
         f.</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <p><label>iv</label> Notes, possibly autobiographical, <hi rend="i">beginning</hi>
         “Edinburgh: John Gray” (n.d.), MS, 1 f.</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <p><label>v</label> “Rough list of people who might or should be included in a
         picture-book of <hi rend="i">William Blake and his friends</hi>” (n.d.), TS, 3 ff. (no
         entry after “Rigaud”).</p>
              </item>
            </list>
            <p>332 List of books in Ruthven Todd’s possession, including some by Blake, apparently
       the latter part of a letter (n.d.), TS (photocopy), 2 ff.</p>
            <p>301 “Books read by Blake: a minimal list.” (n.d.—not before 1964) TS with
       MS additions, 10 ff.</p>
            <p>1970</p>
            <p>307 “Notes for possible experiments respecting the processes of William Blake’s
       ‘Colour printed drawings’” (1970), TS, 2 ff.</p>
            <p>1972</p>
            <p>313 “A Plea for availability” (1972, dated “10 de enero” on f. 4), TS,
       4 ff. Refers to the Tate exhibition of Blake’s watercolors for Gray’s
       poems.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">William Blake: The Commercial Engraver.</hi> According to his letter to GEB of
       28 May 1972 (not in the Leeds collection), the work was to consist of separate essays
       (originally published individually) on <list type="ordered">
	<item><p><label>1</label> “Commercial Engraving at the Time of Blake” (“last to be
          written”)</p></item>
	<item><p><label>2</label> “Henry Fuseli and William Blake”</p></item>
	<item><p><label>3</label> “Thomas Stothard and William Blake” (“to appear in the
           <hi rend="i">Private Library</hi>”)</p></item>
	<item><p><label>4</label> “John Flaxman and William Blake” (“for an anthology
          being edited by Morton [<hi rend="i">Paley</hi>]”)</p></item>
	<item><p><label>5</label> “William Blake <hi rend="i">after</hi> William Blake”
          (“promised to” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>)</p></item>
	<item><p><label>6</label> “William Blake and Sundry Artists”</p></item>
</list></p>
            <p>This book is subsequent to and therefore distinct from his <hi rend="i">William Blake The
        Artist</hi> (1971) but may have been designed to incorporate fallout from it. (It may be the
       same as the “study of Blake’s illustrative techniques to be called <hi rend="i">William Blake: The
Technical Man</hi>” which was announced in <hi rend="i">Blake
        Newsletter</hi>, IV, 1 [Aug. 1970], 30, as being in progress.) The two following groups of
       MSS may be related to it.</p>
            <p>312 Miscellaneous notes mainly on Blake’s artistic techniques.</p>
            <list type="ordered">
              <item>
                <p><label>i</label><hi rend="i"> Begins</hi> “The book should begin . . . ” (n.d.) TS, 2
ff.</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <p><label>ii</label><hi rend="i"> Begins</hi> “Title . . . ” (n.d.) MS (pencil), 1 f.</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <p><label>iii</label><hi rend="i"> Begins</hi> “Many books have been written . . . ”
(n.d.) TS, 10
         ff.</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <p><label>iv</label><hi rend="i"> Begins</hi> “Regarding the Hesiod . . . ” (refers to 
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> [1969] MS (pencil), 1 f.</p>
              </item>
              <item>
                <p><label>v</label><hi rend="i"> Begins</hi> “Introductory notes . . . ” (refers to his 
<hi rend="i">William Blake The Artist</hi> [1971]) MS (pencil), 1 f.</p>
              </item>
            </list>
            <p>331 Fragment of a draft letter on techniques of engraving: <hi rend="i">begins</hi>
       “P.P.S. Mr. Anselmini has pointed out” (1968) TS (carbon).</p>
            <p>316 “William Blake and Thomas Stothard (1755-1834); <pb id="p16-80" n="80"/>
       materials” (n.d.), 6 ff. [A list of engravings in chronological order.]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Other Significant Works Related to Blake in the Leeds University Libraries</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Todd Collection</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Bible: <hi rend="i">Illustrations of The Book of Job</hi> (1825) pl. 20-21, India proofs
         [<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> No. 421]</p>
              <p>“Canterbury Pilgrims”, separate plate (8 Oct. 1810 [printed in 1941, says Todd,
        on modern cardboard]), given him about 1947 (according to his Gilchrist [1945], p. 247 MS
        note)</p>
              <p>“Christ Triumphing Over Urizen”, separate plate</p>
              <p>Dante: <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations of Dante</hi>, pl. VI, “The
        Whirlwind of Lovers”, no inscription [<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> No. 448]</p>
              <p>— Two prints labeled by Lessing J. Rosenwald as restrikes of 1955 [<hi rend="i">Blake
Books</hi> No. 448C]</p>
              <p>— Nine restrikes dated by Lessing J. Rosenwald first proofs 14 Aug. 1968 
[<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> No. 448D]</p>
              <p>298 Album entitled on the spine “William Blake Papers IV”, iv, 75 [171] ff.,
        containing photocopies of Todd’s letters about Flaxman bibliography to Col. William
        Edward Moss and one other document (1941-45) from the originals in Bodley</p>
              <p>Henry Fuseli, <hi rend="i">Lectures on Painting</hi> (1801) [<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>
        No. 459]</p>
              <p>324 Notes on the major paintings in oil of John Martin, a bound notebook compiled by
        Ruthven Todd [c. 1945], MS, 90 ff.</p>
              <p>Romney-Blake engraved portrait of Cowper [from William Hayley, <hi rend="i">The Life of .
         . . William Cowper</hi>, I (1803), frontispiece—<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> No.
        468 (1)]</p>
              <p>J. G. Salzmann, <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality</hi> (1791) [<hi rend="i">Blake
         Books</hi> No. 492]</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (London: Pickering, 1839) 
[<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> No. 171]</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Brotherton Collection</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (1808) [<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> No.
        435A]</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">Poetical Works of William Blake</hi>, ed. W. M. Rossetti (1875) 
[<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> No. 299B] with A. C. Swinburne’s signature, of “dubious”
        authenticity (according to the Brotherton catalogue)</p>
              <p>Henry Fuseli letter to F. J. Du Roveray of 27 Dec. 1802</p>
              <p>William Hayley, <hi rend="i">The Triumphs of Temper</hi>, 12th Edition (1803) 
[<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> No. 471A]</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Brotherton Library</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Bible: <hi rend="i">Illustrations of The Book of Job</hi> (1825) India proofs 
[<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> No. 421]</p>
              <p>John Flaxman letters to Benjamin Gott of 19 May 1825, 19 Jan., 23 May 1826, and
        Gott’s replies of 13 Feb., 20 May 1826 (in the Gott Family Papers, MS 194)</p>
              <p>William Hayley, <hi rend="i">The Life of . . . William Cowper</hi> 3 vols. (1803-04) 
[<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> No. 468]</p>
              <p>Thomas Lawrence letters of 1818-29 (in the Gott Family Papers, MS 194)</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p16-81" n="81" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
