<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.3.hilton</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Some Sexual Connotations</title>
        <author n="Hilton">Nelson Hilton</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1982/1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982-83</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Barbara Guth</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Michael Ackland</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982/1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
      <pb id="p16-166" n="166"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="main">Some Sexual Connotations</title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">NELSON</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">HILTON</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>The last time I taught “To Spring” in California, three students walked out of the
class—dramatic confirmation, perhaps, that the poem suggests a correspondence between dew and other genital
juices, semen especially: “O thou with dewy locks . . . . Come o’er the eastern hills . . . . scatter thy
pearls / Upon our love-sick land.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">1</ref>
Spring’s “dewy locks” are like those of the “beloved” in the Song of Songs, who says, “Open to me,
my sister, my love, my dove, my undefiled: for my head is filled with dew, and my locks with the drops of
night” (5:2). For the ancient Greeks, dew was a manifestation of Zeus’ semen;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">2</ref> so Emile Benveniste can discuss lexical relationships in
Greek which suggest that “tiny new born animals are like dew, the fresh little drops which have just
fallen,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">3</ref> and William Harvey can
equate dew with “the Primigenial Moisture” from which “Seed” is made.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">4</ref> This equation is explicit in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
30[34].3-4: “O how I tremble! how my members pour down milky fear! / A dewy garment covers me all over, all
manhood is gone!” By the end of “To Spring,” Spring has already come (see <hi rend="i">OED</hi>
citations from 1650 and 1714), and so quickly that the speaker is left pointing to the country’s arborescent
“modest tresses” which <hi rend="i">were</hi> bound up. <note id="n42"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Blake is quoted
from David V. Erdman, ed. <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, 3rd printing, rev. (Garden
City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1968).</note>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Géza Róheim, <hi rend="i">Animism, Magic, and The Divine King</hi>
(London: Kegan Paul, Trench, <corr type="emend">Trübner</corr> &amp; Co., 1930), p. 95.</note>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> Indo-European Language and Society</hi>, trans. Elizabeth
Palmer (London: Faber &amp; Faber, 1973), p. 22.</note>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">4</hi><hi rend="i"> Anatomical Exercitations Concerning the Generation of Living
Creatures</hi>, trans. (London, 1653), pp. 462-63.</note></p>
        <p>With “To Summer” things get even hotter as we focus on the presence of Summer 
<hi rend="i">in</hi> the countryside, notably in “our vallies,” “our mossy vallies”: “Our vallies love
the Summer in his pride” (1, 10, 13). We encounter similar content in the “sweet valleys of ripe virgin
bliss” and “valleys of delight” of the Lambeth books (<hi rend="i">Am</hi> c. 30; <hi rend="i">SL</hi>
3.28), evoking, perhaps, the popular etymology, “<hi rend="i">Vulva</hi>, as it were 
<hi rend="i">vallis</hi>, a valley.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">5</ref>
Such contentment often befalls in the summer, and Summer “oft . . . has slept, while we beheld / With joy
[his] ruddy limbs and <corr type="emend">flourishing</corr> hair.” Our joy, or jouissance, is that of
gratified desire, and it allows us to turn to making songs and using other instruments of joy—in accordance
with the notebook quatrain:
<q>
Abstinence sows sand all over<lb/>
The ruddy limbs &amp; flaming hair<lb/>
But Desire Gratified<lb/>
Plants fruits of life &amp; beauty there<lb/>
(E 465)
</q>
Such gratified desire is not the lot of the singer who sweetly “roam’d from field to field / And tasted
all the summers pride” until he had the misfortune of beholding not the ruddy limbs of Summer but “the
prince of love” (Amor does not roam). In a double bind of lilies and “blushing” (e-)roses, the singer
forsakes wide open fields for the <hi rend="i">vita nuova</hi> of love’s cultivated gardens and golden
pleasures. Entering the garden, everything seems permitted: “With sweet May dews my wings were wet.” But
the sweet wetness of what one may do in the warmer months evaporates as Phoebus fires “vocal rage” and the
singer, now come of age, is caught and caged. Another of Blake’s singers feels that whenever he enters the
“sweet village” where his “black-ey’d maid” is sleeping, “more than mortal fire / Burns in my
soul, and does my song inspire.” Just so the first singer now spends his time alone with a prince of love
who loves songs first, then “sport and play,” and who will at last only mockingly stretch out the
singer’s now solitary golden wing. <note id="n46"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Helkiah Crooke, 
<hi rend="i">ΜΙΚΡΟΚΟΣΜΟΓΡΑΦΙΑ, A Description of the Body of Man</hi> (London, 1651), p.
175.</note></p>
        <p>That Blake’s “loom” also invokes the “womb” is well recognized; 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> even repeats on three occasions that “the female is a golden Loom.” The Looms are
a main feature of “Cathedron,” the textile-mill district of Golgonooza. With its spires and domes
Cathedron obviously owes something to “cathedral”—which as a “holy place” also names the female
genitalia, the “holy of holies” as a common vulgarism had it—but even more interesting is the word’s
closeness to the name of the women in Blake’s life, his mother, sister, and wife, Catherine. Blake surely
knew that the name comes from the Greek “katheros,” meaning “pure.” In <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
Enitharmon erects Looms, “And calld the Looms Cathedron in these Looms She wove the Spectres / Bodies of
Vegetation” (100.3-4). There
<q>
The Daughters of Enitharmon weave the ovarium &amp; the integument<lb/>
In soft silk drawn from their own bowels in lascivious delight<lb/>
With songs of sweetest cadence
</q>
“Ovarium” is a curiously technical word to find here, just as “lascivious delight” seems an unusually
strong description, though we hear elsewhere of the “sweet intoxication” in which the Daughters ply their
looms (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 80.80). Going to the Authorized Version and to the Hebrew 
<hi rend="i">rachamim</hi>, “bowels” can also mean “womb,” and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> tells us that
drawn silk can be a sexual “silk of liquid . . . issuing from . . . Furnaces” (87.19-20). This system can
be better understood if we grasp the sexual aspect of “fibres,” suggested parenthetically by Jean Hagstrum
some years ago.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">6</hi> “Babylon Revisited, or the Story of Luvah and Vala,” in Stuart Curran
and Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr., eds., <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory: Essays on The Four Zoas,
Milton, Jerusalem</hi> (Madison: Univ. of Wisconsin Press, 1973), p. 107.</note></p>
        <p>The correlation linking fibres, worms, and semen has one source in Erasmus Darwin’s influential
hypothesis that
<pb id="p16-167" n="167"/>
life originates as a “simple living filament . . . an extremity of a nerve” which is secreted from the
parent.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">7</ref> This “filament” could in
turn be seen as an instance of “the seminal worms, now so well known [which] were first observed in the male
seed by the help of the microscope.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49"
type="note">8</ref> So Orc “like a Worm / In the trembling womb / To be moulded into existence” 
(<hi rend="i">BU</hi> 19.21-23),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">9</ref> appears
to be, in part, a materialization of Los’ spermatozoon—a vermicular fibre. Ejaculation thus consists in
“shooting out”—another common street term (“shooting out in sweet pleasure” [<hi rend="i">J</hi>
88.28])—fibres, or, giving the Female Will a superior position, in having fibres “drawn” out. In 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> we see Enitharmon like a faint rainbow waving before Los and “Filling with Fibres
from his loins which reddend with desire” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 86.51), and in the illustration of plate 85
(illus. 1), one of the fibres handled by the naked Enitharmon leads, evidently, between Los’s thighs to his
phallos—perhaps the propensity of semen to agglutinate into tenuating strands when handled is one source of
its conception as silky “fibre.” <note id="n48"><hi rend="s">7</hi><hi rend="i"> Zoonomia, or the Laws of
Organic Life</hi>, vol. 1 (London: J. Johnson, 1794), p. 489.</note>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Albrecht von Haller, <hi rend="i">First Lines of Physiology</hi>, trans.
William Cullen, The Sources of Science, no. 32, 2 vols. in 1 (1786); facs. rpt., New York: Johnson Reprint,
1966), sect. 882.</note>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">9</hi> G. L. Leclerc de Buffon observes in his <hi rend="i">Natural History,
General and Particular</hi> that “the spermatic worm . . . becomes a real foetus” (trans. William Smellie,
3rd. ed., 9 vols. [London, 1791], 2.137).</note></p>
        <p>Again, when the Daughters are pulling fibres from Albion, as they do all through 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,
<q>
Conwenna sat above: with solemn cadences she drew<lb/>
Fibres of life out from the Bones into her Golden Loom<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 90.21-22)
</q>
Partridge’s <hi rend="i">Dictionary of Slang</hi> reports that “bone” was cockney slang for the erect
penis beginning in the mid-nineteenth century,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51"
type="note">10</ref> but that is for printed reference, which always lags far behind oral speech. Again, at
the end of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> we see Los, himself now “intoxicated,” saying
<q>
. . . my wild fibres shoot in veins<lb/>
Of blood thro all my nervous limbs. soon overgrown in roots<lb/>
I shall be closed from thy sight.
</q>
This saturation of sexual reference suggests that Los is being enclosed in genitality, becoming a sort of
polyphallos (to keep up with the polypuss) with proliferating “nervous Limbs” and “roots.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">11</ref> Los next words are curious in the extreme:
<q>
. . . seize therefore in thy hand<lb/>
The small fibres as they shoot around me draw out in pity<lb/>
And let them run on the winds of thy bosom<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 87.5-9)
</q>
Who is to draw out what in pity? Are the fibres to run on Enitharmon’s bosom as before “All day the worm
lay on her bosom” (<hi rend="i">BU</hi> 19.24)? The passage is striking for the merely suggested quality of
a graphic sexual reference. This is perhaps as Blake would have it: actual sexual relations cannot in the
first instance fully image imagination, and in the second could not describe the nature of the intercourse
between the Daughters and Albion, or Enitharmon and Los. As Los continues, “I will fix them / With
pulsations. we will divide them into Sons &amp; Daughters.” Division is always sexual: into parts, sections,
sects, as the Latin etymology reminds us. <note id="n51"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Eric Partridge, <hi rend="i">A
Dictionary of Slang and Unconventional English</hi>, 5th ed. (New York: Macmillan, 1961), s.v.</note>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">11</hi> “Nerve” is frequent in Latin for the penis 
(<hi rend="i">nervus</hi>), and so used in English by Dryden; this sense appears in Urizen’s address to the
“bowstring” (one of the word’s other meanings) taken from the “serpent”: “O nerve of that lust
form’d monster” (<hi rend="i">BA</hi> 3.27). In other contexts Blake refers to “the sportive root” and
the “delving root,” and, in particular, we see the force of Orc as “Enitharmon cried upon her terrible
Earthy bed / While the broad Oak wreathd his roots round her forcing his dark way” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi>
98.7-8). Los says that men “know not why they love,” and that their misguided idea of “Holy Love” has
“separated the stars from the mountains: the mountains from Man / And left Man, a little grovelling Root,
outside of Himself” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 17.31-32).</note></p>
        <p>Having alluded to coitus interruptus,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53"
type="note">12</ref> it would be fitting to mention Blake’s conception of consummation. The word is
polysemous: Frye notes its ambiguity “in referring to the two chief aspects of the Last Judgment, the
burning world and the sacred marriage.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54"
type="note">13</ref> But since <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> calls “the Loins the place of the Last
Judgment” (44[30].38), consummation surely refers to profane marriage as well. Such consummation, it must be
observed, is rather futile in Blake: while Orc’s parents hope “to melt the chain of Jealousy, not
Enitharmons death / Nor the Consummation of Los could ever melt the chain.” Here the standard English sexual
euphemisms “death” and “melt” point to the physical nature of the consummation. The chain cannot be
melted because it is already part of the body of Los—his phallos is one of the chain’s essential links, as
apparent in some versions of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, pl. 21. Along with the male-female dialectic, there
appear to be two kinds of consummation. “No one can consummate Female bliss in Los’s World without /
Becoming a Vegetated Mortal, a Vegetating Death” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 69.30-31). Such, evidently, is
Blake’s denigration of physical, “Female,” consummation. For male consummation we must turn to 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and another odd episode in Orc’s dealings with the Shadowy Female. In <hi rend="i">The
Four Zoas</hi>, we should first note, it is “in the
<figure n="jerusalem.e.p85" id="jerusalem.e.illbk.85" work-copy="jerusalem.e" rend="db" width="731" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>85<lb/>
	Became a Space &amp; an Allegory around the Winding Worm<lb/>
	They namd it Canaan &amp; built for it a tender Moon<lb/>
	Los smild with joy thinking on Enitharmon &amp; he brought<lb/>
	Reuben from his twelvefold wandrings &amp; led him into it<lb/>
	Planting the Seeds of the Twelwe Tribes &amp; Moses &amp; David<lb/>
	And gave a Time &amp; Revolution to the Space Six Thousand Years<lb/>
	He calld it Divine Analogy, for in Beulah the Feminine<lb/>
	Emanations Create Space, the Masculine Create Time. &amp; plant<lb/>
	The Seeds of beauty in the Space: listning to their lamentation<lb/>
	Los walks upon his ancient Mountains in the deadly darkness<lb/>
	Among his Furnaces directing his laborious Myriads watchful<lb/>
	Looking to the East: &amp; his voice is heard over the whole Earth<lb/>
	As he watches the Furnaces by night, &amp; directs the labourers<lb/>
	And thus Los replies upon his Watch: the Valleys listen silent:<lb/>
	The Stars stand still to hear: Jerusalem &amp; Vala cease to mourn!<lb/>
	His voice is heard from Albion: the Alps &amp; Appenines<lb/>
	Listen: Hermon &amp; Lebanon bow their crowned heads<lb/>
	Babel &amp; Shinar look toward the Western Gate, they sit down<lb/>
	Silent at his voice: they view the red Globe of fire in Los’s hand<lb/>
	As he walks from Furnace to Furnace directing the Labourers<lb/>
	And this is the Song of Los. the Song that he sings on his<lb/>
	Watch<lb/>
	O lovely mild Jerusalem! O Shiloh of Mount Ephraim!<lb/>
	I see thy Gates of precious stones! thy Walls of gold &amp; silver<lb/>
	Thou art the soft reflected Image of the Sleeping Man<lb/>
	Who stretchd on Albions rocks reposes amidst his Twenty-eight<lb/>
	Cities: where Beulah lovely terminates, in the hills &amp; valleys of Albion<lb/>
	Cities not yet embodied in Time and Space: plant ye<lb/>
	The Seeds O Sisters in the bosom of Time &amp; Spaces womb<lb/>
	To spring up for Jerusalem: lovely Shadow of Sleeping Albion<lb/>
	Why wilt thou rend thyself apart &amp; build an Earthly Kingdom<lb/>
	To reign in pride &amp; to opress &amp; to mix the Cup of Delusion<lb/>
	O thou that dwellest with Babylon! Come forth O lovely-one</figTranscr>
	<head>1. <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, pl. 85, copy E, from the collection of Paul Mellon.</head>
</figure>
<pb id="p16-168" n="168"/>
Caverns of the Grave &amp; Places of human seed” that “The nameless shadowy Vortex stood before the face
of Orc” (91.1-2). Here we see that the Female is, in one aspect, the Vortex. George Devereux cites instances
from his psychoanalytic practice in which “the hairy vulva is fantasied as a <hi rend="i">vortex</hi> which,
by <hi rend="i">suction</hi>, draws the victim into the vagina.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n55" type="note">14</ref> This archaic male fear must underlie the intellectual/astronomical
fantasy-projection of the “whirls of generation” by means of which, Thomas Taylor reported, souls descend
to generation; Charles Cotton’s late seventeenth century double-entendre, <hi rend="i">Erotopolis</hi>,
warns that a man, “if he have not a care, he may chance to lose a limb, swallowed up in a whirl-pit, not
without the Effusion of the choycest part of the blood.” The Female vortex stands before Orc “that he
might lose his rage / And with it lose himself” in the intoxicating consolations of the world of generation.
In <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, however, Orc tells the Shadowy Female:
<q>
. . . Behold how I am &amp; tremble lest thou also<lb/>
Consume in my Consummation; but thou maist take a Form<lb/>
Female and lovely, that cannot consume in Mans consummation<lb/>
(18.27-29)
</q>
Orc’s sexual “rage” has now turned to an anger which inures him to sexual temptation—a heavy change
from the conclusion to the foreplay of <hi rend="i">America</hi>, where Orc “seiz’d the panting,
struggling womb” of the Shadowy Daughter. Orc’s anger comes from the realization that the “nameless
shadowy Vortex” has become “Urizens harlot / And the Harlot of Los &amp; the deluded harlot of the Kings
of Earth” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 91.14-15)—in other words, Mystery, the whore of Babylon, “With whom the
Kings of the earth have committed fornication, and the inhabitants of the earth have been made drunk with the
wine of her fornication” (Rev. 17:2). <note id="n53"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Leopold Damrosch, Jr. argues that
“Blake . . . dreads [sexual desire’s] power <hi rend="i">because</hi> it leads to generation,” and
suggests that “We cannot be surprised if at times Blake suggests that the proper response is to withold the
desired seed” (<hi rend="i">Symbol and Truth in Blake’s Myth</hi> [Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press,
1980], p. 203).</note>
	<note id="n54"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Northrop Frye, <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry: A Study of William
Blake</hi> (1947; rpt., Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1969), p. 351.</note>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">14</hi><hi rend="i"> Dreams in Greek Tragedy: An Ethno-Psycho-Analytical
Study</hi> (Oxford: Blackwell, 1976), p. 334.</note></p>
        <p>“Mans consummation,” apparently, is to be “consummated in Mental fires” 
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 85.46), a cerebral destiny which insures against the possibility that “the Sexual Garments
sweet / Should grow a devouring Winding Sheet,” that “Sexual Generation swallow up Regeneration”
(“Keys to the Gates,” 25-26; <hi rend="i">J</hi> 90.37). On the other hand, plate 7 of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> exclaims:
<q>
O holy Generation! [<hi rend="i">Image</hi>] of regeneration!<lb/>
O point of mutual forgiveness between Enemies!<lb/>
Birthplace of the Lamb of God incomprehensible!<lb/>
(65-67)
</q>
Blake’s anger, and the contention that “Humanity knows not of Sex,” may be located in his reaction
against a Pauline world “Where a Man dare hardly to embrace / His own Wife, for the terrors of Chastity that
they call / By the name of Morality” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 44[30].33; 32[36].45-47). It is men who have
created rape, fornication, and a “Female Will / To hide the most evident God in a hidden covert, even / In
the shadows of a woman &amp; a secluded Holy Place” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 30[34].31-32).</p>
        <p>This dynamic can be approached through Robert Stoller’s recent argument that the underlying cause
of sexual excitement is hostility: “it is hostility—the desire, overt or hidden, to harm another
person—that generates and enhances sexual excitement. The absence of hostility leads to sexual indifference
and boredom. The hostility of erotism [Stoller’s term] is an attempt, repeated over and over, to undo
childhood traumas and frustrations that threatened the development of one’s masculinity or
feminity.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">15</ref> This analysis-cum-male
fantasy finds an analogue in Blake’s perception of “Spiritual Hate, from which springs Sexual Love” 
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 54.12). For Blake, however, the threatening childhood traumas and frustrations that underlie
any hostility and excitement are associated more fundamentally with growing up, particularly growing into the
inner hormonal explosion of the world of generation, whose complications are exacerbated by the divisions of
gender which are first and foremost culturally instituted. Blake, “Weeping over the web of life,” will not
accept the basic structures of our experience, and asks us to do the same. As Damrosch notes
unsympathetically, “there is no avoiding the realization that [Blake’s] ideal for human existence does
away with human nature as poets have always described it” (p. 217). Stoller believes further that the
hostility is in part expressed through the “mystery” of the body: “the mystery being managed emanates
from sexual anatomy.” And, he continues, “The point is not simply that in the past a person was frightened
by mystery but that, paradoxically, <hi rend="i">he or she is now making sure the mystery is maintained</hi> .
. . if the appearance [what Blake would call the veil] of mystery does not persist, excitement will fade.” A
similar understanding is the basis for Blake’s indignation. For Blake, the “Sexual texture woven” is the
corollary of “the Veil of Moral Virtue, woven for Cruel Laws” which prompts the “eternal torments of
love &amp; jealousy.” Inexorably, “All the Jealousies become Murderous and unite together in Rahab / A
Religion of Chastity,” an evolution clearly identified by Mary Wollstonecraft as well. In the sacred rites
of Sexual Religion, “the Female lets down her beautiful Tabernacle: / which the Male enters magnificent
between her Cherubim” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 44[30].34-35), but from the perspective of Eden this is just the
pompous High Priest entering an empty room behind the veil: a ritual of guilt and atonement rather than the
delight of joy and at-one-ment. Paul Miner, in “William Blake’s ‘Divine Analogy’ ” 
(<hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 3 [1963]: 46-61), is very good on such correspondences between Old Testament
references and Blake’s sexual context, though his distinction between pompous Atonement and a selfless
“propitiatory offering” of coitus seems problematic. What is to be propitiated? It may well be that “no
one can consummate Female bliss . . . without Becoming a Generated Mortal,” but then, neither can we
<q>
behold Golgonooza without passing the Polypus<lb/>
A wondrous journey <hi rend="i">not passable by Immortal feet</hi> . . .<lb/>
For Golgonooza cannot be seen till having passed the Polypus<lb/>
It is viewed on all sides round by a Four-fold Vision<lb/>
Or till you become Mortal &amp; Vegetable in Sexuality<lb/>
Then you behold its mighty Spires &amp; Domes of ivory &amp; gold<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">M</hi> 35.19-25, italics added)
</q>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">15</hi><hi rend="i"> Sexual Excitement</hi> (New York: Pantheon, 1979), p.
17.</note></p>
        <pb id="p16-169" n="169"/>
        <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> shows us “the beautiful Daughters of Albion,” and adds, “If you
dare rend their Veil with your Spear; you are healed of Love!” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 68.42). Set amidst
graphic passages devoted to the castrating Druidic priestesses, this introduces a countervailing comment
identifying phallic penetration with the soldier’s spear that pierced Christ’s side (John 19:34). The
point may be to show that the “love” of which one may be healed, is, as elsewhere in the passage, pride
&amp; wrath; Los says, “I also have pierced the Lamb of God in pride &amp; wrath” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi>
106.55). Fallen sexuality is seen as inextricably bound up with the context of power, the hostile dehumanizing
and fetishizing of the “sex-object.” Stoller’s argument that hostility underlies a prevalent experience
of sexual excitement lends Blake’s image additional weight. In rending the veil one is healed of a wounding
“love” to become, perhaps, like Bromion sated and bored after having rent Oothoon’s virgin mantle with
his thunders (a scene offering another reference to the Passion and its aftermath). Or, paradoxically, one may
indeed be healed of that spurious love (pride &amp; wrath) by experiencing the void behind the rent veil, a
“healing” which would at least lead to a potentially saving despair and the eventual discovery of delight
in the place of excitement. “Arise O Lord, &amp; rend the Veil!” cries Los in lamentation: only
imagination can expose the unprolific mystery of sexual fascination and worship, the anger and projection that
constitute “that false / And Generating Love: a pretense of love to destroy Love” (<hi rend="i">J</hi>
17.25-26). Foucault would remind us, as well as Los, that the discourse of sexuality is a social fiction.</p>
        <p>The creation of such a fiction may be seen in the “Epilogue” to <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The
Gates of Paradise</hi> (illus. 2). Here we see the Satanic spectre “that has resided in [the traveller’s]
breast” now “rising out of the sleeping traveller.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57"
type="note">16</ref> Commentators seem to have avoided the obvious fact that the starry spectre’s foot is
placed to double for the traveller’s snaky penis (compare illus. 3) rising in his sleep while the spectre in
effect emerges from it. We have, then, a multistable image<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n58" type="note">17</ref>—a graphic equivalent of the double- entendre—of the fallen lost
traveller ready to copulate (“sleep”) with his own nocturnal emission (“emanation”—etymologically, a
flowing-out”), his dream of the starry universe of generation: “The lost traveller’s dream under the
hill.” This visualization of the sleeper’s condition is implicit in earlier references to Luvah’s
“reasoning from the Loins in the unreal forms of Ulro’s night,” or that while “Albion slept,” his
“Spectre from his Loins / Tore forth in all the pomp of War! / Satan his name” (<hi rend="i">J</hi>
27.37-39). <note id="n57"><hi rend="s">16</hi> David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi>
(Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1974), p. 279, and George Wingfield Digby, <hi rend="i">Symbol and Image in
William Blake</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1957), p. 53.</note>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">17</hi> See Aaron Sheon, “Multistable Perception in Romantic Caricatures,”
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 16 (Summer 1977), 331-35; Stephen Leo Carr, “Visionary Syntax:
Nontyrannical Coherence in Blake’s Visual Art,” <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: Theory and
Interpretation</hi> 22 (Autumn 1981), 222-48; and Fred Attneave, “Multistability in Perception,” 
<hi rend="i">Scientific American</hi>, December 1971, pp. 63-71; “multistability” offers another way of
formulating “overdetermination.”</note></p>
        <p>Plate 75 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> offers a different conception in its multistable image
(illus. 4). David Erdman suggests that we
<figure n="gates-sexes.d.p21" id="gates-sexes.d.illbk.21" work-copy="gates-sexes.d" rend="db" width="672" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>To The Accuser who is<lb/>
          The God of This World<lb/>
          <lb/>
          Truly My Satan thou art but a Dunce<lb/>
          And dost not know the Garment from the Man<lb/>
          Every Harlot was a Virgin once<lb/>
          Nor canst thou ever change Kate into Nan<lb/>
          <lb/>
          Tho thou art Worshipd by the Names Divine<lb/>
          Of Jesus &amp; Jehovah; thou art still<lb/>
          The Son of Morn in weary Nights decline<lb/>
          The lost Travellers Dream under the Hill<lb/>
          <lb/>
          19</figTranscr>
	<head>2. <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi>, pl. 19, copy D, by permission of the
Pierpont Morgan Library.</head>
</figure>
<figure n="america.f.p16" id="america.f.illbk.16" work-copy="america.f" rend="db" width="757" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>In the flames stood &amp; view’d the armies drawn out in the sky<lb/>
	Washington Franklin Paine &amp; Warren Allen Gates &amp; Lee:<lb/>
	And heard the voice of Albions Angel give the thunderous command<lb/>
	His plagues obedient to his voice flew forth out of their clouds<lb/>
	Falling upon America, as a storm to cut them off<lb/>
	As a blight cuts the tender corn when it begins to appear.<lb/>
	Dark is the heaven above, &amp; cold &amp; hard the earth beneath;<lb/>
	And as a plague wind fill’d with insects cuts off man &amp; beast;<lb/>
	And as a sea o’erwhelms a land in the day of an earthquake;<lb/>
	<lb/>
	4 JY 59<lb/>
	<lb/>
	Fury! rage! madness! in a wind swept through America<lb/>
	And the red flames of Orc that folded roaring fierce around<lb/>
	The angry shores, and the fierce rushing of th’ inhabitants together;<lb/>
	The citizens of New-York close their books &amp; lock their chests;<lb/>
	The mariners of Boston drop their anchors and unlade;<lb/>
	The scribe of Pensylvania casts his pen upon the earth;<lb/>
	The builder of Virginia throws his hammer down in fear.<lb/>
	Then had America been lost, o’erwhelm’d by the Atlantic,<lb/>
	And Earth had lost another portion of the infinite,<lb/>
	But all rush together in the night in wrath and raging fire<lb/>
	The red fires rag’d! the plagues recoil’d! then rolld they back <lb/>
	with fury</figTranscr>
	<head>3. <hi rend="i">America</hi>, pl. 14, copy F, by permission of the Trustees of the British
Museum.</head>
</figure>
<pb id="p16-170" n="170"/>
<figure n="jerusalem.e.p75" id="jerusalem.e.illbk.75" work-copy="jerusalem.e" rend="db" width="744" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>75<lb/>
	<lb/>
	And Rahab Babylon the Great hath destroyed Jerusalem<lb/>
	Bath stood upon the Severn with Merlin &amp; Bladud &amp; Arthur<lb/>
	The Cup of Rahab in his hand; her Poisons Twenty-seven-fold<lb/>
	And all her Twenty-seven Heavens now hid &amp; now reveal’d<lb/>
	Appear in strong delusive light of Time &amp; Space drawn out<lb/>
	In shadowy pomp by the Eternal Prophet created evermore<lb/>
	For Los in Six Thousand Years walks up &amp; down continually<lb/>
	That not one Moment of Time be lost &amp; every revolution<lb/>
	Of Space he makes permanent in Bowlahoola &amp; Cathedron.<lb/>
	And these the names of the Twenty-seven Heavens &amp; their Churches<lb/>
	Adam, Seth, Enos, Cainan, Mahalaleel, Jared, Enoch.<lb/>
	Methuselah, Lamech; these are the Giants mighty, Hermaphroditic<lb/>
	Noah, Shem, Arphaxad, Cainan the Second, Salah. Heber,<lb/>
	Peleg, Reu. Serug, Nahor, Terah: these are the Female Males:<lb/>
	A Male within a Female hid as in an Ark &amp; Curtains.<lb/>
	Abraham. Moses, Solomon, Paul, Constantine, Charlemaine.<lb/>
	Luther. these Seven are the Male Females: the Dragon Forms<lb/>
	The Female hid within a Male: thus Rahab is reveald<lb/>
	Mystery Babylon the Great; the Abomination of Desolation<lb/>
	Religion hid in War; a Dragon red. &amp; hidden Harlot<lb/>
	But Jesus breaking thro’ the Central Zones of Death &amp; Hell<lb/>
	Opens Eternity in Time &amp; Space; triumphant in Mercy<lb/>
	Thus are the Heavens formd by Los within the Mundane Shell<lb/>
	And where Luther ends Adam begins again in Eternal Circle<lb/>
	To awake the Prisoners of Death; to bring Albion again<lb/>
	With Luvah into light eternal. in his eternal day.<lb/>
	But now the Starry Heavens are fled from the mighty limbs of Albion</figTranscr>
	<head>4. <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, pl. 75, copy E, from the collection of Paul Mellon.</head>
</figure>
<pb id="p16-171" n="171"/>
see “probably Tirzah at the left, ending in a fish tail,” while on our right is “probably Rahab . . .
all woman as far as we can see (yet scaly)” (<hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake</hi>, p. 354). But—especially
in color—we can see that, combining two scales of perspective, Rahab also terminates in a “tail,” that
is to say, a life-size representation of the glans penis (ventral view). In words: scales become a masculine
coat of mail. Going beyond Géza Róheim’s later vision of Aphrodite as “the woman with a
penis,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">18</ref> Rahab is Female Will as
phallus (perhaps even Will Blake’s): “The Female hid within a Male: thus Rahab is reveald” (75.18). S/he
is not only embracing the serpent, but slipping imperceptibly into its coils as well, “a Dragon red, &amp;
hidden Harlot” (75.20). This graphic image should help lift our understanding and visualization of Female
Will out of the entangling gender-traps of language which so hamper discussions of it. For Blake, the phallus
signifies the fall of us into wandering error, the realm of fallacy (“Raha[b], in an outside which is
fallacious!” [<hi rend="i">M</hi> 37.9]). <note id="n59"><hi rend="s">18</hi> See Géza Róheim,
“Aphrodite, or the Woman with a Penis,” <hi rend="i">Psychoanalytical Quarterly</hi> 14 (1945), 350-90;
and also Norman O. Brown, <hi rend="i">Love’s Body</hi> (New York: Random House, 1966), pp. 62ff.</note></p>
        <p>The enveloping spectre of genital sexuality (identified by Blake in the famous letter of 23 October
1804 as “the enemy of conjugal love”) occasions the radical argument of the notebook poem, “My
Spectre”:
<q>
Let us agree to give up Love<lb/>
And root up the infernal grove;<lb/>
Then shall we return &amp; see<lb/>
The worlds of happy Eternity<lb/>
(67-70)
</q>
The “infernal grove” is the site of genital and generative worship, where, as another poem suggests, we
“suffer the Roman &amp; Grecian Rods / To compell us to worship them as Gods” (E492).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">19</ref> Understanding the sexual reference of this
and the other examples presented above, we realize also their limited transitory dimension in the global
contest they serve to illuminate. Blake sees the potential of life, particularly of “All-bionic”
intersubjective life, as exploited by the forces of generation (like the engendering genetic program) and
driven to weave to dreams the sexual strife. These connotations are aspects of an old dream, whose unconscious
status denotes that “Sexes must vanish &amp; cease / To be, when Albion arises from his dread repose” 
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 92.13-14). <note id="n60"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Perhaps the arrestingly curious and repeated
reference to “the detestable Gods of Priam” in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> offers an oblique allusion to a
(castrated?) Priapic pantheon: Priapus becomes polypus (Richard Payne Knight’s <hi rend="i">Discourse on the
Worship of Priapus and its Connection with the Mystic Theology of the Ancients</hi> was published in
1786).</note></p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
