<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.3.mellor</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake’s Portrayal of Women</title>
        <author n="Mellor">Anne K. Mellor</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1982/1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982-83</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Barbara Guth</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Michael Ackland</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982/1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
    <pb id="p16-148" n="148"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-3-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">Blake’s Portrayal of Women</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">ANNE K.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">MELLOR</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>In Eden or Eternity, as Los says in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, the human form divine is both male
and female:
<q>
When in Eternity Man converses with Man they enter<lb/>
Into each others Bosom (which are Universes of delight) In mutual interchange, . . .<lb/>
For Man cannot unite with Man but by their Emanations<lb/>
Which stand both Male &amp; Female at the Gates of each Humanity<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 88:3-5, 9-10; E 244)
</q>
Focusing on such lines as these, critics have hailed Blake as an advocate of androgyny, of a society in which
there is total sexual equality. Irene Tayler has acclaimed Blake’s revolutionary attack on the limited
sex-roles of a patriarchal culture and emphasized that in Blake’s liberated Eternity, “there are no sexes,
only Human Forms,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> forms that
experience no divisions between male and female but exist as “one will.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> And Michael Ferber, after discussing Blake’s idea of
brotherhood as a viable political utopia, insists that “Blake’s fraternity seems not to exclude women”
and that “most of Blake’s female figures are symbols of mental states or their projections that can be
found in any mind, male or female.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Irene Tayler, “The Woman Scaly,” <hi rend="i">Midwestern Modern
Language Association Bulletin</hi> 6 (Spring 1973), 84.</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> p. 86.</note>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Michael Ferber, “Blake’s Idea of Brotherhood,” <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi>
93 (May 1978), 446.</note></p>
        <p>But such attempts to read Blake’s Eden and the fourfold Man as genuinely androgynous are belied
by Blake’s consistently sexist portrayal of women. The poetic and visual metaphors that Blake develops and
uses throughout the corpus of his work typically depict women as either passively dependent on men, or as
aggressive and evil. As Susan Fox has persuasively shown in her fine essay on “The Female as Metaphor in
William Blake’s Poetry,” Blake portrays the female gender “as inferior and dependent (or, in the case of
Jerusalem, superior and dependent), or as unnaturally and disastrously dominant. Indeed, females are not only
represented as weak or power-hungry, they come to represent weakness (that frailty best seen in the
precariously limited “emanative” state Beulah) and power-hunger (“Female Will,” the corrupting lust
for dominance identified with women).”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
type="note">4</ref> Blake’s theoretical commitment to androgyny in his prophetic books is thus undermined by
his habitual equation of the female with the subordinate or the perversely dominant. As I shall try to show,
in Blake’s apocalyptic human form divine, the female elements continue to function in subordination to the
male elements. <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Susan Fox, “The Female as Metaphor in William Blake’s
Poetry,” <hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry</hi> 3 (Spring 1977), 507.</note></p>
        <p>Susan Fox has already pointed out that Blake’s heroines are consistently passive. Thel lacks the
will to confront the fallen world of Experience and try to redeem it. The more courageous Oothoon lacks the
power to break her lover’s or her society’s mind-forged manacles; thus she is, despite her liberated
vision, an impotent revolutionary. Ololon, however eager she is to give up her virginity and to unite with
Milton, remains a submissive Eve. And Jerusalem can only wait patiently for Albion to acknowledge her love and
embrace her; her redemptive role in the poem is circumscribed by male choices and responses. Blake’s attack
on domineering women—on Rahab, Tirzah, Vala, Leutha, the Enitharmon of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, and all
those women whom he denounces as embodiments of the “Female Will”—is overt and repetitive. In a typical
passage, Los urges Albion to rebel against the power of the female:
<q>
. . . what may Woman be?<lb/>
To have power over Man from Cradle to corruptible Grave.<lb/>
There is a Throne in every Man, it is the Throne of God<lb/>
This Woman has claimd as her own &amp; Man is no more!<lb/>
Albion is the Tabernacle of Vala &amp; her Temple<lb/>
And not the Tabernacle &amp; Temple of the Most High<lb/>
O Albion why wilt thou Create a Female Will?<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 30[34]:25-31; E 175)
</q>
Blake identifies the Female Will with the vision of the materialistic world as all-sufficient, and thereby
re-energizes the patriarchal association of woman with nature. Woman has traditionally been seen as the
mother, the womb, the land, earth: she is always fertile, passively waiting to be “plowed and to crop.”
Blake implicitly affirms this image of the woman as passive earth-mother by presenting its alternative, the
aggressive, independent woman, as someone who thwarts imaginative vision (by insisting on the primacy of the
five senses) and at the same time frustrates sensual pleasure (by chastely denying man sexual satisfaction in
order to gain power over him). Moreover, Blake’s depiction of the Female Will as a division from the
harmoniously unified individual further reinforces the Biblical and Miltonic image of the woman as created
from the ribs of the man. Since Blake identifies the Female Will with egoistic selfhood, he implies that women
should have no existence independent of men. “He for God, she for God in him,” proclaimed Milton in 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, and Blake says much the same thing in <hi rend="i">A Vision of the Last
Judgment</hi>: “In Eternity Woman is the Emanation of Man; she has No Will of her own. There is no such
thing in Eternity as a Female Will” (<hi rend="i">VLJ</hi> 85; E 552)</p>
        <pb id="p16-149" n="149"/>
        <figure n="jerusalem.e.p99" id="jerusalem.e.illbk.99" work-copy="jerusalem.e" rend="db" width="699" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>99<lb/>
	All Human Forms identified even Tree Metal Earth &amp; Stone, all<lb/>
	Human Forms identified. living going forth &amp; returning wearied<lb/>
	Into the Planetary lives of Years Months Days &amp; Hours reposing<lb/>
	And then Awaking into his Bosom in the Life of Immortality.<lb/>
	And I heard the Name of their Emanations they are named Jerusalem<lb/>
	The End of The Song<lb/>
	of Jerusalem</figTranscr>
          <head>1. <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 99, copy E, from the collection of Paul Mellon.</head>
        </figure>
        <p>Now I wish to suggest some of the specific ways in which the female—as metaphor, as a set of
human activities, and as an artistic image—is portrayed in Blake’s work as secondary to the male. In
Blake’s metaphoric system, labor is strictly divided on the basis of sex-gender. Males—or the masculine
dimension of the psyche—create ideas, forms, designs; females—or the feminine states of mind—can desire
(and thus inspire) these forms but not create them. Instead, the female obediently embodies those ideas or
designs in physical shapes and perceptible colors. Here, for instance, is the way that Los and Enitharmon
build Golgonooza. Enitharmon first calls out to Los,
<q>
. . . O Los my defence &amp; guide<lb/>
Thy works are all my joy. &amp; in thy fires my soul delights . . .<lb/>
. . . I can sigh forth on the winds of Golgonooza piteous forms<lb/>
That vanish again into my bosom but if thou my Los<lb/>
Wilt in sweet moderated fury. fabricate forms sublime<lb/>
Such as the piteous spectres may assimilate themselves into<lb/>
They shall be ransoms for our Souls that we may live<lb/>
</q>
Los then responds:
<q>
. . . his hands divine inspired began<lb/>
To modulate his fires studious the loud roaring flames<lb/>
He vanquishd with the strength of Art . . .<lb/>
  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
<figure n="jerusalem.e.p28" id="jerusalem.e.illbk.28" work-copy="jerusalem.e" rend="db" width="742" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>28<lb/>
	Jerusalem.<lb/>
	Chap: 2.<lb/>
	Every ornament of perfection, and every labour of love,<lb/>
	In all the Garden of Eden, &amp; in all the golden mountains<lb/>
	Was become an envied horror, and a remembrance of jealousy:<lb/>
	And every Act a Crime, and Albion the punisher &amp; judge.<lb/>
	And Albion spoke from his secret seat and said<lb/>
	All these ornaments are crimes. they are made by the labours<lb/>
	Of loves: of unnatural consanguinities and friendships<lb/>
	Horrid to think of when enquired deeply into; and all<lb/>
	These hills &amp; valleys are accursed witnesses of Sin<lb/>
	I therefore condense them into solid rocks. stedfast!<lb/>
	A foundation and certainty and demonstrative truth:<lb/>
	That Man be separate from Man, &amp; here I plant my seat.<lb/>
	Cold snows drifted around him: ice coverd his loins around<lb/>
	He sat by Tyburns brook, and underneath his heel, shot up!<lb/>
	A deadly Tree, he nam’d it Moral Virtue. and the Law<lb/>
	Of God who dwells in Chaos hidden from the human sight.<lb/>
	The Tree spread over him its cold shadows, (Albion groand)<lb/>
	They bent down, they felt the earth and again enrooting<lb/>
	Shot into many a Tree! an endless labyrinth of woe!<lb/>
	From willing sacrifice of Self. to sacrifice of (miscall’d) Enemies<lb/>
	For Atonement: Albion began to erect twelve Altars,<lb/>
	Of rough unhewn rocks. before the Potters Furnace<lb/>
	He nam’d them Justice. and Truth. And Albions Sons<lb/>
	Must have become the first Victims, being the first transgressors<lb/>
	But they fled to the mountains to seek ransom: building A Strong<lb/>
	Fortification against the Divine Humanity and Mercy.<lb/>
	In Shame &amp; Jealousy to annihilate Jerusalem!</figTranscr>
	<head>2. <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 28, copy E, from the collection of Paul Mellon.</head>
</figure>
And first he drew a line upon the walls of shining heaven<lb/>
And Enitharmon tincturd it with beams of blushing love<lb/>
It remaind permanent a lovely form inspird divinely human<lb/>
Dividing into just proportions Los unwearied labourd<lb/>
The immortal lines upon the heavens till with sighs of love<lb/>
Sweet Enitharmon mild Entrancd breathd forth upon the wind<lb/>
The spectrous dead Weeping the Spectres viewd the immortal works<lb/>
Of Los Assimilating to those forms Embodied &amp; Lovely<lb/>
In youth &amp; beauty in the arms of Enitharmon mild reposing<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> VII, 90:16-17, 20-27, 35-43; E 356)
</q>
In this gender-determined division of labor, Los employs the sons “In Golgonooza’s Furnaces among the
Anvils of time &amp; space” while Enitharmon employs the daughters in the Looms of Cathedron 
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> VIII, 103:35-36; E 361). Men forge, engrave, draw, construct plans; women then add
watercolors, weave coverings (“for every Female is a Golden Loom” [<hi rend="i">J</hi> 67:4; E 217]), and
actually build the city, the city
<pb id="p16-150" n="150"/>
          <figure n="jerusalem.morganprf.P28a" rend="file" width="726" height="1000">
	<head>3. <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 28, the Pierpont Morgan Library copy, first state.</head>
</figure>
          <figure n="jerusalem.morganprf.P28b" rend="file" width="726" height="1000">
	<head>4. <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, plate 28, the Pierpont Morgan Library copy, second state.</head>
</figure>
          <figure n="s-inn.b.p23-14" id="s-inn.b.illbk.23" work-copy="s-inn.b" rend="db" width="630" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>The Little Boy Found<lb/>
	The little boy lost in the lonely fen,<lb/>
	Led by the wand’ring light,<lb/>
	Began to cry, but God ever nigh,<lb/>
	Appeard like his father in white,<lb/>
	He kissed the child &amp; by the hand led<lb/>
	And to his mother brought,<lb/>
	Who in sorrow pale, thro’ the lonely dale<lb/>
	Her little boy weeping sought.</figTranscr>
	<head>5. “A Little Boy Lost,” <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection,
Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</head>
</figure>
that bears a female name, Jerusalem, and serves as the female’s ultimate self-realization. The human form
divine ultimately is “A Man” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 96:6; E 253); while the woman is only a garment that
clothes, physically embodies—or, more negatively, veils or imprisons—that spiritual form.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> In Golgonooza, Los’ furnaces rage,
<q>
. . . Creating Continually<lb/>
The times &amp; spaces of Mortal Life the Sun the Moon the Stars<lb/>
In periods of Pulsative furor beating into wedges &amp; bars<lb/>
Then drawing into wires the terrific Passions &amp; Affections<lb/>
Of Spectrous dead. Thence to the Looms of Cathedron conveyd<lb/>
  The Daughters of Enitharmon weave the ovarium &amp; the integument<lb/>
<pb id="p16-151" n="151"/>
<figure n="Traditio.Legis.16.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="650">
	<head>6. “Traditio Legis,” 4th century mosaic, apse, Mausoleum of Constantina.</head>
</figure>
In soft silk drawn from their own bowels in lascivious delight<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> VIII, 104: 4-10; E 362)
</q>
And in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, Orc says that Jerusalem is the Garment of God, a “Garment of Pity &amp;
Compassion” (<hi rend="i">M</hi> 18:35; E 111). <note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Morton Paley has studied
the image of the garment in similar terms in “The Figure of the Garment in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas,
Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,” in <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory</hi>, ed. Stuart
Curran and Joseph A. Wittreich, Jr. (Madison: University of Wisconsin Press, 1973), pp. 119-39.</note></p>
        <p>Further, in Blake’s metaphoric system, men prophesy; women then realize that prophecy in
historical time and space. Los or Urthona foretells the advent and true nature of Eden, while Cambel and her
sisters</p>
		<q>
. . . sit within the Mundane Shell:<lb/>
Forming the fluctuating Globe according to their will . . . .<lb/>
Sometimes it shall assimilate with mighty Golgonooza;<lb/>
Touching its summits: &amp; sometimes divided roll apart.<lb/>
As a beautiful Veil so these Females shall fold &amp; unfold<lb/>
According to their will the outside surface of the Earth<lb/>
An outside shadowy Surface superadded to the real Surface;<lb/>
Which is unchangeable for ever &amp; ever Amen.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 83:33-34, 43-48; E 239)
</q>
        <p>Men are intellect (at its most abstract and logical, they are intellect as rationalistic
“spectres”); women are “emanations,” divided from and intended to be finally reabsorbed into the male.
And in the rare cases where Blake insists that emanations can be male, he specifically defines the function of
such male emanations as subordinate. They play the role of mediator or reconciler between conflicting ideas or
desires. “For Man cannot unite with Man but by their Emanations / Which stand both Male &amp; Female at the
Gates of each Humanity” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 88:10-11; E 244). Thus both male and female emanations function
primarily to facilitate the greater identity of the male human form divine. Blake’s imagery, in all the
passages I have been quoting, insists that the masculine principle is prior to the feminine principle and that
the female depends upon, serves and reflects the male. As Blake wrote in an early annotation to Lavater’s
<hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man</hi>, “the female life lives from the light of the male; see a man’s female
dependents, you know the man” (E 585). Blake’s divine fraternity walk to and fro in Eternity as One Man,
conversing in visionary forms dramatic; Blake’s females, waiting at home with the children in Beulah, do
not.</p>
        <p>In Blake’s art as well as his poetry, the ideal female is subsumed under the male. In what is
perhaps the most striking visual example of this, the liberated Jerusalem on plate 99 (illus. 1) is portrayed
so ambiguously that critics have seen this figure both as female and as male. David Erdman endorses the
traditional identification of the naked figure as female, as Jerusalem-Britannia, although he also suggests
that this figure represents “all youth,” both male and female.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n6" type="note">6</ref>
	<pb id="p16-152" n="152"/>
<figure n="Thronenden.Christus.16.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="718" height="1000">
	<head>7. “Die thronenden Christus,” 12th century stone-relief, Benedictine Monastery
Petersburg-bei-Fulda, Germany.</head>
</figure>
W.J.T. Mitchell also sees the naked figure as predominantly female, locked in a sexual as well as filial
embrace with the old man, but he also allows for the possibility that this naked figure is male (as in copy E)
or an androgyne.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> On the other hand,
David Bindman in <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist</hi> initially sees the nude figure as male and describes the
scene as “the exultant union between Albion and Christ,” although he later qualifies this identification,
saying that the naked figure “could be either male or female” while the bearded figure is “either Christ
of Jehovah.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> One might conclude that
Blake has here achieved a triumphant visual image of androgyny. But the point I wish to make is that Blake has
presented the ultimately liberated Jerusalem as masculinized, but he has <hi rend="i">not</hi> imaged the
liberated Albion/Christ/Jehovah as feminized. The long white mustache and beard of a male is prominent in the
over-arching, dominating figure of the old man. Here a male nude form has absorbed the female form, but there
is no parallel absorption of femininity by the masculine figure. <note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> David V.
Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> (Garden City: Doubleday Anchor, 1974), pp. 378, 375.</note>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> W.J.T. Mitchell, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art</hi> (Princeton:
University Press, 1978), p. 214.</note>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> David Bindman, <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist</hi> (Oxford: Phaidon and
New York: Dutton, 1977), pp. 180, 183.</note></p>
        <p>Such a visual glorification of the masculine human body is of course intrinsic to the
Michelangelesque style which
          <figure n="ChristRedeemer.CarolingianIvoryBookCover.16.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="632" height="1000">
	<head>8. “Christ the Redeemer,” 9th century Carolingian ivory bookcover, Bodleian Library, Oxford (MS.
Douce 176).</head>
</figure>
Blake adopted as his icon of heroic energy. When Blake imitated Michelangelo’s Sistine Chapel nudes to
depict the human form divine, he tacitly endorsed Michelangelo’s hostility to the female body as well as his
homosexual celebration of the male body. Whether Blake did this consciously or not, it remains the case that
Blake’s female nudes are so similar to his male nudes that when seen from behind, they often cannot be
distinguished from each other. In the controversial case of Plate 28 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (illus.
2), Blake seems to have used the same physical image to present in the figure closest to us on our right first
a male (in the Pierpont Morgan proof sheet; illus. 3) and then, in the final copy, a female nude (illus.
4).</p>
        <p>To the suggestion that Blake did feminize the male figure of Jesus as an alternative image of
androgyny, as in the illustration for “A Little Boy Lost” (illus. 5) where the rescuer has been identified
both as Christ and as the boy’s mother, two counter arguments must be considered. First, in presenting a
beardless Christ with long hair and a high-waisted robe, Blake was following an established iconographical
tradition,
          <pb id="p16-153" n="153"/>
<figure n="ChristGirdingHimselfwithStrength.16.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="849" height="1000">
	<head>9. <hi rend="i">Christ Girding Himself with Strength</hi>, the City Art Gallery, Bristol.</head>
</figure>
as seen in these three examples. First (illus. 6) is a fourth century mosaic from the Mausoleum of Constantina
at Rome, showing Christ giving the Law to Saint Peter and Saint Paul; the second (illus. 7) is a twelfth
century stone-relief of the throned Christ from the Benedictine Monastery in Petersburg-bei-Fulda in Germany;
and, from the Bodleian Library in Oxford, the third (illus. 8) is a ninth-century Carolingian ivory
book-cover, showing Christ the Redeemer trampling the lion, dragon, asp and basilisk.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> In all these examples, Christ appears without a beard and
wears a robe with a sash beneath his breast. <note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> These images are reproduced in,
respectively, Pierre Du Bourguet, <hi rend="i">Early Christian Art</hi>, trans. Thomas Burton (New York:
Reynal and Co., 1971), p. 129; Robert Berger, <hi rend="i">Die Darstellung des thronenden Christus in der
romanischen Kunst</hi> (Reutlingen: Gryphius, 1926), fig. 66, p. 111; and E. Baldwin Smith, <hi rend="i">Early
Christian Iconography</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1918), fig. 169, p. 250.</note></p>
        <p>Secondly, Blake on several occasions took pains to emphasize the <hi rend="i">masculinity</hi> of
this image of Jesus, as in <hi rend="i">Christ Girding Himself with Strength</hi> (illus. 9) and in his
illustration to Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> (illus. 10). Blake apparently valued the male human form as
a more powerful image of physical beauty and grandeur than the female form; as he wrote in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, the masculine is sublime, the feminine is pathos (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 90: 10-11; E
247).</p>
        <figure n="bb435.1.3-2.com" id="bb435.1.comdes.03" work-copy="bb435.1" rend="db" width="739" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>P.1.<lb/>
	Drawn by W. Blake.<lb/>
	Etched by L. Schiavonetti.<lb/>
	Christ descending into the Grave.<lb/>
	Eternal King! whose potent Arm sustains<lb/>
	The Keys of Hell and Death.<lb/>
	London, Published May 1st. 1808, by Cadell &amp; Davies, Strand.</figTranscr>
          <head>10. “Christ descending into the Grave,” illustration for Blair’s <hi rend="i">The
Grave.</hi></head>
        </figure>
        <p>I grant that in Blake’s New Jerusalem, male and female functions converge harmoniously in total
mutual fulfillment, for in Eden “Embraces are Cominglings: from the Head even to the Feet” 
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 69:43; E 221). After all, the masculine artistic imagination needs the feminine manifested
art-product to complete the artistic process; the prophet needs historical time and space to vindicate his
claim to true vision. But such mutual interdependence should not obscure the fact that, in Blake’s
metaphoric system, the masculine is both logically and physically prior to the feminine. The artist can have
ideas to which he does not give manifest artistic form; but no art form can exist without a prior creative
idea or impulse. Similarly, one can prophesy without history, but history cannot be understood (or some modern
historians would say, even exist) without an interpretative idea, structure or “explanation.”</p>
        <p>Moreover, Blake consistently refers to his perfected human being as a Man. And while we might agree
that Blake is here using Man in the generic sense, to refer to the species
<pb id="p16-154" n="154"/>
<figure n="BUT683.1.1r.PD" rend="file" width="778" height="1000">
	<head>11. Portrait of Catherine Blake, British Museum.</head>
</figure>
mankind and not exclusively to males, nonetheless he is subtly supporting a patriarchal attitude. Since
linguistic usage in many ways shapes our conscious experience, to refer to all human beings as Man or mankind
devalues woman.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> By continuing to use
the sexist language of the patriarchal culture into which he was born, Blake failed to develop an image of
human perfection that was completely genderfree. A writer who wished to portray a truly androgynous creature
or society would have to transform the language we use. Such radical revisions have occurred in literature:
Marge Piercy, in <hi rend="i">A Woman on the Edge of Time</hi>, uses the pronoun “per” to refer to all
persons, irrespective of sex-gender. And Ursula Le Guin develops detailed portraits of androgyny in her
science-fiction, both of biological androgynes (in <hi rend="i">The Left Hand of Darkness</hi>) and of
androgynous societies (on the planet of Anarres in <hi rend="i">The Dispossessed</hi>). 
<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> This point has been documented by Wendy Martyna in “What Does ‘He’ Mean? Use of the
Generic Masculine,” <hi rend="i">Journal of Communication</hi> 28 (Winter 1978) and in “Beyond the
‘He/Man’ Approach: The Case for Nonsexist Language,” <hi rend="i">Signs</hi> 5 (Spring 1980),
482-93.</note></p>
        <p>We should not condemn Blake for his failure to escape the linguistic prisons of gender-identified
metaphors inherent in the literary and religious culture in which he lived. But neither should we hail him as
an advocate of androgyny or sexual equality to whom contemporary feminists might look for guidance. Blake
certainly recognized the social injustice involved in treating women as property or slaves, as 
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> makes clear. But he did not transcend the prevailing
patriarchal assumption of his day concerning the appropriate function of the female. In Blake’s art, women
at their best are nurturing mothers. generous sensualists, compassionate lovers, all-welcoming and
never-critical emotional supporters.</p>
        <p>What little we know about Blake’s relationship with his wife Catherine (illus. 11) further
supports this view of Blake as an unconscious sexist. Blake married the illiterate Catherine Boucher because,
when he told her he had been jilted by Polly Wood and asked suddenly. “Do you pity me?”, she responded,
“Yes indeed I do.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> Blake later
came to identify pity with the feminine: in <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>, the “first female now
separate” is called “pity” (18:10, 19:1, E77). Blake shows us in the Tate Gallery color-prints that pity
can have both positive and negative dimensions. The compassionate loyalty of Ruth is there contrasted to the
divisive pity portrayed as death in the print “Pity” and further explained in <hi rend="i">The Book of
Urizen</hi> as co-optation by the enemy, “For pity divides the soul” (13:52; E 76). Pity in this sense is
what Virginia Woolf later called in <hi rend="i">The Three Three Guineas</hi> a “commitment to unreal
loyalties,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> a sympathy for the
oppressors because “after all, they’re human too.” The identification of women with pity, as Susan
Griffin has emphasized in <hi rend="i">Women and Nature</hi>, is a typical metaphor in a patriarchal culture.
“It is said,” Griffin writes, referring to Rousseau’s <hi rend="i">Second Discourse</hi>, “that pity
is the offspring of weakness and that women and animals, being weaker, feel more pity.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> In this context, Darwin’s insistence that
women are more tender and less selfish than men<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">14</ref> becomes a subtle form of male dominance, because it encourages women to heed the needs of
others over the needs of their own selves. <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Frederick Tatham, “Life of
Blake” (c. 1832), cited in G.E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press,
1969), p. 517.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Virginia Woolf, <hi rend="i">Three Guineas</hi> (New York: Harcourt,
Brace, 1978; Harbinger, 1963), p. 78.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Susan Griffin, <hi rend="i">Woman and Nature: The Roaring Inside Her</hi>
(New York: Harper, 1980), p. 30.</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> See Darwin, <hi rend="i">Descent</hi>, as cited by Eva Figges, 
<hi rend="i">Patriarchal Attitudes</hi> (New York: Fawcett, 1970), p. 112.</note></p>
        <p>As far as I can tell, Catherine Blake played the traditional role of the subservient wife in a
patriarchal marriage. She was the student (Blake taught her to read and write and paint); she was Blake’s
unpaid domestic servant—as William Hayley reported, “they have no servant:—the good woman not only does
the work of the House, but she even makes the greatest part of her husband’s dress &amp; assists him in 
<hi rend="i">his art</hi> . . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref>
Above all, she worshipped her husband’s genius. As Crabb Robinson commented, “She was formed on the
Miltonic model—And like the first Wife Eve worshipped God in her Husband—he being to Her what God was to
him.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> However apocryphal, the
following anecdote suggests the degree to which Catherine Blake set her husband on a pedestal above ordinary
mortals. When the Blakes were living in their small, “squalid and untidy” rooms at Fountain Court,
Catherine once excused “the general lack of soap and water” by explaining to George Richmond, 
“<hi rend="i">You see, Mr. Blake’s skin don’t dirt.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n17" type="note">17</ref> A woman who could say that of a man—and a painter!—with whom she had
lived for forty years could not have lived in an egalitarian marriage nor experienced psychological androgyny.
And if Catherine did not regard herself as Blake’s equal, it is not surprising that in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> women—or the female state of mind—do not receive parity with the male. Having had
no emotional
<pb id="p16-155" n="155"/>
experience of sexual equality, Blake was not able to portray such a gender-free androgynous ideal in his
poetry and art, where male characters and mental functions both outnumber and take precedence over female
figures and functions. <note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p.
106.</note>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Henry Crabb Robinson, <hi rend="i">Reminiscences</hi>, 1852; reprinted in
Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 543.</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Mona Wilson, <hi rend="i">The Life of William Blake</hi>, ed. Geoffrey
Keynes (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1971), p. 331n; cf. Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 294;
“squalid and untidy” is Crabb Robinson’s phrase.</note></p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
