<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.3.ackland</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The Embattled Sexes: Blake’s Debt to Wollstonecraft in The Four Zoas</title>
        <author n="Ackland">Michael Ackland</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1982/1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982-83</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Barbara Guth</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Michael Ackland</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982/1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
      <pb id="p16-172" n="172"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-3-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="main">The Embattled Sexes: Blake’s Debt to Wollstonecraft in <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi></title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">MICHAEL</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">ACKLAND</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>Our knowledge of Blake’s acquaintance with the writings of Mary Wollstonecraft is at once precise
and frustratingly incomplete. We know he illustrated, and presumably also read, her novel 
<hi rend="i">Original Stories from Real Life.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61"
type="note">1</ref> We also have evidence in his earlier works, notably in <hi rend="i">Visions of the
Daughters of Albion</hi>, that he was influenced by the doctrines she expressed in <hi rend="i">Vindication of
the Rights of Men</hi> (1790) and <hi rend="i">Vindication of the Rights of Woman</hi> (1792).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62" type="note">2</ref> Moreover, both writers were frequent visitors
at the bookseller and publisher Joseph Johnson in the early 1790s; and would, at the very least, have been
known to each through word of mouth. But here the incidents of explicit contact cease.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63" type="note">3</ref> On 8 December 1792 Wollstonecraft left for France, where she
was to witness the progress of revolution at first hand. Blake’s domicile remained England, and there is
nothing to indicate that they met after her return to London in 1795. Yet Wollstonecraft’s ideas would
continue to act as a catalyst in his protracted exploration of embattled sexuality, long after all personal
ties between them had been severed. <note id="n61"><hi rend="s">1</hi> He also illustrated her translation of
Salzmann’s <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality.</hi> For the details see David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake:
Prophet against Empire</hi>, rev. ed. (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1969), p. 156; Jacob Bronowski, 
<hi rend="i">William Blake and the Age of Revolution</hi> (1965; rpt. London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1972),
p. 150; and Dennis M. Welch, “Blake’s Response to Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Original
Stories</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake: An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 13 (1979), 4-15.</note>
	<note id="n62"><hi rend="s">2</hi> These parallels are noted by Mark Schorer, <hi rend="i">William Blake: The
Politics of Vision</hi> (1946; rpt. New York: Knopf, 1959), pp. 187 and 251; and Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake:
Prophet against Empire</hi>, p. 243.</note>
	<note id="n63"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Commentators, however, have offered a range of conflicting, speculative
readings in an attempt to enlarge this meagre fund of biographical information. In “Notes on the 
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> by William Blake,” <hi rend="i">Modern Language
Quarterly</hi> 9 (1948), 292-97, for instance, Henry H. Wasser argues that <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> is, on
one level, “an expression of Blake’s knowledge of the love affair between Mary Wollstonecraft and Henry
Fuseli” (p. 292). But Kathleen Raine, in <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi> (London: Routledge &amp;
Kegan Paul, 1969), I, 166-68, proposes that elements of the work may reflect a passionate attachment between
Blake and Wollstonecraft, while Morton D. Paley claims that “the story of Oothoon and Bromion reflects that
of Mary Wollstonecraft and her American lover Gilbert Imlay, with at least a possibility that Blake cast
himself as Theotormon” (<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> [Oxford: Phaidon, 1978], p. 27).</note></p>
        <p>The possibility of her continued influence on Blake’s work, however, has been partially obscured
by the illuminated books printed between 1793 and 1795. In these, the emphasis is primarily sociopolitical;
and personae often seem more suited to illuminating the larger historical forces at work in the poet’s time
than the intricate relationship of the sexes.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64"
type="note">4</ref> In particular, the female figure becomes the subject of vast and frequently negative
metaphorical expansion, as in <hi rend="i">Europe a Prophecy.</hi> There Enitharmon and her daughters can
variously represent the all-consuming Female Will, the vegetative world, and the benighted social, moral and
religious constructs of man’s fallen consciousness. Hence discussions of Blake’s debt to Wollstonecraft
tend to focus exclusively on <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, where the basic situation,
despite its wider sociohistorical implications, is that of a lovers’ triangle; and where the heroine Oothoon
offers, in word and deed, a Blakean version of major dilemmas articulated in <hi rend="i">Vindication of the
Rights of Woman.</hi> But, as I hope to demonstrate, Blake’s debt to Wollstonecraft’s 
<hi rend="i">Vindication</hi> does not cease there. Instead, his complex treatment of women in the ensuing Lambeth
books is closely related to Oothoon’s views, and with them to Wollstonecraft’s conception of female
potential. Moreover, these ideas are further developed in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, where many crucial
conceptual links between the works of Blake and Wollstonecraft testify to the enduring impact on him of her
impassioned call for harmony, equality and true friendship between the sexes. 
<note id="n64"><hi rend="s">4</hi> There are obviously exceptions to these broad generalizations. <hi rend="i">The Book of
Urizen</hi>, for instance, presents a cosmic myth, and the Los-Enitharmon-Orc triad portrays recognizable
human archetypes, although the overwhelming preoccupation of the Lambeth books is with the revolutionary
forces manifested in Blake’s time. For the historical background informing these works see 
<hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet against Empire</hi>, pp. 201-79; Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Energy and the
Imagination: A Study of the Development of Blake’s Thought</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1970), pp. 61-88;
and Michael J. Tolley, “<hi rend="i">Europe</hi>: ‘to those ychain’d in sleep,’ ” in 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman and John E. Grant (Princeton: Princeton
Univ. Press, 1970), pp. 115-45.</note></p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> offers evidence not only of Blake’s debt to
Wollstonecraft but, more importantly, of his capacity to assimilate her ideas into his evolving cosmology. As
commentators have noted, Oothoon’s description of the negative and positive roles open to her sex seems to
draw heavily on the <hi rend="i">Vindication.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65"
type="note">5</ref> In essence, her speeches contrast the prevailing feminine mode of “hypocrite modesty,”
which transforms love into a possession and the sexes into ravening beasts, with the female’s potential to
redeem herself and her surroundings through freely given love:
<q>
Open to joy and to delight where ever beauty appears<lb/>
If in the morning sun I find it: there my eyes are fix’d<lb/>
In happy copulation; if in the evening mild, wearied with work;<lb/>
Sit on a bank and draw the pleasures of this free born joy.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">VDA</hi> 6:22-23, 7:1-2, E49/K194)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66"
type="note">6</ref></q>
But while <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Vindication</hi> are remarkably similar in their
critique of debilitating sexual roles, a clear distinction needs to be made between their characterizations of
liberated woman. Wollstonecraft’s ideal woman approximates, not Oothoon, but the chaste and disciplined Jane
Eyre, whom Charlotte Bronte presents as the equal and devoted companion of her husband. In the 
<hi rend="i">Vindication</hi> monogamy is commended; and the way to emancipation is sought in equal access to
education, rather than in what, to Urizenic eyes, must seem Oothoon’s advocacy of universal promiscuity.
<note id="n65"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Other issues, of course, inform her speeches, most notably the contemporary
debate on slavery. For the details see David V. Erdman, “Blake’s Vision of Slavery,” 
<hi rend="i">Journal of the Warburg and Courtauld Institutes</hi> 15 (1952), 242-52, or <hi rend="i">Blake:
Prophet against Empire</hi>, pp. 226-42.</note>
	<note id="n66"><hi rend="s">6</hi> All references to Blake are from E: <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of
William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman, 4th printing, rev. (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1970), and K: 
<hi rend="i">The Complete Writings of William Blake</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes, 3rd printing, rev. (Oxford: Oxford
Univ. Press, 1971), using the following abbreviations: <hi rend="i">VDA: Visions of the Daughters of Albion;
L: The Book of Los; E: Europe a Prophecy; A: The Book of Ahania; FZ: The Four Zoas.</hi></note></p>
        <p>These conservative views, which tend to separate and repress basic human needs, are ruthlessly
exposed in <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi> There education is inherently
sexual,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">7</ref> and one measure of devoted
and unselfish companionship is willing complicity in the total sexual freedom of one’s partner:
<q>
But silken nets and traps of adamant will Oothoon spread,<lb/>
And catch for thee girls of mild silver, or of furious gold;<lb/>
I’ll lie beside thee on a bank &amp; view their wanton play<lb/>
<pb id="p16-173" n="173"/>
<figure n="vda.a.p5-6" id="vda.a.illbk.05" work-copy="vda.a" rend="db" width="750" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>3<lb/>
	And none but Bromion can hear my lamentations.<lb/>
	With what sense is it that the chicken shuns the ravenous hawk?<lb/>
	With what sense does the tame pigeon measure out the expanse?<lb/>
	With what sense does the bee form cells? have not the mouse &amp; frog<lb/>
	Eyes and ears and sense of touch? yet are their habitations.<lb/>
	And their pursuits, as different as their forms and as their joys;<lb/>
	Ask the wild ass why he refuses burdens: and the meek camel<lb/>
	Why he loves man: is it because of eye ear mouth or skin<lb/>
	Or breathing nostrils? No, for these the wolf and tyger have.<lb/>
	Ask the blind worm the secrets of the grave, and why her spires<lb/>
	Love to curl round the bones of death! and ask the rav’nous snake<lb/>
	Where she gets poison: &amp; the wing’d eagle why he loves the sun<lb/>
	And then tell me the thoughts of man, that have been hid of old.<lb/>
	Silent I hover all the night, and all day could be silent,<lb/>
	If Theotormon once would turn his loved eyes upon me;<lb/>
	How can I be defild when I reflect thy image pure?<lb/>
	Sweetest the fruit that the worm feeds on. &amp; the soul prey’d on by woe<lb/>
	The new wash’d lamb ting’d with the village smoke &amp; the bright swan<lb/>
	By the red earth of our immortal river; I bathe my wings,<lb/>
	And I am white and pure to hover round Theotormons breast.<lb/>
	Then Theotormon broke his silence. and he answered.<lb/>
	Tell me what is the night or day to one o’erflowd with woe?<lb/>
	Tell me what is a thought? &amp; of what substance is it made?<lb/>
	Tell me what is a joy? &amp; in what gardens do joys grow?<lb/>
	And in what rivers swim the sorrows? and upon what mountains</figTranscr>
	<head>1. <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, copy A, pl. 3.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
</figure>
In lovely copulation bliss on bliss with Theotormon:<lb/>
Red as the rosy morning, lustful as the first born beam,<lb/>
Oothoon shall view his dear delight, nor e’er with jealous cloud<lb/>
Come in the heavens of generous love; nor selfish blightings bring.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">VDA</hi> 7:23-29, E49/K194-95)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68"
type="note">8</ref></q>
In the <hi rend="i">Vindication</hi>, Wollstonecraft’s apparent neglect of woman’s sexuality is, of
course, in part a reaction against the enforced role of the female as a mere instrument for man’s sensual
gratification.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69" type="note">9</ref> She thus attacks
passionate, physical love as a force which must, and can be, mastered early in a relationship: “a master and
mistress of a family ought not to continue to love each other with passion. . . . they ought not to indulge
those emotions which disturb the order of society, and engross the thoughts that should be otherwise
employed.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70" type="note">10</ref> According to her,
“love, perhaps, the most evanescent of all passions, gives place to jealousy or vanity” (p. 27); and its
unreasonable deification is seen as a major cause of woman’s, and more generally mankind’s, wretched lot.
Blake, characteristically, was able to acknowledge and transcend the partial truth embodied in this view. In
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> perversions do indeed result from such a limited notion
of love, but libidinal energy is also presented
<figure n="vda.a.p6-7" id="vda.a.illbk.06" work-copy="vda.a" rend="db" width="727" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>Wave shadows of discontent? and in what houses dwell the wretched<lb/>
	Drunken with woe forgotten. and shut up from cold despair,<lb/>
	Tell me where dwell the thoughts forgotten till thou call them forth<lb/>
	Tell me where dwell the joys of old? &amp; where the ancient loves?<lb/>
	And when will they renew again &amp; the night of oblivion past?<lb/>
	That I might traverse times &amp; spaces far remote and bring<lb/>
	Comforts into a present sorrow and a night of pain<lb/>
	Where goest thou O thought! to what remote land is thy flight?<lb/>
	If thou returnest to the present moment of affliction<lb/>
	Wilt thou bring comforts on thy wings, and dews and honey and balm;<lb/>
	Or poison from the desart wilds, from the eyes of the envier.<lb/>
	Then Bromion said; and shook the cavern with his lamentation<lb/>
	Thou knowest that the ancient trees seen by thine eyes have fruit;<lb/>
	But knowest thou that trees and fruits flourish upon the earth<lb/>
	To gratify senses unknown? trees beasts and birds unknown:<lb/>
	Unknown, not unpercievd, spread in the infinite microscope,<lb/>
	In places yet unvisited by the voyager. and in worlds<lb/>
	Over another kind of seas. and in atmospheres unknown.<lb/>
	Ah! are there other wars, beside the wars of sword and fire!<lb/>
	And are there other sorrows, beside the sorrows of poverty?<lb/>
	And are there other joys, beside the joys of riches and ease?<lb/>
	And is there not one law for both the lion and the ox?<lb/>
	And is there not eternal fire, and eternal chains?<lb/>
	To bind the phantoms of existence from eternal life?<lb/>
	Then Oothoon waited silent all the day, and all the night,</figTranscr>
	<head>2. <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, copy A, pl. 4.</head>
</figure>
as a potentially regenerative force working within a rationally constrained world. Blake’s Oothoon may be
bound and tortured, but her naked body is nonetheless pictured in sensual and aspiring positions on plates
three and four. <note id="n67"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Or as Paley says of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi>, “Blake envisions, not revolution <hi rend="i">and</hi> sexual freedom, but a revolution which is
libidinal in nature” (<hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination</hi>, p. 16).</note>
	<note id="n68"><hi rend="s">8</hi> In their immediate context, the lines refer only to plural partners for
the male, but Oothoon’s earlier comments on the crippling effects of enforced monogamy seem to project an
ideal of equal freedom for both the male and the female. Similarly, Blake’s contemporary comments in the
Notebook repeatedly recognize the equal and complementary needs of the sexes, as in the following lines, where
the emphatic parallelism negates any possibility of sexist distinctions:
<q>
What is it men in women do require<lb/>
The lineaments of Gratified Desire<lb/>
What is it women do in men require<lb/>
The lineaments of Gratified Desire<lb/>
(E466/K180)
</q>
Failure to recognize this larger context, however, can almost transform the healthy Oothoon into a sexual
deviant, as when Leopold Damrosch, Jr., speaks confidently of her “fantasies, with their sadomasochism and
voyeurism” in <hi rend="i">Symbol and Truth in Blake’s Myth</hi> (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1980),
p. 198.
                    </note>
	<note id="n69"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Alternatively, given the unusual degree of sexual liberation she was to
enjoy in her own life, this omission may reflect a conscious concession to her audience, made in the hope of
winning approval for other radical and, in some senses, more important aspects of her program for female
emancipation.</note>
	<note id="n70"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Mary Wollstonecraft, <hi rend="i">A Vindication of the Rights of Woman:
With Strictures on Political and Moral Subjects</hi>, ed. Carol H. Poston (New York: Norton, 1975), pp. 30-31.
Future page references to this edition will be cited parenthetically.</note></p>
        <p>Throughout the Lambeth period, Blake’s appraisal of female capabilities remains constant,
although their presentation varies according to the scope and aim of the specific work. In 
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> the influence of Wollstonecraft is most apparent, because
this work, like her own <hi rend="i">Vindication of the Rights of Woman</hi>, focuses on the perverted
relationships generated by restrictive social conditioning. The ensuing Lambeth books, however, are more
concerned with developing a coherent cosmology and with exploring the negative effects of mankind’s fall.
Consequently, the identification of woman with the memory or latent promise of visionary renewal is
subordinate to her projection as an active participant in the “torments of love and
<pb id="p16-174" n="174"/>
<figure n="BB209.1.9.MS" rend="file" width="792" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>5<lb/>
							<lb/>
							{7}<lb/>
							<lb/>
							{embracd for}<lb/>
							{love}<lb/>
							<lb/>
							And then they wanderd far away she sought for them in vain<lb/>
							In weeping blindness stumbling she followd them oer rocks &amp; mountains<lb/>
							Rehumanizing from the Spectre in pangs of maternal love<lb/>
							Ingrate they wanderd scorning her drawing her {life; ingrate} Spectrous Life<lb/>
							Repelling her away &amp; away by a dread repulsive power     100<lb/>
							Into Non Entity revolving round in dark despair.<lb/>
							{Till they had drawn the Spectre quite away from Enion}<lb/>
							And drawing in the Spectrous life in pride and haughty joy<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Thus Enion gave them all her spectrous life {in dark despair}<lb/>
							Then {Ona} Eno a daughter of Beulah took a Moment of Time<lb/>
							And drew it out to {twenty years} Seven thousand years with much care &amp; affliction<lb/>
							And many tears &amp; in the {twenty} Every years {gave visions toward heaven} made windows into<lb/>
Eden<lb/>
							She also took an atom of space &amp; opend its center<lb/>
							Into Infinitude &amp; ornamented it with wondrous art<lb/>
							Astonishd sat her Sisters of Beulah to see her soft affections<lb/>
							To Enion &amp; her children &amp; they ponderd these things wondring<lb/>
							And they Alternate kept watch over the Youthful terrors<lb/>
							They saw not yet the Hand Divine for it was not yet reveald<lb/>
							But they went on in Silent Hope &amp; Feminine repose<lb/>
							<lb/>
							But Los &amp; Enitharmon delighted in the Moony spaces of {Ona} Eno<lb/>
							Nine Times they livd among the forests, feeding on sweet fruits<lb/>
							And nine bright Spaces wanderd weaving mazes of delight<lb/>
							Snaring the wild Goats for their milk they eat the flesh of Lambs<lb/>
							A male &amp; female naked &amp; ruddy as the pride of summer<lb/>
							<lb/>
							p. 8<lb/>
							Ellis<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Alternate Love &amp; Hate his breast; hers Scorn &amp; Jealousy<lb/>
							{They kissd not for shame they embracd not}<lb/>
							In embryon passions. they kiss’d not nor embrac’d for shame &amp; fear     150<lb/>
							{Nor kissd nor em[braced]}<lb/>
							{hand in hand in a Sultry paradise}<lb/>
							{these Lovers swum the deep}<lb/>
							His head beamd light &amp; in his vigorous voice was prophecy<lb/>
							He could controll the times &amp; seasons, &amp; the days &amp; years<lb/>
							She could controll the spaces, regions, desart, flood &amp; forest<lb/>
							<lb/>
							But had no power to weave a Veil of covering for her Sins<lb/>
							She drave the Females all away from Los<lb/>
							And Los drave all the Males from her away<lb/>
							<lb/>
							They wanderd long, till they sat down upon the margind sea.<lb/>
							Conversing with the visions of Beulah in dark slumberous bliss<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Night the Second<lb/>
							<lb/>
							{Nine years they view the turning spheres {of Beulah} reading the Visions of Beulah}<lb/>
							But the two youthful wonders wanderd in the world of Tharmas<lb/>
							Thy name is Enitharmon; said the {bright} fierce prophetic boy<lb/>
							{While they} {Harmony}<lb/>
							While thy mild voice fills all these Caverns with sweet harmony<lb/>
							O how {thy} our Parents sit &amp; {weep} mourn in their silent secret bowers</figTranscr>
	<head>3. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 9.</head>
</figure>
<figure n="BB209.1.26.MS" rend="file" width="792" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>6th page<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Vala incircle round the furnaces where Luvah was clos’d<lb/>
							In joy she heard his howlings, &amp; forgot he was her Luvah<lb/>
							With whom she walkd in bliss, in times of innocence &amp; youth<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Hear ye the voice of Luvah from the furnaces of Urizen<lb/>
							<lb/>
							20<lb/>
							Ellis<lb/>
							<lb/>
							If I indeed am {Luvahs Lord} Valas King &amp; ye O sons of Men<lb/>
							The workmanship of Luvahs hands; in times of Everlasting<lb/>
							When I calld forth the Earth-worm from the cold &amp; dark obscure<lb/>
							I nurturd her I fed her with my rains &amp; dews, she grew<lb/>
							A scaled Serpent, yet I fed her tho’ she hated me<lb/>
							Day after day she fed upon the mountains in Luvahs sight        50<lb/>
							I brought her thro’ the Wilderness, a dry &amp; thirsty land<lb/>
							And I commanded springs to rise for her in the black desart<lb/>
							{But} Till she became a {de[mon]} Dragon winged bright &amp; poisonous<lb/>
							I opend all the floodgates of the heavens to quench her thirst<lb/>
							<lb/>
							And<lb/>
							<lb/>
							BRITISH<lb/>
							MUSEUM</figTranscr>
	<head>4. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 26.</head>
</figure>
jealousy.” In these works, she is associated overwhelmingly with dominion and selfish love or, more
alarmingly, with the fall into generative division;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71"
type="note">11</ref> and so with the last stage in that benighted state of consciousness which separates man
from his original unity and divinity.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72"
type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n71"><hi rend="s">11</hi> This is as true of <hi rend="i">America a Prophecy</hi> as it is of other
works of the period, like <hi rend="i">Europe a Prophecy</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.</hi> For as
Minna Doskow has demonstrated in “William Blake’s <hi rend="i">America</hi>: The Story of a Revolution
Betrayed,” <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> 8 (1979), 167-86, the shadowy female of the preludium acts the
part of “the obedient daughter of a tyrannical father” (p. 171). She is used as an instrument to enslave
the dangerous energies of Orc; and when this strategy fails her long training ensures that the love she
returns the fiery youth is selfish and possessive, and that revolutionary potential is thereby severely
limited.</note>
	<note id="n72"><hi rend="s">12</hi> In fact, the negative impression left by these works has been so strong
that Susan Fox has felt compelled to argue against the received view of Oothoon. According to her reading,
Blake’s choice of a woman as the main protagonist in <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> reflects, not even a
relenting in his view of womankind, but rather his need for a figure who could be symbolically raped and
readily enslaved (“The Female as Metaphor in William Blake’s Poetry,” <hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry</hi>
3 [1977], 513). A more persuasive and illuminating commentary on this issue, however, is provided by Irene
Taylor, “The Woman Scaly,” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of the Midwest Modern Language Association</hi> 6 (1973),
rpt. in Mary Lynn Johnson and John E. Grant, eds., <hi rend="i">Blake’s Poetry and Designs</hi> (New York:
Norton, 1979), pp. 539-53. There we are invited to see Blake’s critical treatment of womankind as
“reflecting a view prominent in Western mythologies” (p. 542), rather than a personal animus.</note></p>
        <p>Counterpointing these harsh associations, however, is the awareness that woman, no less than man,
can maintain “the Divine Vision in time of trouble.” In <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>, for instance,
Blake foreshadows the regenerative role of Enion in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, when he attributes to
“Eno aged Mother” the opening lament, which juxtaposes the world of Experience with “Times remote! /
When Love &amp; Joy were adoration” (<hi rend="i">L</hi> 3:7-8, E89/K256). Even in <hi rend="i">Europe a
Prophecy</hi>, the predatory Enitharmon, at the height of her power, is forced to acknowledge the existence of
an antithetical code of female behavior:
<q>
I hear the soft Oothoon in Enitharmons tents:<lb/>
Why wilt thou give up womans secrecy my melancholy child?<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">E</hi> 14:21-22, E64/K244)
</q>
But the most striking evidence for the continuity of Blake’s conception of the female is provided by 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania.</hi> Printed two years after <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> and probably little more
than a year before he began work on <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n73" type="note">13</ref> it portrays man as jealous and vengeful in the figures of Fuzon and Urizen;
whereas Oothoon-like woman is made the advocate of genuine love and forgiveness. The frontispiece presents
Ahania cowering and surrounded by a squatting male figure. Her rather phallic posture, between his spread
legs, suggests both her birth from Urizen’s shattered loins and her relegation to a limited sexual role by
the male. Yet although perverted man will call her Sin and establish her as a fetish for secret worship, the
title-page illustration of solitary, flying Ahania implies the presence of a distinctive personage beyond the
bounds of restricting, Urizenic perception.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74"
type="note">14</ref> This promise she fulfills in her concluding lament over the fallen Urizen, which recalls
Oothoon’s memories of fulfilling love and anticipates a similar plaint by Ahania in Night the Third of 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>:
<q>
Then thou with thy lap full of seed<lb/>
With thy hand full of generous fire<lb/>
Walked forth from the clouds of morning<lb/>
On the virgins of springing joy,<lb/>
On the human soul to cast<lb/>
The seed of eternal science.<lb/>
. . . . . .<lb/>
<lb/>
But now alone over rocks, mountains<lb/>
Cast out from thy lovely bosom:<lb/>
Cruel jealousy! selfish fear!<lb/>
<pb id="p16-175" n="175"/>
Self-destroying: how can delight,<lb/>
Renew in these chains of darkness<lb/>
Where bones of beasts are strown<lb/>
On the bleak and snowy mountains<lb/>
Where bones from the birth are buried<lb/>
Before they see the light.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">A</hi> 5:29-34, 39-47, E88-89/K255)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75"
type="note">15</ref></q>
In the works printed between <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> and <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, then, Blake divided among
separate personae elements of the Wollstonecraftian vision first attributed to Oothoon. This enabled a more
flexible and clearly differentiated treatment of female potential, well suited to his wider examination of
myth, history, and psychological motivation. The division also prepared the way for that dialectical interplay
between positive and negative forces which, in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, is a prelude to apocalypse.
<note id="n73"><hi rend="s">13</hi> The most comprehensive and informed discussions of putative composition
dates and textual details are to be found in William Blake, <hi rend="i">Vala or The Four Zoas: A Facsimile of
the Poem and A Study of Its Growth and Significance</hi>, ed. G. E. Bentley, Jr. (Oxford: Clarendon Press,
1963); David V. Erdman, “The Binding (et cetera) of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>,” <hi rend="i">The Library</hi>
29 (1969), 112-29; <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, pp. 737-39; and in 
<hi rend="i">Blake: An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 12 (Fall 1978), an issue devoted to <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas.</hi></note>
	<note id="n74"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Despite her somewhat ambiguous gestures and posture, I assume that she is
flying because, as David V. Erdman notes, the depiction of her hair “indicates swift flight” 
(<hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> [London: Oxford Univ. Press, 1975], p. 211).</note>
	<note id="n75"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Her concluding words also echo lines eleven to fifteen of “Earth’s
Answer,”
						<q>
                                Selfish father of men<lb/>
                                Cruel jealous selfish fear<lb/>
                                Can delight<lb/>
                                Chain’d in night<lb/>
                                The virgins of youth and morning bear,
                            </q>
                            and thereby link her with the life-and love-giving attributes of the female Earth.
For a full discussion of these implications, and of Blake’s association of the female figure with
apocalyptic renewal in “The Little Girl Lost” and “The Little Girl Found,” see my essay “Blake’s
Problematic Touchstones to Experience: ‘Introduction,’ ‘Earth’s Answer,’ and the Lyca Poems,” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 19 (1980) 3-17.
                    </note></p>
        <p>By the time Blake began <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, Wollstonecraft’s ideas had thus been thoroughly
absorbed into his developing cosmology. Consequently, the full and lasting extent of her influence shows
itself not in direct echoes or explicit allusions, but in broad and significant areas of conceptual agreement,
such as the close resemblance of Blake’s characterization of the delusive emanation to the portrayal of
woman’s severely circumscribed state in the <hi rend="i">Vindication.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76" type="note">16</ref> Wollstonecraft, positing that woman has the same rational
potential as man, claims that she receives a limiting education in accordance with the subordinate role
attributed to her in a male-dominated world. She is taught to be pleasant and alluring; her single goal is to
attract, capture, and then retain a male because, given her lack of any wider education, she is inevitably
dependent on males for her sustenance. As a result women are encouraged, either implicitly or explicitly, to
be charming, vain, proud, jealous, indolent and, above all, cunning: “that pitiful cunning which
disgracefully characterizes the female mind—and I fear will ever characterize it whilst women remain the
slaves of power!” (p. 164). Their social and physical weakness leaves them no option but to use their few
native weapons, such as beauty, tears and smiles, to overcome their legal oppressors. The result is an
undeclared but constant battle between the sexes for command, or as Wollstonecraft explains: “It is this
separate interest—this insidious state of warfare, that undermines morality, and divides mankind!” (p.
97). Similarly in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, as in earlier works, Blake uses the interaction of the
sexes to demonstrate both the fallen, divided state of the original Divine Humanity, and the resulting
distortion of all moral principles. Furthermore, his emanations correspond almost point by point with
Wollstonecraft’s image of perverted
          <figure n="BB209.1.37.MS" rend="file" width="778" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>{1}<lb/>
							19<lb/>
							{18}<lb/>
							<lb/>
							VALA<lb/>
							Night the {Fourth} Third<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Now sat the King of Light on high upon his starry throne<lb/>
							And bright Ahania bow’d herself before his splendid feet<lb/>
							<lb/>
							O Urizen look on Me. {thy Wife, that} like a mournful stream<lb/>
							I Embrace{s} round thy knees &amp; wet{s her} My bright hair with {her} my tears:<lb/>
							Why sighs my Lord! are not the morning stars thy obedient Sons<lb/>
							Do they not bow their bright heads at thy voice? at thy command<lb/>
							Do they not fly into their stations &amp; return their light to thee<lb/>
							The immortal Atmospheres are thine, there thou art seen in glory<lb/>
							Surrounded by the ever changing Daughters of the Light<lb/>
							{Thou sitst in harmony for God hath set thee over all}<lb/>
							Why wilt thou look upon futurity darkning present joy<lb/>
							She ceas’d the Prince his light obscurd &amp; the splendors of his crown<lb/>
							<lb/>
							Infolded</figTranscr>
	<head>5. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 37.</head>
</figure>
<figure n="BB209.1.44.MS" rend="file" width="782" height="1000">
	<head>6. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 44.</head>
</figure>
<pb id="p16-176" n="176"/>
womanhood. They too are portrayed as cunning, alluring, unproductive, and involved in an ongoing struggle for
and against domination, as in the following passage:
<q>
Thus sang the Lovely one in Rapturous delusive trance<lb/>
Los heard reviving he siezd her in his arms delusive hopes<lb/>
Kindling She led him into Shadows &amp; thence fled outstretchd<lb/>
Upon the immense like a bright rainbow weeping &amp; smiling &amp; fading<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 34:93-96, E318/K290)
</q>
And both writers are equally forthright in condemning those who provide instruction in these female arts.
Wollstonecraft for instance, in a chapter entitled “Animadversions on Some of the Writers Who Have Rendered
Women Objects of Pity, Bordering on Contempt,” pillories books that advise the alternate use of chastity and
coquetry,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77" type="note">17</ref> much as Blake
disapprovingly quotes Enitharmon’s advice on ways to manipulate parents:
<q>
To make us happy let them weary their immortal powers<lb/>
While we draw in their sweet delights while we return them scorn<lb/>
On scorn to feed our discontent; for if we grateful prove<lb/>
They will withhold sweet love, whose food is thorns &amp; bitter roots.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 10:3-6, E301/K271)
</q>
Although addressed to Los, this speech provides a succinct recipe for female domination, as it is practiced by
Vala and Enitharmon herself.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78" type="note">18</ref> Yet the
immediate context of her remarks reminds us that these feminine wiles are not restricted to the emanations
alone. Instead, they operate in the fallen world wherever “selfish loves increase”: a point underscored by
the accompanying design on page 9 of exhausted Enion, hopelessly pursuing her taunting, ungrateful children.
<note id="n76"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Some of these female traits had, of course, appeared in earlier works,
such as <hi rend="i">Europe a Prophecy.</hi> But it is not until <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> that they
receive detailed treatment; and only then does their close association with Wollstonecraft’s conceptions
clearly emerge.</note>
	<note id="n77"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Wollstonecraft attacks, for example, the following passage cited from
Rousseau: “ ‘Would you have your husband constantly at your feet? keep him at some distance from your
person. You will long maintain the authority in love, if you know but how to render your favours rare and
valuable. It is thus you may employ even the arts of coquetry in the service of virtue, and those of love in
that of reason.’ ” (p. 89).</note>
	<note id="n78"><hi rend="s">18</hi> For a fuller account of this, and of other scenes mentioned briefly in
this paper, consult Brian Wilkie and Mary Lynn Johnson, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Four Zoas: The Design of a
Dream</hi> (Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard Univ. Press, 1978).</note></p>
        <p>Common also to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and to the <hi rend="i">Vindication</hi> is their
critique of conventional notions of love as a form of self-idolatry, and as a means by which woman obtains
excessive sway. Like Blake, Wollstonecraft argues that man mistakes the shadow for the substance (p. 135), the
ephemeral for the true goals of life: “I see the sons and daughters of men pursuing shadows, and anxiously
wasting their powers to feed passions which have no adequate object” (p. 110). This erroneous condition is,
for both, exemplified by love: “And love! What diverting scenes would it produce—Pantaloon’s tricks must
yield to more egregious folly. To see a mortal adorn an object with imaginary charms, and then fall down and
worship the idol which he had himself set up—how ridiculous!” (p. 111). According to Wollstonecraft,
man’s cherished image of the female emanates from his own fallen consciousness. He then seeks to impose his
projections on women through education (“Why must the female mind be tainted by coquetish arts to gratify
the sensualist . . .?” [p. 31]), and finally falls “prostrate before their personal charms” (p. 92). The
course of fallen love is similarly self-fulfilling in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, although here the
critique of idol-worship encompasses perverted passion in its sexual and religious manifestations. Hence
Albion succumbs to Vala and, even more abjectly, to his own projected divinity:
<q>
Then Man ascended mourning into the splendors of his palace<lb/>
Above him rose a Shadow from his wearied intellect<lb/>
Of living gold, pure, perfect, holy; in white linen pure he hover’d<lb/>
A sweet entrancing self delusion, a watry vision of Man<lb/>
Soft exulting in existence all the Man absorbing<lb/>
<lb/>
Man fell upon his face prostrate before the watry shadow<lb/>
Saying O Lord whence is this change thou knowest I am nothing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n79" type="note">19</ref><lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 40:2-8, E320/K293) <note id="n79"><hi rend="s">19</hi> A parallel image of man’s
idolatry to his female self-projection emerges from the combined accounts of the Spectre of Urthona and the
Shadow of Enitharmon in Night the Seventh (a):
<q>
Listen O vision of Delight One dread morn of goary blood<lb/>
The manhood was divided for the gentle passions making way<lb/>
Thro the infinite labyrinths of the heart &amp; thro the nostrils issuing<lb/>
In odorous stupefaction stood before the Eyes of Man<lb/>
A female bright. . . .<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 84:12-16, E352/K327)<lb/>
Among the Flowers of Beulah walkd the Eternal Man &amp; Saw<lb/>
Vala the lilly of the desart. melting in high noon<lb/>
Upon her bosom in sweet bliss he fainted Wonder siezd<lb/>
All heaven they saw him dark. . . .<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 83:7-10, E351/K326)
</q></note></q>
That the <hi rend="i">Vindication</hi> fails to draw this parallel between debased love and worship is perhaps
another reflection of Wollstonecraft’s conservatism. But it does not impede her radical vision of passion as
an insidious form of self-gratification that leads the sexes further away from an ideal of mutually enhancing
unity; and that produces a situation in which women, as Wollstonecraft contends, “indirectly . . . obtain
too much power, and are debased by their exertions to obtain illicit sway” (p. 167).</p>
        <p>Similarly Blake, throughout <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, stresses the elements of narcissism
and tyranny latent in sexual love. Ahania, for instance, in text and design, is shown in acts of abasement at
the feet of the tyrant Urizen; while the interrelationship of sexual and religious idolatry is demonstrated
with brutal frankness on page 44 by a sketch in which the female genitalia are pictured literally as an altar
for secret worship.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80" type="note">20</ref> But where
Wollstonecraft offers only a fragmentary account of the harmful ascendency of debased sexuality, Blake reveals
it behind all humanity’s successive falls. Thus Ahania argues that man’s original error was the result of
his being “Idolatrous to his own Shadow” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 40:12, E321/K293), and the spectre of
Urthona describes his own fall in terms of a division confirmed through self-copulation:
<q>
My loins begin to break forth into veiny pipes &amp; writhe<lb/>
Before me in the wind englobing trembling with strong vibrations<lb/>
The bloody mass began to animate. I bending over<lb/>
Wept bitter tears incessant. Still beholding how the piteous form<lb/>
Dividing &amp; dividing from my loins a weak &amp; piteous<lb/>
Soft cloud of snow a female pale &amp; weak I soft embracd<lb/>
My counter part &amp; calld it Love I named her Enitharmon.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 50:11-17, E327/K300)
</q>
Fallen love is associated here with an emanation projected from and designated by the male, while the
expression “My counter part” emphasizes her dual function as a constituent of Urthona and as an inherent
property which will hinder a return to his unfallen state. Moreover Wollstonecraft only asserts that these
narcissistic relationships are mutually debilitating, whereas Blake continually demonstrates it, as in Night
the Third. The opening design on page 37 shows
<pb id="p16-177" n="177"/>
Ahania playing the part of a submissive slave, while Urizen’s posture and countenance express
revulsion.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81" type="note">21</ref> The implications of this
scene are articulated later, when Urizen chastizes Ahania for the perfect obedience which he himself demanded,
because he perceives his loathsome self-image in the undistorting mirror she affords:
<q>
Thou little diminutive portion that darst be a counterpart<lb/>
They passivity thy laws of obedience &amp; insincerity<lb/>
Are my abhorrence. Wherefore hast thou taken that fair form<lb/>
Whence is this power given to thee! once thou wast in my breast<lb/>
A sluggish current of dim waters. on whose verdant margin<lb/>
A cavern shaggd with horrid shades. dark cool &amp; deadly. where<lb/>
I laid my head in the hot noon after the broken clods<lb/>
Had wearied me. there I laid my plow &amp; there my horses fed<lb/>
And thou hast risen with thy moist locks into a watry image<lb/>
Reflecting all my indolence my weakness &amp; my death<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 43:9-18, E322/K295)
</q>
By trying to become more than man he too has become less or diminutive. Her “laws” are those he
promulgates and, with the confusion typical of fallen reason, the former image of her that he lovingly invokes
has the characteristics for which he now curses her. Furthermore, because these attributes are, as he
recognizes, dominant in himself, any attempt to reject them in her can precipitate his own fall. So Blake,
with fine dramatic irony, makes Urizen the judge and destroyer of his own realm. For at this stage the tyrant
has only glimmerings of what will become redemptive self-consciousness in Night the Ninth, much as his
precipitation to lower depths ironically foreshadows the lesson of self-abnegation he has yet to learn before
true regeneration can begin. Here undeniably, as in other scenes, Blake’s attack on “selfish loves” is
more specific and coherent than Wollstonecraft’s. But his basic views certainly accord with the details of
her discussion, and with her summary conclusion that man must “willingly resign the privileges of rank and
sex for the privileges of humanity” (p. 149). <note id="n80"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Interestingly, Blake and
Wollstonecraft diverge in their views on the effects of solitary withdrawal and reflection. According to
Wollstonecraft, both are necessary if women are to develop independent thought and genuine feeling, or as she
puts it: “Besides, by living more with each other, and being seldom absolutely alone, they [women] are more
under the influence of sentiments than passions. Solitude and reflection are necessary to give to wishes the
force of passions, and to enable the imagination to enlarge the object, and make it the most desirable” (p.
58). In Blake, such acts are often associated with Urizenic withdrawal from humanity, or with negative
self-enjoyings, like those lamented by Oothoon:
<q>
The moment of desire! the moment of desire! The virgin<lb/>
That pines for man; shall awaken her womb to enormous joys<lb/>
In the secret shadows of her chamber, the youth shut up from<lb/>
The lustful joy. shall forget to generate. &amp; create an amorous image<lb/>
In the shadows of his curtains and in the folds of his silent pillow.<lb/>
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
Is it because acts are not lovely, that thou seekest solitude.<lb/>
Where the horrible darkness is impressed with reflections of desire.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">VDA</hi> 7:3-7, 10-11, E49/K194)
</q></note>
	<note id="n81"><hi rend="s">21</hi> The heavily drawn claw on his foot is eloquent testimony both to
Urizen’s status as tyrant and to <corr type="emend">its bestializing</corr> effects: a theme repeated in other Blake designs, such as
those of Nebuchadnezzar.</note></p>
        <p>Even more important, Blake and Wollstonecraft concur in their analysis of the wider implications of
these fallen passions. Apart from transforming what should be “sports of Glory” into those of Cruelty,
this debased concept of love destroys the possibility of a healthy parental bond, and is ultimately linked
with deleterious social manifestations. In her brief chapter “Parental Affection,” Wollstonecraft remarks
that the parent-child bond is often “a pretext to tyrannize where it can be done with impunity” (pp.
150-51). As such, it becomes, “perhaps, the blindest modification of perverse self-love” (p. 150), and can
serve as a
          <figure n="BB209.1.72.MS" rend="file" width="780" height="1000">
            <head>7. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 72.</head>
          </figure>
          <figure n="BB209.1.86.MS" rend="file" width="783" height="1000">
            <head>8. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 86.</head>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p16-178" n="178"/>
          <figure n="BB209.1.112.MS" rend="file" width="772" height="1000">
            <head>9. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 112.</head>
          </figure>
          <figure n="ahania.a.p1" id="ahania.a.illbk.01" work-copy="ahania.a" rend="db" width="731" height="1000">
	<figTranscr/>
            <head>10. <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, copy A, pl. i.</head>
            <figDesc>Courtesy of the Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <figure n="ahania.a.p2" id="ahania.a.illbk.02" work-copy="ahania.a" rend="db" width="735" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>THE<lb/>
	BOOK of<lb/>
	AHANIA<lb/>
	LAMBETH<lb/>
	Printed by W Blake 1795</figTranscr>
            <head>11. <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, copy A, pl. 1.</head>
          </figure>
model for all other forms of oppression: “Power, in fact, is ever true to its vital principle, for in every
shape it would reign without controul or inquiry. . . . Obedience, unconditional obedience, is the catch-word
of tyrants of every description, and to render ‘assurance doubly sure,’ one kind of despotism supports
another” (p. 150). No less than Blake, Wollstonecraft is aware that the bondage of parenthood and marriage
parallels and supports a constricting social structure which promotes priestcraft, war and mystery.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82" type="note">22</ref> Slavish obedience to parents is, she tells
us, preparation “for the slavery of marriage” (p. 155); and both institutions, founded on their victims’
“weakness and ignorance,” are protected by “mysterious sanctity” (p. 153). Yet if unselfish love can
once prevail, not only may parents and children find natural ground for “mutual sympathy,” but the parents
will be drawn together “when . . . mutual confidence takes place of overstrained admiration—a child then
gently twists the relaxing cord, and a mutual care produces a new mutual sympathy”
<pb id="p16-179" n="179"/>
(p. 152). Without this abandonment of egotistical constraint, however, man remains essentially separate and
disconsolate, like the three exhausted women pictured under a leafless, barren tree of Experience, on page 72
of Night the Sixth. <note id="n82"><hi rend="s">22</hi> In “Of the Pernicious Effects which Arise from the
Unnatural Distinctions Established in Society,” a chapter which closely parallels Blake’s analysis of
fallen England, Wollstonecraft describes the world as “a den of sharpers or oppressors” (p. 140), in which
“a true north-east blast . . . blights the tender blossoms of affection and virtue,” and the “silken
wings” of innocent womanhood are “shrivelled up” (p. 141). British politics is dubbed “the present
system of war” (p. 145), and is seen to consist “in multiplying dependents and contriving taxes which
grind the poor to pamper the rich” (p. 143), while humanity, and in particular woman, is enchained “like
the poor African slaves” (p. 144).</note></p>
        <p>In <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Blake projects similar insights through the actions of Los and
Enitharmon, who appear first as children and then as parents. In their role as parents, they illustrate the
perverse self-love and tyrannical drive for unconditional obedience that Wollstonecraft castigates. But
Blake’s analysis demonstrates more clearly than the <hi rend="i">Vindication</hi>’s that these egotistical
acts recoil harmfully upon their instigators. Los, although he attempts to render “assurance doubly sure”
by binding Orc with the chain of jealousy, is himself a victim of the same chain.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83" type="note">23</ref> It constricts his vital humanity, and even the removal of
its physical presence is no guarantee of complete liberation:
<q>
But when returnd to Golgonooza Los &amp; Enitharmon<lb/>
Felt all the sorrow Parents feel. they wept toward one another<lb/>
And Los repented that he had chaind Orc upon the mountain<lb/>
And Enitharmons tears prevaild parental love returnd<lb/>
Tho terrible his dread of that infernal chain . . .<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 62:9-13, E335/K309)
</q>
Blake is here contrasting the first glimmerings of genuine, self-sacrificing parental feeling with their
destructive opposite: “Love of Parent Storgous Appetite Craving” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 61:10, E334/K308).
The dilemma faced by parents and child is <corr type="emend">analogous</corr> to that confronting fallen man
and woman. They are doomed to feed selfishly on each other, as do Los and Enitharmon on their mother Enion in
Night the First,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84" type="note">24</ref> or to live in
mutual fear and antagonism, until suffering awakens their repressed sense of human sympathy. In a realm where
hatred is dominant instead of love, “stern demands of Right &amp; Duty instead of Liberty” 
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 4: 18-19, E297/K265), the chain of jealousy is justifiably described as “living” and
taking root in the earth’s center (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 63: 1-4, E336/K308). Los feels its pull. He
“dreads” these forces at work within himself and throughout fallen nature. Furthermore, like Enion
“Rehumanizing . . . in pangs of maternal love” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 9:3, E300/K276), he must learn
repentance and that parental “sorrow” which involves recognizing consanguinity with and responsibility for
a world external to the self-centered “I.” This shift is already hinted at in the above passage when
“they wept toward one another” and in a design on page 112, which apparently portrays Los attempting to
assuage Enitharmon’s maternal bereavement.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n85"
type="note">25</ref> The binding of Orc occasions then, in Wollstonecraft’s words, “a mutual care [which]
produces a new mutual sympathy”; and this, in the full context of Blake’s epic, marks a first step towards
that greater self-annihilation which will be demanded of the scattered Zoas, if they are to regain the lost
unity of Eternity. <note id="n83"><hi rend="s">23</hi> Diana Hume George in <hi rend="i">Blake and Freud</hi>
(Ithaca: Cornell Univ. Press, 1980) offers a detailed account of Blake’s exploration of this reciprocal
bondage, and of its psychological roots, in a subsection of her study entitled “Experience: The Family
Romance” (pp. 98-124).</note>
	<note id="n84"><hi rend="s">24</hi><q>
Drawing forth drooping mothers pity drooping mothers sorrow<lb/>
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
And then they wanderd far away she sought for them in vain<lb/>
In weeping blindness stumbling she followd them oer rocks &amp; mountains<lb/>
Rehumanizing from the Spectre in pangs of maternal love<lb/>
Ingrate they wanderd scorning her drawing her Spectrous Life<lb/>
Repelling her away &amp; away by a dread repulsive power<lb/>
Into Non Entity revolving round in dark despair.<lb/>
And drawing in the Spectrous life in pride and haughty joy<lb/>
Thus Enion gave them all her spectrous life<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 8:7, 9:1-8, E300/K269-70)
</q></note>
	<note id="n85"><hi rend="s">25</hi> W.H. Stevenson in <hi rend="i">The Poems of William Blake</hi> (London:
Longman, 1971), p. 428, makes this identification, although Bentley suggests that the leaf on which the
drawing occurs originally concluded Night the Fourth (<hi rend="i">Vala or The Four Zoas</hi>, p. 201). In
this case the design would illustrate Enitharmon’s response to the binding of Urizen in Night the Fourth.
Yet the depiction of Los as at once resolute and tender is closer to the visual description of Los in Night
the Fifth than to that in Night the Fourth where
<q>
Spasms siezd his muscular fibres writhing to &amp; fro his pallid lips<lb/>
Unwilling movd as Urizen howld his loins wavd like the sea<lb/>
At Enitharmons shriek his knees each other smote &amp; then he lookd<lb/>
With stony Eyes on Urizen &amp; then swift writhd his neck<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 55:24-27, E331/K305)
</q>
By transposing the design to page 112 of Night the Eighth, Blake made possible, and even desirable,
Stevenson’s reading. For a visual reference back to events in Night the Fifth is appropriate here, as it
reminds us of the starting-point of Los and Enitharmon’s regeneration, which leads to their redemptive
labors described on page 113 of Night the Eighth.
                    </note></p>
        <p>Although the events in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> take place on a cosmological scale far
removed from the diurnal world described in the <hi rend="i">Vindication</hi>, the redemptive role that Blake
attributes to the emanation also appears to owe much to Wollstonecraft’s vision of liberated female
potential. Her constant emphasis is on the need to emancipate woman from a constricting sexual role: to have
her recognized as an intellectual and, in the widest sense, a human creature. As she explains, the female
“was not created merely to be the solace of man, and the sexual should not destroy the human character”
(p. 53). Accordingly, she stresses that “true beauty and grace must arise from the play of the mind” (p.
118). Woman should be taught not to control others but herself (p. 62), to turn her “sensibility into the
broad channel of humanity” (pp. 174-75); and so “to participate in the inherent rights of mankind” (p.
175). For in Wollstonecraft’s own words, “the corrupting intercourse . . . between the sexes, is more
universally injurious to morality than all the other vices of mankind collectively considered” (p. 192).
Thus “mutual affection, supported by mutual respect,” must replace “selfish gratification” (p. 192);
modesty becomes a “natural reflection of purity” rather than “only the artful veil of wantonness” (p.
193); and compassion be extended “to every living creature (p. 172). Our choice is between “a REVOLUTION
in female manners,” which will have “the most salutary effects tending to improve mankind” (p. 192), and
a condition that encourages woman “by the serpentine wrigglings of cunning . . . [to] mount the tree of
knowledge, and only acquire sufficient to lead men astray” (p. 173).</p>
        <p>The final Nights of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> dramatize the potential inherent in these
alternate conceptions of woman. In Nights the Seventh and Eighth, Blake portrays the spiritual nadir of man,
and takes as his central symbol of this enslavement the Tree of Mystery. Around and through this Tree his
personae move in an elaborate series of actions which explicitly allude to Milton’s portrayal of the fall,
and to the ensuing transformation of Satan and his hellish legions into serpents. But while 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> is here the main source, it is possible that some of Blake’s rich reworkings of
Milton’s motifs were inspired by Wollstonecraft’s comparison of fallen woman’s striving after
fulfillment with a serpentine ascent into the Tree of Knowledge. In Night the Seventh, womankind in its lowest
and most abstract state (the Shadow of Enitharmon) is pictured as descending “down the tree of Mystery”
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 82:16, E350/K327) to lead astray the spectrous form of Urthona. Following their sexual
union, they are found “Conferring times on times among the branches of that Tree” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi>
85:4, E353/K327). In Night the Eighth, this same constellation of images is iterated almost obsessively on
manuscript pages 101 and 103, as Vala exerts her sway:
<q>
Beginning at the tree of Mystery circling its root<lb/>
She spread herself thro all the branches in the power of Orc.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 103:23-24, E361/K345)
</q>
For Blake, this repeated motif presents woman at her most dangerous and debased. In Wollstonecraft’s words,
“the sexual” has been allowed to “destroy the human character.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86" type="note">26</ref> Similarly, in drawings on pages 86 and 26, Vala is portrayed
both as a sensuous, fecund figure, and as a hideous, hybrid dragon-form. The former captures her alluring
presence,
<pb id="p16-180" n="180"/>
the latter constitutes a visionary judgment on her role in entrapping man in the toils of corporeality. Yet
whether pictured as a gazer fixated on external existence or as an embodiment of pestilential evil, woman and
her generative acts can be seen by Blake as potential images or means of regeneration.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n87" type="note">27</ref> Her realm is nature, and nature remains part of the Divine
Humanity. Hence even the triumph of Vala can serve paradoxically as a prelude to apocalypse, for any
consolidation of error makes it more readily identifiable and remediable. Moreover, this dual character of
female action, its potential for good and evil, is made explicit through the respective weaving of Enitharmon
and Rahab-Tirzah:
<q>
Enitharmon wove in tears Singing Songs of Lamentations<lb/>
And pitying comfort as she sighd forth on the wind the spectres<lb/>
And wove them bodies calling them her belovd sons &amp; daughters<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 103:32-34, E361/K345)<lb/>
While Rahab &amp; Tirzah far different mantles prepare webs of torture<lb/>
Mantles of despair girdles of bitter compunction shoes of indolence<lb/>
Veils of ignorance covering from head to feet with a cold web.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 113:19-21, E362/K346)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n88"
type="note">28</ref></q>
Here woman is no longer presented as a single and negative aspect of man. Instead she is used in these Nights
to embody our complex capacity for creative and uncreative labor, for regeneration or self-damnation; and so
she becomes at last the male’s true counterpart in the mental wars of Eternity, as well as in the cruel
sports of the fallen realm. <note id="n86"><hi rend="s">26</hi> My comments here are complemented by Jean H.
Hagstrum’s section on “the phallic woman” in “Babylon Revisited, or the Story of Luvah and Vala,” in
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory: Essays on The Four Zoas Milton Jerusalem</hi>, ed. Stuart Curran and
Joseph Wittreich, Jr. (Madison: Wisconsin Univ. Press, 1973), pp. 108-12, and by John E. Grant’s account of
the motif of “erotic degradation,” which appears in Blake’s designs to the poem, in “Visions in 
<hi rend="i">Vala</hi>: A Consideration of Some Pictures in the Manuscript,” in <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime
Allegory</hi>, pp. 141-202.</note>
	<note id="n87"><hi rend="s">27</hi> The theme is a common one in the later prophecies. Book one of 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, for instance, concludes with a great hymn on the spiritual wonders of vegetative life,
and Los sums up this vision on plate 7 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> with the exclamation: “O holy
Generation [Image] of regeneration!.” (E149/K626).</note>
	<note id="n88"><hi rend="s">28</hi> The complex significance of this weaving motif is dealt with by Morton D.
Paley in “The Figure of the Garment in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Milton</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,” in <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory</hi>, pp. 119-39.</note></p>
        <p>In accordance with this expanded conception of woman, emanations assume the role of moral agents
which Wollstonecraft had foreseen for her sex (p. 178). In Night the Second, for instance, Enion utters from
the Void one of Blake’s greatest condemnatory songs of Experience; and her words suffuse with concern a
fellow emanation, Ahania, who “never from that moment could . . . rest upon her pillow” 
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 36:19, E319/K291). A succession of suffering spokeswomen is thereby assured, and woman is
singled out as a focal point of genuine moral vision. Hence Blake, at the end of Night the Eighth, employs
chants by Ahania and Enion, rather than one by Los, to prepare the reader for the ensuing Vintage of the
Nations. First Ahania, who “Saw not as yet the Divine vision her Eyes are Toward Urizen” 
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 108:7, E368/K353), catalogues the intricate mazes of Experience:
<q>
Will you seek pleasure from the festering wound or marry for a Wife<lb/>
The ancient Leprosy that the King &amp; Priest may still feast on your decay<lb/>
And the grave mock &amp; laugh at the plowd field saying<lb/>
I am the nourisher thou the destroyer in my bosom is milk &amp; wine<lb/>
And a fountain from my breasts to me come all multitudes<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 108:13-17,E369/K354)
</q>
Here woman and earth assume metaphoric equivalence as referents for that vegetative existence which both
nourishes and kills. But in the following chant of Enion, from beyond the limitations of fallen perception,
the female earth is subsumed in the Eternal Man:
<q>
So Man looks out in tree &amp; herb &amp; fish &amp; bird &amp; beast<lb/>
Collecting up the scatterd portions of his immortal body<lb/>
Into the Elemental forms of every thing that grows<lb/>
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
And in the cries of birth &amp; in the groans of death his voice<lb/>
Is heard throughout the Universe whereever a grass grows<lb/>
Or a leaf buds The Eternal Man is seen is heard is felt.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 110:6-8, 25-27, E370/K355-56)
</q>
As in the <hi rend="i">Vindication</hi>, so here lasting harmony is inseparable from the realization of
compassion for all things, and from the merging of secondary distinctions in the redemptive vision of a single
and indissoluble humanity. This vision becomes reality in Night the Ninth. But instead of Wollstonecraft’s
notion of a bloodless revolution having “the most salutary effects tending to improve mankind,” Blake
offers a picture of fierce and, at times, anguished transformation. Mankind is literally threshed and crushed
free from fallen selfhood. Here the virtues of purity, modesty, and disinterested compassion, espoused by
Wollstonecraft, are largely relegated to a “lower Paradise” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 128:30, E382/K369),
where the instinctual passions have to relearn their innocence under the guidance of a morally regenerated
Vala.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n89" type="note">29</ref> By implication, Blake suggests
that these traditional virtues exist in their pure forms only “in Eternal Childhood,” and he is careful to
stress that the protagonists are merely “the shadows of Tharmas &amp; of Enion in Valas world” 
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 131:19, E385/K371). A clear distinction is thus made between the redemptive role of the
female and the role of her conventional attributes. These attributes, at best, are elements in a limited
pastoral interlude; while the truly emancipated female plays a more active and vitally engaged role in the
ongoing spiritual harvest. Characteristically, Blake’s enlarged concept of human potential allows him to
appropriate, and then to develop, progressive ideas from the <hi rend="i">Vindication</hi>; although here, as
in his other reworkings of Wollstonecraft, he shows himself capable of transcending the received assumptions
that are also embodied in her work.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n90" type="note">30</ref>
	<note id="n89"><hi rend="s">29</hi> For a more complete account of this scene see <hi rend="i">Blake’s Four
Zoas: The Design of a Dream</hi>, pp. 223-28.</note>
	<note id="n90"><hi rend="s">30</hi> Blake’s capacity to select only what he needed from Wollstonecraft, and
at the same time to criticize her conservative viewpoints, is well illustrated by Dennis M. Welch in
“Blake’s Response to Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Original Stories.</hi>”</note></p>
        <p>Thus Blake not only found inspiration in Wollstonecraft’s work, but he also succeeded in freeing
her perceptions from many of their contemporary limitations. For <hi rend="i">Vindication of the Rights of
Woman</hi>, despite its revolutionary fervor, remains partly ensnared by conventional notions of morality,
education, and human capacity. Here man, at his noblest, is pictured as a rational creature; literature as
peculiarly suited to increase the scope of his reason; and social stability as a necessity for fruitful human
intercourse.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n91" type="note">31</ref> But Blake, ignoring
this conservatism, focused on the work’s incisive analysis of the conditions generated by debased sexuality,
and on its concrete suggestions for their
<pb id="p16-181" n="181"/>
amelioration. These notions he had thoroughly assimilated by 1793 at the latest, with the publication of 
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>; and they were then expanded and emended in accordance with
the cosmological vision developed in the Lambeth books. For the liberating views expounded in the 
<hi rend="i">Vindication</hi> required a new conception of art, language and human creativity commensurate with
their radical potential. This Blake provided in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, where woman becomes the
fallen emanation, self-realization the prelude to apocalypse, mutual affection and forgiveness the Gates of
Paradise. There at last Wollstonecraft’s precepts attain the fulfillment denied them in her work and in her
tragically brief life; and there also they are saved from the usual fate of truth in this world, which she
pictures as “lost in a mist of words, virtue, in forms” (p. 12), by an art form created specifically
“for the day of Intellectual Battle” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 3:3, E297/K264). 
<note id="n91"><hi rend="s">31</hi> Wollstonecraft, of course, was not alone in her failure to transcend many of the reactionary
values of her age. Even her husband, the anarchist philosopher William Godwin, was capable of attacking all
the institutions of society, and yet of defending the need for material security, in his <hi rend="i">Enquiry
Concerning Political Justice.</hi></note></p>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p16-182-183" n="182-183" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
