<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.3.ostriker</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Desire Gratified and Ungratified: William Blake and Sexuality</title>
        <author n="Ostriker">Alicia Ostriker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1982/1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1982-83</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Barbara Guth</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Michael Ackland</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1982/1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
      <pb id="p16-156" n="156"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">Desire Gratified and Ungratified: William Blake and Sexuality</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">ALICIA</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">OSTRIKER</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>To examine Blake on sexuality is to deal with a many-layered thing. Although we like to suppose
that everything in the canon “not only belongs in a unified scheme but is in accord with a permanent
structure of ideas,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">1</ref> some of
Blake’s ideas clearly change during the course of his career, and some others may constitute internal
inconsistencies powerfully at work in, and not resolved by, the poet and his poetry. What I will sketch here
is four sets of Blakean attitudes toward sexual experience and gender relations, each of them coherent and
persuasive if not ultimately “systematic;” for convenience, and in emulation of the poet’s own method of
personifying ideas and feelings, I will call them four Blakes. First, the Blake who celebrates sexuality and
attacks repression, whom we may associate with Freud and even more with Reich. Second, a corollary Blake whom
we may associate with Jung, whose idea of the emanation—the feminine element within man—parallels Jung’s
concept of the anima, and who depicts sexual life as a complex web of gender complementarities and
interdependencies. Third, a Blake apparently inconsistent with Blake number one, who sees sexuality as a
tender trap rather than a force of liberation. Fourth, and corollary to that, the Blake to whom it was
necessary, as it was to his patriarchal precursor Milton, to see the female principle as subordinate to the
male. <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Northrop Frye, <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi> (Princeton:
Princeton Univ. Press, 1947), p. 14.</note></p>
        <p>Blake number one is perhaps the most familiar to the common reader, although professional Blakeans
have paid little attention to him lately. He is the vigorous, self-confident, exuberant advocate of gratified
desire, writing in his early and middle thirties (that is, between the fall of the Bastille and the execution
of Louis and the declaration of war between England and France) the early <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> poems,
the <hi rend="i">Songs, The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
Albion.</hi> A few texts will refresh the memory. Among the <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> epigrams we are told
that
<q>
Love to faults is always blind<lb/>
Always is to joy inclind<lb/>
Lawless wingd and unconfind<lb/>
And breaks all chains from every mind (E 463)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
type="note">2</ref><lb/>
<lb/>
Abstinence sows sand all over<lb/>
The ruddy limbs &amp; flaming hair<lb/>
But Desire Gratified<lb/>
Plants fruits of life &amp; beauty there (E 465)<lb/>
<lb/>
What is it men in women do require?<lb/>
The lineaments of Gratified Desire<lb/>
What is it Women do in men require?<lb/>
The lineaments of Gratified Desire (E 466) <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Quotations are from David V.
Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi> (New York: Doubleday,
1970).</note></q></p>
        <p>It was probably these lines that converted me to Blake when I was twenty. They seemed obviously
true, splendidly symmetrical, charmingly cheeky—and nothing else I had read approached them, although I
thought Yeats must have picked up a brave tone or two here. Only later did I notice that the epigrams were
tiny manifestoes announcing an identity of interest between sexuality and the human imagination.</p>
        <p>During these years Blake wrote numerous minidramas illustrating how possessiveness and jealousy,
prudery and hypocrisy poison the lives of lovers. He pities the chaste (“The Sunflower”) and depicts the
pathos of chastity relinquished too late (“The Angel”), looks forward to a “future Age” when “Love!
sweet Love!” will no longer be thought a crime, while protesting its repression by Church and State in his
own time. One of his two major statements about sexual repression in <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> is
the deceptively simple “The Garden of Love,” in which the speaker discovers a Chapel built where he
“used to play on the green.” The garden has a long scriptural and literary ancestry. “A garden shut up,
a fountain sealed, is my sister, my bride,” in <hi rend="i">The Song of Solomon.</hi> It is the site of the
<hi rend="i">Roman de la Rose.</hi> It is where Dante meets Beatrice, it is Spenser’s garden of Adonis and
Milton’s Paradise—“In narrow room, Nature’s whole wealth.” The garden is, in brief, at once the
earthly paradise and the body of a woman. Probably Blake saw it so. Later he would draw the nude torso of a
woman with a cathedral where her genitals should be. The briars at the poem’s close half-suggest that the
speaker is being crowned with something like thorns, somewhere about the anatomy, and it anticipates Blake’s
outraged demand, near the close of his life, in the <hi rend="i">Everlasting Gospel</hi>: “Was Jesus chaste?
or did he / Give any lessons of chastity?” Since the design for “The Garden of Love” depicts a priest
and two children kneeling at an open grave beside a church, the forbidden love may be a parent as well as a
peer, and the speaker might be of either
<pb id="p16-157" n="157"/>
sex: all repression is one. It is important that the tone here is neither angry nor self-righteous, but
pathetic and passive—indeed, pathetically passive, for after the opening “I went,” the governing verb is
“saw.” That the speaker only “saw . . . my joys and desires” being bound with briars and did not
“feel” anything, should shock us into realizing that this speaker, at least by the poem’s last line, has
been effectively self-alienated. Repression has worked not merely from without, but from within.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">3</hi> I am disagreeing at this point with Morris Dickstein’s otherwise
excellent essay, “The Price of Experience: Blake’s Reading of Freud” in <hi rend="i">The Literary
Freud</hi>, ed. Joseph Smith (New Haven: Yale Univ. Press, 1980), pp. 67-111. Dickstein (pp. 95-96) sees
“The Garden of Love” as “angry polemical simplification,” arguing that the speaker “thinks of
repression in terms of a very simple etiology: <hi rend="i">They</hi> have done it to him,” and that there
is no question of “delusion or projection” here. A persuasive reading of the poem’s Oedipal dimension is
in Diana George, <hi rend="i">Blake and Freud</hi> (Ithaca: Cornell Univ. Press, 1980), pp.
104-106.</note></p>
        <p>The other major statement is “London,” where Blake hears the clanking of the mind-forg’d
manacles (chains such as “Love . . . breaks from every mind”) he will later associate with Urizen.
Economic exploitation sanctioned by blackening churches and political exploitation sanctioned by bleeding
palace walls are grievous, but “most” grievous is sexual exploitation, perhaps because it is a denial of
humanity’s greatest virtue, charity, as sweep’s cry and soldier’s sigh are denials of faith and hope; or
perhaps because, to Blake, sexual malaise precedes and produces all other ills:
<q>
But most thro’ midnight streets I hear<lb/>
How the youthful Harlots curse<lb/>
Blasts the newborn Infants tear<lb/>
And blights with plagues the Marriage hearse (E27)
</q>
That final stanza is Blake’s most condensed indictment of the gender arrangements in a society where Love is
ruled by Law and consequently dies; where virtuous females are pure, modest, and programmed for frigidity, so
that healthy males require whores; where whores have ample cause to curse; and where their curses have the
practical effect of infecting young families with venereal disease as well as with the more metaphoric plague
of unacknowledged guilt.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">4</ref> Through his
hissing, spitting and explosive alliteration Blake creates an ejaculatory harlot who is (and there are
analogues to her in Spenser, Shakespeare, Milton) not the garden but the snake. That a syntactic ambivalence
common in Blake makes her one who is cursed by others as well as one who curses, does not diminish the point.
<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">4</hi> For a harrowing account of the phenomenon of the youthful harlot in
nineteenth-century England, see Florence Rush, <hi rend="i">The Best-Kept Secret: Sexual Abuse of
Children</hi> (Englewood Cliffs, N.J.: Prentice-Hall, 1980), ch. 5.</note></p>
        <p>The point recurs polemically in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, where, according
to Auden, “the whole of Freud’s teachings may be found.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n22" type="note">5</ref> Here “Prisons are built with stones of Law, brothels with bricks of
Religion,” “Prudence is a rich ugly old maid courted by Incapacity,” and we are exhorted: “Sooner
murder an infant in its cradle than nurse unacted desires” (E 36-37). Here too is the famous pre-Freudian
précis of Freud’s theories on suppression: “Those who restrain desire, do so because theirs is weak
enough to be restrained; and the restrainer or reason usurps its place and governs the unwilling. And being
restrained it by degrees becomes passive till it is only the shadow of desire” (E 34). For Freud, this
process was always in some degree necessary and irreversible, as <hi rend="i">Civilization and its
Discontents</hi> and “Analysis Terminable and Interminable” ultimately confess. But Blake—and this is
what makes him more Reichian than Freudian—joyfully foresees the end of discontent and civilization too:
“For the cherub with his flaming brand is hereby commanded to leave his guard at tree of life, and when he
does, the whole creation will be consumed, and appear infinite. and holy where it now appears finite &amp;
corrupt. This will come to pass by an improvement of sensual enjoyment” (E 38).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">5</hi> W.H. Auden, “Psychoanalysis and Art To-day” (1935), in 
<hi rend="i">The English Auden</hi>, ed. Edward Mendelson (New York: Random House, 1977), p. 339.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Analysis of Freud’s rationalist and scientific pessimism, versus
Blake’s imaginative and artistic optimism, is a primary theme in <hi rend="i">Blake and Freud</hi>, which
argues that in other respects the two men’s diagnoses of western man’s psychosexual ills were close to
identical. Politically of course Freud remained conservative; the close parallels between Blake and Reich as
radical psycho-political thinkers are discussed in Eliot Katz, “Blake, Reich and <hi rend="i">Visions of the
Daughters of Albion</hi>,” unpub.</note></p>
        <p>In all such texts Blake is not only attacking the powers of repression, particularly institutional
religion, which in the name of reason and holiness attempt to subdue desire. He is also asserting that
gratified desire <hi rend="i">does</hi> what religion <hi rend="i">pretends</hi> to do: gives access to
vision, the discovery of the infinite. Moreover—and this is a point to which I will return—Blake in these
texts does not stress the distinction between male and female, or assign conspicuously different roles to the
two sexes. Youth and virgin suffer alike under chastity, man and woman have identical desires, and the
“ruddy limbs and flaming hair” of which an ardent imagination makes a garden, and an abstinent imagination
makes a desert, may belong interchangeably to a lover or a beloved, a male or a female.</p>
        <p>The poem in which Blake most extensively elaborates his celebration of love and his critique of
repression is <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, printed in 1793. <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>
is also the poem most clearly delineating male sexual aggressiveness as a component of Urizenic patriarchy,
and illustrating the kinds of damage it does to both males and females. First of all, Bromion is a number of
things which to Blake are one thing. He is the slaveowner who converts humans into private property and
confirms his possession by impregnating the females, the racist who rationalizes racism by insisting that the
subordinate race is sexually promiscuous, the rapist who honestly believes that his victim was asking for it;
and, withal, he does not actually experience “sensual enjoyment.” But if Bromion represents the social and
psychological pathology of sexual violence, Theotormon represents its pitiable underside, sexual impotence.
“Oerflowd with woe,” asking unanswerable questions, weeping incessantly, Theotormon does not respond to
Bromion’s insult to his masculinity (“Now thou maist marry Bromions harlot,” (pl. 2.1). Playing the
hesitant Hamlet to Bromion’s rough Claudius, intimidated slave to coarse slave-master, Theotormon has been
victimized by an ideology that glorifies male aggressiveness, as much as by that ideology’s requirement of
feminine purity. Dejected and self-flagellant (design, pl. 6), he cannot look Oothoon in her intellectual and
erotic eye as she maintains her spiritual virginity and offers him her love, not only because she is damaged
goods but because she is taking sexual initiative instead of being “modest.” Only with incredulity and
grief does Oothoon realize this (pl. 6.4-20).</p>
        <p>Most of <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> is Oothoon’s opera. Raped, enslaved, imprisoned, rejected, the
heroine’s agonized rhapsody of self-offering rushes from insight to insight. Though she begins by focusing
on her individual condition, her vision rapidly expands outward. She analyzes the enchainment of
<pb id="p16-158" n="158"/>
loveless marriage and the unhappy children it must produce, she praises the value of infant sexuality and
attacks the ethos which brands joy whoredom and sublimates its sexuality in twisted religiosity. She also
bewails other ramifications of the tyranny of reason over desire, such as the abuse of peasant by landlord, of
worker by factory owner, of the faithful by their churches. For Oothoon life means being “open to joy and to
delight where ever beauty appears,” and the perception of any beauty is an erotic activity in which eye and
object join “in happy copulation.” Made desperate by her lover’s unresponsiveness, she cries out for
“Love! Love! Love! happy happy Love! free as the mountain wind! / Can that be Love, that drinks another as a
sponge drinks water?” Though remaining herself “bound” to Bromion, she nevertheless concludes with a
vision of the vitality of all free things:
<q>
Arise you little glancing wings, and sing your infant joy!<lb/>
Arise and drink your bliss, for every thing that lives is holy!<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">VDA</hi> 8.9-10)
</q></p>
        <p>Blake in <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> has created a heroine unequalled in English poetry before or
since. Oothoon not only defines and defends her own sexuality rather than waiting for Prince Charming to
interrupt her nap, and not only attacks patriarchal ideology root and branch, but outflanks everyone in her
poem for intellectuality and spirituality, and is intellectual and spiritual precisely because she is erotic.
Shakespeare’s comic heroines, though witty and sexy, are of course not intellectuals, much less
revolutionaries. The Wife of Bath strongly resembles Oothoon as a voice of “experience, though noon
auctoritee” who “spekes of wo that is in marriage,” celebrates sexuality as such and female sexuality in
particular, and lectures to the Apollyon of Judeo-Christian misogyny from his own texts. Yet she lacks
Oothoon’s generosity, and has been locked by men’s contempt into a perpetuation of the war of the sexes.
(If, though, we amend the portrait of the Wife as she appears in the Prologue by that “imaginative
portion” of her which is her Tale, we have something different. Here perhaps is the Wife as she would
be—neither offensively-defensively bawdy, nor angrily polemical, but lively and charming—telling the
wish-fulfilling story of a rapist enlightened and reformed, of male violence, ignorance and pride transformed
by the “sovereyntee” of feminine wisdom and love.) Hawthorne’s Hester Prynne comes close to being what
Oothoon is, even to the point of foreseeing that “in Heaven’s own time, a new truth would . . . establish
the whole relation between man and woman on a surer ground of mutual happiness.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">7</ref> But Hawthorne cannot sustain or elaborate the vision he
glimpses, and sends Hester back in the end to her knitting, her works of charity, and a lifelong celibacy
which—unlike Oothoon’s—is supposed to be voluntary. <note id="n24"><hi rend="s">7</hi><hi rend="i"> The
Centenary Edition of the Works of Nathaniel Hawthorne</hi>, vol. 1 (Ohio State Univ. Press, 1962), p.
263.</note></p>
        <p>Blake number two appears later than Blake number one, and shifts his psychological principles from
an essentially sociopolitical to an essentially mythic base. Beginning with <hi rend="i">The Book of
Urizen</hi>, engraved in 1794, and throughout his major prophecies, the poet relies on an idea of humanity as
originally and ultimately androgynous, <corr type="emend">attributing</corr> the fall of man and what John
Milton called “all our woe” not to female narcissism but to specifically male pride, male competitiveness,
or male refusal to surrender the self, and depicting a fallen state in which sexual division—lapse of unity
between male and female as one being—is the prototype of every division within the self, between self and
other, and between humanity and God.</p>
        <p>The mythology of these poems posits a hero who is both Great Britain and all mankind, and who lives
in Eternity or Eden as one of a family of Eternals who collectively compose One Man, Christ. Albion’s
“Human Brain,” the equivalent of Jung’s collective unconscious, houses four energetic Jungian Zoas, each
of whom has a feminine counterpart or emanation. At Man’s Fall, precipitated in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> by
Urizen’s pride, in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> by rivalry between Urizen
and Luvah, and in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> by Albion’s selfish refusal to maintain erotic union with his
saviour and his insistence on moral virtue, Albion lapses into what Blake variously calls sleep, death and
disease, and what the rest of us call human history. The Zoas simultaneously lapse into lower forms and mutual
conflict instead of harmony, and are disastrously divided from their emanations. As the late Blake
formulaically puts it, “The Feminine separates from the Masculine &amp; both from Man.” Bodies grow around
them, inimical “To the embrace of love”:
<q>
that no more the Masculine mingles<lb/>
With the Feminine, but the Sublime is shut out from the Pathos<lb/>
In howling torment, to build stone walls of separation, compelling<lb/>
The Pathos, to weave curtains of hiding secresy from the torment.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 90.10-14)
</q>
At the close of his three longest poems Blake imagines an apocalypse in which selfhood is relinquished and
male and female are reunified:
<q>
And the Bow is a Male &amp; Female &amp; the Quiver of the Arrows of Love<lb/>
Are the Children of this Bow: a Bow of Mercy &amp; Loving-Kindness: laying<lb/>
Open the hidden Heart in Wars of mutual Benevolence Wars of Love<lb/>
And the Hand of Man grasps firm between the Male &amp; Female Loves.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 97.12-15)
</q></p>
        <p>To say that Blake’s emanations resemble what Jung calls the anima is to say that they represent a
man’s interior “female part,” the “life-giving aspect of the psyche” and the “a priori element in
his moods, reactions and impulses, and whatever else is spontaneous in psychic life.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">8</ref> As a positive figure the Blakean emanation
like the Jungian anima is a benevolent guide to the unconscious life. As a negative figure she is seductive
and destructive. She seems also to represent
<pb id="p16-159" n="159"/>
a man’s emotionality, sensuousness, sensitivity, receptivity—all that makes him potentially
effeminate—which in a fallen state he rejects or believes to be separate from himself, and must recover if
he is to gain psychic wholeness. According to Jung, of course, an individual man changes and develops during
the course of his lifetime but “his” anima does not. She remains static, and his only problem is to accept
her existence as a portion of himself. What is particularly fascinating about Blake, then, is that he invents
not one but a set of female beings, each appropriate to the Zoa she belongs to, each with her own personality
and history of transformations, not radically different from the personalities in highly symbolic fiction and
drama, and able to shed light very often on characters we thought we knew as well as on larger issues of
sexual complementarity. <note id="n25"><hi rend="s">8</hi> C.F. Jung, “Archetypes of the Collective
Unconscious,” <hi rend="i">Collected Works</hi>, ed. Herbert Read, Michael Fordham, Gerhard Adler and W.
McGuire, trans. R.F.C. Hull, Bollingen Series (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, Bollingen Series XX,
1967-78), vol. 9, part 1, p. 27. Jung also discusses the anima and the anima-animus “sacred marriage” in
“Two Essays on Analytical Psychology” (vol. 7) and “Aion: Researches into the Phenomenology of the
Self” (vol. 9, part 2). Among his less predictable parallels to Blake is Jung’s idea that the anima-animus
marriage is always accompanied and completed by the figure of a Wise Old Man—who I am ready to presume is
“Old” in the same sense that Albion is an “Ancient” Man; i.e., he is Urmensch, not elderly. Among the
critics who identify anima with emanation are June Singer, <hi rend="i">The Unholy Bible: A Psychological
Interpretation of William Blake</hi> (New York: Putnam, 1970), p. 212, and W.P. Witcutt, <hi rend="i">Blake: A
Psychological Study</hi> (Port Washington, N.Y.: Kennikat Press, 1946), pp. 43ff. Christine Gallant, in 
<hi rend="i">Blake and the Assimilation of Chaos</hi> (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1978) disagrees, arguing
that although “the anima in Jungian psychology is a personification in a symbol, or in an actual human
being, of those aspects of his unconscious of which a man is most ignorant, usually his emotional, irrational
qualities,” Blake’s emanations are not animae because “if they were . . . they would have
characteristics as differentiated as those of their Zoas” (pp. 53-54). It is my contention that they do.
Although Jung in general diverges from both Freud and Blake in uncoupling psychological issues from
socio-historic ones, he departs from Freud and coincides with Blake in at least three major respects: his
insistence on the validity of spirituality in human life, his belief in a collective unconscious, and his
relatively non-phallocentric exploration of female identity.</note></p>
        <p>The first figures we encounter in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, for example, are Tharmas and
Enion—humanity’s Sensation—in the midst of a marital quarrel. Tharmas and Enion are bucolic characters
of the sort that the wheels of history run over: good but not too bright, easily confused. We may recognize
their like in mythic pairs like Baucis and Philemon, Deucalion and Pyrrha, and the Wakefield Noah with his
farcically shrewish wife. Fictionally, and especially when a sentimental English novelist needs a pair of
innocent parent-figures, they are legion: they are Sterne’s Shandies, Goldsmith’s Vicar and Mrs.
Wakefield, and a troop of Dickensian folk like the Micawbers and Pockets, Casby (nicknamed “The
Patriarch”) and Flora, and perhaps most interestingly, the Gargeries of <hi rend="i">Great
Expectations.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">9</ref> Across the
Atlantic, they stumble through the fiction of writers like W.D. Howells and John Steinbeck. What Tharmas lacks
when he loses Enion is his own sense of coherence. Without her he is a frantic and suicidal “flood” of
feelings. What she lacks without him is resistance to pain. In her fallen form she becomes a grieving
Demeter-figure who laments the sufferings of all earthly creatures,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n27" type="note">10</ref> and Blake gives her some of his best lines:
<q>
Why does the Raven cry aloud and no eye pities her?<lb/>
Why fall the Sparrow &amp; the Robin in the foodless winter?<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> I. 17.2-3)<lb/>
It is an easy thing to triumph in the summers sun<lb/>
And in the vintage &amp; to sing on the waggon loaded with corn<lb/>
It is an easy thing to talk of patience to the afflicted<lb/>
To speak the laws of prudence to the houseless wanderer . . .<lb/>
It is an easy thing to laugh at wrathful elements<lb/>
To hear the dog howl at the wintry door, the ox in the slaughter house moan . . .<lb/>
While our olive &amp; vine sing &amp; laugh round our door &amp; our children bring fruit &amp; flowers<lb/>
Then the groan &amp; the dolor are quite forgotten &amp; the slave grinding at the mill<lb/>
And the captive in chains &amp; the poor in the prison &amp; the soldier in the field<lb/>
When the shattered bone hath laid him groaning among the happier dead.<lb/>
It is an easy thing to rejoice in the tents of prosperity<lb/>
Thus could I sing &amp; thus rejoice, but it is not so with me.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> II. 35.16-36.13)
</q>
Enion gives birth to Los and Enitharmon, the Eternal Prophet and his Muse, who from the start are as arrogant
and self-absorbed as their parents are humble and selfless. Enitharmon espouses parent-abuse:
<q>
To make us happy let them weary their immortal powers<lb/>
While we draw in their sweet delights while we return them scorn<lb/>
On scorn to feed our discontent; for if we grateful prove<lb/>
They will withhold sweet love, whose food is thorns &amp; bitter roots.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> I. 10.3-6)
</q>
Soon she turns these arts on her twin and consort, becoming a seductive and maddening tease. She is the muse
who won’t come across, taunting the poet with failure and giving her alliance to Reason (Neoclassicism, let
us say) instead of Prophecy, while forbidding the poet to love anyone but herself. As a couple, the Los and
Enitharmon who are united “in discontent and scorn” uncannily resemble the self-destructive, sullen,
jealous, incestuous or quasi-incestuous couples in novels like <hi rend="i">Wuthering Heights, Women in
Love</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Sound and the Fury</hi>: novels which in the light of Blake we can read as
visions of a primitive creative energy thwarted by the impossibility of creativity in a culturally collapsed
world they never made. Enitharmon is also La Belle Dame Sans Merci, she is Pip’s Estella, or Lady Brett, or
Marlene Dietrich in <hi rend="i">The Blue Angel</hi>; which is to say that she is the feminine agent of male
sexual humiliation, who is herself governed by <hi rend="i">ennui.</hi>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">9</hi> That Deucalion-Pyrrha and the Noahs are flood-survivors who renew the
human race, and that the fallen Tharmas-Enion are identified with water and Tharmas in Night III struggles to
take on Man’s form, is a coincidence I do not pretend to understand but feel obliged to notice. My 
<hi rend="i">primary</hi> point here is that these couples are all parental, and all naive. The relation of
Dickens’ Gargeries to Tharmas and Enion seems to me particularly charming in that Joe Gargery is rather a
perfect Tharmas throughout, but is given two wives by Dickens—as it were to parallel the quarrelsome and the
redeemed Enion.</note>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Gallant (p. 54) notes the Poseidon-Demeter/Tharmas-Enion parallel
(another coincidence) and points out that the questing Demeter disguised herself as an old woman.</note></p>
        <p>A third couple is Urizen and Ahania: Reason and the Faith or Idealism necessary to it. Early in 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Urizen as cosmic architect places Ahania in a zodiacal shrine and burns incense
to her. Here we have Blake’s version of the “pedestal,” and of that neo-Platonically inspired sexual
reverence which prefers ladies pure, exalted and static rather than adjacent and active. When Ahania is
uncomfortable in her shrine and tries to give her spouse some advice about returning to Eternity, he seizes
her by the hair, calling her “Thou little diminutive portion that darst be a counterpart,” and throws her
out of heaven, declaring “Am I not God? Who is equal to me?” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> III. 42.21-43.9).
Without Ahania, Urizen is Doubt instead of Faith, and degenerates in the course of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi> from Prince of Light, to tyrannic parody of Milton’s God, to William Pitt opposing the Bread Bill
of 1800, to the Dragon Form of Antichrist. Ahania falls from being a sky goddess who opened her mouth once too
often to “the silent woman” about whom feminist critics are presently writing a good deal.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">11</ref> Until just before the end of <hi rend="i">The
Four Zoas</hi> Ahania has nothing further to say. As “the furrowed field” she is a figure of complete
submission. We should compare her possibly to those other victims of exacerbated and anxious male intellect,
Hamlet’s Ophelia and Faust’s Gretchen.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29"
type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">11</hi> See, for example, Mary Daly, <hi rend="i">Beyond God The Father</hi>
(Boston: Beacon Press, 1973), Marcia Landy, “The Silent Woman,” in <hi rend="i">The Authority of
Experience</hi>, ed. Arlyn Diamond and Lee Edwards (Amherst: Univ. of Massachusetts Press, 1977), Susan
Griffin, <hi rend="i">Woman and Nature: The Roaring Inside Her</hi>(New York: Harper and Row, 1978), Sandra M.
Gilbert and Susan Gubar, <hi rend="i">The Madwoman in the Attic</hi> (New Haven: Yale Univ. Press, 1980),
chaps. 1 and 2. The contention of these and other feminist writers in America, England and France is that
western religion and philosophy, by consistently associating power and authority with masculinity, have
deprived women of access to authoritative speech and muted their ability to “voice” female experience
authentically. The critique of rationalism in such works for the most part tallies very well with
Blake’s.</note>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Ophelia’s selfless “O what a noble mind is here o’erthrown”
speech nicely resembles Ahania’s memory of “those sweet fields of bliss / Where liberty was justice &amp;
eternal science was mercy (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> III.39.12-13). Later, when Hamlet has rejected her and slain
her father (cf. Urizen’s rejection of Ahania and his defiance of Albion), Ophelia’s “speech is
nothing.” Both Ophelia and Gretchen, of course, express profound admiration for their lovers’
intellects.</note></p>
        <pb id="p16-160" n="160"/>
        <p>Luvah and Vala, last of the Zoas and Emanations, are in their unfallen form lover and beloved, the
Eros and Psyche of Man. Fallen, Luvah is born into this world as the revolutionary babe and flaming youth who
must become a sacrificed god in epoch after epoch, while Vala is the <hi rend="i">dolorosa</hi> who, believing
she loves him, always sacrifices him.</p>
        <p>As all Blake readers know, Vala is one of Blake’s most complicated characters. Her name means
“vale” as in “valley,” and as Nature she is the valley of the shadow of death, the declivity of the
female genitals, and the membranous “veil” which preserves virginity, as well as the “veil” covering
the tabernacle of the Old Testament. Like the chapel in “The Garden of Love” and the “chapel all of
gold,” she stands at the intersection between corrupt sexuality and institutional religion; thus she is also
the veil of the temple which was rent when Jesus died, for Vala is the Nature we worship when we should
worship Christ, she is Fortuna, Babylon, the Great Whore, enemy of Jerusalem. Where Enitharmon is a tease and
a betrayer, Vala is the “Female Will” incarnate as killer. She is the chaste mistress who withholds favors
so that her lovers will become warriors, and she is the blood-spattered priestess who with a knife of flint
cuts the hearts out of men—all the while protesting that she craves nothing but Love. So powerful a figure
is she that I expect we see at least as much of her in popular culture—where she is the voluptuous pinup on
barracks walls, and she is the lady in black leather who will punish you—as in conventional fiction and
drama. Pornography magazines offer us endless reproductions of Vala-Babylon, and, in the most high-chic phases
of fashion design, the ideal fashion model is “cruel” Vala.</p>
        <p>If we judge by Mario Praz’ exploration of the “tormented, contaminated beauty” and “femme
fatale” in western literature, this type of female seems—at least prior to Swinburne—to have been more
extensively treated by French than by English writers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30"
type="note">13</ref> Ste.-Beuve, Gautier, Baudelaire adore her. For Swinburne, she becomes the Venus of
“Laus Veneris,” Faustine, and Mary Stuart. But if we look earlier, she certainly figures in Jacobean
drama, and in at least one play of Shakespeare’s. <note id="n30"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Mario Praz, 
<hi rend="i">The Romantic Agony</hi> (1933; rpt. Cleveland: World Publishing Co., 1956) pp. 28ff, 189 ff. Among
Praz’ many valuable observations is a remark on Ste.-Beuve which is particularly relevant to the
Vala-Jerusalem relationship: “Whenever it happens that a writer feels admiration for [female] passionate
energy—particularly if this energy have fatal results . . . it is always the diabolical . . . who ends by
occupying the whole stage and causing her angelic rival . . . to appear a mere shadow” (p. 191).</note></p>
        <p>Late in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, one of Vala’s avatars has a warrior-lover whom she craves to
possess completely. “O that I could live in his sight,” she says; “O that I could bind him to my arm”
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 82.44). Concealing him under her veil, she wishes him to become “an infant love” at
her breast. When she opens the veil, revealing “her own perfect beauty,” her lover has become “a winding
worm.” Blake hopes at this moment to show that Female Will is ultimately self-defeating. The winding worm is
a further degeneration of helpless infancy, so that her wish has come true beyond her intention, as in
folktales. The worm is also the phallic worm (cf. Yeats’ “Chambermaid’s Song,” where “Pleasure has
made him / Weak as a worm”) and the devouring worm of the grave. The parallel story is of course 
<hi rend="i">Antony and Cleopatra.</hi> There, too, Woman reduces Warrior to absurd infantile dependency, out of
pure erotic possessiveness. She then dies by the instrument of a worm that she describes as an infant—“the
baby at my breast / That sucks the nurse asleep (V.ii.308-309) and that she croons to as lover. Without the
aid of Blake, we might not think to identify the asp in <hi rend="i">Antony and Cleopatra</hi> as the last
essence of Antony himself. With Blake, the identification seems compelling. At the same time, with the aid of
Shakespeare, we may see Vala more clearly as the fallen form of female desire.</p>
        <p>As the individual characters of Zoas and Emanations differ, so do the plots of their
reconciliations. Los-Enitharmon’s begins earliest in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, and involves a
channeling of their arrogant energy through suffering. Following the binding of Urizen they have sunk,
exhausted, to their nadir, “shrunk into fixed space . . . Their senses unexpansive” (V. 57. 12-18).
Redemption starts with the painful birth of Orc, and the grief that follows the Los-Enitharmon-Orc Family
Romance. Though repentance and sorrow over their mutual failure to free Orc are apparently useless,
Enitharmon’s heartbreak (V. 63. 10-14) triggers a process of imaginative re-expansion and re-unification
that continues through the complex episodes of Spectre-Shadow and Spectre-Los reunions (VIIa.81.7-86.14) and
the “six thousand years of self denial and of bitter contrition” during which Los builds Golgonooza and
Los and Enitharmon finally labor together as partners in the Art which gives regenerate form to all of life
(VIIa.90.2-57). At the opening of Night IX “Los and Enitharmon builded Jerusalem weeping” and at no point
thereafter are separated. In the final two pages the regenerate “dark Urthona” has reclaimed them
both.</p>
        <p>Reunion of the other Zoas and Emanations completes the Eternal Man’s awakening and resumption of
control over his warring “members.” Ahania revives at the moment of Urizen’s rejuvenation. She bursts
with excess of joy, sleeps a winter and returns in spring as Kore, and finally takes her seat “by Urizen”
(i.e., not enshrined) “in songs &amp; joy.” Next, when Orc’s passion burns itself out, Albion takes the
somewhat-charred Luvah and Vala in hand and admonishes them: “Luvah &amp; Vala henceforth you are Servants
obey &amp; live” (IX. 126.6). They enact their obedience first in the ensuing pastoral episode, with its
idyllic evocation of a new Golden Age, and then in the Last Vintage, where human grapes are orgiastically
crushed in the wine-presses of Luvah. The episode concludes with Luvah and Vala described as a couple linked
to the seasons; together they sleep, wake, and are “cast . . .thro the air till winter is over &amp; gone”
while the “Human Wine” they have made “stood wondering in all their delightful expanses” (IX.
137.30-32). Finally Tharmas and Enion, first pair to be seen in collapse and last to be seen regenerate, also
undergo a double transformation. They are initially reborn into Vala’s garden as naive and wayward children,
as befits their innocent character. But a fully renewed and humanized Enion and Tharmas embrace and are
welcomed by the Eternal Man (IX. 131.10-133.1) to the final feast.</p>
        <p>For the Blake who conceived of humanity as androgynous,
<pb id="p16-161" n="161"/>
the division of Zoas from Emanations signified human disorder and disaster. His poetry describing sexual
division is some of the most anguished in the language. By the same token, re-couplings precipitate and are
accompanied by all the images for joy and order Blake knew: a seasonal cycle culminating in harvest, vintage
and communal feast; a painful bread-making and wine-making which issues in happiness; music and “vocal
harmony” concluding in human “conversing”; and a beaming morning sun.</p>
        <p>To trace the lineaments of Blake number three, we must return to the very outset of the poet’s
career, and the extraordinary lyric “How sweet I roamed from field to field,” where an unidentified winged
speaker is lured and trapped by “the prince of love.” The poem is in a quasi-Elizabethan diction, but with
the swoon of eroticism and ecstatic surrender we associate with Keats. Keatsian too are the lushness and
fertility of the natural setting, and the painful close:
<q>
With sweet May dews my wings were wet,<lb/>
And Phoebus fir’d my vocal rage;<lb/>
He caught me in his silken net,<lb/>
And shut me in his golden cage.<lb/>
<lb/>
He loves to sit and hear me sing,<lb/>
Then laughing, sports and plays with me;<lb/>
Then stretches out my golden wing,<lb/>
And mocks my loss of liberty.
</q>
Un-Keatsian is the ambivalent gender of the speaker and the personification power of love as male not female.
Although the theme of romantic enthrallment of a woman by a man is relatively unusual in English poetry, Irene
H. Chayes argues convincingly that the speaker is Psyche and the manipulator of “silken net” and “golden
cage” is Eros.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">14</ref>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Irene H. Chayes, “The Presence of Cupid and Psyche,” in 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman and John E. Grant (Princeton: Princeton
Univ. Press, 1970), pp. 214-43.</note></p>
        <p>But in later versions of this scenario, the instruments of entrapment and enclosure—net, cage,
locked box—will be the sexually symbolic props of females who imprison males. “The Crystal Cabinet,”
“The Golden Net” and “The Mental Traveller” are all versions of this theme, and the “Woman Old” of
the last of these is a brilliant portrayal of the <hi rend="i">vagina dentata</hi> in action, for she torments
male vitality simultaneously by nailing and piercing, and by binding and catching. As if correcting his own
earlier naiveté, one of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> poems asks rhetorically “Why was Cupid a
Boy?” and answers that the illusion of a male Cupid who inflicts sexual suffering “was the Cupid Girls
mocking plan,” part of a scheme to keep real boys who “cant interpret the thing” unsuspecting while she
shot them full of darts (E 470). Along similar lines, “My Spectre Around Me” envisages a war between the
sexes dominated by female pride, scorn, jealousy and lust for “Victory” imaged as possession and
enclosure: “Living thee alone Ill have / And when dead Ill be thy Grave.” The solution is a Spectral
threat of rejection and retaliation:
<q>
Till I turn from Female Love<lb/>
And root up the Infernal Grove<lb/>
I shall never worthy be<lb/>
To step into Eternity<lb/>
And to end thy cruel mocks<lb/>
Annihilate thee on the rocks<lb/>
And another form create<lb/>
To be subservient to my fate. (E 468)
</q>
This brings the Emanation round, for it is either she, or Emanation and Spectre in duet, who “agree to give
up Love” for “the world of happy Eternity.”</p>
        <p>Among the engraved poems, “To Tirzah” is a furious repudiation of female sexuality in its
maternal aspect as that which encloses and divides man from Eternity. To appreciate the impact of “To
Tirzah” in its original context we should probably see it as the contrary poem to “A Cradle Song” in 
<hi rend="i">Innocence.</hi> Where in <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> a mother sings lullingly to a sleeping infant of
the “sweet” smiles and tears that Jesus as “an infant small” sheds and shares with herself and the
child, in <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> the child responds, ironically using Jesus’ adolescent rejection of
Mary (John 2.4) for his punch line:
<q>
Thou Mother of my mortal part<lb/>
With cruelty didst mould my Heart,<lb/>
and with false self-deceiving tears<lb/>
Didst bind my Nostrils Eyes &amp; Ears.<lb/>
<lb/>
Didst close my Tongue in senseless clay<lb/>
And me to Mortal Life betray.<lb/>
The Death of Jesus set me free,<lb/>
Then what have I to do with thee?
</q>
A second strong repudiation is <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, where erotic entrapment both maternal and sexual, the
former expressing itself as possessive, the latter as seductive manipulation of male desire, takes place so
that “Woman, lovely Woman! may have dominion” during the corrupt centuries of Enitharmon’s reign. Here
Enitharmon’s “crystal house” is analogous to the crystal cabinet, and within it there is a constant
claustrophobic movement of nocturnal binding, circling, cycling, broken only by the dawn of European
revolution.</p>
        <p>How well do these poems fit the Blake who praises “gratified Desire” and insists that “Energy
is the only life and is from the body”? Rather poorly, I think. However allegorically we interpret the
thing, sexual love in these poems is neither gratifying nor capable of gratification, and the poet
consistently associates “sensual enjoyment” with cruelty, imprisonment, illusion and mortality instead of
liberation, vision and immortality. Morton Paley has pointed out that Blake’s Lambeth books involve “a
sort of involuntary dualism, a myth with implications that in some ways conflicted with his own beliefs.
Blake’s intuition of the goodness of the body in general and of sexual love in particular had not weakened .
. . but . . . the Lambeth myth seems to imply that physical life is inherently evil.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">15</ref> If, in other words, we have one Blake for
whom physical life is type and symbol of spiritual life and fulfilled joy in one leads us to the other, there
is also a Blake for whom body and spirit are as irreconcilably opposed as they are for any Church Father. But
the contradiction is exacerbated rather than resolved in the later books, where the anatomical image of the
enclosure vastly expands to become a whole world, the realm of Beulah, a
<pb id="p16-162" n="162"/>
dreamy moony place presided over by tender females, which is both comfort and trap. 
<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination: A Study of the Development of
Blake’s Thought</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1970), p. 90.</note></p>
        <p>To a fallen and depleted consciousness, Beulah is the source of poetry and our one hope of
returning to Eden. The “Daughters of Beulah” are reliably compliant “Muses who inspire the Poets Song”
or nurse-figures who comfort and protect the weary and distressed. That “Contrarieties are equally true”
in Beulah makes it seem an obvious advance over single vision and Newton’s sleep. Yet as another Crystal
Cabinet writ large, Beulah inevitably means confinement, limitation, illusion. It can never mean Infinity.
Where Eden is fourfold and human, Beulah is merely threefold and sexual, the vacation spot for beings who
cannot sustain the strenuous mental excitement of Eden and need “repose”:
<q>
Into this pleasant shadow all the weak &amp; weary<lb/>
Like Women &amp; Children were taken away as on wings<lb/>
Of dovelike softness, &amp; shadowy habitations prepared for them<lb/>
But every Man returnd &amp; went still going forward thro’<lb/>
The Bosom of the Father in Eternity on Eternity.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">M</hi> 31.1-5)
</q>
Of the double potentialities of Beulah, benign yields to malign in successive works. In <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>, Beulah is purely protective. <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> begins to emphasize not only its pleasantness
but also its delusiveness. In <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, where the Daughters of Beulah have been replaced as
muses by a single male muse and lover, “the Saviour . . . dictating the words of his mild song,” Blake
firmly identifies “the lovely delusions of Beulah” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 17.27) with the terrors of
sexuality. Thus Vala, claiming precedence over the Savior, hypnotizes Albion with her concave allure and her
usurped phallic power:
<q>
The Imaginative Human Form is but a breathing of Vala<lb/>
I breathe him forth into the Heaven from my secret Cave<lb/>
Born of the Woman to obey the Woman O Albion the mighty<lb/>
For the Divine appearance is Brotherhood, but I am Love<lb/>
Elevate into the Region of Brotherhood with my red fires<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 29.48-30.1)
</q>
Responding to Vala’s triumph, Los laments:
<q>
What may Man be? Who can tell! But what may Woman be?<lb/>
To have power over Man from Cradle to corruptible Grave.<lb/>
There is a Throne in every Man, it is the Throne of God<lb/>
This Woman has claim’d as her own &amp; Man is no more! . . .<lb/>
O Albion why wilt thou Create a Female Will?<lb/>
To hide the most evident God in a hidden covert, even<lb/>
In the Shadows of a Woman &amp; a secluded Holy Place<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 30.25-33)
</q>
Beulah itself seems at fault, in Los’s agonized cry:
<q>
Humanity knows not of Sex: wherefore are sexes in Beulah?<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 44.3)
</q>
And again, anticipating Keats’s yearning description of a work of art “all breathing human passion far
above:”
<q>
redeem’d Humanity is far above<lb/>
Sexual organization; &amp; the Visions of the Night of Beulah<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 79.73-4)
</q>
For, as Blake in his own persona tells us, however tender and pleasant and full of “ever varying delights”
the “time of love” passed in Beulah may be, where “every Female delights to give her maiden to her
husband” and
<q>
The Female searches sea &amp; land for gratification to the<lb/>
Male Genius: who in return clothes her in gems &amp; gold<lb/>
And feeds her with the food of Eden, hence all her beauty beams<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 69.17-19)
</q>
Love in Beulah inevitably brings a depletion of energy and the advent of jealousies, murders, moral law,
revenge, and the whole panoply of inhuman cruelties the poet has taught us to struggle against. In visionary
contrast, Blake imagines a love that transcends sexuality because it is a mingling of male with male:
<q>
I am in you &amp; you in me, mutual in love divine:<lb/>
Fibres of love from man to man thro Albions pleasant land . . .<lb/>
I am not a God afar off, I am a brother and friend;<lb/>
Within your bosoms I reside, and you reside in me.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 4.7-19)
</q>
Such is the opening promise of the Saviour, and if in Eternity “Embraces are Cominglings from the Head even
to the Feet” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 69.43), we well may wonder whether such embraces can ever occur between
male and female. For if the Blake who celebrates desire sees it as equally distributed between genders, the
Blake who fears desire sees sexuality in general and sexual threat in particular as a female phenomenon. This
third Blake gives us an array, culminating in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, of passive males subject to females
who seduce, reject, betray, bind, lacerate, mock and deceive them. After <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters
of Albion</hi>, though Blake continues strenuously to oppose the idea that woman’s love is 
<hi rend="i">sin</hi>, he increasingly describes it as <hi rend="i">snare.</hi> There is no comparable depiction
of males seducing and betraying females.</p>
        <p>This brings me to Blake number four, who is perhaps not quite a classic misogynist—though he
sometimes sounds like one—but someone who believes that the proper study of woman is the happiness of her
man, and who cannot conceive of a true woman in any but a supportive, subordinate role. In the margin of his
1789 edition of Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man</hi>, Blake wrote, “Let the men do their duty
&amp; the women will be such wonders, the female life lives from the light of the male, see a mans female
dependents, you know the man” (E 585). Females, in other words, may be wonders, but only if men are: and to
be female is to be dependent.</p>
        <p>Examining Blake from this point of view, and returning to <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>, we notice that
Oothoon is good, and she is wise, but she is completely powerless. So long as her menfolk refuse
enlightenment, she will be bound hand and foot, imprisoned in a passivity which she does not desire but to
which she must submit. Looking at <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, we see that Enion and Ahania are likewise
good—indeed, they represent precisely the goodness of selfless love and compassion—but passive, while
Enitharmon and Vala are active and evil. In <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> the story
is the same: female figures
<pb id="p16-163" n="163"/>
are either powerful or good; never both. The late prophecies may even constitute a retreat from the point
Blake arrived at in <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>, for the better the late females are, the more passive, the more
submissive and obedient they also are.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33"
type="note">16</ref> When Ololon finds Milton, she tearfully apologizes for being the cause of Natural
Religion. And when Milton concludes his splendid final speech on “Self-annihilation and the grandeur of
Inspiration” with a peroration against the “Sexual Garments, the Abomination of Desolation,” Ololon
responds by dividing into the six-fold Virgin who dives “into the depths / Of Miltons Shadow as a Dove upon
the stormy sea” and a “moony Ark” who enters into the fires of intellect
<q>
Around the Starry Eight: with one accord the Starry Eight became<lb/>
One Man Jesus the Saviour. Wonderful! round his limbs<lb/>
The Clouds of Ololon folded as a Garment dipped in blood<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">M</hi> 42.9-11)
</q>
At the climax of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> there is a similar self-immolative plunge when “England”
awakes on Albion’s bosom. Having blamed herself for being “the Jealous Wife” who has caused all the
troubles of the poem:
<q>
England who is Brittania enterd Albions bosom rejoicing<lb/>
Rejoicing in his indignation! adoring his wrathful rebuke.<lb/>
She who adores not your frowns will only loathe your smiles<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 95.22-4)
</q>
But this somewhat gratuitous-seeming passage lacks—since we have not met “England” until now—the
systematic quality of Blake’s treatment of his chief heroine. <note id="n33"><hi rend="s">16</hi> A partial
exception is the prophetic figure of Erin in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, yet in a sense Erin is an exception
that proves the rule; for though her voice is inspirational without passivity or subordination, she remains
undeveloped as a character, lacking the internal struggles and self-transformations of the other major figures
in the poem.</note></p>
        <p>The poet’s final and most fully-idealized heroine “is named Liberty among the sons of Albion”
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 26.3-4) yet we seriously mistake Blake’s intention if we think Jerusalem is herself a
free being, or even a being capable of volition. She is the City of God, bride of Christ, and man’s
Christian Liberty, to be sure, but that is only in Eden, and even there she does not act; she simply is. What
happens to Jerusalem within the body of the poem at no point involves her in action or in protest. At its
outset she is withheld by Albion from “the vision &amp; fruition of the Holy-one” (<hi rend="i">J</hi>
4.17) and is accused of sin by Albion and Vala. Unlike Oothoon she does not deny the accusation, nor does she
defend her own vision with anything like Oothoon’s exuberance. Patiently, meekly, she explains and begs Love
and Forgiveness from her enemies. That is her last initiative. Subsequently she is rejected as a whore, cast
out, imprisoned, driven finally to insanity, and becomes wholly incapable even of remembering her original
self without being reminded of her origins by the voice of her pitying and merciful God. Even this comfort
does not help; for at the poem’s darkest moment, just before the advent of the Covering Cherub, Jerusalem
passively receives a cup of poison from the conquering Vala (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 88.56).</p>
        <p>The final movement of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> evokes its heroine twice, when “the Universal
Father” speaking through “the vision of Albion” echoes the Song of Solomon:
<q>
Awake! Awake Jerusalem! O lovely Emanation of Albion<lb/>
Awake and overspread all Nations as in Ancient Time<lb/>
For lo! the Night of Death is past and the Eternal Day<lb/>
Appears upon our hills: Awake Jerusalem, and come away<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 97.1-4)
</q>
and when the poet’s vision of “All Human Forms” is complete:
<q>
And I heard the Name of their Emanations they are named Jerusalem<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 99.5)
</q>
Yet however amorous, however reverential our attitude toward this “persecuted maiden”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">17</ref> redeemed, we do not and cannot encounter the
“awakened” Jerusalem directly. As <hi rend="i">A Vision of the Last Judgment</hi> explicitly tells us, and
as the whole of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> implies, “In Eternity Woman is the Emanation of Man; she has no
Will of her own. There is no such thing in Eternity as a Female Will” (E 552). If we wonder what the
Emanative role in Eternity is, Blake has already told us:
<q>
When in Eternity Man converses with Man, they enter<lb/>
Into each other’s Bosom (which are universes of delight)<lb/>
In mutual interchange, and first their Emanations meet . . .<lb/>
For Man cannot unite with Man but by their Emanations . . .<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 88.3-9)
</q>
Is femaleness, then, ideally a kind of social glue? Susan Fox argues that although “in his prophetic poems
Blake conceives of a perfection of humanity defined by the complete mutuality of its interdependent
genders,” he nevertheless in these same poems “represents one of these equal genders as inferior and
dependent . . . or as unnaturally and disastrously dominant,” so that females come to represent either
“weakness” or “power-hunger.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35"
type="note">18</ref> Anne Mellor has observed that Blake’s ideal males throughout the major prophecies are
creative and independent while his ideal females “at their best are nurturing . . . generous . . .
compassionate . . . all welcoming and never-critical emotional supporters,” and that “in Blake’s
metaphoric system, the masculine is both logically and physically prior to the feminine.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">19</ref> But at its most extreme, Blake’s vision
goes beyond proposing an ideal of dominance-submission or priority-inferiority between the genders. As a
counter-image to the intolerable idea of female power, female containment and “binding” of man to mortal
life, Blake wishfully imagines that the female can be re-absorbed by the male, be contained within him, and
exist Edenically not as a substantial being but as an attribute. Beyond the wildest dreams of Levi-Strauss,
the ideal female functions as a medium of interchange among real, that is to say male, beings. 
<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">17</hi> The term is from Praz, who suggests Clarissa and Sade’s Justine as two
examples of the type.</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Susan Fox, “The Female as Metaphor in William Blake’s Poetry,” 
<hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry</hi> 5 (Spring 1977), 507.</note>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Anne K. Mellor, “Blake’s Portrayal of Women,” in this
issue.</note></p>
        <p>And what are we as readers to make of Blake’s contradictions?<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">20</ref> Morris Dickstein, noting the shift from the “feminism”
of <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> to his later stress on “female Will,” calls it “a stunning change that
seems rooted less in politics than in the nearly unknown terrain of Blake’s personal life.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">21</ref> Diana George believes that Blake became
entrapped in a culturally mandated sexual typology which he initially intended to “redeem.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">22</ref> Although all our anecdotal material about the
Blakes indicates that Catherine adored her visionary husband
<pb id="p16-164" n="164"/>
even when he was not bringing home the bacon, much less adorning her in gems and gold, marital friction looks
like a reasonable source for many <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> and other poems. Perhaps, too, Blake had a model
for Oothoon in Mary Wollstonecraft, whose vigorous equal may not have been encountered in his other female
acquaintances after Wollstonecraft’s death.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
type="note">23</ref> At the same time, we should recognize that the shift in Blake’s sexual views coincides
with other ideological and doctrinal transformations: from a faith in political revolution perhaps assisted or
exemplified by Art to a faith in Imagination as that which alone could prepare humanity for its harvest and
vintage; from what looks like a love of nature that makes him one of the great pastoral poets in the English
language and extends as far as <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, to a growing and finally absolute rejection of nature
and all fleshly things; and from an imminent to a transcendent God. <note id="n37"><hi rend="s">20</hi> For
some readers, of course, no contradiction worth noticing exists. Consider, for example, the following: “Some
modern women may have much to object to in Blake’s latest thought about the relations between the sexes. But
it is hard to believe that <hi rend="i">l’homme moyen sensuel</hi> would reject the hearty bread and
fullbodied wine the late Blake is offering him. Or his wife either, for that matter: ‘let men do their duty
&amp; the women will be such wonders.’ ” Such is Jean Hagstrum’s pleasant conclusion in “Babylon
Revisited, or the Story of Luvah and Vala,” in <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory: Essays on The Four
Zoas, Milton and Jerusalem</hi>, ed. Stuart Curran and Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr. (Madison: Univ. of
Wisconsin Press, 1973), p. 118. David Aers, in “William Blake and the Dialectic of Sex,” 
<hi rend="i">ELH</hi> 44 (1977), 500-14, feels that in <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> Blake “may have slipped toward
an optimistic, idealistic illusion in his handling of Oothoon’s consciousness. The illusion lies in assuming
that revolutionary consciousness can ever be as uncontaminated by dominant structures and ideologies as
Oothoon’s appears to be” (p. 505). By stressing female will in later poems, Blake “is casting out the
vestiges of optimistic delusions,” having discovered that “it is utopian and undialectical to imagine a
female consciousness like Oothoon’s” (p. 507). Since Aers does not seem to reflect that Oothoon’s
inventor himself must have been as “uncontaminated” as his invention, and that Los in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> seems likewise, I take Aers’ position to be that we can believe in a male
uncontaminated consciousness but that it is undialectical to believe in a female one.</note>
	<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Dickstein, pp. 77-78.</note>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">22</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake and Freud</hi>, chap. 6, includes this argument in a
larger discussion of Blake’s treatment of “the feminine.”</note>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">23</hi> See Alicia Ostriker, “Todd, <hi rend="i">Wollstonecraft
Anthology</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 14 (1980-81), 129-31.</note></p>
        <p>Yet to say that Blake’s views moved from X to Y would be an absurd oversimplification. It would
be truer to say that X and Y were with him always—like his Saviour—in varying proportions, and that the
antagonism between them is the life of his poetry. One of the idols of our tribe is System, a Blakean term
signifying a set of ideas bounded by an adhesive inflexible consistency, cognate of the “bounded” which
its possessor soon loathes, the “Circle” that any sensible God or Man should avoid, and the “mill with
complicated wheels.” If “Unity is the cloke of Folly” in a work of art, we might make it our business as
critics not only to discover, but also to admire, a large poet’s large inconsistencies—particularly in an
area like the meaning of sex, where the entire culture, and probably each of us, in the shadows of our
chambers, feel profound ambivalence.</p>
        <p>If “without contraries is no progression,” I think we should be neither surprised nor dismayed
to find in Blake both a richly developed anti-patriarchal and proto-feminist sensibility, in which love
between the sexes serves as a metaphor for psychic wholeness, integrity, and more abundant life, and its
opposite, a homocentric gynophobia in which heterosexual love means human destruction.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">24</ref> If the doors of perception were cleansed everything would
appear to man as it is, infinite.” What then if we concede that Blake’s vision, at least part of the time,
was fogged to the degree that he could perceive Man as infinite but could not perceive Woman as equally so?
Blake understood that it is impossible for any prophet finally to transcend historical time. He understood so
of Isaiah and Ezekiel, he understood the same of John Milton. “To give a Body to Error” was, he believed,
an essential service performed by mighty intellects for posterity. We might, with gratitude for this way of
comprehending great poetry, see him as he saw his precursors. To paraphrase Emerson and the 
<hi rend="i">Gita</hi>, when him we fly, he is our wings. <note id="n41"><hi rend="s">24</hi> The mirror image of
this view appears in a number of contemporary lesbian feminist works. See, for example, Griffin, pp.
207-27.</note></p>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p16-165" n="165" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
