<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.4.lange</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Two Forged Plates in America Copy B</title>
        <author n="Lange">Thomas V. Lange</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1983</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Barbara Guth</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Adelheid M. Atkins</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>John Wilcox</name>
              <name>Carl Woodring</name>
              <name>Warren Keith Wright</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
      <pb id="p16-212" n="212"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-4-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="main">Two Forged Plates in <hi rend="i">America</hi> Copy B</title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">THOMAS V.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">LANGE</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>For nearly a century, copy B of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">America</hi>,
                    now in the Pierpont Morgan Library, has been considered by dealers, auction
                    houses, and scholars as a complete and uncolored copy with the full complement
                    of eighteen plates on eighteen leaves. Detailed examination of this copy has
                    revealed that two plates are, in fact, facsimiles, and were inserted in copy B
                    between 1874 and 1878, most probably with intent to deceive.</p>
        <p>In his <hi rend="i">Blake 
Books</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63" type="note">1</ref> G.E.
Bentley, Jr. discusses the provenance of copy B, which 
was presented to the Morgan by Mrs. Landon K. Thorne in 
1973.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64" type="note">2</ref>
The earliest evidence of ownership of this copy is a penned inscription on the
recto of the frontispiece (mistakenly located by Bentley on the verso of the
title-page), reading, “From the author / to C H Tatham Oct.<hi rend="s">r</hi> 7 /
1799.” While this inscription was once thought to be in
Blake’s hand, later authorities have dismissed this claim. Bentley
suggests that copy B might be the one listed by Lowndes as having been sold by
“Sotheby, 1855, 2£.7s,” described only as a folio with 18
designs.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65" type="note">3</ref> 
This otherwise unidentified
sale at Sotheby’s has not been traced. Evidently copy B was again sold
for £18 in 1874 (according to the note in the 1878 sale catalogue
reproduced below), although no trace of this transaction at auction or in dealer
catalogues has been found. 
		<note id="n63"><hi rend="s">1</hi> G.E. Bentley, Jr.,
			<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977), pp. 100
			et seq.</note>
		<note id="n64"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Morgan Library accession
			number 63938.</note>
		<note id="n65"><hi rend="s">3</hi> W.T. Lowndes, <hi rend="i">The
			Bibliographer’s Manual. . .</hi>, (London, 1856), I, 215. There
			appears to be no justification for this suggestion.</note></p>
        <p>The first printed reference to copy B appears in the sale catalogue “of a
                    very choice library and a small but rich collection of ancient engravings &amp;
                    modern drawings” belonging to Albert George Dew-Smith, sold at auction by
                    Sotheby’s on 29-30 January 1878, as lot 247: 
					<q> 
                    	247 <hi rend="smallcaps">Blake (W.) America,
                        a Prophecy.</hi> <hi rend="i">Engraved throughout by this extraordinary
                            artist.</hi> <hi rend="smallcaps">Excessively Rare</hi>, 
                            <hi rend="i">presentation copy with
                            author’s autograph inscription, splendidly bound in citron
                            morocco, ornamented with variegated leathers and gold tooling, g.e. by
                            F. Bedford; two leaves said to be wanting, but Blake’s original
                            prospectus says</hi>—“America, a Prophecy in illuminated
                        printing,” <hi rend="i">folio, with</hi> 18 <hi rend="i">designs,
                            Lambeth, W. Blake</hi>, 1793<lb/>
                            <hi rend="s">*</hi><hi rend="sub">*</hi><hi rend="s">*</hi> This copy, unbound,
sold for
                        £18 in 1874.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n66"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Reprinted with the kind permission of
                            Sotheby, Ltd.</note>
					</q></p>
        <p>According to the notes in the Sotheby master catalogue deposited at the British
                    Library, lot 247 was sold to the London dealer John Pearson for £16.5.0.
                    The next traced appearance of copy B occured twelve years later, on 23 April
                    1890, when it was again offered by Sotheby’s, as lot 189 in the sale of
                    the library of Thomas Gaisford,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67"
type="note">5</ref> who had
                    presumably acquired the book from Pearson. At the Gaisford sale it fetched
                    £61 to the London firm of Bernard Quaritch, which added its customary
                    pencilled note to the rear flyleaf, “Collated and perfect/ Ap.<hi rend="s">1</hi> 24 90/
J.T.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68" type="note">6</ref>
                    Quaritch included copy B in catalogue 104, May 1890 (no. 460), from which it was
                    purchased for £68 by Bernard Buchanan Macgeorge. Interestingly enough,
                    Macgeorge had attempted to purchase copy B at the Gaisford sale and had given
                    his bid of £30 to Quaritch; it was not until the appearance of
                    Quaritch’s catalogue 104 the following month that the collector was
                    persuaded to pay more than twice his earlier bid. <note id="n67"><hi rend="s">5</hi>
Thomas Gaisford, 1799-1855, Dean of Christ Church, Oxford. See
                        De Ricci, <hi rend="i">English Collectors of Books and Manuscripts</hi>
                        (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1930), p. 165.</note>
	<note id="n68"><hi rend="s">6</hi> In a letter of 10 January 1978, Mr. Nicholas
                        Poole-Wilson of Bernard Quaritch, Ltd. kindly informed me that there were
                        two employees of the firm at the time with the initials J.T.; it has proven
                        impossible to differentiate between them: J. Tuckett and J.
                        Thorowgood.</note></p>
        <p>Let us return to the Dew-Smith sale catalogue, which contains the first printed
                    notice of copy B. There is no doubt that the copy under consideration is the one
                    described in the catalogue: the unusual inscription and the readily-identifiable
                    binding are both unique to this copy. The Dew-Smith sale entry enables us to
                    supply an approximate date for the binding of copy B: it must have been done
                    between 1874 when sold “unbound,” and 1878 when the elaborate
                    binding of “citron morocco, ornamented with variegated leathers and gilt
                    tooling” by Francis Bedford was so carefully described in the Dew-Smith
                    catalogue.</p>
        <p>There is a glaring ambiguity in that catalogue entry: it is not at all clear how
                    many plates were in copy B. As printed, the catalogue entry reads, “<hi rend="i">two
plates said to be wanting, but Blake’s original
                        prospectus says</hi>—‘America, a Prophecy in illuminated
                    printing,’ <hi rend="i">folio, with 18 designs, Lambeth, W. Blake</hi>,
                    1793.” This phrase makes little sense. The conjunction
                    “but” should be used to connect two countering statements; in this
                    case, the second part, “America, a Prophecy in illuminated
                    printing” in no way contradicts or counters the statement that two leaves
                    are said to be wanting. This awkward and illogical sentence can be explained by
                    a simple printer’s error which removed the words “<hi rend="i">folio, with 18
designs</hi>” from the quotation of Blake’s
                    prospectus text and made the words appear a part of Sotheby’s sale entry.
                    The printer, evidently accustomed to setting type in the auction house’s
                    style, assumed that the number of leaves was Sotheby’s description of the
                    copy at hand rather than a part of the quotation. The meaning of the sentence is
                    obvious 
<pb id="p16-213" n="213"/>
when one repairs Blake’s prospectus
                    description. It thus becomes clear that the Sotheby cataloguer could not
                    determine why two plates had at some earlier point been described as lacking,
                    when the copy before him agreed with the prospectus in having the full 18
                    plates. While the meaning of this description is clear, it has not proven
                    possible to locate any statement of imperfection: a note (since lost or erased)
                    in the volume, or a catalogue entry for the untraced 1874 sale are equally
                    plausible sources.</p>
        <p>The Sotheby cataloguer’s insecurity about the number of plates in copy B
                    can be explained by the fact that two plates are not a part of the original
                    volume: careful examination has revealed that plates 4 and 9 not only are not
                    original to this copy, but are facsimiles. Neither plate is sewn into the
                    binding as an integral leaf; instead, both leaves (in their correct positions)
                    are tipped in, pasted to adjacent leaves deep in the gutter of the volume. This
                    is most evident when turning pages: when plates 4 and 9 are turned, plates 5 and
                    10 obediently follow since they are joined by adhesive at the inner margins. The
                    remainder of the leaves in the volume, as one would expect of single bound
                    leaves, turn quite independently of their neighbors. Further, the two leaves in
                    question do not display the gilt edges of the rest of the volume, but form
                    minute gaps at the top, fore, and bottom edges; both plates are shorter than the
                    remaining leaves. As it is virtually impossible to apply matching gilt to a
                    single leaf, inserted leaves could never display the flawless gilding of the
                    edges of the bound leaves. It might be argued that the paper of plates 4 and 9
                    was merely shorter when bound than the remainder of the volume, and thus escaped
                    gilding; two suggestions can be made to show that this is unlikely. Before
                    gilding the edges of this book, the binder was scrupulously careful in cutting
                    and smoothing the edges to provide a perfectly flat surface for the gilt. A
                    binder of Francis Bedford’s reputation and ability would certainly not
                    have permitted these two leaves to remain shorter, but would have trimmed down
                    the remainder of the volume to even all edges. While we would gasp at giving a
                    binder such freedom today, brutally trimming all uncut edges and elaborately
                    gilding the edges was a perfectly normal—in fact, a desirable—way
                    of achieving a finer copy for the nineteenth-century collector.</p>
        <p>Another argument against plates 4 and 9 being an original part of copy B concerns
                    the sewing of the plates before binding. Once again, Bedford, a binder of the
                    highest quality, would have sewn the two leaves with the bulk of the volume (on
                    stubs, if necessary); it is unlikely that he would have simply glued them to
                    adjacent leaves. There is nothing to indicate that the original plates 4 and 9
                    were ever present: there are no stubs, and the binding is extremely tight. If
                    Blake’s original plates 4 and 9 were at some time extracted from copy B,
                    they are nowhere recorded as existing today. Since the binding was executed
                    between 1874 and 1878, the false plates 4 and 9 must also have been inserted
                    between those years.</p>
        <p>Further evidence to demonstrate the alien nature of plates 4 and 9 is found in
                    their hard and smooth wove paper, in general appearance similar to the wove
                    Whatman hand-made paper used in the remainder of the volume.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69" type="note">7</ref> But the surface of plates 4 and 9 is far smoother and
                    does not show the fibrous surface of genuine Whatman paper; the paper of these
                    two plates is without a doubt machine made and is considerably stiffer than
                    Whatman paper. When viewed in a strong light, the paper is also considerably
                    browner in tone than the surrounding Whatman paper. Bentley’s description
                    of copy B in the Thorne catalogue<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70"
type="note">8</ref> notes
                    that (only) “plate 9 seems to be on stiffer paper than the rest”;
                    Joseph Viscomi noticed the same difference in thickness of plates 4 and 9 when
                    examining copy B in 1978, suggesting in conversation with me that these two
                    plates were from another copy of <hi rend="i">America.</hi> After more detailed
                    examination it became clear to me that the two plates were not authentic. It is
                    interesting to note that Bentley deleted his question about the thickness of the
                    paper when incorporating the Thorne catalogue description into <hi rend="i">Blake
Books</hi> and evidently felt no doubts as to authenticity. This is
                    not at all surprising, since both facsimile leaves are of very high quality.
                        <note id="n69"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Watermarks appear on only five of the
                        sixteen genuine plates, but measurement of paper thickness has demonstrated
                        that Whatman paper was used throughout. Were it not for matching stabholes I
                        would be tempted to suggest that the titlepage was substituted from another
                        copy: it alone has an obvious central horizontal crease, and it alone is
                        touched—unconvincingly and with disregard for the design—with
                        grey wash.</note>
	<note id="n70"><hi rend="s">8</hi> G.E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">The Blake
                            Collection of Mrs. Landon K. Thorne</hi> (New York: Pierpont Morgan
                        Library, 1971), pp. 26-27.</note></p>
        <p>Copy B has been variously foliated in pencil—not by Blake—at the
                    upper right corner of each sheet (1-18) and at the lower left corner of each
                    design. Both foliations have been erased and rewritten at various times, all
                    before acquisition by the Morgan. Written below the upper right foliation on
                    plates 4 and 9 appear what could be described as a penciled European
                    “7” with a crossbar, but which may more plausibly be described as
                    a capital “F,” perhaps indicating the word
                    “Facsimile.” It is telling that no other plates in copy B display
                    these markings. Further evidence is provided by the foliation at the lower left,
                    which omits plates 4 and 9 entirely, resulting in a count of 16 plates.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n71"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Further examination of the foliation of the
                        sixteen genuine plates may reveal a different arrangement of the plates
                        before binding, as some erased numbers quite out of sequence are still
                        discernible at the lower left.</note></p>
        <p>The printing ink of the two plates is a dull, dark brownish-black, similar in
                    color to the ink used in the remainder of copy B. When compared with original
                    Blake pulls, however, the printing ink of the spurious leaves appears flat and
                    without surface. Both the flatness of ink and the quality of impression make it
                    evident that these two plates were not printed by Blake’s method of
                    relief etching. Authentic pulls show the ink impressed into the surface of the
                    sheet to such an extent that a clear blind impression of both design and text is
                    visible on the verso of each plate. The versos of plates 4 and 9 are smooth and
                    unblemished.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most conclusive evidence against the authenticity of plates 4 and 9
                    is an obvious platemark, measuring 22.8 × 17 cm. (plate 4) and 24.7
                    × 17.5 cm. (plate 9). There would be no justification for such a
                    platemark on an original pull by Blake, since the size of the artist’s
                    copper plates generally determined the size of his image: for him, margins were
                    undesirable, whether on financial or aesthetic grounds. Bentley and others have
                    discussed the likelihood of Blake using both sides of some of his copper plates,
                    as evidenced by close similarities in size and by the presence of maker’s
                    stamps (usually found on the backs of copper plates).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72" type="note">10</ref> The only instances of substantial margins in
                    Blake’s colorprinting occur in <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> and 
<pb id="p16-214" n="214"/>
	<hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, both conventionally etched (intaglio)
                    works. <note id="n72"><hi rend="s">10</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Books</hi>, pp.
381-82.</note></p>
        <p>The impossibility of the platemark dimensions on plates 4 and 9 can readily be
                    shown on plate 4, where the lower portion of the design was masked by Blake in
                    the printing of most copies, so the area beneath the crouching figure is without
                    the four-line sentiment (so masked in copies C-F, H-M, R, a, and the single
                    Morgan pull). In genuine impressions of this plate, an examination of the
                    surface of the paper will demonstrate that this area was masked by placing a
                    slip of paper over the inked plate; under raking light one can, in fact, see the
                    blind impression of its deckle edge in the single Morgan pull. There is abundant
                    evidence that the original copper plate was not simply cut off to delete this
                    part of the plate. On genuine impressions the copper can be shown to extend 40
                    mm. below the tip of the man’s foot; in copy B the platemark is clearly
                    visible 24 mm. below the foot, locating what would be the bottom of the copper
                    plate in the middle of the text lines.</p>
        <p>Facsimiles—particularly Blake facsimiles—deserve more study. In
                    general, the earliest facsimiles of printed book pages were pen-and-ink
                    facsimiles, often sophisticated redrawings of type. In the case of Blake, such
                    work (as in <hi rend="i">Works by William Blake</hi>) is readily identifiable by
                    comparison with known originals. In the field of early printed books, the most
                    accomplished and annoying facsimilist was John Harris, who worked in England in
                    the mid-nineteenth century, primarily on sixteenth-century religious works. His
                    earliest method was to prepare a tracing of the original leaf to be copied, to
                    transfer the design with a stylus or carbon-like paper to a sheet of
                    appropriately old paper, and to fill in the letters by hand with pen-and-ink.
                    His later technique involved the use of a very lightly printed photolithograph
                    of the page to be reproduced, which was darkened by hand with ink, to form a
                    remarkable facsimile. It is said that he was at times unable to tell his
                    facsimile leaves from originals, and he therefore later insisted on signing his
                    facsimiles with his initials in a lower corner.</p>
        <p>Facsimiles relying on photographic means can be divided into two types: those
                    printed planographically (as lithographs, printed from one surface) and those
                    printed relief (as from zinc blocks). There is no indication that intaglio
                    technique was used for the facsimiles in copy B. Photolithographic prints could
                    be printed from litho stones, or from zinc plates (known as photozincographs).
                    Photorelief blocks were, confusingly enough, also known as zincographs, but the
                    difference in printing is crucial.</p>
        <p>Whichever process was used for plates 4 and 9, there is no doubt that it was
                    rooted in photography. Photolithography is, I feel, the more likely process used
                    for these leaves: that process was executed by photographing an original design,
                    transferring the photographic image to a photosensitive litho stone or zinc
                    plate, and printing that plate or stone through the lithographic (planographic)
                    process. Photolithography was in common use by the 1860s when Henry James
                    instituted the use of “photozincography” for the reproduction of
                    detailed ordnance maps for the British government.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n73" type="note">11</ref> The extreme detail obtained was “such that the greatest
                    error in a photozincographic reduction did not amount to 1/400 part of an inch,
                    a quantity quite inappreciable, and much less than the error due to the
                    contraction of the paper on which the maps were printed.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">12</ref> Because of James’ successful use of
                    the process and at his urging, a photozincographic facsimile of Domesday Book
                    appeared, demonstrating that the process was already considered suitable for the
                    making of exact facsimiles. By the 1880s the technique was totally accepted:
                    William Griggs employed it for his esteemed series of Shakespeare quarto
                    facsimiles, the principal feature of which was exact duplication, barring the
                    variations inherent in paper shrinkage and stretching, and the vagaries of the
                    photographic process. The exact dimensions of the images on plates 4 and 9 of
                    copy B vary somewhat from those of originals, but such variation amounts to less
                    than 2% and can be explained by any of the factors mentioned above. The
                    smoothness of impression argues for a photolithographic process; I have not
                    encountered a craftsman or artist able to differentiate between impressions from
                    stone and those from zinc plates. <note id="n73"><hi rend="s">11</hi> See the
                        biography of James in the <hi rend="i">Dictionary of National
                        Biography</hi>, XXIX, 210-13.</note>
	<note id="n74"><hi rend="s">12</hi> For exhausting details of the anastatic and
                        photozincographic processes see Geoffrey Wakeman, <hi rend="i">Aspects of
                            Victorian Lithography</hi> (Wymondham: Brewhouse Press,
                    1970).</note></p>
        <p>It is also possible that the two plates were printed from relief zinc blocks
                    (also known as linecuts or lineblocks), which are made by transferring a
                    photographic image to a photosensitive sheet of metal. The unexposed areas are
                    etched away, leaving a raised metal surface from which to print with a normal
                    printing press. The plate is mounted on a type-high block of wood for printing.
                    This process is suggested by the overinking on plate 9 around the periphery of
                    the design; on the other hand, there is no trace of impression on the versos of
                    plates 4 and 9 to indicate a relief process.</p>
        <p>Neither process would explain the presence of plate-marks on these two
                    impressions. If printed lithographically from stone there would be only a slight
                    smoothing of the surface of the paper from the stone; if printed from zinc
                    plates there might be a slightly more defined platemark, but barely visible.
                    There is no justification for any platemark if the plates were printed from
                    relief blocks. It may be that in a mistaken understanding of Blake’s
                    technique, a false platemark was applied by running the dampened sheets through
                    a rolling (etching) press next to a sheet of metal, the edges of which would
                    impress a noticeable indentation into the paper.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n75" type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n75"><hi rend="s">13</hi> A curious example of false lithographic
                        platemarks is described by Michael Twyman, “A Note on some
                        Lithographic Stones relating to Alken’s <hi rend="i">Ideas and
                            Notions</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Journal of the Printing Historical
                            Society</hi>, 14 (1979/80), 82-88.</note></p>
        <p>In any case, it is virtually certain that a photographic process was used in the
                    preparation of these facsimile leaves, for minute flaws and printing spots quite
                    incidental to Blake’s designs are reproduced with astonishing fidelity.
                    It would, in fact, serve little purpose to illustrate the two facsimile leaves
                    in their entirety here, since they would appear virtually indistinguishable from
                    originals. Some small details, however, are lost in the reproductions, most
                    noticeably the two small birds hovering in the sky on plate 9, between text and
                    tree boughs in the center of the plate.</p>
        <pb id="p16-215" n="215"/>
        <p>It has not proven possible to identify positively the copy (or copies) of <hi rend="i">America</hi>
from which these two facsimile leaves were made. Plate
                    4 in copy B shows certain affinities with that plate in copy F (British Museum
                    Print Room), which is uncolored, and which has been available since 1859. In
                    particular, the broken flourish of the top of letter “S” beginning
                    the text appears to be an identifying feature, as are other spots and printing
                    flaws. Such a close relationship does not appear between the facsimile of plate
                    9 and that plate in copy F, where there are distinct differences. The birds
                    beneath the tree boughs are absent in the facsimile, and other details of inking
                    also differ.</p>
        <p>When the dubious nature of plates 4 and 9 in copy B was pointed out to Robert N.
                    Essick, he informed me that in his Blake collection are impressions of the same
                    two plates, purchased by him as facsimiles. The ink, impression, and images are
                    identical to plates 4 and 9 in copy B. Essick acquired these leaves from the
                    London firm of antiquarian booksellers, Walter T. Spencer &amp; Co., in whose
                    stock they were found without further identification, and where it is believed
                    they had lain for many years.</p>
        <p>I have not been able to identify the maker of the two facsimile leaves in copy B.
                    The facsimiles were certainly made in England, where (if, indeed, it was the
                    model) copy F was available to scholars, collectors, and dealers during the
                    period of 1874-1878. I have no doubt that photographic services were available
                    at that time, although I have not examined the records of the British Library to
                    verify this. No known facsimilist of Blake’s works can be connected to
                    copy B.</p>
        <p>William Muir, the leading facsimilist of Blake, was active beginning only in the
                    1880s; in fact, no facsimiles of any of Blake’s works are known to date
                    from the 1870s. It appears that those involved with Blake’s illuminated
                    printing were less concerned with completing individual copies than they were in
                    making Blake’s works available to a wider audience (this in spite of the
                    fact that the reviewer of a Muir facsimile wrote in the <hi rend="i">Times</hi>
                    of 29 July 1886, “All the world does not admire Blake, but then
                    [Muir’s] edition of fifty copies is not for all the world”).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76" type="note">14</ref>
	<note id="n76"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Unnumbered advertising brochure of Blake
                        materials issued by Bernard Quaritch, dated Nov. 1886.</note></p>
        <p>It would be tempting to associate John Pearson, the first recorded dealer to
                    handle copy B, with the making of these facsimiles, as he is known to have been
                    responsible for various other facsimiles. Pearson was active in the London Book
                    trade from about 1870, and is known to have handled at least three copies of 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> between 1878 and 1896: he owned copy B in 1878, copy D
                    between 1886 and 1888 (he had difficulty in disposing of this copy, offering it
                    in catalogues for £52, later for £45, and finally auctioning it off
                    for £23 in 1888), and copy E in 1896. But evidence shows it is unlikely he
                    was involved with the facsimiles since they were both present in copy B when he
                    purchased it at auction in the Dew-Smith sale in 1878. If the shadowy sales of
                    1855 and 1874 could be identified, further light might be shed by the names of
                    sellers and purchasers. It would also be tempting to associate the firm of
                    Walter T. Spencer with the preparation of these facsimiles, since Essick
                    purchased his two leaves from their stock, and, as Bentley has shown, the firm
                    was responsible for the fraudulent coloring of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (L) and
                        <hi rend="i">America</hi> (Q).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77"
type="note">15</ref> In
                    collecting circles it is generally known that the firm was less than careful in
                    informing customers about the presence of facsimiles, and it handled a fair
                    number of works by Blake. However, no evidence connects Spencer with the
                    facsimiles in copy B; it is not known whether company records exist. 
<note id="n77"><hi rend="s">15</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Books</hi>, pp. 105-06.</note></p>
        <p>It is also somewhat obscure why these facsimile leaves were made, other than the
                    obvious desire to complete an imperfect copy. It seems unlikely to have been for
                    financial reasons, as the sums involved were never great. Copy B (uncolored)
                    sold for £16.5.0 in 1878, copy L (uncolored) sold for £21 in 1879,
                    copy R (colored) sold for £31.10.0 in 1880, and poor copy D finally fetched
                    £23 in 1888. One wonders if the relatively small sums merited the
                    production of what must have been expensive facsimiles. It is only possible to
                    surmise that an English dealer or collector was responsible for the facsimiles;
                    the fact that the two plates were nowhere described as facsimiles can only lead
                    one to the inescapable conclusion that they were intended to deceive.</p>
        <p>One further—and puzzling—inscription in copy B should be noted. On
                    the free front endpaper, an unidentified hand has written in now-smudged pencil,
                    “Lowndes gives 18 designs. There are two more in some copies but I
                    believe these to be supplementary numbers and that the book as published had
                    only 18.” No copy of <hi rend="i">America</hi> is known to have had more
                    than eighteen plates, nor are the three known proof plates likely to be what is
                    meant in the inscription.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78"
type="note">16</ref> They are unique
                    proofs, one heavily corrected by Blake, and must represent false starts on
                    Blake’s part: the images are much improved in the published versions.
                    There is, in fact, no copy of <hi rend="i">any</hi> of Blake’s work in
                    illuminated printing with twenty plates. While it might be argued that the
                    Sotheby cataloguer for the Dew-Smith sale incorporated this curious note in his
                    description for the catalogue, the above evidence demonstrating the insertion of
                    plates 4 and 9 make this unlikely. <note id="n78"><hi rend="s">16</hi> These
                        proofs are reproduced in David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Illuminated
                            Blake</hi> (New York: Doubleday, 1974), pp. 392-95.</note></p>
        <p>It thus appears that these two facsimile leaves, reproduced by a fundamentally
                    photographic process, were inserted in copy B of <hi rend="i">America</hi>
                    between 1874 and 1878 and have escaped detection by all owners and scholars
                    before identification by Joseph Viscomi and myself in 1978. The quality of
                    reproduction is so deceptive that the facsimiles went undetected in exhibitions
                    at the National Gallery (1913), Manchester (1914), Nottingham (1914), the
                    National Gallery of Scotland (1914), the Fogg exhibition (1930), the
                    Philadelphia exhibition (1939), and at various exhibitions at the Morgan
                    Library, including that of the Thorne Collection (1971), in the catalogue of
                    which both facsimile leaves were reproduced as genuine. One can only wonder what
                    other facsimiles have for so long remained undetected.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n114" type="note">17</ref>
	<note id="n114"><hi rend="s">17</hi> I would like to thank Herbert Cahoon,
                        Barbara Prince, and Lisa Vercollone for their assistance.</note></p>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p16-216" n="216" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
