<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.4.wilcox</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Howard T. Young, The Line in the Margin: Juan Ramón Jiménez and His Readings in
Blake, Shelley, and Yeats</title>
        <author n="Wilcox">John Wilcox</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1983</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Barbara Guth</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Adelheid M. Atkins</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>John Wilcox</name>
              <name>Carl Woodring</name>
              <name>Warren Keith Wright</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-4-0010">
        <div2>
          <pb id="p16-235" n="235"/>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              Howard T. Young. <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">The Line in the Margin: 
              Juan Ramón Jiménez and His Readings in Blake, Shelley, and Yeats.</hi></corr> 
              Madison: Univ. of Wisconsin Press, 1980. Pp. 384. $22.50.
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">John</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Wilcox</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Hispanists consider Juan Ramón Jiménez—the centenary of
                        whose birth on 23 December 1881 has just been celebrated—as a major
                        “modern” European poet. For English readers of poetry,
                        however, his cannot be a familiar name, and the appearance of a full-length
                        study of his readings in Shelley, Yeats, and Blake must come as something of
                        a surprise.</p>
          <p>The author, Howard Young, explored this aspect of Jiménez in earlier
                        research,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n108" type="note">1</ref> 
                        but here for the first
                        time he presents a host of hitherto unknown—and
                        inaccessible—details concerning Jiménez’s readings in
                        the English poets as well as his attempts to translate them into Spanish.
                        The new information Young painstakingly gathered from the Jiménez
                        archives (in Puerto Rico and in Spain) is used, in effect, to re-read Juan
                        Ramón’s poetry. We glimpse a Juan Ramón filtered
                        through the gaze of three English poets. The result is 
<pb id="p16-236" n="236"/>
						of indisputable value for Hispanists, especially those with
                        comparatist leanings. The result should also intrigue scholars who study the
                        English poets themselves, and they will certainly interest those of us who
                        believe that insufficient recognition has been given to the contribution
                        made by English Romanticism in the rise of “modern” European
                        poetry. <note id="n108"><hi rend="s">1</hi> “Anglo-American Poetry in
                            the Correspondence of Luisa and Juan Ramón
                            Jiménez,” <hi rend="i">Hispanic Review</hi>, 44 (1976),
                            1-26. See also, by Howard Young, <hi rend="i">Juan Ramón
                                Jiménez</hi>, Columbia Essays on Modern Writers No. 28 (New
                            York: Columbia University Press, 1967), and <hi rend="i">The Victorious
                                Expression: A Study of Four Contemporary Spanish Poets</hi>
                            (Madison: University of Wisconsin Press, 1966).</note></p>
          <p>Juan Ramón Jiménez (1881-1958) is perhaps better known to
                        English readers as a prose-writer. He is the author of <hi rend="i">Platero
                            and I</hi>,—a lyrical novel centering around the friendship that
                        develops between a lonely and impressionable young poet and his donkey on
                        their trips in and around the tiny Andalusian village of Moguer (where
                        Jiménez was born and where he resided until 1912). Though this book
                        has been translated into numerous languages, Jiménez’s
                        reception abroad as a poet is undoubtedly handicapped by the originality of
                        his style, the unique subtlety of which can be appreciated only in Spanish
                        (despite excellent English translations<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n109" type="note">2</ref>. Nor did Jiménez possess the ability—of a Neruda
                        or a Borges—to project himself onto an international audience. He
                        tended to withdraw to concentrate on his work (<hi rend="i">Obra</hi>, he
                        called it). He moved to Madrid in 1912, and in 1916 (in New York) married
                        Zenobia Camprubí Aymar, who was fluent in English and who always
                        assisted him with his English readings. Even in Madrid, the couple’s
                        life was quiet. Jiménez knew he wrote for a small audience, and in
                        fact dedicated his work “To the Immense Minority.” At the
                        outbreak of the Spanish Civil War, in 1936, they left Spain to live in North
                        America, Cuba, and Puerto Rico, where Jiménez concentrated on his
                        spiritual and aesthetic concerns. Though he won the Nobel Prize in 1956, his
                        wife’s death deprived him of the ability to enjoy it, and he himself
                        died two years later, a pathetic figure in exile in Puerto Rico. 
<note id="n109"><hi rend="s">2</hi> H. R. Hays, <hi rend="i">Selected Writings
                                of Juan Ramón Jiménez</hi> (New York: Farrar, Strauss
                            and Cudahy, 1957); Eloise Roach, <hi rend="i">J. R. J. Three Hundred
                                Poems, 1903-1953</hi> (Austin: University of Texas Press,
                            1962).</note></p>
          <p>Howard Young is able to show that Jiménez was reading Shelley, Yeats,
                        and Blake throughout these phases in his life. In fact, each move brought
                        with it renewed interest in English (and American) poetry. Young sees
                        Jiménez’s reading as an “attachment” and a
                        “lure” and claims that it moved him “beyond the horizon
                        of his Spanish and French literary inheritance to discover confirmation of
                        some of his basic ideas and to delight in a new tone and different
                        perspectives for evoking the ideals and mysteries that beguiled symbolist
                        poets.” To appreciate that claim, we need to know something about
                        Jiménez’s poetry and its historical situation.</p>
          <p>Juan Ramón’s first poems are termed <hi rend="i">modernista</hi> by Hispanic literary critics.
<hi rend="i">Modernismo</hi> is not at all what <hi rend="i">Modernism</hi> is in
                        the Anglo-American world. In general it is taken to be the style of the
                        latter part of the nineteenth century, a form of Art Nouveau (as Young
                        implies). It has certain similarities with “Aestheticism” and
                        “Pre-Raphaelitism” in England, and
                        “Parnassianism” and “Symbolism” in France.
                        Jiménez’s <hi rend="i">modernista</hi> poetry appeared in
                        1900, in two small volumes, <hi rend="i">Ninfeas (Waterlilies)</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Almas de violeta</hi> (<hi rend="i">Violet-souls</hi>); the
                        former were printed in green and the latter in purple ink. Here is a stanza
                        from the “Water-lilies’ Symphony”: “On the lake
                        of blood of my grieving soul, / from the melancholy garden of my weeping
                        soul; / on the lake of blood of a suspiring Love, / on which a most sad swan
                        entones a dying wail. . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n110"
type="note">3</ref> It
                        must come as little surprise to be told that Jiménez repudiated and
                        systematically destroyed these volumes in later life. The artificiality he
                        rejected, but the aesthetic idealism he internalized. His dominant style,
                        until around 1913, is that of a minor symbolist and impressionist. He is a
                        pantheistic lover of nature, a sentimental sensualist; he is self-absorbed
                        and withdrawn, and at times a bitterly disillusioned idealist. Toward the
                        end of this first period in his work, he wrote: “Even as we return
                        the golden moon is shining on the ramparts . . . / a breath of
                        flowers-cum-moon invades the countryside . . . , / the heart becomes
                        melodious and romantic . . . / / Even the love complete has a tragic
                        meaning; / in the gaze of impassioned eyes / the dream of life floats,
                        immense and nostalgic . . . / / we find slow hands in our hands . . . , / we
                        find breasts brushing against our arms, / we find mute lips on our lips . .
                        .” (<hi rend="i">PLP</hi> 1406). This poem is part of the section on
                            <hi rend="i">Melancolía (Melancholy</hi>, published in 1912)
                        dedicated to Louise Grimm de Muriedas, a cultivated North American who, as
                        Howard Young discovered, introduced Juan Ramón to the work of various
                        English poets. <note id="n110"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Juan Ramón
                            Jiménez, <hi rend="i">Primeros Libros de Poesía</hi>, ed.
                            Francisco Garfias, 3rd ed. (Madrid: Aguilar, 1967), p. 1467. Further
                            references are included in text and abbreviated as <hi rend="i">PLP</hi>
                            followed by page. Translations from Spanish are mine throughout the
                            text.</note></p>
          <p>Jiménez’s exposure to English (and American) poetry is
                        certainly one of the <corr type="emend">contributing</corr> factors to the stunning
change that
                        overcomes his work after 1913. The dreamy sentimentalism and self-indulgent
                        pessimism are gone, replaced by precision, deliberate control and cerebral
                        rigor. “Intelligence, give me / the exact name of things!”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n111" type="note">4</ref> is one of his more famous poems of
                        this time. It is as though Juan Ramón reacted utterly against his
                        former poetic personae. Instead of failure, he now encounters (in the figure
                        of his wife Zenobia) a love that is ideal: “All roses are the same
                        rose; / love!, the unique rose; / and all’s contained in it, / brief
                        image of the world, / love, the unique rose” (<hi rend="i">LP</hi>
                        909). He now sees in the real what was before considered eternally elusive.
                            <note id="n111"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Juan Ramón Jiménez,
                                <hi rend="i">Libros de Poesía</hi>, ed. Agustín
                            Caballero, 3rd ed. (Madrid: Aguilar, 1967), p. 553. Further references
                            are included in text and abbreviated as <hi rend="i">LP</hi> followed by
                            page.</note></p>
          <p>Jiménez acquired a reputation for the metaphysical (existential) reach
                        of his poetry. His <hi rend="i">Diario de un poeta reciencasado (Diary of a
                            poet newlywed</hi>, 1916) introduced into Hispanic poetry a poetic
                        subject struggling with the chaos and absurdity of contemporary life who
                        nevertheless quests for integration and harmony. We read the sea symbol in
                        his <hi rend="i">Diary</hi> as indicative of poetic thought at the beginning
                        of this “modern” age experiencing the disintegration of all
                        cherished values and ideals: “It seems, sea, that you’re
                        struggling / —oh endless disorder, unceasing iron!— / to find
                        yourself, or for me to find you” (<hi rend="i">LP</hi> 259).</p>
          <p>Jiménez acquired the reputation for being a fastidious elitist in
                        matters poetic. He is a “high-modern,” in the 
<pb id="p16-237" n="237"/>
manner of
Valéry (and Mallarmé) and Yeats. In
                        this persona, Juan Ramón sees himself as living only for his
                        poetry: “Poetry; dew / of each dawn, child / of each night”
                            (<hi rend="i">LP</hi> 881). He becomes an entity that creates, oblivious
                        to temporal flow: “To create myself, to recreate myself, to empty
                        myself, until / he who goes dead, from me, one day, / to earth, will not be
                        me” (<hi rend="i">LP</hi> 1003).</p>
          <p>Related to this ideal is Jiménez’s struggle to overcome his
                        fear of death (a frequent topic in the early poetry and one that brought him
                        much attention). Juan Ramón achieved renown by claiming “To
                        die is only to look within” (<hi rend="i">LP</hi> 899) and that
                        “Death is an ancient mother of ours, / our first mother, who loves us
                        through all others, century in, century out / and never, never forgets
                        us.” (<hi rend="i">LP</hi> 1088). The poet, in this second phase of
                        his work, appears to be in complete control of all he touches, the master of
                        his universe, and that, in general, is Jiménez’s reputation as
                        a poet today.</p>
          <p>There is, however, a third Jiménez, one that emerges more clearly in
                        the poetry written in exile after 1936. In this period, we hear, as Yeats
                        might have remarked, the voices of an ecstatic “saint”
                        alternating with those of a sceptic “hunchback.” The ecstatic
                        and visionary poetry is encountered in, for example, <hi rend="i">Animal de
                            Fondo (Animal of depth</hi>, 1949). The vision in the poem “Soy
                        animal de fondo” (“I’m an animal of
                        depth”)—an image Ezra Pound used in the <hi rend="i">Cantos</hi>—is one of
transcendence linked to temporal flow, an
                        immanent transcendence, of the beyond flourishing with the here and now.
                        These two “realities” fuse because the poet has cultivated
                        both throughout his lifetime. The poem begins: “ ‘In the depth
                        of air’ (I said) ‘I am’, / (I said) ‘I’m
                        an animal with depth of air’ (on land), / now on sea; shot through,
                        like air, by a sun / that’s a coal up there, my outside, and lights
                        up for me / with its coal my second destined ambit” (<hi rend="i">LP</hi> 1339).</p>
          <p>In competition with this ecstatic visionary is the sceptic, the doubter, who
                        in “Río-mar-desierto”
                        (“River-sea-desert”), after Shelley and Yeats, contemplates
                        with equanimity the “detaining of his wave” (“la ola
                        detenida”), who experiences the river of his life changing into
                        desert sand. But such philosophical resignation is absent in 1954, in the
                        “Third Fragment” of a long prose poem called <hi rend="i">Espacio (Space);</hi>
the poetic voice here cries to its consciousness:
                        “Doesn’t it pain you to leave me? . . . Didn’t you like
                        my life? I searched and found your essence for you. What substance can the
                        gods give to your essence that I couldn’t give you? I have already
                        told you: ‘The gods had no more substance than 
                        what I had.’ ”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n112"
type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n112"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Juan Ramón Jiménez, <hi rend="i">En el otro costado</hi>, ed. Aurora de
Albornoz (Madrid:
                            Júcar, 1974), pp. 82-83.</note></p>
          <p>The reader must surely hear Blake in these lines, and indeed this is one of
                        the topics Howard Young discusses in “The Substance of the
                        Gods,” one of the seven sections he devotes to his study of Blake in
                        Juan Ramón. Young is able to demonstrate that Blake’s impact
                        is still felt by what we termed the “third” Jiménez.
                        Shelley is more important in the first period of his work; then Yeats takes
                        over (Jiménez read Yeats’ essays on Shelley). Though Yeats is
                        present in the third phase, Young amply demonstrates the parallels with
                        Blake.</p>
          <p>Young’s study begins with Shelley because, as Young discovered,
                        Shelley was the first of the three that Juan Ramón read. He read him
                        in a Spanish translation, published by “the British hispanophile
                        Leonard Williams” in 1904, which contained <hi rend="i">A Defence of
                            Poetry</hi>, “On Love,” and “A Discourse on the
                        Manners of the Ancients Relative to the Subject of Love.” Young
                        analyzes the passages marked off by Juan Ramón, and he also discusses
                        his subsequent attempts to translate a few poems (e.g.
                        “Mutability” and “Hymn to Intellectual Beauty”).
                        Young’s thesis is that the Platonism of the <hi rend="i">Defence</hi>, together with
the Platonic idealism prevalent in contemporary
                        schools of Spanish philosophy, encouraged Jiménez to overcome his 
<hi rend="i">modernista</hi> heritage. Shelley is read as helping to
                        convince Juan Ramón that poetry is unquestionably the form
                        “Beauty” chooses to take in this world, and moreover, that the
                        poet, in the moment of the poem, sees “Beauty,” and therefore
                        “Good,” more clearly than any other sentient being.
                        Jiménez was dimly aware of these ideals when he first began writing,
                        as the “Water-lilies’ Symphony” (the first quatrain of
                        which is cited above) implies in the image of a poet suffering to create
                        Beauty and Love. Later, the idealism becomes clearer to him and he expresses
                        it more subtly, as a poem from <hi rend="i">Laberinto</hi> (published 1913)
                        reveals: “Like a quiet river, on the paper, the brow / reflects,
                        sadly, the words, / that vibrate in its heavens, like the golden notes / of
                        a labyrinth of bells. . . . ” Words have become musical notes that
                        form a vague piece of architecture that contains “something from the
                        beyond, that reaches life / along a path of nostalgia” (<hi rend="i">PLP</hi> 1273).
The style here more befits a symbolist, and the
                        idealism is recognizably Platonic.</p>
          <p>Howard Young shows that Shelley’s thoughts on love also impressed
                        Jiménez. He goes on to note that the Spanish poet shared
                        Shelley’s ideals about woman, and he proposes the fascinating
                        interpretation that the Spanish poet’s numerous maidens be read as
                        ideal projections of the elusive antitype. There is indeed an array of
                        “beloveds” in Juan Ramón’s early phase, and to
                        read them as a desire to fill the vacuum within, to suggest that they are
                        part of the narcissistic search for the “other,” is to
                        stimulate future readings of the poet’s work.</p>
          <p>In addition, Young maintains that Shelley’s transcendental attitude
                        toward love, in a “Discourse on the Manner . . . ,” would have
                        helped free Jiménez from the “unadulterated sensuality”
                        that was part of his poetic patrimony (through the Nicaraguan, Rubén
                        Darío) but with which Jiménez never felt at ease. Young also
                        suggests that in Jiménez’s poetry there is a development of
                        the “veiled maiden” symbol; the veils are removed and
                        “ideal nakedness,” not disillusion, is experienced. At the end
                        of one of his famous poems “Vino, primero, pura, / <pb id="p16-238" n="238"/>
vestida de inocencia” (“She came, first, pure, /
                        dressed in innocence”), whose parellels with Yeats’s “A
                        Coat” are taken up later by Young, the poet exclaims: “And she
                        took off her tunic, / and appeared completely naked . . . / O passion of my
                        life, naked / poetry, mine forever!” (<hi rend="i">LP</hi> 555). This
                        “lifelong quest for the spirit of beauty,” Young notes,
                        reaches a “joyous conclusion” in <hi rend="i">Animal of
                            depth.</hi></p>
          <p>If Juan Ramón’s interest in Shelley faded around 1920, his
                        fascination with Yeats and Blake increased. Yeats, of course, was more or
                        less a contemporary, and Jiménez certainly considered him, with
                        reverence, as a peer whose interests were compatible (witness their
                        enthusiasm for Tagore). Jiménez bought and read Yeats’s
                        dramas, his essays and his poems. He read them in English with the help of
                        his wife, who translated Yeats’s early plays into Spanish with
                        Yeats’s permission. (Nothing was ever published, but <hi rend="i">The
                            Countess Cathleen</hi> survives.) Jiménez himself translated
                        about a dozen poems, some of which were published (in the 1940s). Juan
                        Ramón liked a little known “Preface” Yeats wrote for
                        three of his plays, and adapted from it the notion of “spontaneous
                        simplicity” when he was trying to explain his own “naked
                        poetry.” For Jiménez, “spontaneous simplicity”
                        is captured in art only after prolonged and intensive reworking.</p>
          <p>Like Yeats, Jiménez was fascinated by the “rose” and its
                        connotative power. Young shows that he knew “The Rose of All the
                        World” and Yeats’ essay on “Magic.”
                        Jiménez used the rose much more extensively than Yeats but was never
                        as committed to the occult (despite, as Young has discovered, being a
                        sensitive medium when he was a student). In later life Jiménez would
                        refer to “Destiny,” and Young shows that Yeats discussed this
                        in <hi rend="i">Per Amica Silentia Lunae</hi>, a work the Spanish poet knew.
                        Jiménez must in fact have read more of Yeats than we can know (that
                        is, more than his libraries hold today). He cites from “Crazy Jane
                        Talks to the Bishop,” for instance, in <hi rend="i">Space</hi>, but
                        we have no record of his having read this poem. “Love in the palace
                        of excrement” is how he recalled the lines, as though they had been
                        transfixed in his mind for some time. My own suspicion is that the impact
                        Yeats made was stronger than Young would allow in his study.</p>
          <p>But with Blake, Young’s perspective broadens—he sees
                        Jiménez as bringing to a conclusion, in the 1950s, the tradition of
                        the poet as visionary humanist, which Blake began at the dawn of the
                        nineteenth century. Young writes that “Blake is the Modern prophet of
                        the imagination divine, who also worshipped <hi rend="i">lo desnudo</hi>
                        (the naked),” and adds that “Just as Blake signals the opening
                        of modern phase of this tradition of the poet qua divinity, so the <hi rend="i">dios
deseado y deseante</hi> (god desired and desiring)
                        announces its conclusion. For as Pablo Neruda said in Stockholm some twenty
                        years after the publication of <hi rend="i">Animal of depth</hi>, “El
                        poeta no es un ‘pequeño dios.’ ” [“Poets
                        are not ‘little gods.’”] For this reason, Young offers
                        in his final sixty pages a comparison of parallel concerns in Jiménez
                        and Blake.</p>
          <p>Young acknowledges that Jiménez would have been a naive reader of
                        Blake, as he could not have deciphered the symbolism. Despite this, he
                        “carefully read nearly all the lyrical canon of Blake,”
                        beginning around 1916 with Quiller-Couch’s <hi rend="i">Oxford
                            Book</hi>, and continuing in 1927 when the Cambridge Hispanist J. B.
                        Trend gave him Blake’s collected poetry and prose. Young shows that
                        Juan Ramón translated “The Tyger,” “To the
                        Muses,” “A Poison Tree,” “The Sick Rose,”
                        and “The Little Black Boy,” as well as intending to translate
                        two dozen or more (including nothing less than <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
                            Heaven and Hell</hi> and <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
                            Albion</hi>). We also learn that Juan Ramón valued Blake’s
                        “bold nudes” and that on a copy of “The Temptation of
                        Eve” he wrote “Influencia de Blake” (“Influence
                        of Blake”).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n113"
type="note">6</ref> Jiménez
                        himself drew nude figures and found in the naked woman a symbol of complete
                        fulfillment. <note id="n113"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Jiménez’s
                            “Temptation of Eve” was a black and white reproduction of
                            this water color, which he cut from <hi rend="i">The New York Times Book
                                Review</hi>, 20 Nov. 1927, p. 2. In his discussion of the nude
                            figure, Young refers to “Glad Day,” “Urizen
                            Creating” and “Albion Adoring the Crucified Christ”
                            (pp. 220-30). He also notes that Jiménez had a copy of Philippe
                            Soupault’s 1928 study <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, which
                            contains “fifty plates with a wide range of samples from
                            Blake’s production.”</note></p>
          <p>For Hispanists, all of this information is novel. It was known that
                        Jiménez translated a few poems and made a few references to Blake,
                        but the extent of his interest is astounding. It confirms, at least for this
                        reader, a point that Howard Young is tacitly making: that Jiménez was
                        far too original a poet to remain satisfied with his own
                        “latin” poetic tradition (Jiménez’s word). His
                        passion for exploring this alien tradition—Young is more circumspect,
                        for, as we noted, he calls it an “attachment”—was
                        dictated by his need to survive as a poet. His Spanish and French literary
                        inheritance stifled him, and he discovered in the “northern”
                        lyric (his word) sufficient inspiration to keep him alive poetically. The
                        “anxiety of influence” begins to take on strange proportions.
                        We mention only the poets, but there are the real individuals from this
                        alien tradition who also contributed in their incidental ways: Leonard
                        Williams, Louise Grimm, and J. B. Trend we have mentioned; and there was
                        also Lennox Robinson (the director of the Abbey Theatre after Yeats).</p>
          <p>Literary history must yield to literary criticism, and that is how the book
                        ends. Young compares Blake and Jiménez, to show, I think, that
                        Jiménez is unjustly underrated as a European “modern.”
                        Juan Ramón shared with Blake the belief that “imagination is
                        all.” He held this idealism until the last years of his life. He
                        shared with Blake, especially in his later work, “God desired and
                        desiring,” the experience of Eternity in the here and now, not in
                        some “indefinite heaven of Platonic abstraction.” As in Blake,
                        Young notes, in Jiménez the “childlike” forms an
                        integral part of his final vision, into which, notes Young, Juan
                        Ramón incorporates the “innocence, freshness, and suspicion of
                        divinity . . . that clings to children.” As far as nakedness is
                        concerned, Young argues that though the naked human body is put to similar
                        symbolic use by Jiménez, the Spanish poet was never as comfortable
                        with it as Blake was. And finally, in discussing Blake’s conviction
                        that the human mind itself creates that which is divine, Young refers to
                        Juan Ramón’s cry 
<pb id="p16-239" n="239"/>
that “The
                        gods had no more substance than what I have” and argues that in his
                        later work Jiménez is struggling to integrate such apocalyptic
                        humanism with his earlier and deeply entrenched Platonism. Though we at
                        times see him as “shoring fragments against his ruins,” we
                        also see, with Young, Juan Ramón bringing to a successful conclusion
                        Blake’s prophecies that art is a religion, that the artist’s
                        is a divine calling, that the human form be glorified and life deified, and
                        that man encounter paradise, discover immanent and transcendent gods, within
                        the human mind.</p>
          <p>Juan Ramón Jiménez was perhaps the first European in this
                        century to discover Blake’s importance. The Spanish surrealists in
                        the 1920s saw Blake as a surrealist, and Jiménez argued against this
                        view. Students of Blake today might be intrigued by what they see as
                        Jiménez’s “misreading” of their poet, but
                        students of Jiménez, especially those who see him as much more than a
                        “Peninsular” poet, will be long in debt to Howard Young for
                        this challenging reassessment of a poet who deserves to be read with the
                        major European “moderns” of this century.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
