<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.4.bindman</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">An Afterword on William Blake: His Art and Times</title>
        <author n="Bindman">David Bindman</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1983</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Barbara Guth</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Adelheid M. Atkins</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>John Wilcox</name>
              <name>Carl Woodring</name>
              <name>Warren Keith Wright</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
      <pb id="p16-224" n="224"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-4-0009">
        <head>
          <title type="section"><hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">DISCUSSION</hi></hi></title>
          <title type="section-subtitle"><hi rend="i">with intellectual spears &amp; long winged arrows of
thought</hi></title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">An Afterword on <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Art and
                            Times</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>By <docAuthor>David <name>Bindman</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>One of the frustrations and delights of putting on an exhibition is that
                        objects can look different from one’s memory of them when seen
                        together on the walls. It is, of course, part of the raison
                        d’être of such exhibitions that they enable direct comparisons
                        to be made, but they also inevitably make the catalogue, which has to be
                        written many months before the exhibition, out of date, for it cannot
                        include the experience of the exhibition itself. The following notes are
                        intended as corrections to the text and observations arising from the
                        exhibition, and they center largely around the large color prints.</p>
          <p>Martin Butlin’s very recent discovery of an 1804 watermark on the Tate
                        version of the <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> color print (cat. no. 56b) has
                        already demolished the received picture of the chronology and development of
                        the large color prints, some of which are dated 1795. The presence of seven
                        of these prints in the exhibition from various sources offers a useful
                        opportunity to start thinking about them again and I am glad to report some
                        progress. It was clear from seeing the prints together that we have to
                        abandon any sense of a rigid method in their creation; there was no one way
                        of making them and we should see their creation as part of an organic
                        process of trial and error over a number of years. This is brought home by
                        the discovery of Mr. Patrick Noon, Curator of Prints and Drawings at the
                        Yale Center for British Art, that there are definite indications of printing
                        from a relief-etched copper plate on the Metropolitan Museum’s
                        impression of <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi> (cat. no. 51). This has
                        been confirmed by microscopic examination which revealed clear signs of
                        indentation in the printed area and broken fibres around it consistent with
                        pressure from a metal plate. The relief-etched areas, printed in gray, form
                        a kind of broad underdrawing defining the main shapes of the figures, like
                        the relief-etched areas in some of the plates from <hi rend="i">The Book of
                            Urizen</hi> which were color printed. The discovery of relief-etched
                        printing also provides an explanation of the mysterious letters observed on
                        the surface of the New York impression, which appear to be the imprint of
                        part of an embossed address of the kind often found on the back of copper
                        plates; Blake has evidently used the back of a copper plate to make the
                        relief-etched underprinting and not bothered to burnish down the
                        platemaker’s imprint.</p>
          <p>This strongly suggests that <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi> was the first
                        of the large color prints to be worked on and that at first Blake simply
                        extended the method he had employed for color printing the illuminated books
                        by using a very much larger copper plate. We may surmise that he would have
                        found relief etching on this size of plate to be time consuming and
                        difficult and therefore not worth the labor: certainly none of the other
                        color prints shows any signs of such relief etching but only the direct
                        application of color from an unetched surface. There is every likelihood
                        that he began working on these problems in 1795 when he was probably
                        finishing the last of the color-printed illuminated books; on the other hand
                        the watermark on the Tate <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> proves that he was
                        working with a color-printing method as late as 1804, when he was preparing
                        a set of the prints for Thomas Butts. The little known Glen Foerd version of
                        the <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> is also in the exhibition (cat. no. 56), and it
                        is clear that the two versions are quite different in handling, and that
                        there are arguments for seeing the Glen Foerd version as predating the Tate
                        version by several years. The differences between the two figures of
                        Newton—the angle of the head, the contour of the back, the
                        relationship of the feet to each other and the angle of the
                        hands—make it unlikely that they were printed from the same surface:
                        it is probable that Blake made a fresh start with the Tate version,
                        presumably to complete the set for Thomas Butts. The differences are
                        compatible with a space of many years between the two versions, and perhaps
                        with the change of style in Blake’s art in the years around 1800.</p>
          <p>These changes certainly involve a stronger linearity which can be seen in the
                        Tate version in the more incisive contour, and the reduction of broken lines
                        of varied thickness, but the most striking differences are in the modeling.
                        The forms in the Glen Foerd version are built up with a simple plasticity,
                        shadowing from the lower contour leaving the main area without interior
                        modeling. The Tate version, on the other hand, has a high degree of
                        definition within the larger forms so that it is possible to discern the
                        segmentation of the muscles and sense the shape of bone and cartilage
                        beneath. This is achieved in the figure of Newton by a stippling technique
                        applied almost exclusively in watercolor, and it is possible to see here an
                        analogy with the 1803 watercolor in the exhibition of <hi rend="i">St. Paul
                            preaching</hi> (cat. no. 75). This technique may derive from
                        Blake’s experience as a miniature painter, as Raymond Lister has
                        suggested. The background in the Glen Foerd version is defined by dark
                        washes but in the Tate version it is filled with an intense blue color; in
                        fact color pervades all the darker areas of the later print and the modeling
                        of the figure also picks up the blue from the background. <pb id="p16-225" n="225"/>
The curious aqueous anemone-like effect in the vegetation of
                        the Tate version is not present in the Glen Foerd version where Newton is
                        clearly in a cave through which light passes from the top left.</p>
          <p>There are also clear differences in the way the color printing is applied; in
                        the Glen Foerd <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> it has a thick and pasty quality,
                        applied in broad dabs with occasional areas of aqueous reticulation as if
                        the pressure was applied fairly gently from the printing surface. In the
                        Tate Gallery version the color printing seems more controlled and
                        concentrated in specific areas like the rocky background. The lack of the
                        fluid kind of reticulation led me at first to wonder if it was color printed
                        at all and built up instead with a dabber in the thicker areas, but this
                        does not seem likely on further examination. The thickness and density of
                        the Glen Foerd color printing aligns it with the Whitney <hi rend="i">Good
                            and Evil Angels</hi> (cat. no. 53) and I would propose that these two
                        and the Metropolitan <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi> can be dated to
                        about 1795. The <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> (cat. no. 52) and the <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi>
(cat. no. 55) from the Tate, however, present more
                        difficult problems. There can be no doubt from a comparison with the Tate
                            <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> that they were at least finished off in 1804-05
                        for sale to Thomas Butts, but the quality of the color printing underneath,
                        as far as it can be discerned under the final stippled coloring, seems to
                        have the density of the presumed 1795 prints. It is still arguable, then,
                        that these were, as was always thought, printed in 1795 and then finished
                        finally in 1804-05 for Butts. If this is right then it would suggest that
                        when Butts commissioned a set of the prints Blake had a mixed group of
                        impressions of the color prints lying about the studio, most of which could
                        be adapted into a harmonious set while others, including the <hi rend="i">Newton</hi>
for reasons unknown, had to be made anew. This is probably
                        as far as we can go at the moment but we will be able to fill out the
                        account when the other Tate color prints are examined more closely.</p>
          <p>Herewith a few notes on other things in the show:</p>
          <p>Cat. no. 2. <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea</hi> engraving (Trinity College,
                        Hartford, Ct.). This appears to be a more interesting object than I first
                        thought. Apart from touches of wash it has small areas of scraping out, and
                        most unexpected, what appears to be the expressive use of plate tone on the
                        surface to give a greater richness of texture. If this is deliberate then it
                        suggests the use of yet another printing technique by Blake, and one that
                        was hardly ever used in his time. The use of scraping out suggests a date in
                        the 1820s; it is also used in the Mellon copy of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, pl.
99.</p>
          <p>44. <hi rend="i">Europe a Prophecy</hi>, copy A. I had hinted in the
                        catalogue that there might be something wrong with the coloring of this
                        copy, and I am now fully persuaded that most of the color washes, apart from
                        the color printing, have been added by a later hand, perhaps in this
                        century.</p>
          <p>70. <hi rend="i">The Virgin Hushing the Young John the Baptist.</hi> Though a
                        laboratory report states that this work is on paper it looks as if it is on
                        canvas; certainly the weave is very strongly visible. Perhaps it is on very
                        thin paper applied wet to the canvas?</p>
          <p>79. <hi rend="i">The Repose of the Holy Family in Egypt.</hi> Though magical
                        in quality and drawing this watercolor can be seen to be very badly
                        faded.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
