<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.4.viscomi</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Facsimile or Forgery? An Examination of America, Plates 4 and 9, Copy B</title>
        <author n="Viscomi">Joseph Viscomi</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1983</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Barbara Guth</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Adelheid M. Atkins</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>John Wilcox</name>
              <name>Carl Woodring</name>
              <name>Warren Keith Wright</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-4-0008">
        <pb id="p16-219" n="219"/>
        <head>
          <title type="main">Facsimile or Forgery? An Examination of <hi rend="i">America</hi>, Plates
                        4 and 9, Copy B</title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">JOSEPH</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">VISCOMI</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>In 1927 the copy of Blake’s <hi rend="i">America</hi> we now know as copy
                    L was sold as a “facsimile reprint” for £4, though it is
                    quite genuine.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79" type="note">1</ref> It
is not unheard of for an
                    original work of art to be sold as a facsimile, but it is certainly more common
                    for a facsimile to be sold as an original. The authenticity of plates 4 and 9 of
                        <hi rend="i">America</hi> copy B, in the Pierpont Morgan Library, has never
                    been doubted in print. But in fact neither one is an original impression.
                    Although both are facsimiles photomechanically reproduced on wove paper, very
                    little about either image appears suspicious. Indeed, both are reproduced in 
<hi rend="i">The Blake Collection of Mrs. Landon K. Thorne.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n80" type="note">2</ref> The true technical and historical origins
                    of plates 4 and 9 are not easily identified. What information we have is
                    supplied only from the plate measurements and foliation, the binding, and the
                    inscription on the front flyleaf of copy B. From these few facts, and with much
                    caution, we can begin to speculate about who executed the plates, when, how, and
                    why. <note id="n79"><hi rend="s">1</hi> G.E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Books</hi> (Oxford: Oxford Univ. Press, 1977), p. 104.</note>
	<note id="n80"><hi rend="s">2</hi> G.E. Bentley, Jr. (New York: Pierpont Morgan
                        Library, 1971), plates IX and XI. <hi rend="i">America</hi>, copy B, was
                        given to the Morgan Library by Mrs. Thorne in 1973. For the complete
                        provenance of copy B, see <hi rend="i">Thorne Catalogue</hi>, p. 26, or 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 100.</note></p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="i">Plate Measurements</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Plates 4 and 9 are printed on the same paper, the feel, weight, and texture
                        of which are, from the verso, noticeably different from the other sheets in
                        the book. The paper—which called to mind Murillo, an etching paper I
                        had printed on before—and not the image, made me suspicious enough to
                        check some measurements.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81"
type="note">3</ref> As in most
                        copies of <hi rend="i">America</hi>, the last four lines of plate 4 have
                        been masked out. Unlike all other copies, however, the bottom platemark is
                        only 2.4 cm. from Orc’s foot, instead of the usual 4.1 cm. If this
                        bottom platemark were caused by the material used to mask out the four
                        lines, then, because 2.4 cm. is not wide enough, half of line 3 and all of
                        line 4 would have printed. If this were the platemark of an authentic
                        impression, then Blake’s plate had been cut in about the middle of
                        the third line, a possibility not yet to be ruled out since the plate could
                        have been pulled posthumously and there is precedent for such plate
                            tampering.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82"
type="note">4</ref> To make sure I was not
                        looking at a late impression or posthumous pull, I also checked the distance
                        in plate 4 from the top platemark to Orc’s toe: 19.5 cm. in copies A
                        and L, but 20.4 cm. in copy B. In plate 9, the distance from the top
                        platemark to the first line is 11.6 cm. in copy L, but 12.0 cm. in copy B;
                        from the bottom of the text to the bottom platemark is 8.4 cm. in copies A
                        and L, but 9.15 cm. in copy B. Because the relation of image to platemark
                        did not check out, I measured the distance between parts within the image.
                        For example, line 4 of plate 4 is 12.6 cm. long in copies A and L, but 13.0
                        cm. in copy B. Line 7 of plate 9 is 11.5 cm. long in copies A and L, but
                        11.9 in copy B.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83"
type="note">5</ref> More revealing than
                        incorrect measurements within the image and between image and platemarks,
                        however, are the plate measurements themselves. Plate 4 of copy B is 22.9
                        × 16.9 cm. vs. 23.8 × 16.6 cm., and plate 9 of copy B is 24.9
                        × 17.5 cm. vs. 23.5 × 16.8 cm.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84"
type="note">6</ref> These and other differences are too great to have been the
                        result of one paper shrinking less than the others. Damp printing paper
                        shrinks only 1 to 2.5% of the sheet size,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n85" type="note">7</ref> which could not, for example, account for the 1.4 cm.
                        difference between the length of plate 9 of copy B (24.9 cm.) and of copy A
                        (23.5 cm.). <note id="n81"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Thomas Lange, the assistant
                            curator in charge of books and prints at the Pierpont Morgan Library in
                            1978, also noticed the difference in paper and suspected the two plates.
                            Bentley seems to have been a bit puzzled by the difference too, but
                            noted only that plate 9 was printed on “stiffer paper than the
                            rest” (<hi rend="i">Thorne Catalogue</hi>, p. 26).</note>
	<note id="n82"><hi rend="s">4</hi> In the posthumous pull of “The
                            Little Black Boy” (pl. 9), the woman’s bun was removed and
                            her back narrowed with a burin. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (U)
                            contains such a pull, though it is recorded as an extra impression 
(<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 366). See “Posthumous Pulls in
                                <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, copy U”
                            (forthcoming).</note>
	<note id="n83"><hi rend="s">5</hi> These and a list of other measurements
                            concerning plates 4 and 9 of copy B have been corroborated—and
                            corrected—by Robert N. Essick, who has copies of both facsimiles
                            in his collection, and who has been most generous in sharing
                            information. He and G.E. Bentley, Jr. have read early drafts of this
                            paper and have made valuable suggestions, many of which have been
                            incorporated in this final version.</note>
	<note id="n84"><hi rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Books</hi>, p. 70.</note>
	<note id="n85"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Philip Gaskell, <hi rend="i">A New
                                Introduction to Bibliography</hi> (Oxford: Oxford Univ. Press,
                            1972), p. 13.</note></p>
          <p>Except for the platemarks, plates 4 and 9 are free of the embossment that is
                        characteristic of a relief etching, or a process block. Instead, the ink
                        lies flat on the paper, which is characteristic of lithography. The
                        platemarks are themselves suspicious, as I’ll explain later, and do
                        not positively identify the kind of lithography used. But whether these
                        impressions were pulled from stone or metal plates, whether produced from a
                        transfer or directly from a reverse negative, one thing is certain: they are
                        photolithographs. The proportion of the parts to each other is correct,
                        which indicates the work of a camera. But compared to the originals, the
                        overall dimensions are slightly distorted, or elongated, which indicates
                        either the slight distortion in the negative caused by the camera lens or in
                        the contact between the transfer paper and the stone. In any event, with a
                        photomechanically reproduced image, a good solid black ink (and not the
                        thinner greyish black of tonal lithography), an impression that has been
                        touched up in black water color (like the other prints in copy B), and
                        platemarks, it is little wonder that these two plates have escaped
                        detection.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="i">Plate Numbers</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p><hi rend="i">America</hi> copy B was stabbed through two different sets of
                        three holes. Plates 4 and 9, however, have no stab holes, though both plates
                        are numbered. Copy B has two sets of 
      <pb id="p16-217" n="217"/>
        <figure n="america.b.p4" id="america.b.illbk.04" work-copy="america.b" rend="db" width="809" height="1000">
			<figTranscr>Silent as despairing love, and strong as jealousy,<lb/>
			The hairy shoulders rend the links, free are the wrists of fire;<lb/>
			Round the terrific loins he siez’d the panting struggling womb;<lb/>
			It joy’d: she put aside her clouds &amp; smiled her first-born smile;<lb/>
			As when a black cloud shews its light’nings to the silent deep,<lb/>
			Soon as she saw the terrible boy then burst the virgin cry.<lb/>
			I know thee, I have found thee, &amp; I will not let thee go;<lb/>
			Thou art the image of God who dwells in darkness of Africa:<lb/>
			And thou art fall’n to give me life in regions of dark death.<lb/>
			On my American plains I feel the struggling afflictions<lb/>
			Endur’d by roots that writhe their arms into the nether deep:<lb/>
			I see a serpent in Canada, who courts me to his love;<lb/>
			In Mexico an Eagle, and a Lion in Peru;<lb/>
			I see a Whale in the South-sea, drinking my soul away.<lb/>
			O what limb rending pains I feel, thy fire &amp; my frost<lb/>
			Mingle in howling pains, in furrows by thy lightnings rent;<lb/>
			This is eternal death; and this the torment long foretold.</figTranscr>
			<head><hi rend="i">America</hi>, Copy B, plate 4.</head>
			<figDesc>Courtesy of the Pierpont Morgan Library, Thorne Collection.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p16-218" n="218"/>
        <figure n="america.b.p9" id="america.b.illbk.09" work-copy="america.b" rend="db" width="730" height="1000">
			<figTranscr>In thunders ends the voice. Then Albions Angel wrathful burnt<lb/>
			Beside the Stone of Night; and like the Eternal Lions howl<lb/>
			In famine &amp; war, reply’d. Art thou not Orc, who serpent-form’d<lb/>
			Stands at the gate of Enitharmon to devour her children;<lb/>
			Blasphemous Demon, Antichrist, hater of Dignities;<lb/>
			Lover of wild rebellion. and transgresser of Gods Law;<lb/>
			Why dost thou come to Angels eyes in this terrific form?</figTranscr>
			<head><hi rend="i">America</hi>, Copy B, plate 9.</head>
			<figDesc>Courtesy of the Pierpont Morgan Library, Thorne Collection.</figDesc>
        </figure>
<pb id="p16-220" n="220"/>
numbers:
                        1-16 and 1-18. Both sets are in pencil and start on plate 1, and neither set
                        is by Blake or C.H. Tatham, the first owner of copy B.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86" type="note">8</ref> Numbers 1-16 are written just below the platemark on
                        the left hand side; numbers 1-18 are written at the top right corner of the
                        leaf. Plates 4 and 9 are the two plates not in the 1-16 sequence, which
                        indicates that 1-16 is the set of numbers first given to the plates.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n87" type="note">9</ref> Plates 4 and 9 are numbered in set II,
                        and just below “4” and “9” is a
                            “7”.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n88" type="note">10</ref>
That plates 4
                        and 9 are not included in the first set of numbers, and that neither sheet
                        has stab holes, suggest that copy B had for a time only sixteen plates to
                        number and stitch. <note id="n86"><hi rend="s">8</hi> On the verso of the
                            frontispiece is the inscription: “From the author/C H Tatham Octr
                            7/1799.” Presumably this is Tatham’s hand; it is not
                            Blake’s. In any case, the “7” and “9”
                            do not resemble the “7” and “9” in either
                            set of numbers. Blake did number two copies of <hi rend="i">America</hi>
                            (A and M) 1-16, but he started on plate 3, not plate 1, and numbered, as
                            was his custom, in the right hand corner of the plate in ink.</note>
	<note id="n87"><hi rend="s">9</hi> The numbers of set I may not, however,
                            have been the first attempt at pagination. Numbers 4, 5, 7, and 11 of
                            set I are written over other numbers, or marks, that were erased;
                            numbers 6 and 8 are very light, and a 7-like mark is written over the
                            3.</note>
	<note id="n88"><hi rend="s">10</hi> The “7” is the same size
                            (.6 cm.) and in the same position (2 cm.) from the edge of the sheet,
                            right under the number). In plate 4, the bottom of the number is partly
                            erased, or smudged. There is a larger smudge mark just under the
                            “7” on plate 9. This “7” may be a
                            printer’s mark rather than a number.</note></p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="i">Binding</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p><hi rend="i">America</hi> was “splendidly bound in Citron
                        morocco” when it sold in 1878 with the library of A.G. Dew-Smith at
                        Sotheby’s for £16.5 (lot 247) to John Pearson. According to the
                        Sotheby catalogue, copy B sold in 1874, unbound, for £18. Being bound
                        by 1878 would seem to imply that the facsimiles were executed before this
                        date, but this is not necessarily the case, because plates 4 and 9 are not
                        in the binding but are tipped in. They are glued to plates 5 and 10, are
                        without gilding, and are slightly lower than the rest of the pages,
                        noticeable only when looking along the foreedge. The facsimiles enter after,
                        not before, the binding.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n89"
type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n89"><hi rend="s">11</hi> The pages were trimmed before insertion.
                            The two leaves are slightly lower at the top, and less so at the bottom.
                            They appear flush with the fore-edge, but are actually a fraction lower,
                            noticeable when the fore-edge is riffled.In short, plates 4 and 9 were
                            cut and trimmed separate from the other sheets.</note></p>
          <p>The tipping-in of plates 4 and 9 indicates that one of the owners after 1878
                        could also have been responsible for their execution and insertion. Three of
                        these owners had access to facsimilists and to models, and had reason enough
                        to complete an incomplete copy. John Pearson, the bookseller, published the
                        excellent <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> facsimiles with 100 photolithographs
                        in 1877, and was William Muir’s first agent, issuing four of
                        Muir’s Blake facsimiles in 1884-85. Bernard Quaritch, who owned the
                        book in 1890, was Muir’s agent in 1885-94, and issued a series of
                        facsimiles by William Griggs from his own and other collections, including
                            <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (1890) and <hi rend="i">The Book of
                            Ahania</hi> (1892). He also owned another copy of <hi rend="i">America</hi> (R),
which he lent Muir for his 1887 facsimile. Bernard
                        Macgeorge, who owned the copy from 1892 to 1924, also knew Muir; Macgeorge
                        lent Muir <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> copy A, which was then missing five
                        plates, and which were “all supplied in facsimile by
                            Muir.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n90" type="note">12</ref>
Macgeorge also owned
                            <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy A, which entered the British Museum in
                            1927<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n91" type="note">13</ref>
with photolithographs of
                        plates 51, 52, 53, and b. <note id="n90"><hi rend="s">12</hi><hi rend="i"> A Catalogue
of the Library of Bernard Buchanan
                                Macgeorge</hi> (privately printed, 1906), p. 8.</note>
	<note id="n91"><hi rend="s">13</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Books</hi>, p. 412. The only owner after 1878 whom we
                            cannot suspect is Thomas Gaisford, the Greek scholar, and a major Blake
                            collector (<hi rend="i">Thorne Catalogue</hi>, p. 14). Gaisford died in
                            1855, yet his bookplate is pasted on the inside of the front board,
                            which is why Keynes and Bentley have assumed that <hi rend="i">America</hi> (B)
was “acquired by Gaisford” after it
                            was bound, and between Pearson, who bought it at Sotheby’s in
                            1878, and Quaritch, who bought it from Gaisford’s library, which
                            sold at Sotheby’s 23 April 1890. We do not know who acquired 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> (B) for Gaisford’s library, when, from
                            whom, or for how much. There are other Blake books with
                            Gaisford’s bookplate, four of which may have been acquired before
                            1855 (<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> [H], <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> [E], 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> [C], <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> [N]),
                            and at least three, besides <hi rend="i">America</hi> (B), acquired
                            after 1874 (<hi rend="i">Visions</hi> [I], <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> [M],
                                <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> [C]). Apparently, someone familiar with the
                            collector’s taste in books continued to build the
                        library.</note></p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="i">The Inscription</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Before eliminating suspects, we must examine a pencil inscription on the
                        front flyleaf: 
						<q> Lowndes [pens?] 18 designs<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n92" type="note">14</ref><lb/>
 There are 2 more in some copies<lb/>
 but I believe
                            these to be a supplementary number<lb/>
 &amp; that the book is perfect
                            &amp; is only 18 <note id="n92"><hi rend="s">14</hi> “<hi rend="i">America</hi>,
a Prophecy, 18 designs, Folio, Lambeth,
                                1793, Sotheby’s, 1855, <hi rend="i">£
                                    2.7</hi>”—<hi rend="i">W.T. Lowndes, The
                                    Bibliographer’s Manual of English Literature</hi> (1857),
                                I, 215.</note></q>
Assuming “is only 18” refers back to
                        “designs” and not to £18, the price the 1878 Sotheby
                        catalogue says it sold for in 1874, the inscription can still be read in one
                        of two ways, depending on whether “designs” refers to pictures
                        or pages. In the Prospectus, Blake uses the word “design” to
                        mean picture, not plate or page.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n93"
type="note">15</ref>
                        <hi rend="i">America</hi>, minus plates 4 and 9, would still have eighteen
                        designs if, as Blake himself did with the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, one
                        were to separately count the top and bottom pictures on two plates as
                        separate designs. By counting in this way, there would, indeed, be
                        “some copies” with “2 more” designs, whereas in
                        fact there are no copies with twenty plates. If, on the other hand,
                        “designs” is referring to pages, then the inscription is
                        referring to a copy in which the two facsimiles have already been inserted,
                        a copy, in other words, with eighteen plates. In this second interpretation,
                        the statement “There are 2 more in some copies” is probably a
                        reference to Gilchrist’s description of <hi rend="i">America</hi> as
                        “a folio of 20 pages.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n94"
type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n93"><hi rend="s">15</hi> In the Prospectus, Blake says that <hi rend="i">America</hi> has 18
designs, but he also says that <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> has 14 designs
                            (counting top and bottom illustrations on one plate—probably
                            plate 3—as separate designs), and not 27 plates, and that the 
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> has 8 designs, not
                            11 plates or pages. In other words, Blake is using the word
                            “design” to mean picture, counting illustrations on one
                            plate which are independent of one another as separate designs. 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> has 18 pages and at least 18 designs, and
                            therein lies the confusion.</note>
	<note id="n94"><hi rend="s">16</hi><hi rend="i"> Life of Blake</hi> (London, 1863), I, 109.
                            Gilchrist’s description of <hi rend="i">America</hi> as “a
                            folio of 20 pages” is most likely derived from Richard
                            Thomas’s description of <hi rend="i">America</hi> in <hi rend="i">Nollekens and
His Times</hi> (London, 1828), II, 477, as having
                            “18 plates, or twenty pages, including the frontispiece and
                            titlepage.”</note></p>
          <p>The inscription is written on a flyleaf, thus written after the book is
                            bound.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n95" type="note">17</ref>
The insertion of plates 4
                        and 9 also follows the binding, but may precede or follow the inscription.
                        There are only two possible combinations of these three bibliographical
                        facts: binding, inscription, insertion, or binding, insertion, inscription.
                        If the inscription precedes the insertion, the inscription refers to a copy
                        that still has only sixteen plates. If the inscription succeeds the
                        insertion, the inscription refers to a book with eighteen plates. Neither
                        combination rules out the possiblility of the inscription and / or insertion
                        occuring after 1878—unless we can date the inscription. 
<note id="n95"><hi rend="s">17</hi> The inscription is on the verso of the
                            front flyleaf, which is the conjugated part of the end paper pasted to
                            the front board. Because Blake’s original
                            “bindings” were simply wrappers of laid paper, and I do
                            not know of any copy of an illuminated book which has its original
                            wrappers plus a leather binding, I am assuming that the inscription, as
                            well as Gaisford’s bookplate, are on material supplied by the
                            binder, and thus were added to the book no earlier than 1874.</note></p>
          <p>The Sotheby catalogue entry for the 29 January 1878 auction and a comparison
                        of the numbers in set II with those in the inscription make me believe that
                        the inscription followed the insertion of the plates. The catalogue entry
                        describes copy B as: 
						<q> . . . presentation copy with author’s
                            autograph inscription, splendidly bound in Citron morocco, ornamented
                            with variegated leathers and gold tooling, e.g. by F. Bedford; two
                            leaves said to be wanting, but Blake’s original prospectus says
                                “<hi rend="i">America</hi>, a prophecy in illuminated
                            printing, folio, with 18 designs, Lambeth, W. Blake, 1793.” This
                            copy, unbound, sold for £18 in 1874. </q>
The cataloguer’s
                        “two leaves said to be wanting” seems to refer to the
                        assertion in the inscription that “There are 2 more in some
                        copies.” If so, the inscription was already written by 1878. And his
                            “<hi rend="i">but</hi> Blake’s original prospectus
                        says” clearly implies that two leaves are not wanting, that this copy
                        of <hi rend="i">America</hi> has 18 plates, the number that the prospectus
                        says it should. The idea that the cataloguer is counting pages rather than
                        illustrations is supported by internal evidence. As I mentioned, the two
                        sets of plate-numbering are by different hands, but the “8” in
                        the inscription—a very distinct <inline-image n="016-04-p220-8-delta">
	<figTranscr>8</figTranscr></inline-image>—is, I believe, the same
                        “8” in numbers “8” and “18” of the
                        second set of plate-numberings.</p>
          <p>If the inscription is pre-1878 and is written by the same person who
                        renumbered the plates, then the two facsimiles 
<pb id="p16-221" n="221"/>
                        must have entered <hi rend="i">America</hi> copy B between 1874, when it is
                        reported to have been unbound, and January 1878, by which time it was bound
                        and in Dew-Smith’s library. Who bought copy B in 1874 is unknown; it
                        may or may not have been Dew-Smith. Thus plates 4 and 9 could have been
                        inserted either before or during Dew-Smith’s ownership.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n96" type="note">18</ref> In the first case, someone other than
                        Dew-Smith purchased copy B in 1874, had it bound, inserted plates 4 and 9,
                        and, possibly, even wrote the inscription and renumbered the plates. In the
                        second case, Dew-Smith bought the volume either bound with sixteen plates,
                        or unbound in 1874 and had it bound, only to find out later that it was
                        missing plates 4 and 9. He had the two plates made, inserted them, and
                        described his copy as perfect. But it is also possible that Dew-Smith wrote
                        the inscription and renumbered the pages in good faith, having bought a
                        bound volume with plates 4 and 9 already inserted. <note id="n96"><hi rend="s">18</hi>
It is not unlikely that Sotheby’s was
                                given the information about the 1874 sale by Dew-Smith, and that he
                                knew it because he was the one who bought <hi rend="i">America</hi>
                                unbound in 1874 for £18. But the idea that Dew-Smith was the
                                1874 purchaser, i.e., the only owner between 1874 and 1878, cannot
                                be proven.
                            <p>I know nothing about Dew-Smith except that he was “of
                                Cambridge” (<hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi>, 1921), and that
                                he also owned <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy J and Blake’s copy
                                of Swedenborg’s <hi rend="i">The Wisdom of the Angels
                                    Concerning Divine Love and Divine Wisdom</hi>, both of which
                                sold, along with <hi rend="i">America</hi> copy B, at
                                Sotheby’s, 29 January 1878 (<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>,
                                pp. 100, 417, 696). His copy of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
                                printed on vellum and without plates sold at Sotheby’s 27-30
                                June 1906 (<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 644 n2). Dew-Smith is
                                not mentioned in the <hi rend="i">Dictionary of National
                                    Biography.</hi> Knowing nothing of the man, I cannot ascertain
                                his handwriting or his integrity.</p></note></p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="i">Reproductive Process Used to Make Plates 4 and 9</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>In the 1870s, photolithographs could be printed from finegrained limestones
                        and from specially grained zinc plates. To use stone, the negative of the
                        copy to be reproduced is placed in contact with paper coated with a
                        light-sensitive gelatine film. The areas exposed to light become insoluble
                        in water, so that when the sheet is covered with a transfer ink and soaked
                        in a bath of water, all the soluble (unexposed) gelatine lifts off the
                        paper, leaving only the inked image ready to be transferred (counterproofed)
                        onto the prepared stone. To use zinc plates instead of stone, a reverse
                        negative is exposed directly on a sensitized zinc plate, which, because it
                        eliminates the intermediate step of transferring the image, is “much
                        more likely” to retain “the finer qualities” of the
                            original.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n97"
type="note">19</ref> The fine details of
                        plates 4 and 9, including subtle traces of ink along the sides of the text,
                        suggest—as do the platemarks—that these two prints were pulled
                        from zinc plates. Lithography is a planographic method which, at least
                        theoretically, should not leave platemarks. But because a press and a
                        scraper bar are used, printing with too much pressure and with a bar wider
                        than the plate will emboss the shape of the stone or metal plate into the
                        print. The platemarks on plates 4 and 9 reveal the even edges of a metal
                        plate, not the irregular edge of stone. But, as I mentioned, these marks are
                        suspicious. <note id="n97"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Alfred Seymour, <hi rend="i">Practical
Lithography</hi> (London: Scott, Greenwood &amp; Son,
                            1903) p. 100. Reverse negatives were first used in the 1870s with
                            collotypes, and are necessary if the print is to be the same direction
                            as the copy reproduced. Like a counterproof transfer, a reverse negative
                            places the image in reverse on the plate so that the print is in the
                            same direction as the original.</note></p>
          <p>Robert N. Essick has in his collection what are possibly the proofs of plates
                        4 and 9. His two impressions were printed on larger sheets (40.3 ×
                        28.5 cm. for plate 4, and 44.5 × 28.5 cm. for plate 9, vs. 36.3
                        × 26.1 cm.), on different paper (“thin, hard, ivory colored,
                        machine made”),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n98"
type="note">20</ref> and in a dull
                        black ink. Neither of his prints has any trace of side platemarks, while the
                        side platemarks are the ones most noticeable in plates 4 and 9 of copy B. In
                        plate 4, the bottom, top, and left platemarks are sharply defined, while the
                        right side is slightly beveled. In plate 9, the plate lines forming the two
                        bottom corners and top right corner intersect; the bottom platemark, for
                        example, is 18.5 cm. long, while the distance between the platemarks is only
                        17.5 cm. In Essick’s plate 9, this bottom platemark is “about
                        20 cm. long.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n99"
type="note">21</ref> This slight
                        crossing of plate lines in copy B and the fact that the side platemarks are
                        heavier while altogether absent in Essick’s two prints mean that the
                        side platemarks in plates 4 and 9 of copy B are faked. 
<note id="n98"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Private correspondence.</note>
	<note id="n99"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Private correspondence. In both plates 4
                            and 9 there are tiny ink dots slightly outside the right side
                            platemarks. These ink dots seem to be from the border of the
                            relief-etched plates. If so, they are part of the image the camera
                            photographed and are thus on the litho plate or stone. Essick’s
                            two prints, however, do not show these ink spots.</note></p>
          <p>Such platemarks can be made with a stylus along a metal ruler with a bevel,
                        or along a metal plate. The top and bottom platemarks, however, appear to
                        have been produced by a metal plate in the process of printing, and they are
                        the same distance from the image in Essick’s two prints as they are
                        in copy B. Thus, plates 4 and 9 are either printed from zinc plates, or the
                        same blank metal plates are registered <hi rend="i">exactly</hi> on both
                        sets of impressions.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n100"
type="note">22</ref> Pulling a
                        lithograph face down on a blank metal plate through a rolling press would
                        give platemarks, but such a trick doesn’t explain why side platemarks
                        are absent in Essick’s two prints, or how platemarks can intersect,
                        or why the length of a platemark from the same plate is different in two
                        impressions. Perhaps plates 4 and 9 were printed on a litho press using
                        scraper bars of two different sizes, neither of which was as wide as the
                        plates, and thus not able to force paper over the sides, but which came onto
                        and off the plates with enough pressure to catch the top and bottom edges.
                        The missing side platemarks, therefore, had to be added with a stylus. In
                        any event, because lithographs from zinc and stone would ordinarily have
                        been printed without platemarks, the platemarks, however they were made,
                        were made to deceive, to make a flat image appear slightly embossed like a
                        relief etching. The intention to deceive makes plates 4 and 9 forgeries, not
                        facsimiles. <note id="n100"><hi rend="s">22</hi> It seems that a blank plate
                            or a stylus was used to make platemarks in another illuminated book. The
                            leaves of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (J),
                            which are inlaid into larger sheets, were either “provided with
                            artificial plate-marks by putting each print, damped, in press with
                            blank plate” (Keynes and Wolf, <hi rend="i">Census</hi>, p. 59)
                            or “carefully indented at the join of the inner and outer leaves
                            . . . to look like platemarks” (<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p.
                            416).</note></p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="i">The Original Prints Reproduced</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>For there to be two photomechanically reproduced forgeries, two authentic
                        prints must have been photographed. The bottom four lines of the fake plate
                        4 are missing, so the prototype plate 4 must have been masked. And because
                        photolithographs of the period could reproduce line drawings or designs only
                        in pure black and white (half-tone screens not yet having been perfected<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n101" type="note">23</ref>), the two authentic prints
                        photographed must have been uncolored. In addition to there being requisites
                        for the models, both fake prints also have distinguishing, albeit, more
                        subtle, marks. Plate 4 has an extra line on the lower right side of the leaf
                        underneath the text, ink splatters on the right side of the tree, opposite
                        line 8, and at the end of the last word, “foretold”; plate 9
                        is missing the two birds flying under the lowest tree branch, has an ink
                        trail along the left of the tree trunk, a top branch that is lightly
                        extended to the leaves, and ink splatters along the right side of the plate
                        and along the bottom just under the grass. <note id="n101"><hi rend="s">23</hi> “The
half tones of a negative cannot be reproduced
                            by this method, as they can with collotype.” H. T. Wood, <hi rend="i">Modern
Methods of Illustrating Books</hi>, 4th ed. (London:
                            Elliot Stock, 1898), pp. 64-65. Wood goes on to say: “For this
                            reason the process is applicable for reproduction; it cannot produce a
                            print from a negative taken direct from nature. What it can do is to
                            reproduce in facsimile any picture or design that has been produced by
                            any printing process whatever (in which tints are not employed), type,
                            engraving, wood-cuts, or lithograph, also any line-drawing in ink,
                            pencil, or chalk, anything in fact which already possesses the grain,
                            line, or stipple required to hold the ink.”</note></p>
          <p>Of the seven monochrome copies with a masked plate 4, <hi rend="i">America</hi> (F), in the
British Museum since 1859, comes closest to
                        having these peculiar markings.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n102"
type="note">24</ref> Plate
                        4 (F) has both sets of ink splatters and an ink trace that could have 
<pb id="p16-222" n="222"/>
been transformed into an extra leaf line, and the
                        two birds in plate 9 are very faint. On the other hand, plate 9 (F) has no
                        ink trail, no completion of the top branch, and no ink splatters along the
                        right side of the text. But just as the ink stain at the bottom of plate 9
                        (F), the “JY 59” museum accession number (1859), and the birds
                        could have been rubbed off the plate so that they wouldn’t show in an
                        impression, the light marks completing the branch in plate 9 (B) could have
                        been added, and the ink traces accidently printed from the litho plate
                        itself, possibly the result of it not being thoroughly sponged during
                        inking. Because an image on stone or zinc could be altered in such subtle
                        ways, absolute verification may not be possible, but it does seem probable
                        that plates 4 and 9 of copy F were the prints photographed by or for the
                        forgerer. <note id="n102"><hi rend="s">24</hi> I have checked copies D, E,
                            F, H, and L; Robert N. Essick has checked copy I, and Roger S. Wieck
                            (Houghton Library, Harvard) has checked copy C.</note></p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="i">Conclusion</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>We do not know for sure who is responsible for executing and inserting the
                        two forgeries into <hi rend="i">America</hi> copy B. The person who wrote
                        the inscription and renumbered the plates is not necessarily the person who
                        inserted the two prints. The inscription may be the hand of an honest owner
                        warding off Gilchrist’s implication that his copy with only
                        “18 designs” was incomplete. But, according to my reading of
                        the evidence—and other readings may be possible—we do know
                        when (between 1874 and 1878), how (photolithography), where (London), the
                        probable model (F), and, I believe, why. Plates 4 and 9 are not facsimiles;
                        they are not taken from a lost facsimile edition of <hi rend="i">America</hi> made in
the 1870s. In short, they are not like Trianon
                        Press facsimilies doctored up to fool the unsuspecting eye. Plates 4 and 9
                        were executed from the beginning with the intention to pass as originals and
                        thereby secretly complete an otherwise incomplete copy. The plates have done
                        well at both. Many professional bibliographers and bibliophiles have
                        examined this copy of <hi rend="i">America.</hi> To their credit, plates 4
                        and 9 are not only extremely good forgeries, but, and I think this is
                        equally important, as pages in a bound volume, they appear innocent by
                        association. Had plates 4 and 9 been separate prints, it is more likely they
                        would have been detected long ago. As it is, no other illuminated book,
                        bound or loose, is known to contain a facsimile. Do we need to look harder?
                        “Let the collector of prints be cautioned . . . to beware of buying
                        copies for originals. Most of the works of the capital masters have been
                        copied, and many of them so well, that if a person be not versed in prints,
                        he may easily be deceived” (William Gilpin, <hi rend="i">An Essay on
                            Prints</hi>, 4th ed., 1792).</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p16-223" n="223" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
