<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.4.paley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Geoffrey Keynes, The Gates of Memory</title>
        <author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1983</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Barbara Guth</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Adelheid M. Atkins</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>John Wilcox</name>
              <name>Carl Woodring</name>
              <name>Warren Keith Wright</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
	<pb id="p16-233" n="233"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-4-0010">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              Geoffrey Keynes. <hi rend="i">The Gates of Memory.</hi>
                                Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1981, Pp. 428. $24.95.
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Morton D.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Paley</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>When Sir Geoffrey Keynes began working on Blake, there was no reliable
                        edition of the complete writings, no bibliography, and no catalogue of the
                        separate plates. Keynes provided all these and much, much more. Few other
                        scholars can have contributed so much of the fundemental research on a major
                        figure, and yet Blake has been only one of Keynes’s numerous literary
                        interests, and those interests coexisted with his brilliant career as a
                        surgeon. <hi rend="i">The Gates of Memory</hi> provides us with a
                        fascinating account of the “real Self” of one of the
                        extraordinary figures of our century.</p>
          <p>Keynes’ editorial interests seem to date back to 1902, when he met
                        Rupert Brooke at Rugby. As a result of their ensuing friendship, Keynes
                        began collecting Brooke’s poems; much later he would edit the <hi rend="i">Poetical
Works</hi> (1946), <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi>
                        (1954), and <hi rend="i">Letters</hi> (1968). First authorship also occurred
                        at Rugby with the publication of a prize essay on Roman remains unearthed in
                        a field 
<pb id="p16-234" n="234"/>
in Cambridgeshire. (For his prize, Keynes
                        chose the <hi rend="i">Collected Works of Aubrey Beardsley.</hi>) At
                        Pembroke College, Cambridge, another lifelong interest developed: with his
                        friend Cosmo Gordon, Keynes began to collect works by Sir Thomas Browne. His
                            <hi rend="i">Bibliography of Sir Thomas Browne</hi> was to be published
                        in 1924, and his Browne collection is almost certainly the greatest in
                        private hands today. Another Cambridge acquisition was Henry James in the
                        flesh. In response to an invitation from Keynes and two other undergraduates
                        the Master replied: 
						<q> You are all magnificent &amp; I am dazzled,
                            overwhelmed—deeply affected. I subscribe to everything, delight
                            in the prospect of everything, give myself up to you to do with me
                            whatever best suits your convenience—on which, indeed, <hi rend="i">through</hi>
everything, I shall keep my eyes jealously
                            &amp; devoutly fixed. I shall have to tear myself from you on the
                            Tuesday a.m.—&amp; I exhibit the one invidious preference for
                            Tea in one of your gardens (oh <corr type="emend">delirium!</corr>) over even the
sight of your
                            contending crews. But for the rest I am of each &amp; all of you the
                            grateful slave, &amp; have gluttonously marked with rapturous accent
                            the items of the list you have so kindly enclosed. (p. 69) </q>
The
                        visit itself seems to have been remarkably successful, with James exclaiming
                        at Erasmus’ tower “How intensely venerable!” and
                        punting on the Cam with Rupert Brooke.</p>
          <p>Keynes preparation for the medical profession began in 1910 at St.
                        Bartholomew’s Hospital, an institution with which he was to have an
                        enduring relationship. Outside the hospital, one of his early patients was
                        Virginia Woolf, after a suicide attempt. 
						<q> Leonard Woolf and I dashed
                            through the streets to Bart’s in a taxicab waving aside the
                            policemen (in the then absence of traffic lights) shouting
                            ‘Doctor! Doctor!’ if they tried to stop us. However it was
                            that we accomplished our task, we succeeded. The stomach pump was
                            fetched. (p. 116) </q>
It would not be correct to say that
                        Keynes’ medical career was interrupted by World War I, since as a
                        doctor in a field hospital in France he performed thousands of operations
                        and pioneered in techniques of blood transfusion that would later be adopted
                        in peacetime. As a surgeon Keynes no more limited himself to one specialty
                        than he did as a bibliographer. He developed an international reputation for
                        treating both cancer of the breast and myesthenia gravis, the latter a
                        paralytic condition that Keynes learned could be cured by removal of the
                        thymus gland. World War II saw him in uniform once more, this time as Acting
                        Air Vice Marshall in the R.A.F. He retired from medical practice in 1951 and
                        subsequently gave the Harveian Oration to the Royal College of Surgeons and
                        the Oslerian Oration at the Royal College of Physicians. These honors were
                        highly appropriate: Keynes had published his <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi>
                        of Harvey, (based largely on his own great collection) in 1928 (rev. ed.
                        1953) and would receive the James Tait Black Memorial Prize for his <hi rend="i">Life
of William Harvey</hi> in 1966, while with Sir William
                        Osler he had enjoyed a long friendship in which medical and bibliographical
                        interests combined.</p>
          <p>It is astonishing to consider that so distinguished a surgeon also became the
                        great pioneer of textual scholarship on Blake. Keynes writes of this
                        combination of vocations: 
						<q> I wanted to advance British surgery if it were
                            possible and to have a full life, intellectually, aesthetically, and
                            humanly, no matter how hard I had to work. Above all, I wanted the
                            understanding and affection of friends and family. It was asking a great
                            deal of life, but not too much. I had found Blake and his conviction
                            that Imagination was the divine gift to the human race and believed that
                            he was right. The gift must therefore be exercised and appreciated in
                            others to the utmost of one’s ability. (p. 221) </q>
The stages
                        of work on Keynes’ Blake <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi> (1921) are
                        recounted in <hi rend="i">Religio Bibliographici</hi>, a Presidential
                        Address to the Bibliographical Society delivered in 1953 and reprinted as an
                        appendix to <hi rend="i">The Gates of Memory.</hi> One cannot help envying
                        the conditions that prevailed when Keynes began his Blake collecting. Before
                        1914 he obtained the seven Dante engravings from the Linnell family for
                        seven guineas, and even in 1942 he was able to buy eleven major items
                        (including the <hi rend="i">Ugolino</hi> recently given to the Fitzwilliam
                        Museum) for £500. But it is not only the early under-valuation of Blake
                        that accounts for the formation of a magnificent collection by a collector
                        of limited means. In acquiring his Blakes, Keynes seems to have combined the
                        astuteness of a detective with the passion of a lover. All those many Blake
                        scholars who have enjoyed the hospitality of Lammas House can testify to the
                        remarkably high quality of each of the treasures there, as well as to the
                        generosity and patience with which Sir Geoffrey shared his knowledge with
                        us, when it often must have seemed to him that we were busily reinventing
                        the wheel.</p>
          <p>Readers of <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> need hardly be told in detail of the
                        significance of Keynes’ <hi rend="i">Complete Writings</hi>, first
                        published by Nonesuch in 1927 and still alive and well, after numerous
                        revisions, in the Oxford Standard Authors series. The checklist of
                        Keynes’ writings on Blake from 1910 (when he published a note on
                        “Laughing Song”) to 1972<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n106"
type="note">1</ref>
                        is a compendious one, and it now needs to be expanded with the works of
                        another decade, including a third edition of the <hi rend="i">Letters.</hi>
                        Worthy of special mention are the introductions and appendices for the
                        William Blake Trust’s splendid facsimiles. Keynes account of the
                        formation and activities of the Trust also reminds us once more of how much
                        we are indebted to the late Arnold Fawcus, whose Trianon Press produced work
                        of such inestimable quality. <note id="n106"><hi rend="s">1</hi>
                            “Fons et Origo” by G. E. Bentley, Jr., in <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays
in Honour of Sir Geoffrey Keynes</hi>, ed. M.
                            D. Paley and Michael Phillips (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1973), pp.
                            349-76.</note></p>
          <p>An unusual byproduct of Keynes’ Blake scholarship was the ballet <hi rend="i">Job: A Masque for
Dancing.</hi> 
                        With his sister-in-law,<gap type="emend"/> the artist Gwen Raverat (whose
                        delightful <hi rend="i">Period Piece: A Cambridge Childhood</hi> should be
                        read along with <hi rend="i">The Gates of Memory</hi>), Keynes produced a
                        scenario based on the engraved designs. Ralph Vaughan Williams composed a
                        beautiful score with the understanding 
<pb id="p16-235" n="235"/>
that there
                        was to be no dancing on point (“which made him feel ill”). The
                        idea was then offered to Diaghilev, who turned it down as “too
                        English and too old-fashioned.” In the end, the work was brilliantly
                        choreographed by Ninette de Valois and performed by the Camargo Society in
                        1931. Thence it passed into the repertoire of the Sadler’s Wells
                        Ballet, now the Royal Ballet. A revival of this ballet, so splendidly true
                        to Blake’s vision, is long overdue (hopefully with the restoration of
                        the original Raverat sets rather than the rather inappropriate ones by John
                        Piper that were later substituted for them).</p>
          <p>Space does not permit more than the mere mention of Geoffrey Keynes’
                        other bibliographies: those of John Donne (1915, 4th ed. 1974), the works
                        published by William Pickering (1924), Jane Austen (1929), William Hazlitt
                        (1931), John Evelyn (1937), and Bishop George Berkeley (1977). His
                        achievement as a book collector is indicated by the catalogue of his
                        library, comprising over 4,000 titles, published in 1964. His remarkable
                        life is symbolized for me by one of the many fascinating photographs in this
                        book, showing G.L.K. aged ninety-two in front of the enormous tulip tree at
                        Lammas House. When he died three years later, many a scholar half a century
                        younger felt the loss of one who was at the same time a founder of our
                        discipline and an invigorating contemporary presence—“a friend
                        with whom he liv’d benevolent.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n107" type="note">2</ref></p>
                        <note id="n107"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i"> Milton</hi>, 15:27, <hi rend="i">The
Complete Writings of
                                William Blake</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes (London: Oxford University
                            Press, 1966), p. 497.</note>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
