<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.4.woodring</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Marilyn Butler, Romantics, Rebels, and Reactionaries: English Literature and its
Background 1760-1830</title>
        <author n="Woodring">Carl Woodring</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1983</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Barbara Guth</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Adelheid M. Atkins</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>John Wilcox</name>
              <name>Carl Woodring</name>
              <name>Warren Keith Wright</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
	<pb id="p16-232" n="232"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-4-0010">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Marilyn Butler. <hi rend="i">Romantics, Rebels and
                                    Reactionaries: English Literature and its Background
                                    1760-1830.</hi> New York: Oxford University Press, 1982. Pp.
                                213. $17.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Carl</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Woodring</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Several assumptions and these make up a credo for this work. “A book
                        is made by its public, the readers it literally finds and the people in the
                        author’s mind’s eye” (p. 9). The democratization of
                        patronage in 1760-1830 consequently affected all the arts. The writers of
                        the period responded as rebels or reactionaries. Dissent provided
                        “the classic stock of the English left,” hence Priestley,
                        Paine, Godwin, Hazlitt, and Blake, and hence the defections of Wordsworth,
                        Coleridge, and Southey. Conditions and moods changed rapidly, so that
                        literary periods of such short duration as 1790-98, 1800-15, 1817-20, and
                        1820-23 can be identified in critical reviews, fiction, and poetry.</p>
          <p>Marilyn Butler has shown her superior knowledge and control of documentary
                        and intellectual history in books on the novelists Edgeworth, Austen, and
                        Peacock. Her inclusion now of poets and essayists accompanies a greatly
                        increased factor of speculation. Instead of specific citation, she gives for
                        each chapter “suggestions for further reading.” (In keeping
                        with this appeal to the younger student, the publisher has reduced the
                        typeface sufficiently to exclude the aged scholar.) Reliance upon
                        unidentified secondary sources makes it difficult to tell when error is
                        typographical, but insistence upon rapid fluctuations in response to public
                        mood makes significant a misdating of Coleridge’s <hi rend="i">Watchman</hi> and an
implication that Keats could have seen a book by
                        Coleridge entitled <hi rend="i">Lay Sermons.</hi> Organization and method
                        resemble those of Frederick E. Pierce, <hi rend="i">Currents and Eddies in
                            the English Romantic Generation</hi> (Yale, 1918), although Butler
                        subordinates minor authors in a fashion deemed unscholarly in
                        Pierce’s day. She refutes an error then current that Romanticism
                        rebelled against an Augustan eighteenth century. Readings in art history and
                        attention to system lead her to say instead that a “revival of
                        Neoclassicism began with Byron’s <hi rend="i">Childe
                        Harold</hi>” (p. 181).</p>
          <p>The bipolar formulas of the book do not impede novel interpretations and in
                        general encourage them: Wordsworth’s Preface of 1800 advances
                        Neoclassical precepts in a Neoclassical way (p. 60). Wordsworth was
                        counter-revolutionary in 1796 (pp. 64-65); later, slower than Coleridge, he
                        recognized that a counter-revolutionary stance could bring popularity (p.
                        68). Of Blake’s works of 1790-94 “the corporate author”
                        (in accord with the axiom quoted at the beginning of this review) “is
                        the urban subclass which emerged through its opposition to Britain’s
                        national policy” (p. 43). Blake’s roots are “in the
                        artisan world, Protestant, radical, Bible-reading, to which the
                        Swedenborgians appealed before they organized themselves” (pp.
                        48-49); he “conveys no feeling for the English plot of ground”
                        (p. 44). English Blake, made an internationalist by Fuseli, ranges to
                        America, Europe, Africa, Uranus, Creation, and the Last Trump, all in
                        keeping with the public consciousness of changing political events. Shelley
                        wrote for an elite (p. 114, contrast p. 146). Reviving the old argument that
                            <hi rend="i">Alastor</hi> attacks Wordsworth, Butler adds that the
                        “fanatics” at the opening of <hi rend="i">The Fall of
                            Hyperion</hi> are 
<pb id="p16-233" n="233"/>
Wordsworth and other
                        Christian apologists (p. 152) and that <hi rend="i">Mont Blanc</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Frankenstein</hi> likewise reject Wordsworth’s
                        solitaries. Chapter 5, “The Cult of the South,” argues that
                            <hi rend="i">Lamia, Don Juan</hi>, and various works by Shelley and
                        Peacock carry out the anti-Christian sexuality of Erasmus Darwin and Richard
                        Payne Knight. There is a stimulating paragraph on <hi rend="i">The Witch of
                            Atlas</hi>; like almost all the assertions concerning individual works,
                        it would be strengthened by development and demonstration.</p>
          <p>The method, then, is to show how brief segments within 1760-1830 can be
                        characterized by changed relations between and within literary works of
                        rebellion or reaction. Alert application of the method brings the
                        observation that “the Napoleonic Wars may have cost more lives in
                        proportion to the British population than the 1914-18 war,” and that
                        the “failure of literature to reflect the holocaust”
                        illustrates a turning away from the poor after 1800 (p. 115). Setting
                        Germanic Christianity and gloom against liberal Mediterranean classicism,
                        Butler discovers that the early heroes of Byron and Shelley are activists,
                        their later protagonists passive bystanders (p. 125). The same polarization
                        leads to an identification of contradictions in <hi rend="i">Manfred</hi>
                        (p. 122).</p>
          <p>Many of Butler’s past strengths continue in this latest book. I hope
                        that its analysis of rapid fluctuation in taste is accurate enough to
                        predict a short life for this period in which literary historians succumb,
                        at a high price, to the seductions of originality.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
