<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.4.fine</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">David Bindman, William Blake: His Art and Times</title>
        <author n="Fine">Ruth E. Fine</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1983</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Barbara Guth</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Adelheid M. Atkins</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>John Wilcox</name>
              <name>Carl Woodring</name>
              <name>Warren Keith Wright</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
      <pb id="p16-226" n="226"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-4-0010">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure n="but420.1.1.pt" id="but420.1.pt.01" work-copy="biblicaltemperas" rend="db" width="958" height="655">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
</figure>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Art and Times</hi>, an
                                exhibition organized by David Bindman. Yale Center for British Art,
                                15 September–14 November 1982. Art Gallery of Ontario,
                                Toronto, 3 December 1982–6 February 1983. Catalogue by David
                                Bindman, pp. 192, 200 illustrations, 21 color plates. $15.00,
                                paper.
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Ruth E.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Fine</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The exhibition <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Art and Times</hi> was
                        organized by David Bindman and jointly sponsored by the Yale Center for
                        British Art in New Haven (where it was very handsomely installed from 15
                        September to 14 November 1982—the showing on which this review is
                        based) and the Art Gallery of Ontario in Toronto (3 December 1982 – 6
                        February 1983). The exhibition was a rather daring undertaking given the
                        enormous amount of attention already paid to Blake in recent years. For
                        example, G.E. Bentley, Jr.’s <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> was
                        published in 1977; and since 1978, the year of Martin Butlin’s
                        monumental <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> exhibition at the Tate Gallery,
                        accompanied by an excellent and informative catalogue, several other
                        important monographs have been published: among them are Butlin’s
                        catalogue raisonné. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of
                            William Blake</hi>, Robert Essick’s <hi rend="i">William Blake
                            Printmaker</hi>, and Bindman’s own <hi rend="i">The Complete
                            Graphic Works of William Blake</hi> together with his <hi rend="i">Blake
                            as an Artist.</hi> Of course there had not been a large scale exhibition
                        of Blake’s art in this country since the one in 1939 at the
                        Philadelphia Museum of Art, and that show had been selected entirely from
                        collections in the United States. One can understand, therefore, the
                        pressures for a grand display on this side of the Atlantic, all the more so
                        because conservation problems are making Blake collectors wary of lending
                        important objects to the repetitious minor exhibitions that have been
                        organized in great numbers in recent years, and also of showing them at home
                        to anyone other than serious scholars.</p>
          <p>The germ of the New Haven/Toronto show came in conversations between Bindman
                        and Katharine A. Lochnan, Curator of Prints and Drawings at the Art Gallery
                        of Ontario, some years ago. The initial intent was similar to that of the
                        1939 Philadelphia exhibition: to show Blake in North American collections, a
                        much richer body of material than one could find in 1939, thanks principally
                        to the extraordinary acquisitions of Paul Mellon. Thus the Yale Center for
                        British Art, which houses much of the Mellon Collection, was viewed as a
                        most appropriate cosponsor; and, in fact, well over a third of the show was
                        drawn from various Yale institutions (the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript
                        Library, the Yale University Art Gallery, the Lewis Walpole Library at
                        Farmington, as well as the Paul Mellon and other collections at the Center
                        for British Art). Numerous loans also came from Mr. and Mrs. Mellon’s
                        private collection; the Pierpont Morgan Library; the Museum of Fine Arts,
                        Boston; the Library of Congress, Rosenwald Collection; the National Gallery
                        of Art, Rosenwald Collection; and Robert N. Essick. Despite the richness of
                        American collections, however, certain key pieces were necessarily borrowed
                        from abroad—specifically from the Tate Gallery, the British Museum,
                        and the Victoria and Albert Museum in London, and the Fitzwilliam Museum in
                        Cambridge.</p>
          <p>Major Blake exhibitions must now be compared to the Tate show of 1978; and in
                        this case, the comparison seems apt in terms of differences in kind. The
                        earlier show was very large, comprising 339 pieces, all of them by or after
                        Blake except for a drawing by his brother Robert that was the source of
                        William’s relief etching, <hi rend="i">The Approach of Doom.</hi> The
                        exhibition emphasized and explored very specifically Blake’s greatest
                        accomplishments as a visual artist, in part by virtually ignoring such
                        aspects of his work as the reproductive engravings that were the
                        artist’s main source of income. In that exhibition, Martin Butlin
                        convincingly demonstrated that Blake “had an intensity of vision, an
                        imaginative scope, and a multiplicity of means of expression . . . beyond
                        most men.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n103" type="note">1</ref>
In contrast, the New
                        Haven / Toronto show was considerably smaller, comprising some 200 pieces
                        described in 125 catalogue entries (e.g., cat. no. 115 covers sixteen
                        watercolors and engravings for <hi rend="i">Illustrations to the Book of
                            Job</hi>, cat. no. 116 covers thirteen for <hi rend="i">Illustrations
                            for Dante</hi>, and so forth). <note id="n103"><hi rend="s">1</hi>
                            Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (ex. cat.), London, 1978,
                            p. 23.</note></p>
          <p>Accepting the notion that Blake’s greatness as a visual artist had
                        been demonstrated by the Tate exhibition, <pb id="p16-227" n="227"/>
Bindman
                        set out to explore the intellectual and artistic milieu that helped give
                        this greatness its form. While fewer of the major paintings were here than
                        in the London show, this one was, in fact, more comprehensive, including
                        aspects of Blake’s art not considered in 1978 and showing documentary
                        material as well. In addition, Blake’s own works of art were
                        interspersed with a number of pieces by his contemporaries; and the
                        inclusion of books of historical and philosophical interest to him and
                        others of the period placed his oeuvre in a broad intellectual context.</p>
          <p>Bindman carefully balanced and integrated this material so the focus on Blake
                        was in no way diminished. First, the sections devoted to the art of
                        Blake’s time (“The Elevated Style in the 1780s”;
                        “The Revolutionary Background: Blake’s Circles in the
                        1790s”; “<hi rend="i">Jerusalem:</hi> the Antiquarian
                        Background”; and “The Linnell Circle”) were far fewer
                        than those devoted to Blake’s own art; and the main purpose of them
                        was clearly to provide a background for a better understanding of Blake,
                        although the didactic aspects of the exhibition never overshadowed the
                        aesthetic. Much of the ancillary material was quite small, or in the form of
                        books, and was shown in cases, for the most part leaving the walls to
                        feature Blake. The main exception was the section of drawings and prints
                        representing the scope of narrative subjects (“The Elevated
                        Style”) prevalent in English art of the 1780s, and in which pieces by
                        or after John Flaxman, Richard Cosway, John Mortimer, Benjamin West, George
                        Romney and Henry Fuseli were hung. In them one found allusions to the art of
                        classical antiquity and the High Renaissance of the sort one sees throughout
                        Blake’s own oeuvre.</p>
          <p>The basic arrangement of the Blake material was chronological: “The
                        Engraver’s Apprentice, 1772-79”; “Radical History
                        Painter: the 1780s”; “Making a Living: Reproductive
                        Engraving”; “Relief Etching and Experimental Printing,
                        1788-96”; “Illuminated Books and Prophecies, 1788-95”;
                        “Separate Colour Prints, c. 1794-1805”; “After the
                        Prophecies: Illustrated Books”; “An Understanding Patron:
                        Thomas Butts and Paintings from the Bible, 1799-c. 1809” (a conscious
                        contrast, perhaps, to the section in the Tate show called “The
                        Hazards of Patronage: William Hayley and ‘The Grave,’ c.
                        1799-1806”); “Blake in Felpham, 1800-1803”;
                        “Milton: Prophecy and Illustrations, 1801-c. 1820”;
                        “Blake’s Exhibition of 1809: The 
<figure n="SharpafterWest.WitchofEndor.16.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="692">
	<head>1. The Witch of En-dor, by Sharp after West, cat. 22.</head>
	<figDesc>Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="but324.1.1.cpd" id="but324.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="724">
	<figTranscr/>
	<head>2. The Good and Evil Angels Struggling for Possession of a Child,
                                cat. 53.</head>
	<figDesc>Yale Center for British Art, Mrs. John Hay Whitney
                                Collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
            <figure n="but307.1.1.cpd" id="but307.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="733">
	<figTranscr>NEWTON<lb/>
	Fresco WBlake inv</figTranscr>
	<head>3. Newton, cat. 56a.</head>
	<figDesc>Yale Center for British Art.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p16-228" n="228"/>
Descent into Obscurity”; “<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, 1804-27”; and “The
Last Decade,
                        c. 1818-27.”</p>
          <p>One realized that, given the very large body of work that Blake produced,
                        each piece on display was purposefully selected to function in a number of
                        ways. Some pieces allowed for iconographical comparisons both within
                        Blake’s own oeuvre and in relation to the work of other artists. Some
                        made stylistic and technical points. Some had historical or philosophical
                        import. Various threads were woven throughout the fabric of the exhibition,
                        and the viewer was able to perceive again and again relationships between
                        the sections and to sense the totality in a body of work through selected
                        pieces. To mention only a few instances, <hi rend="i">The Witch of Endor
                            Raising the Spirit of Samuel</hi> is seen in a 1783 version by Blake
                        (cat. 11), in a later version by him, c. 1800-1805 (cat. 77), and in an
                        engraving by William Sharp after Benjamin West (cat. 22, illus. 1), thus
                        allowing Blake’s own evolution to be studied while also comparing his
                        representation of the subject with that of another artist. <hi rend="i">Oberon,
Titania and Puck with Fairies Dancing</hi> (cat. 16) introduces
                        the theme of fairies which is often picked up in Blake’s later work
                        (e.g., as Bindman points out, in the title page for <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, cat.
99b). From Blake’s scores of reproductive
                        engravings, Bindman selected works after earlier masters (Watteau, cat. 25),
                        as well as works after Blake’s contemporaries (e.g., Fuseli, cat.
                        27).</p>
          <p>Points about method, too, were well managed. The technical range of
                        Blake’s reproductive prints was evident—from the stipple
                        engraving that the artist presumably despised (e.g., <hi rend="i">Zephyrus
                            and Flora</hi>, after Stothard, cat. 26), through the dot and lozenge
                        engraving technique at its most spectacular in the exceedingly dramatic 
<hi rend="i">Head of a Damned Soul</hi> after Fuseli (cat. 28). In the
                        “Relief Etching and Experimental Printing” section, the single
                        surviving fragment of an etching plate used by Blake for relief printing (a
                        cancelled plate from <hi rend="i">America</hi>) was shown with a proof
                        impression from it (cat. 34, 35), and other trial proofs of various sorts
                        helped the viewer to see and understand Blake’s processes.
                        Particularly interesting was a proof of the title page of <hi rend="i">The
                            [First] Book of Urizen</hi> with areas of monotype-like color printing,
                        but lacking final watercolor refinements (cat. 37). This section showed
                        initial working phases of Blake’s processes, the final results of
                        which were demonstrated in all of their rich variety later in the
                        exhibition. In contrast, a copy of Joseph Ritson’s <hi rend="i">Select Collection of
English Songs</hi> with conventionally engraved
                        illustrations by Blake and others after Stothard (cat. 32) vividly
                        demonstrated the differences between traditional book illustration and
                        Blake’s personal inventions and methods.</p>
          <p>Among the most rewarding sections of the show, one which explored the
                        development of Blake’s conceptual (spiritual) and technical
                        sophistication, was “Illuminated Books and Prophecies.” On
                        view were <hi rend="i">There is no Natural Religion</hi> including the
                        unique “Application” plate (cat. 38b) given by Sir Geoffrey
                        Keynes to the Pierpont Morgan Library (important not only because it is
                        unique, but also because it is an early example of the figure which later is
                        seen as <hi rend="i">Newton</hi>, cat. 56); <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel;
                            The Marriage of Heaven and Hell; Visions of the Daughters of
                            Albion;</hi> and several separately mounted pages from the very
                        beautiful colored copy of <hi rend="i">America a Prophecy</hi> in the Mellon
                        private collection, unusual in that it is richly colored, whereas most
                        surviving copies are uncolored. Three copies (F, P, U) of a single page from
                            <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (cat. 39) colored at different
                        periods of Blake’s career showed his evolution in unifying on the
                        page the image and text relationships. In the earliest (copy F, which
                        Bindman cites as a copy of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> to which has
                        been added an incomplete copy of <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>) the
                        delicate washes tend to heighten only the image, while in the latest (copy
                        U, colored 1815 or later), the color is rich, vibrant, and heightened with
                        gold, fully illuminating both image and text. Quite another matter, and
                        equally marvelous to see, the display of five of the seven known copies of
                            <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> (cat. 45), including the only one colored in
                        watercolor rather than color printed, showed the great variety in
                        Blake’s handcoloring of one title during a rather concentrated period
                        of time (probably 1795-96 for the color printed versions with the
                        watercolored copy probably dating from the early 1820s).</p>
          <p>In the section “Separate Colour Prints, c. 1794-1805,” examples
                        from the <hi rend="i">Small</hi> and <hi rend="i">Large Book of Designs</hi>
                        were represented as well as six images (in seven impressions) of
                        Blake’s series of twelve elaborate monoprints (color printed
                        drawings, as they are more generally known): <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam,
                            Pity, The Good and Evil Angels Struggling for Possession of a Child</hi>
                        (illus. 2); <hi rend="i">Christ Appearing to the Apostles after the
                            Resurrection, Hecate</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> (cat. 51-56).
                        Until recently, all impressions of the twelve subjects, each known in from
                        one to three impressions reworked with paint to a varying extent and every
                        one unique, were thought to date from c. 1795. When the Tate Gallery 
<hi rend="i">Newton</hi> was removed from its mount in preparation for this
                        exhibition, however, it was found to be on paper with an 1804 watermark.
                        This piece was hung side by side with the one other know version of the
                        subject, a far less familiar one, in the collection of the Lutheran Church
                        in America, Glen Foerd at Torresdale (illus. 3). These two <hi rend="i">Newton</hi>
prints present quite a challenge: to the 1804 watermark on
                        the Tate sheet must be added the fact that its surface is exceedingly rich
                        and painterly, making it look quite different from the Lutheran Church
                        version (see David Bindman’s “Afterword” elsewhere in
                        this issue). The painterly surface caused speculation that the Tate version
                        was entirely a painted rather than a reworked color print of the subject.
                        The present writer, like Bindman, is not at all convinced that this is
                        so.</p>
          <p>Another discovery as important as the 1804 watermark 
<pb id="p16-229" n="229"/>
            <figure n="but420.1.1.pt" id="but420.1.pt.01" work-copy="biblicaltemperas" rend="db" width="958" height="655">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
	<head>4. Christ Giving Sight to Bartimaeus, cat. 72.</head>
	<figDesc>Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection.</figDesc>
</figure> was made by Patrick Noon, Curator of Prints and Drawings at the
                        Center for British Art, who observed that the printed base of the
                        Metropolitan’s <hi rend="i">God Judging Adam</hi> was printed from
                        the relief surface of a copper plate into which the image had been
                        etched—quite similar in fact to the plates of the illuminated books
                        (again, see Bindman’s “Afterword” for further
                        discussion).</p>
          <p>Blake’s expressive range in his illustrations for Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>,
Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>,
                        and Gray’s <hi rend="i">Poems</hi> was displayed in the selection of
                        watercolor designs for them. In the section “After the Prophecies:
                        Illustrated Books,” one also found a rejected design and the unique
                        proof of Blake’s own white line etching (printed relief) for the
                        “Death’s Door” plate (cat. 64a,b) in <hi rend="i">The
                            Grave.</hi></p>
          <p>Although conservation considerations prevented the loan of many of the
                        tempera paintings that Blake executed under the patronage of Thomas Butts,
                        there were five to be seen. Among them were <hi rend="i">Christ Giving Sight
                            to Bartimaeus</hi> (cat. 72, illus. 4) and, in a splendid state of
                        preservation, <hi rend="i">The Virgin Hushing the Young John the
                            Baptist</hi> (cat. 70) from a private collection in Chicago; it is
                        always rewarding to see little known works not in the public domain included
                        in exhibitions. In addition to the temperas, the Butts section included a
                        number of watercolors, the most important, perhaps, being those for
                        Revelation, (cat. 80-83) a theme which, as connected with millinarianism,
                        was important to the context that Bindman emphasized in his catalogue (see
                        below).</p>
          <p>Hayley’s patronage was less successful than Butts’ and the
            section of the exhibition devoted to the Felpham period <figure n="BUT645.1.1.PD" rend="file" width="773" height="1000">
	<head>5. The Last Judgment, cat. 98.</head>
	<figDesc>National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C., Rosenwald
              Collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="BUT688.1.1.PD" rend="file" width="673" height="1000">
	<head>6. Portrait of John Linnell, cat. 117.</head>
	<figDesc>National Gallery of Art, Rosenwald Collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p16-230" n="230"/>
relied heavily on documentary material: a letter
                        of 1800 to John Flaxman beside one of two and a half years later to James
                        Blake showed Blake’s delight at being in the country turn to great
                        dismay. The star of this section of the show, however, was the very tiny (4
                        3/16 × 2 ½ inch) tempera on copper, <hi rend="i">The
                            Horse</hi> (cat. 89), related to the illustration in Hayley’s 
<hi rend="i">Ballads.</hi> From Mr. and Mrs. Mellon’s private
                        collection, dating from 1805-06 or possibly from as late as the 1820s, the
                        piece is a jewel.</p>
          <p>During his Felpham sojourn while Blake was helping Hayley with
                        Cowper’s edition of Milton, he became preoccupied with the great
                        poet, and the results of this preoccupation were seen in the section
                        “Milton: Prophecy and Illustrations, 1805-c.1820.” The
                        earliest Milton illustrations, the 1801 <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> watercolors
                        in the Huntington Library, were not available for loan, the same being true
                        for the first (1807) set of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> illustrations.
                        However, selections from the 1808 <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> were on
                        show (as well as an example of the third [1822] set, seen in the section
                        devoted to Blake’s last decade), as were selections from the 1815-20
                            <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> illustrations and from those to 
<hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi> of the same
                        period. The concentrated energy in these small images of the late teens as
                        well as their rich coloration foretell the somewhat larger and equally
                        magnificent Dante series that comes at the end of Blake’s life.
                        Complementing the Milton watercolors, the single complete copy of <hi rend="i">Milton
a Poem</hi> (cat. 90), with fifty plates (copy D) was on
                        show. As Bindman pointed out in his catalogue, this most elaborate of the
                        extant copies of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> handsomely complemented the only
                        known colored copy of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, also on view (cat.
                        99).</p>
          <p>The section devoted to Blake’s unsuccessful 1809 exhibition included
                        its catalogue which sets forth the artist’s most distinguished
                        writing on his own art. Here, too, most of the relevant surviving temperas
                        (“frescos”) were too fragile to travel, and were represented
                        by related material: e.g., a pencil study, <hi rend="i">The Bard</hi> (cat.
                        96) of 1809, <hi rend="i">The Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> engraving,
                        accompanied by the original copper plate from which it was printed and the
                        1809 prospectus for the piece (cat. 97). The star in this section was the
                        National Gallery’s <hi rend="i">Last Judgment</hi> (cat. 98, illus.
                        5) drawing. One technical disagreement here: I suspect this sheet probably
                        was not done with pen and ink at all, but, rather, with a very fine brush
                        and watercolor. I suspect this may also be true for many pieces that are
                        recorded in Bindman’s catalogue and elsewhere as having been reworked
                        with pen and ink.</p>
          <p>Sixteen plates of the one hundred in the exquisite and only colored copy of
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in the Mellon Collection were on view,
                        including the title page and all four full-page frontispieces. <hi rend="i">A
Description of Jerusalem</hi> by Richard Brothers (cat. no. 101) in
                        the section “<hi rend="i">Jerusalem:</hi> The Antiquarian
                        Background” reinforced the belief that the return to Jerusalem was
                        central to millinarianism (as was the idea of apocalypse noted earlier).
                        Other books dealing with the history (mythological and otherwise) of the
                        British Isles were included here as well.</p>
          <p>A diverse group of pieces represented Blake’s last decade, among them,
                        his only wood engravings, the illustrations for Thornton’s <hi rend="i">Virgil</hi>
(cat. 106), the Pierpont Morgan Library’s
                        marvelous pencil study for Blake’s enigmatic <hi rend="i">Arlington
                            Court Picture</hi> (cat. 108), one of two known impressions of the 
<hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> engraving (cat. 110), the late
                        relief-etched treatises <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi>, and <hi rend="i">On
Homer’s Poetry and On Virgil</hi> (cat. 111, 112).
                        The major emphasis of this section, however, as would be expected, was on
                        the Job and Dante illustrations. The Job display (cat. 115) included six of
                        the early (1805-10) watercolors done for Thomas Butts, now in the Morgan
                        Library, and ten of the series of twenty-one engravings, including all six
                        derived from the watercolors on show. This allowed for comparison of the
                        early and later versions (in different techniques) as well as offering a
                        broad representation of the images. Blake’s agreement with Linnell,
                        Linnell’s account book of the Job project, and a related receipt were
                        included in the final, “Linnell Circle,” section of the show.
                        In the watercolors for Job one sees how specific Blake could be in working
                        studies that later were transformed into another medium, while, in contrast,
                        the Dante watercolors show how freely-handled ideas might take form.</p>
          <p>The Dante series (cat. 116) was represented by five watercolors to the
                        “Inferno” (plus four of the seven engravings, all of them for
                        the “Inferno”), three watercolors to
                        “Purgatorio” and, in a sense ending the exhibition, the
                        “St. Peter, St. James, Dante, and Beatrice with St. John
                        also,” for “Paradisio.” In one instance, “The
                        Pit of Disease: The Falsifiers,” the watercolor (one of the more
                        highly finished ones in the series) was shown with the engraving; and the
                        selection of watercolors generally showed the diversity of finish in the
                        set, from subjects that are very loosely worked (e.g., “The Angel
                        Boat”), to highly finished ones like the “Paradiso”
                        scene noted above. For the record, Blake’s seven copper plates for
                        the Dante series are not now in the Library of Congress, Rosenwald
                        Collection, as indicated by Bindman, but in the National Gallery of Art,
                        Rosenwald Collection.</p>
          <p>“The Linnell Circle” section included Blake’s 1825
                        pencil drawing, <hi rend="i">Portrait of John Linnell</hi> (cat. 117, illus.
                        6), two works by Linnell, and an engraved portrait of the engraver Wilson
                        Lowry, worked jointly by Linnell and Blake (cat. 119). Included, too, were
                        works by George Richmond and Samuel Palmer as well as <hi rend="i">George
                            Cumberland’s Calling Card</hi> (cat. 125), “the last thing
                        Blake attempted to engrave,” according to Bindman, quoting Mrs.
                        Blake.</p>
          <p>Exhibitions such as this confirm beyond any doubt the importance of the
                        exhibition form as a carrier of knowledge quite distinct from fully
                        illustrated volumes about the work of an artist. The enormous, if subtle,
                        differences between the two <hi rend="i">Newtons</hi> are observable only
                            <pb id="p16-231" n="231"/>
with the two works physically side by side.
                        Only in this circumstance can one observe similarities, especially in
                        tactile aspects, between the Tate version of <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> and
                        other color printed subjects, similarities that demonstrate (once the
                        question arises) that the <hi rend="i">Newton</hi> does have a printed
                        base—albeit one that probably was made later than previously had been
                        thought (one recalls that similar questions and observations arose from
                        viewing three impressions of <hi rend="i">The Ancient of Days</hi> in the
                        Tate exhibition). Only when seen side by side with the other color prints
                        can the clearly defined greyish outline in <hi rend="i">God Judging
                            Adam</hi> stand out as having been printed in relief from an etched
                        plate. And only in an exhibition of this kind in which Blake is placed next
                        to his contemporaries can one see his extraordinary distinctiveness. For
                        example, Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engraving (cat. 15)
                        practically jumps off the wall as it demonstrates the artist’s
                        exquisite understanding of the expressive potential of the burin, all the
                        more so when it is placed just several feet from a piece by one of the most
                        admired craftsmen of the period, William Sharp. Sharp’s <hi rend="i">Witch of
En-dor</hi> after Benjamin West, mentioned earlier, is
                        strikingly dull in its repetitious description of form. If one does nothing
                        more than study the edges of the folds of clothing in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi>
in contrast to similar forms in Sharp’s piece,
                        it is possible to glimpse the power of Blake’s imaginatively complex
                        world. Although Blake used precisely the same engraver’s vocabulary
                        in general use at the time, parallel strokes, cross hatching, dot and
                        lozenge, etc., each of his marks is made with a passion that appears to be
                        without bounds.</p>
          <p>Throughout his catalogue, Bindman captures the spirit of Blake, summarizing
                        that “Blake . . . intends us always to go further and find that our
                        certainties have evaporated.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n104"
type="note">2</ref>
                        He points out how Blake made use of many of the artistic conventions of his
                        time while rejecting others. Touching upon the ideas that were in the air,
                        so to speak, in Blake’s London, Bindman doesn’t try to project
                        a cause and effect relationship. The same is so when he mentions possible
                        influences on Blake, of, for example, children’s books and satirical
                        political cartoons. He discusses Blake’s relationships with and
                        differences from his artist colleagues while touching as well upon aesthetic
                        affinities that are less clearly pinned down (e.g., Bindman makes cogent
                        comparisons of Blake with Goya while pointing out that it is unlikely that
                        the two artists actually knew each other’s work). Blake’s
                        ambivalence toward confining systems is observable throughout his career.
                        For example, while his relief-etching inventions allowed him to bypass
                        commercial publishers, he continued to try to find both publishers and
                        patrons. As Bindman points out, given Blake’s revolutionary stance
                        his obscurity was undoubtedly his protection. Despite this obscurity Bindman
                        offers us remarkably succinct summary accounts of Blake’s themes,
                        always maintaining a sense of the complexity that is essential to a true
                        study of Blake in depth, but allowing the reader to move intelligently
                        through the exhibition knowing the abbreviated catalogue information alone.
                            <note id="n104"><hi rend="s">2</hi> David Bindman, <hi rend="i">William
                                Blake: His Art and Times</hi> (ex. cat.), (New Haven and Toronto,
                            1982), p. 44.</note></p>
          <p>One of Bindman’s major theses is that Blake’s visionary stance
                        had many parallels with the prevailing dissenting philosophical thought of
                        his time, specifically the millenarianism of Richard Brothers and Joanna
                        Southcott. A central unifying issue was the prophecy of an apocalyptic,
                        revolutionary, and vengeful destruction of the fallen, corrupt,
                        materialistic world, and the beliefs that true redemption was to be found
                        through Christ and that the meaning of the Bible was available in every age,
                        but only to a few privileged individuals who were guided by an inner light.
                        For Blake, this inner light obviously was the force behind his art which he
                        valued as a form of prayer.</p>
          <p>Blake is a difficult artist. This exhibition places him in context; yet, in
                        context, he remains apart. The exhibition rather reinforces one’s
                        awareness of Blake’s own peculiar grasp of the neoclassical and the
                        horrific (the serene juxtaposed with the bizarre), his placement of almost
                        naive formal generalization next to imaginative particularization. One sees
                        obviously exquisite skill displayed next to offhanded clumsiness; one sees
                        extraordinarily subtle color relationships in contrast to rather obvious use
                        of the primaries. One feels delight and pride and sadness and shame at being
                        part of the human experience.</p>
          <p>At home, later, one can review the catalogue, rethink Bindman’s ideas
                        on Blake’s influences and relationships, can further ponder the
                        narrative aspects of the meaning of images that are graspable from catalogue
                        reproductions, essentially in black and white (although this catalogue does
                        include twenty-one color plates), in which objects of various sizes fit into
                        the scale of a page or a column. One can only try to recall what was
                        understood about the world in a new way having had the privilege of peering
                        from the distance of a few inches at the tiny forms in the Morgan Library
                        watercolors for <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il
                            Penseroso</hi> (delicate, brightly colored, and sprightly drawn) having
                        just been knocked-out from across the room by the powerful, somber, dense,
                        dark, watercolor illustrations to the Book of Revelation which were brought
                        together from Brooklyn, New York City, Washington, and Philadelphia for a
                        rare comparative viewing in New Haven and then Toronto.</p>
          <p>Such experiences give one a feeling of elation, and this elation is
                        heightened by awe at the range of this particular human mind. In discussing
                        another intelligence, that of Frederich Hölderlin, Richard Unger made
                        some observations about Blake in a literary context, but they seem equally
                        apt here: “Like Blake, Hölderlin was not adequately valued or
                        even partially understood until the twentieth century. And he has likewise
                        remained permanently esoteric and ‘difficult’ for us; critics
                        are still grappling with the literal meaning of his major poems. But, also,
                        as in the case of Blake, it is perhaps the very quality of this difficulty
                        which often intrigues us. For these 
<pb id="p16-232" n="232"/>
poets
                        sometimes appear to understand more than we do; they admittedly share our
                        problems but we suspect they have seen these problems more clearly and in
                        greater depth. And in our interpretations it may seem that (rather than
                        explaining their ‘relevance’) we are attempting to discover
                        something which, in the silence of their texts, they already
                            know”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n105" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n105"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> Hölderlin’s Major Poetry: The Dialectics of
                                Unity</hi> (Bloomington and London: Indiana Univ. Press, 1975), p.
                            7. My thanks to Larry Day for bringing the Unger paragraph to my
                            attention.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
