<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>16.4.atkins</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">“Both Turk and Jew”: Notes on the Poetry of Henry Fuseli, with Some
Translations</title>
        <author n="Atkins">A. M. Atkins</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1983</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">16.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Barbara Guth</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Adelheid M. Atkins</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
              <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>John Wilcox</name>
              <name>Carl Woodring</name>
              <name>Warren Keith Wright</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_16">
    <body>
      <pb id="p16-206" n="206"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-16-4-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">“Both Turk and Jew”: Notes on the Poetry of Henry
                            Fuseli, with Some Translations</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">A. M.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">ATKINS</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>As Detlef W. Dörrbecker points out in “Fuseli, the Swiss, and the
                    British: Some Recent Publications,” the 1973 Zurich edition of
                    Fuseli’s poems, although not entirely complete, is nevertheless a
                    valuable addition to the expanding fund of knowledge concerning the poetic
                    output of the celebrated painter.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33"
type="note">1</ref>
                    Unfortunately, except for occasionally quoted passages, the poems have not been
                    translated and have received relatively little critical attention. To convey
                    something of the flavor of these poems, I have attempted to translate a few
                    representative samples, appended below. <note id="n33"><hi rend="s">1</hi>
                        Johann Heinrich Füssli, <hi rend="i">Sämtliche Gedichte</hi>,
                        ed. Martin Bircher and Karl S. Guthke (Zürich, 1973), reviewed by
                        Detlef W. Dörrbecker in “Fuseli, The Swiss, And The British:
                        Some Recent Publications,” <hi rend="i">Blake: An Illustrated
                            Quarterly</hi>, 15 (Summer 1981), 54-56.</note></p>
        <p>Modern critical evaluations of the poems, made largely by German or Swiss
                    commentators, are rather negative; usually, “the other side of his art,
                    the literary, is judged with a certain hesitancy” and considered
                    “time-bound, manneristic classicism.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n34" type="note">2</ref> Eudo Mason, the scholar most instrumental in the
                    mid-twentieth-century Fuseli revival, reminds us, however, that Fuseli
                    “can never be fully understood, unless his writings are also taken into
                    account” and acknowledges Fuseli’s talents as translator,
                    aphorist, and critic while being somewhat less than enthusiastic over his
                        poems.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">3</ref> Yet
although critical strictures
                    seem justified, the poems are nevertheless of interest to the historian as well
                    as to the comparatist, especially the latter, inasmuch as they permit insight
                    into the mind of a man who, like Faust, is of a divided soul, imbued by
                    “the passion for everything grand and cutting contempt for everything
                        mean,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">4</ref> a
man “in whose
                    daemonic personality exaltation was forever at war with an almost cynical
                        shrewdness,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37"
type="note">5</ref> a man who was
                    wrestling with two languages and two artistic media. <note id="n34"><hi rend="s">2</hi>
Heinrich Füseli, <hi rend="i">Briefe</hi>, ed. Walter
                        Muschg (Basel, 1942), p. 13. Unless otherwise indicated, all translations
                        are mine.</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Eudo C. Mason, <hi rend="i">The Mind of Henry
                            Fuseli: Selections from his Writings with an Introductory Study</hi>
                        (London, 1951), pp.14, 26-29.</note>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Muschg, p. 19.</note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Mason, p. 32.</note></p>
        <p>To attempt an explanation of why Fuseli largely abandoned poetry in favor of the
                    visual arts must, of course, ultimately remain a matter of speculation. Yet
                    certain events in his life and in the culture of his time, as well as a
                    consideration of his personality, may serve to shed some light, at least, on why
                    he chose to concentrate on the representative arts. All signs in Fuseli’s
                    early life pointed to his becoming a man of letters. As a youngster, he was bred
                    to the ministry and seems to have shown promise as a teacher of considerable
                    rhetorical power. Indeed, “he regarded poetry as his true
                        vocation”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">6</ref>
and, having attained
                    considerable proficiency in several languages, devoured not only the ancient
                    classics but also Shakespeare, Milton, and certain eighteenth-century English
                    poets. It was Fuseli’s good fortune to grow up in Zurich, then one of the
                    fortresses in the Germanic revolt against French neoclassicism. Johann
                    Bodmer—poet, translator of Milton, and one of the leaders of the
                    movement—introduced young Fuseli to the English poets considered such
                    admirable models in the fight against convention. Among contemporary German
                    poets, Friedrich Gottlieb Klopstock, the “German Milton,” was
                    young Fuseli’s favorite. He tried his hand at a Shakespearean tragedy,
                        <hi rend="i">The Death of Saul</hi> (now lost),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">7</ref> and, when barely twenty, created a sensation with his, at
first
                    anonymously circulated, odes in the manner of Klopstock. Indeed, it was thought
                    that these odes were actually Klopstock’s; among those who knew better,
                    Johann Georg Zimmermann went so far as to claim that “compared to
                    Fuseli’s odes, many of Klopstock’s are like
                        ‘water.’”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
type="note">8</ref> And
                    Johann Kaspar Lavater, one of Fuseli’s best friends, ranks him equal to
                        Goethe.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Mason, p. 15.</note>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Muschg, p. 19.</note>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Letter to Herder, 13 April 1775, in Heinrich
                        Düntzer and Ferdinand Gottfried von Herder, eds., <hi rend="i">Aus
                            Herders Nachlass</hi>, vol. 2 (Frankfurt, 1857), p. 348; here quoted
                        from <hi rend="i">Sämtliche Gedichte</hi>, p. 108.</note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Letter to Herder, 4 February 1774, in <hi rend="i">Aus Herders
Nachlass</hi>, p. 89; here quoted from <hi rend="i">Sämtliche Gedichte</hi>, p. 103.</note></p>
        <p>If such praise nowadays seems exaggerated, even stranger is the fact that it is
                    based on a mere handful of poems. According to Martin Bircher, of the 46 poems
                    in the 1973 Zurich edition, only 11 were published during Fuseli’s
                    lifetime. And although Fuseli never seems entirely to have given up writing or
                    at least revising his poetry, the bulk, 28 poems, was written prior to 1780,
                    with the decade from 1760 to 1770 being the most productive. Only 14 of
                    Fuseli’s poems can be assumed to have been written after 1800, and only
                    one after 1812.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">10</ref>
Thus, after 1770 Fuseli
                    turned his back on poetry, except for a brief resurgence in late 1779 and early
                    1780, occasioned by an abortive love affair.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n43" type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Significantly, this is the English
                        “Petrarca Fragment,” <hi rend="i">Sämthiche
                            Gedichte</hi>, p. 100.</note>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Dörrbecker, p. 53, summarizes
                        critical opinion on “Nannas Auge” (“Nanna’s
                        Eye”).</note></p>
        <p>In terms of events, the years between 1762 and 1779 are the stormiest in
                    Fuseli’s life and artistically no doubt the most critical. Having
                    denounced a powerful Zurich official, Fuseli fled in 1763 from his native land,
                    spent some time in Germany, and in 1764 settled in England. There he was
                    initially very active in literary matters but also painted a great deal. In 1768
                    Sir Joshua Reynolds advised Fuseli to go to Italy and concentrate on painting.
                    Fuseli stayed in Italy from 1770 to 1778 and, after a brief visit to
                    Switzerland, returned to England in 1778, settling into a “golden
                        exile”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44"
type="note">12</ref>—golden certainly
                    as far as painting was concerned but not so propitious, it seems, for his
                    poetry. <note id="n44"><hi rend="s">12</hi><hi rend="i"> Gedichte</hi>, p. 106.</note></p>
        <pb id="p16-207" n="207"/>
        <p>To add any new insights to Dörrbecker’s evaluation of the poems and
                    his succinct presentation of their critical reception by others is impossible,
                    except that I should like to plead for a certain freshness and noble cadence in
                    Fuseli’s “Ode to His Friends Left Behind” (see below),
                    which seems to adumbrate that of Hölderlin. Elsewhere, to be sure, Fuseli
                    virtually never descends from the heights of rhetoric, indulging in a great deal
                    of hyperbole and excessively metaphoric language, especially in his penchant for
                    non-functional personification. At the time, of course, this was in perfectly
                    good taste, and even where he is irregular and strident, Fuseli moves safely
                    within the confines of <hi rend="i">Sturm und Drang</hi> language.</p>
        <p>Ironically enough, the impressions conveyed by the original poems do not always
                    come across in the translations. Thus I have refrained from rendering the
                    simple, lovely “Nannas Auge,” which would fall rather flat
                    —not surprising, of course, if one considers the untranslatable quality
                    of lyric poetry. On the other hand (but unfortunately I have no way of proving
                    this), the odes, so bombastic in the original, may actually seem somewhat less
                    so in English.</p>
        <p>Beyond the formal aspects of Fuseli’s poetry, its most salient
                    characteristic, as Dörrbecker points out, is the conventionality of
                        thought.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">13</ref>
Although, as one can readily
                    see, Fuseli often sounds dreadfully daring, revolutionary, and even irrational,
                    such tactics were fast becoming conventional. His ideas are firmly rooted in
                    Englishtenment philosophy, for example, the Great Chain of Being mentioned in
                        “Patience.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46"
type="note">14</ref> And even
                    while he strikes a Satanic pose in “Hell,” his seemingly
                    impressive attack nevertheless validates the great system; despite being overtly
                    “determinéd to be a villain,” Fuseli sanctions traditional
                    values. As with Blake, Milton’s Satan is Fuseli’s hero too, but,
                    according to Gert Schiff, Fuseli’s Satan is merely a convenient
                    “carrier of humanitarian protest against the suffering of the
                        world,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">15</ref>
which at the time of
                    the poem (after 1803) is not an over-whelmingly novel idea. Fuseli may simply
                    have been “more inclined with Milton’s hand to open the gates of
                    Hell than the gates of Heaven”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48"
type="note">16</ref>
                    because he liked dramatically impressive, horrible situations<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">17</ref> eliciting in the reader the sensation of the sublime so
                    fashionable at the time. Unlike Turner, a painter whose poetry suffered from the
                    fact that “he had only an eighteenth-century diction to express a vision
                    that had passed far beyond all eighteenth-century limitations,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">18</ref> Fuseli had in due time come to lack both
                    the diction and the vision. <note id="n45"><hi rend="s">13</hi>
                        Dörrbecker, p. 54.</note>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Ursula Ditchburn-Bosch, <hi rend="i">Johann
                            Heinrich Füsslis Kunstlehre und ihre Auswirkung auf seine
                            Shakespeare-Interpretation</hi> (Zürich, 1968). Her entire essay
                        concerns itself with the conventionality of Fuseli’s ideas.</note>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Gert Schiff, <hi rend="i">Johann Heinrich
                            Füsslis Milton-Galerie</hi> (Zürich, 1963), p. 6.</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Geoffrey Grigson, “Painters of the
                        Abyss,” <hi rend="i">Architectural Review</hi>, 108 (1950),
                        217.</note>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Ernst Wirz, <hi rend="i">Die literarische
                            Tätigkeit des Malers Johann Heinrich Füssli</hi> (Basel,
                        1922), p. 83.</note>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Jack Lindsay, ed., <hi rend="i">The Sunset
                            Ship: The Poems of J.M.W. Turner</hi> (London, 1966), p. 13.</note></p>
        <p>Yet although the merit of Fuseli’s poetic endeavors is at best debatable,
                    one cannot help but concede his obvious potential. If any artist thus doubly
                    gifted abandons one form of expression for the sake of the other, what may have
                    been his reasons? There are several possibilities. One of these may have been
                    that Fuseli acquired a second language. While English presents no overwhelming
                    difficulties to a native speaker of German, to attain polish and full
                    sensitivity to the new language does require time. (Here, of course, one is
                    immediately reminded of exceptions, such as that of Joseph Conrad who
                    successfully crossed a language barrier far more formidable than that between
                    German and English.) It may be remembered that Fuseli had begun to study English
                    at an early age, and throughout his life in England he wrote a good deal of
                    critical prose, as well as lecturing at the Royal Academy. His English prose
                    style has been deemed “assured, learned, lively, and economical, never
                    betraying the fact that German and not English was his native
                        tongue.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">19</ref>
On the other hand, he
                    virtually never attempted writing English verse.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n52" type="note">20</ref> Perhaps he was too proud to engage in a pursuit in which he must
                    have feared to come out second best or worse, a humiliation difficult to accept
                    for one who, like Satan, had been pampered and flattered in his youth. Even such
                    an intimate friend of Fuseli’s as Mary Wollstonecraft was forced to tell
                    him on a certain occasion “I hate to see that reptile Vanity sliming over
                    the noble qualities of your heart”;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53"
type="note">21</ref>
                    no doubt Fuseli’s pride and vanity led him to drink in Reynolds’
                    lavish praise and consequently to change vocations. In painting, of course, one
                    does not have to wrestle with accent and other verbal obstacles to
                    communication. But the objection that his new involvement may simply have left
                    him neither time nor inclination for poetry can be countered easily enough by
                    ample evidence of double talents functioning quite satisfactorily, of which
                    Blake’s is of course one of the best cases in point. And even though
                    Fuseli rejected English poetry as a vehicle of expression, he might at least
                    have continued to write German poetry. <note id="n51"><hi rend="s">19</hi>
                        Marcia Allentuck, “Henry Fuseli’s ‘Queen
                        Katherine’ and Macklin’s Poets’ Gallery: A New
                        Critique,” <hi rend="i">Journal of the Warburg and Courtauld
                            Institutes</hi>, 39 (1976), 267.</note>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">20</hi> “Dunciad of Painting—Four
                        Fragments” and the “Petrarca Fragment,” <hi rend="i">Gedichte</hi>, pp. 80-81,
p. 100 and “The Kings of
                        Earth,” Mason, pp. 117-18.</note>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">21</hi> John Knowles, <hi rend="i">The Life and
                            Writings of Henry Fuseli, Esq. M. A. R. A.</hi> (London, 1831), vol. I,
                        p. 363.</note></p>
        <p>Of all the commentators, Eudo Mason puts his finger most precisely on what seems
                    to have been the heart of Fuseli’s poetic problem, namely, that he turned
                    his back on literature at the very time when exciting breakthroughs were being
                    made by German and English poets. Fuseli not only turned traitor to his own
                    <corr type="emend">culture: “he</corr> lists, bragging a little on occasion, the names
of English
                    poets and learned men against whom the Germans fall far short”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">22</ref>—this could be explained as some
                    sort of overcompensation for culture shock, but “throughout his life,
                    down to his old age, he seems to have clung to certain quasi-orthodox ideas
                    about the nature of God, the relationship of God to man, and the metaphysical
                    reality of sin, evil, and damnation.” This, according to Mason, kept
                    Fuseli from becoming a “real” romantic.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n55" type="note">23</ref>
	<note id="n54"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Muschg, p. 30.</note>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">23</hi> Mason, pp. 14-17.</note></p>
        <p>What happened to Fuseli is an instructive example of what Morse Peckham calls
                    “neo-classic disintegration,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56"
type="note">24</ref> a state perhaps less painful to the visual artist for, as E. H.
                    Gombrich suggests, “the terms ‘true’ and
                    ‘false’ can only be applied to statements. . . . a picture is
                    never a statement in that sense of the term.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n57" type="note">25</ref> Had Fuseli mustered the courage, even at the risk of
                    losing face, to continue to break through Enlightenment restraints and to keep
                    up with the romantic avant-garde, he might have developed into a poet of
                    significance at least equal to that which he attained as a painter. 
<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Morse Peckham, <hi rend="i">The Triumph of
                            Romanticism: Collected Essays</hi> (Columbia, S. C., 1970), p.
                        24n.</note>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">25</hi> E. H. Gombrich, <hi rend="i">Art and
                            Illusion: A Study in the Psychology of Pictorial Representation</hi>
                        (New York, 1961), pp. 67-68.</note></p>
        <pb id="p16-208" n="208"/>
        <p>In light of these considerations, one is tempted to see in Blake’s epithet
                    “both Turk and Jew,” though jocular and friendly on the conscious
                    level, additional and even rather sinister meaning. Can Blake have sensed
                    somehow that Fuseli was an infidel of a different sort, having refused to grow
                    as a poet and thus having betrayed the splendid gift he demonstrated in his
                    youth, that he stonily ignored the progress made by poets at the highest
                    cultural level? Of course it is hardly possible that Blake was aware of the
                    existence of Fuseli’s poems, but Blake the clairvoyant was a man hard to
                    fool. There is something Urizenic in Fuseli’s pride, in his resolution to
                    slam the door on what was truly creative in the poetry of his time. The ideas
                    expressed in the following poems, as well as their style, would seem to lend
                    credence to such speculations.</p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Ode To His Friends Left Behind [Essex, 1765]<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n58" type="note">26</ref>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">26</hi><hi rend="i"> Gedichte</hi>, p. 44.</note>
	</title>
          </head>
          <table rows="5" cols="2">
            <row>
              <cell>Like the childish brook in its glistening bed<lb/>
              Of mossy rocks, nurtured with the fragrance<lb/>
              Gathered of the breathing grove, with your dew,<lb/>
              Spring, by the motherly Naiad;<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Once more, the storms poured out by thundering<lb/>
              Summer, Autumn’s never-dried tears,<lb/>
              The host flocking round winter—<lb/>
              Now they have swelled him into a manly stream:<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell>5<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Tearing himself from his mother’s embraces<lb/>
              And swiftly escaping the echoing narrower urn,<lb/>
              He rolls down the cliffs,<lb/>
              Hastens through groves, meadows, and valleys;<lb/>
<lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              10<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Groves, meadows, and valleys he never saw before<lb/>
              He swiftly traverses in eagle’s flight,<lb/>
              Now playfully winding his course, now moving imprisoned,<lb/>
              Now lordly attracting others with his victorious trumpet.<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              15<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Yet of the blossoms his young mouth once lovingly kissed<lb/>
              As he flowed down the meadows, none drifts on his waves;<lb/>
              Never to see them more, he rushes toward the ocean—<lb/>
              Falls—dies, dissolved in it.<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              20<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Oh country I fled from! Bonds I have broken!<lb/>
              Friends wept for but seldom! Did I not rush thus from you?<lb/>
              May my day roar and play, lost to you;<lb/>
              It drives me toward the sea of eternity!</cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
          </table>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Patience [Second Version] [London, 1766]<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n59" type="note">27</ref>
	<note id="n59"><hi rend="s">27</hi><hi rend="i"> Gedichte</hi>, pp. 49-51.</note>
	</title>
          </head>
          <table rows="20" cols="2">
            <row>
              <cell>Exalted Being, from whose countenance<lb/>
              Streameth eternity, queen of all those<lb/>
              Who strive, wandering through the labyrinth<lb/>
              Of His time, to find the father of all spirits;<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Patience, of Providence the sadly smiling,<lb/>
              Gentle-eyed and submissive daughter, you<lb/>
              From whose healing hand balm trickles<lb/>
              Upon the wounds your mother inflicts;<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell>5<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>At whose bosom of rising hopes the<lb/>
              Children of law subdued by power, of<lb/>
              Expectations betrayed, the myriads<lb/>
              Whom Hell pursues with iron stride,<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              10<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Fling themselves, tired and parched, and drink<lb/>
              Instead of true promises often but new expectations<lb/>
              And the bliss of dreams, often deceived, seeing<lb/>
              Suns in the delusive light of midnight.<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              15<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Oh come, Consoling One! me, too, approach me,<lb/>
              A son of grief! Yet when you come,<lb/>
              Leave behind all vain consolation<lb/>
              That but gleams to be extinguished.<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              20<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>If the tear of despondency moistens my gloomy eye,<lb/>
              Oh, to dry it do not call her who<lb/>
              Regards inexorably the purple of rulers, too,<lb/>
              Surrounded by kneeling slaves.<lb/>
<lb/>
</cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Do not call her who mixes loathing<lb/>
              With the wine of joy’s sparkling cup;<lb/>
              Do not rend asunder the amaranth bowers<lb/>
              Of Eden because flowers also give shelter to snakes;<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell>25<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Nor let me dream of beauty’s lily-breasts,<lb/>
              Of lips’ love-dew whispered ‘round with kisses,<lb/>
              Of cheeks rosily dawning, of the eye’s<lb/>
              Soul, of voluptuousness’ secret treasures<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              30<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <table>
            <row>
              <cell> And of what wafts from Sappho’s side—<lb/>
              If the Father gave it me, he took it back,<lb/>
              Gave it to others—but not to turn the sublime arrow<lb/>
              Into a source of whining lament.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="p208U1"
type="note">*</ref><lb/>
              <lb/>
              <note id="p208U1">* MS difficult to decipher and incomprehensible.</note>
	</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              35<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Deem gold more than dung, and laurel-wreathed fame<lb/>
              More than cymbals to the deaf; do not merely say<lb/>
              To Knowledge: “You are vain—wander on Saturn<lb/>
              Or creep with the lowly hyssop.”<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              40<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>From life’s sunlit heights<lb/>
              Do not exile me to its night-valleys, where<lb/>
              Misery rests its leaden frame<lb/>
              Against the crumbling hut of poverty;<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Where sickness, its daggers heavy, embraces with ailing arm<lb/>
              Job on the pallet withered by agony<lb/>
              And teaches him with pain-winged lip<lb/>
              To curse the day he was born!<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell>45<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Grief and loathing stifle my harp—<lb/>
              Shall pale hatred of men with its dagger eye<lb/>
              Give me consolation mixed with envy? Oh, if so,<lb/>
              Traitress, thrust first my dehumanized heart<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              50<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Into some savage’s tiger-breast, to whom fetters sing of repose,</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
</cell>
        	</row>
          </table>
          <pb id="p16-209" n="209"/>
          <table>
            <row>
              <cell>To whom a prison rattles music because the suffering of strangers<lb/>
              Howls at him, who for the destruction of Lisbon<lb/>
              (Did not even this break his chains?) gives blasphemous thanks unto God!<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              55<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>But let the vertigo of midnight’s despair<lb/>
              With its drooping eye,<lb/>
              Shrouded melancholy, your phantom, Brutus,<lb/>
              Teach me to embrace<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              60<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Before I beg consolation from base comparisons<lb/>
              And rend the unending social ties<lb/>
              Wrought by Nature<lb/>
              And find it [consolation] through you in creation!<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>No! Child of Providence, if you do bring consolation,<lb/>
              Do not come with such, but let the hand of peace<lb/>
              From the light-encircled throne of the Father,<lb/>
              Religion, your Sister, bring it with you.<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell>65<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>(Not the Roman Fury, whose bloodspattered head,<lb/>
              Licked by Hell all around, swells to heaven, not<lb/>
              She who taught Luther to quarrel, Calvin’s<lb/>
              Hectic Theosophy, do not mistake her!)<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              70<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>She, my goddess, when possibility gave birth to<lb/>
              Stars without number, as grains of sand,<lb/>
              Left your place, angels, near to God,<lb/>
              For men’s lowlier circle—Thus the High One speaks:<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              75<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>“Ancient tribes of Genesis! He Who created, created you<lb/>
              For eternity, and only one thing<lb/>
              Shall be immortal—whether it bathe, a Seraphim,<lb/>
              In oceans of light or grope in the dust;<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              80<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>“Host of brethren without number! Diverse but in age, illumination,<lb/>
              And order, yet all alike in essence—<lb/>
              God holds the chain. Can the first of its links<lb/>
              Be closer to Him than the last?<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>“Hasten then, content, cheerful, and steady,<lb/>
              With brotherly hands entwined, hasten<lb/>
              To the grand destiny of all spirits,<lb/>
              To the sun-portal of perfection:<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell>85<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>“Finite being [i.e., finiteness], ‘tis true, will often surround you<lb/>
              With clouds, often with darkness; yet behold her<lb/>
              Who leads you through to the light”—thus she spoke,<lb/>
              And you appeared at her side,<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              90<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Patience, of Providence the sadly smiling,<lb/>
              Gentle-eyed and submissive daughter, you<lb/>
              From whose healing hand balm trickles<lb/>
              Upon the wounds your mother inflicts.</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              95<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>[God’s Gifts] [1766 or 1767]<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60"
type="note">28</ref>
	<note id="n60"><hi rend="s">28</hi><hi rend="i"> Gedichte</hi>, p. 54.</note>
	</title>
          </head>
          <table rows="6" cols="2">
            <row>
              <cell>The King of kings gave unto monarchs pride<lb/>
              And herds of slaves around a fearsome throne—<lb/>
              [Yet] denied them wisdom: why would they deem<lb/>
              Men mere beasts to be strangled and slaughtered?<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>He gave the idle dream of groping for truth<lb/>
              Where no mortal has ever caught her,<lb/>
              To the philosophers’ blind herd,<lb/>
              Armed with telescopes and spectacles;<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell>5<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>To the desecrated order of priests He gave<lb/>
              The illusion of teaching religion and love—<lb/>
              Of human duties the most exalted—<lb/>
              By way of everything but virtue:<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              10<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Gifts of wrath all. Among kings, did any ever<lb/>
              Base royal law and majesty<lb/>
              On God-like benevolence, which raises<lb/>
              The sons of dust to angelic nobility?<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              15<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Gone astray among stars, into oceans sunk,<lb/>
              Hardly a one of the myriads brooding over wisdom<lb/>
              Gets to know the Good and Evil in his own house<lb/>
              Before he is stretched on his bier.<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              20<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>The teacher of priests gave living testimony<lb/>
              Of what his lips asked in sparing words;<lb/>
              Where is the priest whose outpouring of words<lb/>
              Is marked by the seal of good conduct and example?<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>To me, He gave creative power and a flaming heart.<lb/>
              Why ask for anything higher? Should I ask for love,<lb/>
              Heaven’s prerogative? Oh, then I also ought to plead<lb/>
              For virtue, which not to men . . .<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell>25<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Which He to angels gave; here, only its shadow passes. . . .</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>[Second Ode on Art] [between 1772 and 1775]<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n61" type="note">29</ref>
	<note id="n61"><hi rend="s">29</hi><hi rend="i"> Gedichte</hi>, pp. 67-68.</note>
	</title>
          </head>
          <table rows="8" cols="2">
            <row>
              <cell>Among the mob that every northern wind<lb/>
              Blows into your palaces, oh Rome,<lb/>
              The mob of Germans, Britons, French,<lb/>
              The mob of Polish and of Muscovites,<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>The vermin of art—thus I spent a day<lb/>
              Wandering with trembling foot among your temples,<lb/>
              And cursed in furor insensate<lb/>
              The academies of London and of France.<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell>5<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Contempt, disgust, hope with nocturnal<lb/>
              Despair wrestling—these drove me into solitude,<lb/>
              To stretch out on my couch rumpled by<lb/>
              Tossings of agony, and painfully wringing my hands<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              10<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>I exclaimed: “Is this the way to immortality?<lb/>
              Did you create, Prime Mover, this, my exalted spirit,<lb/>
              The sympathies of this, my soul,<lb/>
              But to count muscles and to mix pigments?<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              15<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <pb id="p16-210" n="210"/>
          <table>
          	<row>
          	  <cell>Did Agn[i]olo unlock the gates of heaven<lb/>
          	  And bid the gods stride among men<lb/>
          	  In order now to arbitrate the quarrel<lb/>
          	  Of French and Britons about nature and style?<lb/>
          	  <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Here in the halls of Leo, did Urbino’s son<lb/>
              Athens evoke and spread the vast, magnificent tent<lb/>
              Of faith to lend the Teuton’s hordes<lb/>
              Draperies and heads to carry home?<lb/>
<lb/>
</cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>If this be art, may night eternally<lb/>
              Seal this, my eye, and cause to shrivel<lb/>
              This hand, extended formerly to help others—<lb/>
              Lamed thus, but nevermore defiled.”<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell>25<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Thus cried I, and a slumber shut my lids;<lb/>
              And a vision, such as my soul<lb/>
              Would hardly have dared to wish for,<lb/>
              My genius sent me in a dream.<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              30<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>I thought I stood in Sixtus’ temple-hall<lb/>
              For as long as the time of shifting evening light<lb/>
              Pours trembling beauty and majesty<lb/>
              Over the many pictures of gods.<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              35<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>I think I saw the veil of eternity<lb/>
              Torn: Time and space and matter gave birth:<lb/>
              From the Almighty’s finger streamed<lb/>
              Life, and Adam leaped from the dust.</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              40<lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Hell [after 1803]<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62" type="note">30</ref>
	<note id="n62"><hi rend="s">30</hi><hi rend="i"> Gedichte</hi>, pp. 93-94.</note>
	</title>
          </head>
          <table rows="12" cols="2">
            <row>
              <cell>The theologian’s blasphemous chimera,<lb/>
              Phantom of superstition, faith’s dream,<lb/>
              Snarling of the mob, scourging of the clergy,<lb/>
              Nonsense to the thinker, mockery to the free-thinker,<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Ghastliest sister of a most beautiful brother,<lb/>
              Religion bore you to State in twin-labor,<lb/>
              Lifting him high and calling him Heaven,<lb/>
              Lowering you into the abyss<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell>5<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>
              And contemptuously calling you Hell! I hail you, Hell!<lb/>
              True, you were not given golden light over meadows of amaranth,<lb/>
              Nor ambrosia and streams of nectar,<lb/>
              Nor infant angels yawning in cloud cradles,<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              10<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>
              Choirs of psalmodizing harps,<lb/>
              Saints of fable and by decree — your throne<lb/>
              Flames out amid the roars of<lb/>
              Agonized hosts eternally cast out,<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              15<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Where the waves of mute light and darkness visible<lb/>
              Encircle the poets’ terrifying realms, where<lb/>
              The Great wrestles with the Monstrous,<lb/>
              And Horror with Loathing,<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              20<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Where Styx wallows, a thundering water of curses,<lb/>
              Where Phlegethon’s vortices gleam red, where<lb/>
              Cocytus howls, Lethe slumbers —<lb/>
              There, amid thunder, lightning, and howls your verse falls asleep.<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Cliff-bound by you in adamantine chains,<lb/>
              Friend vainly pleads for friend’s helpless arm!<lb/>
              In you, the flood-encircled thirsty one’s lip<lb/>
              Yearns, and will forever yearn!<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell>25<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Up on the mountain, Sisyphus, in a cloud of dust,<lb/>
              Strives to push the boulder’s weight and strives in vain;<lb/>
              Reversed by the thrust of your powerful hand,<lb/>
              The exultant boulder whirls down to the plain.<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              30<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Odin departs from Walhalla’s starry halls<lb/>
              To propitiate you — Niflheim mutely refuses the god,<lb/>
              From the abyss your finger rises;<lb/>
              Death puts his seal on Balder’s brow.<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              35<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>It was you that dropped the lindentree’s leaf<lb/>
              On the hero’s breast, who, thinking himself invulnerable,<lb/>
              Bathed in the worm’s blood, and who,<lb/>
              Without armor, defied battle sword, bow, and spear.<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              40<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Fanned by your breath, the flame of Dante<lb/>
              Blinds us, grows pale at the dawning summit<lb/>
              On a cliff, and is extinguished<lb/>
              In the slumber of paradise suns.<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell/>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Unsexed by you, the thane’s wife inspires<lb/>
              Her husband’s hesitant hand to murder Duncan;<lb/>
              Somnambulent, guided by you,<lb/>
              She roams through the frightened hall.<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell>45<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>You flung Satan’s fire-pyramid up high;<lb/>
              Yours is the billowing night-tent of the anarchist;<lb/>
              Yours is the sister’s unnatural son, yours<lb/>
              The thousand forms of the lazar-house.<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              50<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Like sand on the seashore, gathered around<lb/>
              The foot of your throne, there trembles the dwarfish host<lb/>
              Of nation-stranglers, mob-gods,<lb/>
              Imperial vermin, and the bandits of hierarchy.<lb/>
</cell>
              <cell><lb/>
              <lb/>
              55<lb/>
              <lb/>
</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p16-211" n="211" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>