<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>16.4.deluca</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="article">The Changing Order of Plates in Jerusalem, Chapter II</title>
                <author n="De Luca">V. A. De Luca</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Spring 1983</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1983</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">16.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
                            <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
                            <name>Susan Corban</name>
                            <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
                            <name>Peter Chase</name>
                            <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
                            <name>Barbara Guth</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
                            <resp>Review Editor</resp>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>Adelheid M. Atkins</name>
                            <name>David Bindman</name>
                            <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
                            <name>Ruth E. Fine</name>
                            <name>Thomas V. Lange</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>John Wilcox</name>
                            <name>Carl Woodring</name>
                            <name>Warren Keith Wright</name>
                            <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date value="1983"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_16">
        <body>
        <pb id="p16-192" n="192"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-16-4-0005">
                <head>
                    <title type="main">
                        <hi rend="b">The Changing Order of Plates in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,
                            Chapter II</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <byline>
                    <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
                    <docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="i">V. A.</hi>
                        <name>
                            <hi rend="i">DE LUCA</hi>
                        </name>
                    </docAuthor>
                </byline>
                <p>As everyone knows who has ever gone from a text of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                    edited by Keynes to one edited by Erdman, the second chapter of the work exists
                    in two arrangements of plates.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n0"
type="note">*</ref>	
                        <note id="n0">I wish to express my gratitude to Morton D. Paley, David V. Erdman and
G.E.
                        Bentley, Jr., for stimulating and enlightening exchanges on the subject
                        treated in this essay and for other generosities during its
                        preparation.</note> Certain inconveniences have attended this fact—a clutter
                    of bracketed numbers to designate the variant plates, confusions in the
                    classroom when students show up with the differing texts, difficulties for
                    readers of the Doubleday edition when they use the Concordance and Damon’s 
                        <hi rend="i">Dictionary.</hi> More troubling, the existence of these widely
                    differing arrangements tends to feed the still common suspicion that the order
                    of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is arbitrary, capricious, and perhaps incoherent.
                    Blake criticism, however, has generally shied away from this textual problem,
                    troubling or not. It remains, in the words of one important critic, “a vexing
                    question that deserves a complete analysis never accorded it.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1"
                        type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Stuart Curran, “The
                        Structures of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,” in <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime
                            Allegory: Essays on</hi> The Four Zoas, Milton, <hi rend="i">and</hi>
                        Jerusalem, ed. Stuart Curran and Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr. (Madison:
                        Univ. of Wisconsin Press, 1973), p. 334.</note></p>
                <p>A complete analysis is perhaps not feasible; the external record is barren of
                    pertinent information, and we still know too little about the principles that
                    inform Blake’s architectonics to settle the matter conclusively by an appeal to
                    those principles. The best we can do is to interpret the available data with
                    hypotheses that are plausible, consistent, and widely applicable to the art of
                        <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Mindful of the speculative nature of the
                    enterprise, I will venture in this essay to provide such hypotheses along with
                    the evidence that supports them. If the following arguments are detailed, it is
                    because I believe that the question of Chapter II is important enough to warrant
                    close pursuit, not only for its intrinsic interest but also for the suggestive
                    light it sheds on the creative forces that shape <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as
                    a whole.</p>
                <p>The questions raised by the reordering of plates in Chapter II are questions of
                    form and structure, not questions of thematic meaning. What kind of work is it,
                    we are forced to ask, that can suffer its internal sequences to become
                    transposed without any radical disturbance to the equilibrium of the whole?
                    Among the possible answers to this question are two that fit the particular
                    characteristics of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>: it is a work composed of
                    sub-units that are discrete and autonomous,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n2" type="note">2</ref>
                    and it is a work where coherence of visual design often rules arrangements at
                    the expense of narrative and thematic continuity. In Chapter II these
                    characteristics are somewhat easier to observe than they are elsewhere in the
                    poem. In transposing pls. 29-41 with 43-46 (as numbered in the First Order<ref
                        target="n3" type="note">3</ref> of copies A and C) when he assembled copies
                    D and E, Blake revealed the seams and faultlines of the chapter, the boundaries
                    of its tectonic components, units that remain undivided themselves in either
                    arrangement. Three extended sets of plates emerge to view, 29-41, 43-46, and
                    47-50 (I refer to them hereafter, respectively, as Sequences 1, 2, and 3). Once
                    we become aware of the seams between these internal units, we are quick to
                    notice other seams even where the “stitching” has remained intact. The thirteen
                    plates of Sequence 1 soon resolve themselves into two more or less autonomous
                    sets, 29-32 and 33-41, the latter containing the centerpiece of the chapter, the
                    parley of the cathedral cities gathered to save Albion. Each of these separable
                    units in the chapter maintains its own autonomous coherence both in verbal
                    content and in framing visual design. As poetry, these units take the form of
                    detachable dramatic setpieces, as in pls. 33-41, or more typically, of radically
                    condensed epics, self-sufficient synoptic visions of Blake’s total myth;<ref
                        target="n4" type="note">4</ref> the work as a whole comes to look like a
                    compilation of brief epic lays devoted to the same cycle of myths, with the
                    inevitable variations overlaps, and repetitions that such compilations
                        display.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> At
the same time the visual
                    designs that penetrate and frame these lays array themselves in demonstrably
                    coherent patterns, and each pattern is specific to the unit it frames, the key
                    signature, as it were, of that unit’s autonomy. It appears that the small
                    narrative units acquired their visual shapes and their etched state long before
                    they fell together into the order we find in the earliest extant copies of 
                        <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Karl Kroeber has
                        cited Blake’s penchant for repetition to account for 
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem’s</hi> structure: “Reiteration permits a fluidity of
                        structure; to a degree plates can be rearranged because reordering does not
                        upset patterns of allusion” (“Delivering <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>” in 
                            <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory</hi>, p. 352n). I would put the matter
                        the other way around: fluidity of structure permits repetition. Because the
                        units are discrete, not enchained in a consecutive argument, they tend
                        toward internal comprehensiveness, and comprehensiveness within the part
                        virtually guarantees repetition in the whole.</note>
	<note id="n3"><hi
                            rend="s">3</hi> The terms “First Order” and “Second Order,” used in this
                        essay to refer to the plate orders of copies A-C-F and copies D-E,
                        respectively, are borrowed from G.E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1977), p. 234. Plate numbers belonging to
                        the First Order are printed in roman type, Second Order numbers in italics,
                        but only when they vary from the First Order numbers. All editors agree that
                        the arrangement of Chapter II found in copies A-C-F is the earlier. For more
                        on the subject, see the seminal essay of David V. Erdman, “The Suppressed
                        and Altered Passages in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,” 
                            <hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi>, 17 (1964), p. 40 ff.</note>	
                            <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> I use the term “synoptic” here in its sense
of
                        “constituting a synopsis,” not in its New Testament sense of a story
                        harmonizable with other accounts, the sense employed, for example, by Joanne
                        Witke in “<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>: A Synoptic Poem.” 
                            <hi rend="i">Comparative Literature</hi>, 22 (Summer 1970), 265-78. To document
                        extensively the conception of the individual sequences within 
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as autonomous synoptic visions would take more space
                        than can be spared here. A brief glance at Sequence 2 (pls. 43-46 in the
                        First Order) may suffice for the time being as an illustration. The sequence
                        starts with a memory of the prelapsarian Eden (“I elected Albion for my
                        glory,” the voice of the Divine Vision begins [43.6]), but Albion turns into
                        “darkning rocks” (43.28) and there ensues a long account of the initial
                        strife of Albion and Luvah (43.33-82), quoted directly from <hi rend="i">The
                            Four Zoas</hi>, Night III, followed by the escape of Enitharmon and the
                        Spectre of Urthona from the wreckage of the fall (44.1-4) and their
                        assimilation in the bosom of Los (44.16-17)—here we see a quick synopsis of
                        much of the action in the five middle nights of <hi rend="i">The Four
                            Zoas.</hi> The sequence then quickly moves us into the present:
                        fortified by his spiritual reunion, Los (Blake) explores London in search of
                        the Minute Particulars (45.2-38) while European war rages (“the strife of
                        Albion &amp; Luvah is great in the east” [45.55-56]), and Albion’s sons
                        aggregate ominously into Druidic powers, bringing the cycle back to where it
                        started: “All things begin &amp; end, in Albions Ancient Druid Rocky Shore”
                        (46.15). Quotations of Blake are from <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of
                            William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday,
                        1970), henceforth cited within the text in parentheses.</note>	
                            <note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi><hi rend="i"> Jerusalem</hi>, considered as a
                        collection of synoptic tales, would have ample precedents in an age filled
                        with compilations and redactions of mythic cycles and bardic remains. The
                        antiquary Edward Davies, whose influence is evident in 
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, thought that Genesis itself might be regarded as a
                        “collection of documents” (with Moses as inspired redactor), especially the
                        first few chapters with their overlapping considerations of the same events
                        and introductory tags that “point out the beginning of detached
                        compilations” (<hi rend="i">Celtic Researches on the Origin, Traditions</hi>
                        &amp; <hi rend="i">Languages of the Ancient Britons</hi> [London: J. Booth,
                        1804], p. 40). Curran, in “The Structures of Jerusalem,” p. 331 ff., is
                        illuminating on the repeating events and overlapping sequences in the work.
                        See also Witke, “<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>: A Synoptic Poem,” 
                            <hi rend="i">passim.</hi></note></p>
                <p>With so much potential autonomy granted to the work’s smaller units it is a
                    wonder that the larger divisions of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, its four
                    chapters, maintain as much stability as they do from copy to copy. Critics often
                    speak of “thematic juxtaposition” as the principle that binds sequence to
                    sequence within the poem,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref> and that principle
                    has fueled enough commentary to make further elaboration of it superfluous here.
                    Less well recognized and more in need of attention is the massive role that
                    patterns of visual design play in forging links between the different sections
                    of each chapter. To cite instances from Chapter II only, sequences 
                        <pb id="p16-193" n="193"/>
rich in large designs<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> are juxtaposed for the sake of balance with sequences that are
                    relatively poor (e.g., pls. 33-41 and 29-32, respectively); iconographically
                    related designs belonging to independent sequences gravitate to one another and
                    bind their respective sequences together (as in the ironic juxtaposition of
                    illuminations on pls. 46 and 47, portraits of Jerusalem and Vala in composure
                    and disarray<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref>);
visual echoes and
                    correspondences appear widely dispersed in the chapter (as in the four half-page
                    illuminations in the chapter, on pls. 28, 37, 41, and 50, the first and the last
                    posted at the extremes of the chapter, the middle pair standing like sentinels
                    on either side of its center—pl. 37 nine positions removed from pl. 28, pl. 41
                    nine positions removed from pl. 50). Such evidence recalls us to the necessity,
                    splendidly demonstrated by W.J.T. Mitchell in <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite
                        Art</hi>, of considering the Blakean illumination “<hi rend="i">as a picture
                        in a world of pictures</hi>,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">9</ref> a world
                    that is essentially independent of the world of text. No attempt to account for
                    the ordering or reordering of plates in a poem as richly illuminated as 
                        <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> can afford to proceed without that insight as a
                    guide. <note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> See Harold Bloom, <hi rend="i">Blake’s
                            Apocalypse: A Study in Poetic Argument</hi> (Garden City, N.Y.:
                        Doubleday, 1963), p. 432.</note>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> By “large”
                        designs, I refer in this essay to illuminations individually occupying a
                        quarter of a plate or more, set off from the text in black (copy E
                        excepted), heavily inked backgrounds, as opposed to small, unframed
                        interlinear or marginal designs. The latter, though often attractive and
                        iconographically significant, do not intrude on the text or strongly
                        demarcate its boundaries as a visual block and are thus left out of my
                        arguments here. There are thirteen large designs, as defined here, in
                        Chapter II of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>: two each on pls. 31, 33, 35, and
                        single blocks on pls. 28, 37, 41, 44, 46, 47, 50. The interlinear design of
                        the plowman on pl. 29 and the headpiece of the blacksmith on 32 are too
                        narrow by far to counteract the visual effect of overwhelming textual
                        presence. The somewhat larger headpieces on pls. 39 and 40 are borderline
                        cases, but I do not consider them to have a significant effect on the
                        balance of distribution in Chapter II’s illuminations.</note>	
                            <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Leopold Damrosch, Jr., in <hi rend="i">Symbol
and
                            Truth in Blake’s Myth</hi> (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1980), p.
                        174, notes that Jerusalem is shown as “Michelangelesque” on pl. 46 and as
                        “contorted in mannerist extremity” on 47.</note>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake’s Composite Art: A Study of the Illuminated
                            Poetry</hi> (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1978), p. 5 (Mitchell’s
                        italics).</note></p>
                <p>Nor may we content ourselves merely with tracing iconographic relationships. The
                    true autonomy of Blake’s designs inheres not in the likelihood that they “mean”
                    something that the text also means, but that they break the text, provide it
                    with spacing, that is, open spaces within it to an antitextual universe. Indeed
                    a study of his work from a purely visual standpoint must see the text itself as
                    a visual element, just as the walls between windows are part of the visual
                    facade of a building. Thus we must attend to the formal layout of Blake’s plates
                        <ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> and consider the location of the
                    design on the plate, the proportions of text space and picture space, and
                    patterns in the distribution of these spaces within the plates taken
                    collectively. Independent of the sense of the texts they accompany, these purely
                    formal patterns often seem to follow laws of their own. As Blake reshapes his
                    work and new patterns arise in his mind, they are quite capable of encroaching
                    on the domain of verbal sense and interfering with its continuity. At the same
                    time local patterns of design become subject to effacement by new influxes of
                    verbal invention. To quote Mitchell again, the “relationship [of text and
                    design] is more like an energetic rivalry, a dialogue or dialectic between
                    vigorously independent modes of expression.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n11" type="note">11</ref> Out of this rivalry (with design often getting the upper hand)
                    come the shape of Chapter II as initially found in the first printed copies and
                    the subsequent changes in order as well. To pursue this argument further,
                    however, and to enforce the general observations made so far, one needs to take
                    a closer look at particulars. <note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> A start in
                        this direction is provided by Kay Parkhurst Easson, “Blake and the Art of
                        the Book,” in <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, ed. Robert N. Essick and
                        Donald Pearce (Bloomington &amp; London: Indiana Univ. Press, 1978), pp.
                        35-52.</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake’s
                            Composite Art</hi>, p. 4.</note></p>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="i">The Early Core of Chapter II: A Reconstruction</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>One useful way of <corr type="emend">approaching</corr> the changes that Blake
introduced into the order
                        of Chapter II when he printed copies D and E is to view these changes as the
                        last visible manifestation of an evolutionary history lost to record except
                        in its very late stages. A certain amount of that history, at least in its
                        latter stages when Chapter II was beginning to coalesce, may be
                        reconstructed, however, from what is actually available to analysis in
                        copies A-C.</p>
                    <p>The long thirteen-plate Sequence 1 is a good place to start. It contains the
                        center of the chapter’s dramatic action, the parley of the cathedral cities.
                        It also contains the most striking example of extended visual patterning in
                        the chapter. Plates 31-37 in particular display as a group a conspicuously
                        formal regularity in the distribution of their designs. Throughout this
                        series plates laden with illuminations alternate consistently with plates
                        fully covered by text (peripheral designs aside); of the illuminated plates,
                        three (31, 33, 35) display a common layout, a miniature pattern of
                        alternation, designs above and below divided by a central band of text; the
                        fourth (37) completes the series on a balanced note, all text in the upper
                        half, all illumination in the lower. Intricacies of correspondence in the
                        size of various blocks of text and illumination in the series augment its
                        visual formality.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12"
type="note">12</ref> There is no need to
                        attempt a reading of the various illuminations in the series 31 to 37 in
                        order to discover patterns in their arrangement; one has only to imagine
                        these plates laid side by side to observe a display of visual order that
                        Blake must have devised deliberately (see illus. 1). Once we notice the
                        pattern, however, we soon realize that it raises as many problems about the
                        nature of its devising as it appears to solve, that it conceals anomalies in
                        the continuity of text and perhaps effacements of earlier patterns. Though
                        unified by its pattern of layout, the series of plates from 31 to 37 proves
                        not to be coextensive with any continuous narrative unit but, rather,
                        overlaps two adjacent units (29-32 and 33-41) that differ in subject matter
                        and in script (an indication that these units were designed independently).
                        Linked to pls. 33 and 35 in its visual design and style of lettering, pl. 31
                        is lodged in the middle of the adventures of Reuben on pls. 30 and 32, even
                        though the text of 31 has no more self-evident connection with that story
                        than the Reuben episode itself has, graphically or thematically, with the
                        series beginning on pl. 33. Elsewhere in Sequence 1 other oddities appear:
                        the continuous narrative that begins at pl. 33 and includes the parley of
                        the cathedral cities fails to end where the visual pattern of formal
                        alternation does, at pl. 37, but flows on to pl. 41, passing through a
                        distinctly different pattern of layout. In the instance of pl. 31, a formal
                        pattern extends itself at the expense of continuity in subject matter; in
                        the second instance, subject matter spills beyond the confinements of formal
                        pattern apparently designed to contain it. 
                                <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> The proportionate measurements of the
illuminations in 
                                <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is a matter that has not been adequately
                            studied. The proportions of text to illuminations on some plates show
                            clear deliberation, e.g., pl. 35, which is vertically symmetrical, the
                            upper and lower designs 2½” in height each, the middle block of text
                            3¾”. There are apparent relations in proportion between different plates
                            as well. Another 3¾” block of text appears on pl. 37 and the single 5”
                            illumination on that plate equals the combined total of the two
                            illuminations on pl. 35. The middle block of text on pl. 35 (3¾”) is
                            roughly twice the height of the middle block on pl. 33 (1¾”). The
                            headpiece design on pl. 31 exactly fits the text space on 37, and the
                            text and tailpiece on 31 fit the space of 37’s large design. This sort
                            of correspondence is evident elsewhere in Chapter II: in Sequence 2, for
                            example, pls. 44 and 46 are like positive and negative images; where
                            text takes up the bulk of pl. 44, a design of nearly identical height
                            assumes its place on pl. 46, and where a design appears at the top of
                            44, on 46 we find a residue of text. Like any good designer, Blake
                            apparently strives for regularity without rigidity: pleasing variation
                            and harmonies sometimes unobtrusive, sometimes bold.</note></p>
                    <p>To account for this apparent misalignment of subject matter and containing
                        formal design, we must attempt to recover what we can of earlier stages in
                        the evolution of the middle plates of the chapter towards their final form.
                        Only if we understand the principles that shaped and modified Blake’s early
                        material into the form we now possess can we begin to hypothesize the
                        reasons for such later revisions of 
<pb id="p16-194" n="194"/>
                        <figure n="JerusalemCopyDOrder.16.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="174">
                            <head>1. Layout, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, pl. 31-37 (First
                                Order).</head>
                            <figDesc>Copy D, Harvard University Library.</figDesc>
                        </figure> Chapter II as the rearrangement of plates in copies D-E. Assuming
                        that <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> grew out of small, self-enclosed units,
                        brief bardic songs internally unified in subject matter and design, we might
                        try to reconstruct the early form of the unit that became the dramatic and
                        visual center of Chapter II, namely, the tale of the Divine Family,
                        particularized in England’s cathedral cities. It is likely that this scene,
                        which in its final form occupies nine plates, was once considerably shorter
                        and more unified in its tone and its visual design. There is convincing
                        evidence that Blake composed, designed, and etched the scene as a unit of
                        five plates, the first four still found together as pls. 33-36 in copies A
                        and C, and the fifth found as pl. 41. In all printed copies there are
                        anomalies in the transitions from pl. 36 to pl. 37 and from pl. 40 to pl.
                        41, evidence which leads us to suspect alteration and patchwork. A
                        proofsheet of pl. 40 in the Morgan Library lacks the final line present on
                        that plate in all the finished copies of the poem. Since this added final
                        line is needed to make the extensive listing of cities tht follows at the
                        top of pl. 41 intelligible, it is clear, first of all, that when 40 and 41
                        were originally etched they were not intended to form a sequence, and,
                        second, that some other plate at one time did introduce 41 intelligibly.<ref
                            target="n13" type="note">13</ref> Now on pl. 36, a catalogue of cities,
                        announced at the outset as “the Twenty-four in whom the Divine Family
                        Appeared” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 36. 45-46), begins to unroll, but it remains
                        incomplete, indeed seems forgotten, on pl. 37. The lost complement of the
                        twenty-four turns out to be the cities listed on pl. 41. All available
                        evidence, then, including a probable catchword tie, “Bath,” points to a
                        perfect continuity between pls. 36 and 41, a continuity that, as we shall
                        see, is lacking in several respects between 36 and 37.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
                            type="note">14</ref>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Both Erdman and
                            Bentley comment on the variation between the Morgan proofsheet and pl.
                            40 as found in the finished copies, with its added line. According to
                            Erdman, “the added line does show that [pl. 40] was made before the
                            present arrangement of plates, that it was first made for one position
                            and later made to fit another” (“Suppressed and Altered Passages,” p.
                            25). Bentley, on the other hand, reasons that plate 41 must be later in
                            origin than 40 and “presumably contemporaneous” with the line added to
                            the previous plate to introduce 41 (<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p.
                            225). Bentley’s reasoning does not explain, however, why Blake, if
                            etching 41 as an afterthought to the sequence, would place its
                            introductory line at the bottom of the previous plate when he could,
                            with less trouble, etch it with the rest of the new lines that were to
                            make up pl. 41. Nor does it explain why pl. 41 completes the unfinished
                            catalogue of cities begun on pl. 36 (see n. 14, below).</note>	
                            <note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> On pl. 36 Blake names Selsey (Chichester),
                            Winchester, Gloucester, Exeter, Salisbury, Bristol, and Bath. Seventeen
                            more cities appear on 41.3, 5-7, 18-19. Erdman, in “Suppressed and
                            Altered Passages,” p. 25, argues that “Bath” is not a catchword, but
                            Blake himself appears to have read it as such. On three different
                            plates, 37, 40, and 41, which other evidence suggests as having at
                            various stages followed pl. 36 directly, he takes pains to insure that
                            the first word is “Bath.”</note></p>
                    <p>The aesthetic integrity of the early five-plate version of the “Divine
                        Family” scene is manifest on several levels (see illus. 2). The tone is
                        sustained in its mildness. The narrative, typically synoptic, tells a tale
                        of Albion “turning from Universal Love” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 34.7) and of
                        Los summoning the twentyfour cities of the Divine Family in emergency
                        session, and it culminates in a catalogue of the cities and a momentous
                        point of crisis. The designs tell a tale of humanity seemingly in the
                        Spectre’s power though actually reposing in the arms of divine love (pl.
                        33), of the apparent triumph of the Spectre as he rides on high (pl. 35),
                        and of the timely arrival of an apocalyptic chariot (pl. 41), immensely
                        complex in its iconography, but certainly carrying the Bride in the arms of
                        a God that is “Not an Avenger” (see 41.28).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> But the most striking pattern of these plates is found in
                        their visual layout. Here are five plates, five blocks of text in strict
                        alternation with five blocks of design, a study in doublings and synoptic
                        concentration: a doubling of doubly-illuminated plates, a doubling of
                        full-text plates, and a final plate that visually emphasizes the duality of
                        the two modes.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16"
type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n15"><hi
                                rend="s">15</hi> A critical tradition is beginning to form that
                            considers this design parody, indeed as self-parody. Thus in 
                                <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday,
                            1974), David Erdman is equivocal; he notes the presence of apocalyptic
                            emblems—the beasts are “ox-hooved, lion-maned, man-headed” (p. 320), but
                            at the same time “Blake knows that the whole contraption would look
                            ridiculous beside a fiery Pegasus” (p. 321). Mitchell, in 
                                <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art</hi>, goes further: “The chariot is an
                            impossible rattletrap of old mythologies. . . . This monstrosity is a
                            self-parody, a satiric vision of Blake’s epic machinery” (p. 216). See
                            also John E. Grant, review of Damon, <hi rend="i">A Blake
                                Dictionary</hi> in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (Winter 1980-81), p. 132.
                            Grant considers the design “pessimistic and parodistic.” These views are
                            invigorating and perhaps correct. But in reading Blake’s designs we may
                            be wise to prefer a cautious approach, separating that which is
                            indisputably there, such as the presence of a combination of apocalyptic
                            emblems, from what is critical inference, based on notions of the
                            grotesque that may not be Blake’s. The iconography of the chariot is not
                            without its precedents in sources available to Blake, as Morton Paley
                            points out in “ ‘Wonderful Originals’—Blake and Ancient Sculpture,” in
                                <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, p. 175.</note>	
                                <note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Plate 33 is in itself a symphony of
doublings
                            and oppositions: there is of course the vertical symmetry of designs
                            above and below a medial text, and within the designs there are the
                            upper pair of wings and the lower pair of wings, a scene of spiritual
                            support above and spiritual disease below, two figures in the upper
                            design, two in the lower, a tree on the left and a tree on the right in
                            the upper, sun on the left and moon on the right in the
                        lower.</note></p>
                    <p>It is pleasant to speculate that this miniature illuminated epic, so
                        internally perfected, was the grain about which the rest of Chapter II
                            crystallized.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">17</ref> But if Blake once
                        intended the five-plate core to cohere as an aesthetic unit, clearly this
                        intent did not survive into the printed copies. Blake’s second thoughts
                        habitually impinge on and dislocate older stable forms (witness the textual
                        crisis that overtakes <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> between the Sixth and
                        Ninth Nights). Four plates, 37-40, in Copies A and C, now separate the once
                        adjacent 36 and 41. This situation is apparently the product of two distinct
                        interpolations, pl. 40, first, and then, possibly much later, pls. 37-39
                        (these latter plates go together as a unit; their script is uniform,
                        syntactic parallels connect pls. 37 and 38, and a catchword, as well as
                        continuous sense, ties 38 to 39). As far as one can reconstruct these
                        revisions, sometime after etching the core unit Blake decided to add pl. 40,
                        possibly to augment the role of Bath (perhaps under the sway of Richard
                        Warner’s <hi rend="i">War Inconsistent with Christianity</hi>).<ref
                            target="n18" type="note">18</ref> Blake linked the new plate to pl. 36
                        via the catchword there but left it detached from 41. Possibly he considered
                        using 40 as a replacement for 41. To do so would avoid the non sequitur of
                        the list of cities on 41, now disjoined 
<pb id="p16-195" n="195"/>
<figure n="HypotheticalCoreJerusalem.16.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="271">
                            <head>2. Layout, hypothetical “core” sequence of 
                                    <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Chapter II, pls. 33-36, [37-40], 41
                                [46].</head>
                            <figDesc>Copy D, Harvard University Library.</figDesc>
                        </figure> from its beginnings on 36. By summarizing all the essential matter
                        of 41 in what were then the last three lines of 40,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
                            type="note">19</ref> Blake might close the sequence on a declaration
                        more chiseled, more final, and more sublime than the final lines of 41
                        afford: “And the Seventeen conjoining with Bath the Seventh/In whom the
                        other Ten shone manifest a Divine Vision / Assimilated and embrac’d Eternal
                        Death for Albions sake” (40.37-39). <note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi>
                            There is some evidence to suggest that this series cohered as a unit
                            from a relatively early period in the coalescence of 
                                <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s plates. On plate 34 of copy A, in the upper
right
                            corner, there is a residual trace of a still earlier stage in the
                            assembling of the poem, a small engraved “6” that Blake has only
                            partially managed to cover over. Versions of pl. 34 that lack this “6”
                            are likely to date from an earlier stage still, and in the Rosenwald
                            Collection of the Library of Congress there is in fact a proofsheet of
                            the plate, printed in black, lacking the “6” (a second proofsheet of pl.
                            34 printed in green, also in the Rosenwald Collection, shows the “6”
                            clearly). Yet even this proofsheet with the missing “6” shows the
                            catchword “By” that links it to pl. 35. These two plates probably
                            cohered from a distinctly early period then, nor can we doubt that pl.
                            33, which is needed to make the start of 34 intelligible, also cohered
                            to it at that time; context guarantees the connection of 35 and 36. For
                            discussion of the “6” on pl. 34, see Erdman, “Suppressed and Altered
                            Passages,” p. 49; see also n. 20 below.</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi
                                rend="s">18</hi> See David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet
                                Against Empire</hi>, rev. ed. (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1969),
                            pp. 476-77.</note>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> One piece of
                            evidence for supposing that pl. 40 is later than 41 is the adventitious
                            nature of the numerical categories on pl. 40, “The Seventeen,” “Bath the
                            Seventh,” “the other Ten.” Blake’s curious reification of “7” and
“17”
                            comes simply from a count of cities named on pl. 36 and a count of their
                            complement on pl. 41. The collectivity of “seventeen” is a
                            nonce-creation, like “Bath the Seventh,” brought in to disguise the
                            interruption that pl. 40 makes in the continuity of 36 and 41. “The
                            other Ten” is an even bolder improvisation. This is a grab bag category
                            composed of the first six cities mentioned on pl. 36 mixed with the four
                            supreme cities “in whom the twenty-four appear’d four-fold” (41.23).
                            Blake is in short effacing his original symbolic scheme and improvising
                            another as part of necessary patchwork. By the time we get to what I
                            take to be the even later interpolation of pls. 37-39, the “Seventeen”
                            have attained an institutional status, Blake causing Los to say,
                            “Bristol &amp; Bath, listen to my words, &amp; ye Seventeen: give ear!”
                            (38.55). “The other Ten” are quite forgotten here. Blake’s references
                            either to “twenty-four” cities or to “twenty-eight” may help to
                            establish the relative dates of certain passages. In the core sequence
                            33-36, 41, the collective number is always “twenty-four,” as it is in
                            Chapter I (19.20) and in its place of probable origin, 
                                <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 42.16 (“I beheld the Twenty-four Cities of
Albion”).
                            But in the presumably later pls. 37-39, the collectivity grows to
                            “twenty-eight” (37.23) and remains so in Sequence 2: “The Twenty-eight
                            Cities of Albion” (44.26).</note></p>
                    <p>By bypassing pl. 41, Blake might also obtain a smoother link with 42. The
                        first line of 42 (“Thus Albion sat, studious of others in his pale disease”)
                        might appear to proceed from 40.36 (“[Albion] frown’d on All his Friends,
                        counting them enemies in his sorrow”). At the same time, however, the
                        sacrifice of pl. 41 would mean the loss of Oxford’s speech there, and, more
                        seriously, the disappearance of the conclusive half-page design of the
                        apocalyptic chariot. Blake apparently decided finally to include both
                        plates, engraving the present final line of 40 to give the opening lines of
                        41 a new rationale. There was still a cost, however: a disturbance in the
                        symmetrical layout of the five-plate core unit, now grown to six. Here then
                        is an instance, one of many, where Blake’s matter and verbal expression
                        managed to override the claims of his form.</p>
                    <p>The insertion of pl. 40 into the core sequence has relatively few aesthetic
                        consequences other than its effect on the visual layout, for it is
                        relatively homogenous with its surroundings. By contrast, pls. 37-39
                        massively intrude on the continuity of the core unit as originally ordered,
                        drastically altering its visual form and noticeably modifying its tone.
                        Although Blake is careful to provide a narrative link to pl. 40 at the
                        bottom of pl. 39, the sequence 36-37 is markedly disjunctive. The script
                        changes abruptly on pl. 37 from the smaller, more graceful, more cursive
                        style of pls. 33-36 and 41; Bath, “benevolent” in the last line of 36,
                        becomes “the poisoner: the best and worst in Heaven and Hell” in the second
                        line of 37; and pls. 37-39 introduce a harsh, congested mass of Blake’s late
                        mythic paraphernalia—the Spectre, the Four Zoas, an infusion of biblical
                        names into English settings—matter virtually absent from the more sweetly
                        rendered account of the Divine Family on adjacent plates and only loosely
                        related to it. Plates 37-39 differ more strongly in these respects from pl.
                        40 than 40 does from 33-36, 41. It is likely that pls. 37-39 allude to a
                        rather different set of historical circumstances from those which inform the
                        original account, circumstances by no means clear but probably reflected in
                        such things as the darker treatment of Bath and the curious account of an
                        attempt to bear Albion back to Eden “against his will” (39.3). These plates
                        may be very late indeed; if the evidence of early suppressed numbers
                        scratched on the copperplates provides any clue, Blake may have already
                        adopted a tentative order for Chapter II before he even etched 37-39.<ref
                            target="n20" type="note">20</ref>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi>
                            Some impressions and proofsheets of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> show
                            faintly engraved numbers that differ from and were superseded by the
                            numbers added in pen in copy A. In Chapter II, Erdman reports besides
                            the “6” on pl. 34 (see n. 17 above) a “1°” or “18” or “12” on pl.
28, a
                            “31” (pl. 31), “36” (pl. 33), “9” (pl. 40), and “19” (pl. 50)
                            (“Suppressed and Altered Passages,” pp. 48-49). Recently the Morgan
                            Library has acquired an early proofsheet of pl. 28 (a reworked version
                            of the well known first-state pull of that plate already in the Morgan’s
                            possession) which confirms the engraved number there as “12.” I cannot
                            read any number on pl. 33 in the copies I have consulted but have been
                            able to corroborate the “6” in various copies, the “9” in copy A, and
                            the “19” in copies D, E, and (faintly) the posthumously printed copy I.
                            These numbers may shed light on the early order of the chapter, for the
                            latter three appear in the same order and at roughly the same intervals
                            as the plates themselves do in the extant First Order (the engraved
                            number on pl. 31 is irrelevant to the early order, since it is likely
                            that this plate is a quite late interpolation in the sequence, and the
                            “36” on 33, if it exists, must belong to a different bout of numbering
                            from the one that produced “6” on pl. 34, for it is highly improbable
                            that 33 was ever physically separated from 34). Indeed, if one numbers
                            Chapter II, starting with pl. 28 as the first and leaving out the
                            probably late arrival pl. 31, one discovers that pl. 34 is indeed the
                            sixth plate in the sequence; plate 40 is indeed the ninth plate if pls.
                            37-39 are omitted as a late interpolation, and if 40 is “9” it is easy
                            to see why pl. 50 would be “19.” <p>The “12” which we now know that
                                Blake inscribed on a plate already designated as the start of
                                Chapter II supports Erdman’s suggestion that “at one time the
                                chapters were under ten pages in length” (“Suppressed and Altered
                                Passages,” p. 49)—or, more precisely, it suggests that the first
                                chapter once consisted of ten plates exactly (“To the Jews” would be
                                pl. 11). This “12” does make the early “6” on 34 and the “9” on 40
                                problematic, though not insolubly so. At some early point Blake may
                                have provisionally situated the six plates of the extended core
                                sequence, 33-36, 40, 41, in a ten-plate Chapter I, following the
                                extant pls. 1-4 (a workable combination; pl. 41, moreover, has both
                                the visual appearance and the rhetorical effect of a 
                                    <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> chapter end-plate); in this case, pl. 34 would
                                still be the sixth and pl. 40 the ninth in the series.
                                Alternatively, the numbers “6,” “9,” and “19” may simply have
                                provided Blake with a private guide to the internal ordering of the
                                plates that make up Chapter II (before late interpolations) without
                                regard to their ultimate numerical place in the poem as a whole.
                                Since this alternative makes better sense of the “19” on 50, ten
                                plates after the “9” on 40, it seems to me more likely that the
                                early engraved numbers represent, for the most part, the internal
                                ordering of Chapter II and that at the time of the numbering the
                                plates had already assumed much the same arrangement as we find in
                                Copy A. By this reckoning the interpolation of pl. 37-39 would not
                                be merely late but very late.</p></note></p>
                    <p>So large an interpolation as that of pls. 37-39 now quite effectively
                        obliterated the early verbal-visual design once intended for the episode of
                        the cathedral cities, but it also provided room for new elements of visual
                        design to integrate themselves with patterns established in plates already
                        etched. Thus the large half-page illumination on pl. 37 of Albion seated in
                        despair occupies the same niche, with respect to preceding plates, that was
                        once filled by the marginally smaller design of the apocalyptic chariot, now
                        displaced; in size, the design on 37 is precisely equal to the sum of the
                        designs on pl. 35; its subject continues the theme of humanity in the
                        Spectre’s power that was displayed in the designs of 33 and 35 and is
                        explicitly enunciated in the 
<pb id="p16-196" n="196"/>
                        mirror-script on 37. Next, by etching pl. 38 as a monolithic block of text,
                        Blake continues a pattern that has prevailed in the even-numbered plates
                        since pl. 30. Further, the designs at the top of 39 and 40 are identical in
                        size and contrapuntally related in subject; both are water-visions, one
                        conveying redemptive possibilities, the other fallen states.<ref
                            target="n21" type="note">21</ref> Thus a new five-plate pattern of
                        layout, 37-41, is added to the old, and the whole episode grows to nine
                        plates. In this expanded sequence, plate 37 becomes a new pivotal fifth; in
                        the thematic sequence, it provides a nadir vision of despair, equidistant
                        from images of the savior at the beginning of the sequence (pl. 33) and the
                        apocalyptic chariot at the end (pl. 41); as an element of visual structure,
                        it anchors 41, the ninth plate, as well as 33 and 35, (the first and third).
                        Thus new patterns supersede old without wholly effacing them, like the
                        overlapping rings of lunar impact craters. Blake’s mode of introducing new
                        matter in his work is often nearly as violent, yet at the same time his
                        instinct for form persists. <note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> See Erdman,
                                <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi>, pp. 318-19.</note></p>
                    <p>How the rest of Chapter II fell into the arrangement extant in Copies A-C is
                        a matter for conjecture only. At some point Sequence 2 (43-46) locked into
                        place with Sequence 3 (47-50) through the nexus of the great designs of Vala
                        and Jerusalem on 46-47. How this series of eight, with its powerful visual
                        center, attached itself to the core sequence is not clear. The somewhat
                        rough connections between pl. 42 and its immediate neighbors suggest a more
                        complex history of joining than we can now recover (42 may be the residue of
                        a longer series of plates pared down at both ends). Meanwhile the five-plate
                        central core had at a relatively early stage incorporated pl. 40. Somewhat
                        later, probably, the augmented core acquired the three-plate sequence 29-30,
                        32, as a proem.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
type="note">22</ref> The chapter now had
                        the form of a double set of nines, anchored together at what became their
                        medial pivot, the appropriately encompassing design of the apocalyptic
                        chariot on 41, equidistant from the beginning and end of the chapter. The
                        latest developments presumably were the interpolation of pls. 37-39 and of
                        pl. 31. The case of pl. 31, long recognized as an intruder,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23"
                            type="note">23</ref> bears further comment. A self-contained doctrinal
                        passage, its text may never have formed part of any extended sequence in the
                        poem, and for the reader it continues to remain aloof from its surroundings.
                        For the viewer, however, pl. 31 coheres very well with what follows it: it
                        displays precisely the same visual layout as pls. 33 and 35 and certain
                        iconographic connections with these as well (particularly in the repetition
                        of flying or hovering figures). By placing 31 where he does, Blake extends
                        forward the pattern of alternating textual and illuminated spaces so that
                        every plate from 30 to 36 (and, with the eventual addition of 37-39, every
                        plate to 38) is made part of the pattern. Here then is evidence that it is
                        often not the sense of the text but the look of the page that determines the
                        location of some plates in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> In form, like
                        apparently gravitates to like, creating a pattern that cuts into narrative
                        continuity and extends itself across the boundaries of discrete narrative
                        units. <note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Plates 29-30, 32 do not appear to
                            have been etched at the same stage as pls. 33 ff., for the style of
                            script on these three plates is uncharacteristically large and elaborate
                            compared with the <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> norm. This script appears
                            in <hi rend="i">J</hi> 56 and <hi rend="i">J</hi> 61, palpable
                            interpolations both, leading Bentley to describe them as “apparently
                            late” (<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 225). A more telling argument
                            for lateness is the close resemblance of this script to that of 
                                <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi> (1822). Although Erdman describes
                            the script on <hi rend="i">J</hi> 29-30 as “an early format” 
                                (<hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi>, p. 309), the evidence leans
                            slightly toward a relatively late date for these plates in the etching
                            of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> But even a very early date of etching is
                            no obstacle to relatively late attachment to the core sequence of the
                            cathedral cities, with which pls. 29-30, 32 share little in subject
                            matter.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> See Erdman,
                            “Suppressed and Altered Passages,” p. 21.</note></p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="i">The Rearrangement of Sequences in Copies D-E</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>This hypothetical reconstruction of some stages in the prehistory of Chapter
                        II brings us finally to the order of the first printed copies. But Blake’s
                        concern for visual form, for a handsome distribution of illuminations, could
                        not have ceased once these printed copies came into being. Certainly Blake’s
                        previous treatment of successive copies of longer works—his rearrangement of
                        full-page illuminations in <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> and 
                            <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, for example—suggests the opposite. Indeed, 
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is actually conservative in the general
                        stability of its order from copy to copy. Yet Chapter II, already the
                        product of much careful designing and many disruptive second thoughts, gets
                        substantially rearranged in copies D and E. In these copies Blake moves pls.
                        43-46 to the front of the chapter, just after the chapter opening on pl. 28,
                        and he inserts plate 42 between what were in the First Order 
                            <pb id="p16-197" n="197"/>
pls. 37 and 38. Any explanation of these changes
                        should base its inferences on the same principles that seem to have
                        motivated Blake’s earlier planning in the chapter.</p>
                    <p>A quest after possible thematic motives for the rearrangement of the chapter
                        seems to me the least promising way of explaining the problem. Commentators
                        on this point have generally pronounced both orders thematically satisfying,
                        and indeed they are. In one order (A-C-F), after the proem of plate 28, the
                        narrative begins with Albion repudiating the Divine Vision; in the other
                        (D-E), it begins with the Divine Vision proclaiming its early intimacy with
                        Albion. The narrative in the earlier order shows Los undertaking a solitary
                        quest to save Albion after the group effort of the cathedral cities fails;
                        in the later order the cathedral cities appear to convene (though not
                        immediately—the Reuben episode and other matter come first) after Los’s
                        individual failure. In terms of thematic significance, these alternatives
                        offer little to choose from, since they both yield the same gloomy outcome,
                        a stubbornly unredeemed Albion. But when we turn our attention from theme to
                        visual form, very different consequences attend the two orders. The
                        rearrangement of narrative sequences demands rearrangement of illuminations
                        as well and an altered set of relations between blocks of illumination and
                        blocks of text. Given Blake’s evident concern for such matters, we may
                        plausibly suppose that he found the distribution of illuminations in copies
                        A and C unsatisfying, even though the arrangement of sequences formed a
                        reasonable, even a desirable, narrative order. If this motive did in fact
                        figure significantly in the shifting of sequences, it provides us with a
                        magnified instance <figure n="LayoutJerusalemChapterII.16.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="524">
                            <head>3. Layout, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Chapter II (First
                                Order).</head>
                            <figDesc>Copy D, Harvard University Library (rearranged).</figDesc>
                        </figure>
<pb id="p16-198" n="198"/>
of Blake’s tendency to allow concerns
                        for form to prevail over an earlier coherence of content.</p>
                    <p>The concern for form in this instance may, however, signal only a desire to
                        rectify imbalances in layout that earlier intrusions of content may have
                        caused in the first place. In planning the layout of the smaller units of
                        the chapter, Blake seems to have pursued a kind of medial symmetry as his
                        goal, sequences with strong pivots at the center and balanced elements
                        flanking it on the imaginary left and right. The same goal appears evident
                        in the plan of Chapter II as a whole. If we visualize its order before the
                        interpolations of pls. 31 and 37-39, we find a series of nineteen plates
                        (omitting the address to the Jews) with large illuminations so distributed
                        that their center of gravity falls in the middle (an appropriate
                        distribution for a middle chapter: large illuminations in Chapter I cluster
                        towards the beginning of the chapter; in Chapter IV they cluster towards the
                            end<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref>).
The half-page illumination
                        of the apocalyptic chariot occupies the tenth position (pl. 41), the exact
                        center of the series, flanked at opposite ends by the half-page
                        illuminations on the first (pl. 28) and the nineteenth plates (pl. 50). The
                        other large illuminations are distributed on either side of the center at
                        roughly corresponding intervals from it, five before and four after (the
                        greater massiveness of the designs on the later plates balances out the
                        slightly greater frequency of designs on the earlier). A well-balanced
                        visual order would thus have prevailed at one time in the chapter as a whole
                        as well as in its individual illuminated units. 
                                <note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Six of the nine large block-illuminations
in Chapter I
                            occur in the first half of the chapter, indeed within the first eight
                            plates of actual verse; eight of Chapter IV’s thirteen large
                            illuminations appear, in crescendo fashion, on its last seven plates of
                            verse, less than a third of the whole chapter. Large illuminations are
                            infrequent in Chapter III. (The five full-page designs in 
                                <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> are excluded from this count.) For a table showing
                            the distribution of large designs in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, see
                            Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 231.</note></p>
                    <p>When Blake expanded the parley of cathedral cities by three plates (none
                        massively illuminated except pl. 37) and 
<figure n="LayoutJerusalemSecondOrder.16.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="530">
                            <head>4. Layout, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Chapter II (Second
                                Order).</head>
                            <figDesc>Copy D, Harvard University Library.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
<pb id="p16-199" n="199"/>
interpolated them between the eighth and
                        ninth plates (36 and 40) of an earlier nineteen-plate sequence, he
                        inevitably displaced the center of gravity in the distribution of
                        illuminations forward in the chapter. The interpolation of pl. 31 near the
                        beginning of the chapter only served to make the shift in balance more
                        pronounced. Thus in the order of copy A, the reader encounters eight large
                        blocks of illumination in the first half of Chapter II and only five in the
                        second (the median of the 24 plates is found between pls. 38 and 39).<ref
                            target="n25" type="note">25</ref> In addition, the very conspicuous
                        pattern of alternation and repetition observed in pls. 31-37 makes the
                        distribution of illuminations in the rest of the chapter seem ungainly, even
                        random. A massive clot of design on pls. 46 and 47 relieves the relatively
                        heavy weight of printed text in the second half of the chapter, but these
                        designs are too powerful in themselves and too isolated from other powerful
                        clusters of design to create an effect of balance. 
                                <note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi> For convenience of division I include pl.
27, “To
                            the Jews,” in this reckoning. Unadorned, it does not affect the
                            distribution of illuminations in any measurable way. The eight large
                            blocks of illumination in the first half of the chapter are on pls. 28,
                            31(2), 33(2), 35(2) and 37. The five blocks in the second half are on
                            pls. 41, 44, 46, 47, and 50.</note></p>
                    <p>For all the presumed defects of Chapter II as a visual sequence, Blake
                        nevertheless produced two printed copies of the chapter in this order before
                        he began to have second thoughts. The second thoughts seem to have coincided
                        with his plans for a full-color version of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (copy
                        E), a version in which the claims of visual design would have
                            preeminence.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26"
type="note">26</ref> If any perceived
                        deficiencies in the sequential design were to be remedied, a project such as
                        the production of copy E would certainly have provided the appropriate
                        occasion, and Chapter II, which is particularly rich in large designs, would
                        be likely to have received special attention. An inspection of the new order
                        of plates in the D-E version of this chapter indeed assures us that the
                        imbalances present in the A-C order have been rectified. If we divide the
                        twenty-four plates that compose the enlarged chapter at its median, we find
                        seven large designs in the first half and six in the second, a considerably
                        more even distribution than the eight and five split of copy A. If we divide
                        the chapter in thirds, the effect of medial symmetry is even more pronounced
                        (see illus. 4). In the first eight plates there are three large designs, in
                        the next eight, seven, and in the final eight, three (a similar calculation
                        applied to copy A yields five, four, and four, even-sounding enough, until
                        we observe that the distribution sequence within the middle third is itself
                        considerably lopsided [see illus. 3]). The medial symmetry that may have
                        been present in an earlier hypothetical nineteen-plate chapter is now
                        restored. <note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Copy D, uncolored and
                            sometimes poorly inked, of course also displays the Second Order. But
                            there is little reason to suppose that D is earlier than E. Both are
                            watermarked 1820, and the length of time that the production of E would
                            need for completion argues for an early start on its
                        planning.</note></p>
                    <p>In the transformation of pls. 43-46 into pl. <hi rend="i">29-32</hi> there is
                        one other consequential gain in pictorial symmetry. With the migration of
                        the former plate 46 towards the beginning of the chapter, Vala and Jerusalem
                        no longer change at the turn of a page from elegant aloof emblems into
                        fleshy women, falling with and falling for a man as contorted as they. An
                        ironic narrative sequence loses the link between its two parts, but at the
                        same time, by undoing this heavy conjunction of massive designs, Blake
                        restores a balance. In D and E the two versions of this female pair, one
                        version depicting eternal states and one depicting fallen vegetative selves,
                        are as symmetrically disposed in their locations in the chapter as the
                        emblems of St. Paul’s and Westminster Abbey are on the first of the panels
                        themselves. Plate <hi rend="i">32</hi>, formerly 46, now concludes the 
                            <hi rend="i">first</hi> movement in the chapter, an epyllion of four plates
                        (not including “To the Jews” and pl. 28); it is more than ever the mirror
                        image of pl. 47, which introduces a <hi rend="i">final</hi> movement of four
                        plates. Both plates are nearly equidistant, on opposite sides, from the
                        midpoint in the chapter (if one leaves “To the Jews” and 28 out of the
                        reckoning, <hi rend="i">32</hi> and 47 are precisely equidistant). The
                        mirroring effect is particularly apparent in E, where Blake employs an
                        identical color scheme for the bodies, clouds, and background sky in both
                            pictures.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27"
type="note">27</ref> The parallels and the
                        radical contrast of these pictures are enforced by the symmetrical relations
                        of their location. They are fit panels to flank the chapter’s visual center,
                        itself filled with symmetrical doublings and oppositions, visual displays of
                        hard choices, of succor and disease, <pb id="p16-200" n="200"/>
of soaring
                        and sinking, where the “best and the worst, Heaven and Hell” often inhabit
                        identical pictorial frames. <note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> This
                            repetition of the color scheme is more exact in the Mellon copy itself
                            than in the Trianon Press facsimile.</note></p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="i">The Status of Plate 42</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>One curiosity in Blake’s rearrangement of Chapter II remains to be discussed.
                        Why is pl. 42 the forty-second plate of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in both
                        Orders, even though the plates adjacent to it shift radically? This plate
                        once directly followed the nine-plate sequence on the cathedral cities that
                        ended with the picture of the apocalyptic chariot. In the Second Order it
                        appears deep within the nine-plate sequence between plates numbered 37 and
                        38 in A-C. Since pl. 37 moves four places back with the transpositions of
                        Sequences 1 and 2 and 42 moves four places forward, the latter needs no
                        renumbering. It is hard to imagine why this one plate should remain fixed in
                        its place like a rock in a stream while a total of seventeen plates before
                        and after shift around it. Fond as Blake is of symbolic numbers, the number
                        42 does not seem to be among them. The plate has no large block-design.
                        Although it presents a powerful speech by Los and some fairly typical
                        rumblings from Albion, there is nothing in the content that marks it as
                        demanding singular treatment. Finally, most curious of all, to remain pl. 42
                        in the Second Order it must interrupt the continuity between pls. 
                            <hi rend="i">41</hi> and <hi rend="i">43</hi> without supplying any new
                        plausibility; indeed it interrupts a series of parallel clauses in
                        apposition: 
						<q> They saw Albion endeavoring to destroy their Emanations 
                                (<hi rend="i">41</hi>:31)<lb/>
<lb/>
 They saw their wheels rising up
                            poisonous against Albion (<hi rend="i">43</hi>:1) </q>
In the Second
                        Order, two non sequiturs in the sense appear where there were none
                        before.</p>
                    <p>In its original location in the First Order, this plate had no inevitable
                        connection to the plates immediately adjacent to it. It cannot have been
                        conceived as part of the scene of the twenty-four cathedral cities that
                        preceded it, for on 42 the parley abruptly disappears, and Albion states
                        that Hand and Hyle “have seized the Twenty-four rebellious ingratitudes”
                        (42:48), though nothing of the sort occurs in the previous nine plates.<ref
                            target="n28" type="note">28</ref> Nor does it connect obviously with the
                        succeeding plate, since 42 concludes strongly on a line of summary finality
                        (“This is the Net &amp; Veil of Vala, among the Souls of the Dead” [81]),
                        and 43 presents a powerful fresh scene with its first line (“Then the Divine
                        Vision like a silent sun appeared”). Even in the First Order, then, pl. 42
                        is inessential to narrative continuity. The most that might be said for its
                        earlier location is that its text provides at least an adequate transition
                        from the collective effort of the cities to the individual effort of Los to
                        redeem Albion. What it does not provide, however, is a fit introduction to
                        that last, immensely powerful synopsis of Blake’s historical myth that
                        bursts upon us on pl. 47, as “Luvah [tears] forth from Albions Loins . . .
                        in rivers / of blood over Europe” (47:3-4). Yet this is precisely what pl.
                        42 must introduce when Sequence 2 is moved to the beginning of the Chapter
                        in the Second Order. Far better is the juncture that actually 
                        <corr type="emend">appears</corr> in D-E,
                        “O God thou art Not an Avenger” (41 [<hi rend="i">46</hi>]) implicitly
                        judging “that Holy Fiend / The Wicker Man of Scandinavia” on the next plate
                        (47:5-6), just as the design of the apocalyptic chariot on 
                            <hi rend="i">46</hi> implicitly judges the disarray of Albion, Vala, and Jerusalem
                        on 47’s adjacent design. <note id="n28"><hi rend="s">28</hi> The plate must
                            have been etched relatively early, however. The “rebellious
                            ingratitudes” are twenty-four, not twenty-eight or eighteen and ten (see
                            n. 19 above). Plate 42 may owe its oddly disconnected character to the
                            loss of a plate or plates once adjacent to it.</note></p>
                    <p>Once again Blake seems to cater to the claims of coherent sense. In that case
                        pl. 42 must be removed, but where? It cannot be pushed further back, since
                        47-50 form a single, sweeping, unbroken movement from the first line of 47
                        right up to the etched words “End of Chap. 2” on 50. Thus it must move
                        forward. Oddly, it comes to rest at a point where it severs a scene in the
                        middle and interrupts a passage of verse previously bound together by
                        syntactic parallels; no catering to sense here. But from a pictorial
                        standpoint, the resting place is not so odd. What appears to have happened
                        is that the large design of the seated Albion on the lower half of 37 
                            [<hi rend="i">41</hi>] has arrested the forward drift of 42, or to put it
                        another way, the first lines of 42, “Thus Albion sat, studious of others in
                        his pale disease: / Brooding on evil,” gravitate toward their precise
                        illustration, tugging the whole plate with them. That the dislodged plate
                        finally locates itself in the forty-second position of the reordered 
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> turns out to be fortuitous. What is important,
                        rather, is that the power of a design appears, once again, sufficiently
                        compelling to Blake to determine the position of a plate. Moreover, just as
                        the claims of narrative continuity failed to deter the interpolation of pl.
                        31 between 30 and 32 at an early stage of the chapter’s arrangement, these
                        claims once again fail to deter the interpolation of 42 between the former
                        37 and 38. In the latter case, more than purely visual elements enter into
                        Blake’s choice, but even here, the continuity or bond that prevails is one
                        between word and picture, not word and word. In the tug of war between the
                        visual and the verbal that goes on throughout the evolution of Chapter II,
                        the visual element appears to prevail.</p>
                </div2>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title>
                            <hi rend="i">Epilogue: 1826</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <p>In the long run, however, no one component of Blake’s composite art can claim
                        a permanent victory. If Blake altered the arrangement of the second chapter
                        in copies D and E, arguably on grounds of felicity of design, not long
                        before his death he changed his mind again, and in the Pierpont Morgan copy
                        of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (F) he restored the First Order of page
                        numbers. His deliberations on the matter evidently occupied him to the very
                        last, for many of the pages in Chapter II of F show signs of erased or
                        altered numbers, inscribed after the printing (one of them on paper
                        watermarked 1826<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29"
type="note">29</ref>) but now superseded
                        by the extant numbers. As far as we can decipher these erasures they invite
                        us to believe that they are the remains of a Second Order foliation like
                        that of copies D and E (for more on this subject, see the Appendix,
                        “Emendations in the Foliation of the Morgan Copy, Chapter II,” below). The
                        erasures and alterations prove conclusively that Blake could not have 
                            <pb id="p16-201" n="201"/>
stumbled back into a First Order foliation
                        accidentally but must have done so deliberately.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30"
                            type="note">30</ref> A decisive endorsement of the First Order seems to
                        have been Blake’s last word on the form of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi><note
                            id="n29"><hi rend="s">29</hi> Plate 30[<hi rend="i">34</hi>].</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">30</hi> The evidence of
                            Blake’s painstaking emendations to produce First Order numbers
                            invalidates Bentley’s hypothesis that Blake intended the Second Order
                            scheme for the plates of Chapter II in copy F “but carelessly copied the
                            former order when he numbered them with a pen” (<hi rend="i">Blake
                                Books</hi>, p. 234).</note></p>
                    <p>We cannot know for certain why he took this last step. Perhaps the
                        restoration of the original order reflects Blake’s tendency to commemorate
                        the firstlings of his conception and belongs with such manifestations of the
                        tendency as the restored “12” on the title page of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
                        and the date 1804 on the title page of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> But it
                        is also possible that verbal and narrative continuity asserted new claims
                        for Blake’s favor. Certainly copy F, though elegantly touched up with China
                        white, is a drab thing compared to the extravagance of E, but as a reading
                        text it is far clearer.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
type="note">31</ref> We may surmise
                        that Blake considered E the viewer’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and F the
                        reader’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> In that case, a sequence agreeable to
                        the viewer might cause discomfort to the reader. The location of plate 42 in
                        the Second Order, for example, is wholly illogical from the standpoint of
                        narrative continuity, a point that Blake might have perceived more
                        forcefully as shapeliness of visual design receded somewhat in importance to
                        him. <note id="n31"><hi rend="s">31</hi> “The retouching of rude mendings .
                            . . is carried through more conscientiously in the Morgan than in any
                            other copy and rather less conscientiously in the Mellon than any other.
                            . . . Blake took more pains to make the text legible in the Morgan copy
                            than in the Mellon” (Erdman, “Suppressed and Altered Passages,” p. 41).
                            Many plates are faintly printed, some (e.g., pl. 15) scarcely legible,
                            in copy E. The orangish ink also contributes more to the visual splendor
                            of the book than it does to ease of reading.</note></p>
                    <p>Although we can only speculate about Blake’s motives for restoring the First
                        Order in F, we can refer to the evolutionary history of 
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, where a competition of two autonomies, the visual and
                        the verbal, goes on continually. Perhaps modern editors of 
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, faced with the choice of the two variant orders,
should
                        first consider what sort of choice Blake himself was making as he moved from
                        one order to the other, what alternative goals he had before him, and they
                        should make their own editorial decisions accordingly. To establish a
                        “preferred” order of plates on extrinsic, mechanical grounds—the order
                        represented in the majority of copies, the one with the most colors, the one
                        produced last—is to neglect the principles of ordering that would have
                        mattered to Blake himself and to evade their problematic nature. If there
                        are such things as a reader’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and a viewer’s 
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, then perhaps the wisest thing a future editor
                        might do is to follow the order of plates that best suits the alternative
                        adopted. If, for example, the edition is to be furnished with reproductions
                        of the illuminations (as in the recent Bentley edition)<ref target="n32"
                            type="note">32</ref>, then the order of copy E, with its superior
                        disposition of designs, would be the one to follow; but if the edition is an
                        unilluminated letterpress text, then the order with the greatest verbal
                        coherence, such as we find in copy F, would be more appropriate. There is no
                        abstract “correct” order to the second chapter of 
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, but neither should our choice be arbitrary; the
                        appropriate order of the poem is profoundly related to the medium of its
                        transmission. <note id="n32"><hi rend="s">32</hi><hi rend="i"> William
                                Blake’s Writings</hi>, ed. G.E. Bentley, Jr., 2 vols. (Oxford:
                            Clarendon, 1978).</note></p>
                    <p>It may be disquieting to some to propose, in place of “the” poem or “the
                        preferred” poem, a plurality of <hi rend="i">Jerusalems</hi> offering faces
                        that accord with the differing desires of viewers and readers. But differing
                        desires, pluralities, unfinished competitions, these are the elements in
                        which Blake breathes. The ordering and reordering of sequences would be
                        impossible in the first place if the poem were not composed of dozens,
                        perhaps scores of smaller poems, internally autonomous but often covering
                        portions of the same ground as the others do: in short, competing with one
                        another to tell the same story, to offer the reader alternate versions of
                        the same truth. And as scene competes with scene, designs come to compete
                        with text, new conceptions with old conceptions, late copies with early
                        copies, and the surface of the poem is dislocated but then reorganized each
                        time. Organization becoming firm in one part often means disorganization
                        somewhere else. This process is perfectly imaged in the figure of
                        “Golgonooza the spiritual Four-fold London eternal . . . ever building, ever
                        falling” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 6.1-2), evading a petrified order. In
                        most of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> the building and rebuilding has arrested
                        itself, leaving only archeological traces of its earlier turbulent
                        development. Chapter II is a gate into the place where the building and
                        rebuilding goes on, allowing us to clarify our conjectures about what the
                        process as a whole must have been like. It is the place where Blake still
                        allows a glimpse of his unappeasable appetite for an unending conversation
                        between strong text and strong design. “Go on, builders in hope” 
                            (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 12.43), it seems to proclaim.</p>
                    <p>Appendix: Emendations in the MS Foliation of the Morgan Copy, Chapter II 
					<q>
                            The matter of erased pen numbers in F needs a somewhat detailed
                            exposition, for the erasures and other emendations have not been
                            completely reported hitherto. Not all the plates subject to shuffling in
                            earlier arrangements of Chapter II show evidence of emendation beneath
                            the extant page numbers, but the mendings are more extensive than
                            previously realized. Erdman finds an erased number, “possibly ‘33’ ” and
                            mendings in the digits of “30,” “31,” and “32” (“Suppressed and
Altered
                            Passages,” p. 51). Close attention to scouring marks on the paper, aided
                            by an ultraviolet lamp, has enabled me to collect more complete
                            information (I am also indebted to Thomas Lange and the staff of the
                            Morgan Library for help in deciphering the evidence presented here).
						</q></p>
                    <p>The listing below follows the Second Order arrangement of copy F’s present
                        binding (of Victorian date): <table rows="16" cols="2">
                            <row>
                                <cell>pls. 28, 43[<hi rend="i">29</hi>], 44[<hi rend="i">30</hi>]</cell>
                                <cell>no evidence of earlier numbers</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>45[<hi rend="i">31</hi>], 46[<hi rend="i">32</hi>]</cell>
                                <cell>beneath extant<lb/>
 First Order numbers</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>29[<hi rend="i">33</hi>]</cell>
                                <cell>extant “29” written over 2 erased digits, almost certainly
                                    “33”</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>30[<hi rend="i">34</hi>]</cell>
                                <cell>“0” written over an erasure and in lighter ink than the
                                    “3”</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>31[<hi rend="i">35</hi>]</cell>
                                <cell>“1” written over an erasure</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>32[<hi rend="i">36</hi>]</cell>
                                <cell>“2” written over an erasure and in lighter ink than the
                                    “3”</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <pb id="p16-202" n="202"/>
                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell>33[<hi rend="i">37</hi>]</cell>
                                <cell>no apparent emendation beneath extant “33”</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>34[<hi rend="i">38</hi>]</cell>
                                <cell>“4” written over a heavy erasure</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>35[<hi rend="i">39</hi>]</cell>
                                <cell>no apparent emendation</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>36[<hi rend="i">40</hi>]</cell>
                                <cell><hi rend="i">both digits</hi> written over severe erasing; to
                                    the left of the extant “3” the imprint of a “4” left by the
                                    pressure of the pen is distinctly visible in ultraviolet light;
                                    a second earlier digit to the right of the “4” illegible beneath
                                    the extant number</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>37[<hi rend="i">41</hi>]</cell>
                                <cell>no apparent emendation</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>42</cell>
                                <cell>written in heavy black ink (unlike emended numbers, written
                                    mostly in a grayer ink)</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>38[<hi rend="i">43</hi>]</cell>
                                <cell>“3” written over an erasure; the “8” is mended in gray ink
                                    from an earlier “3” written in black ink</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>39[<hi rend="i">44</hi>]</cell>
                                <cell>no apparent emendation</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>40[<hi rend="i">45</hi>]</cell>
                                <cell>faint evidence of erasure under “0”</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>41[<hi rend="i">46</hi>], 47, 48, 49, 50</cell>
                                <cell>no apparent emendation; numbers inscribed in gray rather than
                                    black ink</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table> None of this information violates the hypothesis that the erased
                        numbers were those of the Second Order, and all tends to support it. The
                        probable “33” once inscribed on pl. 29, the “4[?]” detectable on pl. 36, and
                        the “[?]3” detectable on pl. 38 raise no barrier to the supposition that
                        these fossil numbers were once the actual Second Order numbers of those
                        plates, <hi rend="i">33, 40</hi>, and <hi rend="i">43</hi>, respectively. If
                        Blake was changing Second Order numbers to First Order, where the plate
                        number was in the 30’s in either Order, we would expect him to erase only
                        the second digit; both digits would need altering for <hi rend="i">40</hi>
                        to become 36; where the First Order catches up to the 40’s, as 
                            <hi rend="i">45</hi> becomes 40, Blake again would need only to change the second
                        digit. All these expectations are confirmed by the physical evidence of the
                        text. That they all point to Second Order numbers beneath the extant
                        mendings and superimposition seems beyond the reach of coincidence.</p>
                    <p>As the table above makes clear, not all the plates show evidence of early
                        fossil numbers beneath the extant First Order numbers. But although the
                        early patterning of numbering was intermittent it was by no means random.
                        Plates 43[<hi rend="i">29</hi>]-46[<hi rend="i">32</hi>] and 47-50 show no
                        signs of earlier numbers; pl. 29 [<hi rend="i">33</hi>]-32[<hi rend="i">36</hi>], on
the other hand, display such signs on every plate; pl.
                            33[<hi rend="i">37</hi>]-41[<hi rend="i">46</hi>] show a pattern of
                        early numbers on <hi rend="i">alternate</hi> plates in the series (pl. 42 is
                        included here as the fifth in the series), with the odds (assuming a likely
                        Second Order arrangement) skipped in the first half and the evens in the
                        second. One plausible way of accounting for these variations is to assume
                        that Blake numbered these plates in different batches and at different
                        times. It is interesting to note that these different batches of plates,
                        29-32, 33-41, 43-46, and 47-50 are virtual replicas of our old
                        acquaintances, those pre-fabricated units that came to form Chapter II of
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in the first place: respectively, the
                        four-plate introductory unit of Sequence 1, the nine-plate central panel of
                        the cathedral cities, the highly mobile Sequence 2 that ends with the
                        tableau of Vala and Jerusalem, and the immobile concluding Sequence 3. Did a
                        sense of the autonomous integrity of these units persist so distinctly in
                        Blake’s mind, even to the last, as to influence the way he initially went
                        about compiling copy F? </p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
	<pb id="p16-203-205" n="203-205" rend="hidden"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
