<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>17.1.keynes</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Geoffrey Keynes and Peter Davidson, eds., A Watch of Nightingales</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1983</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">17.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Barbara Guth</name>
              <name>Letty Rutledge</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert Alter</name>
              <name>Shelley M. Bennett</name>
              <name>Elizabeth B. Bentley</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>David Erdman</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Theresa M. Kelley</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_17">
    <body>
	<pb id="p17-32" n="32"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-17-1-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Geoffrey Keynes, Kt., and Peter Davidson, eds. <hi rend="i">A Watch of
Nightingales.</hi> London: The Stourton Press, 1981. xii + 48 pp. Four hundred copies printed.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">G. E. </hi><name><hi rend="b">Bentley</hi></name>, 
<hi rend="b">Jr.</hi></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Sir Geoffrey Keynes and Professor Peter Davidson have collected “nearly fifty poems” (p.
[xii]), or rather twenty-seven poems and twelve fragments (some of them in prose), addressed or referring to
the “Most musical” of birds, as Milton called the nightingale. Isaac Walton says that the man who hears at
midnight
<q>
the clear aires, the sweet descants, the natural rising and falling, the doubling and redoubling of her voice,
might well be lifted above earth, and say, Lord, what Musick hast thou provided for the Saints in Heaven, when
thou affordest bad men such musick on earth!
</q>
The title derives from the technical term for a group of nightingales, as in an exaltation of larks and a
charm of goldfinches, also derived from Dame Julia Berners’s <hi rend="i">Boke of Hawkyng, Huntyng, and
Fysshyng</hi> (1486).</p>
          <p>The poets are, of course, concerned with the birdsong rather than the songbird, for the bird
itself is negligible in appearance and usually invisible. Some try to imitate the sound of the song, as in
Skelton and Coleridge’s “jug jug” and Fitzgerald’s translation of <corr type="emend">Omar Khayyam,</corr> “Wine!
<pb id="p17-33" n="33"/>
Wine! Wine! Red Wine!,” but most describe it or reproduce its rhythms, like Coleridge’s
<q>
merry Nightingale<lb/>
That crowds and hurries, and precipitates<lb/>
With fast thick warble his delicious notes . . . .
</q></p>
          <p>But perhaps most interesting is the way the poets, moved to a fine frenzy by the shower of song,
are governed not by the song they heard in the “melodious plot / Of beechen green, and shadows numberless”
but by what they heard in the songs of other poets.</p>
          <p>In the Renaissance, the most important influence was that of Ovid, who in his 
<hi rend="i">Metamorphoses</hi> tells of the rape of Philomela by Tereus and, at the moment of her revenge, their
transformation into birds, Philomela into a nightingale and Tereus into a Hoopoe:
<q>
How prettily she tells the tale<lb/>
Of Rape and Blood.
</q>
Richard Barnfield in 1598 hears the legend in the song:
<q><hi rend="i">Fie, fie, fie</hi>, now she would cry<lb/>
<hi rend="i">Teru Teru</hi>, by and by . . . .
</q>
In the myth the singer is female, and so most of the singing birds are too, from Chaucer and Sidney (1598) and
Shakespeare through Thomas Carew (1651) and Milton (1673) and Marvell (1681), down to Sir John Vanbrugh
(1702), William Walsh (1721), Joseph Warton (1746), John Keats implicitly (1820), and even such an acute
observer as John Clare (1825). But it is, of course, the male, not the female, who sings, though the only
poets to get the sex right here are Cowper (1782), Blake in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (1804-?08), and Pound
(1919).</p>
          <p>Similarly, the bird was thought to learn against a thorn to stimulate her song, joyfully to mourn
the prick, as it were, as in the <corr type="emend">anonymous</corr> song set to music by Robert Jones (1600):
<q>
percht with prick against her breast,<lb/>
She sings fie, fie, fie, fie, as if she suffered wrong<lb/>
Till seemingly pleased sweet, sweet concludes her song.
</q>
Clearly it is something added to the birdsong which has carried away the poet’s imagination.</p>
          <p>Almost as powerful is the tradition of jealous musical rivalry echoed by Goldsmith in his 
<hi rend="i">History of the Earth and Animated Nature</hi>, in Buffon’s <hi rend="i">Histoire Naturelle des
Oiseaux</hi>, and in Thomas Pennant’s <hi rend="i">British Zoology</hi>, probably deriving from Pliny’s
<hi rend="i">Natural History</hi>:
<q>
all of them [nightingales] have not the same, but every one a special kind of musicke by her selfe: nay they
strive who can do best, and one laboureth to excel another in varietie of song and long continuance: yea and
evident it is, that they contend in good earnest with all their will and power: for oftentime she that hath
the worse and is not able to hold out with another, dieth for it, and sooner giveth up her vitall breath, than
giveth over her song.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Tr. Philemon Holland (1601), I, 286, quoted in Fred V. Randel,
“Coleridge and the Contentiousness of Romantic Nightingales,” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 21
(1982), 36.</note></q>
William Walsh writes in 1721 of a nightingale driven to suicide by despair at rivaling the echo of her own
song or “the Waters . . . laughing in the Brook.”</p>
          <p>Clearly the liquid measure of sound is not enough for the poets, but they must make what Joseph
Warton calls “Contemplation’s favourite bird” into an emblem of the human condition, in an attempt to
<q>
quite forget<lb/>
What thou among the leaves hast never known,<lb/>
The weariness, the fever, and the fret<lb/>
Here, where men sit and hear each other groan.
</q></p>
          <p>The <hi rend="i">raison d’être</hi> of this little book is the poem called “To the
Nightingale” etched about 1784 by George Cumberland: “This anthology has . . . been built around” the
poem (p. [viii]). Sir Geoffrey owned copies of this poem for many years and cherished them as examples of
Cumberland’s experiments with printing, until abut 1980 Robert Essick suggested a Blake connection. The
suggestion was that the transcription might be not by Cumberland but by Blake, but they soon decided that the
evidence for this was inconclusive.</p>
          <p>However, the inquiry stimulated Sir Geoffrey to speculate that while Blake probably did not
transcribe the poem, he may well have composed it: “the internal evidence that it could have been composed
only [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] by Blake was very strong” (p. [vii]). Sir Geoffrey canvassed a number of
distinguished scholars and critics on the persuasiveness of this internal evidence and published the
consensus, with a facsimile of the print, in <hi rend="i">The Book Collector</hi> in 1981, attributing the
composition of the poem emphatically to Blake. Certainly all the scholars and critics there cited either agree
with Sir Geoffrey, though usually not in terms as emphatic as his own, or at least present evidence tending to
his conclusion. He also printed the poem in a very slim, handsome volume in 1980 called <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">To the
Nightingale</hi>,</corr> though omiting there both the facsimile and most of the evidence that the poem is by Blake.
Readers of <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> will be chiefly concerned with the evidence that
the anonymous poem called “To the Nightingale” printed for George Cumberland was in fact composed by
William Blake.</p>
          <p>The external evidence is very slight. The poem was certainly sent in January 1784 in a letter
from George Cumberland to his brother as an example of his new, cheap, and easy method of etching and
printing. William Blake was probably experimenting with similar methods of etching and printing, which he
apparently alludes to in his <hi rend="i">Island in the Moon</hi> (?1784) and which evolved into his own
illuminated printing. Cumberland certainly knew of Blake at the time, for he mentioned him in his review of
the annual Royal Academy exhibition in 1780, and they became intimate friends, exchanging correspondence from
at least 1795 through 1827. The poem was printed by William Staden Blake, the writing-engraver of Exchange
Alley, and, according to Sir Geoffrey, “It can be inferred from this action that Cumberland was not yet, in
1784, the close friend of William Blake, the artist, that he afterwards became” (p. [viii]). I am puzzled by
<pb id="p17-34" n="34"/>
the logic of this sentence but conclude that it means that if Cumberland had known the poet well he would have
asked <hi rend="i">him</hi> to print the poem. But we do not know that the poet <hi rend="i">could</hi> have
printed it then—we don’t know when he acquired his own printing press (probably not until autumn
1784)—and there is no evidence that he ever welcomed or did casual job-printing, as opposed to printing his
own plates. But the more slightly Cumberland knew the poet, the odder it seems that he should have been
etching his poem and sending it to friends without identifying the author—it rather smacks of plagiarism.
Certainly when a friend sends me a poem in a letter, I assume that he wrote it unless he tells me the
contrary. Sir Geoffrey’s theory is that “To the Nightingale” is a poem left over from 
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (1783), but there is no evidence whatever that the poem was considered for
this collection by the apparent compilers John Flaxman and the Reverend Mr. A. S. Mathew, and there is no
evidence that Cumberland had anything to do with the production of that volume, though he acquired copy D of
it at an unknown date. Cumberland may have known Blake in 1784, he may have seen his manuscript poems then
(though there is no evidence that anyone other than Flaxman and Mathew did), and he could have presented a
printed copy to his brother—but there is no direct evidence that he did so, and the external probabilities
are against it.</p>
          <p>Sir Geoffrey finds “the internal evidence . . . very strong,” but this suggests the
understandable pride of ownership and discovery rather than the dispassionate persuasion of scholarship. “To
the Nightingale” is an agreeable little poem in four six-line stanzas, written in a somewhat stereotyped
eighteenth-century style. The vocabulary is fashionably poetical, with the “lovely Chauntress of the lonely
Bow’r,” “wildly pour[<hi rend="i">ing</hi>] thy mellow Minstrels’y [<hi rend="i">sic</hi>],” a
“Hind,” and “Cynthias’s silvry beams.” This is not Blake’s characteristic vocabulary and
diction—but then, neither is that of a number of poems in <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>, such as “An
Imitation of Spencer” with its “jocund hours,” “tinkling rhimes,” “Pan,” “Mercurius,” and
“Mercury.” “To the Nightingale” runs:
<q>
Come lovely Chauntress of the lonely Bow’r,<lb/>
(Allured by vernal airs to chequer’d shades)<lb/>
And lightly sit upon the moss grown tree,<lb/>
Near where the dark stream glides, and the soft flow’r,<lb/>
Rears its enamel’d head to grace the glades;<lb/>
Come there and wildly pour thy mellow Minstrels’y.<lb/>
<lb/>
And I with open ears will drink thy song,<lb/>
With cautious trembling steps advancing near,<lb/>
Chiding the low hung boughs that bar my way,<lb/>
Then gently stretch my weary limbs among<lb/>
The Fern, and part the Woodbind shoots, and peer<lb/>
About to find thee perch’t upon the bending spray.<lb/>
<lb/>
O then begin thy undulating note,<lb/>
Check’t by faint Echos from the distant grove,<lb/>
And oft recall the sweetly wandring air;<lb/>
Till, bursting forth, the jolly peal shall float<lb/>
Upon the Breeze, and tell a tale, to move<lb/>
Bald Apathy, or smooth the wrinkled brow of Care.<lb/>
<lb/>
And may no Hind thy secret haunt disclose,<lb/>
Or wanton Heifer near the thicket stray,<lb/>
Rudely to break thy song, thy breast affright;<lb/>
But whilst Attention hears thy gentle lay,<lb/>
Soft Eve advance, clad in Her mantle gray,<lb/>
And Cynthia’s silvry beams illuminate the night.
</q></p>
          <p>Sir Geoffrey finds “jolly” characteristic of Blake, as it is used “on three occasions in
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>” (p. [viii]), but it is scarcely a peculiarly Blakean word—Milton uses
it in his sonnet on the nightingale. The phrase “the wrinkled brow of Care” is an eighteenth-century
conceit which is repeated “in a prose composition of about the same date” [“then she bore Pale desire”
(?1783)] as “Care Sitteth in the wrinkled brow,” and “Bald Apathy” is alleged without evidence to be
“an unusual conjunction of words pointing to Blake’s authorship” (pp. [viii-ix]).</p>
          <p>In his article, Sir Geoffrey satisfies himself that Blake composed “To the Nightingale” by
canvassing vainly for an alternative author. For example, he quotes a passage from a poem undoubtedly by
Cumberland which is strikingly different from “To the Nightingale” in diction and accomplishment and
concludes therefore that Cumberland cannot have written it. But this presumes a uniformity of vocabulary and
achievement in a poet which is very rare. It would, for instance, be difficult to demonstrate from internal
evidence alone that the author of
<q>
I’ll draw my sword, nor ever sheath it up,<lb/>
‘Till England blow the trump of victory,<lb/>
Or I lay stretch’d upon the field of death!<lb/>
[“King Edward the Third” from <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (1783)]
</q>
was the same as the author of the famous passage from <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (1804-?8):
<q>
Nor shall my Sword sleep in my hand:<lb/>
Till we have built Jerusalem,<lb/>
In Englands green &amp; pleasant Land.
</q>
Sir Geoffrey notes that Coleridge in his “The Nightingale” follows Blake in making the nightingale’s
song cheerful (“merry”) rather than melancholy and even suggests therefore “that he had seen one of the
counterproofs [of “To the Nightingale”] made for Cumberland” (p. [ix]), but other poets too found the
nightingale’s song cheerful, such as an anonymous author of 1600 (“sweet content”), William Drummond in
1630 (“Well pleased with Delights”), and John Keats in 1820 (“thy happy lot”).</p>
          <p>The internal evidence is far from conclusive, and we should hesitiate to alienate the poem from
George Cumberland and attach it firmly to William Blake. “To the Nightingale” is a poem with an
achievement above competence but scarcely reaching to greatness. And there are words and ideas in it different
from those one associates with Blake. The poet peering between “the Woodbine shoots [<hi rend="i">and</hi>
fern] . . . to find thee” sounds less like Blake than like John Clare in “The Nightingale’s Nest,”
<pb id="p17-35" n="35"/>
“Creeping on hands and knees through matted thorn [<hi rend="i">and</hi> fern-leaves] / To find her nest.”
The “Hind,” the “Woodbine,” “Cynthia,” “Minstrels’y,” and the “wanton Heifer” are very
unusual in Blake’s verse,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">2</ref> and Blake
knew that the singing nightingale was masculine (“his song” appears in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>), not
feminine as in “To the Nightingale” (“lovely Chauntress”).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n20" type="note">3</ref> The evidence for Blake’s authorship of “To the Nightingale” leads
hesitantly to possibility rather than to certainty. He could have written it, but until we have more evidence
it will be safest to assume no more than the possibility—numbers of others could have written it as well.
And there are numerous contemporary poems which might equally well be his, some in periodicals even signed W.
B. “To the Nightingale” does not deserve to be included “in the Blake canon” (p. [viii]), except
perhaps as a footnote. <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Only “hind” appears in Blake’s known writings
(once, in <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi> [1791]), though “minstrel” is found thrice in the 
<hi rend="i">Concordance</hi>, as Professor Essick kindly reminds me.</note>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">3</hi> I must confess that Blake was not always sexually faithful, for Albion is
feminine in the “Prologue to King John” in <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (1783) but masculine
thereafter.</note></p>
          <p>This <hi rend="i">Watch of Nightingales</hi> is, then, a charming nonce collection revealing much
about the nature of the genius of English poets, but leaving the magical nature of the bird’s song and the
authorship of “To the Nightingale” still mysteriously obscure. As Keats wrote in his “Ode to a
Nightingale,” “Darkling I listen” “in embalmed darkness.”</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
