<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>17.1.gourlay</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">An Emendation in “The Chimney Sweeper” of Innocence</title>
        <author n="Gourlay">Alexander S. Gourlay</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1983</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">17.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Barbara Guth</name>
              <name>Letty Rutledge</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert Alter</name>
              <name>Shelley M. Bennett</name>
              <name>Elizabeth B. Bentley</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>David Erdman</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Theresa M. Kelley</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_17">
    <body>
	<pb id="p17-16" n="16"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-17-1-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">An Emendation in “The Chimney Sweeper” of 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Alexander S. <name>Gourlay</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>A curious variant in the text of “The Chimney Sweeper” (<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> 12) in 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, Copy <hi rend="i">AA</hi> (Fitzwilliam Museum), appears to
have gone unremarked in spite of the wide distribution of transparencies of this copy by EP Microform.
Blake’s etched text of line 20 of the poem reads, “He’d have God for his father &amp; never want joy”;
in Copy <hi rend="i">AA</hi>, however, the contraction “He’d” has been replaced by the word “But.”
Though I have not examined the original, the EP transparency appears to reproduce the plate accurately.</p>
          <p>The transparency shows no evidence of erasure, but the inking of the plate was uneven; in
consequence, letters are obscured by overinking and by underinking. The large area washes further reduce
legibility. Someone appears
<pb id="p17-17" n="17"/>
to have strengthened some letters with pen and ink of the same orange-red color used in printing, but the
result is not equal to the legibility of strengthened pages in late copies such as Copy <hi rend="i">Z</hi>
(Rosenwald). The original contraction, “He’d,” has printed very poorly, but vestiges of the word are
still visible beneath the word “But,” which has been supplied in the same orange-red ink.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">1</ref> The upper right serif of the “H” can be
seen protruding from the upper lobe of the “B,” the printed crossbar of the “e” is visible in the
written “u,” and most of the ascender of the “d” is evident to the right of the written “t,” which
has been formed along the curved bowl of the “d.” <note id="n6"><hi rend="s">1</hi> That the variant in
<hi rend="i">AA</hi> is not a change in the plate is certain, for the posthumous Copy <hi rend="i">b</hi>
(Harvard) has the usual reading. See the Albion Facsimile edition (Albion Facsimiles #1) (London and New York:
1947), n.p. This (as well as all other facsimiles of Harvard’s <hi rend="i">b</hi>) should, however, be used
with caution; see below.</note></p>
          <p>There are only a few textual alterations like this one elsewhere in the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>;
most other known instances of textual change attributable to Blake provide plausible readings, and most are
improvements on the etched text. An emendation that is mechanically similar to the one in <hi rend="i">AA</hi>
has been adopted by both David V. Erdman and G. E. Bentley, Jr. in their editions of Blake’s writings. This
change (from “sung” to “sang”) in line 5 of “The Clod &amp; the Pebble” (<hi rend="i">Songs</hi>
32), in Copy <hi rend="i">Z</hi>, has been accepted in spite of the fact that it appears in only that copy,
and could have been accidental; Copy <hi rend="i">Z</hi> was finished at about the same time as 
<hi rend="i">AA</hi> and in a similar style.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
type="note">2</ref> But the emendation in Copy <hi rend="i">AA</hi> should not be accorded the same degree of
respect, for it is a patent corruption. By itself line 20 of “The Chimney Sweeper” as emended in 
<hi rend="i">AA</hi> is not obviously wrong, but in context it leaves the Angel’s promise incomplete and makes
the sweeps’ happy awakening particularly abrupt:
<q>
And the Angel told Tom if he’d be a good boy,<lb/>
But have God for his father &amp; never want joy.<lb/>
<lb/>
And so Tom awoke and we rose in the dark<lb/>
And got with our bags &amp; our brushes to work.
</q>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">2</hi> In addition to the variant in “The Clod and the Pebble” mentioned in
the text, four other <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> are emended in one or more copies: “A Cradle Song” 
(<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> 17), emended substantially in Copy <hi rend="i">J</hi>; “Night” 
(<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> 21), in Copy Q of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (Erdman and Bentley differ slightly as to
which words are changed); and “The Tyger” (<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> 42), in Copy <hi rend="i">P.</hi>
Bentley also mentions an obviously inadvertent textual change in “On Another’s Sorrow” 
(<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> 27), in Copy L of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>: the word “tear” in line 31 printed
faintly and was covered by a painted leaf. Erdman’s textual notes seem to imply that “The Blossom” 
(<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> 11) has been emended “in all copies issued by Blake.” His assertion that the text of
“posthumous copies” reads “thy” rather than “my” in line 6 is based on one of the unaccountably
retouched facsimiles of Harvard’s Copy <hi rend="i">b</hi>, in which “my” has been altered to “thy.”
That Copy <hi rend="i">b</hi> itself contains the usual reading has been demonstrated by Mary Ellen Reisner in
“Folcroft Facsimile of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 40 (Spring 1977),
130. See Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, newly rev. ed. (Berkeley
and Los Angeles: Univ. of California, 1982), and Bentley, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi>, 2
vols. (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1978).</note></p>
          <p>Although this variant is not particularly meaningful in itself, it could well be authorial, and
probably originated in Blake’s workshop. The plate appears to have printed so poorly that it is unlikely
that it would have been issued without any retouching of the text, and all strengthening (both accurate and
inaccurate) appears to have been done with the same ink and in the same style. Whoever did it was certainly
not paying close attention to the syntactic or printed evidence on the page; it is hard to imagine an owner of
the book who would be sufficiently
            <figure n="songsie.aa.p12.detail" rend="file" width="853" height="180">
	<head>Detail of <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> 12, Copy <hi rend="i">AA</hi>.</head>
	<figDesc>Reproduced by permission of the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge.</figDesc>
</figure>
officious to go to the trouble of carefully matching the ink but sufficiently obtuse to make such an
implausible emendation. Because the word seems to have been added so casually, and because the ink used
matches the printing ink so closely (indeed, it could be a diluted form of the printing ink), the emendation
should probably be attributed to one of the Blakes or, as Erdman has suggested in correspondence, to an
anonymous assistant in the workshop. The task of retouching the text was no doubt tedious, and it is likely
that someone, working absentmindedly, relied on an imperfect memory of the line rather than thoughtful
consideration of the evidence in making the unhelpful emendation.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n8" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">3</hi> In correspondence Erdman cites two instances in which retouching has
similarly corrupted the text of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Copy B, on plates 17 and 18. These are mentioned
in his textual notes, p. 809. Copy B of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> contains another
instance of sloppy retouching on plate 25: the word “chariots” is crudely written as
“charots.”</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
