<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>17.1.erdman</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Redefining the Texts of Blake (another temporary report)</title>
        <author n="Erdman">David V. Erdman</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1983</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">17.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Barbara Guth</name>
              <name>Letty Rutledge</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert Alter</name>
              <name>Shelley M. Bennett</name>
              <name>Elizabeth B. Bentley</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>David Erdman</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Theresa M. Kelley</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_17">
    <body>
    <pb id="p17-4" n="4"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-17-1-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">Redefining the Texts of Blake (another temporary report)</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">DAVID V.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">ERDMAN</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>Thirteen years ago I submitted “A Temporary Report on Texts of Blake” to the Damon
Festschrift.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> Wondering how perfectly
or imperfectly the “texts” which Blake had etched, left in manuscript, or submitted to printers were
represented in the available and forthcoming editions of Blake and in the <hi rend="i">Concordance</hi> of
1968 prepared by a team of ten Blake scholars, I made a survey of the “particular passages” that remained
“incompletely transcribed or not certainly established.” Since that time the informal collaboration of
editors and other scholars in a “web of mutual communication of reports and queries and photostats” has
continued, and the number of uncertain passages has diminished. Many cruxes remain, however, and some of the
“certainties” of 1969 have been questioned. And the hope for technological advances that would reduce the
“illegibles” of palimpsest (chiefly in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>) has risen high, only to sink
again. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Pp. 395-413, 494-98, in Alvin H. Rosenfeld, ed., <hi rend="i">William
Blake: Essays for S. Foster Damon</hi> (Brown Univ. Press, 1969).</note></p>
        <p>The texts collated for this new report are four:
<table rows="4" cols="2"><row>
	<cell>E</cell>
	<cell>Erdman, ed. <hi rend="i">The Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi> (Doubleday 1965, fourth printing
1970) with commentary by Bloom.</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>K</cell>
	<cell>Keynes, ed. <hi rend="i">Blake: Complete Writings</hi> (Oxford Univ. Press 1966; 4th revised printing
1976; fifth 1979<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref>). 
<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> The 1976 printing of K was checked thoroughly in the preparation of C; the 1979 printing
reached me only after C had gone to press, but a fairly complete collation of the passages in the present
report revealed very few changes from K1976. Characteristic errors that might have been corrected from E
continue in 1979: “thoughts” for “thought” in Anno. Swedenborg p. 12; “Infinity” for
“Infinite” in Anno. Swed. p. 40; <hi rend="i">America</hi> 5:3 retains “enclos’d” for “inclosd”
and there are no corrections of <hi rend="i">America</hi> c. The K text of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
remains frequently inadequate. On K268 “these” is not corrected to “them” in “I have murderd
them”; “Or hover’d over” (K284:182) should read “Or hoverd oer”; “turned into cries” (K310)
should read “turned to cries”; “better hope” (K355:547) should be “bitter hope”; “girded”
(K370:504) is a mistake for “girded on”; “Aloud” (K380) a misreading of “O Luvah.” In the 3rd
edition of the <hi rend="i">Letters</hi> (1980) Keynes made several corrections—such as changing the date of
letter 56 (K859) from April to March and revising “Home” to “House”—that were not transferred to the
K text.
                                    <p>The “1979” Preface mentions only two corrections (on pp. 184 and
644 respectively: see below). The second of these is a surprising one, replacing “worshipped” with
“warshipped” as probably a “deliberate ‘misprint’ ” that amused Blake (a contextual pun, accepted
in the C text as well). Still more curious is an unmentioned change in <hi rend="i">MHH</hi> 7:13, from
“wholesome” back to Blake’s “wholsom” (K151): curious because the K text is conscientiously
normalized in spelling—and indeed Blake’s “Wholesom” in <hi rend="i">PA</hi> p. 19 is kept in
normalized spelling (“Wholesome”) in K599. Also, for instance, in <hi rend="i">FR</hi> 216 (K144)
Blake’s “beastial” (respected by Johnson’s printer) remains normalized (K144) as “bestial,” and on
K256 the Keynes “steadfast” is not changed to Blake’s “stedfast.”</p>
	<p>It may be deduced from these and several other examples that the K text of 1979 received only a very few
touches of revision or correction, quite possibly more spelling changes than I have noticed but probably very
few substantive changes, or none, except in the two passages called attention to in the Preface. The present
collation, in short, can stand as a near equivalent to a collation of the 1979 as well as the 1976
Keynes.</p></note>
	</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>B</cell>
	<cell>Bentley, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi> (Oxford Univ. Press 1978; two vols. paginated
continuously).</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>C</cell>
	<cell><hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry</hi> &amp; <hi rend="i">Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. Erdman, with
commentary by Bloom (Doubleday, paper; University of California Press, cloth 1982).</cell>
</row></table>
Also occasionally cited are:
<table rows="3" cols="2"><row>
	<cell>BB</cell>
	<cell>Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford Univ. Press 1977).</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell><hi rend="i">N</hi></cell>
	<cell>Erdman and Moore, eds. <hi rend="i">The Notebook of William Blake</hi> (photographic and typographic
facsimile; Oxford Univ. Press 1973; revised ed. Readex Books 1977). N, not in italics, refers simply to the
Notebook itself.</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>SAP</cell>
	<cell>Erdman “The Suppressed and Altered Passages in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi> 17 (1964): 1-54.</cell>
</row></table></p>
        <p>“C” has been chosen as symbol for the new edition (rather than, say, E<hi rend="s">2</hi>) as
more impersonal and in recognition of the committees of textual scholars who watched and assisted the
labor—judicially the CSE (MLA) who approved the procedures and format; critically the four scholars who
helped check the text against originals or via film and facsimile: Robert Essick, John E. Grant, Mary Lynn
Johnson Grant, and E. B. Murray. The present report is not quite exhaustive (dealing rarely with punctuation)
and is intended primarily to enable users of any of the texts collated to find quickly what differences appear
in C. Explanations of changes in C will be found in its textual notes, but certain critical passages are
discussed briefly in this report. (Changes made in the second and third printings of E are not cited.) Points
where B questions readings in E are attended to in the textual notes of C but if puzzling also noted here.</p>
        <p>The fact that text and notes have been completely reset for C (and many of the notes rewritten)
will mean that some errors have crept in. Responses to this report will be welcome, for revisions in
subsequent printings.</p>
        <p>The format of the textual notes in E and C is used in the notes that follow, and the symbols used
in K and B are transposed into the same format. Square brackets [] enclose words or letters editorially
inserted; italicized insertions represent [<hi rend="i">deleted matter</hi>] restored. Angle brackets &lt;&gt;
enclose words or letters inserted by Blake; “rdg” and “del” stand for “reading” and
“deleted.”</p>
        <p>All editorial emendations are indicated, with one exception. For the possessive of “Los” Blake
often wrote “Los’s” but also frequently omitted the apostrophe; in the latter instances, to avoid the
clutter of brackets, the apostrophe has been inserted silently.</p>
        <p>The textual note on punctuation has been revised somewhat. But I find that a further word is
advisable about Blake’s indications for paragraphing and about his occasional intermingling of design and
text, insofar as it concerns the transcriber. Pictures interrupting the text, in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> for instance, sometimes serve as paragraph breaks but sometimes not. The designs
after line 12 and line 27 in <hi rend="i">J</hi> 9 and after lines 13 and 26 in <hi rend="i">J</hi> 20 do not
halt the narrative; those in <hi rend="i">J</hi> 20 after lines 4, 11,
<pb id="p17-5" n="5"/>
20, 21, and 41 definitely do. And in his prose, Blake sometimes indicates a paragraph by a long dash, as after
“Sword” in the <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> Preface.</p>
        <p>Verse paragraphs are usually only spaced, but sometimes they are indicated by indentation; we treat
them alike typographically. Sometimes a punctuation mark seems turning into vegetation or feather; sometimes a
detail of foliage is thrust into position to serve as punctuation. Consider: is not the bird at the end of 
<hi rend="i">J</hi> 61:23 serving as a dash—yet still in flight as a bird?</p>
        <p>The punctuation for this edition (C) has been thoroughly checked by our proofreading team against
originals and photographs and facsimiles, also against B. Agreement within the team has not always been
unanimous; B, however, has been found more often disagreed with than agreed with in this matter. Textual notes
deal with some of these punctuational cruxes, but no attempt is made to cover them in the present report.</p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Works in Illuminated Printing</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>The works are listed, in this and subsequent sections, in the order of arrangement of texts in E
and C.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">All Religions are One</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Now placed first, from evidence given by Geoffrey Keynes in his Blake Trust facsimile (but not
applied in K 1979). Spelling variants are all that occur:</p>
            <p>Principle 4th travelling (KE) / traveling (BC)</p>
            <p>Principle 5th Religeons (E) / Religions (KBC) each Nation’s (EK) / each Nations (BC)</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">There is No Natural Religion</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The paragraph headed “Conclusion” is now moved from version (a) to version (b) following
the paragraph headed “Application.”</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Songs of Innocence &amp; of Experience</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p><hi rend="i">Night</hi> 44 Grase (E) / Graze (KBC—see textual note) <hi rend="i">The
Tyger</hi> [6 eyes!] (E) / eyes? (KBC) 16 clasp? (EK) / clasp! (BC)</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">The Human Abstract</hi> Line 8 in N 107 draft (“The human image”): And spreads
his [<hi rend="i">nets</hi>] baits with care (EK) / corrected by Bentley to “. . . his 
[<hi rend="i">seeds</hi>] baits . . .” (BC)</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">A Divine Image</hi> Now described, since discovery of copy BB, as not simply
“rejected” but early and replaced.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">To Tirzah</hi> C note on date (ca. 1803) is important, since B682 gives “perhaps
1797” (despite own evidence).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">For Children: The Gates of Paradise</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Pl. 13: variant in N 61: What we hope we see (EKC) . . . to see (B)</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The “Proverbs” are now grouped by spacing, to correspond with the grouping by color made in
copy H (with obvious care, since the groups so indicated make sense). Other improvements made by Blake in copy
H include the correction of two scribal errors by using (as ancient scribes did) a macron or horizontal stroke
above a letter to indicate accidental omission of a letter or letters (or small word) immediately following.
In 10:9 Blake corrects “improvent” with a macron over the “v” to make “improvement”(as in the next
line). In 14:5 he etched “at tree” (EKB) but a macron in copy H indicates correction to “at the tree”
(C). (Uncorrected words, “wholsom” and “witheld,” lack only inessential letters.)</p>
            <p>See textual note on 3:6 re “the Devil who dwells.”</p>
            <p>In “A Song of Liberty” corrections of punctuation made in copy H are adopted in C: 3
ocean?] <hi rend="i">corrected to</hi> ocean! 6 weep] <hi rend="i">to</hi> weep! (C).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>All editions agree, except for two variants in B that must be scribal errors: omission of
“are” before “their habitations” in 3:5 (B’s 6:5) and “and” for “&amp;” in 3:12. I.e., no
variants in Blake.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">America a Prophecy</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Canceled plate c:12 mossy pile (KEB) / massy pile (C) c:22 [&amp;] or shut . . . [&amp;] in
(KB) / or shut . . . &amp; in (E) / &amp; shut &amp; in (C)</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Milton</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>2:21 deed (K482) / deed? (E95) / deed[.] (B320) / deed[?] (C96), there being no punctuation at
this point in any copy.</p>
            <p>10:3 into the Space] B omits “the” in error.</p>
            <p>11:35 spake (EK) / spoke (BC)</p>
            <p>23:28 spoke (EK) / spake (BC)</p>
            <p>24[26]: 63-64. lulld by the flutes lula lula / The bellowing Furnaces blare by the . . .
clarion (B, giving text without emendation) / . . . flutes’ lula lula . . . Furnaces blare . . . (K) / . . .
flutes lula lula . . . Furnaces[’] blare (EC). Too late to change, it was noted that C should also give
“flutes[’]”; readers often mistake this passage, not sensing that “blare” is a noun here, not a
verb. The instruments are played “to ameliorate . . . slavery” (61). The sounds of Hammers “are lulld by
the flutes[’] lula lula” and the blare of the Furnaces is lulled by the long sounding clarion; the drum
drowns the howls, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>31:13 Towards America . . . golden bed (EKC) / Line omitted (B)</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Jerusalem</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>To the Public</p>
            <p>3:8 the Ancients entrusted their love to their Writing (EK) / the ancients acknowledge their
love to their Deities (C) / (B questions all restorations of this plate)</p>
            <pb id="p17-6" n="6"/>
            <p>In 1969 I could say that “no passages still in doubt” were “as central and significant as
the Plate 3 deletions in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>” and could describe these as “now restored.” In
February 1980 a letter from Michael Tolley queried my restoration of the words “entrusted” and
“Writing” in this gouged-out passage, and a very careful rechecking, by myself and others, using enlarged
photographs from the Rosenwald and Morgan copies and the posthumous Rosenbloom copy and the unenlarged
photograph of the Morgan page in SAP (which shows nearly everything that the others do).</p>
            <p>My error resulted from incomplete observance of my own procedures, spelled out in SAP. The word
read as “entrusted” or “acknowledge” has three ascending strokes (we must ignore the descending stroke
of “p” from the line above); I had failed to notice that on this page Blake’s t’s barely rise above
the body of the letters, hence that none of the three ascenders could be a “t”. Indeed, the first ascender
has a bend (not apparent in the Morgan, or it would have been noted sooner) which can belong only to a “k”
in this script. The word “Acknowledge” in the very next line is more visible and offers a perfect model to
test the misread word. Of the other queried word, the only plainly visible letters are “iti” in the
center. The first letter, a bombed-out capital, has edges in the Rosenwald copy that fit a Blakean “W”;
but, as I now see, in the Morgan the crater is encircled not merely by dots but by a large loop fitting
exactly the “D” of “Divine” seven lines further down. And the second letter is more like “e” than
“r”. “Writing” was not an impossible hypothesis; “Deities” works perfectly. (I should add that
Mary Lynn Johnson and John Grant, in the Norton Critical <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1979), recognizing something
wrong with the passage, refer to “Blake’s somewhat garbled defense of enthusiasm in this mutilated
passage” (p. 312n4). The garbling was mine.</p>
            <p>(I am told that in semiotic circles, the phrase “entrusted their love to their Writing” was
becoming a favorite <hi rend="i">locus classicus</hi>! Mea culpa!)</p>
            <p>7:65 Generation Image of regeneration!] “Image” was scratched through for deletion and is
illegible or nearly so in most copies but was retouched into legibility in copies B and D. (Some copy B
retouchings are clearly irresponsible: see notes on plate 17 and 18, below.) “Image” is shown undeleted in
KB (with a note in B); “[<hi rend="i">Image</hi>]” in EC, signifying deletion editorially restored, with a
textual note of explanation, but perhaps it should have been printed with this note but without the
bracketing. (The details of the note in B [429] err from the correct account in SAP 16.)</p>
            <p>8:32 The uncircumcised (E, in error but corrected in 4th printing) / Thy Uncircumcised
(KBC)</p>
            <p>17:21 fit for labour (EKBC) / changed to “labours” by printers’ ink in copy B, but
unidiomatic. Noted now in C.</p>
            <p>18:36 So cry Hand &amp; Hyle (EKBC) mended to “So criest thou? &amp; Hyle” in copy
B—first noted in C. The “u” is formed in the space between “n” and “d”; the “?” is made of a
bit of interlinear ornament. This and the change in 17:21 are retouchings in the red-brown ink of the
printing; other words are retouched without change in lines 10, 11, 20, 22, 25. Whoever made the mendings in
18 and 17 was inattentive to the sense and syntax.</p>
            <p>BB 732 notes that some “words and designs are clarified in pencil (pl. 5, 7-10 [but these are
in design only], in Red ink (pl. 8 [design only]), or in Black ink (pl. 9-11, 15, 19-22, 25 [words retouched
in 10, 11, 20, 22, 25, without change]).” B and BB overlook the actual changes in pl. 17 &amp; 18, noted
above.</p>
            <p>21:44 worshipped (EKB) / warshipped (C and 1982K) Footnote on the page points out that the
reading makes sense yet may be a misprint for “worshipped”.</p>
            <p>(The “a” is made with the usual serif at top right, never given to an “o”, which is
made in a circular sweep. The “a” is made with a curved stroke that begins at the top, comes up to make
the serif and down again to connect with the next letter. Of course an “a” can look something like an
“o”, but even the “a” in “massy” in <hi rend="i">America</hi> c, misread until now, though it
lacks the protruding serif does have the vertical right side produced by the up and down motion described.</p>
            <p>24:60 Hope is banished from me] (KBC; yet B in “Addenda and Corrigenda”, p. xxvi, gives
“from us” as a correction, without explanation.)</p>
            <p>27 Begin new paragraph with “But now the Starry Heavens . . .” (BC).</p>
            <p>27: <hi rend="i">next paragraph</hi>: was Created (EKBC) / B738 lists “was” as an error for
“were”; indeed the grammar is polysemous and debatable. Problem overlooked in C.</p>
            <p>32[36]:34 South [ ]ing (E) / South bounding (C). Explained in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
13:106.</p>
            <p>40[45]:31 hands (KEC) / hand (B, printer’s error?)</p>
            <p>42:47 abhorred friend (KBC) / abhorred [<hi rend="i">fiend</hi>] (E); B and C note that
“friend” may be an error for “fiend” but that the context gives support to the original reading.</p>
            <p>30[34]:10 Why have thou elevate (KEC) / [Why has thou elevated] (B). (Yet nine lines earlier
“I am Love / Elevate into the Region” is given without comment or emendation in B.)</p>
            <p>56:37 earth-Worm (KBC) / earth-Worms (E) Changed by ink in copy F, not necessarily by Blake. B
asserts “by Blake” yet retains “earth-Worm”; K does not note; change adopted in E, with note; rejected
in C, with note.</p>
            <p>66:38 Their ear bent (KEBC) B with note: “Blake probably intended ‘ears’ plural”;
perhaps, though singulars come in line 40.</p>
            <p>77: bottom corners. Deleted lines, partly legible in copy F and posthumous copies I and J; for
the first time fully recovered for C; reading column for column instead of line for line, as we all had been
doing:
<pb id="p17-7" n="7"/>
	<table rows="1" cols="1"><row>
	<cell>The Real Self[<hi rend="i">hood</hi>] is the Imagination</cell>
	<cell>in the<lb/>
Divine Man</cell>
</row></table>
K(919n) had read the top row, though not noting that “hood” was scratched out on the copper (Blake, having
begun to write about the <hi rend="i">real</hi> Selfhood as against the spectral Selfhood, then passed beyond
irony to emphasize “The Real <hi rend="i">Self</hi>”).</p>
            <p>In SAP I concurred with the K reading of the top row, venturing only a few letters for the
bottom row:
<table rows="1" cols="1"><row>
	<cell>The Real Self[hood] is the?Spectre?within</cell>
	<cell>in the<lb/>
P . . . . T . . m</cell>
</row></table>
B has now deciphered that last phrase, putting “Divine Man” convincingly in place of “P . . . T . . .
m” but unaccountably losing “in the,” perhaps still trying to read line for line. C puts cautionary
question marks on “Imagination” and “Man,” but “tion” is clearly a better fit for the end of the
first column than “thin.” The <hi rend="i">Concordance</hi> shows Blake speaking several times of “The
Imagination” as the “Real Man,” an idea attributed to Jesus in Anno. Berkeley.</p>
            <p>87:6-7 the space between these lines in E has been properly removed in C (as in KB).</p>
            <p>89:26 Rocks (KE) / flocks (BC)</p>
            <p>96:34 rouze up, rouze up! (K) / rouze up. rouze up. (E) / rouze up! rouze up. (C, as in
originals) / (B omits one “rouze up” altogether and puts an editorial “!” on the one retained;
probably a simple error of transcription). B’s note that lines 1-25 “are curtailed” omits the
explanation found in SAP.</p>
            <p>97:45 mending of “thy Covenant” is correctedly described in B637n but wrongly described in
B634n.</p>
            <p>98:48 Sacrifices (KEC) / Sacrifice (B637, with note treating the “s” as doubtful). But the
“s” is only crowded, not hidden, by the border; the syntax requires a plural.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">On Virgil</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Concluding sequence is rearranged thus:</p>
            <p>Mathematic Form is Eternal in the Reasoning Memory. Living Form is Eternal Existence.</p>
            <p>Grecian is Mathematic Form</p>
            <p>Gothic is Living Form</p>
            <p>(This part of the text is in two columns; previous transcripts have put the second column
first.)</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <corr type="emend"><hi rend="b">Laocoön</hi></corr>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Practise is Art] <hi rend="i">now moved to precede</hi> A Poet a Painter . . . (Printers’
error in C: photograph facing p. 273 is printed as a negative, with black printed for white; corrected in the
clothbound.)</p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">PROPHETIC WORKS, UNENGRAVED TIRIEL</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>1:19 shrinking] <hi rend="i">1st rdg del</hi> heaving (K) / living (EBC); <hi rend="i">2nd
rdg del</hi> ?shriecking (EC) Note in B903 mistakes this conjectured 2nd rdg for a proposed final rdg.</p>
              <p>1:28 serpents [?<hi rend="i">all</hi>] (B) / (del word is not noted in KEC, but B is
correct).</p>
              <p>3:32 seeks] runs <hi rend="i">1st rdg del</hi> (EBC) (K: “<hi rend="i">word
del</hi>”)</p>
              <p>4:50 rent] <hi rend="i">mended from</hi> rend (noted in EBC, not K)</p>
              <p>4:63 . . . and know your father <hi rend="i">1st rdg del</hi> (EC) (K elides; B notes E rdg
but considers its “and know” a single illegible word.)</p>
              <p>5:5 [<hi rend="i">earth</hi>] ground (K) / [<hi rend="i">ground</hi>] world (E) / 
[<hi rend="i">world</hi>] ground (B) / [<hi rend="i">ground</hi>] earth (C) (No comment.)</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The French Revolution</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Having been mistaken in the faulty recollection (I had once checked the original proofs) that
traditional quotation marks were in the printed text, I have now removed them all; Blake himself would have
supplied none.</p>
            <p>More fully explanatory notes are now supplied for the readings bonds/bands (line 74),
cloud/loud (101), war-living/war living (283).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">The Four Zoas</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>This report does not attempt to deal with all the differences among editions in the handling of
deleted matter and in arrangement of pages. For the recovery of passages hitherto considered deleted see
comment on pages 5, 6, and 7. For drastic rearrangement of the constituent pages of Night the Seventh, briefly
described below, one must get one’s sense of the effect by consulting the rearranged text itself.</p>
            <p>In the new edition (C) for convenience of using the <hi rend="i">Concordance</hi> (based on K)
we have given the K line numbers, within brackets, since they are continuous for each Night. But here I cite
simply page and line numbers for the page.</p>
            <p>3:8 no Individual [<hi rend="i">Knoweth nor</hi>] (B accidently omits “Individual”).</p>
            <p>4:13 It is not Love I bear to [Jerusalem] It is Pity] See textual note for explanation of this
editorial replacement of “Enitharmon” by “Jerusalem.”</p>
            <p>Pages 5-6] These pages have each ten new lines, previously considered deleted from failure to
understand that when Blake circled a deleted passage he meant to restore it to the text; page 7 has been
restored from its mistaken conflation (in E) with page 143, the readings in which are now recognized as
preceding, not following, the final readings in p. 7. Andrew Lincoln cleared up these matters in 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 46:91-95.</p>
            <p>27:9 O Lamb] I ?die <hi rend="i">1st rdg erased</hi> (EC) / [<hi rend="i">word del</hi>]
(B)</p>
            <p>30:16 ?halls of <hi rend="i">1st rdg erased</hi> (EB) / centr f[orm] (C)</p>
            <p>39:18-40:1 But saw not . . . in the cloud] Two lines shown as <hi rend="i">del</hi> (KEB); as
undeleted (C): they are simply lined through lightly in pencil to be excluded when the passage was copied into
J 43.</p>
            <p>P. 41: Text unchanged (except for recognizing the
<pb id="p17-8" n="8"/>
“I” in line 10 as undeleted), but see elaborately revised textual note concerning the late insertion of
the name “Albion” on this page. (But K and B, mistaking the page markings, move line 10 to follow line 4,
in error.)</p>
            <p>42:18 She ended. [<hi rend="i">From</hi>] his wrathful throne burst forth (E) / She ended. for
[from] his wrathful . . . (C) KB change the ms period to a comma; E misread the “for” as a canceled
“From”—now supplied in C as the needed connective. The squiggle that looks like “for” may have been
meant for “from”—or both words were intended but one slipped away.</p>
            <p>It is also worth noting that here, and elsewhere, Bentley’s spacing of lines hides the
evidence of paragraph spacing when inserted lines, belonging to one paragraph or the other, physically fill an
original gap. In this dialogue <corr type="emend">between</corr> Ahania and Urizen, the line “She ended 
. . . ” should stand as a paragraph by itself, between her speech and his.</p>
            <p>47:22 despair comes over (KEB) / editorial insertion in C: over [me]</p>
            <p>56:23 is followed by Blake’s instruction: “Bring in here the Globe of Blood as in the B of
Urizen” (a reference to <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> 18); editors have heretofore shirked their duty, but the
lines fit perfectly, treating two <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> lines as one. (We enclose the resulting four lines
within editorial brackets.) (C338)</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Night The Seventh</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The long debated conflation of the two Nights the Seventh (A and B) into one is carried out
here with benefit of the proposals discussed by Andrew Lincoln, Mark Lefebvre, and John Kilgore in 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 12 (1978): 107-34, along the lines of my discussion following theirs (135-39). See the
textual headnote on C836.</p>
            <p>78:13 rangd his [<hi rend="i">Books</hi>] Books around (B1185) / rangd his rocks a[round] Book
around <hi rend="i">1st rdg</hi> (EC) / rang’d his [<hi rend="i">word del.</hi>] Books around (K)</p>
            <p>82:33 face lightnings] face [<hi rend="i">thy sons</hi>] &lt;&amp; his&gt; lightnings 
<hi rend="i">1st rdg</hi> (EC) / face, [<hi rend="i">word del.</hi>] lightnings (K) / face; [<hi rend="i">thy
?Smiles</hi>] lightnings (B1193). Yet not a very difficult ms.</p>
            <p>85:41-42 Thou didst subdue me . . . lust &amp; murder (KE) (Now moved in BC to follow 85:38;
these lines are written in the bottom margin and not precisely marked for insertion; I agree with B1198 that
“The sense seems to sanction their insertion here.”</p>
            <p>91:11 red Orc in his [<hi rend="i">word erased</hi>] fury (K) / . . . in his 
[<hi rend="i">triumphant</hi>] fury (E) / . . . in his [<hi rend="i">blind(?) f th(?)] fury</hi> (B) / . . . in his
[?<hi rend="i">triumphant</hi>] fury (C, a bit less certain). B’s “f” is my “p”; his “th” my
“nt”; “triumphant” is the right length and has only two odd bits of strokes to account for, above the
“p” and the “n” which I take to be a start at deleting the word before erasing it.</p>
            <p>93:23 dropping tears of woe (K) / drinking . . . (EC) / . . . drinking? (B)</p>
            <p>98, after 31 Then I heard the Earthquake &amp;c (KEB) / Then Heavd the Earthquake &amp;c
(C)</p>
            <p>101:31 expelled (KB) / repelled (EC)</p>
            <p>113:25 in its Islands (E) / on its Islands (KBC)</p>
            <p>105:24 there was hidden (E) / then was hidden (KBC)</p>
            <p>119:18 flames whirring up (E) / . . . li[c]king up (KBC)</p>
            <p>121:7 pleasant garden (EB) / pleasant gardens (KC)</p>
            <p>126:6-7 obey &amp; live . . . return O love (EC) / . . . return &amp; Love (KB, missing the
progression of thought. Since the “&amp;” and “O” are written clearly, K and B assume a scribal error;
B even suggests that “&amp; live” could be “O live”).</p>
            <p>145:10 (passage quoted in textual note on 106:6) Of most mournful pity (EK) / Of most
merciful(?) pity (BC)—a more probable reading than “mournful” in the context; the written word is
wobbly, the first 3 letters more clearly “merc” than “mour,” the fourth not obviously either “i”
or “n.”</p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">POETICAL SKETCHES</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>To Summer: 15 Our youth[s] (E) / youths (K) / youth (BC)</p>
              <p>Samson: (10 lines from end): stocks (E) / flocks (KBC)</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">Then She bore Pale desire</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>In this fragment a change of position is made of the clause “Shame bore honour &amp; made
league with Pride,” from line 75 to lines 91-92.</p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">AN ISLAND IN THE MOON</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>In E a fairly “clean” text was printed, without the many slight mendings of letters or
parts of words that strew the manuscript. C includes some of these, when any significance can be deduced. The
few reported here contain some new readings, or confirmation of disputed readings in E.</p>
              <p>E440/C449: question mark now removed from [<hi rend="i">tipsy</hi>] (Mrs Gimblet); plural
retained in “his own imaginations” (despite removal by B875). B, indeed, seems seldom to accept Blake’s
thin terminal “s”; in <hi rend="i">IM</hi> p. 4 he even reduces “the names in the Bible” to a
singular.</p>
              <p>(À propos, B has 21 footnotes citing readings in E, not always questioning them but never
incorporating them; all these have now been multiple-checked and found sound. Most of them are quite legible
to others, as well as to me.)</p>
              <p>Chap. 1, 3rd par.: [<hi rend="i">Quid</hi>] [&lt;<hi rend="i">the Elder</hi>&gt;] (C)</p>
              <p>Ms. p. 2: [<hi rend="i">here the</hi>] (E) / [<hi rend="i">here Etr</hi> (i.e. Etruscan)]
(C)</p>
              <p>p. 3: call me ass (E) / call me *Arse (C). Blake wrote “ass,” then “Arse,” then
“as” again; then put an asterisk on the 2nd rdg to restore it. (K has the asterisk in the wrong place; B
does not transcribe it.)</p>
              <pb id="p17-9" n="9"/>
              <p>Chap. 6, opening: Then all went (E) / They all went (KBC)</p>
              <p>Chap. 8 O ay Lock said Scopprell. [<hi rend="i">Its a book about</hi>] (K, punctuated, C) /
Deletion omitted (E) / [<hi rend="i">three words del</hi>] (B)</p>
              <p>Chap. 11 [<hi rend="i">how many Blackamoors</hi> . . . ] (K) / [[<hi rend="i">If</hi>] 
<hi rend="i">How many</hi> . . . ] (E768/C850) / [<hi rend="i">?If ?we ?manage Blackamoors</hi>] (B898, but
quoting E in a note, as supplying a “rather more plausib[le] reading”).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">[SONGS AND BALLADS]</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="b">To my Mirtle (N106)</hi> The 16 lines (N 113, 111, 106) arranged under the title
“in a mirtle shade” in E460 (18 lines in K169) were recognized as not constituting an authentic separate
poem when I was collaborating with Donald K. Moore on the <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> facsimile; a note to that
effect was inserted in the 4th printing of E (pp. 769-70—and see the extensive note in <hi rend="i">N</hi>
Appendix I pp. 69-71); in C these lines have been allowed to sink back into their proper state as a canceled
extension of “Infant Sorrow” (given and discussed in the notes section C797-99). Yeats and Ellis had
started this rearranging “according to the editor’s taste” (to quote Geoffrey Keynes in his
autobiography, <hi rend="i">The Gates of Memory</hi>, 1981, p. 255) and in 1926 Max Plowman had recognized
that “in a mirtle shade” (lower case) was not a title but a catchphrase indicating where Blake wanted to
fit the lines that follow into his “Infant Sorrow” extension. Plowman unfortunately had made a mistaken
reconstruction of the sequence in the manuscript; so Keynes and the rest of us had carved out a separate poem
(KEB). Alas, A. E. Housman wrote to Keynes (loc. cit.) that he preferred the Yeats version, “the old
eight-line text,” as, “however ill authenticated, . . . one of the most beautiful of all the poems.”
(The eight-line poem was made of the six lines on C469—with “sick” arbitrarily replaced by
“weak”—plus two that Blake canceled: “Love, free love, cannot be bound / To any tree that grows on
ground.”) (Sampson in 1905 had “To My Mirtle” sorted out, but he treated 16 lines of N 111 as a “first
version,” with the title “In a Mirtle Shade.”)</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">Riches (N 103)</hi> Line 1 deletions are correct as given in EC, though
questioned in B975.</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">Eternity (N 105)</hi> 1 He who binds to himself a joy (KEC) / . . . bends (B). B
declares he cannot see a dot on the “i” of “binds”; E says it’s there. But a curious thing is that
there are ten <hi rend="i">i</hi>’s in this four-line poem and its title, none with visible dots except for
two tiny bits over “binds” and “it”; if Bentley followed his own rules, he would print: “hemself . .
. wenged lefe . . . Leves en eternety’s sun rese.”</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">“Abstinence . . . ” (N 105)</hi> 2 The ruddy limbs &amp; flaming hair (KEC)
/ flourishing hair (B). Note: flaming hair <hi rend="i">mended</hi> over what was probably a bad scribble for
the same two words (EC). Note: “flourishing hair” seems to be written over something else (B978). Our
committee struggled with this, to no avail. Was it first “flowery head” or “flourishing head”? No,
Blake clearly wrote “haid” and changed the “d” to “r,” perhaps then dotting the “i” (for here
is one of the few “i” dots on the page). Was it “flaming” changed to “flourishing” or vice versa?
Or “flowing” to “flaming”?</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">“My Spectre . . . ” (N 13, 12)</hi> And let us go to the highest downs (EKC)
/ . . . high downs . . . (B927—but the “st” is legible, though cramped; a one-syllable word would mar
the rhythm).</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">“A fairy . . . ”</hi> [<hi rend="i">leapt</hi>] skipt (K) / 
[<hi rend="i">leapt</hi>] skipd (EC) / leapt Stept (B1070: “‘Stept’ is written above ‘leapt,’ which has
not been deleted”). Presumably B does not mean the line to be read with both verbs in it but means to urge
that Blake had not decided which to keep. Presumably “skipt” or “skipd” is ruled out because Blake
didn’t dot the “i” (yet he did not cross the “t” either).</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">To Mrs Ann Flaxman 2</hi> Its form was lovely (EKC) / lively (B1331—curious
because there is nothing to be taken for an <hi rend="i">i</hi> dot here; in fact the open <hi rend="i">o</hi>
could be mistaken for <hi rend="i">u</hi>: luvely).</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">The Mental Traveller</hi> (Pickering MS scrutinized in the Morgan Library) There
are a few passages written over fairly complete erasures; B1306 attempts some conjectural restorations, for
lines 85, 86, 91, impossible to confirm.</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">The Grey Monk (N 8[12])</hi> Deletion under line 11: From his dry tongue . . .
(K419/E778/C860) / From his aking tongue (B930)</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">When Klopstock (N 1[5]) 29:</hi> [<hi rend="i">Then after</hi>] &lt;From pity
then&gt; (EC; K: “illegible”) / From [<hi rend="i">anger(?)</hi>] &lt;pity then&gt; (B926, not seeing the
“Then” beneath the “From” and so turning “after” into “anger?” to make sense).</p>
              <p>30 And the spell &lt;removed&gt; unwound (EC) / And the &lt;ninefold?&gt; spell unwound (B) /
K declares 29-32 illegible). As I reexamine my photograph of the page, however, I am happy to report that I
can see the <hi rend="i">f</hi> and <hi rend="i">ld</hi> (with room for the <hi rend="i">o</hi>) of
“ninefold”—a word which not only makes better sense but is written in a position more plausibly intended
to precede than follow “spell”: the 2nd printing of C will have to read: “And the ninefold spell
unwound.”</p>
              <p>31-32 B926 quotes a conjectural reading of mine in <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 1968
which was quite mistaken and, as Bentley says, awkward; his own reading confirms the EC reading.</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">“You dont believe . . . ” (N 21)</hi> 11 When he said [Rich] Only Believe
(KEC) / said [<hi rend="i">Beli</hi>] (a start for “Believe”) (B934—which I now, too late for C, see is
correct).</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">From Cratetos (N 64)</hi> B emends title to <hi rend="i">From Cratelos;</hi> but
both <hi rend="i">t</hi>’s are crossed; “Cratetos” is an understandable Blake error about Greek
inflections, while “Cratelos” makes no sense. (See t note in EC).</p>
              <pb id="p17-10" n="10"/>
              <p><hi rend="b">“And his legs carried it . . . ” (N 22-23)</hi> Line 25 And Cur my Lawyer
&amp; Dady [<hi rend="i">my</hi>] Jack Hemps Parson (EC) / . . . &amp; Dadymus(?) . . . (B936). EC infer
deletion, i.e. that Blake having written (for his persona, Stewhard) “Cur my Lawyer and Dady my Parson,”
then decided to call him Flaxman’s parson: “Jack Hemps Parson.” Until we find an explanation either for
Dady or for Dadymus, the crux is empty of content.</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">“Was I angry . . . ” (N 23)</hi> The line 6 deletion “Mirths” (EC, not
in K) stands obviously for “Mirth is.” “Mirth” (B) makes nonsense and ignores the visible “s”
stroke (between the <hi rend="i">u</hi> and <hi rend="i">s</hi> of the overwritten “Because.”</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">“He has observd . . . ” (N 30)</hi> 2 <hi rend="i">del</hi> ?I ?sport ?with
?Fortune ?merry ?Blithe &amp; gay (E, not in K) / ?Sporting ?with fortune [<hi rend="i">words illeg</hi>] gay
(B) / ?Sporting with ?golden ?Fortune ?Blithe &amp; gay (C)</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">“old acquaintance well renew” (N 24)</hi> i.e. “we’ll.” This half line
is written on top of an erased full line beginning “Look ?what [or ?how]” and continuing “Flaxman &amp;
Stothard do” (EC, not in K; B “can read only ‘Stothard’ with confidence”). C868 suggests that Blake
may have meant to retain the first two words, to make the revised line read “Look how [or what] old
acquaintance we’ll renew.”</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">Mr Cromek to Mr Stothard (N31)</hi> 3 you travel all in vain (all texts) / B942
notes “‘travel’ might equally well be read as ‘travil,’ i.e. ‘travail.’” Perhaps (though no
“i” dot), but the <hi rend="i">Concordance</hi> shows that Blake’s “travel” (he never wrote
“travail”) always, in every form, signifies journey or journeying (sometimes associated with travail, e.g.
“returnd from his immense labours &amp; travels” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 2:201)—with two exceptions: (1)
the female in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> Prel 1 is “faint with travel” and (2) Blake in a letter writes of
“the sore travel which has been given me.” (In the present context, Stothard is advised to “turn back”
from his vain “travel”; so the implication of travail is at most a pun.)</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">Cromek’s Language</hi> (I should add, generally, of Cromek that the lyrics by
his persona often contain the words “paint” and “painting” with the spelling “pant” and
“panting” (more “travel”!). It is obvious that Blake wanted Cromek to pant in these passages; whether
in a given instance “ant” or “aint” is intended is sometimes hard to make out, but C prints the
shorter form more often than E did.</p>
              <p>E497/C506 The couplet beginning “To forgive Enemies H— does pretend” is now seen as the
conclusion of “P— loved me,” and no longer printed as a separate poem.</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">“When you look</hi> . . . ” (N 41) 4 About freedom &amp; Jenny Suck awa (KEC
have a note on “Jenny Suck awa”—K912 being the best: “interpreted by Sampson as a grotesque way of
writing <hi rend="i">Je ne sais quoi.</hi>” B953 only notes that this quatrain “is written in Cromek’s
Yorkshire dialect” without mentioning (or noticing?) the French base. The point may still be missed; hence
the fuller explanation here. (As for dialect, B952 fails to recognize “ham” as “them,” not
“him.”)</p>
              <p>Now that we have learned that “poco pen” was really written “poco piu” (a little bit
more), we have a punning glossary of the slippery language of the “Cunning-sures &amp; the aim-at-yours”
(N 40), i.e. the connoisseurs and amateurs. When they are buying or selling they “keep up a Jaw” (N 43)
about that <hi rend="i">soupçon</hi> or <hi rend="i">poco piu</hi> or <hi rend="i">Je ne sais quoi</hi> the
presence or absence of which makes a work precious or worthless. (Of course many readers have always
understood Blake’s Cromek.)</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">Florentine Ingratitude (N 32)</hi> 21 merry hearted Fashion (EC) / warm hearted
Fashion (K) / warm Hearted Fashion (B). B944 gets the capital H from mistaking a descending “p” from the
line above as part of the letter. The “y” of “merry” is quite visible.</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">A Pretty Epigram</hi> . . . B949 rightly corrects E789 (and <hi rend="i">N</hi>
38); the suggested first and second titles, deleted, are not there. The second, “Major Testament of—” is
(notes B) a misreading of “the Entertainment of” and an overlooking of the caret. C872 now reads: “Title
revised in ms thus: A [<hi rend="i">Pretty Epigram for</hi> &lt;<hi rend="i">the entertainment of</hi>&gt; 
<hi rend="i">those who have Given high Prices for Bad Pictures And ?have</hi>] Pretty Epigram for 
[<hi rend="i">those</hi>] the Entertainment of those Who [<hi rend="i">pay</hi>] &lt;have Paid&gt; Great Sums in
the Venetian &amp; Flemish Ooze.”</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">“On the Great Encouragement . . . ” (N 40)</hi> Dilbury Doodle (KEB) /
Dilberry Doodle (C)</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">To Venetian Artists (N 61)</hi> Poco Pen (KEB) / Poco Piu (C)</p>
              <p><hi rend="b">“Her whole Life is an Epigram . . . ” (N 100)</hi> smack smooth &amp; neatly
pend (KE) / ?smart smooth &amp; ?neatly pend (B) / smack smooth &amp; nobly pend (C) / smack-smooth and nobly
pend (K1982). See textual note (C873) on the exchange in <hi rend="i">TLS</hi>, including the idea this may be
a response to Wordsworth’s “perfect Woman, nobly planned.”</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">The Everlasting Gospel</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>John Grant is responsible for the discovery that these four lines,
<q>
What can be done with such desperate Fools<lb/>
Who follow after the Heathen Schools<lb/>
I was standing by when Jesus died<lb/>
What I calld Humility they calld Pride (N 52),
</q>
do not belong <hi rend="i">in</hi> “The Everlasting Gospel” but constitute a comment <hi rend="i">on</hi>
it, by the man who <hi rend="i">was</hi> standing by when Jesus died, not William Blake but Joseph of
Arimathea. In fact these lines are in the darker ink, with finer pen (this fact got left out of the C textual
note) of the Joseph couplets which have hitherto been treated as a separate poem (“I will tell you what
Joseph of Arimathea / Said to my Fairy”) ending with the couplet that begins “Listen patient &amp; when
Joseph has done,” couplets crowded into
<pb id="p17-11" n="11"/>
the margins to serve, physically and poetically, as William Blake’s announcement that he is about to quote
Joseph. In C, then, we are printing, as Preface to the main poem, first Blake’s three couplets, then
Joseph’s two. The other “Comments on this Poem” (as we call them) are printed at the end of the main
text: “I am sure This Jesus will not do . . . ” and “This was Spoke by My Spectre” (a comment on the
Philosophy section).</p>
          <p>Line 58 (now 54 with the moving of “What can be done . . . ” to the Preface) of this first
section of the poem proper (d in EK, k in BC) is a difficult palimpsest and has had a checkered career among
transcribers:</p>
          <p>the seraph hand (Sampson, noted in K921) / Lord Caiaphas hand (E, 4th prtg) / the Caiaphas (?)
hand (B) / [<hi rend="i">the guilty</hi>] Lord Caiaphas hand (<hi rend="i">N</hi>C).</p>
          <p>Line 31, section e: Wherefore has (KE) / has [t] (BC)</p>
          <p>In d:21 the deleted “End” is clearly (from the context) a start for “Ended”; thus: 
[<hi rend="i">End(ed)</hi>] (E<hi rend="i">N</hi>C) but [<hi rend="i">?End</hi>] (B)</p>
          <p>f:51 forgot your (KEC) / forgot our (B)</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">BLAKE’S EXHIBITION AND CATALOGUE OF 1809</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">A Descriptive Catalogue</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>p. 1 The Spiritual form of Nelson . . . wreathings are infolded] The Spirit of Nelson . . .
folds are entangled <hi rend="i">variant inscription on sketch</hi> (Butlin 650). (This textual note got lost
from C on the way to press. It is cited in B, from catalogue; in Butlin from original.)</p>
              <p>p. 2 ordering the Reaper] commanding the reaper <hi rend="i">variant inscription</hi>, on
back of painting, but not in Blake’s hand (nor spelling: ploughman and plough instead of plowman and plow).
Butlin suggests “Perhaps by Palmer” (Butlin 651). (Accepted in B as Blake’s.)</p>
              <p>p. 27 whose whole delight is the destruction of men (KE) / . . . is in the . . . (BC)</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">DESCRIPTIONS OF THE LAST JUDGMENT</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">A Vision of the Last Judgment (N68-93)</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>p. 81 Brittanica (KE) / Britannica (B) / Brittannia (C: see note).</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">PUBLIC ADDRESS</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>Comparing Bentley’s text and his arrangement of the segments of <hi rend="i">Public
Address</hi> has been helpful, though in both respects C differs somewhat from B.</p>
            <p>p. 51 [<hi rend="i">Engraved by William Blake tho Now Surrounded by Calumny</hi> &amp; 
<hi rend="i">Envy</hi>] pencil inscription, deleted. (EC) / Not mentioned in K; mentioned in B (1031 &amp; 1060)
as “illegible.” Easy to read in the <hi rend="i">N</hi> facsimile, however, and included in the Blake 
<hi rend="i">Concordance.</hi></p>
            <p>p. 11, paragraph beginning “If Men of weak Capacities” is transcribed differently in each
text (K591/E560/B1029-30/C571). B was right to question “an artist who has carried on” (E&amp;<hi
rend="i">N</hi>) and to suggest “an unending.” And E had mistakenly dropped “The Fools hand or the”
(KBC).</p>
            <p>p. 55 how then should (EKC) / . . . shall (B, simple error)</p>
            <p>p. 57, 2nd parag: journeymen whose names (EKC) / journeyman whose name (B, compounded
error).</p>
            <p>p. 58, 1st parag. The “you/dey” mendings of the words of Gravelot, given incompletely in E,
are given fully in KBC. But KB treat the deleted “Aliamet” (E<hi rend="i">N</hi>C) as illegible.</p>
            <p>p. 60 Monopolizing Trader [<hi rend="i">whose whole</hi>] (C) / not previously deciphered,
though B gives “whose.” Further along: “Poco Pend” (EKB) / Poco Piud (C); “Drawn with a firm &lt;and
decided&gt; hand” (KEC) / “Drawn with a firm hand &lt;&amp; decided&gt;” (B, a misconstruction)</p>
            <p>p. 17 Corregio &amp; Titian (KB) / Corregio or Titian (EC): technically, “or” written on
top of “&amp;” (<hi rend="i">N</hi>)</p>
            <p>p. 44 to leave it before he has spoild it (EK) / . . . leave off before . . . (BC)</p>
            <p>p. 18 It is the Fashion] written along the right margin of the page, now broken off—but
visible in the 1953 facsimile. B and C agree on the placement of this clause (after “a dark cavern”): E
lacked it. K misplaced “They Produce System &amp; Monotony.”</p>
            <p>p. 18 The two paragraphs beginning “Mr B repeats” have more fully reported deletions in C
than E (and concur with B). K is somewhat in agreement, but misreads “Production of a Man” as “Product .
. . .”</p>
            <p>p. 20 every Body of Understanding must cry out (E) / . . . [<hi rend="i">will</hi>] must cry
out (K) / . . . [<hi rend="i">can(?)</hi>] [<hi rend="i">will</hi>] must cry out (B) / [&amp; 
<hi rend="i">sen</hi>[se] <hi rend="i">will</hi>] must cry out (C) / / Poco-Pen (K) / Poco Pen (EB) Poco Piu
(C)</p>
            <p>p. 23 [<hi rend="i">That Painted as well as Sculptured Monuments</hi> . . . ] Variants reported
more fully in C. B questions several readings, omits “the Plain unpainted” before “Those Sepulchurs,”
reads “dead Marble” as “dull(?) Marble”; but does also call attention to the misspelling
“Sepulchures” in E.</p>
            <p>p. 25 destructive of the true Artist (KC) / . . . Artists (EB)</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">THE MARGINALIA</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Annotation to Lavater’s</hi>
                  <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Date corrected to 1788; underlining and bracketing revised.</p>
              <p>248 beast &amp; devil (KEC) / beast or devil (B1361) It would have been good to have more
ample quotation of Lavater in C, but R. J. Shroyer’s facsimile edition (1980) fills that need.</p>
              <p>One important correction has been made, in Blake’s note on blank page 225. The deletion
given heretofore as “&amp; they converse with the spirit of God!” is corrected to “&amp; these are
either Good or Evil”—a considerable difference.</p>
              <p>11 false for weak (KE) / [?<hi rend="i">Doubtful</hi>] false for weak (BC)</p>
              <pb id="p17-12" n="12"/>
              <p>612 “six or seven words erased” (EC)—still undeciphered.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Annotations to Swedenborg’s Divine Love and Divine Wisdom</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Flyleaf: Good to others (K) / This Good to others (EB) / Thus Good to others (C)</p>
              <p>11 springs up in your thoughts (KB) / . . . thought (EC)</p>
              <p>49 the words Infinity &amp; Eternal (KE) / . . . Infinite . . . (BC)</p>
              <p>336 (Section omitted in KB from failure to note Blake’s marking with large cross in right
margin; given in EC.)</p>
              <p>414 Is it not false then . . . / B399 supplies the wrong context.</p>
              <p>(We have checked every variant in B, including capitalization and punctuation and find B
quite frequently inaccurate.)</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Annotation to Swedenborg’s Divine Providence</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>277.2 The comment “Cursed Folly!” is placed <hi rend="i">after</hi> the paragraph
beginning “Predestination” in K, before it in E, but now (in C, following B) after the phrase “cannot be
removed afterwards.” B also supplies correction, at the end of the “Predestinarian” paragraph, from
“In 69 . . . ” (KE) to “See 29 . . . ” (BC).</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Annotations to Watson’s An Apology for the Bible</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Blake’s second line, “The Beast &amp; the Whore . . . controls” (C) / “control”
(KEB), is canceled by a ruled double line, in pencil, something quite uncharacteristic of Blake. I take it to
have been added by Samuel Palmer, whose signature is on the title page. B gives the line as del.</p>
              <p>B ignores Blake’s guide-lines and daggers in the text and comments of p. 2 (though the
dagger on “Always”—printed as an asterisk—is given, but not the matching dagger in Watson). On p. 4
B’s questioning of the E readings led to further scrutiny of the ms, confirming them.</p>
              <p>p. 5 The reading is “murdered” not “marterd” (B).</p>
              <p>p. 9 A deletion not noted in K, noted but not deciphered in E, is somewhat tentatively
restored in B and C:</p>
              <p>. . . the plan of Providence was . . . not restored til [<hi rend="i">we in</hi>] Christ 
[<hi rend="i">were(?) restord(?)</hi>] (B1414) / . . . [<hi rend="i">?made ?restoration</hi>] (C) I take it that
Blake began to write “we in Christ” and then canceled “we in” before completing the sentence, to read
“restored till Christ made restoration” or possibly “gave restoration”?</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Annotations to Boyd’s Historical Notes on Dante</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>C now includes (from K1976) the new comment on p. 75, “Every Sentiment . . . Opinions &amp;
Principles” (B1448, C634)</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Bacon’s Essays</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>p. 62 Virtuous I supposed to be Innocents (KEC) / . . . Innocent (B)</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Malone’s Reynolds</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Notes in B question several E readings; all have been confirmed, with the exceptions given
below.</p>
              <p>Angle brackets &lt; &gt; to indicate Blake’s inked additions were only incompletely
supplied in printings of E; they are all in place in C.</p>
              <p>C (639) includes a new, partially recovered, Blake annotation—on Malone’s p. xxxviii,
fns. 24 and 25.</p>
              <p>p. 3 Ought not the Employers of Fools (K) / Ought not the &lt;Artists &amp;&gt; Employers
[<hi rend="i">Imbecillity</hi>] of Fools (E) / Ought not the &lt;Patrons(?) &amp;&gt; [<hi rend="i">word
del</hi>] Employers [<hi rend="i">Imbecility</hi>] of [<hi rend="i">Folly</hi>] Fools (B) / Ought not the
&lt;?Patrons &amp;&gt; Employers [<hi rend="i">Imbecility</hi>] of Fools (C)</p>
              <p>p. 4, misnumbered “[iv]” [<hi rend="i">Are there Artists . . . Other Men</hi>] (EC,
questioned in B1461)</p>
              <p>p. 7 There are, at this time, a greater number of excellent artists than were ever known
before at one period in this nation. (Blake’s comment:) [<hi rend="i">Artists . . . ?Heavens ?Fool the hxxx
Pxxxx as xxxxm</hi>] (new in C643)</p>
              <p>p. 30 [<hi rend="i">those who are born for it</hi>] (EC) (not in K) / 
[<hi rend="i">wretches(?) Who are born for it</hi>] (B, plausible, but scrutiny does not confirm.)</p>
              <p>p. 48 without Con or Innate Science (EKC) / with Con . . . (B, clearly a mistake)</p>
              <p>p. 50 following [<hi rend="i">Letter</hi>] &lt;Discourse&gt; (E) / . . . 
[<hi rend="i">Lecture</hi>] . . . (KBC)</p>
              <p>p. 101 B1479 underlines “not Elegance,” misinterpreting Blake’s guide-line.</p>
              <p>p. 126 C654 supplies a context indicating that the “Damnd Fool” is Vasari.</p>
              <p>p. 179 Jan Steen (KE) / Jan Stein (BC)</p>
              <p>p. 201 Knowledge[<hi rend="i">s</hi>] (EC) / Knowledge (KB)</p>
              <p>p. 202 Reason or A Ratio (KEB) / Ratio <hi rend="i">mended from</hi> Ration (C textual
note)</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Berkeley’s Siris</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>p. 212 I will not leave you Orphans (KB) / Orphanned (EC)</p>
              <p>p. 215 Imagination &amp; Visions (KEB) / Imaginations &amp; Visions (C) // the business of
Plato &amp; the Greeks . . . Wars &amp; Dominency over others (KE) / baseness . . . Dominency . . . (B) /
baseness . . . Domineering . . . (C) (The “ee” of “Domineering” is quite clear, the conclusion of the
word less so.)</p>
              <p>p. 219 A new paragraph begins with “Man is All Imagination” (BC)</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Thornton’s The Lord’s Prayer</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Photostats that Keynes and I had used for this text had been made with the loose, unnumbered
leaves of the pamphlet out of order; I had not noticed this even while checking the original. But Robert
Essick has now straightened out the sequences.</p>
              <p>KE p. iii should be [ii]; “The Beauty of the Bible . . . how was it” should be the 2nd
paragraph of Dr. Johnson’s remark. Our p. 1 should be p. 9 and should be moved to follow p. 6 and precede
the fly-leaf, p. 10. (B has p. 9 in the right place but has not shifted the Bible remark from Byron to
Johnson.)</p>
              <p>Changes in the p. 3 transcript, from E to C, are perhaps
<pb id="p17-13" n="13"/>
worth noting (B has a garbled transcript and his notes question several E readings, all now rechecked).
“Heaven &lt; s &gt;” (C) corrects “Heavns” (EB) and “heaven” (K). A somewhat revised sequence is
“([<hi rend="i">His Judgment</hi>] &lt; His Accusation &gt; shall be Forgiveness [<hi rend="i">and he
shall</hi>] &lt; that he may &gt; be consumd in his own Shame &gt; / Give [<hi rend="i">me</hi>] &lt; us &gt;
This Eternal Day [<hi rend="i">my</hi>] &lt; our &gt; [<hi rend="i">Ghostly</hi>].</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Annotation to Cellini(?)</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Our source for the annotation (one sentence, on the Pope’s confusion of Nature and the
Virgin Mary) is the slipshod E. J. Ellis, who says it was “In the margin of a copy of Cennini’s book on
fresco painting.” B documents this with evidence that Linnell gave Blake a copy of Cennini’s book and in
it Blake found support for his use of carpenter’s glue. Very well, but nothing in Cennini could have
inspired the remark about a Pope and the Virgin; whereas Cellini’s work (Ellis just confused the names)
offers direct inspiration. (Each work was called “Trattato.”)</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">Annotation to Young’s Night Thoughts</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>Blake’s identification of the five books of pompous Ignorance in <hi rend="i">NT</hi>199
constitutes a new entry (Plato, Cicero, Plutarch, Locke). (C670).</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">INSCRIPTIONS AND NOTES ON OR FOR PICTURES</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>There are several changes and additions here and, most important, cancellations.</p>
            <p>The N 116 Exodus list is now deciphered as “Exodus [from] Egypt”; item 3 reads “River
turnd to blood”; item 12 “First born Smitten.”</p>
            <p>The inscriptions “Teach these Souls to Fly” and “I labour upwards . . .” and the long
note on the back of <hi rend="i">The Fall of Man</hi> (“The Father indignant . . . the Lamb”) (E662) are
dropped from C because not in Blake’s hand. (B1332 confuses matters by silently revising the spelling of
“Tiger” to “Tyger” in the latter.)</p>
            <p>The note on a pencil drawing of Nine Grotesque Heads (E667/C686) has been freed of the
editorialy inserted period after “varies”. (It would probably work better after “Thus”, but the sense
is the same either way: the grotesque heads vary; all genius varies; Devils vary—i.e. “All Genius varies
Thus”—or “Thus Devils are various”.)</p>
            <p>New in C are some notes in John Varley’s hand but copied at Blake’s dictation—having
similar authority to Blake’s memorandum on John Scolfield, a dictated document customarily included in
Blake’s writings. The caption on the fourth state of Blake’s Chaucer engraving (C mistakenly says
“third”) reads:
<table rows="1" cols="2"><row>
	<cell>The Use of Money &amp; its Wars [title inscription]</cell>
	<cell>An Allegory of Idolatry or Politics</cell>
</row></table>
It seems to get lost easily. Not in K, it was put into a Supplement entry for the 
<hi rend="i">Concordance</hi> but did not get into E or B. It is now in C687—but failed to get into the Index
under “Use”!</p>
            <p>For Blake’s inscriptions on his <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>, we give a
list of the verbal variants from his source, the King James Bible.</p>
            <p>On C688 is a tracing of Blake’s hieroglyphic signature on the drawing for Job design XIV; the
explanation (C891) with aid from John Beer makes out that the hand and thumb are respectively “W” and
“B,” followed by an eye, the “I” of Imagination; the first and last symbols being a line and a sun,
text and illumination.</p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="b">[On Blake’s Illustrations to Dante]</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>No. 3 &amp; his ?Porch in Purgatory (EC) / and his throne(?) . . . (B) / (not in K). (Butlin,
<hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings</hi>, 812:3, makes some bad guesses at words in this design, getting
the sequence scrambled. Where we read “Porch” or “throne” he tries “Paradise”; he divides “The
Thunder of Egypt” (EBC) into “The Turks God of Egypt”. These guesses don’t check out.</p>
              <p>No. 7 &amp; the Goddess Nature Memory [<hi rend="i">Nature</hi>] is his Inspirer (K) / &amp;
the Goddess Nature &lt; Memory &gt; &lt; is his Inspirer &gt; (EC) / the Goddess Nature Mystery is his
Inspirer (B, surely wrong) / ?Memory (Butlin)</p>
              <p>No. 38 (new entry in C689 but printed out of order) Virgin Casella Dante Venus (not in EKB)
(Butlin notes only “Venus?”)</p>
              <p>No. 68 (not in KEBC) Butlin notes “M . . . y” and conjectures “Mercury” or
“Memory” (The letters are spaced about that far apart, with all between erased.)</p>
              <p>No. 86 (B prints “and” for “&amp;”)</p>
              <p>No. 99 Butlin reads “Laws Dominion” where I see “Thrones Dominion[s]”; B spells
“Scepter” Sceptre.</p>
              <p>No. 101 B gives “Gulphs” as “Gulfs”.</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Miscellaneous Prose</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Blake’s paragraph in Benjamin Heath Malkin’s book (E671/C693) is at last properly described
as “On the drawings of Thomas Williams Malkin” not “Thomas Heath Malkin.” Also in this section now are
the inscriptions in the ms of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, on pp. 56, 88, and 93; also the fragment of
riddle answers in Blake’s hand (though not invented by him).</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">The Letters</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>A large addition to C consists of all the letters not selected for E. (Here “K” stands for
Keynes’ 1980 edition of the <hi rend="i">Letters.</hi>)</p>
          <p><hi rend="b">To Dr Trusler</hi>, August 23, 1799: 6th line: regret (E) / reject (BKC); 2nd
paragraph: Thievery (EC) / Thieving (KB)</p>
          <p><hi rend="b">To Flaxman</hi>, Sept. 12, 1800, with poem. Collated afresh: the time is arriv’d
(EB)/ the time is now arrivd (KC)</p>
          <p><hi rend="b">To Hayley</hi>, March 21, 1804; 2nd parag. I have been to look (KC) / I have been
able to look (B)</p>
          <p><hi rend="b">To Hayley</hi>, March 31, 1804: If . . . before I deliver then pray (KC) / deliver
them (B) (K inserts comma after “deliver” to fit the sense).</p>
          <pb id="p17-14" n="14"/>
          <p><hi rend="b">To Hayley</hi>, May 4, 1804 (source Gilchrist <hi rend="i">Life</hi>) younger than I
have known him (BC) / younger than I knew him (K, silently revising)</p>
          <p><hi rend="b">Letter 20</hi>, previously thought to be ca. 1800 to Hayley, is now dated Sept.-Oct.
1801, To Thomas Butts? (noted by Mary Lynn Johnson). E. B. Murray has corrected the date of letter 24 to Butts
from “Jany 10, 1802” to 1803 (a slip of Blake’s thought).</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Recent Conjectural Attributions</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>C785: tucked in at the last minute is a note telling of Sir Geoffrey’s conjectural but
confident attribution to Blake of a 24-line poem “To the Nightingale” (about which the note reflects the
skepticism of the proofreading team) and another unknown poem reported by Keynes as “a remarkable piece of
Blakean doggerel written in pale blue watercolour with a brush” and “addressed to Mrs Butts.” C does not
give the texts of these poems; the latter has not been seen by any of us.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Errata emendata</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Misprints (and omissions) already noted in the first printing of <hi rend="i">The Complete
Poetry</hi> &amp; <hi rend="i">Prose of William Blake</hi> 1982 (C).</p>
          <p>p. 3 NNR [b] The spacing of the “Therefore” sec tion should almost exactly follow Blake thus:
<q>
Therefore<lb/>
God becomes as we are,<lb/>
that we may be as he<lb/>
is
</q>
(I.e., to isolate “Therefore” and “is” as one-liners. Alternative, to follow exactly:
<q>
Therefore<lb/>
<lb/>
God becomes as<lb/>
we are, that we<lb/>
may be as he<lb/>
is<lb/>
p. 121 <hi rend="i">M</hi> 24[26]: 63 flutes <hi rend="i">shd read</hi> flutes [’].<lb/>
pl. 2, facing p. 273 is printed inside out in the paperback volume but correctly in the hardbound.<lb/>
p. 148 <hi rend="i">J</hi> 5:60 A misspelling: “Jersualem.”<lb/>
p. 167 <hi rend="i">J</hi> 22; 25 This time “Jersualsm.”<lb/>
p. 271 Running head “THE GHOST OF ADEL”!<lb/>
p. 273 The first Hebrew letter in the transcript should be heh, not thay; Blake engraved it correctly.
(Pointed out by Stephen Mitchell.)<lb/>
p. 501 “Klopstock” 30: Spell removed <hi rend="i">shd read</hi> ninefold spell . . . .<lb/>
p. 687 Incriptions <hi rend="i">shd read</hi> Inscriptions.<lb/>
p. 689 On design No 38 <hi rend="i">should follow</hi> On verso of No 36 . . . .<lb/>
p. 727 the word “Hebrew” should not be followed by a colon.<lb/>
p. 729 Letter 27 After the 11th line this line was omitted: “Maries at the Sepulcher. 4 The Death of the
Virgin”<lb/>
p. 789 Add to note the statement: John Grant has pointed out that the “Conclusion” should precede the
“Application” (one cannot apply a conclusion until it has been reached).<lb/>
p. 808 <hi rend="i">M</hi> 32:15 In “Kerabim” Blake wrote Kaph for the first Hebrew letter instead of
Khaph; our printer tried several times but missed.<lb/>
p. 814 <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> 1: 28 serpents] serpents [?all] <hi rend="i">1st rdg</hi><lb/>
p. 863 “You dont believe . . . ” 11: <hi rend="i">note shd read</hi>: After “said” Blake first wrote
“Beli,” a start for “Believe”; my previous rdg (“Rich”) has been corrected by G. E. Bentley,
Jr.<lb/>
p. 881 [The Catalogue] Insert new note:<lb/>
p. 1 The Spiritual form of Nelson . . . ] The Spirit of Nelson . . . folds are entangled . . . 
<hi rend="i">variant inscription on sketch</hi> (Butlin 650)<lb/>
p. 895 Seventh line from bottom “nothern” <hi rend="i">shd be</hi> “northern.”
</q>
Index corrections:
<q>
p. 978 Index entry “Her whole Life . . . ” <hi rend="i">shd read</hi> “nobly pend.”<lb/>
p. 980 Joseph of Arimathea, incriptions <hi rend="i">shd read</hi> inscriptions<lb/>
p. 981 “Leave O leave . . . 6850 <hi rend="i">shd read</hi> t850<lb/>
p. 982 Insert: Nightingale, To the 785<lb/>
p. 983 Poetical Sketches . . . t864 <hi rend="i">shd read</hi> t846<lb/>
p. 985 “The Angel . . . borth” <hi rend="i">shd read</hi> “ . . . birth”<lb/>
p. 986 “The grand style of Cert . . . ” <hi rend="i">shd read</hi> “ . . . of Art . . . ”<lb/>
p. 986 insert: “The Use of Money &amp; its Wars” 687<lb/>
p. 988 insert: To the Nightingale 785
</q></p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Postscript on Blake’s Hebrew lettering:</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Stephen Mitchell points out that in Blake’s 2d Job design he misspells the Hebrew word for
“angel” in “Angel of the Divine Presence” (though he has it right in the Laocoön plate) and leaves
out an aleph; so the word appears to melekh (king) instead of mal’akh (angel), leading Foster Damon to the
mistaken conclusion that “The Hebrew letters beneath his name . . . identify [Satan] as ‘King Jehovah,’
Job’s false God.”</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p17-15" n="15" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
