<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>17.1.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Charles Parr Burney as a Blake Collector</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1983</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">17.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Barbara Guth</name>
              <name>Letty Rutledge</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert Alter</name>
              <name>Shelley M. Bennett</name>
              <name>Elizabeth B. Bentley</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>David Erdman</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Theresa M. Kelley</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_17">
    <body>
      <pb id="p17-16" n="16"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-17-1-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Charles Parr Burney as a Blake Collector</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Charles Parr Burney (1785-1864), the grandson of Charles Burney (1726-1814) the musicologist and
nephew of Fanny Burney (1752-1840) the novelist, was a wealthy schoolmaster and Archdeacon successively of St.
Albans and of Colchester. He is not known to have had any connection with William Blake, except for a letter
which he wrote on 29 September 1862 to D. P. Colnaghi the print dealer asking about
<q>
a Volume of ‘Blake’s’ eccentric, but very interesting Drawings, accompanied by Verses, written with
great care and in very minute characters,—which is now in my possession,—was purchased from you . . .
.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Quoted from the manuscript in Beinecke Library, Yale University.
Colnaghi’s does not have records which extend back to this period. The firm sold <hi rend="i">For Children:
The Gates of Paradise</hi> (B) to the British Museum on 12 January 1862.</note></q>
This “Blake” can only be the artist-poet (despite the quotation marks round his name), but no such
“Volume” of “Drawings, accompanied by Verses, written . . . in very minute characters” by Blake is
known to survive.</p>
          <p>On the other hand, the work may not be a manuscript at all. In the nineteenth century Blake’s
etched works in illuminated printing were sometimes referred to as drawings. For instance, in 1818 Coleridge
wrote of “the Drawings” of that “strange publication” <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">2</ref> If Charles Parr
Burney was similarly casual in confusing drawings and engravings, the volume he owned might be one of
Blake’s works in illuminated printing. Few of these have “Verses, written with great care and in very
minute characters,” but <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> seems to fit the description
fairly well. Perhaps Burney owned a copy of the printed <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi> Or he could have had a copy
of <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi> (?1818) which has eighteen printed designs and some
verses in a small hand. But no copy of either work can be traced to Burney. 
<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi> (1969), pp. 252, 251.</note></p>
          <p>It was also common to consider Blake’s works in illuminated printing primarily as books of
designs. Allan Cunningham speaks of the “wild verses, which are scattered here and there” among the
powerful designs of <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>, and he refers to <hi rend="i">America</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> as being “plentifully seasoned with verse” (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, pp. 487,
500).</p>
          <p>But the most likely candidate seems to be a “Volume” of “Drawings, accompanied by 
[<hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi>] Verses, written . . . in very minute characters” which is neither a printed work
nor a manuscript by Blake. It may be a facsimile of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> made by a contemporary
of the poet. There are two such manuscript copies, the first (Alpha) apparently copied from 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (P) and the second (Beta) copied from Alpha by 1825.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">3</ref> Alpha is known to have stayed in the same family throughout
the nineteenth century, but the history of Beta is known only from recent times. It may have been Beta (or
another, as yet untraced, contemporary facsimile) which C. P. Burney owned. Beta is colored with considerable
imagination and skill, but the text was somewhat carelessly transcribed and was extensively covered by the
coloring. These facts may explain why Burney describes it as primarily “a Volume of . . . Drawings” and
why he puts “Blake’s” name in quotation marks; the designs and words are Blake’s but the hand that
held brush and pen was not his. <note id="n5"><hi rend="s">3</hi> See “Two Contemporary Facsimiles of 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Publications of the Bibliographical
Society of America</hi>, 64 (1970), 450-63. In 1982, copy Alpha belongs to Mr. Paul Mellon and Copy Beta to
Mr. Justin Schiller.</note></p>
          <p>It would be plesant to think that such a Blake volume as Charles Parr Burney acquired from
Colnaghi about 1862 had remained in the family, but C. P. Burney’s direct descendant Mr. John R. G. Comyn,
who has a number of Burney treasures including C. P. Burney sketchbooks, tells me that he has nothing of the
kind, and Professor Joyce Hemlow of McGill University, the editor of Fanny Burney’s letters and journals,
who has given me generous advice, can throw no more light on the subject. Of all the possibilities among
surviving “Blake” works, the contemporary manuscript facsimile of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (Beta) seems
to me most plausible.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
