<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>17.1.tolley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Grant Hehir, Blake, a play</title>
        <author n="Tolley">Michael J. Tolley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1983</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">17.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Barbara Guth</name>
              <name>Letty Rutledge</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert Alter</name>
              <name>Shelley M. Bennett</name>
              <name>Elizabeth B. Bentley</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>David Erdman</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Theresa M. Kelley</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_17">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-17-1-0007">
		<pb id="p17-25" n="25"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Additions to the Blake Apocrypha</title>
            <title type="main">Blake, a play written and directed by Grant Hehir. Music by Bruce Stewart.
Performed at the Sheridan Theatre, Adelaide, Australia, 4-20 March 1982.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Michael J.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Tolley</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Adelaide, Australia, has a biennial Arts Festival in March and this Festival has developed a
Fringe and among the Fringe activities in March 1982 was a play called <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, written and
directed by Grant Hehir, with music by Bruce Stewart. This play was performed at the Sheridan Theatre on
eleven occasions from 4-20 March; I attended the final performance.</p>
          <p>The play began promisingly enough with a harangue from a Russian, then one from an Anglican
clergyman, who were both led, in celebrating Blake’s 1957 bicentenary, to make the claim that he was the
greatest genius who ever lived; they were then mocked by a sly bearded rogue calling himself John Joseph
Hidson (the star of the show), who claimed to be the cynical alter ego Blake alone could see in his life, a
life Hidson bedeviled. Thus we were prepared for amusing situation comedy of the type in which Blake, courting
Polly or being patronized by Sir Joshua Reynolds, was goaded into shouting rudely at an invisible
interlocutor. In his own person, Blake appeared as a morose, doubting coward, unluckily bearing a bald patch
from his tender years and not even allowed a red flourishing wig.</p>
          <p>This was a production that breathed the spirit of amateurism, which a full house enjoyed at $4.50
a head. Eight performers handled all the characters deemed necessary in a rough representation of Blake’s
life, two of them playing ten parts each, with the actresses all compelled to play male parts, one pleasant
effect of which was, apparently, the adaptation of the character of Tom Paine to a womanish figure. To
compensate, Mary Wollstonecraft appeared as a very mannish feminist who made a determined assault on Blake’s
virtue, Fuseli being inexplicably absent from Johnson’s radical circle. The entertainment consisted
essentially of a number of Blake’s songs, set charmingly to music and, alas, all scrannelly sung,
interspersed with travestied episodes from Blake’s life and illuminated by a double-screen slide projection,
some of the slides being rare and excellent, some well-known ones appearing reversed, including the 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> frontispiece.</p>
          <p>All of those Blakean purists who could not bear the heresies of Adrian Mitchell’s 
<hi rend="i">Tyger</hi> would have stormed from the small Sheridan Theatre breathing threats of libel, but we are
all so civilized in Adelaide (that is to say, we do not take art seriously here), and it was such a pleasant
warm night, and the whole enterprise was so patently harmless in such of its intentions as could be inferred,
that even I sat back and chuckled at each fresh absurdity and clapped with the others at the end of each act
(there was an interval of fifteen minutes for refreshments: superb orange juice for 40 cents or, in this
renowned wine state, plonk for 50).</p>
          <p>The unsuspecting credulous members of the audience would have left believing some curious
apocryphal facts. Among these are the idea that Blake was, indeed, mad, though this was partly the fault of
Hidson who, however, provided Blake with the experience which led to the doctrine of contraries; that the girl
he first courted was a tartish model called Polly from the life class at the Royal Academy where he studied
with Rowlandson and argued with Reynolds about painting from imagination; that he went to Felpham as an
expedient to avoid accepting the position of Royal Engraver (selected by the mad George III on the
blind-dab-at-a-moving-list principle), where Mr. and Mrs. Hayley first introduced themselves to him and
Catherine (Mrs. Hayley remaining visibly alive and well through the whole trial for sedition); that it was to
rescue Catherine from a sexual assault of the drunken Schofield that Blake grappled with the trooper and
ejected him from his garden; that Blake was saved from hanging or worse (transportation to Australia) from a
hostile judge largely by the Royal-Engraver-selection story; that thereafter Coleridge befriended him, meeting
him at the womanish Charles Lamb’s house, in the intervals of insulting Wordsworth (Coleridge misremembered
Blake’s poetry but Blake capped him with a word-perfect recollection of “Kubla Khan”); that Blake died
alone, chanting (partly under Parry’s inspiration) the famous lyric “And did those feet,” which he wrote
on his deathbed.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
