<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>17.1.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1983</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">17.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Barbara Guth</name>
              <name>Letty Rutledge</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert Alter</name>
              <name>Shelley M. Bennett</name>
              <name>Elizabeth B. Bentley</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>David Erdman</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Theresa M. Kelley</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_17">
    <front>
      <pb id="p17-1-2" n="1-2"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.017.01.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="336">
          <figTranscr>BLAKE<lb/>
            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
            65<lb/>
            VOLUME 17<lb/>
            NUMBER 1<lb/>
            SUMMER 1983</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-17-1-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="18" cols="2">
          <row>
            <cell>
        	  <head>
          		<title>
            	  <hi rend="b">
              		<hi rend="i">CONTENTS</hi>
            	  </hi>
          		</title>
        	  </head>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="17.1.erdman">Redefining the Texts of Blake (another temporary
report)</ref><lb/>
by David V. Erdman</cell>
            <cell>4</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">
                <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
              </hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="17.1.bentley">Charles Parr Burney as a Blake Collector</ref> by
G. E. Bentley, Jr.</cell>
            <cell>16</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="17.1.gourlay">An Emendation in “The Chimney Sweeper” of 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi></ref><lb/>
by Alexander S. Gourlay</cell>
            <cell>16</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="17.1.kelley">A Minute Particular in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs
of Innocence</hi>, Copy O</ref> by Theresa M. Kelley</cell>
            <cell>18</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">
                <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
              </hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="17.1.alter">Northrop Frye, <hi rend="i">The Great Code: The Bible
and Literature</hi></ref>, reviewed by Robert Alter</cell>
            <cell>20</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><corr type="emend"><ref type="article" issue="17.1.bennett">Raymond Lister, George Richmond: A Critical Biography;<lb/>
            William L. Pressly, <hi rend="i">The Life and Art of James Barry</hi></ref>,</corr> reviewed by Shelley M. Bennett</cell>
            <cell>22</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><corr type="emend"><ref type="article" issue="17.1.warner">Essick and 
<corr type="emend" rend="plain">La Belle,</corr> eds., <hi rend="i">Flaxman’s Illustrations to Homer</hi></ref>,</corr>
reviewed by Janet Warner</cell>
            <cell>24</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="17.1.tolley">Blake, a play written and directed by Grant
Hehir</ref>, reviewed by Michael J. Tolley</cell>
            <cell>25</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><corr type="emend"><ref type="article" issue="17.1.reiman">James King and Charles Ryskamp, eds., 
<hi rend="i">The Letters and Prose Writings of William Cowper Vol. II: Letters 1782-1786</hi></ref>,</corr> reviewed by
Donald H. Reiman</cell>
            <cell>26</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="17.1.hilton">Davis Grubb, <hi rend="i">Ancient Lights</hi></ref>,
reviewed by Nelson Hilton</cell>
            <cell>30</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="17.1.deluca">Warren Stevenson, <hi rend="i">The Myth of the Golden
Age in English Romantic Poetry</hi></ref>, reviewed by V. A. De Luca</cell>
            <cell>32</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="17.1.keynes">Geoffrey Keynes, Kt., and Peter Davidson, eds., 
<hi rend="i">A Watch of Nightingales</hi></ref>, reviewed by G. E. Bentley, Jr.</cell>
            <cell>32</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="17.1.willard">Nancy Willard, <hi rend="i">A Visit to William
Blake’s Inn, Poems for Innocent and Experienced Travelers</hi></ref>, reviewed by Elizabeth B.
Bentley</cell>
            <cell>35</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
          	<cell><supplied type="emend"><hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">NEWSLETTER</hi></hi></supplied></cell>
          </row>
          <row>
          	<cell>
			  <supplied type="emend" rend="plain">
          	  <ref type="article" issue="17.1.symposium">Blake Symposium</ref>, 
 			  <ref type="article" issue="17.1.morgan">Morgan Library Exhibition</ref>, 
 			  <ref type="article" issue="17.1.docudrama">Blake Docudrama</ref>, 
 			  <ref type="article" issue="17.1.sambos">Draw the Line at Sambo’s!</ref>, 
 			  <ref type="article" issue="17.1.paley">Paley’s Autumn Address</ref>, 
 			  <ref type="article" issue="17.1.stratford">Blake: Stratford Festival</ref>, 
 			  <ref type="article" issue="17.1.papers">Call for Papers</ref>
			  </supplied>
          	</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-17-1-0002">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">CONTRIBUTORS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="b">ROBERT ALTER</hi> is Professor of Hebrew and Comparative Literature at the University
of California at Berkeley. His two most recent books are <hi rend="i">The Art of Biblical Narrative</hi>
(Basic Books, 1981) and <hi rend="i">Motives for Fiction</hi>, which will be published in 1984 by Harvard
University Press.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">SHELLEY M. BENNETT</hi>, Ph.D. in Art History from UCLA (1977), has published on
aspects of English art, in particular eighteenth-century book illustration. She is currently Assistant Curator
of the Henry E. Huntington Art Gallery.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">ELIZABETH B. BENTLEY</hi> wrote her review at the Bodleian Library. The proofreading
was done in Shanghai, where she is teaching at Fudan and Tongji Universities. Normally, she teaches and
resides in Toronto.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">G. E. BENTLEY, JR.</hi>, sometime of the universities of Chicago, Toronto, Algiers and
Poona, is currently Fulbright Professor at the Department of Foreign Languages and Literature of Fudan
University, Shanghai, Peoples Republic of China, where he lives in luxury (maid-service, personal interpreter,
transportation) and teaches Blake.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">V. A. DE LUCA</hi> is Professor of English at the University of Toronto. His article,
“The Changing Order of Plates in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Chapter II,” appeared in the Spring 1983
issue of <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi></p>
        <p><hi rend="b">DAVID ERDMAN</hi> is very hopeful he’s found a publisher for the <hi rend="i">Four
Zoas</hi> facsimile with commentary on the designs, by Professor Magno and himself.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">ALEXANDER S. GOURLAY</hi> is an instructor at the College of Wooster (Ohio). He is
writing a dissertation on <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> and <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
Albion</hi> and is co-author (with John E. Grant) of an essay on Blake and Reynolds forthcoming in the
Bulletin of Research in the Humanities.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">NELSON HILTON’S</hi><hi rend="i">Literal Imagination: Blake’s Vision of Words</hi>
has just been published by the University of California Press.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">THERESA M. KELLEY</hi>, Associate Professor of English at the University of Texas at
San Antonio, is the author of articles on Wordsworth, romantic figuration, eighteenth-century iconography and
the sister arts. She is completing a book on Wordsworth’s aesthetics as an archeology of the mind.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">DONALD H. REIMAN’S</hi> volumes VII and VIII of <hi rend="i">Shelley and His
Circle</hi> wend their way through several stages of proof toward publication in 1984, while he also shepherds
to press the first dozen volumes of <hi rend="i">Manuscripts of the Younger Romantics</hi>, of which he is
General Editor. In this series Garland Publishing
<pb id="p17-3" n="3"/>
will issue in facsimile, with full scholarly apparatus, important literary manuscripts of Byron, Shelley,
Keats, and their circles. 
                </p>
        <p><hi rend="b">MICHAEL J. TOLLEY</hi> is currently Chairman of the Department of English at the
University of Adelaide, thus adding further delays to his continuing work on <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Designs to Edward Young’s Night Thoughts</hi> and Blake’s use of the Bible: an annotated checklist. He is,
however, reviewing Tannenbaum for <hi rend="i">SiR</hi> and preparing an article on Blake’s (as he
maintains) “To the Nightingale.”</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">JANET WARNER</hi> is Associate Professor of English at Glendon College, York
University, Toronto.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-17-1-0003">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">EDITORS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="b">Editors:</hi> Morris Eaves, Univ. of New Mexico, and Morton D. Paley, Univ. of Calif,
Berkeley.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Bibliographer:</hi> Thomas L. Minnick, Ohio State Univ.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Review Editor:</hi> Nelson Hilton, Univ. of Georgia, Athens.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Associate Editor for Great Britain:</hi> Frances A. Carey, Assistant Curator,
Department of Prints and Drawings, British Museum.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Production Office:</hi> Morris Eaves, Department of English, University of New Mexico,
Albuquerque NM 87131, <hi rend="b">Telephone</hi> 505 / 277-3103.<lb/>
Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley, CA 94720.<lb/>
Thomas L. Minnick, University College, Ohio State University, 1050 Carmack Road, Columbus, OH 43210.<lb/>
Nelson Hilton, Department of English, University of Georgia, Athens, GA 30602.<lb/>
Frances A. Carey, Department of Prints and Drawings British Museum, Great Russell Street, London WC1B 3DG,
England.</p>
        <figure n="CatKing.17.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="127"></figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-17-1-0004">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">INFORMATION</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="b">Editorial Assistants in charge:</hi> Marcy Erickson, Susan Corban, Univ. of New
Mexico. Editorial Assistants: Peter Chase, Leslie Donovan, Barbara Guth, Letty Rutledge Univ. of New
Mexico.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is published under the sponsorship of the
Department of English, University of New Mexico.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Subscriptions</hi> are $15.00 for 1 year, 1 volume (4 issues). Special rates for
individuals, $12.00 for 1 year surface mail subscriptions. Air mail subscriptions are $10.00 more than surface
mail subscriptions. U.S. currency or international money order if possible. Make checks payable to 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly.</hi> Address all subscription orders and related communications to
Marcy Erickson, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Dept. of English, Univ. of New Mexico, Albuquerque, NM 87131,
USA.</p>
        <p>Some <hi rend="b">back issues</hi> are available. Address Marcy Erickson for a list of issues and
prices.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Manuscripts</hi> are welcome. Send two copies, typed and documented according to the
forms suggested in the MLA Style Sheet, 2nd. ed., to either of the editors: Morris Eaves, Dept. of English,
Univ. of New Mexico, Albuquerque, NM 87131; Morton D. Paley, Dept. of English, Univ. of California, Berkeley,
CA 94720.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">International Serial Number</hi> is 0006-453x. <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> is <hi rend="b">indexed</hi> in the Modern Language Association’s International Bibliography,
the Modern Humanities Research Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature, 
<hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi>’ annual Romantic Bibliography, <hi rend="b">ART</hi>bibliographies 
<hi rend="b">MODERN</hi>, American Humanities Index, and the Arts and Humanities Citation Index.</p>
        <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 1983 by Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</note>
        <figure n="PoemsForTravelers.17.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="126"></figure>
      </div1>
    </front>
    <body>
    	<pb id="p17-40" n="40"/>
    	<div1>
    		<div2>
    			<div3 type="in-memoriam">Karl Kiralis<lb/>
    			1923–1982</div3>
    		</div2>
    	</div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
