<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>17.1.kelley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">A Minute Particular in Blake’s Songs of Innocence, Copy O</title>
        <author n="Kelley">Theresa M. Kelley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1983</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">17.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Peter Chase</name>
              <name>Barbara Guth</name>
              <name>Letty Rutledge</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert Alter</name>
              <name>Shelley M. Bennett</name>
              <name>Elizabeth B. Bentley</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>David Erdman</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Theresa M. Kelley</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_17">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-17-1-0006">
        <pb id="p17-18" n="18"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A Minute Particular in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, Copy
O</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Theresa M. <name>Kelley</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>As several commentators have remarked, the eight tiny vignettes or panels which frame the text of
the “Introduction” in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> are difficult to decipher, if indeed
they can be deciphered at all.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">1</ref> Yet as
a group these vignettes are clearly derived, as Sir Geoffrey Keynes has argued, from “a medieval manuscript
illustrating the Tree of Jesse.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">2</ref>
With this antecedent in mind, recent commentators have suggested that the sixth vignette, the second from the
top in the group of four to the right of Blake’s text, may be Jesse. David Erdman summarized much of earlier
commentary when he described this figure as “huddled” with “legs crossed, head on hand; Jesse himself
(suggests Essick) as in the Sistine fresco; or regarding or working at something in his lap,
            <figure n="s-inn.O.P3-4" rend="file" width="646" height="1000">
	<head>1. “Introduction,” <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> copy O, reproduced by permission of the
Humanities Research Center, the University of Texas at Austin.</head>
</figure>
perhaps writing.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">3</ref> However, in 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, Copy O, the figure is well defined. It is not Jesse, but a woman who holds a
baby in her lap (illus. 1).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">4</ref> This
figure is clearly a deliberate variant, of interest not only because it may be unique among copies of the 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, but also because it demonstrates Blake’s atypical attention to this minute particular
in the “Introduction” of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See, for example, Edwin J. Ellis’s introduction for the facsimile edition
of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (London: Bernard Quaritch, 1893), xviii. For easier
reference, my citations of specific volumes of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> follow G. E. Bentley Jr.’s
practice of referring to <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> as <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, and to 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> as <hi rend="i">Experience (Blake Books</hi>, 1977). The
Ellis facsimile is of <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, U. See Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 436.
Bentley describes the vignette as “a man reading” in <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi>, 2 vols.
(Oxford: Clarendon, 1978), I, 24, and in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 389.</note>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Keynes’s commentary for <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi> (London: Trianon, 1967), pl. 4. Facsimile of <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, Z. See Bentley, 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 369.</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Erdman’s commentary for <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> (N.Y.:
Anchor Doubleday, 1974), p. 45. Facsimile of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, I, with reference in this instance
to <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, U. See Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, pp. 407 and 422.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">4</hi><hi rend="i"> Songs of Innocence</hi>, O. Reproduced here as illus. 1
through the courtesy of the Humanities Research Center, University of Texas at Austin. See Bentley, 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 409.</note></p>
          <p>Impressions of this plate that have not been retouched show, in the sixth vignette, a figure that
appears to be sitting, the legs slightly crossed, and the left arm possibly 
bent.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">5</ref> 
Otherwise, little can be distinguished. A similar figure
appears in retouched or tinted copies, although a few exhibit variations in the definition of the arms and
legs (illus. 2).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">6</ref> In still other
copies there is something—but it is unclear what—in the lap of the 
figure.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">7</ref> 
Finally, two Muir facsimiles respond with admirable
inventiveness to the muddled as well as huddled figure of most copies by altering its seated position or by
having the figure stand.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">8</ref> Even in 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, Copy N, one of three copies which Blake produced shortly before and after Copy O, the
figure is indistinct.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">9</ref> Yet if the
clearly depicted image of a mother and child in Copy O is unusual in the context of
<figure n="s-inn.i.p3-4" id="s-inn.i.illbk.03" work-copy="s-inn.i" rend="db" width="715" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>Introduction<lb/>
	Piping down the valleys wild<lb/>
	Piping songs of pleasant glee<lb/>
	On a cloud I saw a child.<lb/>
	And he laughing said to me.<lb/>
	Pipe a song about a Lamb:<lb/>
	So I piped with merry chear,<lb/>
	Piper pipe that song again__<lb/>
	So I piped, he wept to hear.<lb/>
	Drop thy pipe thy happy pipe<lb/>
	Sing thy songs of happy chear,<lb/>
	So I sung the same again<lb/>
	While he wept with joy to hear<lb/>
	Piper sit thee down and write<lb/>
	In a book that all may read__<lb/>
	So he vanish’d from my sight.<lb/>
	And I pluck’d a hollow reed.<lb/>
	And I made a rural pen,<lb/>
	And I stain’d the water clear,<lb/>
	And I wrote my happy songs,<lb/>
	Every child may joy to hear</figTranscr>
	<head>2. “Introduction,” <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> copy I, reproduced by permission of the
Huntington Library, San Marino, California.</head>
</figure>
<pb id="p17-19" n="19"/>
other versions of the same plate, it is typical of its immediate context, Copy O, which displays extensive ink
modeling of individual figures and designs, particularly notable in the frontispiece, “Introduction,”
“The Little Black Boy” (1 and 2), “The Little Boy Found,” “The Chimney Sweeper,” and “Night”
(1). Together with applications of color specific to this copy, such modeling either gives sharper definition
to principal figures or permits some redefinition of smaller ones, as is the case with the “mother and
child” vignette discussed here. Because there may be other variants of this figure in copies which I have
not consulted, this note invites additional notes and queries concerning the “Introduction” of 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Copies which show just the image printed from the copperplate or an image
that is unretouched in the area of this vignette are: <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, E (New York Public Library,
Berg Collection), U (facsimile, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> [Boston, 1883]) and 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, C, b, h, A (facsimile, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> [London: Ernest Benn,
1926]). I am indebted to Robert N. Essick for descriptions of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, U and 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, c, b, h, and AA (see below).</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Copies which are retouched or tinted but still show the same image as that
of the unretouched copies include: <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, B (facsimile, London: Trianon, 1954), D and K
(Morgan Library), I (reproduced here as illus. 2 through the courtesy of the Henry E. Huntington Library), N
(Estelle Doheny Collection of the Laurence Doheny Memorial Library) and <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, B
(facsimile, David Bindman, <hi rend="i">The Complete Graphic Works of William Blake</hi> [N.Y.: Putnam, 1978],
p. 217), E (Henry E. Huntington Library), I (reproduced in <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi>, p. 45), V
(Morgan Library), Y (Metropolitan Museum of New York), Z (facsimile, London: Trianon, 1967), AA. For
additional information concerning the copies cited in these notes, see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>,
pp. 365-438.</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Two copies besides <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, O and possibly 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, AA (see Erdman’s note concerning Essick’s reading of this figure in 
<hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi>, p. 45) appear to show something in the lap of the figure: 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, U (mentioned by Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi>, p. 45) and T
(facsimile, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> [Liverpool: Henry Young and Sons, 1923]).
See Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, pp. 436 and 421.</note>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">8</hi><hi rend="i"> Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (facsimile of 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, D [Edmonton: Muir, 1884]) and <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (Muir and Trumble
facsimile of <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, A [London: Bernard Quaritch, 1927]). See Bentley, 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, pp. 434 and 488.</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">9</hi> See Bentley’s chronological list of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> in 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 367.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
