<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>17.2.minnick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="checklist">Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Recent Publications</title>
        <author n="Minnick">Thomas L. Minnick</author>
        <author n="Dörrbecker">Detlef W. Dörrbecker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1983</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1983</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">17.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <name>Susan Corban</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <name>Chapel Petty</name>
              <name>Dennis Kane</name>
              <name>Karen Sunde</name>
              <name>Tom Elder</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>James Bogan</name>
              <name>Detlef Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Jon Stallworthy</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1983"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_17">
    <body>
      <pb id="p17-62" n="62"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-17-2-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Recent Publications</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">THOMAS L.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">MINNICK</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
          <hi rend="i">AND</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">DETLEF W.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">DÖRRBECKER</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>This year’s issue of our annual checklist of studies on Blake and his circle summarizes an
especially active year of scholarship, with nearly thirty per cent more items than last year’s issue. As
always, we have tried to be exhaustive in our hunt for items on Blake, while coverage of scholarship on his
contemporaries may be less thorough. As in previous checklists, an asterisk beside an entry number or
preceding the citations of some reviews indicates an item that we have not personally examined.</p>
        <p>It is a pleasure, annually renewed, to record our gratitude to authors who helped to keep us up to
date by sending on news of their own publications and, occasionally, of those of their colleagues.</p>
        <p>T.L.M.</p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part I</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">William Blake</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">
                  <hi rend="i">Editions, Translations, Facsimiles, Reproductions</hi>
                </hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>1. Blake, William. “The Divine Image.” P. 294 in <hi rend="i">The Enduring Legacy: Biblical
Dimensions in Modern Literature</hi>, ed. Douglas C. Brown. New York, N.Y.: Charles Scribner’s Sons,
1975.</p>
            <p>2. Blake, William. <hi rend="i">Selected Poems</hi>, ed. P.H. Butter. [Everyman’s Library,
no. 1125.] London, Melbourne &amp; Toronto: J.M. Dent &amp; Sons, 1982. [Selections chiefly drawn from
Blake’s published writings; excerpts only from <hi rend="i">Vala, Milton</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>; introduction, select bibliography, and brief annotations; the punctuation modernized;
obviously designed to replace Plowman’s edition of the <hi rend="i">Poems and Prophecies</hi>, 1927 
<hi rend="i">et seq.</hi>, in the same series.]</p>
            <p>3. Blake, William. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience.</hi> Manchester:
Manchester Etching Workshop, 1983. [A magnificent new facsimile edition of those plates which have survived in
the form of electrotypes, printed in a limited edition of 75 copies “on a rolling press with hand-made
intaglio ink on dampened wove paper.” There are 35 monochrome copies and 40 copies which have been
hand-colored plate by plate (without the use of the Trianon collotype-stencil process) in imitation of Copy B.
A prospectus is available from Paul Ritchie at the Manchester Etching Workshop, 3-5 Union Street, off Church
Street, Manchester, M4 1PB, England.]</p>
            <p>4. Blake, William. <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi> (series b), ed. James
Drougas. Hancock, Vt.: Top Drawer Enterprises, 1980 [Manifold Review; vol. 1, no. 1, July 1980.] [Priced at $1
this is the “Sixfold Postcard/Poster/Periodical Book,” a foldout with re-worked photographic reproductions
from eleven plates in the Trianon Press facsimile, printed in black, and also available in a limited handbound
edition from the editor at 270 Avenue of the Americas, New York, N.Y. 10014; regular copies are distributed by
Top Drawer Enterprises, P.O. Box 38, Hancock, Vt. 05748, who will also supply copies of the 1979 reprint of
Fiske’s <hi rend="i">Bernard Shaw’s Debt to William Blake</hi> which has been listed previously.]</p>
            <p>5. Blake, William. “An Ehrw. Dr. Trusler.” Pp. 442-44 in <hi rend="i">Künstlerbriefe aus
dem neunzehnten Jahrhundert</hi>, ed. Else Cassirer, 3rd ed. Berlin: Bruno Cassirer, 1923. [There is no
mention of either the translator, or the source from which this German version of the text has been taken, yet
it may well be that this is an unacknowledged reprint of Zweig’s translation which was first printed in the
<hi rend="i">Deutscher Almanach auf das Jahr 1907</hi>, Leipzig 1907, pp. 75-77; see Bentley, 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, 1977, item 89. The first edition of this collection of artists’ letters was
published in 1914.]</p>
            <p>6. Blake, William. “London.” P. 128 in <hi rend="i">London: Eine europäische Metropole in
Texten und Bildern</hi>, ed. Norbert Kohl. [Insel Taschenbuch, vol. 322.] Frankfurt am Main: Insel, 1979; 2nd
ed. 1980. [This translation, based on the text in the Stevenson-Erdman edition, by Maja Ueberle.]</p>
            <p>*7. Cumberland, George. <hi rend="i">Thoughts on Outline.</hi> [1796; microfiche rpt.] Zug
(Switzerland): Inter Documentation Company, 1982. SFr. 12 (c. $7.50).</p>
            <pb id="p17-63" n="63"/>
            <p>*8. Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>,
with commentary by Harold Bloom. Berkeley, Cal.: University of California Press, and New York, N.Y.:
Doubleday, 1981. $29.95. [The new, enl. and rev. ed. of Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Poetry and Prose of William
Blake</hi>, 1965 <hi rend="i">et seq.</hi>]</p>
            <p>*9. Rees, Abraham. <hi rend="i">The Cyclopaedia, or Universal Dictionary of Arts, Sciences and
Literature</hi>, 39 vols. (1819-1820; microfiche rpt.). Zug (Switzerland): Inter Documentation Company, 1982.
SFr. 1,188.</p>
            <p>*10. Shroyer, Richard J., ed. <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man</hi> (<hi rend="i">1788</hi>) 
<hi rend="i">by Johann Caspar Lavater: A Facsimile Reproduction of William Blake’s Copy of the First English
Edition.</hi> Delmar, N.Y.: Scholar’s Facsimiles and Reprints, 1980.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Bibliographies, Bibliographical Essays, Exhibition Catalogues</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>11. Bentley, G.E., Jr. “Ruthven Todd’s Blake Papers at Leeds.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1982), 72-81. [See also items 21 and 195.]</p>
            <p>12. Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Art and Times.</hi> [Exhb. cat.] Yale
Center for British Art, New Haven, and Art Gallery of Ontario, Toronto. [London]: Thames and Hudson, 1982.</p>
            <p>13. Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Movement: A Selective and Critical
Bibliography for 1979.</hi> [Garland Reference Library of the Humanities, vol. 211.] New York, N.Y. and
London: Garland, 1980, pp. 68-82.</p>
            <p>14. Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Movement: A Selective and Critical
Bibliography for 1980.</hi> [Garland Reference Library of the Humanities, vol. 213.] New York, N.Y. and
London: Garland, 1981, pp. 71-86.</p>
            <p>15. Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Movement: A Selective and Critical
Bibliography for 1981.</hi> [Garland Reference Library of the Humanities, vol. 216.] New York, N.Y. and
London: Garland, 1982, pp. 76-91.</p>
            <p>16. Grant, John E. “Who Shall Bind the Infinite and Arrange It in Libraries? 
<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi> and <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi>” [Review article.] 
<hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi>, 61 (1982), 277-304. [Besides the two Bentley items which are mentioned
in the title of this essay, many other recent publications are discussed.]</p>
            <p>17. Kauffmann, C.M. <hi rend="i">The Bible in British Art: 10th to 20th Centuries.</hi> [Exhb.
cat.] Victoria and Albert Museum. London: HMSO, 1977. [The exhibits included works by West, Mortimer, Barry,
Fuseli, Flaxman, and eight of the VAM’s own Blakes from the Butts collection.]</p>
            <p>18. McCord, James. <hi rend="i">With Corroding Fires: William Blake as Poet, Printmaker and
Painter.</hi> [Exhb. cat.] Schenectady, N.Y.: Schaffer Library of Union College, 1980. [The exhibition was
held at Scribner Library of Skidmore College from 21 April to 11 May 1980 and at Schaffer Library of Union
College from 12 May to 15 June 1980.]</p>
            <p>19. Minnick, Thomas L., and Detlef W. Dörrbecker. “Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of
Recent Scholarship.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1982), 111-20.</p>
            <p>20. Modern Language Association of America. “Blake, William (1757-1827).” Pp. 55-56 in 
<hi rend="i">1981 MLA International Bibliography of Books and Articles on the Modern Languages and
Literatures</hi>, vol. 1: “Classified Listings.” New York, N.Y.: MLA, 1983. [See also s. v. “Blake” in
the subject index.]</p>
            <p>21. [Morrish, P.S., and Jean Radford]. <hi rend="i">University of Leeds—The Library, MS. 470:
Blake Letters and Papers of Ruthven Todd.</hi> [Handlist no. 49.] Leeds: The Brotherton Library of the
University of Leeds, [1981]. [See also items 11 and 195.]</p>
            <p>22. Natoli, Joseph P. <hi rend="i">Twentieth-Century Blake Criticism: Northrop Frye to the
Present.</hi> [Garland Reference Library of the Humanities, vol. 285.] New York, N.Y. &amp; London: Garland
Publishing, 1982. $45.00. [This compilation has been “primarily designed for college students . . . to guide
the student through the chaff and into the kernel (p. ix).” For this purpose Natoli has listed almost 1700
items, which are organized in eleven sections and range from Schorer’s <hi rend="i">Politics of Vision</hi>
to publications which appeared in 1980.]</p>
            <p>23. Newey, Vincent. “The Nineteenth Century: Romantic Period—1. Verse and Drama.” Pp.
265-68 in <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English Studies</hi>, vol. 60 (1979), ed. James Redmond. [London]:
John Murray, for the English Association, 1981.</p>
            <p>24. Robinson, K. E. “The Eighteenth Century.” Pp. 256-58 in <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work
in English Studies</hi>, vol. 56 (1975), ed. James Redmond. London: John Murray, for the English Association,
1977.</p>
            <p>25. Smith, Michael, ed. <hi rend="i">Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature for
1975</hi>, vol. 50. London: Modern Humanities Research Association, 1978. [Blake entries are numbered 6311
through 6433, pp. 357-63.]</p>
            <p>26. Smith, Michael, ed. <hi rend="i">Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature for
1976</hi>, vol. 51. London: Modern Humanities Research Association, 1980. [Items 6183 to 6253 list
contributions to Blake scholarship, pp. 353-57.]</p>
            <p>27. Smith, Michael, ed. <hi rend="i">Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature for
1977</hi>, vol. 52. London: Modern Humanities Research Association, 1980. [Blake entries to be found on pp.
297-302, numbered 5187 through 5299, and <hi rend="i">passim.</hi>]</p>
            <p>28. Smith, Michael, ed. <hi rend="i">Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature for
1978</hi>, vol. 53. London: Modern Humanities Research Association, 1981. [Blake entries listed as items 5416
to 5509 on pp. 300-04.]</p>
            <p>29. Smith, Michael, ed. <hi rend="i">Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature for
1979</hi>, vol. 54. London: Modern Humanities Research Association, 1982. [Blake entries will be found on pp.
332-37 and <hi rend="i">passim.</hi>]</p>
            <p>30. Vaughan, William. “Blake and the Interpreters.” <hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, 5
(1982), 106-09. [Contains reviews of
<pb id="p17-64" n="64"/>
Butlin’s catalogue raisonné, of the reproductions of the <hi rend="i">NT</hi> designs, and of Dunbar’s
study of the Milton illustrations, also some general remarks.]</p>
            <p>31. Viscomi, Joseph. <hi rend="i">Prints by William Blake and His Followers.</hi> [Exhb. cat.]
Ithaca, N.Y.: Herbert F. Johnson Musuem of Art at Cornell University, 1983. [The 64 prints on show
included—besides a few Blakes—works by Linnell, Sherman, Richmond, Calvert, and Palmer.]</p>
            <p>32. Watson, J. R. “The Nineteenth Century: Romantic Period—1. Verse and Drama.” Pp.
237-41 in <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English Studies</hi>, vol. 57 (1976), ed. James Redmond. London:
John Murray, for the English Association, 1978.</p>
            <p>33. Watson, J. R. “The Nineteenth Century: Romantic Period—1. Verse and Drama.” Pp.
257-60 in <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English Studies</hi>, vol. 58 (1977), ed. James Redmond. London:
John Murray, for the English Association, 1979.</p>
            <p>34. Watson, J. R. “The Nineteenth Century: Romantic Period—1. Verse and Drama.” Pp.
264-68 in <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English Studies</hi>, vol. 59 (1978), ed. James Redmond. London:
John Murray, for the English Association, 1980. [See also pp. 206-07 and <hi rend="i">passim.</hi>]</p>
            <p>35. Wright, John W. <hi rend="i">Magnifying Blake’s Books.</hi> [Exhb. cat.] Ann Arbor,
Mich.: Department of Rare Books at the Graduate Library of the University of Michigan, 1981. [A four-page
exhibition hand-out, concerned with Blake’s later illuminations, the problems raised by the use of facsimile
editions, and leading towards the discovery of Blake’s stereoptic art. The exhibition was also shown in
connection with the <hi rend="i">Blake &amp; Criticism</hi> conference at Kresge College Library of the
University of California, Santa Cruz; see item 133.]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Critical Studies</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>36. Ackland, Michael. “The Embattled Sexes: Blake’s Debt to Wollstonecraft in 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1982-83), 172-83.</p>
            <p>37. Adams, Hazard. “Post-Essick Prophecy.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 21
(1982), 400-403. [A contribution to the special <hi rend="i">Festschrift</hi> issue of <hi rend="i">SiR</hi>
for David Erdman, following up the argument of Essick’s statement in the same issue; see item 64.]</p>
            <p>38. Ahearn, Edward J. “Confrontation with the City: Social Criticism, Apocalypse and the
Reader’s Responsibility in City Poems by Blake, Hugo and Baudelaire.” <hi rend="i">The Hebrew University
Studies in Literature</hi>, 10 (1982), 1-22.</p>
            <p>39. Alford, Steven Edward. “Irony and the Logic of the Romantic Imagination.” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 43 (1983), 2656-A. Diss., University of North Carolina at
Chapel Hill, 1982. [“Schlegel and Blake wrote in reaction to what they saw as the inadequate concepts of
poetry and of understanding of the Enlightenment. . . .” Part II “examines the suggestive relationship
between Blake’s and Schlegel’s views on logic. . . . After examining Blake’s views on logic, dialectic,
and rhetoric, the presence of Romantic Irony in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> (1794) is
examined.”]</p>
            <p>40. Anon. “Blake at Cornell: Exhibitions and Symposium.” <hi rend="i">Herbert F. Johnson
Museum of Art</hi> [Newsletter], March-April 1983, pp. C-D [A short note on the Cornell symposium on
“William Blake: Ancient &amp; Modern,” and two of the three exhibitions which were held at Ithaca in
conjunction with this conference.]</p>
            <p>41. Baker, John Steven. “Blake and the Will.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
International</hi>, 43 (1982), 1550-A. Diss., University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, 1982. [“This
study treats the will as an important neglected theme in William Blake’s writings. . . . ‘Chapter Three’
argues that Tharmas embodies the will in Blake’s myth. . . . The last chapter explores the will’s relation
to Blake’s states by comparing Blake with Soren Kierkegaard.”]</p>
            <p>*42. Bentley, G.E., Jr. “The Great Illustrated-Book Publishers of the 1790s and William
Blake.” Pp. 57-96 in William Blissett, ed., <hi rend="i">Editing Illustrated Texts: Papers Given at the
Fifteenth Annual Conference on Editorial Problems.</hi> New York and London: Garland Publishing Co., 1980.
[The conference was held at the University of Toronto, 2-3 November 1979.]</p>
            <p>43. Bertholf, Robert J., and Annette S. Levitt, eds. <hi rend="i">William Blake and the
Moderns.</hi> Albany, N.Y.: State University of New York Press, 1982. Cloth, $39.50; paper, $14.95. [Essays by
Hazard Adams on “The Seven Eyes of Yeats,” by Donald Pease on “Blake, Whitman, Crane: The Hand of
Fire,” by Leroy Searle on “Blake, Eliot, and Williams,” by Jay Parini on “Blake and Roethke,” by
Robert J. Bertholf on “Robert Duncan: Blake’s Contemporary Voice,” by Alicia Ostriker on “Blake,
Ginsberg, Madness, and the Prophet as Shaman,” by Robert F. Gleckner on “Joyce’s Blake,” by Myra
Glazer on “Blake and D.H. Lawrence,” by Annette S. Levitt on “ ‘The Mental Traveller’ in ‘The
Horse’s Mouth’: New Light on the Old Cycle,” by Susan Levin on “William Blake and Doris Lessing,” by
Minna Doskow on “Blake and Marx,” by Eileen Sanzo, “Blake, Teilhard, and the Idea of the Future of
Man,” and by William Dennis Horn on “William Blake and the Problematic of the Self.”]</p>
            <p>44. Bindman, David. “An Afterword on <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Art and Times.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1983), 224-25.</p>
            <p>*45. Blois, R.E. <hi rend="i">The American Reputation and Influence of William Blake.</hi> New
York, N.Y.: Gordon Press, 1982 [?].</p>
            <p>46. Bogan, James. “Blake’s City of Golgonooza in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>: Metaphor and
Mandala.” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1981), 85-98.</p>
            <p>47. Bogan, James, and Fred Goss, eds. <hi rend="i">Sparks of Fire: Blake in a New Age.</hi>
Richmond, Ca.: North Atlantic Books, 1982. [This volume includes more than 100
<pb id="p17-65" n="65"/>
varied contributions that touch on Blake in many ways. Articles of scholarly interest include those by Albert
Roe, “Blake’s Symbolism,” pp. 67-90; Karleen Middleton Murphy, “The Emanation: Creativity and
Creation,” pp. 104-14; Morris Eaves, “Teaching Blake’s Relief Etching,” pp. 127-40; Howard Schwartz,
“The Form of the Fall: ‘The Mental Traveller,’ ” pp. 147-51; E. B. Murray, “A Pictorial Guide to
Twofold Vision: Copy ‘O’ of <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>,” pp. 156-68; Daniel
Zimmerman, “From Prophecy to Vision: Blake’s Track,” pp. 222-25; Fred Whitehead, “Visions of the
Archaic World,” pp. 231-43; Karleen Middleton Murphy, “ ‘All the Lovely Sex’: Blake and the Woman
Question,” pp. 272-75; James Bogan, “A Tour of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,” pp. 348-66; and Roger
Easson, “On Building a Blake Library,” pp. 426-37. Readers will also enjoy the poems, imaginary
conversations, drawings, and other creative responses to Blake’s work that make up the other sections of
this book.]</p>
            <p>48. Bohrer, Karl Heinz. “In den Wäldern der Nacht—William Blake: Prophet der Zerstörung
Britanniens.” In <hi rend="i">Ein bisschen Lust am Untergang: Englische Ansichten.</hi> Munich and Vienna:
Carl Hanser, 1979; pp. 214-23 (pp. 204-12 in the 2<hi rend="s">nd</hi> ed. [Suhrkamp Taschenbuch, vol. 745.]
Frankfurt am Main: Suhrkamp, 1982.) [Bohrer’s essay was first published as an article in the 
<hi rend="i">Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung</hi>, 1975.]</p>
            <p>49. Butlin, Martin. “A Concordance Between William Rossetti’s Annotated Lists, W. Graham
Robertson’s Supplementary List, and Butlin’s Catalogue Numbers,” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1982), 12-21.</p>
            <p>50. Chan, Victor. “Blake, Goya, Flaxman, Romney and Fuseli: Transcriptions and
Transformations of a Dantesque Image.” <hi rend="i">Arts Magazine</hi>, 55 (1981), 80-84.</p>
            <p>51. Chatwin, Deryn. <hi rend="i">Notes on Blake’s Poetry.</hi> [Methuen Notes: Study-Aids
Series.] London: Methuen Paperbacks, 1979.</p>
            <p>52. Corti, Claudia. “Visualità e iconismo nella poesia di Blake.” <hi rend="i">Rivista di
Letterature moderne e comparate</hi>, n.s. 35 (1982), 13-26.</p>
            <p>53. Cox, Stephen D. <hi rend="i">“The Stranger Within Thee”: Concepts of the Self in Late
Eighteenth-Century Literature.</hi> Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1980. $14.95. [Includes
chapters on Cowper and Blake.]</p>
            <p>54. Damrosch, Leopold, Jr. “Burns, Blake, and the Recovery of Lyric.” <hi rend="i">Studies
in Romanticism</hi>, 21 (1982), 637-60.</p>
            <p>55. Davies, J.M.Q. “‘Embraces are Cominglings’: Passion and Apocalypse in Blake’s
‘Paradise Regained’ Designs.” <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi>, 74, n.s. 43 (1981), 75-96.
[39 illus.]</p>
            <p>56. De Luca, V.A. “The Changing Order of Plates in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Chapter
II.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1983), 192-205.</p>
            <p>57. De Luca, V.A. “‘The Unwearied Sun’: An Echo of Addison in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>” <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi>, 20 (1982), 8-10.</p>
            <p>58. Doskow, Minna. “The Shape of Limitation: A Visual Pattern in the Illuminated Works of
William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1981), 121-60.</p>
            <p>59. Eaves, Morris. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Theory of Art.</hi> [Princeton Essays on the
Arts, vol. 13.] Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press, 1982.</p>
            <p>60. Eaves, Morris, ed. “Romantic Texts, Romantic Times: Homage to David V. Erdman.” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 21 (1982), 277-550. [For the contents of this special 
<hi rend="i">Festschrift</hi> issue of <hi rend="i">SiR</hi> (no. 3) which are concerned with Blake and David
Erdman’s contributions to Blake scholarship, see the individual entries for Adams, Essick, Gleckner, Grant,
Hilton, Kroeber, Mitchell, Paley, and Viscomi in this section of our checklist; also entries for Brown and
Eaves in part III, below.]</p>
            <p>61. Erdman, David V. “Art against Armies.” [“Blake and the Night Sky: II.”] 
<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi>, 84 (1981), 296-304.</p>
            <p>62. Erdman, David V. “The Future of Blake Studies.” <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi>, 21 (1982), 391-94.</p>
            <p>63. Essick, Robert N. “Blake in the Marketplace 1980-1981.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1982), 86-106.</p>
            <p>64. Essick, Robert N. “Blake Today and Tomorrow.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>,
21 (1982), 395-99.</p>
            <p>65. Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue.</hi>
Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press, 1983.</p>
            <p>*66. Fergensen, Laraine. “Blake’s ‘Eternal Now’: A Prophetic Vision of Post-Newtonian
Physics.” <hi rend="i">Studia Theologica: Scandinavian Journal of Theology</hi>, 3 (1980), 122-32.</p>
            <p>67. Fogel, A. “Pictures of Speech: On Blake’s Poetic.” <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi>, 21 (1982), 217-42.</p>
            <p>68. Fuller, David S. “The Translation of Vision: Reading Blake’s ‘Tiriel.’” 
<hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi>, 75, n.s. 44 (1982), 29-36.</p>
            <p>69. Gilchrist, Alexander. <hi rend="i">The Life of William Blake</hi>, ed. Ruthven Todd.
[Everyman’s Library / An Everyman Paperback, vol. 1971.] London, Melbourne &amp; Toronto: J.M. Dent &amp;
Sons, 1982. [This is <hi rend="i">not</hi> the fully revised edition on which the late Ruthven Todd had been
engaged during the last decade of his life but rather a reprint of the 1945 version of his text and notes;
nevertheless, all those who are teaching Blake in the classroom will rejoice that this standard source book is
available once again at a fairly reasonable price (£4.50) to any of their students.]</p>
            <p>70. Gleckner, Robert F. “Blake’s ‘Little Black Boy’ and the Bible.” 
<hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi>, 18 (1982), 205-13.</p>
            <p>71. Gleckner, Robert F. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prelude, Poetical Sketches.</hi> Baltimore and
London: The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1982. $15.00.</p>
            <p>72. Gleckner, Robert F. “A Creed Not Outworn.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 21
(1982), 431-35.</p>
            <p>73. Gleckner, Robert F. “Edmund Spenser and
<pb id="p17-66" n="66"/>
Blake’s Printing House in Hell.” <hi rend="i">South Atlantic Quarterly</hi>, 81 (1982), 311-22.</p>
            <p>74. Gleckner, Robert F. “The Strange Odyssey of Blake’s ‘The Voice of the Ancient
Bard.’” <hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and Present</hi>, 6 (1982), 1-25.</p>
            <p>75. Grant, John E. “Some Drawings Related to Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
Designs: The Coda Sketch and Two Pictures Not Previously Connected with the Series.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1982), 7-11.</p>
            <p>76. Grant, John E. “Blake in the Future.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 21
(1982), 436-43.</p>
            <p>77. Greenberg, Mark L. “The Rossettis’ Transcription of Blake’s Notebook.” 
<hi rend="i">Library</hi>, 6th ser., 4 (1982), 249-72.</p>
            <p>78. Hampsey, John Coleman. “Blake’s Bound Children: A Study of <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> and
Other Works.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 43 (1982), 1978-A-1979-A. Diss.,
Boston College, 1982. [“Many of Blake’s works include images of problem children who are tyrannized and
enslaved by their father until they rebel. The rebellion is only part of a cycle and offers no permanent
freedom because the child will later become just like the tyrant father he overthrew. This endless conflict of
parent and child . . . is emblematic of the world of generation in general, and is responsible for the
narrative movement in the plot structures in Blake’s poetry.”]</p>
            <p>79. Hanke, Amala M. <hi rend="i">Spatiotemporal Consciousness in English and German
Romanticism: A Comparative Study of Novalis, Blake, Wordsworth, and Eichendorff.</hi> [European University
Studies, ser. XVIII: Comparative Literature, vol. 25.] Berne, Frankfurt am Main, and Las Vegas: Peter Lang,
1981.</p>
            <p>80. Heppner, Christopher. “Reading Blake’s Designs: <hi rend="i">Pity</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Hecate.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi>, 84 (1981), 337-65.</p>
            <p>81. Hilton, Nelson. “Becoming Prolific Being Devoured.” <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi>, 21 (1982), 417-24.</p>
            <p>82. Hilton, Nelson. “Some Sexual Connotations.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1983), 166-71.</p>
            <p>*83. Hodnett, Edward. <hi rend="i">Image and Text: Studies in the Illustration of English
Literature.</hi> London: Scolar Press, 1982. [Said to contain a chapter on Blake.]</p>
            <p>*84. Holmes, John R. “The Surprising Orthodoxy of Merton’s Blake.” 
<hi rend="i">Cithara</hi>, 20 (1981), 38-66.</p>
            <p>85. Hyland, Dominic. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Songs of Innocence and Songs of
Experience.</hi> [York Notes, vol. 173.] Beirut &amp; Harlow, Essex: Longman York Press, 1982.</p>
            <p>86. Ide, Nancy Marie. “Patterns of Imagery in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Four
Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 43 (1983), 3325-A. Diss., The
Pennsylvania State University, 1982. [“The patterning of images across the text of William Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> reveals that a substantial portion of the poem’s meaning is conveyed both by the
interaction among associations and connotations of the images within specific passages and by the reader’s
perception of the distributional configurations themselves. . . . Computer-generated graphs of image
distribution show that many of the poem’s images are distributed symmetrically across a linear axis
representing the text. . . .”]</p>
            <p>87. James, David E. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Laocoön:</hi> A Degree Zero of Literary
Production.” <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi>, 98 (1983), 226-36.</p>
            <p>88. James, G. Ingli. “Blake.” <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary
Supplement</hi>, 27 March 1981, p. 351. [A letter on Michael Mason’s <hi rend="i">TLS</hi> review of
Essick’s <hi rend="i">Printmaker</hi>; see also Wyler, item 138.]</p>
            <p>89. Johnson, Mary Lynn. “Observations on Blake’s Paintings and Drawings (Based on
Butlin’s Catalogue Raisonné).” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1982), 4-6.</p>
            <p>*90. Johnson, Mary Lynn. “Coleridge’s Prose and a Blake Plate in Stedman’s
‘Narrative’: Unfastening the ‘Hooks &amp; Eyes’ of Memory.” <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi>,
13 (1982), 36-37.</p>
            <p>91. Johnson, Mary Lynn, and John E. Grant. “The Norton Critical Edition of Blake: Addenda and
Corrigenda.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1982), 107-10.</p>
            <p>92. Kaltenbrunner, Gerd-Klaus. “William Blake: Chiffren vom Ursprung und Fall der Welt.”
<hi rend="i">Scheidewege: Vierteljahresschrift für skeptisches Denken</hi>, 10 (1980), 480-87; rpt. in
*Kaltenbrunner, Gerd-Klaus. <hi rend="i">Europa: Seine geistigen Quellen in Porträts aus zwei
Jahrtausenden</hi>, vol. 1. Heroldsberg: Glock &amp; Lutz, 1981.</p>
            <p>*93. Katsuya, Hiromoto. “ ‘Comus’ and ‘Visions of the Daughters of Albion’: Two Poems
on Sexual Love.” <hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature</hi> (Tokyo), (1980), 3-15.</p>
            <p>94. Kroeber, Karl. “Infirm Perswasion.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 21
(1982), 428-30.</p>
            <p>95. Kumbier, William Allen. “Sound, Form, and Signification: Studies in Blake, Smart, and
Rousseau.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 43 (1982), 164-A. Diss., State University
of New York at Buffalo, 1981. [“The three sections of the thesis show how phonetic elements in Blake’s
epics, Smart’s <hi rend="i">Jubilate Agno</hi>, and Rousseau’s musical treatises sever whatever ties those
works may have had with univocal significance, or the unqualified reinforcement of <hi rend="i">one</hi>
meaning, and how these elements in turn present new and divergent meanings as their play assumes more and more
space in the text.”]</p>
            <p>96. Lange, Thomas V. “Two Forged Plates in <hi rend="i">America</hi>, Copy B.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1983), 212-16.</p>
            <p>97. Lee, Judith. “Ways of Their Own: The Emanations of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala, or The
Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi>, 50 (1983), 131-53.</p>
            <p>98. Lincoln, Andrew. “Blake’s Lower Paradise: The Pastoral Passage in <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>, Night the Ninth.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi>, 84 (1981),
470-78.</p>
            <p>99. Loudon, Michael Douglas. “The Story in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>:
A Guide to the Events of the Epic.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 43 (1983),
2998-A. Diss., State University of New York at
<pb id="p17-67" n="67"/>
Buffalo, 1982. [“The narrative of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is shaped in the fashion of a dream. Thus,
the typical narrative line is absent. . . . By constructing a linear narrative, the dissertation explicates,
stanza by stanza, the action within the dream.”]</p>
            <p>100. Lucie-Smith, Edward. “The fiery vision of William Blake is burning bright.” 
<hi rend="i">Smithsonian</hi>, 13, no. 6 (September, 1982), 50-59. [Includes comments on the Blake exhibition held
at the Yale Center for British Art and the Art Gallery of Toronto.]</p>
            <p>*101. Magno, Concettina Tramontano. “L’imagery poetico-pittorica di W. Blake nei romanzi di
P. White.” P. 45 in <hi rend="i">Atti del Convegno di Studi Australiani: L’Australia negli anni
‘80.</hi> Messina: Università di Messina, 1981.</p>
            <p>*102. Mahon, W.D. Maxwell. “William Blake and Thomas Gray: Two Fine Artists.” 
<hi rend="i">De Arte</hi>, 24 (1980), 20-24.</p>
            <p>103. Martin, Floyd Weatherby. “The Changing Fortunes of Reynolds’ 
<hi rend="i">Discourses</hi>, c. 1770-1850.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 43 (1982),
572-A. Diss., University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, 1982. [Includes consideration of lectures and
writings on Reynolds by Blake, West, Barry, Fuseli, Flaxman, Turner, Farington, and others.]</p>
            <p>104. Mathews, Lawrence. “The Value of the Saviours Blood: The Idea of Atonement in Blake’s
<hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Wascana Review</hi>, 15 (1980), 72-86.</p>
            <p>105. Mellor, Anne K. “Blake’s Portrayal of Women.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1982-83), 148-55.</p>
            <p>106. Miller, Dan Clinton. “Binding Allegory: Images of Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 43 (1982), 1154-A. Diss.,
The University of Iowa, 1982. [“This reading of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> focuses on the fundamentally
allegorical nature of Blake’s prophetic art. A theory of allegory, based both on Blakean and modern
conceptions of the mode, serves as an instrument to explore Blake’s representational practice and the
conditions of reading this complex work.”]</p>
            <p>107. Miner, Paul. “Visionary Astronomy.” [“Blake and the Night Sky: III.”] 
<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi>, 84 (1981), 305-36.</p>
            <p>108. Mitchell, W.J.T. “Dangerous Blake.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 21
(1982), 410-16.</p>
            <p>109. Niimi, Hatsuko. “The Proverbial Language of Blake’s ‘Marriage of Heaven and
Hell’.” <hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature</hi>, 57 (1982), 3-20.</p>
            <p>110. Ostriker, Alicia. “Desire Gratified and Ungratified: William Blake and Sexuality.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1982-1983), 156-65.</p>
            <p>111. Ostrom, Hans. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> and the Dramatization of Collapsed
Language.” <hi rend="i">Papers on Language and Literature</hi>, 19 (1983), 167-82.</p>
            <p>112. Pace, Claire. “Blake and Chaucer: ‘Infinite variety of character.’ ” 
<hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, 3 (1980), 388-409.</p>
            <p>113. Paley, Morton D. “What is to be Done?” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 21
(1982), 425-27.</p>
            <p>114. Piquet, François. “Le Tragique et la différence: Blake et le problème de
l’incarnation.” <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi>, 36 (1983), 24-33.</p>
            <p>115. Punter, David. <hi rend="i">Blake, Hegel, and Dialectic.</hi> [Elementa, 26.] Amsterdam:
Rodopi, 1982. hfl 50.00.</p>
            <p>116. Ragghianti, Carlo Ludovico. “La fortuna di Blake.” <hi rend="i">Critica d’arte</hi>,
44 (1979), 111-24.</p>
            <p>117. Raine, Kathleen J. “Blake: The Poet as Prophet.” <hi rend="i">Essays and Studies</hi>,
35 (1982), 66-83.</p>
            <p>118. Rao, Valli. “‘Back to Methuselah’: A Blakean Interpretation.” <hi rend="i">Shaw:
The Annual of Bernard Shaw Studies</hi>, 1 (1981). [“Shaw and Religion,” ed. Charles A. Berst],
141-81.</p>
            <p>119. Read, Dennis M. “Blake’s ‘Tender Stranger’: ‘Thel’ and Hervey’s
‘Meditations.’” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi>, 18 (1982), 160-67.</p>
            <p>120. Read, Dennis M. “The Context of Blake’s ‘Public Address’: Cromek and the
Chalcographic Society.” <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi>, 60 (1981), 69-86.</p>
            <p>121. Reiman, Donald H., and Christina Shuttleworth Kraus, “The Derivation and Meaning of
‘Ololon.’” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1982), 82-85.</p>
            <p>*122. Roberts-Jones, Philippe. “Blake, image concertée, image visitée.” 
<hi rend="i">L’Oeil</hi>, no. 274, May 1978, 40-45.</p>
            <p>123. Rumsby, R.L. “Trinities of The Tyger.” <hi rend="i">Cambridge Quarterly</hi>, 11
(1982), 316-28.</p>
            <p>124. Schaar, Eckhard, and Hanna Hohl. “Graphische Sammlung: Erwerbungen 1980.” 
<hi rend="i">Idea: Jahrbuch der Hamburger Kunsthalle</hi>, n.s. 1 (1982), 198-202. [Brief notes on the acquisition
of a Bartolozzi engraving after Fuseli, of two drawings by Romney, of Blake’s “Ugolino” drawing (Butlin
1981, no. 208), of Calvert’s “Ploughman,” and Richmond’s “The Shepherd.”]</p>
            <p>125. Shaviro, Steven. “Differential Structure of Romantic Imagination: Blake, Shelley,
Stevens.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 43 (1983), 2355-A. Diss., Yale University,
1981.</p>
            <p>*126. Sinderen, Adrian van. <hi rend="i">Blake: The Mystic Genius.</hi> [1949; rpt.]. Darby,
Pa.: Arden Library, 1982.</p>
            <p>127. Smith, Mark Trevor. “William Blake’s Transfiguration of the Bible in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 43 (1982), 2685-A. Diss.,
State University of New York at Stony Brook, 1982. [“This dissertation investigates minute particulars of
Blake’s use of the Bible in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and fits them into my scheme of the structure of the
poem. My thesis is that Blake recreates the Bible in two opposed ways: he accepts and imitates it as a model
of Vision, but at the same time he rejects and rewrites it as a restrictive system.”]</p>
            <p>128. Taylor, Ronald C. “Semantic Structure and the Temporal Modes of Blake’s Poetic
Verse.” <hi rend="i">Language and Style</hi>, 12 (1979), 26-49.</p>
            <p>129. Viscomi, Joseph. <hi rend="i">The Art of William Blake’s Illuminated Prints.</hi>
Manchester: Manchester Etching Workshop, 1983. [Designed by the Gladiola Press, New
<pb id="p17-68" n="68"/>
York, as a commentary booklet for the Manchester Etching Workshop’s facsimile edition of the 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (see item 3), and printed in an edition of 200 copies, of which about 100 will be sold
separately.]</p>
            <p>130. Viscomi, Joseph. “Facsimile or Forgery? An Examination of <hi rend="i">America</hi>,
Plates 4 and 9, Copy B.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1983), 219-23.</p>
            <p>131. Viscomi, Joseph. “The Workshop.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 21 (1982),
404-09. [Concerns the “mechanical” side of Blake’s art and its relevance for a proper understanding of
the “symbolic” meaning.]</p>
            <p>132. Viscomi, Joseph Steven. “The Workshop of William Blake: The Making of an Illuminated
Book.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 43 (1982), 1558-A. Diss., Columbia
University, 1980. [“Part I is a technical analysis based on historical research of eighteenth-century
engraving and book production . . . ” Part II discusses “on a factual basis the appeal that the medium of
relief etching had for Blake.”]</p>
            <p>133. Vogler, Thomas A., ed. <hi rend="i">Blake and Criticism</hi>: [Papers read at] 
<hi rend="i">A Conference at the University of California, Santa Cruz—20-22 May 1982.</hi> Santa Cruz, Cal.:
Kresge College at the University of California, 1982. [A small number of xerox reprints from the conference
papers was produced at Kresge College in 1982; the bound volume contains Paul Mann’s “‘The Book of
Urizen’ and the Horizon of the Book,” pp. 1-25; Michael Fischer’s “Blake’s Quarrel with
Indeterminacy,” pp. 26-34; W.J.T. Mitchell’s “Dangerous Blake,” pp. 35-42; Donald D. Ault’s
“Re-Visioning Blake’s ‘Four Zoas,’” pp. 43-62; Morton D. Paley’s “‘Milton’ and the Form of
History,” pp. 63-76; Daniel Stempel’s “Blake and Wordsworth: From Classical Space to Modern Time,” pp.
77-103; Morris Eaves’s “Blake’s Illuminated Books and Criticism: A Sometimes Annotated Documentary
History of an Old Story,” pp. 104-18; Vince[nt] A. De Luca’s “Blake’s Wall of Words: The Sublime As
Text,” pp. 119-42; Margaret Storch’s “The Spectrous Fiend Cast Out: Blake’s Mid-Life Crisis,” pp.
143-79; Alicia Ostriker’s “Androgynous Concept? Misogynist Metaphor?,” pp. 180-92; and Gavin Edwards’
“Repeating the Same Dull Round,” pp. 193-223.]</p>
            <p>*134. Webster, Brenda S. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic Psychology.</hi> Athens, Georgia:
University of Georgia Press, 1983. $27.50.</p>
            <p>135. Williams, Porter, Jr. “Blake’s ‘An ancient Proverb’ and a Dash of ‘Blood.’”
<hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi>, 60 (1981), 264-71.</p>
            <p>136. Worrall, David. “The ‘Immortal Tent.’” [“Blake and the Night Sky: I.”] 
<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi>, 84 (1981), 273-95.</p>
            <p>137. Wright, Warren Keith. “The Scholars &amp; A Grain of Sand.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1983), 225.</p>
            <p>138. Wyler, Stephen. “Blake.” <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary
Supplement</hi>, 13 March 1981, p. 285. [A letter on Mason’s review of Essick’s 
<hi rend="i">Printmaker</hi>; see also G. Ingli James, item 88.]</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part II</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">Blake’s Circle</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">James Barry</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>139. Pressly, William L. <hi rend="i">James Barry: The Artist as Hero.</hi> [Exhibition
catalogue.] London: Tate Gallery, 1983. £4.50.</p>
            <p>See also items 17, 103, 172, and 197.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">William Cowper</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>140. Dawson, P.M.S. “Cowper’s Equivocations.” <hi rend="i">Essays in Criticism</hi>, 33
(1983), 19-35.</p>
            <p>141. King, James, and Charles Ryskamp, eds. <hi rend="i">The Letters and Prose Writings of
William Cowper. Volume III: Letters, 1787-1791.</hi> Oxford: The Clarendon Press, 1982. $79.00.</p>
            <p>142. Rogers, Deborah D. “Cowper’s ‘Ode on Reading Sir Charles Grandison’ Again.” 
<hi rend="i">Papers on Language</hi> &amp; <hi rend="i">Literature</hi>, 18 (1982), 416-20.</p>
            <p>See also item 53.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Richard Cumberland</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>143. Ritz, Regis. <hi rend="i">Le Théâtre de Richard Cumberland.</hi> Lille: Université de
Lille III; Paris: Honoré Champion, 1979.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Erasmus Darwin</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>*144. King-Hele, Desmond, ed. <hi rend="i">The Letters of Erasmus Darwin.</hi> Cambridge:
Cambridge University Press, 1982.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">John Flaxman</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>145. Dennis, Rodney G. “Flaxman’s Answers to Klopstock.” <hi rend="i">Harvard Library
Bulletin</hi>, 24 (1976), 197-203. [A sequel to the author’s earlier article on Klopstock and Flaxman 
(<hi rend="i">HLB</hi>, 16 [1968], 5-17), centered around the publication of two hitherto unpublished letters of
the sculptor to the German poet, both dating from 1801.]</p>
            <p>146. Egerton, Judy. “London: Water-colours and Drawings.” <hi rend="i">Burlington
Magazine</hi>, 124 (1982), 114-15. [Briefly reviews an exhibition at the Covent Garden Gallery which included
a hitherto unpublished Flaxman drawing, connected with the sculptor’s <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> outlines;
the drawing is reproduced as pl. 53.]</p>
            <p>147. Grate, Pontus, et al. <hi rend="i">På klassik mark: Malare i Rom på 1780-talet.</hi>
[Exhb. cat.] [Nationalmuseums <corr type="emend">utställningskatalog,</corr> vol. 455.] Stockholm: National-museum, 1982. [Pp. 39-42,
cat. nos. 21-27, are devoted to some of Flaxman’s Roman drawings, executed in preparation for his outline
engravings.]</p>
            <pb id="p17-69" n="69"/>
            <p>148. Lyle, Janice S. “John Flaxman and the Outline Style in Rome: 1785-1800.” Pp. 103-08 in
<hi rend="i">The Anglo-American Artist in Italy 1750-1820</hi> [exhb. cat.], ed. Corlette Rossiter Walker.
Santa Barbara, Cal.: University Art Museum, 1982.</p>
            <p>See also items 17, 50, 103, 172, and 197.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Henry Fuseli</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>149. Atkins, A.M. “‘Both Turk and Jew’: Notes on the Poetry of Henry Fuseli, with Some
Translations.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1983), 206-11.</p>
            <p>150. Bircher, Martin, ed. <hi rend="i">Maler und Dichter der Idylle: Salomon Gessner
1730-1788.</hi> [Exhb. cat.] [Ausstellungskataloge der Herzog August Bibliothek, vol. 30.] Wolfenbüttel:
Herzog August Bibliothek, 1980; 2nd rev. ed., 1982. [Cat. no. 26 is a drawing by the 13-year-old Fuseli
published here for the first time.]</p>
            <p>151. Carr, Stephen Leo. “Verbal-Visual Relationships: Zoffany’s and Fuseli’s
Illustrations of ‘Macbeth.’” <hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, 3 (1980), 375-87.</p>
            <p>*152. Hahn, Karl-Friedrich. <hi rend="i">Denkertypen bei Johann Heinrich Füssli:
Untersuchungen zum Selbstverständnis des Künstlers im Verhältnis zu seinen Einflusssphären</hi>,
unpublished M.A. thesis, Universität Stuttgart, 1981.</p>
            <p>*153. Hahn, Karl-Friedrich. “‘Füssli im Gespräch mit Bodmer’—ein sokratischer
Dialog.” Pp. 177-206 in <hi rend="i">Interaktionsanalysen: Aspekte dialogischer Kommunikation</hi>, ed.
Gerhard Charles Rump and Wilfried Heindrichs. Hildesheim: Gebr. Gerstenberg, 1982.</p>
            <p>154. Land, Melinda. “The Influence of Mannerist Art and Erotica of the 16th Century on Henry
Fuseli and His Circle: Rome in the 1770s.” Pp. 76-82, in <hi rend="i">The Anglo-American Artist in Italy
1750-1820.</hi> [Exhb. cat.] ed. Corlette Rossiter Walker. Santa Barbara, Cal.: University Art Museum,
1982.</p>
            <p>155. Michaelis, Sabine. <hi rend="i">Freies Deutsches Hochstift Frankfurter Goethe-Museum:
Katalog der Gemälde</hi>, ed. Detlev Lüders. [Schriften, vol. 26.] Tübingen: Max Niemeyer, 1982. [Includes
a list of the important Fuseli holdings at Frankfurt (cat. nos. 30-36, pp. 19-25), but has nothing new to say
about any of these paintings.]</p>
            <p>156, Weinglass, David H. <hi rend="i">Henry Fuseli and the Engraver’s Art.</hi> [Exhb. cat.]
[UMKC Friends of the Library Publication Series, vol. 4.] Kansas City, Miss.: The University of
Missouri-Kansas City Library, 1982. [Though it is often hard to tell a wash drawing from a stippled engraving
in the reproductions of this catalogue, its text will prove extremely useful for every collector and student
of book illustrations after Fuseli’s designs. Weinglass’ catalogue comes close to a complete inventory of
commercial reproductive engravings after Fuseli and is the most important addition to Fuseli studies of the
year. D.W.D.]</p>
            <p>*157. Woźniakowski, J. “Bohaterowie naszych czasów: Kilka uwag o Fuselim i komiksach
przygodowych.” Pp. 705-11 in <hi rend="i">Ars auro prior: Studia Ioanni Białostocki sexagenario
dedicata.</hi> Warsaw: Pánstwowe Wydawnictwo Naukowe, 1981, pp. 705-11. [An article in the Białostocki 
<hi rend="i">Festschrift</hi> tracing Fuseli’s influence on the “art” of the comic strip.]</p>
            <p>See also items 17, 50, 103, 172, and 197.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">William Hayley</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>158. Chan, Victor. <hi rend="i">William Hayley and His Circle: Leader of My Angels.</hi> [Exhb.
cat.] Edmonton, Alberta: The Edmonton Art Gallery, 1982.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">John Linnell</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>See item 31 and 163.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>159. Brown, David Blayney. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer 1805-1881: Loan Exhibition from the
Ashmolean Museum Oxford.</hi> [Exhb. cat.] London: Hazlitt, Gooden, and Fox, 1982. [The exhibition was
afterwards shown at the National Gallery of Scotland; the catalogue was sold in aid of The Friends of the
Ashmolean Museum.]</p>
            <p>160. Brown, David Blayney. “The Landscapes of Palmer.” <hi rend="i">The National Galleries
of Scotland News</hi>, September-October 1982, p. [2].</p>
            <p>161. <hi rend="i">English Watercolours 1750-1850: First Collection.</hi> Gloucester, Glos.:
Museum Prints, 1982. [This is not a book publication but a set of high-quality color reproductions
(“facsimiles”) which includes three of Palmer’s works from the Ashmolean: “The Valley Thick with
Corn,” and “The Valley with a Bright Cloud,” both of 1825, and “Barn in a Valley (Sepham Farm)” of
c. 1828; the prints in the series may be ordered separately.]</p>
            <p>162. Lister, Raymond G. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer in Palmer Country.</hi> East Bergholt,
Suffolk: Hugh Tempest Radford, 1980.</p>
            <p>163. Wark, Robert R. <hi rend="i">British Landscape Drawings and Watercolors 1750-1850:
Twenty-four Examples from the Huntington Collection.</hi> San Marino, Cal.: Huntington Library, 1981. [Works
by John Linnell, Francis Oliver Finch and Samuel Palmer are included in this selection.]</p>
            <p>See also item 31.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">George Richmond</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>See items 31 and 124.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Henry Crabb Robinson</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>164. Wellens, Oskar. “Henry Crabb Robinson, Reviewer of Wordsworth, Coleridge, and Byron in
the <hi rend="i">Critical Review</hi>: Some New Attributions.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the
Humanities</hi>, 84 (1981), 98-120.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">George Romney</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>See items 50, 124, and 197.</p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p17-70" n="70"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>165. Bennett, Shelley M. “Some Unpublished Landscapes by Thomas Stothard and Their Influence
on John Constable.” <hi rend="i">Master Drawings</hi>, 17 (1979), 273-77.</p>
            <p>166. Rhyne, Charles S. “Constable Drawings and Watercolors in the Collections of Mr. and Mrs.
Paul Mellon and the Yale Center for British Art; Part II: Reattributed Works.” <hi rend="i">Master
Drawings</hi>, 19 (1981), 391-425. [A fair share of these drawings is here attributed to Stothard; see pp.
392-95.]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Josiah Wedgwood</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>167. Cossa, Frank. “Josiah Wedgwood: His Role as a Patron of Flaxman, Stubbs and Wright of
Derby.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 32 (1982), 1325-A. Diss., Rutgers
University, 1982.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Edward Young</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>168. May, James Edward. “A Critical Reader’s Edition of Edward Young’s Satiric Poetry:
<hi rend="i">Love of Fame</hi> and <hi rend="i">Two Epistles to Mr. Pope.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation
Abstracts International</hi>, 43 (1982), 810-A. Diss., University of Maryland, 1981.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part III</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">Works of Related Interest</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>169. Behrendt, Stephen C. “Art as Deceptive Intruder: Audience Entrapment in Eighteenth-Century
Verbal and Visual Art.” <hi rend="i">Papers on Language and Literature</hi>, 19 (1983), 37-52.</p>
          <p>170. Bodgan, Deanne. “Northrop Frye and the Defence of Literature.” <hi rend="i">English
Studies in Canada</hi>, 8 (1982), 203-14.</p>
          <p>171. Brogan, T.V.F. <hi rend="i">English Versification, 1570-1980: A Reference Guide with a
Global Appendix.</hi> Baltimore: The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1981. $47.50.</p>
          <p>*172. Brown, David Blayney. <hi rend="i">Ashmolean Museum Oxford: Catalogue of the Collection of
Drawings</hi>, vol. 4: “The Earlier British Drawings (Artists Born before c. 1775).” Oxford: Clarendon
Press, 1982. [Besides the five Blakes at the Ashmolean, numerous drawings by Barry, Flaxman, Fuseli, 
<hi rend="i">et al.</hi> are listed and described.]</p>
          <p>173. Brown, Norman O. “The Prophetic Tradition.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 21
(1982), 367-86.</p>
          <p>174. Butler, Marilyn. <hi rend="i">Romantics, Rebels, and Reactionaries: English Literature and
its Background 1760-1830.</hi> New York: Oxford University Press, 1982. $17.95.</p>
          <p>*175. Cassavant, Sharron Greer. <hi rend="i">John Middleton Murry: The Critic as Moralist.</hi>
University, Ala.: University of Alabama Press, 1982.</p>
          <p>176. Cave, Kathryn, ed. <hi rend="i">The Diary of Joseph Farington</hi>, vols. 9-10 (January
1808—December 1810). [Studies in British Art.] New Haven, Conn. and London: Yale University Press, for the
Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art, 1982.</p>
          <p>177. Clarke, Michael, and Nicholas Penny, eds. <hi rend="i">The Arrogant Connoisseur: Richard
Payne Knight 1751-1824.</hi> Manchester: Manchester University Press, 1982. £9.50.</p>
          <p>178. Eaves, Morris. “Bread, Politics, and Poetry: Morris Eaves Interviews David and Virginia
Erdman.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 21 (1982), 277-302.</p>
          <p>179. Fite, David Joseph. “Criticism as Scripture: The ‘Belated’ Romanticism of Harold
Bloom.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 43 (1982), 797-A. Diss., University of
Southern California, 1982.</p>
          <p>180. <hi rend="i">Frederick Shields 1833-1911.</hi> [Exhb. cat.] Hartlepool: Hartlepool Borough
Council Department of Leisure and Amenities, for Gray Art Gallery &amp; Museum, 1983. [A tiny 9-page leaflet
with a few illustrations which was published in connection with an exhibition held in Shields’s home-town to
commemorate the 150th anniversary of his birth; Shields is the author of the “Descriptive Notes of the
Designs to Young’s ‘Night Thoughts,’” which were printed in the 2nd edition of Gilchrist’s 
<hi rend="i">Life</hi>; he also published a note “Blake’s Work Room and Death Room” in 1910, which was
illustrated with a reproduction from his drawing of the room.]</p>
          <p>181. Gundry, Doris. <hi rend="i">Petworth.</hi> Pulborough, Sussex: Woodmans &amp; Fittleworth,
[?1981-1982]. [A guide to the house and its collections.]</p>
          <p>*182. Gurewitsch, Susan. “Golgonooza on the Grand Canal: Ruskin’s ‘Stones of Venice’ and
the Romantic Imagination.” <hi rend="i">The Arnoldian: A Review of Mid-Victorian Culture</hi>, 9 (1981),
25-39.</p>
          <p>183. Harper, J. Steven. “The Devotional Life of John Wesley, 1703-38.” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 43 (1982), 188-A. Diss., Duke University, 1981.</p>
          <p>184. Hayes, Elliott. <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> [A play.] Stratford, Ontario: Echo Hill Ltd.,
1983.</p>
          <p>185. Hopkins, James K. <hi rend="i">A Woman to Deliver Her People: Joanna Southcott and English
Millenarianism in an Era of Revolution.</hi> Austin: University of Texas Press, 1982.</p>
          <p>186. Lucas, John. <hi rend="i">Romantic to Modern Literature: Essays and Ideas of Culture,
1750-1900.</hi> Brighton: Harvester, 1982. £18.95.</p>
          <p>187. Matheson, William. “Lessing J. Rosenwald: ‘A Splendidly Generous Man.’ ” 
<hi rend="i">Quarterly Journal of the Library of Congress</hi>, 37 (1980), 2-24.</p>
          <p>188. [McKitterick, David J.] “Sir Geoffrey Keynes.” <hi rend="i">Transactions of the
Cambridge Bibliographical Society</hi>, 8 (1982), 139-40. [An obituary.]</p>
          <p>189. Paulson, Ronald. <hi rend="i">Literary Landscape: Turner and Constable.</hi> New Haven and
London: Yale University Press, 1982.</p>
          <p>190. Pfauch, Wolfgang, and Reinhard Röder. <hi rend="i">C. G. Salzmann-Bibliographie: Unter
Berücksichtigung von Besitznachweisen in Bibliotheken.</hi> Weimar: Hermann Böhlaus Nachf., 1981. [Blake
probably engraved
<pb id="p17-71" n="71"/>
some of the illustrations in Johnson’s English edition of Salzmann’s <hi rend="i">Elements of
Morality</hi>; see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, 1977, item no. 492.]</p>
          <p>191. Rosenblum, Robert. <hi rend="i">Die moderne Malerei und die Tradition der Romantik: Von C.D.
Friedrich zu Mark Rothko</hi>, trsl. Reinhard Kaiser. Munich: Schirmer-Mosel, 1981. [The German edition of
Rosenblum’s study which originally was published in 1975.]</p>
          <p>*192. Rozenberg, Paul. <hi rend="i">Le Romantisme anglais: Le défi des vulnérables.</hi>
[Collection L: Larousse Université.] Paris: Librairie Larousse, 1973.</p>
          <p>193. Salzmann, Christian Gotthilf. <hi rend="i">Moralisches Elementarbuch</hi>, ed. Hubert
Göbels. [Die bibliophilen Taschenbücher, vol. 184.] Dortmund: Harenberg Kommunikation, 1980. [A reprint of
the 1785 edition with Chodowiecki’s engravings on which Blake based his own work for the 
<hi rend="i">Elements of Morality</hi>—if indeed he was the engraver.]</p>
          <p>194. Shanes, Eric. <hi rend="i">The Genius of the Royal Academy.</hi> London: John Murray, for
the Royal Academy, 1981.</p>
          <p>195. Todd, F.C.C. [Francis Christopher]. <hi rend="i">Ruthven Todd (1914-1978): A Preliminary
Finding-List.</hi> Leeds: [mimeographed for the author], 1980. [A bibliographical checklist containing “a
general chronological list, plus a list of miscellaneous unpublished prose works” and “an alphabetical
list of poems” with an index of first lines. This is the third version of the TS, and there are four pages
of addenda, dated February 1981. See also Bentley and Morrish entries, items 11 and 21.]</p>
          <p>196. Todd, Ruthven. “Memoirs,” ed. Robert Latona. <hi rend="i">The Malahat Review</hi>, no.
62 (1982), 8-60.</p>
          <p>197. Walker, Corlette Rossiter, ed. <hi rend="i">The Anglo-American Artist in Italy
1750-1820.</hi> [Exhb. cat.] Santa Barbara, Cal.: University Art Museum, 1982. [Barry, Flaxman, Fuseli,
Angelica, Ottley, Romney, and West amongst others were represented in the exhibition; the catalogue contains a
series of interesting essays written by a group of graduate students of the UCSB’s Art History
Department.]</p>
          <p>198. Willard, Nancy. <hi rend="i">A Visit to William Blake’s Inn: Poems for Innocent and
Experienced Travelers</hi>, illus. by Alice and Martin Provensen. New York, N.Y.: Harcourt Brace Jovanovich,
1981.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part IV</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">Reviews of Works Cited Above and in Previous Checklists</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>199. Ault, Donald D. <hi rend="i">Visionary Physics: Blake’s Response to Newton.</hi> Reviewed
by Dewey R. Faulkner, <hi rend="i">Yale Review</hi>, 64 (1975), 271-74; by Florence Sandler, 
<hi rend="i">Western Humanities Review</hi>, 29 (1975), 301-03; and by Susan Skelton, <hi rend="i">Southern
Humanities Review</hi>, 12 (1978), 389-90.</p>
          <p>200. Bandy, Melanie. <hi rend="i">Mind Forg’d Manacles: Evil in the Poetry of Blake and
Shelley.</hi> Reviewed by William H. Galperin, <hi rend="i">Southern Humanities Review</hi>, 16 (1982),
360-62.</p>
          <p>201. Bentley, G.E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi> Reviewed by Morton D. Paley, 
<hi rend="i">Papers of the Bibliographical Society of America</hi>, 72 (1978), 396-400; by “M.D.”, 
<hi rend="i">English</hi>, 27 (1978), 200-201; and by John E. Grant, <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi>, 61
(1982), 277-304.</p>
          <p>202. Bentley, G.E., Jr., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings.</hi> Reviewed by John Beer,
<hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi>, 76 (1981), 676-82; by John E. Grant, <hi rend="i">Philological
Quarterly</hi>, 61 (1982), 277-304; by Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 111 (1980), 169; and by
Edward J. Rose, <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 21 (1982), 509-14.</p>
          <p>203. Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist.</hi> Reviewed by John Spurling, 
<hi rend="i">New Statesman</hi>, 94 (18 November 1977), 698; and by Adrienne Atkinson, 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 12 (1979), 229-34.</p>
          <p>204. Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">The Complete Graphic Works of William Blake.</hi> Reviewed in
*<hi rend="i">The New Yorker</hi>, 20 November 1978, p. 238.</p>
          <p>205. Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Art and Times.</hi> [Exhb. cat.] Reviewed
(briefly) in <hi rend="i">Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung</hi>, 24 November 1982, p. 25; by Morton D. Paley,
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 124 (1982), 789-90; and by Ruth E. Fine, <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1983), 226-32.</p>
          <p>206. Bindman, David, ed. <hi rend="i">John Flaxman.</hi> [Exhb. cat.] Reviewed by Nicholas Penny,
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 121 (1979), 805-06.</p>
          <p>207. Blake, William. <hi rend="i">The Everlasting Gospel—L’Évangile éternel</hi>, trsl.
Joëlle Abitbol. Reviewed by Krzystof Z. Cieszkowski, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16
(1982), 128-29.</p>
          <p>208. Borgmeier, Raimund. <hi rend="i">Gedichte der englischen Romantik.</hi> Reviewed by Horst
Höhne, <hi rend="i">Zeitschrift für Anglistik und Amerikanistik</hi>, 31 (1983), 66-68. [Includes criticisms
of the selection and the prose translations of Blake’s poems in this anthology.]</p>
          <p>209. Brogan, T.V.F. <hi rend="i">English Versification, 1570-1980: A Reference Guide with a
Global Appendix.</hi> Reviewed by Judith W. Page, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16
(1982), 125-26.</p>
          <p>210. Brown, David Blayney. <hi rend="i">Ashmolean Museum Oxford: Catalogue of the Collection of
Drawings</hi>, vol. 4. Briefly reviewed in <hi rend="i">Gazette des Beaux-Arts</hi>, 6th ser., 101, no. 1369
(1983), “Chronique” 18; and by Judy Egerton, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 125 (1983),
369-70.</p>
          <p>211. Brown, David Blayney. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer 1805-1881.</hi> [Exhb. cat.] Reviewed by
Roy Strong, <hi rend="i">The Financial Times</hi>, 27 July 1982; by William Feaver, <hi rend="i">The
Observer</hi>, 1 August 1982; by Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 124 (1982), 571-73; and
in <hi rend="i">Art Book Review</hi>, 1, no. 3 (1982), 73.</p>
          <p>212. Butler, Marilyn. <hi rend="i">Romantics, Rebels, and Reactionaries: English Literature and
Its Background 1760-1830.</hi> Reviews by Virgil Nemoianu, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Notes</hi>, 97 (1982),
1245-48; by Carl Woodring, <hi rend="i">Blake / An</hi>
	<pb id="p17-72" n="72"/>
	<hi rend="i">Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1983), 232-33; by Jean Raimond, <hi rend="i">Études
Anglaises</hi>, 36, no. 1 (1983), 88-89; and by Tony Boorman, <hi rend="i">English</hi>, 31 (1982),
150-57.</p>
          <p>213. Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by
Michael Mason, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 11 September 1981,
p. 1044; by Jean H. Hagstrum, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi>, 79 (1982), 445-51; by Zachary Leader, 
<hi rend="i">Art Book Review</hi>, 1, no. 1 (1982), 36-43; by David Bindman, <hi rend="i">Burlington
Magazine</hi>, 125 (1983), 370-71; by William Vaughan, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, 5 (1982), 106-09; by
David Brown, <hi rend="i">Art International</hi>, 25 (1982), 111-12; by Kenneth J. Garlick, <hi rend="i">Notes
and Queries</hi>, n.s. 29 (1982), 451-54; by Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1982), 22-65; and by Jerold Ziff, <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi>, 64 (1982), 673-75. [See
also Mary Lynn Johnson’s article, listed above in part I as item 89, as well as a number of contributions to
the Erdman <hi rend="i">Festschrift</hi> which are concerned with the future of Blake studies and—<hi
rend="i">inter alia</hi>—the effect that Butlin’s catalogue will have on it.]</p>
          <p>214. Butter, P.H., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Selected Poems.</hi> Reviewed by D. J.
Enright, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 14 January 1983, p.
29.</p>
          <p>215. Cave, Kathryn, ed. <hi rend="i">The Diary of Joseph Farington</hi>, vols. 7-10. Reviewed in
<hi rend="i">Art Book Review</hi>, 1, no. 2 (1982), 101 [vols. 7-8]; in <hi rend="i">Art Book Review</hi>, 1,
no. 4 (1982), 66 [vols. 9-10]; by Luke Hermann, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 125 (1983), 235-36
[vols. 7-10]. [See also Garlick, Kenneth J., and Angus D. Macintyre, eds., item 232.]</p>
          <p>216. Clarke, Michael, and Nicholas Penny, eds. <hi rend="i">The Arrogant Connoisseur: Richard
Payne Knight 1751-1824.</hi> Reviewed by Richard Jenkyns, <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Memorial Bulletin</hi>,
32 (1982), 75-80.</p>
          <p>217. Cox, Stephen D. <hi rend="i">“The Stranger Within Thee”: Concepts of the Self in Late
Eighteenth-Century Literature.</hi> Reviewed by Eric Rothstein, <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi>, 20
(1982), 66-68.</p>
          <p>218. Crouan, Katharine, ed. <hi rend="i">John Linnell: A Centennial Exhibition.</hi> Reviewed by
Christiana Payne, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 124 (1982), 783-84; and in <hi rend="i">Art Book
Review</hi>, 1, no. 4 (1982), 65. [See also the news release which was published in connection with the
exhibition in <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1982-1983), 184-85.]</p>
          <p>219. Damrosch, Leopold, Jr. <hi rend="i">Symbol and Truth in Blake’s Myth.</hi> Reviewed by
Daniel Karlin, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 26 June 1981, p.
738; by Jacques Blondel, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi>, 35 (1982), 332-33; by Hazard Adams, 
<hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi>, 80 (1983), 316-20; by Robert F. Gleckner, <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi>, 21 (1982), 666-74; and by Morris Eaves, <hi rend="i">JEGP</hi>, 81 (1982), 438-41.</p>
          <p>220. Darwin, Erasmus. <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi>, ed. Donald H. Reiman. Reviewed by
Karina Williamson, <hi rend="i">The Review of English Studies</hi>, 33 (1982), 480-82.</p>
          <p>221. Davis, Michael. <hi rend="i">William Blake: A New Kind of Man.</hi> Reviewed by *Diana Hume
George, <hi rend="i"><corr type="emend">RACAR:</corr> Revue d’Art Canadienne</hi>, 6 (1979), 69-71; by François-Marie Piquet, 
<hi rend="i">Dix-huitième Siècle</hi>, 11 (1979), 528-29; and by “P.v.S.,” <hi rend="i">UNISA English
Studies</hi>, 20 (1982), 73.</p>
          <p>222. Dunbar, Pamela. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Poetry of Milton.</hi>
Reviewed by *Peter Quennell, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 114 (1981), 136-37; by William Vaughan, 
<hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, 5 (1982), 106-09; by Jean-Jacques Mayoux, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi>, 35
(1982), 216-17; and by Desiree Hirst, <hi rend="i">The Review of English Studies</hi>, n.s. 34 (1983),
222-24.</p>
          <p>223. Eaves, Morris. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Theory of Art.</hi> Reviewed by Andrew
Lincoln, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 4 February 1983, p. 111;
and (briefly) in <hi rend="i">Gazette des Beaux-Arts</hi>, 6th ser., 101, no. 1369 (1983), “Chronique”
18.</p>
          <p>224. Engell, James. <hi rend="i">The Creative Imagination.</hi> Reviewed by R. Quintana, 
<hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi>, 77 (1982), 688-89; by Zachary Leader, <hi rend="i">English</hi>, 31
(1982), 252-57; and by L. J. Swingle, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Quarterly</hi>, 43 (1982), 89-97.</p>
          <p>225. Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi>
Briefly reviewed in <hi rend="i">The Malahat Review</hi>, no. 63 (1982), 248.</p>
          <p>226. Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake.</hi> Reviewed by Dewey R.
Faulkner, <hi rend="i">Yale Review</hi>, 64 (1974), 271-74; by Florence Sandler, <hi rend="i">Western
Humanities Review</hi>, 29 (1975), 301-03; and by Pamela M. Dunbar, <hi rend="i">The Yearbook of English
Studies</hi>, 7 (1977), 269-71.</p>
          <p>227. Essick, Robert N., and Donald R. Pearce, eds. <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time.</hi> Reviewed
by Spencer Hall, <hi rend="i">Southern Humanities Review</hi>, 14 (1980), 75-76; and by *Aileen Ward, 
<hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 11 (1980), 160-62.</p>
          <p>228. Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">William Blake, Printmaker.</hi> Reviewed by Michael Mason,
<hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 13 February 1981, p. 169; by
*George Quasha, <hi rend="i">Parabola</hi>, 6 (1981), 97-102; by *Peter Quennell, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>,
114 (1981), 136-37; by John Gage, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, 4 (1981), 470-74; by David Irwin, 
<hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi>, 74, n.s. 43 (1981), 112-13; and by Zachary Leader, <hi rend="i">Art
Book Review</hi>, 1, no. 1 (1982), 36-43.</p>
          <p>229. Essick, Robert N., and Morton D. Paley. <hi rend="i">Robert Blair’s ‘The Grave’
Illustrated by William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by Zachary Leader, <hi rend="i">Art Book Review</hi>, 1, no. 3
(1982), 37-41.</p>
          <p>230. Fox, Susan C. <hi rend="i">Poetic Form in Blake’s ‘Milton’.</hi> Reviewed by *Piloo
Nanavutty, <hi rend="i">Aligarh Journal of English Studies</hi>, 4 (1979), 195-201; by Stanley K. Freiberg,
<hi rend="i">Ariel</hi>, 8, no. 2 (1977), 97-99; and by *Donald Wesling, <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth
Circle</hi>, 8 (1977), 233-36.</p>
          <p>231. Gallant, Christine. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Assimilation of Chaos.</hi> Reviewed by
*Brian Wilkie, <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 11 (1980), 158-59; and by *James Swearingen, 
<hi rend="i">Clio</hi>, 11 (1982), 209-11.</p>
          <p>232. Garlick, Kenneth J., and Angus D. Macintyre, eds. <hi rend="i">The Diary of Joseph
Farington</hi>, vols. 1-6. Reviewed by David Irwin, <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi>, 75, n.s. 44
(1982), 89-91. [See also Cave, Kathryn, ed., item 215.]</p>
          <pb id="p17-73" n="73"/>
          <p>233. George, Diana Hume. <hi rend="i">Blake and Freud.</hi> Reviewed by D.M. Thomas, 
<hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 27 March 1981, p. 332; by Thomas A.
Vogler, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1982), 121-24; and by Zachary Leader, 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 21 (1982), 683-89.</p>
          <p>234. Grant, John E.; Edward J. Rose; and Michael J. Tolley, eds.; <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Designs for Edward Young’s ‘Night Thoughts’: A Complete Edition</hi>, co-ordinating ed. David V. Erdman.
Reviewed by *John Russell Taylor, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times</hi>, 7 October 1980; by
*Daniel Traister, <hi rend="i">ABC</hi>, March-April 1981, pp. 60-73; by Andrew Lincoln, <hi rend="i">The</hi>
[London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 5 June 1981, p. 646; by *Peter Quennell, 
<hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 114 (1981), 136-37; by Dennis Welch and Joseph Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Philological
Quarterly</hi>, 60 (1981), 539-42; by William Vaughan, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, 5 (1982), 106-09; by
Robert Halsband, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi>, 84 (1982), 576-77; by Detlef W.
Dörrbecker, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1982), 130-39; by W.J.T. Mitchell, 
<hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi>, 80 (1982), 198-205; and by Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi>, 21 (1982), 674-82.</p>
          <p>235. Gundry, Doris. <hi rend="i">Petworth.</hi> Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Art Book Review</hi>, 1,
no. 2 (1982), 100.</p>
          <p>236. Hagstrum, Jean H. <hi rend="i">Sex and Sensibility.</hi> Reviewed by Calvin S. Brown, 
<hi rend="i">Comparative Literature</hi>, 33 (1981), 277-79; by Douglas Brooks-Davies, <hi rend="i">Modern
Language Review</hi>, 77 (1982), 150-53; by Arthur Sherbo, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi>, 79 (1982),
323-26; by Alain Morvan, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi>, 35 (1982), 436-37; by Patricia Meyer Spacks, 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 16 (1982-1983), 175-78; and by Jeffrey C. Robinson, 
<hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi>, 20 (1982), 63-66.</p>
          <p>237. Haskell, Francis, and Nicholas Penny. <hi rend="i">Taste and the Antique.</hi> Reviewed by
John Gage, <hi rend="i">Art Book Review</hi>, 1, no. 1 (1982), 63-65; by Peter Gerlach, <hi rend="i">Kritische
Berichte</hi>, 10, no. 2 (1982), 61-65; by Jennifer Montagu, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, 5 (1982), 117-19;
and by Michele H. Bogart, <hi rend="i">The Georgia Review</hi>, 36 (1982), 208-12. [Earlier reviews of this
exhibition handbook appeared in 1981-1982 in <hi rend="i">The New York Times Book Review, The New York Review
of Books</hi> (by Horst W. Janson), the London <hi rend="i">Sunday Times</hi> (by J.W. Lambert), the London
<hi rend="i">Daily Telegraph</hi> (by Terence Mullaly), the <hi rend="i">Connoisseur</hi> (by Godfrey Barker),
<hi rend="i">The New Republic</hi> (by Joseph Alsop), and the <hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi> (by Sir
Ernst H. Gombrich); the exhibition itself, as shown at the Ashmolean, was reviewed by Alex Potts, 
<hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 10 April 1981, p. 407.]</p>
          <p>238. Hayes, Elliott. <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> Reviewed by Katherine Doud, <hi rend="i">Kalamazoo
Gazette</hi>, 20 June 1983.</p>
          <p>239. Hodnett, Edward. <hi rend="i">Image and Text.</hi> Reviewed by William Feaver, 
<hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 2 July 1982, p. 722.</p>
          <p>240. Honour, Hugh. <hi rend="i">Romanticism.</hi> Reviewed by Martin Lebowitz, 
<hi rend="i">Southern Review</hi>, 19 (1983), 247-50.</p>
          <p>241. Hopkins, James K. <hi rend="i">A Woman to Deliver Her People: Joanna Southcott and English
Millenarianism in an Era of Revolution.</hi> Reviewed by David Martin, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 26 November 1982, pp. 1287-88.</p>
          <p>242. Hutchings, Bill. <hi rend="i">The Poetry of William Cowper.</hi> Croon Helm, £12.95.
Reviewed by Pat Rogers, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 8 April
1983, p. 343.</p>
          <p>243. Irwin, David. <hi rend="i">John Flaxman 1755-1826.</hi> Reviewed by Nicholas Penny, 
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 121 (1979), 805-06; and by *N. Llewellyn, <hi rend="i">British Journal of
Aesthetics</hi>, 21 (1981), 376-78.</p>
          <p>244. Jackson, J.R. de. <hi rend="i">Poetry of the Romantic Period.</hi> Reviewed by E.B. Murray,
<hi rend="i">The Review of English Studies</hi>, 33 (1982), 209-13; by Jacques Blondel, <hi rend="i">Études
Anglaises</hi>, 35 (1982), 334; and by Charles Sherry, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi>, 78 (1983),
153-54.</p>
          <p>245. Jackson, Wallace. <hi rend="i">The Probable and the Marvellous: Blake, Wordsworth, and the
Eighteenth-Century Critical Tradition.</hi> Reviewed by Leslie Tannenbaum, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century
Studies</hi>, 15 (1982), 463-67.</p>
          <p>246. James, David E. <hi rend="i">Written Within and Without: A Study of Blake’s
‘Milton’.</hi> Reviewed by Stephen Pritchard, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>, n.s. 27 (1980),
551-52.</p>
          <p>247. Keynes, Geoffrey L. <hi rend="i">The Gates of Memory.</hi> Reviewed in <hi rend="i">The
Bookseller</hi>, 19 September 1981, p. 1062; by Anthony Quinton, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] 
<hi rend="i">Times</hi>, 22 October 1981; by Rebecca West, <hi rend="i">The Sunday Telegraph</hi> (London), 25
October 1981, p. 12; by Robert Chesshyre, <hi rend="i">The Observer</hi>, 25 October 1981; by Peter Quennell,
<hi rend="i">Evening Standard</hi>, 28 October 1981; by Nigel Nicolson, <hi rend="i">The Financial Times</hi>,
31 October 1981; by Nicolas Barker, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary
Supplement</hi>, 6 November 1981, p. 1290; in <hi rend="i">The Economist</hi>, 21 November 1981; and by Morton
D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1983), 233-35.</p>
          <p>248. Keynes, Geoffrey L., ed. <hi rend="i">The Letters of William Blake</hi>, 3rd rev. ed.
Reviewed by *Peter Quennell, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 114 (1981), 136-37; and by Jacques Blondel, 
<hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi>, 35 (1982), 331-32.</p>
          <p>249. King, James, and Charles Ryskamp, eds. <hi rend="i">William Cowper: The Letters and Prose
Writings.</hi> Reviewed by Pierre Danchin, <hi rend="i">English Studies</hi>, 63 (1982), 177-78 [Vol. I]; by
John Barrell, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi>, n.s. 33 (1982), 476-77 [Vol. I]; and by Pat Rogers,
<hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 8 April 1983, p. 343 [Vols.
I-III].</p>
          <p>250. King-Hele, Desmond, ed. <hi rend="i">The Letters of Erasmus Darwin.</hi> Reviewed by Redmond
O’Hanlon, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 19 March 1982, pp.
299-300.</p>
          <p>251. Klonsky, Milton. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Dante.</hi> Reviewed by Tom Phillips, 
<hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 13 February 1981, p. 169; by *George
Quasha, <hi rend="i">Parabola</hi>,
<pb id="p17-74" n="74"/>
6 (1981), 97-102; by *Ron Padgett, <hi rend="i">Drawing</hi>, 2 (1981), 134-35.</p>
          <p>252. Klonsky, Milton. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Seer and His Visions.</hi> Reviewed by John
Spurling, <hi rend="i">New Statesman</hi>, 94 (18 November 1977), 698.</p>
          <p>253. Leader, Zachary. <hi rend="i">Reading Blake’s ‘Songs’.</hi> Reviewed by David Bindman,
<hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 4 September 1981, p. 1017; by Mary
Lynn Johnson, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi>, 84 (1982), 572-76; by Jacques
Blondel, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi>, 35 (1982), 333-34; and by Stephen Gill, <hi rend="i">Essays in
Criticism</hi>, 33 (1983), 49-55.</p>
          <p>254. Leyris, Pierre, ed. <hi rend="i">Oeuvres de William Blake</hi>, vol. 2. Reviewed by
Pierre-François Moreau, <hi rend="i">Nouvelle Revue française</hi>, no. 303 (1 April 1978), 137-38.</p>
          <p>255. Lindberg, Bo. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Book of Job.</hi> Reviewed
by Henry Summerfield, <hi rend="i">Malahat Review</hi>, no. 42 (1977), 132-35.</p>
          <p>256. Lindsay, Jack. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by *Joan Digby, 
<hi rend="i">Library Journal</hi>, 104 (1979), 953; by Milton Klonsky, <hi rend="i">Commentary</hi>, 68 (1979),
84-86; and by *H. Boone Porter, <hi rend="i">Anglican Theological Review</hi>, 63 (1981), 105-06.</p>
          <p>257. Lister, Raymond G., et al. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer: A Vision Recaptured</hi>, exhb. cat.
Reviewed in *<hi rend="i">Old Water-Colour Society’s Club</hi>, 54 (1979), 53-55.</p>
          <p>258. Lister, Raymond G. <hi rend="i">George Richmond.</hi> Reviewed by Martin Butlin, 
<hi rend="i">Art Book Review</hi>, 1, no. 2 (1982), 53-55.</p>
          <p>259. Lucas, John. <hi rend="i">Romantic to Modern Literature: Essays and Ideas of Culture,
1750-1900.</hi> Reviewed by Graham Hough, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary
Supplement</hi>, 4 March 1983, p. 217.</p>
          <p>260. Mitchell, W.J.T. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art.</hi> Reviewed by François-Marie
Piquet, <hi rend="i">Dix-huitième Siècle</hi>, 11 (1979), 529-30; by John Beer, <hi rend="i">Modern Language
Review</hi>, 76 (1981), 676-82; and by Elaine Kreizman, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Notes</hi>, 94 (1979),
1250-57.</p>
          <p>261. Ostriker, Alicia, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Complete Poems.</hi> Briefly reviewed
by “M.D.,” <hi rend="i">English</hi>, 27 (1978), 200-01.</p>
          <p>262. Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by William Vaughan, 
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 121 (1979), 394; and by *Edwin Wolf [2nd], <hi rend="i">Fine Print</hi>, 5
(1979), 60-61.</p>
          <p>263. Paulson, Ronald. <hi rend="i">Literary Landscape: Turner and Constable.</hi> Reviewed by
John Barrell, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 7 January 1983, p.
8.</p>
          <p>264. Phillips, Michael, ed. <hi rend="i">Interpreting Blake.</hi> Reviewed by John Beer, 
<hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi>, 76 (1981), 676-82.</p>
          <p>265. Pressly, Nancy L. <hi rend="i">The Fuseli Circle in Rome</hi>, exhb. cat. Reviewed by *T.G.
Greenspan, <hi rend="i">Pantheon</hi>, 38 (1980), 36-37; and by [Anne-Marie S. Logan], <hi rend="i">Master
Drawings</hi>, 18 (1980), 54-55.</p>
          <p>266. Pressly, William L. <hi rend="i">The Life and Art of James Barry.</hi> Reviewed by Peter
Funnell, <hi rend="i">Oxford Art Journal</hi>, 4, no. 2 (1981), 64-66; by David Bindman, <hi rend="i">New
Statesman</hi>, 102 (11 September 1981), 19-20; by Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 30 October 1981, p. 1251; and by David Brown, <hi rend="i">Art Book
Review</hi>, 1, no. 1 (1982), 58-60.</p>
          <p>267. Pressly, William L. <hi rend="i">James Barry: The Artist as Hero</hi>, exhb. cat. Reviewed
by Marc Jordan, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 4 March 1983, p.
213; and by David Bindman, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 125 (1983), 241-42.</p>
          <p>268. Raine, Kathleen J. <hi rend="i">Blake and the New Age.</hi> Reviewed by *Helen McNeil, 
<hi rend="i">Spectator</hi>, 14 December 1979, pp. 943-44; and by *Julie Howe Stewart, <hi rend="i">Journal of
Religion</hi>, 61 (1981), 445-47.</p>
          <p>269. Raine, Kathleen J. <hi rend="i">The Human Face of God: William Blake and the Book of
Job.</hi> Reviewed by Michael Mason, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary
Supplement</hi>, 16 April 1982, p. 432; by Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 124 (1982),
772-73; and by Zachary Leader, <hi rend="i">Art Book Review</hi>, 1, no. 3 (1982), 37-41.</p>
          <p>270. Ritz, Regis. <hi rend="i">Le Théâtre de Richard Cumberland.</hi> Reviewed by Arnold Hare,
<hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi>, 36, no. 1 (1983), 80-82.</p>
          <p>271. Rozenberg, Paul. <hi rend="i">Le Romantisme anglais: Le défi des vulnérables.</hi>
Reviewed by Helmut Viebrock, <hi rend="i">Archiv für das Studium der neueren Sprachen und Literaturen</hi>,
219 (1982), 188-92.</p>
          <p>272. Scholz, Joachim J. <hi rend="i">Blake and Novalis.</hi> Reviewed by Alain Montandon, 
<hi rend="i">Romantisme</hi>, 9 (1979), 253.</p>
          <p>273. Shroyer, Richard J., ed. <hi rend="i">Aphorisms on Man</hi> (<hi rend="i">1788</hi>) 
<hi rend="i">by Johann Caspar Lavater.</hi> Reviewed by Jenijoy LaBelle, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1982), 126-28.</p>
          <p>274. Stock, R. D. <hi rend="i">The Holy and the Daemonic from Sir Thomas Browne to William
Blake.</hi> Reviewed by Anya Taylor, <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi>, 25 (1983), 75-79.</p>
          <p>275. Tannenbaum, Leslie. <hi rend="i">Biblical Tradition in Blake’s Early Prophecies.</hi>
Reviewed by Andrew Lincoln, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 30
July 1982, p. 838.</p>
          <p>276. Tyson, Gerald P. <hi rend="i">Joseph Johnson: A Liberal Publisher.</hi> Reviewed by O.M.
Brack, Jr., <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 15 (1982), 484-85.</p>
          <p>277. Vaughan, William. <hi rend="i">German Romanticism and English Art.</hi> Reviewed by Frank
Büttner, <hi rend="i">Kunstchronik</hi>, 35 (1982), 469-79.</p>
          <p>278. Weinglass, David H., ed. <hi rend="i">The Collected English Letters of Henry Fuseli.</hi>
Reviewed by Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">Art Book Review</hi>, 1, no. 4 (1982), 32-33.</p>
          <p>279. Wendorf, Richard. <hi rend="i">William Collins and Eighteenth-Century Poetry.</hi> Reviewed
by Patricia Meyer Spacks, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Quarterly</hi>, 43 (1982), 179-81.</p>
          <p>280. Wilkie, Brian, and Mary Lynn Johnson. <hi rend="i">Blake’s ‘Four Zoas’: The Design of
a Dream.</hi> Reviewed by John Beer, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi>, 76 (1981), 676-82; by Jacques
Blondel, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi>, 36 (1982), 82-83; and by C. C. Barfoot, <hi rend="i">English
Studies</hi>, 60 (1979), 770 [with
<pb id="p17-75" n="75"/>
brief mentions of Lindsay’s 1978 biography and Jackson’s <hi rend="i">The Probable and the Marvelous</hi>
on pp. 770-71].</p>
          <p>281. Willard, Nancy. <hi rend="i">A Visit to William Blake’s Inn.</hi> Reviewed in 
<hi rend="i">Michigan Quarterly Review</hi>, 21 (1982), 220.</p>
          <p>282. “William Blake: His Art and Times.” [Exhibition.] Yale Center for British Art, Autumn,
1982. Reviewed by L. N., <hi rend="i">Vogue</hi>, October, 1982, p. 82.</p>
          <p>283. Wittreich, Joseph A., Jr. <hi rend="i">Visionary Poetics: Milton’s Tradition and
Legacy.</hi> Reviewed by J.M.Q. Davies, <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi>, 75, n.s. 44 (1982),
109-10.</p>
          <p>284. Young, Howard T. <hi rend="i">The Line in the Margin: Juan Ramón Jiménez and His Readings
in Blake, Shelley, and Yeats.</hi> Reviewed by John C. Wilcox, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Notes</hi>, 96
(1981), 457-59; by the same, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1983), 235-39.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Index to Authors</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Abitbol, Joëlle 207</p>
          <p>Ackland, Michael 36</p>
          <p>Adams, Hazard 37, 43, 219</p>
          <p>Ahearn, Edward J. 38</p>
          <p>Alford, Steven Edward 39</p>
          <p>Alsop, Joseph 237</p>
          <p>Atkins, A. M. 149</p>
          <p>Atkinson, Adrienne 203</p>
          <p>Ault, Donald D. 133, 199</p>
          <p>Baker, John Steven 41</p>
          <p>Bandy, Melanie 200</p>
          <p>Barfoot, C. C. 280</p>
          <p>Barker, Godfrey 237</p>
          <p>Barker, Nicolas 247</p>
          <p>Barrell, John 249, 263</p>
          <p>Beer, John 202, 260, 264, 280</p>
          <p>Behrendt, Stephen C. 169</p>
          <p>Bennett, Shelley M. 165</p>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. 11, 16, 42, 201, 202</p>
          <p>Bertholf, Robert J. 43</p>
          <p>Bindman, David 12, 44, 203, 204, 205, 206, 213, 253, 266, 267</p>
          <p>Bircher, Martin 150</p>
          <p>Blois, R. E. 45</p>
          <p>Blondel, Jacques 219, 244, 248, 253, 280</p>
          <p>Bloom, Harold 6</p>
          <p>Bodgan, Deanne 170</p>
          <p>Bogan, James 46, 47</p>
          <p>Bogart, Michele H. 237</p>
          <p>Bohrer, Karl Heinz 48</p>
          <p>Boorman, Tony 212</p>
          <p>Borgmeier, Raimund 208</p>
          <p>Brack, O.M., Jr. 276</p>
          <p>Brogan, T.V.F. 171, 209</p>
          <p>Brooks-Davies, Douglas 236</p>
          <p>Brown, Calvin S. 236</p>
          <p>Brown, David 213, 266</p>
          <p>Brown, David Blayney 159, 160, 172, 210, 211</p>
          <p>Brown, Douglas C. 1</p>
          <p>Brown, Norman O. 173</p>
          <p>Butler, Marilyn 174, 212</p>
          <p>Butlin, Martin 49, 211, 213, 258, 278</p>
          <p>Butter, P.H. 2, 214</p>
          <p>Büttner, Frank 277</p>
          <p>Carr, Stephen Leo 151</p>
          <p>Cassavant, Sharron Greer 175</p>
          <p>Cassirer, Else 7</p>
          <p>Cave, Kathryn 176, 215</p>
          <p>Chan, Victor 50, 158</p>
          <p>Chatwin, Deryn 51</p>
          <p>Chesshyre, Robert 247</p>
          <p>Cieszkowski, Krzystof Z. 207</p>
          <p>Clarke, Michael 177, 216</p>
          <p>Cossa, Frank 167</p>
          <p>Corti, Claudia 52</p>
          <p>Cox, Stephen D. 53, 217</p>
          <p>Crouan, Katharine 218</p>
          <p>Cumberland, George 5</p>
          <p>Damrosch, Leopold, Jr. 54, 219</p>
          <p>Danchin, Pierre 249</p>
          <p>Davies, J.M.Q. 55, 283.</p>
          <p>Davis, Michael 221</p>
          <p>Dawson, P.M.S. 140</p>
          <p>De Luca, V.A. 56, 57, 133</p>
          <p>Dennis, Rodney G. 145</p>
          <p>Digby, Joan 256</p>
          <p>Dörrbecker, Detlef W. 19, 234</p>
          <p>Doskow, Minna 43, 58</p>
          <p>Doud, Katherine 238</p>
          <p>Drougas, James 4</p>
          <p>Dunbar, Pamela 222, 226</p>
          <p>Easson, Roger 47</p>
          <p>Eaves, Morris 47, 59, 60, 133, 178, 219, 223</p>
          <p>Edwards, Gavin 133</p>
          <p>Egerton, Judy 146, 210</p>
          <p>Engell, James 224</p>
          <p>Enright, D.J. 214</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V. 6, 13, 14, 15, 61, 62, 225, 226, 234</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N. 63, 64, 65, 88, 213, 227, 228, 229</p>
          <p>Faulkner, Dewey R. 199, 226</p>
          <p>Feaver, William 211, 239</p>
          <p>Fergensen, Laraine 66</p>
          <p>Fine, Ruth E. 205</p>
          <p>Fischer, Michael 133</p>
          <p>Fite, David Joseph 179</p>
          <p>Fogel, A. 67</p>
          <p>Fox, Susan C. 230</p>
          <p>Freiberg, Stanley K. 230</p>
          <p>Fuller, David S. 68</p>
          <p>Funnell, Peter 266</p>
          <p>Gage, John 228, 237</p>
          <p>Gallant, Christine 231</p>
          <p>Garlick, Kenneth J. 213, 232</p>
          <p>Galperin, William H. 200</p>
          <p>George, Diana Hume 221, 233</p>
          <p>Gerlach, Peter 237</p>
          <p>Gilchrist, Alexander 69</p>
          <p>Gill, Stephen 253</p>
          <p>Glazer, Myra 43</p>
          <p>Gleckner, Robert F. 43, 70, 71, 72, 73, 74, 219</p>
          <p>Göbels, Hubert 193</p>
          <p>Gombrich, Ernst H. 237</p>
          <p>Grant, John E. 16, 75, 76, 91, 201, 202, 234</p>
          <p>Grate, Pontus 147</p>
          <p>Greenberg, Mark L. 77</p>
          <p>Greenspan, T.G. 265</p>
          <p>Gundry, Doris 181, 235</p>
          <p>Gurewitsch, Susan 182</p>
          <p>Hagstrum, Jean H. 213, 236</p>
          <p>Hahn, Karl-Friedrich 152, 153</p>
          <p>Hall, Spencer 227</p>
          <p>Halsband, Robert 234</p>
          <p>Hampsey, John Coleman 78</p>
          <p>Hanke, Amala M. 79</p>
          <p>Hare, Arnold 270</p>
          <p>Harper, J. Steven 183</p>
          <p>Haskell, Francis 237</p>
          <p>Hayes, Elliott 184, 238</p>
          <p>Heppner, Christopher 80</p>
          <p>Hermann, Luke 215</p>
          <p>Hilton, Nelson 81, 82</p>
          <p>Hirst, Desiree 222</p>
          <p>Hodnett, Edward 83, 239</p>
          <p>Hohl, Hanna 124</p>
          <p>Höhne, Horst 208</p>
          <p>Holmes, John R. 84</p>
          <p>Honour, Hugh 240</p>
          <p>Hopkins, James K. 185, 241</p>
          <p>Horn, William Dennis 43</p>
          <p>Hough, Graham 259</p>
          <p>Hutchings, Bill 242</p>
          <p>Hyland, Dominic 85</p>
          <p>Ide, Nancy Marie 86</p>
          <p>Irwin, David 228, 232, 243</p>
          <p>Jackson, J. R. de 244</p>
          <p>Jackson, Wallace 245</p>
          <p>James, David E. 87, 246</p>
          <p>James, G. Ingli 88</p>
          <p>Janson, Horst W. 237</p>
          <p>Jenkyns, Richard 216</p>
          <p>Johnson, Mary Lynn 89, 90, 91, 213, 253, 280</p>
          <p>Jordan, Marc 267</p>
          <p>Kaltenbrunner, Gerd-Klaus 92</p>
          <p>Karlin, Daniel 219</p>
          <p>Katsuya, Hiromoto 93</p>
          <p>Kauffmann, C.M. 17</p>
          <p>Keynes, Geoffrey L. 247, 248</p>
          <p>King, James 141, 249</p>
          <p>King-Hele, Desmond 144, 250</p>
          <p>Klonsky, Milton 251, 252, 256</p>
          <p>Kohl, Norbert 8</p>
          <p>Kraus, Christina Shuttleworth 121</p>
          <p>Kreizman, Elaine 260</p>
          <p>Kroeber, Karl 94</p>
          <p>Kumbier, William Allen 95</p>
          <p>LaBelle, Jenijoy 273</p>
          <p>Lambert, J. W. 237</p>
          <p>Land, Melinda 154</p>
          <p>Lange, Thomas V. 96</p>
          <p>Latona, Robert 196</p>
          <p>Leader, Zachary 213, 224, 228, 229, 233, 253, 269</p>
          <p>Lebowitz, Martin 240</p>
          <p>Lee, Judith 97</p>
          <p>Levin, Susan 43</p>
          <p>Levitt, Annette S. 43</p>
          <p>Leyris, Pierre 254</p>
          <p>Lincoln, Andrew 98, 223, 234, 275</p>
          <p>Lindberg, Bo 255</p>
          <p>Lindsay, Jack 256</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond G. 162, 257, 258</p>
          <p>Llewellyn, N. 243</p>
          <p>Logan, Anne-Marie S. 265</p>
          <p>Loudon, Michael Douglas 99</p>
          <p>Lucas, John 186, 259</p>
          <p>Lucie-Smith, Edward 100</p>
          <p>Lüders, Detlev 155</p>
          <p>Lyle, Janice S. 148</p>
          <p>Macintyre, Angus D. 232</p>
          <p>Magno, Concettina Tramontano 101</p>
          <p>Mahon, W. D. Maxwell 102</p>
          <p>Mann, Paul 133</p>
          <p>Martin, David 241</p>
          <p>Martin, Floyd Weatherby 103</p>
          <p>Mason, Michael 88, 213, 228, 269</p>
          <p>Matheson, William 187</p>
          <p>Mathews, Lawrence 104</p>
          <p>May, James Edward 168</p>
          <p>Mayoux, Jean-Jacques 222</p>
          <p>McCord, James 18</p>
          <p>McKitterick, David J. 188</p>
          <p>McNeil, Helen 268</p>
          <pb id="p17-76" n="76"/>
          <p>Mellor, Anne K. 105</p>
          <p>Michaelis, Sabine 155</p>
          <p>Miller, Dan Clinton 106</p>
          <p>Miner, Paul 107</p>
          <p>Minnick, Thomas L. 19</p>
          <p>Mitchell, W. J. T. 108, 133, 234, 260</p>
          <p>Montagu, Jennifer 237</p>
          <p>Montandon, Alain 272</p>
          <p>Moreau, Pierre-François 254</p>
          <p>Morrish, P. S. 21</p>
          <p>Morvan, Alain 236</p>
          <p>Mullaly, Terence 237</p>
          <p>Murphy, Karleen Middleton 47</p>
          <p>Murray, E. B. 47, 244</p>
          <p>Nanavutty, Piloo 230</p>
          <p>Natoli, Joseph P. 22</p>
          <p>Nemoianu, Virgil 212</p>
          <p>Newey, Vincent 23</p>
          <p>Nicolson, Nigel 247</p>
          <p>Niimi, Hatsuko 109</p>
          <p>O’Hanlon, Redmond 250</p>
          <p>Ostriker, Alicia 43, 110, 133, 261</p>
          <p>Ostrom, Hans 111</p>
          <p>Pace, Claire 112</p>
          <p>Padgett, Ron 251</p>
          <p>Page, Judith W. 209</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D. 113, 133, 201, 205, 229, 234, 247, 262, 269</p>
          <p>Parini, Jay 43</p>
          <p>Paulson, Ronald 189, 263</p>
          <p>Payne, Christiana 218</p>
          <p>Pearce, Donald R. 227</p>
          <p>Pease, Donald 43</p>
          <p>Penny, Nicholas 177, 206, 216, 237, 243</p>
          <p>Pfauch, Wolfgang 190</p>
          <p>Phillips, Michael 264</p>
          <p>Phillips, Tom 251</p>
          <p>Piquet, François-Marie 114, 221, 260</p>
          <p>Porter, H. Boone 256</p>
          <p>Potts, Alex 237</p>
          <p>Pressly, Nancy L. 265</p>
          <p>Pressly, William L. 139, 266, 267</p>
          <p>Pritchard, Stephen 246</p>
          <p>Punter, David 115</p>
          <p>Quasha, George 228, 251</p>
          <p>Quennell, Peter 222, 228, 234, 247, 248</p>
          <p>Quintana, R. 224</p>
          <p>Quinton, Anthony 247</p>
          <p>Radford, Jean 21</p>
          <p>Ragghianti, Carlo Ludovico 116</p>
          <p>Raimond, Jean 212</p>
          <p>Raine, Kathleen J. 117, 268, 269</p>
          <p>Rao, Valli 118</p>
          <p>Read, Dennis M. 119, 120</p>
          <p>Redmond, James 23, 24, 32, 33, 34</p>
          <p>Rees, Abraham 9</p>
          <p>Reiman, Donald H. 121, 220</p>
          <p>Reynolds, Graham 201, 266</p>
          <p>Rhyne, Charles S. 166</p>
          <p>Ritz, Regis 143, 270</p>
          <p>Roberts-Jones, Philippe 122</p>
          <p>Robinson, Jeffrey C. 236</p>
          <p>Robinson, K. E. 24</p>
          <p>Roe, Albert 47</p>
          <p>Roeder, Reinhard 190</p>
          <p>Rogers, Deborah D. 142</p>
          <p>Rogers, Pat 242, 249</p>
          <p>Rose, Edward J. 202, 234</p>
          <p>Rosenblum, Robert 191</p>
          <p>Rothstein, Eric 217</p>
          <p>Rozenberg, Paul 192, 271</p>
          <p>Rumsby, R. L. 123</p>
          <p>Ryskamp, Charles 141, 249</p>
          <p>Sanzo, Eileen 43</p>
          <p>Sandler, Florence 199, 226</p>
          <p>Schaar, Eckhard 124</p>
          <p>Scholz, Joachim J. 272</p>
          <p>Schwartz, Howard 47</p>
          <p>Searle, Leroy 43</p>
          <p>Shanes, Eric 194</p>
          <p>Shaviro, Steven 125</p>
          <p>Sherbo, Arthur 236</p>
          <p>Sherry, Charles 244</p>
          <p>Shroyer, Richard J. 10, 273</p>
          <p>Sinderen, Adrian van 126</p>
          <p>Skelton, Susan 199</p>
          <p>Smith, Mark Trevor 127</p>
          <p>Smith, Michael 25, 26, 27, 28, 29</p>
          <p>Spacks, Patricia Meyer 236, 279</p>
          <p>Spurling, John 203, 252</p>
          <p>Stempel, Daniel 133</p>
          <p>Stewart, Julie Howe 268</p>
          <p>Stock, R. D. 274</p>
          <p>Storch, Margaret 133</p>
          <p>Strong, Roy 211</p>
          <p>Summerfield, Henry 255</p>
          <p>Swearingen, James 231</p>
          <p>Swingle, L. J. 224</p>
          <p>Tannenbaum, Leslie 245, 275</p>
          <p>Taylor, Anya 274</p>
          <p>Taylor, John Russell 234</p>
          <p>Taylor, Ronald C. 128</p>
          <p>Thomas, D. M. 233</p>
          <p>Todd, F. C. C. 195</p>
          <p>Todd, Ruthven 69, 196</p>
          <p>Tolley, Michael J. 234</p>
          <p>Traister, Daniel 234</p>
          <p>Tyson, Gerald P. 276</p>
          <p>Ueberle, Maja 8</p>
          <p>Vaughan, William 30, 213, 222, 234, 262, 277</p>
          <p>Viebrock, Helmut 271</p>
          <p>Viscomi, Joseph 31, 129, 130, 131, 132, 234</p>
          <p>Vogler, Thomas A. 133, 233</p>
          <p>Walker, Corlette Rossiter 148, 154, 197</p>
          <p>Wark, Robert R. 163</p>
          <p>Ward, Aileen 227</p>
          <p>Watson, J. R. 32, 33, 34</p>
          <p>Webster, Brenda S. 134</p>
          <p>Weinglass, David H. 156, 278</p>
          <p>Welch, Dennis 234</p>
          <p>Wellens, Oskar 164</p>
          <p>Wendorf, Richard 279</p>
          <p>Wesling, Donald 230</p>
          <p>West, Rebecca 247</p>
          <p>Whitehead, Fred 47</p>
          <p>Wilcox, John C. 284</p>
          <p>Wilkie, Brian 231, 280</p>
          <p>Willard, Nancy 198, 281</p>
          <p>Williams, Porter, Jr. 135</p>
          <p>Williamson, Karina 220</p>
          <p>Wittreich, Joseph A., Jr. 283</p>
          <p>Wolf, Edwin, [2nd] 262</p>
          <p>Woodring, Carl 212</p>
          <p>Worrall, David 136</p>
          <p>Wózniakowski, J. 157</p>
          <p>Wright, John W. 35</p>
          <p>Wright, Warren Keith 137</p>
          <p>Wyler, Stephen 138</p>
          <p>Young, Howard T. 284</p>
          <p>Ziff, Jerold 213</p>
          <p>Zimmerman, Daniel 47</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
