<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>17.3.dorrbecker</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Joachim J. Scholz, Blake and Novalis: A Comparison of Romanticism’s High
Arguments</title>
        <author n="Dörrbecker">Detlef W. Dörrbecker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1983-1984</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1983-84</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">17.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistant in Charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <name>Chapel Petty</name>
              <name>Dennis Kane</name>
              <name>Karen Sunde</name>
              <name>Tom Elder</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Hazard Adams</name>
              <name>Detlef Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Sheila Spector</name>
              <name>Dena Taylor</name>
              <name>Nicholas Warner</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Welch</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1983-1984"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_17">
    <body>
	<pb id="p17-111" n="111"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-17-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Joachim J. Scholz. <hi rend="i">Blake and Novalis: A Comparison of
Romanticism’s High Arguments.</hi> Frankfurt am Main, Bern, Las Vegas: Peter Lang, 1978. [“European
University Papers,” Series XVIII: Comparative Literature, vol. 19]. 397 pp., SFr. 64.00</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Detlef W.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Dörrbecker</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>This rather expensive book, reproduced photographically from the corrected typescript, contains
Joachim Scholz’s Ph.D. thesis, written under the guidance of such literary critics as Victor Turner, Manfred
Hoppe, and Edith Hartnett at the University of Chicago. A comparative study may investigate the reception and
remodeling of one poet’s works in the writings of another author, and this is what all the recent
publications on Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> have in common, despite their otherwise differing
approaches. Or a comparative study may make a parallel investigation of the formal and iconographical concepts
of two or more poets who were contemporaries of each other, and this is what Scholz attempts in 
<hi rend="i">Blake and Novalis.</hi> (The same subject has been dealt with before in a short essay by Jean Wahl,
in Jacques Roos’s study of Boehme’s and Swedenborg’s influence on early romanticism, and, more recently,
in the dissertations of Susan Skelton and Amala M. Hanke.)</p>
          <p>Joachim J. Scholz might have written a rewarding and competent book on either Novalis or Blake.
The strictures hinted at in the following notes come in where he tries to write on both of these poets at the
same time. Thus where I disagree with the results of his study I deal with more general problems in
methodology which by no means are those of Scholz alone. What makes two poets comparable? Is it their
biography?—certainly not as long as we try to take poetry as an independent and peculiar mode of gaining
knowledge. Is it their subject matter or their style?—though the emphasis is clearly on the former, Scholz
sometimes attempts to work both fields. If, nevertheless, I argue that his book fails where he actually
compares the German romantic with the London poet and painter, it is because of a “mechanical
parallelization” which takes style and subject matter as only loosely connected, and leaves the level of
creative method (which initially unifies the realms of style and content) unexamined. Comparability in
literature must have to do with similar workings of the poetic imagination, and the use of comparable methods
of molding the material which outward experience supplies must be more important than the arbitrary allusions
in any two poets’ “<hi rend="i">high</hi> arguments.”</p>
          <p>Knowing what I knew about the subject matter, the imagery, and the style of Blake’s and
Novalis’ major works, I could not imagine that an attempt to compare (for example) the <hi rend="i">Hymnen
an die Nacht</hi> with the nine “Nächte” of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> would lead to any remarkable new
insights. Now, having read Scholz’s study, I still cannot see that the actual contrasts in both poetical
structure and imagery are outweighed by the rather abstract similarities in content which are brought forward
by the author. In addition—and arguing from the stance provided by Blake’s own aesthetics—I doubt that
there is much critical value in a method which is based on the division or separation of the minute
particulars of form from the meaning of a work of art. They then are conceived of in terms of “abstract
philosophy,” and only as such do they become “intermeasurable” with each other. And yet “Art &amp;
Science cannot exist but in minutely organized Particulars / And not in generalizing Demonstrations of the
Rational Power” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 55:62-63). Even though the latter tendency is perpetually
lurking behind the pages of this book, Scholz’s work may still serve as an example of both the advantages
and the dangers of the comparative method. In his finest moments the author actually succeeds in elucidating
one poet’s work by confronting it with the other’s, and one might argue that, in the end, it
<pb id="p17-112" n="112"/>
is of secondary importance whether this aim has been achieved by a clarification of the similarities
or—though involuntarily—by a presentation of the disparities between the poems under discussion.</p>
          <p>The book opens not with the “comparison of romanticism’s high arguments,” but with an
introductory chapter comparing first the outlines of Blake’s and Novalis’ biographies, and then the
reception of their respective works during the nineteenth and twentieth centuries. The contrasts, of course,
prevail in the lives of the two poets (pp. 1-2). Carlyle’s essay on Novalis and Crabb Robinson’s article
on Blake have something in common and prepare the ground for the first yoking together of the two poets in
1830 (pp. 2-4). Scholz’s attacks on the nineteenth-century view of the lives of Novalis and Blake as “more
inspiring than [their] poems or paintings” and on the attitude by which “character is saved at the expense
of . . . art” (p. 5) are of course fully justified; and yet this similarity in the reception of the two
poets’ <hi rend="i">vitae</hi> does not necessarily imply any peculiar similarity in their poetry. Scholz
seems to forget that the interdependent phenomena of “biographism” and the later concept of 
<hi rend="i">l’art pour l’art</hi> dominated aesthetics in the second half of the nineteenth century not just
where Blake and Novalis were concerned; in fact, these concerns gained ascendancy in almost every field of
historical research during that period.</p>
          <p>The argument of this chapter and, in consequence, of the whole book is hampered by another
misunderstanding similarly produced by the author’s need to establish a parallel between Novalis’ and
Blake’s poetical works. Since Scholz takes no notice of William Blake’s activities as a pictorial artist
(see pp. 19-20)—a procedure which might seem legitimate in a <hi rend="i">literature</hi> study—a mistaken
picture of “comparatively brief . . . times of insight and creativity” in Blake’s long artistic career
evolves. According to Scholz the development of “Novalis’ thought and poetry . . . that <corr type="emend">occurred</corr> over just
five short years” otherwise could not have been “compared with an artistic career that spanned more than
forty years” (p. 16). The “non-creative” years in Blake’s life, i.e., all those apart from “the
years from 1789 to 1795 and the years from 1802 to 1804” (p. 16), were in fact taken up by the creation of
some of the most important prints and paintings ever to be produced by an English artist, and by the creation
of Blake’s major epics, <hi rend="i">Vala, Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> (The distinction
made by Scholz between the “conception” and the “time-consuming execution” of these works [p. 16] is
not only utterly un-Blakean, but contradictory to the bibliographical evidence gained from proofs and finished
copies of the illuminated books.)</p>
          <p>Serving as Scholz’s model is S. Foster Damon’s essay on “Blake and Milton” (in 
<hi rend="i">The Divine Vision</hi>, ed. Vivian de Sola Pinto [London: Victor Gollancz, 1957], pp. 91-96), which
provides him with a “methodological exemplar” by “juxtaposing representative works for each given
stage” in the development of the two poets’ oeuvres. This “developmental comparison,” though less
“succinct or smooth [than] a thematic approach,” “should be rewarded by an increasing ability to
elucidate the problems and solutions of one poet through the problems and solutions of the other” (p. 18).
That Scholz actually had to combine the chronological with the thematic reading in order to reach his aim is
quite evident from his chapter headings (“The Discovery of the Poetic Genius,” “Visions of Romantic
Politics,” “The Encyclopedic Imagination and Its Myth,” etc.), as well as from the programmatic
contention that “both poets started out from a similar problem: man’s divided existence in a divisive and
contradictory world” (p. 18), a problem which became a theme for both Novalis and Blake that serves as the
starting point for Scholz’s detailed analyses. In his third chapter the author discusses the concepts of the
poetic genius in Novalis and Blake, and then goes on to deal with their view of “a political utopia,” of
an “all-encompassing system of creative references” and of “a tradition of visionary progress,” of
“Romantic criticism [and] the ethical foundation of all creative advancement,” and finally of the
“poetry of life in which all of us can be poets and all poets are heroes” (all quotations from p. 19).</p>
          <p>The achievement of both Blake and Novalis, as seen by Scholz, at the same time becomes the
“message” of his analysis: “Blake and Novalis reached a synthesis of such apparent incompatibilities as
desire and fulfillment, vision and action, imagination and reality, poet and hero, aesthetics and ethics”
(p. 19). “It is certainly wrong to confuse poetry with life; they are quite obviously different. Still, they
are also related: poetry not only telling us about life but holding out to us, in the very practice of the
poetic process, a crucial pattern, an imaginative figure which, if only writ large, will lead to a creative
conduct beyond words” (p. 381). This “mission” (p. 382) of poetry then constitutes the basic similarity
between Novalis and Blake. I do not want to enlarge upon my doubts in respect to this assumed ideology, yet I
must question the underlying assumption that any such general statement might describe what is related in the
work of two specific poets. Scholz is arguing here on a level of “philosophical” abstraction which to me
appears to be in closer contact with a bastardized version of modern German aesthetic theories than with the
minute particulars of the works from which he says he extracted these thoughts. (Benjamin, Adorno, Marcuse et
al. in one sense all started out from a critical reevaluation of nineteenth-century aesthetics; in their
conclusions, however, they remained much more careful than Scholz and well aware of the dialectics of such an
ideology.) This is not to say that I completely disagree with Scholz’s positive view of the possible effect
of art in post-secularized society;
<pb id="p17-113" n="113"/>
on the contrary, I wish I could be as naively optimistic. Still, I ask myself whether or not such a stance can
serve as a justification for seeing Blake in a more particular and closer relationship to Hardenberg than,
say, to Hölderlin, who shared at least as many “thoughts and concepts” with the British poet-painter as
did Novalis. On the other hand we will have to remember that, more or less, Scholz employs the whole system of
comparative methodology as a heuristic technique which proves to be legitimate, or disqualifies itself,
according to its success. We add to our knowledge most of all by asking new questions; Scholz’s study shows
that the context of German romanticism’s “high arguments” may provide a number of such questions
relevant to the study of Blake and vice versa, even though the common denominator of the work of Novalis and
Blake appears to be a rather amorphous abstractum.</p>
          <p>Interested readers may appreciate the following substitute for the missing index. The body of
Scholz’s book is devoted to interpretations of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> (pp. 21-24),
<hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi> (pp. 24-27), <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (pp. 27-38), 
<hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> (pp. 38-39), <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> (pp. 39-41), and the <hi rend="i">Songs
of Experience</hi> (pp. 41-49), which are compared with Novalis’ so-called <hi rend="i">Dichterische
Jugendarbeiten</hi> (pp. 50-53) and <hi rend="i">Fichte-Studien</hi> (pp. 53-72). Next come the 
<hi rend="i">Blüthenstaub</hi> fragments (pp. 84-93), compared with Blake’s “Annotations to Lavater” (pp.
95-97), the three <hi rend="i">Religion</hi> tracts (pp. 97-103), and <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi> (pp. 103-19). <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi> (pp. 120-26), <hi rend="i">America</hi> (pp.
128-32), <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (pp. 132-37), <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> (pp. 138-42), <hi rend="i">Ahania,
The Book</hi> (and <hi rend="i">The Song</hi>) <hi rend="i">of Los</hi> (pp. 142-46) are compared with
Novalis’ political studies of the 1790s (pp. 147-52), his <hi rend="i">Blumen</hi> (pp. 153-60), his eulogy
on feudalism, entitled <hi rend="i">Glauben und Liebe</hi> (pp. 160-68), and the <hi rend="i">Politische
Aphorismen</hi> (pp. 168-69). This is followed by a comparison of the <hi rend="i">Allgemeines Brouillon</hi>
(pp. 180-200) with <hi rend="i">Vala, or The Four Zoas</hi> (pp. 201-32). <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (pp.
235-66) is discussed as the developmental parallel of <hi rend="i">Die Lehrlinge zu Sais</hi> (pp. 268-87),
the <hi rend="i">Geistliche Lieder</hi> (pp. 287-91), and the <hi rend="i">Hymnen an die Nacht</hi> (pp.
292-300). Finally, Novalis’ novel fragment <hi rend="i">Heinrich von Ofterdingen</hi> (pp. 312-38) is put
side by side with Blake’s epic <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (pp. 339-75).</p>
          <p>This inventory of subjects shows that the main corpus of both Novalis’ and Blake’s writings
has been taken into account; it fails, however, to demonstrate how Scholz’s comparisons actually work. These
are primarily concerned with the imagery of the texts and with the “similar ideas” behind them, seldom
ever with structural elements such as diction, syntax, rhythm, and meter (which in most cases would have shown
fundamental disparities). If this implied demand for formal analysis sounds rather oldfashioned, it is telling
to consider that even on his “elevated” level of discussion Scholz misses some important points. Thus, the
basic difference between Blake and Novalis in both their poetic theory and practice goes unobserved. For the
German, the romanticization of the world—Blake’s “<hi rend="i">this</hi> world”—in a sense remains
an “artige[r] Kunstgriff” [a pretty artifice] and does <hi rend="i">not</hi> mean “much more than a
game”; for Hardenberg, it is the “schwärmerische Dichter” [the enraptured poet] himself who actively
supplies the finite with an “unendliche[n] <hi rend="i">Schein</hi>” [the semblance of infinity] (pp.
90-91; italics mine), whereas Blake the poetetcher, “by printing in the infernal method,” claims to
display the <hi rend="i">reality</hi>, not merely a <hi rend="i">semblance</hi> of “the infinite which was
hid” (<hi rend="i">MHH</hi> 14). Thus, Blake is clearly denying the <hi rend="i">Scheincharakter</hi> of
art. There are, however, examples of similar imagery by Novalis and Blake in Scholz’s book which admittedly
are rather breathtaking. Thus Novalis’ draft for the ending of his <hi rend="i">Ofterdingen</hi> finds a
mirror image in the last lines of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>:
<q>
Sketching the end of <hi rend="i">Heinrich von Ofterdingen</hi>, Novalis had written: ‘Menschen, Tiere,
Pflanzen, Steine und Gestirne, Flammen, Töne, Farben müssen hinten zusammen, wie Eine Familie oder
Gesellsch[aft], wie Ein Geschlecht handeln und sprechen.’ [Men, animals, plants, stones, and stars, flames,
sounds, colors all must be linked together at the end, act and speak like One family or society, like One
race]. . . . Blake, who had never heard of his young German companion in vision, fulfilled the promise as he
let <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> conclude with just such an end in Albion: ‘All Human Forms identified, even
Tree, Metal, Earth &amp; Stone: all/Human Forms identified, living, going forth &amp; returning wearied/Into
the Planetary lives of Years, Months, Days &amp; Hours; reposing, / And then Awaking into his Bosom in the
Life of Immortality.’ (pp. 374-375)
</q></p>
          <p>In his notes, Scholz frequently provides a secondary or <hi rend="i">meta</hi> level of arguments
concerned with methodological discussions of both modern Novalis and Blake scholarship (see, e.g., pp. 119n1,
121n1, 244-45n2, 376-87 and passim). The apparatus here not only serves to demonstrate that the author is well
versed in the scholarly literature on his subject, but at the same time provides the reader with a valuable
commentary on other critics’ approaches.</p>
          <p>I strongly agree with Scholz’s belief that criticism cannot do without value judgments, even
though these are necessarily subject to ideological prejudices (see Scholz’s chapter of “Conclusions”).
On the other hand, Scholz himself tends to develop his criteria in what appears to me to be a rather arbitrary
procedure. He does not start out from the task as faced by each poet under certain historical conditions
(which themselves need interpretation) and its counterpart in our own present-day attitude towards the
relevance of the poet’s problem and its “solution”; rather, Scholz works from a perspective that is
offered by the critic’s own evaluation of the <hi rend="i">other</hi> poet’s work, which by chance he
believes to offer the correct correlative. To me, at least, it is neither self-evident, nor following from my
appreciation of Novalis’ aphorisms that Blake’s <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> has to be considered a
“failure,” filled with “not particularly successful” allegories which, in addition, are to be
understood as offering a reactionary apology for “the managers, the exploiters of the human
<pb id="p17-114" n="114"/>
mind,” and thus forming an “ominous anticlimax” (pp. 115-16)! Since for me there <hi rend="i">is</hi> a
qualitative difference between the satiric mocker and the satirized mocked, I cannot follow Scholz’s logic
when he states that Blake’s “Memorable Fancies” as a whole do not differ “from Swedenborg’s
predestinarian theology” (p. 117). If this critique of Blake’s concept of contraries in the 
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> is to be justified by reference to his later doctrine of the forgiveness of sins (which
of course is an anti-doctrinal idea), Scholz would not only violate his “developmental approach,” but at
the very same time misinterpret both ideas: error has to be cast out, not less so in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> than in Blake’s early works such as <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell.</hi> “Blake, for one,” as Scholz himself states, “did not hesitate about where he wanted to
belong” (p. 119). Similarly, Blake’s prophetic books of the Lambeth period hardly provide the criteria to
evaluate Novalis’ <hi rend="i">Glauben und Liebe.</hi> Written under widely different political and social
conditions, the respective “vision of romantic politics” had to be as different, and we ought to be
careful not to reproach poets with the historical situation which to a certain extent determines their
production.</p>
          <p>It may well be that other readers of this book will find all the shortcomings I have tried to
point out rather irrelevant when <hi rend="i">compared</hi> with the many interesting and erudite
interpretations the book certainly contains. Yet, as Scholz himself puts it in a passage related to Novalis’
fragments, the “quest towards truth demands an endless progression in which every step has to be exceeded
and every gain has to remain a mere approximation” (p. 90). This review, then, is simply intended to supply
the Blakean contrary which is necessary for such a progression. “Reflection must sooner or later begin to
stagnate because it relates ‘nur unter dem <hi rend="i">Gleichen</hi>’ . . . ; poetry can progress because
it relates what is unlike and unlikely. Only from such unlikely marriages, such incongruous crossbreeding, can
we expect any new and promising off-spring”(p. 92). Though (or because?) Novalis and Blake remain an
unlikely marriage, this last quotation may well legitimate the procedure chosen by Joachim J. Scholz. He has
written a provocative book, well worth the attention of any literary critic dealing with the international
phenomenon of romanticism and its “high arguments.”</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
