<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>17.4.ott</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Iris &amp; Morpheus: Investigating Visual Sources for Jerusalem 14</title>
        <author n="Ott">Judith Ott</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1984</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1984</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">17.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants in charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Gu Jing-Yu</name>
              <name>Anne Maheux</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Judith Ott</name>
              <name>Joan Koster Stemmler</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1984"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_17">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-17-4-0008">
        <pb id="p17-149" n="149"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Iris &amp; Morpheus: Investigating Visual Sources for 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 14</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Judith <name>Ott</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The design on plate 14 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (illus. 1) consists of a winged Jerusalem
descending from a rainbow through a starry sky to awaken Albion from his deathlike sleep of mortality beside
watery shores where he is attended by
<figure n="jerusalem-D-14.17.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="643">
	<head>1. William Blake.</head>
	<figDesc><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>: 14. By permission of the Houghton Library, Harvard
University.</figDesc>
</figure>
two angels.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84" type="note">1</ref> Although this design has
been variously identified, the specific iconographic sources have not yet come to light. Attention paid to the
particulars of the scene clearly shows that the illumination on plate 14 is, among other things, a parallel
visual interpretation of the Greek myth of Iris and Morpheus.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n85" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n84"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Some Blake scholars have identified the woman as Jerusalem: David V.
Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> (New York: Anchor Press/Doubleday, 1974), pp. 111, 293;
Geoffrey Keynes, ed., <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (London: Trianon Press, 1974), pl. 14; Vivian de Sola Pinto,
<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (New York: Schocken Books, 1965), p. 53; Jean H. Hagstrum, 
<hi rend="i">William Blake, Poet and Painter</hi> (Chicago: University of Chicago, 1964), p. 42; and Joseph
Wicksteed, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Jerusalem</hi> (London: Trianon Press, 1954), pp. 139-40, identifies
her as “Jerusalem-Enitharmon/Fairy.”
                            <p>Those who identify her as someone else include S. Foster Damon, 
<hi rend="i">William Blake, His Philosophy and Symbols</hi> (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1924), p. 469, as
Enitharmon; Edwin John Ellis and William Butler Yeats, <hi rend="i">The Work of William Blake: Poetic,
Symbolic</hi> &amp; <hi rend="i">Critical</hi> (London: Bernard Quaritch, 1893), vol. I, pp. 313-14, identify
her as Leutha, daughter of Beulah “that follows sleepers in their dreams.” All further references to these
authors are taken from the sources listed above unless otherwise indicated.</p>
	<p>The male figure is identified either as Albion (Wicksteed, de Sola Pinto, Erdman) or Los (Hagstrum, Damon,
Keynes). Keynes identifies the last four lines on plate 14 as the passage from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
interpreted in Blake’s design.</p></note>
	<note id="n85"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Martin Butlin, in <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William
Blake</hi> (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1981) illus. 795, identifies a sketch on a sheet from Hayley’s
ballads (1802) as “Enitharmon shown as Iris with peacock wings, at the floor of plate 14”; Erdman offers
an interpretation that is the most agreeable with the Iris myth, “a vision of the soul as the portion of man
that wakes him from sleeping as body” (p. 111); Wicksteed and Ellis and Yeats state that the figure appears
as if in a dream; de Sola Pinto calls her “Divine Womanhood” watching over his sleep; Damon interprets the
design as inspiration visiting the poet in his sleep, but this is more likely an interpretation for 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 37 and 64.</note></p>
          <p>Iris was the Greek goddess who personified the rainbow on which she descended to earth as a
messenger of the gods.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86" type="note">3</ref> Juno sent Iris
to release the soul of Dido by rousing the sleeping Morpheus, the god of dreams.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n87" type="note">4</ref> The Kingdom of Hypnos was described by Ovid 
(<hi rend="i">Metamorphoses</hi> 11:589-632) as a cave in a hollow mountainside below which ran the River Lethe and
next to which Blake shows Albion asleep. Lethe is the River of Forgetfulness, one of the five rivers
surrounding Hades—an appropriate resting place for the god of dreams (and for Albion at this stage of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n88" type="note">5</ref> Iris is
most often represented with her rainbow, as in this emblem from Boudard’s <hi rend="i">Iconologie</hi> of
1766 (illus. 2), or descending on bright wings from a rainbow to rouse the sleeping god.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n89" type="note">6</ref> Perhaps the lines around Albion’s shoulder
in plate 14 are meant to indicate wings at rest.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n90"
type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n86"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Hall, James, <hi rend="i">Dictionary of Subjects and Symbols in Art</hi>
(New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1979), p. 162.</note>
	<note id="n87"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Hall, p. 284. Morpheus was the brother of Thanatos (Death) and son of
Hypnos (Sleep) and Nyx (Night). Nyx is usually represented with black wings outspread and holding an infant on
each arm, one white (Sleep) and one dark (Death)—a possible thematic source for <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
4 and 33.</note>
	<note id="n88"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Several scholars have commented on the watery shore in plate 14: Wicksteed
calls it “a promontory surrounded by gentle water”; Keynes notes the “water’s edge”; and Erdman
names it a “foaming ocean.”</note>
	<note id="n89"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Hall, p. 284. Blake’s engraving of a Cumberland design of Cupid and
Psyche (in Irene Chayes, “The Presence of Cupid and Psyche,” <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms
Dramatic</hi>, ed. Erdman and Grant (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1970), illus. 14, 118) shows two
butterflies resting on a hill that looks like a rainbow. Could this further connect Iris with the butterfly
wings that Blake has given her?</note>
	<note id="n90"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Another interpretation could be that Albion is shown as a body, without
its soul, carried down to the banks of Lethe by Sleep and Death.</note></p>
          <pb id="p17-150" n="150"/>
          <figure n="Boudard.Iris.17.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="772">
            <head>2. J.B. Boudard.</head>
            <figDesc><hi rend="i">Iris</hi>, from “Nymphes de L’Air,” 
<corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">Iconologie</hi></corr> (Vienna: 1766; Parma: 1759), <corr type="emend">Bodleian</corr> Library,
Oxford.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>Although the various elements in plate 14 (rainbow, butterfly / woman, sleeping figure, water)
clearly point to the myth of Iris and Morpheus, this parallel with the Greek theme alone does not account for
the entire composition. The visual motif of reclining-male/hovering-female appears in several representations
of physical-death/spiritual-rebirth throughout art. Ancient Egyptian funerary inscriptions (illus. 3) depict
the Pharoah in his tomb attended by a hovering, female-headed, Ba bird—the soul separated from the physical
body.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n91" type="note">8</ref> The soul as female, hovering
over the body as male, is a visual motif used repeatedly by Blake. <note id="n91"><hi rend="s">8</hi> A. S.
Roe, “The Thunder of Egypt,” <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays for S. Foster Damon</hi>, ed. A.H.
Rosenfeld (Providence: Brown University Press, 1969), p. 170. Bryant’s <hi rend="i">Mythology</hi> (1774)
contains a section entitled “Of Egypt and Its Inhabitants . . . ” that was probably Blake’s early source
for Egyptian symbols.</note></p>
          <p>With his broad knowledge of art themes, Blake frequently drew from one artistic tradition while
illustrating
            <figure n="FuneraryInscription.EgyptianPapyrus.17.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="756">
	<head>3. Portion of a funerary inscription, Egyptian papyrus.</head>
	<figDesc>John G. White Rare Book Collection, the Cleveland Public Library.</figDesc>
</figure>
            events from another.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n92" type="note">9</ref> An
example of this flexibility is seen in the motif of the swirling arch of angels in the preliminary drawing for
plate 14 (illus. 4) which Blake also used in his <hi rend="i">The Death of The Virgin</hi> (illus. 5). The two
compositions are remarkably similar and enlightening when one considers the changes enacted: the substitution
of mythological figures for Christian ones; the turning of the angels away from their charge; and the reversal
of female / male positions. If there is a visual connection between plate 14 in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
and Gothic tomb sculpture, the derivation of Blake’s composition for <hi rend="i">The Death of The
Virgin</hi> is too obvious to be overlooked.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n93"
type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n92"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Many scholars have commented upon this quality in Blake’s art: W.J.T.
Mitchell, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1977), p. 10,
where he asserts the “multiple metaphorical complexities”; Bo Lindberg, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Illustrations to the Book of Job</hi> (<corr type="emend">Åbo</corr>: <corr type="emend">Åbo</corr> Akademi,
1973) p. 114, states that what Blake was really using in his images was a “common language of art”; and
Wicksteed pronounces Blake’s borrowings a “pictorial language.”</note>
	<note id="n93"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Erdman, p. 293, describes Albion as “miserable in his tomb” and “as
stone cold as an effigy on a gothic tomb” (p. 293). It is well known that Blake sketched tomb monuments in
Westminster Abbey as a young apprentice engraver. He was also linked to current funerary symbolism through a
close friendship with John Flaxman, who conducted a substantial and successful trade in designs for tomb
monuments.</note></p>
          <p>In Gothic tomb sculpture, the Medieval gisant, usually shown reclining on his back, is sometimes
depicted
            <pb id="p17-151" n="151"/>
<figure n="BUT563.1.1.PD" rend="file" width="958" height="605">
	<head>4. Preliminary study for <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 14 (c. 1810), Victoria and Albert Museum,
London.</head>
</figure>
<figure n="but512.1.1.wc" id="but512.wc.01" work-copy="but512.wc" rend="db" width="958" height="968">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB 1803</figTranscr>
	<head>5. William Blake.</head>
	<figDesc><hi rend="i">The Death of The Virgin.</hi> (1803) Tate Gallery, London.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p17-152" n="152"/>
            <figure n="EdmundEarlofLancaster.SideViewTomb.17.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="746">
	<head>6. <hi rend="i">Edmund Earl of Lancaster, Side View of His Tomb</hi> (c. 1774-1779), Bodleian Library,
Oxford.</head>
</figure>
lying on his side, as in plate 14. This is the position of <hi rend="i">Edmund Earl of Lancaster</hi> (illus.
6) in an engraving from Basire’s <hi rend="i">Sepulchral Monuments</hi> believed to have been executed by
the apprentice Blake. As in this engraving, the deceased is frequently attended by miniscule angels who often
support his head and feet (illus. 7), or, occasionally, kneel in perpetual prayer.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n94" type="note">11</ref> In the <hi rend="i">Tomb of Frederigo di Lavellongo</hi>
(illus. 8), the reclining knight is visited by a vision of the Blessed Virgin, intercessor for Christian
souls, a role not unlike Iris’. Her double halo resembles both the butterfly wings of the Greek messenger
and of the Egyptian Ba.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n95" type="note">12</ref> Beneath her
is the waning moon and a picture of Frederigo himself, upon presentation by his patron saints. The arch above
the Virgin’s head serves the same compositionally enclosing function as Blake’s rainbow. 
<note id="n94"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Seemingly unique to Blake (I have found it nowhere else) are the angels turned
<hi rend="i">away</hi> from the deceased. Their unusual position certainly lends gravity to Albion’s
condition.
                            <p>In Buddhist iconography, Albion’s pose is called the “lion-posture,” a
pose assumed by Buddha when he was about to pass from the world of rebirths or into the state of Parinirvana.
Although this symbolic posture contains none of the other elements of Blake’s design, its similarity to the
actual pose of Albion is intriguing. Joseph Campbell, <hi rend="i">The Mythic Image</hi> (Princeton: Princeton
University Press, 1974), p. 355.</p>
	<p>Keynes and Wicksteed refer to the angels as “guarding” the figure. Ellis and Yeats state that the
human form “lying upon its side . . . is then in . . . [a] region of instinctive or vegetative
feeling.”</p></note>
	<note id="n95"><hi rend="s">12</hi> The arch in the Frederigo tomb is an Islamic/Gothic one and contains
grape leaves symbolizing Christ’s role as the Vine of the Church. It could just as well be a rounded arch
and contain cherubs, as in <hi rend="i">The Death of The Virgin.</hi> Erdman and Hagstrum both note the
“mandorla” wings of Jerusalem.</note></p>
          <p>Finally, the celestial bodies in plate 14 are worth noting.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n96" type="note">13</ref> The placement of the waxing moon is similar in the
preliminary drawing, the finished plate design and
            <figure n="EdmundEarlofLancaster.Effigy.17.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="805">
	<head>7. <hi rend="i">Edmund Earl of Lancaster, his Effigy seen from above</hi> . . . (c. 1774-1779),
Bodleian Library, Oxford.</head>
</figure>
the Frederigo tomb painting, but the optimism of Blake’s waxing moon is more in keeping with the artist’s
intent for <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> The sun, sending out such bright rays in the preliminary drawing, is
here hidden by clouds (or cave mouth?). This may be further indication of the location of Iris’ descent—a
land of perpetual twilight beneath the earth. In these surroundings, the rainbow could not be a natural
phenomenon but a hopeful attribute of the promised salvation Iris/Jerusalem brings.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n97" type="note">14</ref> Surely the rainbow is an omen of Albion’s awakening, for,
as Wicksteed pointed out, even Albion’s eyes seem to watch her descent behind heavy lids.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n98" type="note">15</ref>
	<note id="n96"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Erdman identifies the planets on the upper right of plate 14 as Saturn,
Venus, Mercury, Earth and the Moon. He presents an interesting theory: the six stars surrounding Jerusalem
identify her as the true sun or seventh star. Several scholars have commented upon the portion of the sky
within the arch of the rainbow: Erdman “Universe within” Albion (p. 293); Damon the State of Beulah; and
Ellis and Yeats, Mundane Shell.</note>
	<note id="n97"><hi rend="s">14</hi> The rainbow in emblem literature (i.e., Emblem XXXII, Wither’s 
<hi rend="i">A Collection of Emblemes, Ancient</hi> &amp; <hi rend="i">Moderne</hi>, 1635) follows the Old
Testament precedent as a good omen, covenant or reward for suffering. John Gage in “Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Newton</hi>,” “Warburg &amp; Courtald Institute Journal,” 34 (November 1971), 376, argues that
the rainbow in Blake’s work represents materialism (coming from water, not light) because it used the
Newtonian order of colors, thus representing a negative or pessimistic element. This does not seem an accurate
reading for <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></note>
	<note id="n98"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Wicksteed, p. 140. “The eyes seem to be watching the Vision as though
to show it as a dream . . . .” This detail in plate 14 varies among the copies of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></note></p>
          <p>The artistic sources for plate 14 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> demonstrate the diversity,
richness and amazing clarity with which Blake chose his visual parallels.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n99" type="note">16</ref> In plate 14, he tied Jerusalem and Albion to compatible and
expansive sources: the Egyptian Ba-Soul hovering over the material body; the Blessed Virgin in her role as
intercessor for Christian souls; and, most obviously, the rainbow messenger,
            <pb id="p17-153" n="153"/>
            <figure n="TombFrederigodiLavellongo.17.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="433">
	<head>8. Tomb of Frederigo di Lavellongo (St. Antonio, Padua).</head>
	<figDesc>Alinari Art Resources.</figDesc>
</figure>
Iris, in her descent to awaken Albion/Morpheus from his mortal dreams to spiritual life. The rays of the sun
may be temporarily dimmed and the angels recoiled in momentary grief, but the design clearly heralds the
positive outcome of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>
	<note id="n99"><hi rend="s">16</hi> As Mitchell says (p. 6) “the essential point is to note the wealth of
implication which Blake can deposit in a design that has no ‘illustrative’ function . . . an independent
symbolic statement.”</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p17-154" n="154" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
