<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>17.4.mann</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Robert J. Bertholf and Annette S. Levitt, eds., William Blake and the
Moderns</title>
        <author n="Mann">Paul Mann</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1984</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1984</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">17.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants in charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Gu Jing-Yu</name>
              <name>Anne Maheux</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Judith Ott</name>
              <name>Joan Koster Stemmler</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1984"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_17">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-17-4-0009">
        <pb id="p17-169" n="169"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Robert J. Bertholf and Annette S. Levitt, eds. <hi rend="i">William Blake and
the Moderns.</hi> Albany: State Univ. of New York Press, 1982. 352 pp. Cloth, $39.59; paper, $14.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Paul</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Mann</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Is Harold Bloom the Covering Cherub of <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Moderns</hi>? His work
is mentioned in only a few of these thirteen essays, and discussed in any depth in only one, but as the most
visible current theorist of influence, he must be taken into account in any discussion which attempts to graph
potential arcs of influence—even if that accounting turns out to be merely a prelude to dismissal. And
dismissal appears to be one of Bertholf’s and Levitt’s purposes:
<q>
The literature which contains reference to preceding literatures becomes an indication that the central
imagination is alive and provocative, and not an indication of a metaphysical scheme of influence dominated by
the anxiety of that influence and the obligation to remove that antecedent force. Harold Bloom’s system in
the end only explains the psychology of itself, and not the literature it raids for illustrations. Instead of
declaring a necessary independence from antecedent masters, writers in this tradition seek out (often
consciously) examples of this central imagination in order to penetrate further into the life of the
sustaining vision. (xi)
</q></p>
          <p>It’s fairly clear from this passage that Bertholf and Levitt have misread Bloom. Where in his
writing does he claim that poets are under an obligation to remove their precursors? Ashbery wants to 
<hi rend="i">remove</hi> Stevens? To what misty realm? Bloom’s theory seems rather to insist that, even in their
most strident oppositions, poets manifest an indissoluble bond with their precursors. If “strong” poets do
labor to revise antecedent masters, if they “swerve” from those masters in what Bloom terms a 
<hi rend="i">clinamen</hi>, they remain nonetheless anchored in them. Bloom’s theory is a great deal more
dialectical than Bertholf and Levitt credit it with being: it is a theory of sublation, not of excision. But
it’s the word “anxiety” which appears to cause them the greatest anxiety; what they desire for this
central imagination is a healthier rhetoric, something purer and less troubled than the neurotic imagery of
Bloomian influence.</p>
          <p>And what they arrive at is something rather like a platonic Form:
<q>
The poet seeks out, both consciously and unconsciously, influences, attunements, and disruptions that provoke
his awareness of his engagement in a literary history of recurring forms. His occupations are not driven by a
creative anxiety into intricate procedures of misreading in an effort to do away with his predecessors. The
forms of expressions dominate. The generation of particular forms to present a vision specifies a line of
writing that grew out of the period of the Romantic in literature. The forms develop within the vision,
present and enact it; they are not imposed as external agents of structure. But while the freedom of the
imagination acts as a bulwark against the passivity of conventional structures, the active principle of
insistent reference to preceding literature picks out what is most vital in the line. If Blake had not taken
up Milton’s <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, for example, as a projection of what he called “The One
Central Form,” that omission would have been an indication that Milton’s poem had so mismanaged itself
that it was not part of the common form of the imagination’s life. The tradition of enacted forms by
necessity refers to itself because it seeks out examples that most vigorously present the vision of the
imagination engaged in an area of meaning greater than itself. If there is one central form of the
imagination, then the possibilities of imaginative literature are manifestations, as approximations, of that
central form. (x-xi)
</q></p>
          <p>If I understand this passage, literary history is construed here less as a set of intimate
relations than as a wide field in which all writers can participate in “One Central Form,” the Imagination
itself. Writers may constellate in or around that form, but no single writer can ever embody it. A writer
might be taken to exemplify it, or to mediate other writers’ encounters with it, but that writer can never
be entirely central to it. In other words, the true title of this work is not <hi rend="i">Blake and the
Moderns</hi> but <hi rend="i">Imaginative Form and the Moderns</hi>; the book is centered in Blake primarily
in the sense that it is his definition of that form which mediates its relations—in which case, it is
certainly curious that so many of the essays in the collection are rather superficial and old-fashioned
influence studies.</p>
          <p>It is difficult, of course, to lump together thirteen essays by thirteen different critics, and
foolish to hold the contributors responsible for the claims and errors of their editors. This is, however, a
remarkably coherent book.
<pb id="p17-170" n="170"/>
There are certainly differences—in focus, in emphasis, in style, in interpretive skill—but, in the view of
these critics, the writers influenced by Blake have much in common. And what this common denominator turns out
to be is a fairly superficial reading of Blake. For according to their critics, the writers under
consideration prize Blake not so much for his poetry but as a symbol of the Poet, an exemplar of the central
imagination.</p>
          <p>It might have been useful, then, for the editors to have employed critics concerned with how this
imagination operates in and is transmitted through history; they might have attended more closely to discourse
as a determining force, to linguistic systems, to the functions and interference of ideology, to the critique
of the subject, to discontinuity as well as continuity, or, at the very least, to the ways in which
“Romanticism” is variously defined by twentieth century writers and critics. But no. “Even without a
survey of contemporary criticism—which would not be to the point here—the fundamental principle persists
that a poet names the preceding artists who will comprise his essential literary history, the authors and the
texts which extend into his own work, either consciously or unconsciously” (ix). Why isn’t contemporary
criticism relevant? It simply isn’t. The cursory treatment of Bloom is the editors’ single gesture of
contemporaneity; the “fundamental principle” of interpersonal literary influence is merely posited.
Context in <hi rend="i">Blake and the Moderns</hi> will be barely sketched: intertextuality here is 
<hi rend="i">mano a mano.</hi></p>
          <p>Take, for instance, the book’s first essay: Hazard Adams, once again, on Blake and Yeats. If
Yeats was influenced by Blake, and it would be impossible to deny that he was, he did not, according to Adams,
really understand Blake. Adams notes seven areas or Blakean themes from which Yeats borrowed—notions of
contraries and negations, center and circumference, the creative primacy of belief, and so on—but in all
cases rather superficially, and distorted by other previously-held beliefs and ideas. Adams explicitly rejects
Bloom’s proposal that such distortions are the result of a <hi rend="i">clinamen</hi>; in Yeats’s case,
Adams argues, “a simpler, more mundane explanation” is in order: “an inexperienced or fanatical
interpreter will interpret through what is either familiar or an <hi rend="i">idée fixe.</hi>” “The
reasons for Yeats’s misinterpretation of Blake were principally his lack of critical sophistication and the
occultist thoughts that dominated him at the time” (4-5).</p>
          <p>We find such preconception and lack of critical sophistication in most of the writers addressed
in <hi rend="i">Blake and the Moderns.</hi> What these writers tended to take from Blake was obvious, general
and personal: divisions in mental activity cause divisions in and alienation from the “external” world;
creative imagination can reintegrate subject and object; and Blake’s personal example serves as a sort of
muse for other writers inclined toward similar activity. Blake’s influence is less as an actual writer of
actual poems than as a good angel of the imagination perched on the shoulders of writers who do not, for the
most part, take much more from him than that. If his work explores division and reintegration in complex and
pertinent forms, his successors seem to have found these forms, these actual poetic operations, either
irrelevant or secondary. When one of these writers wants to make use of Blake’s “minute particulars” it
is not in their minute particularity but as a general rule; Blake <hi rend="i">exemplifies the general
possibility</hi> of attention to particulars.</p>
          <p>Donald Pease’s Crane “returns to Blake to recover the tradition of epic prophecy” (16);
since his own epic era differs from Blake’s he cannot use Blakean prophecy directly, only as an idea for a
project he might himself enact. When Jay Parini’s Roethke finds in Blake’s “Orc cycle” the twin of his
own desire to “compete with papa” (73), it seems merely in the sense that it is possible to do so; and
Roethke appears to find himself under no obligation to compete with Blake as a <hi rend="i">poetical</hi>
papa. Bertholf’s Duncan is an avowedly “derivative poet” who both “takes off from Blake’s poems”
and “regards Blake as a poetic companion of the sacramental imagination” (92). Alicia Ostriker’s
Ginsberg models his own prophetic or “shamanistic” career on what he takes to be Blake’s; he too tries
to invert socially determined definitions of “madness,” and proceeds from “giving Error a body” to
“visions of reintegration” (118); but his own poetry has little of the psychological depth or verbal
density which, in Blake’s work, are keys to such a project. Most peculiar, but in many ways most
representative of all, Robert Gleckner’s Joyce seems barely to have read Blake’s poetry; his chief
“Blakean” influence was E. J. Ellis’s highly embellished quasi-biography, <hi rend="i">The Real
Blake</hi> (sic) of 1907. According to Gleckner, what Joyce took from Blake were less poetic insights and
particular strategies than a more general <hi rend="i">confirmation</hi> for what must have been a
predisposition to devote himself to the life of the imagination.</p>
          <p>Surely it is natural for writers to seek such confirmation. For writers working in often severe
isolation, discouraged by countless mundane influences from continuing in their work, to be able to attach
themselves to so single-minded and dedicated an artist as Blake, an artist so firmly persuaded and persuasive
about the virtue and necessity of imaginative labor, must seem a saving grace. As Gleckner says, for Joyce
“it was the <hi rend="i">fact</hi> of Blake that he finally adhered to, what he knew <hi rend="i">of</hi>
him rather than his works that finally mattered” (159). So also, evidently, for many of these poets and
writers: they might have read Blake more closely than Joyce did—Duncan is certainly a student of Blake, and
Joyce Cary is said by Levitt to have used “The Mental Traveller” to organize several chapters of 
<hi rend="i">The Horse’s Mouth</hi>—but what they all find in Blake is not so much the practice of poetry, but
spiritual affinity.</p>
          <p>Affinity is, finally, the true subject of <hi rend="i">Blake and the Moderns</hi>: affinity is
the answer to anxiety. It is for this
<pb id="p17-171" n="171"/>
reason that the editors include among so many influence studies a number of essays about writers who knew
little or nothing at all about Blake. In one of the book’s more interesting essays, Leroy Searle
domesticates one of the strangest <hi rend="i">ménages à trois</hi> on record: Blake, Eliot and Williams.
Eliot hated Blake and Williams hated Eliot, and Williams cannot even be said with any certainty ever to have
opened a book of Blake’s poetry, but Searle is nonetheless able to unite them through each writer’s
concern with “the continuity of imaginative labor”—again, the attempt to counter perceived
disintegration with artistic reintegration, with the unity of the imagination itself. But what does this
really tell us about imaginative practice? Given affinity, would it not be possible to link any two
imaginative writers?</p>
          <p>The answer to that question appears to be affirmative. In the book’s nadir essay, we encounter
Blake and Marx. Certainly, as Minna Doskow argues, both men believed that the individual’s labor tends to be
alienated from his or her world, and that the world should be reconceived as the actual product of a labor
defined in more or less humanistic terms. But whether this constitutes true affinity or only a vague
coincidence of interests authorized by the most general aegis, whether Blakean humanism and Marxian humanism
have anything substantial in common, whether humanism itself might then be a determining form, and, most
importantly, whether this surface similarity is belied by deeper and more abiding differences in 
<hi rend="i">practical</hi> approach—none of this is seriously considered. Doskow herself notes, in discussing
the subject-object problem, that for Blake “the answer lies in man’s loss of imagination, while for Marx
it lies in the alienation of his labor under capitalism,” but she immediately glosses over this crucial
difference: “Yet these answers are not as different as they may at first appear, for the causes, evidences,
and consequences of each are almost identical. Both writers see a distortion of human subjectivity which
extends outward to encompass the world and results in distorted practices and a distorted world which are
further reflected by the subject.” (232)</p>
          <p>The passage not only describes a circle, it rhetorically enacts one: Doskow begins to consider
effective response to a general problem but immediately reverts to the problem itself. Given her premise, she
can really go no further. But the differences between these responses cannot be ignored. Each writer, in his
own way, insisted on the unity of theory and practice, but where Blake’s practice led through visionary art,
Marx’s led through political economy—matters which Blake would likely have rejected as mathematical
ratios. In fact, the two men’s courses run exactly opposite: Blake increasingly away from “political”
solutions, Marx increasingly toward them. To ignore such deepseated difference renders the connection purely
gratuitous. Indeed, Doskow is able to make this connection only by giving heavy priority to the early Marx of
the <hi rend="i">Economic and Philosophical Manuscripts</hi>, in which he was just beginning to formulate his
approach, rather than the later work which fully demonstrates how different from Blake’s that approach
always was.</p>
          <p>But if Doskow’s essay is the most ludicrous argument for affinity in the book, it is not
unrepresentative. The minute particulars of formal strategy and discursive context are continually sacrificed
to the most general notions of affinity; actual work is continually glossed over for the sake of the
brotherhood of individual writers. It is only in the book’s final essay that such individuality, at least,
is considered <hi rend="i">as problematic</hi>, and it leads me to believe that <hi rend="i">Blake and the
Moderns</hi> might better have begun than ended here. William Dennis Horn is willing to wrestle with influence
as a question, not as an a priori answer, and to wrestle with it in the current terms of the debate. He
doesn’t exactly embrace Bloom, but neither does Horn merely dismiss him. And in addressing the
“problematic of the self” in Blake’s work, Horn indirectly points up one of the most disturbing traps of
the entire book: “In the case of Blake we find a criticism, as problematic, of all notions of self,
occurring in works which have as their main action the creation and psychomachia of mental agents” (280). In
the jolly fraternity of <hi rend="i">Blake and the Moderns</hi> there is no such problematic, no such
critique, no psychomachia of mental agents. Blake was indeed concerned with imaginative reintegration, but he
was also concerned with the annihilation of the selfhood, and that selfhood is reincarnated in essay after
essay of this volume.</p>
          <p>Furthermore, the critique of agency indicated by Horn should have been, but was not, extended to
the mediating influence of criticism itself. There is no chapter on Blake and the modern critic. One misses
it, first of all, for the simple fact that Blake seems to have influenced some critics as much as some poets
and novelists. A number of Blake’s most influential critics—Frye, Hirsch, Bloom himself—have progressed
from early studies of Blake to theoretical or metacritical interests. Frye would have been particularly worth
considering: his work might be the closest anyone has yet come to a Blakean theory of literature and literary
history; and Bloom’s own theory of influence must owe something to what Frye originally termed the Orc
cycle. Parini seems to believe the term was invented by Blake himself, and his essay further demonstrates the
danger of ignoring critical mediation of writer relations. (Adams and Gleckner do not exactly ignore it, but
neither do they fully explore it.) “ ‘Blake gives us,’ <hi rend="i">says Price</hi>, ‘a world
conceived as the manifestation of imaginative energy, hardened into opacity as energy fails, raised through
intense and confident assertion to the image of One Man, containing all powers within himself and exercising
them in the creation of works of art.’ <hi rend="i">Likewise Roethke</hi>, in ‘The Far Field,’ envisions
‘the end of things, the final man . . . ’ ” (79; emphases added). The
<pb id="p17-172" n="172"/>
rhetorical, and possibly the actual, connection demonstrated by Parini in this passage is not between Roethke
and Blake but between Roethke and Martin Price.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n129"
type="note">1</ref> My point is not simply that, like Adams’s Yeats, Roethke was an unsophisticated reader
of Blake, nor that, like Gleckner’s Joyce, he might have relied heavily on critical accounts, but that this
mediation is virtually ignored by the book’s contributors, and most grievously in terms of 
<hi rend="i">their own</hi> critical agency. <note id="n129"><hi rend="s">1</hi> I am indebted to Professor
Jenijoy La Belle for pointing out this apparently unwitting trope, and for supplying the Roethke quotations
that appear in the following paragraph. The Price citation is from “The Standard of Energy,” 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism and Consciousness</hi>, ed. Bloom (New York: Norton, 1970), p. 273.</note></p>
          <p>It is undeniable that Roethke took Blake as an ancestor, but Roethke himself claimed that a
“son has many fathers” (“O, Thou Opening, O”), and when he wrote, “Walk into the wind, willie!”
(“I Cry, Love! Love!”), he probably also meant Willie Wordsworth and Willie Yeats. It is undeniable that
Yeats valued Blake, but simply to privilege this relation over others—Dante, Swift, Shelley, Rossetti
(albeit mentioned by Adams), Lady Gregory, Synge, Pound, Rosicrucianism (simply to note the prism of occultism
doesn’t go far enough), Irish mythology and history, even Maud Gonne—begs too many questions of discursive
context and actual compositional practice, and brute differences of time and place. It is undeniable that Marx
and Blake held a handful of notions in common, but what good does it do anyone who is interested in either
Marx or Blake to note them without also noting differences, or noting that these notions were much more widely
held? By isolating such influences and affinities, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Moderns</hi> virtually unravels
the intertextual fabric. By embodying influence strictly in persons and separating it from discursive practice
on a larger scale—if not from an ill-defined central imaginative form then certainly from historical
contexts which are both literary and non-literary, from the intercessions of critical ideologies themselves,
and from the complex of ways in which all of this affects the actual production of actual works—<hi
rend="i">Blake and the Moderns</hi> distorts both immediate influence and more general problems of literary
history. The book is of very little use to the reader of Blake, who will learn nothing new about Blake from
it, or to readers of Blake’s heirs, for whom these links must already be common knowledge, or even to those
who might still be waiting for an adequate way to swerve from Bloom.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
