<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>17.4.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">The 1821 Edwards Catalogue</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1984</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1984</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">17.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants in charge</resp>
              <name>Marcy Erickson</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Gu Jing-Yu</name>
              <name>Anne Maheux</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Judith Ott</name>
              <name>Joan Koster Stemmler</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1984"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_17">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-17-4-0008">
        <pb id="p17-154" n="154"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">The 1821 Edwards Catalogue</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>One of the most important early printed references to William Blake appeared in the 1821 shop
catalogue of Thomas Edwards of Halifax. However, the catalogue is very uncommon and has rarely been seen in
this century. It was first—and last—reported in print in an article by T. W. Hanson on the Edwards family
in 1912-1913<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n100" type="note">1</ref>, there-after Mr. Hanson
forgot where he had seen it, and numbers of scholars searched vainly for it in scores of libraries on four or
more continents, particularly since about 1960. Now a copy of the catalogue has been found in the collection
of a member of the family, and a few more details can now be provided about it. 
<note id="n100"><hi rend="s">1</hi> T.W. Hanson, “Edwards of Halifax. Book Sellers, Collectors and Book-Binders,” 
<hi rend="i">Halifax Guardian</hi>, Dec. 1912 &amp; Jan. 1913, reprinted in <hi rend="i">Papers, Reports, &amp;c.
Read before the Halifax Antiquarian Society, 1912</hi> (Halifax [1913]), pp. 142-200; Hanson deals cursorily
with the same material in “Richard Edwards, Publisher,” <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 8
Aug. 1942, p. 396.</note></p>
          <p>Thomas Edwards was a member of a family important for selling antiquarian books, for publishing
new books, particularly illustrated ones, and for inventing new and beautiful methods of binding, particularly
in painted transparent vellum or Etruscan calf with illuminated fore-edges. The firm was apparently founded by
William Edwards in Halifax in the first half of the eighteenth century, and four of his sons carried on the
business, Thomas in Halifax until about 1826, and James, John, and Richard with two shops in London from 1785
to 1799. Richard Edwards commissioned William Blake’s 537 watercolors for Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> and published the first forty-three engravings of them in the autumn of 1797, before he abruptly
left the publishing business midway through 1798. The <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs evidently
stayed in his possession even when he went briefly to Minorca in 1799 as a servant of the crown, for they bear
an inscription on the titlepage of High Elms where he lived for a time on his return to England about 1803.
However, the drawings had passed to his brother Thomas in Halifax by 1821, for they were offered in his shop
catalogue for that year,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n101" type="note">2</ref> with a
description in terms which are not repeated elsewhere:
<q>
3 Young’s Night Thoughts, the Author’s original Copy, illustrated with drawings, very 
<corr type="emend">spirited designs</corr> by Mr. Blake, many of them in <corr type="emend">the Style</corr> of
Michael Angelo, they occupied <corr type="emend">nearly two</corr> years of the time of this singular 
<corr type="emend">and eminent</corr> Artist, which renders this <corr type="emend">Work unique,</corr> as well as
highly valuable, in <corr type="emend">2 vols.</corr> Atlas Folio, each leaf <corr type="emend">surmounted
with</corr> a border and sumptuously bound in <corr type="emend">red morocco,</corr> gilt leaves, 300 l.<lb/>
<pb id="p17-155" n="155"/>
1743<lb/>
This Work is perhaps unequaled for the boldness of conception, and spirit of execution, exhibited in the
masterly designs of Mr. Blake. The Bookbinder from inattention lost the blank leaf, with the Author’s
signature.
</q>
Fortunately T. W. Hanson had quoted this passage accurately, so there is little need to expatiate upon it
here.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n102" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n101"><hi rend="s">2</hi> It is possible, I suppose, that Thomas was merely offering the drawings
on commission for Richard Edwards, but this seems unlikely, as he offered them again, also in vain, in
auctions of his stock in 1826 and 1828.</note>
	<note id="n102"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Such commentary may be found in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>
(1969).</note></p>
          <p>What is important is to record other details about the newly refound volume. Its owner was Mrs.
Rosa M. Edwards, whose husband the late Col. Walter P. Edwards, Emeritus Professor of Greek, was a descendant
of James Edwards; Professor Edwards seems, however, to have acquired the book by purchase rather than by
inheritance. The work is described here through the courtesy of Mrs. Edwards, who generously provided me with
a xerox copy of it. It was sold in 1983 to the Bodleian Library.</p>
          <p>Unfortunately the title leaf of this copy is missing, so the title can only be reconstructed
hypothetically as EDWARDS’S CATALOGUE. / = / <hi rend="i">Superb Books of Prints, Atlasses, Books printed on
Vellum / with Miniatures, and other Superlatively fine Articles.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n103" type="note">4</ref> / <hi rend="i">R. Sugden, Printer, Hall-end, Halifax</hi><supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n104" type="note">5</ref> / [for Thomas Edwards] At No 2. Old Market
Halifax, 1821.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n105" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n103"><hi rend="s">4</hi> The title thus far derives from the heading on p. 1, which may apply only
to the first section of the catalogue.</note>
	<note id="n104"><hi rend="s">5</hi> The printer’s name derives from the colophon on p. [120].</note>
	<note id="n105"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Thomas Edwards’s address derives from the inscription by Professor
Edwards on the flyleaf; as this address is not recorded elsewhere, it must derive from another copy of the
1821 catalogue which Professor Edwards had seen.</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Size:</hi> 12.4 × 20.2 cm.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Format:</hi> Octavo by half-sheets: [?a]<hi rend="s">2</hi> [A]<hi rend="s">4</hi>
B-P<hi rend="s">4</hi> A-D<hi rend="s">4</hi> [bis] <hi rend="i">Contents:</hi> [?Half-title]; [titlepage];
Folio Books of Prints, &amp;c. (pp. [1]-20); [other] Folios (pp. [21]-27); Quarto (pp. [28]-53); Octavo (pp.
[54]-84); Duodecimo Et Infra (pp. [85]-117); Magazines and Odd Volumes Octavo (pp. [117]-118) and Duodecimo
(p. [119]); advertisements for Whitaker’s <hi rend="i">Craven</hi> (1811) and <hi rend="i">Whalley “lately
published by Thomas Edwards of Halifax”</hi>, plus colophon (p. [120]); Drawings (pp. [1]-4); Books of
Prints (pp. 5-6); Historical Prints (pp. 6-10); Shakespeare (pp. 10-12); Shipping (p. 12): Views (pp. 13-15);
Scripture Prints (pp. 15-17); Antiquities (p. 18); Battles (pp. 18-19); After the Antique (p. 19); Portraits
(pp. 19-27); and [miscellaneous] Prints (pp. 27-31, p. [32]). In all, there are 2103 lots of books and 901
lots of prints.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Plate:</hi> None.</p>
          <p>Perhaps the most remarkable feature of the catalogue is the bindings. One might expect splendid
bindings in the catalogue of a famous bookbinder, but the care with which the bindings are described here is
unusual even among the Edwards’ catalogues, and Thomas Edwards is unlike his brother James in identifying
the family styles of binding. Two lots here are said to be “sumptuously bound,” three are “richly
bound,” thirty-one more are “superb” or “splendid,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n106" type="note">7</ref> and ninety-nine lots (one in twenty-six volumes) are merely “elegant,” A
number of the “elegantly bound” works are in Etruscan calf (thirty-four lots, fourteen omitting the
qualifier “elegantly”), and eighteen of these are further described as “Elegant in Etruscan binding,
gilt leaves, with a drawing thereon,” while five more lots specify a fore-edge painting but do not mention
Etruscan calf. The Etruscan style of binding, with classical designs burned with acid through the surface
patina of the calf, was apparently invented by the Edwards family and largely confined to their Halifax and
London binderies, but none of the shop catalogues of James Edwards in 1785, 1787, 1789, 1790, 1794, and 1796
mentions these bindings, though some of the books there were certainly bound thus. 
<note id="n106"><hi rend="s">7</hi> “Splendidly” and “superbly” are evidently used here as synonyms, for lot 13,
Macklin’s Bible (1800) “Splendidly bound,” is “uniform” in binding with lot 14, which is Boydell’s
Shakspeare (1802) “superbly bound.”</note></p>
          <p>Even more striking is the mention of fore-edge paintings, for though the Edwardses had revived
this long-lapsed art, it was apparently quickly imitated, and today it is very difficult to ascertain whether
an individual fore-edge painting on an old book was made either for the Edwards family or even in their
time—some have been added to eighteenth century books in very recent times. When the fore-edge subject is
actually identified, we have information which will enable us to identify positively a work from this
catalogue, if it were found today, as being virtually unimpeachably from the Edwards atelier. These valuably
identified copies with fore-edge painting are:
<table rows="14" cols="2"><row>
	<cell>629</cell>
	<cell>Bewick, <hi rend="i">General History of Quadrupeds</hi> (Newcastle, 1807), 8vo, in Etruscan calf, gilt
edges (= g.e.) “with a drawing of Blackfriars bridge,” £2.12.6</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>630</cell>
	<cell>Bewick, <hi rend="i">History of British Birds</hi> (Newcastle, 1809), 8vo, Etruscan calf, g.e., “with
a drawing of Blenheim thereon,” £2.12.6</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>644</cell>
	<cell>Bewick, <hi rend="i">Quadrupeds</hi> (Newcastle, 1807), 8vo, Large Paper, Etruscan binding, g.e.,
“with a drawing of Chatsworth thereon,” £3.10.0</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>818</cell>
	<cell>Gessner, <hi rend="i">Death of Abel</hi>, with plates after Stothard ([London:] Heptinstall, 1791),
8vo, Etruscan calf, g.e., “with a drawing thereon of Melvin Constable,” £2.10.0</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>827</cell>
	<cell><hi rend="i">Ibid</hi> (1797), 8vo, Etruscan calf, g.e., “with a drawing thereon of Harewood
House,” £2.12.6</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>934</cell>
	<cell>Mason “on Self-Knowledge” (1813), 8vo, in Etruscan calf, g.e., “and a drawing thereon of Coomb
Lodge on the Thames,” £1.16.0</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>973</cell>
	<cell>[Dodsley] <hi rend="i">Œconomy of Human Life</hi> ([London:] Gardiner, 1806), 8vo, “first
impressions of Harding’s fine plates,” in Etruscan binding, g.e., “with a drawing thereon of Coghill
Hall,” £2.10.0</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>1021</cell>
	<cell>[i.e., 1022] Lady Rachel Russell, <hi rend="i">Letters, from the Manuscript in the Library at Wooburn
Abbey</hi> (London, 1801), 8vo, in Etruscan calf, g.e., “with a drawing thereon of Harewood House,”
£2.10.0<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n107" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n107"><hi rend="s">8</hi> No. 1019 is a Large Paper copy of the same work with an unidentified
fore-edge painting (£2.10.0), and this (or another) copy, with a fore-edge of Woburn Abbey and an inscription
of 1826 by Thomas Edwards, is now in my own collection.</note>
	</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>1023</cell>
	<cell>D. Robertson, <hi rend="i">Tour to the Isle of Man</hi> (1794), 8vo, in Etruscan calf, g.e., “with a
Drawing thereon of Milton Constable in Norfolk,” £2.12.6</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>1244</cell>
	<cell>Young, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1798), 8vo, Large Paper, in Etruscan calf, g.e., “with a
drawing of the Grounds in Ham Hall, Staffordshire,” £2.7.6</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>1899</cell>
	<cell>[i.e., 1299] <hi rend="i">Holy Bible</hi> ([London:] Bowyer, 1796), 12mo, red morocco, g.e., “with a
drawing thereon of King’s College Chapel,” £3.3.0</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>1378</cell>
	<cell><hi rend="i">The Book of Common Prayer</hi> ([Edwards] 1791), 12mo, in vellum “with a drawing of
Oxford on the leaves,” £1.16.0</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>1706</cell>
	<cell>Milton, <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> (Edinburgh, 1810), 12mo, in red morocco, g.e., “with a
drawing of Comb Lodge thereon,” £1.7.6</cell>
</row>
</table>
<pb id="p17-156" n="156"/>
<table>
<row>
	<cell>1865</cell>
	<cell>Rev. F. Skurray, <hi rend="i">Bidcome Hill and other Rural Poems</hi> ([London:] W. Miller, 1808),
12mo, in Etruscan calf, g.e., “with a drawing thereon of Brocket Hall, Herts,” £1.15.0</cell>
</row></table>
Clearly the prices of the twenty-three books with fore-edge paintings were based chiefly upon size; £3.13.6
for a quarto, £2.7.6 to £2.12.0 for an octavo (with one inexplicably at £1.16.0 and a Large Paper copy at
£3.10.0), and £1.15.0 to £1.16.0 for a duodecimo. Manifestly the genius of the artist scarcely affected the
price.</p>
          <p>The catalogue contains a number of publications by the Edwards family, four by Richard Edwards,
eleven by Thomas Edwards, and a striking thirty-six by James Edwards, who had gone out of business over twenty
years before. In particular, there are five copies of <hi rend="i">The Book of Common Prayer</hi>, the
printing of which James Edwards had arranged with Didot in Paris and which the Edwardses published in 1791,
and three of them (lots 1378-1380) have fore-edge paintings, while two (lots 1377-1378) are in “vellum
bindings,” which may well be the painted transparent vellum style of binding which James Edwards patented in
1785—no book is identified in any Edwards catalogue known to me as being in a painted transparent vellum
binding.</p>
          <p>Many of the lots are colored, extra-illustrated, with proofs, or otherwise “unique.” Two
works of special incidental interest are:
<table rows="2" cols="2"><row>
	<cell>13</cell>
	<cell><hi rend="i">Holy Bible</hi>, 7 vols. ([London:] Macklin, 1800), folio, extraillustrated “with a
great profusion of old and curious prints by Sadeler, Lucas Van Leyden, Martin Schoen, Albert Durer, Visscher,
Pintius, Bloemart, Rembrandt, Goltzius, Barraccio, Poilly, Strange, and others; after the finest pictures by
Raphael, Caravaggio, Rubens, Pietro di Cortona, Guercino, Pous[s]in; etchings by Bartolozzi, Strange, &amp;c.
likewise a fine miniature of the Virgin Mary, in gold and colours, executed by Don Sylvestro about the year
1350. Splendidly bound in russia, gilt leaves, and the insides lined with crimson velvet, 
<hi rend="i">unique</hi>,” £200<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n108" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n108"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Extra-illustrated Macklin Bibles were popular; see E.B. Bentley &amp;
G.E. Bentley, Jr., “Bishop Phillpotts Library, The Franke Parker Bequest and Its Extra-Illustrated Bible,
1800,” <hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi>, 29 (1980), 363-94.</note>
	</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>75</cell>
	<cell>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Comedies, Histories, and Tragedies</hi> (1632), Second Folio, purple morocco,
g.e., £12.12.0</cell>
</row></table></p>
          <p>There are also three minor Blake items:
<table rows="3" cols="2"><row>
	<cell>16</cell>
	<cell>Young, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> ([London:] R. Noble for R. Edwards, 1797), “Many fine plates
by Blake,” g.e., half russia, £2.12.6</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>314</cell>
	<cell>R. Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> “with 12 Etchings after Blake’s designs, by Schiavonetti,”
([London:] “Bensley” [not Cromek], 1808), boards, £3.3.0</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>217</cell>
	<cell>in the appended prints “Fall of fair Rosamond, 6s. . . . . . . [Painter] Stothard [Engraver]
Blake”</cell>
</row></table>
All these Blake lots seem somewhat random; the remarkable thing is that there is only <hi rend="i">one</hi>
copy of Blake’s edition of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>—and no more appear in Thomas
Edwards’s other catalogues of 1826 and 1828. What happened to them all? Clearly the work was not sold out
when Richard Edwards went out of business in 1798—indeed, it is generally assumed that the work was a
commercial failure. Who then got the copies Richard Edwards still had in stock when he went out of
business?—for the work is not rare today. One might perhaps expect them to have gone to his brother James,
whose business in Pall Mall was not far from Richard’s shop in Bond Street, but James too was winding up his
business then, and they did not go to James Edwards’s successor R.H. Evans—or at least, they do not appear
in Evans’s catalogues of 1804 and later. And they do not appear, except very casually, in Thomas Edwards’s
catalogues either. Indeed, I know no contemporary catalogue in which there are more than a couple of copies of
the 1797 <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi> Even the discovery of a copy of the long-lost Thomas Edwards shop
catalogue of 1821 does not solve this mystery.</p>
          <p>The long-lost-to-sight Thomas Edwards shop catalogue of 1821 is an exceedingly impressive work
for a provincial bookseller, and it is of considerable importance today for what it tells us of William Blake
and of the Edwards bookbindings.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
