<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>18.1.carr</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">W. J. T. Mitchell, ed., The Language of Images</title>
        <author n="Carr">Stephen Leo Carr</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1984</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1984</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">18.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen Leo Carr</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
              <name>Joseph S. Salemi</name>
              <name>Santa Cruz Blake Study Group</name>
              <name>Thomas A. Vogler</name>
              <name>Bette Charlene Werner</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1984"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_18">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-1-0005">
        <pb id="p18-35" n="35"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">W. J. T. Mitchell, ed. <hi rend="i">The Language of Images.</hi> Chicago and
London: Univ. of Chicago Press, 1980. 307 pp. $7.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Stephen Leo</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Carr</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Language is an intricate and elusive object of study, yet language increasingly offers many
disciplines a privileged model <hi rend="i">for</hi> study. This is perhaps most obvious in structuralist and
poststructuralist writings, which insistently return to, and revise, Saussurian linguistics as a seemingly
inevitable movement of their inquiry. Such theories have fostered a renewed attention to the role of language
in earlier works, in Freud and Wittgenstein, for example, whose complex discursive practices further their use
of language as a means of questioning, modeling, and understanding their subjects. It is no surprise, then,
given the impressive genealogy and current prestige of language as a critical metaphor, that even fields
removed from the direct influence of such theoretical developments should adopt issues and terms made relevant
by more systematic uses of linguistic or, more generally, semiotic models. Undoubtedly, even casual
redeployments of language metaphors can produce useful insights. But the danger here is of studies in which a
haphazard use of critical commonplaces and an atheoretical electicism gloss over the fundamental uncertainties
and anomalies that maintain language as such a richly complex model for critical study.</p>
          <p>W.J.T. Mitchell recognizes—indeed emphasizes—the diversity of interests in <hi rend="i">The
Language of Images</hi>, a collection of fourteen essays, most of which first appeared in a special issue of
<hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry.</hi> Mitchell’s introduction identifies three meanings for its title: (1)
“language <hi rend="i">about</hi> images” (how we describe and discuss images); (2) “images regarded 
<hi rend="i">as</hi> a language”; and (3) “verbal language as a system <hi rend="i">informed by</hi> images”
(how pictorial and spatial images structure language). I suppose this generous definition of the project is in
keeping with <hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry</hi>’s insistence on an “ideology of pluralism.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">1</ref> Yet it seems <hi rend="i">too</hi> generous,
especially since the category of “language <hi rend="i">about</hi> images” seems to have included any
piece reflecting slightly on critical practice. I do not see that the essays by Steinberg, Mast, Arnheim,
Gombrich, Searle, and Morgan have much very directly to do with <hi rend="i">language.</hi> Several of them do
challenge received critical <hi rend="i">concepts</hi> (e.g., Mast, Morgan) or clarify how a specific problem
should be conceived (Searle’s “<hi rend="i">Las Meninas</hi> and the Paradoxes of Pictorial
Representation” neatly lays out the issues raised by Velasquez’s painting). But none of them extends his
analysis to the particularities of language, to the ways critical terms represent—or constitute—images in
useful or misleading ways. <note id="n45"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See Mitchell’s “<hi rend="i">Critical
Inquiry</hi> and the Ideology of Pluralism,” <hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry</hi>, 8 (1982), 609-18, for a
revealing statement of the journal’s position. Though Mitchell is aware of the social and economic
underpinnings of ideology, he tends to discuss it as a set of practices and beliefs that individuals can adopt
or reject at will.</note></p>
          <p>What is at stake here is not the “unity” of a collection of essays, which seems a trivial and
fruitless complaint. In one sense, it would be unfair to charge contributors with not concentrating on what an
editor (or reviewer) names as the unifying concern of the collection. But as I read and reread this volume, it
became increasingly clear that what distinguished the best essays was their serious attention to language,
especially to the complexity of the exchanges between verbal and visual systems. And what marked the less
successful essays was lack of specific concern for language, or else a relatively uncritical or even mistaken
notion of language. Quite apart from abstract questions of whether the title is appropriate, “the language
of images” would seem to designate the close involvement with verbal-visual exchanges needed to develop
further our understanding of images. Studies that shy away from considering the reciprocal interactions of
language and images are ignoring what is crucial to either the production or interpretation of both verbal and
visual art.</p>
          <p>The difficulties arising when the complexity of such interactions is slighted are exemplified by
Rudolph Arnheim’s “A Plea for Visual Thinking,” which claims that higher level thinking “is impossible
without recourse to perceptual images” (176). Arnheim attacks the view of perception as a neutral gathering
of data with no effect on the way we think, and argues that perception significantly mediates the information
it makes available to thought. This may offer a useful if unremarkable corrective to some benighted
psychologists. But Arnheim himself falls prey to a similar positivistic error by denying language’s role in
perception or in the production or interpretation of images used in thought. He treats language as a simple
“reflector” of thought, as a way of “codifying” its results, as “only a set of references to facts
that must be given and handled in some other medium” (172, 173, 175). This scientistic reduction of language
is necessary to isolate a purely visual thinking as a necessary component of information processing. Yet even
the simple schematic diagrams Arnheim uses to illustrate his thesis always depend on linguistic operations for
their conceptual value. One of Arnheim’s figures, for example, is derived from a
<pb id="p18-36" n="36"/>
painting entitled “The Sensation of Flight”: it depicts several rectangles and a cross, all tilted so that
they are oriented on the diagonal from lower left to upper right. Arnheim claims that “one can take
cognizance of the picture by simply looking at it” (176). Yet the way we construe this image is never simply
a matter of visual apperception. Guided by the title, for example, I may “see” the figures as floating
upwards and to the right. Given a different <hi rend="i">verbal</hi> cue, I would “see” it differently,
as, say, a schematic aerial view of “buildings” in a landscape, or as an abstraction of a “hammer”
falling on several surfaces, or even (curiouser and curiouser) as several “rectangles” and a “cross”
oriented along an invisible “diagonal.” Language always supplements perception: altering the semiotic
context will lead viewers to construe features of images differently. Since Arnheim ignores language, he
oversimplifies how even simple diagrams come to signify, to say nothing of far richer and more problematic
pictorial or phenomenological images.</p>
          <p>Even as intriguing and at times brilliant an essay as Leo Steinberg’s “The Line of Fate in
Michelangelo’s Painting” falters because it does not attend to the signifying process with the care that
more concern for the “language of images” should entail. Steinberg discerns a descending diagonal in
several of Michelangelo’s paintings, and he uses this “line of fate” as the geometric basis for
speculative, yet richly detailed and suggestive readings of these images. What he does not explain, however,
is how an abstract linear construction, especially one not strongly marked by compositional devices, can carry
such a heavy burden of meaning. Steinberg takes for granted an audience familiar with the elaborate 
<corr type="emend">apparatus</corr> of modern art history and formalist aesthetics, and thus comfortable with
interpretations based on abstract formal relationships. Armed with such formidable mechanisms for producing
readings, clever critics may discover any number of significant configurations. But such interpretations,
however ingenious, ignore the question of <hi rend="i">reading</hi>, of how images function 
<hi rend="i">as</hi> a language: instead, they reproduce quite standard disciplinary methods of constituting
visual meaning, even if they present themselves (as this essay sometimes does) as extravagantly iconoclastic.
This is too bad. Steinberg makes several acute comments on how art historical discourse seems to blind viewers
to remarkable qualities of an image. Moreover, he develops an interesting critical techniques by studying
small variations among contemporaneous copies of Michelangelo’s images: the different visual qualities
produced by these variants allow him to articulate the significance of minute details that ordinarily fall
beneath the threshold of critical vision. Steinberg’s method should be especially interesting to students of
Blake, who was a reproductive engraver and who also “copied” himself—with significant variations—in
(re)producing his illuminated pages.</p>
          <p>The three best essays in the volume carefully explore the verbal-visual exchanges that underlie
the production and interpretation of images. Ernest B. Gilman’s “Word and Image in Quarles’ 
<hi rend="i">Emblemes</hi>” is an exemplary study of the problematic interactions between verbal and visual
components in a genre too often dismissed as Gilman challenges the traditional view that image and text in
emblem books are “commensurate and reinforcing,” that they are “complementary codes” with “each
holding the key to deciphering the other” (61.) He argues instead that text and design interrogate their own
inadequacies as representations of divine truths. Quarles’ use of Catholic images for a logocentric English
Protestant culture distrustful of sight, moreover, transformed the emblem till it was “not a transparent
sign pointing toward a spiritual meaning but an impediment to what [a viewer] would truly wish to see” (77).
What Gilman demonstrates is the difficulty of reading emblems: the text does not simply articulate its
image’s meaning nor does the design simply “illustrate” its accompanying poem. There are problems with
this essay: Gilman discusses a rather arbitrary selection of emblems without explaining why these emblems are
privileged or how they enter into and effect the dynamics of the whole book. But his emphasis on the
illegibility of emblems and on the conflicting movements of text and design seems to me to open the issue of
the “language of images” in a way that prevents a quick reduction of one medium into a reflection or
repetition of the other. This historical study begins to provide a new general understanding of verbal-visual
relations: it seems appropriate, therefore, that the essay should end with a reference to Blake, whose
practice radically extends the movements Gilman discerns in Quarles’ emblems, and who thus forces a
recognition that text and design need not be “commensurate and reinforcing.”</p>
          <p>Probably the most innovative and farreaching theoretical account of the “language of images”
is Joel Snyder’s “Picturing Vision,” which demonstrates the need to replace resemblence theories of
“natural” correspondences between image and world with historical analyses of the conventional
relationships between images and language. Snyder shows that Gombrich’s influential critique of a
“realistic” connection between an image and the object it represents merely displaces the question of
“natural” resemblences to the visual experience of viewers, to the way certain images stimulate what
Gombrich treats as the “automatic” or “programmed” (and hence “natural”) mechanisms of
sight.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">2</ref> Snyder argues instead that it
is not some unchangeable fact of visual experience that paintings seek to emulate. Rather, emerging styles of
pictorial representation provide models for describing visual experience with the result that our
understanding of how (or even what) we see changes with different systems of making images. It is because we
first “picture vision” (that is, define it in terms of the pictorial laws or methods of a culture) that we
can then treat pictures as
<pb id="p18-37" n="37"/>
accurate representations of vision. <note id="n46"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Snyder refers to <hi rend="i">Art and
Illusion</hi>, but his critique also applies to Gombrich’s contribution to this volume, “Standards of
Truth: The Arrested Image and the Moving Eye.” Gombrich asserts “there are certain classes of experience
to which we are programmed to respond from birth, while others are readily assimilated to this initial
stock” (212). He identifies the convention of the “eye-witness principle” (representing nothing that
could not be seen by a single individual) as what best matches our visual “programming.”</note></p>
          <p>Snyder substantiates this apparently paradoxical idea most impressively by showing that
photography does not offer neutral evidence for the “realism” of Western pictorial conventions. He reminds
us that “cameras represent the <hi rend="i">incorporation</hi> of those schemata into a tool designed and
built, with great difficulty and over a long period of time, to aid painters and draughtsmen in the production
of certain kinds of pictures” (231). It is because we first built cameras so they would duplicate pictorial
conventions that we can then treat some paintings as “photographically” realistic. He makes a similar
argument about the enduring “realistic” pictorial convention, perspectival representation. By examining
Alberti’s <hi rend="i">De Pictura</hi>, Snyder shows that this technique was not an inevitable discovery,
but an artificial construction of sight. Contemporary pictorial styles enabled Alberti to redefine medieval
theories of vision, and thus to develop a rational theory of sight that could then be used as the basis for a
rationalized system of pictorial representation. As with photography, perspectival compositions seem
“true” to visual experience because we have so insistently “pictured vision” in terms of pictorial
perspectivism.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">3</ref> Snyder concludes that
“there are no end runs that get us out of language or depiction to the really real” (246). His essay
suggests that images are never innocent records: even the most “natural” pictorial features can never
simply be referred to some alleged fact of visual experience, but must be interpreted in terms of the
discursive, technological, and metaphysical systems that almost literally make them visible. Not just
emblematic or iconographic details but the style and formal properties and subject matter of paintings can
only be adequately “seen” by being “read.” <note id="n47"><hi rend="s">3</hi> The geometric theory of
vision that underlies perspective has been so long dominant in Western culture that Snyder’s conclusion may
still seem counter-intuitive. I refer sceptical readers to Colin Murray Turbayne’s neglected classic, 
<hi rend="i">The Myth of Metaphor</hi>, which challenges the hegemony of the geometric model by adopting
Berkeley’s linguistic theory of vision and showing it to be equal or superior to geometric
theories.</note></p>
          <p>W.J.T. Mitchell’s “Spatial Form in Literature: Toward a General Theory” likewise has
significant theoretical consequences for the study of relations among the arts. Mitchell shows the
pervasiveness of spatiality not only in literary texts but also in critical terms (e.g., “form,”
“structure,” “levels” of meaning) used to describe them.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n48" type="note">4</ref> He thereby neatly collapses the dichotomy between literature as a
“temporal” and painting as a “spatial” art that has been a commonplace since Lessing, not so much by
arguing for some empirical presence of “spatial form” in certain texts (as Joseph Frank did about modern
literature) as by reflecting on the uses of language that underlie and sustain that opposition. He shows how
spatial metaphors tend to be effaced and forgotten when convenient, or else reified into abstract qualities of
the object of study. Mitchell suggests that we accept these metaphoric “ ‘contaminations’ as an
inescapable part of literature and the languages of criticism and”—what is more to the point—“work for
a systematic understanding of the ways in which the infections are carried” (281). His own immediate concern
is to develop a general theoretical and historical mapping of the multiple forms of spatiality associated with
literary texts. But his consideration of this particular problem shows an exemplary attentiveness to the
subtle and historically variable exchanges that occur reciprocally between language and images. Mitchell
rightly criticizes claims about “universal” or “intrinsic” features of verbal or visual media, and
argues for a methodologically rigorous understanding of the multiple possibilities of interart relations.
<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Robert Morgan’s “Musical Time / Musical Space” likewise demonstrates
how spatial images permeate what is conventionally defined as the temporal art of music. For more discussion
of these views, see Leon Surette’s challenge to the “spatiality” of form, “Rational Form in
Literature,” and Mitchell’s defense, “Diagrammatology,” <hi rend="i">CI</hi>, 7 (1981), 612-21 and
622-33.</note></p>
          <p>Mitchell’s thoughtful reflections on language and images makes the inadequacies of other essays
in the volume only too apparent. Howard Nemerov’s thesis—that “painter and poet want to reach the
silence behind the language, the silence within the language” (9)—may be an appropriately “poetic”
conceit, but it is the kind of abstract, ahistorical generalization that Mitchell deftly reveals as an
oversimplification. Nemerov has simply universalized a post modern cliché in disregard of the many divergent
goals of the real historical men and women who wrote and painted. Elizabeth Abel studies a particular
historical interaction between the arts, that of Baudelaire and Delacroix, but her conclusions—that “both
manage to create a harmonious atmosphere” (51) and “to synthesize movement with form” (52)—are
generalizations that reproduce the commonplaces of literary criticism. Despite its announced adaptation of
“structuralist” methods to study underlying patterns in the artistic ordering of materials, this essay
lacks the precision and detail that Mitchell shows to be necessary for systematic understandings of interart
relations.</p>
          <p>The essays by Gilman, Snyder, and Mitchell high-light the values of a self-reflexive critical
stance toward theoretical suppositions about art and its interpretation. Without some such metacritical
questioning, the subtle interpenetrations of language and images may be effaced, and we may continue to
construe the “language of images” by means of the interpretive decisions and methods most congruent with
received disciplinary self-understandings. Thus, when Guilio Carlo Argan defines iconology as a kind of
“philological” study, he names Panofsky, the inventor of this field of study, as “the Saussure of art
history” (17). The analogy is an unhappy one, for Saussure attacked the inadequacies of philology, and
redefined linguistics in diametrically opposing ways to the diachronic study of language development. Like the
confusions about spatial metaphors that Mitchell traces, this faulty comparison is not a trivial mistake, but
underlies a basic problem of Argan’s argument. If “iconology” is a kind of “philology,” then why
should it be exempt from the well-established critiques of that form of linguistic study? Can one construct a
valid historical “series” of images (see p. 16)? If so, do such series significantly determine the meaning
or function of an image? It may be possible to answer these sceptical questions, or to define a synchronic
aspect of iconology to supplement its historical concerns. But Argan seems unaware of the need to consider
such issues. His ambitious proposal for
<pb id="p18-38" n="38"/>
future study, therefore, seems on closer examination to be mainly an apology for the traditional historical
discourse of art criticism.</p>
          <p>The “language of images” announces what would be, in terms of contemporary academic
institutions, an “interdisciplinary” project. But this volume often fails to live up to what its title
promises. Some essays seem limited to a single medium: the studies of film by Gerald Mast and Christian Metz,
for example, are competent essays, but do not even begin to address the general theoretical issues of the
“language of images.” Other essays (e.g., those by Argan, Abel, and Steinberg) remain confined within the
respective disciplinary boundaries of their writers even as they consider untraditional topics. Still others
(Arnheim’s and Gombrich’s) are simply “crossdisciplinary”: they rewrite the problems of one discipline
(art history) in the dominant codes of another (psychology), using its different terms and procedures to
produce the <hi rend="i">effect</hi> of a novel “solution.” What these diverse efforts have in common is a
fairly uncritical acceptance of received disciplinary methods of constituting meaning and value. As a result,
exchanges between language and images are too quickly assimilated by conventional interpretive strategies, and
the potential challenge to methods and categories developed for more singlemindedly homogeneous works in
either verbal or visual media is substantially deflected. If an “ideology of pluralism” may occasionally
engender the debates about critical assumptions that are its prime rationale and justification, like all
“ideologies” it also serves established interests. And one interest of “pluralism” is the preservation
of relatively stable institutional bases from which a continual array of competing perspectives may be safely
generated. In the case of this collection, its potential “interdisciplinary” quality never emerges from
the contention of alternative disciplinary claims to authority.</p>
          <p>Both the successes and, in a more oblique manner, the failures of this collection underscore the
importance of attending closely to the multiple ways language and images interact. Though Blake is mentioned
in only a few brief asides, the volume may usefully serve as a stimulus and a caution for all those involved
in understanding the verbal-visual dynamics of his works of illuminated printing. There have been relatively
few recent attempts to develop a comprehensive theory of how text and design interrelate in Blake’s pages,
Mitchell’s <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art</hi> being the most notable exception. And in the absence of
sustained theoretical reflection, it is too easy simply to hurry through the question of Blake’s
verbal-visual exchanges, and to find refuge in some such trusty strategy as the discovery of a textual
“referent” that can be used to identify the characters, action, and meaning of a design. <hi rend="i">The
Language of Images</hi> identifies an area and a problem in need of much further historical and theoretical
inquiry. Our understanding of Blake will benefit from all such investigation. But given the current state of
this critical field, it may well be that the study of Blake’s illuminated printing offers an especially
effective way of intervening in the general issue of the “language of images.”</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
