<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>18.1.erdman</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">David V. Erdman, ed., The Complete Poetry and Prose of William
          Blake</title>
        <author n="Santa Cruz Blake Study Group">Santa Cruz Blake Study Group</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1984</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1984</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">18.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen Leo Carr</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
              <name>Joseph S. Salemi</name>
              <name>Santa Cruz Blake Study Group</name>
              <name>Thomas A. Vogler</name>
              <name>Bette Charlene Werner</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1984"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_18">
    <body>
    <pb id="p18-4" n="4"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-1-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">David V. Erdman ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of
                William Blake.</hi> Commentary by Harold Bloom. Berkeley and Los Angeles: University
              of California Press; and Garden City, N.Y.: Anchor Books, Doubleday; 1982. xxvi + 990
              pp. $29.95, cloth and $19.95, paper.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by the</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <name><hi rend="b">Santa Cruz Blake Study Group</hi></name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, edited by David
            Erdman, arrives as a “Newly Revised Edition” to replace and “complete” (principally by
            the inclusion of all the letters) the editor’s earlier effort, <hi rend="i">The Poetry
              and Prose of William Blake</hi>, now out of print after selling over 38,000
              copies.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> The old E, as it
was usually cited,
            quickly became the generally recognized authoritative text for Blake’s work. The new E,
            as it will be cited here,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref>
adds to this impressive
            mantle of approval two more layers of certification. First, thanks to a transfer of the
            hardcover rights by Anchor/Doubleday, a University Press now publishes the library
            copies. The new E’s second <hi rend="i">nil obstat</hi> appears in the form of an actual
            “emblem” gracing the back of the dust jacket, signifying that this volume is approved
            and sanctioned by the Modern Language Association Committee on Scholarly Editions, known
            as the MLACSE (illus. 1). The distinction conferred by award of this emblem of approval
            raises a number of questions that make a review of this volume more than an ordinary
            enterprise. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> The hardcover edition was first published
              in 1965 and had sold 6,913 copies by 1972; the paperback was introduced in 1970, and
              in its most successful year (1974) it sold just under 4,000 copies. <hi rend="i">The
                Illuminated Blake</hi>, by contrast, has sold only about 15,000 copies in all, with
              fewer than 1,000 of these in hardcover, since it was published in 1974. We are
              grateful to Mr. David Gernett of Anchor Press, Doubleday &amp; Co., for supplying
              these figures. <p>The initial University of California Press printing of 1,500 copies
                sold out within a year, leading to a second printing of 1,000 copies and a list
                price of $38.50. 2,800 additional copies were printed with the first run for a
                subscription book club. Our thanks to Ms. Anne Ebers, University of California
                Press, for this information.</p></note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> In
              “Redefining the Texts of Blake (another temporary report)” David Erdman announces that
              “ ‘C’ has been chosen as symbol for the new edition (rather than, say, E<hi
rend="s">2</hi>) as more impersonal and in recognition of the committees of textual scholars
              who watched and assisted the labor . . . ” We prefer at least for the time being, for
              the purposes of this review/essay, to refer to the new E simply as E, specifying “old
              E” where necessary to avoid confusion. There are indeed pertinent consonantal
              alliterations that support the Choice of “C” as symbol. It is a Collective enterprise
              (though we note the Copyright is David V. Erdman, 1965, 1981). It Claims to be the
              Complete Poetry and Prose, and it has been approved by the Committee on Scholarly
              Editions which is Chaired by Don Cook who announces that “We are particularly pleased
              to have been able to Co-operate in this wedding of scholarly and practical publishing”
              (E VI). There may also be suggestions of Correctness and Certainty and Canonical for
              “a volume that can be expected to receive immediate acceptance both as a standard
              scholarly edition and a Classroom text” (E VI). But whose Expectations are these? And
              is it not possible that “C” is a (small) part of the machinery that may enable those
              expectations to become self-fulfilling? It may be fanciful to imagine that adopting
              “C” too readily would have any Consequences at all; but the tactical effect of a new
              Edition with its powerful Claims are potentially vast, not the least of which may be
              drastically to alter the “value” of the many thousands of Copies of and citations to
              the old E still in use and circulation. Is the new E in fact so much changed and so
              much more authoritative that scholars who claim to be reputable will now have to make
              the switch and require their students to do the same? Has the “text” Changed, even
              where the wording is the same, by having been more authoritatively Certified? How
              substantial are the changes? Will those readers who continue to use the old E be in
              Error? Will scholars who cite it be Errant? Must E go the way of K, and must B
              Continue to remain in left field? We prefer to keep the designation “E,” suggesting
              not only Erdman, but Editing and Editor and Edition, which will be the focus of much
              of our discussion.</note></p>
          <p>Is this new revised standard edition now officially authorized as the one which should
            be purchased and read in the sizable academic market? Has the MLACSE presumed to make
            definitive the long-standing distinction between Blake’s verbal and his visual artistic
              components?<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> Does the
MLACSE emblem of approval
            extend to the distinctly <hi rend="i">not</hi> “newly revised” commentary by Harold
            Bloom still included? In what follows we shall examine a few minute particulars of this
            edited version of Blake’s “text” bound back-to-back with the “Commentary” in this
            volume. But our main concern shall be to raise some theoretical questions about the
            assumptions and presuppositions that inform the editorial enterprise which made the
            production and institutional approval of this volume possible. 
                <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> The new E, like the old E, has four illustrations and eight
figures,
              along with the seventeen emblems for <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi> (G. E.
              Bentley, Jr. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi> [2 vols.; Oxford: Clarendon,
              1978], by contrast, offers three hundred and eleven illustrations).</note></p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>I. MINUTE PARTICULARS</title>
            </head>
			<q> The Ancients entrusted their [ ] to their Editors<lb/>
<lb/>
 Now then, after four
              hundred years, the truth of the law comes forth to us; it has been bought for money in
              the synagogue. When the world is grown old and everything hastens to the end let us
              even put it on the tombs of our ancestors, so that it may be known to them too, who
              read a different version, that Jonah did not have the shadow of a gourd but of an ivy;
              and again, when it so pleases the legislator, not an ivy but some other bush.
              (Rufinus, <hi rend="i">Apologia contra Hieronymum</hi>) </q>
            <p>Blake is no longer the prophet of <hi rend="i">écriture.</hi> Perhaps the single
              statement that some young critics of the new age found most compelling in Blake, his
              remark in the Preface to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> that “the Ancients entrusted
              their love to their Writing,” has literally been obliterated. Or, leaving open a
              recuperative strategy, could these young critics say that 
              <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s traces have achieved a new dissemination? The line now reads:
“the
              Ancients acknowledge their love to their Deities” (illus. 2). The alteration may serve
              as a lesson for all of us who were—or become—wholly one with the Editor’s text: CAVEAT
              LECTOR. (Without concern for the accuracy of Erdman’s recovered reading, we should
              note the <hi rend="i">effect</hi> of including in a reading “text” lines that were
              deleted by Blake: compare illustrations 2, 3, and 4.)</p>
            <p>Comparing Erdman’s “text” with examples of the productions by Blake that it
              re-presents, we realize again 
<pb id="p18-5" n="5"/>
with added force the absolute
              justice of the Editor’s admission that “In print it is impossible to copy Blake
              exactly: his colons and shriekmarks [!] grade into each other; he compounds a comma
              with a question mark; his commas with unmistakable tails thin down to unmistakable
              periods.” We realize as well the profound contradiction in the subsequent disclaimer
              that “In Blake the practical difference between comma and period, however, is almost
              unappreciable” (E 787). Contradictory, because the reader of this “complete” Blake is
              never “in” Blake, but is rather in the editing and altering “I” that has “been
              inclined . . . to read commas or periods according to the contextual expectations.”
              The Editor does offer the reader without access to originals or facsimiles one check
              on his calibration, for one of the book’s illustrations (following p. 272) reproduces
              plate 10 of <hi rend="i">America</hi> (copy not specified) which has twelve lines of
              text. Lines 7-9 of the printed version (E 55) offer the following: 
			<q> Because from
                their bright summits you may pass to the Golden world<lb/>
 An ancient palace,
                archetype of mighty Emperies,<lb/>
 Rears its immortal pinnacles, built in the forest
                of God </q>
But the reader of even the reproduction included in <hi rend="i">The
                Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi> will probably perceive: 
				<q> An
                ancient palace. archetype of mighty Emperies.<lb/>
 Rears its immortal pinnacles,
                built in the forest of God </q></p>
            <p>We cannot do too much with this one instance, however, because as Erdman notes, he
              has prepared a “collected” edition “as against transcripts of individual copies.” The
              study of an individual copy of an illuminated work cannot call into question a
              collected transcript that has been produced as the fruit of the Editor’s compositing
              art. But for those several works that exist in only one copy, the individual
              transcript <hi rend="i">is</hi> the basis of the collected edition. One such, 
                <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, offers a kind of introductory exemplum, and has
              the further virtue of having been printed in intaglio, which gives to its text more
              clearly defined lines than the usual relief etching. “Editing the works that Blake
              etched and printed himself,” writes the Editor, requires first of all “precise
              transcription.” The MLACSE has stated that it “signifies” by its emblem that this
              volume “records all emendations to the copy-text introduced by the editors,” according
              to “explicit editorial principles.” In Erdman’s printed text Ahania remembers, towards
              the conclusion of the book: 
			<q> My ripe figs and rich pomegranates<lb/>
 In infant joy
                at thy feet<lb/>
 O Urizen, sported and sang (5.26-28, E 89) </q>
Erdman’s version
              leads us to think that Ahania reports to Urizen how her fruits acted, because of the
              comma which makes “O Urizen” into an apostrophe. But no such punctuation is visible in
              Blake’s plate (illus. 5). As with her exclamation six lines before (“O! eternal births
              sung round Ahania”) so here, in less exclamatory fashion, Ahania jumps to the catching
              memory that “Urizen sported and sang.” Further: evidently Ahania suggests a strange
              time when her fruits were the feet of Urizen. The syntax then, the mere absence of the
              comma, complicates considerably our image of Urizen. Such proliferating complication,
              struggling against “contextual expectations,” is at the core of our vision of Blake’s
              work. To appeal to “contextual expectations” as a neutral and universal given is to
              avoid the possibility that the difference between a period and a comma, or between a
              comma and nothing at all, is “the difference we see—and, by seeing, make.”<ref
                target="n4" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Stanley Fish, 
                  <hi rend="i">Is There A Text In This Class?</hi> (Cambridge: Harvard University Press,
                1980), p. 148. Two chapters in Fish’s book are especially pertinent to our
                discussion here: “Interpreting the Variorum,” where what Erdman calls “contextual
                expectations” are discussed by Fish as the “hazarding” of what he calls
                “interpretive closure;” and “Structuralist Homiletics,” where an extended analysis
                of a passage from Lancelot Andrewes gives more detailed examples of how an unfolding
                verbal and semantic structure is answerable to and shaped by our expectations for
                its form and meaning.</note></p>
            <p>The possible complications suggested by letter configurations can be equally
              prolific. Consider illustration 6, showing lines that Erdman transcribes to report
              that Urizen “fixed / The sinew in its rest” (<hi rend="i">BA</hi> 3.32-33). This
              “sinew” was addressed six lines earlier in the poem: “O nerve of that lust form’d
              monster!” A comparison of “ ‘sinew’ ” with the “sinews” of 3.21 (illus. 6, again)
              suggests that the second instance may be trying <hi rend="i">graphically</hi> to
              become—as it is conceptually—both “nerve” and “sinew” at once, a “sinerv.”
Certainly
              the eighteenth-century semantics of “nerve” allows us to think of a “nerve of sin,” a
              new sin constituted with the advent of the Rock: 
			<q> So saying, In torment of his
                wounds.<lb/>
 He bent the enormous ribs slowly;<lb/>
 A circle of darkness! then
                fixed<lb/>
 The sinerv in its rest: then the Rock<lb/>
 Poisonous source! </q>
The
              Rock is, of course, “Mount Sinai. in Arabia.” (Erdman reads “Mount Sinai,” 
                <hi rend="i">BA</hi> 3.46). The (material, graphic) nature of “Sin” is itself
              problematic. According to Erdman, in <hi rend="i">BA</hi> 2.34 Urizen names Ahania:
              “He groand anguishd &amp; called her Sin,”.</p>
            <p>Those who delight in dread terrors may see additional complexities in illustration 7.
              This first chapter of <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi> is much involved with “astronomical”
              cosmology—that is, with the “Globe of Wrath.” The first stanza ends with a description
              of Fuzon and/or his wrath as “Son of Urizens silent burnings” (2.9), and the last
              stanza concludes with the picture of the fiery beam of Fuzon seized by Los and “beat
              in a mass / With the body of the sun.” (2.47-48). The reader’s “contextual
              expectations” must point to the multiple possibilites in calling anything, especially
              “his parted soul” (sol—“<hi rend="i">so n</hi>ame his parted soul”),<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5"
                type="note">5</ref> “S—n.” The graphics of 2.34, through the novel “n” shape and the
              absent dot for the “i” bear out the possibilities. Perhaps what we see happening to
              Urizen, his so[u]lar failing is, indeed, <hi rend="i">identified</hi> in almost all
              its forms as sui-sun-sin, seen one on top of the other rather than linearly. The
              reader’s probable query here is our answer: you reason it out. 
                  <note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Or, to invoke the French Blake might have known: “so
name”: 
                  <hi rend="i">son âme</hi>: “his parted soul.”</note></p>
            <p>Lest this seem too much quibbling over trifles, we should reemphasize one of the
              basic rules of the game: that to change anything that physically appears in Blake’s
              work to an editorial alternative is to “emend” the text in favor of an editorial line
              of interpretation. It is for this reason that the terms of the MLACSE approval state
              “explicit editorial principles” which include the recording of 
<pb id="p18-6" n="6"/>
              “all emendations to the copy-text introduced by the editors” (E VI). In his longest
              comment on any word or line in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 21.44,
              E 809-10), Erdman explains why he did not emend his reading of “warshipped” to
              “worshipped” which would follow the common assumption that the “a” is a simple
              spelling mistake on Blake’s part (this reading is discussed in greater detail below).
              Bentley, on the other hand, prints “worshipped” in his text without comment, leaving
              open the question of whether he <hi rend="i">saw</hi> an “a” and silently changed it
              or instead simply saw and recorded an “o.” For <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> 19.46 Bentley
              notes that “ ‘Enitharmon’ is spelt ‘Enitharman’ ” (<hi rend="i">William Blake’s
                Writings</hi>, I, 266) and presents what he assumes to be the correct spelling in
              his printed text. In his text Erdman prints “Enitharmon” at this point without
              comment. Did he <hi rend="i">see</hi> the “a” and silently correct it? If so, was it
              truly a “correction” or was it an unrecorded emendation to the copy text in violation
              of the MLACSE code? In his note to <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 10.1, Erdman, having
              printed “Enitharmon” in his text, announces explicit disagreement with those who see
              an “a” at this point instead of an “o.” (“Not misspelled ‘Enitharman’ despite
Bentley,
              following Keynes” E 807.)</p>
            <p>There are two levels of interpretation intertwined in these examples. One is the
              graphic at the level of physical perception (“Of course an ‘a’ can look something like
              an ‘o,’ ” Erdman observes). The other level is the still more difficult one of
              authorial intention, which raises the issue of whether or not the letter in question
              may be a “mistake.” These problems are compounded by the issue of editorial policy or
              principle with respect to the category of “mistakes,” and the editorial prerogative—or
              presumption—to make a better “text” than the author/printer William Blake. We believe
              that the reader has the right to know that Blake made “mistakes,” and the even more
              important right to weigh the possibility that what looks like a mistake may not be
              one—that “Enitharman” and “warshipped” and “sinerv” might be meaningful or provide
              clues to meaning. But first one must <hi rend="i">see</hi> the “a” in the place of the
              “o” and the “rv” in the place of the “w.” Erdman does not give us the option of
seeing
              the “a” in “Enitharman,” and Bentley does not give us the option of seeing the “a”
in
              “warshipped.” Neither Editor gives us the synergetic possibilities of seeing
              “sinerv.”</p>
            <p>Another curiosity in the “precise transcription” of Blake’s printing is the practice
              Erdman shares with other Blake Editors of disregarding Blake’s original line shape.
              Presumably to suit the exigencies of typographic economics, Editors often permit
              short, hyphenated lines to be printed straight through, while they gratuitously double
              Blake’s “long resounding” line to suit the dictates of their formats. This is
              inconsequential if the letters and lines are merely abstract linear vehicles of sense;
              but if this is not the case then the practice does violence to the visual semiotics of
              Blake’s printed text. In Blake, perhaps more than most poets, the arrangement of words
              on the printed page has a graphic potential that should not be ignored. Words (and
              sub-units of words) can be meaningfully associated by a vertical contiguity and
              patterning as well as by the more obvious syntagmatic syntactic order exhibited by the
              text. Consider this minor instance from <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> as printed in
              Erdman’s text: 
			<q> 5. But no light from the fires. all was darkness<lb/>
 In the flames
                of Eternal fury<lb/>
 6. In fierce anguish &amp; quenchless flames (5.17-19, E 73)
			</q>
			In Blake’s text—disregarding the diacritical figures and connection-lines which
              we grant to be outside the typographical concern—the reader will find a different
              experience: 
			<q> 5. But no light from the fires. all was darkness<lb/>
 In the flames of
                Eternal fury<lb/>
 6. In fierce anguish &amp; quenchless flames </q>
The text reads
              up and down as well as across; vertical relationships imply a connection between “no
              light / darkness,” “darkness / flames” and “fierce / flames” which is repeated five
              lines later: 
			<q> In howlings &amp; pangs &amp; fierce madness<lb/>
 Long periods in
                burning fires labouring </q>
The cumulative effect of such encoding asserts the
              existence of the “fires” as another presence, so that when “Los shrunk from his task”:
				<q> His great hammer fell from his hand:<lb/>
 His fires beheld, and sickening,<lb/>
                Hid their strong limbs in smoke. (13.21-23) </q>
Such connections lead to the
              core-text of 5.32-34: 
			<q> . . . eternal fires . . .<lb/>
 . . . Eternity . . .<lb/>
 . .
                . sons . . . </q></p>
            <p>So too the first appearance of that son of Eternity, Los, is more problematic if,
              rather than reading the line straight across, we encounter Blake’s arrangement: 
			<q> 8.
                And Los round the dark globe of Urizen (5.38) </q>
(round Los = the dark globe of
              Urizen? = like a black globe . . . like a human heart?) The differences seem even more
              telling when we compare the Editorial version of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> 4.24 with a
              version that follows what Blake printed: 
			<q> 6. Here alone I in books formd of
                metals<lb/>
 6. Here alone I in books formd of metals </q>
It is appropriate enough,
              in this book so polysemously predicated <hi rend="i">of</hi> Urizen, for the
              protagonist, speaking of his books, to describe them and himself as “I in books formd
              of me-.” This mind forgery is one alloyed me-tell.</p>
            <p>The transition to type also alters Blake’s spacing, and so obliterates many
              significant effects. In Blake’s <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> 20.1-2 the exact correlation
              (and thus contrast) of: 
			<q> . . . eternity:<lb/>
 . . . Eternity. </q>
becomes in
              Erdman’s text: 
			<q> Stretch’d for a work of eternity;<lb/>
 No more Los beheld Eternity.
				</q>
	<pb id="p18-7" n="7"/>
For another example in this vein, we note that Blake’s
              “Ah !SUN-FLOWER” (not Erdman’s “Ah! SUN-FLOWER”) begins “Ah Sun-flower ! weary of
              time.” rather than “Ah Sun-flower! weary of time,” as in Erdman (and Bentley and
              Keynes). To conclude these issues regarding “precise transcription,” consider the new
              rendering of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> 3.26: “The petrific abdominable chaos” (the
              MLACSE award assures us that the volume “has been scrupulously and repeatedly
              proofread to prevent unintentional alterations”—but note also the heading, p. 85. The
              editor, to be sure, knows that every “new printing will have its own fresh
              errors”).</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>II. A DIGRESSION ON FORM AT MISE—EN—PAGE</title>
            </head>
			<q> Format: general plan of physical organization or arrangement. </q>
            <p>No matter how unconscious we are of the effects on our mode and mood of perception,
              we are constantly influenced in our reading by how a poem looks on the page. Our first
              glance at a new poem can reveal a traditional form printed in metrically-regulated
              neat stanzas, suggesting among other things how the poem will sound or feel to our
              ears. A glance at a poem in free verse with a wide variety of line lengths will create
              quite different expectations of the nature of what we will be experiencing as we read
              the words. As John Hollander remarks in <hi rend="i">Vision and Resonance</hi>: “The
              very look of the received poem on the page jingles and tinkles today the way neat,
              accentual-syllabic rhyming once did” (New York: Oxford University Press, 1975, p.
              240). Part of the formal content and context of any poem, then, will be perceived in
              our encounter with the image made by the words as they are printed on the page which
              represents our field of vision. For the most part the effects these visual
              arrangements stimulate do not receive our direct attention. We only notice them in a
              printed book when they obtrude themselves upon our consciousness, disturbing the
              generally bland and neutral matrix of subordination that is supportive of the often
              desired effect of reading the poem through a transparent medium.</p>
            <p>The normative tendency in letterpress or offset printing seems to be the disposition
              of words on the page in a way that is essentially arbitrary and meaningless in itself,
              with page breaks simply coming when the available space has run out. With printed
              prose, only paragraph indentations break the monotonous scanning motion of the eyes;
              with poetry a few more flexible and varied options are accommodated by the format, but
              financial expediency and typographical proprieties tend to keep these at a minimum.
              The form of the book is extensively and efficiently coded by the nature of the
              processes involved in its production, and the finished result operates to structure
              the reading process in ways that are compatible with that code. Since reading involves
              the ability to distinguish functional units through visual identification, anything we
              perceive as surrounded by white space will be a semiologically significant unit. In
              conventional typography the units are almost exclusively semantic ones: words, lines,
              paragraphs or stanzas.</p>
            <p>A growing body of research suggests that much of perception, even up to fairly high
              interpretive levels, is automatic and independent of conscious awareness. The effects
              of peripheral vision are especially powerful in this regard, and it has now often been
              shown that what we are unaware of seeing is nonetheless influencing what we see and
              how we feel about the content of our consciously focused vision.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
                type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Cf. Tony Marcel, “Unconscious
                Reading: Experiments on People Who Do Not Know That They Are Reading,” in 
                  <hi rend="i">Visible Language</hi>, 12.4 (Autumn 1978). Julia Kristeva, among others,
                has emphasized the importance of visibility as a component in establishing the
                semiotic modality and meaning of a work: “The lines of a grapheme, disposition on
                the page, length of the lines, blank spaces, etc. . . . contribute to the building
                of a semiotic totality that can be interpreted along multiple paths, a substitute
                for thetic unity.” <hi rend="i">La Revolution du langage poetique</hi> (Paris:
                Seuil, 1974), p. 219.</note></p>
            <p>Further understanding and appreciation of Blake’s poetry calls for more attention to
              conceptual structures in his visual semiotic and to what might be called the visual
              syntax of his written work. “Vision” is a key term for Blake, and the visual form of
              his poetry, especially as it violates traditional linear forms, is an important
              functional element of his work—though even W.J.T. Mitchell, who has advanced our
              understanding of Blake’s “composite art” more than anyone else, still accepts a
              primary distinction between the (non-visual) poetry and the illustrations.<ref
                target="n7" type="note">7</ref> To explore the visual syntax of Blake’s poetry and
              to grasp the visual statements he creates requires paying attention to a variety of
              features that are unavailable in the conventionally presented editions of his work.
                <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> See <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art</hi>
                (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1978). At the “Blake and Criticism”
                Conference held at Santa Cruz in May 1982, Mitchell remarked that while working on
                Blake’s illuminated poetry he “had to have a printed version of the poetry in order
                to read it.”</note></p>
            <p>Among these, perhaps the most fundamental to the emergence of visual form are
              figure-field relationships. Every semantic unit is seen with respect to its
              background, and it establishes its own particular visual presence in terms of its
              magnitude (both size and shape), position, and orientation perceived against this
              background. Some of the main factors which influence our reading of figure-field
              relationships, as pointed out by Arnheim, include texture, spatial proximity, the
              qualities of enclosed forms, vertical distinctions between bottom and top, horizontal
              vs. oblique positioning, convexity of forms, suggestions of overlap, and consistency
              or simplicity (or their opposites) in shape.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">8</ref> Even
              if the visual stimulus is physically two-dimensional, it contains clues that influence
              the viewer’s perception and evoke a reading of implied depth, making the figure-field
              relationship a distinctive aspect of the syntactic meaning. 
                  <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Rudolf Arnheim, <hi rend="i">Art and Visual
Perception</hi> (Berkeley:
                University of California Press, 1954), pp. 32-81.</note></p>
            <p>Reading Blake’s work in the original or in facsimile takes time, which leads most of
              us to try to “get” the poetry from a printed edition while studying the plates for
              purely visual information. Our ability to read has been conditioned by our familiarity
              with traditional linear text forms and the consistent and powerful appearance 
                <pb id="p18-8" n="8"/>
they present, which stimulates and rewards certain conventions of
              reading, while affecting the dynamics of the reading experience. In this experience
              the poem presents itself to the reader as centered within or on a single abstract
              plane. We engage the visual composition at the upper left and scan line after line
              horizontally while picking up information and rhythmic impact visually from variations
              in line length and from variations in typographic forms (e.g., capital letters) and
              punctuation. The margins framing our encounter with the text are typically large,
              neutral, and relatively consistent. The figure-field relationship of the poem is one
              of neutrality, and the interior visual syntax of the poem is empty of significance,
              with maximum consistency in spacing between letters, words, and lines. Where
              variations in spacing are required to justify line-endings they are often made as
              subtle as possible in the attempt to keep them below our threshold of perception.
              Blake’s poetry, in contrast, persistently violates and challenges our assumptions
              about the proper orientation of visual symbols in a field, as well as about their
              shape, size, orientation, color, physical material and texture. There is crucial
              information of a visual-semiotic nature in Blake’s disposition of individual letters,
              words, sentences and other semantic units on his printed page, and in the visual
              boundaries that make such disposition possible. At least some of these effects can be
              hinted at even within the physical and economic constraints of the typographic medium,
              and Editors of Blake should be much more imaginative and insistent in their attempts
              to do so.</p>
            <p>The format of individual pages in a book is of course only part of the impact made by
              the material form of the text on the reader. There are numerous intrinsic properties
              attendant upon the design and order of books and their component parts. The effects
              generated by the emblematic characteristics of the book will constitute a significant
              part of the terms on which the contents of the book are offered and received. In the
              conventional printed book the assignment of text to a given page is arbitrary or even
              accidental; yet the turning of a page is a vital act performed by the reader, one
              which is structured in relation to the poem’s form and meaning by where and how the
              text has been separated by the printer. To quibble over commas and periods, while
              randomly introducing “punctuation” on the magnitude of page division, is a bit like
              swallowing the camel and choking on a gnat, in terms of the impact on the visual and
              semantic structure of the work. Divisions that Blake made are not functionally
              present, while divisions he did not make are operative—and juxtapositions can be as
              significant as divisions. How are we to measure the impact of Erdman’s page 144, where
              the “Finis” of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> is separated from the title 
                <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> by only ¾ of an inch and the intervening two-leafed tendril that
he
              used at tops of pages in <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> (illus. 8)?</p>
            <p>Blake’s constant attention to the overall form of his “books” and to minute formal
              nuance within them should pose a challenge to the Editor to try to achieve as many of
              Blake’s effects as the typographic medium will allow (as David Erdman does, for
              example, in his remarkable edition of <hi rend="i">The Notebook of William
              Blake</hi>), rather than disguising those effects and lulling the reader into
              believing that he is getting the “book” as well as the poetry in the book. This might
              lead to expensive decisions about blank space in some cases and non-blank space (e.g.,
              narrow or minimal margins) in others. It might not be considered worth it to print 
                <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> on only one side as Blake did, but the possibility should be
              considered before going to press, along with the possibility of presenting the text in
              the original bicolumnar form which constitutes one of its most conspicuous and
              meaningful features. <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> is an especially important
              case in point, because in it Blake was concerned not only with “writing” but also with
              the “bookishness” of the book, with the problem of the book as an object, a volume
              which offers its contents <hi rend="i">in terms of its physical and formal properties
                as an object.</hi> Blake’s <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> is designed within a specific
              historical and contextual field of purposes, conventions and assumptions; yet while
              designed within them, it is also engaged with them in intellectual warfare. Blake’s
              books are addressed to the “Reader! of books!”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n9" type="note">9</ref>
              Blake did not “write texts”—he made books which posed a critique of the book-making
              practices of his own era, and which challenge all future readers and editors to
              confront the nature of books as material embodiments of texts. 
                  <note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Or to the “Reader! <hi rend="i">[lover]</hi> of
books!” or to the
                “Reader ! <hi rend="i">lover</hi> of books!” (the first from E 145; the second from
                the Trianon Press typographical reprint included with its facsimile
              [1952]).</note></p>
            <p>If we move from considerations of format at the level of 
                <hi rend="i">mise-en-page</hi> to the organization of the volume as a whole, we encounter
              difficulties with Erdman’s text that are not necessarily limited to the typographic
              medium of reproduction. Erdman continues to reject the organizing principle of
              chronology that leads other Editors to attempt to present Blake’s works in the order
              of their composition. Instead, he conceives of four more or less parallel chronologies
              which are presented consecutively: works in illuminated printing; “prophetic works”
              never engraved; other works, mostly lyrical, never engraved; and miscellaneous “late
              prose treatises, marginalia and letters.” Within each of these categories “a rough
              chronology is observed, but only when thematic or generic relations fail to offer more
              meaningful groupings” (XXIII). The lines separating these categories are somewhat
              obscured by their numbering, with the first two each marked by its own Roman numeral,
              the third category marked by five Roman numerals (III-VII) and the fourth marked by
              eight Roman numerals (VIII-XV). Within these subdivisions a section like 
                <hi rend="i">The Everlasting Gospel</hi> or the 1809 <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>
may
              occupy a specific moment in Blake’s career, while others—the letters for
              instance—encompass its whole range. The fundamental 
<pb id="p18-9" n="9"/>
              organizational unit, in other words, is not chronology but format (a format most
              wearing on the book after even moderate use). We must therefore note that while
              Blake’s production format is deleted or effaced by editorial and print technologies,
              some aspects of his actual format survive in E in this awkward and vestigial
              organizational structure.</p>
            <p>There are further consequences and complications. Erdman sensibly prints 
                <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> back to back,
              whereas a stricter chronological principle (as followed by Keynes and Bentley) would
              have had to place <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> among the later Lambeth books—next to
                <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, perhaps, where another set of thematic implications might
              appropriately be emphasized. Better still might be to print 
                <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> twice, once where E has it then again later on with 
                <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, thereby reflecting at least some of the shifts and revisions
which
              this new context suggests. There were not, after all, <hi rend="i">always</hi> two
              contrary states of the human soul. In Blake’s project, one printing of title A can
              precede a printing of title B, with a reprinting of title A following B and
              incorporating revisions inspired by B. A<hi rend="s">2</hi> could influence changes
              made in a printing of B<hi rend="s">2</hi> so that a satisfactory chronology of
              Blake’s works cannot be determined solely on the basis of first copy (e.g.,
              title-plate date). Even if all these dates were clearly determinable, which they are
              not, Blake’s ongoing revisions render the establishment of a chronological canon of
              his work—even within Erdman’s format categories—essentially problematic.</p>
            <p>We must conclude that there is no clearly satisfactory answer to the editorial
              problems imposed by the nature of Blake’s <hi rend="i">oeuvre</hi> and by the decision
              to publish “all” of Blake in a single volume. A one-volume Blake reduces much of the
              potential integrity of individual books, and physically limits and prestructures the
              potential range of patterns of relations between them. The sense in which we can have
              “all” of Blake in a single volume might therefore induce in the reader even more than
              the usual sensation of claustrophobia, of being—with Macbeth—“cabin’d, cribb’d,
              confined, bound in.” If the desire of the reader of Blake is truly Infinite, so that
              “less than All cannot satisfy,” then that desire will be to have more truly at his or
              her disposal <hi rend="i">all</hi> of Blake—individual photographic copies, at least,
              of every copy of every illuminated book, every manuscript and notebook and annotated
              book and letter: A Complete Blake Unbound, the imagined existence of which will
              provide the best measure of the inevitable limitations of any specific Editorial
              production.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>III. [MORE] MINUTE PARTICULARS</title>
            </head>
            <p>Let us return to the problem of Blake’s punctuation, with the honest and grateful
              acknowledgement that David Erdman has done more than any previous editor to free us
              from our programed desire for conventional syntax. Erdman is, in places, not at all
              uncomfortable with Blake’s short periods: 
			<q> 2. That Energy. calld Evil. is alone
                from the Body.<lb/>
 &amp; that Reason. calld Good. is alone from the Soul.<lb/> 
                  (<hi rend="i">MHH</hi> 4, E 34) </q>
Such periods break up completion. logical syntax,
              and invite the reader. to a more active, participation in the production of text.
              Blake could use commas elegantly when he chose, as in the following quotation (where
              our reading of <hi rend="i">MHH</hi> copy D tallies exactly with that offered on E
              39): 
			<q> But first the notion that man has a body distinct from his soul, is to be
                expunged; this I shall do, by printing in the infernal method, by corrosives, which
                in Hell are salutary and medicinal, melting apparent surfaces away, and displaying
                the infinite which was hid. </q></p>
            <p>But still, there are more periods in Blake than in Erdman, and we need to accept them
              as such if we are truly to grapple with the at times discontinuous folds of Blake’s
              syntax. “Truth can never be told so as to be understood. and not be believ’d.” (E
              reads “understood,”). “I must Create a System. or be enslav’d by another Mans” (E
              reads “System,”). Periods can be banished completely, rather than be demoted to
              commas, if Erdman finds them “intrusive” (E 808), as he does the one after “dance” in
                <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 26.3:
<q> Thou seest the gorgeous clothed Flies that dance
                &amp; sport in summer<lb/>
 Upon the sunny brooks &amp; meadows: every one the
                dance[.]<lb/>
 Knows in its intricate mazes of delight artful to weave: (E 123) </q>
              With the removal of this “intrusive” period vanishes the mazing possibility of weaving
              not only a dance of Flies, but also a dance of sunny brooks and meadows. So vanishes,
              perhaps, another “Period” in which “the Poets Work is Done”, that startling stop in
              which, by which, “Events of Time start forth &amp; are concievd in such a Period”
              (29.1-2). In Blake’s “London” (E 27), we can instructively compare lines 5-8 as
              transcribed by Erdman with what appears in copy C: 
			<q> In every cry of every Man,<lb/>
                In every Infants cry of fear,<lb/>
 In every voice: in every ban,<lb/>
 The
                mind-forg’d manacles I hear<lb/>
<lb/>
 In every cry of every Man.<lb/>
 In every
                Infants cry of fear.<lb/>
 In every voice: in every ban.<lb/>
 The mind-forg’d
                manacles I hear </q>
The next stanza of the poem, amplifying the unending line of
              the preceding one and the first line of the last, gives us an example of Blake’s
              vertical ordering that does not elude the typographic medium: 
                <pb id="p18-10" n="10"/><q> The mind-forg’d manacles <hi rend="i">I hear</hi><lb/>
<lb/>
 How the
                Chimney-sweepers cry<lb/>
 Every blackning Church appalls,<lb/>
 And the hapless
                Soldiers sign<lb/>
 Runs in blood down Palace walls<lb/>
<lb/>
 But most thro’ midnight
                streets <hi rend="i">I hear</hi><lb/>
 (E 27, emphasis added<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
                  type="note">10</ref>) <note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> For further discussion,
                  see Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Literal Imagination: Blake’s Vision of Words</hi>
                  (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1983), pp. 63-66.</note></q></p>
            <p>Another minute particular involves what Erdman calls “one kind of 
                <hi rend="i">silent</hi> insertion”—the occasional addition of an apostrophe to the
possessive
              of Los. Without the apostrophe, Erdman notes, we are “otherwise subject to confusion
              with ‘Loss’ ” (E 787). So, for example, we have this Editor’s Spectre “driven to
              desperation by Los’s terrors &amp; threatning fears” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 10.28, E 153)
              rather than by “Loss terrors &amp; threatning fears”. Yet the Spectre speaks precisely
              out of an intense sense of loss (“Where is my lovely Enitharmon,” “Life lives on my /
              Consuming”). Blake knows as well as Milton or Lacan that our feeling of “loss” feeds
              (“unwearied labouring &amp; weeping”) our emotional and imaginative life. Los’s
              possession is loss (to our profit);<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">11</ref> and these
              references can be connected to the solar aspect of Los’s name as well, for when we can
              go inside out and see even our sun as a loss, then we have solace. 
                  <note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> On this still much neglected pun, see also Aaron Fogel,
“Pictures
                of Speech: On Blake’s Poetic,” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 21 (Summer
                1982), 224.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>IV. PART<lb/>
 ICULAR MINUTENESSES: A DIGRESSI<lb/> 
 ON THEORETICAL IMPLICATIONS</title>
            </head>
			<q> I have a disease: I see language (Barthes)<lb/>
<lb/>
 For the weak, merely to begin
              to think about the first letter of the alphabet might make them run mad forthwith.
              (Rimbaud)<lb/>
<lb/>
 For A is the beginning of learning and the door of heaven.
              (Smart)<lb/>
<lb/>
 For that (the rapt one warns) is what papyr is meed of, made of,
              hides and hints and misses in prints. Till ye finally (though not yet endlike) meet
              with the acquaintance of Mister Typus, Mistress Tope and all the little typtopies.
              Fillstup. (Joyce) </q>
            <p>One would not presume to speak of—or practice—<hi rend="i">editing</hi> a painting or
              a sculpture, no matter how valuable and useful the attempt to represent such objects
              in photographic and book form may be, because of the essential materiality of their
              mode of existence. Nor, we would assume, would anyone try to correct Joyce’s spelling
              in <hi rend="i">Finnegans Wake</hi> in order to make it easier for the reader to get
              at the “text” of Joyce’s work. The problems with the Erdman edition and related
              matters we have been discussing so far have all been within the context of exploring
              and recommending what is <hi rend="i">possible</hi> in attempting to achieve a
              typographic representation of Blake’s work. In this digression we will emphasize even
              more the negative (the Loss) in any edition of Blake that uses typography. We do so
              not in the spirit of fetishizing the unique original as a sacred relic, or of endowing
              it with some magical authority because it was physically assembled by Blake, but
              rather from the conviction that a significant part of the <hi rend="i">complete</hi>
              poetry of the illuminated books is a visual-verbal semiotic in which form and meaning
              cannot be separated from material substance, or the adequate representation of the
              materiality of substance.</p>
            <p>We wish to call attention to the visual aspects of linguistic communication in
              writing in general, but more particularly in Blake, as our concern moves from an
              awareness of graphic space as a structural agent on a large scale (page format and
              “book”) to the minutiae; from an emphasis on the spatial-structural relationships of
              the linguistic materials to the actual materiality of the signifiers: their
              “concreteness” in a perhaps metaphorical sense, their “visibility” in a literal
              sense.</p>
            <p>There seems to be a pervasive cultural and intellectual tendency to suppress the
              graphic element of writing, its graphology. For the general linguistic approach to the
              study of language, the primary function of writing systems (with the occasional
              exception of ideographic or hieroglyphic forms) is to give phonological information.
              But <hi rend="i">ink</hi>—like air disturbed into sound and patterned into words—can
              also be a linguistically patterned substance, a different medium, and one which by its
              very nature is not invisible or transparent. Yet the typographic production of books
              in the usual manner strives for invisibility or transparency of its signifiers in the
              service of the idealized “text.” If we print or write the word “red” in red ink, there
              may be a non-arbitrary relationship between the <hi rend="i">graphic</hi> signifier
              and its signified; and this is only a simple and obvious instance. As soon as we come
              down with the Barthesian dis-ease of “seeing language” we enter a combined semantic
              and visual semiotic field in which an enormous range of meaningful effects becomes
              possible. For Blake this was not a neutral possibility, but a poetic necessity:
              “Writing / Is the Divine Revelation in the Litteral expression” (<hi rend="i">M</hi>
              42.13-14, E 143), and the <hi rend="i">literal letter</hi> (Lat. 
                <hi rend="i">littera</hi>) is the medium of the revelation, as doubly indicated by Blake’s
              spelling. Earlier we mentioned that Mitchell, in his valuable book, has separated the
              poetic text from the visual text in his dialectical approach to Blake’s composite art.
              We want to suggest that something like Mitchell’s “dialectic” is going on within the
              poetry itself, and that more attention to and respect for that visual form is long
              overdue, to appreciate a different form of “composite” art which combines a heightened
              visual and acoustic attention to Blake’s signifiers (i.e., <hi rend="i">not</hi> to
              his “text”).</p>
            <p>To “see” words can be considered a disease because it is non-normative. It may be
              typical, as Freud said, of the state of consciousness present in dreams, but it is a
              deviational mode of attention verging on epistemological error in our ordinary state,
              much as attention to particulars was aesthetic error for Reynolds’ aesthetic of the
              grand style. Linguistics tends to share this attitude through its definition of the
              mode of existence of language, with graphological forms as purely arbitrary indicators
              of phonological 
<pb id="p18-11" n="11"/>
acts. The historical theory and practice of
              typography are complicitous with the same set of assumptions and values. The
              fundamental aim of typography as a practical discipline is to achieve a state of
              invisibility, a type so “legible” that the reader looks <hi rend="i">through</hi> it
              not <hi rend="i">at</hi> it. How are we to understand this self-effacement? The goal
              in this practice is to make print a perfectly functional <hi rend="i">language
                medium</hi>, which is to ignore the difference between spoken and written
              utterance—to ignore the fact that the necessity of vision is built into the production
              of writing, the reproduction of writing, and the reception of writing in the literate
              mind.</p>
            <p>It is one of the strongest conventions within the dominant mode of book production
              that the materiality of the printed sign-vehicle be ignored as non-iconic. It is not
              printing per se that is at issue, for Blake printed his own work from what he called
              “stereotypes,” adopting the word from conventional printers’ usage. It is rather the
              desire to make the medium transparent in the service of a disembodied “text” which
              negates Blake’s persistent efforts to exploit the materiality of his mode of
              production as a significant part of the potential meaning of his work. The form of
              Blake’s work signals a change of signfunction, with its marked departure from linear
              printing, and challenges the reader to a different mode of reading. We are arguing
              that it is neither a “service” to Blake nor to the reader of Blake to make the
              experience of reading him easy or convenient. It may at first seem fanciful to suggest
              that to “buy” meaning from Blake requires—in the sense of classical economics—an
              exchange of <hi rend="i">labor</hi> of comparable value. But Blake could easily have
              “written” his works for the typesetter and saved himself and us enormous
              labors—especially us, since his writings would very likely not have been published at
              all. How much of what he put into his “works” can we get out if we continue to make
              things as easy as possible?<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12"
type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n12"><hi
                  rend="s">12</hi> Cf. the policy of the Longman Annotated English Poets Series, as
                written by F.W. Bateson: “the series concerns itself primarily with the meaning . .
                . . whatever impedes the reader’s sympathetic identification with the poet . . .
                whether of spelling, punctuation or the use of initial capitals—must be regarded as
                undesirable” (<hi rend="i">The Poems of William Blake</hi>, ed. W.H. Stevenson
                [London: Longman, 1971], p. ix). Although this edition is described on the title
                page as having “text by David V. Erdman” (i.e. poems <hi rend="i">of</hi> Blake,
                text <hi rend="i">by</hi> Erdman), the policy of the series produces (and, of
                course, copyrights) a “text” <hi rend="i">out of</hi> the “text”—a “text” which
asks
                us to identify sympathetically with its text-destroying pretense that “writing/Is
                the divine revelation in the literal expression—.”</note></p>
            <p>What we mean by the “iconic” dimension of Blake’s writing is not a naive privileging
              of the authority of the author’s own handwriting as authenticating “signature” of
              presence. It is more like the definition that Peirce gave of a 
                <hi rend="i">motivated</hi> relationship between the iconic sign and its object, where the
              iconic sign is “like [some]thing and used as a sign of it.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13"
                type="note">13</ref> We would not limit our use of “iconic” as Peirce does, to cases
              where the qualities of the iconic sign must “resemble” those of its denotatum and
              “excite analogous sensations in the mind for which it is a likeness” (p. 168), because
              resemblance is too narrow a limit to assign to the iconic-function potential.
              Resemblance is only the most obvious of the motivating connections that can exist
              between the shape of individual letters, their combination into words and larger
              units, their color, material substance and form, and what those letters mean, or stand
              for, or represent, or signify. <note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Charles Sanders
                Peirce, <hi rend="i">Elements of Logic, Collected Works</hi>, vol. 2, ed. Hartshorne
                and Weiss (Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1932), p. 143.</note></p>
            <p>To maintain that Blake’s writing is visible or iconic means that a signifying process
              is functioning which cuts through, disrupts, and challenges the ordinary reading
              process without necessarily destroying it or superseding it. Blake’s signifying
              practice must be sensed through both auditory and visual means, and there is no reason
              why the same writing cannot give evidence of both operations simultaneously at work—or
              play. In this context we want to return to the instance of “warshipped” mentioned
              above, and the difficulty in determining whether it is, in Erdman’s words, 
                “<hi rend="i">an error for</hi> worshipped” or “<hi rend="i">possibly a punning
                coinage.</hi>” What we have here is not simply a physical question of seeing, but a
              complex perceptual field which includes the possibility that a problem of seeing (“o”
              or “a”) may relate to a mode of hearing. Tony Tanner has argued for a conceptual
              relationship between puns and adultery in the novel, suggesting that two meanings that
              don’t belong together in the same word are like two people who don’t belong together
              in the same bed.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref>
Tanner’s is an important
              comparison, because there is in each case a “law” of propriety that is being broken.
              The overdetermination of a lexeme by multiple meanings that it does not carry in
              ordinary usage violates a cultural sense of textual and linguistic propriety. When
              this happens in Blake, the visual lexeme can be an important functional component of
              the auditory experience, and provide a simultaneous violation of the linearity and
              univocity of discourse (cf. illus. 9). <note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> “ . . . we
                may say that puns and ambiguities are to common language what adultery and
                perversion are to ‘chaste’ (i.e., socially orthodox) sexual relations. They both
                bring together entities (meanings/people) that have ‘conventionally’ been
                differentiated and kept apart; and they bring them together in deviant ways,
                bypassing the orthodox rules governing communications and relationships. (A pun is
                like an adulterous bed in which two meanings that should be separated are coupled
                together). It is hardly an accident that <hi rend="i">Finnegans Wake</hi>, which
                arguably demonstrates the dissolution of bourgeois society, is almost one continuous
                pun (the connection with sexual perversion being quite clear to Joyce).” 
                  <hi rend="i">Adultery in the Novel</hi> (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press,
                1979), p. 53.</note></p>
            <p>We want to emphasize that we are not dealing here with a trivial textual crux, which
              may or may not be resolved definitively by improved photographic techniques. We are
              dealing with an editorial practice (relaxed in this case by Erdman), with ontological
              notions of the “text” that call for a typographical transparency in the material
              manifestation of that text. When Byron yearned for words that are things, he was using
              a metaphor implying a non-human language, the unmediated generative speech of God, or
              at least a long-lost referentiality of language. But the Blake text insists on the
              materiality of its words as things in a <hi rend="i">literally literal</hi> sense, the
              sense in which Freud could say that “Words are a plastic material with which one can
              do all kinds of things,” and the sense in which W. H. Stevenson is ironically 
                <hi rend="i">not</hi> being literal when he changes Blake’s “Litteral.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15"
                type="note">15</ref> Freud frequently uses metaphors of writing in his
              representation of the unconscious. In <hi rend="i">The Interpretation of Dreams</hi>
              he speaks of the symbolism of dreams in general as a cryptography or rebus, a
              hieroglyphic or pictographic script, but notes more specifically that “It is true . .
              . that words are treated in dreams as though they were concrete things, and for that
              reason they are apt to be combined in just the same way as presentations of concrete
              things. Dreams of this sort offer the most amusing and curious neologisms.”<ref
                target="n16" type="note">16</ref> For Freud words are presented in the unconscious
              in ways that must be distinguished from the perceptual mode of consciousness, which
              looks through the word only for its lexically coded signification. Something that is
              ordinarily 
<pb id="p18-12" n="12"/>
invisible to consciousness is ordinarily visible
              in the unconscious, and the interpreter must see language differently, must stop short
              before the accepted or expected meaning of a word in order to perceive language in its
              material density. A certain amount of regression may help the interpreter in this
              enterprise, since “the habit of still treating words as things” is most common in
              children, and is “rejected and studiously avoided by serious thought.”<ref
                target="n17" type="note">17</ref>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Sigmund Freud,
                  <hi rend="i">Jokes and their Relation to the Unconscious</hi> (New York: W.W.
                Norton, 1960), p. 34; on Stevenson, see note 12, above.</note>
	<note id="n16"><hi
                  rend="s">16</hi> Sigmund Freud, <hi rend="i">The Interpretation of Dreams</hi>,
                tr. James Strachey (New York: Basic Books, n.d.), pp. 295-96.</note>	
                  <note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Freud, <hi rend="i">Jokes and their Relation to the
                  Unconscious</hi>, p. 120. Freud’s formulation here suggests that the “habit” is
                not automatically outgrown. It must be rejected and studiously avoided, and “when we
                make serious use of words we are obliged to hold ourselves back with a certain
                effort from this comfortable procedure” (p. 119).</note></p>
            <p>When Freud moves on in Chapter V of <hi rend="i">Jokes and their Relation to the
                Unconscious</hi> to consider the general question of the subjective determinants of
              jokes, he makes some interesting speculations on the relationship between joke-work
              and the infantile as the source of the unconscious, suggesting that “the thought
              which, with the intention of constructing a joke, plunges into the unconscious is
              merely seeking there for the ancient dwelling place of its former play with words.
              Thought is put back for a moment to the stage of childhood so as once more to gain
              possession of the childish source of pleasure” (p. 170). But playing with words, like
              playing with feces, is not countenanced by authoritative parents (or editors). Thus,
              “it is not very easy for us to catch a glimpse in children of this infantile way of
              thinking, with its peculiarities that are retained in the unconscious of adults,
              because it is for the most part corrected, as it were, <hi rend="i">in statu
                nascendi</hi>” (p. 170). It may well be that a large part of the editor-work is
              operating over against something like Freud’s joke-work in the production of the
              idealized Blake “text.” Freud emphasizes that the “laugh” can function as a
              confirmation of the possibility that <hi rend="i">Witz</hi> has a profound
              relationship to instinctual drives already at work in infancy. Laughter can dismiss as
              “children’s ‘silliness’ ” that which the adult must reject and studiously avoid when
              he makes “serious use of words.” In this context the laughter advocated by a serious
              arbiter of the arts takes on a certain nervous resonancy: “One would laugh at a writer
              who would wish his text to be printed now in small unspaced type fonts, now in large
              spaced ones, or in ascending and descending lines, in inks of different colors, and
              other such things.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Alain, <hi rend="i">Systeme des Beaux-Arts</hi>, in <hi rend="i">Les
                  Artes et les dieux</hi> (Paris: Gallimard, 1958), p. 439, quoted in Leon S.
                Roudiez, “Readable/Writable/Visible,” <hi rend="i">Visible Language</hi>, 12.3
                (Summer 1978), 240.</note></p>
            <p>What we can see and hear in Blake is influenced by what we expect to see and want to
              see; our desires for a purely phonological information and a “pure” lexical
              codification of that information make it difficult both to see and to accept the
              unexpected. To put a letter different from the expected one is a disruptive act, one
              which has the effect of engaging with other signifiers in the near vicinity. This
              engagement can be visual (we can see “ear” in “hear” or “orc” in “force” or
“los” in
              “close”) and phonetic. The surrounding visual and phonemic area becomes charged and
              structured (or unstructured and skewed) in ways not immediately or ordinarily
              available to consciousness in conventional reading. Such disruptions hint at the force
              of a desire which is ordinarily censored, a desire for play, for unconfinedness, for
              regression, perhaps even for subversion. But to speculate on the identity of the force
              of desire requires a recognition of the effects of that desire, and an unconscious
              mode of censorship that screens out “what ought not to be” in the text, in language,
              in the psyche—with hints of an uncanny gap between the subject and his discourse in
              which “language” seems to be acting on its own, or where the unconscious usurps
              language as the servant of a subversive desire rather than the servant of
              well-mannered thought and the communication of sharable meaning. As Wordsworth
              observed, in commenting on how words can be “things”: “ . . . they are 
                <hi rend="i">powers</hi> either to kill or animate . . . a counter-spirit, unremittingly and
              noiselessly at work to derange, to subvert, to lay waste, to vitiate, and to
                dissolve.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref> At
times editing can seem to a kind
              of toilet training of the text, or the work of a normalizing or idealizing airbrush
              removing all blemishes on its pure surface. Too often with the “blemishes” go a whole
              range of potential semiotic effects produced at the level of the letter, rather than
              the word or the sentence.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20"
type="note">20</ref>
	<note id="n19"><hi
                  rend="s">19</hi> “Essay on Epitaphs II,” in <hi rend="i">The Prose Works of
                  William Wordsworth</hi>, ed. W.J.B. Owen and Jane W. Smyser (Oxford: Clarendon
                Press, 1974), pp. 84-85.</note>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> When such effects
                can’t be censored <hi rend="i">in statu nascendi</hi> as Freud suggests, they can be
                laughed at as childish. If they can’t be laughed at, the metaphors that become
                available for describing them are revealing. Susanne Langer has argued against the
                possibility of a “marriage” between the visual and the verbal in art, asserting that
                there are “no happy marriages . . . only successful rape” (<hi rend="i">Problems of
                  Art: Ten Philosophical Lectures</hi> [New York, 1957], p. 86, quoted in Mitchell,
                  <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art</hi>, p. 3). The metaphor of rape is even
                stronger than Tanner’s analogy between puns and adultery. Under the rubric of the
                “concealed offense,” Kenneth Burke discusses various puns and sound effects among
                “the many modes of criminality hidden beneath the surface of art” (see 
                  <hi rend="i">The Philosophy of Literary Form</hi> [Berkeley: University of California Press,
                1973], pp. 51-66).</note></p>
            <p>If we are right in our emphasis on the integral semiotic significance of the visible
              signifier in Blake, a number of consequences follow. For example, the question of
              “format” raised above becomes even more complex. If we load the individual letters
              with significant visibility, then the contextual field in which they appear will be
              changed also, with an even greater emphasis on the complete two-dimensional page over
              against the more limited linear path traced through the page by the normal itinerary
              of the printed text. Printing itself is not the problem, as we have said before. The
              main criterion for print is simply the existence of an “image carrier” that allows
              large numbers of nearly identical images to be produced from it. The image carrier can
              be anything from an engraved plate to a letterpress form to a photographic film or
              magnetic tape. The unique feature of Blake’s printing in the illuminated books is that
              he was printing traces or representations of marks he himself had made (“Grave the
              sentence deep”—and print it). Thus although he produced printed works, they
              retained—even before he did additional work on the prints—evidence of what Arnheim has
              called “writing behavior,” pointing out that “to the extent to which a reader
              perceives written material as the product of writing behavior, kinesthetic overtones
              will resonate in the visual experience of reading,” producing kinesthetic connotations
              that tend to transform our perception of the field from a vertical to a horizontal
              field of action. The implied <hi rend="i">motor behavior</hi> of writing thus
              emphasizes the surface of the page “as a microcosm of human activity, dominated by the
              symbolism of relations to the self: close and distant, far and near, outgoing and
              withholding, active and passive.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21"
type="note">21</ref> Blake’s
              writing behavior when he was engraving words on a plate was different from his
              manuscript activity when working on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, 
                <pb id="p18-13" n="13"/>
which poses additional considerations of its own—some of which will
be
              taken up in the next section. But his mode of production insisted on making that
              writing behavior visible, with the consequences that we have been trying to emphasize.
              It is unusual, more difficult to read, calls for a different mode of attention, and
              reminds us that the body was involved in the process of production. When Blake invokes
              his muses, he asks them to descend “down the Nerves of my right arm” 
                (<hi rend="i">M</hi> 2.6, E 96). <note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> “Spatial Aspects of
                Graphological Expression,” <hi rend="i">Visible Language</hi>, 12.2 (Spring 1978),
                167.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">V. FURTHER [INSOLUBLE?] PROBLEMS</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
			<q> The complexities of the ms, in short, continue to defy analysis and all assertions
              about meaningful physical groupings or chronologically definable layers of composition
              or inscription must be understood to rest on partial and ambiguous evidence. (Erdman
              on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>) </q>
            <p>What if we then accept this as the major edition, accept its inevitable errors or
              questionable readings, accept its concessions to print technology—is that all one need
              say? One’s belief in the necessity of such concessions is dependent on a sense of the
              necessity of print editions themselves; and if we read Erdman’s <hi rend="i">as
                if</hi> it were Blake’s own text, even knowing that it is not, it will be in order
              to avoid a constant consideration of the concessions, or in order to induce one’s
              students into a more immediate, unmediated confrontation with the text. But this
              review continues to exercise lingering doubts about editing and typography themselves,
              about their very necessity.</p>
            <p>A Shakespeare editor must be concerned that variations between the Folio and Quarto
              editions of <hi rend="i">King Lear</hi> represent different and perhaps irreconcilable
              notions of how the play was written or performed at different times.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
                type="note">22</ref> With differences in performances, print is resubmerged in
              subsequent productions; these productions tend not only to reinterpret but to re-edit
              the play as well. The problem is not simply one of editorial methodology but of
              fundamental differences between performance and print situations, differences obscured
              or obliterated by the phenomenology of print itself. In the case of Blake the problem
              is just as striking, for here we are obviously faced with different forms of print,
              materially different values of production. Blake’s production is itself a performance
              situation, a “scene of writing” which continually draws attention to itself as
              graphological production. The possible “sinerv” of <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi> or 
                <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>’s “books formd of me- / -tals” are not only polysemous, they
              also rouse the reader to such a graphological awareness. Someone is/was actually
              writing. If print is so fixed and final and regular as to be virtually self-effacing,
              Blake’s writing is self-reflective or reflexive as material production and multifold
              in both meaning and form. It is now commonly believed that Blake’s methods of
              engraving and copperplate printing purposefully set themselves apart from
              industrially-determined print technologies; his practice may even have constituted an
              active critique or subversion of what Walter Benjamin has called the age of mechanical
              reproduction, anticipating Brecht’s combined aesthetic and ideological insistence on
              exhibiting—rather than hiding—the means of producing the artistic effect.<ref
                target="n23" type="note">23</ref> The variety in the existing copies of the 
                <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> may lead us to constitute, in part, a sense of a kind of
              metamorphic variance under a general controlling aegis or governing form which we call
              “the” <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi> But in another sense, those varieties undermine and
              contradict the very notion of such a generality. It is difficult to speak of the 
                <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> entirely as if “it” were a single text, and such a difficulty
              can be very useful for Blake’s readers. The printed hybrid editions, however, rob the
              reader of that difficulty by presenting an editorial fiction based on the implicit
              assumption of the existence of an “ideal text” which they are representing in the most
              adequate fashion. If this is the case, then <hi rend="i">any</hi> print edition, no
              matter how “accurate” to the letter of the text, will necessarily represent a counter
              subversion, a recuperation of Blake’s text by the very forces it sought to oppose.
                <note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> The problems of editing Shakespeare in general,
                and <hi rend="i">Lear</hi> in particular, have led to a powerful interrogation of
                conventional editorial practices, and to the disturbing necessity of facing the
                existence of multiple substantive texts of <hi rend="i">Lear.</hi> The trailblazing
                essay on this topic is that of Michael J. Warren, “Quarto and Folio 
                  <hi rend="i">King Lear</hi> and the Interpretation of Albany and Edgar,” in David
Bevington
                and Jay L. Halio, eds., <hi rend="i">Shakespeare: Pattern of Excelling Nature</hi>
                (Newark: University of Delaware Press, 1978), pp. 95-107. The theatrical
                differentiation of the Quarto and Folio versions has been explored in great detail
                by Steven Urkowitz in <hi rend="i">Shakespeare’s Revision of King Lear</hi>
                (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1980). A volume of essays focusing on the
                two texts of <hi rend="i">Lear</hi> and on the editing tradition, edited by Gary
                Taylor and Michael J. Warren, is forthcoming from Oxford (to be called 
                  <hi rend="i">The Division of the Kingdom</hi>). The relationship between editing practice
and
                typography has been extensively explored by Randall McLeod in a number of articles
                that are pertinent to our critique in a variety of ways, most recently in “UN
                Editing Shak-speare,” <hi rend="i">SubStance</hi> 33/34, 12.1 (1982),
                26-55.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> For an excellent discussion of
                Blake’s practice in the context of the commercial norms of the time, see Morris
                Eaves, “Blake and the Artistic Machine: An Essay in Decorum and Technology,” 
                  <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi> 92.5 (October 1977), 903-927.</note></p>
            <p>One of Erdman’s many virtues as an editor is that he has always tended to be
              hospitable to minute graphological particulars. If print forces the necessity of
              compromise, he makes fewer than most editors. Earlier editors were so accommodating to
              the standards of print and public taste that they often seemed like schoolteachers
              correcting a messy or overly-inventive child. Where Keynes, for instance, regularly
              normalized spelling and punctuation, one always feels a greater confidence in Erdman
              because he tends <hi rend="i">not</hi> to normalize, because his editions look more
              like the original texts, even though not as much like them as print technology might
              allow if fully exploited. If we have taken occasion in this review to indicate
              passages where Erdman is not fully consistent with this practice, where he does
              normalize, it should not be taken as a sign that we fail to appreciate his work as the
              considerable advance over previous editions which it often is. Indeed, if anything, we
              might express the fear that these virtues constitute a danger if they lull the reader
              into a false confidence that he now has the Blake “text” in his hands, lacking only
              the illustrations for a full encounter with the author.</p>
            <p>Editorial sensibility and technological strictures weigh heavily on this new edition,
              and are perhaps nowhere so evident as in Erdman’s treatment of <hi rend="i">The Four
                Zoas</hi>—especially Night VII, which provides also the single most radical
              editorial change from the old E. The problems here are exceedingly complex, and in
              some ways might be considered exemplary: a history of editorial approaches to Night
              VII alone could provide a useful study of the ways in which Blake’s text has been
              processed and disseminated. There are too many approaches to describe them all in the
              space of this review, but readers who need a fuller sense of the issues involved
              should 
<pb id="p18-14" n="14"/>
consult <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 46 (Summer 1978),
              which contains studies of the Night VII problem by John Kilgore, Andrew Lincoln, Mark
              Lefebvre and Erdman, and which provides indispensable aid for a full understanding of
              what Erdman calls his “drastic rearrangement” of Night VII.</p>
            <p>The problem, of course, is that Blake left two Nights titled “Night the Seventh,” and
              no fully reliable clues to their probable order or priority; the editor’s task is to
              find ways to present them in print. Erdman’s earlier solution had what was called VIIa
              (ms pp. 77-90) written “later than and presumably to replace” VIIb (ms pp. 91-98);
              VIIa was printed between VI and VIII, and VIIb left as a kind of appendix after IX.
              Erdman’s decision reflected a wide tendency in the past generation of Blake
              scholarship to treat VIIa and VIIb as <hi rend="i">units</hi>, a practice which made
              it impossible to fit either or both into the text in a narratively coherent way. Of
              course narrative coherence in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is generally problematic
              and, insofar as one understands coherence in anything like the terms of linear logic
              or “realist” novels, a false issue.</p>
            <p>The textual studies of Kilgore, Lincoln and Lefebvre made it possible to redefine the
              problem: VIIa and VIIb were no longer described as units but as sets of two which
              could be reshuffled in at least three ways.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24"
type="note">24</ref>
              Erdman’s textual note is a handy summary of the choices: 
			<q> Andrew Lincoln, arguing
                from an impressive hypothetical reconstruction of the evolution of the ms, would
                insert VIIa between the two portions of VIIb (as Blake rearranged them). Mark
                Lefebvre and John Kilgore, arguing mainly from fit, propose inserting all of VIIb
                between the two portions of VIIa (taking the first portion of VIIa as concluding
                with 85:22, originally followed by “End of the Seventh Night”). Kilgore would return
                the transposed parts of VIIb to their original order; Lefebvre would keep them in
                the order of Blake’s transposing. In the present edition I have decided to follow
                the latter course. (E 836) </q>
Erdman does not fully explain here why he prefers
              Lefebvre’s theory, but from his article in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 46, with its
              fascinating system of notation, it would seem that he does so on the basis of best
              possible fit. But the concern with fit is itself problematic. As Erdman himself
              reminds us, when Ellis and Yeats first “discovered” the manuscript it was unbound,
              entirely a pile of loose leaves. In other words, to conceive VIIa and VIIb as either
              single <hi rend="i">or</hi> bipartite units is highly speculative. In <hi rend="i">The
                Four Zoas</hi> in general, unity is not <hi rend="i">a priori</hi> but the result of
              interpretive and/or editorial theory. <note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Kilgore,
                however, believes that previous editions were “undoubtedly correct in presenting
                each Night as a unit, rather than attempting to reintegrate VIIb into VIIa or VII or
                both, for such an attempt would be highly presumptuous, and would 
                  <hi rend="i">obscure a problem it could not solve</hi>” (p. 112, emphasis added). Our own
                argument, it will be seen, moves along somewhat similar lines.</note></p>
            <p>To call unity theoretical is not to say that it is wrong, but that it does require us
              to examine the theory more closely—a difficult task, since many decisions are not
              based on strict textual evidence but on inadequately articulated assumptions of, or
                <hi rend="i">desires for</hi>, a unity beyond the manuscript’s actual state. These
              assumptions and desires are frustrated by what appear to be conflicting notions of
              poetic unity in the poem itself. It is likely, and often suggested, that Blake’s
              difficulties in completing the <hi rend="i">Zoas</hi> arose from changes during its
              composition in his own sense of appropriate unity, that the poem represents a series
              of transformations leading from the never-ordinary narratives of the Lambeth books to
              the even more radical procedures of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> The manuscript
              evidence of such transformations has led many readers to consign <hi rend="i">The Four
                Zoas</hi> to the category of brilliant failures.</p>
            <p>The point is crucial, for what the manuscript exhibits in the most graphologically
              explicit fashion is an ongoing, unfinished process of self-editing, a process which
              print ordinarily shuts down. The process would be even more evident in the manuscript
              had not its keepers in London deemed it necessary to bind the leaves. This should be
              restated: the manuscript’s editor must be responsible to the phenomenological closures
              of print, but this is not to say that Blake’s editors always seek unity like that of
              the most ideally ordered classical epic. Rather, the editor seeks unity by attempting
              to extend the interrupted trajectory of Blake’s compositional process in such a way as
              to create a “Blakean” unity, in this case in order to salvage both Nights VII and
              approach a hypothetically Blakean conclusion of this infamously unfinished poem. One
              could describe this procedure as an editorial version of the intentional fallacy: a
              compositional fallacy, perhaps, or at least a compositional fiction. Passages like the
              following one from John Kilgore—who, as Erdman says, is concerned mostly with
              “fit”—are virtually standard in editorial commentaries: 
			<q> It is as if Blake could
                not content himself with completing <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> as such, but had
                to go on to attempt a wholesale demonstration of the poem’s consistency with its
                offspring; as if, after a certain point, everything had to be said over again from
                the standpoint of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Nights I and II contain certain late
                additions which suggest that Blake may have decided to work through his six Nights
                yet again, installing passages which would anticipate the new vision, before
                tackling the problem of VIIb. Yet at the same time, judging by the virtually
                atemporal structures of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,
                Blake was undergoing a crisis of disenchantment with narrative itself . . . . </q>
              We have selected this passage from Kilgore (p. 112) not because he is the worst
              offender, merely the handiest practitioner of the compositional fiction. In fact, with
              his rhetoric of “as if” and “may have decided,” Kilgore’s speculations are a great
              deal more modest and palatable than the assertive certainties of several other
              commentators.</p>
            <p>Would it be such apostasy to say that <hi rend="i">none of this matters</hi>, or that
              it matters only because unities we more or less subliminally associate with printed
              editions, with print itself, demand that it matters? The plain fact is that this Night
              VII is not Blake but Erdman “on” Blake; but however obvious this fact is, Erdman on
              Blake will tend to be read and taught <hi rend="i">as</hi> Blake. If Night VII reads
              more easily as narrative in new E than it did in old E; if the reshuffling of the two
              Nights VII better accommodates certain links between VI and VIIa<hi rend="s">1</hi>
              and VIIa<hi rend="s">2</hi> and VIII by inserting a transposed VIIb between them; if
              this “drastic rearrangement” more closely approximates a coherent theory of Blake’s
              intention or at least one probable arc of that intention, in another sense the gains
              of new E are also a loss, for it even more effectively obscures the nature 
                <pb id="p18-15" n="15"/>
of the text as manuscript, its writing of 
                <hi rend="i">still-latent</hi> choices, its graphological, poetic uncertainties. If Erdman has
              produced a more accessible version—accessible in the double and related senses of wide
              availability and surface coherence—we must also ask what has been lost.<ref
                target="n25" type="note">25</ref> Consider, for a minute particular, the following
              passage from Night the Seventh: 
			<q> the howling Melancholy<lb/>
 For far &amp; wide she
                stretchd thro all the worlds of Urizens journey<lb/>
 And was Ajoind to Beulah as the
                Polypus to the Rock<lb/>
 Mo[u]rning the daughters of Beulah saw nor could they have
                sustained<lb/>
 The horrid sight of death &amp; torment But the Eternal Promise<lb/>
                They wrote on all their tombs &amp; pillars<lb/>
 (94.55-95.5, E 367) </q>
Like other
              editors, Erdman emends 95.3, but a consideration of what sense that alteration is
              designed to save offers tangible evidence of Blake’s manner of expanding a line’s
              reference. Do the daughters see “Mourning” rather than a more violent “howling
              Melancholy”? or “Mourning” rather than “death &amp; torment”? If the daughters
              themselves, through inverted predication, are “Mourning,” what did they see, and how
              are they able, a few lines later, to wait “with patience” and to sing “comfortable
              notes”? Perhaps the daughters see a morning that lightens the horrid sight of “black
              melancholy.” If critics are correct in feeling that the passage calls for emendation,
              it seems more likely—since the text offers a situation “when Morn shall blood renew”
              (93.19)—that “Morning the daughters of Beulah saw [<hi rend="i">not</hi>?] nor could
              they have sustaind/The horrid sight of death &amp; torment.” 
                  <note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi> In a similar light, the practical value of Erdman’s
“Editorial
                Rearrangement” of “Auguties of Innocence,” retained in this edition, might be less
                in its treatment of the poem than as a vivid synecdochic reminder of a more general
                editorial presence.</note></p>
            <p>Surely Blake must have wished to “finish” <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, whatever
              that finishing might have turned out to mean, but at the same time the very
              strangeness of the manuscript fascinates us: its surface chaos, its false starts, its
              palimpsestuous revisions and deletions are invitations to a kind of labor which is
              itself deleted from the print edition. Erdman prevents his reader from enjoying the
              difficult pleasures he himself experienced; the reader’s participation at certain
              graphological levels is itself edited out because the editor assumes, and must assume,
              that such participation is inessential to reading. To correct the graphic traces of a
              struggle for resurrection to unity is to assume that they are irrelevant to the
              reader’s experience of the text as a struggle <hi rend="i">in writing</hi>, an
              energetic exertion of talent including a potential grammar of mistakes which might
              advance reading.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref> And
what if the manuscript’s
              unfinished form is somehow appropriate to the unfinished world it explores? By
              resurrecting the manuscript to an editorial unity, the editor interferes with the
              reader’s capacity for taking the manuscript as a call for and challenge to unity on
              other levels. Of course this disruption cannot be total, since most of the text’s
              disruptions remain, so to speak, intact. If <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> as
              manuscript is not yet resurrected to unity, neither are the Zoas themselves; and it is
              perhaps a probing recognition of the strangely discordant harmony of graphological
              form and spiritual content which will produce the richest readings. Perhaps our best
              hope as readers of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is still to find a copy of the
              Bentley facsimile and apply a razor to its binding, or to wait for the promised
              edition (“made from infra-red photographs”) being prepared by Erdman and Cettina
              Magno. <note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> The phrase, “grammar of mistakes,” is from
                Henri Frei, cited by Roland Barthes in his essay on “Flaubert and the Sentence,” in
                  <hi rend="i">New Critical Essays</hi>, tr. Richard Howard (New York: Hill and
                Wang, 1980), p. 71.</note></p>
            <p>We wish again to emphasize that we fully appreciate E as the best available printed
                edition,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref> an
accomplishment so remarkable that
              to object to it at all seems ungrateful. But we remain troubled by the hidden power to
              distort in the editorial praxis and the typographic medium; if print editions are
              necessary to accommodate a reading public, we must nonetheless question their
              efficacy, and point out that “reading” Blake in this edition is as far from 
                <hi rend="i">experiencing</hi> “the Divine Revelation in the Litteral expression” as the
              “performance” on a synthesizer would be from a symphonic rendition of Beethoven’s
              Ninth Symphony. And if E is the best available edition, we wish to question the notion
              of best edition. If E becomes, as it is likely to do, the major if not universally
              accepted edition, problems such as that of the two Nights VII will continue to
              demonstrate that for the serious reader the matter of editing must remain a conscious
              issue, that this is <hi rend="i">not</hi> Blake’s text, that at the very least one
              must always attempt to triangulate, so to speak, Blake’s text through as many editions
              and editorial theories as one can lay hands on. This edition is one more possible
              text, one more hypothetical unity to be placed in the field of all other possible
              unities in order to prevent oneself from ever assuming a single and final unity. The
              reader must never accept the authority of print at type-face value, never allow the
              editor and his medium to become invisible, but always raise the question of mediation,
              of how Blake’s works are processed and disseminated, under what aegis, according to
              what ideologies and economic imperatives, what assumptions of unity, what
              interpretation, what Zoic impulse. <note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> Considering
                that the one possibly competing edition, Bentley’s <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
                  Writings</hi>, retails at $185, the new E—especially in hardback—is a bargain as
                well (perhaps Oxford University Press will consider marketing a paperback version of
                Bentley’s edition, so that interested students might have the luxury of comparing
                the two editions without a trip to the library).</note></p>
            <p>It may well be, as Randall McLeod has suggested, that traditions of editing are
              maintained by pedagogy “in which the teacher’s role mediates the students’
              confrontation with art, and shapes it according to various intellectual and social
              paradigms, which impose ideal order on recalcitrant facts.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28"
                type="note">28</ref> There are of course even more profound philosophical and
              ideological factors at work, but for the moment, we wish rather to emphasize
              that—whatever the reasons—there has been too little concerted effort to exploit the
              syntax of concrete ideas offered by photography in bringing the work of Blake to the
              audience Blake deserves in a form closer to what the audience deserves. 
                <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is perhaps the least available of all Blake’s major works
and
              yet, except for size, it poses fewer problems of photographic reproduction than the
              engraved works. In an age of photographic transmission almost every reader of 
                <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> must 
<pb id="p18-16" n="16"/>
still seek an encounter
              with Blake’s writing through the elaborate and expensive mediation of editorial and
              compositorial middlemen.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29"
type="note">29</ref>
	<note id="n28"><hi
                  rend="s">28</hi> “UN Editing Shak-speare,” p. 38.</note>
	<note id="n29"><hi
                  rend="s">29</hi> For a comparable case, how can we not regard the recent and
                expensive Oxford edition of Christopher Smart’s <hi rend="i">Jubilate Agno</hi> as a
                scandal? The editor claims that this work “has been given pride of place” in the
                proposed complete edition of Smart’s work; yet even the most cursory examination of
                the two pages of the holograph ms reproduced in that volume (greatly reduced) shows
                that the typographic edited version is a blatant composite editorial fabrication.
                Smart’s holograph ms consists of thirty-two pages in all (ten single and three
                double folio leaves, written on both sides). It is relatively easy to read, even in
                the reduced format of the Oxford edition (though the “Let” verses are unaccountably
                placed to the right, the “For” verses to the left). Thirty-two pages of
                photofacsimile, 12-1/2” X 8”, could have brought this remarkable work before the
                reader in its own concrete syntax and iconic forcefulness. Instead, we have another
                editorial curiosity and fiction (copyright, of course) with editorial punctuation
                supplied, omitted words supplied, emendations added, spelling “mistakes” corrected,
                ampersands and contractions “silently expanded” and apostrophes “silently supplied.”
                Karina Williamson, ed., <hi rend="i">The Poetical Works of Christopher Smart, I,
                  Jubilate Agno</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1980).</note></p>
            <p>Reproduction by print, even of a photographic image, may not be the best answer
              technology has for the multitude of problems posed by Blake’s work. Even the best
              photographic facsimile of the ms of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> would not bring
              out the details and editorial clues that X-ray photography and related technologies
              may help uncover—but the unaided eye with the original ms would be almost as much at a
              loss for these traces as with a photograph of it. In addition to the possible
              solutions to textual problems offered by new technologies, there are also vistas of
              promise for the goal of providing “eye” access to Blake. We imagine future Blake
              students examining the illuminated books and the ms materials from video discs and
              high-resolution screens, comparing variants in split-screen images, isolating and
              magnifying cruces and details, jumping instantly from plate to plate and copy to copy,
              having access to images of all the works without having to travel to the various
              collections. Once the images were actually encoded on disc, the cost of reproducing
              multiple copies would be minimal. This is not a utopian proposal: if print editions
              necessarily involve formal compromises and the interference of a technology Blake’s
              project was designed to circumvent, then with such video reproductions we will no
              doubt be trading one set of compromises for another. But we could also provide
              ourselves with a much richer range of readings unmediated by editorial assumptions of
              unity, and untransformed by print.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">VI. THE COMMENTARY: PRACTICAL CONSIDERATIONS</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
			<q> Commentary: A systematic series of explanations or interpretations of the text of a
              writing. (<hi rend="i">Webster’s Unabridged Dictionary</hi>, 3d ed.)<lb/>
<lb/>
              Reviewers, whether journalistic or academic, who chant malice while they proclaim
              their love for poems, trope also, and for defensive purposes all their own. What do we
              mean when we think we love poems, and what does that love defend, or defend against?
              (Bloom, <hi rend="i">Agon</hi>)<lb/>
<lb/>
 From the start all received readings of this
              poem, including my own, are wholly mistaken . . . . A copying-canonization fosters
              misreading, of a peculiarly uninteresting, weak, and unproductive kind. A canonical
              reading, like a canonical copying, attempts to stop the mind by making a text
              identical with itself, so as to produce a total presence, an unalterable meaning.
              (Bloom, <hi rend="i">Poetry and Repression</hi>)<lb/>
<lb/>
 All canonizing of literary
              texts is a self-contradicting process, for by canonizing a text you are troping upon
              it, which means that you are misreading it. Canonization is the most extreme version
              of what Nietzsche called Interpretation, or the exercise of the Will-to-Power over
              texts. (Bloom, <hi rend="i">Kabbalah and Criticism</hi>) </q>
            <p>The dust jacket of the Newly Revised Edition announces this volume as containing
              “eighty-two pages of critical commentary by Harold Bloom.” Since there are only
              seventy-six pages of commentary by Bloom included in the volume, there may be more
              than one kind of puffery going on here. Of the seventy-six pages of commentary,
              fifty-four are devoted to the Big Three (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">The
                Four Zoas</hi> have nineteen pages each, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> has sixteen)
              leaving only twenty-two pages for the remainder of the <hi rend="i">oeuvre</hi>, and a
              substantial number of the works receive no commentary or critical annotation at
                all.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">30</ref> As in 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s
                Apocalypse</hi>, where Bloom’s readings are offered as “justification” for his
              “experience that the poems are usually quite independent of their illustrations,”
              there is nothing in the commentary to suggest that the poems exist in any but their
              printed forms.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">31</ref> There
are a number of larger
              theoretical and practical concerns raised by the inclusion of any commentary at all
              with what seeks to present itself as “the text” of Blake’s work, but we shall defer
              consideration of these issues to the next section, limiting the present one to a
              consideration of the commentary on its most obvious level, examining it in terms of
              its own self-presentation. <note id="n30"><hi rend="s">30</hi> Among these exclusions
                are the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, both versions of <hi rend="i">The Gates of
                  Paradise, The Ghost of Abel, An Island in the Moon</hi>, the Songs and Ballads,
                including the Pickering Manuscript poems, and <hi rend="i">The Everlasting
                  Gospel.</hi></note>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">31</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake’s
                  Apocalypse</hi> (Garden City: Doubleday, 1963), p. 9. There is one possible
                exception to this observation in Bloom’s statement (E 898) that in plate 14 of 
                  <hi rend="i">MHH</hi> “Blake relates his apocalyptic vision to his work as poet and
                engraver.” How Blake does so is not explained.</note></p>
            <p>If we do so, an immediate question arises: is the commentary “newly revised” after
              seventeen years of stable existence? The answer is both yes and no. Yes, since the
              minimal number of mechanical changes have been made to keep the order of the
              commentary congruent with the revisions in the order of the printed text, and the
              forty references to Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Prophet Against Empire</hi> have received
              supplementary page references to the latest edition of that work. Predictably, the
              introductory note to Night VIIa (E 876) stating the belief that VIIa is later in
              composition and an “imaginative advance” on VIIb is omitted; the note formerly to VIIb
              96:19-27 (E 885), where the comment on Los’s evolution provided the occasion to claim
              it as “one of the many indications that VII[a] might be later in composition than
              VII[b],” is altered so that the same evidence is now “one of the good reasons for
              taking pages 85-90 to be the proper conclusion to this Night.” The remainder of the
              commentary on the two Nights is simply shifted to follow the new order of printing. In
              the process of shifting the notes around, Bloom’s observations on 94:37-95:14 (the
              concluding note to the separately-printed VIIb in 1965, [p. 886]) seem to have been
              lost in the shuffle; lest we think that this was a deliberate revision, the “c”
              indication remains in the printed text as a signifier of carelessness.</p>
            <p>Even at this minimal level of change and correction, there are a number of things
              that could have improved the utility and accuracy of the Commentary that remain
              untried. The reader new to the edition will still have to hunt to find the list of
              works cited in the notes (E 788). Once it is found, he or she will look in vain for
              information about many citations in the Commentary that give authors’ names only (e.g.
              Murry, Percival, Schorer, C.S. Lewis, Sloss and Wallis). Although the order of the
              edition puts <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> later, many of the comments on 
                <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> presume a reading of it,
              constantly referring to points as “already familiar” from that 
              <pb id="p18-17" n="17"/>
              poem.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">32</ref> 
              Libra still “follows Leo” (E 953) in
              Bloom’s Zodiac, making us wonder whether this is a strong misreading of centuries of
              astrological writing or merely a mistake. The inclusion of a few maps, a simple
              explanation of the basics of copperplate engraving—helpful aids of this sort fall
              through the gap between the textual notes and the commentary, leaving the edition less
              useful than it might be for pedagogical purposes. <note id="n32"><hi rend="s">32</hi>
                Bloom’s tendency toward a linear, chronological notion of poetic “career” both
                compounds and points up the difficulties of E’s organizational model; the Commentary
                would have fit more easily in-to an edition like Keynes’s. E and its Commentary
                represent, therefore, intersecting and conflicting definitions of poetic career. In
                E the model is vertical, so to speak, a value hierarchy descending from illuminated
                works to marginalia and letters; in the Commentary the model is horizontal,
                following Erdman’s order but consistently implying more conventional, biographical
                lines of poetic development.</note></p>
            <p>One of the most embarrassing aspects of the non-revision process is the frequent
              claim made in the commentary that it is a comprehensive guide to other scholarship on
              Blake. The notes resound with superlatives: “fullest comment,” “best elucidated by,”
              “best commentary” are phrases which imply much more than they deliver. There are ways,
              as Borges suggests in his <hi rend="i">Pierre Menard, Author of the Quixote</hi>, that
              a subsequent text can repeat an earlier one verbatim and yet be totally different. The
              superlatives in the Newly Revised Edition may repeat exactly the text of 1965, but
              words like “remains” and “still,” after eighteen years of proliferating Blake
              scholarship, have quite a different resonance. In 1965 Bloom could speculate that the
              problems he experienced with the structure of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> “may be only
              that the poem has not had enough accurate and close readers as yet” (E 928). No doubt
              we can still argue about whether we have enough (or too much?) in the way of close
              readings of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>; but there have certainly been many new
              observations and speculations since 1965, all of which would seem to be implicitly
              discounted by preserving this aspect of Bloom’s commentary. At times the anachronisms
              can be amusing, as when we find a moral lecture that doesn’t seem to have whatever
              urgency it might once have merited: “One must also warn against misunderstanding 
                [<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>] 41:25. Blake is certainly not repudiating sexuality . . . .
              This would not be worth dwelling upon, were it not that this misinterpretation of
              Blake is <hi rend="i">still</hi> a prevalent one.” (E 927, emphasis added) The
              adequacy of Bloom’s coverage of Blake scholarship could be questioned even in 1965;
              but consider the following table, which lists the five (of a total of about fifteen)
              authors most frequently cited by Bloom: <table rows="6" cols="3">
                <row>
                  <cell>AUTHOR</cell>
                  <cell>AGE OF WORK IN 1982</cell>
                  <cell>NUMBER OF CITATIONS</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Erdman</cell>
                  <cell>28</cell>
                  <cell>40</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Damon</cell>
                  <cell>58</cell>
                  <cell>30</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Frye</cell>
                  <cell>35</cell>
                  <cell>21</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Percival</cell>
                  <cell>44</cell>
                  <cell>10</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <cell>Margoliouth</cell>
                  <cell>26</cell>
                  <cell>9</cell>
                </row>
              </table> The average age of the works most frequently cited is thirty-eight years in
              1982. Surely <hi rend="i">something</hi> must have been noticed by the Young Men and
              Women of the New Age that would be worth mentioning in a commentary appended to what
              presumes to be the basic text for students of Blake in the 1980s.</p>
            <p>Other aspects of the commentary have changed by remaining the same. The description
              Bloom gave of Blake in 1965 was very much a self-description: “He was not an
              antiquarian, a mystic, an occultist or theosophist, and not much of a scholar of any
              writings beyond the Bible and other poetry insofar as it resembled the Bible. His
              references to esoteric traditions are few, and tend to be superficial when they are
              not mocking” (E 934-35). Misreading was still a crime back in those days, before Bloom
              had discovered the Kabbalah and Gnosticism and Freud, and the anonymous hordes of
              occultists are so constantly denounced that one yearns for an <hi rend="i">Index
                Librorum Prohibitorum</hi> in order to know who they were/are. The sins committed by
              these occultists seem to be twofold; first, to assume that Blake read such trash
              (though that category may not be so clear in Bloom now that he has found light in the
              darkness), and second to assume that he might have been influenced by it. Apparently
              we are to believe that “Blake rejects all occultism” (E 945) <hi rend="i">without
                having read it.</hi> This aspect of Bloom’s opinions seems not to have changed much,
              for in his recent essay “Catastrophe Creation: Gnosis, Kabbalah and Blake” he still
              maintains that “the Perpetual Philosophy gang of pseudo-Blakeans have failed to
              demonstrate that Blake knew anything much of his Gnostic and Kabbalistic
                precursors.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">33</ref>
Apparently the correct view is
              still that Blake was able to get it all out of the Bible and “a kind of primal
              anxiety,” since “the elements of catastrophe are gathered all too readily from the
              innate puzzlements of the orthodox accounts” (<hi rend="i">Agon</hi> p. 77). Bloom’s
              attitude in 1965 may perhaps be understood as a reaction to Raine’s insistence that
              not one symbolic figure or theme in Blake was of his own invention, and that Blake was
              steeped in ancient traditions, particularly Neoplatonism. Paradoxically, Bloom would
              now seem to agree with Raine that Blake did not invent anything, even though he is
              still adamant about denying Blake any occult “sources” in the conventional sense. For
              Bloom the answer to the vexing question of how Blake could have been a Gnostic without
              having read any Gnostic writings must be based on a “truly enlightened Freudian
              perspective” (87) that agrees with the affirmation of Gnosis “that fantasy must be
              primary in our belated condition” (89) because of “the priority of anxiety over its
              stimuli” and the origins of human consciousness as a primal catastrophe of creative
              origins (97). <note id="n33"><hi rend="s">33</hi><hi rend="i"> Agon</hi> (New York:
                Oxford University Press, 1982), p. 73.</note></p>
            <p>Although Bloom has done relatively little interpretation of Blake since his work in
              the 60s, what he has published shows radical changes from the views expressed in the
              Commentary. One example must suffice here. In 1965 <hi rend="i">The Book of
                Urizen</hi> was “primarily an intellectual satire” and Urizen was a bad guy. In
              1982, “Urizen is Blake’s prophetic version of the author of <hi rend="i">Beyond the
                Pleasure Principle</hi>,” and “Blake’s wisdom” is to see Urizen’s creativity as 
                “<hi rend="i">the</hi> sublime stance, the agonistic 
<pb id="p18-18" n="18"/>
glory of
              Milton <hi rend="i">and</hi> of Blake, the final truth of Freud’s Psychological Man”
              (89). Freud was mentioned only once in 1965, to be dismissed in passing as only worth
              the bother “if an attempt to translate Blake’s psychic cartography into Freud’s seems
              worth the making” (E 955). The subjunctive sounds strange now that we have the “final
              truth” of a transcendental understanding based on a “truly enlightened Freudian
              perspective.”</p>
            <p>To look back at the commentary after eighteen years, after Bloom’s subsequent
              theorizing and the proliferation of other work on Blake, is to find a “reading” of
              Blake that is by now thoroughly familiar, if not “canonical.” The Blake of this
              commentary is the hero of the Imagination, original and creative, leading us towards
              imminent apocalypse: “It is Blake’s work <hi rend="i">as a creative artist</hi> that
              will expunge the notion of dualism, and cleanse the doors of perception, the
              infinitely expandable senses of man” (E 898). Bloom’s reading of 
                <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (the comments on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and 
                <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> are too patchy and tentative to constitute “readings”) leads
us
              towards “the moment of salvation” and “the revelation that is to climax the poem” (E
              925) with a final glimpse of “the poet prophet who has been tried severely, and has
              triumphed over his trials” (E 928). The tone of the Commentary is that of a purveyor
              of truth, who can speak authoritatively of “the proper understanding of the poem” (E
              901) and “the central truth of the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>” (E 903) and who can
              unfailingly illuminate lines that are “most frequently misread in Blake” (E 901).</p>
            <p>The trope that Bloom was most comfortable with in the 60s was irony, and his
              discriminations of nuance among the modes of irony, satire and paradox were prolific.
              Blake’s irony could be plain “irony,” or it could be “pungent,” “cyclic,”
“complex,”
              “final,” “palpable,” “highest,” “curious,” “fine,” “prophetic,”
“outrageous,”
              “intellectual,” “central,” “ferocious,” “supreme,” “evident,” “bitter and
effective,”
              “savage,” or “skillful.” In addition to the plain variety, Blake’s “satire” could
be
              “intellectual,” “desperate,” “complex,” “grim,” “oblique,” or “implied.”
Bloom’s
              inventiveness flags with “parody,” which is as often plain “parody” as it is “demonic
              parody.” A quick count finds combinations and selections of these phrases used
              thirty-three times in a twelve-page sample of the commentary (E 896-907).</p>
            <p>If these are to be practical considerations, we must eventually ask ourselves what—in
              spite of its idiosyncrasies and shortcomings—is the value of this Commentary that we
              will now continue to live with and have our students buy for perhaps another eighteen
              years? Here we think the numerous references to the Bible, and to Milton and Spenser,
              are still helpful and remain one of the strengths of the Commentary. Whatever our
              arguments about Blake and the occult may continue to be, we do know that Blake read
              these works and was profoundly influenced by them, and we know that our students are
              increasingly unfamiliar with them. The kind of study Leslie Tannenbaum has provided in
              his <hi rend="i">Biblical Tradition in Blake’s Early Prophecies</hi> (Princeton:
              Princeton University Press, 1982) is a much-needed tool in this area, especially with
              its emphasis on the context of biblical criticism in Blake’s own time, in which
              Blake’s strategies seem less idiosyncratic and more traditional than might otherwise
              be the case. Perhaps what we really need for Blake is some equivalent of the Gifford
              and Seidman <hi rend="i">Notes for Joyce</hi>, or of Ronald McHugh’s 
                <hi rend="i">Annotations to Finnegans Wake.</hi> Such a work would not simply mention the
              Nightingale’s song in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> as “perhaps honoring Milton” and give a
              reference to the invocation to Book III of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi> It would
              also mention “Il Penseroso” and provide the minimal classical references. And it would
              not overlook the even greater honor Blake does to Milton in his poem by shifting his
              emphasis from the Nightingale to the Lark, reminding us of Milton’s Lark in 
                <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained:</hi><q> and now the Herald Lark<lb/>
 Left his
                ground-nest, high towring to descry<lb/>
 The morns approach, and greet her with his
                Song<lb/>
 As lightly from his grassy Couch up rose<lb/>
 Our Saviour, and found all
                was but a dream<lb/>
</q></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>VII. THE FUNCTIONS OF COMMENTARY</title>
            </head>
			<q> . . . the Commentary therefore aims at being a comprehensive and detailed guide to
              the reading of Blake’s poetry. . . . The emphasis throughout . . . is on the
              resolution of apparent problems in continuity and poetic unity. (E XXIV) </q>
            <p>The Book of Nehemiah (8:1-8) gives us what may well be the earliest account of the
              essential collaboration between editing and commentary. As a redactor of the
              Pentateuch or Torah, Ezra had begun the awesome task of “putting back together” an
              ideal text which had never existed. The formal presentation of the text to those who
              would understand it requires translation and commentary. In this section we propose to
              look briefly at Bloom’s Commentary in Erdman’s edition, <hi rend="i">not</hi> as the
              practice of an individual critic or commentator—but as representative of an important
              function, the institutionalization of the reciprocal play of power between the text
              and its commentary. In this mutual reinforcement system, 
			<q> . . . criticism’s
                self-separation from its object is a kind of feint—a mere prelude to reuniting with
                it more completely. Its analytic distantiation of its object is the parody of
                knowledge—a means of “possessing it more closely, dissolving itself into a oneness
                with it.” The end of criticism is to efface itself before the text, vicariously
                naturalising its own troubled “artifice” by its power to elicit the “naturalness” of
                the text itself. In a spiral of mutual reenforcements, the literary text naturalizes
                experience, critical practice naturalises the text, and the theories of that
                practice legitimate the “naturalness” of criticism.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">34</ref>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">34</hi> Terry Eagleton, 
                    <hi rend="i">Criticism and Ideology: A Study in Marxist Literary Theory</hi> (London:
Verso
                  Editions, 1978), p. 18.</note></q></p>
            <p>Fredric Jameson has observed that critical commentary presents itself as answering
              the question “What does it mean?” and in answering the question performs an
              allegorical operation in which a text is systematically 
<pb id="p18-19" n="19"/>	
                <hi rend="i">rewritten</hi> in terms of some implicit fundamental code.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35"
                type="note">35</ref> In this view, the operative theoretical framework and
              presuppositions of a critical approach will reflect the ideology which that method
              seeks to perpetuate, and it is the congruence between the assumptions guiding the
              production of the text and those guiding the extraction of meaning 
                <hi rend="i">from</hi> the fixed text which allows the system to work in all its fearful
                symmetry.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">36</ref> Apart from
whatever its particular
              qualities as interpretation may be, there is an important emblematic aspect to the
              inclusion of Commentary in a definitive edition. The Commentary “ends” the book as a
              form of closure and enclosure. After the conflict and disorder of the various
              materials that constitute Blake’s work have given way to the editorial order, any
              residual problems of “interpretation” can be successfully negotiated by an
              interpretive process that shares and collaborates with the editorial assumption that
              Blake’s meaning must be if not simple, at least univocal. The Commentary begins with
              the assumption of unity and coherence that guided the editorial creation of the text,
              and proceeds to “discover” that in a quite predictable fashion as the characteristic
              identifying mark of the text. As a reading of the “text,” following it and doubling
              it, citing it and depending on it, the Commentary functions to confirm certain things
              about the text, including—for our concerns—the most important aspect of all, its
              “textuality.” The reinforcement of persistent citation, whether in a closing
              Commentary at the end, in running notes, or in those earlier modes of scriptural
              publication with the sacred scripture in the center of the page (surrounded on all
              sides by annotations, glosses and commentary, including even interlinear glosses), is
              an important formal part of the presentation of an edited text. The Commentator will
              respect the supposed stability and authenticity of the text, and will securely
              reproduce that stability in a critical commentary that—either literally or
              figuratively—stands alongside the text; the formalist practices of the Commentary will
              presuppose the desired formal characteristics to be “there” in the text to receive the
              formal doubling of meaning in the Commentary. <note id="n35"><hi rend="s">35</hi> See
                Fredric Jameson, <hi rend="i">The Political Unconscious</hi> (Ithaca: Cornell
                University Press, 1981), p. 58.</note>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">36</hi> Some of
                the hermeneutic implications of this circularity are hinted at in Northrop Frye’s
                claim that Blake “is writing for enthusiasts of poetry who, like readers of mystery
                stories, enjoy sitting up nights trying to find out what the mystery is” 
                  (<hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry: A Study of Blake’s Thought</hi> [Princeton: Princeton
                Univ. Press, 1947], p. 7).</note></p>
            <p>The citational doubling of the edited text is part of a larger doubling structure of
              citation which deserves a moment’s attention. When we say that the editing process
              creates the text, we have in mind the way in which everyone knows that the printed
              book is clearly not Blake’s text per se, but an elaborate citation of a set of events
              which presents itself, in the form of citation, as a <hi rend="i">representation</hi>
              of the absent text. The acceptance of this elaborate citational representation as “the
              text” is strengthened and reinforced by the citation of it as such that is found in
              the Commentary’s relational structure, which confirms the textuality of the text by
              taking its “proper place” alongside or after. We might express this double
              relationship in the form of a ratio: 
			<q> Commentary: Edited Text:: Edited Text: Ideal
                Text </q>
This may seem so obvious and inevitable as to require no attention, but
              the obviousness is precisely why we persist in teasing out the assumptions implicit in
              the conventional text <hi rend="i">cum</hi> commentary format. From Plato on, the
              standard accounts of representation have assumed the existence of the categories of
              the “original” and the “copy” or representation, one prior in time and higher in
              value, the other later in time and lower in value—the first determining the second.
              The rationale for the practice of representation or copying is the absence of the
              original, for which the copy is a convenient or available substitute in the absence of
              the original. 
			<q> Reengravd Time after Time<lb/>
 Ever in their youthful prime<lb/>
 My
                Designs unchanged remain<lb/>
 Time may rage but rage in vain<lb/>
 For above Times
                troubled Fountains<lb/>
 On the Great Atlantic Mountains<lb/>
 In my Golden House on
                high<lb/>
 There they Shine Eternally (E 480-81) </q>
The representation or copy,
              being different from the original, is tainted or contaminated by that difference. It
              is one of the paradoxical strategies of the authoritative, edited “text” to present
              itself as <hi rend="i">less</hi> belated in the series of copy-representations of the
              ideal text than the particular version(s) of it produced by the author, less
              contaminated by difference from the original, which simply <hi rend="i">is</hi>
              itself.</p>
            <p>We have suggested that the notion of the ideal text is both a component and symptom
              of that set of traditions in Western metaphysics which Derrida has analyzed in terms
              of its privileging of the spoken word over the written within the oppositional
              categories of presence and absence, of original and copy or supplement. If spoken
              language is what fundamentally constitutes all language, then the written word will be
              seen as secondary and derivative. If the ideal text is what constitutes the
              ontological axis of literature, then as writing is seen merely to redouble speech, to
              be an artificial or auxiliary reproduction, a pallid reproduction or representation of
              the spoken word—then so will the “writing” of the author be seen as a veil covering
              the sublimity of the ideal text. If there is a tradition that can be called
              “phonocentric” in language theory and metaphysics, there is also one that can be
              called “textocentric” in literary studies and the production of what we call “texts”
              of literary works.</p>
            <p>Blake worked in a system in which the “inventor” of an image and the engraver of the
              image were often different people, with the inevitable implication that the engraving
              was a derivative and secondary category or mode of existence, as well as more
              “mechanical” and not truly of the “fine arts.” William Ivins and Morris Eaves have
              spelled out some of the details and implications of this system, including the
              “reverse-contamination” of the original by the nature of the medium in which it was
              meant to be reproduced. Or is it a “contamination”? It is, <pb id="p18-20" n="20"/>
in
              effect, a reduction of the “difference” which enhances the value and adequacy of the
              “representation” by bringing it closer to the “original.” A similar reduction of
              difference can be seen in a mode of writing that is intended for reproduction in
              conventional printed production in linear form; the “difference” in this case is not
              significant in a functional sense, and the printed version—if it is “accurate”—is
              considered fully adequate as a representation of the “text” of the work. We could say
              that Blake’s printed “plates” are copies of his copper plates, and that those plates
              are copies or traces of the act of engraving itself, that energetic exertion of talent
              which is itself still only a trace of something else, perhaps some 
                <hi rend="i">Dasein</hi> “unchanged . . . Far above Times troubled Fountains.” But
wherever that
              realm is, we are presumably not there, and we must still deal with tangible artifacts
              in our attempts to encounter the Designs. In the realm of tangible artifacts Blake had
              his own methods for reducing the series of “differences” between the imagination of a
              design, its initial rendering, its engraving (preparation for printing) and its
              printing—including final touches to the printed form that must be considered as
              “original” as any other stages in the production. Thus the notion of difference in
              this context is already contained as a problematic part of Blake’s mode of production,
              in which his printed designs avoid, as much as possible, the whole concatenation of
              the implications of conventional production. In addition, the same problematic is
              thematized in the “meaning” of the works so produced.</p>
            <p>What we are leading up to here is the point that, if the edited/printed text presents
              itself as <hi rend="i">simply</hi> different from the ideal text, different as all
              printed representations are, then the <hi rend="i">problematic</hi> differences that
              concerned Blake in both the invention and execution of his designs will be obscured,
              and we will be lulled into taking the edited text as a representation adequate to our
              interpretive needs, not being able to see what editing does to its “originals.” When
              the edited text is presented in a formal context as fully adequate to serve as
              “original” for the copy-representation of a Commentary, then the Commentary will have
              as one of its most significant functions the bearing of testimony to the adequacy of
              the edited text to serve as a substitute for the absent “original,” functioning 
                <hi rend="i">as</hi> the original for the copy-function of the Commentary.</p>
            <p>To look now at the situation we are describing from the vantage point of Erving
              Goffman, we can suggest that the conventionally edited text constitutes a “scene of
              editing,” or a “scene of text production.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n37" type="note">37</ref> A
              correctly staged and performed scene/edition leads the audience/reader to impute a
              “text” to the performance, and the imputation of “text” is the 
                <hi rend="i">product</hi> of the scene that comes off successfully rather than the 
                <hi rend="i">cause</hi> of it. When the Commentary gets out of hand, expanding to devour the
              text or manifesting “a stronger apparent presence,” in Bloom’s terms,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38"
                type="note">38</ref> then the conventional decorum of the textual performance has
              been violated and the carefully maintained illusions may be shattered. But if this
              happens what we have—as Bloom’s recent theoretical arguments emphasize—is not a change
              in kind, but a change in degree; a different performance, no longer self-effacing
              Commentary in the service of an imputed text but Commentary upstaging the text. The
              decorous Commentary, such as we have in the now officially-sanctioned edition of
              Blake, is no less a “performance” for playing a different role or interpreting the
              same role in a different way. <note id="n37"><hi rend="s">37</hi> On Goffman, see 
                  <hi rend="i">The Presentation of Self in Everyday Life</hi> (London: Allen Lane The
                Penguin Press, 1969) and <hi rend="i">Frame Analysis: An Essay on the Organization
                  of Experience</hi> (New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1974).</note>
	<note id="n38"><hi
                  rend="s">38</hi><hi rend="i"> Kabbalah and Criticism</hi> (New York: Seabury
                Press, 1975), p. 121.</note></p>
            <p>To return to the scene of editing as performed in the Erdman edition in its initial
              “production” in the sixties, we find a number of elements characteristic of
              conventional academic canonization and text formation. The scholarly credentials of
              both Erdman and Bloom had been established to an impressive degree. Bloom had
              published (among other things) two books dealing directly with Blake, and in each had
              paid the obligatory obeisance to the appropriate doyens of Romantic and Blakean
              scholarship: “Of published criticism of the Romantic poets, I have been most deeply
              influenced by Northrop Frye’s work on Blake. . . . In matters of critical theory, I
              have been guided by Frye’s <hi rend="i">Anatomy of Criticism</hi>, and by Abrams’ 
              <hi rend="i">The Mirror and the 
              Lamp.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">39</ref> 
              “My specific critical debts are to the Blake studies of S. Foster Damon, J. Middleton
              Murry, David Erdman, and especially Northrop Frye. . . . To Mr. Frye’s work I have a
              more pervasive obligation, for by reading him I learned to read Blake” 
              (<hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse</hi>, p. 10). <note id="n39"><hi rend="s">39</hi> 
              <hi rend="i">The Visionary Company: A Reading of English Romantic Poetry</hi> 
              (Garden City, N.Y.: Doubleday, 1961), p. xi.</note></p>
            <p>The Commentary does indeed frequently acknowledge specific indebtedness to Frye and
              others, but the more important “learning” manifested in the Commentary is of a general
              nature. Frye’s Blake was and is a spectacular and powerful invention—a Blake who
              “seldom altered anything,” whose works “were intended to form an exclusive and
              definitive canon,” in which even <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, though left
              abandoned, provides “an imaginatively coherent account of how we got from an original
              Golden Age to the world we are now in” (<hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi>, pp. 10,
              309). Frye’s Blake must be approached according to certain rules, which are for the
              most part those followed by Bloom’s Commentary in 1965. “In the study of Blake it is
              the analogue that is important, not the source; and even essential sources such as the
              Bible and Milton are of value only as sources of analogues” (p. 12). Blake exhibits
              everywhere “the sanity of genius” and provides the consummate model of “the creative
              power of the artist,” and of the “vision” which is “the goal of all freedom, energy
              and wisdom” (p. 25). Frye’s concept of “freedom,” however, did not extend to all
              readers of Blake: 
			<q> I am not speaking now of merely vulgar misunderstandings. No one
                who has read three lines of our straightforward and outspoken poet can imagine that
                he wished to be pursued by a band of superstitious dilettantes into the refuge of a
                specialized cult. Whatever Blake’s prophecies may be, they can hardly be code
                messages, They may need interpretation, but not deciphering: there can be no “key”
                and no 
<pb id="p18-21" n="21"/>
open-sesame formula and no patented system of
                translation. The amateur of cabalism who accepts obscure truisms for profound
                truths, and sentimental platitudes for esoteric mysteries, would do well to steer
                clear of Blake. No: I mean the tendency to describe Blake in terms of certain
                stereotypes which imply that he can be fully appreciated only by certain types of
                mind, and which tend to scare the ordinary reader away from him. (p. 7) </q>
This is
              strong stuff, and strikes a posture echoed by Bloom throughout the Commentary and a
              position repeated in later works.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
type="note">40</ref> Bloom has
              observed that “Any poem’s initial problem is to make room for itself—it must force the
              previous poems to move over and so clear some space for it.” In this Darwinian
              struggle, “Poems fight for survival in a state of poems, which by definition has been,
              is now, and is always going to be badly over-populated” (<hi rend="i">Kabbalah and
                Criticism</hi>, p. 121) <note id="n40"><hi rend="s">40</hi> Though not without
                contradiction. In <hi rend="i">Kabbalah and Criticism</hi> Bloom announced that if a
                “reading is wholly a received one, then it will not produce other readings. An
                entire academy can convene to declare that reading the right one, but of course it
                will be wrong. It will also be weak” (p. 107). In his review of Martin Butlin’s 
                  <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (<hi rend="i">New York
                  Times Book Review</hi>, January 3, 1982, p. 4), Bloom adopts the authoritative
                voice of the Academy to rule that the “growing fashion” of studying Blake’s work in
                unedited form “has not proved intellectually sound.” He goes on to dismiss a variety
                of “followers,” including Marxists, and to praise the “generation of readers who
                have achieved a loving and accurate understanding of Blake’s poetry and prose within
                the traditions of Western literature.”</note></p>
            <p>It does not seem unfair to us to view Frye’s comments, quoted above, as exemplary of
              a comparable situation in the academic world. In a rhetoric of democratic
              egalitarianism, Frye was freeing Blake and the reader from the tyranny of rival modes
              of interpreting. But he was also clearing “professional” space for his reading,
              dismissing as “dilettantes” and “amateurs” those who would take a different view. We
              do not doubt that Frye—and Bloom in his Commentary—were speaking the truth as they saw
              it. But from our vantage point we can see that the Erdman edition in its present form
              with Commentary continues to reflect the institutional dominance of a definable set of
              views, now reinforced by the MLACSE seal of approval and the perhaps inevitable
              adoption of the new Erdman text as the text of reference for “reputable” Blake
              scholars. The very datedness of the Commentary is, in this context, of no small
              heuristic value, because it enables us to see more clearly what is often hidden under
              unexamined contemporary assumptions of truth and propriety. In this case, the power
              relationship is truly reciprocal, for as the Commentary helps to substantiate the
              “textuality” of the edited text, the institutionalized canonical authority of the text
              confers special status on the Commentary.</p>
            <p>To return now to the first aspect of this reciprocal relationship, we note that the
              Commentary proceeds to elucidate the poetry by following and paralleling the edited
              text, failing its task to some degree by commenting selectively on only a part of the
              poetry, and conflicting with the editorial arrangement of texts by citing 
                <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> frequently in the Commentary on <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 
                <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, which Erdman has chosen to print before in his insistence
              on a non-chronological order. The Commentary is oblivious to the 
                <hi rend="i">interpretive</hi> problems posed by the variations in existing copies of works
like
                <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, or <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, where the edited text is
              different from each of the four extant copies. Bloom acknowledges “problems of
              continuity” in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (E 909) but seems in the Commentary to have no
              trouble at all in following the “strictly narrative sequence” of the 
              poem.<ref target="n41" type="note">41</ref>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">41</hi> Apropos of the
                Erdman “text,” Erdman finds D “the latest and most nearly complete copy,” but fails
                to respect its omissions even though he speculates that Blake was working towards
                the goal of making <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> “an even 50” plates “as he saw 
                  <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> shaping into 100 plates” (E 806). He claims that Blake,
                “though keeping to two Books, was proud to commemorate his original plan” by clearly
                printing the numeral 12 and using “careful stipple work to strengthen the shadow
                emphasizing each digit.” If this is the case, why does Erdman choose for his printed
                title “MILTON/a Poem in 2 Books” rather than “MILTON/a Poem in 12 Books,” or “MILTON
                / a Poem in [1]2 Books”?</note></p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> also is open to different readings, given the “variant”
              order of the plates in Chapter 2. It seems clear that the five copies of the poem can
              be arranged chronologically in the order A C D E F by means of watermark dating. The
              only variation of the order of the plates occurs in Chapter 2, where ACF have one
              order and DE have a different order. The editorial views on which ordering is best to
              follow in a printed text are divided, with Erdman choosing to follow the ACF order as
              base text, indicating the DE order in brackets, while acknowledging that in his view
              Blake “found both sequences attractive but considered neither definitive” (E 809). The
              editorial decision is made by Erdman without giving a reason, but Bloom, in 
                <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse</hi>, may provide a clue to the choice. In that earlier
              work Bloom had announced his preference for the ACF order, describing the structural
              principle of Chapter 2 as “thematic juxtaposition, of enforcing an opposition by a
              progressive sharpening of spiritual conflict” rather than “continuous narrative.”
              Furthermore, he found this “sharpening . . . more skillfully rendered in the revised
                sequence.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">42</ref> In
spite of his disclaimers of
              narrative sequence for Chapter 2 in <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse</hi>, Bloom can
              proceed in his Commentary with a narrativizing reading that asserts of plates
              46:3-48:12 that “The general power of this sequence is founded to an unusual degree
              upon Blake’s careful preparation for it. . . . The collapse of man’s hope in the
              nightmare of history is the theme of this sequence, and the context Blake has
              developed allows him to make so large a statement with appropriate authority” (E 938).
                <note id="n42"><hi rend="s">42</hi> It is curious that Bloom refers to the order of
                ACF as “revised,” since it is chronologically the earlier order. Since Bloom mistook
                the first sequence for a revised one, could it be possible that later-is-better
                presuppositions (such as those followed in his discussion of <hi rend="i">The Four
                  Zoas</hi> VIIa and b, and the canon in general) led him to detect the “More
                skillfully rendered” sharpening that he <hi rend="i">expected</hi> to find? For a
                comprehensive and enlightening discussion of the issues involved, see V.A. De Luca,
                “The Changing Order of Plates in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Chapter II,” 
                  <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 16.4 (Spring 1983), pp. 192-205.</note></p>
            <p>Such claims are clearly contrary to Bloom’s rejection of “continuous narrative” form
              for Chapter 2 in <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse</hi>; but perhaps more to the point,
              since we all change our minds, is the fact that in the revised order of 
                <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, copies D and E, there is no possibility of a “sequence”
linking
              46-48, since Blake had moved plate 46 to position 32, almost at the beginning of the
              chapter. Nor is there the possibility of finding “careful preparation” for the
              non-existent “sequence,” since plates 43-45 were moved to positions 29-31 (the very
              first plate of the Chapter is 28 in both versions). Plate 43 does indeed begin with a
              “Then . . . .” but the <hi rend="i">when</hi> of the “then” is quite different for the
              two chapters if one is set on narrativizing them. Similarly the “now” of Bloom’s “Vala
              now appears” (E 935, referring to plate 29 in ACF but to plate 33 in DE) is quite
              different—and other similar variations could be cited. Anyone who has actually tried
              to reconstitute and “read” the DE version out of Erdman’s text knows that, although
              theoretically possible, doing so is as difficult as “reading” the other three versions
              of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> from the edited version. Given this difficulty, and the
              reinforcing pressure of Bloom’s narrativizing Commentary; given also the expectation
              announced on p. VI that this volume “can be expected to receive immediate acceptance .
              . . as a standard scholarly edition,” do we 
<pb id="p18-22" n="22"/>
not have what
              amounts to a <hi rend="i">de facto</hi> canonization of the ACF Chapter 2 with no
              adequate reason brought forth to justify it?</p>
            <p>The reciprocal reinforcement of text and Commentary is much more symbolic than
              practical in the nineteen pages of Commentary on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> Here
              is a case where the relationship between interpretation and establishing the “text” is
              so problematic as to be crucial, yet Bloom could shift his Commentary based on the
              “rival versions” of Night VII to conform to the new order without making more than the
              minimum perfunctory changes. Perhaps this is because the interpretation of the poem
              worked out in <hi rend="i">The Visionary Company</hi> and <hi rend="i">Blake’s
                Apocalypse</hi> preceded the establishment of “the text” by Erdman, being “based”
              instead on “the standard edition of Sir Geoffrey Keynes” with Bloom’s quotations
              departing silently from Keynes “sometimes [according to] a judgment of my own.”<ref
                target="n43" type="note">43</ref> At any rate, the frequent citations of Erdman
              throughout the Commentary on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, and the powerful play of
              a formalizing and narrativizing approach—shared with or derived from Frye—manage to
              order and domesticate the poem without mentioning a single textual crux. The effect of
              this reading, juxtaposed with Erdman’s text, is to suggest both the adequacy of the
              reading to the text <hi rend="i">and</hi> the adequacy of the text to the reading.
                <note id="n43"><hi rend="s">43</hi> The quotation is from <hi rend="i">Blake’s
                  Apocalypse</hi>, p. 10. Bloom’s survey of Romanticism in <hi rend="i">The
                  Visionary Company</hi> does not cite a single edition for any of its hundreds of
                quotations. He does mention de Selincourt as “Wordsworth’s modern editor” (p. 136),
                but, without explaining why, he chooses to “cite the 1850 text, but with reference,
                where it seems desirable, to the 1805 version.” Needless to say, he does not
                indicate where or why the deviations are “desirable.” It is in some ways an irony
                worthy of one of Bloom’s favorite modifiers (“curious”? “supreme”? “fine”?
                “outrageous”?) that it is <hi rend="i">his</hi> Commentary that still serves the
                textualizing functions that we are emphasizing here.</note></p>
            <p>To conclude, let us tune in to Bloom’s Commentary as it nears the “end” of the poem.
              In his Commentary on Night VIII (perhaps written <hi rend="i">after</hi> the
              apocalyptic Night IX) Bloom detects “apocalyptic yearnings” manifested by Blake. He
              discovers a “great and climactic passage” which “testifies to a dramatically matured
              Los” and moves on to Night IX to find Blake’s “most poetically successful section,”
              apparently because it is “the simplest to follow as far as narrative continuity is
              concerned,” and therefore best exhibits the desired “apocalyptic pattern.” Night IX is
              followed through “deliberate crises” and “brilliant fantasia,” through “restoration of
              Luvah and Vala” and “restoration of Tharmas and Enion” to the end where “Blake’s
              vision . . . attains one of its triumphs.” Along the way, “between the last ‘Winter in
              the night of Time’ in 138:19 and the new Sun of line 20, the world turns inside out
              and reality at last appears.” Is what we have here Blake’s apocalypse, or Bloom’s
              apocrypha? Bloom lifts the veil of Blake’s language for reality “at last” to appear.
              But the reader, confronting the Erdman text, may be reminded of Joyce’s parodic
              “ending” of the Ithaca section in <hi rend="i">Ulysses</hi> and of the concluding
              interrogations: 
			<q> When?<lb/>
 Going to a dark bed there was a square round Sinbad the
                Sailor roc’s egg in the night of the bed of all the auks of the rocs of Darkinbad
                the Brighdayler,<lb/>
 Where?<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">44</ref>
	<note id="n44"><hi
                    rend="s">44</hi> Quoted from the Vintage edition (New York: Random House, 1961),
                  p. 737.</note></q>
In spite of Bloom’s evocation of a “personal reference” in the
              conclusion of Night IX, and the post-apocalyptic bathos of his surprising and
              unexplained assertion that the poem “was never properly completed in the Blakean
              sense,” readers are left to confront the presumed reciprocal adequation between the
              words of the printed text and the Commentary. If readers are puzzled in this
              situation, can we blame them if they turn towards alternative views of the text and of
              Commentary?</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">CODA</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>The collective Angelic voice of the Modern Language Association Committee on
              Scholarly Editions has <corr type="emend">announced</corr> the emergence of the new E as the
consummation of a
              “wedding of scholarly and practical publishing.” As such—like the nuptials of Los and
              Enitharmon—it is deserving of “enormous Revelry, Responsing!” We applaud the new
              typefont for the <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>! We
              rejoice over the inclusion of running line totals for each night of <hi rend="i">The
                Four Zoas</hi>, which alleviates the necessity of the Keynes interface for locating
              citations in the Blake <hi rend="i">Concordance</hi>! We take pleasure in the deletion
              of the exclamation mark, “The Tyger” 1.6, and in the deletion of the question mark,
                <hi rend="i">VDA</hi> 1.7, as well as in a host of other improvements! But we hope
              that all who care about Blake will not rest too long in the “mild &amp; pleasant Rest”
              of this textual Beulah, accepting it as “a pleasant lovely shadow/Where no dispute can
              come . . . . Enraptured with affection sweet and mild benevolence” (E 129). Such an
              attitude would tend to leave Editor Erdman as the current Angel sitting at the tome of
              Blake’s energetic exertion of talent, and to find that this edition is the linen
              clothes all folded up. For however improved, approved, or newly revised it may be, the
              straight and narrow edited road of typeset print neither brings forth the excess,
              surplus, or overflowing of Blake’s text, nor leads to its palace of wisdom.</p>
            <figure n="Improvement1.18.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="650" height="573">
            	<figTranscr>Improvement makes strait roads, but the crooked roads without<lb/>
            	Improvement, are roads of Genius.<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	Improvement makes strait roads, but the crooked roads <lb/>
            	without Improvement, are roads of Genius.<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	Improve[me]nt makes strait roads, but the crooked roads without<lb/>
            	Improvement, are roads of Genius.<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	Improv[em]ent makes strait roads, but the crooked roads with-<lb/>
            	out Improvement are roads of Genius.<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	Improvement makes strait roads; but the crooked roads<lb/>
            	without Improvement are roads of Genius.<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	Improve[me]nt makes strait roads; but the crooked roads without<lb/>
            	Improvement are roads of Genius.<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	Improvement makes straight roads, but the crooked <lb/>
            	roads without improvement are roads of genius.<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	Improvement makes strait roads; but the crooked <lb/>
            	roads without Improvement are roads of Genius.</figTranscr>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p18-23" n="23"/>
            <figure n="Improvement2.18.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="650" height="465">
            	<figTranscr>Improvement makes strait roads; but the crooked roads with<lb/>
            	out Improvement are roads of Genius.<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	Improve[me]nt makes strait roads, but the crooked roads <lb/>
            	without Improvement, are roads of Genius.<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	Improvement makes strait roads, but the crooked roads without<lb/>
            	Improvement are roads of Genius.<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	Improvement makes straight roads; but the crooked roads without<lb/>
            	improvement are roads of Genius.<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	Improvement makes straight roads, but the crooked <lb/>
            	roads without improvement are roads of Genius.<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	Improvent makes strait roads, but the crooked roads<lb/>
            	without Improvement, are roads of Genius.</figTranscr>
            	<figDesc>Sources for above reproductions (top to bottom): the new E; <hi rend="i">William
                Blake, Selected Poetry</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman, in the Signer Classic Poetry
                Series (1976); the old E; <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi>, ed. G.E.
                Bentley, Jr. (1978); <hi rend="i">Blake, Selected Poetry</hi>, ed. Ruthven Todd, in
                the Laurel Poetry Series, gen. ed. Richard Wilbur (1960); <hi rend="i">The Complete
                Writings of William Blake</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes (1966); <hi rend="i">Poems of
                William Blake</hi>, ed. W.B. Yeats (1969; rpt. of 1905 ed.); <hi rend="i">The
                Portable Blake</hi>, ed. Alfred Kazin (1946); <hi rend="i">Selected Poetry and Prose
                of William Blake</hi>, ed. Northrop Frye (1953); <hi rend="i">William Blake: The
                Complete Poems</hi>, ed. Alicia Ostriker (1977); <hi rend="i">Blake’s Poetry and
                Designs</hi>, eds. Mary Lynn Johnson, John E. Grant (1979); <hi rend="i">The
                Poetical Works of William Blake</hi>, ed. John Sampson (1913); <hi rend="i">The
                Poems of William Blake</hi>, ed. W.H. Stevenson (1971); William Blake, 
                <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, pl. 10 (copy D, Rosenwald Collection,
                Library of Congress).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="Erdman.backjacket.detail.18.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="298">
              <figTranscr>CENTER FOR<lb/>
              SCHOLARLY EDITIONS<lb/>
              <lb/>
              AN APPROVED EDITION<lb/>
              <lb/>
              MODERN LANGUAGE<lb/>
              ASSOCIATION OF AMERICA</figTranscr>
              <head>1. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David
                V. Erdman, back dust jacket, detail.</head>
              <figDesc>“The Modern Language Association Committee on Scholarly Editions has voted to
                award this revised edition its emblem of approval. According to the CSE chairman,
                Don L. Cook of Indiana University, this is the first time that a volume that can be
                expected to receive immediate acceptance both as a standard scholarly edition and a
                classroom text has received the CSE emblem. ‘We are particularly pleased to have
                been able to co-operate in this wedding of scholarly and practical
                publishing.’<lb/>
<lb/>
 “The advice and inspection by the committee have inspired the
                editor to reconsider and improve the exactness of the several kinds of editorial
                treatment required by the diversity of textual sources. ‘By award of this emblem the
                CSE signifies that this volume is based on a thorough study of the variant forms, is
                prepared through consistent application of explicit editorial principles, records
                all emendations to the copy-text introduced by the editors, and has been
                scrupulously and repeatedly proofread to prevent unintentional alterations.’ ” (p.
                VI)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure n="Erdman.p145.detail.18.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="650" height="620">
              <figTranscr>JERUSALEM: TO THE PUBLIC<lb/>
              <lb/>
              PLATE 3<lb/>
              <lb/>
              SHEEP<lb/>
              <lb/>
              GOATS<lb/>
              <lb/>
              To the Public<lb/>
              <lb/>
              After my three years slumber on the banks of the Ocean, I again<lb/>
              display my Giant forms to the Public: My former Giants &amp; Fairies<lb/>
              having reciev’d the highest reward possible: the [love] and [friendship]<lb/>
              of those with whom to by connected, is to be [blessed]: I cannot doubt<lb/>
              that this more consolidated &amp; extended Work, will be as kindly recieved<lb/>
              <lb/>
              The Enthusiasm of the following Poem, the Author hopes [no<lb/>
              Reader will think presumptuousness or arroganc[e] when he is reminded<lb/>
              that the Ancients acknowledge their love to their Deities, to the full as Enthusiastically<lb/>
              as I have who Acknowledge mine for my Saviour and Lord,<lb/>
              for they were wholly absorb’d in their Gods.] I also hope the Reader will<lb/>
              be with me, wholly One in Jesus our Lord, who is the God [of Fire]<lb/>
              and Lord [of Love] to whom the Ancients look’d and saw his day afar<lb/>
              off, with trembling &amp; amazement.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              The Spirit of Jesus is continual forgiveness of Sin: he who waits to<lb/>
              be righteous before he enters into the Saviours kingdom, the Divine<lb/>
              Body; will never enter there. I am perhaps the most sinful of men! I<lb/>
              pretend not to holiness! yet I pretend to love, to see, to converse with<lb/>
              daily, as man with man, &amp; the more to have an interest in the Friend<lb/>
              of Sinners. Therefore [Dear] Reader, [forgive] what you do not approve,<lb/>
              &amp; [love] me for this energetic exertion of my talent.</figTranscr>
              <head>2. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, p. 145,
                detail.</head>
            </figure>
            <figure n="Bentley.vol1.p419.18.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="650" height="691">
              <figTranscr>Jerusalem pl. 3<lb/>
              <lb/>
              [Plate 3]<lb/>
              <lb/>
              SHEEP<lb/>
              <lb/>
              To the Public<lb/>
              <lb/>
              GOATS<lb/>
              <lb/>
              [¶1]<lb/>
              After my three years slumber on the banks of the Ocean, I<lb/>
              again display my Giant forms to the Public: 1 My former Giants<lb/>
              &amp; Fairies having reciev’d the highest reward possible; the<lb/>
              2 and 3 of those with whom to be connected<lb/>
              is to be : 4 I cannot doubt that this more consolidated<lb/>
              &amp; extended Work will be as kindly recieved——The<lb/>
              Enthusiasm of the following Poem, the Author hopes<lb/>
              <lb/>
              5 I also hope<lb/>
              the Reader will be with me, wholly One in Jesus our Lord,<lb/>
              who is the God 6 and Lord 7 to whom the<lb/>
              Ancients look’d and saw his day afar off, with trembling &amp;<lb/>
              amazement.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              [¶2]<lb/>
              The Spirit of Jesus is continual forgiveness of Sin; he who<lb/>
              waits to be righteous before he enters into the Saviours kingdom,<lb/>
              the Divine Body; will never enter there. I am perhaps the<lb/>
              most sinful of men! I pretend not to holiness! yet I pretend to<lb/>
              love, to see, to converse with daily, as man with man, &amp; the<lb/>
              more to have an interest in the Friend of Sinners. Therefore<lb/>
              8 Reader, 9 what you do not approve, &amp; 10<lb/>
              me for this energetic exertion of my talent.</figTranscr>
              <head>3. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi>, ed. G. E. Bentley, Jr., 2
                vols.</head>
              <figDesc>(Oxford: Clarendon, 1978), vol. 1, p. 419, detail.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p18-24" n="24"/>
            <figure n="jerusalem.F.P3" rend="file" width="730" height="1000">
              <figTranscr>3<lb/>
				SHEEP                                                                                 GOATS                3<lb/>
															To the Public<lb/>
						   After my three years slumber on the banks of the Ocean, I again<lb/>
				display my Giant forms to the Public: My former Giants &amp; Fairies<lb/>
				having reciev’d the highest reward possible: the          and<lb/>
				of those with whom to be connected. is to be               : I cannot doubt<lb/>
				that this more consolidated &amp; extended Work. will be as kindly<lb/>
				recieved                           The Enthusiasm of the following Poem, the<lb/>
				Author hopes<lb/>
																						  in                  I also<lb/>
				hope the Reader will be with me. wholly One in Jesus our Lord, who<lb/>
				is the God                   and Lord                   to whom the Ancients look’d<lb/>
				and saw his day afar off. with trembling &amp; amazement.<lb/>
					 The Spirit of Jesus is continual forgiveness of Sin; he who waits<lb/>
				to be righteous before he enters into the Saviours kingdom. the Divine<lb/>
				Body; will never enter there. I am perhaps the most sinful of men!<lb/>
				I pretend not to holiness! yet I pretend to love, to see, to converse with<lb/>
				daily, as man with man, &amp; the more to have an interest in the Friend<lb/>
				of Sinners. Therefore         Reader.          what you do not approve, &amp;<lb/>
						 me for this energetic exertion of my talent.<lb/>
									Reader!        of books!          of heaven.<lb/>
								  And of that. God from whom<lb/>
								  Who in mysterious Sinais awful cave,<lb/>
								  To Man the wond’rous art of writing gave.<lb/>
								  Again he speaks in thunder and in fire!<lb/>
								  Thunder of Thought, &amp; flames of fierce desire:<lb/>
								  Even from the depths of Hell his voice I hear,<lb/>
								  Within the unfathomd caverns of my Ear.<lb/>
								  Therefore I print; nor vain my types shall be:<lb/>
								  Heaven, Earth &amp; Hell, henceforth shall live in harmony<lb/>
													 Of the Measure, in which<lb/>
													 the following Poem is written<lb/>
					We who dwell on Earth can do nothing of ourselves, every thing<lb/>
				is conducted by Spirits, no less than Digestion or Sleep.<lb/>
					When this Verse was first dictated to me I consider’d<lb/>
				a Monotonous Cadence like that used by Milton &amp; Shak-<lb/>
				-speare &amp; all writers of English Blank Verse. derived<lb/>
				from the modern bondage of Rhyming; to be a necessary<lb/>
				and indispensible part of Verse. But I soon found that<lb/>
				in the mouth of a true Orator such monotony was not<lb/>
				only awkward, but as much a bondage as rhyme itself.<lb/>
				I therefore have produced a variety in every line. both<lb/>
				of cadences &amp; number of syllables. Every word and<lb/>
				every letter is studied and put into its fit place: the<lb/>
				terrific numbers are reserved for the terrific parts<lb/>
				the mild &amp; gentle, for the mild &amp; gentle parts. and<lb/>
				the prosaic, for inferior parts; all are necessary to<lb/>
				each other.     Poetry     Fetter’d.     Fetters the Human Race.<lb/>
				Nations are Destroy’d, or Flourish, in proportion as Their<lb/>
				Poetry Painting and Music, are Destroy’d or Flourish! The<lb/>
				Primeval State of Man, was Wisdom, Art, and Science.</figTranscr>
              <head>4. <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (copy F), pl. 3.</head>
              <figDesc>Courtesy of the Pierpont Morgan Library.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p18-25" n="25"/>
            <figure n="ahania.a.p6" id="ahania.a.illbk.06" work-copy="ahania.a" rend="db" width="742" height="1000">
              <figTranscr>But I wander on the rocks<lb/>
              With hard necessity.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              6: Where is my golden palace<lb/>
              Where my ivory bed<lb/>
              Where the joy of my morning hour<lb/>
              Where the sons of eternity. singing<lb/>
              <lb/>
              7: To awake bright Urizen my king:<lb/>
              To arise to the mountain sport,<lb/>
              To the bliss of eternal valleys:<lb/>
              <lb/>
              8: To awake my king in the morn:<lb/>
              To embrace Ahanias joy<lb/>
              On the breath of his open bosom:<lb/>
              From my soft cloud of dew to fall<lb/>
              In showers of life on his harvests.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              9: When he gave my happy soul<lb/>
              To the sons of eternal joy:<lb/>
              When he took the daughters of life.<lb/>
              Into my chambers of love:<lb/>
              <lb/>
              10: When I found babes of bliss on my beds.<lb/>
              And bosoms of milk in my chambers<lb/>
              Fill’d with eternal seed<lb/>
              O! eternal births sung round Ahania<lb/>
              In interchange sweet of their joys.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              11: Swell’d with ripeness &amp; fat with fatness<lb/>
              Bursting on winds my odors.<lb/>
              My ripe figs and rich pomegranates<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              In infant joy at thy feet<lb/>
              O Urizen sported and sang;<lb/>
              <lb/>
              12: Then thou with thy lap full of seed<lb/>
              With thy hand full of generous fire<lb/>
              Walked forth from the clouds of morning<lb/>
              On the virgins of springing joy,<lb/>
              On the human soul to cast<lb/>
              The seed of eternal science,<lb/>
              <lb/>
              13: The sweat poured down thy temples<lb/>
              To Ahania return’d in evening<lb/>
              The moisture awoke to birth<lb/>
              My mothers-joys, sleeping in bliss.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              14: But now alone over rocks. mountains<lb/>
              Cast out from thy lovely bosom:<lb/>
              Cruel jealousy: selfish fear!<lb/>
              Self-destroying: how can delight.<lb/>
              Renew in these chains of darkness<lb/>
              Where bones of beasts are strown<lb/>
              On the bleak and snowy mountains<lb/>
              Where bones from the birth are buried<lb/>
              Before they see the light.<lb/>
              <lb/>
                               FINIS</figTranscr>
              <head>5. <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, pl. 5.</head>
              <figDesc>Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p18-26" n="26"/>
            <figure n="ahania.a.p4" id="ahania.a.illbk.04" work-copy="ahania.a" rend="db" width="743" height="1000">
              <figTranscr>Chap: II:d<lb/>
              <lb/>
              1: But the forehead of Urizen gathering.<lb/>
              And his eyes pale with anguish, his lips<lb/>
              Blue &amp; changing; in tears and bitter<lb/>
              Contrition he prepar’d his Bow.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              2: Form’d of Ribs: that in his dark solitude<lb/>
              When obscur’d in his forests fell monsters.<lb/>
              Arose. For his dire Contemplations<lb/>
              Rush’d down like floods from his mountains<lb/>
              In torrents of mud settling thick<lb/>
              With Eggs of unnatural production<lb/>
              Forthwith hatching; some howl’d on his hills<lb/>
              Some in vales; some aloft flew in air<lb/>
              <lb/>
              3: Of these: an enormous dread Serpent<lb/>
              Scaled and poisonous horned<lb/>
              Approach’d Urizen even to his knees<lb/>
              As he sat on his dark rooted Oak.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              4: With his horns he push’d furious.<lb/>
              Great the conflict &amp; great the jealousy<lb/>
              In cold poisons: but Urizen smote him<lb/>
              <lb/>
              5: First he poison’d the rocks with his blood<lb/>
              Then polish’d his ribs, and his sinews<lb/>
              Dried: laid them apart till winter;<lb/>
              Then a Bow black prepar’d; on this Bow.<lb/>
              A poisoned rock plac’d in silence:<lb/>
              He utter’d these words to the Bow.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              6: O Bow of the clouds of secresy:<lb/>
              O nerve of that lust form’d monster!<lb/>
              Send this rock swift, invisible thro’<lb/>
              The black clouds, on the bosom of Fuzon<lb/>
              <lb/>
              7: So saying, In torment of his wounds.<lb/>
              He bent the enormous ribs slowly;<lb/>
              A circle of darkness! then fixed<lb/>
              The sinew in its rest: then the Rock<lb/>
              Poisonous source! plac’d with art, lifting dif-<lb/>
                 -ficult<lb/>
              Its weighty bulk: silent the rock lay.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              8: While Fuzon his tygers unloosing<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              Thought Urizen slain by his wrath.<lb/>
              I am God. said he. eldest of things!<lb/>
              <lb/>
              9: Sudden sings the rock. swift &amp; invisible<lb/>
              On Fuzon flew. enter’d his bosom;<lb/>
              His beautiful visage, his tresses.<lb/>
              That gave light to the mornings of heaven<lb/>
              Were smitten with darkness. deform’d<lb/>
              And outstretch’d on the edge of the fo-<lb/>
                 -rest<lb/>
              <lb/>
              10: But the rock fell upon the Earth,<lb/>
              Mount Sinai. in Arabia.<lb/>
              <lb/>
                               Chap: III:<lb/>
              <lb/>
              1: The Globe shook; and Urizen seated<lb/>
              On black clouds his sore wound anointed<lb/>
              The ointment flow’d down on the void<lb/>
              Mix’d with blood; here the snake gets<lb/>
                 her poison<lb/>
              <lb/>
              2: With difficulty &amp; great pain; Urizen<lb/>
              Lifted on high the dead corse:<lb/>
              On his shoulders he bore it to where<lb/>
              A Tree hung over the Immensity<lb/>
              <lb/>
              3: For when Urizen shrunk away<lb/>
              From Eternals, he sat on a rock<lb/>
              Barren; a rock which himself<lb/>
              From redounding fancies had petrified<lb/>
              Many tears fell on the rock,<lb/>
              Many sparks of vegetation;<lb/>
              Soon shot the pained root<lb/>
              Of Mystery. under his heel:<lb/>
              It grew a thick tree; he wrote<lb/>
              In silence his book of iron:<lb/>
              Till the horrid plant bending its boughs<lb/>
              Grew to roots when it felt the earth<lb/>
              And again sprung to many a tree.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              4: Amaz’d started Urizen! when<lb/>
              He beheld himself compassed round<lb/>
              And high roofed over with trees<lb/>
              He arose but the stems stood so thick<lb/>
              He with difficulty and great pain<lb/>
              Brought his Books. all but the Book<lb/>
                                                  Of</figTranscr>
              <head>6. <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, pl. 3.</head>
              <figDesc>Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p18-27" n="27"/>
            <figure n="ahania.a.p3" id="ahania.a.illbk.03" work-copy="ahania.a" rend="db" width="726" height="1000">
              <figTranscr>AHANIA<lb/>
              <lb/>
              Chap: Ist<lb/>
              <lb/>
              1: Fuzon. on a chariot iron-wing’d<lb/>
              On spiked flames rose; his hot visage<lb/>
              Flam’d furious! sparkles his hair &amp; beard<lb/>
              Shot down his wide bosom and shoulders<lb/>
              On clouds of smoke rages his chariot<lb/>
              And his right hand burns red in its<lb/>
                    cloud<lb/>
              Moulding into a vast globe. his wrath<lb/>
              As the thunder-stone is moulded<lb/>
              Son of Urizens silent burnings<lb/>
              <lb/>
              2: Shall we worship this Demon of smoke.<lb/>
              Said Fuzon. this abstract non-entity<lb/>
              This cloudy God seated on waters<lb/>
              Now seen. now obscur’d; King of sorrow?<lb/>
              <lb/>
              3: So he spoke. in a fiery flame,<lb/>
              On Urizen frowning indignant,<lb/>
              The Globe of wrath shaking on high<lb/>
              Roaring with fury. he threw<lb/>
              The howling Globe: burning it flew<lb/>
              Lengthning into a hungry beam. Swiftly<lb/>
              <lb/>
              4: Oppos’d to the exulting flam’d beam<lb/>
              The broad Disk of Urizen upheav’d<lb/>
              Across the Void many a mile.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              5: It was forg’d in mills where the winter<lb/>
              Beats incessant: ten winters the disk<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              Unremitting endur’d the cold hammer.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              6: But the strong arm that sent it. remember’d<lb/>
              The sounding beam; laughing it tore through<lb/>
              That beaten mass: keeping its direction<lb/>
              The cold loins of Urizen dividing.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              7: Dire shriek’d his invisible Lust<lb/>
              Deep groan’d Urizen! stretching his awful hand<lb/>
              Ahania (so name his parted soul)<lb/>
              He siez’d on his mountains of Jealousy,<lb/>
              He groand anguishd &amp; called her Sin,<lb/>
              Kissing her and weeping over her:<lb/>
              Then hid her in darkness in silence;<lb/>
              Jealous tho’ she was invisible.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              8: She fell down a faint shadow wandring<lb/>
              In chaos and circling dark Urizen.<lb/>
              As the moon anguishd circles the earth;<lb/>
              Hopeless! abhorrd! a death-shadow.<lb/>
              Unseen. unbodied. unknown,<lb/>
              The mother of Pestilence.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              9: But the fiery beam of Fuzon<lb/>
              Was a pillar of fire to Egypt<lb/>
              Five hundred years wandring on earth<lb/>
              Till Los siezd it and beat in a mass<lb/>
              With the body of the sun.</figTranscr>
              <head>7. <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, pl. 2.</head>
              <figDesc>Rosenwald Collection, Library of Congress.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p18-28" n="28"/>
            <figure n="Erdman.p144.detail.18.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="263">
              <figTranscr>PLATE 43 [50]<lb/>
              To go forth to the Great Harvest &amp; Vintage of the Nations<lb/>
              Finis<lb/>
              <lb/>
              JERUSALEM<lb/>
              The Emanation of The Giant Albion<lb/>
              1804 Printed by W. Blake Sth Molton St.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              PLATE I<lb/>
              <lb/>
              [Frontispiece]</figTranscr>
              <head>8. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, p. 144,
                detail.</head>
            </figure>
            <figure n="SatansSubmarines.18.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="650" height="508">
              <figTranscr>Satan’s Submarines<lb/>
              Heb. 6:18-20.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              Ship  	Church<lb/>
              Pilot 	Christ<lb/>
              Compass	Holy [Spir]it<lb/>
              Chart 	Scripture<lb/>
              Anchor	Hope<lb/>
              Cable 	Faith<lb/>
              Cargo 	Souls<lb/>
              <lb/>
              CHURCH<lb/>
              WOR-SHIP<lb/>
              <lb/>
              Jas. 4:10<lb/>
              Pride<lb/>
              Prov. 16:18; 13:10;<lb/>
              1 Pet. 5:5<lb/>
              <lb/>
              Phil. 2:12; 3:13-14.<lb/>
              [Indifference]<lb/>
              Rev. [3:10;]<lb/>
              <lb/>
              Heb. 2:1-2.<lb/>
              Unbelief<lb/>
              Heb. [3:13-19;]<lb/>
              <lb/>
              Mt. 7:3-5.<lb/>
              Hypocrisy<lb/>
              Job 20:4-5; Mt. 23:3,5;<lb/>
              <lb/>
              Col. 3:1-2.<lb/>
              Worldliness<lb/>
              Jas. 2:15-17<lb/>
              Rom. 12:2; 2 Cor. 6:17.</figTranscr>
              <head>9. Photograph by Harry Annas Studio, Lockhart, Texas, c. 1950s.</head>
              <figDesc>From the Photography Archive, Carpenter Center for the Visual Arts, Harvard
                University.</figDesc>
            </figure>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p18-29-31" n="29-31" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
