<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>18.1.ostriker</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Jean H. Hagstrum, Sex and Sensibility: Ideal and Erotic Love from Milton to
Mozart</title>
        <author n="Ostriker">Alicia Ostriker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1984</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1984</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">18.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen Leo Carr</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
              <name>Joseph S. Salemi</name>
              <name>Santa Cruz Blake Study Group</name>
              <name>Thomas A. Vogler</name>
              <name>Bette Charlene Werner</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1984"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_18">
    <body>
	<pb id="p18-52" n="52"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-1-0005">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Jean H. Hagstrum. <hi rend="i">Sex and Sensibility: Ideal and Erotic Love from
Milton to Mozart.</hi> Chicago: Univ. of Chicago Press, 1982. 368 pp., illustrated. Cloth, $30.00; paper,
$9.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Alicia</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Ostriker</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>That man must have a heart of stone, says Oscar Wilde, who can read through the death of Little
Nell without laughing. This has always been my sentiment about the death of Richardson’s Clarissa; 
<hi rend="i">Clarissa</hi> as a whole has always struck me as the greatest, most sustained piece of soft-core
pornographic soap opera in English. That such a fuss should be made over the deflowering of a not otherwise
interesting bourgeois young lady; that Clarissa herself, her abductor, everyone else in the novel, and
apparently
<pb id="p18-53" n="53"/>
all of Europe from Dr. Johnson to Diderot and de Sade, should agree to apprehend the young woman’s steady
and humorless concentration on her own purity as the symbol not only of virtue but of Virtue, sensibility,
nobility, sublimity, greatness of soul, angelic exaltedness and even sainthood, to me seems marvelous. I can
imagine that the novel, and the feminization of culture it represents, would have deeply offended and
irritated Blake; cf. the “subtle modesty” passage in <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>,
“My Spectre Around Me,” and much else.</p>
          <p>Far otherwise is it in <hi rend="i">Sex and Sensibility</hi>, Jean Hagstrum’s monumental survey
of love in the Restoration and the eighteenth century. Hagstrum’s admiration for Richardson’s “amazingly
perspicuous and intense portrayal of love” extends to exclamations of his own about Richardson’s heroine
(“How profoundly inner and intuitive the Protestant Clarissa is!”) and to the urgent insistence that she
is no prude but “deeply a woman” who would have loved Lovelace had he been worthy of her. Clarissa
“dreamed of a man who would combine virtue with physical charm. . . . One of the most poignant of the letter
fragments that survive the rape shows that Clarissa really wanted marriage.” Lovelace “is made to run the
gamut of human evil” when he dreams of siring, by Clarissa and Anna, children who will intermarry. Yet he is
an “appealing” being of “heterosexual exuberance” (Hagstrum defends his potency and masculinity
against doubters), possessed of considerable though amoral “sensitiveness,” a potential Man of Feeling
capable of rising finally to a full appreciation of Clarissa’s greatness; which, however, “cannot of
course avail to salvation.” Clarissa’s death is “this great apotheosis.”</p>
          <p>That Hagstrum is not so much a theoretical analyst of the cult of sensibility as a member of it
in good standing, is the chief defect and the chief strength of <hi rend="i">Sex and Sensibility.</hi>
Literary issues of language, style, structure and genre scarcely concern him. Neither Freud nor De Rougemont,
much less Foucault or Bataille, impinge, although the connection <corr type="emend">between</corr> love and
death is one of his major topics. The seventeenth- and eighteenth-century development of the “closed
domesticated nuclear” family ideally based on personal choice and affection, documented by Lawrence Stone,
is cited by Hagstrum as the social basis behind the cultural phenomena he investigates, but the relation
between art and literature and social change is not his subject: the interpretation of characters and their
feelings is.</p>
          <p>To the post-Romantic reader, Hagstrum’s inclination to moralize his song may seem excessive.
Milton’s ideal of wedded love and uxorial joy, love as an elevating and civilizing influence, the
domestication of heroism, tender feeling in particular and heterosexuality in general, are approved of. Thus
Dryden’s works “often throb with a bold and hearty physicality.” When the good Maria confesses her love
for the criminal George Barnwell on the eve of his execution in Lillo’s <hi rend="i">The London
Merchant</hi>, “seldom has the theme [of love and death] been more movingly exploited.” The love of Pamela
and Mr. B. “elevates a spirited and determined girl to high station and gives to the noble husband . . . a
marriage of true minds, hearts and bodies.” Hagstrum is unmoved by the ideal of “angélism,” the female
too pure for physical passion, or by any sort of platonism. He admires passionate heroines, and feels that
Dryden’s portrayal of Dido as weak and licentious is “perhaps unforgivable.” In his chapter on “The
Abandoned and Passionate Mistress,” he asserts that the period took to exotic deserted heroines like Dido,
the Portugese Nun, and Eloise, “not because it wanted to escape reality” but because it needed “to fuel
the domestic enterprise” by depictions of women who feel “intense devotion to a single man that is
lifelong and irreversible and that lasts to the very edge of doom.”</p>
          <p>Antithetic to normative heterosexuality is what Hagstrum calls “morbid” or “narcissistic”
love, the <hi rend="i">locus classicus</hi> of which he finds again in Milton, both in the Satan-Sin relation
and in Adam’s antihierarchial attachment to Eve as “flesh of my flesh,” i.e. his similitude. Incest,
threatened and actual, is a huge and fascinating motif in this period; both incest and love for one’s
likeness or mirror-self belong in the category of “the narcissistic sins.” Thus Southerne’s stage
version of Behn’s <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">Oroonoko</hi>,</corr> which displaces the themes of “love of woman for disguised
woman, love of woman for effeminate male” into a farcial subplot, may be a “healthy attempt to expunge a
potential stain on the psyche and on society.” Interestingly, Hagstrum does not disapprove the intense
erotic friendships of Clarissa-Anna and of Julie-Claire in <hi rend="i">La Nouvelle Eloise</hi>, perhaps
because they do not successfully challenge the primacy of heterosexual passion.</p>
          <p>The primary advantage of Hagstrum’s approach is that it enables him enthusiastically to
consider an immense range of works, among byways as well as highways, more or less on their own terms. His
investigations of Pope’s, Swift’s, and Sterne’s quirky and poignant variations on the theme of
sensibility are tolerant and tender. The subject of ungratified infantilized eroticism—the lover as son—in
Goethe and Rousseau is finely handled. The sorts of questions he tends to ask—has the Portugese Nun really
stopped loving her ravisher? Should Clarissa have married Lovelace? Why does Uncle Toby retreat from the Widow
Wadman?—capture, one feels, the actual preoccupations of the authors and their original readers, far better
than a cooler, theoretically-oriented reading could have done. So too, Hagstrum’s inclination to moralize
emotion places us squarely within the ethos he describes. A bonus, throughout <hi rend="i">Sex and
Sensibility</hi>, is Hagstrum’s discussion of sex and love in the parallel traditions of painting and music.
The array of plates, reproducing a set of highly-charged erotic paintings from Barry and Correggio to Greuze,
should convince anyone that the Age of Reason enjoyed its steamy side.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
