<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>18.1.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1984</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1984</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">18.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen Leo Carr</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
              <name>Joseph S. Salemi</name>
              <name>Santa Cruz Blake Study Group</name>
              <name>Thomas A. Vogler</name>
              <name>Bette Charlene Werner</name>
              <name>Andrew Wilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1984"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_18">
    <front>
      <pb id="p18-1-2" n="1-2"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.018.01.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="333">
          <figTranscr>Blake<lb/>
            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
            VOLUME 18<lb/>
            NUMBER 1<lb/>
            SUMMER 1984</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-1-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="12" cols="2">
          <row>
    		<cell>
        	  <head>
          		<title>
            	  <hi rend="b">
              		<hi rend="i">CONTENTS</hi>
            	  </hi>
          		</title>
        	  </head>
    		</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.1.erdman">David V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Complete
Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi></ref>, reviewed by the Santa Cruz Blake Study Group</cell>
            <cell>4</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.1.worrall">Stephen D. Cox, <hi rend="i">“The Stranger Within
Thee”: Concepts of the Self in Late Eighteenth-Century Literature</hi></ref>, reviewed by David
Worrall</cell>
            <cell>31</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.1.werner">Pamela Dunbar, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Illustrations to the Poetry of Milton</hi></ref>, reviewed by Bette Charlene Werner</cell>
            <cell>33</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.1.carr">W.J.T. Mitchell, ed., <hi rend="i">The Language of
Images</hi></ref>, reviewed by Stephen Leo Carr</cell>
            <cell>35</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.1.vogler">Zachary Leader, <hi rend="i">Reading Blake’s
“Songs,”</hi></ref> reviewed by Thomas A. Vogler</cell>
            <cell>39</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.1.labelle">James Bogan and Fred Goss, eds., <hi rend="i">Sparks
of Fire: Blake in a New Age</hi></ref>, reviewed by Jenijoy La Belle</cell>
            <cell>48</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.1.salemi">Aquilino Sanchez Perez, <hi rend="i">Blake’s
Graphic Work and the Emblematic Tradition</hi></ref>, reviewed by Joseph S. Salemi</cell>
            <cell>50</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.1.ostriker">Jean H. Hagstrum, <hi rend="i">Sex and
Sensibility: Ideal and Erotic Love from Milton to Mozart</hi></ref>, reviewed by Alicia Ostriker</cell>
            <cell>52</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.1.wilton">Robert N. Essick and Morton D. Paley, 
<hi rend="i">Robert Blair’s</hi> The Grave, <hi rend="i">Illustrated by William Blake</hi></ref>, reviewed by
Andrew Wilton</cell>
            <cell>54</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.1.deluca">Minna Doskow, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s</hi>
Jerusalem: <hi rend="i">Structure and Meaning in Poetry and Picture</hi></ref>, reviewed by V.A. De
Luca</cell>
            <cell>56</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.1.punter">Blake/Hegel/Derrida: A response to Nelson Hilton’s
review of <hi rend="i">Blake, Hegel and Dialectic</hi></ref>, by David Punter</cell>
            <cell>58</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-1-0002">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">CONTRIBUTORS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="b">STEPHEN LEO CARR</hi> teaches at the University of Pittsburgh. He has published
several articles on Blake’s graphic art, and is at work on a book that interrelates Blake’s print-making
process and his strategies of literary and pictorial representation.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">V.A. DE LUCA</hi> of the University of Toronto is at work on a book about Blake and
the poetics of the sublime.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">JENIJOY LA BELLE</hi> is an Associate Professor of Literature at the California
Institute of Technology.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">ALICIA OSTRIKER</hi> is the editor of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Complete Poems</hi>
(Penguin) and has cogitated on Blake and sex in this journal. Her most recent book of poems is <hi rend="i">A
Woman Under the Surface</hi> (Princeton). She is a Professor of English at Rutgers University.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">DAVID PUNTER</hi> is Senior Lecturer in English Studies at the University of East
Anglia. His writings on Blake include <hi rend="i">Blake, Hegel and Dialectic</hi> (Amsterdam, 1982) and
articles in <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism, Literature and History</hi> and <hi rend="i">Criticism.</hi>
His most recent work, “The Sign of Blake,” will be appearing in <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> shortly.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">JOSEPH S. SALEMI</hi> is on the adjunct faculty of the Humanities Department at New
York University. His interest in Blake dates from a seminar with Aileen Ward in 1976.</p>
        <p>The <hi rend="b">SANTA CRUZ BLAKE STUDY GROUP</hi> is at work on a review of contemporary Blake
criticism.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">THOMAS A. VOGLER</hi> is Professor of Literature at the University of California,
Santa Cruz. He has recently co-edited (with Nelson Hilton) a collection of essays on Blake, 
<hi rend="i">Unnam’d Forms: Blake and Textuality</hi>, to be published by The University of California Press in
1985.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">BETTE CHARLENE WERNER</hi> is Editor of Publications for the Healthcare Internal Audit
Group and an Instructor of English at The University of Toledo. Her book on Blake’s Milton illustrations
will be published by Bucknell University Press. 
                </p>
        <pb id="p18-3" n="3"/>
        <p><hi rend="b">ANDREW WILTON</hi> is an Assistant Curator, Department of Prints and Drawings, at the
British Museum. His most recent publication is <hi rend="i">Turner and the Sublime.</hi></p>
        <p><hi rend="b">DAVID WORRALL</hi> teaches in Newcastle-upon-Tyne, England. His article on Blake’s
star imagery, “The ‘Immortal Tent,’ ” appeared in <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the
Humanities.</hi></p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-1-0003">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">EDITORS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="b">Editors:</hi> Morris Eaves, University of New Mexico, and Morton D. Paley, University
of California, Berkeley.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Bibliographer:</hi> Thomas L. Minnick, Ohio State University.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Review Editor:</hi> Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia, Athens.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Associate Editor for Great Britain:</hi> Frances A. Carey, Assistant Curator,
Department of Prints and Drawings, British Museum.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Production Office:</hi> Morris Eaves, Department of English, University of New Mexico,
Albuquerque, NM 87131, <hi rend="b">Telephone</hi> 505/277-3103.<lb/>
Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley, CA 94720.<lb/>
Thomas L. Minnick, University College, Ohio State University, 1050 Carmack Road, Columbus, OH 43210.<lb/>
Nelson Hilton, Department of English, University of Georgia, Athens, GA 30602.<lb/>
Frances A. Carey, Department of Prints and Drawings, British Museum, Great Russell Street, London WC1B 3DG,
United Kingdom.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-1-0004">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">INFORMATION</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="b">Managing Editor:</hi> Robin Tawney.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Editorial Assistants:</hi> Leslie Donovan, Chapel Petty, University of New Mexico.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is published under the sponsorship of the
Department of English, University of New Mexico.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Subscriptions</hi> are $18 for institutions, $15 for individuals. All subscriptions
are by the volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments received after the
summer issue will be applied to the 4 issues of the current volume. Foreign addresses (except Canada and
Mexico) require a $3 per volume postal surcharge for surface mail, a $10 per volume surcharge for air mail
delivery. U.S. currency or international money order necessary. Make checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly.</hi> Address all subscription orders and related communications to Robin Tawney, 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Department of English, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, NM 87131, USA.</p>
        <p>Many <hi rend="b">back issues</hi> are available at a reduced price. Address Robin Tawney for a
list of issues and prices.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Manuscripts</hi> are welcome. Send two copies, typed and documented according to the
forms suggested in the MLA Style Sheet, 2nd ed., to either of the editors: Morris Eaves, Dept. of English,
University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, NM 87131; Morton D. Paley, Dept. of English, University of California,
Berkeley, CA 94720.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">International Standard Serial Number:</hi> 0006-453x. <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is <hi rend="b">indexed</hi> in the Modern Language Association’s International
Bibliography, the Modern Humanities Research Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and
Literature, <hi rend="i">English Languge Notes</hi>’ annual Romantic Bibliography, ART bibliographies
MODERN, American Humanities Index, and the Arts and Humanities Citation Index.</p>
        <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 1984 Morris Eaves and Morton Paley</note>
        <figure n="AsleepMan.18.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="171"></figure>
      </div1>
    </front>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
