<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>18.2.minnick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="checklist">Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Recent Publications</title>
        <author n="Minnick">Thomas L. Minnick</author>
        <author n="Dörrbecker">Detlef W. Dörrbecker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1984</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1984</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">18.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D. W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary V. Jackson</name>
              <name>James McCord</name>
              <name>Jerome J. McGann</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1984"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_18">
    <body>
      <pb id="p18-100" n="100"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-2-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Recent Publications</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">THOMAS L.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">MINNICK</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
          <hi rend="i">AND</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">DETLEF W.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">DÖRRBECKER</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>This year’s checklist testifies to the continuing high level of activity and productivity by
scholars of William Blake and his circle. As has become our custom, an asterisk beside an entry on the
following list identifies an item that we have not examined personally.</p>
        <p>Compiling this checklist is an occupation made lighter by the thoughtful scholars who have sent
along offprints or notices of their own recent publications or of the work of their students and colleagues.
It is always a pleasure for us to record our gratitude to those contributors.</p>
        <p>T.L.M.</p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part I</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">William Blake</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Editions, Translations, Fascimiles, Reproductions</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>*1. Blake, William. <hi rend="i">Annotations to Richard Watson</hi>: An Apology for the Bible
in a Series of Letters Addressed to Thomas Paine, <hi rend="i">8th ed., 1797.</hi> Ed. G. Ingli James. Regency
Reprints, 1st ser. Cardiff: University College Cardiff Press, 1984.</p>
            <p>*2. Blake, William. <hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi> America: A Prophecy <hi rend="i">and</hi>
Europe: A Prophecy—<hi rend="i">Facsimile Reproductions of Two Illuminated Books.</hi> Fine Art Series. New
York, N.Y.: Dover, 1983. $6.95 [There are 35 color plates.]</p>
            <p>3. Blake, William. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas: The Torments of Love and Jealousy in the Death
and Judgment of Albion the Ancient Man</hi>, derived from [Blake’s] original drawings, engravings and the
manuscript dated 1797. Ed. Landon Dowdey, assisted by Patricia Hopkins Rice. Chicago, Ill.: Swallow Press,
1983. [The first edition consists of 3000 copies. This is neither a scholarly edition nor a facsimile. Dowdey
has done away with Blake’s line divisions, introduced punctuation, and changed Blake’s tenses. The editor
advises his readers: “ . . . out of such communion with the poet, create in your imagination your own poem,
your own vision—vaguely perceived perhaps; . . . ” (p. v.). The edition includes reproductions from new
infra-red photographs of the drawings in the <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> MS.]</p>
            <p>*4. Blake, William. <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi> New York: N.Y.: Dover, 1984.</p>
            <p>*5. Bryant, Jacob. <hi rend="i">A New System; or, An Analysis of Ancient Mythology.</hi> 3
vols. 2nd ed. 1775; rpt. Ed. Burton Feldman and Robert D. Richardson, Jr. <hi rend="i">Myth and
Romanticism</hi>, 5. New York, N.Y. and London: Garland Publishing, 1984.</p>
            <p>6. Keynes, Geoffrey L., and Peter Davidson, eds. <hi rend="i">A Watch of Nightingales.</hi>
London: The Stourton Press, 1981. [A limited edition of 400 copies. This anthology has been “built around”
a nightingale poem which was etched by Cumberland and has been attributed to Blake by the late Sir Geoffrey
Keynes.]</p>
            <p>See also item 45 for a complete reproduction of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Bibliographies, Bibliographical Essays, Exhibition Catalogues</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>7. Allen, Robert R., ed. <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A Current Bibliography</hi>, NS 4
(1978). New York, N.Y.: AMS Press, 1981. [Blake entries will be found on 282-87.]</p>
            <p>8. Bennett, James R. “The Comparative Criticism of Blake and Wordsworth: A Bibliography.”
<hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 14 (1984), 99-106.</p>
            <p>9. Bentley, G.E., Jr. “The 1821 Edwards Catalogue.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1984), 154-56.</p>
            <p>10. Butlin, Martin. “<hi rend="i">Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (1981): Some
Minor Additions.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1984), 159.</p>
            <pb id="p18-101" n="101"/>
            <p>11. Essick, Robert N. “A Supplement to <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A
Catalogue.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1984), 139-44.</p>
            <p>12. Fabian, Bernhard. “William Blake (1757-1827).” In his <hi rend="i">Von Chaucer bis
Pinter: Ausgewählte Autorenbibliographien zur englischen Literatur.</hi> Athenäum Taschenbücher:
Literaturwissenschaft, 2154. Königstein i. Ts.: Athenäum, 1980, pp. 14-18.</p>
            <p>13. de Groot, H.B., with the assistance of Susan Douglas-Drinkwater. “Blake and the
Ancients.” [Ontario]: n.p., n.d. [This catalogue accompanied an exhibition of works by Blake, his
contemporaries, and his followers that was shown at University College from 17-21 January 1983 and at the
Thomas Fisher Rare Books Library from 25 January to 28 February 1983. After his introductory essay, the author
lists 36 items, including engravings by Blake and drawings by Romney, Flaxman, Palmer, and Richmond, and
numerous etchings by the Ancients.]</p>
            <p>14. Jing-yu, Gu. “Unlisted Articles on Blake Published in China.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1984), 157-59.</p>
            <p>15. Korshin, Paul J., and Robert R. Allen, eds. <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A Current
Bibliography</hi>, NS 5 (1979). New York, N.Y.: AMS Press, 1983. [See 347-65 and s.v. “Blake” in the
index; the more extensive reviews are listed in part IV, below.]</p>
            <p>16. Minnick, Thomas L., and Detlef W. Dörrbecker. “Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of
Recent Publications.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983), 62-76.</p>
            <p>17. Modern Language Association of America. “Blake, William (1757-1827).” In 
<hi rend="i">1982 MLA International Bibliography of Books and Articles on the Modern Languages and
Literatures.</hi> Vol. 1: “Classified Listings.” New York, N.Y.: MLA, 1983 [i.e., 1984], 57-59. [See also
s.v. “Blake” in the subject index for further references.]</p>
            <p>18. Newey, Vincent, Bryan Burns, and Philip Dodd. “The Nineteenth Century: Romantic
Period.” In <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English Studies</hi>, vol. 61 (1980). Ed. James Redmond.
[London]: John Murray, for the English Association, 1982, see pp. 259-62.</p>
            <p>*19. Piquet, François. “Blake: <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence, Songs of Experience, The
Book of Thel, The Marriage of Heaven and Hell, America, Visions of the Daughters of Albion, Vala or The Four
Zoas (Nights II &amp; III), The Everlasting Gospel</hi>—Bibliographie sélective et critique.” 
<hi rend="i">Bulletin de la Société d’études Anglo-Américaines des XVII<hi rend="s">e</hi> Siècles</hi>, 15
(1982), 43-66.</p>
            <p>20. Smith, Michael, ed. <hi rend="i">Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature for
1980</hi>, vol. 55. London: Modern Humanities Research Association, 1983. [Blake entries listed on pp. 352-57
as items 6495 to 6581.]</p>
            <p>21. Walker, Dean. “Aspects of Blake and the Art of His Time.” <hi rend="i">Ackland Art
Museum Newsletter</hi>, no. 16 (1984), n. pag. [The eight pages of this issue are devoted to a brief catalogue
of an exhibition held at the Ackland Art Museum at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. There is
an introduction by Innis H. Shoemaker, an essay and a “Checklist of Exhibited Works” which, among its 31
items, includes four drawings on loan from the estate of the late Gregory Bateson.]</p>
            <p>See also item 53, Gizzi.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Critical Studies</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>*22. Ackland, Michael. “Blake’s Critique of Enlightenment Reason in <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Colby Literary Quarterly</hi>, 19 (1983), 173-89.</p>
            <p>23. Adams, Hazard. “The Blakean Symbolic.” In his <hi rend="i">Philosophy of the Literary
Symbolic.</hi> Tallahassee and Gainesville, Fl.: University Presses of Florida, 1983, pp. 99-116. $37.50
cloth, $17.50 paper. [See also pp. 5-12 of the introduction for “Some Blakean and Vichean Views.”]</p>
            <p>*24. Adams, Hazard. <hi rend="i">William Blake: A Reading of the Shorter Poems.</hi> 1963; rpt.
Philadelphia, Pa.: Richard West, 1983.</p>
            <p>25. Anderson, Mark Ransom. “Apollyon’s Bow: Perspective, Reading, and Meaning in the
Illuminated Works of William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 44 (1984),
2475A-2476A (Cornell University, 1983). [“Recent theories of reader response have tended to conclude that
the reader’s role in a work of art is largely predetermined by the author’s intention or by the structure
of the text; Blake’s works argue against that conclusion. The prophetic tradition (especially as practiced
by Spenser and Milton), and his own ideas of the sublime (antithetical to those of Burke and Kant), led him to
the belief that a truly prophetic work of art must reflect the spiritual, or imaginative, state of each
individual member of its audience. His poems are therefore constructed so as to mean different things
according to the different perspectives from which they may be read.”]</p>
            <p>26. Avens, Roberts [sic]. <hi rend="i">Blake, Swedenborg, and the Neo-Platonic Tradition</hi>,
with an introduction by Dr. George F. Dole. New York, N.Y.: The Swedenborg Foundation, n.d. [1983]. [Ten pages
of text to accompany the Swedenborg Foundation’s film “Blake: The Marriage of Heaven and Hell”; see 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983), 38.]</p>
            <p>*27. Behrendt, Stephen C. <hi rend="i">The Moment of Explosion: Blake and the Illustration of
Milton.</hi> Lincoln, Nebr.: University of Nebraska Press, 1983.</p>
            <p>28. Bender, John, and Anne K. Mellor. “Liberating the Sister Arts: The Revolution of
Blake’s ‘Infant
<pb id="p18-102" n="102"/>
Sorrow.’ ” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi>, 50 (1983), 297-319.</p>
            <p>29. Bentley, G.E., Jr. “Blake and the Ancients: A Prophet with Honour Among the Sons of
God.” In <hi rend="i">Essays on the Blake Followers.</hi> Ed. Robert R. Wark. San Marino, Cal.: Henry E.
Huntington Library and Art Gallery, 1983, pp. 1-17. [Published simultaneously in the <hi rend="i">Huntington
Library Quarterly</hi>, 46 (1983), 1-17; this paper—with others by Robert N. Essick, Shelley M. Bennett, and
Morton D. Paley (q.v.)—was delivered as part of a symposium on “Prints by the Blake Followers” at the
Huntington Library and Art Gallery on 13 February 1982.]</p>
            <p>30. Bentley, G.E., Jr. “Charles Parr Burney as a Blake Collector.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983), 16.</p>
            <p>31. Bidney, Martin. “Structures of Perception in Blake and Whitman: Creative Contraries,
Cosmic Body, Fourfold Vision.” <hi rend="i">ESQ: A Journal of the American Renaissance</hi>, 28 (1982),
36-47.</p>
            <p>32. Birenbaum, Harvey. <hi rend="i">Tragedy and Innocence.</hi> Washington, D.C.: University
Press of America, 1983. [As the title page indicates, this volume consists “of a treatise on the psychology
of tragedy together with an essay on the vision of William Blake, the two comprising a study in the nature of
myth, symbolism and consciousness.” “Blake’s Myth of Innocence” is pages 97-159.]</p>
            <p>*33. Brinkley, Robert A. “Blake and the Prophecy of Satan.” <hi rend="i">New Orleans
Review</hi>, 9 (1982), 73-76.</p>
            <p>34. Brisman, Leslie. “Re: Generation in Blake.” In his <hi rend="i">Romantic Origins.</hi>
Ithaca, N.Y. and London: Cornell University Press, 1978, pp. 224-75.</p>
            <p>35. Christensen, Bryce J. “The Apple in the Vortex: Newton, Blake and Descartes.” 
<hi rend="i">Philosophy and Literature</hi>, 6 (1982), 147-61.</p>
            <p>36. Cope, Kevin Lee. “The Criteria of Certainty: Philosophical Currents in the Literature of
the English Enlightenment.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 44 (1984), 2152A
(Harvard University, 1983). [“This dissertation offers an aesthetic history of the answers provided by the
English Enlightenment to the question, ‘what constitutes certainty?’ . . . The final chapter turns to
Hume, Blake, and Coleridge. These writers not only subordinate magnificent systems to the author organizing
them, but also long for some still higher foundation for that still more elusive system, the author himself. .
. .”]</p>
            <p>37. Copland, James Alexander. “The Influence of Old Testament Versification on English Poetry
after 1750.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 43 (1983), 3918A (University of
Toronto, Canada, 1982). [“ ‘The majestic rhythms of the King James Bible’ and, behind them, the
parallelism of Biblical Hebrew prosody, are widely held to have influenced the prosody and rhythm of
Christopher Smart’s <hi rend="i">Jubilate Agno</hi>, James Macpherson’s <hi rend="i">The Poems of
Ossian</hi>, William Blake’s three major prophecies, and Walt Whitman’s <hi rend="i">Leaves of Grass.</hi>
This thesis is an examination of that claim. . . . In Chapter III, I look for this rhythmic parallelism in
Smart, Macpherson, Blake and Whitman, finding it in only a relatively few lines in Blake. . . .”]</p>
            <p>38. Corti, Claudia. “La Bibbia ‘infernale’ di William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Rivista di
Letterature moderne e comparate</hi>, NS 36 (1983), 123-31.</p>
            <p>*39. Crehan, Stewart. <hi rend="i">Blake in Context.</hi> Dublin: Gill and Macmillan, 1984.
£20.</p>
            <p>*40. Damon, S. Foster. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Job: William Blake’s</hi> Illustrations of the
Book of Job. 1966; rpt. Hanover, N.H.: University Press of New England, for Brown University Press, 1982.</p>
            <p>41. Davies, J.M.Q. “ ‘ Embraces are Cominglings’: Passion and Apocalypse in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> Designs.” <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi>, NS 43 (1981),
75-96.</p>
            <p>42. De Luca, V.A. “Blake and the Two Sublimes.” pp. 93-105 in Harry C. Payne, ed., 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Eighteenth-Century Culture. Volume 11.</hi> Madison: University of Wisconsin Press,
1983.</p>
            <p>43. Dilworth, Thomas. “The Hands of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: Blake’s Multistable Image of
Self-Annihilation.” <hi rend="i">Mosaic</hi>, 16 (1983), 11-27.</p>
            <p>*44. DiSalvo, Jackie. <hi rend="i">War of Titans: Blake’s Critique of Milton and the Politics
of Religion.</hi> Pittsburgh, Pa.: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1984. $35.00.</p>
            <p>45. Doskow, Minna. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem: <hi rend="i">Structure and
Meaning in Poetry and Picture.</hi> Rutherford, Madison and Teaneck, N.J.: Fairleigh Dickinson University
Press; East Brunswick, N.J., London and Toronto: Associated University Presses, 1982. [The appendix to this
study is made up by a complete reprint of the 1955 Beechhurst Press facsimile of the Rinder copy (C) of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>]</p>
            <p>*46. Duffy, H. “Un visionnaire: William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Vie des Arts</hi>, 27, No. 110
(1983), 62-63.</p>
            <p>*47. Ellis, Helen B., and Warren U. Ober. “<hi rend="i">Grendel</hi> and Blake: The
Contraries of Existence.” In <hi rend="i">John Gardner: Critical Perspectives.</hi> Eds. Robert A. Morace
and Kathryn van Spanckeren. Carbondale, Ill.: Southern Illinois University Press, 1982, pp. 42-61.</p>
            <p>48. Erdman, David V. “Redefining the Texts of Blake (Another Temporary Report).” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983), 4-15.</p>
            <p>49. Essick, Robert N. “John Linnell, William Blake, and the Printmaker’s Craft.” In 
<hi rend="i">Essays on the Blake Followers.</hi> Ed. Robert R. Wark. San Marino, Cal.: Henry E. Huntington Library
and Art Gallery, 1983, pp. 18-32. [Published simultaneously in the Huntington Library Quarterly, 46 (1983),
18-32.]</p>
            <p>50. Essick, Robert N. “Some Unrecorded States, Printings, and Impressions of Blake’s
Graphic Works.”
<pb id="p18-103" n="103"/>
	<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1984), 130-38.</p>
            <p>51. Franci, Giovanna, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: mito e linguaggio.</hi> Collezione
Biblioteca, 16. Pordenone: Edizioni Studio Tesi, 1983. [This handsomely produced paperback volume contains a
selection of essays by Vita Fortunati on Blake’s “apocalyptic city,” by Stefania D’Ottavi on
“metapoetic aspects” of the names in his mythology, by Paola Colaiacomo on Blake’s rhymes in the
“Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, by Claudia Corti on Blake as the “maestro” of Joyce, by
Pamela Dunbar on Blake’s use and interpretation of the Bible, by Renato Barilli on Blake as one of the first
“moderns,” by Sergio Givone on Blake and philosophy, by Gianni Scalia on Blake as the prophet of
revolution, by Roman Jakobson on the verbal art of Blake and other poet-painters (trans. from an essay first
published in 1970), and by the editor on irony and prophecy in Blake. There are 29 illustrations, and the
slip-cased volume sells at Lit. 15000.]</p>
            <p>*52. Gillespie, Diane Filby. “A Key to Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi>: Design XX.” 
<hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi>, 19 (1983), 59-68.</p>
            <p>53. Gizzi, Corrado, ed. <hi rend="i">Blake e Dante.</hi> Milan: Nuove edizioni Gabriele
Mazzotta, 1983. [This volume, published in conjunction with an exhibition of twenty-three of Blake’s Dante
watercolors at the Casa di Dante in Abruzzo, combines a set of color plates from all the works on show with
tiny halftone reproductions of the complete run of the watercolors and engravings in this series. The
reproductions are accompanied by a number of scholarly essays by Renato Barilli, Fortunato Bellonzi, Martin
Butlin, Claudia Corti, Luigi Paolo Finizio, Ursula Hoff, Ferruccio Ulivi, and the editor.]</p>
            <p>54. Glen, Heather. <hi rend="i">Vision and Disenchantment: Blake’s</hi> Songs 
<hi rend="i">and Wordsworth’s</hi> Lyrical Ballads. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1983. £25. [Part of
the edition is available in the Cambridge Paperback Library series.]</p>
            <p>55. Gourlay, Alexander S. “An Emendation in ‘The Chimney Sweeper’ of 
<hi rend="i">Innocence.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983), 16-17.</p>
            <p>56. Gourlay, Alexander S., and John E. Grant. “The Melancholy Shepherdess in Prospect of Love
and Death in Reynolds and Blake.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi>, 85 (1982),
169-89.</p>
            <p>*57. Grčić, Marko. “William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Forum</hi>, 38 (1979), 155-81.</p>
            <p>*58. Greco, Norma A. “Blake’s ‘The Little Girl Lost’: An Initiation into Womanhood.”
<hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi>, 19 (1983), 144-54.</p>
            <p>59. Greenberg, Mark L. “Blake’s ‘Science.’ ” <hi rend="i">Studies in
Eighteenth-Century Culture</hi>, 12 (1983), 115-30.</p>
            <p>*60. Hammacher, Abraham M. <hi rend="i">Phantoms of the Imagination: Fantasy in Art and
Literature from Blake to Dali.</hi> Trans. Tony Langham and Plym Peters. New York, N.Y.: Abrams, 1981.</p>
            <p>61. Heppner, Christopher. “The Woman Taken in Adultery: An Essay on Blake’s ‘Style of
Designing.’ ” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983), 44-60.</p>
            <p>*62. Hilton, Nelson. <hi rend="i">Literal Imagination: Blake’s Vision of Words.</hi>
Berkeley, Cal., Los Angeles, Cal. and London: University of California Press, 1983.</p>
            <p>63. Hogan, Joseph David. “Milton, Blake’s Orpheus: Theory of Poetry, Poetry as Theory.”
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 43 (1983), 3920A (University of Colorado at Boulder,
1982). [“William Blake’s Orphic epic, <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, presents a theory of poetry as a power to
shape the world. . . . Blake, endeavoring to write an epic, has to justify the authority of the epic to
pronounce on the world. <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, his prelude to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, presents this
justification. When Milton, like Orpheus, descends into the underworld and resumes his emanation, Ololon (his
Eurydice), he reclaims poetry from the false tongue and regenerates it as a vehicle for the visionary warfare
of Eden. Poetry becomes the vehicle for a theory of poetry and of the world.”]</p>
            <p>64. Howard, Seymour. “Blake, Classicism, Gothicism, and Nationalism.” In 
<hi rend="i">Transactions of the Sixth International Congress on the Enlightenment/Actes du Sixième Congrès
international des Lumières</hi>, Brussels, July 1983. Oxford: The Voltaire Foundation at the Taylor
Institution, 1983, p. 132. [A resumé of Howard’s conference paper.]</p>
            <p>65. Kelley, Theresa M. “A Minute Particular in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence</hi>, Copy O.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983), 18-19.</p>
            <p>*66. Kobayashi, Keiko. “Blake no Hohō: Job-ki Sashie no Hajime to Owari.” In his 
<hi rend="i">Yamakawa Kōzō Kyōju Taikan Kinen Ronbunshū.</hi> Toyonaka: n.p., 1981, pp. 232-48.</p>
            <p>67. Larrissy, Edward. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">America</hi>: An Early Version?” 
<hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>, NS 30 (1983), 217-19.</p>
            <p>*68. Larrissy, Edward. “A Description of Blake: Ideology, Form, Influence.” In 
<hi rend="i">1789: Reading, Writing, Revolution—Proceedings of the Essex Conference on the Sociology of
Literature, July 1981.</hi> Ed. Francis Barker, et al. Colchester: University of Essex, 1982, pp. 101-09.</p>
            <p>69. LeBris, Michel. “Blake oder das innere Jerusalem.” In his <hi rend="i">Die Romantik in
Wort und Bild.</hi> Trans. Elfie Riegler. Geneva: Editions d’Art Albert Skira; Stuttgart:
Verlagsgemeinschaft Ernst Klett-J.G. Cotta’sche Buchhandlung, 1981, pp. 63-69.</p>
            <p>*70. LeBris, Michel. <hi rend="i">Romantics and Romanticism.</hi> Trans. Barbara Bray and
Bernard C. Swift. New York, N.Y.: Rizzoli International, 1981. [Contains chapters on Blake, Fuseli, et
al.]</p>
            <p>71. Lee, Judith. “Ways of Their Own: The Emanations of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala, or The
Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">ELH: A Journal of English Literary History</hi>, 50 (1983), 131-53.</p>
            <p>72. Lee, Richard V. “The Generalist: A Jaundiced View. XXVI. A Message from Mister William
Blake.”
<pb id="p18-104" n="104"/>
	<hi rend="i">The American Journal of Medicine</hi>, 75 (1983), 902-04. [Dr. Lee, of the Department of
Medicine of Children’s Hospital of Buffalo, New York, begins by mentioning the great Blake exhibit—at New
Haven and Toronto—of 1982-83 but goes on to discuss Blake’s “message” in general.]</p>
            <p>73. Lincoln, Andrew. “Blake’s Lower Paradise: The Pastoral Passage in <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>, Night the Ninth.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi>, 84 (1981),
470-78.</p>
            <p>74. Lister, Raymond. “The National Gallery and Blake’s ‘Spiritual Form of Pitt Guiding
Behemoth.’ ” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983-1984), 105-06.</p>
            <p>75. Maheux, Anne. “An Analysis of the Watercolor Technique and Materials of William Blake.”
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1984), 124-29.</p>
            <p>76. Mayoux, Jean-Jacques. “William Blake, illuminé.” In his <hi rend="i">Vivants piliers
II: Sous de vastes portiques—études de littérature et d’art anglais.</hi> Paris: Les Lettres Nouvelles,
Maurice Nadeau &amp; Papyrus, 1981, pp. 59-71.</p>
            <p>*77. Middleton, Peter. “The Revolutionary Poetics of William Blake—Part I: The Critical
Tradition.” In <hi rend="i">1789: Reading, Writing, Revolution—Proceedings of the Essex Conference on the
Sociology of Literature, July 1981.</hi> Ed. Francis Barker, et al. Colchester: University of Essex, 1982, pp.
110-18.</p>
            <p>78. Middleton, Peter. “The Revolutionary Poetics of William Blake: Part II—Silence, Syntax,
and Spectres.” <hi rend="i">The Oxford Literary Review</hi>, 6 (1983), 35-51.</p>
            <p>79. Mitchell, W.J.T. “Metamorphoses of the Vortex: Hogarth, Turner, and Blake.” In 
<hi rend="i">Articulate Images: The Sister Arts from Hogarth to Tennyson.</hi> Ed. Richard Wendorf. Minneapolis,
Minn.: University of Minnesota Press, 1983, pp. 125-68. [This is Mitchell’s contribution to the Hagstrum 
<hi rend="i">festschrift.</hi>]</p>
            <p>*80. Mourão Ferreira, David. “Traduzindo William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Loreto</hi>, 13
(1979), 23-30. [On translating Blake’s poetry into Portuguese.]</p>
            <p>81. Munson, Rita. “Blake ‘Night.’ ” <hi rend="i">UNISA English Studies</hi>, 22 (1984),
7-13.</p>
            <p>82. Noble, Andrew. “Burns, Blake, and Romantic Revolt.” In <hi rend="i">The Art of Robert
Burns.</hi> Eds. Ronald D.S. Jack and Andrew Noble. Critical Studies Series. London: Vision Press; Totowa,
N.J.: Barnes and Noble, 1982, pp. 191-214.</p>
            <p>83. Ostrom, Hans Ansgar. “British Romantic Verse Satire.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation
Abstracts International</hi>, 44 (1983), 177A (University of California, Davis, 1982). [“ . . . I believe
that the achievements of Burns, Crabbe, Blake, Byron, and Shelley in satire demonstrate that the British
Romantics were as much a ‘revisionary company’ as they were a ‘visionary company’. . . . That is, to
envision new social, political, and imaginative orders, they often felt the need first to sweep away old
ones.” <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> are among the works
discussed.”]</p>
            <p>84. Ott, Judith. “Iris &amp; Morpheus: Investigating Visual Sources for 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 14.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1984), 149-54.</p>
            <p>85. Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">The Continuing City: William Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem.
Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1983.</p>
            <p>86. Paley, Morton D. “The Fourth Face of Man: Blake and Architecture.” In 
<hi rend="i">Articulate Images: The Sister Arts from Hogarth to Tennyson.</hi> Ed. Richard Wendorf. Minneapolis,
Minn.: University of Minnesota Press, 1983, pp. 184-215. [This is Paley’s contribution to the Hagstrum 
<hi rend="i">festschrift.</hi>]</p>
            <p>*87. Pauchard, Jean. “ ‘The Blossom’: Une visualisation.” In <hi rend="i">Visages de
l’harmonie dans la littérature angloaméricaine.</hi> Reims: Centre de Recherche sur l’Imaginaire dans
les Littératures de Langue Anglaise à l’Université de Reims, 1982, pp. 61-70.</p>
            <p>88. Paulson, Ronald. “Blake’s Bible.” In his <hi rend="i">Book and
Painting—Shakespeare, Milton and the Bible: Literary Texts and the Emergence of English Painting.</hi> The
Hodges Lectures, [3]. Knoxville, Tenn.: University of Tennessee Press, 1982, pp. 115-24.</p>
            <p>89. Paulson, Ronald. “Blake’s Lamb-Tiger.” In his <hi rend="i">Representations of
Revolution (1789-1820).</hi> New Haven, Conn. and London: Yale University Press, 1983, pp. 88-110.</p>
            <p>90. Paulson, Ronald. “Blake’s Revolutionary Tiger.” In <hi rend="i">Articulate Images:
The Sister Arts from Hogarth to Tennyson.</hi> Ed. Richard Wendorf. Minneapolis, Minn.: University of
Minnesota Press, 1983, pp. 169-83. [This is Paulson’s contribution to the Hagstrum 
<hi rend="i">festschrift.</hi>]</p>
            <p>91. Piquet, François. “ ‘Techniques infernales’: Blake e le Livre.” 
<hi rend="i">Romanticisme</hi>, no. 43 (1984), 5-18.</p>
            <p>*92. Piquet, François. “ ‘Un arbre empoisonné’ et la généalogie blakienne du
sacré.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin de la Société d’Etudes Anglo-Américaines des XVII<hi rend="s">e</hi> et
XVIII<hi rend="s">e</hi> Siècles</hi>, 14 (1982), 75-89.</p>
            <p>93. Punter, David. “Blake: Social Relations of Poetic Form.” <hi rend="i">Literature and
History</hi>, 8 (1982), 182-205.</p>
            <p>94. Ramalho de Sousa Santos, Maria Irene. “Blake no tempo: Introdução ao poeta com
traduções inéditas de Paulo Quintela.” <hi rend="i">Biblos: Revista de Faculdade de Letras</hi>, 57
(1981), 677-751. [Thirty pages of introductory materials are followed by forty pages with a bilingual
English-Portuguese “edition” of Blake’s poetry.]</p>
            <p>*95. Ravindran, S. “<hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> and Threefold Occult Vision.” 
<hi rend="i">Indian Journal of English Studies</hi>, NS 3 (1982-1983), 1-12.</p>
            <p>*96. Reisner, M.E. “William Blake and Westminster Abbey.” In <hi rend="i">Man and
Nature—Proceedings of the Canadian Society for Eighteenth-Century Studies/L’Homme et la nature—Actes de
la Société Canadienne d’études du Dixhuitième Siècle.</hi> Vol. 1. Eds. Roger L. Emerson, Gilles
<pb id="p18-105" n="105"/>
Girard, and Roseann Runte. London, Ont.: Faculty of Education at the University of Western Ontario, 1982, pp.
185-98.</p>
            <p>97. Richardson, Bruce Alan. “William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as History
Painting.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 44 (1983), 1462A (University of
California, Los Angeles, 1983). [“The difficult designs of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> can
be better understood than they are now if seen as a response to the practices and problems of English history
painters. Despite his angry opposition to Sir Joshua Reynolds, Blake supported history painting. . . . The
first three chapters study <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as a fulfillment of the art and experiences of John
Flaxman, Henry Fuseli, and George Romney. The last three essays examine antique sculpture, death scenes, and
the artist-hero as thematic and structural devices in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>”]</p>
            <p>*98. Singh, Gurbhagat. “Lacan, Lévi-Strauss and William Blake: A Note on <hi rend="i">The
Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Literary Criterion</hi>, 16 (1982), 56-65.</p>
            <p>99. Sosnowski, Terry Ford. “Music of an Angel’s Tongue: Meter and Prosodic Devices in the
Lyrics of William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 44 (1983), 494A (Case
Western Reserve University, 1983). [“The <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> show that Blake was equipped
with all the usual literary meters and had tried to extend them beyond their usual limits. Beginning with 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, the lyrics restore not only the beauty of the illuminated page but also the
form of ancient English poetry as Blake found it described by Bishop Percy in his <hi rend="i">Reliques of
Ancient English Poetry</hi> and as he found it surviving in the nursery rhymes, ballads, and hymns that
comprise much of English poetry in the folk tradition.]</p>
            <p>100. Spector, Sheila. “Kabbalistic Sources—Blake’s and His Critics’.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983-1984), 84-101.</p>
            <p>*101. Spittles, Brian. “Arkenholz Discovering Beulah: Strindberg’s Blakean Vision in 
<hi rend="i">Spöksonaten.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Scandinavica</hi>, 20 (1981), 145-70.</p>
            <p>*102. Steinberg, Robert E. “The Experiential and Theoretical Basis of Dante’s and Blake’s
Writings.” In <hi rend="i">Dante in the Twentieth Century.</hi> Ed. Adolph Caso. Dante Studies, 1. Boston,
Mass.: Dante University of America Press, 1982, pp. 25-43.</p>
            <p>103. Stemmler, Joan K. “Cennino, Cumberland, Blake and Early Painting Techniques.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1984), 145-49.</p>
            <p>104. Stock, R.D. “Religious Love and Fear in Late Eighteenth Century Poetry: Smart, Wesley,
Cowper, Blake.” In his <hi rend="i">The Holy and the Daemonic form Sir Thomas Browne to William Blake.</hi>
Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press, 1982, pp. 314-73.</p>
            <p>105. Syamken, Georg. “ ‘Human Form Divine.’ ” In <hi rend="i">Luther und die Folgen
für die Kunst.</hi> Exhb. cat. Ed. Werner Hofmann. Munich: Prestel-Verlag, for the Kunsthalle Hamburg, 1983,
pp. 402-13. [Discusses a number of works by Blake and Fuseli in the context of <corr type="emend">Lutheran</corr> and Calvinist
concepts of art.]</p>
            <p>106. Taylor, Dena. “A Note on William Blake and the Druids of Primrose Hill.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983-1984), 104-05.</p>
            <p>107. Thorpe, Douglas Joseph. “Metaphor as Building in <hi rend="i">Pearl</hi>, Herbert’s
<hi rend="i">Temple</hi>, and Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
International</hi>, 44 (1983), 1095A (University of Washington, 1983). [“In this study of three of
England’s greatest religious poets—the <hi rend="i">Pearl</hi>-Poet, Herbert, and Blake—I wish to show
how each grounds his own poetics in what I shall call a Biblical Poetics, which is a theory of metaphorical
language implicit in the Bible and more particularly in the parables of Jesus. Thus the central purpose of
this work is an analysis of metaphorical language in the particular context of the religious poem: what such
language is, and what it claims to do.”]</p>
            <p>108. Van Pelt, William Vern. “The Gates of Paradise: A Study of Images of Desire in the
Poetry and Illustrations of William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 44
(1984), 2776A-2777A (University of California, Santa Cruz, 1983). [“This dissertation examines the verbal
and visual imagery of Blake’s composite art, focusing on the two versions of <hi rend="i">The Gates of
Paradise</hi> entitled <hi rend="i">For Children</hi> (1793) and <hi rend="i">For the Sexes</hi> (1818). The
images in this work are treated as ‘images of desire’ not only because they invite the reader to enter
into a participatory and interpretive response to the work, ‘rouzing the faculties of act’ and entreating
us to ‘leave mortal things,’ but also because they tell the story of human desire from its inception in
the womb to its final release in the tomb.”]</p>
            <p>109. Warner, Nicholas O. “Blake’s ‘I Saw a Chapel All of Gold.’ ” 
<hi rend="i">Explicator</hi>, 41, No. 4 (1983), 24-26.</p>
            <p>*110. Warner, Nicholas O. “ ‘The Eye Altering Alters All’: Blake and Esthetic
Perception.” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi>, 19 (1983), 18-28.</p>
            <p>*111. Warner, Nicholas O. “The Iconic Mode of William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Rocky Mountain
Review of Language and Literature</hi>, 36 (1982), 219-34.</p>
            <p>112. Warner, Nicholas O. “Shaw, Tolstoy and Blake’s Russian Reputation.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983-1984), 102-04.</p>
            <p>113. Zeigelman, Lois. “Blake, the Druids, and the Regeneration of Generation.” 
<hi rend="i">University of Hartford Studies in Literature</hi>, 15 (1983), 13-32.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part II</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">Blake’s Circle</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">General Studies</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>114. Bennett, Shelley M. “The Blake Followers in the Context of Contemporary English Art.”
In <hi rend="i">Essays on</hi>
	<pb id="p18-106" n="106"/>
	<hi rend="i">the Blake Followers.</hi> Ed. Robert R. Wark. San Marino, Cal.: Henry E. Huntington Library and
Art Gallery, 1983, pp. 33-47. [Published simultaneously in the <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi>,
46 (1983), 33-47.]</p>
            <p>115. Wark, Robert R., ed. <hi rend="i">Essays on the Blake Followers.</hi> San Marino, Cal.:
Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery, 1983. [Also published as the first, i.e. Winter, issue of the 
<hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi>, 46 (1983). The essays presented here are all based on talks at a
symposium held at the Huntington on 13 February 1982.]</p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">James Barry</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>116. Masheck, J.D.C. “Irish Gothic Theory Before Pugin.” <hi rend="i">Studies: An Irish
Quarterly Review</hi>, 70 (1981), 206-19. [Discusses the role of Barry, Burke, and other Irishmen in the
rediscovery of the Gothic.]</p>
              <p>*117. Pressly, William L. “ ‘Antiochus and Stratonice’: A Copy after a Lost Painting by
James Barry.” <hi rend="i">Worcester Art Museum Journal</hi>, 4 (1980-1981), 12-27.</p>
              <p>*118. Pressly, William L. “ ‘Scientists and Philosophers’: A Rediscovered Print by
James Barry.” <hi rend="i">Royal Society of Arts Journal</hi>, 129 (1981), 510-15.</p>
              <p>119. Solkin, David H. “A Landscape Drawing by James Barry.” <hi rend="i">Master
Drawings</hi>, 21 (1983), 408-09.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Edward Calvert</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>See items 114, Bennett; 115, Wark; and 165, Cannon-Brookes.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">William Cowper</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>120. Dilworth, Thomas. “Cowper’s ‘Lines Written During a Period of Insanity.’ ” 
<hi rend="i">Explicator</hi>, 42 (1984), 8-10.</p>
              <p>*121. Hutchings, Bill. <hi rend="i">The Poetry of William Cowper.</hi> London and Beckenham,
Kent: Croom Helm, 1982.</p>
              <p>*122. King, James, and Charles Ryskamp, eds. <hi rend="i">The Letters and Prose Writings of
William Cowper.</hi> Vol. IV: “Letters, 1792-1799.” Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1984. [“This final volume
of letters charts Cowper’s friendship with the mercurial William Hayley, . . . ”]</p>
              <p>123. Newey, Vincent. <hi rend="i">Cowper’s Poetry: A Critical Study and Reassessment.</hi>
Liverpool English Texts and Studies, 20. Liverpool: Liverpool University Press; New York, N.Y.: Barnes and
Noble, 1982.</p>
              <p>124. Priestman, Martin. <hi rend="i">Cowper’s Task: Structure and Influence.</hi>
Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1983. £19.50.</p>
              <p>125. Trickett, Lionel. “Cowper, Wordsworth, and the Animal Fable.” <hi rend="i">Review of
English Studies</hi>, NS 34, (1983), 471-80.</p>
              <p>See also item 104, Stock.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Robert Hartley Cromek</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>126. Read, Dennis M. “Practicing ‘The Necessity of Purification’: Cromek, Roscoe, and
<hi rend="i">Reliques of Burns.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi>, 35 (1982), 306-19. [On
Cromek’s 1808 edition of Burns.]</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Erasmus Darwin</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>127. King-Hele, Desmond. “Shelley and Erasmus Darwin.” In <hi rend="i">Shelley Revalued:
Essays from the Gregynog Conference.</hi> Ed. Kelvin Everest. Leicester: Leicester University Press, 1983, pp.
129-46.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">John Flaxman</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>128. Archer, Mildred. “Neo-Classical Sculpture in India.” <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 120
(1984), 50-55. [Discusses some of Flaxman’s tomb sculptures at Madras, Tanjore; and Ghazipur.]</p>
              <p>129. Bentley, G.E., Jr. “Flaxman’s Drawings for <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s
Progress.</hi>” In <hi rend="i">Woman in the 18th Century and Other Essays.</hi> Ed. Paul Fritz and Richard
Morton. Toronto, Ont. and Sarasota, Fl.: Samuel Stevens/Hakkert, 1976, pp. 245-78.</p>
              <p>130. Bentley, G.E., Jr. “Flaxman’s ‘Sports of Genius’: ‘The Casket’ as an
Illustrated Poem.” <hi rend="i">Harvard Library Bulletin</hi>, 31 (1983), 256-84. [A discussion of
Flaxman’s illustrated poem of 1812, complete with a transcription of the text and a descriptive catalogue of
the wash drawings which are housed at the Houghton Library of Harvard University.]</p>
              <p>131. Berkowitz, Roger M. “The Patriotic Fund Vases: Regency Awards to the Navy.” 
<hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 113 (1981), 104-05. [A brief discussion of Flaxman’s designs for the Trafalgar
Vase.]</p>
              <p>132. Hunt, Leslie B. “The Mystery of the Galvanic Goblet.” <hi rend="i">Burlington
Magazine</hi>, 126 (1984), 347-48. [Executed by Paul Storr of Rundell, Bridge &amp; Rundell from a design by
Flaxman in 1814, the “Galvanic Goblet” represents an early example of the electroplating process.]</p>
              <p>*133. Irwin, David. “Sentiment and Antiquity: European Tombs 1750-1830.” In 
<hi rend="i">Mirrors of Mortality: Studies in the Social History of Death.</hi> Ed. Joachim Whaley. London: Europa
Publications, 1981.</p>
              <p>134. <corr type="emend">Poprzęcka</corr>, Maria. “Flaxman 1793—Picasso 1903.” In 
<hi rend="i">Tessera: sztuka jako przedmiot badań.</hi> Cracow: Muzeum Narodowe w Krakowie i Wydawnictwo
Literackie, 1981, pp. 206-14. [A comparison of Flaxman’s “Hector and Andromache” with Picasso’s “La
vie.”]</p>
              <p>*135. Symmons, Sarah. <hi rend="i">Flaxman and Europe: The Outline Illustrations and Their
Influence.</hi> Outstanding Theses from the Courtauld Institute of Art. New York, N.Y. and London: Garland
Publishing, 1984 [forthcoming].</p>
              <p>See also item 156, Gehren.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Henry Fuseli</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>136. Chayes, Irene H. “Between Reynolds and Blake: Eclecticism and Expression in Fuseli’s
Shakespeare
<pb id="p18-107" n="107"/>
Frescoes.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi>, 85 (1982), 140-68. [Discusses
Fuseli’s Roman wash drawings and their position in late 18th-century art; the frescoes which are envisioned
in these sketches were never executed, of course.]</p>
              <p>137. Halsband, Robert. “Fuseli and <hi rend="i">The Rape of the Lock</hi>,” and
“Fuseli’s Disciples.” In his The Rape of the Lock <hi rend="i">and Its Illustrations 1714-1896.</hi>
Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1980, pp. 44-67.</p>
              <p>138. Mayoux, Jean-Jacques. “La tentation de Füssli.” In his <hi rend="i">Vivants piliers
II: Sous de vastes portiques—études de littérature et d’art anglais.</hi> Paris: Les Lettres Nouvelles,
Maurice Nadeau &amp; Papyrus, 1981, pp. 111-38.</p>
              <p>*139. Meyenburg, B. von. “Von der Weibermacht zur femme fatale bei Johann Heinrich
Füssli.” <hi rend="i">Hafnia</hi>, 8 (1981), 7-33.</p>
              <p>*140. Michalski, Sergiusz. “Neomanierystczne zjawiska w malarstwie miedzy barokiem a
romantyzmem.” In <hi rend="i">Tradycja i innowacja: Materialy Sesji Stowarzyszenia Historykòw Sztuki.</hi>
Warsaw: PWN, 1981, pp. 127-45. [Michalski’s essay, based on a paper which he read at the 1979 Lòdź
Conference of the Polish Society of Art Historians, discusses neo-mannerist tendencies in the paintings of
Boucher, Creti, Giani, and Fuseli.]</p>
              <p>141. Paulson, Ronald. “Zoffany and Fuseli: The Miltonic Shakespeare.” In his 
<hi rend="i">Book and Painting—Shakespeare, Milton and the Bible: Literary Texts and the Emergence of English
Painting.</hi> The Hodges Lectures, [3]. Knoxville, Tenn.: University of Tennessee Press, 1982, pp.
124-37.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">William Hayley</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>See item 122, King and Ryskamp.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">John Linnell</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>See items 49, Essick; 114, Bennett; 115, Wark; and 165, Cannon-Brookes.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>142. Cecil, [Lord] David. <hi rend="i">Visionary and Dreamer, Two Poetic Painters: Samuel
Palmer and Edward Burne-Jones.</hi> 1969; rpt. London: Academy Editions, 1977. [A reprint of Lord Cecil’s
Mellon Lecture in the Fine Arts for 1966, which had originally been published in the Bollingen Series XXXV,
15; this entry has been verified for us by Morton D. Paley.]</p>
              <p>143. Paley, Morton D. “‘To Realize After a Sort the Imagery of Milton’: Samuel
Palmer’s Designs for <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso.</hi>” In 
<hi rend="i">Essays on the Blake Followers.</hi> Ed. Robert R. Wark. San Marino, Cal.: Henry E. Huntington Library
and Art Gallery, 1983, pp. 48-71. [Published simultaneously in the <hi rend="i">Huntington Library
Quarterly</hi>, 46 (1983), 48-71.]</p>
              <p>*144. Strudwick, R.F. <hi rend="i">A Catalogue of Samuel Palmer’s Etchings.</hi> n.p., n.d.
[London: privately printed for the author, 1982]. [This catalogue of twenty-five pages was printed in a
limited edition of only 50 copies.]</p>
              <p>See also items 74, Lister; and 165, Cannon-Brookes.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">George Richmond</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>145. Tscherny, Nadia. “George Richmond: Blake’s Strayed Sheep?” 
<hi rend="i">Marsyas</hi>, 21 (1981-1982), 37-45.</p>
              <p>See also items 74, Lister; 114, Bennett; and 115, Wark.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">George Romney</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>146. Allen, Brian. <hi rend="i">George Romney as a Painter of Children: The 250th Anniversary
of His Birth.</hi> Exhb. cat. London: Leger Galleries, 1984. $20.00.</p>
              <p>147. Burkett, M.E. “George Romney, Portrait Painter.” <hi rend="i">Antique
Collector</hi>, 55, No. 5 (May 1984), 72-77.</p>
              <p>148. Chan, Victor Chin-keung. “Pictorial Image and Social Reality: George Romney’s Late
Drawings of <hi rend="i">John Howard Visiting Prisoners.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
International</hi>, 44 (1983), 1095A (Stanford University, 1983). [“In portraying the drama of hope and
despair, of condemption and redemption, Romney’s prison drawings reveal the psychological crisis of a
Romantic artist’s longing for liberation of the spirit and express the agony of his struggle.”]</p>
              <p>149. [Powney, Christopher, and Edith Powney.] <hi rend="i">Drawings by George Romney.</hi>
Exhb. cat. London: Morton, Morris, and Company, 1980. [A fine selection of 81 of Romney’s sketches were on
view from 21 October to 7 November 1980, only. The exhibition, however, is documented in this illustrated
catalogue. Of particular interest for the Blake scholar is the sequence of six different versions of a design
for Romney’s projected painting of “The Fall of the Rebel Angels.”]</p>
              <p>150. Rogal, Samuel J. “George Romney’s Portrait of John Wesley.” 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Life</hi>, NS 5 (1978), 38-47.</p>
              <p>See also item 175, Pointon.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>151. Bennett, Shelley M. “Thomas Stothard’s Adaption to the Semi-Industrial Arts.” 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Life</hi>, NS 7 (1982), 19-30.</p>
              <p>152. Finlay, Nancy. “Thomas Stothard’s Illustrations for Parnell’s ‘Hermit.’ ”
<hi rend="i">The Princeton University Library Chronicle</hi>, 45 (1984), 174-77.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Thomas Taylor</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>*153. Taylor, Thomas, trans. <hi rend="i">The Works of Plato.</hi> 5 vols. 1804; rpt. Eds.
Burton Feldman and Robert D. Richardson, Jr. Myth and Romanticism, 24. New York, N.Y., and London: Garland
Publishing, 1984.</p>
              <p>154. Webb, Timothy, ed. <hi rend="i">English Romantic Hellenism, 1700-1824.</hi> Manchester:
Manchester University
<pb id="p18-108" n="108"/>
Press, 1982. [Includes selections from Thomas Taylor the Platonist, with Webb’s prefatory comments.]</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">John Varley</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>*155. Bury, Adrian. “Bi-Centenary of the Birth of John Varley (1778-1842).” 
<hi rend="i">Old Water-Colour Society’s Club</hi>, 53 (1978), 8-27.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Josiah Wedgwood</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>*156. Gehren, G. von. “Josiah Wedgwood und die Kunst seiner Zeit.” 
<hi rend="i">Weltkunst</hi>, 52 (1982), 2283-84. [Outlines Wedgwood’s collaboration with such artists as Flaxman
and Stubbs.]</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Edward Young</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>157. Forster, Harold. “The Marriage of Edward Young.” <hi rend="i">English Language
Notes</hi>, 21 (1983), 23-29.</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part III</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">Works of Related Interest</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>158. Aers, David, Jonathan Cook, and David Punter. <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Ideology: Studies
in English Writing 1765-1830.</hi> London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1981. $16.50.</p>
          <p>159. Bayard, Jane Hildreth. “From Drawing to Painting: The Exhibition Watercolor 1770-1870.”
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>, 44 (1983), 308A (Yale University, 1982). [“When
exhbitions began in England, watercolor was low in the hierarchy of art, a useful tool for engravers and a
cheap form of portraiture. But exhibitions brought watercolor directly to the public eye, and put it in
competition with oil painting. This resulted in a revolution of watercolorists’ aims and means: within a
generation watercolor grew from tinted drawing to an ambitious form of painting. . . .”]</p>
          <p>160. Beckson, Karl, ed. <hi rend="i">The Memoirs of Arthur Symons: Life and Art in the
1890s.</hi> University Park, Pa., and London: Pennsylvania State University Press, 1977. [See s.v. “Blake”
in the index.]</p>
          <p>161. Bogan, James. “Outside the Toronto Art Gallery.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983), 60. [A poem on the 1982-1983 Toronto Blake exhibition.]</p>
          <p>*162. Boulger, James D. <hi rend="i">The Calvinist Temper in English Poetry.</hi> The Hague:
Mouton, 1980.</p>
          <p>163. Brantley, Richard E. <hi rend="i">Locke, Wesley, and the Method of English Romanticism.</hi>
Gainesville, Fl.: University Presses of Florida, 1984. $35.00.</p>
          <p>164. Brogan, T.V.F. “Addenda and Corrigenda to <hi rend="i">English Versification,
1570-1980.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi>, 81 (1983), 50-52. [For a review of Brogan’s book see
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1982), 125-26.]</p>
          <p>165. [Cannon-Brookes, Peter, et al.] <hi rend="i">The British Neo-Romantics, 1935-1950.</hi>
Exhb. cat. London: Fischer Fine Art; Cardiff: National Museum of Wales, 1983. [A few works by Blake, Linnell,
Calvert, and Palmer (items 1-18) served to illustrate the roots of neo-romantic artists such as Ayrton,
Craxton, Jones, Piper, and Sutherland.]</p>
          <p>166. Cave, Kathryn, ed. <hi rend="i">The Diary of Joseph Farington.</hi> Vols. XI-XII (January
1811-December 1813). Studies in British Art. New Haven, Conn. and London: Yale University Press, for the Paul
Mellon Centre for Studies in British Art, 1983.</p>
          <p>167. Cook, Eleanor, Chaviva Hosek, Jay Macpherson, Patricia Parker, and Julian Patrick, eds. 
<hi rend="i">Centre and Labyrinth: Essays in Honour of Northrop Frye.</hi> Toronto: University of Toronto Press,
1983. $30.00.</p>
          <p>168. Dickinson, H.T., ed. <hi rend="i">The Political Works of Thomas Spence.</hi> Newcastle upon
Tyne: Avero Publications, 1982. £4.74.</p>
          <p>*169. Eichner-Dixon, Peter. <hi rend="i">Studien zum Verhältnis von Dichtung und Malerei im
englischen Neoklassizismus des 18. Jahrhunderts.</hi> Europäische Hochschulschriften/ European University
Papers, ser. 14, 93. Frankfurt am Main and Bern: Lang, 1981.</p>
          <p>170. Fine, Ruth E. <hi rend="i">Lessing J. Rosenwald: Tribute to a Collector.</hi> Exhb. cat.
Washington, D.C.: National Gallery of Art, 1982. [See s.v. “Blake” in the index of this beautifully
produced book for the numerous references to Rosenwald’s activities as a Blake collector as well as for the
catalogue entries for works by Blake and members of his circle which were included in the exhibition.]</p>
          <p>171. Fisch, Harold. “Job as Modern Archetype.” <hi rend="i">Hebrew University Studies in
Literature and the Arts</hi>, 11 (1983), 102-14.</p>
          <p>172. Gleckner, Robert F. “W.J. Linton, a Latter-Day Blake.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research
in the Humanities</hi>, 85 (1982), 208-27. [To most readers of this journal, William James Linton will be best
known as the engraver of the plates in Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of Blake</hi>, 1863 and 1880. Gleckner,
drawing on Francis B. Smith’s biography of the artist, shows that there is more to this casual
connection.]</p>
          <p>173. Goldyne, Joseph R. “British Art at San Francisco.” <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 111 (1980),
224-31. [For a brief discussion of Blake’s early “Complaint of Job” (Butlin 1981, no. 164), see
228-29.]</p>
          <p>174. Paulson, Ronald. <hi rend="i">Representations of Revolution (1789-1820).</hi> New Haven:
Yale University Press, 1983. $29.95.</p>
          <p>175. Pointon, Marcia. “Portrait-Painting as a Business Enterprise in London in the 1780s.”
<hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, 7 (1984), 187-205. [An extremely interesting account of the socio-economic
conditions under which painters such as Reynolds, Northcote, Romney, or Opie had to work when Blake was just
about to embark on his rather unsuccessful artistic career. Pointon’s article makes us appreciate Blake’s
decision for non-conformity even more than before.]</p>
          <pb id="p18-109" n="109"/>
          <p>176. Pressly, Nancy L. <hi rend="i">Revealed Religion: Benjamin West’s Commissions for Windsor
Castle and Fonthill Abbey.</hi> Exhb. cat. San Antonio, Tx.: San Antonio Museum of Art, 1983. $9.00.</p>
          <p>177. Purkis, John. <hi rend="i">The World of the English Poets. A Visual Approach.</hi> London:
Heinemann, 1982. £12.50.</p>
          <p>178. Sales, Roger. <hi rend="i">English Literature in History 1780-1830: Pastoral and
Politics.</hi> London: Hutchison, 1983. £5.95.</p>
          <p>179. Schweizer, Paul Douglas. “John Constable and the Rainbow.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation
Abstracts International</hi>, 44 (1984), 2611A (University of Delaware, 1979). [In discussing the Western
iconography of the rainbow, Schweizer examines instances of its portrayal by Blake, Flaxman, and Turner, among
others.]</p>
          <p>180. Stallworthy, Jon. “In Memory of Geoffrey Keynes, Kt. late of Lammas House, 1887-1982.”
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983), 61. [A lyrical obituary.]</p>
          <p>181. [Sutton, Denys.] “Editorial: ‘Conversing with Paradise.’ ” <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>,
112 (1980), 74-77. [On Sir Robert Laurence Binyon, 1869-1943.]</p>
          <p>182. Tolley, Michael J. “Additions to the Blake Apocrypha.” <hi rend="i">Blake/ An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1984), 25. [An amusing report from Adelaide, commenting on a performance of
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, a play written and directed by Grant Hehir.]</p>
          <p>*183. Wendorf, Richard, ed. <hi rend="i">Articulate Images: The Sister Arts
from Hogarth to Tennyson.</hi> Minneapolis, Minn.: University of Minnesota Press, 1983. [A collection of
essays on visual-verbal relationships which was presented as a <hi rend="i">festschrift</hi> to Jean H.
Hagstrum.]</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part IV</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">Reviews of Works Cited Above and in Previous Checklists</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>184. Aers, David, Jonathan Cook, and David Punter. <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Ideology: Studies
in English Writing 1765-1830.</hi> Reviewed by Theresa M. Kelley, <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 14
(1983), 127-29.</p>
          <p>185. Allen, Brian. <hi rend="i">George Romney as a Painter of Children.</hi> Reviewed by Patricia
Jaffé, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 119 (1984), 460.</p>
          <p>186. Andrews, Keith. <hi rend="i">Drawings from the Bequest of W.F. Watson, 1881-1981.</hi>
Briefly reviewed by [Anne-Marie S. Logan], <hi rend="i">Master Drawings</hi>, 21 (1983), 183.</p>
          <p>187. Baird, John D., and Charles Ryskamp, eds. <hi rend="i">The Poems of William Cowper, Vol.
I.</hi> Reviewed by Patricia Craddock, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi>, 80 (1983), 308-13; by Philip Drew,
<hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi>, 78 (1983), 905-06; and by Pierre Danchin, <hi rend="i">English
Studies</hi>, 64 (1983), 376-77.</p>
          <p>188. Bandy, Melanie. <hi rend="i">Mind Forg’d Manacles: Evil in the Poetry of Blake and
Shelley.</hi> Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 19 (1982), 1063-64; by William Keach, <hi rend="i">The
Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 13 (1982), 142-43; and by Joseph A. Wittreich, Jr., <hi rend="i">Modern
Philology</hi>, 80 (1983), 428-30.</p>
          <p>189. Beckson, Karl, ed. <hi rend="i">The Memoirs of Arthur Symons.</hi> Reviewed by John Stokes,
<hi rend="i">The Yearbook of English Studies</hi>, 10 (1980), 335-38.</p>
          <p>190. Bellin, Harvey, and Tom Kieffer, prods. <hi rend="i">Blake: The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi> [film]. The Swedenborg Foundation, 1982-1983. Reviewed by Maginel Galt, <hi rend="i">Logos: The
Swedenborg Foundation Newsletter</hi>, Summer 1983, pp. 1-3.</p>
          <p>191. Bentley, G.E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi> Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 14
(1977), 1021; by Michael Gassenmeier, <hi rend="i">Anglia</hi>, 102 (1984), 248-59.</p>
          <p>192. Bentley, G.E., Jr., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings.</hi> Reviewed by Michael
Gassenmeier, <hi rend="i">Anglia</hi>, 102 (1984), 248-59.</p>
          <p>193. Bertholf, Robert J., and Annette S. Levitt, eds. <hi rend="i">William Blake and the
Moderns.</hi> Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 20 (1983), 1143; by Stuart Peterfreund, 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and Present</hi>, 7, No. 2 (1983), 41-48; by Winston Weathers, <hi rend="i">James
Joyce Quarterly</hi>, 21 (1984), 192-93; by Paul Mann, <hi rend="i">Blake/ An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17
(1984), 169-72; and by George Bornstein, <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 14 (1983), 162-63.</p>
          <p>194. Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist.</hi> Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>,
14 (1978), 1632.</p>
          <p>195. Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">The Complete Graphic Works of William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by
Joseph A. Wittreich, Jr., <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A Current Bibliography</hi>, NS 4 (1978). Ed.
Robert R. Allen. New York, N.Y.: AMS Press, 1981, pp. 282-83.</p>
          <p>196. Bindman, David, ed. <hi rend="i">John Flaxman.</hi> Exhb. cat. Reviewed by Theodore Crombie,
<hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 110 (1979), 446.</p>
          <p>197. Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Art and Times.</hi> Exhb. cat. Reviewed in
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 20 (1983), 964; by William L. Pressly, <hi rend="i">Art Journal</hi>, 43 (1983),
77-80; by Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">Master Drawings</hi>, 21 (1983), 62-64; by *Carter
Ratcliff, <hi rend="i">Print Collector’s Newsletter</hi>, 13 (1982-1983), 209-11; by David Fuller, 
<hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 6 (1983), 207-08; and by Edward Larrissy, 
<hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, 6 (1983), 478-81.</p>
          <p>198. Boulger, James D. <hi rend="i">The Calvinist Temper in English Poetry.</hi> Reviewed by
Dennis M. Welch, <hi rend="i">Blake/ An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983-1984), 117-18.</p>
          <p>199. Brisman, Leslie. <hi rend="i">Romantic Origins.</hi> Reviewed by Daniel Hughes, 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 18 (1979), 316-22; by Stuart M. Tave, <hi rend="i">The Yearbook of
English Studies</hi>, 11 (1981), 290-93; by Joseph A. Wittreich, Jr., <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A
Current Bibliography</hi>, NS 5 (1979), eds. Paul J. Korshin and Robert R. Allen, New York, N.Y.: AMS Press,
1983, 258-60.</p>
          <p>200. Brown, David Blayney. <hi rend="i">Ashmolean Museum Oxford: Catalogue of the Collection of
Drawings.</hi> Vol. IV. Reviewed by Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 118 (1983),
<pb id="p18-110" n="110"/>
529-30.</p>
          <p>201. Brown, David Blayney. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer, 1805-1881.</hi> Exhb. cat. Reviewed by
John Gage, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, 6 (1983), 390-91.</p>
          <p>202. Butler, Marilyn. <hi rend="i">Romantics, Rebels and Reactionaries: English Literature and
Its Background 1760-1830.</hi> Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 19 (1982), 1555; by Michael Scrivener,
<hi rend="i">Criticism</hi>, 24 (1982), 286-90; by J.H. Haeger, <hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and
Present</hi>, 7, No. 1 (1983), 63-76; by Robert F. Gleckner, <hi rend="i">South Atlantic Quarterly</hi>, 82
(1983), 449-51; by Michael O’Neill, <hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 6
(1983), 205-07; by Christopher Clausen, <hi rend="i">Sewanee Review</hi>, 91 (1983), 672-80; by Frederick W.
Shilstone, <hi rend="i">Southern Humanities Review</hi>, 18 (1984), 178-80; by Karl Kroeber, <hi rend="i">The
Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 14 (1983), 126-27; by John Clubbe, <hi rend="i">The Byron Journal</hi>, 11 (1983),
64-65; and by Aileen Ward, <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi>, 32 (1983), 204-07.</p>
          <p>203. Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>, Reviewed in
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 19 (1981), 60; by *Eric Shanes, <hi rend="i">Turner Studies</hi>,
1 (1981), 45-47; by *Peter Quennell, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 115 (1982), 295; by Irene
Tayler, <hi rend="i">Art Journal</hi>, 42 (1982), 66-69; by *John Hayes, 
<hi rend="i">Journal of the Royal Society of Arts</hi>, 130 (1982), 594-95; by Jonathan Wordsworth, 
<hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi>, NS 35 (1984), 92-95.</p>
          <p>204. [Cannon-Brookes, Peter, et al.] <hi rend="i">The British Neo-Romantics, 1935-1950.</hi>
Exhb. cat. Reviewed by Richard Shone, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 125 (1983), 637-38; and by Martin
Butlin, <hi rend="i">Blake/ An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1984), 162-64.</p>
          <p>205. Cave, Kathryn, ed. <hi rend="i">The Diary of Joseph Farington.</hi> Vols. XI-XII. Reviewed
by Luke Herrmann, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 126 (1984), 240.</p>
          <p>206. Clarke, Michael, and Nicholas Penny, eds. <hi rend="i">The Arrogant Connoisseur: Richard
Payne Knight 1751-1824.</hi> Exhb. cat. Reviewed by Grevel Lindop, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 19 February 1982, p. 186; by John Gage, <hi rend="i">Burlington
Magazine</hi>, 124 (1982), 315-16; by Michael Rosenthal, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, 6 (1983), 242-46; by
[Anne-Marie S. Logan], <hi rend="i">Master Drawings</hi>, 21 (1983), 181-82.</p>
          <p>207. Crouan, Katharine. <hi rend="i">John Linnell: A Centennial Exhibition.</hi> Exhb. cat.
Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 20 (1983), 1276-77; by Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 118
(1983), 529-30.</p>
          <p>208. Damrosch, Leopold, Jr. <hi rend="i">Symbol and Truth in Blake’s Myth.</hi> Reviewed in 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 18 (1981), 1544; by Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 17
(1983), 64-69; by Henry Summerfield, <hi rend="i">Studies in Mystical Literature</hi>, 3 (1983), 75-79; by
Andrew Lincoln, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi>, NS 34 (1983), 345-46; by Edward Larrissy, 
<hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, 6 (1983), 478-81; by John Beer, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi>, 79
(1984), 425-30; and by Thomas R. Frosch, <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 13 (1983), 152-56.</p>
          <p>209. Davis, Michael. <hi rend="i">William Blake: A New Kind of Man.</hi> Reviewed in 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 14 (1977), 1211-12.</p>
          <p>210. Dickinson, H.T., ed. <hi rend="i">The Political Works of Thomas Spence.</hi> Reviewed by
G.E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake/ An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1984), 172-74.</p>
          <p>211. Doskow, Minna. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem: <hi rend="i">Structure and
Meaning in Poetry and Picture.</hi> Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 21 (1983), 92-94.</p>
          <p>212. Dunbar, Pamela. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Poetry of Milton.</hi>
Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 18 (1981), 931; by Joseph A. Wittreich, Jr., <hi rend="i">The Yearbook
of English Studies</hi>, 14 (1984), 329-31.</p>
          <p>213. Eaves, Morris. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Theory of Art.</hi> Reviewed by Edward
Larrissy, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, 6 (1983), 478-81; by Hazard Adams, <hi rend="i">Blake/ An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983-1984), 107-11; and by David Wagenknecht, <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 14
(1983), 157-59 [with a reply by Morris Eaves, 159-60].</p>
          <p>214. Einem, Herbert von. <hi rend="i">Deutsche Malerei des Klassizismus und der Romantik
1760-1840.</hi> Reviewed by Keith Andrews, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 112 (1980), 63-64.</p>
          <p>215. Engell, James. <hi rend="i">The Creative Imagination: Enlightenment to Romanticism.</hi>
Reviewed by Alex Page, <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 13 (1982), 150-51; and by Thomas McFarland,
<hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi>, 31 (1982), 198-202.</p>
          <p>216. Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi>
Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 20 (1982), 424.</p>
          <p>217. Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake.</hi> Reviewed in 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 21 (1983), 262-63; in the <hi rend="i">Gazette des Beaux-Arts</hi>, 6th ser., 102, No.
1378 (1983), “Chronique des Arts,” 19-20; by David Fuller, <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi>, NS
45, No. 1 (1983), 141-43.</p>
          <p>218. Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Printmaker.</hi> Reviewed in 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 18 (1980), 517; by *Robert H. Getscher, <hi rend="i">Arlis/NA
Newsletter</hi>, 9 (1981), 253-54; by Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 17 (1983),
64-69; and by Dennis M. Read, <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 13 (1982), 139-41.</p>
          <p>219. Essick, Robert N., and Donald Pearce, eds. <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time.</hi> Reviewed in
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 16 (1979), 516; by Robert F. Gleckner, <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A
Current Bibliography</hi>, NS 5 (1979), eds. Paul J. Korshin and Robert R. Allen, New York, N.Y.: AMS Press,
1983, pp. 349-52.</p>
          <p>220. Essick, Robert N., and Jenijoy LaBelle, eds. <hi rend="i">Flaxman’s Illustrations to
Homer.</hi> Reviewed by Janet Warner, <hi rend="i">Blake/ An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983), 24-25.</p>
          <p>221. Essick, Robert N., and Morton D. Paley, eds. <hi rend="i">Robert Blair’s</hi> The Grave:
<hi rend="i">Illustrated by William Blake.</hi> Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 20 (1982), 254; in the
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 125 (1983), 777.</p>
          <p>222. Fine, Ruth E. <hi rend="i">Lessing J. Rosenwald.</hi> Exhb.
<pb id="p18-111" n="111"/>
cat. Reviewed by [Anne-Marie S. Logan], <hi rend="i">Master Drawings</hi>, 21 (1983), 179-80.</p>
          <p>223. Frye, Northrop. <hi rend="i">The Great Code: The Bible and Literature.</hi> Reviewed by
Elizabeth Robertson, <hi rend="i">English</hi>, 31 (1982), 274-81; by Robert Alter, <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983), 20-22; by Richard Kearney, <hi rend="i">Studies: An Irish Quarterly
Review</hi>, 72 (1983), 190-92; by Paul H. Fry, <hi rend="i">Yale Review</hi>, 72 (1983), 605-12; see also
Louis Dudek, David L. Jeffrey, Emero Stiegman, and George Woodcock, “Northrop Frye and the Bible: A Review
Symposium,” <hi rend="i">University of Toronto Quarterly</hi>, 52 (1982-1983), 127-54; by Charles B.
Wheeler, “Professor Frye and the Bible,” <hi rend="i">South Atlantic Quarterly</hi>, 82 (1983), 154-64; by
A.D. Nuttall, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi>, 78 (1983), 882-83; by Joseph Gold, 
<hi rend="i">English Studies in Canada</hi>, 9 (1983), 487-98; and by Gweneth B. Schwab, <hi rend="i">Christianity
and Literature</hi>, 33 (1983), 87-89.</p>
          <p>224. Gallant, Christine. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Assimilation of Chaos.</hi> Reviewed in 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 16 (1979), 388; by *Leslie Tannenbaum, <hi rend="i">Computers and the Humanities</hi>
[US], 13 (1979), 200-02; by Mary Lynn Johnson, <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A Current
Bibliography</hi>, NS 5 (1979), eds. Paul J. Korshin and Robert R. Allen, New York, N.Y.: AMS Press, 1983, pp.
353-55.</p>
          <p>225. George, Diana Hume. <hi rend="i">Blake and Freud.</hi> Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>,
18 (1981), 723.</p>
          <p>226. Gizzi, Corrado. <hi rend="i">Blake e Dante.</hi> Exhb. cat. Reviewed by Martin Butlin, 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1984), 160-61.</p>
          <p>227. Givone, Sergio. <hi rend="i">William Blake: arte e religione.</hi> Reviewed by *L. Bottani,
<hi rend="i">Revista di Estetica</hi>, No. 5 (1980), 143-45.</p>
          <p>228. Glen, Heather. <hi rend="i">Vision and Disenchantment: Blake’s</hi> Songs <hi rend="i">and
Wordsworth’s</hi> Lyrical Ballads. Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 21 (1984), 821; by Susan Matthews,
<hi rend="i">English</hi>, 33 (1984), 66-71; and by Chris Baldrick, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 19 August 1983, p. 884.</p>
          <p>229. Grant, John E., and Mary Lynn Johnson, eds. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Poetry and Designs.</hi>
Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 17 (1980), 536.</p>
          <p>230. Grant, John E., Edward J. Rose, and Michael J. Tolley, eds. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Designs for Edward Young’s</hi> Night Thoughts: <hi rend="i">A Complete Edition.</hi> Reviewed in 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 18 (1981), 932.</p>
          <p>231. Grubb, Davis. <hi rend="i">Ancient Lights.</hi> Reviewed by Nelson Hilton, 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983), 30-31.</p>
          <p>232. Hagstrum, Jean. <hi rend="i">Sex and Sensibility.</hi> Reviewed by Dimiter Daphinoff, 
<hi rend="i">English Studies</hi>, 64 (1983), 279-81.</p>
          <p>233. Hammacher, Abraham M. <hi rend="i">Phantoms of the Imagination: Fantasy in Art and
Literature from Blake to Dali.</hi> Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 19 (1982), 1057.</p>
          <p>234. Harvey, A.D. <hi rend="i">English Poetry in a Changing Society, 1780-1825.</hi> Reviewed by
E.B. Murray, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi>, 35 (1984), 96-98.</p>
          <p>235. Haskell, Francis, and Nicholas Penny. <hi rend="i">Taste and the Antique.</hi> Reviewed in
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 19 (1981), 366.</p>
          <p>236. Hayes, Elliott. <hi rend="i">Blake: Innocence and Experience</hi> [a play]. Reviewed by V.A.
DeLuca, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1984), 161-62.</p>
          <p>237. Hodnett, Edward. <hi rend="i">Image and Text: Studies in the Illustration of English
Literature.</hi> Reviewed by Anthony Payne, <hi rend="i">Art Book Review</hi>, (2), No. 5 (1983), 17; by
Richard Maxwell, <hi rend="i">Victorian Studies</hi>, 27 (1983-1984), 281-82; by Nicholas Pickwoad, 
<hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi>, NS 35 (1984), 272-75.</p>
          <p>238. Honour, Hugh. <hi rend="i">Romanticism.</hi> Reviewed by Graham Reynolds, 
<hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 112 (1980), 286-87.</p>
          <p>239. Hurlebusch, Klaus, ed. <hi rend="i">Friedrich Gottlieb Klopstock: Epigramme. Text und
Apparat.</hi> Reviewed by P.M. Mitchell, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi>, 82
(1983), 417-18.</p>
          <p>240. Hutchings, Bill. <hi rend="i">The Poetry of William Cowper.</hi> Reviewed in 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 20 (1983), 1454-55.</p>
          <p>241. Irwin, David. <hi rend="i">John Flaxman 1755-1826: Sculptor, Illustrator, Designer.</hi>
Reviewed by Thomas J. McCormick, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 16 (1983), 468.</p>
          <p>242. Jackson, J.R. de J. <hi rend="i">Poetry of the Romantic Period.</hi> Reviewed by Michael G.
Cooke, <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi>, 31 (1982), 206-07.</p>
          <p>243. Keynes, Geoffrey L. <hi rend="i">The Gates of Memory.</hi> Reviewed by B.C. Bloomfield, 
<hi rend="i">Papers of the Bibliographical Society of America</hi>, 77 (1983), 512-14 [includes a list of
obituaries]; by George S. Rousseau, <hi rend="i">South Atlantic Quarterly</hi>, 83 (1984), 114-17.</p>
          <p>244. Keynes, Geoffrey L., ed. <hi rend="i">The Letters of William Blake.</hi> 3rd rev. ed.
Reviewed by Mary Ellman, <hi rend="i">Sewanee Review</hi>, 91 (1983), 120-28; by John Beer, 
<hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi>, 79 (1984), 425-30.</p>
          <p>245. Keynes, Geoffrey L., and Peter Davidson, eds. <hi rend="i">A Watch of Nightingales.</hi>
Reviewed by G.E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983), 32-35.</p>
          <p>246. King, James, and Charles Ryskamp, eds. <hi rend="i">The Letters and Prose Writings of
William Cowper.</hi> Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 19 (1981), 504 [Vol. II]; by Donald H. Reiman, 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983), 26-29 [Vol. II]; by Vincent Newey, <hi rend="i">Prose
Studies</hi>, 6 (1983), 76-77 [Vol. II]; by John H. Pittock, <hi rend="i">British Journal for
Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 6 (1983), 208-11 [Vols. I-II]; in <hi rend="i">Prose Studies</hi>, 6 (1983),
310 [Vol. III]; by Pierre Danchin, <hi rend="i">English Studies</hi>, 65 (1984), 80-82 [Vol. II]; and by
Patricia Craddock, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi>, 80 (1983), 308-13 [Vol. II].</p>
          <p>247. King-Hele, Desmond, ed. <hi rend="i">The Letters of Erasmus Darwin.</hi> Reviewed by
*Michael Scott, <hi rend="i">Daily Telegraph</hi>, 12 November 1981; by *Francis Huxley, <hi rend="i">The
Guardian</hi>, 26 November 1981; by Richard Fifield, <hi rend="i">New Scientist</hi>, 10 December 1981; by
Walter Tyson, <hi rend="i">Oxford</hi>
	<pb id="p18-112" n="112"/>
	<hi rend="i">Times</hi>, 18 December 1981; by Roy Porter, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times
Higher Education Supplement</hi>, 22 January 1982; by John Cule, <hi rend="i">Pharmaceutical Journal</hi>, 24
April 1982; by Gavin Bridson, <hi rend="i">Nature</hi>, 296 (29 April 1982), 873; by Alex Paton, 
<hi rend="i">British Medical Journal</hi>, 284 (1 May 1982), 1319-20; by Robert J. Richards, 
<hi rend="i">Science</hi>, 216 (4 June 1982), 1101-02; by Trevor I. Williams, <hi rend="i">Endeavour</hi>, June
1982; by N.W. Pririe, <hi rend="i">The Biologist</hi>, 29 (1982); by W.A. Smeaton, <hi rend="i">Ambix</hi>, 29
(1982), 115-16; by Sir Charles Fleming, <hi rend="i">Interdisciplinary Science Review</hi>, 7 (1982), 325; by
Ralph Colp, Jr., <hi rend="i">Bulletin of the New Academy of Medicine</hi>, 58 (1982), 341-44; by Donald M.
Hassler, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 13 (1982), 137-38; by *Maureen McNeil, <hi rend="i">British
Journal of the History of Science</hi>, March 1983; by Pat Rodgers, <hi rend="i">British Journal for
Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 6 (1983), 80-81; by Richard W. Burkhardt, Jr., <hi rend="i">Isis</hi>, 74
(1983), 616-17.</p>
          <p>248. Klonsky, Milton. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Dante.</hi> Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 18
(1981), 1094.</p>
          <p>249. Klonsky, Milton. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Seer and His Visions.</hi> Reviewed in 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 15 (1978), 58.</p>
          <p>250. Kroeber, Karl, and William Walling, eds. <hi rend="i">Images of Romanticism: Verbal and
Visual Affinities.</hi> Reviewed by Stuart M. Tave, <hi rend="i">The Yearbook of English Studies</hi>, 11
(1981), 290-93.</p>
          <p>251. Leader, Zachary. <hi rend="i">Reading Blake’s</hi> Songs. Reviewed by Nelson Hilton, 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 17 (1983), 64-69; by Hazard Adams, <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi>, 22 (1983), 458-62; by John Beer, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi>, 79 (1984),
425-30; and by Jeffrey C. Robinson, <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 14 (1983), 160-61.</p>
          <p>252. LeBris, Michel. <hi rend="i">Romantics and Romanticism.</hi> Reviewed in 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 19 (1981), 227; by Dennis M. Read, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17
(1983-1984), 114-16.</p>
          <p>253. Lindsay, Jack. <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Life and Work.</hi> Reviewed by Horst Höhne,
<hi rend="i">Deutsche Literaturzeitung für Kritik der internationalen Wissenschaft</hi>, 102 (1981), cols.
575-78; by Wallace Jackson, <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A Current Bibliography</hi>, NS 5 (1979).
Eds. Paul J. Korshin and Robert R. Allen. New York, N.Y.: AMS Press, 1983, pp. 356-58.</p>
          <p>254. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">George Richmond: A Critical Biography.</hi> Reviewed by
Shelley M. Bennett, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983), 22-24; by David Brown, 
<hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, 6 (1983), 485-88.</p>
          <p>255. Lister, Raymond, ed. <hi rend="i">The Letters of Samuel Palmer.</hi> Reviewed by Katharine
Crouan, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 118 (1976), 528.</p>
          <p>256. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer: A Biography.</hi> Reviewed by Katharine Crouan,
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 118 (1976), 528.</p>
          <p>257. Lister, Raymond, et al. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer: A Vision Recaptured.</hi> Reviewed by
Luke Herrmann, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>, 121 (1979), 54-57.</p>
          <p>258. Mellor, Anne K. <hi rend="i">English Romantic Irony.</hi> Reviewed by Peter L. Thorslev,
Jr., <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi>, 31 (1982), 202-04.</p>
          <p>259. Mitchell, W.J.T. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art.</hi> Reviewed in 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 15 (1978), 848-49; by Leslie Tannenbaum, <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A Current
Bibliography</hi>, NS 5 (1979), eds. Paul J. Korshin and Robert R. Allen, New York, N.Y.: AMS Press, 1983,
358-60.</p>
          <p>260. Newey, Vincent. <hi rend="i">Cowper’s Poetry: A Critical Study and Reassessment.</hi>
Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 20 (1983), 986; by Peter Faulkner, <hi rend="i">Durham University
Journal</hi>, NS 45, No. 1 (1983), 141; and by Grevel Lindop, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, 2 December 1983, p. 1352.</p>
          <p>261. Nurmi, Martin K. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 14
(1977), 377.</p>
          <p>262. Paananen, Victor N. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>,
14 (1977), 683.</p>
          <p>263. Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 15
(1978), 852-53; by *Susan Hoyal, <hi rend="i">Connoisseur</hi>, 198 (1978), 330.</p>
          <p>264. Paulson, Ronald. <hi rend="i">Book and Painting: Shakespeare, Milton, and the Bible.</hi>
Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 21 (1983), 80; by Estella Schoenberg, <hi rend="i">Milton
Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983), 51-52.</p>
          <p>265. Paulson, Ronald. <hi rend="i">Literary Landscape: Turner and Constable.</hi> Reviewed by
Anne K. Mellor, <hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and Present</hi>, 8 (1984), 51-55; and by Carole Fabricant, 
<hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 14 (1983), 130-33.</p>
          <p>266. Paulson, Ronald. <hi rend="i">Representations of Revolution (1789-1820).</hi> Reviewed by
Richard King, <hi rend="i">Kenyon Review</hi>, NS 5, No. 4 (1983), 128-31; by John Barrell, <hi rend="i">Art
History</hi>, 7 (1984), 120-24; by Regenia Gagnier, <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi>, 26 (1984), 201-03.</p>
          <p>267. Phillips, Michael C., ed. <hi rend="i">Interpreting Blake.</hi> Reviewed by Stan Smith, 
<hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi>, 6 (1980), 267-69; by Neil Fraistat, <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century:
A Current Bibliography</hi>, NS 5 (1979), eds. Paul J. Korshin and Robert R. Allen, New York, N.Y.: AMS Press,
1983, 360-62.</p>
          <p>268. [Powney, Christopher, and Edith Powney.] <hi rend="i">Drawings by George Romney.</hi> Exhb.
cat. Briefly reviewed in <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 112 (1980), 283.</p>
          <p>269. Pressly, Nancy L. <hi rend="i">The Fuseli Circle in Rome.</hi> Exhb. cat. Reviewed in 
<hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 110 (1979), 518.</p>
          <p>270. Pressly, William L. <hi rend="i">James Barry: The Artist as Hero.</hi> Exhb. cat. Reviewed
by Anna Ottani Cavina, <hi rend="i">Paragone</hi>, 34, No. 397 (1983), 65-72.</p>
          <p>271. Pressly, William L. <hi rend="i">The Life and Art of James Barry.</hi> Reviewed in 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 19 (1981), 499; by Anna Ottani Cavina, <hi rend="i">Paragone</hi>, 34, No. 397 (1983),
65-72; by Shelley M. Bennett, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983), 22-24; and by David
Brown, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, 6 (1983), 485-88.</p>
          <p>272. Priestman, Martin. <hi rend="i">Cowper’s Task: Structure</hi>
	<pb id="p18-113" n="113"/>
	<hi rend="i">and Influence.</hi> Reviewed by Grevel Lindop, <hi rend="i">The</hi> [London] <hi rend="i">Times
Literary Supplement</hi>, 2 December 1983, p. 1352; and in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 21 (1984), 823.</p>
          <p>273. Punter, David. <hi rend="i">Blake, Hegel and Dialectic.</hi> Reviewed by Nelson Hilton, 
<hi rend="i">Blake/ An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1984), 164-69; by François Piquet, <hi rend="i">études
Anglaises</hi>, 37 (1984), 208-09.</p>
          <p>274. Purkis, John. <hi rend="i">The World of the English Poets. A Visual Approach.</hi> Reviewed
by John Clubbe, <hi rend="i">The Byron Journal</hi>, 11 (1983), 66-67.</p>
          <p>275. Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">Blake and the New Age.</hi> Reviewed in 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 17 (1980), 674.</p>
          <p>276. Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">The Human Face of God: William Blake and the Book of Job.</hi>
Reviewed by *Raymond Lister, <hi rend="i">Journal of the Royal Society of Arts</hi>, 130 (1982), 595-96; by
David Fuller, <hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi>, 6 (1983), 76-79.</p>
          <p>277. Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">The Inner Journey of the Poet.</hi> Reviewed by Elizabeth
Bartlett, <hi rend="i">Dalhousie Review</hi>, 62 (1982), 524-26.</p>
          <p>278. Scholz, Joachim J. <hi rend="i">Blake and Novalis: A Comparison of Romanticism’s High
Arguments.</hi> Reviewed by Detlef W. Dörrbecker, <hi rend="i">Blake/ An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17
(1983-1984), 111-14.</p>
          <p>279. Starobinski, Jean. <hi rend="i">1789: Die Embleme der Vernunft.</hi> Reviewed by Bernd
Growe, <hi rend="i">Pantheon</hi>, 42 (1984), 101-02.</p>
          <p>280. Stevenson, Warren. <hi rend="i">The Myth of the Golden Age in English Romantic Poetry.</hi>
Reviewed by V.A. DeLuca, <hi rend="i">Blake/ An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983), 32.</p>
          <p>281. Stock, R.D. <hi rend="i">The Holy and the Daemonic from Sir Thomas Browne to William
Blake.</hi> Reviewed by *John M. Aden, <hi rend="i">Sewanee Review</hi>, 91 (1983), liv; by Anya Taylor, 
<hi rend="i">Criticism</hi>, 35 (1983), 75-79; by J.M. Armistead, <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi>, NS
45, No. 1 (1983), 131-34; and by Lionel Basney, <hi rend="i">Christianity and Literature</hi>, 33 (1984),
53-55.</p>
          <p>282. Tannenbaum, Leslie. <hi rend="i">Biblical Tradition in Blake’s Early Prophecies.</hi>
Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 19 (1982), 1562.</p>
          <p>283. Vaughan, William. <hi rend="i">German Romanticism and English Art.</hi> Reviewed by Keith
Andrews, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 112 (1980), 63-64; by Deborah Cherry, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, 4
(1981), 335-39.</p>
          <p>284. Webb, Timothy, ed. <hi rend="i">English Romantic Hellenism, 1700-1824.</hi> Reviewed by
Philip Wheatley, <hi rend="i">English</hi>, 32 (1983), 176-87.</p>
          <p>285. Wilkie, Brian, and Mary Lynn Johnson. <hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi> Four Zoas: 
<hi rend="i">The Design of a Dream.</hi> Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>, 15 (1978), 1056.</p>
          <p>286. Willard, Nancy. <hi rend="i">A Visit to William Blake’s Inn: Poems for Innocent and
Experienced Travelers.</hi> Reviewed by Elizabeth B. Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake/ An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi>, 17 (1983), 35-37.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Index of Authors</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Ackland, Michael 22</p>
          <p>Adams, Hazard 23, 24, 213, 251</p>
          <p>Aden, John M. 281</p>
          <p>Aers, David 158, 184</p>
          <p>Allen, Brian 146, 185</p>
          <p>Allen, Robert R. 7, 15, 195, 199, 219, 224, 253, 259, 267</p>
          <p>Alter, Robert 223</p>
          <p>Anderson, Mark Ransom 25</p>
          <p>Andrews, Keith 186, 214, 283</p>
          <p>Archer, Mildred 128</p>
          <p>Armistead, J.M. 281</p>
          <p>Avens, Roberts 26</p>
          <p>Baird, John D. 187</p>
          <p>Baldrick, Chris 228</p>
          <p>Bandy, Melanie 188</p>
          <p>Barilli, Renato 51, 53</p>
          <p>Barker, Francis 68, 77</p>
          <p>Barrell, John 266</p>
          <p>Bartlett, Elizabeth 277</p>
          <p>Basney, Lionel 281</p>
          <p>Bayard, Jane Hildreth 159</p>
          <p>Beckson, Karl 160, 189</p>
          <p>Beer, John 208, 244, 251</p>
          <p>Behrendt, Stephen C. 27</p>
          <p>Bellin, Harvey 190</p>
          <p>Bellonzi, Fortunato 53</p>
          <p>Bender, John 28</p>
          <p>Bennett, James R. 8</p>
          <p>Bennett, Shelley M. 114, 151, 254, 271</p>
          <p>Bentley, Elizabeth B. 286</p>
          <p>Bentley, G.E., Jr. 9, 29, 30, 129, 130, 191, 192, 210, 245</p>
          <p>Berkowitz, Roger M. 131</p>
          <p>Bertholf, Robert J. 193</p>
          <p>Bidney, Martin 31</p>
          <p>Bindman, David 194, 195, 196, 197</p>
          <p>Birenbaum, Harvey 32</p>
          <p>Bloomfield, B.C. 243</p>
          <p>Bogan, James 161</p>
          <p>Bornstein, George 193</p>
          <p>Bottani, L. 227</p>
          <p>Boulger, James D. 162, 198</p>
          <p>Brantley, Richard E. 163</p>
          <p>Bray, Barbara 70</p>
          <p>Bridson, Gavin 247</p>
          <p>Brinkley, Robert A. 33</p>
          <p>Brisman, Leslie 34, 199</p>
          <p>Brogan, T.V.F. 164</p>
          <p>Brown, David 254, 271</p>
          <p>Brown, David Blayney 200, 201</p>
          <p>Burkett, M.E. 147</p>
          <p>Burkhardt, Richard W., Jr. 247</p>
          <p>Burns, Bryan 18</p>
          <p>Bury, Adrian 155</p>
          <p>Butler, Marilyn 202</p>
          <p>Butlin, Martin 10, 53, 197, 203, 204, 226</p>
          <p>Cannon-Brookes, Peter 165, 204</p>
          <p>Caso, Adolph 102</p>
          <p>Cave, Kathryn 166, 205</p>
          <p>Cavina, Anna Ottani 270, 271</p>
          <p>Cecil, David 142</p>
          <p>Chan, Victor Chinkeung 148</p>
          <p>Chayes, Irene H. 136</p>
          <p>Cherry, Deborah 283</p>
          <p>Christensen, Bryce J. 35</p>
          <p>Clarke, Michael 206</p>
          <p>Clausen, Christopher 202</p>
          <p>Clubbe, John 202, 274</p>
          <p>Colaiacomo, Paola 51</p>
          <p>Colp, Ralph, Jr. 247</p>
          <p>Cook, Eleanor 167</p>
          <p>Cook, Jonathan 158, 184</p>
          <p>Cooke, Michael G. 242</p>
          <p>Cope, Kevin Lee 36</p>
          <p>Copland, James Alexander 37</p>
          <p>Corti, Claudia 38, 51, 53</p>
          <p>Craddock, Patricia 187, 246</p>
          <p>Crehan, Stewart 39</p>
          <p>Crombie, Theodore 196</p>
          <p>Crouan, Katherine 207, 255, 256</p>
          <p>Cule, John 247</p>
          <p>Damon, S. Foster 40</p>
          <p>Damrosch, Leopold, Jr. 208</p>
          <p>Danchin, Pierre 187, 246</p>
          <p>Daphinoff, Dimiter 232</p>
          <p>Davidson, Peter 6, 245</p>
          <p>Davies, J.M.Q. 41</p>
          <p>Davis, Michael 209</p>
          <p>DeLuca, V.A. 42, 236, 280</p>
          <p>Dickinson, H.T. 168, 210</p>
          <p>Dilworth, Thomas 43, 120</p>
          <p>DiSalvo, Jackie 44</p>
          <p>Dodd, Philip 18</p>
          <p>Dole, George F. 26</p>
          <p>Dörrbecker, Detlef W. 16, 278</p>
          <p>Doskow, Minna 45, 211</p>
          <p>D’Ottavi, Stefania 51</p>
          <p>Douglas-Drinkwater, Susan 13</p>
          <p>Dowdey, Landon 3</p>
          <p>Drew, Philip 187</p>
          <p>Dudek, Louis 223</p>
          <p>Duffy, H. 46</p>
          <pb id="p18-114" n="114"/>
          <p>Dunbar, Pamela 5, 212</p>
          <p>Eaves, Morris 213</p>
          <p>Eichner-Dixon, Peter 169</p>
          <p>Einem, Herbert von 214</p>
          <p>Ellis, Helen B. 47</p>
          <p>Ellman, Mary 244</p>
          <p>Emerson, Roger L. 96</p>
          <p>Engell, James 215</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V. 48, 216</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N. 11, 49, 50, 217, 218, 219, 220, 221</p>
          <p>Everest, Kelvin 127</p>
          <p>Fabian, Bernhard 12</p>
          <p>Fabricant, Carole 265</p>
          <p>Faulkner, Peter 260</p>
          <p>Feldman, Burton 5, 153</p>
          <p>Fifield, Richard 247</p>
          <p>Fine, Ruth E. 170, 222</p>
          <p>Finizio, Luigi Paolo 53</p>
          <p>Finlay, Nancy 152</p>
          <p>Fisch, Harold 171</p>
          <p>Fleming, Charles 247</p>
          <p>Forster, Harold 157</p>
          <p>Fortunati, Vita 51</p>
          <p>Franci, Giovanna 51</p>
          <p>Fraistat, Neil 267</p>
          <p>Fritz, Paul 129</p>
          <p>Frosch, Thomas R. 208</p>
          <p>Fry, Paul H. 223</p>
          <p>Frye, Northrop 223</p>
          <p>Fuller, David 197, 217, 276</p>
          <p>Gage, John 201, 206</p>
          <p>Gagnier, Regenia 266</p>
          <p>Gallant, Christine 224</p>
          <p>Galt, Maginel 190</p>
          <p>Gassenmeier, Michael 191, 192</p>
          <p>Gehren, G. von 156</p>
          <p>George, Diana Hume 225</p>
          <p>Getscher, Robert H. 218</p>
          <p>Gillespie, Diane Filby 52</p>
          <p>Girard, Gilles 96</p>
          <p>Givone, Sergio 51, 227</p>
          <p>Gizzi, Corrado 53, 226</p>
          <p>Gleckner, Robert F. 172, 202, 219</p>
          <p>Glen, Heather 54, 228</p>
          <p>Gold, Joseph 223</p>
          <p>Goldyne, Joseph R. 173</p>
          <p>Gourlay, Alexander S. 55, 56</p>
          <p>Grant, John E. 229, 230</p>
          <p>Grčić, Marko 57</p>
          <p>Greco, Norma A. 58</p>
          <p>Greenberg, Mark L. 59</p>
          <p>de Groot, H.B. 13</p>
          <p>Growe, Bernd 279</p>
          <p>Grubb, Davis 231</p>
          <p>Hagstrum, Jean 232</p>
          <p>Halsband, Robert 137</p>
          <p>Haeger, J.H. 202</p>
          <p>Hammacher, Abraham M. 60, 233</p>
          <p>Harvey, A.D. 234</p>
          <p>Haskell, Francis 235</p>
          <p>Hassler, Donald M. 247</p>
          <p>Hayes, Elliott 236</p>
          <p>Hayes, John 203</p>
          <p>Heppner, Christopher 61</p>
          <p>Herrmann, Luke 205, 257</p>
          <p>Hilton, Nelson 62, 208, 218, 231, 251, 273</p>
          <p>Hodnett, Edward 237</p>
          <p>Hoff, Ursula 53</p>
          <p>Hofmann, Werner 105</p>
          <p>Hogan, Joseph David 63</p>
          <p>Höhne, Horst 253</p>
          <p>Honour, Hugh 238</p>
          <p>Hosek, Chaviva 167</p>
          <p>Hoval, Susan 263</p>
          <p>Howard, Seymour 64</p>
          <p>Hughes, Daniel 199</p>
          <p>Hunt, Leslie B. 132</p>
          <p>Hurlebusch, Klaus 239</p>
          <p>Hutchings, Bill 121, 240</p>
          <p>Huxley, Francis 247</p>
          <p>Irwin, David 133, 241</p>
          <p>Jack, Ronald D.S. 82</p>
          <p>Jackson, J.R. DeJ. 242</p>
          <p>Jackson, Wallace 253</p>
          <p>Jaffé, Patricia 185</p>
          <p>Jakobson, Roman 51</p>
          <p>James, G. Ingli 1</p>
          <p>Jeffrey, David L. 223</p>
          <p>Jing-yu, Gu 14</p>
          <p>Johnson, Mary Lynn 224, 229, 285</p>
          <p>Keach, William 188</p>
          <p>Kearney, Richard 223</p>
          <p>Kelley, Theresa M. 65, 184</p>
          <p>Keynes, Geoffrey L. 6, 243, 244, 245</p>
          <p>Kieffer, Tom 190</p>
          <p>King, James 122, 246</p>
          <p>King, Richard 266</p>
          <p>King-Hele, Desmond 127, 247</p>
          <p>Klonsky, Milton 248, 249</p>
          <p>Kobayashi, Keiko 66</p>
          <p>Korshin, Paul J. 15, 199, 219, 224, 253, 259, 267</p>
          <p>Kroeber, Karl 202, 250</p>
          <p>LaBelle, Jenijoy 220</p>
          <p>Langham, Tony 60</p>
          <p>Larrissy, Edward 67, 68, 197, 208, 213</p>
          <p>Leader, Zachary 251</p>
          <p>LeBris, Michel 69, 70, 252</p>
          <p>Lee, Judith 71</p>
          <p>Lee, Richard V. 72</p>
          <p>Levitt, Annette S. 193</p>
          <p>Lincoln, Andrew 73, 208</p>
          <p>Lindop, Grevel 206, 260, 272</p>
          <p>Lindsay, Jack 253</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond 74, 254, 255, 256, 257, 276</p>
          <p>Logan, Anne-Marie S. 186, 206, 222</p>
          <p>Macpherson, Jay 167</p>
          <p>Maheux, Anne 75</p>
          <p>Mann, Paul 193</p>
          <p>Masheck, J.D.C. 116</p>
          <p>Matthews, Susan 228</p>
          <p>Maxwell, Richard 237</p>
          <p>Mayoux, Jean-Jacques 76, 138</p>
          <p>McCormick, Thomas J. 241</p>
          <p>McFarland, Thomas 215</p>
          <p>McNeil, Maureen 247</p>
          <p>Mellor, Anne K. 28, 258, 265</p>
          <p>Meyenburg, B. von 139</p>
          <p>Michalski, Sergiusz 140</p>
          <p>Middleton, Peter 77, 78</p>
          <p>Minnick, Thomas L. 16</p>
          <p>Mitchell, P.M. 239</p>
          <p>Mitchell, W.J.T. 79, 259</p>
          <p>Morace, Robert A. 47</p>
          <p>Morton, Richard 129</p>
          <p>Mourão Ferreira, David 80</p>
          <p>Munson, Rita 81</p>
          <p>Murray, E.B. 234</p>
          <p>Newey, Vincent 18, 123, 246, 260</p>
          <p>Noble, Andrew 82</p>
          <p>Nurmi, Martin K. 261</p>
          <p>Nuttall, A.D. 223</p>
          <p>Ober, Warren U. 47</p>
          <p>O’Neill, Michael 202</p>
          <p>Ostrom, Hans Ansgar 83</p>
          <p>Ott, Judith 84</p>
          <p>Paananen, Victor N. 262</p>
          <p>Page, Alex 215</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D. 85, 86, 143, 221, 263</p>
          <p>Parker, Patricia 167</p>
          <p>Paton, Alex 247</p>
          <p>Patrick, Julian 167</p>
          <p>Pauchard, Jean 87</p>
          <p>Paulson, Ronald 88, 89, 90, 141, 174, 264, 265, 266</p>
          <p>Payne, Anthony 237</p>
          <p>Payne, Harry C. 42</p>
          <p>Pearce, Donald 219</p>
          <p>Penny, Nicholas 206, 235</p>
          <p>Peterfreund, Stuart 193</p>
          <p>Peters, Plym 60</p>
          <p>Phillips, Michael C. 267</p>
          <p>Pickwoad, Nicholas 237</p>
          <p>Piquet, François 19, 91, 92, 273</p>
          <p>Pittock, John H. 246</p>
          <p>Pointon, Marcia 175</p>
          <p><corr type="emend">Poprzęcka</corr>, Maria 134</p>
          <p>Porter, Roy 247</p>
          <p>Powney, Christopher 149, 268</p>
          <p>Powney, Edith 149, 268</p>
          <p>Pressly, Nancy L. 176, 269</p>
          <p>Pressly, William L. 117, 118, 197, 270, 271</p>
          <p>Priestman, Martin 124, 272</p>
          <p>Pririe, N.W. 247</p>
          <p>Punter, David 93, 158, 184, 273</p>
          <p>Purkis, John 177, 274</p>
          <p>Quennell, Peter 203</p>
          <p>Raine, Kathleen 275, 276, 277</p>
          <p>Ramalho de Sousa Santos, Maria Irene 94</p>
          <p>Ratcliff, Carter 197</p>
          <p>Ravindran, S. 95</p>
          <p>Read, Dennis M. 126, 218, 252</p>
          <p>Redmond, James 18</p>
          <p>Reiman, Donald H. 246</p>
          <p>Reisner, M.E. 96</p>
          <p>Reynolds, Graham 200, 207, 238</p>
          <p>Rice, Patricia Hopkins 3</p>
          <p>Richards, Robert J. 247</p>
          <p>Richardson, Bruce Alan 97</p>
          <p>Richardson, Robert D., Jr. 5, 153</p>
          <p>Riegler, Elfie 69</p>
          <p>Robertson, Elizabeth 223</p>
          <p>Robinson, Jeffrey C. 251</p>
          <p>Rodgers, Pat 247</p>
          <p>Rogal, Samuel J. 150</p>
          <p>Rose, Edward J. 230</p>
          <p>Rosenthal, Michael 206</p>
          <p>Rousseau, George S. 243</p>
          <p>Runte, Roseann 96</p>
          <p>Ryskamp, Charles 122, 187, 246</p>
          <p>Sales, Roger 178</p>
          <p>Scalia, Gianni 51</p>
          <p>Schoenberg, Estella 264</p>
          <p>Scholz, Joachim J. 278</p>
          <p>Schwab, Gweneth B. 223</p>
          <p>Schweizer, Paul Douglas 179</p>
          <p>Scott, Michael 247</p>
          <p>Scrivener, Michael 202</p>
          <p>Shanes, Eric 203</p>
          <p>Shilstone, Frederick W. 202</p>
          <pb id="p18-115" n="115"/>
          <p>Shoemaker, Innis H. 21</p>
          <p>Shone, Richard 204</p>
          <p>Smeaton, W.A. 247</p>
          <p>Singh, Gurbhagat 98</p>
          <p>Smith, Michael 20</p>
          <p>Smith, Stan 267</p>
          <p>Solkin, David H. 119</p>
          <p><corr type="emend">Sosnowski,</corr> Terry Ford 99</p>
          <p>Spanckeren, Kathryn van 47</p>
          <p>Spector, Sheila 100</p>
          <p>Spittles, Brian 101</p>
          <p>Stallworthy, Jon 180</p>
          <p>Starobinski, Jean 279</p>
          <p>Steinberg, Robert E. 102</p>
          <p>Stemmler, Joan K. 103</p>
          <p>Stevenson, Warren 280</p>
          <p>Stiegman, Emero 223</p>
          <p>Stock, R.D. 104, 281</p>
          <p>Stokes, John 189</p>
          <p>Strudwick, R.F. 144</p>
          <p>Summerfield, Henry 208</p>
          <p>Sutton, Denys 181</p>
          <p>Swift, Bernard C. 70</p>
          <p>Syamken, Georg 105</p>
          <p>Symmons, Sarah 135</p>
          <p>Tannenbaum, Leslie 224, 259, 282</p>
          <p>Tave, Stuart M. 199, 250</p>
          <p>Tayler, Irene 203</p>
          <p>Taylor, Anya 281</p>
          <p>Taylor, Dena 106</p>
          <p>Thorpe, Douglas Joseph 107</p>
          <p>Thorslev, Peter L., Jr. 258</p>
          <p>Tolley, Michael J. 182, 230</p>
          <p>Trickett, Lionel 125</p>
          <p>Tscherny, Nadia 145</p>
          <p>Tyson, Walter 247</p>
          <p>Ulivi, Ferruccio 53</p>
          <p>Van Pelt, William Vern 108</p>
          <p>Vaughan, William 283</p>
          <p>Wagenknecht, David 213</p>
          <p>Walker, Dean 21</p>
          <p>Walling, William 250</p>
          <p>Ward, Aileen 202</p>
          <p>Wark, Robert R. 29, 49, 114, 115, 143</p>
          <p>Warner, Janet 220</p>
          <p>Warner, Nicholas O. 109, 110, 111, 112</p>
          <p>Weathers, Winston 193</p>
          <p>Webb, Timothy 154, 284</p>
          <p>Welch, Dennis M. 198</p>
          <p>Wendorf, Richard 79, 86, 90, 183</p>
          <p>Whaley, Joachim 133</p>
          <p>Wheatley, Philip 284</p>
          <p>Wheeler, Charles B. 223</p>
          <p>Wilkie, Brian 285</p>
          <p>Willard, Nancy 286</p>
          <p>Williams, Trevor I. 247</p>
          <p>Wittreich, Joseph A., Jr. 188, 195, 199, 212</p>
          <p>Woodcock, George 223</p>
          <p>Wordsworth, Jonathan 203</p>
          <p>Zeigelman, Lois 113</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
