<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>18.2.albion</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">The Daughters of Albion and the Butts Household</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1984</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1984</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">18.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D. W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary V. Jackson</name>
              <name>James McCord</name>
              <name>Jerome J. McGann</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1984"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_18">
    <body>
      <pb id="p18-116" n="116"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-2-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">The Daughters of Albion and the Butts Household</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>G.E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Thomas Butts was a munificent patron of William Blake in 1795-1810 and perhaps longer, paying him
regular sums for books and pictures to be delivered and filling his walls to overflowing with designs such as
“Samson Breaking Bonds” and “The Sons of God Shouting for Joy.” Blake used to go regularly on Tuesday
evenings to the spacious Butts house in Marlborough Street, round the corner from where he had lived at No. 28
Poland Street in 1785-90, and in 1801-09 he painted miniature portraits of Mrs. Butts, Mr. Butts, and Master
Tommy Butts.</p>
          <p>We know something of Thomas Butts’s profession as clerk in the office of the Commissary General
of Musters, of his income, and of his property at his death,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n31" type="note">1</ref> but we know little of his household. Some surprising light is thrown on this
by the printed census return filled out in manuscript in 1801 for the city of Westminster.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">2</ref> The house of Mr. Butts (at No. 9) on the North
side of Great Marlborough Street, five houses from Blenheim Mews (the houses were not numbered in the return),
was occupied by a single family of <hi rend="i">twenty-two</hi> persons, consisting of three males and
“19” females. Among the members of this family, none was occupied in Agriculture, there were three
“Persons chiefly employed in Trades, Manufactures, or Handicrafts,” and “19” persons, presumably the
females, were not employed at all. <note id="n31"><hi rend="s">1</hi> “Thomas Butts, White Collar
Maecenas,” <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi>, 71 (1956), 1052-66.</note>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Westminster Public Library Archives, Buckingham Palace Road, London;
pressmark D1742.</note></p>
          <p>The three males pose little problem. One must be Mr. Thomas Butts the clerk in the Muster Master
General’s office, another may be his son Tommy, then thirteen years old, who was later (from 1805) trained
by Blake as an engraver and also employed in his father’s office, and the third may be an otherwise unknown
son or, more probably, a servant such as a butler, coachman, or bootboy.</p>
          <p>But who can all those nineteen females have been? A wife and perhaps a daughter or so we may
grant readily enough, and even a few parlormaids, tweenies, and female cooks might be permitted, despite the
fact that all the females in the Butts family were said to be unemployed. But this leaves us with at least ten
females still unaccounted for, and perhaps as many as eighteen.</p>
          <p>Can Butts have taken in female relations on an heroic scale? Did he provide lodgings for female
orphans? Can his wife have had a little boarding school? (Almost next door to him in the 1790s lived Thomas
Martyn, who had a house full of boys whom he trained to engrave and color his natural history designs for his
extraordinarily beautiful books.) Can Butts, then forty-three years old, have had nineteen children, eighteen
of them female? Can he have had a harem—did Butts agree with Blake that, as Crabb Robinson reported of Blake
in 1826, “Eine Gemeinschaft der Frauen statt finden sollte”?<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n33" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi> (1969), 332; Robinson translated this in
1852 as “wives should be in common” (p. 548).</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">What</hi> were all those females doing in his house? I don’t know,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">4</ref> but William Blake must have, though he gives
no hint of the explanation in his letters to Butts of 1800-03. Such a number of females must have dominated
the arrangements of the house. Here are enough women to represent all the Daughters of Albion. Can Blake’s
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> (1793) have been, as it were, addressed to Thomas
Butts’s household? Was it at his house in Great Marlborough Street that “The Daughters of Albion hear her
[<hi rend="i">Oothoon’s</hi>] woes &amp; echoe back her sighs?” <note id="n34"><hi rend="s">4</hi> The
figure is unlikely to have been a simple clerical error, for the numbers are repeated in the census-return; 22
in the family, 3 males, 19 females; 3 in the family employed in Trades, 19 unemployed, 22 in all.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
