<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>18.2.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The Felpham Rummer: A New Angel and “Immoral Drink” Attributed to William
Blake</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1984</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1984</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">18.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D. W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary V. Jackson</name>
              <name>James McCord</name>
              <name>Jerome J. McGann</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1984"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_18">
    <body>
      <pb id="p18-94" n="94"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-2-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">THE FELPHAM RUMMER: A New Angel and “Immoral Drink” Attributed to William
Blake</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
          <docAuthor><hi rend="i">G. E. </hi><name><hi rend="i">BENTLEY</hi></name>, 
<hi rend="i">JR.</hi></docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>A new document attributed to William Blake has recently appeared in a surprising form. It is a
drinking goblet of the type called a rummer, with a very faint etching of an angel on one side of the bowl
(illus. 12 in Essick, above), a curious couplet of indifferent quality on the other side (illus. 1), and on
the stem Blake’s name (illus. 10 in Essick, above) and the date August 1803 (illus. 11 in Essick, above). As
art and as literature, the achievement is certainly indifferent by Blake’s standards, but, if the work
really is by him, it is fascinating because of the medium—Blake was not previously known to have made
designs on any other solid surface than metal or wood—and because of the biographical context, for it was in
August 1803 that Blake was charged with sedition. The purpose of the present note is to describe the object
and how it was made, to record its history, to test its authenticity, and to suggest its significance.</p>
        <p>A “rummer” is a goblet made usually of thick glass with a comparatively large bowl and a short
stem; an ordinary rummer holds four ounces or more of fluid and is up to 24 cm. high.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> The somewhat stubby rummer flourished as a type from the late
eighteenth century, partly because the Glass Excise Acts of 1777-1787 “in effect abolished tall,
long-stemmed drinking glass,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> which
had previously been popular. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> E. Barrington Hayes, <hi rend="i">Glass through
the Ages</hi> (1970), p. 200; there are also Giant Rummers over 24 cm. high and Mammoth Rummers over 28.8 cm.
high.
                        <p>For reproductions of rummers made about 1800, see L. M. Bickerton, <hi rend="i">An
Illustrated Guide to Eighteenth-Century Drinking Glasses</hi> (1921), pl. 685-86 (c. 1805), pl. 687 (c. 1805),
pl. 688 (c. 1805), pl. 689 (early nineteenth century), pl. 691 (c. 1800); Derek C. Davis, <hi rend="i">English
and Irish Antique Glass</hi> (1964), pl. 69 (1800-25), pl. 70 (c. 1800, “finely wheel engraved”), pl. 71
(dated 1746, the design in “Diamond point”); <hi rend="i">English Glass</hi>, ed. Sidney Crompton (1967),
pl. 168 (c. 1810, rather like the Felpham Rummer, “with ovoid~ogee bowls collared at base on short plain
stem”), pl. 169 (early nineteenth century), pl. 170 (early nineteenth century); Hayes, pl. 35d (c. 1805),
pl. 42d (c. 1800), pl. 95h (no date suggested, very like the Felpham Rummer, with the same foot but of course
made of glass); Hugh Wakefield, <hi rend="i">Nineteenth Century British Glass</hi> (1961), pl. 45A-B (c.
1805).</p></note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Francis Buckley, <hi rend="i">A History of Old English Glass</hi> (1925),
p. 37.</note></p>
        <p>Blake was clearly familiar with rummers, for he often represented them in his designs of about
1800<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> to indicate celebration or
inebriation or dedication. Usually of course they imply debauchery, as in the engraving of “headlong
appetite,” with rummer in hand, watched by Conscience for Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797)
p. 27 (illus. 2) and in that of Belshazzar, “high-flush’d with insolence and wine,” overturning his
rummer, “amazed,” as he sees the hand writing on the wall, for <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, p. 33
(illus. 3). A rummer is standard equipment for Blake’s Whores of Babylon (see <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> watercolor no. 345 and Dante design no. 89), presumably containing abominations and
fornications, but it is also the vessel proferred by the Good Samaritan (<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
watercolor no. 68) or one which contains faith (<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> watercolor no. 152) or a
utensil at a banquet of men and angels (<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> watercolor no. 479). Clearly the
rummer does not invariably imply wine or abomination in Blake’s designs before and after 1800—it is merely
a drinking vessel whose significance derives from its use. <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> For example,
“Lot and His Daughters” (1799-1800), “Christ in the House of Martha and Mary” (1803-05), “The Magic
Banquet,” for <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> (c. 1801, c. 1815), “Comus with his Revellers” (c. 1815), “The
Brothers Driving Forth Comus” (c. 1801, c. 1815), “Christ Ministered to by Angels,” for 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> (c. 1816-20), “The Whore of Babylon” (1809)—see Martin Butlin, 
<hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (1981), catalogue nos. 381 (pl. 485), 489 (pl. 563),
527.5 and 528.5 (pls. 620 and 628), 528.1 (pl. 624), 527.6 and 528.6 (pls. 621 and 629), 544.11 (pl. 694), 523
(pl. 584). See also <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> watercolors (1794-97) no. 52 (“headlong 
<hi rend="i">Appetite</hi>” with Conscience, engraved [1797] as p. 27), no. 60 (the vision of Belshazzar when
“high flusht with Insolence, and Wine,” engraved as p. 33), no. 68 (the Good Samaritan, engraved as p.
37), nos. 69, 152 (one of the misguided souls “who push our <hi rend="i">Antidote</hi> [Faith] aside”),
no. 185 (the Soul rejecting “<hi rend="i">Earth’s</hi> inchanted Cup”), nos. 271, 289, 331, 345
(“Mystery” with her rummer of fornication), no. 380 (“A thousand Demons lurk within the Lee”), nos.
409, 479 (“A Banquet . . . where Men, and Angels, meet”)—in <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Designs for
Edward Young’s Night Thoughts</hi>, ed. D.V. Erdman et al. (1980). See also Gray design (1798) p. 128 in
Irene Tayler, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations to the Poems of Gray</hi> (1971). See also the Canterbury
Pilgrims engraving (1810) (the wife of Bath) in R.N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William
Blake</hi> (1983), pl. 38. See also Dante design no. 89 (1824-27) (“The Whore [of Babylon with her rummer of
abominations] and the Giant”) in A.S. Roe, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Illustrations to the Divine Comedy</hi>
(1953). See also “Laughing Song” in <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (1789), pl. 15.
                        <p>An “Important silver mounted glass bowl” distantly related to a rummer
“engraved round rim ‘William Hogarth to Dr. Samuel Johnson 1762’ ” is reproduced in <hi rend="i">The
Antique Dealer and Collectors’ Guide</hi> (June 1959), p. 9.</p></note></p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
          </head>
          <p><hi rend="i">Size:</hi> Height 14 cm., diameter of bowl 10.5 cm.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Materials:</hi> English lead glass bowl and stem. Under ultra-violet light, the
glass shows white, indicating the use of lead in its manufacture and pointing to Britain as its source; had it
shown yellow, it would have implied a Continental origin of the glass. Air bubbles from bits of melted
“stone” and striations in the body of the bowl are characteristic of early nineteenth-century glass.</p>
          <p>The foot is of copper with traces indicating that it was originally silvered, and below the foot
is a paper shagreen lining. The foot could have been broken and replaced at almost any time after the glass
was made, but the worn silver on the replaced foot indicates that it is of some age. The glass itself is
neither uncommon nor valuable, and obviously it would scarcely have been worth repairing unless it had
sentimental value (“it was Uncle George’s”), or was needed to complete a set, or was especially
treasured because of the inscription or design. The copper foot is comparatively inexpensive and ugly,
suggesting either that it was not thought worth spending much money to restore the rummer to usable, standing
condition or that there was not much money to spend. The technique of using copper for such a purpose is old
and well known, and the material and method seem to imply no hint of date.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Pickering &amp; Chatto in their catalogue say that the “Foot [was]
replaced . . . probably late [in the] 19th Century,” and they attach some importance to the date but provide
no evidence for it, and I have none to indicate that the foot could not have been replaced in this
century—though I agree that it looks old, worn, and somewhat shoddy.</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Shape:</hi> Tulip bowl on a short stem, with a “bladed knop or collar,”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> and a simple circular foot. 
<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Hayes, p. 202.</note></p>
          <pb id="p18-95" n="95"/>
          <p><hi rend="i">Engravings:</hi> On one side of the bowl, most easily seen through the glass from
inside the bowl: a faint design of a nude angel with his right arm outstretched, the left wing fully
feathered, the right wing scarcely visible (illus. 12 in Essick, above).</p>
          <p>On the other side, rather crudely scratched in the glass:
<q>
THOU HOLDER OF IMMORAL DRINK<lb/>
I GIVE THEE PURPOSE NOW I THINK<lb/>
<lb/>
(illus. 1)<lb/>
<lb/>
On the collar:<lb/>
<lb/>
BLAKE IN ANGUISH AUG 1803<lb/>
(illus. 10-11 in Essick, above)
</q></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">History:</hi> (1) Sold by an anonymous owner<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n6" type="note">6</ref> in a miscellaneous sale of English and Continental Glass at Christie’s
(London), 2 November 1982, lot 68 (not reproduced, described as decorated “<hi rend="i">in the manner of
William Blake</hi>,” estimate £50-£100) for £55 to (2) Pickering &amp; Chatto, who offered it in their
Catalogue 651: <hi rend="i">A Miscellany of Rare and Interesting Books and Manuscripts</hi> ([March] 1983),
lot 1 (“in a new display box in Pickering green morocco”) for $45,000. <note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> A
letter from me to the owner, forwarded by Christie’s in August 1983, has not been answered. For assistance
with technical information, I am grateful particularly to Brian A. Musselwhite of the Royal Ontario Museum
(Toronto) and to Roger Gaskell and Christopher Edwards of Pickering &amp; Chatto Ltd. (17 Pall Mall, London
SW1Y 5NB) for showing me the Felpham Rummer in July 1983.</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Techniques of incision:</hi> There are a number of ways
<figure n="FelphamRummer.engravedcouplet.18.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="796" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>THOU HOLDER OF IMMORAL DRINK<lb/>
	I GIVE THEE PURPOSE NOW I THINK</figTranscr>
	<head>1. The Felpham Rummer, view of the couplet on the bowl.</head>
</figure>
of incising glass.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> (1) One is
engraving with a diamond tip, which leaves chips of unequal depth, and this was a common method. The Dutch
were leaders in the field, though often they worked with glass made in England. “No particular training was
necessary to produce a good engraving with a diamond point. Any one who was accustomed to engraving on metal .
. . might be able, with a little practice, to produce reasonably effectively with the diamond point on the
strong English glass.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> The lettering
on the Felpham Rummer is fairly plainly incised at irregular depths with a diamond tip not unlike a
conventional book-engraver’s tool. <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> A method patented in 1806 gave the
appearance of incising the glass, but in fact a permanent ground of powdered glass paste was added to the
surface, giving a frosted appearance, and then partially removed, so that the designs, etc., are in the
superficial ground and not in the glass (see Wakefield, p. 28 and pl. 29A). But this is not the method used in
the Felpham Rummer, whose glass is transparent, not frosted or opaque.</note>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Buckley, p. 75.</note></p>
          <p>(2) Wheel engraving on glass was developed especially in Germany and was brought to England about
1727.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">9</ref> It was, however, not much used
commercially in England until the 1830s, and as late as 1850 it was still experimental.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> It was only suitable for heavy glass, but the
English were not very good at it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref>
“By far the greatest number of glasses were decorated by the <hi rend="i">wheel process</hi>, which proved
the most important one for artistic and conventional ornamentation.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n12" type="note">12</ref> In wheel engraving, “the finished vessel [is pressed] against the edge of
a swiftly working wheel . . . the wheels are minute, some of them not reaching a fraction of an inch in
diameter
            <figure n="bb515.1.17.com" id="bb515.1.comb.17" work-copy="bb515.1" rend="db" width="803" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>inv &amp; sc<lb/>
	WB<lb/>
	Pubd. June 27. 1796, by R. Edwards, No. 142, New Bond Street.</figTranscr>
	<head>2. Blake’s engraving for <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797), p. 27, showing a rummer.</head>
</figure>
<pb id="p18-96" n="96"/>
and made of copper.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> “As many as
fifty or more different ones could be used in the formation of one design.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> Since the glass was pushed away from the engraver into the
wheel, he could scarcely see what he was doing directly, and a very high degree of traditional skill was
involved. Even with such a wheel, it would be exceedingly difficult for one untrained in the craft of wheel
engraving on glass to produce a creditable image, and of course it is scarcely possible that such a
specialized tool was available in Felpham in August 1803, the date on the Felpham Rummer. If the Felpham
Rummer were wheel engraved, we could on that basis alone fairly confidently eliminate Blake as the maker of
the design. But there seems to be no good reason to believe that the design <hi rend="i">was</hi> wheel
engraved. <note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Buckley, pp. 42, 48.</note>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Wakefield, pp. 41-42.</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Hayes, pp. 120, 123.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Davis, p. 84.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Davis, p. 85, quoting Henry J. Powell, <hi rend="i">Magazine of Art</hi>
(1904).</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Davis, p. 85.</note></p>
          <p>(3) The third conventional method is etching in the ordinary way, adapted for curved surfaces.
The chief problem for an etcher of copperplates would probably have been to discover an acid appropriate for
etching on glass. The standard acid for etching copper, the mordant probably used by Blake’s master James
Basire and by Blake himself, was aqua fortis composed of “vinegar (acetic acid), salamoniac (ammonium
chloride), . . . salt,
            <figure n="bb515.1.19.com" id="bb515.1.comb.19" work-copy="bb515.1" rend="db" width="789" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>inv &amp; sc<lb/>
	WB<lb/>
	Pubd. June 27th. 1796, by R. Edwards, No. 142 New Bond Street.</figTranscr>
	<head>3. <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797), p. 33.</head>
</figure>
and verdigris (an acetate of copper).”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15"
type="note">15</ref> The acid necessary for etching on glass, however, was quite different, a hydrofluoric
acid,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> directions for which were
given in Rees’s <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia</hi> (and doubtless in similar terms elsewhere):
<q><hi rend="i">Etching on Glass</hi>, is performed in the following manner: Lay a thin coat of white wax (as
etching ground is laid) on the plate of glass. On this the drawing must be traced in the usual way. When the
subject is etched, a border or wall of wax of a very even height must be put around [as Blake did for his
relief etchings]: taken then some fluor spar powdered to about the fineness of oatmeal, and strew it 
<hi rend="i">evenly</hi> over the etching, and on this pour a mixture of equal quantities of sulphuric acid and
water, till the whole is about the consistence of thick cream. . . .<lb/>
If the subject be to be etched with care, and high finishing be required, the acid mixture must be taken off
occasionally, and the plate, after being well washed and dried, must have the parts that are bit-in enough,
stopped-out, as in common etchings, when the mixture must be again put on, . . . and this must be repeated
till the several gradations of shade are believed to be sufficiently corroded.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref></q>
It seems likely enough that formulae for acids designed to etch on surfaces other than metal were common
knowledge among professional engravers and that, at the very least, plausible mordants could be discovered
            <figure n="BUT330.1.341.WC" rend="file" width="801" height="1000">
	<head>4. Blake’s watercolor No. 341 (1794-97) for <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (British Museum Print
Room): “Angels shout—<hi rend="i">An Infidel Reclaim’d.</hi>”</head>
	<figDesc>Compare the angels here with that on the Felpham Rummer.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p18-97" n="97"/>
by professional experimentation. <note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William
Blake Printmaker</hi> (1980), p. 16; an unlikely alternative recommended by [Robert Dossie], <hi rend="i">The
Handmaid to the Arts</hi> (1764), II, 146-50, is “nitric acid made with ‘spirits of nitre and vitriol.’
”</note>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Davis, p. 84, says, “the first use of the <hi rend="i">hydrofluoric
acid</hi> technique is said to have emanated from Germany . . . [where it had been discovered] towards the end
of the 17th century,” but “Acid-etching was not seriously developed in this country [England] until the
mid-19th century” (Crompton, pl. 170).</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Anon., “Glass,” <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia</hi>, ed. Abraham Rees
(1820; originally issued 1802-1819), Vol. XIII, f. 3Z2<hi rend="s"><hi rend="i">v</hi></hi> (a reference
pointed out by my friend Robert Essick). Note that the <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia</hi> directions are for
etching on flat surfaces to be “printed by means of the rolling press” and that the specifications for
“a cover of metal or wood . . . [to] be laid over, and fitted close on the border of wax, to keep in the
fumes of the acid,” and for the border of wax, are presumably irrelevant to the process of etching on a
curved surface.</note></p>
          <p>The chief novelties for Blake would probably have been how to get the acid to bite uniformly over
a curved surface, how to get the acid the right strength for glass, and how long to allow it to bite. With
etching on copper, one tests one’s progress by taking a proof on paper, but with glass the design in the
solid surface is the end itself, rather than the means to the end (printing the design on paper). Someone
experimenting with the process is likely to use comparatively weak acid formulae and short bites, to etch
lightly at first, to see how the process works.</p>
          <p>The angel in the design on the outside of the bowl bears the stigmata of an experimental etching.
The depth of the incisions is of a uniformity virtually impossible to achieve with engraving in the ordinary
way, by chipping with a diamond point or wheel engraving. The incisions are very shallow and are so faint as
to be difficult to see even when holding the object in one’s hands and turning it to the light to catch the
refraction from the incisions. And one side of the design, the angel’s right wing, is almost invisible,
suggesting either that it was never completed in the drawing at all or that, if drawn, the acid did not bite
there effectively—a problem perhaps caused by the curved surface.</p>
          <p>Designs on rummers are usually heads of the famous or of patrons, or symbols of drink such as
grapes, or pastoral scenes or elegant houses or ships. The design of the angel here is of course not peculiar
to Blake—many artists of the time might have designed similar angels, artists such as Fuseli, Stothard,
Barry, and Westall. On the other hand, Blake made similar angels; that in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
watercolor no. 341 (illus. 4) is very like that on the Felpham Rummer, and the shape is repeated elsewhere, as
in <hi rend="i">Job</hi> (1826) pl. 14. The design on the Felpham Rummer could well be his, allowing for the
experimental character of the shape in an unfamiliar medium.</p>
          <p>The lettering is scratched on somewhat crudely in diamond point. All the lettering seems to be in
the same hand. Since no other work on glass by Blake is known, we may presume that the medium was unfamiliar
to him. It is therefore very likely that, if he were writing thus on glass, the style would not much resemble
his own<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref>—and in fact, the style is
very conventional and anonymous, with stick capitals throughout and some difficulty with curved lines.
Considerable trouble was experienced with the N, but the T, H, E, F, and K have some degree of elegance, with
deft little flourishes at the ends of lines, and the curious G is not un-Blakean. One could scarcely say that
the form of the writing is much like that which Blake made with pen, brush, pencil, graver, or etching
needle—but, on the other hand, it is not significantly inconsistent with his either, if one bears in mind
the unfamiliarity of the medium. <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Or rather any of his own. In Upcott’s
Autograph Album, Blake wrote: “I do not think an Artist can write an Autograph[,] especially one who has
Studied in the Florentine &amp; Roman Schools[,] as such an one will Consider what he is doing but an
Autograph as I understand it, is writ helter skelter like a hog upon a rope” (<hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Writings</hi> [1978], p. 1321). Blake had numerous styles of lettering, from the most beautiful copperplate
hand to hurried, almost illegible scrawls.</note></p>
          <p>The language of the couplet is certainly not characteristically Blakean. Most of the words which
are in any way unusual—“holder,” “immoral,” “drink” as a noun, “give . . . purpose”—do not
appear in Blake’s previously recorded vocabulary, or appear only in different senses. The noun “drink”
is not uncommon in Blake,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref> but it
never seems to have elsewhere the pejorative alcoholic connotation it clearly bears here. Neither “holder”
nor “give . . . purpose” is found elsewhere at all, and the only use of “immoral” is not pejorative:
“the grandest Poetry is Immoral[,] the Grandest characters Wicked.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> Only the use of “immoral” in the couplet gives one much
cause to pause, for Blake does not use forms derived from it at all (e.g., “immorality”), and ordinarily
he avoids moral questions:
<q>
If Morality was Christianity Socrates was the Saviour.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21"
type="note">21</ref><lb/>
<lb/>
. . . Satan first the Black Bow bent<lb/>
And the Moral Law from the Gospel Rent.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
type="note">22</ref><lb/>
<lb/>
The Moral Christian is the Cause<lb/>
Of the Unbeliever &amp; his Laws.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi><hi rend="i"> A Concordance to the Writings of William Blake</hi>, ed.
D.V. Erdman et al. (1967).</note>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Annotation (?1800) to Boyd’s translation of Dante (1785) in 
<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi> (1978), p. 1447.</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake’s Writings</hi>, p. 664.</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake’s Writings</hi>, p. 929.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake’s Writings</hi>, p. 1056.</note></q>
It would certainly be surprising to find Blake using “immoral” as it appears on the Felpham Rummer—but
then almost everything Blake did is surprising. 
                    </p>
          <p>The attitude toward “immoral drink” is also surprising, for Blake himself had no aversion to
drink or to pubs:
<q>
he fetched the porter for dinner himself, from the house at the Corner of the Strand [near where he lived
1821-27]. Once, pot of porter in hand, he espied coming along a dignitary of Art—that highly respectable
man, William Collins, R.A., whom he had met in society a few evenings before. The Academician was about to
shake hands, but seeing the porter, drew up, and did not know him. Blake would tell the story very quietly,
and without sarcasm. . . . It was only in later years he took porter regularly. He then fancied it soothed
him, and would sit and muse over his pint after a one o’clock dinner. When he drank wine, which, at home, of
course, was seldom, he professed a liking to drink off good draughts from a tumbler, and thought the wine
glass system absurd. . . .<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake. “Pictor
Ignotus”</hi> (1863), I, 313-14, quoted in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (1969), pp. 307,
308.</note></q></p>
          <p>The justification for the attitude toward “immoral drink” must come, if at all, from the
events of August 1803. Blake was then living at the little seaside village of Felpham, and he must have gone
repeatedly to the local gossip center, The Fox Inn fifty yards from his cottage, for his landlord was also the
proprietor of The Fox.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref> During the
invasion hysteria of the summer of 1803, a troop of Royal Dragoons was quartered at The Fox, and the public
bar must have been full of soldiers. On 12 August Blake had a violent quarrel with a soldier named Scolfield
whom he found unexpectedly in his garden, and, as he wrote in his account of the incident, “Mr. Hayley’s
Gardener came past at the time of the Contention at the Stable Door [of The Fox Inn], &amp; going to the
Comrade [Private Cock] Said to him, Is your Comrade drunk?—a Proof that he thought the Soldier abusive,
&amp; in an Intoxication of Mind.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref>
Blake may well have known then what his attorney Samuel Rose
<pb id="p18-98" n="98"/>
said at his subsequent trial for sedition, that Scolfield had been “degraded on account of drunkenness”
from the rank of Sargeant.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref> In “AUG
1803” Blake was certainly “IN ANGUISH,” and he may well have had reason to believe that the perjured
evidence against him was manufactured by Private Scolfield partly because of his indulgence in “IMMORAL
DRINK.” It is imaginable that this rummer is from The Fox Inn and even that Private Scolfield or his
accomplice Private Cock had drunk from it. Blake must have had to go to The Fox Inn after the incident in
order to collect evidence with which to defend himself before the magistrates on 15 August or at his
subsequent Quarter Sessions trial on 4 October, and it is at least conceivable that he scratched the couplet,
date, and signature on the rummer with a borrowed diamond in a few minutes on such an occasion. (Among his
local acquaintances, only his patron William Hayley and their friend Henrietta Poole are likely to have had a
diamond.) <note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi>, p. 561.</note>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi>, p. 127.</note>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi>, p. 142.</note></p>
          <p>The etching could not have been done so casually—even professional engravers like Blake do not
ordinarily carry wax and etching acid in their jacket pockets. If the angel is by Blake, it was probably made
at his cottage, as an experiment quickly abandoned. Or perhaps the sequence was reversed—perhaps the
landlord of The Fox, wishing to profit from the presence in the village of a tame artist and engraver, had
asked Blake to decorate the pub rummer with an angel and Blake had the unfinished vessel in his cottage on
August 12th when he emerged to find Private Scolfield in his garden “drunk . . . abusive, &amp; in an
Intoxication of Mind.” In such circumstances, it would not be astonishing to find him returning, after the
excitement had diminished a little, to add the words to the rummer. Certainly he was writing such anguished
and indifferent couplets in his <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> at about the same time:
<q>
On H—<lb/>
Thy Friendship oft has made my heart to ake<lb/>
Do be my Enemy for Friendships Sake<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28"
type="note">28</ref><lb/>
<lb/>
When H—y finds out what you cannot do<lb/>
That is the very thing he[’]ll set you to<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29"
type="note">29</ref>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">28</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake’s Writings</hi>, p. 947.</note>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">29</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake’s Writings</hi>, p. 946.</note></q></p>
          <p>Are the etching and engraving by Blake? The glass may well have been made before 1803—certainly
the style of rummer was popular long before then, the glass seems to be British rather than Continental, and
the quality of the glass suggests it was made about 1800. The inscriptions were scratched and the angel etched
by techniques familiar to Blake, though the material was strange and therefore difficult. We should not expect
to find his very personal hand strongly marked in either words or design, even if he made them. The
biographical context is right, and on other occasions Blake certainly made poems and designs as puzzling and
indifferent as these. The chief grounds for doubt are the curious material, the very troubling lack of history
before 2 November 1982 (an obscurity which the previous owner seems to be unwilling to dissipate), and the
reference to “IMMORAL DRINK,” a reference apparently explicable only in terms of the biographical
context.</p>
          <p>Of the various possibilities to be considered—forgery, memento, copy, adaptation, and
original—copy and adaptation seem unlikely, since no original significantly like this in any way is known.
The possibility that it is a memento, made by a friend at the time or later, is also negligible, for there was
no other etcher in Felpham at the time, and no artist friend of later years is likely to have had the
biographical information as well as the inclination to make it. It could of course be a forgery,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">30</ref> made at almost any time between 1863, when
Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life</hi> resurrected Blake’s reputation, and 1982, but, if so, the modesty with
which it was introduced into the market was scarcely likely to bring its creator much profit—if indeed he
still had it to profit from. All the tests concerning date, place, and technique for a modern fake have proved
negative; date, place, and technique may all have been accessible to Blake. On balance, it seems to me
probable that the couplet, the signature, and the angel are all by Blake. <note id="n30"><hi rend="s">30</hi>
Pickering &amp; Chatto say in their catalogue:
<q><hi rend="i">We have, of course, considered the question of authenticity very carefully. The hypothesis of
forgery would require it to have been carried out before 1900, that is, before the repair to the foot, for
no-one at that time would have bothered to repair an ordinary pub rummer, if it had not already been engraved.
At that time, a forgery could have had little commercial justification. It would have required the skill to
forge a Blake drawing of an angel, to forge Blake’s lettering by a separate method of engraving, to invent a
metrically correct two-line Blake poem, in the right style of that period of his life, and biographical
knowledge to invent and date the inscription, information which was probably</hi> [sic] <hi rend="i">not
available before the publication in 1926 of the</hi> [16 August 1803] <hi rend="i">letter to Butts. In our
view, forgery can therefore be eliminated as a possibility.</hi></q>
However, much of this evidence seems to me weak. There is no solid evidence that the foot was repaired by
1900; a repair might have been made at any time for reasons other than preservation of the inscriptions;
imitations of Blake were in any case made before 1900, such as those by Camden Hotten (see M.D. Paley, “John
Camden Hotten, A.C. Swinburne, and the Blake Facsimiles of 1868,” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of the New York
Public Library</hi>, 79 [1976], 259-96, and “A Victorian Blake Facsimile,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 [1981], 24-27), and there are reasons for repairing it other than commerce. The
skill in creating the design and poem is not formidable (“metrically correct” may be the poem’s highest
praise), and the biographical information was available in Gilchrist in 1863 (Vol. II, pp. 196-98), long
before 1926. Forgery therefore should not be “eliminated as a possibility,” though I agree that it is
somewhat improbable.
                        </note></p>
          <p>If so, the <corr type="emend">significance</corr> of the Felpham Rummer is not what it adds to
our knowledge and suppositions of Blake’s poetry and art, but what it suggests about the ANGUISH he felt in
August 1803—and the immediacy with which he expressed his anguish in poem and design. And the ambivalence in
his attitudes towards DRINK and IMMORALITY suggested by the couplet are worth bearing in mind. If the couplet
is his, we must be more cautious in our conclusions about Blake’s views of morality. The allegation that it
is the artist who gives purpose to objects is very Blakean, but the attribution of immorality has not
previously seemed to be so. The Felpham Rummer, like most “Blake” discoveries, seems to raise more
questions than it answers—and this, at least, is a very Blakean quality.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p18-99" n="99" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
