<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>18.2.mccord</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">An Unrecorded Colored Copy of Young’s Night Thoughts</title>
        <author n="McCord">James McCord</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1984</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1984</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">18.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>D. W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary V. Jackson</name>
              <name>James McCord</name>
              <name>Jerome J. McGann</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1984"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_18">
    <body>
	<pb id="p18-116" n="116"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-2-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">An Unrecorded Colored Copy of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>James <name>McCord</name></docAuthor>
            <ref target="p116u1" type="note">*</ref>
          </byline>
          <note id="p116u1">* I would like to thank Donald Finkel, Holly Hall, and Timothy Murray of
Washington University, and Ellen A. Nollman, Head Librarian of the Freer Gallery of Art, for their expert
assistance in helping me with bibliographical details.</note>
          <p>In their two-volume study, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Designs for Edward Young’s Night
Thoughts</hi> (Oxford, 1980), the editors write that “at present twenty-three coloured copies are believed
to exist.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">1</ref> Their census includes
twenty-two copies, the twenty-third being Moss-Bentley G, which is discussed briefly in the “Introduction”
and described in footnote 81; it was omitted from the census apparently because it was untraced. Another copy,
Bentley T, is not mentioned at all, and it may still be owned,
<pb id="p18-117" n="117"/>
as G.E. Bentley, Jr. records in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n36" type="note">2</ref> by Mr. and Mrs. H.P. Cook. In part to justify their “new census” and
“new system of coding copies,” the editors write that a “useful system should . . . allow for the
addition of new copies, which recent experience suggests will continue to come to light.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">3</ref> For their edition, Erdman, Grant, Rose, and
Tolley were, in fact, able to add four new copies to the list of twenty compiled by Bentley for 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>; and recently Thomas V. Lange has written of his rediscovery of the Moss-Bentley G
copy, describing it in full.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">4</ref> The
occasion for this “minute particular” is to share information about a previously unrecorded colored copy
that has been housed in the library of Washington University, St. Louis, for over fifty years,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">5</ref> a volume that brings to twenty-five the number
of colored copies that are thought to be extant. <note id="n35"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi rend="i"> William
Blake’s Designs for Edward Young’s Night Thoughts</hi>, edited with commentary by John E. Grant, Edward J.
Rose, and Michael J. Tolley; co-ordinating editor David V. Erdman (London: Oxford University Press, 1980), pp.
52-53.</note>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">2</hi> G.E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford at the Clarendon
Press, 1977), pp. 956-57. For Bentley’s description of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> and full
census, see pp. 636-46. See also the earlier studies by W.E. Moss, “The Coloured Copies of Blake’s
‘Night Thoughts,’ ” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 2 (Fall 1968), 19-23, and G.E. Bentley, Jr.,
“A Census of Coloured Copies of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797),” <hi rend="i">Blake
Newsletter</hi>, 2 (Winter 1968-69), 41-45.</note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Grant, Rose, Tolley, and Erdman, p. 61.</note>
	<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Thomas V. Lange, “A Rediscovered Colored Copy of Young’s 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 15 (Winter 1981-82),
134-36.</note>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">5</hi> This copy is, incidentally, listed in the <hi rend="i">National Union
Catalog Pre-1956 Imprint</hi>, vol. 679, p. 278.</note></p>
          <p>Following the format adopted by the editors of the Oxford <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, the
copy would be described as follows:
<q>
I-6B or I-7B (Previously unknown) <hi rend="i">White</hi> Death<lb/>
<lb/>
Bound in full red morocco with gilt-tooling around the edges and gilt dentelles by Riviere &amp; Son. Spine
stamped in gold: “YOUNG’S NIGHT THOUGHTS ILLUST<hi rend="s">D</hi> BY BLAKE 197.” Blue, red, yellow,
green, and white marbled pastedowns with facing marbled endpapers. Front cover unhinged. Top edge of papers
gilt; side and bottom uncut. Six sheets (pp. v-vi, 29-30, 61-62, 73-74, 81-82, and 91-92) watermarked “J.
Whatman 1794.” Explanation of the Engravings after p. 95. Grotesque coloring on 6E (p. 10) and 20E (p. 35);
slight grotesque coloring on 18E (p. 31). On 11E (p. 17) Death wears a black hood and cloak that covers his
head and body. No J C monogram. Pencilled “As Pattern” at bottom left on 37E (p. 86). Four designs are
uncolored: 22E (p. 40), 29E (p. 57), 38E (p. 87), and 39E (p. 88).<lb/>
A letter of 9 April 1920 from Katharine N. Rhoades to W. K. Bixby that apparently accompanied the book when it
was sent to Bixby is laid in.<lb/>
<lb/>
<list type="ordered">
	<item><p><label>(1)</label> Acquired by Charles Lang Freer (1856-1919), whose executors sent it as a gift on
9 April 1920 to</p></item>
	<item><p><label>(2)</label> William K. Bixby. It was probably between 1921 and 1926 that the book was given
as part of the William K. Bixby Collection to</p></item>
	<item><p><label>(3)</label><hi rend="i">Washington University</hi>, which attached its bookplate, “Library
of Washington University The Gift of W. K. Bixby.” A second bookplate, “Library of Washington University
The George N. Meissner Rare Book Department,” was added when the copy became housed in that department in
1962. Special Vault PR 3782 N5 1797 fol.</p></item>
</list></q></p>
          <p>Except for heavy foxing on 13E and 14E, and touches of foxing on 15E, 16E, and 17E, the prints
are in very good condition. The copy is carefully washed in vivid colors with the colorist(s) using two
distinct methods; some prints are finished in soft, light tones with subtle modulations in shading (e.g. 1E,
10E, 18E, 30E, and 31E), while others are worked up in bright contrasting tones for dramatic effect (e.g. 8E,
24E, 25E, 26E, 32E, and 36E). In 11E (which is in the common “masculine” 4th state) a black hood and gown
cover the head, entire left forearm, and body of the figure of Death, the added coloring being almost
identical to that of the same print in the Moss-Bentley G copy which is reproduced in Thomas Lange’s
article.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">6</ref> This unusual addition is
recorded as a distinct feature in only three other copies besides Moss-Bentley G: I-8, I-9, and I-11. 
<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Lange, 135.</note></p>
          <p>So-called “grotesque colouring” in 6E, 18E, and 20E accounts for the other main variation in
coloring. What has been described as a “generally muddy effect” in 6E is clear in this copy as a blotchy
brown medium applied over light violet watercolor on the lower back and both legs and feet of the figure of
Disease, and on the left side only of her sweeping gown. As scholars have described,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">7</ref> the texture and effect of this medium are quite different
from those of the “grotesque colouring” in 18E and 20E. In 20E heavy lines of brown-black coloring accent
the old pedagogue’s brow and forehead, eye, and the side of his nose, with two dashes on his beard. The same
dark and rather ominous coloring appears on the aged woman’s eyebrows, beneath her eyes, on her throat, and
under her chin. By comparison, the touches of brown-black in 18E are much less evident, though they do appear
beneath the brow of the “good man,” as well as beside his nose, under his chin, and on his throat. That
these striking touches are strong in 6E and 20E and comparatively slight in 18E is a circumstance that this
copy seems to have in common with only two others: I-3 and I-5. <note id="n41"><hi rend="s">7</hi> There have
been at least two sound technical explanations for the unusual coloring in 6E. The editors of the Oxford 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, pp. 58-59, suggest that “a running wet paint” was applied over dry or nearly
dry color. Some scholars have also discussed the possibility of pigment decay.</note></p>
          <p>It is curious that a copy worked up so carefully, characterized by these coloring variations, and
complete in every other way would include four uncolored prints. The colorist, of course, may simply have
overlooked these designs, but evidence also suggests that they may be substitutes for “lost” colored
plates that were originally in the copy. For unlike other prints in this volume, the four uncolored designs on
three leaves are tipped in, the bottom margins of each are trimmed, and the inlaid text of E39 is seriously
askew to the design. Assuming that these prints were added at a later date, it seems reasonable to hope that
colored leaves of 22E, 29E, and 38E and 39E may come to light, and that they might be then reinserted in this
volume from which at one time they were separated. Taking all of the distinguishing details and variations
into consideration, and using the criteria established by the editors of the Oxford <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi>, this copy would fit most comfortably after I-6 or I-7 in the census compiled by Erdman, Grant,
Rose, and Tolley.</p>
          <p>The main clue to the provenance of the volume is an ink inscription on the plain verso of the
marbled front endpaper written by W.K. Bixby shortly after he received it:
<q>
This book was sent me by the sister in law of Chas L. Freer and Miss Katharine Rhodes [sic] Frank Hecker
Freer’s Executors together with another book &amp; a Chinese painting they being requested
<pb id="p18-118" n="118"/>
by him to send after his death. He was an old and dearly prized friend of mine. He died Sept 25th 1919.<lb/>
W K Bixby<lb/>
S Louis 4/15/20
</q>
Bixby’s references and lack of punctuation here are somewhat confusing, but he probably received the book
directly from Anna Hecker Freer (one of several sisters-in-law of Charles Freer) and Katharine N. Rhoades,
Freer’s secretary, who would have made the request of the two executors of Freer’s will: Frank J. Hecker,
a lifelong friend and business associate of Freer’s, and Charles D. Walcott, Secretary of the Smithsonian.
Below this inscription, also in Bixby’s hand, is written in pencil:
<q>
Wash. Un.<lb/>
Comps.<lb/>
W K B
</q>
which was Bixby’s way of designating those books and manuscripts in his collection that were slated for
Washington University with his compliments (“Comps.”). The only other notations in the volume are the
penciled directive, “As Pattern,” on 37E, a variant that appears in only three other copies: I-10, I-11,
and I-13; what might be the name of a bookseller or earlier owner—“L [or P] Dawsons”—this signature
scrawled upside down in ink on the verso of 43E; and a dealer’s price code that reads “x <hi rend="i">gli
sx</hi>” and is located on the blank recto of the back marbled endpaper. I have not been able to trace the
provenance of this copy further back than Freer, but information might come to light that would help identify
eighteenth- and nineteenth-century owners of the book, or associate it with one of the sales catalogue
descriptions that has been listed in reference to another copy.</p>
          <p>This unrecorded color copy of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> is the most unusual
Blake item in Washington University Special Collections, but there are also several other books with
commercial engravings by Blake that are worthy of mention: Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (London:
for R. H. Cromek, 1808); Erasmus Darwin, <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi> (London: for J. Johnson, 1806);
two copies of John Gay, <hi rend="i">Fables</hi> (London: for John Stockdale, 1793); C.G. Salzmann, 
<hi rend="i">Gymnastics for Youth</hi> (London: for J. Johnson, 1800); James Stuart and Nicholas Revett, 
<hi rend="i">The Antiquities of Athens</hi>, volume 3 (London: John Nichols, 1794); and Mary Wollstonecraft, 
<hi rend="i">Original Stories from Real Life</hi> (London: for J. Johnson, 1791).</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
