<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>18.3.reiman</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">James King and Charles Ryskamp, eds., The Letters and Prose Writings of William
Cowper, vol. 3: Letters, 1787-1791</title>
        <author n="Reiman">Donald H. Reiman</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1984-85</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1984-85</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">18.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Shelley M. Bennett</name>
              <name>James Bogan</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Christopher Fox</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>W.J.T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Nicholas O. Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1984-85"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_18">
    <body>
	<pb id="p18-146" n="146"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">James King and Charles Ryskamp, eds. <hi rend="i">The Letters and Prose
Writings of William Cowper. Vol. III: Letters, 1787-1791.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1982. xxiv + 630 pp.
$79.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Donald H.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Reiman</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>When I received this third volume of William Cowper’s <hi rend="i">Letters</hi> for review, I
hoped to be able to relate the ideals of Cowper to those of the Romantics by centering my essay on how Cowper
confronted the French Revolution. I soon discovered, however, that he successfully <hi rend="i">avoided</hi>
confronting it. Although the letters contain a handful of remarks on events in France (so few that I shall be
able to quote the bulk of them in this review), his persistent concerns were more local and parochial. In
<pb id="p18-147" n="147"/>
this insularity, he probably mirrors the general attitudes of older liberals (“Whig[s] on the old plan,”
as he describes himself on pp. 245 and 354-55) toward social and political change within Britain and across
the Channel.</p>
          <p>In these letters, Cowper strongly supports the Parliamentary battle of 1788 against the slave
trade (now almost forgotten) and even contributes his mite by writing some propagandistic poems to be set to
music, in an effort to influence public opinion (see pp. 89, 103, 106-07, 172, 177-78). He opposes cruel field
sports, describing in disgusting detail the only fox hunt that he ever witnessed (pp. 117-19). On 19 April
1790, he explains “thank heav’n!” that “the Bastile [is] now no more” but he does so in parentheses,
while alluding to his own passage in <hi rend="i">The Task</hi> (V, 379-445) that describes the plight of a
prisoner in the Bastille (p. 369). He supports religious toleration and particularly a bill put forward by his
Catholic friends the Throckmortons to ease the Catholic disabilities (pp. 295, 301, 354 f.), and at the end of
the volume he even refuses to translate four of Milton’s Latin poems on the Gunpowder Plot because he thinks
that “they are written with an asperity, which, however it might be warranted in Milton’s Day, would be
extremely unseasonable now”: “I should think . . . that the dying embers of antient animosity had better
not be troubled” (p. 583 and fn.). Like all right thinking people of his day, he honored the humanitarian
prison reformer John Howard and wrote a (prose) epitaph for a proposed monument to be erected at the site of
Howard’s death in the Crimea (p. 411).</p>
          <p>Though Cowper’s actual comments on the French struggles for self-government are not numerous,
they are friendly and relatively sanguine at first. Apart from the earlier aside on the fall of the Bastille,
Cowper’s first such comment comes on 1 December 1789 in a letter to John Newton, in which he also alludes to
his central interest throughout this volume—his translation of <hi rend="i">The Iliad</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">The Odyssey</hi>:
<q>
In my next, perhaps, I shall find leisure to bestow a few lines on what is doing in France and in the Austrian
Netherlands; though to say the truth I am much better qualified to write an essay on the siege of Troy, than
to descant on any of these modern revolutions. I question if in either of the countries just mention’d, full
of bustle and tumult as they are, there be a single character whom Homer were he living, would deign to make
his hero. The populace are the heroes now, and the stuff of which gentlemen heroes are made, seems to be all
expended. (p. 321)
</q></p>
          <p>In a letter to his cousin Lady Hesketh on 7 July 1790, Cowper shows his system of values to be in
direct conflict with the course of events in France:
<q>
The French who like all lively folks, are extreme in every thing, are such in their zeal for Freedom, and if
it were possible to make so noble a cause ridiculous, their manner of promoting it could not fail to do so.
Princes and peers reduced to plain gentlemanship, and gentles reduced to a level with their own lacqueys, are
excesses of which they will repent hereafter. Difference of rank and subordination, are, I believe of God’s
appointment, and consequently essential to the well being of society: but what we mean by fanaticism in
[religion] is exactly that which animates their politics, and unless time should sober the[m], they will,
after all, be an unhappy people. Perhaps it deserves not much to be wondered at, that at their first escape
from tyrannic shackles, they should act extravagantly, and treat their kings, as they have sometimes treated
their idols. (pp. 396-97)
</q>
A comparison of these sentiments with such Romantic reflections on the Revolution as “France: An Ode” and
the Preface to <hi rend="i">The Revolt of Islam</hi> shows that the Romantics shared more of Cowper’s
prejudices and values than might at first seem likely, while a backward glance confirms that the chief article
on which they differed—the divine ordinance of a social hierarchy—was a preconception that Cowper shared
with Milton, among many others.</p>
          <p>On 26 February 1791, at a time when Lafayette and his allies were still very much in control in
France and the most notable events in recent memory were the Festival of the Federation of the previous July
and the passage of laws designed to commit the loyalty of the clergy to the civil constitution (nothing to
frighten a loyal Anglican), Cowper defended the French against the scorn of his friend Walter Bagot:
<q>
I think your Latin quotations very applicable to the present state of France. But France is in a situation new
and untried before. When she is a little more accustom’d to it and has time to digest coolly and arrange the
chaos of business before her, she will acquit herself better. At least, I think, she will never be enslaved
again. (p. 470)
</q>
Cowper was now optimistic enough, partly because of the changes he had seen wrought by the French on an
entrenched tyranny, to assert “Le bon tems viendra” (p. 260), the exact sentiment that (in Italian, rather
than French) would adorn Shelley’s ring thirty years later.</p>
          <p>Finally, however, in a letter to Lady Hesketh, 11 July 1791, Cowper shows that he pities the
plumage more than he remembers the dying bird:
<q>
You judge right in supposing that I pitied the King and Queen of France. I can truly say that, except the late
melancholy circumstances of our own (when our Sov’reign had lost his sense, and his wife was almost worried
out of hers) no Royal distresses have ever moved me so much. And still I pity them, prisoners as they are now
for life, and since their late unsuccessful attempt, likely to be treated more scurvily than ever. Heaven help
them, for in their case, all other help seems vain! (p. 543)
</q>
This passage points us back to Cowper’s concern for the madness of King George III (partly because, like the
Romantics, he despised and feared the self-seeking politics of the Prince of Wales), and to his affirmation on
25 February 1789, when the King had recovered from his first attack:
<q>
The King’s recovery is with <hi rend="i">us</hi> a subject of daily conversation and of continual joy. It is
so providentially timed, that no man who believes a providence at all, can say less of it than that 
<hi rend="i">This is the finger of God!</hi> Never was a hungry faction so mortally disappointed. . . .
<pb id="p18-148" n="148"/>
It is a wonderful æra in the history of this country; and posterity will envy us the happiness of having
lived at such a period (pp. 263-64).
</q>
Let me set beside this pæon to the recovery of George III (and to the confusion of the Prince and of Charles
James Fox, his crony of that period) Shelley’s sentiments at the end of “A Defence of Poetry”: “our
own will be a memorable age in intellectual achievements, and we live among such philosophers and poets as
surpass beyond comparison any who have appeared since the last national struggle for civil and religious
liberty.” Whereas Cowper places his faith in the governance of historical process by Providential forces,
Shelley celebrates the powers of the human intellect and spirit that are stirred up in times of political
crisis. Both set their faith in a causal relationship between times of stress and extraordinary achievements,
but whereas for Shelley the activating force is (probably) imminent, for Cowper, He is transcendent. Blake’s
position, I believe, is more ambiguous than either of these. Certainly his rhetoric and the structures of his
works often suggest that he is as much of Cowper’s party as Shelley’s.</p>
          <p>William Cowper represents many of the best features of the world that was about to dissolve in
the acid of acrimonious conflicts between ideologies that took form or gained adherents in the wake of the
French Revolution. His reactions to the early development of those ideologies and parties, from which he kept
totally aloof, enable us to mark the extent of their growth and dissemination throughout the society. They
also help to remind us that morality and humanity were not novel concomitants of the modern ideologues, as
some superficial partisans of the Romantics occasionally try to imply. Indeed, though Cowper was in every way
unfit to provide a model for surviving in the rough and tumble world of the nineteenth and twentieth
centuries, he can (as I suggested in an earlier review) remind us of qualities and virtues we have lost and
might well seek to foster, as a safety check upon and as a complement to Romantic freedom and
individuality.</p>
          <p>Cowper’s central subject, in these lengthy letters, as in those of the earlier volumes, is
himself and his own simple life and desires. But he has changed his orientation. He is no longer a religious
enthusiast, as in volume I, or simply the man of rural retirement and quiet observation and commentary,
sometimes in occasional poetry, that we encountered in volume II. Now he is the Poet—or even “An Author by
profession . . . ” (p. 311). In this shift, he would seem to be moving in the direction that the Romantics
were to adopt as their central identities. But Cowper does not succumb to the tendency of even the great
Romantics sometimes to place their egos at the center of their value-systems. Cowper, indeed, refuses to make
his imagination or consciousness either a source or the center of values. He accepts himself as a limited
being, neither a paragon in himself nor a model for most other men and women.</p>
          <p>When others called Blake and Shelley mad, they and their admirers retorted that the real madmen
were those running the asylum. Cowper, on the other hand, was very much aware that his grasp upon sanity was
precarious and that he had to struggle to mediate between his desires and ideals and unpleasant realities that
surrounded him. He therefore withdrew to a defensive position that enabled him to control a portion of his
environment, without totally withdrawing from society. Even when he was not under any particular emotional
stress, Cowper (like the late William Ellery Leonard) had a strong phobia about traveling. When Mrs. King, a
correspondent with whom he had developed a strong epistolary friendship but whom he had never seen, asks him
to visit her and her husband, he obliquely tells her that such a trip would be impossible for him: “I am a
strange creature, who am less able than any man living to project any thing out of the common course with a
reasonable prospect of performance. . . . Almost twenty years have I been thus unhappily circumscribed, and
the remedy is in the hand of God only” (p. 400). About two weeks later, he is slightly more explicit with
his old friend and benefactor Joseph Hill: “you must understand that I have not slept from home these 19
years and that I despair of being ever able to do it more” (p. 403). These remarks help to explicate a more
offhand remark to his cousin Lady Hesketh (to whom he had obviously revealed his secret fear) as he prepared
to journey by chaise to visit his friend Charles [Bagot] Chester at nearby Chicheley:
<q>
when I saw this moment a poor old woman coming up the lane, opposite my window, I could not help sighing and
saying to myself—“Poor, but happy old woman! Thou art exempted by thy situation in life from riding in
chaises, and making thyself fine in a morning, happier therefore in my account than I, who am under the cruel
necessity of doing both.” (p. 389)
</q></p>
          <p>Feeling as he did his own limitations, Cowper spent much time in these letters advising two young
university men who came to him during the years covered by this volume and became his admiring friends to
follow practical pursuits and to resist any shyness and fear of novelty or of travel. One of these men, Samuel
Rose, wrote to him as an admirer in 1787 and sent him a copy of Burns’s <hi rend="i">Poems, Chiefly in the
Scottish Dialect.</hi> This unexpected stimulation helped Cowper to break out of six months of depression.
Rose became almost a son to Cowper for a time, to a certain extent comforting him for the loss of William
Unwin, whose death on 29 November 1786 may have precipitated that period of depression. (Cowper mentions Unwin
only three times in this volume.) By the time that Rose’s London legal career—in which Cowper had aided
him by judiciously introducing him to influential friends—and his marriage had left Rose less time to visit
Cowper and to act as amanuensis for the Homeric translations, Cowper had met and taken a
<pb id="p18-149" n="149"/>
warm liking to his young maternal cousin John Johnson, then a student at Cambridge. Johnny, Cowper wrote to
Johnson’s aunt, “I love as if he were my son, and . . . I believe is not unwilling to serve me in that
capacity since I am likely never to have any other” (24 November 1790; p. 431).</p>
          <p>Samuel Rose, the lawyer whom William Hayley hired to defend Blake against the charge of sedition
in January 1804, was not, it seems, a blood relation of John Johnson, as Geoffrey Keynes was led to believe
(see Blake, <hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, ed. Keynes [3rd edition, 1980], pp. xxi, 75-80, and passim). Rather, he
was related to John Johnson and Cowper by more significant intellectual, moral, and humane affinities. When
Blake imagined Rose’s death (late in 1804) and saw “Sweet Rose” entering “into the Celestial City,”
with bells ringing and trumpets sounding to mark his “arrival among Cowper’s Glorified Band of Spirits of
Just Men made Perfect” (Blake, <hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, p. 106), Blake was also linking himself to the
same “great society” of noble men. Significantly, however, Hayley, who formed the strongest link between
Cowper’s circle and Blake, also saw a negative affinity between the two greater poets. Hayley wrote to Lady
Hesketh:
<q>
I have also ever wished to befriend Him [Blake] from a motive, that, I know, our dear angelic Cowper 
<hi rend="i">would approve</hi>, because this poor man with an admirable quickness of apprehension &amp; with
uncommon powers of mind, has <hi rend="i">often appeared to me on the verge of Insanity.</hi> . . . (Blake,
<hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, p. 118)
</q>
Blake, to avoid being relegated to the level of a weak-spirited valetudinarian, whose wife (Haley thought) was
his strongest prop, had to reject the condescending “pity” of this most helpful of his patrons and so
distance himself from Cowper’s memory.</p>
          <p>Even when Cowper identified himself as a “Poet” or “Author,” he kept “art” in
perspective. He had begun to write poetry—just as he had earlier gardened and made furniture—to occupy his
mind and keep it from morbid thoughts. He also enjoyed writing letters to his few friends for the same reason,
and in order to make sure that his correspondents did not forget him, he had always answered his mail promptly
with letters as entertaining as possible. In this volume, having committed himself to translating 
<hi rend="i">The Iliad</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Odyssey</hi> for a large group of subscribers and finding that
most of his time was occupied in constant revision in order to approach the quality that he demanded of
himself (as well as to satisfy the critics to whom he and his publisher sent the early drafts for review),
Cowper necessarily modified his habits by writing all his letters before breakfast, apologizing to his growing
list of correspondents when he had to delay or curtail his replies. And, though he blamed his occupation of
translating for this falling off in his epistolography, he always assumed that he should apologize (e.g.,
“You must know, my dear Rowley, that a man having two great volumes in the Press, is no more master of his
time than the greatest man in the Kingdom . . . ,” p. 458). He never pretended that his correspondents were
imposing upon his valuable time, thereby impeding literary history. Unlike Joyce or other more recent authors,
he did not believe that authorship, of whatever character or quality, licensed a person to use or abuse his
friends and acquaintances.</p>
          <p>In my review of volume II of Cowper’s <hi rend="i">Letters</hi> (<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, 17
[#65, Summer 1983], 26-29), I discussed how poets of Cowper’s social class (which included Wordsworth,
Coleridge, Byron, and Shelley of the later period) began with a gentlemanly ideal of authorship that was
opposed to the commercial attitudes of “authors by trade.” Eventually the great financial success enjoyed
by the poetry of Scott, Byron, Moore, and others forced even Wordsworth and Shelley to deal with the question
of commercial success, if only in a negative sense (by saying that the public taste was debased and predicting
their own vindication by posterity). Cowper, whose small patrimony was being eaten away by daily expenses,
even with the largess of Lady Hesketh, Joseph Hill, and other friends, finally came to count on a monetary
reward for his translations from Homer. He worked hard—and encouraged his friends to work—to secure
subscribers for the edition. And he engaged in what for him was a difficult negotiation with Joseph Johnson,
who bought the rights to the first printing of the edition, leaving Cowper with the copyright (see
particularly pp. 537-40, 542-43, 544-45, and 569). But Cowper retained the basic attitudes of the gentleman
author, in the sense that he devoted extraordinary time and care to every word he published, abjuring the
quick, easy way to make extra money by hurrying through his translations or even through the few reviews he
wrote for Joseph Johnson’s <hi rend="i">Analytical Review</hi>, beginning in 1789 (see pp. 239, 259-61, 277,
etc.).</p>
          <p>One very practical result of Cowper’s concern for his reputation was the meticulous care he
took, not only in composing and correcting his poems, but even in transcribing them for his personal friends.
In two letters of August and September 1788, Cowper transcribes the eleven quatrains of his poem “The Dog
and the Waterlily” (pp. 200-02 and 212-13), and a collation shows that, not only did Cowper make no verbal
changes in the text when he transcribed it three weeks later, but he made very few variations even in
orthography and punctuation. The first text, copied for Lady Hesketh, has no abbreviations, whereas in copying
for his young admirer Samuel Rose, he indulges himself by using the ampersand in place of “and” five times
and by using the alternative form “tho’ ” in place of “though” once. The only other changes alter
five capital letters to lower-case and one lower-case initial letter to a capital (in the title,
“Water-lily” becomes “Water-Lily”), omit one hyphen (“newly-blown” to “newly blown”), and
change a period at the end of the tenth stanza to a semicolon. All other
<pb id="p18-150" n="150"/>
capitalizations and every apostrophe used to indicate that a syllable ought not to be pronounced (e.g.,
“mark’d” and “consid’rate” in the sixth stanza) are identical in the two versions. Editors of
Cowper’s poetry, at least, need not change “accidentals” on the theory that he did not care or failed to
give time to such minutiae. (I am amused at those textual editors—and copy editors—who seem to believe
that their knowledge and concern with the form of a work are automatically greater than those of its
author.)</p>
          <p>James King and Charles Ryskamp deserve our gratitude for their care and faithfulness in
presenting Cowper’s letters just as he wrote them. Because the editors have not interfered with the form of
presentation, we can make such judgments on Cowper’s attitude toward the form of his poetry without having
to consult the original manuscripts each time. Only such diplomatic editions begin to fulfill the needs of the
serious scholar (and who besides large libraries and serious specialist scholars can afford to purchase
editions at these prices?). Naturally, if even Homer sometimes nods, the editors of his translator’s letters
also do. But though my function as a reviewer requires me to mention a few minor problems, I will say again
that the edition has an overall high quality of textual accuracy that is rare even in our age of massive,
cooperative editorial enterprises.</p>
          <p>In collating the texts of a number of letters with the manuscripts in the Carl H. Pforzheimer
Library, I found a few discrepancies that deserve mention, but I found more frequently that the editors had
captured perfectly Cowper’s idiosyncrasies of idiom and orthography where I was at first misled by
superficial appearances. Among the minor oversights I encountered were these: First, the editors give Cowper
the benefit of the doubt occasionally by adding apostrophes where they are appropriate but do not appear in
the manuscript (e.g., in “Book’s” at p. 145, line 26). Second, they sometimes fill in syllables actually
missing from an abbreviated or stylized word (e.g., the “<hi rend="i">ment</hi>” in “Compli<hi
rend="i">ments</hi>” on p. 497, bottom). Third, they occasionally print without brackets letters and even
short words that are actually illegible because marred by seal tears or covered by the seal (e.g., “in” at
p. 184, line 22); sometimes they also record without brackets dates and other information from postmarks that
are, in fact, totally illegible (e.g., the date on the London morning duty stamp on p. 144, where their
inference of “13” may well be an error). Finally, there are a few minor omissions, mistranscriptions, and
palpable typographical errors. In one manuscript Cowper interlined very faintly, with an almost dry pen, the
clause, “were I to send you verse,” (p. 86, line 5, caret between “you” and “which”); those words
apparently did not appear on the photocopy and were omitted from the transcription. On page 497 (line 10),
“above” has been mistranscribed as “about” (but since the whole issue is whether Cowper has “not
about” or “not above” two ounces of cheese left, no great harm results). I have also noted what seem to
be typos—omissions, transpositions, or substitutions of one or two letters of a word—on pages 30, 266,
283, 339, 343, 396, and 573; none of these interferes with Cowper’s clear meaning. In the mass of Cowper’s
words crowded into 600 pages of closely printed text, there must be a few dozen more such minor oversights,
but unless they are of greater moment than any I discovered, they would have no effect on any use I can
imagine for Cowper’s correspondence. More remarkable than these signs of human fallibility is the minute
fidelity with which Cowper’s characteristic capitalizations, spellings, abbreviations, and idioms have been
reproduced throughout the first three volumes.</p>
          <p>The quality of the annotation in this volume, however, does not seem to me to be quite as high as
in the previous two volumes of <hi rend="i">Letters.</hi> In general, the notes become less pertinent and
precise as the subject matter widens from Cowper’s immediate circle to events in the larger political and
social worlds and as the need for biographical reference works yields to the need for comprehension of
historical events and Cowper’s reaction to them. For example, Cowper comments several times on the
Birmingham Riots of 14-17 July 1791 (see pp. 547, 548, 550, and 568), in each case expressing his contempt for
the hoodlums who burned and destroyed in the name of King, Church, and Country. Yet the footnotes at pp. 547
and 568 seem to imply that Cowper considered the riots to be as much the fault of the Nonconformist
sympathizers with the French Revolution as of the Loyalist mob. The sentiments of Mrs. Carter quoted in the
latter note were obviously not what Lady Hesketh had conveyed to Cowper in the letter he was answering, for in
the other three comments, he does not hold the liberals at all to blame for the disturbance. Or, to take a
subtler problem of annotation, on page 275, when Cowper mentions that his friend Mrs. Throckmorton was to be
present “at the Ball at Brooks’s,” we find a long note giving the location and founding date of the
famous London club, but no indication of the real significance of Cowper’s gossip to Lady Hesketh: the
Throckmortons were in the circle of the Prince of Wales and Charles James Fox, who held forth at Brookes’s
during this period. As a rule, Cowper’s letters do not require extensive historical annotation, but his few
political and historical allusions are, therefore, like Jane Austen’s, even more significant than in the
case of a writer who can be assumed to be vitally interested in such things. I have a short list of other
examples of incomplete or erroneous annotations that need not occupy space here, but which I shall send to the
editors.</p>
          <p>Readers of <hi rend="i">Blake/ An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> will, however, be interested in a
valuable supplement to the story of Cowper’s translation of Homer, as it unfolds throughout
<pb id="p18-151" n="151"/>
this volume. Professor James King has published an essay entitled “An Unlikely Alliance: Fuseli as Revisor
of Cowper’s Homer” in <hi rend="i">Neophilologus</hi>, 67 (1983), 468-79, that adds to Cowper’s few
comments on Henry Fuseli’s involvement some quotations from Fuseli’s manuscript letters about his reading
and suggestions for improvements in the translation. This article, together with Cowper’s remarks to and
about Joseph Johnson’s way of sending him manuscripts to read for possible publication, casts light on the
way Johnson—and presumably other bookseller-publishers—conducted business in the 1780’s and 1790’s.
The attentive reader of Cowper’s <hi rend="i">Letters</hi> will learn many other things about authorship and
publication in the period, but let me leave students of Blake with two in the area of technology: Cowper asked
for—and seems to have received—in December 1787 “a new invention, called an everlasting pencil,” which
seems to have been very similar to mechanical pencils of more recent vintage (see pp. 72 and 76). And unless I
am much mistaken, Cowper’s remark to John Johnson on 18 December 1790, “I address you with a new pen, a
great rarity with me, and for which I am indebted to my Lady Cousin” (p. 443), must mean that he wrote with
a steel pen point, rather than a quill—something I would not have thought likely for a person in Cowper’s
rural retirement at that date. (According to the article on “Pen” in the <hi rend="i">Encyclopædia
Britannica</hi>, “Metallic pens, although known since the days of Pompeii, were little used until the 19th
century and did not become common until near the middle of that century.” The article goes on to mention
that Joseph Priestley had such a pen handmade for him in 1780 and to describe “Steel pens made and sold in
London by a man named Wise in 1803. . . .”) Neither of these innovations in writing equipment struck me as
being as novel, however, as some of Cowper’s idiomatic phrases, as when he (addicted to the use of playful
pet names, such as the “Frogs” for the Throckmortons and “Cuzzy-Wuzzy” for Lady Hesketh) addressed
Lady Hesketh, in a term of endearment, as a “gentle Yahoo” (p. 76).</p>
          <p>The copy that Oxford University Press sent for review this time seems to be more sturdily bound
and more physically durable than the copies of volumes I and II about which I complained in the earlier
reviews. Though a reviewer’s single copy remains too small a sample for purposes of valid generalization, I
am delighted to testify to my pleasure in finding improvement in an area that posed a serious problem in the
copies of the two previous volumes that I saw. A British colleague once suggested to me that the reason that
the food in English restaurants remained so abominable, in comparison with the very fine cooking in British
homes of my acquaintance, was simply that the British are too polite to complain about the shoddy goods and
service. Rather than allow major publishers or other institutions in our area of professional interest and
competence to degenerate into the equivalent of Fawlty Towers, it is our individual and collective
responsibility to call their attention to inadequacies that are within their power to correct, assured that
they will consider such advice a favor because those in positions of responsibility really strive to gain the
respect and gratitude of the profession they serve. To find that a problem I pointed out in reviewing previous
volumes (they almost fell apart in one’s hand) has, apparently, been remedied gives me renewed hope for the
return of the World’s Great Age.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
