<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>18.3.warner</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Visual Analogues to Blake’s “The Dog”</title>
        <author n="Warner">Nicholas O. Warner</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1984-85</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1984-85</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">18.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Shelley M. Bennett</name>
              <name>James Bogan</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Christopher Fox</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>W.J.T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Nicholas O. Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1984-85"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_18">
    <body>
      <pb id="p18-140" n="140"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Visual Analogues to Blake’s “The Dog”</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Nicholas O. <name>Warner</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Apart from the poetic text it was meant to illustrate, Blake’s frontispiece to one of William
Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>, “The Dog,” appears to have two curious visual analogues in a
caricature by James Gillray and an emblem by the sixteenth-century Hungarian emblem writer, Joannes Sambucus.
While the primary impetus for the frontispiece comes, of course, from Hayley’s poem, its affinities with the
emblem and caricature suggest that the earlier works had some influence on Blake’s illustration (or perhaps,
even on Hayley’s ballad itself). The pictures in question deal with vastly different issues: the Blake
focuses on a little dog’s faithfulness; the emblem, entitled “Sobriè Potandum,” or “we must drink
soberly,” warns against the evils of drunkenness; the caricature, called “The Republican Rattle-Snake
Fascinating the Bedford Squirrel,” mocks the relationship between two contemporary English politicians,
Charles Fox and Francis Russell, fifth Duke of Bedford. Yet all these designs share the basic feature of a
reptilian beast laying snares for the unwary, and in the case of Blake and Gillray, of such a beast about to
devour an animal falling toward it.</p>
          <p>Blake’s design takes as its subject the climactic moment in Hayley’s sentimental ballad. Here
the faithful Fido, as Hayley calls him, seeing his young master about to dive unwittingly into a crocodile’s
watery lair, saves the youth by deliberately leaping ahead of him into the jaws of the waiting crocodile. The
specific lines Blake depicts are as follows:
<q>
His faithful friend with nobler pace,<lb/>
And not with silent tongue,<lb/>
Outstript his master in the race,<lb/>
And swift before him sprung.<lb/>
<lb/>
Heaven! How the heart of Edward swell’d<lb/>
Upon the river’s brink,<lb/>
When his Brave guardian he beheld<lb/>
A glorious victim sink!<lb/>
<lb/>
(William Hayley, “The Dog,” 11.65-72)
</q>
(The lines given are those of the 1802 version; in 1805, lines 65-66 were slightly altered: “nobler” was
changed to “quicker,” while “not” was changed to “now.”) Blake’s illustrations for these verses
in both the 1802 and 1805 editions of the <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n18" type="note">1</ref> take essentially the same form—we see the canine hero spreadeagled in the
air, as he hurtles kamikaze-fashion toward the crocodile’s cavernous maw; meanwhile his startled master,
seeming to brake himself just in time, looks down from the safety of the cliff on the dismaying scene below
(illus. 1 and 2). For the 1805 edition, Blake engraved a smaller version of the 1802 picture, eliminating the
fanciful border of the earlier engraving, adding the title, “The Dog,” and changing various details in the
background as well as in the positions and expressions of the dog, crocodile and youth. Some of these changes
render the 1805 version more dramatic than the earlier design. In 1805, the fierceness of the confrontation
between dog and crocodile is intensified by their jaws being more bared—Fido is shown barking (or at least
snarling), while the crocodile is less submerged, thus revealing more of his fearsome teeth.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">2</ref> In the later design, the increased height of
the cliff makes Fido’s leap seem all the more courageous. We also see more of Edward’s face in 1805, and
Blake has endowed his features with greater anguish. Uninspired as the designs remain, these alterations not
only increase the drama of the scene, but also accompany a general improvement in the quality of the 
<hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> illustrations. As Robert N. Essick observes, “The five
            <figure n="bb466.2.12.com" id="bb466.2.comb.12" work-copy="bb466.2" rend="db" width="794" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>Blake inv &amp; sc<lb/>
	Publish’d Septr: 9: 1802 by W Blake Felpham</figTranscr>
	<head>1. William Blake.</head>
	<figDesc>“The Dog,” from William Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1802). Courtesy of Henry E.
Huntington Library and Art Gallery, San Marino, California.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p18-141" n="141"/>
plates for a new, octavo edition of Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>, published in 1805, show Blake’s
renewed power, at least on the purely technical level of copy engraving. His abilities as a designer still
seem shackled to a literary context unable to call forth the Blakean sublime, but the tonal and textural
variety of the linear patterns are superior to those of any of the intaglio plates executed in
Felpham.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">1</hi> William Hayley, <hi rend="i">Designs to a Series of Ballads</hi>
(Chichester: J. Seagrave, 1802); and William Hayley, <hi rend="i">Ballads . . . Founded on Anecdotes Relating
to Animals</hi> (Chichester: J. Seagrave, 1805). For detailed physical descriptions of the designs, see David
Bindman, <hi rend="i">The Complete Graphic Works of William Blake</hi> (New York: G.B. Putnam’s &amp; Sons,
1978), pp. 479-80, and Roger R. Easson and Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake, Book Illustrator</hi>
(Normal, Illinois: American Blake Foundation, 1972), I, 31-35, 41-44. For a full account of the entire
Blake-Hayley <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> project, see G.E. Bentley, Jr., “William Blake as Private
Publisher,” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of the New York Public Library</hi>, 61 (1957), 539-60; G.E. Bentley, Jr.,
<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969), pp. 88, 92-98, 100-02, 157-62; and Robert N.
Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake, Printmaker</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1980), pp.
169-73.</note>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Curiously, Blake’s 1802 illustration of a non-barking Fido fits
Hayley’s 1805 text more closely than it does the earlier text, for in 1805 Fido is described as leaping
“<hi rend="i">now</hi> with silent tongue”; the 1805 design, however, shows Fido as he was described three
years before, “<hi rend="i">not</hi> with silent tongue.”</note>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake, Printmaker</hi>, p. 172. Blake himself
understandably says little about these timid designs, though in a letter to Hayley dated 22-25 March 1805,
Blake remarks that “The Subjects I cannot do better than those already chosen, as they are the most eminent
among Animals Viz. The Lion, The Eagle, The Horse, The Dog. Of the Dog Species the Two Ballads are so
preeminent &amp; my Designs for them please me so well that I have chosen that design in our Last Number of
the Dog &amp; Crocodile, &amp; that of the Dog defending his dead Master from the Vultures.” 
<hi rend="i">The Letters of William Blake</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes, 3rd ed. rev. (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1980),
p. 111.</note></p>
          <p>If we turn from the Blake line-engravings to the emblem by Sambucus (number 41 in Sambucus’ 
<hi rend="i">Emblemata</hi>, Antwerp, 1564, reproduced exactly as number 125 in Geffrey Whitney’s <hi rend="i">A
Choice of Emblemes</hi>, Leyden, 1586), we may be surprised to find the same cast of characters as in Blake
and Hayley—a nude young man, a dog, and a threatening crocodile (illus. 3). Sambucus’
            <figure n="bb465.2.1.com" id="bb465.2.comb.01" work-copy="bb465.2" rend="db" width="630" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>Blake. inv &amp; s<lb/>
	The Dog,<lb/>
	Pubd, June, 18, 1805, by R Phillips N 6, Bridge Street. Black Friers.</figTranscr>
	<head>2. William Blake.</head>
	<figDesc>“The Dog,” from William Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> (1805). Courtesy of Henry E.
Huntington Library and Art Gallery, San Marino, California.</figDesc>
</figure>
composition is, however, different from Blake’s. In the emblem, a youth lies on a river bank, drinking from
a bowl; near him, a dog laps gingerly at the water, eyeing a menacing crocodile in the stream. (Sambucus’
text informs us that the dog represents the careful drinker, wary of the poisons of inebriation as imaged by
the crocodile, while the youth signifies the heedless bacchanal who, presumably, will fall prey to the
crocodile’s snares. The water, conveniently enough, represents both the Nile as well as liquids of a more
fermented nature.) For all of their compositional differences, the emblem and Blake’s frontispiece share
several notable details, in addition to having the same characters. In both instances, the crocodile and man
are separated by a body of water in which the beast already finds itself; the dog is closer to the crocodile
than is the man; the crocodile is on the left, the man on the right, with the dog more or less between them;
vague indications of buildings appear in the pictures’ backgrounds; the crocodile is clearly associated with
hidden danger and entrapment. In both cases, moreover, we find a sharp juxtaposition between the levels of
awareness of man and dog—while the youth is carelessly oblivious to danger, the dog is markedly superior to
him in being vigilant and perceptive.</p>
          <p>Given these parallels, it is not unreasonable to suppose that Blake was familiar with Sambucus’
emblem, either through Sambucus’ own <hi rend="i">Emblemata</hi>, or what is more likely for a late
eighteenth/early nineteenth-century British artist, through the famous anthology, <hi rend="i">A Choice of
Emblemes</hi>, compiled by the Englishman Geffrey
<figure n="SobriePotandum.18.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="802">
	<head>3. Joannes Sambucus.</head>
	<figDesc>“Sobriè Potandum,” from Geffrey Whitney’s <hi rend="i">A Choice of Emblemes</hi> (1586).
Courtesy of Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery, San Marino, California.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p18-142" n="142"/>
Whitney. In fact, a Blake-Whitney connection has been persuasively suggested by several scholars<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">4</ref> (though not with regard to the 
<hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> designs). First published in 1586, Whitney’s collection reproduced numerous
Continental emblems with Englished versions of the original texts; the work also contained twenty-three of
Whitney’s own designs and poems.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">5</ref><hi
rend="i">A Choice of Emblemes</hi> established
<figure n="Gillray.RepublicanRattlesnake.18.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="720" height="1000">
	<head>4. James Gillray, “The Republican Rattle-Snake Fascinating the Bedford Squirrel.”</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
</figure>
its editor as the earliest English emblematist, and “it was to Whitney that the first English emblem writers
turned for their model.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">6</ref> Thus it is
highly conceivable that Blake, “steeped in the emblem tradition”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n24" type="note">7</ref> as he was, and almost certainly familiar with other devices from Whitney,
would have known the “SobrièPotandum” design. <note id="n21"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Piloo Nanavutty first
suggested a parallel between Blake and Whitney in “A Title-Page in Blake’s Illustrated Genesis
Manuscript,” <hi rend="i">Journal of the Warburg and Courtauld Institutes</hi>, 10 (1947), 115; in a later
article, Nanavutty pointed to evidence of Whitney as a definite source for some of Blake’s work (e.g. “The
Sick Rose”)—see “Blake and Emblem Literature,” <hi rend="i">JWCI</hi>, 15 (1952), 258-61. For other
connections between Blake and Whitney, see Mary Lynn Johnson, “Emblem and Symbol in Blake,” 
<hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi>, 37 (1974), 151, 153; Judith Wardle, “‘For Hatching Ripe’:
Blake and the Educational Uses of Emblem and Illustrated Literature,” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in
the Humanities</hi>, 81 (1978), 337, 346; and Joseph S. Salemi, “Emblematic Tradition in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi>,” Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly, 15 (1981-82), 108-24. Mentioning
Johnson’s comparison of Blake’s first illustration to the <hi rend="i">Gates of Paradise</hi> with
Whitney’s emblem of a “skull-gathering woman,” Wardle goes on to note that “one might also suggest the
original of this in Johannes Sambucus’ <hi rend="i">Emblemata</hi>” (Wardle, 346); as far as I know, this
is the first reference to a link between Blake and Sambucus. In 1952, Nanavutty listed Sambucus among those
emblematists who did <hi rend="i">not</hi> seem to have influenced Blake (Nanavutty, “Blake and Emblem
Literature,” p. 261).</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Geffrey Whitney, <hi rend="i">A Choice of Emblemes</hi>, ed. Henry Green
(London, 1866, reprinted New York: Benjamin Blom, Inc., 1967, with an introduction by Frank B. Fieler), p.
252. Fieler’s introduction has some useful bibliographical information both on Whitney and on the history of
English emblem books. The “SobrièPotandum” emblem, incidentally, is reproduced not only in this modern
facsimile (number 125, as in Whitney’s original edition), but also in Arthur Henkel and Albrecht Schöne,
<hi rend="i">Emblemata: Handbuch zur Sinnbildkunst des XVI. und XVII. Jahrhunderts</hi> (Stuttgart: J.B.
Mezlersche Verlagsbuchhandlung, 1967), p. 565. While Henkel and Schöne, as well as Mario Praz, in his 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Seventeenth-Century Imagery</hi>, 2nd ed. rev. (Roma: Edizioni di Storia e Letteratura,
1964), both cite instances of crocodiles and dogs throughout Renaissance emblem literature, neither of these
sources indicates any emblem where the two animals appear together, except, as noted only by Henkel and
Schöne, in Sambucus’ (and Whitney’s) “SobrièPotandum.” Green’s edition, moreover, though it
supplies notes for many of Whitney’s emblems, silently passes over number 125, that of the dog and
crocodile.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Rosemary Freeman, <hi rend="i">English Emblem Books</hi> (New York:
Octagon Books, 1948), p. 56.</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Jean Hagstrum, <hi rend="i">William Blake: Poet and Painter</hi> (Chicago:
University of Chicago Press, 1964), p. 53.</note></p>
          <pb id="p18-143" n="143"/>
          <p>Less strikingly similar to the Blake but still suggestive of it in composition is Gillray’s
colored engraving, “The Republican Rattle-Snake Fascinating the Bedford Squirrel.” Published 16 November
1795, Gillray’s caricature depicts the Whig leader Charles Fox as a huge rattlesnake coiled around an oak
tree. Falling out of the tree in a pose quite like that of Blake’s self-sacrificing Fido, and heading
directly toward the snake’s open mouth, is a squirrel with a human head—that of the Duke of Bedford
(illus. 4). The picture, on a topic dear to Gillray, satirizes “the political influence by Fox over Francis,
Duke of Bedford, who had become one of the most zealous of the popular party.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">8</ref> Despite obvious differences, the genuine similarities between
Gillray’s engraving and Blake’s design (the small animal in midflight falling into a reptile’s mouth,
the reptile with open jaws, gazing upwards) lend support to the view that Blake was sufficiently well
acquainted with Gillray’s work to echo certain of the caricaturist’s motifs in his own art.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">9</ref> While in some instances such echoes seem
intentional (as demonstrated by Nancy Bogen—see note 9), there is no evidence of a conscious imitation of
Gillray in “The Dog.” Yet perhaps the similarities are not purely coincidental. Indeed, the parallels
between Blake’s illustration and the Gillray cartoon could partly stem from Blake’s unconscious absorption
of Gillray’s composition long before Blake ever knew he was going to illustrate a poem about a dog and a
crocodile. <note id="n25"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Thomas Wright and R.H. Evans, <hi rend="i">Historical and
Descriptive Account of the Caricatures of James Gillray</hi> (London: Henry G. Bohn, 1851), p. 70; see also M.
Dorothy George, <hi rend="i">Catalogue of Political and Personal Satires</hi> (London: British Museum
Publications, Ltd., 1978), 7, 198.</note>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Intriguing connections between Blake and Gillray have been convincingly
presented by David V. Erdman in his <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire</hi>, 2nd ed. rev. (Princeton:
Princeton University Press, 1969), pp. 203-05, 218-19, and by Nancy Bogen in her “Blake’s Debt to
Gillray,” <hi rend="i">American Notes &amp; Queries</hi>, 6 (Nov. 1967), 35-38. For an earlier version of
Erdman’s discussion, see “William Blake’s Debt to Gillray,” <hi rend="i">Art Quarterly</hi>, 12
(1949), 165-70.</note></p>
          <p>The analogues we have explored here provide further evidence of Blake’s links to Gillray and to
the emblem tradition. Continued investigation of popular art forms such as emblem books and caricatures will
doubtless tell us still more about the breadth of material assimilated by Blake and recast in his own designs,
even when those designs exist primarily to illustrate the words of others.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
