<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>18.3.bogan</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">John Beer, William Blake</title>
        <author n="Bogan">James Bogan</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1984-85</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1984-85</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">18.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Shelley M. Bennett</name>
              <name>James Bogan</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Christopher Fox</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>W.J.T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Nicholas O. Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1984-85"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_18">
    <body>
	<pb id="p18-151" n="151"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">John Beer. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Windsor, Berkshire, England:
Profile Books, 1982. 52 pp. £1.50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">James</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Bogan</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The concept is admirable: a fifty-page booklet on Blake and his works, something more than a
textbook introduction and less than a major study. John Beer’s <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> fits the
outward description but does not provide the essential information needed by the newcomer to Blake. He does
chart Blake’s intellectual life well, making clear the links to Swedenborg and Thomas Taylor. His perceptive
reading of “London” is enhanced by the contrast to an Isaac Watts poem for children which begins:
“Whene’er I take my Walks abroad, / How many Poor I see?” Other comparisons to Watts are interesting but
inappropriate for a general reader.</p>
          <p>After a generation of warnings that Blake’s poems cannot be experienced fully without the
illustrations, I have often felt that the <hi rend="i">words</hi> are now being overlooked in favor of the
pictures, but Beer totally ignores Blake as an artist-engraver. No mention is made of the designs that are
fused to the poems. Perhaps the author was restricted by the format of a “Writers and Their Work” series,
which shows once again that Blake does not submit to categorization without a severe distortion of his
work.</p>
          <p>Attempting to describe <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
briefly is a challenge Blake himself never took up—with good reason. In a book such as this, the task should
be to intrigue the reader and provide a few landmarks
<pb id="p18-152" n="152"/>
by which to explore the <hi rend="i">terra incognita</hi> of the epics. Although Urizen is characterized
deftly, everyone else gets short shrift. All that is said about Los is that in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,
“Los is now the hero.” The balance of creative and destructive forces in Blake’s works needs fuller
exposition.</p>
          <p>The bibliography is problematic since Blake’s works are given without indication of the number
of editions he printed or the variation in plate arrangement, a fact that should not be left out even for a
neophyte. The list of critical works is fairly complete but indifferently annotated.</p>
          <p>In 1799 the Reverend Dr. Trusler insulted Blake by suggesting that the artist needed someone to
“elucidate” his ideas. Blake rejoined: “That which can be made Explicit to the Idiot is not worth my
care.” As teachers of Blake we are on perilous ground unless our own instruction is calculated to “rouze
the faculties [of our students] to act.” In bringing a class beyond <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi> (and back again) it does help to set up some guideposts and do some unabashed elucidating, but I do
not believe the day should be spent in endless distinctions between shadows and spectres. Blake’s
picture-poems work magic if they are experienced visually and aurally. For those who need explanation without
oversimplification I still recommend Albert Roe’s chapter on “Blake’s Symbolism” in <hi rend="i">The
Illustrations to the Divine Comedy</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1953). After that, as they say
on the shores of Lake Udan Adan, you are on your own.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
