<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>18.3.paley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">Further Thoughts on Night Thoughts</title>
        <author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1984-85</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1984-85</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">18.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Shelley M. Bennett</name>
              <name>James Bogan</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Christopher Fox</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>W.J.T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Nicholas O. Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1984-85"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_18">
    <body>
	<pb id="p18-183" n="183"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-3-0008">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Further Thoughts on <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Morton D. <name>Paley</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>John Grant’s discussion article falls into three parts: a consideration of the reliability of
the published <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> reproductions, some new information and conjecture, and a
defense of his mode of interpreting the designs. On the first subject, there is little more to be said.
Comparing these reproductions against the originals in the British Museum Print Room was the most depressing
experience I have ever had as a book reviewer. How the Clarendon Press, one of the world’s few truly great
scholarly publishers, came to accept such poor work is beyond my comprehension; that they did dismays me as it
does many others. There is no point in quibbling about this, as Grant concedes the major objections that his
reviewers have made.</p>
          <p>Regarding the new material in Grant’s essay, I am concerned about three matters. One is the
reversal of images from water color to engraving in some instances, something that has a fairly simple
explanation. If we imagine Blake’s procedure, we can see that when he executed the water colors he had no
idea as to whether the pictures finally selected for engraving would be on recto or verso pages. He could only
know, with the obvious exception of title pages, whether the pictures were recto or verso in the edition that
he in effect created by using Dodsley’s printed pages. However, since Edwards’ letterpress would have been
printed first and the leaves later passed through a plate printer’s press,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">1</ref> Blake would have known whether the pictures to be engraved
were to be recto or verso simply by counting lines. The text was not centered on the page but was offset to
the left on recto pages and to the right on verso pages wherever there were illustrations. This was in
accordance with standard book production procedures of the period—a subject of which Grant takes little
cognizance. In some instances, therefore, reversal was necessary for formal reasons. <hi rend="i">All the
designs that were reversed in engraving were on pages that had to be changed from recto to verso or vice
versa</hi>, as follows: 14, 20, 24, 31, 87, 94, 99, 121, 125, 143, 148, and 153—a total of twelve engravings
out of the forty-three published. <note id="n32"><hi rend="s">1</hi> This was of course the usual printing
procedure, in this instance illustrated by the existence of a copy of the Edwards edition bearing only the
letterpress. See G.E. Bentley, Jr., “Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (London: R. Edwards, 1797):
A New Unillustrated State,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An <corr type="emend">Illustrated</corr> Quarterly</hi>, 14
(1980), 34-35.</note></p>
          <p>The incredible theory that the <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 6 water color <hi rend="i">followed</hi> the
engraving is one of those mare’s nests too frequently encountered in the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
edition (“grotesque coloration,” as Grant now admits, being another). All the differences that Grant notes
between <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 6 and engraving 1E are there—and all can be accounted for by Mr. Blake’s
revising and re-revising on the copper plate using his burnisher. Blake was if anything unusually fecund in
his improvisations on the plate. No <hi rend="i">ur-NT</hi> 6 is necessary to account for changes in the
mother’s nose or in the angels’ hands or in any of the other details that Grant mentions. We normally
assume that drawing precedes engraving unless it can be proved otherwise; by this assumption we now know the
New Zealand set of <hi rend="i">Job</hi> to have been produced by someone other than Blake, since engraving
preceded drawing in this instance, as Bo Lindberg has shown. As if to becloud the issue, Grant laboriously
proves that the state of the engraving that obviously is the first state is—the first state. At this point,
a careful reperusal of Essick’s <hi rend="i">William Blake Printmaker</hi> would be in order.</p>
          <p>Third, did Blake color <hi rend="i">any</hi> copy of the Edwards edition? There is no certain
proof that he did. From time to time the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> editors admit this, yet
<pb id="p18-184" n="184"/>
Grant says that “Type I colored copies are normally <hi rend="i">not</hi> by Blake” (emphasis his) and
that “Type II colored copies” are “probably not by Blake.” No one doubts this, yet there is something
about the peculiar wording that makes one sense in these references to a classification system itself
seriously open to question an insinuation that <hi rend="i">some</hi> copy actually was colored by Blake. This
is the time to assert that for all we know Blake may have colored one or more copies of the Edwards 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, but it has never been proved that he did so. Again, the New Zealand set of 
<hi rend="i">Job</hi> ought to offer a cautionary example.</p>
          <p>Last comes the question of a general approach to Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi> In
my 1969 essay I offered one perspective: that the designs reflect in many ways the system of Zoas and
Emanations that Blake was beginning to conceive for <hi rend="i">Vala.</hi> Grant rather over-simplifies my
argument in his comments, but I will leave it for the reader to judge its usefulness.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">2</ref> But Grant also challenges me to <hi rend="i">disprove</hi>
his schematization of the first Night’s illustrations in <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms
Dramatic.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">3</ref> At first this seems
rather hard, since Grant also says that the schematization really depends on his commentary on all 537
designs—a commentary to which, if it exists, I have certainly had no opportunity to refer. Nevertheless, let
me offer one instance from “Envisioning the First <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>,” comprising water
colors 13-17, designated by Grant as Group III, and entitled by him “The Circle of Destiny and Edward
Young.” <note id="n33"><hi rend="s">2</hi> “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>: an Exploration of
the Fallen World,” <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays for S. Foster Damon</hi>, ed. Alvin H. Rosenfeld
(Providence, R.I.: Brown University Press, 1969), pp. 131-57.</note>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">3</hi> “Envisioning the First <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman and John E. Grant (Princeton, N.J.:
Princeton University Press, 1970), pp. 304-35.</note></p>
          <p>No. 13, showing a winged boy emerging from the cracked Mundane Shell is called “Male
Aspiration” by Grant, although we know that the meaning Blake attached to the very similar image in 
<hi rend="i">For Children</hi> (no. 6, plate 8) was birth: “At length for hatching ripe he bursts the shell.”
Furthermore, since each of Grant’s “units” in Night I must begin with “a major incursion into the
scene of a superhuman character from another realm of existence,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n35" type="note">4</ref> this image must become one! Even Grant admits that in this case “the
symmetry is complicated by the fact”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36"
type="note">5</ref>—but in this case is there any symmetry at all? <note id="n35"><hi rend="s">4</hi>
“Envisioning the First <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>,” p. 308.</note>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">5</hi><hi rend="i"> Ibid.</hi></note></p>
          <p>The caption “Young’s Distractions” certainly could apply to <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 14, where
the picture shows the poet dreaming his dreams in accordance with Young’s text. But no. 15, which shows the
poet looking into an open grave under a cypress tree is not so clearly one of “Young’s Distractions,”
unless this term is to be trotted out for every graveyard contemplation in this Graveyard poem. As for 16, the
young woman rising from a broken egg shell does obviously relate to no. 13, but as a parallel image of birth,
not of Grant’s superimposed “Female Aspiration.” Young’s own lines on this page are in fact very close
to Blake’s <hi rend="i">For Children</hi> caption:
<q>
Embryos we must be, till we burst the Shell,<lb/>
Yon ambient, azure shell, and spring to Life . . .
</q>
And why isn’t <hi rend="i">this</hi> “a major incursion into the scene of a superhuman character from
another realm of existence”? Because it doesn’t begin one of Grant’s “units”?</p>
          <p>In 17 we see a caterpillar-man inside a chained circle, looking at himself in a mirror while a
female figure looks on appalled. This is Blake’s image of the spiritual condition of Young as described on
this <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> page:
<q>
How, like a Worm, was I wrapt round and round<lb/>
In silken thought, which reptile <hi rend="i">Fancy</hi> spun,<lb/>
Till darken’d <hi rend="i">Reason</hi> lay quite clouded o’er . . .
</q>
This is <hi rend="i">Young’s</hi> error; there is no convincing reason to designate it as “Masculine
Error” or to pair it with 16 as a sub-group called “Female Aspiration, Masculine Error.” Nor does the
title “The Circle of Destiny and Edward Young” appear particularly useful when applied to the entire
“unit,” even if one accepts Grant’s simplistic definition of the Circle of Destiny (“promising new
beginnings fade away into ancient errors and perennial frustrations”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n37" type="note">6</ref>) or perhaps <hi rend="i">especially</hi> if one accepts this definition,
since if the term “Circle of Destiny” is to be used for every such <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
situation, it is not going to mean very much. (Incidentally, it’s strange to find an author who objects so
strenuously to the presence of Zoas and Emanations in the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> series here
employing a term Blake uses only in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>) <note id="n37"><hi rend="s">6</hi>
“Envisioning the First <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>,” p. 318.</note></p>
          <p>It would be tedious to go on. These five pictures don’t compose a “unit” in any meaningful
sense. Grant’s schematization has never gained currency among Blake scholars first of all because of its
arbitrariness and secondly for what may be an even more important reason. Viewing the <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> series as a huge linear construction to be divided into linear sub-compartments, each with its
own catchy title is an enormous disservice to Blake’s artistic accomplishment. It is as if Blake were to be
conceived as a Urizenic plodder spinning out his pictorial themes like the caterpillar man of 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 16. Is such a model as this really to serve for the projected “Commentary” on 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>? If so, the text volume of this edition is likely to prove as great a
disappointment as the plates have been.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
