<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>18.3.grant</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">A Re-View of Some Problems in Understanding Blake’s Night Thoughts</title>
        <author n="Grant">John E. Grant</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1984-85</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1984-85</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">18.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Shelley M. Bennett</name>
              <name>James Bogan</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Christopher Fox</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>W.J.T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Nicholas O. Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1984-85"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_18">
    <body>
	<pb id="p18-155" n="155"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-3-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">DISCUSSION</hi></hi>
          </title>
          <title type="section-subtitle">
            <hi rend="b">with intellectual spears &amp; long winged arrows of thought</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">A Re-View of Some Problems in Understanding Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi></hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">John E.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Grant</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>I. On the Reproductions in the Clarendon Edition</title>
            </head>
            <p>Like other scholars, the editors of the Clarendon edition of Blake’s water colors and
engravings for <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> were disappointed with the overall quality of the 800
reproductions in our massive two-volume edition published in 1980. Neither the color nor the black and white
reproductions are, on average, commendable, though neither their shortcomings nor those of the lengthy, mostly
factual Introduction should be seriously misleading, particularly for readers who are aware that in most art
books the reproductions are untrustworthy. Our edition has been fortunate to have received some of the most
detailed reviews ever devoted to an edition of Blake’s pictures. My aim in this response is not to defend
the Clarendon edition where it is indeed deficient but to clarify standards and deviations from them.</p>
            <p>I believe the broader descriptive and interpretive issues I shall discuss should be aired now,
before our projected commentary is completed. I shall first examine instances—some critiques of the
reproductions, others of the editorial matter—in which the edition is not, in fact, deficient in the ways or
to the extent alleged. In the second part of this essay, I shall discuss some key pictures in the 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> series that require more thorough exposition than they have received heretofore.
The commentary, when it finally appears, will not be the proper forum for detailed discussion of several
points I shall raise. Furthermore, some of the issues I shall address extend beyond the specific problems of
the Clarendon edition of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> to larger questions of how Blake’s visual works
can be presented and understood. This re-view of the Clarendon edition should make it easier for readers to
use the edition in ways that will advance scholarship on Blake’s most extensive project of pictorial
criticism.</p>
            <p>For two reasons I have not attempted to develop a committee defense of the Clarendon edition.
First, despite our numbers, the Clarendon editors—E.J. Rose, M.J. Tolley, D. V. Erdman, and I—do not
constitute a party. Though my fellow editors are aware of my thinking, they have not endorsed this text as a
joint position paper. Second, it is easier from a single point of view to establish the necessary distinctions
between the <hi rend="i">kinds</hi> of problems in the edition and specific allegations of inadequacy that
have erroneously been made by reviewers. I shall freely acknowledge many shortcomings in the edition which I
had much responsibility for designing—some of which seem to have escaped the notice of reviewers.</p>
            <p>The Clarendon edition has been reviewed at length by distinguished Blake scholars, and these
reviews have greatly expanded the volume of significant commentary on the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
designs. Detlef Dörrbecker’s exceptionally specific negative review in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (1982)
offers a detailed set of assertions as to where the reproductions went wrong and judges that the Introduction
suffers as a result of too great a fondness for Blake’s work. Dörrbecker’s concluding quotation—of some
severe thoughts on scholarly procedures I had written years ago in the first volume of this journal—suggests
that he intended to stimulate corrective debate about matters of fact and interpretation. Other especially
noteworthy critiques include Morton D. Paley’s detailed, somewhat less unfavorable review (1982) and W.J.T.
Mitchell’s decidedly unfavorable review (1982), which addresses some interpretative problems. These may be
weighed against such favorable reviews as those by Jean H. Hagstrum (1982) and Karen Mulhallen (1981). In the
aggregate, the reviews
<pb id="p18-156" n="156"/>
which I have duly listed in my Bibliography offer a fair indication of the capacities of the present Blake
community to deal with Blake’s most extensive project in visionary criticism.</p>
            <p>For most purposes all reproductions, especially of water colors—even when they can be given a
clean bill of health—are valuable chiefly to jog the memories of those who already know what the actual
pictures look like. I have checked all the complaints made by Dörrbecker and Paley against the reproductions
in the Clarendon edition. But since it is unlikely that the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> plates will ever
be redone by Clarendon, and since it is certain that exhaustive disputes about many of such data could only
concern Blake scholars engaged in a project involving essentially all the pictures, I shall not attempt to
chart each of the alleged shortcomings and my evaluations of them. Dörrbecker’s diligence in commenting on
the quality of sixty-nine reproductions in the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> edition has not resulted in a
large enough percentage of valid objections and corrections to be trustworthy or generally useful. Due to such
procedural errors as color-averaging, he is wrong from onethird to two-thirds of the time. Often when the
reproduction in question is not satisfactory, the problem lies less with a single color that may be in some
degree defective in a number of reproductions than with an inadequate color balance in individual
reproductions that are comparable in only the most general way to others that show much the same color. Even
if a green, say, that is similar in two original pictures is badly rendered in the reproductions, this error
may make much more difference in one case than another because of such factors as the size and position of the
color area or the quality of the other colors. Paley, who follows a similar method of reporting individual
colors, is not much more successful than Dörrbecker in presenting a reliable analysis of the real problems in
the reproductions. The basic question for the reproduction of a Blake picture is whether the viewer can
construe enough to recognize what it is supposed to be about. Normally the Clarendon edition provides at least
that much. Judged as a reference volume, it is adequate for most purposes. For example, commentary in the 1972
and 1976 theses by Hill and Mulhallen, both of which I have been able to read only recently, would have been
more effective if the authors had been able to consult the 1980 Clarendon edition.</p>
            <p>In order to evaluate the quality of Dörrbecker’s opinions about the adequacy of
reproductions, it is necessary to consider the standards he seems to have in mind. Unlike Paley, who declares
that he checked the Clarendon reproductions against the originals, Dörrbecker admits that he is judging by
other criteria. Naturally, comparing the reproductions with the originals should help in evaluating their
quality, but, perhaps surprisingly, such checking may not be either necessary nor sufficient for a reliable
report. Though I have not laid eyes on the actual <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> watercolors since 1978, I
am confident that I can judge well enough from slides, photographs, and notes for the project whether the
qualities of at least most of the reproductions sufficiently resemble those of the originals to pass muster.
There is no point in asking (as we would of the Trianon facsimiles of the Gray designs) whether a
well-informed viewer could easily distinguish between the original and the facsimile if these were placed side
by side. The basic question is whether the reproduction resembles the original enough to indicate all the
details of the picture in monochrome shades or in colors as much like those of the original as possible. And
that the qualities be not misrepresented—as when washes are rendered opaque—or that the color balance not
be rendered repugnant with ugly hues.</p>
            <p>While it is always best to vet reproductions in the presence of the originals, much reporting
of such a multifarious set of pictures breaks down either because it is based on a bewildered vision or
results from an erroneous translation into words. Clear evidence of this kind of error occurs in the chief
specific criticism by Welch and Viscomi (1981)—the latter of whom checked the originals. They discuss the
color reproduction of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 81 (III, 6), a design made familiar as engraved 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 25E (p. 46): it depicts a beautiful woman among bleak hills pursued by the pall of Death,
probably at sundown. Welch and Viscomi prescribed these corrections: “the greens should be bright, the rose
wash of the hills should be glowing, the yellow streaks should be bright lime, the body white, and the sky
lighter” (p. 539). The first and last two stipulations are roughly correct, but the second and third are
simply wrong: there is no “rose wash” on the <hi rend="i">hills</hi> though this wash is indeed missing in
the reproduction of the sunset sky. And the only real yellow in the picture occurs in the sunset streaks in
the sky, where “lime” naturally has no place. Such descriptive errors abound in other reviews that also
purport to be specific.</p>
            <p>It is easy to set an impossibly high standard of expectation, as Dörrbecker often does in
complaining when the pictures are only a little off. At times he is just plain wrong by any standard, as when
he laments that “the brilliance and intensity of the varied hues of green . . . are lost almost completely
in the color reproduction from <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 30” (I, 25) (p. 132). In fact, there is no
green whatever in Blake’s water color and probably never was. In about half the cases Dörrbecker complains
about, however, there is indeed something seriously amiss in the reproduction. He rightly objects (p. 137, n.
8) to the monochrome reproduction of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 264 (illus. 2), the frontispiece for the
second volume in which the designs were originally bound. Both as it appears in its place in the series and
              <pb id="p18-157" n="157"/>
<figure n="BUT330.1.2.WC" rend="file" width="789" height="1000">
	<head>1. <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 1, Frontispiece, Volume I, by permission of the Trustees of the
British Museum.</head>
</figure>
<pb id="p18-158" n="158"/>
again, enlarged to slightly greater than actual size on the back of the dust jacket of the first volume of the
Clarendon edition, the monochrome reproduction of this scene of Jesus the Awakener at the Resurrection renders
one of the two recumbent soldiers practically invisible. Given the prominence of this reproduction—I myself
chose it for the dust jacket, though, as usual without benefit of monochrome proofs—it would seem fair to
attack its shortcomings as typical of the edition. But Dörrbecker goes on to compare the 1980 reproduction
unfavorably with the one in the great 1927 Keynes-edited Harvard University Press portfolio of thirty 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> reproductions, which he judges to have been reproduced “to perfection.”
Indeed it was, within the capacity of monochrome reproduction. Oddly and unfairly, however, Dörrbecker
neglects to point out that <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 264 is clearly reproduced in color in the
Clarendon edition—as the forty-first color plate (alas, uncaptioned but cross-referenced). Paley, who also
rightly criticized the monochrome, did take notice of the fact that “it came out much better in color”
(1982, p. 680). In the color reproduction all three figures and the clouds above and below are as plainly
visible as they are in the original. It should be understood, however, that the large areas of black or dark
gray in Blake’s picture are rendered in the reproduction as dark violet or brown. These non-corresponding
hues are the best pidgin English for black achieved in much modern color reproduction.</p>
            <p>Dörrbecker cannot resist remarking how much better the 1927 Harvard edition reproduced
Blake’s work than the 1980 Clarendon edition, even though he is also at pains to point out that the former
was reproduced in collotype, “a printing technique which progress has now almost put beyond price for
publishers and their consumers.” The real issue is not what may have been technologically or institutionally
possible fifty-three years earlier but whether better work could actually have been published in 1980. For the
forty years that Harvard University Press kept the Keynes edition of five-hundred copies in print, copies were
sold for $35 each (the price was never raised). At 1927 prices, in other words, and at the ratio of
twenty-five monochromes to five color collotypes, it would have cost $630 to publish a complete portfolio of
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> watercolors—leaving out of consideration the extensive presentation of
graphic works and drawings (and the lengthy Introduction) included in the 1980 Clarendon edition. The Harvard
portfolio appeared during a period when an uncolored copy of the 1797 edition could be purchased for $20 to
$100; also when—as a fluke, to be sure—a defective engraved copy, with sixteen pages undoubtedly colored
by Blake, sold for £5 (see Clarendon edition, p. 69). The 1980 publication price for the Clarendon edition,
£150 or $365, does not therefore seem entirely out of line. At least the large format requires only moderate
reduction of the page size and leaves the text of Young’s poem perfectly legible. And an idea of both the
aesthetic and conceptual presence of the exceptionally large type of the 1742-1745 printed pages of Young’s
poem, which accompany the watercolors, needs to be communicated to the viewer in a complete edition. To be
able to get out of Blake’s pictures what Blake put into them, in short, you must be able to read Young’s
text, whether or not the verse accords with modern taste. This is an important aspect of the designs that is
possible, if expensive, to communicate in a large-format edition.</p>
            <p>Dörrbecker chose at the outset of his review to distance himself rhetorically from “Blake
enthusiasts” and “their worshipped hero” and his remarks are punctuated throughout by what Blake would
have recognized as similar “Grecian mocks,” both against the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> series
itself and the efforts of the Clarendon editors to convey in writing something of the overall excellence of
Blake’s accomplishment. I cannot, of course, hope to improve Dörrbecker’s taste for Blake, but I am
confident that if the properly attuned reader puts in the time required to study the original watercolors—a
matter of months rather than weeks—he or she will not be satisfied with Bindman’s commonsense opinion,
commended by Dörrbecker (see pp. 130 and 137, n. 3), that Blake, while on the <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> project, must have been frequently off his form because producing the pictures was such a vast
and toilsome undertaking. Remarks in this vein, particularly as they operate as half-stated principles in
Reynolds’s <hi rend="i">Discourses</hi>, infuriated Blake, not simply because Blake was a self-professed
enthusiast, but because, <hi rend="i">faute de mieux</hi>, it elevates Prudence to the status of the mother of
the Muses. Of course, there is a sense in which any grand artistic project is more subject to failure than a
humble one, and large-scale failure is more embarrassing. Yet rightly considered, as I shall maintain
elsewhere, Blake has no need to fear comparison with his artistic masters, Michelangelo and Raphael, even if
he did not attempt to improve on their drawing, as Andrea del Sarto is said to have thought he could.</p>
            <p>A few of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs were not seriously worked up, e.g.,
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 219 (VI, iv), or well-conceived, e.g., <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 259 (VI, 38), but ninety
percent are at least fine pictures and convey a critically interesting response to Young’s frequently
amorphous poetry. And there are some great pictures, such as the title pages for Nights Three and Eight, 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 78 (illus. 3) and 345 (illus. 6); both of which I shall discuss below. It is also important
that most of the water colors are still fresh, not having suffered from overexposure to light as has been the
fate of too many of Blake’s other pictures. In consequence, it is particularly unfortunate that most of the
color reproductions in the Clarendon edition are dead, lacking the vibrancy that it is possible to convey
<pb id="p18-159" n="159"/>
in color reproduction, for example in Butlin’s 1978 Tate Gallery exhibition catalogue of <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> 78.</p>
            <p>Dörrbecker interestingly attributes the lack of vitality in the Clarendon color reproductions
to the choice of cream-colored paper for printing. Quite possibly this was a contributing factor, but it is
apparent that the Yale University Press choice of a much whiter paper for Butlin’s 1981 catalogue was not
sufficient to have resulted in satisfactory color reproductions. The worst of the Clarendon color
reproductions, say <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 117 (IV, 8), despite its wretched pinks, is no worse than
and probably not as bad as the entire run of twenty-six designs (now in the Huntington Art Gallery and
forbidden by the terms of the bequest from ever traveling) for <hi rend="i">Comus, Paradise Lost</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">On the Morning of Christ’s Nativity</hi>, as they are reproduced in color in the Yale catalogue
(pls. 616-23; 632-43; 666-71). Essick (1982, p. 24) has also noted the inadequate rendering of the Huntington
Milton pictures. The ambient blues that distort these reproductions bear no relation whatever to the present
condition of the Huntington pictures, which is, of course, all a modern edition aims to reproduce. They are
not, we should understand, attempts at photographic restoration of the blues that have probably been lost
through overexposure to light of the original pictures; they are simply accidents of the sort that occur in
most art books. One who compares the reproduction of Huntington <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> 5, 
<hi rend="i">Satan Watching the Endearments of Adam and Eve</hi> in Butlin 1981, pl. 636 (cat. 529.5) with its
counterpart in Behrendt 1983 (plate 9) might be forgiven for supposing that they represent two different Blake
pictures. Could there be two opinions as to which is adequate, which not?</p>
            <p>Dörrbecker makes a number of appreciative comments about the utility and design of the
Clarendon edition which may, from a user’s rather than an editor’s point of view, be amplified. The
inconvenience of working with this large number of atlas-scale water colors—to say nothing of the widely
dispersed books of colored engravings—has retarded the development of scholarship on the series. It is fair
to say that the water colors are now more accessible in the Clarendon edition than they have ever been before,
especially since 1970, when (for justifiable reasons), the British Museum enclosed each of the 269
sheets—all but three of which bear water colors on both sides—in rigid, heavy envelopes of Perspex, a
plastic similar to Lucite. Even if one is permitted into the gallery of the Department of Prints and Drawings
to handle the thirty-one heavy storage boxes directly, without dependency on having them delivered by one of
the ever-attentive assistants, often what should be a simple matter of checking one design against another
becomes a time-consuming research project that has to be carried on in too little space. Understandably, the
twenty-odd laminated sheets in each box are sometimes out of sequence or otherwise misplaced. Moreover,
research was probably not much easier even when the sixteen-inch designs were in the original pair of enormous
leather volumes to which they were attached by being inlaid in nineteen-inch paper. Probably the pages had
been incorrectly sequenced for Edwards when they were placed in the original bindings—as they certainly were
when Shields described many of them in 1880. But the separation of the mounting leaves when the designs
entered the British Museum in 1928 was not a satisfactory solution either, for reasons not wholly apparent
until one tries to work with them.</p>
            <p>The problem of accessibility, which is closely connected with the problem of comprehension of
the intended arrangement, has been partly solved by the large format of the Clarendon edition. On the whole I
do not regret the decision to publish such a ponderous book, which one reviewer has weighed as twenty pounds.
The 14½-inch Clarendon page is indeed cumbersome, particularly in the second volume, which contains all the
color plates and graphic works and thus weighs twice as much as the first volume. One needs an inordinately
large work area to have both volumes and Butlin’s catalogue and other reference books, together with slides
and notes, open and ready to consult at the same time. Some of the editors wished to include the proofs for
the engravings at the end of the first volume, both to facilitate comparison and to balance the volumes, and
would have preferred to enlarge the pictures to extend to the edge of the paper—as Blake did in the water
colors after Night the First and intended to do in all the engravings. But since publishers and editorial
teams must work together by compromising, with cost and feasibility always at issue, this was not to be.
Dörrbecker finds “those beautiful wide margins” (p. 136) one of the features of the Clarendon edition
that he can wholeheartedly praise. I consider the margins an aesthetic and scholarly nuisance, a barrier
against free access to a major critical and artistic accomplishment. They are useful only for taking
notes—for those who can afford to write in such an expensive edition.</p>
            <p>Yet even if the Clarendon edition had been altered in every possible way, it could not have
provided convenient access to all important aspects of Blake’s designs: other study devices are necessary as
well. The poorquality Microform transparencies from the E.P. Group of Companies can be used as reminders of
what the color looks like. But slides are too small to be seen clearly when they are displayed on a light
tray; the new kinds of magnifying slide viewers, however, can be quite helpful. The scholar also needs to have
photographs small enough to arrange and rearrange in order to discover the sequences or “chapters” of from
two to a dozen designs that Blake arranged as sub-structures in each of the nine Nights. At present I am
developing a computer-indexed
              <pb id="p18-160" n="160"/>
<figure n="BUT330.1.264.WC" rend="file" width="796" height="1000">
	<head>2. <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 264, Frontispiece, Volume II, by permission of the Trustees of the
British Museum.</head>
</figure>
<pb id="p18-161" n="161"/>
videodisc that will allow immediate access to all the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs, in any order
desired. This new technology should help considerably in solving the old problem of access which has certainly
limited the effective critical attention devoted to this great series.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>II. Interpretation</title>
            </head>
            <p>Let us turn from problems of adequate reproduction and access to Blake’s pictures of 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> to the question of interpretation, of understanding what Blake intended to convey
about Young and the ways of imagination. I am well aware that some readers will doubt whether such a
formulation of the interpretive question has much value or interest. To refer to “intention” may appear to
bespeak preoccupation with what is, either in a short run or a long run, indeterminate. Or if perhaps
determinate, of little more significance than some alternate scheme that may occur to an active mind that
takes a number of Blake’s pictures together with some lines from Young as an occasion for reverie or as
illustrations of a thesis about Neoclassic or Romantic art. While this is not a comprehensive or fair account
of the theoretical alternatives, I believe that some discourse about Blake and Young has been animated by such
insouciant premises.</p>
            <p>Those committed to ascertaining Blake’s intentions must be concerned with matching words and
pictures with pictures in order to decide who is who and what Blake made of pictorial resemblances that
confirm or contradict what Young seems to have been saying. The best evidence is usually to be found among the
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> pictures considered as a coordinated program of visual commentary rather than
somewhere else in the Blakean oeuvre, though we normally expect that implications in accord with “Blake’s
philosophy” will probably be the ones intended. After long study I have concluded that the 537 water colors
for <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> were arranged or organized in a significant sequence of pictorial units
or visual chapters within each of the Nine Nights of Young’s poem. These usually consist of from two to a
dozen pictures expressive of a leading idea or theme, often demarcated quite sharply from the other units that
precede or follow them. It would be hard to deny that Blake’s next project, the designs for Gray’s poems,
which are also executed on the same kind of drawing paper surrounding the poetical texts, are organized in
this fashion, but of course the units of Gray’s poetry are far more concise and determinate than is the case
with Young.</p>
            <p>Some current theories in art criticism tend to discourage critics from attempting to recognize
Blake’s visual sequences either in the program for <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> or elsewhere. The tide
of taste that is now running against the great scholar (not of Blake, to be sure), E.H. Gombrich, is not
interested in claims for pictorial programs. What such viewers want to know is what the pictures may be taken
to imply about Blake the artist or the member of the working class. They prefer to think of the pictures as
the expressions of Blake’s feelings about “Life, Death, and Immortality” and anything else that might
have come into the mind of the artist rather than as an intelligible pictorial commentary. I can have no hope
of persuading those who would respond “yes” to the following question: do you deny that Michelangelo’s
set of pictures in the Sistine ceiling constitute a program? Those who do not deny it may still find it
difficult to say exactly why the central sequence concludes with the <hi rend="i">Drunkenness of Noah</hi>,
but they do not doubt that Michelangelo demanded a viewer who would make the effort to understand the
arrangement.</p>
            <p>After surveying the literature on Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs we can see
that attempts to ascertain the chief patterns in the overall arrangement of the pictures seem questionable for
two reasons: first, Young’s poem is associative rather than tightly structured; this leads the viewer to
expect the “illustrations” to be likewise disorderly. Second, the commonsense assumption that Blake was so
out of sympathy with Young and so burdened by the sheer numbers of pictures required to accompany the 526
pages of printed text that he must have struggled adventitiously to come up with some picture to fill the
blank surrounding paper for every page. If these attitudes indeed predominated in Blake’s mind, one would
hardly expect to find in the pictures consistent quality or order. This would lead to the suspicion that Blake
was using the project mainly as an excuse for bootlegging in his own supposed “system” rather than wasting
his energies on illustrating the unworthy Young. How natural, then, for the critic to deploy an abstract of
Blake’s monomyth derived from <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> in
such a way as to indicate that he was again chiefly concerned to tell the same “one story only” in the 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs!</p>
            <p>Thus, Paley (1969) declared the applicability of a pattern of “creation, fall, redemption,
and apocalypse,” Frye’s summary of “Blake’s central myth” (p. 140, referring to <hi rend="i">Fearful
Symmetry</hi>, p. 124). If you follow Paley’s account closely, however, you will find that it is largely his
critical rhetoric that fills the vacuum of “creation.” And as for the “fall,” while there are scenes
that recall the Temptation in the Garden of Eden, it is not clear that they are supposed to be an adequate
explanation of the causes of the richly imagined desperate state of the world in the designs or in the poem.
Even Young’s pietistic mind was not satisfied to regard all misery under the aspect of “The Fall.” When
Blake wished his viewer to think continuously of “The Fall,” as in <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi>, he began by presenting a picture of
<pb id="p18-162" n="162"/>
the Expulsion on the title page.</p>
            <p>Look again at the water color frontispieces for the two volumes of <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi>: both <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 1 (illus. 1) and <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 264
(illus. 2) are scenes of the Resurrection. This is the context Blake provided for a consideration of his 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> series. You can, of course, argue that, without the Fall, the Resurrection would
not have been a possibility or necessity. Similarly, you can maintain that any vision of things presupposes a
“Creation.” Or that every Christian vision—and therefore Blake’s—is premised on the doctrine of
“the Fortunate Fall.” But such reasonings are those of an Interpreter whose parlor needs sweeping. If you
ask the simple radical question, where in his own writings does Blake speak of “The Fallen World,” you are
bound to answer, “never.” This discrepancy at least suggests a disproportion between the concerns of Blake
and of his expositor. What concerned Blake was “Fallen Man.” And Regeneration.</p>
            <p>In 1970 I proposed a different view of the designs, maintaining with considerable specificity
that the five prefatory pictures and thirty pictures for Night the First are arranged in a distinct sequence
of units, veritable chapters. Paley (1982, p. 683) continues to chide me for this undertaking, pointing out
that in his 1971 review he had reproved me for affirming that the pictures fall into such units of vision. But
he is still unwilling to offer much by way of disproof. Although the theory of pictorial units was not much in
evidence in the 1980 Clarendon edition, it remains on the docket for the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
commentary because nobody has shown that it doesn’t work. Of course there is a sense in which it is the
obligation of the proponent of a theory to lay out all the evidence, both for it and against it, and I have
not yet done so, but this theory cannot be persuasively maintained without a consideration of all 537
designs.</p>
            <p>I have thought that an adequate presentation of the theory would necessitate a thorough
discussion of issues that shade off from the question of organization: in other words, the as-yet-uncompleted
commentary on all the designs. But I now believe that the question can usually be abstracted so that, with the
help of charts, a concise overview of the entire series could be presented and still allow room to discuss
areas where the theory is strained to accommodate particular designs. Rather than attempt such a chart here, I
shall simply mention some considerations bearing on the probability of such an order as I claim to be
ascertainable. No doubt any attempt to discern overall patterns of both pervasive and local schemata will
encounter problem areas where the connections and distinctions are less evident than in others. But what does
the skeptic do in, for example, encountering the sequence of <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 198-207 (V, 43-52), in which
Death appears in all but one of the designs <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 199? Declare that the sequence is
coincidental? Concentrate on the single apparent exception? Often what is needful in an attempt to recognize
Blake’s patterns is to make the proper identifications and discriminations of figures. I shall go into a
number of cases below. Here I shall point to a suggestive correlation having to do with the figure of
Young’s dead wife, “Lucia” (VIII, 1256), who in the poem was alluded to chiefly in the opening lines of
Night the Sixth. But the footnote reference to her was cut off in mounting the text on the drawing paper for
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 222 (no doubt in Edwards’ shop before Blake received the sheets), and the reader might
infer that Young speaks again here of the dead Narcissa, a recurrent concern. Blake shows us the dead wife of
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 221, a prefatory design with a textually blank page for Night the Sixth. When we
recognize her there, we can also see that she was the woman depicted in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 110, the title
page in the water color sequence for Night the Fourth. This is a clear case of the general need to look back
and forth in the series to recognize the picture story that Blake is weaving around the materials provided by
Young’s poetry. As with other forms of narrative, such departures from Young’s order produce a different
story, a critique and a correction. Blake’s story is often closer to that of Young than the comments in much
literary criticism, ancient and modern, that purports to address a particular writing. But after more than
twenty years of study I am not satisfied with any answer I have heard to the question of whether Blake’s
designs ought to be referred to as “illustrations.”</p>
            <p>As for the question of whether there are verifiable major divisions within each Night of the
series, those who patiently wait to see the evidence, as set forth in the Clarendon commentary, or who are
prepared to ascertain it for themselves should note well that Paley does not absolutely pronounce the theory
that such an order exists preposterous; he speaks only of “a somewhat arbitrary structuring of the
material” and declares “that this system of classification has been partly superimposed on the
material.” These words indicate that Paley is by now grudgingly persuaded that there is something to the
idea. If so, it should be possible to debate several of the truly problematic cases and then, after having
tested the evidence, correct our misconceptions and modify our arbitrariness.</p>
            <p>In reconsidering the exegetical part of the Introduction, I agree both with favorable reviewers
such as Hagstrum and negative reviewers such as Dörrbecker and Mitchell that English was not always kept up.
Occasionally a dismally religiose tone obtrudes. Such lapses should have been corrected. While these days
readers of criticism have become inured to styles that seem to me still more objectionable, condescending,
jargonistic, and mechanical, no reader should have to endure inauthentic enthusiastic superstition. But our
patches of bad writing seem to have given both Dörrbecker and Mitchell the
              <pb id="p18-163" n="163"/>
              <figure n="BUT330.1.78.WC" rend="file" width="781" height="1000">
                <head>3. <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 78, Title page, Night the Third: 
“<hi rend="i">NARCISSA</hi>,” by permission of the Trustees of the British Museum.</head>
              </figure>
              <pb id="p18-164" n="164"/>
              <figure n="BUT330.1.79.WC" rend="file" width="779" height="1000">
                <head>4. <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 79, Night the Third, verso of title page, by
permission of the Trustees of the British Museum.</head>
              </figure>
              <pb id="p18-165" n="165"/>
impression that the sample commentary promises a fulllength study choked with “neo-Blakean Fables”
(Mitchell) or “pseudo-Blakean associations” (Dörrbecker, p. 134).</p>
            <p>A crucial problem in understanding Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> series is to
ascertain exactly which figures are supposed to be identical: that is, which represent Young or other
characters he mentions—Lorenzo, Philander, Narcissa, Lucia, Florello, in one or another of their
aspects—and which characters represent Young’s major mythological characters and
personifications—Christ, Death, Time, the Devil, Nature, Darkness, Conscience, etc. All these in Blake’s
representations sometimes change their shapes and presumably their meanings drastically, though by aligning
verbal and pictorial clues it is usually possible to determine with certainty who is supposed to be who, and
who otherwise, and why. Thus Mulhallen (1981, p. 159) reasonably objected that the Clarendon edition erred (p.
89, n. 40) by lumping together <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 2, 3, 5, 7, and 8 (illus. 10) as representations of
“Young.” The apparently inspired poet with long wavy hair in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 5 can hardly be
identical with the curly-haired reader of <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 2 and the curly-haired insomniac of 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 8. Yet sometimes “Young” aspired to the bardic competence assuredly (though not
unqualifiedly—consider the occluded luminary) depicted in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 5. And Blake’s indubitable
representations of “Young” at times degenerate into such a figure as the pale lank-haired lyrist shown
serenading the Duchess of Portland, Young’s patroness, who (at a fancy-dress ball) affected the guise of
Cynthia, the moon-goddess, in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 82 (III, 7) (illus. 5). Here Young is revealed
in a degraded condition almost as abject as the amatory flautist-laureate in bondage to Venus and Cupid in 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 162 (V, [7]). Blake’s reader must consider all the factors bearing on the
establishment of a legal identity in everyday life and then balance them with the transformational
possibilities for showing spiritual identity which were available to Blake the artist. In a number of cases
the interpreter may be indeed hardpressed to decide whether a particular figure is supposed to be yet another
representation of a familiar character—Young again—or simply a representative man or woman in a common
human predicament. Several times even the gender is questionable—though one should not promptly infer that
in such cases the figure is supposed to represent Blake’s mythical androgyne. We must recall Blake’s
commonsense approach to Fuseli’s <hi rend="i">Ugolino</hi> in which it had been complained by a reviewer
that one of the children looked female: “Whether boy or girl signifies not, (but the critic must be a fool
who has not read Dante, and who does not know a boy from a girl)” (E 1982, 768).</p>
            <p>Mitchell devotes almost half his review (pp. 201-204) to a critique of the account of 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 78 (illus. 3), the title page of Night the Third, entitled “Narcissa,” which
depicts, in the words of the “Explanation” in Edwards’ 1797 edition: “A female figure, who appears
from the crescent beneath her feet to have surmounted the trials of the world, is admitted to an eternity of
glory: eternity is represented by its usual emblem—a serpent with its extremities united.” Mitchell
justifiably deplores some of the pietistic writing in the Clarendon exposition (p. 36) and corrects the
mistaken assertion that the eye of the great dragon-python “glances at the reader.” But he seems most
concerned to show that the commentary “disregard[s] . . . the text which Blake is illustrating.” Assuming
that even readers of <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi> may be rusty on Young’s story of Night the Third,
Mitchell points out that in it there is much talk of Phoebe and of the Duchess of Portland (to whom Night the
Third is dedicated—in the 1742 edition used with Blake’s watercolor, but <hi rend="i">not</hi> in the 1797
edition with Blake’s engravings). And Mitchell explains, as though he had made a discovery, that the figure
on the title page contradicts Young since she is not a lunar goddess but “the woman clothed with the sun,
and the moon under her feet, and upon her head a crown of twelve stars,” beleaguered by a dragon, of
Revelation 12:1. Mitchell spins many remarks out of this “witty” mixture, some of which may be preferable
to what is said in the Clarendon edition. But on the whole his long discussion is more concerned to chide the
Clarendon text for its pietism and errors, such as the unfortunate assertion that the serpent looks at the
reader, than to put forward an alternative interpretation of Blake’s picture. While the conventions of
shorter book reviews permit the reviewer to deplore a proposed interpretation without articulating the
preferred alternative, Mitchell spends five pages discussing things said about Blake’s picture without
indicating what he takes its meaning to be. One may infer indeed, that he does not have a theory.</p>
            <p>Most of Mitchell’s discussion is taken up with three critical moves. He as much as says that
only those who had never read Night the Third could suppose that the woman on the title page is Narcissa. But
he neglects in the first place to remind the reader that <hi rend="i">“Narcissa”</hi> is the name of the
Night, printed in large letters as the title, and in the second place to mention that he is the first
commentator to question whether the woman depicted has some connection with the woman mentioned in the
text—probably, after Lorenzo, the most famous character in the poem, except for the figure of Young himself.
In asserting that the woman depicted is Narcissa, the Clarendon editors were not being eccentric but were
following the well-established tradition of Essick and La Belle (1975), Bindman (1975), Butlin (1978), Paley
(1978), <hi rend="i">et al.</hi> Mitchell’s second dubious move is to make it appear (p. 202) that he
discovered the Revelation connection, or at least that the Clarendon editors had overlooked it. He
accomplishes this by cutting a rather lengthy quotation from our text and then bringing
<pb id="p18-166" n="166"/>
the point up as if from his own better-informed perspective. But of course we did mention and discuss the
connection in the sentences immediately following the ones he quotes. Mitchell’s third dubious move is to
pretend ignorance (p. 203) about the ambiguities of the serpent as an ouroboros symbol, though all he had to
do was follow our footnote 52 to de Groot’s 1969 article (Clarendon Bibliography No. 46) to become
enlightened. Once again, this route was well trodden, having been properly followed by Essick and La Belle
before us.</p>
            <p>There is no denying one point that Mitchell labors without elucidating: the connection of the
lunar symbolism of the title page with the lunar associations of the Duchess of Portland in the text of Night
the Third. The problem is so complicated, however, that not much of value can be said about the question
without an overall consideration of the representation of characters in Night the Third. For the Clarendon
edition it seemed consistent with our introductory purposes to concentrate (pp. 35-39) on connections among
the frontispieces and some title pages and tailpieces within the entire <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
series rather than to get into the intricacies of Night the Third, or any other Night. Mitchell’s impression
that he had come up with new ideas might have been allayed if we had not carelessly neglected a footnote
referring to an article by one of the editors that was given as a paper in 1972 and finally published in 1977,
at about the time our Introduction was being put into shape. The article by E.J. Rose, “<hi rend="i">Ut
Pictura Poesis</hi> and the Problem of Pictorial Statement in William Blake,” was, however, duly listed as
item 96, the last entry in our Bibliography, where it was noted that <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 78, 79, and 345 are
discussed and that the first two are reproduced. But we neglected to go into Rose’s handling of some of the
problems subsequently brought up by Mitchell. The further observations I shall present here include a good
deal that is not a rehash of already published commentary.</p>
            <p>Of the two women mentioned on Young’s title page, Narcissa, who was thought to have been
modeled on Young’s stepdaughter but who seems both in the poem and in Blake’s pictures to be more like a
wife—an Emanation, perhaps—died pathetically, leaving the poet bereft. The Duchess of Portland, Young’s
patroness, on the other hand, is glorified as a veritable moon goddess, and her mortality is not considered in
the poem. I don’t know whether Blake could have construed Young’s epigraph for Night the Third, attributed
to Virgil, “<hi rend="i">Ignoscenda quidem, scirent si ignoscere Manes</hi>,” or located it in 
<hi rend="i">Georgics</hi> 4:469, where it is a pathetic reflection on the <corr type="emend">intractability</corr> of the Manes—roughly,
the souls of the dead as underworld deities—to the folly of Orpheus in losing Eurydice.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">1</ref> The woman shown in the title page is in a
superlunary position and thus recalls the occasional triumphal position of the woman clothed with the sun of
German Renaissance prints. She is on the upper arch of an inverted crescent moon, rather than within the
crescent (the latter is traditionally the commoner position), but it evidently is not to be understood as
signifying a reservation as to the glory of Mary’s position.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n29" type="note">2</ref> With regard to the crucial question of whether the woman in 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 78 (24E) is conscious of the threat presented by the proximity of the enormous
serpent, the water color indicates one thing, the engraving another. Our perfunctory note, Clarendon edition
p. 78, gives little guidance in this matter save for the indication that the woman has only five (visible)
stars in the water color but seven in the engraving. More indicative of meaning is the fact that in the water
color the woman’s mouth is wide open, probably distorted with a scream, whereas in the engraving her
rapturous face expresses unmitigated joy. Presumably when Blake made the (undated) engraving he knew there was
to be no sequel such as is represented by <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 79 (illus. 4), and thus decided not
to qualify the radiant impression, whereas in the water color he prepared the viewer for the peripety
overleaf. In looking at <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 78 alone we may suppose that the radiance of the
threatened woman will enable her to evade the tails and loop of the serpent, whereas at least the un-luminous
moon will fall into them. The impression created by the engraving, 24E, is, in contrast, entirely optimistic,
suggesting that somehow all will be well and that the serpent will not succeed in springing his trap. 
<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">1</hi> He might have got the drift simply by consulting Lemprière’s 
<hi rend="i">Classical Dictionary</hi> on “Manes,” which he would earlier have had occasion to do while
engraving Fuseli’s fantasy on <hi rend="i">Aeneid</hi> 6:896. See Essick 1983, no. xxx, pp. 175-76 and pl.
76.</note>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Note that in Blake’s two splendid water colors entitled <hi rend="i">The
Great Red Dragon and the Woman Clothed in the Sun</hi> (Butlin 1981, cat. 519, 520; pls. 580, 581), the woman
is within the crescent, not on top of it.
                                <p>Outside Night the Third in the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> series the
figure who most closely resembles the apocalyptic woman of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 78 (illus. 3)
appears as the sky goddess in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 446 (IX, 28), identified as “Night” in
Young’s poem. This cosmic woman is crowned with stars, and her body and sky-filling robes are punctuated
with stars; those on her hand and foot are displayed as though they were stigmata. In order to handle the
interpretive linkage to the woman in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 78, however, one must first establish
her relationship to the poem in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 447 and then treat both as episodes of the
recurrent poet-muse theme in the entire series. In other words, the connection between <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 78
and <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 446 is not close enough to be interpretively decisive.</p>
	<p>The intended significance of Blake’s apocalyptic woman’s gesture of raised arms and hands outspread
may be more specific than ardent supplication or generalized prayer. One can hardly be indifferent to Benjamin
West’s treatment of practically the same subject, probably also done in 1797 as part of his scheme to
decorate Fonthill Abbey: <hi rend="i">The Woman Clothed with the Sun</hi>, as West represented her, stands,
levitated by angels and her own wings, above the dry crescent moon as well as above the threatening, staring
sea serpent who vomits water. She looks rapturously upward with upraised arms and outspread hands toward her
infant boy, who is being carried up into heaven by one angel and convoyed by another (see Nancy L. Pressly,
<hi rend="i">Revealed Religion: Benjamin West’s Commissions for Windsor Castle and Fonthill Abbey</hi> [San
Antonio: San Antonio Museum of Art, 1983], fig. 33 [cat. 37, p. 69], or John Dillenberger, 
<hi rend="i">Benjamin West: The Context of His Life’s Work</hi>, with Particular Attention to Paintings with
Religious Subject Matter [San Antonio: Trinity University Press, 1977], pl. 76). Prompted by West’s
illustration of Rev. 12: 1-5, 13-17, one might infer that Blake’s woman in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
78 (24E) is likewise supposed to be understood as having just passed her own infant son up to angels that are
visible to her, but not to the viewer. Yet this gesture has no point of correspondence with Young’s poem,
and Blake’s other aspiring women in the front designs for each Night or in Night the Third do not disburden
themselves of a child. See <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 6 (I,[1]: 1E) (illus. 8), <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 37 (II, tp
verso), and III, p. 6: <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 81; 25E, III, p. 10: <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 85, III, p. 12: 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 87; 26E, III, p. 34: <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 109. The aspiring women in Night the Fourth all
gesture differently, but they too appeal for themselves rather than for another. It seems, therefore, that the
West picture, despite its suggestive similarities to <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 78, does not provide any
useful interpretive perspective on Blake’s picture.</p></note></p>
            <p>In the water color series any optimistic expectations aroused by <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> 78 are dashed when one turns overleaf and finds a pessimistic sequel, <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> 79 (illus. 4): here a long-haired woman, shackled, howls her distress within the belly of an
ouroboros, which has swallowed half his length of tail. This distraught, un-attractive woman is an antithesis
of the glorious woman in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 78, who had, however, shown at least two signs that she was
indeed threatened and might not triumph.</p>
            <p>Is she “the same” woman, “Narcissa” (<hi rend="i">pace</hi> Mitchell) who, like
Eurydice alluded to in the Virgilian inscription, is a victim of the unforgiving Manes? Or should we think of
her as, like Wordsworth’s Lucy, all too mortal? Her fate, howling, shackled, being digested by the rooting
innards of the malicious serpent, forbids us to suppose that she is undergoing a benign natural death. A
moment’s thought, however, at least assures us that she can hardly represent the Duchess of
Portland—except she be supposed to be <hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi> idea of the Duchess, mortal like the rest
of us and now in agony because she had been flattered into disregarding it. But Blake would have thought this
idea too commonplace to be interesting. One must look ahead to the thirty other designs in Night the Third to
recognize the point Blake is making in presenting in the prefatory designs two women
              <pb id="p18-167" n="167"/>
              <figure n="BUT330.1.82.WC" rend="file" width="785" height="1000">
	<head>5. <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 82, Night the Third, page 7, by permission of the Trustees of the
British Museum.</head>
</figure>
<pb id="p18-168" n="168"/>
who are the same yet different.</p>
            <p>In <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 101 the visionary in his chariot of the universe gazes
upward at two ascending women. In the sequel, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 102, three women genuflect
before Time, and in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 85 and 98 respectively six and seven tiny spirit women
emanate about a single source figure. Clearly Blake deploys more than two females in Night the Third, but
students of Blake’s later prophecies should not find such multiplication of characters unduly perplexing.
There are further pictorial connections suggesting that the open-mouthed figure in <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> 79 (illus. 4) is related to the figure of “Tyrant Life” in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
105, who has manacled, shackled, and imprisoned “Mind” in a cage and then in the sequel, 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 106, is herself startled, open mouthed, by the prospect of what Young calls
“<hi rend="i">Death</hi> the Spirit Infinite! Divine!” This in turn anticipates the theme depicted in the
final water color, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 109, where, surprisingly, Death has unshackled a woman,
who already soars, and is about to be joined by a young man now being freed by Death the liberator. Earlier,
in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 81 (25E) the woman, nude except for the band of a shackle on her ankle,
and with long agitated locks, had frantically attempted to escape the sinister cope of Death. A little later,
in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 94 (27E), one woman is swept down the river of Death while another, her
hair in a bun, like the woman who finally escapes in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 109, paces upstream,
against the flow, in front of the huge brooding figure of Darkness. The “Silver Queen of Heaven,” the
lunar goddess with braided hair, who with crossed arms slumbers to the serenade of her enervated poet in 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 82 (illus. 5), has awakened in the sequel, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 83,
where her hair falls free, but (trapped within the crescent, like the woman in the ouroboros in 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 79 [illus. 4]) she holds up her hands in consternation, viewing some spectacle
not included in this picture.</p>
            <p>What distresses her, the reader can see, is the flotilla of “Woes” that “cluster” as
they swim into her ken, shown in the facing page, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 84. Her eyes are on the
squadron of five Woes, doubtless corresponding to the senses, that are most prominently featured beneath the
text panel. The curious reader may, however, study the second cluster, powered by two howling old men, and
note the strangely lumpish “snow personage” that is the chief burden of this group. Here adumbrated, this
figure was again sketched as a coda design in the unfinished drawing for <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 538,
as I recently pointed out in this journal (Grant 1982, p. 8 and fig. 1). It is as a consequence of this vision
of “Woes” that the woman in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 85 is moved to sacrifice her own joy, virtue,
love, youth, beauty, and song, in a flame emanating from her and in a pictorial order that exactly reverses
the verbal order of Young’s line 97. In the Clarendon edition it is declared that the marking of this line
is an “accidental stain,” but the reproduction indicates that Blake’s original marking may have been
accidentally smudged. In any case, this is the line Blake illustrated, and in the way I have indicated. The
last time the moon appears in Night the Third is in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 103, where it appears at
the full, shining above the darkened surface of the Earth, now empty of the moon goddess, who had, as
indicated in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 85, sacrified her Joys. Above the full moon, meditating upon it, is a dark
goddess called “<hi rend="i">Night</hi>” in Young’s poem (III, 429). Those who recognize that this
figure is derived from Durer’s famous print <hi rend="i">Melencolia</hi> I—an impression of which, at
least later, Blake hung above his work table—will not distrust her or her influence. After some thirty more
years of meditation, this figure reappeared as the angelic scribe in the lower right border of plate 17 of
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job.</hi> What she wrote there I shall not repeat here
lest I again be guilty of offensive pietism.</p>
            <p>Dörrbecker chose to challenge the reliability of the Clarendon <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> commentary by raising a number of ill-coordinated points about our discussion of 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 264 (illus. 2), the frontispiece for the second volume. It is evident from
Dörrbecker’s response that our exposition of this picture (which does not closely illustrate any passage in
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>) was too affirmative in tone. We also depended too much on the viewer’s
being able to see what Blake’s picture looks like and, as I have already agreed, the monochrome (but not the
color) reproduction of this great picture is woefully inadequate in the Clarendon edition.</p>
            <p>Whether criticism addresses a work of literature or a picture, the role of accurate and
thorough description is crucial. Most bad criticism achieves its purposes by disregarding inconvenient
details. I am glad to concur in this belief with the authority of the late Kenneth Clark, who was a good art
historian even if he couldn’t help condescending to Blake: “I have found careful description an
enlightening form of criticism. It is often humiliating to discover how much one has failed to observe, or to
understand, in a picture, until one tries to describe it in detail. Descriptions can be a labour of love . . .
” (Introduction to Vasari, <hi rend="i">Lives</hi> . . . [1978], p. xxvii).</p>
            <p>The viewer who studies the frontispiece to the second volume of <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi>, non-interpretatively, in the British Museum Department of Prints and Drawings, sees: a nude
male figure with long hair, a short full beard, open mouth, and upcast eyes, who bursts into a dark place
bounded by clouds above and below. He displays wounds on his outstretched hands and casts beams of yellow
light throughout the cavernous enclave. On closer inspection, it is apparent that this figure is not simply
flying toward the viewer (as are, for example,
<pb id="p18-169" n="169"/>
the comparable figures in the <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> 14 and <hi rend="i">Visions of
the Daughters of Albion</hi> 8); the left side of the chest and hip are distinctly visible and can be traced
even, as it were, behind the coverlet of the uppermost two recumbent figures who are stretched out beneath the
central figure. There is a mark on the left breast of this man whose cruciform position is much like that of
the resurrecting Christ as he is depicted in the engraved version of the title page of Night the Fourth (31E),
though, surprisingly, wounds are not shown on the otherwise practically identical figure as he appears in the
water color frontispiece for the first volume, <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 1 (illus. 1). In <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 264
(illus. 2) the indubitable stigmata on the hands, together with the characteristic facial features and the
wound on the chest, identify the central figure as Christ; remarkably, Christ wears a wedding ring on the
fourth finger of his left hand. This is distinguishable even in the inadequate monochrome reproduction in the
Clarendon edition. Though this ring was described in our (unpublished) descriptive notes, we neglected to
mention it in our commentary in the Clarendon edition, out of carelessness rather than design, since it could
only strengthen our interpretation of the picture. This omission was duly noted by Mulhallen in 1981. (She
also mentions the ring in her 1975 thesis, which has recently become available for study.) Not only does this
small but crucial piece of symbolism—a wedding ring on Christ—not appear elsewhere in Blake’s work, but
it may well be unique in Christian art. Once having observed the ring in this picture, however, the viewer
will hardly be mystified as to its meaning.</p>
            <p>The uppermost of the two recumbent shrouded males has his curly head cast back, with eyes and
mouth closed, so as almost to face the left edge of the picture. His muffled left arm is apparently raised to
ward off the illumination, while on his chest appears, perhaps through a semi-transparent shroud, the
suggestion of scaly chest armor. The lower figure, with helmeted head to the right, is open mouthed, howling,
but has probably closed eyes, as he twists his torso away from the illumination. Yet he is seated in such a
way as to show both shrouded legs as they bend across the picture. The dark shapes at the top and bottom of
the cavern are curved and resemble clouds, as is often the case in Blake’s depictions of underground
scenes.</p>
            <p>How the first describer of the picture, Frederick Shields, understood this frontispiece is
worth recalling: “Christ the Light of the World, the Sun of Righteousness, appears in the centre of the
design, seen only to the bust, and environed with thick darkness, which, with His outspread, pierced hands and
the radiant glory which emanates from His person, He parts and dispells. Dimly apparent within the darkness
visible beneath him, looms the shrouded image of the power of darkness, writhing in mortal agony, pierced
through and through with the sharp shafts of ‘The Light that shineth in Darkness’ ” (Gilchrist, 
<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, 1880, II, 298-99).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30"
type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Why did Shields think the soldier he noticed (the one at the right)
represents Satan, “the power of darkness”? Probably because the face closely resembles that of
“Satan,” otherwise called “Head of a Damned Soul in Dante’s Inferno,” a head engraved by Blake after
Fuseli some years earlier. It too is seen from below, with open mouth and blank eyes, at practically the same
angle as the soldier in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 264. Essick 1983, no. xxxii, pp. 170-72, and fig. 73, now dates
the states as c. 1789 and notes that much the same head appears in five other pictures, including 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 432—though he overlooks <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 264 (illus. 2).</note></p>
            <p>That what Blake shows is the Resurrection has been mentioned more recently by Grant 1970 (p.
316), Hagstrum 1973 (pp. 148-49, with reservation), Bindman 1975 (p. 180), and Butlin 1981 (I, 216). Paley
1978 (p. 40), following Hagstrum while expressing deeper reservations, in keeping with his theory that
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs are supposed to be about “the Fallen World,” seems
unaware that this is a scene of Resurrection and pays no attention at all to the two soldiers in the picture.
Such selective procedures naturally guarantee the production of “neo-Blakean fables,” such as Dörrbecker
and Mitchell deplore—in principle.</p>
            <p>Butlin 1981, p. 216 (cat. 330.<hi rend="i">264</hi>) has no difficulty in recognizing the
derivation of the frontispiece of the second volume of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> from the final plate
of <hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi> (pl. 10, Principle 7). Erdman, <hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake</hi>
1974, p. 26 (with a typographical error), quotes Essick to the effect that the scene represents “Christ
before two pagans overcome by His light and glory.” This is too general a conception for 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 264, but it is appropriate enough for the tiny design at the top of <hi rend="i">ARO</hi> 10,
where there is no specific indication that the miniscule recumbent figures (whose legs may be tangled
together) are the soldiers at the tomb of Christ.</p>
            <p>The visual similarity between <hi rend="i">ARO</hi> 10 (Clarendon Fig. 8) and 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 264 would seem to be obvious for most viewers, once it has been pointed out, but Dörrbecker,
holding that the commentary in the Clarendon edition is animated by “pseudo-Blakean associations,” uses
our asserted connection to exemplify his complaint (see p. 134 and fn. 24, p. 138): he declares that we affirm
the connection “probably just because [<hi rend="i">ARO</hi> 10] is considered as an early appearance of the
motif of outspread arms in Blake’s <hi rend="i">oeuvre.</hi>” No. The figure with outspread arms in the
illuminated printing appears within a cave and is undoubtedly exhorting the two recumbent figures. This means
that the basic pictorial elements are the same in both pictures—not that the Clarendon interpreters were
unduly swayed by the similarity of the single motif of outspread arms. A thorough interpretation should,
indeed, go on from the overall resemblance of the two designs to make the necessary discriminations. But the
viewer who is unable to recognize the basic similarity of the two designs can never arrive at a valuable
comment on either.</p>
            <p>On page 134 Dörrbecker quotes five sentences from pages 38-39 that set forth an interpretation
of <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 264 and deplores them as “such [a] free flow of pseudo-Blakean associations (or
should I say ‘illuminations’?) which if only translated into less ecstatic phrasing, are truisms as
relevant for a painting of the resurrection by,
              <pb id="p18-170" n="170"/>
<figure n="BUT330.1.345.WC" rend="file" width="791" height="1000">
	<head>6. <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 345, Title page, Night the Eighth, by permission of the Trustees of
the British Museum.</head>
</figure>
<pb id="p18-171" n="171"/>
for example, Sebastiano Ricci. . . .” A few touches of rhapsody in the style I too regret, though I may have
penned them myself. But all the points claimed can be verified in context, except perhaps these sentences,
which are too compressed: “The hands [of Jesus] simultaneously display to doubters that Jesus 
<hi rend="i">is</hi> the human family; as he suffered for all, he can offer the infinite expanse to all, and even
prepare to offer the handclasp of Friendship. Blake never quite depicts this moment of fraternity. . .
.”</p>
            <p>As for “doubters,” the reference here is not only to the soldiers who cannot bear this
illumination, but to the next design in the series, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 265, the title page of
Volume Two, in which Jesus displays the wound on his hand and the wound on his breast to a Doubting Thomas. In
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 264 the explosion of Jesus within the cave might for a Blakean audience
suggest “the infinite expanse,” even though Blake himself never used exactly that term (consult the 
<hi rend="i">Concordance</hi>). The “handclasp of friendship” is, to be sure, a gesture that Blake’s Jesus
never quite stoops to, though Jesus comes so close to it in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 531 (IX, 113),
with Young, in the poet’s penultimate appearance, that the reader has justification for reflecting on
Blake’s final reticence in representation: why <hi rend="i">don’t</hi> the two there shake hands? Then
there is the case of “Sebastiano Ricci,” one of the also-rans Dörrbecker introduces in his race to catch
up with Blake. I have already declared (without having checked them all!) that no other artist, large or
small, represented the adult Jesus as wearing a wedding ring, but I would be happy to retract if some
precedent could actually be shown. But it is most unlikely that such a hypothetical precedent, if it could be
found, would change what Blake meant the reader to understand when he employed this familiar symbol in an
unexpected context. Blake first made reference to the “human families” in Night the Ninth of 
<hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> (E 1982, 404: p. 135, 1. 37), complementing references
to the “universal” or “divine family” in <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> I, all presumably written later than
the pictures for <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi> But the wedding ring in the frontispiece to the second
volume indicates that Blake had recognized the basis of “the human family” before he saw fit to write
about it. No doubt Blake here intended to challenge the view of the future of marriage offered by a simple
reading of Matthew 22:30; appearing as he does to those who dwell in realms of Night, Jesus the bridegroom is
showing the way, not yet the end.</p>
            <p>One of the best pictures Blake ever painted, <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 345 (illus. 6),
the title page of Night the Eighth, ought next to be considered, both with regard to the adequacy of the
reproductions in the Clarendon edition and for what it shows about Blake’s fundamental ideas and symbols
while he was engaged in the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> project. As a vision of the Whore and Beast of
Revelation 17, this picture has never been surpassed—either by Durer’s wonderful woodcuts or by Blake’s
own later awesome water colors of this subject. According to Young’s title page, this section of the poem
constitutes “Virtue’s Apology” and an <hi rend="i">Answer</hi> to “<hi rend="i">The</hi> MAN 
<hi rend="i">of the</hi> WORLD,” together with a consideration of “<hi rend="i">The</hi> Love 
<hi rend="i">of</hi> This Life; <hi rend="i">The</hi> Ambition <hi rend="i">and</hi> Pleasure, <hi rend="i">with
the</hi> Wit <hi rend="i">and</hi> Wisdom <hi rend="i">of the</hi> World.”</p>
            <p>Young fulfills this announcement in lines 525 ff., where his effusive censures of illicit 
<hi rend="i">Pleasure</hi> and <hi rend="i">Ambition</hi> are well enough summarized by the rather tame 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 373. This picture of a fascinated Roman emperor tethered by a chain to a blithe young
woman—a prototype of “Mirth” in Blake’s first design for <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> (Butlin 1981,
cat. 543.<hi rend="i">1</hi>, pl. 672)—represents the tenor of disapproval Young was able to articulate,
whereas the title page presents a prophetic denunciation in the manner of St. John. Blake’s
grotesque-sublime title page goes far beyond Young’s ethical vision of vanity to achieve a consolidated
epiphany of evil. Blake must have expected his viewers to notice that Young’s words are unable to identify
that pair “that was, and is not, and yet is” (Revelation 17:18). And more recently we search in vain
through “Blake’s myth,” with Paley, to find some connections with the stories of Vala and Orc. But
connections close enough to elucidate anything in the picture will not appear: Orc never grew seven heads and
ten horns.</p>
            <p>In the strict privacy of Blake’s first precisely dated annotations, those to 
<hi rend="i">Watson’s Apology for the Bible . . . addressed to Thomas Paine</hi>, however, we observe Blake the
author using the same images as in the picture to express his own almost despairing beliefs: “To defend the
Bible in this year 1798 would cost a man his life[.] The Beast &amp; the Whore rule without controls” (E
1982, 611).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">4</ref> The picture tells the
same story and analyzes the institutional mechanisms through which tyranny perpetuates its sway. Dörrbecker
has nothing good to say about the quality of the reproductions of <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 345 in the Clarendon
edition, singling out the following aspects of the color version for reproval: “The bright translucent
washes of blue and yellow are strongly affected by the color of the ‘ground,’ the creamy tinge of the
printing paper; they lost much of their brilliance and depth, and in some places in the reproduction are
omitted altogether” (Dörrbecker 1982, 132). Of the examples he cites, <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 107, 125, and
156 lack vibrancy, though the reds are not seriously off. This is also the case with the duller reds of 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 345; indeed, Paley declared it to be, overall, “fairly good, although the Whore of
Babylon’s scarlet cloak has gone too far toward orange.” Paley adds, “in contrast, the reproduction in
Butlin’s <hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi>, plate 344, conveys the true color” (1982, p. 680). 
<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Bentley 1978, 1404, declares that the second sentence is deleted. Erdman 1982,
884-85, declares that the cancel is a ruled double line in pencil uncharacteristic of Blake and thus perhaps
attributable to Samuel Palmer. Alas, Erdman does not comment on the terminal word, which he renders
“controls,” though his 1965 edition, like those of both Keynes and Bentley (1978), reads it as singular.
Erdman (1983) offers no further clarification. The concordance reveals that Blake does not use the plural noun
elsewhere, and also that he always elsewhere spelled the word with two <hi rend="i">ll</hi>s. The OED shows
that the plural noun was in use, with specific political reference, in Blake’s time.
                                <p>I am grateful to Robert N. Essick and Thomas Lange for having restudied
Blake’s inscription, which is in the Huntington Library. With the aid of a special microscope, they were
able to discern these facts: there is a smudge at the end of “controls,” but the letter “s” appears to
have been written in the same ink as the rest of the word. What might be construed as a stroke through this
letter, using the same ink, could also be construed as an indistinct cancel. Blake’s preference for the
double spelling must also be given some weight. But on the whole Essick and Lange feel that it is more in
accord with the evidence to retain the new reading of a plural noun. As for the pencil cancel, the first part
of the aphorism is crossed with three horizontal but <hi rend="i">unruled</hi> lines, the second part with two
lines, also <hi rend="i">unruled</hi>; only “controls” lacks any pencil lines. It should be understood
that a number of the subsequent annotations are also in pencil, though most are written in the same ink as is
used on the title page aphorism. Samuel Palmer signed the book in ink, not pencil. There is no sign elsewhere
that he altered Blake’s annotations. Therefore, there is no reason to assign the rather faint pencil cancels
on the second aphorism to anyone other than Blake.</p>
	<p>My conclusion from this review of the evidence is as follows: in 1798 Blake saw overwhelming evidence that
“The Beast &amp; the Whore rule without Controls.” Subsequently, perhaps as late as the Peace of Amiens,
1802-03, Blake took another look at Watson, with pencil in hand. In addition to adding certain comments, he
(faintly) canceled at least most of the second aphorism. Ordinarily, Blake might have conceded, the Beast and
the Whore rule with (some) controls; in the best of times the rule of the Beast and the Whore is so veiled
that it need not be affirmed. In evaluating the alterations, there is no obligation to think that the
cancellation by Blake represents a retraction. Much as in the case of “Opposition is true Friendship,” 
<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, pl. 20, which was painted out in colored copies (E 1982, 42 and
802 n), we need not suppose that Blake actually changed his mind about the principle involved. Every honest
man as prophet is bound to see the marks of the Beast and the Whore much of the time in the activities and
relationships prevailing in an imperium.</p></note></p>
            <p>In point of fact the fairly prominent <hi rend="i">skirt</hi>—the Whore wears no
“cloak”—is in the Clarendon edition
<pb id="p18-172" n="172"/>
indeed, as alleged, rather “too orange.” This hue was an attempt to render a violet-rose pink. On the
whole, this Clarendon color reproduction is somewhat less successful than the color reproduction of the
drawing, plate 35 in Paley’s 1978 Phaidon selection. The appreciable difference between these reproductions
is, however, less a matter of particular hues, which are usually quite similar, than of the superior
distinctness of the Phaidon reproduction. The Clarendon version is too fuzzy and the hues are insufficiently
vivid, though in itself the matte finish looks more like water color than the rather glossy finish of the
Phaidon. In one aspect the Clarendon is clearly superior: the background sky (apart from the blue or white
flakes/stars that punctuate it) is varied grey, whereas the Phaidon renders it a muddy brown—a color Blake
almost never uses, but one which shows up regularly in reproductions of his sky-greys.</p>
            <p>Neither the Clarendon nor the Phaidon edition was able to do anything with the wonderful blue
washes (to which Dörrbecker perhaps alluded) on the face, neck, bosom, and hand of the Whore, or the stronger
blue highlight on the Judge-head—the rightmost—of the Beast. If you look closely at the superb color
collotype reproduction in Keynes’s 1927 Harvard selection you will feel that nothing in either the 1978 or
1980 editions of <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 345 was satisfactorily reproduced—when measured against such a high
standard. But I am sorry to say that Paley was profoundly mistaken to have held up Butlin’s 1981 Yale
reproduction, which is a dreadful botch—due, perhaps, to an attempt to bring out Blake’s elusive blues. In
the Yale reproduction the Whore’s blouse, the skin of the serpentine body of the Beast that forms the
background for her figure, and the huge lips of the Pope-head at the lower left, all turned out a bloody awful
red, while the blue overlaying the grey is a darker cousin to the aforementioned dreadful blues that disfigure
the reproductions of the Huntington designs for Milton’s poems. On the other hand, the features of the Whore
and Beast can at least be distinguished in the Yale color reproductions, whereas the monochrome in the
Clarendon edition is atrociously bad, turning everything to mud. Considering that Clarendon had earlier
published a quite acceptable monochrome of the picture (Paley and Phillips 1974, pl. 67, p. 269), this botch
in the 1980 edition is unaccountable.</p>
            <p>As the arrow-headed tail of the serpentine Beast curls above the text panel seeking to enlist a
third part of the inchoate, flaky stars of heaven, “Mystery,” duly labeled, with long blond agitated hair
and heavily rouged cheeks, wearing a reddish-gold spiked crown and large ostentation of other gold and red
jewelry on her expanse of flesh, prominently displays her huge chalice that contains the blood of the Saints.
Her heavy slanted eyelids, which do not match her pretty, hard face, give her a sly look as she peers, with a
set mouth, out of the picture, apparently seeing something alarming since her left hand is raised, with
fingers parted, expressing consternation. There is a horizon line near her raised hand to signify the curve of
the globe that is beneath the sway of her machine. We need not wonder long about whom she is married to.</p>
            <p>The middle pair of the front four heads of the Beast, the ram-horned King who wears a spiked
crown like that of the Whore and the budding-horned and helmeted Warrior, stare at the viewer; the King with
small, shaded, and sad indistinct eyes and downturned mouth, the skull-like Warrior with huge red eyes and
vast toothy would-be smiling mouth. After commenting on the aforementioned error in the Clarendon
edition—describing the direction of the gaze of the serpent in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 78 (illus.
3) as being toward the viewer—Mitchell was emboldened to raise a semiotic question as to whether one can
ever be certain that a figure who looks out from a picture is supposed to be looking directly at the
spectator. While rules for ascertaining the direction of view may be no easier to formulate for pictures than
for life, in the actual experience of pictures this is not ordinarily a serious problem. Those viewers who
have confronted Memling’s <hi rend="i">Blessing Christ</hi> in the Norton Simon Museum or the central figure
in Michelangelo’s <hi rend="i">The Crucifixion of St. Peter</hi> in the Pauline Chapel of the Vatican
(viewed from the floor, not at picture-level as in photographs) can have no doubt that the figures are looking
directly at them. In Blake’s own tempera quartet of 1810 (Butlin 1981, cat. 667-70; pl. 890, 891, 962, 892),
three of the four central characters likewise look the viewer straight in the eye. A paradoxalist might argue
that Blake’s Warrior in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 345 has only pseudo or mask eyes, but still one must insist
that the eyes are directed toward the viewer. A more convincing case could be made for the theory that it is
the King who is truly sightless. According to <hi rend="i">this</hi> pictorial analysis, these two figures are
the most pressing part of the problem; later, in 1809, when Blake redid the subject (Butlin 1981, cat. 523,
pl. 584), none of the heads addresses the viewer; and when Blake redid it yet again as the picture for
Dante’s <hi rend="i">Purgatory</hi> 32 (Butlin 1981, cat. 812:<hi rend="i">89</hi>), it is a different head
that stares at the reader with, necessarily, a different implication.</p>
            <p>The heads at the ends of the front four look down and up; at the right the bewigged Judge who
wears only a single large horn (with its spiral curve that Hogarth would have declared the line of
beauty)—and also, note, a dark crown with blunt knobs—this Judge has saber-tooth fangs and stares down
ominously with intense small red eyes. Positioned at the right, it appears that the Judge is the chief support
of the Whore. It might be argued that the weight of the Whore falls upon this (the wider) side simply to
accommodate the text panel, but I believe that Blake seldom allowed
              <pb id="p18-173" n="173"/>
<figure n="BUT330.1.417.WC" rend="file" width="787" height="1000">
	<head>7. <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 417, Title page, Night the Ninth, by permission of the Trustees of
the British Museum.</head>
</figure>
<pb id="p18-174" n="174"/>
spatial exigencies to dictate insignificant arrangements of figures; as a rule, position is indicative of
meaning. Design is no less apparent in the figure at the viewer’s left end of the front four, the Bishop.
His triple crown—the bottom circlet merely spiked (like those of the Whore and King), the upper two with
decorated spikes, surmounted by the cross and ball of sovereignty—marks him as the Pope, who would not
abjure secular power. For this reason too he is flanked beside and above by two kings, whose sheep horns
contrast with the Pope’s two sharp-pronged goat horns: thus the Beast is an amalgamation of sheep and goats
designed to retard the radical distinction of the Last Judgment. The Pope’s most disturbing characteristic
is that he is gazing up with white blind eyes, uncannily lacking distinct pupils, though the position of the
pupils has been carefully drawn in. Of all the characters Blake portrayed as lacking in vision, the Pope’s
case of cataracts is undoubtedly the worst. He is linked with the frontline King in that both betray
serpentine scales about their collars and wear beards. He is also linked with the Judge at the right because
both have long, whitish hair and other connecting features of similarity and contrast.</p>
            <p>The three heads at the left above the Pope almost seem to emanate from him and appear resolute
in staring at some invisible prospect (perhaps the future), evidently unalarmed. The crown of this king is
made of softly-bent bands that contrast with the sharp spikes on most of the others. Above him is another
white-bearded regal-ecclesiastic, who shows only a single cow’s horn, and wears a fantastic double-spiked
crown which decorates a huge bent triangular headpiece: we must count three horns on this figure in order to
find the requisite tally of ten horns. At the very top of the column is a humble priest who wears a biretta,
the button of which stands as a kind of counterpart to the horns of the others. Though subject to the
influence of the varied authority of the others, this Priest (despite the tension shown in his face) is the
component least responsible for the abominations perpetrated by the other facets of the Beast and its rider.
He bears some resemblance to the Clerk and Reeve, who bring up the rear of Chaucer’s dubiously-led
cavalcade, at least in Blake’s tempera representation of the <hi rend="i">Canterbury Pilgrimage</hi> (Butlin
1981, cat. 653, fig. 587—detail only).</p>
            <p>All five major characters in the title page for Night the Eighth reappear in subsequent
pictures throughout the Night: the Whore is first modulated as tyrannical Miss World, <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> 347; the Judge as the three Accusers of the Just Man in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 363;
the King at first shares his sovereignty with Miss World in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 347, then enacts
Caesar falling to assassins in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 372, and thereafter, in his youthful identity,
is enchained by Pleasure, in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 373. The Pope becomes more weirdly reptilian to
guide Leviathan on a trivial portentous mission in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 349, then in 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 396 he sits enthroned under a balacherion and offers an arrogant blessing as a
humble tonsured priest grovels, about to plant a kiss on his cloven hoof.</p>
            <p>Other spiritual presences, greater and lesser, continue to operate throughout Night the Eighth,
for good and ill, as they must do in order to bring on the Last Judgment in Night the Ninth. But a crucial
“consolidation of error” (to employ one of Frye’s useful terms) occurs as the Beast and the Whore are
first revealed in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 345 and ramified thereafter. Blake was to employ much the
same strategy in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, introducing in plate 75, at the end of Chapter Three, the
(doubled) figure of the Whore as Tirzah and Rahab disporting with the mostly-serpentine Beast of seven
dragon-heads and ten horns: they represent the Whore <hi rend="i">in</hi> the Beast, as it were. The
redemption described in the final Chapter begins with the frontispiece in which Albion emulates the beneficent
posture of Christ crucified on the Tree of Mystery and gives himself for the healing of the nations. The
counterpart to this sequence in the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> series is <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> 417 (illus. 7), the title page for Night the Ninth, where Blake shows—in spite of Young—that
the real “Consolation” began with the Presentation of the Christ child in the Temple: the blessed Simeon,
holding the Child, shares his radiance, while the prophetic Anna celebrates the presence so long anticipated
and now at hand. Probably the most skeptical viewer could appreciate that in this picture the eyes of Simeon
are upcast as he delivers his blessing, in contrast to the eyes of Anna and Jesus, which are fixed on the
viewer, on whoever happens to return that gaze. Viewers of a Keatsian disposition will complain that the
figures in this picture have a palpable design on them, or respond that only “Blake enthusiasts” could be
impressed by what they see: the torsos of Anna and Simeon are not long enough for any viewers of taste and
judgment to be taken in by what is, after all, not a very well-drawn picture. So say the connoisseurs in all
ages.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>III. Some Engraved Copies, with Particulars of Three Engraved Designs</title>
            </head>
            <p>A point made several times in connection with the new Census of colored engraved copies of 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> in the Clarendon edition is that few copies were probably colored by Blake. The
presence of discolored pigments in some details in most White Death, Type I, copies of 6E, 18E, and 20E points
to their common origin in Richard Edwards’ workshop, since many of these copies (though not the pages in
question) bear various inscriptions. Moreover, the more one sees of the copies I-2
<pb id="p18-175" n="175"/>
through I-14, the more certain one becomes that none of them are by Blake. Copy I-1, in contrast, a Mellon
copy now at the Yale Center for British Art, bears an owner’s inscription declaring that Blake had colored
it for him. The washes are different enough from those in the other White Death copies to set it apart and
assure that it was not a model copy used as the standard for the other copies. On the other hand, the quality
of the washes suggests that this may have been a unique copy colored by Blake. When I last studied this copy
in 1981, however, I became increasingly skeptical about Blake’s responsibility for its coloring.</p>
            <p>The case for Blake’s having colored seventeen plates, some very carefully, others merely
touched with color, in the battered but quite wonderful White Death Copy I-15 is, on the other hand, very
strong. Bentley (1977, pp. 956-57) and Butlin apparently agree with me that these are Blake’s own washes.
The best of these pages are considerably better than their counterparts in Copy I-1 and thus tend to discredit
them, though since we know nothing about the time or circumstances of either copy, and since we are aware of
the variety of effects Blake was capable of achieving in various copies of the illuminated books, all such
deducations must be extremely tentative.</p>
            <p>Lange (1981-82) has reported the rediscovery of a White Death copy mentioned in a note on page
92 of the Introduction of the Clarendon edition but not included in the new Census because it had been out of
sight since 1926. He points out that the combination of characteristics in this copy necessitates listing it
as Copy I-12A, rather than as I-16, and he correctly complains that this awkwardness of designation results
from our unfortunate attempt to employ small variations as a principle of organization for the new Census.
Since Copy I-12A, though extremely well preserved, is simply one of the many copies commercially colored for
Edwards, like Copies I-2 to I-14, however, no great issue is at stake in this particular case.</p>
            <p>More important is Lange’s soon-to-be amplified demonstration that the three pages in which
the coloring went bad are the result of unintended oxidation of the pigments, rather than the employment of
odd colors for symbolic purposes either by Blake or colorists in Edwards’ shop. In the Clarendon edition
this phenomenon is referred to as “Grotesque Coloring,” an unhappy phrase chosen to keep open the
possibility that the blotched paint on Disease in 6E (p. 10) is deliberate rather than coincidental. I myself
had come to the same conclusion that these colors are accidental before seeing Lange’s compelling evidence
that the colors were never intended to look as they do now in unrestored copies. (Copy I-12A, now on loan to
the Morgan Library, has been beautifully restored.) Whether our attempt to hedge on the possibility of
purposiveness be attributed to carelessness, timidity, or ignorance, would that we had laid the ghost of
purposive “Grotesque Colouring” before publication of the Clarendon edition!</p>
            <p>Some of the other things the Clarendon Introduction attempts to do fail quite badly. Apparently
no reviewer checked out our tedious attempt (pp. 17-35) to enumerate the alterations of the various states of
the engravings. Mitchell (1982) in an unscholarly way, indeed, tried to poke fun at this whole enumerative
undertaking. Yet the information had to be presented because Blake the engraver thought that minute
alterations often needed to be made. Such matters are wearisome to report in words, but they are as much the
concern of true scholarship as the reporting of manuscript variants in writing. Insofar as Mitchell wished
merely to object that such unengaging data are made unduly prominent in the large type of the Introduction, he
had a point. But his dyspathies with exact reporting go deeper than that. Unfortunately, the whole job will
have to be done over again, in the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> commentary volume, because the 1980
edition contains too many inaccuracies. The errors of fact in these matters, as well as the neglect to include
a chart of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>—Notebook correlations that had already been included in the
Erdman-Moore edition of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> (see Grant 1982, 7 and 
<hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>, pp. 51-52), the absence of captions for the final engraved designs, and the absence of
an overall system of plate numbers for all the pictures, can indeed be attributed to the “sheer
carelessness” that Dörrbecker finds in other features of the book.</p>
            <p>The descriptions of the first, second, and fifth of the (uncolored) engravings for Edwards’
1797 edition of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, for example, contain many lapses or lacunae; in consequence,
the viewer is not assisted to grasp Blake’s purposes in introducing significant variations in the designs as
he prepared them to be issued as engravings. Here are sample corrections that do not involve rewriting the
entries for two of the pictures in the Table of Engraved Designs: <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 6 (I.[1]);
1E (title page), Clarendon pp. 17-18, and <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 20 (I. 15); 5E (p. 8), Clarendon p.
19. Concerning <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 6 (illus. 8), we remarked: “the watercolor is a full-page
picture, painted edge-to-edge, thus differentiating it from most other pictures in Night the First (e.g. 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 20) which were deliberately not carried to the edge of the paper.” This indicates that 
<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 6 is a late addition to the pictures, since only a few after Night the First were painted in
the deliberately reduced format. (Our comment, Clarendon edition, p. 88, n. 34, on this stylistic aspect does
not really face the issue.) The text panel for <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 6 was surrounded by seven framing lines of
varying thickness such as were employed for subsequent title pages. The running text panels have only a single
framing line. My inference is that these lines were added in Edwards’ shop after the text pages
              <pb id="p18-176" n="176"/>
<figure n="NightThoughts.1E.Proofs.page4.18.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="865" height="1000">
	<head>8. <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 1E, Private Proofs, page 4, First State (NT 6).</head>
</figure>
<pb id="p18-177" n="177"/>
were mounted in windows in the drawing paper but before Blake began to work on them. The engraving of 1E lacks
the decisive ruled edges that appear first in 3E (<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 14). In what we refer to as the first
state, “Private Proofs, p. 4,” we declare that the “mother’s foot will be indicated later.” It is
not in fact shown in any state. We neglect to mention that two prime indications of this priority of the first
state are, first, that the mother has a pointed nose and receding chin, as in the water color but not the
published engraving. And second, that the ground is indicated only by sketchy contour lines, not hatching, as
in later states. Also the hands of the receiving angels above the text panel are outstretched rather than bent
down as in <hi rend="i">both</hi> the water color <hi rend="i">and</hi> the later engraved states. The eyes of
the aspiring girl who stands in Death’s hand are more distinct than in either the water color or the later
states. And the semi-draped female spirit above her, who is being received by the angels, is as distinct as
any other figure in the first state, whereas in the water color (which includes noteworthy pentimenti
indicating that the figure was shortened), the flying figure becomes a transparent spirit, an idea retained in
subsequent states. One might infer that Blake already intended to add the shading to indicate that the flying
female is a spirit but that he was, as artist, preoccupied in the (surviving) first state with defining other
details before finishing the picture for the public.</p>
            <p>It is always a nice question as to which stage in the evolution of a work of art the critic is
justified in premising the full potentiality of implication that a finished work affirms. The fact that the
mouth of Death is clearly (but not prominently) indicated in the first state but <hi rend="i">not</hi> in the
water color or in later states of the plate is not a difference that can be attributed to accident. Yet one
should hesitate to attribute a symbolic import to this deliberate alteration—to declare, for example, that
the diminution of pictorial attention to the mouth “means” that Blake was intent on avoiding any
implication, at this stage of his narrative, of “Death the Devourer.”</p>
            <p>On the other hand, a major pictorial element in all stages of the developing picture, such as
the long hair agitated by the wind blowing it to the right exhibited both by the woman standing in Death’s
hand and the flying female spirit, demands recognition and interpretation because it is presented in
unmistakable contrast with the unvexed hair of the other figures, most notably with that of the deliberately
bound hair of the woman with the distaff and the slack hair and beard of the giant form of Death as he first
appears in the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> series. Later, of course, as in <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> 20 (5E), Death’s hair too is whipped by the wind—and his eyes are opened—as he frantically
strikes at the sun: Young’s “insensate archer” (who also stimulated Byron in <hi rend="i">Childe
Harold</hi> I, st. 91) there shows an aspect the viewer could not have told at the outset. The details of 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 6 (1E), more accurately reported, would veto our Nota Bene that “the watercolor
is closer to proof state two than state one.” But they increase the likelihood that the First engraved State
preceded the water color.</p>
            <p>The water color for <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 20 (illus. 9), on the other hand, surely
preceded the engraving, 5E, (the order one would, of course, have expected) because it is not an edge-to-edge
picture: the feathers on Death’s Dart fade out sketchily in the upper corner where there was plenty of space
to have indicated them. Both at the left and at the bottom much pictorial space is deliberately unoccupied, in
contrast to the essentially full-plate style of engraving. As we indicate, the image was reversed in
engraving, to produce a recto design. This reversal makes for awkwardness in reporting the right and left
sides for corresponding details. In the water color the crown for the king beneath the outstretched leg of
Death has four spikes while the crown for the king beneath the vertical leg (as we neglected to specify) shows
six spikes. In the engraving both crowns show five spikes. The head of the king beneath the vertical leg is
little changed in the first state of the engraving except that his hair is indicated and a collar and
medallion are added at the throat. The change in the other head is more remarkable, and problematic. In the
first state of the engraving the features of this king, a youngish man with a moustache, are shown in profile;
his hair appears on both sides of his head, which seems at first simply to have been cut off by the bottom
edge of the plate. But the king’s crown appears in the corner as though it had fallen off; within and above
it is a piledup mound, which more closely resembles hair than engraved lines that delineate the curve of the
earth and contours of the ground. This mound is off-center in relation to the crown but is painted (normally
<hi rend="i">not</hi> by Blake) reddish-purple in Type I colored copies, as though it were a regal cloth
lining for the crown. In Type II colored copies (also probably not by Blake), it is painted brown, like hair.
These details of coloring at least tell us what the colorists took the mound to be. Another detail of the
engraving we neglected to specify is that in the engraving a tail of Death’s robe crosses the throat of this
king, suggesting that he is being strangled by the robe as well as by the foot of insolent Death, who, having
trodden two kings whose torsos are twisted together in a single shroud, now has his dart poised to strike the
very sun.</p>
            <p>More thorough reporting of the details of the engraving might have allayed Dörrbecker’s
judgment (p. 138, n. 21) that our description and suggested interpretation of water color <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> 20 are “fantastic.” Dörrbecker wishes to maintain that the king’s head beneath Death’s
outstretched foot in the water color version
<pb id="p18-178" n="178"/>
is invisible for no other reason than that it was twisted so that all that can be seen is the bottom of a
chin; and that the providing of a face in the engraved version was simply a matter of facilitating
recognition. We had stated flatly that this king was decapitated in the water color and had remarked earlier
(p. 13) that this representation was politically “provocative,” obviously because it would recall the fate
of the King of France. Once the reader has discerned that Dörrbecker’s citation of a painting ascribed to
the <corr type="emend">Pollaiuolos</corr> is a red herring, having nothing to do with the question of whether decapitation is indicated
in either Blake’s water color or his engraving, it is evident that his counter-evidence has no force.
Conceivably what the viewer is supposed to see in the water color is indeed the underside of the chin rather
than a head cut off above the neck. But the crown is not on the king’s head in either version: 
<hi rend="i">some</hi> king has been uncrowned. And this king is twisted into the same shroud as another dead
king, one still wearing his crown. Let us forego the possibility (I believe it to be a certain implication in
both cases) of decollation. Let us suppose instead that in 1797 Blake had been called into court because of
his dubious political associations. Question: “Mr. Blake, which two degraded kings are we supposed to think
of when we look at this picture of yours?” Answer: “The kings of Asia, Your Honour. The kings of Japan and
China.”</p>
            <p>The description on page 18 of the Clarendon edition of the water color for <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> 8 (I.[3]) (illus. 8) is too perfunctory and does not provide a clear enough basis for explaining
the slightly varied picture that becomes engraving 2E (p. 1). In the foreground a young man, muffled in a robe
except for his head and the toes of his sandalled right foot, rests on his right side and leans on his right
elbow with his body stretched out in front of a sleeping dog and a flock of sheep. Near his head a vine with
thirteen leaves stretches up the left side of the text panel, while in the starry night sky the angel-winged
figure of Sleep hovers in the air and touches the flock with a wand. Above the text panel, against the
background of a break in the clouds, a small male figure with a visible but indistinct face sleeps on his left
side underneath a coverlet. The dog has long curly hair, and the heads of a horned ram and two ewes are
distinguishable in the flock. The text confirms that the figure in the foreground is Young the insomniac, who
has a tense sleepless look about his eyes as he stares into space, not meeting the look of the viewer. The
coverlet on his right arm is curiously draped, suggesting that he holds a long thin object that hangs down to
a point just above the ground: this object seems to me to have the shape of a (foreshortened) book.</p>
            <p>The water color, which was contracted on three sides, has been expanded in the engraving by
adding grass to the left edge of the plate and in the foreground, as well as by straightening the sky enclave
above the text. In the engraved version it becomes virtually a fullplate design. Young’s face becomes less
tense, and his eyes are more heavily lidded. The coverlet over the hidden object has deeper folds, but the
covered object still suggests a book. The dog is now shorter haired and the quality of his coat becomes hardly
distinguishable from that of the sheep. Above the dog the back and ears of another sheep have been added in
what had been an indistinct area, while the rumps of three more sheep and the left horn of the ram have been
added. The staff of Sleep is slimmer, the coverlet on the sleeping man above the text panel is symmetrically
twisted (in a possibly sinister manner), while the thirty-six stars are in almost exactly the same positions
they were in in the water color. The stars appear to be arranged in particular constellations (which I have
not been able to identify); the arrangement may add some further overtone of significance.</p>
            <p>It is unlikely, however, that the stars are as important as the suggestion of a muffled book
hidden beneath the coverlet of Young the insomniac. Appearing as it does at the end of the varied book-scroll
sequence of <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 2, 5, 6 (illus. 8), and especially facing design 7, and linking with the
books shown in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 14 (3E), <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 18 (4E), and <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 34 (9E),
the hidden book in <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 8 represents an important stage in the relation of the author with his
text. Several possibilities suggest themselves, once the viewer concedes the likelihood that if the object is
a book it must be Young’s own poem, <hi rend="i">The Complaint and the Consolation or Night Thoughts on
Life, Death, and Immortality</hi>, which the author is at pains to conceal.</p>
            <p>If we take as a starting point Blake’s later motto, “No Secrecy in Art” (E 1982, 275) and
infer that the vine with thirteen leaves that grows up next to Young, together with his concealed book,
indicate the results of bad influences on his spirit, we will not place too much trust in Young’s book. Yet
Blake’s vast project of illustrating the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> must have proceeded on the faith
that the poem constitutes a base worth building on: most details in most pictures are in accord with the
spirit and letter of Young’s poem. But Blake must also have believed that he was authorized by the spirit
from prophecy to add much from his own visionary perspective in order to free the visionary elements of
Young’s poem from their all-too-often timorous author and place the whole work in the light of prophecy. In
suggesting at the outset of the poem that there is something resembling a book beneath a cloak of
respectability in <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 8, Blake had begun the task of rectification. The rest of
the pictures are designed to bring Young’s latent imaginings and evasions out into the open.</p>
            <pb id="p18-179" n="179"/>
            <figure n="BUT330.1.20.WC" rend="file" width="785" height="1000">
              <head>9. <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 20, Night the First, page 15 (Cf. 5E), by permission
of the Trustees of the British Museum.</head>
            </figure>
            <figure n="BUT330.1.8.WC" rend="file" width="783" height="1000">
              <head>10. <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 8, Night the First, page [3] (Cf. 2E), by permission
of the Trustees of the British Museum.</head>
            </figure>
            <pb id="p18-180" n="180"/>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>BIBLIOGRAPHY</title>
              </head>
              <p><hi rend="i">William Blake’s Designs for Edward Young’s Night Thoughts: A Complete
Edition.</hi> Ed. John E. Grant, Edward J. Rose, Michael J. Tolley; co-ordinating ed. David V. Erdman. Oxford:
Clarendon Press, 1980. 2 volumes: Plates and an Introduction. (Abbrev.: “the Clarendon <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts.</hi>”)</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>REVIEWS</title>
              </head>
              <p>Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">The Burlington Magazine</hi>, 123 (June 1981), 312-13.</p>
              <p>Chayes, Irene. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Movement: A Selective and Critical Bibliography for
1980.</hi> Ed. David V. Erdman. New York and London: Garland Publishing Co., 1981), p. 75.</p>
              <p>Dörrbecker 1982: Dörrbecker, Detlef W. <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
#62, 16 (Fall, 1982), 130-39.</p>
              <p>Hagstrum 1982: Hagstrum, Jean H. <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 15 (Spring,
1982), 339-44.</p>
              <p>Halsband, Robert. <hi rend="i">JEGP</hi>, 81 (October, 1982), 576-77.</p>
              <p>Lincoln, Andrew. “Images of Solitude.” <hi rend="i">TLS</hi>, 5 June 1981, 646.</p>
              <p>Mitchell 1982: Mitchell, W.J.T. <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi>, 80 (November, 1982),
198-205.</p>
              <p>Mulhallen 1981: Mulhallen, Karen. <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi>, 12 (Summer, 1981),
157-61.</p>
              <p>Paley 1982: Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 21 (Winter, 1982),
674-82.</p>
              <p>Quennell, Peter. <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>, 114 (August, 1981), 136-37.</p>
              <p>Taylor, John Russell. <hi rend="i">The Times</hi> (London), 7 October 1980.</p>
              <p>Traister, Daniel. <hi rend="i">American Book Collector</hi>, 2 (March-April, 1981),
60-73.</p>
              <p>Vaughan, William. <hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, 5 (March, 1982), 106-09.</p>
              <p>Viscomi, Joseph. <hi rend="i">Fine Print</hi>, 8 (April, 1982), 49-50.</p>
              <p>Welch and Viscomi 1981: Welch, Dennis and Viscomi, Joseph. <hi rend="i">Philological
Quarterly</hi>, 60 (Fall, 1981), 539-42.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>OTHER REFERENCES</title>
              </head>
              <p>Behrendt 1983: Behrendt, Stephen C. <hi rend="i">The Moment of Explosion: Blake and the
Illustration of Milton.</hi> Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press, 1983.</p>
              <p>Bentley 1977: Bentley, G.E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Books: Annotated Catalogues of William
Blake’s Writings.</hi> . . . Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977; esp. Addenda item 515, pp. 956-57.</p>
              <p>Bentley 1978: Bentley, G.E., Jr. Ed., <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings.</hi> Oxford:
Clarendon Press, 1978; esp. II, 1404.</p>
              <p>Bindman 1975: Bindman, David, et al. <hi rend="i">William Blake, 1757-1827.</hi> Munich:
Prestel, 1975. Pp. 178-84. No. 86 in Clarendon <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi></p>
              <p>Butlin 1978: Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> London: Tate Gallery, 1978.
Esp. pp. 66-71 and color plate for #106.</p>
              <p>Butlin 1981: Butlin, Martin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake.</hi>
New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1981.</p>
              <p>Erdman, David V., annotator. <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake.</hi> Garden City: Anchor
Press/Doubleday, 1974.</p>
              <p>E 1982: Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William
Blake</hi>, with a commentary by Harold Bloom. Garden City: Anchor Press/Doubleday; Berkeley and Los Angeles:
University of California Press, 1982.</p>
              <p>Erdman 1983: Erdman, David V. “Redefining the Texts of Blake (another temporary report).”
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> #65, 17 (Summer, 1983), esp. 12.</p>
              <p>Erdman, David V. and Moore, Donald K. <hi rend="i">The Notebook of William Blake: A
Photographic and Typographic Facsimile.</hi> New York: Readex Books, rev. 1977. No. 81 in Clarendon 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi></p>
              <p>Essick 1982: Essick, Robert N. Review of Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of
William Blake.</hi> In <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> #61, 16 (Summer, 1982), 22-65.</p>
              <p>Essick 1983: Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A
Catalogue.</hi> Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1983.</p>
              <p>Essick, Robert and La Belle, Jenijoy, eds. <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts or, The Complaint and
the Consolation: Illustrated by William Blake, Text</hi>
	<pb id="p18-181" n="181"/>
	<hi rend="i">by Edward Young.</hi> New York: Dover Publications, 1975. No. 83 in Clarendon <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts.</hi></p>
              <p>Gabbett-Mulhallen, Karen A. “William Blake’s Illustrations to Edward Young’s 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>: Context, Christology and Composite Work.” Unpublished dissertation. University
of Toronto, 1975. 3 vols. No. 84 in Clarendon <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi> The text, without plates,
recently released for circulation in microfiche.</p>
              <p>Grant 1970: Grant, John E. “Envisioning the First <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>,” in
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic.</hi> Ed. David V. Erdman and John E. Grant. Princeton:
Princeton University Press, 1970. Pp. 304-35. No. 54 in Clarendon <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi></p>
              <p>Grant 1982: Grant, John E. “Some Drawings Related to Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> Designs: The Coda Sketch and Two Pictures Not Previously Connected With the Series,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> #61, 16 (Summer, 1982), 7-11.</p>
              <p>Hagstrum, Jean H. “Christ’s Body,” in <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays in Honour of
Sir Geoffrey Keynes.</hi> Ed. Morton D. Paley and Michael Phillips. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1974. Pp. 129-56.
No. 74 in Clarendon <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi></p>
              <p>Hill, Gillian McMahon. “Blake as Interpreter: His Illustrations of Young, Gray, and Blair
with a Descriptive Catalogue of, and Subject Index to, the Drawings for Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts.</hi>” Unpublished dissertation. Exeter University, 1972.</p>
              <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Writings of William Blake with Variant
Readings.</hi> London: Oxford University Press, 1966.</p>
              <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. <hi rend="i">Illustrations to Young’s Night Thoughts: Done in
Water-Colour by William Blake.</hi> Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1927. No. 19 in Clarendon 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi></p>
              <p>Lange 1981-82: Lange, Thomas V. “A Rediscovered Copy of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> #59, 15 (Winter 1981-82), 134-36.</p>
              <p>Paley 1969: Paley, Morton D. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>: An Exploration of
the Fallen World,” in <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays for S. Foster Damon.</hi> Ed. Alvin H. Rosenfeld.
Providence: Brown University Press, 1969. Pp. 131-57. No. 49 in Clarendon <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts.</hi></p>
              <p>Paley 1971: Paley, Morton D. Review of Erdman and Grant, eds., <hi rend="i">Blake’s
Visionary Forms Dramatic. Blake Studies</hi>, 4 (Fall, 1971), 93-99.</p>
              <p>Paley 1978: Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> London: Phaidon Press,
1978.</p>
              <p>Paley and Phillips 1973: Morton D. Paley and Michael Phillips, eds. <hi rend="i">William
Blake: Essays in Honour of Sir Geoffrey Keynes.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1973.</p>
              <p>Rose, Edward J. “<hi rend="i">Ut Pictura Poesis</hi> and the Problem of Pictorial Statement
in William Blake,” in <hi rend="i">Woman in the Eighteenth Century and Other Esays.</hi> Ed. Peter Fritz and
Richard Morton. Toronto and Sarasota: Samuel Stevens, Hakkert &amp; Co., 1976. Pp. 279-99. No. 96 in Clarendon
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi></p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
