<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>18.3.toc</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="toc">Contents</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1984-85</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1984-85</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">18.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Shelley M. Bennett</name>
              <name>James Bogan</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Christopher Fox</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>W.J.T. Mitchell</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Nicholas O. Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1984-85"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_18">
    <front>
      <pb id="p18-129-130" n="129-130"/>
      <div1 id="cover">
        <figure n="cover.018.03.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="335">
          <figTranscr>Blake<lb/>
            AN ILLUSTRATED QUARTERLY<lb/>
            VOLUME 18<lb/>
            NUMBER 3<lb/>
            WINTER 1984-85</figTranscr>
        </figure>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-3-0001">
        <table id="contents" rows="16" cols="2">
          <row>
            <cell>
        	  <head>
          		<title>
            	  <hi rend="b">
              		<hi rend="i">CONTENTS</hi>
            	  </hi>
          		</title>
        	  </head>
            </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.3.bennett">A Newly Discovered Blake at the Huntington</ref> by
Shelley M. Bennett</cell>
            <cell>132</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">
                <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
              </hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.3.warner">Visual Analogues to Blake’s “The Dog”</ref> by
Nicholas O. Warner</cell>
            <cell>140</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">
                <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
              </hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.3.fox">R.D. Stock, <hi rend="i">The Holy and the Daemonic from
Sir Thomas Browne to William Blake</hi></ref>, reviewed by Christopher Fox</cell>
            <cell>144</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.3.reiman">James King and Charles Ryskamp, eds., 
<hi rend="i">The Letters and Prose Writings of William Cowper</hi></ref>, reviewed by Donald H. Reiman</cell>
            <cell>146</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.3.bogan">John Beer, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi></ref>,
reviewed by James Bogan</cell>
            <cell>151</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.3.fischer">Jerome J. McGann, <hi rend="i">The Romantic
Ideology: A Critical Investigation</hi></ref>, reviewed by Michael Fischer</cell>
            <cell>152</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">
                <hi rend="i">DISCUSSION</hi>
              </hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.3.grant">A Re-View of Some Problems in Understanding Blake’s
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi></ref> by John E. Grant</cell>
            <cell>155</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.3.mitchell">Reply to John Grant</ref> by W.J.T.
Mitchell</cell>
            <cell>181</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.3.paley">Further Thoughts on <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi></ref> by Morton D. Paley</cell>
            <cell>183</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell><ref type="article" issue="18.3.dorrbecker">Grant’s “Problems in Understanding”: Some
Marginalia</ref> by D.W. Dörrbecker</cell>
            <cell>185</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <hi rend="b">
                <hi rend="i">NEWSLETTER</hi>
              </hi>
            </cell>
            <cell/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>
              <ref type="article" issue="18.3.records">Supplement to <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi></ref>, 
              <ref type="article" issue="18.3.frye">Frye on Film</ref>
            </cell>
            <cell>191</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-3-0002">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">CONTRIBUTORS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="b">SHELLEY M. BENNETT</hi>, Associate Curator of British Art, Henry E. Huntington Library
and Art Gallery, San Marino, California, publishes on various aspects of British art, particularly eighteenth
century book illustration.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">JAMES BOGAN</hi> is an Associate Professor of Art &amp; Film at the University of
Missouri-Rolla. With Les Blank he has recently co-edited <hi rend="i">Burden of Dreams</hi> (North Atlantic
Books), a casebook on the film which features Werner Herzog and the Amazon River.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">D.W. DÖRRBECKER</hi>, who teaches art history at the University of Trier in West
Germany, is presently conducting a course on the etchings of Rembrandt. He feels that—by way of
contrast—even this can be helpful for one’s attempt to understand the peculiarities of Blake’s graphic
style.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">MICHAEL FISCHER</hi> is an Associate Professor of English at the University of New
Mexico. He is the author of <hi rend="i">Does Deconstruction Make Any Difference?</hi> (Indiana University
Press) and co-editor (with Morris Eaves) of <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Contemporary Criticism</hi>
(forthcoming, Cornell University Press).</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">CHRISTOPHER FOX</hi> teaches English at Wilkes College, edited <hi rend="i">Psychology
and Literature in the 18th Century</hi> (AMS Press, forthcoming), and authored “Locke and the Scriblerians:
The Discussion of Identity in Early Eighteenth-Century England,” which placed third and received an
honorable mention for the James L. Clifford Prize (1982-83).</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">JOHN E. GRANT</hi>, Professor of English at the University of Iowa, is co-editor of
the Norton Critical Edition <hi rend="i">Blake’s Poetry and Designs</hi> and author of numerous articles on
Blake’s work.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">W.J.T. MITCHELL</hi> is the author of <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art</hi> and
has edited several volumes of essays, including <hi rend="i">The Language of Images</hi> and <hi rend="i">The
Politics of Interpretation.</hi> He is the editor of <hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry</hi> and Professor of
English and Art and Design at the University of Chicago. His new book, <hi rend="i">Iconology: Image, Text,
Ideology</hi>, will be published later this year.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">MORTON D. PALEY’s</hi> latest book is <hi rend="i">The Continuing City: William
Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem, published by Oxford University Press. He is now completing a study of the
Apocalyptic Sublime in British art.</p>
        <pb id="p18-131" n="131"/>
        <p><hi rend="b">DONALD H. REIMAN</hi>, Editor of <hi rend="i">Shelley and his Circle</hi> (Harvard
Univ. Press) and General Editor of <hi rend="i">The Bodleian Shelley Manuscripts</hi> (Garland), is currently
preparing the annual review of scholarship on the literature of the nineteenth century for 
<hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature.</hi></p>
        <p><hi rend="b">NICHOLAS O. WARNER</hi>, Assistant Professor of Literature at Claremont McKenna
College, has published articles in <hi rend="i">The Colby Library Quarterly</hi> and <hi rend="i">The
Explicator</hi>, as well as this and other scholarly journals.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-3-0003">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">EDITORS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="b">Editors:</hi> Morris Eaves, University of New Mexico, and Morton D. Paley, University
of California, Berkeley.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Bibliographer:</hi> Thomas L. Minnick, Ohio State University.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Review Editor:</hi> Nelson Hilton, University of Georgia, Athens.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Associate Editor for Great Britain:</hi> Frances A. Carey, Assistant Curator,
Department of Prints and Drawings, British Museum.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Production Office:</hi> Morris Eaves, Department of English, University of New Mexico,
Albuquerque, NM 87131, <hi rend="b">Telephone</hi> 505/277-3103.<lb/>
Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley, CA 94720.<lb/>
Thomas L. Minnick, University College, Ohio State University, 1050 Carmack Road, Columbus, OH 43210.<lb/>
Nelson Hilton, Department of English, University of Georgia, Athens, GA 30602.<lb/>
Frances A. Carey, Department of Prints and Drawings, British Museum, Great Russell Street, London WC1B 3DG,
United Kingdom.</p>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-3-0004">
        <head>
          <title>
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">INFORMATION</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <p><hi rend="b">Managing Editor:</hi> Robin Tawney.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Editorial Assistants:</hi> Leslie Donovan, Chapel Petty Schmitt, University of New
Mexico.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is published under the sponsorship of the
Department of English, University of New Mexico.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Subscriptions</hi> are $ 18 for institutions, $ 15 for individuals. All subscriptions
are by the volume (1 year, 4 issues) and begin with the summer issue. Subscription payments received after the
summer issue will be applied to the 4 issues of the current volume. Foreign addresses (except Canada and
Mexico) require a $ 3 per volume postal surcharge for surface mail, a $ 10 per volume surcharge for air mail
delivery. U.S. currency or international money order necessary. Make checks payable to <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly.</hi> Address all subscription orders and related communications to Robin Tawney, 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, Department of English, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, NM 87131, USA.</p>
        <p>Many <hi rend="b">back issues</hi> are available at a reduced price. Address Robin Tawney for a
list of issues and prices.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">Manuscripts</hi> are welcome. Send two copies, typed and documented according to the
forms suggested in the MLA Style Sheet, 2nd ed., to either of the editors: Morris Eaves, Dept. of English,
University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, NM 87131; Morton D. Paley, Dept. of English, University of California,
Berkeley, CA 94720.</p>
        <p><hi rend="b">International Standard Serial Number:</hi> 0006-453x. <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> is indexed in the Modern Language Associations International Bibliography, the
Modern Humanities Research Association’s Annual Bibliography of English Language and Literature, 
<hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi>’ annual Romantic Bibliography, ART bibliographies MODERN, American
Humanities Index, and the Arts and Humanities Citation Index. <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">© 1984
Morris Eaves and Morton D. Paley</note></p>
      </div1>
    </front>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
