<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>18.4.ostriker</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">Reply to Hagstrum</title>
        <author n="Ostriker">Alicia Ostriker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1985</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">18.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Wayne Glausser</name>
              <name>Jean H. Hagstrum</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1985"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_18">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-4-0009">
        <pb id="p18-238" n="238"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Reply to Hagstrum</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Alicia <name>Ostriker</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>One can never be sure about such things, but I hope my opinions on <hi rend="i">Clarissa</hi> are
unrelated to snobbery, of the Yale variety or otherwise. When I say that the novel is soft-core pornography, I
mean that, like pornography, it creates a closed world in which nothing is important but sex—or, more
precisely, sexual dominance. It is of the persecuted-maiden variety so thoroughly elaborated later in Sade’s
<hi rend="i">Justine</hi>, which uses many of the same plot devices (a useful book on this subject is Angela
Carter’s <hi rend="i">The Sadeian Woman and the Ideology of Pornography</hi>, Pantheon 1980). It is
soft-core because it merely teases, while feeding, the desires and anxieties of its audience. It is an
ancestor of soap opera in its conduct of plot-as-ongoing-crisis, the attractive villainy and virtue of its
characters, and its exclusive concentration on personal relationships. It is a work of genius in that it is
able to sustain, for hundreds of pages, an interest in Clarissa’s little curtain of flesh, while maintaining
a perfect, pure, moral high-mindedness.</p>
          <p>As to the impact of <hi rend="i">Clarissa</hi> on Blake: I have elsewhere presented my views on
the complex issue of Blake and sexuality (“Desire Gratified and Ungratified: William Blake and Sexuality,”
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, winter 1982-83). I agree with Hagstrum that Blake (in part) belongs to the Age of
Sensibility. Pathos is, as Morton Paley has recently pointed out, one of his chief effects. The persecuted and
suffering female recurs significantly throughout his work. Richardson’s cankered-flower passage may well
have inspired the rhetoric as well as the metaphor of “The Sick Rose.” Nevertheless, Blake’s letter to
Hayley has to my ear the ring of something written under duress, and when we recall the gap between
conventional piety and Blakean impiety, it is not hard to understand why.</p>
          <p>Where would Richardson and his palpitating audience have been without Moral Virtue? But to Blake
Moral Virtue was the result of a pathological failure of the human imagination; in his mid-thirties he was an
advocate of free love and considered marriage a sick institution; at no time in his career does he admire
sexual purity, much less equate it with sainthood. Clarissa expires in the arms of her bridegroom, Christ, but
as an old man Blake was still exploding: “Was Jesus Chaste?” In the area of filial obedience we find the
same distinction: Richardson approves submissiveness (even when the parents are monsters), Blake admires
rebellion. At no point does Richardson question any of the social and religious institutions Blake spent his
life trying to overthrow. And so <hi rend="i">Clarissa</hi> was a pan-European bestseller, and Blake was an
unknown.</p>
          <p>One small point: Blake’s gallery of types includes rapists but not rakes. I think it is a
mistake to call the smooth, calculating and mannered Lovelace “Orcan,” though he surely resembles
Milton’s seductive and self-deluding Satan.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
