<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>18.4.essick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The Four Zoas: Intention and Production</title>
        <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1985</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">18.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Wayne Glausser</name>
              <name>Jean H. Hagstrum</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1985"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_18">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-4-0007">
        <pb id="p18-216" n="216"/>
        <head>
          <title type="main"><hi rend="i">The Four Zoas:</hi> Intention and Production</title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="i">by</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">ROBERT N.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">ESSICK</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>Paul Mann’s challenging theory in “The Final State of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>” offers
an opportunity for others to test their sense of Blake’s plans for his long and various manuscript poem.
Mann very kindly allowed me to read his essay before publication and accepted my suggestion that I send to
this journal a companion piece in the hope that the two articles together will produce more light than would
either in isolation. I wish merely to pursue a few lines of speculation that support his basic theory but
evolve into a hypothesis about Blake’s first plans for his text.</p>
        <p>I trust it has become something of a truism that Blake was much concerned with the processes and
materials of publication. A man trained to the book and print business of his time who also invented a number
of unconventional ways of producing and distributing images could hardly avoid such interests. A corollary
proposition is that Blake’s works are media specific—that is, his images (whether pictorial or
calligraphic) differ in some observable ways because of the different technologies used to produce them. Given
the practical exigencies of image production, as well as Blake’s insistence on the radical unity of
conception and execution,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">1</ref> it is
reasonable to assume that the preliminary stages in the development of an image <hi rend="i">may</hi> reveal
the medium in which Blake intended to produce the final form of that image. I take this to be the perspective,
as well as the context in which we are to understand the meaning of “intention,” implicit in Mann’s
essay. I share that perspective and usage, and thus I will also view <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
manuscript not only as the “text” of a “poem” (i.e., the physical embodiment of an aesthetic
experience) but also as a preliminary—perhaps even a mockup—for a subsequent work never executed. 
<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See, for example, Blake’s statement that “Invention depends Altogether upon
Execution or Organization” in his annotations (c. 1808) to Reynolds’ <hi rend="i">Discourses</hi> and
similar statements in the <hi rend="i">Public Address</hi> (c. 1811). The best and most recent study of this
central principle of Blake’s aesthetics is Morris Eaves, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Theory of Art</hi>
(Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1982), Chap. III.</note></p>
        <p>Is <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> manuscript the signifier of an unrealized intention to produce
the poem in some other form? The physical condition of the work as we know it, with its deletions, erasures,
marginal insertions, and designs rendered as pencil sketches, immediately suggests as much. Mann has argued
cogently that Blake did not intend to create a single illuminated manuscript—either the one we have or
another never executed—as an end in itself. Such works are generally produced on commission only, much as
Blake was hired by Flaxman, Butts and others to make watercolored illustrations to the works of other poets,
but it is difficult even to imagine a late eighteenth-century sponsor for an epic like <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>
or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> This does not, of course, allow us to rule out completely the theory that
Blake originally planned to create a beautiful illuminated manuscript as his final product and only later
allowed it to degenerate into a working draft. Yet, as Mann suggests, Blake’s entire career as a publisher
indicates a consistent desire to find a wider audience for his poetry than the very limited number of people
who could see, read, and be moved by a unique manuscript. From the prospectus of October 1793 to the first
chapter of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (c. 1804-1820), Blake addressed himself “To the Public”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">2</ref> and tried an extraordinary range of media and
publication methods to reach them. <note id="n43"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i"> The Complete Poetry and
Prose of William Blake</hi>, Newly Revised Edition, ed. David V. Erdman (Berkeley and Los Angeles: Univ. of
Calif. Press, 1982), pp. 145 (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, pl. 3), 692 (1793 prospectus).</note></p>
        <p>The development of Blake’s publishing efforts in the mid- and late-1790s provides some sense of
the range of media he had available for the publication of his illustrated poetry. In 1795, Blake published
<hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> (illus. 4). Both have texts etched
in intaglio, whereas the other illuminated books were printed from letters etched in relief.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">3</ref> The visual differences between intaglio and
relief letters are less significant than the considerable changes in production procedures. It is not at all
clear why Blake abandoned his own invention, relief etching, which he trumpeted as both a practical and
beautiful method of self-publication in his 1793 prospectus, and returned to a far more conventional
medium.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">4</ref> The Books of Los and Ahania
are also notable for their paucity of interlinear decoration, as in letterpress, even though the intaglio
medium would not in itself prohibit the root and vine motifs punctuating <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>
or even larger and more elaborate designs set anywhere on the page. Clearly, Richard Edwards’ 1797 edition
of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, with a typographic text surrounded by intaglio designs on
slightly less than half the printed pages, bears a special relationship to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>
But we should also keep in mind <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>,
for they indicate the medium Blake chose for the production of his <hi rend="i">own</hi> poetry published
closest in time to the beginning of his labors on <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">3</hi> The one exception discovered to date is the title page of <hi rend="i">The
Song of Los</hi> (1795), which appears to have been printed planographically. See Essick, <hi rend="i">William
Blake, Printmaker</hi> (Princeton: Princeton Univ. Press, 1980), pp. 128-29. This title page, like the
evolution of the 1795 color printed drawings, offers further evidence of Blake’s movement away from relief
etching in the mid-1790s.</note>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">4</hi> There are a number of English eighteenth-century books with etched and/or
engraved texts, including several illustrated editions of Philip Ayres, <hi rend="i">Emblems of Love.</hi>
Several Continental publications of considerable length were completely engraved, including a Virgil in five
volumes (The Hague: Henry Justice, 1753-1767) and an edition of Ovid’s <hi rend="i">Metamorphoses</hi> in
141 plates (Paris: <corr type="emend">Basan et Lemire,</corr> plates dated 1767-1770).</note>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">5</hi> G.E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press,
1977), pp. 454-55, and Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">Poetry and Prose of Blake</hi>, p. 817, agree that Blake
worked on the manuscript c. 1796-1807. <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> summarizes the information Bentley first
presented in his facsimile edition of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> (Oxford:
Clarendon Press, 1963) and repeated in his edition of <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi> (Oxford:
Clarendon Press, 1978), II, 1721-32.</note></p>
        <p>Turning to the manuscript itself, we can immediately see that some pages are written in what
Bentley calls a “Copperplate Hand” (illus. 1), others in a related
      <pb id="p18-210" n="210"/>
        <figure n="BB209.1.23.MS" rend="file" width="796" height="1000">
          <head>1. Blake.</head>
          <figDesc><hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, page 23. Pen &amp; ink
manuscript with ink and pencil drawing, c. 1797-1800? Sheet approx. 42 × 32.5 cm. Courtesy of the British
Library.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p18-211" n="211"/>
        <figure n="BB209.1.43.MS" rend="file" width="789" height="1000">
          <head>2. Blake.</head>
          <figDesc><hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, page 43. Pen &amp; ink
manuscript (c. 1800-1804?) on a published-state impression of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
etching/engraving, page 63 in the 1797 edition. Sheet approx. 42 × 35.2 cm. Courtesy of the British
Library.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p18-212" n="212"/>
        <figure n="BB209.1.59.MS" rend="file" width="805" height="1000">
          <head>3. Blake.</head>
          <figDesc><hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, page 59. Pen &amp; ink
manuscript (c. 1800-1804?) on a second-state proof impression of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
etching/engraving, page 73 in the 1797 edition. Sheet approx. 42 × 35.2 cm. Courtesy of the British
Library.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p18-213" n="213"/>
        <figure n="ahania.a.p3" id="ahania.a.illbk.03" work-copy="ahania.a" rend="db" width="726" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>AHANIA<lb/>
              <lb/>
              Chap: Ist<lb/>
              <lb/>
              1: Fuzon. on a chariot iron-wing’d<lb/>
              On spiked flames rose; his hot visage<lb/>
              Flam’d furious! sparkles his hair &amp; beard<lb/>
              Shot down his wide bosom and shoulders<lb/>
              On clouds of smoke rages his chariot<lb/>
              And his right hand burns red in its<lb/>
                    cloud<lb/>
              Moulding into a vast globe. his wrath<lb/>
              As the thunder-stone is moulded<lb/>
              Son of Urizens silent burnings<lb/>
              <lb/>
              2: Shall we worship this Demon of smoke.<lb/>
              Said Fuzon. this abstract non-entity<lb/>
              This cloudy God seated on waters<lb/>
              Now seen. now obscur’d; King of sorrow?<lb/>
              <lb/>
              3: So he spoke. in a fiery flame,<lb/>
              On Urizen frowning indignant,<lb/>
              The Globe of wrath shaking on high<lb/>
              Roaring with fury. he threw<lb/>
              The howling Globe: burning it flew<lb/>
              Lengthning into a hungry beam. Swiftly<lb/>
              <lb/>
              4: Oppos’d to the exulting flam’d beam<lb/>
              The broad Disk of Urizen upheav’d<lb/>
              Across the Void many a mile.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              5: It was forg’d in mills where the winter<lb/>
              Beats incessant: ten winters the disk<lb/>
              <lb/>
              <lb/>
              Unremitting endur’d the cold hammer.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              6: But the strong arm that sent it. remember’d<lb/>
              The sounding beam; laughing it tore through<lb/>
              That beaten mass: keeping its direction<lb/>
              The cold loins of Urizen dividing.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              7: Dire shriek’d his invisible Lust<lb/>
              Deep groan’d Urizen! stretching his awful hand<lb/>
              Ahania (so name his parted soul)<lb/>
              He siez’d on his mountains of Jealousy,<lb/>
              He groand anguishd &amp; called her Sin,<lb/>
              Kissing her and weeping over her:<lb/>
              Then hid her in darkness in silence;<lb/>
              Jealous tho’ she was invisible.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              8: She fell down a faint shadow wandring<lb/>
              In chaos and circling dark Urizen.<lb/>
              As the moon anguishd circles the earth;<lb/>
              Hopeless! abhorrd! a death-shadow.<lb/>
              Unseen. unbodied. unknown,<lb/>
              The mother of Pestilence.<lb/>
              <lb/>
              9: But the fiery beam of Fuzon<lb/>
              Was a pillar of fire to Egypt<lb/>
              Five hundred years wandring on earth<lb/>
              Till Los siezd it and beat in a mass<lb/>
              With the body of the sun.</figTranscr>
          <head>4. Blake.</head>
          <figDesc><hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, 1795. Copy A, plate 3. Intaglio etching 13.6 × 9.8
cm. Courtesy of the Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p18-214" n="214"/>
        <figure n="BB209.1.115.MS.jv" rend="file" width="764" height="1000">
          <head>5. Blake.</head>
          <figDesc><hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, page 115. Pen &amp; ink
manuscript (c. 1800-1804?) on a third-state proof impression of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
etching/engraving, page 73 in the 1797 edition. Sheet approx. 42 × 32.5 cm. Courtesy of the British
Library.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p18-215" n="215"/>
        <figure n="BB209.1.137.MS.jv" rend="file" width="820" height="1000">
          <head>6. Blake, <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, page 137.</head>
          <figDesc>Pen &amp; ink manuscript and pencil drawing (c. 1800-1804?) on a first-state proof
impression of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> etching/engraving, page 88 in the 1797 edition. Sheet
approx. 42 × 32.5 cm. Courtesy of the British Library.</figDesc>
        </figure>
<pb id="p18-217" n="217"/>
but “Modified Copperplate Hand,” and still others in Blake’s usual plain manuscript hand (illus. 2-3,
5-6).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">6</ref> Our sense of an important
structural distinction between the copperplate and plain hands is reinforced by stab holes indicating that
Blake “had once sewed together into one group all the sheets with elegant script [i.e., both copperplate and
modified copperplate] and into another group those sheets . . . in his usual [plain] hand.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">7</ref> If we now consider the manuscript as a mockup,
it is reasonable to begin with the assumption that the three hands may indicate at least two different
intentions to publish. In what follows I will also assume that the deletions and marginal additions to pages
bearing fine script, as well as designs that intrude into fine text areas (on page 25, for example), were made
after the abandonment of whatever intentions for publication the copperplate hand(s) may embody. 
<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 455, where pp. 1-14, 17-18, 23-30 are
listed as written in copperplate hand and pp. 15-16, 31-42 in modified copperplate. Erdman, ed., 
<hi rend="i">Poetry and Prose of Blake</hi>, p. 816, records pp. 1, 3-18, 23-42 as containing all the “fine
copperplate script.” Thus the only discrepancy is p. 2, the verso of the titlepage, which bears only a
pencil sketch and a rough pencil inscription. In what follows, however, I will include that page among the
“fine script” sections since it clearly accompanies pages written in that hand.</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">Poetry and Prose of Blake</hi>, p.
817.</note></p>
        <p>Through a process of elimination and the weighing of practical probabilities, we can reach some
conclusions about the intentions that may lurk behind those sections of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
written in fine script. There would have been no reason to write in such a hand if the method of publication
was to be either letterpress or relief etching. A typographic printer must of course select one of the
available typefaces—or go to the great expense of having a new font case—regardless of the author’s
manuscript hand. All that is wanted is a clear script, as in the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> manuscript and large
portions of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> itself. As for relief etching, that is a direct process in which
the forms of the letters are composed directly on the copper. Here again, the manuscript needs to be no more
elaborate than a fair copy. Blake may have even avoided that stage of production by moving directly from a
finished working draft, of the sort found in his <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>, to the copperplate because
corrections can be made easily on the plate at any time before acid is applied. The one extant mockup for
pages in a published illuminated book is a rough pencil sketch with only horizontal lines to indicate the
approximate position of the text.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">8</ref>
There is no extant manuscript for any of the illuminated books with lettering even vaguely like the
copperplate hand(s) in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> This negative evidence cannot prove that such
manuscripts never existed; but, given the production characteristics of relief etching, there are practical
reasons why Blake need not have written such manuscripts. Even if Blake used a transfer method for applying
his texts to the surface of the copper (which I very much doubt), the letters would have to be written on
specially treated paper in a glutinous, acid-resistant material.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n50" type="note">9</ref> No part of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> manuscript meets these
requirements and it is difficult to conceive how they could be added after writing had begun. 
<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">8</hi> A drawing (sheet 22.4 × 31.7 cm.) for <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, pl. 6,
and an alternative design for pl. 7, recently acquired by the British Museum. See Martin Butlin, 
<hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (New Haven and London: Yale Univ. Press, 1981), I,
no. 218, and II, pl. 249.</note>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Such a method was invented by Ruthven Todd and W.S. Hayter and first
described by Todd in 1948. See Todd, “The Techniques of William Blake’s Illuminated Printing,” reprinted
in <hi rend="i">The Visionary Hand: Essays for the Study of William Blake’s Art and Aesthetics</hi>, ed.
Essick (Los Angeles: Hennessey &amp; Ingalls, 1973), pp. 35-36.</note></p>
        <p>We are left then with intaglio publication of text and illustration. As practiced in Blake’s day,
intaglio was an indirect process in that the image was generally developed to a fairly high level of
completeness and finish in materials—usually pencil, ink, or wash on paper—preliminary to the graphic
medium itself. This work was then transferred, often by mechanical or semimechanical means, to the copper.
Blake describes a completely mechanical transfer process in his <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>, but like most it
requires an image executed in “black lead pencil”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51"
type="note">10</ref> or chalk. In a letter to George Cumberland of 6 December 1795, Blake outlines a soft-wax
technique that works very well for transferring an intaglio print to copper for reengraving.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">11</ref> Lines printed in intaglio are raised slightly
above the surface of the paper, and thus it is possible to make an impression of them in a soft material. The
copperplate hand in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is of course in ink on paper, and I suspect that even a
soft-wax process would not permit its transfer. <note id="n51"><hi rend="s">10</hi> “To Engrave on
Pewter,” <hi rend="i">Poetry and Prose of Blake</hi>, ed. Erdman, p. 694. Joseph Viscomi has demonstrated
that Blake used this type of procedure for transferring the drawing for <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> pl. 26 to
the copper for etching in white line; see <hi rend="i">Blake: An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 16 (1982),
46.</note>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">11</hi><hi rend="i"> Poetry and Prose of Blake</hi>, ed. Erdman, p. 700.
Blake’s method is very similar to the one described in <hi rend="i">Sculptura Historico-Technica: or, the
History and Art of Engraving</hi>, Fourth Edition (London: J. Marks, 1770), pp. 99-100.</note></p>
        <p>If we must rule out mechanical transfer, the sections of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> in
copperplate hand could still serve a purpose for an intaglio etcher/engraver. After composing his script with
some care on paper, Blake could look at the manuscript in a mirror and copy it backwards onto an etching
ground or blank plate, following the manuscript letter-forms as closely as he wished within the limitations
set by a nonmechanical method. This two-step process avoids the problems of composing (as distinct from
copying) a handsome script backwards on a varnished plate or copper surface. Throughout the manuscript, Blake
has consistently limited illustration to the margins and avoided interlinear designs on major pictures set
between sections of the text on a single page. This format follows what we find in the intaglio plates of 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania.</hi> If the copperplate hand sections of
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, before deletions and insertions, are in some sense a mockup for a
publication, the most probable technology would seem to be a text etched and/or engraved in intaglio with
surrounding intaglio designs. This method of production would allow Blake to produce the entire book using
techniques in which he was thoroughly skilled and not require him, as would letterpress, to acquire the
services of journeymen with tools and materials he did not himself possess.</p>
        <p>Where would Blake acquire enough large copperplates to etch or engrave a poem anywhere near the
length of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas?</hi> Mann’s suggestion that Blake may have
acquired the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> coppers from Richard Edwards is compelling. It is certainly
possible that Blake was paid partly in copper for his labors on <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, regardless
of who retained the rights to publish the images first etched on the plates. By writing much of his poem on
unused leaves of Whatman paper also left over from the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> project, Blake insured
that the size of his text blocks and accompanying designs would fit with minimal adjustments
<pb id="p18-218" n="218"/>
onto the plates illustrating Young. We need not assume that Blake intended to use the engraved 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs themselves in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> The proofs used in the
later parts of the manuscript may be there because of similarities in format—a text panel surrounded by
designs—rather than symbolic or thematic conjunctions between Young’s poem and Blake’s. The presence of
proofs from the plate printed on page 73 of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, showing Christ crowned with
thorns, on pages 59 (illus. 3), 111, and 115 (illus. 5) of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> creates an
unusually repetitious sequence of illustrations. It is unlikely that the present arrangement of 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs in the manuscript represents the format for an intended publication of
any sort. If Blake did have the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> coppers, he could simply scrape and burnish
away the designs to Young’s poem and etch or engrave new images. The backs of the plates could also be used,
as in many of the illuminated books, for a total of eighty-six etchings and/or engravings—a good many more
than the thirty-eight pages of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> bearing fine script. Or, if one side only was
to be used, perhaps it is significant that the number of fine script pages is just five short of the number of
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> coppers.</p>
        <p>Pursuing this line of speculation a bit further, we should even consider the possibility that Blake
abandoned the idea of using all the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> plates for <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi> between c. 1804 and 1807 and began using them for <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> By then the manuscript poem may have grown too long for the forty-three known 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> coppers,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53"
type="note">12</ref> forcing on Blake some alternative publication plans if he had not already made them
before extending the poem. Exact comparisons of the sizes of the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts, Milton</hi>, and
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plates are not possible because of paper shrinkage and stretching and the
unavoidable loss of some copper when a plate is cut and its edges beveled. It is certain, however, that the
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> plates could have supplied more than enough copper for both illuminated
books. If pieces of copper were made from seventeen <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> plates by cutting along a
horizontal line at a point 13.5 to 17 cm. from the top or bottom edge (ie., just short of the middle of the
plate), each of the pieces could be cut into thirds to make three <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> coppers. If all
seventeen pieces were cut this way they would provide a total of fifty-one plates for etching on one
side.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">13</ref> Each of the remaining,
slightly larger pieces from these seventeen <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> plates could be cut in half to
yield two <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> coppers each, for a total of sixty-eight pages in the illuminated book
if etched recto and verso. This procedure would require no further cutting, except possibly for minor trimming
or filing of edges, and would waste very little copper.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55"
type="note">14</ref> Other <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plates could have been cut from the remaining 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> coppers, although we know that at least plate 96 of the illuminated book was made
from a quarter-piece of the “Moore &amp; Co’s Advertisement” Blake designed and engraved c.
1797-1798.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">15</ref> The presence of the Moore
plate in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> indicates that Blake may have retained possession of similar commercial
engravings, clearly executed on commission, and reused them for his own productions. The possibility that
Blake could have used <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> coppers for <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> lends some (admittedly circumstantial and speculative) support to Mann’s theory that
Blake might have retained those very plates and once contemplated using them for <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">12</hi> There appears to have been at least one further plate, for a “leaf from
Night 5” (presumably illustrated) was offered for sale by the London bookdealer Francis Edwards in a
catalogue of c. 1927-1928, item 44 (£26). There may of course have been other plates acquired by Blake or
Richard Edwards in contemplation of publishing further Nights of Young’s poem.</note>
	<note id="n54"><hi rend="s">13</hi> We can assume that <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> was etched on both sides
of its copperplates because of paired platemark dimensions and the presence of platemakers’ marks. (Many 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> plates can also be paired, but I know of no evidence of platemakers’ marks).</note>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 225 n. 2, suggests that the
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plates could have been made from the text panels of the <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> coppers. This procedure would have wasted a good deal of copper, leaving large but awkwardly
shaped and probably useless fragments.</note>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">15</hi> The telltale fragments of white lines from the Moore engraving were first
pointed out and identified by Erdman in “The Suppressed and Altered Passages in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi>, 17 (1964), 36-37. Other plates in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> may have been made from other pieces of the Moore copper—or for that matter from any
used intaglio plate.</note></p>
        <p>The plain-hand portions of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> offer even less evidence than pages in
copperplate hand concerning methods of publication. The intended medium <hi rend="i">might</hi> have been
relief etching (although that still seems unlikely), intaglio etching/engraving, or letterpress. It is most
tempting to conclude with Mann that the change from fine scripts to plain might record a change in publishing
plans, roughly parallel in chronology to the shift from an unrecoverable poem entitled <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>
to an unfinished poem entitled <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n57" type="note">16</ref> The contextual and historical evidence Mann assembles in support of his
letterpress hypothesis comes from what is generally taken to be a middle or later period in the development of
the manuscript—the years with Hayley, 1800-1803. Blake’s work with the provincial printer Joseph Seagrave
on a book (the 1802 <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>) with a typographic text and intaglio illustrations may have
suggested a return to that combination of techniques, also used in Edwards’ <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
edition, for the publication of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> Such a change could account for the
appearance of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> proofs in the plain script pages of the manuscript and the use
of their text panels as a mockup for a projected publication with the same format. At this point, Blake could
have cut up some of the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> coppers for other purposes if the new plans for 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> required fewer than one design per page of text, again as in <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts.</hi> The first <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> proof appears on page 43 of the manuscript (illus.
2), immediately following the last page in fine script. If the plain-hand revisions to pages first composed in
copperplate script are later revisions, as seems probable, the differences between pages 42 and 43 may record
a significant shift in Blake’s intentions for publication.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n58" type="note">17</ref>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Bentley accepts the usual assumption that the copperplate-hand portions
were composed before the plain-hand pages and states that a reversal of this sequence “cannot . . .
satisfactorily account for such diverse factors as symbolism, stab holes, corrections, and handwriting” 
(<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, p. 455 and n. 5). Erdman notes that “on certain copperplate pages a distinctly
late style appears in the script, marked by the g which Blake adopted after Nov. 1802” and states that “it
is safer to conclude that the copperplate pages range in inception from 1797 to 1803” (<hi rend="i">Poetry
and Prose of Blake</hi>, p. 817). Yet even if some of the fine script was written as late as 1803, the
sequence of copperplate hand to plain is not thereby upset.</note>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Bentley places page 42 as the last in a group he dates 1797 and page 43
(illus. 2) the first in a group he dates “?1802” (but see Erdman’s statements on the date of the fine
script in note 16, above). These are also the last and first pages in groups once separately sewn, as the two
distinct patterns of stab-holes indicate (see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, pp. 454-56).</note></p>
        <p>As attractive as Mann’s theory—or the combination Mann/Essick theory—may at first seem, the
manuscript pages on <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> proofs exhibit a few recalcitrant features. The number of
lines written in the text panels ranges between twenty-eight and fifty-seven (not including pages bearing
part-titles or those on which Nights end short of the lower margin), the text begins above the panel on
fourteen pages (illus. 6), and extends below it on two (illus. 5). Accommodating marginal additions would
cause further dislocations. If these portions of the
<pb id="p18-219" n="219"/>
manuscript are a letterpress mockup, they form a rather loose one. Blake may have planned to create somewhat
larger text panels in a variety of sizes. If the panels were not altered, a sympathetic printer might be able
to manage difficulties by shifting the text about as required, although this would probably disrupt some
text-design relationships. A minor form of this problem occurred in the production of the 1797 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, with the result that the lines illustrated by the design on page 54 begin on
page 53.</p>
        <p>The treatment of the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> proof on page 137 of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi> (illus. 6) throws into doubt at least two of our theories. Blake has drawn-in the back of one of the
wrestling figures right through the text panel. The text carefully follows the new lower left margin created
by the outline of the back. If this drawing was composed as part of the development of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi> (as distinct from a drawing executed earlier for some other purpose), it strongly suggests that at
least this one <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> design was to be used in Blake’s poem. At the same time, the
drawing argues against a letterpress text. It would not have been impossible to adjust the left margin of a
typographic text according to the pencil line of the back, but such a format would have been highly unusual
for an early nineteenth-century letterpress book. An etched or engraved text, however, would have accommodated
the drawing without technical difficulties or the violation of printing conventions. On page 72 of the
Edwards’ <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, a figure’s head intrudes slightly into the lower right corner
of the text panel, but this in no way disrupts normal letterpress margins. In spite of his introduction of
printed designs with rigid text panels, Blake’s extensions and revisions of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
forced the manuscript ever further from a recognizable mockup.</p>
        <p>At some point Blake must have given up any plans for eventual publication, and perhaps that
occurred before he ceased fussing with the manuscript. If this is indeed the case, then the suggestions
presented here can be summarized as a three-step process of changing plans for a manuscript reflecting those
changes as follows:
<list type="ordered">
	<item><p><label>(1)</label> a manuscript and production mockup for a poem (<hi rend="i">Vala?</hi>) intended
for publication of text and designs as intaglio etchings/engravings (i.e., the <hi rend="i">Blake of Los</hi>
and <hi rend="i">Book of Ahania</hi> format), tentatively dated c. 1796-1800;</p></item>
	<item><p><label>(2)</label> a manuscript and production mockup for a poem (<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas?</hi>)
intended for publication as a letterpress text accompanied by intaglio etched and/or engraved designs
surrounding selected pages of text (i.e., the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> format), tentatively dated c.
1800-1804;</p></item>
	<item><p><label>(3)</label> a working manuscript unrelated to any specific publication intentions (i.e., 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> manuscript as we know it today), tentatively dated c. 1804-1807.</p></item>
</list></p>
        <p>The foregoing has clearly <hi rend="i">proven</hi> only one proposition: it is impossible to prove
any theory about Blake’s production plans for <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> Yet I believe that these
companion essays may contribute to a better understanding of the manuscript and the intentions it never
completely reveals. Our speculative arguments may have the additional benefit of providing a more
comprehensive view of the evolution of Blake’s activities as a poet, engraver, and printer from 1796 to
1807.</p>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p18-220" n="220" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
