<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>18.4.nhilton</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">Pudendaddendum</title>
        <author n="Hilton">Nelson Hilton</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1985</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">18.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Editorial Assistants</resp>
              <name>Leslie Donovan</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Wayne Glausser</name>
              <name>Jean H. Hagstrum</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Alicia Ostriker</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1985"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_18">
    <body>
      <pb id="p18-235" n="235"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-18-4-0009">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">DISCUSSION</hi></hi>
          </title>
          <title type="section-subtitle">
            <hi rend="b">with intellectual spears &amp; long winged arrows of thought</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Pudendaddendum</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Nelson <name>Hilton</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>In “Some Sexual Connotations” (<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 16 [Winter 1982-83], 166-71), I
attempted to detail the overt sexual referents in several polysemous, or “multi-stable,” textual passages
and illustrations. Such referents are significant not only in their own right, proof of Blake’s practice of
“No Secrecy in Art,” but as well for the way in which they are contained in their overdetermined context,
since “what is not too Explicit” is “the fittest
for Instruction because it rouzes the faculties to act” (letter to Trusler, 23 August 1799). This context
includes, as Blake puts it on the titlepage of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, “The torments of Love &amp;
Jealousy”; and it includes those torments in their most physical and emotional expression.</p>
          <p>As for overt sexual imagery, I am happy to find Brenda Webster’s independent suggestion of the
Rahabpenis figure in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, pl. 75 (<hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic Psychology</hi>
[Athens, Ga.: Univ. of Georgia Press, 1983], p. 286; reproduced in “Some Sexual Connotations,” p. 170).
But I am ashamed (<hi rend="i">pudeo</hi>!) to have to add another instance, and one, no less, from an
illustration accompanying my earlier discussion. Perhaps there is consolation in thinking that the realization
of such repression of the signifier is a promise of pleasure to come as we learn to read Blake with fewer
inhibitions, in greater polymorphous perversity: with the enjoyment of all his senses. 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, pl. 85, copy E (illus.), like the other designs discussed in “Some Sexual
Connotations,” offers a “multistable” image as well, since the figure of Los’s doubled right leg
stands out from its ground as a side-on view of a tumescent penis (foreskin not yet drawn back). The two
clusters of grapes might in this case suggest (removed?)
            <figure n="jerusalem.e.p85" id="jerusalem.e.illbk.85" work-copy="jerusalem.e" rend="db" width="731" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>85<lb/>
	Became a Space &amp; an Allegory around the Winding Worm<lb/>
	They namd it Canaan &amp; built for it a tender Moon<lb/>
	Los smild with joy thinking on Enitharmon &amp; he brought<lb/>
	Reuben from his twelvefold wandrings &amp; led him into it<lb/>
	Planting the Seeds of the Twelwe Tribes &amp; Moses &amp; David<lb/>
	And gave a Time &amp; Revolution to the Space Six Thousand Years<lb/>
	He calld it Divine Analogy, for in Beulah the Feminine<lb/>
	Emanations Create Space, the Masculine Create Time. &amp; plant<lb/>
	The Seeds of beauty in the Space: listning to their lamentation<lb/>
	Los walks upon his ancient Mountains in the deadly darkness<lb/>
	Among his Furnaces directing his laborious Myriads watchful<lb/>
	Looking to the East: &amp; his voice is heard over the whole Earth<lb/>
	As he watches the Furnaces by night, &amp; directs the labourers<lb/>
	And thus Los replies upon his Watch: the Valleys listen silent:<lb/>
	The Stars stand still to hear: Jerusalem &amp; Vala cease to mourn!<lb/>
	His voice is heard from Albion: the Alps &amp; Appenines<lb/>
	Listen: Hermon &amp; Lebanon bow their crowned heads<lb/>
	Babel &amp; Shinar look toward the Western Gate, they sit down<lb/>
	Silent at his voice: they view the red Globe of fire in Los’s hand<lb/>
	As he walks from Furnace to Furnace directing the Labourers<lb/>
	And this is the Song of Los. the Song that he sings on his<lb/>
	Watch<lb/>
	O lovely mild Jerusalem! O Shiloh of Mount Ephraim!<lb/>
	I see thy Gates of precious stones! thy Walls of gold &amp; silver<lb/>
	Thou art the soft reflected Image of the Sleeping Man<lb/>
	Who stretchd on Albions rocks reposes amidst his Twenty-eight<lb/>
	Cities: where Beulah lovely terminates, in the hills &amp; valleys of Albion<lb/>
	Cities not yet embodied in Time and Space: plant ye<lb/>
	The Seeds O Sisters in the bosom of Time &amp; Spaces womb<lb/>
	To spring up for Jerusalem: lovely Shadow of Sleeping Albion<lb/>
	Why wilt thou rend thyself apart &amp; build an Earthly Kingdom<lb/>
	To reign in pride &amp; to opress &amp; to mix the Cup of Delusion<lb/>
	O thou that dwellest with Babylon! Come forth O lovely-one</figTranscr>
	<head>William Blake.</head>
	<figDesc><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, pl. 85, copy E (detail).</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p18-236" n="236"/>
testicles, or sperm “removed” by being “fibred” over to/by Enitharmon: a sort of conceptual
representation of intercourse (note how one collateral fibre does branch off toward/from the area of Los’s
heart). The difficulty in seeing such images—as this addendum witnesses—is that they are, at first, so
unexpected. Here the viewer has to be able to enter the image and make some of the connections: to focus on
the shaded body of the leg, treating it as one form, to continue the outline of the penis-form through the
ankle lines, to disregard the light area of the foot, even to see the upper outline of the left leg as no
outline but another fibre (not that difficult if one tries to conceive how, as an outline, it connects to the
trunk of the body). The foreskin is marked by the kneecap and the orifice by the small circle, resembling an
indentation, across from the top of the lower cluster of grapes. One need only trust the initial impression
that there’s something oddly emphasized about this (third) leg, that it seems to possess a life and
existence of its own. This erection might serve to explain why Los and Enitharmon are so emphatically looking
away from each other, not wishing to acknowledge the (pictorially-speaking, anyway) most important thing
between them.</p>
          <p>Which leads us to a reconsideration of the implied ascetic message of the lines quoted from “My
Spectre” in “Some Sexual Connotations,” p. 171 (11. 49-52 [erroneously cited as 67-70]; see also
Ostriker’s remarks in the same issue, p. 161). It now seems to me that a truly “radical” argument might
be read as, in effect, “let’s forget about ‘Love’ and get physical—really ‘tear up,’ ‘root
up’ the ‘infernal grove.’ Then, having disposed of the lineaments of gratified desire, may we ‘return
&amp; see / The worlds of happy Eternity.’ ” The crucial point, what allows the return and vision of the
worlds, is the initial mutual agreement. This might explain why the phrase is repeated. Thus the speaker
argues, at first:
<q>
Till I turn from Female Love<lb/>
And root up the Infernal Grove<lb/>
I shall never worthy be<lb/>
To Step into Eternity (41-44)
</q>
But it can’t be done alone. Eternity, in fact, is nothing but this ongoing process of agreeing, rooting up,
and returning. So, the speaker concludes:
<q>
Let us agree to give up Love<lb/>
And root up the infernal grove<lb/>
Then shall we return &amp; see<lb/>
The worlds of happy Eternity<lb/>
<lb/>
&amp; Throughout all Eternity<lb/>
I forgive you you forgive me<lb/>
As our Dear Redeemer said<lb/>
This the Wine &amp; this the Bread (49-56)
</q>
So should all couples consummate “the fleshly bread . . . the nervous wine” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi>
12.44).</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
