<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>19.2.sketch</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">A Pencil Sketch for Blake’s Dante Illustrations</title>
        <author n="La Belle">Jenijoy La Belle</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1985</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">19.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Karl Kroeber</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Josephine McQuail</name>
              <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>Margaret LaFrance</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1985"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-2-0007">
        <pb id="p19-73" n="73"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A Pencil Sketch for Blake’s Dante Illustrations</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Jenijoy <name>La Belle</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The Huntington Library is known the world over for its great collection of
                        books, for its splendid eighteenth century paintings, and for its lovely
                        gardens. It now seems also to be the place for discovering previously
                        unknown drawings by William Blake. In 1982 a pencil sketch of Blake’s
                        “Pestilence” was discovered in a group of uncatalogued
                        drawings which apparently had been languishing in the Library’s rare
                        book stacks for many years.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
type="note">1</ref> Recently,
                        yet another Blake drawing has come to light. <note id="n17"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See
Shelley M. Bennett, “A Newly Discovered Blake in
                            the Huntington,” <hi rend="i">Huntington Calendar</hi>
                            (July-August 1983), 2-4; and Bennett, “A Newly Discovered Blake
                            at the Huntington,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
                                Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-85), 132-39.</note></p>
          <p>Since December 1916, the Huntington Art Gallery has owned an important pencil
                        sketch for Blake’s Dante Illustrations, “The Six-Footed
                        Serpent Attacking Agnolo Brunelleschi.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n18" type="note">2</ref> This somewhat rubbed and stained yet powerful drawing has long
                        been firmly pasted down on all four edges to its backing mat, probably
                        supplied by A.S.W. Rosenbach, the great book dealer from whom Henry E.
                        Huntington acquired this and many other Blake materials.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">3</ref> Late in December of 1984, Carol Verheyen, the
                        Preparator/Registrar for the Huntington Art Collections, decided that the
                        preservation of the drawing required its removal from the highly acidic mat
                        board. As soon as the operation was completed, she found on the verso a
                        pencil sketch of a standing woman (illus. 1) near the left margin of the
                        sheet. The figure may be holding something in her right hand, but stains in
                        the paper and some abrasion obscure this area. The verso also bears the
                        number “8/16” in pencil—perhaps a price or other
                        notation made by a dealer. <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">2</hi> C.H. Collins
                            Baker, <hi rend="i">Catalogue of William Blake’s Drawings and
                                Paintings in the Huntington Library</hi>, revised edition by R. R.
                            Wark (San Marino: Huntington Library, 1957), p. 46, pl. xxxvi; Martin
                            Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>
                            (New Haven: Yale Univ. Press, 1981), No. 822, pl. 1073 (hereafter cited
                            as “Butlin No. —”).</note>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">3</hi> To the provenance information supplied by
                            Butlin, No. 822, I can add that this drawing is very probably the design
                            for “Dante’s ‘Inferno’ ” offered for
                            sale in Rosenbach’s catalogue 18 of 1916, <hi rend="i">Catalogue
                                of A Remarkable Collection of Rare and Choice Books Manuscripts and
                                Autograph Letters</hi>, item 17, with a collection of other works by
                            Blake including the Thomas set of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> designs for
                            $29,000. This entire group was acquired by Henry Huntington in December
                            1916 for $17,200 (according to Rosenbach’s receipt of 1 January
                            1917 in the Huntington Archives). I am grateful to Robert N. Essick, who
                            is now completing a new catalogue of all original Blake materials at the
                            Huntington, for this information.</note></p>
          <p>The basic features of the woman’s anatomy, the slightly <hi rend="i">contrapposto</hi> stance
with her head in profile but her body twisting
                        towards us, and the qualities of the draftsmanship are all representative of
                        Blake’s work. The hesitancy and sketchiness of the lines, while
                        hardly indicative of Blake’s theories about firm and determinate
                        bounding lines, are nonetheless typical of his drawing style late in his
                        life. In his description of a stylistically similar work, a “sketch,
                        probably for ‘Bunyan’s Dream,’ ” (Butlin No.
                        830), Butlin has nicely characterized this technique as one “in which
                        a multitude of lightly sketched lines gradually picks out the main
                            forms.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">4</ref>
Several of the Dante
                        drawings left at an early stage of development (e.g., Butlin Nos. 812.68,
                        812.70, 812.71, 812.83, 812.100) also exemplify this method. Thus all
                        features of the newly discovered drawing, including of course its presence
                        on the verso of a known work by Blake, indicate that it too is from
                        Blake’s hand. It was probably sketched in the period when Blake was
                        working on the Dante designs, ca. 1824-1827. <note id="n20"><hi rend="s">4</hi>
Butlin, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, catalogue of the
                            Tate Gallery exhibition (London, 1978), p. 147. In correspondence,
                            Butlin has accepted the newly discovered drawing as Blake’s
                            work.</note></p>
          <p>There are a good many females in Blake’s art generally similar to the
                        Huntington sketch, but none that I can find is identical. The drawing has
                        all the qualities of a preliminary design, and the first possibility that
                        springs to mind is that it relates to one of the large Dante watercolors.
                        Martin Butlin has suggested in correspondence that the Huntington drawing is
                        an early version of the figure second from the left margin in
                        “Beatrice Addressing Dante from the Car” (illus. 2). If this
                        is indeed the case, then it seems likely that this verso drawing was
                        executed prior to the composition on its recto (“The Six-Footed
                        Serpent Attacking Agnolo Brunelleschi”) because the latter is
                        probably a preliminary drawing for the engraving of 1826-1827 rather than
                        for the slightly earlier watercolor.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n21" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">5</hi> As Butlin points out under his No. 822,
                            the Huntington recto drawing, which he dates to 1826-1827.</note></p>
          <figure n="BlakeSketchStandingWoman.19.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="745">
            <head>1. Blake.</head>
            <figDesc>Pencil sketch of a standing woman, ca. 1824-1827, on the verso of
                            “The Six-Footed Serpent Attacking Agnolo Brunelleschi.”
                            Sheet 24.5 × 32.9 cm; image 17.5 × approx. 5.5 cm.
                            Huntington Art Galleries, accession no. 000.43 verso.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p19-74" n="74"/>
          <p>The woman in the newly revealed verso sketch and the much more highly
                        finished figure in “Beatrice Addressing Dante” have similar
                        feet and leg positions, torsos, and extended right arms. Indeed, the two
                        women are about the same size and are similarly situated in relationship to
                        the edges of the sheets of paper on which they appear, suggesting that even
                        in the sketch Blake was thinking about the location of his figure within a
                        larger design. However, the head positions and hair of these two women are
                        very different, and the left arm of the sketched woman is not shown.
                        Actually, the head in profile with the face turned slightly upward and the
                        coiffure with hair piled up on top of the head associate the pencil drawing
                        with the central figure (second from the right) who looks toward Beatrice
                        standing on the chariot. It seems as though Blake has made use of the
                        preliminary figure by dividing her characteristics between two women in the
                        finished composition. While the newly discovered drawing is far from being a
                        major work, it does provide some interesting insights into Blake’s
                        methods of developing a composition as he moved from first thoughts on paper
                        to a highly wrought watercolor design.</p>
          <figure n="but812.1.91-88.wc" id="but812.1.wc.91" work-copy="but812.1" rend="db" width="958" height="679">
	<figTranscr>P-g Canto 29 &amp; 30</figTranscr>
            <head>2. Blake.</head>
            <figDesc>“Beatrice Addressing Dante from the Car,” ca.
                            1824-1827. Pen and watercolor, 37.2 × 52.7 cm. Tate Gallery,
                            London.</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
