<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>19.2.kroeber</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Stephen C. Behrendt, The Moment of Explosion: Blake and the Illustration of
Milton; Edward Hodnett, Image and Text: Studies in the Illustration of English Literature</title>
        <author n="Kroeber">Karl Kroeber</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1985</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">19.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Karl Kroeber</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Josephine McQuail</name>
              <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>Margaret LaFrance</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1985"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <body>
      <pb id="p19-75" n="75"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-2-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Stephen C. Behrendt. <hi rend="i">The Moment of Explosion:
                                    Blake and the Illustration of Milton.</hi> Lincoln and Lond:
                                University of Nebraska Press, 1983. 235 pp., 24 color plates, 54
                                b&amp;w illus. $32.50.</title>
            <title type="main">Edward Hodnett. <hi rend="i">Image and
                                    Text: Studies in the Illustration of English Literature.</hi>
                                London: Scolar Press, 1982. 280 pp., 42 illus. $35.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Karl</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Kroeber</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Behrendt presents us with a conscientious study of Blake’s Milton
                        illustrations, which he regards as undertaking to “correct not only
                        Milton but also the presumed faults of his eighteenth- and early
                        nineteenth-century critics” (p. 1). Blake’s designs accomplish
                        this double correction by abstracting the spiritual or symbolic essence of
                        the poetry, rediscovering and realigning Milton’s mythical and
                        metaphorical structures in order to induce in the reader a visionary
                        perception comparable to the artist’s. This alertness to
                        Blake’s concern for his art’s effect is salutary. Behrendt,
                        naturally enough, begins with a discussion of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> that
                        leads logically into an analysis of <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and
                            <hi rend="i">Il Penseroso</hi> illustrations. The crux of his findings
                        is developed in the second chapter treating “The Theme of
                        Choice,” in Behrendt’s view “central to all
                        Blake’s Milton illustrations” (p. 34), and the foundation for
                        his correcting both in his poetry and in his illustrations what he took to
                        be misreadings of Milton. The centerpiece for all such considerations must
                        be, of course, <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, and for Behrendt the epic
                        proves the core of Blake’s re-orienting of tradition, deformed in
                        part by Milton’s own obscuring of the true thrust of his poem.
                        Blake’s re-clarifying of Milton’s self-obscuring pivots on
                        insistence that the Son is the “absolute hero of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>,”
effecting and providing “the
                        paradigm for eternal spiritual and imaginative resurrection” (p.
                        185). Behrendt’s thesis is difficult to disagree with, and it is no
                        denigration of his good sense and perspicuity to suggest that his
                        book’s most exciting feature is its eighty large, clear
                        illustrations, most of Blake’s designs, of course, but including
                        well-chosen examples from other Milton illustrators. The bibliography,
                        however, is highly “selected” indeed, and the index of names
                        only is virtually useless.</p>
          <p>Hodnett’s book is far more provocative and stylistically surprising.
                        The chapter on Blake seems a shade more impressive than other chapters, but
                        its manner is, I should judge, representative. On p. 87 we are told of Blake
                        that “nudes were his stock in trade, and he did his best to draw them
                        correctly.” Our man gets an E for effort here, but later in the
                        paragraph the accolade is a bit clouded: “By reducing most of his
                        figures to nudes, by picturing types rather than individuals, and by
                        generalizing or eliminating backgrounds, Blake sought to achieve a sense of
                        universality, and to a degree he succeeded.” One does wonder what
                        degree of universality might be regarded as successful. Pressing on to p.
                        92, however, one encounters a reference to “Enitharman,” to
                        add new diversity to Blake’s sexual ambiguities in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, the
passage climaxing, if that is the word: “The
                        extraordinary title-page design pictures Urizen as a naked long-bearded man
                        huddled cross-legged on an open book writing with a quill in both extended
                        hands. The colours are said to have been mixed with glue and applied by a
                        second impression of the plate.” I wish I had space to explore fully
                        Hodnett’s sequiturs, but I can at least suggest a possible source for
                        that quill in both extended hands: it is found on p. 102, where we are
                        reassured, sort of, that “Blake probably got his effects
                        unintentionally to a certain extent.” Particularly when dealing with
                        an eccentric like Blake, a scholar can’t be too careful</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
