<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>19.2.palmer</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">An Address to the Electors of West Kent, 1832</title>
        <author n="Palmer">Samuel Palmer</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1985</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">19.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Karl Kroeber</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Josephine McQuail</name>
              <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>Margaret LaFrance</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1985"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <body>
      <pb id="p19-60" n="60"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-2-0006">
                    <figure n="AddressElectorsWestKent.19.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="779"/>
        <pb id="p19-61" n="61"/>
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">AN ADDRESS TO THE ELECTORS OF WEST KENT.</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>My Lords and Gentlemen ;</title>
          </head>
          <p>An individual, who has the honour to be of your number, ventures to address
                        you on the subject of the approaching election; and entreats you to afford
                        him a few moments’ serious attention; which he claims, not for
                        himself, but for the importance of his subject.</p>
          <p>Sir William R. P. Geary comes forward, and offers himself as your
                        Representative; promising an assiduous attention to Parliamentary duties. He
                        will strenuously support the agricultural interest; and such a modification
                        of the tithe laws as may comport with the security of all other kinds of
                        property. He will also promote, to the utmost of his power, every rational,
                        effective and substantial reform. He comes from the heart of the county; and
                        from his family and connections, we cannot but believe him to be a lover of
                        agriculture; an interest now upon the very verge of destruction. Sir William
                        is an INDEPENDENT CANDIDATE, and the son of a late INDEPENDENT MEMBER.</p>
          <p>Surely no person connected with the agricultural interest, and solicitous for
                        the welfare of this great county, can for a moment lend his influence to the
                        opposing faction, who denounce the protecting duties as a “Bread
                        Tax,” and taunt Sir William with a desire of continuing it. Now as
                        every Kentish farmer, who is in his right wits, conceives some sort of
                        “Bread Tax” to be the very condition of his existence, how
                        could our adversaries be so very simple as to tell him plainly, that his
                        only chance of preserving it was by voting for Sir William Geary? However,
                        as they have been so kindly explicit, I hope, like men of common sense, we
                        shall take them at their word, and vote for Sir William, as they advise.
                        Their hostility to Agriculture, which could not long be concealed,
                        notwithstanding any professions they might have made to the contrary,
                        sufficiently bespeaks them to belong to the caste of the Radical Reformers,
                        MOST FALSELY SO CALLED; who are the natural enemies of the farmer, and, by
                        consequence, of the manufacturer; for commerce and agriculture must stand or
                        fall together;—and, therefore, of all national prosperity.</p>
          <p>One is almost tempted to believe that some cunning Agriculturist, in
                        disguise, drew up their manifesto, and laughed at them in his sleeve; for
                        certainly it is its own best refutation. Sir William Geary has promised to
                        support the Agriculturist; and this is the very reason for which
                        agricultural Kent is called upon to repudiate him! <hi rend="i">Risum
                            teneatis.</hi> Rome was saved by the cackling of geese: and truly, if
                        the jacobinic citadel might be preserved by similar multitudes, it must be
                        acknowledged to be impregnable!</p>
          <p>Thus have they forfeited the support of all sensible farmers; and at the same
                        time disgusted every honest man, whether Whig or Tory, by retailing, in the
                        true spirit of jacobinism, a falsehood respecting the income of the Church,
                        so outrageous; that it looks like a droll burlesque and caricature, even of
                        the flagitious system of misrepresentation and imposture, by which that
                        profligate faction is supported.</p>
          <p>With respect to the Candidates themselves, who have been unitedly soliciting
                        your suffrages; nothing can be farther from the writer’s intention
                        than to offer them personal disrespect: he would be the first to yield them
                        that deference which all gentlemen have a right to claim from each other in
                        private society: but he feels it his duty to speak very plainly of the
                        faction whose support those gentlemen have deigned to conciliate.</p>
          <p>Another objection to Sir William is his youth. It is said, “We want
                        men of experience in Parliament:” But, beside that often one man of
                        thirty will be found wiser than another of seventy; that multitude of years
                        does not always teach wisdom: that every profession affords numerous
                        instances of the young attaining honours and distinction; and of aged men
                        who could never rise from mediocrity; and that some of our most splendid
                        public characters have signalized themselves when but scarcely out of their
                        minority: how, we should be glad to know, are we to obtain Representatives
                        of great Parliamentary experience, unless by sending them in betimes, we
                        give them an opportunity to acquire it? If we return none but old men, we
                        defeat that object entirely; and our <hi rend="i">Council of Ancients</hi>
                        must ever be a bench of venerable novices. But, above all, I would ask, is
                        it not most expedient, that in the great senate of a nation there should be
                        found the energy and fire of youth, as well as the deliberative sagacity of
                        age? The parents of all sublime works are Intellect and Will.</p>
          <p>Some have strangely refused to support Sir William Geary, on account of their
                        being, from early associations, attached to the Whigs. Alas! it is but an
                        ill compliment to the Whigs of sixteen hundred and eighty-eight, to mistake
                        for their successors a rabble of incendiaries and jacobins. The politics
                        promulgated by our adversaries are not those of MARLBOROUGH or CHATHAM, but
                        of THISTLEWOOD and BRAN-DRETH!</p>
          <p>NO! Brother Electors!—The Radical upas tree never sprouted from the
                        stock of ancient British Whiggism; <pb id="p19-62" n="62"/>
but it is the
                        importation of yesterday, from poor, degraded, dishonoured, Atheistical
                        France.</p>
          <p>That once gay nation long led the mode in our more innocent fripperies of
                        dress and fashion: we amused ourselves with her toys and trinkets; and with
                        perfect good humour saw her play the Harlequin to Europe. But she rose in
                        our estimation, when she began to struggle against aristocratic tyranny. She
                        obtained her freedom: and, alas! immediately lost it again, irretrievably;
                        by confiding it, as the people of England are at this moment confiding their
                        own—to revolutionary empyrics. Then, when suddenly distracted with an
                        infernal phrenzy, her songs and dances became the yells and contortions of
                        possession; and, in a frantic spasm, she hurled over the Continent
                        fire-brands, arrows, and death: who, with more alacrity than the Kentish
                        patriot, sprang forward, and bound the demoniac?</p>
          <p>And shall <hi rend="i">we</hi>, even now, bitten with that selfsame madness;
                        while, though somewhat exhausted with her paroxysm, France yet heaves in
                        incurable distraction; shall <hi rend="i">we</hi> mistake her ravings for
                        the voice of Delphic Sibyl; and proceed to model, or rather unmodel, every
                        institution of our country, and tumble them all together, into the semblance
                        of that kingless, lawless, churchless, Godless, comfortless, and most
                        chaotic Utopia of French philosophy?</p>
          <p>Shall we assay to repair here and there a crumbing pinnacle of our
                        Constitution, by cannonading the buttresses and sapping the foundations?</p>
          <p>Shall we invite over the Gaul to help us raze those bulwarks, which he too
                        well knows to be thunder-proof; and put up a pagoda of trash and tinsel on
                        the site?</p>
          <p>But now, behold, you are called out, Men of Kent—yes, YOU, whose frown
                        has made the Frenchman shiver—to mince and caper in the ballet of
                        liberalism; and to bring up the death-dance of Parisian assassins and
                        sanscullotes!</p>
          <p>They were the Men of Kent who dictated terms to the Norman Conqueror: and
                        they are Men of Kent, who are now asked to become morally the vassals of
                        France.</p>
          <p>Who does not remember that crisis—God forbid any Englishman should
                        forget it!—when Wordsworth sang, 
						<q> “Ye men of Kent,
                            ’tis Victory or Death!” </q></p>
          <p>Then, even as one man, rose up this noble county; and with a front of
                        spotless loyalty, scared Napoleon from our shore. O let not their degenerate
                        children crouch to an invasion of much more fatal principles and
                        doctrines.</p>
          <p>The mane of the British Lion can receive no decoration from shreds of
                        tri-coloured ribbon; nor will he cut any very majestic figure in the eyes of
                        Europe, if we suffer our new-fangled politicians to retrench his tusks and
                        talons; and to lead him about as a show, with the Monkey of French
                        innovation mounted upon his back.</p>
          <p>O my countrymen, for shame! for shame!—Methinks I see the mouldered
                        heroes of Crecy and Agincourt, of Trafalgar and Waterloo rise up to hoot us
                        from among the nations!</p>
          <p>But let it be so no longer! Put on, once more, the invincible armour of old
                        English, of old Kentish loyalty. Strangle the snake corruption wherever you
                        shall find it; and every where promote, in God’s name, effectual
                        reform: but leave not your hearths and altars a prey to the most heartless,
                        the most bloody, most obscene, profane, and atrocious faction, which ever
                        defied God and insulted humanity.</p>
          <p>You will NOT suffer those temples where you received the Christian name to
                        fall an easy prey to sacrilegious plunderers! You will NOT let that dust
                        which covers the ashes of your parents, be made the filthy track of
                        Jacobinical hyenas!</p>
          <p>Farmers of Kent—we are tempted with a share of the promised spoliation
                        of the CHURCH!—There <hi rend="i">was</hi> a time when every Kentish
                        yeoman would have spurned at the wretch who should have dared to tickle him
                        with such a bait—to offer him such an insult! But piety and honour
                        are in the sepulchre.</p>
          <p>I would fain hope, however, that there are still very few of us who would not
                        experience some shudder of conscience, at the thought of thieving from the
                        Church of England her freehold lands and tenements: few among the
                        uncultivated; few among the vicious: few in our jails and halls: few
                        anywhere, but within the precincts of our political unions. There are
                        gradations even in atrocious felony. It is not every burglar who would
                        violate an altar. But what are we to think of those vassals of perdition who
                        would put forth their hands to the freeholds of the Church: who are not
                        afraid to appear in the presence of their Creator branded with sacrilege! It
                        is scarcely, perhaps, to be regretted, that these lepers are now catalogued,
                        and marked, and numbered, and huddled together in the pest-house of the
                        unionists.</p>
          <p>So much for the Church lands. As to the tithe laws, they are about to undergo
                        revision: perhaps very considerable alteration. Sir William Geary has
                        offered to promote any amelioration; any equitable adjustment: nor can any
                        one be more likely to watch the interests of the Kentish farmer closely,
                        during the discussion in Parliament.</p>
          <p>But there are some very honest and well meaning persons to be found, who
                        imagine that an abolition of the tithe altogether would relieve the farmer
                        from his present difficulties: who suppose that if the tenth sheaf were not
                        put into the tithe waggon, the farmer would put the value of that sheaf into
                        his own pocket; whereas nothing can be more false; because the tithe is
                        always allowed for in the rent, which would be so much greater if there were
                        no tithe. Land will always be let to the 
<pb id="p19-63" n="63"/>
best
                        bidders; and whatever men will give for a piece of land to-day, knowing it
                        to be subject to tithe; they would give proportionably more for it
                        to-morrow, tithe free; whether the tithe be a real tenth, or seventh, as
                        some say; or whatsoever proportion it bears to the farmer’s
                        returns.</p>
          <p>Farmers! Messrs. Hodges and Rider are to attempt two things in behalf of
                        their constituents. In the first place, they will sweep away the
                        “Bread Tax,” that is, the protecting duties on foreign corn;
                        which you know will utterly ruin you. But then, they tell you that they will
                        try to abolish the payment of tithe: and who would not gladly be ruined, for
                        the pleasure of seeing the tithe laws abolished! Now it is not unlikely that
                        they may bring about a free trade in corn; because free trade is the
                        fashion: but it is by no means so probable they will succeed in immediately
                        abolishing the tithe, because that can scarcely be done without a
                        revolution. Well; you know that a free trade in corn will throw the farms
                        out of cultivation; starve the whole of the peasantry; and force many of you
                        to emigrate from your native country for ever: but I will show you that the
                        abolition of tithe, at the same moment, would not put a farthing into your
                        hands, to defray the expences of the melancholy passage!</p>
          <p>In all matters of sale and traffic 
		<q> “—The worth of
                            anything<lb/>
 Is as much money as ‘twill bring.” </q>
A
                        tithe-free farm fetches a proportionably high rent: therefore were all the
                        farms tithe free, from the abolition of the tithe laws; all the farms would
                        fetch a rental proportionably increased. What then would the farmer gain by
                        it? Supposing the tithe were doubled: you would go [to] the landlord for an
                        equivalent deduction in your rent—supposing the tithe abolished; he
                        would come to <hi rend="i">you</hi> for an equivalent increase. Our mistake
                        lies in not clearly understanding <hi rend="i">what it is</hi> that we rent
                        of our landlord. We may, perhaps, imagine that we pay him for the whole of
                        the crops which we produce; and that the tithe card takes away a tenth of
                        that produce, for the whole of which we have made our landlord a
                        consideration: but it is no such thing: we never paid for that tenth: it was
                        not charged in our rent. In short, we pay our landlord for the right of
                        disposing of nine tenths of the produce of his land; and if the other tenth
                        were not removed by the tithe man the landowner would take care to demand it
                        in rent. It is irksome to be put to the proof of anything so self-evident,
                        where every argument is like a truism.</p>
          <p>The best informed authors will inform us that the ancient landowners, who
                        built most of our parish churches, left to their children only nine tenths
                        of the profits of the estates which descended to them: the remaining tenth
                        they bequeathed in the shape of the present tithe, to their respective
                        churches for ever: and that bequest was and is ratified by the laws of our
                        country. Therefore the landowner who is possessed of a thousand acres,
                        receives only the profits of nine hundred: to-morrow, were the tithe law
                        repealed, he would have ten hundred, bona fide disposable to his own use and
                        benefit. Now when we can suppose our landlord not to be aware that a
                        thousand acres are worth a higher rental than nine hundred, then indeed we
                        may expect to be benefited by an abolition of the tithes!</p>
          <p>The small tradesman and the poor would be losers indeed, by the proposed
                        innovation: for the money which is in most cases spent and distributed among
                        them by the clergyman’s family, would be often drawn away by absentee
                        landlords, and spent at a distance from the parish, if not in a foreign
                        land.</p>
          <p>As to the very ancient triple distribution of the tithe, which has been
                        spoken of in certain quarters; one part to the poor; another to the
                        parochial clergy; and a third towards the repairs of the Cathedral; a
                        moment’s reflection will convince us of its impractibility at
                        present; when by the blessing of God our parish churches are so vastly
                        multiplied; and I am happy to add, multiplying. The solicitude of the enemy
                        for the beauty of our cathedrals is a little out of character: we may
                        believe it to equal their sympathy for the poor: with respect to whom, be it
                        remembered, that the clergyman <hi rend="i">pays his full share of poor-rate
                            upon his income</hi>; to say nothing of the innumerable private
                        charities, and neighbourly benefits conferred on their parishioners, by the
                        great majority of that amiable and venerable, though most shamefully
                        calumniated order.</p>
          <p>But the landholder would, in effect, gain little more than the farmer, by the
                        abolition of tithe: for, as the whole income of the Church, divided equally
                        among her clergy, has been calculated scarcely to afford a decent
                        maintenance to each; at least as much as was before levied in tithe, must
                        then be imposed as a tax by government. So long then as the clergy should be
                        decently supported, there would be no transfer of their incomes to the
                        landed proprietor or to any one else. And if a revolutionary government were
                        to ensue, and abolish our religious establishment altogether; which would be
                        one of its first achiev[e]ments; the landholder will not be so simple as to
                        believe that the Radicals would suffer him to sit down quietly with his
                        increased rent: that is, supposing there were any rent to be had, after free
                        trade had emptied his farms and exiled his tenants. No; they will tax him,
                        and fleece him to the skin; and then confiscate his estates. The demagogue
                        is the natural enemy of the landholders: for he finds in them at once the
                        toughest obstacles to his ambition, and the most delicious temptations to
                        his voracity. He will, therefore, spare no pains to decoy and devour
                        them.</p>
          <p>I will not attempt to adumbrate the gradations of 
<pb id="p19-64" n="64"/>
                        slow torment, through which the crew of a triumphant political union would
                        pare down the wretch who should fall into their clutches; condemned of that
                        crime, in their estimation the most inexpiable; the possession of wealth.
                        The spectacle of a whale under the hatchets of his harpooners; or rather of
                        the South American Indian, made through a summer day the amusement of his
                        captors, would present a lively type of the proceedings of these national
                        anatomists with the catalogue of his possessions; and, perhaps, with the
                        members of his person! I most humbly confess myself inadequate to do justice
                        to that consummation of fraud, rapine, outrage, and barbarity, which may be
                        expected from the Radicals of England, improving upon the example of the
                        French Jacobins.</p>
          <p>The British landholders are, however, too well aware of the motives of the
                        Liberals, very readily to accept any boon from their hands. But, lest the
                        people at large should be wired in a like gin; I shall take the liberty to
                        exhibit before them, for a few moments, their French neighbours, gulled by
                        the bait, and struggling in the toils: and it is then to be hoped that they
                        will take care not to render themselves most forlorn exceptions to the
                        general verity of the sacred proverb, that “the snare is surely
                        spread in vain, in the sight of any bird.”</p>
          <p>“Having”—“prepared the public mind, the assembly
                        made a bold attack on the Church. They discovered, by the light of
                        philosophy, that France contained too many churches, and, of course, too
                        many pastors. Great part of them were therefore to be suppressed; and to
                        make the innovation go down with the people, all tithes were to be
                        abolished. The measure succeeded; but what did the people gain by the
                        abolition of the tithes?—not a farthing; for a tax of twenty <hi rend="i">per
cent.</hi> was immediately laid on the lands in consequence
                        of it. The cheat was not perceived till it was too late.”</p>
          <p>“But, the abolition of the tithes, the only motive of which was to
                        debase the Clergy in the opinions of the people, was but a trifle to what
                        was to follow.”</p>
          <p>Then, with respect to the seizure of the landed property of the French
                        Church; which was, beyond comparison, more extensive than that of our
                        own:—“To obtain the sanction of the people to this act, they
                        were told, that the wealth of the Church would not only pay off the national
                        debt, but render taxes in future unnecessary. No deception was ever so
                        barefaced as this; but even this was not wanted; for the people themselves
                        had already begun to taste the sweets of plunder. Avarice tempted the
                        trading part of the nation to approve of the measure. At the time of passing
                        the decree they were seen among the first to applaud it. They saw an easy
                        means of obtaining those fine rich estates, the possession of which they
                        had, perhaps, long coveted. In vain were they told, that the purchaser would
                        partake in the infamy of the robbery; that, if the title of the communities
                        could not render property secure, that same property could never be secure
                        under any title the plunderers could give. In vain were they told, that in
                        sanctioning the seizure of the wealth of others, they were sanctioning the
                        seizure of their own, whenever that all-devouring monster, the sovereign
                        people, should call on them for it. In vain were they told all this: they
                        purchased: they saw with pleasure the plundered Clergy driven from their
                        dwellings; but scarcely had they taken possession of their ill-gotten
                        wealth, when not only that, but the remains of their other property were
                        wrenched from them. Since that we have seen decree upon decree launched
                        forth against the rich: their account books have been submitted to public
                        examination: they have been obliged to give drafts for the funds which they
                        possessed even in foreign countries: all their letters have been intercepted
                        and read. How many hundreds of them have we seen led to the scaffold, merely
                        because they were proprietors of what their sovereign stood in need of!
                        These were acts of unexampled tyranny; but, as they respected the persons
                        who applauded the seizure of the estates of the Church, they were perfectly
                        just. Several of these avaricious purchasers have been murdered within the
                        walls of those buildings, whence they had assisted to drive the lawful
                        proprietors: this was just: it was the measure they had meted to others.
                        They shared the fate of the injured Clergy, without sharing the pity which
                        that fate excited. When dragged forth to slaughter in their turn, they were
                        left without even the right of complaining: the last stab of the assassin
                        was accompanied with the reflection, that it was just.”</p>
          <p>“I have dwelt the longer on this subject, as it is, perhaps, the most
                        striking and most awful example of the consequences of a violation of
                        property, that the world ever saw. Let it serve to warn all those who wish
                        to raise their fortunes on the ruin of others, that sooner or later, their
                        own turn must come. From this act of the Constituent Assembly we may date
                        the violation, in France, of every right that men ought to hold dear. Hence
                        the seizure of all gold and silver as the property of the nation: hence the
                        law preventing the son to claim the property of his father: hence the
                        abominable tyranny of requisitions; and hence thousands and thousands of the
                        murders, that have disgraced unhappy France.”</p>
          <p>These extracts are from pages 169, and 180, of a little book printed at
                        Philadelphia, and reprinted in London about the year 1797: it is entitled,
                        “The Bloody Buoy, thrown out as a Warning to the Political Pilots of
                        America; or, a Faithful Relation of a Multitude of Acts of Horrid Barbarity,
                        such as the Eye never witnessed, the Tongue never expressed, or the
                        Imagination conceived, until the commencement of the French Revolution. To
                        which is added an Instructive Essay, tracing these dreadful Effects to their
                        real Causes.”</p>
          <p>My Countrymen! the primary sources of all, were 
<pb id="p19-65" n="65"/>
                        INFIDELITY; and those <hi rend="i">principles</hi> of rebellion and plunder,
                        its legitimate offspring, which are now so industriously disseminated among
                        ourselves: and if it be reasonable to anticipate like effects from like
                        causes, we should be holding ourselves in solemn preparation for the worst:
                        yet with no dreary misgiving, that the Providence which has so long signally
                        blessed and protected this island, will forsake us in extremity: but with an
                        ardent faith and confidence that He who has now withdrawn Himself for a
                        while, and from His high and invisible watch tower in the heavens, is
                        beholding the fury of His enemies, and the lukewarmness of his servants;
                        will suddenly descend among us, and deliver us gloriously, at that moment
                        when we shall lay the ark of our liberties on the altar of the sanctuary;
                        and, banded together in one impregnable phalanx of holy
                        patriotism—SWEAR TO DEFEND THEM IN HIS NAME!</p>
          <p>Is this the rant of a fanatic?—NO. It is the zealous but sober voice
                        of one who dares to speak what millions think: millions, who seem stunned
                        and panic-stricken, by the yelling of a crew of savages, and a thoughtless
                        rabble who follow them. It is the voice of one who would deem it happiness
                        and glory indeed, to die for his country, in some great struggle against
                        some great enemy: but who shudders to take his death at the talons of a club
                        of runnagates whom his fathers would have hissed into the sea! It is the
                        voice of one, who, among other histories, has perused the awful annals of
                        the great French revolution, and has not nodded over the book: wherein
                        rivers of blood, and plains of desolation; conflag[r]ation, assassination,
                        violation, treachery, sacrilege, blasphemy, and every variety of
                        wretchedness, and every enormity of abomination, are as familiar as
                        household words.</p>
          <p>And it is to this, Kentish Yeomen, that our heartless adversaries are
                        reducing <hi rend="i">us:</hi> it is thus they began in France: and the most
                        ready dupes of the Parisian radicals became the earliest victims of their
                        fury, the moment they hesitated to plunge with them into gulfs of blood.</p>
          <p>We charge the Radicals of England; and they will, perhaps, glory in the
                        charge; with having eulogized that revolution through all its stages: with
                        having palliated its atrocities, that they might promulgate its principles.
                        Nor have they, from that day to this, left a stone unturned to accomplish an
                        imitation of it among ourselves. Indeed we cannot refuse to admire the
                        industry and ingenuity of these spiders; though we desire to tear their web:
                        nay we could find in our heart, to pity the unfortunate fowler, who, after
                        completing all his trains and contrivances; and standing ready in mute
                        expectation with his hand half extended toward the prey; should suddenly
                        behold all his nets, and gins, and springes broken in pieces. There will,
                        indeed, be much sympathy, and much surprise, should we venture to transfer
                        these doctors of absurdity, and “architects of ruin” from the
                        University of Europe to the Academy of Laputa: should our frigid obtuseness
                        be unable to conceive the sublimity of their vast plans for the emancipation
                        of the species; after all the breath which the illuminati of more genial
                        climates have spent upon us:—after all their <hi rend="i">performances</hi> on the
Continent of Europe, to demonstrate
                        it:—should we still be found unable precisely to apprehend, how the
                        subversion of all government will tend to the security of peace, liberty,
                        and property; and how exceedingly both learning and virtue, and above all
                        religion and piety would be promoted, by the plunder and extirpation of
                        Christian establishments!</p>
          <p>The sentimental Ceruti said, with his last breath, “The only regret I
                        have in leaving the world, is, that I leave a religion on earth.” His
                        words were applauded by the Assembly, the Radical Assembly of France. And it
                        is, no doubt, with many of our own tender hearted liberals, a melancholy
                        reflection; that their most venerable and hoary sages of revolution may,
                        even now, perhaps, not survive <hi rend="i">every</hi> civil and religious
                        institution:—that they may “go to their own place,”
                        before they have amassed a full legacy of curses for their posterity.
                        However, no exertions have been wanting on their part: their efforts have
                        been alike patient, orderly, united, and energetic. Their army is at last
                        drawn out; and is about to make the grand charge. It has many raw recruits:
                        but many disciplined veterans, and able marshals. Their watchwords are
                        Liberty, and Reform: noble words indeed, but most foully abused. Let us
                        execrate their principles; but imitate, for once, their union and energy. If
                        we are divided, and disorganized; and above all, if we are panic-stricken,
                        every thing is lost. No superiority of numbers will avail us, if we are
                        separated, or wavering, or unprepared. In 1780 eight hundred thousand
                        Londoners looked on in consternation, while a handful of pickpockets ravaged
                        their property for three days! An eye witness of the Bristol outrages
                        declared, that at the beginning, forty persons might have dispersed the
                        rioters easily. On the 9th of November 1830, the leaders of the Radicals not
                        being prepared to show themselves; and being disconcerted by a premature
                        discovery of their plot; their mobs being consequently not so well organized
                        as the police; the latter saved the metropolis from destruction. It was, I
                        think, Marat, one of the Radical Reformers of France, who boasted that with
                        three hundred ruffians hired at a Louis d’or per day, he could govern
                        all France: and why? because all France was dismembered and
                        panic-stricken.</p>
          <p>Let us remember the fable of the lion and the bulls.</p>
          <p>It is true we vastly, and beyond comparison outnumber the enemy: but then we
                        are men of peace; and they are beasts of prey. We are strongest by day: they
                        ravine in the night; for their optics are adapted to darkness. And it is now
                        a very dark night for Europe. The radicals are elated; for it is a dark and
                        foggy night; when 
<pb id="p19-66" n="66"/>
thieves are always on the alert.
                        They are housebreakers: we are quiet householders, who have drawn the
                        curtains, and retired to rest!</p>
          <p>Permit me to suggest to you, Electors of West Kent, that this is no time to
                        multiply party distinctions, or to remember old grudges. We should travel in
                        Caravan; prepared against a horde of thieves far more cruel than wandering
                        Arabs. These highwaymen will rifle us if they catch us singly; but take to
                        their heels over hedge and ditch, should they once meet us walking together
                        on the King’s Highway.</p>
          <p>Let the <hi rend="i">good old</hi> Whigs, the Tories high and low, and the
                        men of no party, for once come together, and twist a threefold cord which
                        may not easily be broken.</p>
          <p>It was thus Britain was saved in 1792, from a revolution which our illuminati
                        were then on the very point of effecting. She was saved by nothing less than
                        an inspiration from Heaven: by nothing else than a most sudden, universal
                        revulsion of patriotism; and a simultaneous consociation, from one end of
                        the kingdom to the other. And this revolution our abandoned Liberals had
                        striven to bring about, while the blood of France was yet hot and reeking;
                        and with the stench of that great butchery under their nostrils! In the
                        extension of their philanthropy, which, indeed, they truly allege to be
                        trammelled with no vulgar demarkations of patriotic geography, they were
                        instituting a flesh market for the cannibals of Europe; and preparing to
                        slay their brethren for the shambles. France was too narrow for them: and
                        they were about to enlarge that slaughter-house of Europe by throwing into
                        it the habitations of their fathers.</p>
          <p>The French had been smitten with giddiness from God; and distracted with
                        delirious theories, more multitudinous than the tongues of Babel: but it was
                        not while they were aspiring to raise a pinnacle to the skies; but were
                        laying, in the very depths of Hell, the foundations of a charnel-house for
                        Christendom.</p>
          <p>But they meted out upon <hi rend="i">themselves</hi> the “line of
                        confusion and the stones of emptiness.” After laying waste one of the
                        richest countries in the world, to obtain liberty and equality; they fell at
                        once into the most abject military bondage, under a remorseless tyrant; who,
                        wonderful to say, has ever been the pagod of our own most furious
                        republicans and levellers: at whose spoliation of the liberties of Europe
                        they exulted: at whose signal defeat and overthrow, by the blessing of God
                        on the valour of their countrymen, they have scarcely ceased their wailings
                        to this day.</p>
          <p>In words, they are peace-makers and philanthropists: in deeds, they are
                        incendiaries and assassins. They extenuated Buonaparte’s most
                        unprovoked a[g]gressions and invasions; and had he invaded <hi rend="i">their own
country</hi>, would have hailed him with acclamations! But,
                        when the standard of Spanish independence was lifted up; no sooner did
                        Wellington and British valour drive him from the Peninsula, and unbind the
                        nations; than truly, on a sudden, no cloistered maiden was to be found so
                        sensitive, nay, so pious as the Radical! Yes, he who had beheld with sullen
                        indifference the excesses of Robespierre, and with savage transport the
                        exploits of Napoleon; would now, forsooth, doubt the very lawfulness of
                        defensive warfare! He would question whether any true disciple of the Prince
                        of Peace could take up arms! He would faint at the clash of a sword or the
                        beating of a drum!</p>
          <p>Gratitude the Radicals do not know. Their insolence ever increases with
                        indulgence. Till they get the power into their hands, they whimper like
                        school-boys; nay they can sob, and lisp, and languish like an
                        infant:—the moment they are elevated, they dash in pieces the dupe
                        who lifted them up. They are a generation of crocodiles, who mimic the
                        wailings of distress, and devour those who come to relieve it.</p>
          <p>They can put on the most saintly garb of Apostolic simplicity; and associate
                        with the disciples that they may betray the Master. They are, at present,
                        filled with apprehension, lest Christiantiy should suffer through an
                        over-fed priesthood; and are most politely assiduous to relieve them of
                        their superfluities: nay, so earnest are they found in this pious work; that
                        even freehold estates, secured by the most indubitable titles to the Church,
                        and legacies entailed upon it with the most awful sanctions, would be
                        alienated at their touch: and signatures, and seals, and stamps, and rolls
                        of parchment, would become dissolved in a moment, in the furnace of their
                        Evangelical charity! Did our fathers pour forth their treasures at the feet
                        of the Redeemer; and, in the most solemn manner, endow the Church with them
                        for ever?—Hark!—these children of Judas Iscariot are
                        inquiring, “Why is not all this sold, and the money given to the
                        poor?[”]—But this they say, not because they care for the
                        poor; but because they are thieves, and desire to clutch the bag, and to
                        make off with its contents!” [sic]</p>
          <p>The Radicals have long clamoured for Parliamentary Reform, and a full
                        representation, as the national panacea. This has been granted them, even to
                        the extent of their own desires: and are they satisfied? Are they about to
                        treat this reformed Parliament, this darling of their hopes, as nursing
                        mothers?—or have they, while it is yet in the womb, prepared their
                        political unions to hector over, and bully it?</p>
          <p>They now declare that this is but a <hi rend="i">first step:</hi> it is
                        tolerated, however, because they imagine that they behold in it the dawn and
                        twilight of a republic.</p>
          <p>By this faction the Queen has already been most publicly menaced with the
                        scaffold, in terms aggravated by personal insult: and our Sovereign, whose
                        venerable parent’s memory is, at present, a favourite butt of their
                        savage vituperation: our beloved Sovereign, whose reign has been hitherto
                        one series of concession; will fall the 
<pb id="p19-67" n="67"/>
earliest
                        victim to their baseness and perfidy; unless it should please the Almighty
                        to dash their projects, and to “turn the counsel of Ahitophel into
                        foolishness.”</p>
          <p>The English Radical, and the Gallic Jacobin “are brethren; instruments
                        of cruelty are in their habitations. O my soul, come not thou into their
                        secret; unto their assembly, mine honour, be not thou united: for in their
                        anger they slew a man, and in their self-will they digged down a wall.
                        Cursed be their anger, for it was fierce; and their wrath, for it was
                        cruel.” They are the abortions and monsters of the moral universe;
                        uncouth, perverse, and opposite to nature. They will grovel in the dust
                        before a tyrant: but with a gentle and parental Sovereign “their neck
                        is as an iron sinew; and their brow brass.” They will cringe under
                        the rod; and bite the hand that caresses them.</p>
          <p>And will you, my countrymen, suffer this deplorable faction to pour out, not
                        their representatives, but their delegates over the counties: to send forth
                        their foxes, two by two, into your harvests, tied together by revolutionary
                        pledges; and dragging between them the firebrands of destruction? Samson
                        sent fire-b[r]ands to the <hi rend="i">Philistine</hi> fields. But 
<hi rend="i">we</hi>, if we make Constituents of these foxes of free trade
                        and liberalism; shall be directing the matches of a starving peasantry to
                        our own garners; and politically, shall light up such a fire in our country,
                        as nothing will extinguish but the waters of desolation.</p>
          <p>Samson, in death as in life heroic, brought down upon his head the vault of
                        Dagon; and perished with his foes. But <hi rend="i">we</hi> are shattering
                        the citadel of <hi rend="i">our own</hi> strength; the tabernacle of our
                        constitution, the temple of our liberties, and the sanctuary of our God. We
                        are tugging at those two main pillars; our loyalty and our piety; and shall
                        be ground to powder, in the crash and perdition of our country.</p>
		<q> So fond are mortal men,<lb/>
 Fallen into wrath divine,<lb/>
 As their own
                        ruin on themselves t’ invite;<lb/>
 Insensate left or to sense
                        reprobate;<lb/>
 And with blindness internal struck.”<lb/>
 Milton. </q>
          <p>Brother Electors; we have been requested to return to Parliament two
                        Gentlemen, who have, unhappily, ranked themselves under the standard of the,
                        so called, Radical Reformers. Personal remark is remote from my intention:
                        but I would remind you that the Radicals have ever been found adverse to the
                        agricultural interest: that whatever they may pretend; they will, if
                        possible, sweep away your protecting duties.</p>
          <p>Farmers! They were the wretched leaders of this wretched faction, who, during
                        the late dreadful fires, strenuously encouraged the incendiaries! Some of
                        the most abandoned of them published cheap tracts for distribution among the
                        poor, stimulating them to fire their master’s property. But now, if
                        there be a Radical Parliament; the starvation produced by free trade, and
                        the consequent reckless desperation of the peasantry; will supersede the
                        necessity of all other stimulants. If, then, you patronise Radicalism, in
                        any shape, you will have yourselves to thank for the consequences.</p>
          <p>Already, the fires have begun. Do you wish them to blaze once more over the
                        kingdom? If you do; send Radicals into Parliament; make Radicals of the
                        poor; and as those principles effectually relieve all classes from every
                        religious and moral restraint; neither property nor life will be for a
                        moment secure. Conflagration has already ravaged your harvests; and
                        assassination and massacre are in its train.</p>
          <p>Landholders, who have estates to be confiscated, or laid in ashes: Farmers,
                        who have free trade, and annihilation impending over you: Manufacturers, who
                        must be beggared in the bankruptcy of your country: Fund-holders, who desire
                        not the <hi rend="i">wet sponge:</hi> Britons, who have liberty to lose:
                        Christians, who have a religion to be blasphemed: now is the time for your
                        last struggle! The ensuing Election is not a question of party politics;
                        much less, a paltry squabble of family interests: but Existence, or
                        Annihilation, to good old England!</p>
          <p>Let us then rally once more: Whigs, Tories, Moderates; and especially every
                        Christian man in West Kent;—it may be for the last time;—round
                        the noble standard of Old Kentish Loyalty; and defend it to the last. If we
                        triumph; our children will say of us;—“These were the sacred
                        heroes, who, amid the convulsion of the world, serenely held fast, and
                        transmitted to us the birthright of our liberties: nay, all our glory, in
                        the inheritance of the British Name.” If we perish in the contest;
                        let it not be, O Spirit of Albion, as recreants and dastards: but with Thy
                        standard clenched in our grasp; or folded about our hearts!</p>
          <p>God prosper the good old cause: it is His Own. Is it the cause of old
                        England: of our beloved Monarch: of our nobles: most truly of all our middle
                        classes; and preeminently of the poor; who, in the destruction of commerce
                        and agriculture; of order and property, get nothing of the spoil; but suffer
                        every extremity of wretchedness and famine.</p>
          <p>The other cause is that of the Devil and his Angels; masked under a pretended
                        indignation at State tyranny, and Church corruption: witness, again, the
                        great French Revolution: wherein the King, after making every just
                        concession, and much more was savagely murdered: the nobles were massacred
                        and banished: the Clergy butchered by companies, or assassinated at their
                        church doors. A strumpet was dressed up, and publicly adored in the
                        Cathedral of Paris, as the Goddess of Reason: our Saviour was denounced as
                        an arch imposter, and the profession of his religion was prohibited!</p>
          <p>The whole Radical and Atheistical party of England is now marshalled against
                        the constitutional and religious; <pb id="p19-68" n="68"/>
and Europe is
                        looking on in solemn expectation[.]</p>
          <p>The result of the ensuing Election will turn the balance. <hi rend="i">One
                            additional Conservative Member may save this great nation:—the
                            vote of any one individual may secure that Member’s
                            election.</hi> Every friend to our cause, however humble, should
                        energize as if all depended on himself.</p>
          <p>Unanimous co-operation and individual energy may do all things.</p>
          <p>Electors; he who has thus taken the liberty to address you, however
                        inadequate to the task; claims, at last, the merit of disinterestedness. Sir
                        William Geary is personally unknown to him: nor will he obtain any sort of
                        benefit by that Gentleman’s return to Parliament. He has addressed
                        you, without the instigation of a second person: without the knowledge of
                        Sir William, or any of his Committees. The writer receives not one farthing
                        of the great or small tithe: <hi rend="i">he has no connection with, or
                            dependence on the Clergy:</hi> he is neither a prophet, nor the son of a
                        prophet. Alas! it is no longer a little cloud of the bigness of a
                        man’s hand, which hovers in our political horizon, but a blackness of
                        [word illegible] which it requires no prophetic direction to perceive. He is
                        not accustomed to push himself forward: he loves not to hear himself talk;
                        but would rather have listened while another spoke. He has not obtruded into
                        the front ranks of the loyal army: but would be overwhelmed by the sense of
                        such presumption. He has waited long in the rear and outposts, hoping that
                        some stronger arm might be lifted up against the big and boastful Philistine
                        of Jacobinism, who has hurled defiance alike at the institutions of men and
                        the armies of God. And he has no heartier desire than that while he is
                        picking up these few pebbles from the brook, and cutting out this rustic
                        sling, he may be superseded and borne away by one sudden acclamation of
                        re-kindled patriotism from Guernsey to the Hebrides: that Britain may never
                        become intellectually a province of France: that her wolves of revolution
                        may hear once more the British lion roaring from the cliffs of Kent, and be
                        discomfitted: that we may never like the Trojans; whom old historians repute
                        our ancestors; be undone by the presents of an enemy: but that the liberty
                        and equality which our treacherous neighbours have offered us, as winged
                        steeds to be yoked into the car of human improvement; may be timely
                        suspected to be full of armed men: and, finally: that all our countrymen who
                        have been deceived and over-persuaded by the internal troublers of our
                        peace, may have the true nobility of mind readily and frankly to confess
                        their mistake: and, instead of setting by the ears every class and order of
                        society; may strive as heartily to promote that universal good will, and
                        blessed brotherly union, which are the only root and basis of our prosperity
                        and strength: which are able to lift us up, once more, in the scale of
                        nations; and to constitute Britannia, as she was ever wont to be, the
                        arbitress of the destinies, and the guardian of the liberties of Europe.</p>
          <p>FINIS.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
