<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>19.2.viscomi</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Selections from William Blake’s Songs of Innocence and of Experience, 
musical settings by Gregory Forbes; Gregory Forbes, A Companion to the New Musical Settings</title>
        <author n="Viscomi">Joseph Viscomi</author>
        <author n="LaFrance">Margaret LaFrance</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1985</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">19.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Karl Kroeber</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Josephine McQuail</name>
              <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>Margaret LaFrance</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1985"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <body>
	<pb id="p19-84" n="84"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-2-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main"><hi rend="i">Selections from William Blake’s</hi>
                                Songs of Innocence and of Experience; <hi rend="i">Musical Settings
                                    by Gregory Forbes</hi>, Ecchoing Green Records, 1983. <hi rend="i">A
Companion to the New Musical Settings by Gregory
                                    Forbes.</hi> Gregory Forbes. Kingston, Ontario: Quarry Press,
                                1983. 48 pages. Together $27.70; with a set of 20 slides, $35.70.
                                Slide set only, $11.20. Prices include shipping.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Joseph</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Viscomi</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">with</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Margaret</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">LaFrance</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>As Ruthven Todd points out, “no one can fully understand the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> divorced
of their setting.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">1</ref> Some fine,
hand-colored facsimiles have made it
                        possible to read Blake’s illuminated poetry as graphic art consisting
                        of text and illustration in complex relations. In short, to read it as
                        originally presented. Or have they? Poetry and painting were only two of the
                        “three Powers in Man of 
<pb id="p19-85" n="85"/>
conversing with
                        Paradise which the flood did not Sweep away” (K 609). The third Power
                        was Music, and music, according to Cunningham, was an integral part of the
                        composing process as manifest in the illuminated print: “As he drew
                        the figure he mediated the song which was to accompany it, and the music to
                        which the verse was to be sung, was the offspring too of the same
                            moment.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
type="note">2</ref> Must the
                        poetry’s setting, then, be musical as well as visual? 
<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi rend="i"> Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (Norwood, Pa.:
                            Norwood Editions, 1973), p. viii.</note>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Allan Cunningham, <hi rend="i">Lives of
                                the Most Eminent British Painters, Sculptors and Architects; Blake
                                Records</hi>, p. 482.</note></p>
          <p>That music was important to Blake, there can be no doubt. According to
                        Gilchrist, Blake “was very impressionable . . . to simple national
                        melodies . . . though not so to music of more complicated structure.”
                        At the Linnells’, he “would sit by the pianoforte, tears
                        falling from his eyes, while he listened to the Border Melody” sung
                        by Mrs. Linnell. Even then, as late as 1825, he “still sang, in a
                        voice tremulous with age, sometimes old ballads, sometimes his own songs, to
                        melodies of his own.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41"
type="note">3</ref> Blake is
                        recorded as having died with a song on his lips, while some of our earliest
                        accounts of him as a poet emphasize his singing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">4</ref> At Mrs. Mathew’s salon, “he was
                        listened to by the company with profound silence and allowed by most of the
                        visitors to possess original and extraordinary merit.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">5</ref> And although Blake “was entirely
                        unacquainted with the science of music, his ear was so good, that his tunes
                        were sometimes most singularly beautiful, and were noted down by musical
                            professors.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44"
type="note">6</ref> In <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi> (c. 1784), in large part a satire of salon
                        society, Quid, Blake’s caricature of himself, continually bursts into
                        song. True, Gittipin, Gimblet, Obtuse Angle, and the other Islanders may not
                        have been musically sophisticated, but Blake’s real salon audience
                        certainly was. “Being a musical house,” the Mathew gatherings
                        included accomplished singers like Elizabeth Billington, composers like
                        Thomas Billington, famous musicologists like Dr. Charles Burney (perhaps one
                        of the music professors?) and Flaxman, who evidently “sang
                        beautifully, having an excellent and beautiful voice.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">7</ref> Singing to people who knew a thing or
                        two about music suggests not only that Blake was confident of his voice and
                        compositions, but that he actually was a good singer. Like the Italian
                        saying: If you want to see if you can sing, go to where women wash clothes;
                        if they stop singing, you’re good. <note id="n41"><hi rend="s">3</hi>
                            Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (London: J.
                            M. Dent &amp; Sons, 1942), p. 41.</note>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Fredrick Tatham; <hi rend="i">Blake
                                Records</hi>, p. 305.</note>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">5</hi> J. T. Smith, in Gilchrist, p. 41.</note>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> Ibid.</hi></note>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Tatham; <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>,
                            p. 521. For a list of possible guests at the Mathews’ and of the
                            pleasure gardens and theatres where Blake would have heard popular
                            music, see. B.H. Fairchild, <hi rend="i">Such Holy Song</hi> (Kent,
                            Ohio: Kent State University Press, 1980), p. 7.</note></p>
          <p>That Blake should sing while he worked is as natural as words and images
                        generating and being generated by melodies. It is more interesting, though,
                        that the simultaneity in the illuminated printing process of melos, logos,
                        and graphics is manifest in the reception of the illuminated print. In the
                        “Introduction” to the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>,
                        music, singing, and writing, though executed sequentially by the Piper, come
                        together in the form of the book, so that “all [who] read” the
                        “happy songs . . . may joy to hear” (K 111). Reading is
                        hearing the songs, the melody being the activity of mind as it reads. As
                        Blake says, “Nature has no Tune, but Imagination has” (K 779).
                        Because “Melody,” like “Invention [and]
                        Identity,” is one of the “Objects of Intuition” (K
                        474), the songs are given settings each time they are read. Historically, it
                        is the only time the three Powers do come together, for Blake is not known
                        to have passed out illuminated prints as song sheets as he read or sang
                        them.</p>
          <p>Gregory Forbes, with his album of twelve songs selected from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and
of Experience</hi>, sixteen “facsimiles
                        of Blake’s coloured engravings,” a set of twenty slides, and a
                        large size illustrated commentary, attempts to combine the aural and visual
                        Blake within a historical context.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n46" type="note">8</ref> His
                        “aim . . . in writing . . . has been to bring the listener to an
                        understanding of the song lyrics in a way that Blake intended them”
                        (p. 9). Blake’s exact intentions, of course, aren’t known,
                        since he never wrote down the music (it is not “lost,” p.
                            7),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">9</ref> but
Forbes reasons that
                        “because [Blake’s] sympathies were always with the common
                        people . . . traditional folk music stylings are especially appropriate for
                        Blake’s songs” (p. 7).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48"
type="note">10</ref>
                        So, “to bring Blake to the people,” he based his aural
                        reconstructions on children’s hymns, folk ballads, and Elizabethan
                        songs, as well as “the street music of Blake’s London, the jig
                        and reels of itinerant fiddlers and pipers” (p. 7), and used
                        contemporaneous instruments, such as guitars, flutes, flageolers, violin,
                        and hand-drums. From <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> he has set
                        “Introduction,” “The Shepherd,” “The
                        Lamb,” “The Divine Image,” “Laughing
                        Song,” “The Ecchoing Green” [side A]; from <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>
“Introduction,” “London,”
                        “A Little Girl Lost,” “The Garden of Love,”
                        “The Tyger,” “Ah! Sun-flower” [side B]. The
                        songs were chosen to represent “the main themes of the complete
                        cycle” (p. 8). Blake’s contrary states and their accompanying
                        symbols and images are discussed in some detail (pp. 24-27), but the song
                        order, instrumentation, and arrangement of the reproductions do not pair
                        contrary states or make explicit the connections within or between the two
                        sets. <note id="n46"><hi rend="s">8</hi> The basis for the album project is
                            the series of workshops Forbes conducted for secondary school children
                            in “Frontenac County, Ontario, Canada, and later presented . . .
                            at two conferences of the Ontario Council of the Teachers of English.
                            All of these were arranged by David Schleich of St. Lawrence College,
                            Kingston” (p. 47). With the encouragement of Schleich, also
                            editor of Quarry Press and tom-tom player on “The Tyger,”
                            Gregory Forbes seems to have done everything himself, including writing
                            the accompanying commentary. Despite its elaborate presentation, the
                            project is quite Blakean in spirit. The logo for Ecchoing Green Records
                            (a company certainly created for this project) is the Piper from the 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> title page, while the record label is
                            “The River of Life,” printed in green, with its flute
                            players on either side of the spindle hole.</note>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">9</hi> There is an odd use of sources and
                            significant omissions. Forbes describes the music as
                            “lost,” referring, one assumes, to those tunes Smith says
                            were “noted down by musical professors.” However, he never
                            refers to Smith, but to Cunningham’s statement that Blake
                            “wanted the art of writing it down” (p. 7), which leaves
                            the reader with the impression that Blake’s unrecorded musical
                            notations are missing or lost. Cunningham also notes that if they
                            “equalled many of his drawings and some of his songs, we have
                            lost melodies of real value” (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p.
                            482).</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Forbes is certainly correct to argue
                            that an understanding of the music of Blake’s day is the first
                            step to hearing the poetry as Blake meant us to hear it. But I think he
                            overstates the case when he says that “not much has been written
                            about Blake’s musical sources since very little is known about
                            the subject; the study must be based almost entirely on Blake’s
                            lyrics” (p. 47). By citing only one work in the bibliography on
                            the subject, Martha England’s “Blake and the Hymns of
                            Charles Wesley” (<hi rend="i">Bulletin of the New York Public
                                Library</hi>, 70 [1966], 7-33), he makes clear the need for his
                            album project at the expense of strengthening it as an introduction to
                            the subject, about which much is actually already known. What is not
                            known is if Blake’s familiarity with popular ballads derived from
                            reading or singing them. Forbes does mention (p. 22) Thomas
                            Percy’s <hi rend="i">Reliques of Ancient English Poetry</hi>
                            (1765), a copy of which Blake owned; but not Christopher Smart’s
                                <hi rend="i">Hymns for the Amusement of Children</hi> (3 editions
                            between 1770-1775); Joseph Ritson’s <hi rend="i">A Select
                                Collection of English Songs</hi> (1783), for which Blake engraved
                            several plates; nor any of the contemporary essays on the relation
                            between music and poetry, like John Aiken’s <hi rend="i">Essays
                                on Song-Writing</hi> (1774); Ambrose Philips’ “Letter
                            on Song-writing,” in <hi rend="i">The Guardian</hi>, #16 (1713);
                            Anselm Bayly’s <hi rend="i">The Alliance of Musick, Poety, and
                                Oratory</hi> (1789); or Daniel Webb’s <hi rend="i">Observations on the
Correspondence between Poetry and Music</hi>
                            (1769); nor does he mention recent theoretical work, like Bertrand H.
                            Bronson’s <hi rend="i">Music and Literature in England in the
                                Seventeenth and Eighteenth Centuries</hi> (Los Angeles: Clark
                            Memorial Library of the University of California at Los Angeles, 1953),
                            or Herbert M. Schueller’s “Correspondences between Music
                            and the Sister Arts, According to Eighteenth-Century Aesthetic
                            Theory” (<hi rend="i">Journal of Aesthetics and Art
                                Criticism</hi>, 11 [1953], 334-59). These works may be too esoteric
                            for Forbes’ audience of high school students, but he seems not to
                            have read them himself or six works that are crucial to discussing the
                            influence of hymns and popular ballads on Blake’s poetry: Albert
                            B. Friedman’s <hi rend="i">The Ballad Revival: Studies in the
                                Influence of Popular on Sophisticated Poetry</hi> (Chicago: Chicago
                            University Press, 1961), George Sampson’s “The Century of
                            Divine Songs,” in <hi rend="i">Proceedings of the British
                                Academy</hi>, 29 (1943), Martha England and John Sparrow’s
                                <hi rend="i">Hymns Unbidden: Donne, Herbert, Blake, Emily Dickinson,
                                and the Hymnographers</hi>; Nick Shrimpton “Hell’s
                            Hymnbook: Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                                Experience</hi> and Their Models,” in <hi rend="i">Literature
                                of the Romantic Period: 1750-1850</hi>, Ed. R. T. Davies and B.G.
                            Beatty (New York: Barnes &amp; Noble, 1976), pp. 19-35; John
                            Adlard’s <hi rend="i">The Sports of Cruelty: Fairies, Folk-Songs,
                                Charms and other Country Matters in the Work of William Blake</hi>
                            (London: Cecil &amp; Amelia Woolf, 1972); and, most important, B.H.
                            Fairchild’s <hi rend="i">Such Holy Song: Music as Idea, Form, and
                                Image in the Poetry of William Blake</hi> (Kent, Ohio: Kent
                            University Press, 1980).</note></p>
          <p>The slides are for “classroom presentation,” to be viewed
                        “while listening to the music,” an audio-visual presentation
                        which Forbes believes will “project [the listener] into that time
                        when Blake created each illustration and, at the same time ‘meditated
                        the song which was to accompany it’ ” (p. 10). The slides,
                        which are of the same plates as the reproductions, plus Linnell’s
                        sketch of Blake and the three title pages to <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, are
                        used not only to accommodate a student audience, but because they
                        “are much clearer and more vivid than the printed reproductions, and
                        the lyrics can be read without difficulty” (p. 8). Indeed, the 16
                        photomechanical reproductions (the songs, frontispieces, and “The
                        Voice of the Ancient Bard,” which is not set to music), though
                        printed on fine, heavyweight ivory paper, are in no way 
<pb id="p19-86" n="86"/>
facsimiles. None is easily readable; all give a poor idea of
                        what illuminated prints look like. The copy is not identified, but seems to
                        be copy Z without the frame lines.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n49" type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">11</hi> The reproductions seem to be of 6 and 8
                            color offset reproductions of copy Z, published by Rupert Hart-Davis
                            Ltd. in 1967. Forbes mentions twice (pp. 23, 47) that the first color
                            facsimile of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> was 1967, which, of course, is
                            not true, but it does seem to indicate that he used the 1967 volume to
                            make his “facsimiles.” (Hard to believe that offset
                            lithography could have undone so many!) For a list of early color
                            facsimiles of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, see <hi rend="i">Blake
                                Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1978), pp. 432-39. For a history of
                            Blake facsimiles, see Robert N. Essick’s review of the Manchester
                            Etching Workshop facsimiles, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
                                Quarterly</hi>, 19 (1985), 39.</note></p>
          <p>Introducing Blake through song and image is both creative and practical, and
                        a logical extension of what W.H. Auden said—or almost
                        said—somewhere: “No poetry is good poetry that is not good
                        when read aloud.” One would think that the voice of the balladeer
                        could easily join those of piper, bard, and prophet, and, like theirs, add
                        to our understanding and enjoyment of Blake. But, unfortunately, the
                        Donovan-like style of these settings does little to enhance the inherent
                        musicality of Blakes words—let alone reveal the meaning of the
                            songs.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">12</ref>
Missing here is the
                        poet’s ear for what a poet said. <note id="n50"><hi rend="s">12</hi>
                            The Donovan album they recall most clearly is <hi rend="i">A Gift from a
                                Flower to a Garden</hi> (Epic, 1967), which is probably only
                            coincidence, but it is interesting to note that Donovan in this
                            two-record set seems to think he’s Blake. As a
                            “minstrel,” he sings his “poems” so that
                            “all may see and know . . . that God is Love,” sings one
                            of them to experienced “youth” and the other to innocent
                            “children of the dawning generation.” The texts of the 12
                            songs for children are printed and illustrated with pen line drawings,
                            and the sheets form both a booklet and a song cycle.</note></p>
          <p>A familiarity with eighteenth-century folk stylings and ballad structures may
                        be necessary to capture the popular sounds of Blake’s age, but it is
                        no assurance of communicating the spirit of Blake’s poems. Because of
                        the musical limitations of Forbes’ compositional style, the settings
                        too often seem like impositions on, rather than expositions of, the text.
                        Indeed, the style seems even more limited than it is because Forbes, perhaps
                        confusing the distinction between simplicity and monotony, not only sings
                        all the songs himself, but uses only one instrument, the guitar, as the
                        dominant accompanimental instrument in all of the settings. While his guitar
                        playing is more than adequate, his voice is not the sort that can sustain
                        interest for an entire album. While Forbes does incorporate other
                        instruments throughout the album, using sometimes as many as six musicians,
                        he uses them in such limited and subordinate ways that their presence almost
                        frustrates more than it pleases. The flute, for instance, which he uses to
                        represent the innocent Piper, often plays trills in the background, which
                        are meant to sound pastoral and serene. But the trills rarely grow
                        organically from the musical context, seeming instead to have been a concept
                        of innocence thought of and tacked on after the setting was complete. A more
                        successful use of other instruments is in the jig-like sections that follow
                        “Laughing Song” and the “Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Songs of
Experience</hi>, although in both instances, the jigs
                        go on so long that we lose the initial freshness of the idea. And, while
                        this type of postlude certainly captures the energetic spirit of the former,
                        it seems a questionable ending to the latter.</p>
          <p>From <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, “The Lamb” is the setting
                        that works best. In this song, Forbes’ compositional techniques (a
                        small melodic range, and repetitive rhythms and harmonies) enhance the text.
                        Here the gentle arpeggiation in the guitar and the quiet flute obligato lend
                        a lovely simplicity to the song without becoming monotonous or saccharine.
                        These same compositional techniques do not, however, work in every song.
                        Indeed, in “The Divine Image,” Forbes’ style actually
                        destroys the meaning of the poem. The melody for the first line
                        (“Mercy, Pity, Peace, and Love”) is mi, re, ti, do, a
                        seemingly inoffensive and simple arrangements of tones. But when this melody
                        is imposed on the text, and in the syllabic rhythm of the text, the effect
                        is unsettling at best. The seventh step of the scale (ti) is unstable
                        because of its half-step proximity—and its consequent need to
                        “pull”—to tonic (do). That the word
                        “peace” occurs on ti and is then given rhythmic stress (i.e. a
                        longer note value) is not only awkward and unaccomplished writing, but it
                        destroys the very peacefulness and harmony that the words (as a phrase) are
                        trying to convey.</p>
          <p>From <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, “London” and “Ah!
                        Sun-flower” are the best. In “London,” the drone bass
                        note successfully portrays the hopeless plodding of downtrodden people and
                        the wailing guitar notes become the cries of the “chimney
                        sweeper” and “youthful harlot.” In this song,
                        Forbes’ technique of repeating his melodies by couplets rather than
                        stanzas (a technique which contributes to the stasis of many of the
                        settings) works very well as a way of accentuating the key words and images.
                        The coda to “Ah! Sun-flower,” which goes on almost as long as
                        the song itself (but, unfortunately, at such a reduced audio level that it
                        is difficult to hear), features a guitar solo by Thomas Handy, the
                        improvisatory nature of which is a welcome change from Forbes’
                        consistent and controlled guitar accompaniments to the songs. One only
                        wishes that Forbes had been this adventurous in all of his settings.</p>
          <p>The commentary is in two parts and, with forty-eight pages of wide double
                        columns of type, is quite extensive. “William Blake and the Age of
                        Revolution,” the first section of part I, examines the
                        “Political” “Industrial,”
                        “Intellectual,” “Social,” and
                        “Romantic” revolutions of Blake’s day, and his
                        reactions to them. “William Blake’s Life and Writing,”
                        the second section, focuses on those events of Blake’s life and his
                        other writings that have a “bearing on the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>” (p. 9). “The
Poetics of the Songs,”
                        section three, analyses the form, diction, and symbolism of the poems and
                        discusses the main literary devices Blake employs. Irony, unfortunately, is
                        not included, but an erroneous definition of illuminated printing is. Part
                        II is primarily an explication of each of the twelve songs and designs, with
                        a very “Select Bibliography.” The booklet is decorated with
                        monochrome vignettes from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and other illuminated
                        books, none of which is identified or discussed in the text.</p>
          <p>The background material is mostly derived from Bronowski’s <hi rend="i">William Blake and the
Age of Revolution</hi>, while the
                        interpretation of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> is mostly derived from
                        Wicksteed and Hirsh. Oddly, though, Forbes ignores the latter’s sense
                        of change and the former’s warning of reading Blake backwards, in
                        favor of reading the songs within Blake’s “system,” an
                        approach more in keeping 
<pb id="p19-87" n="87"/>
with Adams and
                            Gleckner.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51"
type="note">13</ref> At any rate, Forbes has
                        written a very solid introductory text, with Blake intelligently placed in
                        his time, and the poems, “London” and the “Garden of
                        Love” in particular, given fine, detailed explications. The page or
                        two on each poem is designed to help the student read the poem, literally,
                        by identifying verbs, nouns, antecedents, and parallel structures, and by
                        pointing out important biblical and historical allusions, key words,
                        symbols, and recurrent images. <note id="n51"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Jacob
                            Bronowski, <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Age of Revolution</hi>
                            (New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1965); Joseph H. Wicksteed, <hi rend="i">Blake’s
Innocence and Experience</hi> (London: J.M. Dent
                            &amp; Sons Ltd., 1928); E.D. Hirsh, Jr., <hi rend="i">Innocence and
                                Experience: An Introduction to Blake</hi> (New Haven: Yale
                            University Press), which was published in 1964, not “1927”
                            (p. 47); Hazard Adams, <hi rend="i">William Blake: A Reading of the
                                Shorter Poems</hi> (Seattle: University of Washington Press, 1963);
                            Robert Gleckner, <hi rend="i">The Piper and The Bard</hi> (Detroit:
                            Wayne State University Press, 1959).</note></p>
          <p>In the discussion of the poems, of diverse “revolutions, . . . and how
                        [Blake] reacted to them” (p. 11), it is obvious that Forbes knows his
                        audience well. His definition of Experience for woman as sexual repression,
                        for example, and his comments about the marriage of love (and thus
                        Blake’s own marriage), the arranged marriage, and the influence of
                        the role of women in the American Colonies on Blake, Wollstonecraft, and
                        other writers, will, I think, be of particular interest to high school
                        students (“Social Revolution: Marriage and Women’s
                        Rights,” p. 15). So, too, will many of the facts he cites: “A
                        teenage boy could be hanged for minor theft. There were 150 crimes
                        punishable by hanging (although murder was not one of them); most of them
                        were crimes against public property” (pp. 11-12); “there were
                        50,000 prostitutes, not counting mistresses kept by men of wealth,”
                        in Blake’s London (p. 16); “of the 70 years of Blake’s
                        life, Britain was at war for 35” (p. 11).</p>
          <p>Some of his facts, though, are wrong. He defines engraving as a technique in
                        which “a design was copied on to a copper plate with an
                        acid-resistant varnish; when acid was applied to the plate, the design would
                        remain in relief” (p. 23). In other words, he confuses engraving with
                        relief etching, as well as the concepts of negative and positive (using them
                        to mean reverse and regular writing). He cites Todd and Hayter’s 1948
                        experiments as the last word, ignoring Essick’s <hi rend="i">William
                            Blake, Printmaker</hi> (Princeton University Press, 1980), a careful
                        reading of which would have prevented these and a number of other technical
                            errors.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">14</ref>
And he sees the stimulus
                        for illuminated printing in the printing of the <hi rend="i">Poetical
                            Sketches</hi> (1783). It is, however, highly unlikely that Blake sought
                        “an inexpensive method of self publication” because the
                        apology in the advertisement proved an “embarrassing
                        experience” (p. 19). Publishing juvenilia was very fashionable
                        (especially in the 1770’s and 1780’s) and, though Blake was
                        certainly no “untutored youth,” excusing its merit quite
                            common;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53" type="note">15</ref>
fashion and convention are
                        still to be seen in Byron’s preface to <hi rend="i">Hours of
                            Idleness</hi>, 1807. Besides, Blake was given the book in sheets; that
                        he made no attempt to distribute it cannot be attributed to one offending
                        page, which could have been easily extracted. <note id="n52"><hi rend="s">14</hi> A
few technical corrections: Blake’s apprenticeship
                            was not to the Society of Antiquaries but to Basire, the
                            Society’s official engraver (pp. 23, 26). Illuminated books of
                            the Middle Ages were not “hand-printed” (p. 19), nor is
                            “illuminated printing” a “technique that married
                            the arts of engraving with watercolor painting” (p. 7). It is
                            doubtful that “Blake was a victim of technological change in that
                            engraving was a dying craft, gradually giving way to lithography in the
                            first two decades of the 18th century [sic]” (p. 13). Forbes
                            means, of course, the nineteenth century, but during this period the
                            most popular reproductive method was aquatint, the mainstay of the
                            picturesque view industry, and engraving, even after Hullmandel set up
                            his lithography press, 1817-1818, was in great demand, because the
                            development of steel engraving (1822) made it possible to print tens of
                            thousands of impressions with great detail and without loss of
                            quality.</note>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Margaret Ruth Lowry, <hi rend="i">Windows of the Morning: A Critical
Study of William
                                Blake’s</hi> Poetical Sketches, <hi rend="i">1783</hi> (New
                            Haven: Yale University Press, 1940), pp. 39-41.</note></p>
          <p>We can dismiss the idea that for five years Blake was actively looking for an
                        alternative means for publishing his works—or four years, if the
                        “illuminate the manuscript” phrase in <hi rend="i">An Island
                            in the Moon</hi> (1784) is misinterpreted as referring to illuminated
                        printing. He would have been one very unimaginative printmaker had he not
                        known that texts could be illustrated and multiplied on one page by etching
                        or engraving; the former, after all, is the method Blake used for three of
                        his illuminated books, and one or the other method is what all
                        eighteenth-century writing engravers and trade card makers used to print and
                        illustrate their texts. Why Blake used relief etching instead of any other
                        method and waited till 1788 to begin experiments are important questions,
                        but they go unanswered when relief etching is pictured as a major
                        breakthrough after years of trying and searching.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n54"><hi rend="s">16</hi> For a discussion of why Blake chose to
                            use relief etching when other, more conventional, methods would have
                            enabled him to combine text and illustrations on one plate, see my 
<hi rend="i">The Art of William Blake’s Illuminated Prints</hi>
                            (Manchester: Manchester Etching Workshop, 1983), pp. 1,
                        19-20.</note></p>
          <p>The picture of Blake as a graphic artist is a bit out of focus in other ways,
                        too. Forbes inadvertently perpetuates an image of Blake that we recognize as
                        Victorian, though its originator was himself a contemporary of
                        Blake’s. Borrowing from Cunningham, Forbes pictures Blake as
                        “a man of tireless industry, and after a day’s work . . . for
                        other artists and booksellers . . . he would paint or write through the
                        night” (p. 20). Cunningham says: “During the day [Blake] was a
                        man of sagacity and sense, who handled his graver wisely, and conversed in a
                        wholesome and pleasant manner; in the evening, when he had done his
                        prescribed task, he gave loose to his imagination.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">17</ref> But the image of an artist who “engraved by
                        day,” as though in some shop, but “saw visions at
                            night”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">18</ref>
while laboring in
                        his own studio, presents a schizophrenic artist and a melodramatic scene
                        worthy of George Sand, and one which appeals to those who need conflict in
                        order to see meaning in what would otherwise be plotless day-to-day living.
                        But there was no physical or temporal separation between Blake’s
                        commissioned works as an engraver or designer and his own work in relief
                        etching. All the plates were executed at home, in his own studio, cut and
                        drawn on the same tables, proofed and printed with the same ink, on the same
                        press. Blake did not work in a copperplate printer’s workshop, or a
                        large engraving studio, or a pressroom. It is a mistake to think of him as a
                        craftsman constantly under someone’s watchful eye, or under the
                        pressure of deadlines like nineteenth-century wood engravers working for the
                            <hi rend="i">Illustrated London News.</hi>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">17</hi> <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, p. 488.</note>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">18</hi> P. 501.</note></p>
          <p>The image of Blake as a mere craftsman, and not just a mistaken notion of the
                        relation between invention and execution (a relation beyond the scope of
                        this or probably any introductory text), is partly responsible for the idea
                        that Blake “wanted . . . skill of hand,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n57" type="note">19</ref> an idea that Blake fought so hard to overcome. Why
                        the “Tyger” looks like a harmless cat, for example, cannot be
                        explained by a lack of skill on Blake’s part, or, as Forbes suggests,
                        a case in which Blake, “in executing the drawing . . . ended up with
                        a creation quite different 
<pb id="p19-88" n="88"/>
from what he had in
                        mind” (p. 44). Picturing Blake as a nineteenth-century craftsman is
                        not only misleading, but contradicts Cunningham’s own image of Blake
                        as a multitalented artist “sketching designs, engraving plates,
                        writing songs, and composing music” all at the same time<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">20</ref>—of a man conversing with
                        Paradise with all his Powers. <note id="n57"><hi rend="s">19</hi> P.
                            485.</note>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">20</hi> P. 482.</note></p>
          <p>Forbes’ settings are not art songs or compositions like those of
                        Benjamin Britten, Ralph Vaughan Williams, or George Rochberg.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">21</ref> Nor are they “Airs simple and
                        etheral to match the designs and poems of William Blake,” which, as
                        Gilchrist admits, “would be a novelty in music.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">22</ref> As simple folk songs, they are more
                        successful at introducing Gregory Forbes than the spirit of William Blake.
                        The settings are not “aural facsimiles,” but, then, what is
                        appealing in theory is almost always impossible in practice. Whatever the
                        album’s scholarly merit, and despite the commentary’s minor
                        misrepresentations, Forbes’ triadic presentation (and sound argument
                        for such a presentation) ought to stimulate lively and imaginative
                        discussion about the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> in and out of the classroom.
                            <note id="n59"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Britten, <hi rend="i">Songs &amp;
                                Proverbs of William Blake</hi>, for baritone and piano, op. 74
                            (London: Faber &amp; Faber, 1965); Williams, <hi rend="i">Ten Blake
                                Songs</hi>, for voice and oboe (London: Oxford University Press,
                            1958); Rochberg, <hi rend="i">Blake Songs</hi>, for soprano and chamber
                            ensemble (New York: Leeds Music Corp., 1963). There is, admittedly, a
                            thin line between poor translation and exciting variation. New settings
                            of a song or play can become works of art in their own right,
                            celebrating the original and displaying what may have been hid. It seems
                            that musicians have been more successful in creating new works of art
                            based on Blake’s songs than have other artists. Illustrations of
                            Blake’s poetry struck Ruthven Todd as “the most horrible
                            of all things”—though, admittedly, he had the
                            “whimsical drawings of some cheery, chintzy girl, who is
                            ‘so fond of Blake as he inspires her so much.’ From such
                            nightmares as these, Good Lord, Deliver us!” (Todd, <hi rend="i">Songs of
Innocence and of Experience</hi>, p. viii). He is
                            apparently referring to (and quite rightly, I think) Pamela
                            Bianco’s line drawings in <hi rend="i">The Land of Dreams</hi>
                            (New York: Macmillan, 1928).</note>
	<note id="n60"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Gilchrist, p. 41.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p19-89" n="89" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
