<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>19.2.deluca</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Morton D. Paley, The Continuing City: William Blake’s Jerusalem</title>
        <author n="De Luca">V. A. De Luca</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1985</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">19.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Karl Kroeber</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Josephine McQuail</name>
              <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>Margaret LaFrance</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1985"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-2-0008">
        <pb id="p19-76" n="76"/>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Morton D. Paley. <hi rend="i">The Continuing City: William
                                    Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1983.
                                330 pp., 22 illus. $57.00</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">V.A.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">De Luca</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s reputation as a great English poem is
                        essentially a post-war phenomenon. Indeed this reputation, in so far as it
                        commands reasonably wide assent in the profession, is largely a product of
                        the past twenty years, gathering its momentum from the enthusiasms of the
                        apocalyptically inclined sixties. By the time the poem began to be taken
                        seriously, the New Criticism, with its emphasis on nuances of language and
                        subtleties of formal technique, was well on the wane. The older modes of
                        literary scholarship—the elaboration of historical background, the
                        tracing of sources and influences, the inventorying of themes and formal
                        features—were even more remote to nascent Blakeans. The criticism of
                        Blake’s longer poems found its distinctive voice in an impassioned
                        translation or paraphrase of themes, in which a certain evangelical impulse
                        played no small part. This enthusiastic approach was enormously valuable for
                        kindling a widespread interest in Blake, and only now is it beginning to
                        give way to more specialized and technical kinds of inquiry into his work.
                        But the approach also led to an impoverishment in our sense of the ways in
                        which <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> works as a poem and of its place in a
                        historical and cultural context. Because of its belated arrival in the
                        canon, the study of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> has passed from fervent
                        interpretation to scholarly specialization without having paused to offer a
                        clearly outlined, basic <hi rend="i">description</hi> of the thing itself.
                        Categorical description, the forte of the older modes of criticism and
                        regularly applied to poems whose reputation consolidated earlier, say, 
<hi rend="i">The Canterbury Tales, The Faerie Queene</hi>, or <hi rend="i">The Prelude</hi>, has not until now
figured significantly in work on
                            <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>—much to our cost.</p>
          <p>These circumstances heighten the importance of Morton Paley’s
                        much-awaited study. As Paley himself points out, “at this point we do
                        not need yet another recension of the beliefs of an idealized Blake”
                        (p. 32), and in <hi rend="i">The Continuing City</hi> he avoids any such
                        thing. The originality and strength of the book lie in its refusal of a
                        thematic centering, in its disinclination to translate Blake’s poem
                        into an argument or to impose an argument of the author’s own
                        devising. Although Paley refrains from stating what he considers the aim of
                        his study to be, that aim is clear enough from the design of the whole: to
                        explore the essential frames of reference in which an adequate study of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> might begin. It attempts more or less to
                        describe in an orderly fashion what the poem contains, where it finds
                        models, models, and how it works. Sometimes, as in the introductory chapter
                        and occasionally elsewhere, this approach involves a survey of familiar
                        material (such as a review of the poem’s publishing history and of
                        its critical reception) that is readily available in other secondary
                        sources. The inclusion of such material indicates that Paley aims ultimately
                        not for novelty but for comprehensiveness. Indeed, in its range of coverage
                        and its willingness to stoop to the familiar and to basic facts, <hi rend="i">The
Continuing City</hi> resembles nothing so much as those
                        impressively magisterial introductions that one or two generations ago would
                        accompany critical editions of major texts—say, Maynard Mack on <hi rend="i">The
Essay on Man</hi> in the Twickenham Pope or Frank
                        Kermode’s introduction to the Arden <hi rend="i">Tempest.</hi> It is
                        precisely this sort of treatment—erudite but plain-speaking,
                        objective, comprehensive, topically subdivided—that <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> has
sorely lacked, as it has lacked the honor of a
                        definitive annotated critical edition (a need, incidentally, that Paley
                        recognizes). <hi rend="i">The Continuing City</hi>, more leisurely in pace,
                        more loosely textured, is perhaps not quite in the class of Mack on Pope,
                        but the comparison serves to suggest the kind of scholarly company that
                        Paley’s work keeps and the importance of what 
<pb id="p19-77" n="77"/>
he has
accomplished.</p>
          <p>Like the imaginative city that gives the book its title and provides the
                        subject of its central chapter, this work too is a structure with many
                        gates, each leading from a different direction to the sanctuary of the poem
                        itself. There are chapters on the verse of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and
                        its relation to period styles and theories, on approaches to the reading of
                        the designs, on the millenarian framework and its symbolism, on the dramatis
                        personae, and on the formal organization. This varied set of concerns calls
                        for a range of different skills in handling them, and although certain
                        chapters do rise above others in distinction, virtually all parts of the
                        work display a shrewd common sense, a facility in discovering relevant
                        connections, a resourcefulness in posing interesting kinds of issues to
                        address, and a thorough command of background information.</p>
          <p>Paley is at his best when he has tangible kinds of evidence before him to
                        engage his attention. He clearly likes to gather and correlate information,
                        to probe it for its implications, and to dispose it in orderly arrangements
                        for his reader. The role of literary historian seems particularly congenial,
                        and one of the most impressive things in <hi rend="i">The Continuing
                            City</hi> is the devotion that Paley bestows in detailing a tradition of
                        analogues to Blake’s four-gated city. As Paley proceeds methodically
                        from Ezekiel, Revelation, and Josephus, through such later visionaries of
                        millennial architecture as Villapandus, Lightfoot, and John Wood, the very
                        accumulation of examples gives the reader a vividly heightened sense of the
                        perennial force of the visionary impulse, a process aptly caught in
                        Blake’s trope of Golgonooza, “ever building, ever
                        falling” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 6.2), only to give rise again in
                        successive prophets. As a summary account of sources and analogues for
                        Blake’s city of vision, this part of Paley’s book is likely to
                        remain definitive; future students of the subject will want to consult it
                        before any other account.</p>
          <p>But the triumph of Paley’s empirical approach comes not in his
                        investigations of literary history but in his analysis of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s form. His skill in handling formal matters is
                        evident early in the book, in the chapter on versification, where through an
                        array of resourceful and patiently applied methods—scansion,
                        syntactical analysis, comparison with analogues—he arrives at
                        characterizations that are virtually always on the mark (e.g.,
                        “pauses do not typically create a balanced tension, as often in
                        Augustan poetry, but rather appear to resist the onrush of the verse and
                        then yield to it; . . . enjambement transfers energy from one line to
                        another and creates a sense that statements [not always sentences] are
                        structural units” [p. 51]). The best treatment of form in the book is
                        reserved, however, for last. In this chapter, simply called
                        “Form,” Paley unquestionably makes his most useful
                        contribution to the criticism of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> After
                        surveying some possible models for the poem’s peculiarities of
                        organization (the most interesting of which, from the Blake critic’s
                        point of view, is Handel’s <hi rend="i">Messiah</hi>), he launches
                        into a scrutinizing analysis of the work’s construction. There is a
                        valuable exposition of the problem of the two extant arrangements of plates
                        in Chapter 2, and although this treatment cannot be taken as definitive (the
                        interested reader may wish to compare Paley’s findings with my own
                        somewhat different account of the same matters, previously published in
                        these pages [Spring 1983]), it demonstrates clearly that a critical
                        understanding of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s foundations cannot
                        proceed without a firm bibliographical understanding. More important still
                        is Paley’s comprehensive and illuminating attempt to chart the
                        recurrences of the important narrative and thematic motifs in the poem.
                        Borrowing his technique from synoptic tabularizations of the four gospels
                        (why has no one thought of applying this technique to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
before?), Paley analyzes these motifs into their
                        component parts and pinpoints their recurrences on a spatial grid
                        representing <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s four chapters. As a result
                        any reader consulting these tables may henceforth take in at a glance the
                        location of the major narrative strands and motifs, the distribution of
                        their recurrences throughout the poem, and the weight of concentration Blake
                        gives to each. At once a concordance of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s
                        motifs and a map of its thematic structure, these tables are likely to prove
                        an indispensable reference tool.</p>
          <p>Paley’s close investigations of the poem’s construction pay off
                        in some finely judicious observations on the rationale of the structure of
                        the whole. Usefully distinguishing what he calls the
                        “organization” of the work (its “official”
                        symmetrical division into four equal chapters) from its “form”
                        (small, potentially shiftable gatherings of plates, or synchronous narrative
                        events recurring in unpredictably distributed clusters), he concludes that
                        Blake’s technique, in effect, is to set the two kinds of order in a
                        kind of antagonism to one another: “The organizational container
                        reinforces the expectation of a strong narrative line, an expectation which
                        is subverted time after time in the work itself”; “regularity
                        is an aspect of what I have called the ‘container’; the poem
                        and the designs build up a tension with that regular order” (pp. 302,
                        307). From this strong insight it follows that “attempts to view the
                        chapters as discrete units depend upon rationalizing after the fact, and
                        quite different chapter constructions could be so rationalized” (p.
                        303). One hopes that this firmly persuasive observation will lay to rest
                        finally all those by now wearisome attempts to allegorize 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s four-part scheme as a thematic medley or as
                        stages in a conceptual argument. The schematic divisions of the text, it
                        would seem, confer meaning no more readily than rhyming or isochronous meter
                        do in prosody. They are formal points 
<pb id="p19-78" n="78"/>
of departure
                        for an unpredictable play of intellectual and emotional energy, the definite
                        outlines from which an infinite potential recoils.</p>
          <p>Paley’s finest critical insights, then, are reserved for matters of
                        form. In its handling of theme and meaning, however, the distinction of 
<hi rend="i">The Continuing City</hi> is oddly enough not so assured. The
                        two explicitly thematic chapters “The Myth of Humanity”
                        (Albion-Vala-Jerusalem) and “The Prophetic Myth”
                        (Los-Enitharmon-Spectre) are not themselves problematic; they do not bring
                        many new large-scale insights to bear on these “myths” (there
                        are many gratifying small illuminations) but the mode of exposition is as
                        lucidly and as rationally organized as we are likely to find in any
                        commentary on Blake’s longer poems. The chapter on
                        “Art” however raises problems of a larger order, for here
                        Paley’s concern is explicitly with the search for meaning itself and
                        the principles according to which such a search might be based. Using five
                        designs from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, chosen as exemplary of differing
                        kinds of interpretative problems posed by the visual side of Blake’s
                        work, Paley hopes to show “How to Read Blake’s
                        Pictures” (p. 89). As usual, his principles are sensible, his
                        observations keen, and his references learned. But the discussion as a whole
                        begs the question of what it means to “read” a picture. It
                        proceeds on the assumptions that interpretation is a self-evident
                        desideratum and that the meaning of a picture is to be found in a presumed
                        doctrinal intention paraphrasable in words. But such assumptions merely
                        extend to the world of designs that yearning for a “recension of
                        beliefs” or for “rationalizations after the fact” about
                        which Paley is properly skeptical elsewhere in the book as a program for
                        Blake criticism. Paley appears somewhat uncomfortable with the otherness of
                        the pictorial medium, with the evasiveness of its reponse to demands that it
                        serve a signifying role; hence his preference that ambiguous
                        “readings” of certain designs be settled on one side of the
                        argument or the other. Yet one needs to ask why Blake takes refuge
                        intermittently in pictures at all, if the pictures can be re-spoken as words
                        conformable to unequivocal words that the poet has already used.</p>
          <p>Take, for instance, what from the standpoint of interpretation are the two
                        most difficult of Paley’s five exemplary cases. According to various
                        critics the crucifixion scene on pl. 76 depicts either a vegetated Christ,
                        in which case we are to deplore Albion’s posture of reverence, or a
                        Christ sacrificing himself in divine Friendship, in which case we are
                        enjoined to imitate Albion’s <hi rend="i">imitatio.</hi> But are we
                        to assume that Blake’s advice regarding which attitude we should
                        choose is somehow encoded in the visual lines of the picture? It seems more
                        likely that the design is an invitation to choice, not a determination of
                        it. After alluding to the crucifixion in various contexts, positive and
                        negative throughout <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Blake is saying, in effect,
                        here is the thing itself, the visual sign for a permanent act or reality, a
                        “Representation of what Eternally Exists. Really &amp;
                        Unchangeably.” (<hi rend="i">VLJ</hi>, E 554). He who would see in
                        this visual depiction a display of divine love and he who would see a
                        religion of atonement with a corpse as centerpiece see, to borrow a phrase
                        from Wallace Stevens, nothing that is not there in the design itself. The
                        alternatives are both encoded in its iconographic details and in the
                        religious assumptions of viewers, whether liberated or benighted. Paley is
                        on the right track when he suggests that it is better to trust our intuitive
                        response to designs such as this than to consult some doctrinal abstract of
                        Blake’s thought for our opinion. But what is required here is an
                        intuitive response to the crucifixion itself, not to a
                        “message” of the poet regarding it. Perhaps the function of
                        this design, and many others in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as well, is to
                        suspend the strongly directive <hi rend="i">voice</hi> of the poet and to
                        yield to the spectator the opportunity to test his or her own imaginative
                        capacities in an act of <hi rend="i">seeing.</hi></p>
          <p>The same point holds for the other difficult case among Paley’s
                        samples. The notoriously recondite chariot vision on pl. 41[46] is, as Paley
                        admits, “almost a Rorschach test for Blake scholars.” Prolific
                        with unknown metamorphic forms and half-recognizable iconographical hints at
                        accessible meaning, it virtually begs for interpretation. But what it so
                        conspicuously invites it then proceeds to impede. Paley is inclined to see
                        this design as a dark vision, a triumph of Vala, but if one is inclined to
                        view the design as a representation of the fulfillment of apocalyptic
                        prophecy, the supports for such a reading are also readily available. If the
                        woman in the chariot is clothed, and hence Vala, as Paley argues, one might
                        point out that Jerusalem also appears clothed on pls. 26 and 92; the older
                        bearded figure embracing the woman appears somber, but no more somber than
                        he does in similar embraces in the indisputably ecstatic and apocalyptic
                        contexts of pls. 96 and 99; and the last line of verse on pl. 41, directly
                        over the design of the embracing couple, refers to “The Bride and
                        Wife of the Lamb” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 41.28). As for the drawers,
                        one might be reminded, as Paley is, of certain pictorial sources that
                        suggest Covering Cherubs or rides through the underworld; but iconography
                        even more readily yields, in response to the lion-maned, human-faced,
                        ox-hooved, eagle-guided creatures depicted here, the traditional scriptural
                        emblems of the Four Living Creatures that surround the Divine Vision; from
                        Blake’s own works one might point to the collaboration of serpents,
                        eagles, lions, and men in <hi rend="i">MHH</hi> 15 to bring grand works of
                        art into being, or to those vehicular serpents on which energetic children
                        joyously ride in <hi rend="i">America</hi> 11 and <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 6.
                        To collect counter-evidence against Paley’s position is not, however,
                        my point here; it is not a question of 
<pb id="p19-79" n="79"/>
right and
                        wrong interpretations. If Paley’s treatment falls short of a full
                        response to the complexities that pl. 41 poses, it is not for any lack of
                        skill in the reading of emblems; rather, it is because he bypasses an issue
                        that Blake’s technique in many parts in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                        raises insistently: why does the “Rorschach” effect appear so
                        frequently in the designs (and not just the designs) unless Blake is making
                        a point about the process of signification itself?</p>
          <p>If a design or a passage of verse (such as the notorious vortex passage in
                            <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 15) perennially begets fresh interpretations
                        and controversy, while continuing to frustrate the formation of a consensus
                        opinion, then the interpretive effort becomes not a vehicle for overcoming a
                        difficulty but rather a signifier of that difficulty;
                        “difficulty” itself is foregrounded as the
                        “message.” Perhaps spots such as the design on pl. 41 have
                        been established as interpretive Free Zones, fashioned so as perpetually to
                        invite and to evade univocal readings. Such points might act as vortices in
                        the surface of accessible meaning, drawing us down into the depths where all
                        meanings are seen as potential, as “regenerations terrific or
                        complacent” varying according to our perceptions or to the turns in a
                        visionary conversation dramatic. The unreadable (or too variously readable)
                        chariot of pl. 41 compacts such a conversation in a tightly determinate
                        visual form.</p>
          <p>Plausibly, Paley might respond to this argument with one of his own
                        interpretive principles: “Interpretations according to which mutually
                        exclusive meanings are seen as equally valid are not likely to be helpful.
                        We should remember Blake’s love of the definite” (p. 118).
                        What one finds helpful of course depends on what one is asking the poem to
                        supply; if it is a series of securely identifiable “correct”
                        meanings, then Paley’s cautions are well taken. But generally Blake
                        praises the definite not as an attribute of meaning but as an attribute of
                        form; it is a quality of the bounding outline, or to use Paley’s own
                        terminology, the regularity of the “container,” and it applies
                        to the incisive visual clarity of the signifier, not to the possibilities of
                        the signified. For within the walls of the definite there ricochets its
                        antonym the infinite, equally loved, a surging and ultimately untameable
                        waywardness that will not abide our question or accommodate itself to our
                        paraphrases. Despite some excellent remarks in Chapter II on the
                        “Titanic striving” of Blake’s sublime mode in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and on
the effort of its “language to
                        abandon its function as mediator and to become meaning itself” (p.
                        64), in general Paley shows little responsiveness to this wayward element in
                        the poem. It is a lack that demarcates the limits of his study of the
                        subject.</p>
          <p>I speak of limits not in any pejorative sense. A different kind of critical
                        approach would have curbed the excellence that <hi rend="i">The Continuing
                            City</hi> achieves in its own kind, and one can only be grateful for a
                        study that manages to pack between two covers as many valuable observations
                        as it does in such a wide range of contexts. If one ventures to weigh the
                        actual achievements of this work against the possibilities that it has
                        neglected to explore, it is simply because the appearance of a major book on
                        a great English poem impels us to take stock of the critical tradition
                        gathering around that poem, locating the book in hand within the tradition
                        by glancing at what has gone before and what might come after. <hi rend="i">The
Continuing City</hi> functions as a practical guide; it is not
                        surprising that Paley invokes the “helpful” as a principle in
                        reading Blake’s designs, for such a principle underlies his whole
                        enterprise. This is indeed a genuinely helpful book, seeking everywhere to
                        accommodate the strangeness and difficulty of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> to
                        our understandings and vice versa, and its commonsense approach accomplishes
                        what had to be accomplished sooner or later. But one suspects that a future
                        criticism will make strangeness and difficulty its very theme, bringing to
                        the fore a Blake who is himself anything but accommodating. Such a criticism
                        is likely to differ as much from Paley’s lucid, well-rounded course
                        of instruction as that mode differs from the evangelical commentaries of the
                        past generation, mentioned at the outset. Newer readings will have come to
                        terms with a sensibility that in mood and in expressive tendency can be
                        brooding, obsessive, devious, secretive, sometimes even brutal, even as it
                        is also radiant and humane. Here lies a fruitful direction for the criticism
                        of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> to take, not because a conception of Blake as
                        problematic is desirable for its own sake (though a certain clearing of the
                        air of pieties is always welcome) but because an unsentimental gauging of
                        the human complexities and strenuous tensions in his work will serve to
                        underscore his genius and to deepen our own thought. One need only glance at
                        the history of Wordsworth criticism in the past twenty years to see the
                        effects of a resourceful phenomenological probing of ambiguities; not only
                        is Wordsworth now seen as a difficult proto-modern poet but he has moved to
                        the center of that revival of Romantic concerns which has so significantly
                        nourished the most venturesome and vital strands of recent critical
                        discourse. To establish Blake, a poet of equivalent genius, in a similar
                        nourishing and energizing role is an enterprise that all of us should
                        want.</p>
          <p>Nevertheless, as a conspicuously Orcan figure of our own day once phrased it,
                        if you can’t always get what you want you can get what you need.
                        Before anyone can scale the craggiest heights or probe the gloomiest caverns
                        of Blake’s most demanding poem, there needs to be an expertly
                        conducted exploration of the basic terrain, and this Paley has provided. As
                        it stands, <hi rend="i">The Continuing City</hi> is the most significant and
                        useful book on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> that we have.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
