<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>19.2.mulhallen</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">The Crying of Lot 318; or, Young’s Night Thoughts Colored Once More</title>
        <author n="Mulhallen">Karen Mulhallen</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1985</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">19.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Karl Kroeber</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Josephine McQuail</name>
              <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>Margaret LaFrance</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1985"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <body>
	<pb id="p19-71" n="71"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-2-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">The Crying of Lot 318; or, Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
                                Thoughts</hi> Colored Once More</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Karen <name>Mulhallen</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
		<q> Sotheby’s (London, Monday, 17 December 1984, 2.30 p.m.)<lb/>
<lb/>
                        318<lb/>
<lb/>
 Blake (William)—Young (Edward) The Complaint and the
                        Consolation, or Night Thoughts, 43 pictorial borders designed and engraved
                        by William Blake and coloured by hand, slightly soiled, three borders
                        slightly offset, a few short tears in margin of explanation leaf and one
                        slightly affecting one border repaired, red straight-grained morocco gilt,
                        uncut, folio, R. Noble for R. Edwards, 1797 </q>
          <p>The Clarendon edition of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">1</ref> lists and describes 23 colored copies
                        of the engraved work, and refers to one more, the Moss-Bentley copy G<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">2</ref> recently rediscovered by Thomas V.
                        Lange in a closet of the Lutheran Church of America (<hi rend="i">Blake
                            Quarterly</hi> 59, pp. 134-36). To these 24, in 1983, James McCord added
                        the copy housed for over 50 years, but not recorded, in the library of
                        Washington University, St. Louis.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">3</ref> While
                        doing research in London in the winter of 1984-85, I came upon yet another
                        unrecorded copy of the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, bringing to 26 the
                        number of recorded copies. Following the format of the Clarendon census, I
                        would list this most recent copy as<lb/>
 III-2 (Previously unknown) Grey
                        Death. <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake’s
                                Designs for Edward Young’s “Night
                                Thoughts,”</hi> edited by John E. Grant, Edward J. Rose,
                            Michael J. Tolley, coordinating editor David V. Erdman (Oxford:
                            Clarendon Press, 1980), pp. 62-72.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Clarendon <hi rend="i">Night
                            Thoughts</hi>, p. 61 and n. 81, p. 92; G.E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977), pp.
                            636-46.</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">3</hi> James McCord, “An Unrecorded
                            Colored Copy of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>,”
                                <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 18 (Fall 1984),
                            116-18. McCord’s tally of copies includes Bentley copy T, the
                            Cook copy, which he argues is not included in the Clarendon census. He
                            is incorrect, as this is Clarendon copy I-15.</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Description:</hi> Handsome, early twentieth century “Arts
                        &amp; Crafts Style” binding in red straight-grained morocco gilt
                        with five raised bands running horizontally across the spine terminating in
                        stamped fruit and leaf motifs. Binding stamp WHS (for W.H. Smith and Sons)
                        on lower border of inner back cover. Spine stamped in gold “Night
                        Thoughts By Edward Young. Designs By W<hi rend="s">m</hi>. Blake
                        1797.” Pale pink and blue marbled endpapers. All edges uncut.
                        Watermarked in lower right hand corner on ten sheets, pp. iii-iv, 3-4, 5-6,
                        29-30, 31-32, 49-50, 55-56, 69-70, 85-86, and 91-92, as well as on the
                        “Explanation of the Engravings” sheet which appears after page
                        95, “J Whatman 1794.”</p>
          <p>The prints are in good condition, except for one repair slightly affecting
                        the border of pp. 89-90, a few short tears in the margin of the explanation
                        leaf, some slight soiling, and three borders a little offset. As is usual,
                        in a few instances the plate marks extend slightly beyond the foredge of the
                        leaf, but only five borders have the engraved surface touching the page
                        edge.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Provenance:</hi> Inscribed on the verso of the title page in
                        pencil in the upper left hand corner is “Baron Dimsdale”.
                        According to Sotheby’s, this copy was acquired by Charles John, fifth
                        Baron Dimsdale, together with copies of <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>
                        and <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n15" type="note">4</ref> Sold by Sotheby’s (London, 17 December 1984) to Sims,
                        Reed &amp; Fogg, £13, 750. <note id="n15"><hi rend="s">4</hi> The
                            Dimsdale copies of the illuminated works are described in <hi rend="i">Blake
Books</hi>, pp. 170, 180, 384, and 410. The Sotheby’s
                            catalogue states that the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> was
                            “probably acquired . . . together with copies of <hi rend="i">The
                                Book of Urizen</hi> and <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Innocence.</hi>” No evidence is given for this assertion,
                            although Michael Heseltine of Sotheby’s confirmed the
                            copy’s provenance and wrote the catalogue entry. However, <hi rend="i">Blake
Books</hi> notes that it was the <hi rend="i">first</hi> Baron Dimsdale (1712-1800) who acquired copies of the
                            illuminated books, whereas the Sotheby’s catalogue states that it
                            was the <hi rend="i">fifth</hi> Baron Dimsdale who acquired all
                            three.</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Pencil Markings:</hi> There are four sets of pencil markings in
                        this copy: Front of fly-title “2.P 7”; verso of title page,
                        upper left, “Baron Dimsdale”; page 50 “1.5
                        <hi rend="s">—</hi>” or “1. <inline-image n="019-02-p71-curved-stroke"/> .”,
or upside down “<hi rend="s">—</hi>
                        6.1”, difficult to make out but likely bookseller’s price
                        code; verso of Explanation leaf, near gutter in lower right hand corner,
                        “EB”.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Some other distinctive features:</hi> Page 23 has a faint
                        L-shaped line in ink in the bottom margin, as if the plate accidentally
                        skipped in the press, thereby creating a line with the same configuration as
                        one of the etched/engraved lines in the plate.</p>
          <p>Pages 23, 26, 27 and 33 use the color red for drapery, clothing and wine, and
                        in some instances the color seems blotchy, as if, as the color dried, the
                        pigment has come out of suspension in patches.</p>
          <p>Pages 37 and 70 stand out from all the others in that the foliage and ground
                        are in various shades of green, appearing as a surprisingly naturalistic use
                        of color, especially in comparison to other of the engravings.</p>
          <p>The title page to Night III displays Narcissa, illustrated in the
                        Sotheby’s catalogue in color, as remarkably naked, the slight drapery
                        on the front of her body emphasizing this.</p>
          <p>Page 75, Phoebus, shows quite clearly the coloring technique. The whole page
                        was first washed in yellow, grey was then added to the clouds and hair, then
                        a deeper yellow was added to the sun and to the body of Phoebus. Finally,
                        his body while still wet was wiped and a pink wash applied. In coloring this
                        plate seems to have a close connection with one copy in the Rosenwald
                        Collection (Copy I-4), where the horses, the sun, and Phoebus are all golden
                        yellow. In I-4, the gold is set against an <corr type="emend">iridescent</corr> sky of reds, blues,
                        purples and yellows. While it would be difficult to make a case for one as a
                        model for another, the similarity of some of the coloring and the coloring
                        steps as revealed in the Dimsdale copy together suggest a close dating for
                        the two copies.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Issues raised by the Dimsdale Copy (III-2):</hi> The Clarendon
                            <pb id="p19-72" n="72"/>
census codes copies according to the color of
                        Death’s gown on the title page to Night I, the most common color
                        being white (Type I), the next green (Type II), with a single copy, in the
                        Houghton Library at Harvard, being grey (Type III). Grey is the key color
                        for the entire Dimsdale copy. Not only is Death charmingly portrayed in a
                        grey gown, but many other figures are also robed in grey. The angels, for
                        example, from pages 40-42, are depicted with grey wings, whereas in several
                        other copies these are multi-colored with an iridescent effect. And on page
                        80, the red-faced Thunder God with gold rays emanating from his head is
                        dressed by dramatic contrast in grey clothes while the sea beneath is grey
                        and green.</p>
          <p>In III-2 special attention has also been paid to skin, hair and eyes.
                        Death’s skin is quite tanned and many figures show very careful
                        highlighting and pale blue veining. Hair is often cap- or wig-like, and the
                        eyes are usually brightly demarcated.</p>
          <p>Pages 53-54, 60 and 62 of the Clarendon census discuss the
                        “non-standard” details of Type III, “the colouring of
                        the beard of Time in 11E (NT36)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16"
type="note">5</ref> being
                        brown, rather than white or grey as in all other copies.” In the
                        Dimsdale copy, however, Time’s beard is white, although his topknot
                        by contrast is black. The Clarendon editors conjecture that the Harvard copy
                        was “quite likely to have been done by some possessor of an
                        uncoloured copy for his own enjoyment, or as a forgery” (p. 60). They
                        conclude that III-1 “Stands apart from all others. In such specific
                        details as the colour of Death’s garments and the colours of the
                        garments and hair of other figures as well as in its general character, this
                        copy is peculiar. Of all copies it seems most likely to have been done
                        without close reference to any copy that might have had Blake’s
                        authorization” (p. 62). <note id="n16"><hi rend="s">5</hi> 11E is in
                            the masculine state.</note></p>
          <p>The discovery of the Dimsdale copy necessitates a re-examination of the
                        Clarendon speculations about Type III, and the similarity of III-2 to Type I
                        copies reconfirms the need to be sceptical about fixity of coloring patterns
                        and their dating.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
