<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>19.2.labelle</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">William Blake, America: A Prophecy and Europe: A Prophecy 
[Dover Publications]; William Blake, Songs of Experience [Dover Publications]</title>
        <author n="La Belle">Jenijoy La Belle</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1985</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">19.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Karl Kroeber</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Josephine McQuail</name>
              <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>Margaret LaFrance</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1985"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-2-0008">
        <pb id="p19-83" n="83"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Blake. <hi rend="i">America: A Prophecy</hi> and
                                    <hi rend="i">Europe: A Prophecy.</hi> Facsimile Reproductions of
                                Two Illuminated Books with 35 Plates in Full Color. New York: Dover
                                Publications, 1983. $5.95</title>
            <title type="main">William Blake. <hi rend="i">Songs of
                                    Experience.</hi> Facsimile Reproduction with 26 Plates in Full
                                Color. New York: Dover Publications, 1984. $3.00</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Jenijoy</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">La Belle</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Dover Publications has made a fine reputation for itself by publishing
                        well-made paperbacks useful to students and scholars. Among its Blake titles
                        are <hi rend="i">Drawings of William Blake</hi> (1970) and a reduced
                        facsimile reproduction of Richard Edwards’ 1797 edition of
                        Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (1975). In 1971 Dover
                        embarked upon the production of color facsimiles with an original-size
                        reproduction of copy B of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> Some of the
                        plates are fuzzy and the backgrounds are a little too dark, but for only two
                        dollars (later raised to three), the volume is valuable for handy reference
                        and classroom use. Dover has recently issued two further volumes containing
                        color reproductions of three illuminated books.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">America</hi> and <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> are reproduced
                        original size in a single pamphlet-style paperback. The brief
                        “Publisher’s Note” includes the following information:
                        “The present volume reproduces the complete copy M of <hi rend="i">America</hi>
(printed on paper made in 1799), whereas the complete <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> reproduced here includes
colored plates from copies
                        B and G of that book and the black-and-white plate from copy K (all these
                        copies are privately owned). Note that <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> contains two
                        plates numbered 9—referred to in the present edition as 9(a) and
                        9(b)—and has no plate numbered 11.” Some of this information
                        is wrong, and the whole statement is misleading. Copy M of <hi rend="i">America</hi>
and B of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> are indeed in private
                        collections, but copy G of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> is now in the Pierpont
                        Morgan Library and copy K has been in the Fitzwilliam Museum since 1950. The
                        comment about two plates numbered 9 implies that this repetition appears in
                        original copies of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> and that none contains a plate
                        numbered 11. This is not the case at all. Both copies B and G are numbered
                        consecutively, and the presence of two plates numbered 9 in the facsimile
                        results from its composite nature. In copy G, plate 12 (following the plate
                        numbers in Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>) is numbered 9, while the
                        same number is given to plate 13 in copy B.</p>
          <p>The Publisher’s Note implies that the Dover reproductions were made
                        directly from the original copies cited. I am highly suspicious of
                        this—partly because none of the owners of the originals is named and
                        also because there is no statement of permission to reproduce. Further, the
                        mixture of three copies of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> is exactly the same as
                        that appearing in the Blake Trust/Trianon Press facsimile of 1969. The copy
                        of <hi rend="i">America</hi> reproduced by Dover is the same as the one used
                        by the Blake Trust for its 1963 facsimile. The Dover reproductions of both
                        illuminated books show distinct boundary lines between contiguous colors,
                        and this feature is typical of the Blake Trust method of stencil coloring,
                        rather than of Blake’s own method with its gentle gradations of
                        tones. Thus it would appear that the Dover volume is based on two Blake
                        Trust facsimiles and that these are the books “privately
                        owned” (perhaps by Mr. Hayward Cirker, founder and owner of Dover?).
                        Since the volume lacks any reference to the Blake Trust, I assume that no
                        permission was necessary.</p>
          <p>Using the Blake Trust facsimile of <hi rend="i">America</hi> copy M as a
                        standard, I find that most of the plates in the Dover reproduction have
                        acceptable color fidelity. The only major problem would seem to be a dulling
                        of the blue tones, particularly on plates 3 and 5 (as numbered in copy M).
                        The sunburst on plate 7 has lost some of its brilliance, and the outlining
                        of the ram and the two figures has become a little unfocused. Several other
                        plates suffer from indistinct outline in design areas, but the only really
                        bad reproductions are plates 8 and 9. Both have a brown tint to the white
                        paper in text areas, and this browning has seriously affected the blues on
                        plate 8 and the greens on plate 9. Clearly, the Dover reproductions are not
                        suitable for the detailed analysis of Blake’s hand coloring. No one,
                        however, should expect an inexpensive reproduction to provide the basis for
                        such analyses. The Dover reproductions are certainly adequate for many other
                        types of studies.</p>
          <pb id="p19-84" n="84"/>
          <p>The color work in the <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> facsimile is also generally
                        satisfactory. Three plates, however, have a distinct color shift not found
                        in their Blake Trust archetypes: plate 9 (inscribed “6” in the
                        reproduction) has been given a rather ghoulish green tint; plate 11
                        (inscribed “8”) has the same brown shift found in some of the
                            <hi rend="i">America</hi> plates; and the final plate is a little too
                        yellow. I would not be surprised to find variations among copies of the
                        Dover volume—particularly if they continue to print from the same
                        transparencies. The later printings of the Dover <hi rend="i">Songs of
                            Innocence</hi> show just this sort of decay of both color and sharpness
                        of outline.</p>
          <p>In addition to the reproductions, the volume includes exceedingly brief
                        summaries of the poems and descriptions of the designs. The latter seem to
                        be summary paraphrases of Sir Geoffrey Keynes’s notes on the designs
                        in the Blake Trust facsimiles. The Dover volume concludes with a
                        transcription of the texts. Lacking any indication to the contrary, the
                        typographic texts appear to be new transcriptions rather than reprints of a
                        previously published edition. The details of punctuation do not follow
                        Keynes, Erdman, Stevenson, or Bentley.</p>
          <p>Dover’s new facsimile of <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> has the
                        same format as its 1971 <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> facsimile. The two
                        volumes are clearly meant to be companions. In this later volume, the
                        publisher’s only reference to the copy reproduced is a statement on
                        the verso of the typographic title-page that the facsimile is based on
                        “a copy printed ca. 1826.” On the back cover, this same date
                        is given rather misleadingly as the date of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence
                            and of Experience.</hi> The appearance of the Dover plates makes it
                        clear that the work reproduced is the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> section
                        from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, copy Z, with
                        Blake’s inscribed plate numbers, but not his hand-drawn framing
                        lines, eliminated. For unexplained reasons, the frontispiece to 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi> is also omitted. Copy Z is well known from the fine
                        Blake Trust facsimile of 1955. The appearance of fairly definite boundary
                        lines between colors in the Dover reproduction makes me suspect that, once
                        again, Dover is silently reproducing the work of the Trust. It is even
                        possible that the plates are based on the 1967 Orion Press/Rupert Hart-Davis
                        reproductions of Z, reissued in 1970 by Oxford University Press. These
                        complete reproductions of copy Z are themselves based on the Blake Trust
                        facsimile, and thus the Dover volume could be a reproduction of a
                        reproduction of a reproduction. (I doubt that this is what Blake meant by
                        “Fourfold Vision.”) In comparison to all of these possible
                        forebears, Dover’s plates show a strong and most unfortunate shift
                        towards a magenta tint. This feature, plus the fact that about half the
                        plates seem a little out of focus, make the volume less handsome and less
                        useful than the <hi rend="i">America/Europe</hi> facsimile. The 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi> volume concludes with a transcription of the text.</p>
          <p>Although I’ve been rather grumpy about the problems, these are nice
                        volumes (particularly for the classroom) and well worth having—as
                        long as they are not treated with the same sort of trust we give to the real
                        Trust facsimiles. Dover is to be congratulated for producing these books and
                        for offering them for a song.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
