<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>19.2.lister</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">G. E. Bentley, Jr., Robert N. Essick, Shelley M. Bennett, and Morton D. Paley,
Essays on the Blake Followers; Joseph Viscomi, Prints by William Blake and His Followers</title>
        <author n="Lister">Raymond Lister</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1985</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">19.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Karl Kroeber</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Josephine McQuail</name>
              <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>Margaret LaFrance</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1985"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-2-0008">
        <pb id="p19-80" n="80"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">G. E. Bentley, Jr., Robert N. Essick, Shelley M. Bennett,
                                Morton D. Paley. Preface by Robert R. Wark. <hi rend="i">Essays on
                                    the Blake Followers.</hi> San Marino, California: Huntington
                                Library and Art Gallery, 1983. 71 pp., 51 illus. $8.00</title>
            <title type="main">Joseph Viscomi. <hi rend="i">Prints by William Blake and His
                                    Followers.</hi> Ithaca, New York: Herbert F. Johnson Museum of
                                Art, Cornell University, 1983. 36 pp., 18 illus. No price
                                stated.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Raymond</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Lister</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Samuel Palmer, the most important of William Blake’s followers, was a
                        few years ago in the news in England on account of the crude fakes of his
                        work, executed by the late Tom Keating, which appeared on the London art
                        market. Several of us said at once that they were not authentic; others
                        appeared to give them their blessing. Some were reproduced in the book 
<hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer</hi> by James Sellars (London, 1974)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n22" type="note">1</ref> and one in the <hi rend="i">Burlington
                            Magazine.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23"
type="note">2</ref> One at least was
                        accepted by the late Edward Croft-Murray of the British Museum, and Martin
                        Butlin of the Tate Gallery said there was “a considerable case for
                        their being by the artist.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24"
type="note">3</ref>
                        Which surely all goes to show that enthusiasm, even when combined with
                        academic scholarship, is not always supported by perfect connoisseurship.
                            <note id="n22"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Plates 41, 43, 78, 87, 89.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">2</hi> August 1965, p. 439.</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> The Times</hi>, 16 July 1976, pp. 1-2.</note></p>
          <p>But the fact remains that this all did Palmer’s reputation
                        considerable harm if only temporarily, for when leading experts, especially
                        if they are also important museum officials, are deceived into accepting
                        fakes as original works, and when the fakes are illustrated in a leading art
                        journal and in an otherwise scholarly book, people begin to ask themselves
                        if the original artist’s work is as good as it is reputed to be,
                        considering that it apparently could be so easily faked as to deceive such
                        expert opinion. This point is often put to me by those outside art circles.
                        Even on Keating’s own assessment his fakes were “crude
                            daubs,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">4</ref>
so the non-expert
                        must have found it doubly puzzling that, if Palmer were such an outstanding
                        artist, experts should have been prepared to accept the
                        “daubs” as original work. Consequently the non-expert observer
                        could hardly be blamed for thinking Palmer a lesser figure than before.
                            <note id="n25"><hi rend="s">4</hi><hi rend="i"> The Times</hi>, 20 August 1976, p.
13.</note></p>
          <p>The books under review, especially the Huntington volume, should do something
                        towards correcting this. Indeed few of those who even glance over the
                        reduced reproductions in the Huntington book would possibly imagine that
                        Palmer could have been the same man who made the fakes. The essays in the
                        book provide further evidence of the way in which the authentic Palmer
                        thought and worked, how he translated his visual and literary experiences
                        into original works of his own, how his own complicated personality acted as
                        a catalyst on his reading of, for instance, the poems of Milton, or on his
                        visual experience of the drawings and paintings of Claude Lorrain,
                        transforming each experience into visions of the English countryside with,
                        later on, accents derived from his visits to Devon, Wales, and Italy.</p>
          <p>In the first essay, G. E. Bentley, Jr., places the Palmer circle, “The
                        Ancients” as they called themselves, in the Blake milieu, noting,
                        correctly, the prudery and religious conventionality of some of them.
                        Strangely, they seem to have had little comprehension of the mind of their
                        great mentor. It is practically certain that one of them, Frederick Tatham,
                        destroyed much of Blake’s work on religious grounds. Again, when
                        Eliza Finch wrote her memoir of her husband, Francis Oliver Finch, another
                        Ancient, she did not even mention Blake; the Finches were Swedenborgians and
                        Blake had thrown the beliefs of that sect aside, so obviously his views
                        rankled. And in a letter of 27 June 1862 to Anne Gilchrist, who was
                        preparing her late husband’s life of Blake for press, Palmer advised:
                        “Pray don’t send to the printers any <hi rend="i">extracts</hi> made from the book
itself [<hi rend="i">The Marriage of
                            Heaven and Hell</hi>] which has not been looked over and prepared for
                        the press as I saw this ev—g an indecent word in the text—at
                        least a coarse one.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26"
type="note">5</ref> To which he
                        added a footnote: “I would recommend the same caution as to all Blake
                        manuscripts not already prepared—on account of other matters which
                        ‘crop up’ now and then and which would be considered
                        BLASPHEMOUS and might ruin the sale of the work if shown up in any
                        illnatured review.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27"
type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Raymond Lister, ed., <hi rend="i">The
                                Letters of Samuel Palmer</hi> (Oxford, 1974), p. 657.</note>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> Letters</hi>, p. 661.</note></p>
          <p>As a matter of fact Palmer had little, if any, understanding of the bulk of
                        Blake’s poetry. The lyric poems he could no doubt appreciate, but
                        when it came to the mythological books he was all at sea. “His poems
                        were variously estimated,” he wrote. “They tested rather
                        severely the imaginative capacity of their readers. Flaxman said they were
                        as grand as his designs, and Wordsworth delighted in his <hi rend="i">Songs
                            of Innocence.</hi> To the multitude they were unintelligible. In many
                        parts full of pastoral sweetness, and often flashing with noble thoughts or
                        terrible imagery, we must regret that he should sometimes have suffered
                        fancy to trespass within sacred precincts.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n28" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">7</hi><hi rend="i"> Letters</hi>, p. 509.</note></p>
          <p>In truth these young followers of Blake followed him in a very limited way.
                        Edward Calvert was in a visual sense more influenced by him than any other
                        member of the circle; in his few engravings references to Blake may be
                        traced again and again.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29"
type="note">8</ref> There is a 
<pb id="p19-81" n="81"/>
little of Blake in Richmond’s early work,
                        and Palmer’s visionary mode had been developed before he ever met
                        Blake, although after they had met the younger man made considerable
                        borrowings. Even so, the influence of the old man was mainly through his
                        wood-engravings for Thornton’s <hi rend="i">Virgil</hi> and his 
<hi rend="i">Job</hi> engravings, and to a lesser extent through his designs
                        for <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and through a few of his
                        watercolors. Within a few years of his death the Ancients were each going
                        separate ways: George Richmond as a fashionable portrait painter, Calvert as
                        a painter of idealized classical scenes, and Palmer as a landscape painter
                        developing along more conventional, though far from uninteresting lines; F.
                        O. Finch had always painted Claudean landscapes and continued to do so. Here
                        and there there is a backward glance at Blake, as in Calvert’s
                        “A Young Shepherd on a Journey”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n30" type="note">9</ref> which is an almost exact copy of Blake’s illustration to
                        the line “With wand’ring feet unblest . . . ” in
                        Thornton’s <hi rend="i">Virgil.</hi> Nevertheless the impact of these
                        little engravings on the young men was, for a few years, enormous; and if
                        the period of their ascendancy was brief, it did enable them to produce, at
                        least for that time, work as compelling as anything they were to produce in
                        the future. <note id="n29"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Raymond Lister, <hi rend="i">Edward
Calvert</hi> (London, 1962), Chapter 5, <hi rend="i">passim.</hi></note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">9</hi> c. 1860. British Museum.</note></p>
          <p>Robert N. Essick’s essay on “John Linnell, William Blake, and
                        the Printer’s Craft” is, as one has come to expect from him,
                        an elegantly written and well argued study. The influence of Samuel
                        Palmer’s father-in-law, John Linnell, among the Ancients has not
                        often been seriously considered, and it is refreshing to see it given some
                        prominence here. But who has influenced whom it is sometimes difficult to
                        decide; some early Linnells, drawn or painted before the two men had met,
                        seem to be precursors of works by Palmer (for example “Primrose
                            Hill”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">10</ref>
and
                            “Twilight”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">11</ref>), whereas
                        his “The Weald of Kent,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33"
type="note">12</ref>
                        drawn years after Linnell’s first meeting with Palmer, might almost
                        be the work of the younger man. <note id="n31"><hi rend="s">10</hi> 1811.
                            Fitzwilliam Museum.</note>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">11</hi> c. 1819. Private collection,
                            England.</note>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">12</hi> 1833. Fitzwilliam Museum.</note></p>
          <p>Essick’s study is, as its title implies, concerned with printmaking
                        rather than with drawings, but much the same remarks apply: Linnell’s
                        etchings, “Sheep at Noon” and “Woodcutters
                        Repast” (both 1818) again look like precursors of later work by
                        Palmer, especially in the composition and shape of those watercolors he
                        called “Little Longs.”</p>
          <p>But the most compelling part of this section is Essick’s analysis of
                        the engraving techniques used by Blake and Linnell, in which he endeavors to
                        demonstrate Linnell’s influence on Blake, especially in their jointly
                        executed plates (for example in “Wilson Lowry,” begun in
                        1824). It is illuminating, too, to read his remarks, brief though they are,
                        on the relationship between Palmer’s only known wood-engraving,
                        “Harvest under a Crescent Moon,” and Blake’s Virgil
                        wood-engravings. It is, he writes, “very close in size, mood, and
                        technique to Blake’s Virgil cuts. Palmer once noted that Blake
                        particularly admired some of Claude Lorrain’s paintings because,
                        ‘when minutely examined, there were, upon the focal lights of the
                        foliage, small specks of pure white which made them appear to be glittering
                        with dew.’ The Virgil wood engravings, with their bold but skillfully
                        deployed flick work, exhibit a graphic equivalent to this technique. In
                        turn, Palmer’s single effort in wood achieves its moon-lit effects
                        through an almost identical, if slightly less energetic, use of the
                        graver.”</p>
          <p>Shelley M. Bennett, who compiled an attractive catalogue of the 1982
                        Huntington Library and Art Gallery exhibition, <hi rend="i">Prints by the
                            Blake Followers</hi>, contributes an essay entitled, “The Blake
                        Followers in the Context of Contemporary British Art.” In this Palmer
                        and his circle are considered against the background of the work of Turner,
                        Constable and other Romantics. Bennett, also with considerable originality,
                        compares them with certain aspects of the Pre-Raphaelites; one piquant
                        comparison concerns their similar surface textures: “The dense rich
                        surfaces of the meticulously worked plates, woodblocks and drawings of the
                        Blake followers produced a glowing, often jewel-like effect. The
                        Pre-Raphaelites obtained a similar luminosity in their oils by working on a
                        wet white ground which created a bright cloisonné-like clarity and
                        sparkle.”</p>
          <p>Bennett also makes interesting points concerning portraits by the Palmer
                        circle, claiming that they were indebted in some measure to Blake’s
                        Visionary Heads, and drawing attention to “their frontal, almost
                        iconic presentation.” She makes a similar point about
                        Linnell’s portrait of John Varley, painted against a star-studded sky
                        which, she writes, combined with “the fixed, hypnotic stare of the
                        eyes,” produces “an emotionally charged, almost visionary,
                        effect quite different from Lawrence’s slick grand-manner
                        exhibition-style portraits.” She might, more tellingly, have used
                        George Richmond’s later portraits as a comparison instead of those of
                        Lawrence.</p>
          <p>If I have a minor criticism of Bennett’s essay (and this also applies
                        in places to the other essays) it is of her continual reference to the
                        “Shoreham circle” and to the “Shoreham period.”
                        Shoreham, though highly important to the young men as a place of spiritual
                        recreation and inspiration, was their center for only a brief period; Palmer
                        alone was there for any length of time and the other members of the circle
                        were only intermittent visitors. Moreover, some of Palmer’s most
                        intensely visionary works—the great sepia watercolors of
                        1825—were completed before he moved there. There is nothing against
                        using “Shoreham” as a convenient label—and that is
                        doubtless what Bennett has done—but this ought to be kept in
                        perspective.</p>
          <p>The final chapter in <hi rend="i">Essays on the Blake Followers</hi> is by
                        Morton D. Paley and is entitled “‘To Realize After A Sort the
                        Imagery of Milton’: Samuel Palmer’s Designs for <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and
<hi rend="i">Il Penseroso.</hi>” It is
                        in many ways the 
<pb id="p19-82" n="82"/>
most interesting in the book, for
                        it deals with a group of watercolors, painted in Palmer’s later
                        years, which have attracted little critical attention during the present
                        century, though there is now strong evidence of a revival of interest.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">13</ref> Commissioned by Leonard Rowe Valpy,
                        John Ruskin’s solicitor, the series contains some of the most
                        powerful works created by Palmer during his middle and old age. 
<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Arnold Fawcus, Sir Geoffrey Keynes,
                            Raymond Lister and Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer: A Vision
                                Recaptured</hi> (London, 1978); Helen Irwin, “Samuel Palmer,
                            Poet of Light and Shade,” <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> (August 1981),
                            pp. 109-13.</note></p>
          <p>Milton’s influence on Palmer was strong; he loved especially <hi rend="i">L’Allegro</hi> and
<hi rend="i">Il Penseroso.</hi> He
                        also loved <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, which provided subjects for an earlier
                        series of watercolors, which though splendid in many ways, are less vital
                        than the Valpy watercolors. In the later Miltons Palmer drew on the
                        experiences of a lifetime, and it is possible to discover in them
                        recollections of his visionary years, of his visit to Italy, and of his work
                        in Devon, Surrey and Wales. His technique had matured impressively since his
                        early years, and he was now a complete master of the watercolor medium.
                        Incidentally, it is not surprising that Keating did not attempt to forge
                        works in Palmer’s later style with its formidable mastery of
                        technique. The mannerisms present in the works of the 1820s and early 1830s
                        made them misleadingly more inviting, though even here Keating did not come
                        within miles of making convincing forgeries.</p>
          <p>Paley discusses the Milton watercolors with great perception, relating them
                        to other contemporary interpretations of the same themes, and contrasting
                        their conception with that of similar works by William Blake, in the course
                        of which he demonstrates Palmer’s artistic independence, at least in
                        his maturity, of the older man.</p>
          <p>Yet it is a pity that he does not write more of the influence of earlier
                        artists on these works. Of these the influence of Claude Lorrain is the
                        strongest; indeed “A Towered City” seems to have been based
                        largely on an idealized view of Tivoli in Claude’s <hi rend="i">Liber
                            Veritatis</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35"
type="note">14</ref> which Palmer
                        probably knew through the mezzotints of Richard Earlom, published in 1777.
                        But Paley is absolutely right when he claims that among those of his
                        contemporaries who painted subjects from Milton, “only Palmer
                        captures the enticing atmosphere of poetic mystery we find in ‘The
                        Bellman’ and ‘The Lonely Tower.’ ” <note id="n35"><hi rend="s">14</hi>
Reproduced in Michael Kitson, <hi rend="i">Claude Lorrain: Liber Veritatis</hi> (London, 1978), plate
                            67.</note></p>
          <p>It is to be hoped that Paley’s impressive essay will help to initiate
                        a more widespread interest in these works which, even if they lack the
                        intense visionary qualities of the artist’s more youthful work,
                        remain sublime evocations of the mind of the poet whose work they
                        illustrate. They are also a survey in old age of the artist’s
                        lifetime of artistic endeavor, of wide reading and of deep thought; akin to
                        what W.B. Yeats called “An old man’s eagle mind.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">15</ref>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">15</hi> “An Acre of Grass” from
                                <hi rend="i">Last Poems</hi> (1936-39).</note></p>
          <p>Joseph Viscomi’s survey, <hi rend="i">Prints by Blake and His
                            Followers</hi>, is more specialized than <hi rend="i">Essays on the
                            Blake Followers</hi>, but within its self-imposed limits it is a
                        successful little work. It contains, in addition to the essay, a catalogue
                        of an exhibition held in March and April 1983 at the Herbert F. Johnson
                        Museum of Art at Cornell University. It is a shame that the unique
                        impression of Welby Sherman’s mezzotint “Illustration to
                        Byron’s <hi rend="i">Sennacherib</hi>,” now in the British
                        Museum, did not come to light soon enough to have been discussed by Viscomi,
                        for it is a remarkable little work, a tiny plate that seems to show the
                        influence of John Martin. It is to be included in the big exhibition 
<hi rend="i">Palmer and</hi> “<hi rend="i">The Ancients</hi>”
                        at the Fitzwilliam Museum during the coming autumn [1984].</p>
          <p>Incidentally, Viscomi is not quite right in claiming that George
                        Richmond’s “The Robber” and “The
                        Shepherd” were the only plates he executed, for later, in 1844, he
                        made a first class etching of Filippino Lippi’s portrait of Masaccio
                        in the Uffizi Gallery, Florence.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37"
type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Raymond Lister, <hi rend="i">George
                                Richmond</hi> (London, 1981), p. 176, pl. XXIX.</note></p>
          <p>Viscomi’s discussions of technique are always trenchant. To take an
                        example, his argument against Bo Lindberg’s views of how Blake
                        prepared the designs on his <hi rend="i">Job</hi> plates are convincing. I
                        do not know what studies Viscomi has made during his career, but it would
                        not surprise me if he were a practical engraver, as he seems to be familiar
                        with nuances of technique that usually become apparent only to a
                        practitioner.</p>
          <p>But the author is at his best in discussing the engravings of Calvert, that
                        wonderful world of <hi rend="i">multum in parvo</hi>, of callipygous
                        beauties, of Christian allegories in classical landscapes. Here again he
                        analyzes with intelligence the practical methods used by Calvert, explaining
                        how he arrived at his effects; this is particularly fascinating in the case
                        of his lithographs.</p>
          <p>Of Palmer, Viscomi’s remark that “compared to the vibrantly
                        free etched lines of James McNeil Whistler and Seymour Haden,
                        Palmer’s etchings are paintings executed with needles and
                        acid” is perceptive. Palmer’s approach to etching was always
                        that of a painter—how could it be otherwise?—so it is strange
                        that he was so cautious in his attitude to retroussage,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">17</ref> a device which gave to his etchings some of their
                        most painterly effects. <note id="n38"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Increasing the
                            strength of the lines by dropping a piece of muslin on to the plate to
                            drag up the ink in them before a print is taken.</note></p>
          <p>To sum up, these two books, small though they are, are serious studies which
                        should help to bring greater understanding to Blake’s followers, and
                        should also help to show those who were misled by the Keating forgeries how
                        to look at their works.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p19-83" n="83" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
