<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>19.2.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Keynes and Blake at Cambridge</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1985</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">19.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Karl Kroeber</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Josephine McQuail</name>
              <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>Margaret LaFrance</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1985"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <body>
      <pb id="p19-69" n="69"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-2-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Keynes and Blake at Cambridge</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>G.E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>When Sir Geoffrey Keynes died on 5 July 1982 at the age of ninety-five, he had the
            greatest Blake collection in private hands in Britain, and his Blake collection was only
            a small part of the entire library, though it seemed to be where his heart lay. His
            collections were the basis of his own bibliographies of, inter alia, John Donne (1914;
            1932; 1958; 1973), Sir Thomas Browne (1924; 1968), William Harvey (1928; 1953), Jane
            Austen (1929), William Hazlitt (1931; 1981), John Ray (1941; 1951), Rupert Brooke (1954;
            1959), Robert Hooke (1960), Siegfried Sassoon (1962), George Berkeley (1976), and Henry
            King (1977), and among these the contemporary copies of books by Blake were
            comparatively small in number. But when to these were added books with commercial
            engravings by Blake (such as five copies of <hi rend="i">Remember Me!</hi> [1825; 1826]
            in different original boards), proofs, prints, sketches, paintings, imitations,
            embroidery, facsimiles, and the scholarship of the subject (much of it his own), the
            size of his Blake collection became substantial, and its interest to students of Blake
            was unsurpassed of its kind—particularly when displayed by the collector.</p>
          <p>The mark of the collector was strongly impressed upon these cherished and beautiful
            books, from his bookplate, to his manuscript notes on provenance and condition, to his
            published descriptions of them, and it was exceedingly desirable that the collections
            should be kept together, both as an aid to scholars of the future—what 
              <hi rend="i">has</hi> become of Blake’s transcription of a poem by Sheridan which Sir Geoffrey
            alluded to so tantalizingly in 1964?—and as a memorial to the collector. Sir Geoffrey’s
            intentions altered from time to time, and there seemed to be a strong possibility that
            the collection would be separated subject by subject, which would have been a great
            pity.</p>
          <p>Fortunately that has not occurred, for the collection of books was sold to Cambridge
            University Library. There they have been arranged by subject in the exceedingly handsome
            Keynes Room, which is to be used as a meeting-place for the Syndics of the Library. Not
            only are the books in a beautiful room, but they are now for the first time gathered in
            one place, for in his London residence and at Lammas House, Brinkley, not far from
            Cambridge, the books were scattered in many rooms—and sometimes shelved five deep. They
            make a brave display in the Keynes Room, and my only regret when I saw it in November
            1984 was that, for reasons of security and convenience, mere scholars will not be able
            to work there, though they may of course use the books in the rare book reading
            room.</p>
          <p>There was a Keynes exhibition at the University Library in the summer of 1983, without
            a catalogue, but it is only fairly recently that the final payment has been made for the
            collection and the books have become officially the property of the University and
            accessible to readers.</p>
          <p>What Blakes are here? In general, everything associated with Blake printed from movable
            type or in manuscript is in the Keynes Room in the Cambridge University Library. The
            easiest means of identifying what is there at the moment is Sir Geoffrey’s own
            description of his collection, <hi rend="i">Bibliotheca Bibliographici</hi> (1964),
            supplemented by the card file he made (also in the collection) of about five hundred
            important works he acquired after 1964. In terms of Blake, the most exciting addition to
            the 1964 list is <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> copy P, which was previously
            described, at least by me, only at second hand. That description should read as
            follows:</p>
		<q><hi rend="i">BINDING:</hi> “BOUND BY RIVIERE &amp; SON” (according to a stamp on the
            front inner board) in Green morocco, gilt, top edge gilt, other edges untrimmed, with
            the Advertisement and pp. 57-70 in type-facsimile, the Advertisement of remarkably
            persuasive quality (titlepage size: 13.7 × 22.1 cm). The book has no MS correction and
            almost certainly passed at Blake’s death to Catherine Blake and thence to
              Tatham.<lb/>
<hi rend="i">HISTORY:</hi> (1) Acquired from Quaritch about 1900
            (according to Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> [1949]) by (2) General Archibald
            Stirling of Keir, who added on a flyleaf his initials and a note of 12 February 1921
            about the presence of the facsimile gatherings; from him, it passed to (3) Lt.-Col.
            William Stirling, who sold it; (4) Sold anonymously at Sotheby’s, 25 April 1978, lot 50,
            to (5) Sir Geoffrey Keynes, who sold it in 1982 to (6) Cambridge University Library. </q>
          <p>But there are treasures for the scholar which will not be found in either 
              <hi rend="i">Bibliotheca Bibliographici</hi> or in Sir Geoffrey’s card-addenda to it.
Naturally he
            did not trouble to list copies of ordinary books which any modern scholar might be
            expected to own, such as Butlin’s <hi rend="i">Paintings and Drawings of William
              Blake</hi> (1981) or Paley’s presentation copy of his Phaidon <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
            (1978). Some of the most interesting features of the collection are the annotations
            which Sir Geoffrey made in his books, particularly in copies of his own publications.
            These occasionally contain information of significant value, so minor that Sir Geoffrey
            thought them scarcely worth printing but which are yet of real interest to those with
            somewhat lower standards of novelty. For instance, in the interleaved proof copy of his
              <hi rend="i">Bibliography of William Blake</hi> (1921) he annotated the 1868 Camden
            Hotten facsimile of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell:</hi> “Edward Gordon
            Duff told John Sampson that Lord Houghton 
<pb id="p19-70" n="70"/>
lent his copy of the
            original [<hi rend="i">Copy F</hi>] to Swinburne, and that Camden Hotten made his
            facsimile without permission, whereat Lord Houghton was much incensed.” This provides a
            persuasive context for the otherwise puzzling relationship between Lord Houghton and
            Camden Hotten; it was not previously known that “Camden Hotten made his facsimile
            without permission.”</p>
          <p>Similarly, in his copy of the Keynes &amp; Wolf <hi rend="i">Census</hi> (1953), Keynes
            inserted a facsimile of a letter from the U.S. artist Francis Lathrop of 9 January 1908
            to Mr. [Beverley] Chew (the original is in the Grolier Club Library) offering “the
            ‘Stothard copy’ of the Book of Thel [<hi rend="i">Copy E</hi>]—the original Blake, that
            I spoke about” for $350. Lathrop had not previously been known to have any original
            Blake—and Chew is not known to have owned a copy of <hi rend="i">Thel.</hi></p>
          <p>In the interleaved copy of his <hi rend="i">Bibliography of William Blake</hi> at p.
            371 he drew attention to a reference to Blake which has not heretofore been reprinted:
			<q> Anon., “Art. VIII. <hi rend="i">The Chimney-Sweepers’ Friend, and Climbing-Boys’
                Album</hi> . . . Arranged by James Montgomery . . . Price 9s. London, 1824.” 
                <hi rend="i">Eclectic Review</hi>, N.S., XXI (June 1824), 558-562.<lb/>
 The review
              includes on pp. 559-560 a puzzled reference to “The Chimney Sweeper” with a quotation
              of the poem from Montgomery’s book:<lb/>
 We know not how to characterize the song
              given from Blake’s ‘Songs of Innocence.’ It is wild and strange, like the singing of
              ‘a maid in Bedlam in the spring,’ but it is the madness of genius. </q>
Montgomery’s
            book has long been known, but this printing of Blake’s poem, showing the “madness of
            genius,” has not. Most accounts of Blake omitted the phrase “of genius.”</p>
          <p>Finally in his 1921 <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi>, at p. 417, Sir Geoffrey referred to
            a work by Joseph Hallett Junior which apparently belonged to Blake but which has not
            heretofore been associated with him in print. It is in three volumes, each with a
            different titlepage: 
			<q> A | Free <hi rend="i">and</hi> Impartial Study <hi rend="i">of
                the</hi> | HOLY SCRIPTURES <hi rend="i">recommended:</hi> | BEING | NOTES | ON SOME
              | PECULIAR TEXTS; | WITH | Discourses and Observations | ON | The following Subjects;
                <hi rend="i">viz.</hi> | I. Of the Quotations from the <hi rend="i">Old
                Testament</hi> in the Apocrypha. | II. Of the <hi rend="i">Septuagint</hi> Version
              of the <hi rend="i">Bible;</hi> and the Diffe-|rence between the 
                <hi rend="i">Citations</hi>, as they lie in the <hi rend="i">New Testa-|ment</hi>, and the 
                <hi rend="i">Original Passages</hi> in the <hi rend="i">Old.</hi> | III. 
                <hi rend="i">Christians</hi> not bound by any Authority of the <hi rend="i">Law</hi> of | 
                <hi rend="i">Moses</hi> in the <hi rend="i">Ten Commandments.</hi> | IV. Of the Doxology
              at the End of the Lord’s-Prayer. Of | blessing the <hi rend="i">Eucharistical
                Elements</hi>, and of Grace before | and after Meat, | V. The Son of God knows the
              Hearts of Men; and, of Anger, | Catechising, <hi rend="i">&amp;c.</hi> | VI. A Passage
              in Bishop <hi rend="i">Pearson</hi> on the Creed, and another | in Bishop 
                <hi rend="i">Patrick’s</hi> Commentaries examin’d. | VII. Of the Soul; its Immortality,
              Immateriality, <hi rend="i">&amp;c.</hi> with | the Impossibility of proving a Future
              State by the Light | of Nature; and of the Place where Good Men shall dwell | after
              the Resurrection. | - | By <hi rend="i">JOSEPH HALLETT</hi>, Jun<hi rend="s">r</hi>. |
              - | <hi rend="i">LONDON;</hi> | Printed for J. Noon, at the 
                <hi rend="i">White-Hart</hi> in <hi rend="i">Cheapside</hi>, near | 
                <hi rend="i">Mercers-Chapel.</hi> M. DCC. XXIX [1729].<lb/>
<lb/>
 A | SECOND VOLUME | OF | NOTES
              | AND | DISCOURSES: | CONTAINING | I. A New List of Errors noted in the present 
                <hi rend="i">Hebrew</hi> Copies | of the <hi rend="i">Old Testament.</hi> | II. Notes on
              several Texts of Scripture. | III. Discourses on the Reality, Kinds, and Number of our
              | Saviour’s Miracles; occasion’d by Mr. <hi rend="i">Woolston’s</hi> Six | Discourses.
              | The Meaning of the Word, <hi rend="i">God;</hi> and the Doctrine of Providence. |
              The Nature of <hi rend="i">Sacrifices;</hi> particularly of the Sacrifice of | 
                <hi rend="i">Christ.</hi> | The Original of <hi rend="i">Evil.</hi> | The Nature of 
                <hi rend="i">Ordination.</hi> | A <hi rend="i">Review</hi> of the former 
                <hi rend="i">Volume</hi>, particularly relating to the | Passage in Bishop 
                <hi rend="i">Pearson</hi> on the <hi rend="i">Creed.</hi> concerning the | Meaning of the
Word,
                <hi rend="i">Almighty</hi>, in the Sixth Article; | and to the Nature of 
                <hi rend="i">Anger.</hi> | - | <hi rend="i">By</hi> JOSEPH HALLETT 
                <hi rend="i">jun.</hi> | - | <hi rend="i">LONDON:</hi> | Printed for J. Noon, at the 
                <hi rend="i">White Hart</hi> in <hi rend="i">Cheapside</hi>, near 
                <hi rend="i">Mercers-chapel.</hi> M.DCC.XXXII [1732].<lb/>
<lb/>
<figure n="ThirdVolume.19.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="165"/></q>
Sir Geoffrey’s note says
            that in each octavo volume of an untraced set of three volumes in old calf is Blake’s
            autograph, dated 1799, with the price he paid for it (£1.5.0) in the first volume. Sir
            Geoffrey probably found the reference to Blake’s copy of Hallett’s book in the Anderson
            Gallery sale catalogue of The Library of the Late H. Buxton Forman, Part Two (26 April
            1920), lot 46, where the price, however, is given as a guinea, not as £1.5.0.</p>
          <p>Doubtless other “discoveries” concerning Blake and many other authors remain to be
            found in the very rich collection of books which passed from Sir Geoffrey Keynes to the
            Cambridge University Library. But for efficient access to them we must wait for the
            collection to be catalogued. Many besides myself will hope for the appearance at least
            of a handlist concerning William Blake as soon as possible.</p>
          <p>Over the years Sir Geoffrey clearly changed his mind about the destination of his
            Blakes; a few he gave away and sold, as is recorded in Robert N. Essick’s great
            catalogue raisonné of <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Separate Plates</hi> (1981). The
            final decision was that the Blakes which were printed from movable type and in
            manuscript should go with the rest of his books to the University Library. Most of the
            Keynes collection of “paintings, drawings, and prints by William Blake” were handed over
            to the Fitzwilliam Museum as this article went to press (according to Donald
            Wintersgill, “Museum Is Given Blakes,” <hi rend="i">Guardian</hi>, 16 May 1985, p.
            5).</p>
          <p>One may lament their separation from Blake’s purely literary works but recognize that
            this is a twentieth century commonplace. It is paralleled by the division of the
            splendid Rosenwald Collection a few years ago between the Library of Congress and the
            U.S. National 
<pb id="p19-71" n="71"/>
Gallery, and it will be paralleled by the
            separation of the illuminated and other graphic works in the British Museum Print Room
            from the typographical and manuscript works in the British Library when the latter
            eventually finds its new quarters. It is a touching irony that Blake labored all his
            life to unite the arts of the eye and the ear, the vision and the word, but that this
            union is posthumously divorced in the disposition of the great collections of his
            works.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
