<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>19.2.bindman</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Samuel Palmer’s An Address to the Electors of West Kent, 1832
Rediscovered</title>
        <author n="Bindman">David Bindman</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1985</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">19.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>David Bindman</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Karl Kroeber</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Josephine McQuail</name>
              <name>Karen Mulhallen</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>Margaret LaFrance</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1985"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <body>
    <pb id="p19-56" n="56"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-2-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">Samuel Palmer’s <hi rend="i">An Address to the Electors
                                of West Kent, 1832</hi> Rediscovered</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">DAVID</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">BINDMAN</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>In 1975 I gave a lecture at London University on Samuel Palmer in which I
                    attempted to relate some major themes in his work to the political upheavals of
                    his time. The idea was to demonstrate that the study of politics could be as
                    relevant to the discussion of visionary artists as it was to those like Madox
                    Brown and Courbet who made direct reference to political issues in their
                    paintings. Palmer seemed a good example because his letters of the later 1820s
                    reveal him as bitterly hostile to radicalism and dissent in all its forms.
                    Furthermore Palmer was known to have been moved in the face of the Reform Act of
                    1832 to produce an anonymous political pamphlet, <hi rend="i">An Address to the
                        Electors of West Kent</hi>, by “an Elector.” No copy appeared
                    to have survived, but its existence was known from a reference to it in a letter
                    by John Linnell, and Geoffrey Grigson had found some extracts held up for
                    derision in a reform newspaper, the <hi rend="i">Maidstone Gazette</hi> for 11
                    December 1832.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> In
preparing my lecture I
                    made strenuous efforts to find the pamphlet but without success, and I had to
                    rely for my picture of Palmer’s political views on the extracts and
                    various passages from his letters. Some time later I mentioned the missing
                    pamphlet to Michael Collinge of the Institute of Historical Research of London
                    University. As it happens he was going shortly afterwards to the Maidstone
                    Public Record office which I had searched in vain, and a few days later he sent
                    me a photocopy of the whole pamphlet. It is here reprinted in full for the first
                    time since 1832, and it is Palmer’s longest and most considered piece of
                    prose to have survived, dating from a critical period in his career. 
<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> G. Grigson, <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer: The
                            Visionary Years</hi> (1947), pp. 104-107.</note></p>
        <p>In this introduction I want to discuss briefly the political background to the
                    pamphlet and suggest some possible connections with his art. To a degree I will
                    be following in the footsteps of Geoffrey Grigson who in an article in 
<hi rend="i">Horizon</hi> of 1944<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> and his
                    book on Palmer of 1947 argues that Palmer’s political reactions in the
                    period around the Reform Act were symptomatic of his retreat from the visionary
                    basis of his work which led to his eventual departure from Shoreham. The
                    pamphlet as we already know from the published fragments is strongly
                    anti-radical and defensive of the Established Church which he believed to be the
                    true Apostolic Church through its descent from the pre-Reformation Catholic
                    Church, as he makes clear in a letter to George Richmond of 24 June 1828:
                    “I hope, Sir, that the Lord will confirm you &amp; comfort you in true
                    and sweet affiliation to the Apostolic Church which has only Bishops and pastors
                    (tho’ many drones &amp; wolves) in which only are the efficacies of the
                    holy sacraments, the authority and absolution &amp; blessing, the delegated
                    power of Jesus Christ, the eternal shield against the gates of Hell, The chief
                    corner stone . . . the rock St Peter, the indissoluble foundation of the
                    apostles &amp; prophets, stronger than the pillars of the world &amp; the
                    fabric of the universe &amp; the gift of the Holy Ghost.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> In this devotion to the Church of England
                    Palmer was perfectly consistent throughout his life and he accepted the paternal
                    view of society it implied, but in 1828 it did not alienate him from his friends
                    in the Shoreham circle many of whom were, like John Linnell, themselves
                    dissenters: “Politics we dabble in: Mr. L[innell] though of no party
                    magnifies the peasants; I, also, as you know, of no party, as I love our fine
                    British peasantry, think best of the old high tories, because I find they gave
                    most liberty to the poor, and were not morose, sullen and blood-thirsty like the
                    whigs, liberty jacks and dissenters; whose cruelty when they reign’d, was
                    as bad as that of the worst times of the worst papists; only more sly and
                    smoothlier varnish’d over with a thin shew of reason.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> “Samuel Palmer: The Politics of an
                        Artist,” <hi rend="i">Horizon</hi>, 4 (1944), 314-28.</note>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> The Letters of Samuel Palmer</hi>,
                        ed. R. Lister (1974), I, no. 1828 (4), p. 24.</note>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Palmer, <hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, I, no. 1828
                        (9), p. 31.</note></p>
        <p>The year 1828 saw the final repeal of the Test and Corporation Acts which removed
                    the statutory bar upon non-Anglicans from holding public and municipal offices.
                    The issue neatly polarized political and religious attitudes, with Radicals and
                    Dissenters on one side, and the “old high tories” and the Church
                    of England, who rightly feared that the Act would spell the end of what Norman
                    Gash calls the “oligarchic Anglican constitution of the eighteenth
                        century,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> on
the other. For the
                    Church of England the 1820s were years of ever-increasing threat, and Palmer,
                    like Constable who spent much time in the close of Salisbury Cathedral, saw the
                    Church, the repository of all true values, progressively isolated by the spread
                    of dissent, especially in the towns where Anglicans 
<pb id="p19-57" n="57"/>
                    were often in a minority. In the countryside the complaints of Radicals gathered
                    around the issue of tithes, the traditional method of paying the clergy whereby
                    a farmer was obliged to give one tenth of his produce either in cash or kind to
                    the local parish. The problems this system created were endless, for assessment
                    could always be at issue; in hard times there was always the cry that the clergy
                    should abate their demands. While some clergy were genuinely poor themselves
                    there were church pluralists who lived very comfortably without ever seeing
                    their parishioners. Furthermore Dissenters normally regarded the Church as an
                    “unscriptural institution” and denied the Church its title to the
                    tithe in the first place. Most threatening from the point of view of the Church
                    was the fact that the issue of tithes could unite farmers and farm laborers in
                    common cause against them.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> N. Gash, <hi rend="i">The Age of Peel</hi>
                        (1968), p. 2.</note>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> E.J. Evans, “Some Reasons for the Growth
                        of English Rural Anti-Clericalism,” <hi rend="i">Past and
                            Present</hi>, Feb. 1975.</note></p>
        <p>On what grounds could the Church mount a defense of the system of tithes which
                    made the clergy such an obvious target for Reform? An unsigned article in the
                        <hi rend="i">Quarterly Review</hi> of 1830<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n7" type="note">7</ref> claimed among other things that the Church in consequence of its
                    independence from the state provided a means of betterment for poor men without
                    social advantages. These men having acquired a good education would then return
                    to rural areas the advantage of a learned clergy; here the author quotes Burke:
                    “In retired parishes, the family of the clergyman is often a little
                    centre of civilization, from which gleams of refinement of manners, of neatness,
                    of taste, as well as of science and general literature, are diffused through
                    districts into which they would otherwise never penetrate.” In the last
                    resort, however, the anonymous author rests the defense of tithes on more
                    ineffable ideas, in this case those of the mature Wordsworth of the 
<hi rend="i">Excursion</hi>, first published in 1814, in particular the words of the
                    country pastor in Book VI: 
					<q> Hail to the state of England and conjoin<lb/>
                        With this a salutation as devout<lb/>
 Made to the spiritual fabric of her
                        church,<lb/>
 Founded in truth; by blood of martyrdom<lb/>
 Cemented; by the
                        hands of wisdom reared<lb/>
 In beauty of holiness, with ordered pomp,<lb/>
                        Decent and unreproved. . . .<lb/>
 And O, ye swelling hills and spacious
                        plains,<lb/>
 Besprent from shore to shore with steeple towers<lb/>
 And
                        spires, whose silent finger points to heaven<lb/>
 Nor wanting at wide
                        intervals, the bulk<lb/>
 Of ancient minster, lifted above the cloud<lb/>
 Of
                        the dense air which town or city breeds,<lb/>
 To intercept the sun’s
                        glad beams—may ne’er<lb/>
 That true succession fail of English
                        hearts,<lb/>
 Who with ancestral feeling can perceive<lb/>
 What in those holy
                        structures ye possess<lb/>
 Of ornamental interest, and the charm<lb/>
 Of
                        pious sentiment diffused afar,<lb/>
 And human charity and Social love.<lb/>
                        Thus never shall the indignities of time<lb/>
 Approach their reverend graces
                        unopposed;<lb/>
 Nor shall the elements be free to hurt<lb/>
 Their fair
                        proportions; nor the blinder rage<lb/>
 Of bigot zeal, madly to
                        overturn:<lb/>
 And if the desolating hand of war<lb/>
 Spare them, they shall
                        continue to bestow<lb/>
 Upon the thronged abodes of busy men<lb/>
 (Depraved,
                        and ever prone to fill their minds<lb/>
 Exclusively with transitory
                        things,)<lb/>
 An air and mien of dignified pursuit,<lb/>
 Of sweet civility,
                        on rustic wilds.<lb/>
</q>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi><hi rend="i"> Quarterly Review</hi> (1830), pp.
                        105-47.</note></p>
        <p>I have quoted that passage at length because it seems to be in sympathetic accord
                    with the painting by Palmer in the Tate Gallery entitled by him <hi rend="i">Coming from
Evening Church, Shoreham</hi>, dated 1830. It shows a group of
                    people leaving a village church set in a valley beneath the moon. The bold form
                    of the church is balanced by the warm and homely cottage on the right, and the
                    villagers represent all ages and generations from small children to old men; in
                    the middle distance can be seen the parson in the midst of his flock. The church
                    spire whose “silent finger points to heaven” (in fact Shoreham
                    Church did not have a spire, though most others in that part of Kent do)
                    dominates the village but seems to grow out of the hillside, which with the
                    overhanging trees appears to protect the village. The painting is a
                    representation of the village as part of the natural order of things, under the
                    benign auspices of the Old English Church, which guarantees the indivisible
                    harmony of nature, nation and religion.</p>
        <p>The painting, therefore, offers a positive if highly idealized vision of rural
                    life, and one that can be paralleled in Palmer’s letters of 1828, like
                    the one already cited. It is all the more striking that the <hi rend="i">Address</hi>
should be so bleak in tone even though it cannot have been
                    written much more than two years after the painting. It expresses primarily
                    Palmer’s rage at the very idea of electoral reform, the supporters of
                    which are seen as nothing less than beasts and despoilers who wish only for the
                    destruction of the Church. The note of hysterical intolerance can be matched
                    with that in a letter to George Richmond of 21 September 1832 in which he
                    repents of the indulgence he had shown to friends even until quite recently: 
					<q>
                        If people knew how deeply the whole world lieth in wickedness, and how
                        totally it is estranged &amp; set in opposition against God; they would I
                        cannot help thinking, no longer wonder why all kinds of sects &amp; schisms
                        may not equally be term’d the Churches of Christ. . . . Once I was
                        full of this lightness and folly—yea even to the present time my old
                        Adam can see no reason why the sleek &amp; sober Quaker or the meek &amp;
                        moral Unitarian should be beholden to the Church, claiming the power of the
                        keys of the kingdom of Heaven—But blessed be God. I am changed ever
                        since you saw me—I am a free thinker in art in literature in music in
                        poetry—but as I read of but one way to Heaven &amp; that a narrow
                        one it is not for me to chuse which way, I will be saved &amp; make it a
                        pretty speculation or matter of taste, &amp; run to seek my Saviour in
                        holes &amp; corners, but go at once where He is ever to be found, at the
                        Apostolick altar of the Melchisedekian priesthood.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Palmer, <hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, I, no.
                            1832 (1), pp. 58-59.</note></q></p>
        <pb id="p19-58" n="58"/>
        <figure n="Palmer.ComingfromEveningChurch.19.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="775">
          <head>Samuel Palmer.</head>
          <figDesc><hi rend="i">Coming from Evening Church, Shoreham</hi> (1830). Courtesy
                        of Tate Gallery Publications Department.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p19-59" n="59"/>
        <p>Evidently something traumatic had happened to Palmer in the years before 1832,
                    and Grigson astutely pointed out that the early 1830s were the time of the
                    “Captain Swing” riots when unemployed and hungry farm laborers
                    terrorized farmers, particularly in Kent, by setting fire to ricks. In fact
                    Shoreham was right in the heart of the discontents and Palmer by moving there in
                    the late 1820s with the dream of finding “a primitive village where none
                    of the King-choppers had set up business”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n9" type="note">9</ref> found himself in a position similar to someone who had recently
                    sought refuge from civilization in the Falkland Islands. By the end of the 1820s
                    more than a third of the population of the Kentish Weald was unemployed
                    following the agricultural recession after Waterloo. According to Hobsbawm and
                    Rudé, in the counties of Southern England by 1828 “Pauperism,
                    degradation, desperation, and sullen discontent were almost
                        universal.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
type="note">10</ref> In 1829 a
                    disastrous harvest was followed by a cruel winter, and misery increased even
                    further especially in Kent. In 1830 the farm laborers turned to open revolt in
                    the form of rick burning and the destruction of threshing machines, sometimes
                    accompanied by sinister letters in the name “Captain Swing,” which
                    became part of life in the area around Shoreham. In retrospect the causes of the
                    revolt can be seen to have lain in local desperation and it was not part of a
                    general uprising. But 1830 was the year of a revolution in France and renewed
                    agitation for Reform in the towns, so one can well see how someone of
                    Palmer’s temperament might persuade himself that the pathetic actions of
                    the rick burners were fomented by Jacobins rushing over from France to join with
                    their English counterparts in the destruction of the property-owning classes.
                    The first recorded outbreak came in Orpington on 1 June 1830 and by the end of
                    20 September fires were reported within the area of a few miles about Shoreham,
                    including one on land belonging to Mr. Love of Filston Hall Farm in Shoreham
                    whom Palmer had described as “one of the best farmers
                        hereabout.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">11</ref> The revolt was
                    suppressed by the end of the year, but one may presume that the fires consumed
                    not only Palmer’s hopes of a rural retreat but also his faith in the
                    “fine old English peasantry.” <note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Palmer, 
<hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, I, no. 1828 (11), p. 51.</note>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> E. Hobsbawm and G. Rudé, <hi rend="i">Captain Swing</hi> (1969), p.
81.</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Palmer, <hi rend="i">Letters</hi>, I, no.
                        1827 (3), p. 14.</note></p>
        <p><hi rend="i">An Address to the Electors of West Kent</hi> was published in
                    support of the Tory candidate Sir William Geary in December 1832 in the general
                    election which followed the passing of the Reform Act, which would have further
                    confirmed Palmer’s despairing vision of the future. The political imagery
                    of the pamphlet is essentially of the kind popularized by Canning and the 
<hi rend="i">Anti-Jacobin</hi> and also the caricatures of Gillray, in which the
                    movement for Reform even in its most moderate and respectable form was equated
                    unequivocally with the worst excesses of the French Revolution; to support
                    Reform was to open the floodgates to mob rule and the imposition of French
                    atheism and equality, for in Palmer’s words it was “the
                    importation of yesterday, from poor, degraded, dishonoured, Atheistical
                    France.” It is easy to see on reading the pamphlet why a radical
                    newspaper should complain of its “gross invectives and foul
                    vituperation,” and why it should have offended John Linnell who also
                    complained of its impertinent imitation of Milton. Nonetheless it is full of
                    stirring imagery, even a certain visionary quality which is not incompatible
                    with the rapturous imagination of the Shoreham paintings. This pamphlet deserves
                    to be regarded not as an aberration nor simply the product of disillusionment,
                    but as the other side of the coin of the political and religious vision which is
                    implicit in Palmer’s Shoreham paintings. In the last resort
                    Palmer’s art is as essentially High Tory in spirit as Blake’s is
                    indelibly Radical and apocalyptic.</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
