<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>19.3.staley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Nancy L. Pressly, Revealed Religion: Benjamin West’s Commissions for Windsor
Castle and Fonthill Abbey</title>
        <author n="Staley">Allen Staley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1985/1986</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985-86</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">19.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Dan Bell</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Max Byrd</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Stuart Peterfreund</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Allen Staley</name>
              <name>David Wagenknecht</name>
              <name>Nicholas Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1985/1986"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <body>
	<pb id="p19-120" n="120"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-3-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Nancy L. Pressly. <hi rend="i">Revealed Religion: Benjamin West’s Commissions
for Windsor Castle and Fonthill Abbey.</hi> San Antonio: San Antonio Museum of Art, 1983.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Allen</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Staley</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>From September to November 1983 the San Antonio Museum of Art presented a small but distinguished
exhibition of sketches by Benjamin West for three ambitious cycles of paintings and stained glass windows
depicting biblical subjects. The organizer of the exhibition and author of its extremely informative catalogue
was Nancy Pressly, the museum’s chief curator, who previously had organized the exhibition of 
<hi rend="i">The Fuseli Circle in Rome</hi> at the Yale Center for British Art in 1979.</p>
          <p>The three series for which the exhibited sketches were preparatory studies were intended for the
Royal Chapel in Windsor Castle, St. George’s Chapel also at Windsor Castle, and Fonthill Abbey in Wiltshire.
The two Windsor undertakings occupied West on and off for over two decades. The Fonthill commissions came only
in 1796, when William Beckford started to build the Abbey, and West’s work for Beckford all seems to have
been done by 1801. West did complete eighteen very large pictures for the Royal Chapel, all of which he
exhibited at the Royal Academy between 1781 and 1801, but they were never installed in the Castle. For St.
George’s Chapel he painted an altarpiece and made designs for five windows, of which four were installed.
These were on a vast scale (the triptychal east window depicting the <hi rend="i">Resurrection</hi> measured
some thirty-six feet high by twenty-eight across) and, as they were in the fully late-Baroque style that West
used consistently for the biblical subjects he painted in the 1780s and 1790s, they conflicted dramatically
with the Perpendicular Gothic style of their architectural setting. They were removed and destroyed in
mid-nineteenth-century restorations of the Chapel. For Fonthill Abbey, West’s chief religious subjects were
intended for a Revelation Chamber planned
<pb id="p19-121" n="121"/>
to house his patron’s tomb. The Chamber was never built, and the compositions intended for it never
proceeded beyond painted sketches, but four of those sketches were exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1798.
Three of the four, plus a drawing of <hi rend="i">The Angel in the Sun</hi> and two paintings of 
<hi rend="i">St. Michael</hi> and <hi rend="i">St. Thomas à Becket</hi> undertaken for windows in the Abbey, were
shown at San Antonio, providing the visual climax of the exhibition, as well as a focused look at a hitherto
all but unknown aspect of West’s multi-faceted <hi rend="i">oeuvre.</hi></p>
          <p>Pressly’s catalogue comprises not only lucid historical accounts of the three projects, but
also important analyses of their positions in the art of the period. She is particularly interesting in her
discussion of the Apocalyptic subjects for Beckford, which she relates to the millenarian ideas current in
England following the French Revolution, specifically to the exhortations of Richard Brothers, the
self-proclaimed prophet of a revolutionary millenium.</p>
		<q>
When one looks at a painting like <hi rend="i">The Beast Rising from the Sea</hi> [collection of Thomas and
Margaret McCormick; no. 40], it is difficult, in the light of the millenarian spirit of the times, not to see
some radical political commentary underlying its religious imagery. The prominent lion head of the beast could
easily be interpreted as an only slightly veiled reference to England whose emblem was the lion, particularly
when one remembers that Brothers explicitly identifies the Beast with the British Monarchy. (p. 64)
</q>
          <p>When one looks at West’s <hi rend="i">Beast Rising from the Sea</hi>, it is also difficult not
to see some foretaste of the multi-headed monsters in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Great Red Dragon and the
Beast from the Sea</hi> (National Gallery of Art, Washington; Butlin no. 521), particularly when we read in
Joseph Farington’s diary that Blake’s friend Ozias Humphry called West’s sketch the “finest conception
ever come from mind of man.” Due to the rarity of illustrations of Revelation in post-Medieval art, West’s
paintings exhibited in the 1790s must have provided useful guide posts for Blake when he turned to Apocalyptic
subjects in the next decade, and every one of West’s subjects did find an echo in a drawing done by the
younger artist a few years later. On the other hand, we should note that on 19 February 1796, well before West
had begun to work for Beckford, Farington recorded a conversation in which West, Humphry, and Richard Cosway
“spoke warmly in favour of the designs of Blake the Engraver, as works of extraordinary genius and
imagination.” At that date, West may well have been at work on the version of his <hi rend="i">Death on the
Pale Horse</hi>, composed for the Royal Chapel at Windsor, which he exhibited the following May (Detroit
Institute of Arts). By 1796 he probably had seen some of Blake’s large color prints of 1795, and Blake is
said to have given him a copy of <hi rend="i">America, A Prophecy</hi> of 1793. Although West first composed
<hi rend="i">Death on the Pale Horse</hi> between 1779 and 1783 and exhibited a version of it in 1784 (Royal
Academy of Arts, London), it is possible that his awareness of Blake prompted him in 1796 to return to what
had been an isolated venture into a visionary mode, and, at the least, we must acknowledge that he was not
unaware of Blake when he began to paint his Apocalyptic sketches for Beckford in the following year. Despite
vast differences in temperament and in their positions in English artistic life, there was some common ground
between the two artists at a time when it could have been of use to them.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
