<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>19.3.mellor</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Richard Wendorf, ed., Articulate Images—The Sister Arts from Hogarth to
Tennyson</title>
        <author n="Mellor">Anne K. Mellor</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1985/1986</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985-86</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">19.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Dan Bell</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Max Byrd</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Stuart Peterfreund</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Allen Staley</name>
              <name>David Wagenknecht</name>
              <name>Nicholas Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1985/1986"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-3-0007">
        <pb id="p19-112" n="112"/>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Richard Wendorf, ed. <hi rend="i">Articulate Images—The Sister Arts from
Hogarth to Tennyson.</hi> Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1983. 272 pp., illus.; includes
bibliography of works of Jean H. Hagstrum and a checklist of modern scholarship on the Sister Arts.
$29.50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Anne K.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Mellor</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The nine essays in this <hi rend="i">festschrift</hi> for Jean H. Hagstrum both document the
enormous impact Hagstrum has had on the study of the sister arts tradition and also achieve to a remarkably
consistent degree that learned elegance we have come to expect of Hagstrum’s own work. The ideal
introduction both to this volume and to the significance of Hagstrum’s work is provided by Lawrence Lipking
in his essay “Quick Poetic Eyes: Another Look at Literary Pictorialism,” in which he restates Hagstrum’s
thesis on eighteenth-century pictorialism in a simpler and more controversial way. He suggests that we must
train ourselves to visualize all the elements described in an eighteenth-century poem, that we must be able to
<hi rend="i">see</hi> them, because the very definition of poetic genius in that century was the capacity to
create mental pictures. Eighteenth-century poetry calculatedly explored the various dimensions of this
pictorialist project: the depiction of darkness as well as light, the difficulty of seeing, the search for an
adequate point of view, and finally the pain of eyestrain or <hi rend="i">fear</hi> of seeing. Lipking
provides illuminating discussions of poems by Pope, Smart, Collins and Gray to illustrate both his summary of
the modes of eighteenth-century pictorialism and his argument that it broke down as people gradually came to
think primarily in terms of words or photographic images rather than created mental pictures.</p>
          <p>Robert Wark, writing from the perspective of the art historian and connoisseur, very sensibly
reminds us of the difficulties faced by any student of literature who attempts to use pictorial evidence: that
the assignment of any given art work to a particular artist is often problematic (as we have seen most
recently in <hi rend="i">The Discovery of Constable</hi>, the magisterial study by Ian Fleming-Williams and
Leslie Parris of Constable forgeries and misattributions); that the artist’s choice of media plays a large
role in determining the effects that can be created; and most important, that the interpretation of the
meaning of visual images depends to a far greater degree than in literature on a traditional iconology and on
inherited pictorial conventions.</p>
          <p>As background to the essays which deal with specific comparisons between the sister arts, Larry
Silver contributes a helpful survey of the development of the <hi rend="i">paragone</hi>, the debate between
the relative merits of poetry and painting, from Alberti through the eighteenth century, with particular
emphasis on how painting justified its claim to equality by its focus on moral exempla, its appeal to the
higher sense of sight, and its greater capacity for <hi rend="i">inventio</hi> as demonstrated by ekphrastic
works. Earl Miner shows us how limiting our western, classical assumptions concerning the relationship between
art and nature can be by examining a Japanese text, Kyoden/Masanobu’s illuminated <hi rend="i">Edo
Mumare</hi>, which defies western conceptions of the artist as a single “self” and of the art-work as
mimetic. Instead, Miner’s fascinating discussion emphasizes, Japanese aesthetics are “relational,” with
meaning generated entirely out of the play of one signifier with another in a field where there is constant
“leakage” between written word and visual image. Richard Wendorf’s competent examination of biography
and portrait painting as sister arts rightly stresses the difference that the medium makes: biography can
encompass the passage of time while portraiture can capture only a single, albeit more self-conscious, moment
in the sitter’s life. And Karl Kroeber fittingly closes the volume with a detailed examination of four
texts, Millais’ “The
<pb id="p19-113" n="113"/>
Blind Girl,” Constable’s “Salisbury Cathedral, From the Meadows,” Wordsworth’s “Michael” and
Tennyson’s “Enoch Arden,” that persuasively develops into the provocative suggestion that Victorian art
asks us to stand back and see clearly one meaning, while Romantic art engages us in that very flux of
experienced sensation that denies clarity of meaning. He further suggests that Victorian art, in its emphasis
on making the reader see, is closer to Modern art than is Romantic art and also, he might have added, looking
back at Lipking’s essay, to eighteenth-century pictorial art.</p>
          <p>The three essays on Blake’s “composite art” (Hagstrum’s term, of course) will be of
special interest to readers of <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> Ronald Paulson’s discussion of “Blake’s
            Revolutionary Tiger” usefully situates the poem within the context of an anti-<corr type="emend">Jacobin</corr> rhetoric that
frequently identified the bestial French revolutionaries as tigers but falls into that strong mis-reading
heralded by Harold Bloom and represents the voice of the poem as that of the outraged Burke. While Paulson’s
essay contains several scattered insights, it too closely resembles a patchwork quilt of pieces stitched
together haphazardly from other essays and fails to develop a cogent argument of its own.</p>
          <p>Morton Paley’s study of Blake’s use of architecture, both as visual structure and as symbol,
masterfully documents an important and unjustifiably neglected dimension of Blake’s thought and practice. He
first surveys the seven periods of architectural styles that appear in Blake’s works, Egyptian, Eastern,
Classical, Druid, Gothic, Baroque and contemporary, and carefully defines the meaning each style had for
Blake, usefully adding the caveat that in many cases, the meaning of a given style depends on its pictorial
context—this is particularly true of Blake’s use of neoclassical motifs. Paley then examines the
significance of particular architectural types, such as altars, walls, stairways (spiritually spiral or
oppressively slab), doorways, superstructures, and cottages, and concludes with an insightful discussion of
Golgonooza and the city of Jerusalem as the perpetually rebuilding Temple and Tabernacle of Christ.</p>
          <p>W.J.T. Mitchell’s analysis of the vortex as both iconic image and structuring form in the work
of Hogarth, Turner and Blake brilliantly traces the transformation of the vortex from Hogarth’s S-line of
beauty, carefully contained within a stable neoclassical form, through Turner’s identification of the vortex
with the very flux of chaotic nature, showing that the vortex functions in Turner’s art simultaneously as
structural pattern and as a signifier of perpetual death and renewal, most notably in his great late paintings
of the Deluge and the Apocalypse. Mitchell then discusses Blake’s all-encompassing vortex as both the
contrary and the instrument of vision, manifested most seminally in “Newton” and the text of 
<hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> After commenting on the Vorticists’ transformation of the vortex as a kind of image
into every image as a kind of vortex, Mitchell reminds us that “image-magic operates not just at the
explicit level of iconographic representation, but in those structures or spaces that organize the way we
think about history, logic, or the human condition itself. The demystification of these subliminal idolatries
will be the goal of a truly historical iconology.” The essays in this handsomely illustrated volume have
made some notable progress toward this goal, a goal that Jean Hagstrum himself, albeit in different terms,
established for us. For the sister arts, this process of demystification is doubly complex, since it requires
that we bring to consciousness not only what has been thought but the very shapes—both aural and visual—in
which that thinking has occurred.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
