<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>19.3.essick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake’s Job: Some Unrecorded Proofs and Their Inscriptions</title>
        <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1985/1986</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985-86</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">19.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Dan Bell</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Max Byrd</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Stuart Peterfreund</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Allen Staley</name>
              <name>David Wagenknecht</name>
              <name>Nicholas Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1985/1986"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <body>
    <pb id="p19-96" n="96"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-3-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job:</hi> Some Unrecorded Proofs and Their
              Inscriptions</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">ROBERT N.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">ESSICK</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>Over the last several years, I have been attempting to record all pre-publication proofs
          of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engravings. The resulting catalogue raisonné will
          soon be published (or perhaps by now has been published) by the William Blake Trust as a
          supplement to its long-awaited <hi rend="i">Job</hi> facsimiles. This catalogue includes a
          large number of previously unrecorded states, as well as several pre-publication sets of
          all 22 plates which have never been described. One such group of proofs merits individual
          notice in the journal of record for Blake scholarship because of the light it throws on
          Blake’s interpretation of the Book of Job. Further, two of the proofs bear inscribed
          aphorisms that deserve inclusion in the canon of Blake’s original writings.</p>
        <p>On 9 December 1936, the American Art Association/Anderson Galleries Inc. of New York
          offered at auction as lot 62 a group of 21 pre-publication <hi rend="i">Job</hi> proofs.
          The catalogue includes a 4¼-page description of this collection. The vendor is not named
          and the extensive sales pitch says nothing about provenance. The title page of the
          catalogue names eight sellers, but none is known to have been a Blake collector. The
          auction included “other properties,” and thus the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> proofs may not
          have come from any of the eight. An annotated copy of the catalogue at the Rosenbach
          Museum &amp; Library, Philadelphia, records a price of $5000 for lot 62,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1"
            type="note">1</ref> but I have not been able to discover the purchaser or present
          whereabouts of the proofs. They clearly are not the same as any of the 9 sets of complete
          proofs I have located, nor can any of the individual proofs outside these major sets be
          identified as dispersed remnants of the group sold in 1936. 
              <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> I am grateful to Leslie A. Morris of the Rosenbach for this
            information.</note></p>
        <p>The auction catalogue notes that all leaves in this proof set measure 11⅞ × 9 9/16 inches
          (30.2 × 24.3 cm.) and show a “single stab-hole.” Plates 17 and 20 are on laid paper and
          the remainder are on wove, with plates 3, 9, 12, 16, and 21 showing a “J. Whatman 1823”
            watermark.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> The title page,
printed on laid India
          paper, is the only plate not in a pre-publication proof state. It probably was not printed
          with the other plates and may have been added at a later date to complete the set. The
          plate by plate descriptions in the sale catalogue range from helpful comparisons between
          the proofs and finished states to vague generalities (e.g., on plate 8 “the general
          treatment of the finished work is more finished and pronounced”). These descriptions do
          not permit the precise determination of each print’s position in the sequence of known
          proof states, but it would seem as though many, perhaps all, of these impressions
          represent the first states after the addition of border designs. All are described as
          lacking imprints and the “Proof” inscription. If indeed these are first pulls after the
          addition of borders, they record a crucial point in Blake’s development of the 
            <hi rend="i">Job</hi> copperplates, perhaps the first time he could determine fully the
          success or failure of his combination of outline borders and highly-finished central
          designs. The rediscovery of these impressions could occasion some major adjustments in the
          known record of progress proofs.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3"
type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n2"><hi
              rend="s">2</hi> The Riches set of proofs in the Fitzwilliam Museum, the
            White-Rosenwald set in the National Gallery of Art, Washington, and some of the proofs
            in the Linnell-Rosenwald group (National Gallery of Art) are on laid papers of at least
            two varieties. One example from the last group, plus five impressions in the set of
            proofs owned by Philip Hofer, show the Whatman 1823 watermark.</note>
	<note id="n3"><hi
              rend="s">3</hi> The sale catalogue descriptions are not sufficient to permit the
            inclusion of the untraced proofs in the Blake Trust catalogue of states. It will,
            however, contain a separate list of excerpts from the 1936 auction catalogue and
            speculations about the state of each untraced proof.</note></p>
        <p>Among the more intriguing features of these proofs—or, to be more exact, of the 1936
          catalogue descriptions—is the absence of a few biblical inscriptions which appear on all
          previously recorded and traced impressions. Plate 5 is said to lack “And it grieved him at
          his heart / Who maketh his Angels Spirits &amp; his Ministers a Flaming Fire.” These words
          appear as the second and third lines of text beneath the central design on the earliest
          traced state of plate 5 with the border design (Riches set, Fitzwilliam Museum, and
          Linnell-Rosenwald set, National Gallery of Art, Washington) and in all subsequent states.
          Plate 16 is described as lacking “The Accuser of our Brethren is Cast down / which accused
          them before our God day &amp; night.” The first of these lines, but not the second, is
          present just left of the central design in the previously recorded first proof state with
          the borders (Linnell-Rosenwald set). The next state (Riches, Linnell-Rosenwald, and
          White-Rosenwald) also lacks the second line, but it appears in all later states. The 1936
          auction catalogue also notes a variant in the second line of text beneath the design on
          plate 16: “Even the Devils are Subject to Us thro thy Name. And he said unto them, I saw
          Satan as lightning fall from Heaven.” These words from Luke 10: 17-18 are emended in the
          next proof state so that the beginning 
<pb id="p19-97" n="97"/>
of the second sentence
          reads “Jesus said unto them, . . . ” Blake very probably made the change simply to
          identify the speaker.</p>
        <p>By far the most significant variants, textual or pictorial, noted in the 1936 catalogue
          appear on plates 1 and 21. Fortunately, both are reproduced. The illustrations
          accompanying this essay were made from photographs 
<figure n="1936PhotoJobFamily.19.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="578">
            <head>1. Blake.</head>
            <figDesc><hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi>, plate 1. Intaglio
              engraving, image 18.3 × 15 cm. Proof between states 4 and 5, c. 1824.
              Untraced.</figDesc>
          </figure> of the 1936 reproductions. In the first plate (illus. 1), the ground below the
          altar in the lower border is inscribed “Prayer to God is the Study of Imaginative Art.”
          The final plate (illus. 2) bears an inscription parallel in its placement and syntax:
          “Praise to God is the Exercise of Imaginative Art.” The reproductions not only confirm the
          presence of these lines but strongly suggest 
<pb id="p19-98" n="98"/>
that, like the other
          inscriptions on these two proofs, the letters were scratched into the copperplates in
          drypoint rather than written with pen or pencil on the individual impressions. The style
          of lettering is the same as that exemplified by the scratched inscriptions on the altars
          and found throughout the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> plates. There can be little doubt that the
          lines were written by Blake.</p>
        <figure n="1936PhotoJobPlate21.19.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="618">
          <head>2. Blake.</head>
          <figDesc><hi rend="i">Job</hi>, plate 21. Image 19.8 × 14.9 cm. Proof between states 1 and
            2, c. 1824. Untraced.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <p>The inscriptions beneath the altars are unique to the untraced proofs. In the next known
          state of plate 1 (Essick collection [illus. 3] and Linnell, White, and Riches proof sets),
          the ground has been completely cleared of all letters and “The Letter Killeth / The Spirit
          giveth Life” added to the upper part of the altar. Ground and altar remain unchanged in
          all later states. The next 
<pb id="p19-99" n="99"/>
recorded state of plate 21 (White
          [illus. 4] and Riches proofs) shows that the ground has been cleared, additional tongues
          of flame have been added above the altar, and the lettering on the altar has been recut
          more clearly. These features remain unaltered in subsequent states.</p>
        <p>The proof inscriptions in question are the only 
<figure n="bb421.1.3-2.ps" id="bb421.1.spb.03" work-copy="bb421.1" rend="db" width="846" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>1<lb/>
	Our Father which art in Heaven hallowed be thy Name<lb/>
	Thus did Job continually<lb/>
	There was a Man in the<lb/>
	Land of Uz whose Name<lb/>
	was Job. &amp; that Man<lb/>
	was perfect &amp; upright<lb/>
	The Letter Killeth<lb/>
	The Spirit giveth Life<lb/>
	It is Spiritually Discerned<lb/>
	&amp; one that feared God<lb/>
	&amp; eschewed Evil. &amp; there<lb/>
	was born unto him Seven<lb/>
	Sons &amp; Three Daughters<lb/>
	WBlake inv &amp; sculp<lb/>
	London. Published as the Act directs. March 8: 1828. by Willm Blake N3 Fountain Court Strand<lb/>
	Proof</figTranscr>
            <head>3. Blake.</head>
            <figDesc><hi rend="i">Job</hi>, plate 1. Proof state 5, c. 1824-25. Essick
              collection.</figDesc>
          </figure> words (other than signatures and imprints) in the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> series
          not quoted from, or at least closely based on, the Bible.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n4" type="note">4</ref> This might have been one reason for their removal. Both inscriptions are
almost
          certainly Blake’s own words. Their composition—or at least their inscription in copper—can
          be dated to c. 1824 on the 
<pb id="p19-100" n="100"/>
basis of the known chronology of the
            <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engravings.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5"
type="note">5</ref> They are
          strikingly similar to two adjacent lines inscribed along the left margin of Blake’s 
            <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> engraving of c. 1820 (illus. 5): “Prayer is the Study of Art /
          Praise is the Practise of Art.” A further close parallel between late proof states of 
            <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> is established 
          <figure n="BB421.1.22.st2.PS" rend="file" width="758" height="1000">
            <head>4. Blake.</head>
            <figDesc><hi rend="i">Job</hi>, plate 21. Proof state 2, c. 1824-25. White set of
              proofs, Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection, National Gallery of Art,
              Washington.</figDesc>
          </figure> 
          by the presence on the latter of “The Angel of the Divine Presence” above “Angel
          of Jehovah” in Hebrew. Blake added the same arrangement of the same words (with a spelling
          change in the Hebrew) to the eighth and last pre-publication proof state of 
            <hi rend="i">Job</hi> plate 2.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi>
            Perhaps the line farthest from its Biblical source is “The Angel of the Divine Presence”
            on plate 2. S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Job</hi> (Providence: Brown Univ.
            Press, 1966), p. 56, notes that “this phrase does not appear in the Bible.” However, it
            is clearly based on Isaiah 63:9 (“and the angel of his presence saved them”), as was
            first pointed out in Joseph Wicksteed, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Vision of the Book of
              Job</hi> (London: Dent, 1910), p. 45.</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> The
            “Memorandum of Agreement” between Blake and John Linnell to engrave the 
              <hi rend="i">Job</hi> designs is dated 25 March 1823 (G.E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
              Records</hi> [Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969], p. 277), but it is unlikely that Blake
            could have brought the plates to the state of finish represented by the untraced proofs
            until early in the next year. Indeed, in a letter to C. W. Dilke of 27 September 1844,
            Linnell noted that the border designs “were an after thought” (<hi rend="i">Blake
              Records</hi>, pp. 326-27). The first recorded printing of <hi rend="i">Job</hi> proofs
            is 3 March 1825 (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, pp. 588, 602), and these were probably
            pulls of a state later than the untraced proofs, a state just prior to the addition of
            the 8 March 1825 imprints to all but plate 1 (mistakenly dated 1828).</note>	
            <note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> An 1825 Linnell imprint was added to the fourth state, then
            changed to the Blake imprint in the fifth. Thus the lines in question would appear to be
            additions of late 1825 or even early 1826. See also note 4. On Blake’s misspelling(?) of
            “Angel” in Hebrew, thereby changing it to “King” on the Job plate, see David V. Erdman,
            “Redefining the Texts of Blake,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>, 17
            (1983), 14.</note></p>
        <pb id="p19-101" n="101"/>
        <p>The marginal inscriptions throughout <hi rend="i">Job</hi> influence the “reading” of the
          central designs. The position of the unique lines on the untraced proofs of plates 1 and
          21 recommends them as the grounds for interpretations of all that is pictured and written
          above. “Praise to God is the Exercise of Imaginative Art” contrasts with the 
<figure n="laocoon.A.P1" rend="file" width="846" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>If Morality was Christianity Socrates was the Saviour<lb/>
 יה &amp; his two Sons Satan &amp; Adam as they were copied from the Cherubim<lb/>
		of Solomons Temple by three Rhodians &amp; applied to Natural Fact. or History of Ilium<lb/>
		              Art Degraded Imagination Denied War Governed the Nations<lb/>
		Evil<lb/>
		                  Good &amp; Evil are<lb/>
		Riches &amp; Poverty a Tree of<lb/>
		                                        Misery<lb/>
		                  propagating<lb/>
		                  Generation &amp; Death<lb/>
		The Gods of Priam are the Cherubim of Moses &amp; Solomon: The Hosts<lb/>
		                                                                                             of Heaven<lb/>
		    Without Unceasing Practise nothing can be done Practise is Art<lb/>
		     If you leave off you are Lost<lb/>
		The Angel of the Divine Presence<lb/>
		                                             מלאך       יהוה<lb/>
		ΟΦΙουΧος<lb/>
		                                              Hebrew Art is<lb/>
		                                       called Sin by the Deist Science<lb/>
		                            All that we See is Vision<lb/>
		from Generated Organs gone as soon as come<lb/>
		                     Permanent in The Imagination; Considerd<lb/>
		                                 as Nothing by the<lb/>
		                                       Natural Man<lb/>
		What can be Created<lb/>
		Can be Destroyed<lb/>
		    Adam is only<lb/>
		The Natural Man<lb/>
		&amp; not the Soul<lb/>
		or Imagination<lb/>
		Good<lb/>
		                                       לילית<lb/>
		Satans Wife The Goddess Nature is War &amp; Misery &amp; Heroism a Miser<lb/>
		    Spiritual War<lb/>
		Israel deliverd from Egypt<lb/>
		    is Art deliverd from<lb/>
		       Nature &amp; Imitation<lb/>
		         A Poet a Painter a Musician an Architect : the Man<lb/>
		         Or Woman who is not one of these is not a Christian<lb/>
		You must leave Fathers &amp; Mothers &amp; Houses &amp; Lands if they stand in the way of Art<lb/>
		The Eternal Body of Man is The Imagination, that is God himself<lb/>
		                                   The Divine Body }    ישע     Jesus   we are his<lb/>
		                                                                                             Members<lb/>
		                     It manifests itself in his Works of Art (In Eternity All is Vision)<lb/>
		The True Christian Charity not dependent on Money (the lifes blood of Poor Families)<lb/>
		         that is on Caesar or Empire or Natural Religion<lb/>
		Money, which is The Great Satan or Reason<lb/>
		              the Root of Good &amp; Evil<lb/>
		                  In The Accusation of Sin<lb/>
		Prayer is the Study of Art                            <lb/>
		Praise is the Practise of Art                            <lb/>
		Fasting &amp;c. all relate to Art<lb/>
		The outward Ceremony is Antichrist<lb/>
		       Where any view of Money exists Art cannot be carried on, but War only Read Matthew C X. 9 &amp; 10v<lb/>
		by pretences to the Two Impossibilities Chastity &amp; Abstinence Gods of the Heathen<lb/>
		He repented that he had made Adam<lb/>
		            (of the Female, the Adamah)<lb/>
		                                       &amp; it grieved him at his heart<lb/>
		Art can never exist without<lb/>
		         Naked Beauty displayed<lb/>
		The Gods of Greece &amp; Egypt were Mathematical<lb/>
		                                                        Diagrams<lb/>
		                                                            See Plato’s<lb/>
		                                                                   Works<lb/>
		       Divine Union<lb/>
		    Deriding<lb/>
		And Denying Immediate<lb/>
		Communion with God<lb/>
		The Spoilers say<lb/>
		Where are his Works<lb/>
		That he did in the Wilderness<lb/>
		           Lo what are these<lb/>
		Whence came they<lb/>
		These are not the Works<lb/>
		Of Egypt nor Babylon<lb/>
		Whose Gods are the Powers<lb/>
		Of this World. Goddess, Nature.<lb/>
		Who first spoil &amp; then destroy<lb/>
		Imaginative Art<lb/>
		For their Glory is<lb/>
		War and Dominion<lb/>
		Empire against Art          See Virgils Eneid.<lb/>
		                                               Lib. VI.v 848<lb/>
		For every<lb/>
		Pleasure<lb/>
		Money<lb/>
		Is Useless<lb/>
		     There are States<lb/>
		         in which. all<lb/>
		     Visionary Men<lb/>
		     are accounted<lb/>
		           Mad Men<lb/>
		         such are<lb/>
		     Greece &amp; Rome<lb/>
		     Such is<lb/>
		     Empire<lb/>
		     or Tax<lb/>
		See Luke Ch 2 v 1<lb/>
		Jesus &amp; his Apostles &amp; Disciples were all Artists Their Works were destroyd by the Seven Angels of the Seven Churches in Asia    Antichrist      Science<lb/>
		                            The unproductive Man is not a Christian much less the Destroyer<lb/>
		The Old &amp; New Testaments are<lb/>
		    the Great Code of Art       Art is the<lb/>
		                                                   Tree<lb/>
		                                               of Life<lb/>
		                                                   GOD<lb/>
		                                               is Jesus<lb/>
		                                               Science is the<lb/>
		                                               Tree of Death<lb/>
		The Whole Business of Man Is<lb/>
		The Arts &amp; All Things     Common<lb/>
		                         No Secresy in Art<lb/>
		What we call Antique Gems                 <lb/>
		                are the Gems of Aarons Breast Plate<lb/>
		                Christianity is Art<lb/>
		                &amp; not Money<lb/>
		                Money is its Curse<lb/>
		       Is not every Vice possible to Man<lb/>
		                described in the Bible openly<lb/>
		       All is not Sin that Satan calls so<lb/>
		                  all the Loves &amp; Graces of Eternity.<lb/>
		Drawn &amp; Engraved by William Blake.</figTranscr>
            <head>5. Blake.</head>
            <figDesc><hi rend="i">Laocoön.</hi> Intaglio etching/engraving, image 26.2 × 21.6 cm. C.
              1820. Estate of Sir Geoffrey Keynes.</figDesc>
          </figure> words cut into the altar (“In burnt Offerings for Sin / thou hast had no
          Pleasure”) and provides an appropriate caption for the central design on plate 21.
          Wicksteed’s comment that Job and his family are “lifting to heaven the harmonies of
          redemption” fairly represents all modern commentary on the final design.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
            type="note">7</ref> Thus, the plate 
<pb id="p19-102" n="102"/>
21 proof inscription
          tends to confirm interpretations made without knowledge of its existence. However, the
          impact of the plate 1 proof inscription on the iconography of its central design is far
          more complex. <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Wicksteed, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Vision of
              the Book of Job.</hi> 2nd ed. (London: Dent, 1924), p. 209.</note></p>
        <p>Charles Eliot Norton was the first to suggest that Blake pictures Job in a fallen state
          of consciousness at the beginning of the series. As Norton wrote in 1875, “Job’s prayers
          and burnt-offerings, in the days of his prosperity, were, after all, but the propitiatory
          and selfish sacrifices of the law.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">8</ref> Subsequent
          criticism has followed this crucial conception of Blake’s vision of Job, one that places
          the first and last plates in opposition and thereby influences the shape of the entire
          visual narrative. This perspective is placed into doubt by the proof inscription which,
          when combined with the inscription (“It is Spiritually Discerned”) on the altar
          immediately above, suggests that the books held by Job and his wife and the prayerful
          attitudes of the whole family represent a “Study of Imaginative Art” capable of achieving
          spiritual insight. The proof inscriptions together thwart the usual juxtaposition of the
          first and last plates and suggest instead underlying similarities between passive prayer
          and active praise. The latter may be superior to the former, but the difference is in
          means, not ends. <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake’s
              Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> (Boston: James R. Osgood, 1875), unnumbered page
            of comments on “Plate I.”</note></p>
        <p>Before thoroughly revising our sense of the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engravings on the basis
          of the proof inscriptions, we must consider several important details in the development
          of the first design. Its proof inscription certainly disrupts the conventional
          interpretation of the central design for the proof state on which it appears, and perhaps
          for all earlier versions including the water color executed for Thomas Butts c. 1805-1806,
          but the elimination of the line may also signal a shift in Blake’s own conception of the
            <hi rend="i">Job</hi> series. The removal of the sentence from the ground in the next
          recorded proof state is accompanied by the addition of “The Letter Killeth / The Spirit
          giveth Life” on the altar above (see illus. 3). These words prompt a very different view
          of the books and family activities in the central design. The text lower on the altar from
          1 Corinthians 2:14 tends to confirm the truth and importance of the new lines from 2
          Corinthians 3:6 opposing letter and spirit. Norton, in his commentary noted above, begins
          by quoting these lines; later critics also stress their importance in establishing the 
            <hi rend="i">donnée</hi> for the whole series.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n9" type="note">9</ref>	
            <note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> See for example Wicksteed (1924), p. 90: “The written books,
            and the silent instruments above, represent the letter and the spirit, referred to on
            the altar below, and here we see Job dwelling on the letter that ‘killeth,’ while the
            Spirit that ‘giveth life’ is not yet waked.”</note></p>
        <p>In his writings on the arts, Blake stresses the unity of conception and execution. The
          textual revisions on the first <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engraving would seem to demonstrate
          the practical relevance of this ideal to Blake’s habits as a visual/verbal artist. In
          light of the considerable change in interpretation warranted by this two-fold revision, we
          cannot assume that Blake’s full conception of the meaning of the design preceded its
          execution in copper. Only as he slowly developed his images in the difficult medium of
          line engraving did Blake come to realize that the “perfect and upright” man of “the land
          of Uz” (Job 1:1) was not an archetype of the prayerful student of the arts but one who had
          already fallen in thrall to the dead letter of the law. The thematic shape of the entire
          series, particularly the errors which adumbrate Satan’s entry into Job’s life and the
          oppositions between letter and spirit visualized by the first and last scenes, came into
          being at a late stage in Blake’s long history as an interpreter of the Book of Job.</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
