<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>19.3.byrd</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Richard B. Schwartz, Daily Life in Johnson’s London</title>
        <author n="Byrd">Max Byrd</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1985/1986</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985-86</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">19.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Dan Bell</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Max Byrd</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Stuart Peterfreund</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Allen Staley</name>
              <name>David Wagenknecht</name>
              <name>Nicholas Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1985/1986"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <body>
	<pb id="p19-110" n="110"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-3-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Richard B. Schwartz, <hi rend="i">Daily Life in Johnson’s London</hi>,
Madison: University of Wisconsin Press, 1984; 196 pp. + xix; $25.00 cloth, $9.95 paper.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Max</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Byrd</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Sooner or later every reader must yearn to grasp one of Richard B. Schwartz’s sentences at each
end and wring it dry, like a wet towel. For twenty-five of the first thirty verbs in chapter one of 
<hi rend="i">Daily Life in Johnson’s London</hi> he chooses either the passive voice or a form of “to be”: 
“Traffic upon the Thames was slow . . . The smell of sewage was apparent . . . The city’s streets were
covered. . . .” And throughout the book his verbs continue to lie motionless in this way, on their backs and
silent, their legs wriggling feebly in the air. Such passivity of style dejects us all the more because
Schwartz employs it upon a subject matter that has become almost proverbial for its vitality: the great
thrashing, bustling, unceasingly noisy London that Johnson made synonymous with life itself.</p>
          <p>Schwartz has intended his book as an introduction “to certain aspects’ of eighteenth-century
social history”
<pb id="p19-111" n="111"/>
and also as a companion for students struggling to understand the details of daily life that lie behind the
major works of eighteenth-century English literature, particularly behind Boswell’s <hi rend="i">Life of
Johnson.</hi> Accordingly, he organizes his chapters around topics such as “Work and Money,” “Pastimes
and Pleasures,” “Health and Hygiene”—a familiar and serviceable scheme also used in books like Dorothy
Marshall’s <hi rend="i">Dr. Johnson’s London</hi> and Roy Porter’s <hi rend="i">English Society in the
Eighteenth Century</hi> (neither listed in Schwartz’s bibliography). To focus his discussions more sharply,
Schwartz takes the figure of Samuel Johnson as a recurrent point of reference, not only because we so closely
identify Johnson with the city he loved, but also because, as Schwartz rightly observes, Johnson’s moral
thought takes so seriously what he called in <hi rend="i">Idler</hi> 84 “the general surface of life.”</p>
          <p>For the second of his goals, the development of a “background” to major texts, this approach
works very well. From time to time in the book we do seem to peer over Johnson’s shoulder and to register,
as he must have done, the presence of “pools of urine and stagnant water” on London streets, the stench of
sewage and nightsoil permeating every street and house, the universal coal smoke, from domestic fires and
factories, settling like a cloud over the city all year long. Schwartz has an excellent eye for such details,
shrinks from no subject (e.g., his account of chamberpots in the sideboards of elegant dining rooms), and
clearly revels, like most students of the period, in its vicarious and bracing lowlife. Hence, he covers
thoroughly such questions as false bosoms made of wirework—and the false buttocks made of cork—that
ornamented fashionable Englishwomen for a time. He explains the “growing dominance of the Norwegian, or
brown, rat over the English black rat.” He lists the prevalent venereal diseases of the period, the
locations and specialties of prostitutes (a floating brothel, called the <hi rend="i">Folly</hi>, lay anchored
opposite Somerset House), and goes enthusiastically into the distinction between ordinary and “deep”
gaming. And no one, perhaps, in all the vast literature about eighteenth-century London, has crammed more
information on domestic manners and routines into shorter space, from the usual ingredients and dressings used
in salads to the fact that dogs were sometimes harnessed to butter churns. “It must be remembered,”
Schwartz aptly quotes Johnson as saying, “that life consists not of a series of illustrious actions, or
elegant enjoyments; the greater part of our time passes in compliance with necessities, in the performance of
daily duties, in the removal of small inconveniences, in the procurement of petty pleasures. . . . The true
state of every nation is the state of common life.”</p>
          <p>But as an introduction to aspects of eighteenth-century social history, <hi rend="i">Daily Life
in Johnson’s London</hi> suffers from its remarkable, nearly complete absorption in such detail: no idea
interrupts the unending flow of information. For generalizations Schwartz never rises much above “The period
was one of great hoaxes.” And for analysis he never reaches past the simple categories of his chapter
titles. Thus the information he so generously sets down usually remains shapeless, following no particular
order, leading to no particular conclusion. He gives us, for example, nothing comparable to Dorothy George’s
moving account of the ravages of gin-drinking in the opening chapter of <hi rend="i">London Life in the
Eighteenth Century</hi>, where she controls and justifies her narrative by asserting in the very first
sentence that “The key to the social history of London is to be found in its changes in population—its
growth, and the ratio between births and deaths.” Nor can he sum up and transfer his information to a new
context, as George brilliantly does, connecting the “uncertainties of life and trade” to that “sense of
instability, of liability to sudden ruin, which runs through so much eighteenth-century literature.”
Likewise, Schwartz conveys little sense of the dynamics of class that figures prominently in most contemporary
social history, as for instance in Roy Porter’s discussions of the simultaneous resiliance and porousness of
the English social hierarchy. In part these failings derive from the brevity of Schwartz’s book—he simply
gives himself too little space in which to develop ideas—and in part they derive from the essentially static
picture he paints of social institutions: he has nothing like George’s thesis of gradual humanitarian
progress in the Hanoverian years or Porter’s continual awareness that Johnson’s London stands at the
threshold of the Industrial Revolution. Students who come to Schwartz’s book expecting to learn what it is
that social historians do—and why it is so exciting—will return unenlightened, ill equipped to apply
historical techniques to literary issues. Students who expect to see how social history illuminates
literature—how, to take one instance, the enormous size and consequent anonymity of life in London lead to
new themes of alienation, masquerade, and self-consciousness—will find that the concept of literature at
work here rarely goes beyond the anecdotal. His book, in other words, interesting though it is, belongs to the
honorable but quite limited genre of antiquarianism.</p>
          <p>I should add that the bibliography includes many items having nothing directly to do with
London—Johnson’s <hi rend="i">Poems</hi> in the Yale edition—and omits a great many items
(e.g., James Sutherland’s <hi rend="i">Background for Queen Anne</hi>) that most students of the period
would want to know; readers will do better to consult the still useful bibliography at the end of George
Rudé’s <hi rend="i">Hanoverian London.</hi> The University of Wisconsin Press has printed an unusually
handsome volume; both they and Schwartz deserve credit for the beautifully reproduced and exceedingly
well-selected illustrations.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
