<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>19.3.peterfreund</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Stewart Crehan, Blake in Context</title>
        <author n="Peterfreund">Stuart Peterfreund</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1985/1986</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985-86</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">19.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Dan Bell</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Max Byrd</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Stuart Peterfreund</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Allen Staley</name>
              <name>David Wagenknecht</name>
              <name>Nicholas Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1985/1986"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <body>
	<pb id="p19-113" n="113"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-3-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Stewart Crehan. <hi rend="i">Blake in Context.</hi> Atlantic Highlands, NJ:
Humanities Press [Dublin: Gill and Macmillan], 1984. 364 pp. $47.50</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Stuart</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Peterfreund</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The context to which Stewart Crehan’s title refers is specified in the introduction to his
study, which has as its “main concern . . . the social and historical context within which an artist such as
Blake emerges, and how this context makes necessary a revolution in artistic form and practice” (p. 13).
Writers such as Bronowski, Schorer, and above all, Erdman, have dealt with precisely this context, but not,
apparently, to Crehan’s satisfaction. In his view, the discussion of Blake’s artistic form and practice
has been dominated by “formalists” such as Erdman and Anne K. Mellor (see pp. 240-45), who hold power in
the academy and insist that the ideology in Blake’s art be de-emphasized or ignored outright. Crehan’s
conception of his mission, then, much like Edward Said’s conception of the deconstructionist enterprise (see
“The Problem of Textuality,” <hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry</hi>, 4 [1978], 673-714), is that of a rescue,
a recapturing of scholarly territory held by hostile colonialist forces. In Crehan’s own words, “As long
as the formalists continue to hold sway in all discussions of art and literature, the historical materialist
approach will repeatedly stress art’s historical and class content, guided by an understanding of the
primacy of social laws over artistic ones” (p. 13).</p>
          <p>The preceding quotation suggests what Crehan elsewhere states forthrightly: the basis of his
approach to Blake is Marxist, carried out with the intent of studying
<pb id="p19-114" n="114"/>
Blake as a case in point “in order to explore certain problems and develop a method of analysis” (p. 12).
Though historical, Crehan’s approach is not, strictly speaking, chronological, either in the sense of being
narrative or developmental in any larger sense. Crehan defends his choice of historical focus with the same
sort of proleptic pugnacity he exhibits in his animadversions against the “formalists.” Responding to the
charge, not leveled by anyone but himself, that the chapters of the book, lacking broad focus or narrative
continuity, may lend themselves to being read as discrete essays, Crehan states that the synchronic is as
valid an approach to historical issues as the diachronic, which is apparently the approach of choice for the
Blake establishment.
<q>
I am not a “Blakean” and do not subscribe to any cultist appreciation of his work. I have tried to explain
Blake’s famed ‘uniqueness’ in historical terms—taking the poetry and the visual art together—rather
than leaving it an inexplicable mystery. If I am consequently accused of reductivism, of overstressing art’s
“subsidiary role in social process” [quoting Leon Trotsky in <hi rend="i">Literature</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Revolution</hi>] and hence of neglecting art’s inherent laws, then this is because there are too
many books on Blake that analyse the art, poetry and ideas (especially the ideas) and forget the social
process. (pp. 12-13)
</q>
Tellingly enough, neither at this juncture nor at any other point subsequent to it does Crehan undertake the
sort of systematic critique that his introductory comments virtually beg for.</p>
          <p>Ten chapters follow the introductory comments. The first of these, “The Romantic Artist,”
attempts to situate Blake as a case in point of “the Romantic artist” who “begins to appear at the
moment when feudal social relations are decisively challenged,” Blake’s particular “moment” lasting
three quarters of a century during “the period of the bourgeois-democratic revolution (1776-1848)” (p.
16). Crehan argues that the result of such revolution is freedom, especially in the realm of art, where Blake
“pushed the freedom principle further than any other English Romantic poet, even to the extent of writing a
free verse poem—the first of its kind in English” (p. 30). The poem Crehan has in mind is 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, which supposedly makes good Blake’s intention to move away from the decasyllabic
line and thus avoid “any ‘Augustan’ relapse into some easy, confident expectation or passive
observation” (p. 31). As the basis for his claim that <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> both attains a new level
of formal freedom and apotheosizes “the Romantic revolt against metrical restrictions” (p. 34), Crehan
cites much of the concluding paragraph of the prefatory third plate of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, entitled
“To the Public.” On the basis of Blake’s statement, Crehan concludes that “the revolt against
‘fettered’ verse and the ordered, rational world-view, begins, if it begins anywhere, with Blake” (p.
35). What Crehan does not seem to realize is that most of what Blake has to say in the paragraph under
discussion refers, in a highly self-conscious manner, to the statement entitled “The Verse” which prefaces
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi> If Blake really intends to repudiate the poetic past, including the Miltonic
source of his very words of repudiation, Blake does so more in the service of convention than in the service
of freedom, authenticating his vision in relation to his poetic precursors just as Milton had authenticated
his vision in relation to his precursors. For example, Blake’s repudiation of “a Monotonous Cadence, like
that used by Milton &amp; Shakespeare &amp; all writers of English Blank Verse, derived from the modern
bondage of Rhyming,” as “a necessary and indispensable part of verse,” echoes Milton’s repudiation of
rhyme itself. “This neglect then of Rime so little is to be taken as a defect, though it may seem so perhaps
to vulgar Readers, that it rather is to be esteem’d an example set, the first in <hi rend="i">English</hi>,
of ancient liberty recover’d to Heroic Poem from the troublesome and modern bondage of Riming.”</p>
          <p>The direction in which Milton seeks freedom from modern constraints is toward the past—the
classical past in <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and, ultimately, the hebraic past in <hi rend="i">Paradise
Regained</hi>, in which Milton redeems himself in Blake’s eyes from any imputation of succumbing to the
idolatry of classicism. The point of Blake’s comments is likewise to indicate that he is seeking freedom
from modern constraints in the past, and avoiding the enticements of classicism that temporarily seduced
Milton by going directly to the hebraic source. Specifically, Blake in his comments embraces perhaps the most
ancient of poetic conceptions, that of <hi rend="i">mashal</hi>, defined by Robert Lowth in his 
<hi rend="i">Lectures on the Sacred Poetry of the Hebrews</hi> (tr. 1787): “The word <hi rend="i">Mashal</hi> .
. . denotes resemblance, and is therefore directly expressive of the figurative style, as far as the nature of
figures consists in the substitution of words, or rather of ideas, for those which they resemble. . . .” As
with style, so with substance: it may well be, as Crehan argues, that Blake’s formal revolt can be linked to
his revolt against Enlightenment rationalism; but Blake’s revolt, though “not . . . simply against
rational analysis and the general laws of science <hi rend="i">per se</hi>, but against their 
<hi rend="i">social consequences</hi>” (p. 46; Crehan’s emphasis), is a backward-looking action rather than a
forward-looking one. As a notebook poem like “Mock On Mock On Voltaire Rousseau” makes clear, the cure for
such rationalism is hebraic vision, not bourgeois or popular revolution. Indeed, one could make a similar
argument for the very marxist program with which Crehan attempts to understand Blake. The final stage of the
socialist revolution, with its harmonization of abilities and needs, is a lot closer to the situation Blake
describes as the “sands along the Red sea shore/ Where Israels tents do shine so bright” than it is to the
situation of the French Republic, either before or after the rise of the Jacobins.</p>
          <p>I have devoted a perhaps inordinate amount of space to a discussion of Crehan’s first chapter
because that
<pb id="p19-115" n="115"/>
chapter both illustrates his strategy of argument throughout the book and illustrates the rather severe
limitations of the strategy. In virtually every case, Crehan meditates on one or more texts that, for him,
identify the social issues informing Blake’s artistic milieu and practice alike. Crehan then moves rapidly
from the text to the sociohistorical context—the French Revolution in particular and the age of revolution
in general, in the case of the first chapter. When he has moved to the sociohistorical context, which is
finally what he wants to talk about, Crehan glosses that context (and less often than not, the text with which
he began) with some broadly marxist truism that is based on a less broad but universally applicable marxist
truth. For example, in a discussion of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 91. 18-30, Crehan brings two passages from
<hi rend="i">Capital</hi> to bear on 11. 26-27 (“You accumulate Particulars, &amp; murder by analyzing, that
you / May take the aggregate; &amp; you call the aggregate Moral Law”) and explains that the lines have to
do with “the creative ‘soul’ of the worker himself. . . . Only through accumulating particular
individuals within factories, where ‘one man’s business’ has been reduced to “one simple question,’
can modern capitalist accumulation take place” (p. 50). What Blake is actually talking about is the effect
of pharisaical codification on one’s perception of divinity in the world, the sort of codification that
Jesus fought against and in doing so presented the example that Albion ultimately follows in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Blake’s dark mill-wheels, having more to do with Aristotle’s 
<hi rend="i">Analytics</hi> than Arkwright’s looms, are nowhere to be found in the passage Crehan discusses.
There is nothing to say that a marxist homily cannot be as good as a Jewish or Christian one, but good
homiletics demands first and foremost the selection of a good anecdote or text: Crehan’s text has nothing to
do with his point, which here and elsewhere overwhelms the particular Blakean text of choice.</p>
          <p>Thus the second chapter, “The Artist in the City,” seeks to bring into some correlation
Blake’s reaction to the capitalist and geopolitical expansion of London in his lifetime and Engels’
subsequent reaction to London, the point being to illustrate that what is for Blake “the possibility of 
<hi rend="i">imaginatively</hi> breaking out of the system” (p. 84; Crehan’s emphasis) is for Engels the
possibility of analytically and politically breaking out of the system. “London” is the text of choice.
The same sort of procedure characterizes subsequent chapters. The third chapter, “Radical Innocence,” uses
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> to demonstrate that even in these apparently sweet and innocent poems,
Blake is radicalizing his readers against the likes of Isaac Watts and Anna Laetitia Barbauld, who would, in
their own children’s literature, turn their young readers into well-behaved homunculi and capitalist dupes.
The fourth chapter, “The Politics of Experience,” uses the title of R.D. Laing’s book, cited elsewhere
with approval by Crehan (see pp. 305, 307), to suggest that Blake, in <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>,
accomplishes something of the same kind of breakthrough that Laing reports of the inmates of his Tavistock
Clinic. Blake moves from innocence and illusion to experience and a sense of play rather than disillusion: “
. . . the songs express not ‘disillusionment’ or a cynical awareness of social and psychological
realities, but a new dialectical awareness” (p. 122; Crehan’s emphasis).</p>
          <p>Crehan’s fifth chapter, “Blake’s Tyger and the ‘Tygerish Multitude,’ ” is probably
the best of the book. Here Crehan has a genuine context—that of anti-Jacobin discourse, contemporaneous with
and accessible to Blake—in which to situate Blake’s poem. Despite a broad context of anti-Jacobin
discourse equating the revolutionary masses of France with tigers and tigerish multitudes, Crehan remains
sensitive to the nuances and ambiguities of the poem, not trying to reduce it to the sum of its allusions or
sources, while at the same time suggesting how they do inform a reading of “The Tyger.” In addition to its
contribution to our historical perspective on Blake’s “Tyger,” the chapter is notable for its brevity
and the virtual absence of dialectical wrangling.</p>
          <p>Not so with the next four chapters, which attempt to view Blake’s art both as social document
and in the context of a theory of artistic production: moreover, in undertaking their attempt, these chapters
make good on Crehan’s introductory threat to “stress art’s historical and class content, guided by an
understanding of the primacy of social laws over artistic ones” (p. 13). At its best and brightest, this
approach gives us a document like Lovejoy’s <hi rend="i">The Great Chain of Being</hi>, which explains John
Davies and Herbert of Cherbury, but not Donne or Shakespeare <hi rend="i">as artists.</hi> Used by Crehan, the
approach gives us an analysis of how Blake attained artistic autonomy that depends for its point on a
comparison of Blake to William Sharp, “a friend . . . and a follower of the millenarian Richard Brothers and
later of Joanna Southcott . . . whose struggle for independence (not wholly achieved in terms of an original
art, however) closely parallels that of Blake, and tells us something about the conflict between
‘producers’ and ‘devourers’ within the print trade itself” (p. 150). Although Crehan’s book
probably went to press before he could frame and incorporate a rebuttal of Morris Eaves’ 
<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Theory of Art</hi> (1982) in his own arguments, he seems completely oblivious (or
willfully impervious) to earlier statements by Eaves that seek at once to understand how Blake’s situation
motivated him to attain artistic autonomy <hi rend="i">and</hi> the uniqueness of that attainment. In “What
Is the ‘History of Publishing?’ ” (<hi rend="i">Publishing History</hi>, 2 [1977], 57-77), Eaves
declares “Blake’s artistic decision to become an independent publisher . . . a landmark in the history of
publishing, not because he was the first or last to make that decision, but because he was far
<pb id="p19-116" n="116"/>
more aware than most others of why he was doing it” (p. 76). From this insight it is possible to develop a
coherent and consistent theory of artistic production, which is at the same time sensitive to nuances of
context and faithful to Blake as an individual. Eaves succeeds in his book, while Crehan fails in his.</p>
          <p>The reasons for Crehan’s failure, suggested from virtually his first paragraph, are clearly
evident in his book’s tenth and final chapter “Jerusalem and Albion.” Here Crehan seeks to show that the
aptness of his social and artistic analysis rests on a hitherto undiscussed tradition of working-class English
radical protestantism that exhorts its followers to a life of inspired artisanship for the spiritual
redemption of the world. To paraphrase Voltaire (in the infernal sense, of course), if radical protestantism
had not existed, Blake, Marx (perhaps), and Crehan (certainly) would have found it necessary to invent in
order to promulgate a dialectical changing of the -isms. In his pisgah-vision, Crehan sees context as Adam saw
history in Book XII of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>: “The context of Blake’s utopian vision is a
transition from millenarism and communitarianism to the utopian socialist experiments of the St-Simonians and
Owenites” (p. 330). Notably absent in Crehan’s discussion is any reference to Harold Fisch’s 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem and Albion</hi> (1964), which would have forced Crehan to address spiritual as well as
social issues. Nor is there, despite the bandying about of the idea of millenarianism, any reference to Norman
Cohn’s <hi rend="i">The Pursuit of the Millennium</hi> (1957; 1961). Nor is there even a passing reference
to the analysis of the same transformation that Crehan argues for that is found in M.H. Abrams’ 
<hi rend="i">Natural Supernaturalism</hi> (1971).</p>
          <p>And these are hardly the only oversights: if not Eaves, then why not include the work of marxists
such as Lucien Lefebvre and Pierre Macherey who have already come to grips with the issue of how to articulate
a marxist theory of artistic production? Why not include a broader sampling of those formalist critics sent up
from the start, if only to rebut them on matters of substance? In the final analysis, as the appended
bibliography shows, Crehan’s book is either a thinly researched dissertation, a badly updated one, or some
combination of these. It may not be possible to gain access to eighteenth-century rare books at the University
of Zambia, where he teaches, but Crehan surely could have taken the trouble to buttress his arguments with
more evidence of careful and reputable research. To do so would not have mitigated the sting of the gratuitous
nastiness that abounds in the book. My special selection in this regard is taken from Crehan’s analysis of
Blake’s color-printed monotype <hi rend="i">Newton</hi>: “the whole body curves in upon itself, hunching
itself into an embryo-like ball (the characteristic position of all intellectuals) . . . ” (p. 165). Come
the revolution, I trust the bureaucracy of the proletariat will help me and my fellow sufferers to shake off
the chains of our scholarship—and scoliosis.</p>
          <p>One finally wonders why someone in the academy would do everything in his power to 
<hi rend="i">épater</hi> his version of <hi rend="i">les bourgeois</hi>—even to ridicule them—without doing
his level best to make sure that in the aftermath he edified them by edifying himself to the greatest possible
extent. Crehan’s is an angry, inept, and ultimately saddening effort. Marxist approaches to Blake do not
have to be so—David Punter’s <hi rend="i">Blake, Hegel, and Dialectic</hi> (1982) is a case in point. And
a marxist approach to Blake’s theory and practice of artistic production could be richly edifying. But such
an approach has not yet been tried successfully, Crehan’s <hi rend="i">Blake in Context</hi>
notwithstanding.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
