<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>19.3.simpson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Steven E. Alford, Irony and the Logic of the Romantic Imagination</title>
        <author n="Simpson">David Simpson</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1985/1986</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1985-86</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">19.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Dan Bell</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Max Byrd</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Mary Lynn Johnson</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Stuart Peterfreund</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Allen Staley</name>
              <name>David Wagenknecht</name>
              <name>Nicholas Warner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1985/1986"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <body>
      <pb id="p19-106" n="106"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Steven E. Alford. <hi rend="i">Irony and the Logic of the Romantic
Imagination.</hi> American University Studies, Series III: Comparative Literature, vol. 13. New York, Berne,
Frankfort on the Main, Nancy: Peter Lang, 1984. 177 pp., paper, $19.45.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">David</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Simpson</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Steven Alford’s book is a comparative study of Blake and Friedrich Schlegel in which the German
critic is read as providing the model of romantic irony necessary for the proper reading of Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Marriage.</hi> The aims of the book, which is an unmodified doctoral dissertation, are modest.
Schlegel’s early writings are expounded, and the essay <hi rend="i">On Incomprehensibility</hi> examined in
some detail; Blake is represented in detail only by <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi></p>
          <p>After unpromising beginnings, in which the author appears to want to take seriously the
accusation that Romantic poetry is “flowery” in order to reassert the counterclaim that its aims were
“noble and beautiful” (pp. 1, 3, 4)—the probable irony of Keats’s “flowery tale” might have been
usefully recalled here—the major argument comes clear: that the Romantics moved toward an emphasis on the
“rhetorical” over the “logical” as the essence of meaning (p. 6). The substantial vehicle of this
shift is a move away from “understanding” to “imagination” by means of irony (p. 7).</p>
          <p>Unfortunately for Blake specialists, the discussion of Schlegel is considerably more adventurous
than that of Blake. Schlegel is argued to be recommending and embodying a move from logic to poetry as the
proper model of the philosophical enterprise, which then becomes “performative” rather than deductive (p.
42). Suggesting convincingly that Schlegel was unwilling to accept the potentially tragic Kantian distinction
between the phenomenal and the noumenal (p. 107)—an unwillingness shared by almost all of Kant’s
self-styled followers—Alford demonstrates the case in Schlegel’s writings for a unification of the
empirical and the absolute through the medium of romantic poetry (p. 55). In particular, romantic irony is the
unity of the “cognitive and rhetorical” in which otherwise abstract philosophical problems are adjudicated
in performance, in the actions and spiritual gestures of individual persons (pp. 64, 58).</p>
          <p>As this model is carried over into a reading of the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, it becomes
somewhat platitudinous. Alford sees a parallel to Schlegelian irony in Blake’s “visionary form of
language” (p. 123), whereby the irritable reaching after fact and reason (fixed allegories, stable speakers,
simple ironies of inversion, etc.) is to be replaced by “the eternally active creative imagination” (p.
167). Alford is surely right to lead us away from simple readings of Blake—but even a moderately experienced
reader is unlikely to perpetrate such readings in the terms he describes. He is right also to encourage the
search for “functional analogy,” not simple definition, as the proper approach to Blake’s myth (p. 148).
But I cannot see that anything that is not already habitual happens to our reading of the 
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> if we agree that “irony functions to suspend the understanding and to make way for an
act of vision” (p. 13). If anything, such a conclusion is likely to contribute to the morass of relativism
that surrounds the presence of Blake in print and in the classroom. Even if we accept that such readings are
part of Blake’s purpose, at least two kinds of inquiry are called for: one into the composite identity of
Blake’s art, ignored here, and a very specific incidence of “vision”; and another (not unrelated) into
the <hi rend="i">narrative</hi> identity of the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, if any. Forms of coherence
obtained by the privileging of luminous aphorisms are no longer enough, even as there is a great deal in
Blake’s writing to encourage such an approach.</p>
          <p>The book’s somewhat military style—the naming of parts that is all too standard as a
dissertation format—and the fact that long and important passages in German are not translated, is not
likely to assist the author in finding a wide audience for his book. But he does demonstrate, once again, that
Friedrich Schlegel is an important figure for the understanding of Romantic theories of meaning and
communication.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
