<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>19.4.butlin</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">Connoisseurship and the Palmer Fakes</title>
        <author n="Butlin">Martin Butlin</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1986</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1986</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">19.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Greg Crossan</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Bo Ossian Lindberg</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>Anne Williams</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1986"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-4-0008">
      	<pb id="p19-155" n="155"/>
        <head>
          <title type="section"><hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">DISCUSSION</hi></hi></title>
          <title type="section-subtitle"><hi rend="i">with intellectual spears &amp; long winged arrows of
thought</hi></title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Connoisseurship and the Palmer Fakes</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Martin <name>Butlin</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Raymond Lister, in his review of publications on Blake and his followers, particularly Samuel
Palmer, in the fall 1985 issue of <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (p. 80), has chosen to repeat his accusation that I
said of Keating’s fake Palmers that there was “a considerable case for their being by the artist.” The
last time he said something of this kind, in his <hi rend="i">The Paintings of Samuel Palmer</hi> (Cambridge
University Press, 1985), he did at least include the vital words, “was reported by <hi rend="i">The
Times</hi> as saying. . . .” This time he merely gives a reference to <hi rend="i">The Times</hi> of 16 July
1976, leaving the reader, by his use of quotation marks, to assume that this is a verbatim transcript of my
own words. He then goes on to assert that this “all goes to show that enthusiasm, even when combined with
academic scholarship, is not always supported by perfect connoisseurship,” a very happy conclusion for an
enthusiastic amateur such as himself. What I did say at the time (and I have no precise recall of my exact
words) came as part of a defense of one of those fooled by what was a deliberate attempt to deceive, by means
of period frames, a backing of old letters, and a false provenance; I am happy to say that the words
attributed to me do not reflect my opinion, then or now, of the actual authenticity of the drawings
themselves. In any case it is a pity that Raymond Lister has to return on two further occasions in the course
of a not very long review to the Keating scandal. This is to give the affair, and the reviewer’s cleverness
in not being taken in, far more attention than they deserve.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
