<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>19.4.groves</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake, Thomas Boston, and the Fourfold Vision</title>
        <author n="Groves">David Groves</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1986</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1986</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">19.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Greg Crossan</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Bo Ossian Lindberg</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>Anne Williams</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1986"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <body>
      <pb id="p19-142" n="142"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-4-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake, Thomas Boston, and the Fourfold Vision</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>David <name>Groves</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The word “fourfold” or “four-fold” appears many times in Blake’s longer poems, and is
clearly one of his favorite expressions. Probably the best-known example occurs in his letter to Thomas Butts:
<q>
Now I a fourfold vision see,<lb/>
And a fourfold vision is given to me;<lb/>
‘Tis fourfold in my supreme delight<lb/>
And threefold in soft Beulah’s night<lb/>
And twofold Always. May God us keep<lb/>
From Single vision &amp; Newton’s sleep!<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">1</hi> William Blake, letter to Butts, 22 Nov. 1802, rpt. in <hi rend="i">The
Letters of William Blake</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes (Cambridge, MA, 1968), pp. 59-63.</note></q>
The word “fourfold” can be found twice in the 1611 Bible and once in <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, but
its frequent use by Blake is very striking. Contemporary readers may have detected an echo of Thomas
Boston’s book <hi rend="i">Human Nature, in its Four-fold State</hi>, a popular work of theology which went
through at least two dozen editions in Britain between 1720 and 1800.</p>
          <p>Thomas Boston was a Presbyterian clergyman until his death in 1732. He tried to modify the
predestinarianism of the Presbyterian Church by proposing that human experience takes place on four distinct
levels. A look at these levels or stages will show that they might well have inspired, obliquely, the
“fourfold vision” of Blake. The first condition is a “State of Innocence, or Primitive Integrity”
which exits only at birth. This is followed by the “State of Nature, or Entire Deprivation,” in which the
“natural man” can “do nothing but sin.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
type="note">2</ref> In the third state “The conscience is renewed” (p. 197), and one apparently
experiences “a <hi rend="i">mysterious</hi> union” (p. 237), a “mystical union betwixt Christ and
Believers” (p. 233). <note id="n10"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Boston, <hi rend="i">Human Nature, in its Four-fold
State; of Primitive Integrity, Entire Deprivation, Begun Recovery, and Consummate Happiness or Misery</hi> . .
. (1720; 15th. ed. rev., Glasgow, 1761), p. 109. The names of Boston’s states are taken from the table of
contents. Subsequent references to this edition are included parenthetically in the text.</note></p>
          <p>The last of Boston’s four stages is entered at death, when the ungodly see “the dark side of
the cloud” while the righteous perceive “the bright side of it, shining on the godly, as they are entering
upon their eternal state” (p. 341). This may perhaps partly explain Blake’s reference, earlier in the poem
cited above, to “my Brother John the evil one / In a black cloud making his mone.”</p>
          <p>It might at first seem unlikely that Blake would have been influenced by a Presbyterian minister.
But Thomas Boston’s literate, allusive, and metaphorical style did indeed appeal to people of imagination.
Another poet, writing in 1832, notes that
<q>
It has been the fashion for a good while past, with a certain class of professed Christians, . . . to sneer at
the doctrines of Boston. I decidedly differ from them, and will venture to assert that there are no such
fervour and strength of reasoning to be met with in any modern composition, as predominate in his. Let any
person take up “The Four-fold State of Man,” and peruse seriously and without prejudice one of the
divisions, or say only twenty pages at random, and he will join with me. There is even an originality of
thought and expression in old Boston which are quite delightful and refreshing.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">3</hi> “Statistics of Selkirkshire, By Mr. James Hogg, ‘the Ettrick
Shepherd,’ ” in <hi rend="i">Prize-Essays and Transactions of the Highland and Agricultural Society of
Scotland</hi> (Edinburgh, 1832), pp. 303-04.</note></q></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
