<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>19.4.crossan</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">“Infant Sorrow” and Robert Greene’s Menaphon</title>
        <author n="Crossan">Greg Crossan</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1986</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1986</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">19.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Greg Crossan</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Bo Ossian Lindberg</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>Anne Williams</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1986"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_19">
    <body>
	<pb id="p19-142" n="142"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-19-4-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">“Infant Sorrow” and Robert Greene’s <hi rend="i">Menaphon</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Greg <name>Crossan</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The origins of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> in
eighteenth-century children’s hymns, nursery rhymes, cradle songs and the like are by now well documented,
but cradle songs in particular were a popular Renaissance genre (the lullabies of Dekker and Gascoigne being
the best known), and there is a source here for one of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, “Infant Sorrow,” that
was suggested long ago by Foster Damon but has never, I think, been explored.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">1</ref> The source is “Sephestias Song to Her Childe” from Robert
Greene’s pastoral romance <hi rend="i">Menaphon.</hi> In particular, the opening lines of Blake’s song,
<q>
My mother groand! my father wept.<lb/>
Into the dangerous world I lept
</q>
recall the opening lines of the last stanza of Greene’s:
<q>
The wanton smilde, father wept;<lb/>
Mother cride, babie lept.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">2</ref></q>
The echo here is plain enough, but I want to suggest that there are two ways in which “Sephestias Song”
makes a particularly interesting context in which to read “Infant Sorrow.” 
<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">1</hi> S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Philosophy and Symbols</hi> (1924; rpt.
Gloucester, Mass.: Peter Smith, 1958), p. 282.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">2</hi> My text is from vol. 6 of <hi rend="i">The Life and Works of Robert
Greene</hi>, ed. A. B. Grosart (1881-86; New York: Russell and Russell, 1964), p. 44. The poem may also be
found in several anthologies, such as <hi rend="i">The Oxford Book of English Verse.</hi></note></p>
          <pb id="p19-143" n="143"/>
          <p>The first is that “Sephestias Song” as a whole lends support to Norman Nathan’s point that
childbirth not only initiates the infant into sorrow but also brings sorrow upon the parents.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">3</ref> The stanza just quoted from, for instance,
continues thus:
<q>
More he crowde, more we cride;<lb/>
Nature could not sorowe hide.<lb/>
He must goe, he must kisse<lb/>
Childe and mother, babie blisse:<lb/>
For he left his pretie boy<lb/>
Fathers sorowe, fathers joy.<lb/>
Weepe not my wanton, smile upon my knee,<lb/>
When thou art olde, ther’s grief inough for thee.
</q>
The last line here, with its warning of what is in store for the child, might almost serve as a motto for the
<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, but it is the father’s sorrow and joy that dominate the poem. In
context, the father’s tears are occasioned by his imminent parting from his son as a result of having been
banished from that archetypal domain of innocence, Arcadia. The family has been cast adrift on a stormy sea,
and it is after surviving a shipwreck that Sephestia sings this song, in which she recalls the joy of her
husband (now presumed drowned) at the birth of a son, and his tears at the prospect of losing him. In short,
the sorrow is as much the father’s as the infant’s. <note id="n14"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Norman Nathan,
“Blake’s ‘Infant Sorrow,’ ” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>, 7 (1960), 99-100.</note></p>
          <p>The second point of contextual interest is that Greene goes on to develop the father’s sorrow
in an unexpected way. By means of various contrivances, Greene has the child (Pleusidippus) grow up to fall in
love with Sephestia (now calling herself Samela) without knowing that she is his mother, and he becomes in due
course a rival of his own father (Maximus,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15"
type="note">4</ref> alias Melicertus), who in fact survived the wreck and has ended up courting Sephestia
without knowing that she is his wife. Greene in his usual fanciful way asks us to accept the proposition that
because Sephestia’s identity is concealed she can find herself being wooed by her husband, her son, and even
her father (Democles) at the same time. Given that commentators now tend to read “Infant Sorrow,” both in
its <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> version and in its longer <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> version,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">5</ref> as a poem which hints at the oedipal conflict
between father and son (“Struggling in my father’s hands”), it is interesting that this is precisely
what <hi rend="i">Menaphon</hi> builds up to as its climax. Father and son angrily confront each other in
single combat, and, in Greene’s phrase, “they fell toughly to blowes.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">6</ref> That fight is eventually stopped by Democles and the two are
imprisoned, but all is at length resolved by the timely intervention of a sibyl. Sephestia is reunited with
her husband, and her son craves “pardon for the fondnesse of his incestuous affection.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">7</ref> He also apologizes to his father, then marries
someone else. <note id="n15"><hi rend="s">4</hi> He is called Maximus at the beginning of the story and
Maximius at the end.</note>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">5</hi> For an oedipal reading of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> version see, most
recently, Diana Hume George, <hi rend="i">Blake and Freud</hi> (Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 1980), pp.
89-90, and of the <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> version, Stewart Crehan, <hi rend="i">Blake in Context</hi>
(Dublin: Gill and Macmillan, 1984), pp. 113-14.</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> Menaphon</hi>, p. 133.</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">7</hi><hi rend="i"> Menaphon</hi>, p. 144.</note></p>
          <p>While it seems certain that Blake knew “Sephestias Song,” it may be that he knew little of
its context: and yet, considering its appropriateness to his own nascent theme in “Infant Sorrow,” we can
perhaps surmise that he sensed in Greene’s lullaby the suggestion of potential oedipal conflict, and carried
that suggestion over into his own song. Greene and Blake make, at first sight, an improbable coupling, but in
the matter of Blake’s sources we are repeatedly, it seems, like Lyca’s parents on finding an angel in the
eyes of a lion, “Filled with deep surprise.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">8</hi> For some other out-of-the-way sources of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>
see especially chapter 2 of John Holloway’s <hi rend="i">Blake: The Lyric Poetry</hi> (London: Edward
Arnold, 1968).</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
