<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>2.1.kostelanetz</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Frederick Cummings and Allen Staley, eds., 
Romantic Art in Britain: Drawings and Paintings 1760-1860</title>
				<author n="Kostelanetz">Anne T. Kostelanetz</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>June 1, 1968</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1968</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">02.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>Anne T. Kostelanetz</name>
                            <name>Karen Walowit</name>
                            <name>Alvin Rosenfeld</name>
                            <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr.</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <authority/>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_02">
        <body>
			<pb id="p02-4" n="4"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-02-1-0003">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">REVIEW</title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="u">Romantic Art in Britain: Drawings and Paintings 1760-1860</hi>,
Exhibition Catalogue ed. by Frederick Cummings and Allen Staley (Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1968)</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Anne T. <name>Kostelanetz</name></docAuthor><lb/>
                        English Department<lb/>
                        Stanford University</byline>
                    <p>Blakists will probably be more impressed by Robert Rosenblum’s single trenchant
paragraph comparing Blake to Jakob Carstens than by Frederick Cummings’ superficial, occasionally erroneous
ten page entry on the Blake paintings and drawings exhibited in Detroit and Philadelphia this winter. In an
introductory essay for this catalogue, “British Art and the Continent, 1760-1860,” Rosenblum first locates
Blake in the eighteenth century school which, having rejected as an impossibility the Academicians’ attempt
to fuse the real and the ideal, turned in the opposite direction from such empiricists as Stubbs and Joseph
Wright toward a wholly non-illusionistic, visionary art. The taste for the “demonic and fantastic,” for “the
extravagantly heroic and sublime,” first advocated by the Runcimans, John Mortimer and Henry Fuseli, among
others, reached a simultaneous culmination in the totally “anti-empirical” art of Blake and Asmus Jakob
Carstens.
<pb id="p02-5" n="5"/>
Although unknown to each other, both Blake and Carstens felt “a compulsive need to invent strange private
cosmologies that could replace stagnant religious beliefs”; both created “a <corr type="emend">Michelangelesque</corr> style of heroic
figures that soared through flattened, abstract spaces”; both were “vehement in their hatred of the academic
art establishment”; and both used drawing, tempera and watercolor to “counter the earthbound illusionism of
the oil medium” (p. 12). Rosenblum thus shows that Blake was not the isolated artistic figure we sometimes
think him; rather, he derives from a specific eighteenth century nonillusionistic tradition which flourished
both in England and on the Continent. Rosenblum develops this idea even further in his doctoral dissertation,
“The International Style of 1800” (New York University, 1956); unfortunately he omitted his most illuminating
analyses of Blake’s art from his published <hi rend="u">Transformations in Late Eighteenth-Century Art</hi>
(Princeton, 1966).</p>
                    <p>Although Frederick Cummings persuasively argues that the chalk drawing we know as a
nude study of Robert Blake is only an academic figural exercise done when Blake was attending the Royal
Academy school under Georg Moser in 1778, he errs in his descriptions of Catalogue Entry 98 (“Illustration to
Milton’s <hi rend="u">Paradise Lost</hi>: The Fall”) and 99 (“Albion Compelling the Four Zoas to Their
Proper Tasks”). Discussing Blake’s Milton illustrations, Cummings unnecessarily confuses us by asserting
that Blake did “three series of illustrations” to <hi rend="u">Paradise Lost</hi> (p. 164). To the two, and
only two, known series of Blake’s <hi rend="u">Paradise Lost</hi> illustrations—the complete twelve
drawing set at the Huntington Library, and the scattered but now complete Butts set at the Boston Museum (nine
drawings), the Huntington Library (“Satan, Sin and Death”), Victoria and Albert Museum (“Satan summons his
Legions”) and Harvard College Library (the recently “rediscovered” White drawing, “So judged he man,”
exhibited here)—Cummings has wrongly added a third set of <hi rend="u">Paradise Lost</hi> illustrations
actually done by Edward Burney and bound into an extra-illustrated edition of <hi rend="u">Paradise Lost</hi>
(London, 1827).</p>
                    <p>Cummings’ identification of the pencil drawing titled “Los kneeling” in Keynes’ 
<hi rend="u">Pencil Drawings, II</hi> as “Albion Compelling the Four Zoas to their Proper Tasks” is highly
dubious. Although I have not had a chance to study the drawing first-hand, the reproductions in Keynes and in
this catalogue depict a kneeling male figure with a sharply pointed spear or arrow in his left hand and the
handle of what Keynes identifies as “(apparently) a sickle,” rather than the bow Cummings sees, in his right
hand. His radiating, spiky hair and the shafts (of light?) he hurls clearly identify him as a personification
of the Sun; in fact he closely resembles the personified Sun on Plate 11 of <hi rend="u">The Marriage of
Heaven and Hell.</hi>
                        <hi rend="u">If</hi> this drawing was originally intended to illustrate Plate 95 of
<hi rend="u">Jerusalem</hi>, as Cummings asserts, it pictures not Albion but “the Sun in heavy
clouds/Struggling to rise above the Mountains. in his burning hand/He takes his Bow, then chooses out his
arrows of flaming gold” (95:11-13). If this figure must be identified with a major character in 
<hi rend="u">Jerusalem</hi>, surely he more closely resembles the youthful Los who is pictured on Plates 6, 95, 97
and 100 than the aged Albion, the white-haired and bearded “Universal Father” (97:6) who appears on Plates 94,
96 and 99.</p>
                    <p>But I question whether Blake ever intended this drawing to illustrate 
<hi rend="u">Jerusalem.</hi> Such an obvious personification of the Sun is more characteristic of Blake’s
illustrations for Young’s <hi rend="u">Night Thoughts</hi> (1797) than for his own late Prophetic Books. The
sharply pointed arrows or spears in this drawing also appear on Pages 7, 8, 13, 57 and 63 of the published 
<hi rend="u">Night Thoughts</hi> engravings; the sensuously full lips are identical with those of
<pb id="p02-6" n="6"/>
the “mighty hunter,” Death, on Page 70 and of the Thunderer on Page 80; the heavy, wavy eyebrows span the brow
of the figure of the Sun on Page 95; and throughout the illustrations, the sickle consistently symbolizes the
destructions of Time. Perhaps this drawing was intended to illustrate a passage from Young, possibly the
passage in <hi rend="u">Night III</hi> in which even the Sun, seeing the dying Narcissa, “(As if the sun could
envy) check’d his beam,/Denied his wonted succor,” and cruelly helped Death seize her. Certainly, the size
of this drawing would make it more suitable for the <hi rend="u">Night Thoughts</hi> edition than for 
<hi rend="u">Jerusalem.</hi> Blake’s drawing measures 12 5/16″ × 9 ⅞″; the <hi rend="u">Jerusalem</hi>
full-plate pages measure only 6 ⅝″ × 8 ¾″ (and this drawing could only have been a half-plate); while
the <hi rend="u">Night Thoughts</hi> pages measure 12 ¼″ × 21 ½″. Blake’s drawing would fit the top
of a <hi rend="u">Night Thoughts</hi> page almost perfectly. Since this drawing, both in style and content, so
closely resembles the <hi rend="u">Night Thoughts</hi> illustrations (both the sketches in the British Museum
and the published engravings), I would hesitate to accept a date as late as Cummings’ “c. 1815-1818.” A much
earlier date, perhaps c. 1795-1797 when Blake was illustrating Young’s poem, seems more probable.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>