<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>2.1.wittreich</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">A Bibliographical Note</title>
				<author n="Wittreich">Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr.</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>June 1, 1968</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1968</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">02.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>Anne T. Kostelanetz</name>
                            <name>Karen Walowit</name>
                            <name>Alvin Rosenfeld</name>
                            <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr.</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <authority/>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_02">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-02-1-0004">
                <pb id="p02-13" n="13"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">4. A Bibliographical Note</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Joseph Anthony <name>Wittreich</name>, Jr.</docAuthor> The University of
Wisconsin</byline>
                    <p>References to Blake in the first half of the nineteenth century are astonishingly few.
Those listed in the Nurmi-Bentley <hi rend="u">Blake Bibliography</hi> typically portray Blake as a “madman”
who excelled as an artist but faltered as a poet. A reference, hitherto unnoticed — “The Poetry of Sacred
and Legendary Art”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="p13u1" type="note">*</ref>—anon. rev.,
<hi rend="u">Blackwood’s Edinburgh Magazine</hi>, LXV (Feb. 1849), 183 — at once reveals the reigning
attitude of the early nineteenth century toward Blake and suggests the direction that subsequent criticism was
to take. The reviewer comments, “There is greatness in the simplicity of Blake’s angels: ‘The morning
stars sang together, and all the sons of God shouted for joy.’<supplied type="emend">”</supplied> 
Apparently this remark was inspired by Mrs.
Jameson’s statement: “The most original, and, in truth, the only new and original version of the Scripture
idea of angels which I met with, is that of William Blake, a poet painter, somewhat mad as we are told, if
indeed his manners were not rather ‘the telescope of truth,’ a sort of poetical 
<hi rend="u">clairvoyance</hi>, bringing the unearthly nearer to him than to others. His adoring angels float
rather than fly, and, with their half-liquid draperies, seem to dissolve into light and love: and his
rejoicing angels — behold them — sending up their voices with the morning stars, that ‘singing in their
glory move’” (I, 80; the quotation is from <hi rend="u">Lycidas</hi>, 1. 180). <note id="p13u1">*Reviewing a
book of the same title by Mrs. [Anna Brownell Murphy] Jameson (1848). Immensely popular, this book went
through many editions until it was edited and enlarged by Estelle M. Hurll, <hi rend="u">Sacred and Legendary
Art by Anna Jameson</hi>, 2 vols. (Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company, 1895).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>The context in which the reviewer’s remark appears is perhaps of special
significance. Blake is mentioned among those artists who skillfully combine poetry with painting, using the
former to enliven and
<pb id="p02-14" n="14"/>
illumine the latter; among those artists who, working with the sublimest materials, prove that Christian art
may rival, indeed surpass, that of the ancients. Still more important is the fact that the reviewer points to
Blake in a passage discussing the emergence of a new Christian art imbued with an iconoclastic spirit.</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>