<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>2.2.erdman</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="query">Revising Blake: Prophet for a new edition</title>
				<author n="Erdman">David V. Erdman</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>September 15, 1968</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1968</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">02.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr.</name>
                            <name>W.E. Moss</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1968"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_02">
        <body>
            <pb id="p02-24" n="24"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-02-2-0004">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="u">QUERIES</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">1. David V. Erdman, revising <hi rend="u">Blake: Prophet</hi> for a
new edition, writes:</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>
                        <hi rend="u">Is</hi> the swimmer at the bottom of <hi rend="u">J</hi>.11 “a
resplendent American Indian”? (p. 445)</p>
                    <p>Has anyone in the 20th century seen Paine’s face in the “Spiritual form of Pitt”? Cp.
416)</p>
                    <p>Is “Tyburns Brook” the same as “Tyburns River”; and is it the Serpentine River; or is
one that and the other not that? Damon’s <hi rend="u">Dictionary</hi> under TYBURN has a brook flowing like
a uroboros: crossing “Oxford Street a little to the east of the present Marble Arch,” then flowing “through
St. James’s Park” (a mile away!) and “then plung[ing] underground at the intersection of Stratford Place and
South Molton Street” (i.e. a little to the east of Marble Arch, said intersection being at or with Oxford
Street): the brook’s mouth then swallowing its tail. (pp. 429-430; 368)</p>
                    <p>On pp. 446-447, after saying that at the end of chapter three of 
<hi rend="u">Jerusalem</hi> “Blake sees ‘the youthful form of Erin’ arising, ‘a Feminine Form . . .
Beautiful but terrible struggling to take a form of beauty’ (<hi rend="u">J.</hi>74),” I am tempted to
add—for people (like myself) who like a hint of prophetic influence now and then—: “a century later
Blake’s son Yeats will see the terrible beauty born.”</p>
                    <p>Is there any evidence that Blake was aware, when he lamented his friend Fuseli’s
being “hid” from/by the royal and noble patrons of art (p. 406), that the wealthiest banker in England, Thomas
Coutts, had patronized Fuseli from the beginning, bought most of his works, and continued to encourage his
elitism? (See Frederick Antal, <hi rend="u">Fuseli Studies</hi>, 1956, pp. 79-80 &amp; notes) That “Fuseli
certainly knew how to treat rich clients”?</p>
                    <p>An unverifiable hypothesis about THEL: In dates of etching (and presumably of
composition) the last plate and the Motto are quite certainly of a later time than the rest of the poem. The
last plate must have replaced an earlier plate or plates, something hardly to have been undertaken unless some
important change was involved. Question: What was the original THEL like, i.e. how did it end? Mightn’t it
have been an “Innocence” version, the new ending producing an “Experience” version—and the Motto made for
the latter? Obviously Blake felt that the patch worked, that the changed poem had its own unity, or sufficient
to be worth saving the copper and labor of thorough revision. But doesn’t this hypothesis account for the
reader’s difficulty—and help him over it by suggesting that when he reads the last page he must look back
and alter his view of the preceding pages?</p>
                    <p>MHH: Is “Enough! or Too much” a final proverb by the Devil—or the poet’s intrusion?
Both?</p>
                    <p>In note 14, p. 407, I dismiss the John Sartain account of the Cromek-Sartain affair
with the point that Sartain “has Henry Richter become Stothard’s pupil about two decades later (1807) than
he actually did.” But Damon, in his recent <hi rend="u">Blake’s Grave</hi> (p. [3] of introduction), treats
Sartain’s as the true
<pb id="p02-25" n="25"/>
“inside story” and has it that Richter was refused as Stothard’s pupil. Does anyone know how to untangle
this?</p>
                    <byline>(The New York Public Library Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street New York City, New
York)</byline>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>