<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>2.2.paley</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">David V. Erdman, ed., et al., A Concordance to 
the Writings of William Blake</title>
				<author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>September 15, 1968</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1968</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">02.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr.</name>
                            <name>W.E. Moss</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1968"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_02">
        <body>
            <pb id="p02-33" n="33"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-02-2-0006">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="u">REVIEW</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <head>
					<title type="main"><hi rend="u">A Concordance to the Writings of William Blake</hi>, ed. by David V.
Erdman, with the assistance of John E. Thiesmeyer and Richard J. Wolfe; also G.E. Bentley, Jr., Palmer Brown,
Robert F. Gleckner, George Mills Harper, Karl Kiralis, Martin K. Nurmi, and Paul M. Zall. Cornell University
Press, 2 vols., 2317 pp., $25.00.</title>
				</head>
                <p>A concordance is something we take for granted, as our students do “The Dictionary.” Yet up
to now, we have lived without a Blake concordance. The closest things to it has been the Index volume of Sloss
and Wallis’ <hi rend="u">Prophetic Writings</hi>, useful at times but having no claim to completeness and
inadequate to the needs of contemporary Blake scholarship. A modern <hi rend="u">Concordance</hi> has at last
been published, with implications for the study of Blake that we can only begin to glimpse now.</p>
                <p>First, a few facts. The <hi rend="u">Concordance</hi> is one of those produced at Cornell
under the general editorship of S.M. Parrish. These are computer-made concordances, with the entries printed
as reduced-size IBM printout. In order to produce a text for keypunching, it was virtually necessary to
re-edit Blake, and as a result Mr. Erdman’s edition of <hi rend="u">The Poetry and Prose</hi> was produced.
The <hi rend="u">Concordance</hi>, however is keyed to the pagination and line numbering of the Keynes
editions of 1957 and 1966. In addition to the concordance proper, there are 72 pages of corrections and
additions to the Keynes text, and there is a 62-page grouped-frequency word list. A short preface by Mr.
Erdman includes some suggestions as to the significance of the <hi rend="u">Concordance</hi> for future
scholarship.</p>
                <p>One of the immediate applications of the Concordance will no doubt be to the study of
Blake’s vocabulary and its development. One is struck, for example, by the startling growth of Blake’s
“technical” language. Spectre, for example, appears only twice before<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n6" type="note">1</ref>
                    <hi rend="u">The Four Zoas</hi>, 179 times in and after it (not counting possessives and
plurals). Selfhood does not occur before <hi rend="u">Milton.</hi> Imagination is used 29 times in verse and,
interestingly, 57 times in prose; only one of these comes before the letter to Dr. Trusler in 1799. Jerusalem,
with a surprising 222 verse occurrences, is found only three times before <hi rend="u">The Four Zoas.</hi>
Blake’s most frequent noun<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">2</ref> turns out
to be neither day (225 occurrences, the same as Enitharmon) nor night (356) but Los (512)! However, Albion and
Albion’s have a sum total of 669 verse occurrences. 
                    <note id="n6">
                        <hi rend="s">1</hi> Considering the existing problems of chronology, one must of
course use “before” and “after” advisedly.</note>
                    <note id="n7">
                        <hi rend="s">2</hi> The most frequent word, after exclusions, in all (1007) is its
several grammatical functions.</note>
                </p>
                <p>The <hi rend="u">Concordance</hi> is full of implications for Blakean chronology. A
suggestion made in the editor’s preface, that “Vocabulary changes . . . would appear to support the
hypothesis that Night VII was written later than VIIb,” deserves to be pursued, for a start. Another
suggestive area of study is the relationship of Blake’s vocabulary to that of his contemporaries, a subject
on which nothing seems to have been done since Josephine Miles’ <hi rend="u">Eras and Modes in English
Poetry.</hi> Many other values of the <hi rend="u">Concordance</hi> have, I suspect, yet to occur to us. As
Professor Miles remarked in her review of the first two Cornell concordances, “The future opens many more
possible lines of inquiry about poetry, because the speed and accuracy of complex tabulations will prepare for
the asking of new questions in the giving of more and more new answers.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">3</ref>
                    <note id="n8">
                        <hi rend="s">3</hi>
                        <hi rend="u"> Victorian Studies</hi>, VIII (1965), 292.</note>
                </p>
                <byline>
                    <docAuthor>MDP</docAuthor>
                </byline>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>