<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>2.2.news</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">Publications, periodicals, and exhibitions</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>September 15, 1968</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1968</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">02.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr.</name>
                            <name>W.E. Moss</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1968"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_02">
        <body>
            <pb id="p02-16" n="16"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-02-2-0002">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="u">NEWS</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <p>The 1964 volume of <hi rend="u">The Library</hi>, with David V. Erdman’s article “The
Binding (et cetera) of <hi rend="u">Vala</hi>,” has at last been published.</p>
                <p>Sir Geoffrey Keynes’ new edition of <hi rend="u">Blake’s Letters</hi> will be published
by Rupert Hart-Davis Ltd. on September 16.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="u">Energy and the Imagination: a Study of the Development of Blake’s
Thought</hi> by Morton D. Paley is scheduled for publication by The Clarendon Press in 1969.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="u">Burke Newsletter</hi> has become <hi rend="u">Studies in Burke and His
Time</hi>, published three times yearly by Alfred University, Alfred, N.Y. 14802.</p>
                <p>We expect to run a report on the English Institute (Sept. 3-5) in the winter 
<hi rend="u">Newsletter.</hi> Scheduled Blake papers are: “Apprenticeship in the Haymarket?” by Martha Winburn
England; “Metamorphoses of a Favorite Cat” by Irene Tayler; and “<hi rend="u">America</hi>: New Expanses” by
David V. Erdman. The winner of the essay prize has not yet been announced.</p>
                <p>The Blake holdings of the British Museum Print Room are at present in the Museum Bindery
for mounting and new binding. They will be available for visitors by November 1968.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="u">Blake Studies</hi> (University of Tulsa, Tulsa, Okla. 74104) announces that
its first issue, scheduled for this coming fall, contains articles by E.J. Rose, Karl Kiralis, and Clyde
Taylor; notes by Ruthven Todd and Joseph Wittreich; a short story by Winston Weathers; book reviews by Desiree
Hirst, and abstracts of two new dissertations.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="u">Johnsonian News Letter</hi> is sponsoring a listing of 18th-century work
in progress. A survey form is included in the March 1968 issue; the list will be published in fall 1968. (610
Philosophy Hall, Columbia University, New York, N.Y. 10027).</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>