<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>2.2.toc</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="toc">Contents</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>September 15, 1968</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1968</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">02.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr.</name>
                            <name>W.E. Moss</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1968"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_02">
        <front>
            <pb id="p02-15" n="15"/>
            <div1 id="cover">
                <figure n="cover.002.02.bqscan" rend="file" width="258" height="332">
                    <figTranscr>Blake Newsletter<lb/>
                        Volume II, Number 2<lb/>
                        Whole #6<lb/>
                        September 15, 1968<lb/>
                        <hi rend="u">BUSINESS</hi><lb/>
                        Many subscriptions expired with <hi rend="u">Newsletter</hi> 4, and we have had to
bill quite<lb/>
                        a few readers who, as contributors of material or colleagues to whom we owe<lb/>
                        scholarly favors, we’d much rather send complimentary copies.  The response to<lb/>
                        our dunning notice has been gratifying, indicating that our readers understand<lb/>
                        the need for their support.  It was not necessary to raise the price of sub-<lb/>
                        scriptions, except for overseas subscribers who wish air delivery.<lb/>
                        The supply of back copies is just about exhausted. We are now investigating<lb/>
                        the possibility of producing an offset edition of volume 1 for those newer sub-<lb/>
                        scribers who did not receive it.  There is also a chance that increasing demand<lb/>
                        for the <hi rend="u">Newsletter</hi> will mean going offset in the future.<lb/>
                        For volume II, we have received some support from the University of Cali-<lb/>
                        fornia, providing eidotiral assistance; and the English Department office staff<lb/>
                        has taken over the task of production.  Our existence for the present academic<lb/>
                        year is therefore assured, but after the University grant expires in June we<lb/>
                        will probably have to find some other source of aid.  This will almost certainly<lb/>
                        be true if we begin offset production.  Suggestions from readers are welcome.<lb/>
                        With this issue, you will receive an index to volume I, which Mr. Ruthven<lb/>
                        Todd has kindly prepared.  Volume II, in response to requests from readers, is<lb/>
                        being paginated continuously rather than by separate numbers.  For the informa-<lb/>
                        tion of those who want to keep their BNL’s in binders, we have found the kind<lb/>
                        called “Accogrip” useful.<lb/>
                        The BLAKE NEWSLETTER is edited by Morton D. Paley, Department of English,<lb/>
                        University of California, Berkeley California  94720.  Subscription price:<lb/>
                        $2.00 for one year; overseas subscribers who wish delivery by air, please add<lb/>
                        one dollar.  Please make checks or money orders payable to Morton D. Paley.<lb/>
                        Residents of Britain may pay by Postal Money Order for 16/9 (£1 10s by air)<lb/>
                        if the money order is <hi rend="u">open</hi> and <hi rend="u">uncrossed</hi>.<lb/>
                        Copyright 1968 by Morton D. Paley</figTranscr>
                </figure>
            </div1>
			<div1 id="BQ-02-2-0000">
					<supplied type="emend" rend="plain">
						<table id="contents" rows="17" cols="2">
						  <row>
							<cell><head><title><supplied type="emend">Contents</supplied></title></head></cell>
							<cell/>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><hi rend="b">News</hi></cell>
							<cell/>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><ref type="article" issue="2.2.news">Publications, periodicals, and exhibitions</ref></cell>
							<cell>16</cell>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><ref type="article" issue="2.2.checklist">Additions to the Checklist of Blake
Publications</ref><lb/>
							<hi rend="i">with thanks to David V. Erdman, Charles Ryskamp, Roger R. Easson</hi></cell>
							<cell>16</cell>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><hi rend="b">Notes</hi></cell>
							<cell/>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><ref type="article" issue="2.2.wittreich">1. A Note on Blake and Milton</ref><lb/>
							<hi rend="i">Joseph Anthony Wittreich, Jr.</hi></cell>
							<cell>17</cell>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><ref type="article" issue="2.2.moss">2. The Coloured Copies of Blake’s “Night
Thoughts”</ref><lb/>
							<hi rend="i">W.E. Moss</hi></cell>
							<cell>19</cell>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><hi rend="b">Queries</hi></cell>
							<cell/>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><ref type="article" issue="2.2.erdman">1. Revising <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet</hi> for a new
edition</ref><lb/>
							<hi rend="i">David V. Erdman</hi></cell>
							<cell>24</cell>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><ref type="article" issue="2.2.todd">2. Revising edition of Gilchrist’s 
<hi rend="i">Life</hi></ref><lb/>
							<hi rend="i">Ruthven Todd</hi></cell>
							<cell>25</cell>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><hi rend="b">Discussion</hi><lb/>
							<hi rend="b">“With Intellectual spears, &amp; long winged arrows of thought”</hi></cell>
							<cell/>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><ref type="article" issue="2.2.grant">Mother of Invention, Father In Drag</ref><lb/>
							<hi rend="i">John E. Grant</hi></cell>
							<cell>29</cell>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><hi rend="b">Review</hi></cell>
							<cell/>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><ref type="article" issue="2.2.paley"><hi rend="i">A Concordance to the Writings of William
Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman et al.</ref><lb/>
							<hi rend="i">reviewed by Morton D. Paley</hi></cell>
							<cell>33</cell>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><ref type="article" issue="2.2.butlin">Note regarding the review of <hi rend="i">Romantic Art in
Britain</hi></ref><lb/>
							<hi rend="i">Martin Butlin</hi></cell>
							<cell>34</cell>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><hi rend="b">Poem</hi></cell>
							<cell/>
						  </row>
						  <row>
							<cell><ref type="article" issue="2.2.stevenson">Are there fairies still in London?</ref><lb/>
							<hi rend="i">Warren Stevenson</hi></cell>
							<cell>34</cell>
						  </row>
						</table>
					</supplied>
			</div1>
            <div1 id="BQ-02-2-0001">
                <head>
                    <title>
                        <hi rend="u">BUSINESS</hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <p>Many subscriptions expired with <hi rend="u">Newsletter</hi> 4, and we have had to bill
quite a few readers who, as contributors of material or colleagues to whom we owe scholarly favors, we’d
much rather send complimentary copies. The response to our dunning notice has been gratifying, indicating that
our readers understand the need for their support. It was not necessary to raise the price of subscriptions,
except for overseas subscribers who wish air delivery.</p>
                <p>The supply of back copies is just about exhausted. We are now investigating the possibility
of producing an offset edition of volume I for those newer subscribers who did not receive it. There is also a
chance that increasing demand for the <hi rend="u">Newsletter</hi> will mean going offset in the future.</p>
                <p>For volume II, we have received some support from the University of California, providing
editorial assistance; and the English Department office staff has taken over the task of production. Our
existence for the present academic year is therefore assured, but after the University grant expires in June
we will probably have to find some other source of aid. This will almost certainly be true if we begin offset
production. Suggestions from readers are welcome.</p>
                <p>With this issue, you will receive an index to volume I, which Mr. Ruthven Todd has kindly
prepared. Volume II, in response to requests from readers, is being paginated continuously rather than by
separate numbers. For the information of those who want to keep their BNL’s in binders, we have found the
kind called “Accogrip” useful. <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">The BLAKE NEWSLETTER is edited by
Morton D. Paley, Department of English, University of California, Berkeley California 94720. Subscription
price: $2.00 for one year; overseas subscribers who wish delivery by air, please add one dollar. Please make
checks or money orders payable to Morton D. Paley. Residents of Britain may pay by Postal Money Order for 16/9
(£1 10s by air) if the money order is <hi rend="u">open</hi> and <hi rend="u">uncrossed.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <note type="unreferenced" place="footer">Copyright 1968 by Morton D. Paley</note>
                </p>
            </div1>
		</front>
		<body>
            <pb id="p02-34" n="34"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-02-2-0007">
                <p>The winter <hi rend="u">Newsletter</hi> will be published on December 15, 1968. Deadline
for news copy is December 1.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>