<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>2.3.butlin</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="note">William Rossetti’s Annotations to Gilchrist’s Life of William
Blake</title>
				<author n="Butlin">Martin Butlin</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>December 15, 1968</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1968</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">02.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>John Buck</name>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Frederic Cummings</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>John E. Grant</name>
                            <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1968"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_02">
        <body>
            <pb id="p02-39" n="39"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-02-3-0003">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="i">
                            <hi rend="u">NOTES</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">1. William Rossetti’s Annotations to Gilchrist’s 
<hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Martin <name>Butlin</name></docAuthor><lb/>
                        Tate Gallery</byline>
                    <p>Some Blake scholars may not know of the copy of the first, 1863 edition of
Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> containing annotations by William Rossetti. This is now
in the Houghton Library, Harvard University, where I examined it in the summer of 1966. It bears William
Rossetti’s name on the short title-page and also the inscription “Handed over to Olive/W.M.R./Septr. 1908,”
which presumably refers to his daughter Mrs. Olive Rossetti Agresti.</p>
                    <p>Most of the annotations were made to William Rossetti’s own lists of Blake’s works
in the second volume. There are some corrections, for instance regarding the duplication of certain works in
the 1863 lists. References are inserted to pictures in the sale of George Blamire, deceased, at Christie’s
on 7th and 9th November 1863 (which included “The Black Madonna” now in the collection of Mr. and Mrs. Paul
Mellon), and to works in the Aspland and H.A. Bright collections which were unknown to Rossetti when he
compiled his lists. Some changes of ownership and two cases of cracked surfaces being repaired are noted and a
few dates changed or inserted. Most valuable of all are two references to “Mr. Chase” which, as my colleague
Leslie Parris will show in a forthcoming note,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n0"
type="note">*</ref> help in establishing the identity of a patron who commissioned a number of works from
Blake surpassed in importance only by those executed for Thomas Butts and John Linnell.</p>
                    <p>Rossetti’s notes also identify the <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> drawings, listed as “of
uncertain subject” in the 1863 edition, and there are one or two annotations to Gilchrist’s text in the
first volume. It is difficult to date the notes precisely; indeed, they may have been done over a number of
years, as is suggested by the references to both Chase and Aspland alongside the same items. One change of
ownership, of List 1 no. 133 from “Mr. Strange” to “Mr. Scott,” gives a terminus ante quem for this annotation
of 1876, when William Bell Scott lent the work concerned to the Burlington Fine Arts Club exhibition. The
references to Mr. Chase were almost certainly done before 1872 when the watercolours were sold anonymously at
Sotheby’s while those to Aspland must follow this date, when they apply to the works in that sale.</p>
                    <p>The additional entries, corrections and dates, notes of condition and so on were
incorporated in the revised lists included in the 1880 edition of Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life.</hi> The
fresh information about ownership, on the other hand, was not. In fact the revised lists are less informative
in this respect than those of 1863, only the works from the collections of Butts and Linnell being so noted.
Doubtless William Rossetti found the task of keeping up with the increasingly frequent changes of ownership
difficult; the present writer can sympathize.</p>
                    <p>May I take this opportunity of appealing for help over an untraced catalogue for a sale
of works from the Butts collection? This included a number of illustrations to the Apocalypse which appear in
Rossetti’s list with the note
<pb id="p02-40" n="40"/>
“Described in the Sale-catalogue as ‘very fine’,” “ . . . ‘very powerful and characteristic’,” “ . . .
‘of grand conception and highly characteristic’,” and so on. Although I have traced sales from the Butts
collection at Sotheby’s on the 26th March 1852, and at Foster’s on the 29th June 1853 and again on 8th
March 1854 (omitting sales later than 1863) none of them includes these works or these descriptions. Nor are
they to be found in the Joseph Hogarth sale at Southgate’s on 7th to 23rd June 1854 or the anonymous
Frederick Tatham sale at Sotheby’s on 29th April 1862. Any help in tracing this catalogue will be greatly
appreciated.</p>
<pb id="p02-48" n="48" rend="hidden"/>
<note id="n0">Note:<gap type="emend"/> “William Blake’s Mr. Thomas” by Leslie Parris has now been
published in the <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> for 5 Dec. 1968, p. 1390.</note>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>