<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>2.3.grant</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="discussion">Mothers and Methodology</title>
				<author n="Grant">John E. Grant</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>December 15, 1968</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1968</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">02.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>John Buck</name>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Frederic Cummings</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>John E. Grant</name>
                            <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1968"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_02">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-02-3-0004">
                <pb id="p02-50" n="50"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">3. Mothers and Methodology 
(<ref type="article" issue="2.2.grant">continued from <hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> 6</ref>)</title>
                    </head>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>John E. <name>Grant</name></docAuthor><lb/>
                        Department of English<lb/>
                        University of Iowa</byline>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title>II</title>
                        </head>
                        <p>In an earlier statement I argued that the only possible principle for the
interpreter of Blake is that every version of Blake’s illuminated pages has independent authority.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">3</ref> That is, if a figure appears to be thus and so
in one copy and something else in another we are not justified in adding them up, dividing by two, and then
telling the world that the golden mean is what Blake really intended. Blake himself was out of all patience
with devotees of the general idea and alternately begged and commanded the reader to attend to “minute
particulars.” For the man with a different creed, Blake’s dictum that only through the minute particulars
can virtue or beauty be approached has no authority. Even if, it can be argued, Blake himself tried to live up
to his principles, the critic has merely to invoke the Intentional Fallacy in order to obtain a license to
take whatever pleases him from what Blake has left us. 
                            <note id="n16">
                                <hi rend="s">3</hi> See John E. Grant, “Tense and the Sense of Blake’s
‘The Tyger’” (A Controversy), <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi> LXXXI (1966), Section 111, p. 601.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>It may seem unlikely that anyone would wish to take such an extreme position in
public but this is essentially what Professor W. K. Wimsatt said in the Forum II conference, entitled
Literature and the Visual Arts: The Problem of Critical Terms, at the 1967 MLA Annual Meeting. In a paper
entitled “Laokoön Revisited” he declared that the pictures for “The Tyger” and “London” were obviously
failures and irrelevant besides. Curiously enough, one of the discussants, Professor Jean Hagstrum,
remonstrated with Wimsatt because of his principled indifference to Blake’s union of the arts, but Hagstrum
was unwilling to challenge Wimsatt’s inaccurate description of Blake’s picture of the Tyger. To be sure it
was not easy for Hagstrum to do so because Wimsatt quoted Hagstrum’s book which declares that “the
magnificent verbal ‘Tyger’ is unworthily illustrated by a simpering animal” (p. 86). I found Hagstrum’s
refusal distressing because in my review of his book I had particularly commented on this point reminding him
that the allegation is false—at least as a generalization—and pointing out that it also plays into the
hands of dogmatic divorcers of the arts such as Warren and Wellek.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n17" type="note">4</ref> Yet if one tacitly admits such allegations against Blake’s design he cannot
hope to prevail in arguments on this subject. 
                            <note id="n17">
                                <hi rend="s">4</hi> In <hi rend="i">JAAC</hi> xxiv, No. 1, Pt. 1 (1965), 127.
Now that Copy U, which contains the most formidable Tyger I have seen, is publicly more accessible, in the
Firestone Library at Princeton (see <hi rend="i">Newsletter</hi> 3, pp. 6-7), the existence of an heroic Tyger
should be easier to prove.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>While he did not condescend to mention the names of the offending scholars, Wimsatt
was very polemical in insisting that attempts to establish contrapuntal relationships between Blake’s poems
and designs must be ruled out of court. He was willing to tolerate some cases like “Infant Joy” (evidently
because of the slightness of the poem) where poem and design are obviously antithetical, but he had no mercy
on “London,” which seemed to him downright incoherent when judged as a marriage of graphics and poetry.
Because of the intransigence with which Wimsatt resists recognizing unequal unions of the arts, it would
probably have been impossible to persuade him that the concurrence of poetry and picture in “London” is not
fortuitous or inartistic. And in this case, as opposed to “The Tyger,” no thorough attempt has been made in
print to justify this design. If one chose he could begin such an apologia by combining brief comments in
Hirsch’s book and in one of my reviews,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">5</ref> but this task remains unattempted. Clearly, however, and this is the immediate point of
relationship between the
<pb id="p02-51" n="51"/>
interpretational problem in “London” and LBI and F, the designs for <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> usually contain
one or more pictorial elements that have no verbal correlatives in the poems. In a strict sense of the word
Blake so rarely attempted literally to <hi rend="u">illustrate</hi> the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, that is,
depict only objects mentioned in the poems without making suggestive additions, that scholars should be
vigilant for significant differences even when there is a fairly close correspondence. Until more of these
crucial problems in Blakean iconography have been studied, however, anti-Blakean opinions about Blake will
doubtless remain current. 
                            <note id="n18">
                                <hi rend="s">5</hi>
                                <hi rend="i"> Innocence and Experience: An Introduction to Blake</hi>, (New
Haven, 1964), p. 265 and Grant, “The Colors of Prophecy,” <hi rend="i">The Nation</hi>, CC (January 25, 1965),
p. 92.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Let us consider again the fact, first remarked by Connolly and Levine, that the
guide in LBF is often effeminate-looking and sometimes distinctly busty. When it is admitted that the figure
in the margin undoubtedly is the mother described in the poem, the adult guide, who is always clothed in
white, can be none other than “God ever nigh” who “appeard like his father in white.” The interpretational
problem, as posed by Connolly and Levine in their original article, was put backward and thus became the
source of much confusion; it is not a question of why the mother looks like Christ but why God sometimes looks
maternal. That is; what point is made when God is depicted as having feminine attributes, especially when the
poem says that he appears as a father? Connolly and Levine can apparently think of nothing more reputable than
“vaudeville” where matters of role playing are involved, but all Blake’s theology is radically based on the
relativity of perception, e.g., “The Vision of Christ that thou dost see / Is my Vision’s Greatest Enemy. .
. .” Certainly an essential part of Blake’s interpretation of the Book of Job is that God looks like Job. It
is not culpable pride but the beginning of wisdom to recognize that God “becomes as we are, that we may become
as he is.”</p>
                        <p>I do not believe that the further suggestions I shall make here constitute a
significant change from what I have written before, but the depiction of God with female attributes does
entail more explanation. In my piece, “Recognizing Fathers,” I argued essentially that, <hi rend="u">from the
Little Boy’s point of view</hi>, the father imago presented in every version of the design must be
sufficiently credible, just as the poem says it is. But in those copies of the design where the guide is
busty, there is undeniably something more to explain. Elsewhere in <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> God
does appear as a paternal shepherd, or as a child, or as a lamb, but God the mother (as distinguished from the
Mother of God) is a conception that would not have made Blake’s contemporaries feel easy. And of course
Blake himself had a profound mistrust of the Female Will, which is expressed over and over in the prophecies
and is summed up in the tyranny of Mary, which is depicted in plate 99 of the illustrations to the 
<hi rend="i">Divine Comedy.</hi> Nevertheless Blake would have strenuously resisted the kind of presumptuous
superstition which pretends to know that God “is really” either a male or a female.</p>
                        <p>Keynes puts the matter succinctly in his commentary for the photographic edition of
the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> when he declares that “probably [the rescuer] is one of Blake’s not infrequent
androgynous figures, having both mother and father attributes.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n19" type="note">6</ref> In spite of the impropriety Connolly and Levine warned me would be involved
in doing so, I thought it would not be indecent if I troubled to examine the breasts of God, as Blake chose to
represent God. After all, Connolly and Levine wouldn’t admit the authority of Schiavonetti’s busty
rendering of Blake’s Jesus to which I had referred them. I must report that a quick survey through 
<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Bible</hi> revealed no pictures of either the Father or the
Son that are as pendulous as some versions of the guide in LBF. Only in six pictures, nos. 76, Christ Girding
Himself (see the reproduction in <hi rend="i">The Blake Collection of W. Graham Robertson</hi>, pl. 38); 110,
The Third Temptation;
<pb id="p02-52" n="52"/>
119, The Transfiguration; 122, Christ Blessing the Little Children; 125, The Raising of Lazarus; and 171,
Christ the Mediator, does He seem notably effeminate and in all these pictures of His maturity Christ wears a
beard. This lack of confirmation does not, however, subvert the specific evidence in LBF. Indeed, though it
would be dangerous to attempt this form of argument if there were no other evidence, Blake often tried his
daring ideas only once or rarely; precisely because he establishes iconographic norms, striking departures
from them are strong evidence of allegorical meaning. Just as it can have been no accident that Blake once
painted the “Sick Rose” white rather than Red, so he had a point to make when he painted a Black Madonna (no.
98)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">7</ref> near the end of his life. It is
quite probable that he also chose to produce a single indubitably busty guide in LBF because (so to speak) the
Diana of Ephesus had been lost sight of at the time. 
                            <note id="n19">
                                <hi rend="s">6</hi> Mr. Tolley reminds me that the clearest example of
androgyny in <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> is the main figure in the tailpiece design, Pl. a, which is reproduced in
Wicksteed.</note>
                            <note id="n20">
                                <hi rend="s">7</hi> I have heard it alleged that the negroid coloration in
this picture is the accidental result of the deterioration of the tempera. After having studied it quite
closely twice I doubt that the allegation is correct. But if there is any evidence of accident having produced
design this should be presented where all can read it.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>If we make a serious attempt to interpret LBF as a design in context, both of the
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and of Blake’s work as a whole a number of factors not previously considered must be
born in mind. Several critics have observed that distinctly paternal roles are disfavored in 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, but the designs are not anti-paternal more than twice. So far as pictures
are concerned, the masculine leadership role seems to be enacted in <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> in the
following plates: 7, 10, 12, 14, 18, 19, 26. To this one might add: 5, 8, 23, and possibly 54, “The Voice of
the Ancient Bard,” which was at first included in <hi rend="i">Innocence.</hi> In plates 12 and 19 the male
guide is less authoritative or less human than he seems, but he is a benign presence elsewhere. In pl. 7, the
second of “The Ecchoing Green,” the guide is not really in charge because the gift of the grapes of pleasure
behind his back unmistakably reveals him to be Mr. Parental Spoilsport, rather than a good guide. In 10 the
Good Shepherd or Jesus (who is sometimes depicted as being almost without beard) suffers little children to
come unto him—beside the waters (of Life), which are uniquely depicted on the original plate of this
design.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">8</ref> In 12 the “Angel with a
bright key” has, in late versions, a halo, but no wings. Comparison with the water color drawing “The Woman
Taken In Adultery” will show that the liberating “Angel” is almost identical, though reversed, with Jesus in
the drawing. The Innocent but benighted Chimney Sweeper did not recognize Jesus when he saw Him, but the
reader of Blake will recall the first picture of <hi rend="i">Blair’s Grave</hi>, entitled “Christ
Descending Into the Grave,” because there the Savior carries a key in each hand. I referred to this design for
Blair in my earlier article on “Recognizing Fathers” (pp. 8-9) because the posture of Christ is very similar
to that of the boy’s savior in LBF. I shall also mention some other designs related to pl. 14 but must first
consider the other three designs in <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> that depict masculine authority. In 18, “The
Divine Image,” at the bottom, Jesus, who is duly haloed in late copies, evidently raises Adam (who is shown
under the flames of wrath in the general title page of the combined anthology, pl. 1) in a gesture that
recalls Michelangelo’s version of his Creation and anticipates Blake’s own later depiction of Jesus in
“The Creation of Eve” in the designs for <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi> The same motif occurs, with greater
modification, in the second of the two versions of the Genesis frontispiece in the Huntington Library. The
beadles regimenting the boys and girls in 19, “Holy Thursday,” are, of course, trying to contain the work of
Christ the Liberator. Finally, in 26, “A Dream,” the glow-worm who impersonates the watchman of the night, is
shown in his human form as he redirects the errant mother Emmet. 
                            <note id="n21">
                                <hi rend="s">8</hi> In contrast with places 4, 7, 8, 20, and 21 where a small
strip was added to the plate and the area was painted as water. In later copies of plates 12 and 23
indications of water are added in paint but the plates themselves were not similarly enlarged.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>In Blake’s work as a whole it is not inappropriate to ask what happens to the
Little Boy who was Found and returned to his Mother by an androgyne who resembles Christ and the Boy’s
father as he imagined him.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">9</ref> We can say
that the
<pb id="p02-53" n="53"/>
Boy, together with his archetypal sister who is not mentioned in this pair of poems, may be observed in such a
tempera painting as “Bathsheba at the Bath” (Tate #22) in company with his mother. But insofar as the Boy and
girl are always small they remain in the keeping of the Good Father, as shown in the tempera painting “Christ
Blessing Little Children” (Tate #23) where Jesus sits under the same kind of tree depicted in 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> 6, the first plate of “The Ecchoing Green,” and in the background of 8, “The Lamb.” In
this tempera one should notice the river in the background and also observe the motif of the intertwined trees
in the left background.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">10</ref>
                            <note id="n22">
                                <hi rend="s">9</hi> In Blake’s cosmic myth we can also ask how it is that
one can get lost in spite of essential innocence. Here the final design of the <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>
series, “The Expulsion,” is particularly apposite, since the angel Michael is depicted as an androgynous guide
who grasps the hands of those adult children, Adam and Eve, and leads them down from freedom. The nadir of
human fortunes is represented, it may be added, in the great picture “Pestilence: Death of the First Born,”
which is also in the Boston Museum of Fine Arts. There Michael’s Satanic aspect is inflated, as it were, by
the four wild horsemen in the background of the “Expulsion” until he has become a giant reptile sowing the
tares of disease. Conversely his polite but firm policeman’s role in the “Expulsion” is represented by the
diminished angel, seen between the Satanic legs, who modestly guards the way out as the Covering Cherub. The
sequel to this, in turn, is shown in another great picture, “The Angel Binding the Dragon,” which is in the
Fogg Museum. The action here occurs in the time of the end when the alliance between Michael and Satan has
been broken as a result of the further degeneration of Satan from a smiter with disease into a dragon old.
This consolidation of error, brought about by the redemptive action of Christ in history, which I trace in the
conclusion of this piece, is nevertheless not sufficient for Michael to free himself entirely by belated
positive action. As some critics have previously noted, one coil of the chain is looping Michael’s shoulder,
presumably because his ages of complicity have taught him some bad habits.</note>
                            <note id="n23">
                                <hi rend="s">10</hi> This key symbol in <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> also appears
on pls. 2, 7, 28 (in some copies), and 36, and in more attenuated forms on pls. 3, 4, and 53 as well as in
pls. 5, 8, 9, 18, 20, 24, 27, 28, 34, 36, 38, (41), (43), 51, and 53, where the motif becomes a tree and
clinging vine.</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>This sweet company is delivered to its ultimate destiny in “The River of Life”
(Tate #37), a painting which integrates most of the motifs that have been employed in the pictures we have
chiefly been concerned with. Here Christ turns his back to us, taking the little boy and the girl by the hand
as he swims up the river whose lower reaches were depicted in the other paintings. He has left the keys in the
Grave into which he had descended facing the reader (as well as the Mother in LBF) and is departing with the
regained children to the source of Life. The mother, who was about to accept the Little Boy Found and who
submitted her children for Christ’s blessing, here is shown cutting the line that connects them to this
world. St. John, who flies out of the sun, points downward, in a posture comparable to that of Jesus in “The
Woman Taken in Adultery” and the “Angel” in “The Chimney Sweeper,” though adapted to this more complex design.
One may also observe, on the right bank of the river, the standing mother holding a child, who also appears in
“Christ Blessing” and the second plate of “The Ecchoing Green,” and the girl reaching up for the fruit of the
Tree of Life, which also supports bunches of grapes such as were handed down by a boy to a girl at the end of
the procession in the latter design. She has at last reached the condition unencumbered by prohibitions.
Potential naysayers are now on the other side of the River and in any case, they are now studying the Book of
Life rather than the holy book of cursing. Music is provided by the Piper depicted in 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> pls. 2, 3, and 27, accompanied by a flutist who is a wingless counterpart of the angel
evidently required to “Sound the Flute” in pl. 22 of <hi rend="i">Innocence.</hi> The eternal counterpart of
this music of “Spring” is provided by the chorus of angels standing on the Sun, having evidently foresworn the
happy pipe. Between them <hi rend="u">putti</hi> enact ecstatic reunions such as appear on the title page of
<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi> The joy here, as it were, on the top of Day, is to be
contrasted with the sorrow depicted in the lower borders of LBI where (in later copies) the 4 angels stand
despondently against the background of a starry night while the wingless creatures trailing ribbons separate
from one another. The Little Boy will be Found in the next plate, and perhaps also Saved, but the pictures of
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> contain only a few emblems of such blessedness and ecstasy. The strenuous future
is only adumbrated in the world more attractive called the contrary state of Innocence.</p>
                    </div3>
				<pb id="p02-54" n="54" rend="hidden"/>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>