<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>2.3.kolker</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">Blake in the Institute</title>
				<author n="Kolker">Robert P. Kolker</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>December 15, 1968</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1968</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">02.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>John Buck</name>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Frederic Cummings</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>John E. Grant</name>
                            <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1968"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_02">
        <body>
	<pb id="p02-36" n="36"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-02-3-0002">
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">Blake in the Institute</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>He said himself that he was speaking to future generations, and the fact is that
William Blake is finally being exposed beyond the—to now—somewhat small circle of friendly Angels to a
wider literary public, many of whom have considered him some kind of excrescence upon the otherwise smoothly
cultivated land of English literary history. One of the most pleasant events in this progress of exposure
occurred at the meeting of The English Institute, September 3rd through September 5th, at Columbia University
(where, coincidentally, Orc is currently being reborn and bound).</p>
                    <p>Under the careful guiding hand of David Erdman, three papers and a prize essay were
read, each dealing with some aspect of the dramatic vision in Blake’s work. Martha England read a superb
piece, speculating upon Blake’s debt, in “An Island in the Moon,” to Samuel Foote’s dramatic
improvisations in the Haymarket. Her analogies between Blake’s methods of characterization, his settings,
his jokes, his songs in “An Island” and the things Foote was doing in his satirical stage pieces were rather
convincing. Irene Taylor presented a meticulous analysis of Blake’s illustrations to Gray’s “Ode on the
Death of a Favourite Cat,” an analysis which attempted to demonstrate how Blake interpreted in visual terms
Gray’s satirical allegory. The prize essay, by Robert Simmons, was concerned with <hi rend="i">The Book of
Urizen.</hi> It was an ingenious attempt to show an incredibly formal symmetry in the structure of the book,
in which all the elements, arrangement of stanzas, arrangement and style of illustrations, produce an
intricate and literally graphable structure of vision. This was a valuable exercise, important perhaps to
those who still think that Blake was some kind of disorderly thinker of half-baked ideas. But the dangers of
such a subjectively formal analysis may outweigh the advantages: the prospect of abstracting the Prophecies
into geometric forms is not a happy one, even though one might agree that in a book about Urizen, Blake might
well have wanted to parody the very things Urizen is doing. Mr. Simmons recognized some of the parodic
elements in the work, though he stressed too strongly his notion that in this book Blake is a “visionary of
the comic.”</p>
                    <p>The best event of the proceedings was David Erdman’s slide lecture on 
<hi rend="i">America.</hi> Despite an intractable projector, he managed to demonstrate the fullness, scope,
detail, and power of Blake’s vision and execution. If there were any unbelievers left in the audience, Mr.
Erdman had to have convinced them of
<pb id="p02-37" n="37"/>
the extraordinary synthesizing powers of Blake’s imagination.</p>
                    <p>The proceedings were properly friendly and informal; the papers served well to indicate
the kind of work that is being carried on. But I think one bit of general criticism might be offered: more and
more people are studying and writing about Blake, and although exposure of their findings to a wider academic
public is beginning, it is only beginning. Would it not be proper, at this stage, for programs such as that at
the English Institute to concentrate on Blake’s place within the literary and artistic framework in which he
was working? In other words, for a general audience of literary scholars and critics, is it not necessary
still to establish Blake as a poet and painter among poets and painters and not some kind of sport to whom no
one but a small group of enthusiasts need pay much attention? Certainly many of the papers read did take this
problem into consideration to some degree. But my general impression was still of one group of the knowing
talking to another group of the knowing. To my mind, the paper that did the most toward furthering a general
understanding of what Blake was about was one read in another section. In a profoundly suggestive piece on the
changing attitudes toward imitation in eighteenth-century English literature, William K. Wimsatt presented
both a paean to and a brief analysis of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> that, hopefully, left the audience
with a feeling that Blake is a creator they’d better come to grips with if they are to understand fully the
organism of literary history.</p>
                    <p>David V. Erdman adds:<lb/>
                        <lb/>
Honorable mentions were awarded to three people: Alicia Ostriker (Rutgers) for “Thomas Wyatt and Henry Surrey:
Dissonance and Harmony” (not a Blake paper but by a Blake scholar); W. J. Thomas Mitchell (Ohio State
University, Columbus) for “Blake’s Composite Art”; and Helen T. McNeil (Hunter) for “Blake’s Confidence: A
Study of Formal Originality in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” Altogether 25 Blake papers were submitted,
more than half of them well worthy publication.</p>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>Robert P. <name>Kolker</name>
                        </docAuthor> Columbia University</byline>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>