<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>2.3.gates</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="news">The Gates of Paradise</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>December 15, 1968</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1968</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">02.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>John Buck</name>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Frederic Cummings</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>John E. Grant</name>
                            <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1968"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_02">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-02-3-0002">
				<div2>
                    <pb id="p02-38" n="38"/>
                    <div3>
                        <head>
                            <title type="main">
                                <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi>
                            </title>
                        </head>
                        <p>Scheduled for publication this month: a facsimile reproduction 
                        of the complete <hi rend="i">Gates of Paradise</hi>, published for 
                        the William Blake Trust by the Trianon Press (Chateau de Boissia, 
                        Clairvaux, Jura, France).</p>
                        <p>Volume 1 includes seventeen preliminary sketches from Blake’s 
                        <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>, reproduced in facsimile by collotype, 
                        together with Sir Geoffrey Keynes’s introduction, page-by-page 
                        explanation and comparative study of all three stages of the work, 
                        and a census of every known copy of the two volumes of engravings. 
                        In his illuminating text, Sir Geoffrey has outlined the origins of 
                        Blake’s project from a series of sixty-four drawings in the 
                        <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> which are listed and described. From 
                        these drawings Blake chose seventeen which he engraved and issued 
                        in 1793 entitled <hi rend="i">For Children. The Gates of 
                        Paradise.</hi> Later, in about 1818, he re-worked all the plates, 
                        adding three and issued them under the title <hi rend="i">For the 
                        Sexes.</hi> Volume 2 of this edition is a facsimile of the 
                        <hi rend="i">For Children</hi> series made from the Lessing J. 
                        Rosenwald copy in the Library of Congress, and contains additional 
                        states of an earlier version. Volume 3 is a facsimile of the 
                        Huntington Library copy of <hi rend="i">For the Sexes</hi>, 
                        together with a number of comparative plates from other 
                        sources.</p>
                        <p>The engravings have been reproduced in facsimile by two-tone 
                        collotype with the plate mark impressed from hand-bevelled copper 
                        plates. The paper is pure rag Arches Vergé. The edition is limited 
                        to 700 copies for sale: 50 copies numbered 1 to 50, containing 
                        extra plates and material used in printing the book, are bound in 
                        full morocco and presented in a cloth slip-case (49 gns.); 650 
                        copies numbered 51 to 700 are bound in cloth and presented in a 
                        cloth-covered slip-case (16 gns.).</p>
                    </div3>
                </div2>
            </div1>
		</body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>