<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>2.4.fugitive</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="query">A Fugitive or Apocryphal Blake Engraving</title>
				<author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>April 1, 1969</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1969</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">02.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>W.H. Stevenson</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1969"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_02">
        <body>
            <div1 id="BQ-02-4-0007">
                <pb id="p02-74" n="74"/>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">3. A Fugitive or Apocryphal Blake Engraving</title>
                    </head>
                    <p>According to the British Museum Print Room accessions records, on 9 July 1859 Messrs
Evans sold to the Print Room a Blake engraving of “The World before the Flood. Canto 7. page 136,” which
evidently formed the “Frontispiece to The Minor’s[?] Pocket Book. 1814.”</p>
                    <p>No such print is known to Blake scholars. The title suggests that the work is an
ephemeral publication, which may account for the fact that it does not appear in the catalogues of major
libraries. Unfortunately, the print itself cannot now be traced in the British Museum Print Room; perhaps it
has been reattributed in the last century and is now filed under another name. The fact that the entry in the
Print Room accessions records was made in 1859, when Blake’s reputation was still moribund, suggests that
the cataloguer was not merely associating the engraving with a well-known name and that he may have had some
information such as an inscription on which to base his attribution. However, until someone can locate a copy
of <hi rend="i">The Minor’s Pocket Book</hi>, we will have to presume that the cataloguer was in error.</p>
                    <byline>
                        <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor> University of Toronto</byline>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>