<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>2.4.stevenson</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="review">Geoffrey Keynes, ed., The Letters of William Blake, 2nd ed.</title>
				<author n="Stevenson">W. H. Stevenson</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>April 1, 1969</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1969</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">02.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editor</resp>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>David V. Erdman</name>
                            <name>W.H. Stevenson</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of California</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1969"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_02">
        <body>
            <pb id="p02-71" n="71"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-02-4-0006">
                <head>
                    <title type="section">
                        <hi rend="i">
                            <hi rend="u">REVIEW</hi>
                        </hi>
                    </title>
                </head>
                <div2>
                    <head>
                        <title type="main">
                            <hi rend="u">The Letters of William Blake</hi> edited by Geoffrey Keynes<supplied
type="emend">.</supplied> Rupert Hart-Davis (second edition, 1968)
                        </title>
                    </head>
                    <byline></byline>
                    <p>It is always regrettable when a standard text goes out of print, though no doubt it is
a sign of the times that publishers do not like to keep books on their shelves unless they are also moving off
briskly. The new edition of Blake’s letters is therefore welcome. It is also a sign of the times that this
edition, which has been entirely reset, is in somewhat reduced print, a smaller format, and an increased price
(from 50/- to 75/-), though “in real terms”, as they say, this is perhaps no increase at all. These are small
criticisms, however; the first edition was so amply spacious that it has been possible to shrink it without
producing an unduly cramped page or minute text.</p>
                    <p>The dust-jacket makes a point of announcing that new material has been incorporated
into the second edition. When one comes to look for these new discoveries, they turn out to comprise two
receipts given to John Linnell, and the entries from Linnell’s personal cash accounts between March 1822 and
September 1836, where they refer to Blake or his works; and one real letter,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="nE1">*</ref> dated 29 December 1826, in which Blake apologises to Mrs. Aders for not
responding to an invitation, on account of his serious illness - writing in a blend of respectful anxiety not
to give offence, with considerable (and surely justified) fear for his own welfare. It is a pity that Mr.
Keynes did not amend his index to refer to this additional letter.</p>
					<note id="nE1"><supplied type="emend">* <hi rend="i">Correction (June 1969):</hi> Sir Geoffrey Keynes
wishes to point out that the second edition of <hi rend="i">Blake’s Letters</hi> contains four letters not
included in the first edition, and not one.... In addition to the brief letter to Mrs. Aders, there are two
complete letters to Hayley and one to Linnell.</supplied></note>
                    <p>These are, then, interesting but not really major additions to the whole. It is a
blessing that the original numbering of the letters has been retained, the additions being numbered 114a,
122a, 136a and 140a, so that any critic henceforth can continue to refer to the old numbering without fear of
confusion - a sin (if one may use the word in Blakean circles) - an error of which Mr. Keynes has not always
been innocent, as for example in his labelling of the copies in the <hi rend="u">Census</hi> in a completely
different way from the <hi rend="i">Bibliography.</hi>
                    </p>
                    <p>It is always a problem, and an unanswerable one, to know how Blake’s texts should be
punctuated when they are reproduced. Mr. Keynes, as before, has retained Blake’s spellings and capitals, but
has added punctuation. On the whole one cannot quarrel with the restrained amount of punctuation he has added,
though it is a pity that, inevitably, one cannot now be sure when one is faced by a point that Blake meant to
stand out. And, since the punctuation is editorial, it is a little strange that Mr. Keynes has retained the
clumsy excess of inverted commas in the poem sent to Thomas Butts on 22 November 1802.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="nE2">**</ref></p>
					<note id="nE2"><supplied type="emend">** <hi rend="i">Correction (June 1969):</hi> The inverted commas in
the poem sent to Butts are not editorial, but form part of Blake’s original letter.</supplied></note>
                    <p>These are still minor complaints. The critics of the earlier edition were not slow to
remark that, though Mr. Keynes had produced an excellent edition, its usefulness was doubtful since most of
the material was available anyway in his own Nonesuch edition of the complete works. This is still true. The
O. U. P. successor to the Nonesuch edition does not contain the letters
					<pb id="p02-72" n="72"/>
					to Blake, nor the minor items such as receipts; but with a small extension it could easily have been made
to do so. The major advantage to researchers of this collection of the letters is the fifty-page 
<hi rend="i">Register</hi> at the end, which gives the bibliographical details, including information about where
the letters are to be found. It is an irony of commerce that, to have this information to hand, the researcher
must pay his 75/ - or $6.95, more than enough to put the whole of Blake’s text in his hands.</p>
                    <byline>
                        <corr type="emend"><docAuthor>W. H. <name>Stevenson</name>
                        </docAuthor></corr> University of Ibadan Nigeria</byline>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>