<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>20.1.rochester</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">Blake Moves to Rochester</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1986</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1986</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">20.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Robin Tawney</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Thomas L. Minnick</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of New Mexico</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Albuquerque, NM, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1986"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_20">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-1-0007">
      <pb id="p20-31" n="31"/>
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">NEWSLETTER</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main"><hi rend="i">BLAKE</hi> MOVES TO ROCHESTER</title>
          </head>
          <p>After a decade and a half at the University of New Mexico, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> will accompany
Morris Eaves to the University of Rochester this summer when he assumes a position there as Professor of
English. From 1 July 1986 all correspondence that would have gone to the University of New Mexico should be
addressed to <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, c/o Morris Eaves, Dept. of English, Univ. of Rochester, Rochester, New
York 14627.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Blake</hi> will leave many unpaid debts of gratitude at the University of New
Mexico. Our first thanks must go to various members of the University administration, especially Nathaniel
Wollman and Joseph Zavadil, who were, respectively, Dean of the College of Arts and Sciences and Chair of the
English Department in 1970, when <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> was looking for a home. This commitment has continued
in the persons of Hamlin Hill, Chair of the English Department since 1979, and Chris Garcia, Dean of Arts and
Sciences since 1980, who have never refused their help when we needed it. They have been supported in turn by
others, especially former Provost McAllister Hull, Jr., former Associate Provost Joel Jones, and former Acting
Vice-President for Research, Joseph Scaletti.</p>
          <p>Our second debt is owed to the students and staff of the English Department who have worked on
<hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> Roberta Goetsch was <hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi> first editorial assistant, and many
of the procedures that she helped devise stand us in good stead sixteen years later. But 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> could not have continued without the competence and devotion to the job of Robie’s
numerous successors. In recent years, editorial assistant (now managing editor) has been a fulltime position,
filled by three very fine people whom all subscribers and contributors should remember: Susan Corban, Marcy
Erickson, and (the present managing editor) Robin Tawney. They have been assisted by an equally memorable
group of graduate students, several of whom have gone on to careers in printing, editing, and publishing.</p>
          <p>Finally, we gratefully acknowledge our indebtedness to the skills of the various experts at the
University Printing Plant. Tom Payne, the present Director, and Jim Cheek, the present Assistant Director,
have guided us through the mysteries of their craft since the day we arrived on campus, as have Jim Doolittle,
Dave Spear, Frank Luna, Jr., and numerous other Plant employees whose patient advice and training have been
sincerely appreciated.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
