<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>20.2.paley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">C. A. Patrides and Joseph Wittreich, eds., The Apocalypse in English Renaissance
thought and Literature: Patterns, Antecedents, and Repercussions</title>
        <author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1986</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1986</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">20.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Tim Hoyer</name>
              <name>Wallace Jackson</name>
              <name>Edward Larrissy</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
              <name>David Scrase</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Dena Bain Taylor</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1986"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_20">
    <body>
      <pb id="p20-53" n="53"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-2-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure n="apocalypse.bookcover.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="431">
          	<figTranscr>The<lb/>
          	Apocalypse<lb/>
          	in English Renaissance<lb/>
          	thought and literature<lb/>
          	C. A. PATRIDES<lb/>
          	JOSEPH WITTREICH editors</figTranscr>
          </figure>
          <head>
            <title type="main">C.A. Patrides and Joseph Wittreich, eds. <hi rend="i">The Apocalypse in English
Renaissance Thought and Literature: Patterns, Antecedents, and Repercussions.</hi> Ithaca, N.Y.: Cornell Univ.
Press, 1984, viii + 452 pp. $49.50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Morton D.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Paley</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Any student of Blake must perforce be interested in the Apocalypse and in its role in the culture
of Blake’s time. Although this collection of essays is far broader in scope, beginning with the early Church
Fathers and concluding near the end of the nineteenth century, it provides a perspective in which we can view
Blake’s apocalypticism not as isolated and unique but as participating in a tradition that goes back at
least to the Book of Daniel in the Old Testament. The reader who wants to take such a Blake’s-eye view of
the subject might do well to begin with the book’s concluding essay, M.H. Abrams’s “Apocalypse: Theme
and Variations” and then to return to it at the end; here, as in <hi rend="i">Natural Supernaturalism</hi>,
Abrams is concerned with the manner in which Blake and some of his contemporaries transformed biblical
hermeneutics into personal poetic statements with immediate applications to history. Thus essays like the two
opening ones in <hi rend="i">The Apocalypse</hi> may have no immediate reference to the Romantic period and
yet be full of implications about it.</p>
          <p>The initial essay, “Early Apocalypticism: The Ongoing Debate” by Bernard McGinn, declares the
necessity “for a synthetic view as the proper background for detailed study of special epochs and topics,”
and McGinn’s discussion is itself a masterful contribution towards such a view. The apocalyptic genre is
defined as a revelation by an angel to a usually pseudonymous recepient, a message encoded in visionary
symbols to be written down. The rise of apocalypticism is traced to the Judaism of the third and second
centuries B.C., and the apocalyptic elements of the New Testament are briefly described. McGinn also
demonstrates the extent to which the chiliastic nature of Christianity was fully accepted by early Church
Fathers such as Irenaeus, Tertullian, and Lactantius, all of whom believed in the coming thousand-year reign
of Christ on earth. It was Augustine who, rejecting his own earlier view, made the idea of the millennium,
once an article of faith, a matter of controversy.</p>
          <p>There were nevertheless always those within the Church who attempted to re-establish the
thousand-year reign as a central doctrine. The medieval manifestations of such attitudes are the subject of
Marjorie Reeves’s essay “The Development of Apocalyptic Thought.” The structuring of time is
particularly important here. In Augustine’s later writings the conception of a world-week of six ages plus a
seventh existing outside of time<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">1</ref> was
transformed into “a one-directional process” whereby God unfolded His purpose within history. Paul’s
doctrine of three phases of salvation (Romans v. 13-15) continued nevertheless to provide a model for
millenarian speculation. Joachim of Fiore, to the study of whose thought Reeves has made such an immense
contribution elsewhere,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">2</ref> made the
third <hi rend="i">status</hi> the Age of the Spirit and combined it with the Seventh Day of the world-week.
The effects of this idea were indeed far-reaching; whether far enough to reach Blake is a subject demanding
further investigation.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">1</hi> For a discussion of the world-week with reference to Blake, see my 
<hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1970), p. 138.</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">2</hi> See <hi rend="i">The Influence of Prophecy in the Later Middle Ages</hi>
(Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1969) and Marjorie Reeves and Beatrice Hirsch-Reich, <hi rend="i">The Figurae of
Joachim of Flora</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1972).</note>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">3</hi> I do not know whether there may be new material on this subject in two
as-yet-unpublished works: a study of the later influence of Joachim of Fiore by Reeves and Warwick Gould and
E.P. Thompson’s book on Blake (which, he has informed me, places considerable emphasis on
millenarianism).</note></p>
          <p>Following these two rich essays, Jaroslav Pelikan’s “Some Uses of Apocalypse in the
Magisterial Reformers” is somewhat disappointing, not for any fault of its own as a specialized contribution
to the history of theology but because of the relative lack of importance, remarked upon in some of the other
essays in this volume,
<pb id="p20-54" n="54"/>
            <figure n="Durer.horsemen.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="855">
	<figTranscr>AD</figTranscr>
	<head>1. Albrecht Dürer.</head>
	<figDesc>The <hi rend="i">Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse, Apocalypsis cum Figuris.</hi> 1511. Woodcut.
15⅜×11 in. Henry E. Huntington Library.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p20-55" n="55"/>
that Luther and Calvin attached to the Book of Revelation: Luther, as Pelikan himself notes, at one time
expressed the view that the Apocalypse did not belong in the Bible at all, and Calvin did not include it among
his New Testament commentaries. What Pelikan does show is that Revelation nevertheless played a role in the
preaching of both. More valuable in creating a frame of reference for the literary essays to follow is Bernard
Capp’s “The Political Dimensions of Apocalyptic Thought.” Capp argues that Foxe’s <hi rend="i">Acts
and Monuments</hi>, more commonly known as <hi rend="i">The Book of Martyrs</hi>, along with John Bale’s 
<hi rend="i">The Image of Both Churches</hi>, inculcated a form of “apocalyptic nationalism” that was to have
important consequences for the next century in the millenarian aspect of the English Revolution. The works of
Spenser, Shakespeare and Milton that are discussed in Part III of <hi rend="i">The Apocalypse</hi> also show,
in varying degrees, characteristics of such an attitude.</p>
          <p>“Revelation and the Seventeenth Century” by Michael Murrin, the last essay in Part II, has as
its subject the two seventeenth-century commentators most important to literary scholars—David Pareus and
Joseph Mede, both of whom have been connected with Milton.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n37" type="note">4</ref> Murrin’s critical approach to Pareus’s <hi rend="i">Commentary</hi> and
to Mede’s <hi rend="i">Key to the Revelation</hi> is in some ways puzzling. It may be, for example, that
Pareus made “strained act divisions [in Revelation] as with the seals”—but from what standpoint is such
a judgment made, and what are its implications? Again, if Mede’s interpretations lack originality as Murrin
says, how does this affect our view of Mede? We do not read David Pareus for a “true” exposition of
John’s meaning; for that we would go to modern scholars (only to find considerable disagreement despite the
use of linguistic and cultural evidence). Mede’s originality lies not in his individual glosses but in the
idea of synchronicity as applied to John’s visions. No author is beyond criticism, but it seems centuries
late to concentrate on the problems these two had in their approaches to their chosen text. 
<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See Joseph Wittreich, <hi rend="i">Visionary Poetics</hi> (San Marino: Huntington Library,
1979).</note></p>
          <p>The heart of <hi rend="i">The Apocalypse</hi> is Part III, where Florence Sandler begins by
arguing cogently that the Legend of Holiness in <hi rend="i">The Faerie Queene</hi> is patterned after
Revelation. Many of Sandler’s statements about Spenser’s typology seem equally applicable to Blake’s in
his later works. This is of course not surprising, considering the interest in Spenser evidenced by Blake’s
<hi rend="i">Characters in Spenser’s</hi> Faerie Queen (National Trust, Petworth). Nor need we hypothesize
about Blake’s sense of engagement with Joseph Wittreich’s subject in “‘Image of that Horror’: The
Apocalypse in <hi rend="i">King Lear.</hi>” Positing a “poet’s revelation” different from the
theologians’ in that Shakespeare’s goal is “to turn responsibility for the shaping of history over to
man and thereby secularize the Christian prophecy,” this finely considered essay makes us think once more of
Blake. C.A. Patrides treats of the most important English poet of all to Blake in his “ ‘Something like
<corr type="emend">Prophetic</corr> Strain’: Apocalyptic Configurations in Milton.” In opposition to Michael Fixler’s view that
“Milton based <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> on an elaborate systematic transformation of the Apocalypse or
Revelation of St. John,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">5</ref> Patrides
sees the apocalyptic content as projected into the pretemporal realm of the War in Heaven in Book VI.
Nevertheless, Patrides recognizes the apocalyptic structuring of history according to typological patterns as
“descriptive of the strategy at the heart of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>” (and, one might add, of
Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> as well). <note id="n38"><hi rend="s">5</hi> “The Apocalypse within 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>,” <hi rend="i">New Essays on</hi> Paradise Lost, ed. Thomas Kranidas (Berkeley
and Los Angeles: Univ. of California Press, 1969), pp. 131-78.</note></p>
          <p>In Part IV we begin to approach Blake’s era or at least its background with Paul Korshin’s
“Queuing and Waiting: the Apocalypse in England, 1660-1750.” Korshin begins with a brief but informative
consideration of some later seventeenth century figures, most notably the Behmenist Jane Lead, whose writings
continued to be studied in millenarian circles a century later.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n39" type="note">6</ref> Curiously, there is no mention of Thomas Beverley, who is too important a
figure to be left out, as he was a prolific millenarian writer—the bibliography of this book lists eleven
titles published in the decade beginning 1684—at a time when the Commonwealth flood of apocalyptic tracts
had subsided to a Restoration and then post-Restoration trickle. Even more curious is the manner in which the
essay appears gradually to adopt the attitude of the millenarians’ critics and enemies. One expects to find
<hi rend="i">A Tale of a Tub</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Dunciad</hi> discussed here, but it is surprising that
the view of the satires is assumed by the author as well: “Swift pays special attention to certain aspects
of millenarian behavior—sexual licentiousness, glossolalia, visionary experiences, madness. His gaze is
almost medical, as if the fanatic were a patient in an asylum (as, no doubt, some of them were) and he were
the physician writing a case history” (p. 259). Such a remark as this recalls the bad old days typified by
Hoxie Neale Fairchild’s <hi rend="i">Religious Trends in English Poetry</hi>, where all forms of Dissent are
viewed as deviations from an implied norm. There is, moreover, another omission of an important writer on
apocalyptic subjects, in this instance Richard Roach, who assumed leadership of the Philadelphian Society from
Jane Lead. As Roach’s works do not appear in the bibliography, they should be mentioned here: 
<hi rend="i">The Great Crisis: or, the Mystery of the Times and Seasons Unfolded</hi> (1725) and <hi rend="i">The
Imperial Standard of the Messiah Triumphant</hi> (1727). <note id="n39"><hi rend="s">6</hi> See Désirée
Hirst, <hi rend="i">Hidden Riches</hi> (London: Eyre &amp; Spottiswoode, 1964), p. 260.</note></p>
          <p>There is unfortunately no essay to link the mid-eighteenth century to the Romantic period in this
book, and consequently the early Swedenborgian milieu in England is left undiscussed, as are the writings of
Richard Brothers, Joanna Southcott, and their respective followers. The American side of the subject is,
however, thoroughly presented by Stephen Stein in “Transatlantic Extensions: Apocalyptic in Early New
England,” beginning
<pb id="p20-56" n="56"/>
with the Puritans of the first generation and extending to the aftermath of the American Revolution. Most
pertinent, perhaps, for one interested in speculating about Blake’s connection with this subject is the
Great Awakening. Could Blake in calling his Milton “the Awakener” have had in mind the Awakening in
America? Blake must have known that George Whitefield, whom he praises in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, had a
prominent role in the latter part of this phenomenon.</p>
          <p>The post-Romantic period is the subject of two important essays in <hi rend="i">The
Apocalypse.</hi> Mary Wilson Carpenter and George P. Landow center their exposition of the Apocalypse in
Victorian literature upon George Eliot, remarking that Eliot’s fascination with the fulfillment of
Revelation is related to a renewed sense of the importance of this subject among contemporary intellectuals.
The latter part of their essay argues that in <hi rend="i">Romola</hi> Eliot structures her novel according to
a sevenfold division based on Revelation. Last before Abrams’s fine Omega comes “The Millenarian Structure
of <hi rend="i">The Communist Manifesto</hi>” by Ernest L. Tuveson, whose <hi rend="i">Millennium and
Utopia</hi> (1949) remains a classic study of millenialist thought. Tuveson’s thesis that the communism of
Marx and Engels involves a displacement of religious belief is familiar, but his application of this view to
the Communist Manifesto succeeds in bringing out some striking parallels between Engels’ document and
John’s.</p>
          <figure n="Beast.Chickpublications.bqscan" rend="file" width="900" height="295">
          	<figTranscr>WITH THE USE OF COMPUTERS, THE BEAST WILL BE ABLE<lb/>
          	TO CONTROL EVERY PERSON ON THE GLOBE.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	EVERYONE SHALL RECEIVE MY<lb/>
          	MARK ON THEIR FOREHEADS OR<lb/>
          	ON THEIR RIGHT HAND. WITHOUT<lb/>
          	THIS MARK—YOU WILL BE<lb/>
          	UNABLE TO BUY OR SELL!<lb/>
          	REV 13:16-17<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	“IF ANY MAN WORSHIP THE BEAST AND HIS IMAGE, AND RECEIVE HIS MARK IN HIS<lb/>
          	FOREHEAD, OR IN HIS HAND” ------- “HE SHALL BE TORMENTED WITH FIRE AND<lb/>
          	BRIMSTONE IN THE PRESENCE OF THE HOLY ANGELS.”.........Rev. 14:9-10<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	THERE ARISES A FALSE PROPHET<lb/>
          	WHO CAUSES THE MULTITUDES TO WORSHIP THE BEAST.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	I COMMAND FIRE <lb/>
          	TO COME OUT OF THE <lb/>
          	HEAVENS (REV 13:13)<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	HE’S NOT A <lb/>
          	MAN...HE’S <lb/>
          	A GOD!<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	AND DECEIVETH THEM THAT DWELL ON THE EARTH, BY THE MEANS OF THOSE<lb/>
          	MIRACLES WHICH HE HATH POWER TO DO IN THE SIGHT OF THE BEAST. ... SAY-<lb/>
          	ING TO THEM THAT DWELL ON THE EARTH, THAT THEY SHOULD MAKE AN<lb/>
          	IMAGE TO THE BEAST.   Rev. 13:14</figTranscr>
            <head>2. From <hi rend="i">The Beast.</hi></head>
            <figDesc>Chick Publications, P.O. Box 662, Chino, Calif. 91710. (I thank Alan H. Pesetsky for
bringing this booklet to my attention).</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>One might wish for a full-fledged index rather than a scant “Index nominum” to this book, but
the elaborate and extremely helpful bibliography compiled by Wittreich deserves the last word. Divided into
commentaries on/interpretations of Revelation (arranged chronologically) and ancillary reading (alphabetized),
this section of some seventy pages will be helpful to scholars for a long time to come—as, indeed, will this
entire book.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
