<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>20.2.larrissy</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake and the Hutchinsonians</title>
        <author n="Larrissy">Edward Larrissy</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1986</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1986</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">20.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Tim Hoyer</name>
              <name>Wallace Jackson</name>
              <name>Edward Larrissy</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
              <name>David Scrase</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Dena Bain Taylor</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1986"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_20">
    <body>
	<pb id="p20-44" n="44"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-2-0005">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake and the Hutchinsonians</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Edward <name>Larrissy</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Albert J. Kuhn was the first and perhaps the only person to notice Blake’s debt to the
Hutchinsonians.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> These “thinkers,”
followers of John Hutchinson (1674-1737) were the main school of anti-Newtonians with any claim to scientific
method in eighteenth-century England.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref>
Kuhn, whose article is not confined to a study of them, is chiefly concerned with their notion that the
“cherubim” had originally represented the Trinity, and that “heathens” had debased those
“cherubim” into their gods and idols.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3"
type="note">3</ref> Clearly, such a notion might well have contributed to Blake’s idea that “the Grecian
gods were the ancient Cherubim of Phoenicia” (<hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, E536/K571). But
Kuhn’s case is not conclusively made. It is, however, possible to demonstrate quite clearly Blake’s
indebtedness to Hutchinsonian ideas, for there are precise verbal echoes as well as general resemblances; nor
is this indebtedness confined to the matter of the “cherubim,” for it appears to be evident in a number of
Blake’s later ideas. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Albert J. Kuhn, “Blake on the Nature and Origins of
Pagan Gods and Myths,” <hi rend="i">Modern Language Notes</hi>, 72 (Dec., 1957), 569-72.</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Robert E. Schofield, <hi rend="i">Mechanism and Materialism: British
Natural Philosophy in an Age of Reason</hi> (Princeton, 1970), pp. 122-28.</note>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Kuhn, p. 570.</note></p>
          <p>Hutchinson, like Blake, believed that the original faith was Christian, and that it had been
perverted by the Jews, and stolen in a corrupt form by the Greeks
<pb id="p20-45" n="45"/>
and the Druids. The Trinity had been emblematized in the Cherubim, but were in themselves better thought of as
“Elohim” (or “Aleim,” as Hutchinson often spells it). In accordance with his belief in primeval
Christianity Hutchinson insisted that the idea of Man was included in the Trinity.</p>
          <p>These ideas may be illustrated from the <corr type="emend">following</corr> passage, obscure
though it is:
<q>
As the . . . <hi rend="i">cherubim</hi>, was a similitude of the Divinity, and of man taken into the Essence,
and becoming . . . <hi rend="i">one Mighty to save;</hi> so the supreme [<hi rend="i">rbym</hi>, i.e.,
“rubim”] are the <hi rend="i">Great ones</hi>, of whom we are allow’d to take ideas from . . . the 
<hi rend="i">names</hi>, or the heavens. They, ere the world began, became confederates under the band of an oath,
and so [<hi rend="i">alhym</hi>, i.e., “Elohim”].<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Anon., <hi rend="i">An Abstract from the Works of John Hutchinson</hi>
(Edinburgh, 1753), p. 221. This work (henceforth <hi rend="i">Abstract</hi>) is cited frequently because there
is evidence that Blake had read it. Its formulations are more concise than those of Hutchinson’s unreduced
works, and lend themselves more readily to selective quotation. Hebrew script is transliterated in square
brackets according to the conventional notation. I am grateful to Richard Judd, recently of Keble College, for
helping me with this.</note></q>
Compare the passage from the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue:</hi><q>
Visions of these eternal principles or characters of human life appear to poets, in all ages; the Grecian gods
were the ancient Cherubim of Phoenicia; but the Greeks, and since them the Moderns, have neglected to subdue
the gods of Priam. These Gods are visions of the eternal attributes, or divine <hi rend="i">names</hi>, which,
when erected into gods, become destructive to humanity. (E536/K571; my emphasis)
</q>
Hutchinson held that the cherubim were emblems of aspects of God. These aspects became the objects of
idolatrous worship:
<q>
The human head and body, the wings, hands, <hi rend="i">corona</hi>, and other <hi rend="i">insignia</hi> of
the <hi rend="i">Cherubim</hi>, appear so frequently among the idolatrous symbols of worship, that a very
small attention may serve to convince one, by comparing particulars, that the whole heathen 
<hi rend="i">cultus</hi> had a plain resemblance to the sacred institutions, from which it was originally
stolen.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi><hi rend="i"> Abstract</hi>, p. 229.</note></q>
In modern times, according to Hutchinson,
<q>
the cause of <hi rend="i">Christianity</hi> is betray’d, <hi rend="i">revelation</hi> disbelieved, and men
trust to their own merit, morality, repentance, <hi rend="i">&amp;c.</hi> to intitle them to the joys of
another world: youth have their heads early filled with heathen authors, mythology <hi rend="i">&amp;c.</hi>
but are never taught to understand them by a comparison with the perfect original from whence they are 
<hi rend="i">stolen and perverted.</hi> . . . <ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> (my emphasis) 
<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> Abstract</hi>, p. 244.</note></q>
Blake, using the same words, stated that “the Poetry of the Heathen” was “Stolen &amp; Perverted from
the Bible” (notes on Dante illustrations, E689/K785). As for modern philosophy, Hutchinson says (in what may
be an allusion to his hatred of Newton) that it is “made up of senseless Words for Non-Entities, instead of
the Agents, their Powers and Actions, described in the Bible.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n7" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> J. H. [John Hutchinson], <hi rend="i">The Religion of Satan, or Antichrist,
Delineated</hi> (London, 1736), p. 114.</note></p>
          <p>The “oath” or “covenant” referred to above is that of “JEHOVAH ALEIM” (i.e., Jehovah
Elohim).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref> The covenant is that Jehovah
Aleim will become a man, Christ, and redeem men by forgiveness of sins. This goes a long way towards
explaining certain obscure passages in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel.</hi> Thus Hutchinson says:
<q>
The heathens were never so stupid as to think their crimes could be blotted out, unless their ALEIM were
propitiated: and so they could listen to our Almighty Saviour without prejudice, when he declared his merciful
intentions, that himself was as ready as able to forgive sins. . . .<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n9" type="note">9</ref></q>
This refers to the idea that the heathens, or gentiles, although they made sacrifices, were ready to give up
“their” Elohim (i.e., the corrupt forms they worshipped) and listen to Christ; whereas the Jews, according
to Hutchinson, were complacent enough to believe they could utterly propitiate their Elohim, and did not feel
the need of Christ. Neither heathens nor Jews believed in forgiveness of sins once the original “covenant”
of forgiveness was forgotten. <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi><hi rend="i"> Abstract</hi>, p. 136.</note>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi><hi rend="i"> Abstract</hi>, p. 124.</note></p>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi> Satan says:
<q>
I will have Human Blood &amp; not the blood of Bulls or Goats<lb/>
And no Atonement O Jehovah the Elohim live on Sacrifice<lb/>
Of Men: hence I am God of Men. . . .<lb/>
(E272/K780)
</q>
But Jehovah says that Satan must go to Eternal Death. And then a chorus of angels enters singing:
<q>
The Elohim of the Heathen Swore Vengeance for Sin! Then Thou stoodst<lb/>
Forth O Elohim Jehovah! in the midst of the darkness of the Oath! All Clothed<lb/>
In Thy Covenant of the Forgiveness of Sins. . . .<lb/>
(E272/K781)
</q>
The correspondences are very close, even to the distinction between Elohim Jehovah on the one hand and the
“Elohim of the Heathen” on the other.</p>
          <p>“The emblem of this grand adjuration [i.e., the covenant] between the ALEIM,” says
Hutchinson, “was . . . an <hi rend="i">oak-tree</hi>,” signifying peace. He adds that “This memorial was
not lost even among the latter heathens.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
type="note">10</ref> He quotes Homer, where Hector signifies the antagonism between himself and Achilles by
saying, “There’s now no way from th’ <hi rend="i">oak</hi>, or from the <hi rend="i">rock</hi> / To hold
discourse with him.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> For
Hutchinson, the rock is the pillar of a supposed Druid temple. And he adds that “<hi rend="i">Maximus
Tyrius</hi> observes of the <hi rend="i">Druids</hi>, that they worshipped <hi rend="i">Jupiter</hi> under the
form of a tall oak.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> This is the
oak as object of idolatry, where it was once merely an emblem of the covenant. These two types of oak are to
be found in Blake. Thus at the introduction to chapter 2 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> he addresses the Jews:
<q>
Your ancestors derived their origin from Abraham, Heber, Shem, and Noah, who were Druids: as the Druid Temples
(which are the Patriarchal Pillars &amp; Oak Groves) over the whole Earth Witness to this day. (E171/K649)
</q>
But, on the other hand, in <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi> Satan promises to crucify Christ “By the rock
&amp; Oak of the Druid” (E272/K781): this refers to that period of fallen Druidism when the Elohim have
become externalized gods, and the Divine Humanity is sacrificed on the Tree of Mystery. The Rock and the Oak
become the “serpent temple” at Avebury. <note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi><hi rend="i"> Abstract</hi>, p.
222.</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi><hi rend="i"> Abstract</hi>, p. 222.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi><hi rend="i"> Abstract</hi>, pp. 222-23.</note></p>
          <p>Speaking of Avebury, William Cooke (d. 1780), who 
<pb id="p20-46" n="46"/>
was interested in Hutchinson, provides important clues about the nature of that “temple,” and of the
religion practiced there, in his <hi rend="i">Enquiry into the Patriarchal and Druidical Religion.</hi> This
is an ingeniously eclectic selection of plagiarisms, mostly culled from Stukeley’s pages. Explaining the
name “Abury” Cooke maintains that “such as were the ABIRI worshiped in <hi rend="i">Britain;</hi> such
also <hi rend="i">originaly</hi> were the CABIRI worshiped in the East.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> He agrees with the opinion that “the 
<hi rend="i">Cabiri</hi> were the Gods of the Phoenicians” (cf. “Cherubim of the Phoenicians”) and claims,
arguing from Hebrew and Arabic, that “<hi rend="i">Cabiri</hi> in the plural are THE GREAT or MIGHTY
ONES.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> It will be recalled that
Hutchinson referred to his Cherubim as “<hi rend="i">Great ones.</hi>” Cooke uses Hutchinson’s
description of the Cherubim to support his own argument.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15"
type="note">15</ref> But what should particularly interest the scholar of Blake is the graphic way in which
the decline from “Cherubim” to “Abiri”—a decline of vision—can be illustrated from these sources.
The difference between the imagined splendors of the Phoenician temples and the “geometric” crudity of
Avebury’s “Druid” rocks is very suggestive. <note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> (London, 1754), p.
53.</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi><hi rend="i"> Enquiry</hi>, p. 54</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi><hi rend="i"> Enquiry</hi>, p. 65 n.</note></p>
          <p>The fussiness of the Hutchinsonians about the terms “Elohim” and “Jehovah” might also
serve to illuminate Blake’s own use of these terms. It should be clear from his writings that the tendency
to talk about Urizen as a kind of “Jehovah” is at best a guide to the novice. In fact Blake seems to have
regarded Elohim as more normally the evil Demiurge. The distinction between Jehovah as visible and Elohim as
invisible God, which was based on the distinction between “Elohim” and “Jehovah Elohim” in the Hebrew
of Genesis 1:1-10, was well known. The two were commonly interpreted as God the Father and the Logos
respectively. Hutchinson’s claim that “In a special manner CHRIST was JEHOVAH” was not especially
radical.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">16</ref> Nor is Blake’s that
“after Christs death, he became Jehovah” (<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, pl. 6). The novel thing about this
passage is the claim that “the Jehovah of the Bible” is “no other than he, who dwells in flaming
fire”—that is, Jehovah is Energy. Elohim, the hidden God, is its deprivation. 
<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi><hi rend="i"> Abstract</hi>, p. 224.</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s <hi rend="i">Elohim Creating Adam</hi> belongs with his <hi rend="i">Newton:</hi> and
the Hutchinsonians had much to say about Sir Isaac. Many of their remarks have a distinctly Blakean ring:
<q>
Prodigious fabricator! who wanted only an air-pump to make a <hi rend="i">vacuum</hi>, and a pendulum or swing
to prove it; a loadstone, a bit of amber or jet, to form a philosophy; a spyglass, and a pair of compasses, to
find out infinite worlds. . . .<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi><hi rend="i"> Abstract</hi>, p. 157.</note></q>
It will be recalled that the Application of <hi rend="i">No Natural Religion</hi> (series 2) reads: “He who
sees the Infinite in all things sees God. He who sees the Ratio only sees himself only.” And the
illumination for this aphorism shows a bearded man on hands and knees drawing a triangle with the aid of a
pair of compasses. The Hutchinsonian description of Newton contains much the same sense of a ludicrous
disparity between ends and means. And according to Hutchinson Newton’s God was really “the heathen 
<hi rend="i">Jupiter.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref> He, as we
know, was the “iron-hearted tyrant, the ruiner of ancient Greece” mentioned by Blake in his letter to
Hayley of 23 October 1804; and whom he seems, with some reason perhaps, to have regarded as the God of the
Deists. <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi><hi rend="i"> Abstract</hi>, p. 165.</note></p>
          <p>It may be that Blake was not alone in including John Hutchinson, along with Paracelsus, Boehme
and Swedenborg, among his interests. The Behmenist John Byrom is the source of some of the fascinating
information in Désirée Hirst’s <hi rend="i">Hidden Riches</hi> about eighteenth-century English
Behmenists.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">19</ref> He, like Blake, attacked
the “Selfhood.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> And like Blake
he was interested in Hutchinson, though he did not like his system.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n21" type="note">21</ref> And he corresponded with the Hutchinsonian William Jones of
Nayland.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref> Possibly John Wood of Bath
had come across Hutchinson’s ideas, but in any case he was concerned to show “the <hi rend="i">Plagiarism
of the Heathens</hi>” from the Jews in his work on <hi rend="i">The Origin of Building.</hi><supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref> Blake had likeminded antecedents and
contemporaries: there is still much to discover about their world. <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi><hi
rend="i"> Hidden Riches: Traditional Symbolism from the Renaissance to Blake</hi> (London, 1964), pp. 192,
198.</note>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> John Byrom, <hi rend="i">Miscellaneous Poems</hi>, 2 vols. (Manchester,
1773), 2: 160-62.</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi><hi rend="i"> The Private Journal and Literary Remains of John Byrom</hi>,
ed. Richard Parkinson, D.D., F.S.A., 2 vols. in 2 parts each (being vols. 32, 34, 40 and 44 of 
<hi rend="i">Remains Historical and Literary Connected with the Palatine Counties of Lancaster and Chester</hi>,
published by the Chetham Society [Manchester 1854, 1855, 1856 and 1857]), 2: 23, 26, 131.</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi><hi rend="i"> Private Journal</hi>, 2: 573-78.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> John Wood, <hi rend="i">The Origin of Building; Or, The Plagiarism of the
Heathens Detected</hi> (Bath, 1741), p. 11. I am grateful to Morton Paley for reminding me about this work.
Wood was also interested in Stonehenge, and believed that Druidism had spread across the world from Britain;
<hi rend="i">Choir Gaure, Vulgarly called Stonehenge</hi> (Oxford, 1747), p. 12.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p20-47" n="47" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
