<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>20.2.scrase</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Robert N. Essick, The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue</title>
        <author n="Scrase">David Scrase</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1986</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1986</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">20.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Tim Hoyer</name>
              <name>Wallace Jackson</name>
              <name>Edward Larrissy</name>
              <name>Raymond Lister</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>David Punter</name>
              <name>David Scrase</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Dena Bain Taylor</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1986"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_20">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-2-0007">
        <pb id="p20-64" n="64"/>
        <div2>
          <figure n="Plates.bookcover.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="400"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Robert N. Essick. <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A
Catalogue.</hi> Princeton, NJ: Princeton Univ. Press, 1983. 302 pp., 114 illus. $75.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">David</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Scrase</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>It is a little difficult to pinpoint the market at which this handsomely produced volume is
aimed. All institutions who own prints by William Blake will need it as a standard reference work, but these
are not many; for the layman, interested in Blake, but neither the happy owner of one of his separate plates
nor a scholar to whose interest Blake studies is central, Bindman’s
<pb id="p20-65" n="65"/>
	<hi rend="i">The Complete Graphic Works of William Blake</hi> is more likely to find a place upon his library
shelf. This is a less comprehensive account of the <hi rend="i">minutiae</hi> of theories and analyses of the
various states, known or suggested by Essick, but it is very much cheaper, and, with the illustrations
integrated into the body of the text easier to handle.</p>
          <p>Essick is a scholar of the comprehensive kind. In the tradition of G.E. Bentley, Jr. he has
attempted an exhaustive study of his chosen field, which is admirable where the evidence and material is small
but becomes confused and confusing when, as with <hi rend="i">Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> (XVI) his list
of untraced impressions runs to 142, some of which he admits “are no doubt the same as the traced prints,
and there are in all probability other extant impressions not recorded here in either category” (75). After
wading through the description of the 142 items one is tempted to ask what is the point of the exercise,
unless to show how careful Essick has been to incorporate everything he knows into his text lest some eager
reviewer points out something which has escaped him. This may sound unnecessarily tart, but this reviewer
feels it sufficient to list examples in public collections only, except where a unique state is in the private
domain.</p>
          <p>To an Englishman there are always some problems of different nuance of meaning when reading an
American book. Essick’s style, in accordance with the high seriousness with which he treats his subject, is
measured and a little ponderous, but not obscure or difficult to read. A few things confused me. In his
description of <hi rend="i">Charity</hi> (II), he uses the technical description “planographic transfer
print,” a term which usually implies the lithographic process, whereas this looks much more like a
“monotype,” as Essick admits in the text. A similar confusion arises in his description of the making of
the large color monotypes, worked up by hand, in his introduction, p. xxv. But on the whole Essick is accurate
and intelligible in his description of the processes of printmaking and his introduction is well balanced and
interesting. The main text is clear and for the most part he avoids subjective judgments, a major pitfall in
Blake studies. One comment with which I had to take exception is Essick’s description of the reworking of
the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> and <hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi> prints: “Job’s heavy burden is underscored by the
thick cross hatching defining his covering. The more delicate lines of ‘Ezekiel’ follow the flowing
contours of garments and the burnished areas suggest enlightenment rather than oppression” (23). but on the
whole this book is remarkably free of such attempts at interpretation.</p>
          <p>Under <hi rend="i">Albion Rose</hi> (VII), as it is impossible to see the first state in an
intaglio impression, is it not possible that the Huntington Library impression is a 2nd state with the
“bat-winged moth” burnished out, or that Essick’s state 1 should be state 2 in accordance with the
evidence of <hi rend="i">The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder</hi> (VIII) and that there was an earlier
“hypothetical” state 1, no examples of which have yet been found? To suggest this may sound
perverse—after all, just because Blake produced a preliminary pull of one print does not prove that this was
his invariable practice. Whilst conceding that in some instances it is likely that there were trial
“states” which have not survived—the plates after Morland, <hi rend="i">The Idle Laundress</hi> (XXX)
and <hi rend="i">Industrious Cottager</hi> (XXXI), are cases in point—to presuppose them and list them as
hypothetical states is hedging one’s bets a bit. Better to have made an aside, suggesting that there may
have been an additional state rather than boldly to list one.</p>
          <p>In a work which is in so many ways so admirable and accurate, it is a little disconcerting to
read with reference to the Butts, “Under these circumstances it is impossible to disentangle the father’s
work from the son’s. Fortunately this quandary is of little consequence: the important issue is to determine
the extent of Blake’s involvement in the Butts family’s graphic activities” (211). This may put the
viewpoint of the Blake scholar, but the art historian is every bit as involved in ascertaining which Butts,
father or son, is responsible for which print. To uncover the truth is after all our aim and responsibility.
<hi rend="i">Christ Trampling on Satan</hi> (XLIV) seems to this reviewer to owe rather more to Blake in its
handling than Essick allows, nor does it seem logical to dismiss his participation in the <hi rend="i">Lear
and Cordelia</hi> plate (XLV), and both of the odd plates of afflicted children, <hi rend="i">Two Afflicted
Children</hi> (XLVI) and <hi rend="i">Two Views of an Afflicted Child</hi> (XLVII), can only, in the light of
their relationship in draughtsmanship to the series of imaginary heads, be attributed to Blake himself.</p>
          <p>The book is extremely well produced: the print clear and the paper of high quality. There are
remarkably few errors of proofreading. It should be noted that the <hi rend="i">Industrious Cottager</hi>
(165) is no. XXXI; on p. 146, C, the owner is the Ashmolean Museum, and on p. 230 an unnecessary “d” is
attached to the word “once” (paragraph 2, line 8). The color plates are a little disappointing, but
Blake’s color is so intense and vivid that it is almost impossible to reproduce. It would have been useful
to have had the ownership of the items reproduced listed below each illustration as well as in the
acknowledgments.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Comments:</hi> The dating of Blake’s prints is not easy. On the whole Essick’s
conclusions seem to be justified, although Erdman’s “left-pointing serif” hypothesis (see 
<hi rend="i">The Accusers</hi> [VIII]) is by no means conclusive.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Edward &amp; Elenor</hi> (IV): Bindman’s date of late 1770s or early 1780s makes
sense.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Chaining of Orc</hi> (XVII): From the reproduction the date appears to be
1813.</p>
          <pb id="p20-66" n="66"/>
          <p><hi rend="i">Rev. John Caspar Lavater</hi> (XXIX): Bindman’s suggestion that this was intended
as a frontispiece to Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Physiognomy</hi> is attractive.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Industrious Cottager</hi> (XXXI): <hi rend="i">Is</hi> the child female? Untraced
impressions 6. Essick’s observation is undoubtedly correct.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Falsa ad Coelum</hi> (XXXIV): Schiff’s rejection of “Ganesa” as a type for the
elephant and his proposal of the phallic symbolism of the trunk and the pun on elephant are plausible.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">An Estuary with Figures in a Boat</hi> (XXXV): Although it cannot be established
that this relates to the sketching party on the Medway taken by Blake, Stothard and Mr. Ogleby, Bindman’s
dating of c. 1780 is preferable in terms both of composition and coloring to 1790-94.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Edmund Pitts, Esq<hi rend="s">r</hi>.</hi> (XXXVI): Much more probable that
“Armig” was added after Earle’s knighthood in 1802, even if it counters the “left-pointing serif”
theory.</p>
          <p>
            <hi rend="i">Addenda:</hi>
          </p>
          <p>The Pierpont Morgan Library now owns <hi rend="i">Head of a Damned Soul in Dante’s Inferno</hi>
(XXXII, 1E; given by Charles Ryskamp). The British Museum owns the unique state of <hi rend="i">Mirth</hi>
(XVIII, 2; allocated by Her Majesty’s Treasury).</p>
          <p>The Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge, has been allocated the following items by Her Majesty’s
Treasury, through the Minister of the Arts, accepted in lieu of capital taxes from the estate of the late Sir
Geoffrey Keynes: <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea Among the Rocks of Albion</hi> (I, 1A, 2E, 2F); 
<hi rend="i">The Accusers of Theft Adultery Murder</hi> (VIII, 3F); <hi rend="i">Enoch</hi> (XV, 1C); 
<hi rend="i">Laocoön</hi> (XIX, 1A); <hi rend="i">The Man Sweeping the Interpreter’s Parlour</hi> (XX, 2H); 
<hi rend="i">George Cumberland’s Card</hi> (XXI, 1N, 1O, 1P, 1Q); <hi rend="i">Morning Amusement</hi> (XXII, 1B,
1C); <hi rend="i">The Fall of Rosamond</hi> (XXV, 1A, 2C); <hi rend="i">Zephyrus and Flora</hi> (XXVI, 1A, 1B,
F); <hi rend="i">Calisto</hi> (XXVII, 2C, 2D, F); <hi rend="i">Venus dissuades Adonis from Hunting</hi>
(XVIII, 2A, 2B); <hi rend="i">Rev. John Caspar Lavater</hi> (XXIX, 2B, 3J, 3K); <hi rend="i">The Idle
Laundress</hi> (XXX, 2C, 3E, 3F); <hi rend="i">Industrious Cottager</hi> (XXXI, 3D, 4G, 4H); <hi rend="i">Head
of a Damned Soul in Dante’s Inferno</hi> (XXXII, 1D); <hi rend="i">An Estuary with Figures in a Boat</hi>
(XXXV); <hi rend="i">The Child of Nature</hi> (XXXVIII, 1B, 1C); <hi rend="i">James Upton</hi> (XL, 2C); 
<hi rend="i">M</hi><hi rend="s">rs</hi><hi rend="i"> Q.</hi> (XLII, 2E); <hi rend="i">Wilson Lowry</hi> (XLIII, 2B,
3D, 3E, 4J); <hi rend="i">Bust and large wings of an angel looking to the left</hi> (Part 3, a); 
<hi rend="i">Centaur in a landscape with a Lapith on his back</hi> (Part 3, b); <hi rend="i">Classical figure
seated on a pedestal and holding a lyre</hi> (Part 3, c); <hi rend="i">Head of a Saint</hi> (Part 3, d); Satyr
with a dancing figure (Part 3, e); <hi rend="i">Christ Trampling on Satan</hi> (XLIV, 1K); <hi rend="i">Lear
and Cordelia</hi> (XLV, 3C, 4E); <hi rend="i">Two Afflicted Children</hi> (XLVI); <hi rend="i">Two Views of an
Afflicted Child</hi> (XLVII); <hi rend="i">Coin of Nebuchadnezzar and Head of Cancer</hi> (LVII).</p>
          <p>The following items, which are the property of the Keynes Family Trust, are on deposit at the
Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge: <hi rend="i">Job</hi> V, 1A); <hi rend="i">Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>
(XVI, 2B, 3O); <hi rend="i">The Ancient of Days</hi> (LXVII). This last item does not appear to be a print at
all. Under 7 × magnification there was no evidence of a printed line, nor does it appear to have been
produced by a lithographic process. The underlying image may have been reproduced by a mechanical process, but
the watercolor is applied by hand. The support is card, which is unusual in Blake’s work, and Essick’s
hypothesis that this is some sort of facsimile is probably correct.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
