<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>20.3.crehan</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">Blake, Context and Ideology</title>
        <author n="Crehan">Stewart Crehan</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1986-87</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1986-87</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">20.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stewart Crehan</name>
              <name>D. W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Stuart Peterfreund</name>
              <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1987"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_20">
    <body>
	<pb id="p20-104" n="104"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-3-0006">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake, Context and Ideology</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Stewart <name>Crehan</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Stuart Peterfreund’s review of my <hi rend="i">Blake in Context, Blake</hi>, 19 (winter
1985-86), shows, once again, that while the liberal text can be encompassed and “deconstructed” by the
Marxist text, the Marxist text can only be ignored or misread by the liberal text. Peterfreund begins by
stating that writers such as Bronowski, Schorer, “and above all, Erdman,” have already dealt with the
social and historical context of Blake’s poetry and art, “but not, apparently, to Crehan’s
satisfaction.” Although I do not say so in the book, I did not find Bronowski’s pioneering study
satisfactory, though it was one of my starting points. Erdman’s work was an inspiration, as will be evident
from the references, and the fact that I followed Erdman in foregrounding the phrase “Republican Art,”
used as the title for chapter 8. The tone of Peterfreund’s comment implies, however, that Bronowski, Schorer
and Erdman have closed the case on the context issue, a fear I myself began to harbor until I realized that
some areas (especially that of ideology) still needed to be explored, and that new approaches were possible.
But Peterfreund oversteps the bounds of academic propriety when he attributes to me the view that “the
discussion of Blake’s artistic form and practice has been dominated by ‘formalists’ such as Erdman and
Anne K. Mellor (see pp. 240-45), who hold power in the academy and insist that the ideology in Blake’s art
be de-emphasized or ignored outright.” In the pages cited, Anne K. Mellor is not even mentioned, and nowhere
do I attach the label “formalist” to Erdman, or to Mellor. Indeed, my criticism of Mellor’s approach
(pp. 260-62) is that it is not formalist enough: “Such a loose, generalising approach, which interprets
‘the bounding line <hi rend="i">or enclosed form</hi> as the work of an oppressive reason,’ fails to
appreciate the fact that meaning, execution and design in Blake are subtly and <hi rend="i">necessarily</hi>
interwoven” (p. 261). As for David Erdman, in a personal letter to me dated 21 January 1985, he graciously
said of my book that it would help others writing on Blake “to get a better sense of Blake’s context,”
and that “All of us who study and teach Blake will benefit—and our students especially—from your book.
Thank you for writing it!” Had I regarded Erdman as some kind of establishment enemy, as Peterfreund tries
to insinuate, it is highly unlikely that he would have responded so favorably.</p>
          <pb id="p20-105" n="105"/>
          <p>A quotation from my discussion of metrics leads to a more serious misreading. Blake, I say,
“pushed the freedom principle further than any other English Romantic poet, even to the extent of writing a
free verse poem—the first of its kind in English” (p. 31). Peterfreund says: “The poem Crehan has in
mind is <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, which supposedly makes good Blake’s intention to move away from the
decasyllabic line and thus avoid ‘any “Augustan” relapse into some easy, confident expectation or
passive observation’ (p. 31).” First, the poem Crehan has in mind is <hi rend="i">not Jerusalem</hi>, as
is clear from the context. The poem he has in mind is the short free-verse Argument at the beginning of 
<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, which opens: “Rintrah roars,” and is introduced on page 33:
“The next stage, then, is free verse itself. . . .” Nowhere do I refer to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as a
“free verse poem.” But Peterfreund evidently wants to put in my mind that which will serve his own
project. <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (which I am supposed to champion as the apotheosis of formal freedom,
against everything I say elsewhere) is used to advance Peterfreund’s own undialectical approach to literary
history. Concerning “To the Public,” Peterfreund says: “What Crehan does not seem to realize is that
most of what Blake has to say in the paragraph under discussion refers, in a highly self-conscious manner, to
the statement entitled ‘The Verse’ which prefaces <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi>” Why I should be
thought unaware of such an obvious quotation is quite beyond me. Let me simply refer Peterfreund to my note on
the same passage on page 249 of my <hi rend="i">William Blake: Selected Poetry and Letters</hi> (Pergamon,
1976), to clear him of any misapprehensions. Blake’s self-conscious repudiation of blank verse involves both
a repudiation of Milton and, at the same time, through the use of the phrase “modern bondage,” a
recognition of Milton’s contribution towards such a metrical revolution. But the dialectics of transcendence
are lost on Peterfreund, who sees both Blake’s and Milton’s metrical innovations simply as a return to the
past. The key word here is “modern” (rather than “bondage”).</p>
          <p>“If Blake really intends to repudiate the poetic past, including the Miltonic source of his
very words of repudiation, Blake does so more in the service of convention than in the service of freedom,
authenticating his vision in relation to his poetic precursors just as Milton had authenticated his vision in
relation to his precursors.” From details of metrics we have wandered into “vision.” But this vision,
according to Peterfreund, depends for its authenticity, within its own terms, not on Poetic Genius, or
Imagination, or Inspiration, but on the Letter—on written tradition, and memory of that written tradition.
According to Blake, “As a man is, So he Sees. As the Eye is formed, such are its Powers. You certainly
Mistake, when you say that the Visions of Fancy are not to be found in This World. To Me This World is all One
continued Vision of Fancy or Imagination. . . .” Peterfreund would presumably add that none of this was
authentic for Blake until it had been stamped by the authority of certain “poetic precursors.” While we
are on this topic, do poets have given precursors, like people have ancestors? Or do poets select their own
precursors? And if they select their own, in what sense are they a validating authority? Why, in particular,
was Milton a precursor for Blake, rather than Pope or Shakespeare? What makes a poet anyhow? Peterfreund’s
glibness suddenly betrays an appalling superficiality.</p>
          <p>Let us return to the text in question. What Milton says (and Peterfreund quotes) is that his
rhyme-less poem should be “esteem’d an example set, the first in <hi rend="i">English</hi>, of ancient
liberty recover’d to Heroic Poem from the troublesome and modern bondage of Riming.” The invocation of
ancient rights and liberties was, of course, the accepted rhetoric of the seventeenth-century parliamentary
cause. Milton is proclaiming his verse as “the first” of its kind in English. In other words, as something
<hi rend="i">new.</hi> In quoting “the Miltonic source of his very words of repudiation,” Blake is not
serving “convention,” or tying himself to the past, but self-consciously placing his own work as the next
stage in the metrical revolution after Milton, rejecting <hi rend="i">blank verse itself</hi> as “derived
from the modern bondage of Rhyming.” I had, I confess, thought all this too obvious to go into, not
realizing that for some, nothing is obvious. (The comparisons I make between Miltonic and Blakean epic on
pages 292-98 are a critical analysis of Blake’s attempt to transcend Milton.)</p>
          <p>Peterfreund’s way of thinking is further illustrated when, referring to Enlightenment
rationalism, he says: “As a notebook poem like ‘Mock On Mock On Voltaire Rousseau’ makes clear, the cure
for such rationalism is hebraic vision, not bourgeois or popular revolution.” Peterfreund does not explain
his handy catchphrase. However, if it has anything to do with Mosaic law and the God of the Old Testament, we
should bear in mind Blake’s annotations to Watson’s <hi rend="i">Apology for the Bible</hi>, where he
defends a notable Enlightenment rationalist and revolutionary, Thomas Paine. (I ought to point out that I do
not share Peterfreund’s simplistic view of Blake’s relationship to Enlightenment rationalism.) Paine,
according to Blake, “only denies that God conversed with Murderers &amp; Revengers such as the Jews were,
&amp; of course he holds that the Jews conversed with their own State Religion which they call’d God &amp;
so were liars as Christ says,” adding: “That the Jews assumed a right Exclusively to the benefits of God
will be a lasting witness against them &amp; the same will it be against Christians.” Not much “hebraic
vision” there. But then it all depends what is meant by the phrase. In a late letter to
<pb id="p20-106" n="106"/>
George Cumberland (12 April 1827) Blake speaks of “Newton’s Doctrine of the Fluxions of an Atom, A Thing
that does not Exist.” However, the last stanza of the notebook poem cited by Peterfreund reads:
<q>
The Atoms of Democritus<lb/>
And Newton’s Particles of light<lb/>
<hi rend="i">Are</hi> sands upon the Red sea shore,<lb/>
Where Israel’s tents do shine so bright.<lb/>
(my emphasis)
</q>
Instead of simply denying the existence of atoms and particles, the poem imagines how, perceived from a
synthesizing viewpoint, they are <hi rend="i">transformed.</hi> In the synthesizing vision, they “Are” Red
Sea sands and shining tents, viewed prophetically, “every sand <hi rend="i">becomes</hi> a Gem” (stanza
two). For Blake, the atomizing mentality justifies a social order in which “minute particulars” (human
beings) are reduced and hardened into “grains of sand”—a profound critique, as I show on pages 78-84, of
<hi rend="i">both</hi> analytical philosophy <hi rend="i">and</hi> the alienating isolation of the individual
under the new capitalism. For the catchphrase “hebraic vision” to mean anything at all, it would have to
include such a critique, one that relates, as I point out on page 41, to a major Blakean insight: the 
<hi rend="i">ideological</hi> nature of perception. For some reason, Peterfreund associates “the situation Blake
describes as the ‘sands along the Red sea shore / Where Israel’s tents do shine so bright’ ” with the
“final stage of the socialist revolution,” i.e., the millennium. Why? Even if we accept that the lines
allude to the Israelites’ encampment <hi rend="i">after</hi> the crossing (Exodus in fact only mentions the
Israelites encamping <hi rend="i">before</hi> the crossing), there is nothing necessarily millennial here. The
Israelites still had a long way to go, and many difficulties to overcome, before they would see the Promised
Land. On one level, then, the phrase “shine so bright” connotes faith in the certainty of final victory,
rather than celebration of an achieved “final stage.”</p>
          <p>Peterfreund objects to the way I connect the lines: “You accumulate Particulars, &amp; murder
by analyzing, that you / May take the aggregate; &amp; you call the aggregate Moral Law” with passages from
<hi rend="i">Capital</hi>, informing us that what Blake “is actually talking about is the effect of
pharasaical codification on one’s perception of divinity in the world.” Like Thomas A. Vogler, reviewing
Morris Eaves’ <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Theory of Art</hi> (<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>,
24 [summer 1985]), I am always suspicious of those who, with an air of magisterial authority, tell us what
Blake is “<hi rend="i">actually</hi> talking about.” If the Blakean text were so transparent, Blakean
criticism and interpretation would have dried up long ago. Blake’s “actual” words are, in fact, merely
given another pseudo-Blakean gloss by Peterfreund. Every “explanation” of the Peterfreund type thus leads
to another: every decoding becomes another encoding. In this way, the tedious business of interpreting,
paraphrasing and explaining to the uninitiated what poets are “actually talking about” helps to keep the
mill-wheels of the academy turning. While I do not claim that my own gloss mirrors more faithfully what Blake
is “actually talking about”—I leave that to Peterfreund—I <hi rend="i">would</hi> claim that by
placing the passage in which the quoted lines occur in the context of contemporary philosophical, scientific
and economic discourse, I am at least able to suggest the historical and ideological resonances of the precise
words used, namely: “accumulate,” “Particulars,” “analyzing,” “aggregate,” and “Moral
Law.” Instead of rewriting Blake, which invariably means concocting a prosaic pseudo-Blake (“the effect of
pharasaical codification on one’s perception of divinity in the world”), I tried, through the contextual
approach, to show how the Blakean text <hi rend="i">refracts</hi> contemporary ideological discourses,
grapples and battles with them, and seeks, through its various literary strategies, to absorb, criticize, and
finally transcend them.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Blake in Context</hi> is, as Peterfreund obsessively reiterates, a Marxist analysis.
Its faults I would now be the first to acknowledge, especially the tendency towards reductionism and
“economistic” Marxism. Nevertheless, its discussion of visual art (praised by other critics as the most
original part of the book) best demonstrates its thesis, and it may be for this reason that Peterfreund has
chosen to completely ignore these crucial chapters. Instead, he pillories me for being “completely oblivious
(or willfully impervious)” to earlier statements by Morris Eaves, notably an article in 
<hi rend="i">Publishing History</hi>, 2 (1977), which addresses one of the central concerns of my book: the artist
as independent producer. Here I plead guilty. I did not know the article. What Eaves, quoted by Peterfreund,
says, is that “Blake’s artistic decision to become an independent publisher” was “a landmark in the
history of publishing” because “he was far more aware than most others of why he was doing it.” Nothing
to argue with there. My own view, carefully elaborated throughout the book, is that Blake’s independent
stand was a radical yet logical extension of the Romantic project (the emergence of “a freely creating
individual” whose source of creativity lies within his “own” personality and way of perceiving—what
Caudwell calls the quintessential bourgeois illusion); a break with Tory patronage and Royalist norms; an
attempt to “absorb the role of that spectre, the commercial middleman” (p. 16); a utopian reaction against
the middle-class art market and the reduction of art to a commodity, a reaction that is also part of a new
historical phenomenon—“the Radical, plebeian intellectual and self-educated artist or craftsman who is now
emerging as a potent force for change” (pp. 143-44); a revival of the medieval illuminated manuscript
tradition, combined with a conscious enhancement of the print, unparalleled in the history of art; a triumph
of anti-illusionism, “visionary art” and the linearist
<pb id="p20-107" n="107"/>
tradition, impossible without an independent stand; a craftist reaction, anticipating William Morris; an
aesthetic revolution (unity and interdependence of text and illustration, word and image); a series of
technical innovations (etching technique, color printing, etc.) foreshadowing Walter Benjamin’s argument
that any artistic challenge to the dominant production relations must also revolutionize “the techniques and
forces of artistic production” (p. 242); an insistence on the unity of conception and execution, separated
in the patron-protégé relationship, as with Hayley; an assertion of the central importance of creative
labor, and so on. In sum: “Blake was always his own printer and bookseller—not out of some Crusoe-like,
do-it-yourself crankiness, but for important artistic and ideological reasons” (p. 148).</p>
          <p>Ignoring this analysis, Peterfreund says: “Eaves succeeds in his book, while Crehan fails in
his.” By way of reply, I would refer Peterfreund to Vogler’s review of <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Theory of Art</hi>, which “undoes” Eaves’ text by revealing, and thus deconstructing, its recurrent
metaphors of private property. Far from equipping us with a historically objective account of Romantic
ideology, which <hi rend="i">Blake in Context</hi> explicitly attempts, these metaphors remain imprisoned in
that ideology. As Jerome McGann says: “the scholarship and criticism of Romanticism and its works are
dominated by a Romantic Ideology, by an uncritical absorption in Romanticism’s own
self-representations.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> To quote
Vogler: “Eaves’ argument is thus informed by a paradigm of class structure which privileges the isolation
and monadic autonomy of the bourgeois subject, and ‘behind’ his theory of art there would seem to be a
theory of the subject in consumer or late monopoly capitalism.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n2" type="note">2</ref> One could go further: Eaves’ ‘monadic’ paradigm is even given
determinate form by the subject of Eaves’ own discourse: William Blake. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi>
Jerome McGann, <hi rend="i">The Romantic Ideology: A Critical Investigation</hi> (Chicago: Univ. of Chicago
Press, 1983), p. 1.</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Thomas A. Vogler, review of Morris Eaves, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Theory of Art</hi>, in <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>, 24 (summer 1985), 294.</note></p>
          <p>We come, finally, to the most astonishing remark in Peterfreund’s review: that in chapter 10 I
seek to show “that the aptness of [my] social and artistic analysis rests on a hitherto undiscussed
tradition of working-class English radical protestantism,” and that if this tradition had not existed,
“Blake, Marx (perhaps), and Crehan (certainly) would have found it necessary to invent” it! I am hardly
the first to view Blake’s work in the light of this radical, millenarian tradition. Denis Saurat began to do
so as long ago as 1929. The many references in my book to Edward Thompson’s classic study, <hi rend="i">The
Making of the English Working Class</hi>, and to related work by A. L. Morton, Christopher Hill, Jack Lindsay,
J. F. C. Harrison, and others, including David Erdman, are proof enough. One is left with the astonishing
conclusion that Peterfreund himself thinks that such a tradition has been “hitherto undiscussed.” His
remarks about having to invent it even indicate a certain careless indifference as to whether it existed or
not. I would not insist that an intimate knowledge of this tradition is essential for readers of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, or that writers of pseudo-Blake need to brush up on their working-class history to be
clear on what Blake “is actually talking about.” However, if I were ignorant of such a tradition, I would
not feel particularly proud of the fact, especially if I claimed to know something about the Blakean
millennium. Peterfreund evidently <hi rend="i">is</hi> proud, and for this he surely deserves an award of some
kind. His attitude shows star quality.</p>
          <p>Peterfreund’s last little dart is that my book was written in Zambia (in fact, it was written
in England) and needs buttressing with “more evidence of careful and reputable research.” Dutiful,
graduate-style buttressing was a preliminary stage, admittedly; after four or five years I was able to get rid
of the scaffolding, and to resist the temptation to fill the book with counterarguments and refutations. The
task was not easy, but in Blake studies, one has to be selective. I decided, in other words, to let the
argument speak for itself, to present my ideas in a distilled form, rather than playing the academic game, in
the possibly naive belief that no amount of buttressing compensates for a poverty of ideas. The principle was
this: that when a building is complete, the scaffolding is removed, and that when a wine is bottled, no
sediment remains. If Peterfreund likes sediment in his wine, that is up to him. Likewise, should he wish, at
some future date, to rifle my book for his own scholarly purposes without acknowledging his source (I
particularly recommend the comparison between Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and Richard Brothers’
<hi rend="i">Description of Jerusalem</hi> on pages 348-49), then that is also up to him. What he should not
do is pretend, with First World arrogance, that he has something spiritually in common with Blake because he
can trot out a phrase such as “hebraic vision.” The school of Blake is a hard school, especially for
reactionary academicians (whom Blake, we know, detested). For the likes of Peterfreund, who have made it their
profession to twist revolutionary thought into its opposite, I doubt if it is possible to gain access to what
Blake “was actually saying” at all, despite pretensions to the contrary.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
