<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>20.3.dorrbecker</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="checklist">Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Recent Publications</title>
        <author n="Dörrbecker">Detlef W. Dörrbecker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1986-87</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1986-87</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">20.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stewart Crehan</name>
              <name>D. W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Stuart Peterfreund</name>
              <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1987"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_20">
    <body>
    <pb id="p20-76" n="76"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-3-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Recent Publications</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">D.W.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">DÖRRBECKER</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>Because of various technical and organizational difficulties, no annual checklist of recent
scholarship was published in the 1985 volume of <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> The present compilation therefore
tries to catch up with what has happened since Thomas L. Minnick and I handed in the 1984 list (see 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 18 [1984]: 100-15); it covers the period from summer 1984 to—roughly—early summer
1986, with some additional pre-1984 items interspersed which previously had escaped our attention. If,
therefore, the 1986 edition of the checklist is much bulkier than earlier ones, this is the most important and
obvious reason. But there are some others, too.</p>
        <p>It needs no stressing, I suppose, that a periodical checklist like this may well reach for but
never will attain completeness, and this is especially so if such a list is concerned with English art and
literature, but compiled at various museum and university libraries in Germany. However, there are at least
two distinct features of <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>’s checklists which, I believe, guarantee their usefulness
to its readers. One is the actuality of this report on recent developments in Blake studies and its
neighboring fields (particularly when we resume publication on an annual basis). The other is the reviews
section. This part of the checklist—despite its being very likely the least complete—gives access to a
field of publication where one can often meet with observations as pertinent and innovative as those of the
scholarly books and articles listed in the other sections. Since no other bibliography attempts to give a full
account of the review literature in Blake studies, I have devoted more time and care to this than to any other
class of publications—well knowing that all too many lacunae will remain.</p>
        <p>A few more words concerning the organization, entry format, and coverage of the present checklist
may prove useful. In general, I have retained the format of four main sections with a number of subdivisions
which has been known to the readers of this journal since 1980. Coverage in parts II and III, however, has
always been—and probably to a certain extent will remain—problematic. Are Mary Wollstonecraft and Angelica
Kauffmann or Thomas Paine and William Godwin to be considered members of Blake’s circle?—and has not the
Related Interest section always looked a little haphazard in scope, either too inclusive or exclusive in its
coverage?</p>
        <p>Let me recite a few of the criteria for selection, annotation, and bibliographical style that I
have followed while compiling the present list.</p>
        <p>(1) Blake’s circle has been drawn slightly smaller than in previous years, thus excluding, for
example, Edward Young and Robert Blair (whose works were illustrated by the artist, just as those of Dante and
Milton or the Bible, but whom he did not know personally), while retaining entries for such figures as Cowper
or Erasmus Darwin (contemporaries at least, whose inclusion is nevertheless open to discussion, I think).</p>
        <p>(2) Part III is the only section of the checklist which—by necessity—is selective rather than
extensive in its coverage. Its contents have been assembled (and subdivided) according to the following few
guidelines. First there are entries for some general studies of British Romantic poetry and art which either
mention Blake’s works in a larger context and/or are thought to have some bearing on the interpretation of
these works, and/or have been reviewed in the pages of this journal. Then, I have included here a selection of
books and articles on what might be termed Blake’s “outer circle,” i.e., some contemporary authors and
artists who may have been influential for his productions here or there, and who are not covered in any other
subject bibliography that is known to me. Since the history of Blake scholarship—during the next decade or
so—is bound to become a major field of study in itself, part III also includes entries for biographical and
critical assessments of some influential Blake scholars and collectors (and even lists the printing of two of
Foster Damon’s poems). Reports on poetical, theatrical, or film adaptations of Blake’s works, as well as
statements concerning their influence on modern contemporary art and literature, make up the final section of
part III. I have decided, however, to omit adaptations of Blake’s poems by recording artists such as
Marianne Faithfull, who quotes from “The Tyger” in her “Eye Communication,” or Sting, who refers
<pb id="p20-77" n="77"/>
to the “dark satanic mills” in his “We Work the Black Seam.”</p>
        <p>(3) Brief annotations have been provided for at least those book-length studies which to my
knowledge have not hitherto been the subject of extensive reviews, and to a number of articles the titles of
which I thought were not fully self-explanatory. These annotations follow the bibliographical information in
square brackets. Prices have been quoted where available.</p>
        <p>(4) I have agreed with the editors to adopt (with very few exceptions) for the formal presentation
of the bibliographical data the rules and regulations laid down by Walter S. Achtert and Joseph Gibaldi in 
<hi rend="i">The MLA Style Manual</hi> (New York, NY: Modern Language Association of America, 1985). This explains
the punctuation of the entries, which differs slightly from our earlier lists, and explains the use of certain
standard abbreviations such as “U” for “University,” or “P” for “Press.” The items in each
section are arranged in strict alphabetical order by name of author and title. At least in the reviews section
of earlier editions of this checklist I often attempted a chronological sequence where the same book had been
reviewed more than once; now, these entries have been alphabetized by the reviewers’ names and, for easy
reference, have also been numbered review by review.</p>
        <p>From the foregoing it should be fairly evident that something can be done (and maybe even has to be
done) about the organization and the scope of parts II and III in the future. I shall be grateful for any
suggestions made by those who work with these checklists.</p>
                  <p>Finally, it gives me great pleasure to record my <corr type="emend">indebtedness</corr> to those friends and colleagues who
have shared some bibliographical information with me or have kindly sent offprints from their articles (which
is always very helpful): Rodney M. Baine, Stephen C. Behrendt, G. E. Bentley, Jr., Martin Butlin, Claudia
Corti, Morris Eaves, Helen B. Ellis, Robert N. Essick, Michael Fischer, David S. Fuller, Marilyn Gaull and
Maurizio Giammarco, Mark L. Greenberg, Jean H. Hagstrum, Nelson Hilton, Terence A. Hoagwood, Traude
Kannengiesser, Donald Masterson, Horst Meller, Edward O’Shea, Morton D. Paley, François Piquet, Kathleen
Raine, Aquilino Sánchez Pérez, Wilhelm Schlink, and Joseph S. Viscomi. The Darwin section would not be half
so well informed without the expert knowledge of Desmond King-Hele. Also, I wish to thank all those publishing
houses, museums, and journal editors in Britain, Italy, Japan, and the United States who have kindly supplied
me with inspection copies and have thus contributed largely to the accuracy and completeness of the present
list. Any omissions that remain, will, of course, if brought to my attention, duly be recorded in next
year’s compilation.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="i">Note: An asterisk beside an entry on the list identifies an item that I have not
examined.</hi>
        </p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part I William Blake</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Editions, Translations, Facsimiles, Reproductions</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>1. Bentley, G. E., Jr., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Works in Conventional Typography:
Facsimile Reproductions.</hi> Scholars’ Facsimiles and Reprints 388. Delmar, NY: Scholars’ Facsimiles and
Reprints, 1984. $55.</p>
            <p>2. *Blair, Robert. <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi> 1858. West Orange, NJ: Saifer, 1984. $25.
[Probably a facsimile reproduction of the Stanford and Delisser reissue of A. L. Dick’s steel engravings
after Blake’s 1808 Blair illustrations.]</p>
            <p>3. Blondel, Jacques, ed. and trans. <hi rend="i">Vala, ou Les Quatre vivants.</hi> Vol. 4 of
<hi rend="i">Oeuvres de William Blake.</hi> Paris: Aubier, 1983. Fr.150. [This is the fourth volume of the
bilingual edition which was initiated by Pierre Leyris. Besides the translation of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, it
also contains the French versions of Blake’s annotations to Watson’s <hi rend="i">Apology</hi>, to
Bacon’s <hi rend="i">Essays</hi>, and to Boyd’s commentary on Dante’s <hi rend="i">Inferno.</hi>
Blondel’s introduction takes up pp. 7-55, and there is a short bibliography on pp. 597-98.]</p>
            <p>4. Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. <hi rend="i">To the Nightingale.</hi> By William Blake. Isle of Ely:
Waterside P, 1981. [This edition, printed privately and limited to 100 copies which are signed by the editor,
consists of only two printed crown quarto pages of text, the first of which contains the poem itself, and the
second a “Statement” concerning its attribution to the author of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches.</hi> This
attribution has also been made in an article for the <hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi> and a 
<hi rend="i">Nightingale</hi> anthology, compiled by the late Sir Geoffrey in collaboration with Peter Davidson;
see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 16 (1982): 114, #80; 18 (1984): 100, #6.]</p>
            <p>5. *Milton, John. <hi rend="i">On the Morning of Christ’s Nativity.</hi> With a Note on the
Illustrations by Martin Butlin. Andoversford: Whittington P, 1981. [Reproduces the Whitworth series of
Blake’s watercolors in color.]</p>
            <p>6. Schmiele, Walter, ed. <hi rend="i">Poesie der Welt: England.</hi> Edition Stichnote: Ex
Libris Ausgabe. Frankfort on Main, W. Ger.: Propyläen-Ullstein, 1985. 50-71. [These pages contain a selection
of translations from Blake’s shorter poems; no translator is credited.]</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">See also #110 for a complete printing of Blake’s</hi> Song of Los, 
<hi rend="i">and #119 for a newly attributed poem.</hi></p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p20-78" n="78"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Bibliographies, Bibliographical Essays, Catalogues</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>7. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Keynes and Blake at Cambridge.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 69-71.</p>
            <p>8. Borck, Jim Springer, ed. <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A Current Bibliography</hi> ns
6 for 1980. New York, NY: AMS P, 1984. [For Blake entries see pp. 320, 396 to 402. The more extensive reviews
in this annotated bibliography are listed separately in part IV, where this volume is referred to in
abbreviated form as “<hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 6 (1980).”]</p>
            <p>9. Borck, Jim Springer, ed. <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A Current Bibliography</hi> ns
7 for 1981. New York, NY: AMS P, 1985. [For Blake entries see pp. 392-401 and passim. The more extensive
reviews in this annotated bibliography are cited separately in part IV, where this volume is referred to in
abbreviated form as “<hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 7 (1981).”]</p>
            <p>10. Brown, David Blayney. “The Romantic Tradition: William Blake to Robin Tanner.” 
<hi rend="i">The Print in England, 1790-1930: A Private Collection.</hi> Ed. Craig Hartley and Susan Ridyard.
Cambridge, Cambs.: Fitzwilliam Museum, 1985. 40-69. [Works by Blake, Flaxman, and Palmer were included in this
section (#53-108) of an exhibition which drew on the holdings of the Robert Loder collection. See also #19,
below.]</p>
            <p>11. Burns, Bryan, Philip Dodd, and Vincent Newey. “The Nineteenth Century: Romantic
Period.” <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 62 (1981). Ed. Laurel Brake. London: Murray;
Atlantic Highlands, NJ: Humanities P; for the English Association, 1984. 277-305. [See pp. 280-84 for a
summary review of 1981 Blake scholarship by Newey; additional references are listed in the index of authors
treated.]</p>
            <p>12. Burns, Bryan, Philip Dodd, and Vincent Newey. “The Nineteenth Century: Romantic
Period.” <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 63 (1982). Ed. Laurel Brake. London: Murray;
Atlantic Highlands, NJ: Humanities P; for the English Association, 1985. 277-307. [See pp. 278-81 for Vincent
Newey’s summary review of 1982 Blake scholarship; again, more references to Blake will be found in the
index.]</p>
            <p>13. Cox, Stephen D. “Recent Work on Blake.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18
(1985): 391-405. [A review article; its contents are listed separately in part IV, below.]</p>
            <p>14. Erdman, David V., with the assistance of Brian J. Dendle, et al., eds. <hi rend="i">The
Romantic Movement: A Selective and Critical Bibliography for 1982.</hi> Garland Reference Library of the
Humanities 217. New York, NY: Garland, 1983. [For Blake entries see pp. 77-94. The more extensive reviews in
this annotated bibliography are also cited separately in part IV, where this volume is referred to in
abbreviated form as “<hi rend="i">RMB for 1982.</hi>”]</p>
            <p>15. Erdman, David V., with the assistance of Brian J. Dendle, et al., eds. <hi rend="i">The
Romantic Movement: A Selective and Critical Bibliography for 1983.</hi> Garland Reference Library of the
Humanities 218. New York, NY: Garland, 1984. [For Blake entries see pp. 74-89. The more extensive reviews in
this annotated bibliography are also listed separately in part IV, where this volume is referred to in
abbreviated form as “<hi rend="i">RMB for 1983.</hi>”]</p>
            <p>16. Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">The Works of William Blake in the Huntington Collections: A
Complete Catalogue.</hi> San Marino, CA: Henry E. Huntington Library, 1985. [Very fully annotated entries, a
model of what a catalogue of a museum’s special collections can be, and often supplying information which is
important for the understanding of Blake’s works in other collections, too.]</p>
            <p>17. [Haddad, Rosemary, Christopher Heppner, and Elizabeth Lewis]. <hi rend="i">A Catalogue of
the Lawrence Lande William Blake Collection in the Department of Rare Books and Special Collections of the
McGill University Libraries.</hi> Montreal, PQ: McLennan Library/McGill U, 1983. $60. [A limited edition of
500 numbered copies, only 400 of which are for sale. A fine collection, and a catalogue printed on fine paper;
the compilation of the entries, however, does follow standard librarian practice, which is not particularly
illuminating for a figure like Blake, whose works have already—and more than once—been the subject of
competent bibliographical description. The contents of the Lande collection can best be compared with those of
the Preston Blake Library; the catalogue of the latter, published by Westminster City Libraries in 1969 and
1976, is similar in scope, but was sold at a much more reasonable price.]</p>
            <p>18. Hawcroft, Francis W. <hi rend="i">“The most beautiful art of England:” Fifty
Watercolours, 1750-1850.</hi> Manchester, Lancs.: Whitworth Art Gallery, 1983. [Blake was represented by no
less than four out of the fifty works in this exhibition; they are here catalogued as #17-20.]</p>
            <p>19. Loder, R[obert] B. <hi rend="i">William Blake to David Hockney: A Private Collection of
British Prints.</hi> Oxford, Oxon.: Ashmolean Museum, 1982. £0.75. [This leaflet was published to accompany
an exhibition of some of the finest works in the Loder collection, staged at the Ashmolean from 5 Feb. to 28
Mar. 1982. Besides a brief foreword by Kenneth Garlick, it contains an introduction and a list of the exhibits
by the collector, including eleven Blakes, one Linnell, four Calverts, and thirteen Palmer prints. See also
#10, above, for another exhibition catalogue with materials from the same private collection.]</p>
            <p>20. Minnick, Thomas L., and Detlef W. Dörrbecker. “Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of
Recent Publications.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 100-15.</p>
            <pb id="p20-79" n="79"/>
            <p>21. Modern Language Association of America. “Blake, William (1757-1827).” <hi rend="i">1983
MLA International Bibliography of Books and Articles on the Modern Languages and Literatures.</hi> Vol. 1:
“Classified Listings.” New York, NY: MLA, 1984. 59-60. [See also s. v. “Blake” in vol. 1 of the
subject index for further references.]</p>
            <p>22. Modern Language Association of America. “Blake, William (1757-1827).” <hi rend="i">1984
MLA International Bibliography of Books and Articles on the Modern Languages and Literatures.</hi> Vol. 1:
“Classified Listings.” New York, NY: MLA, 1985. 62-63. [See also s. v. “Blake” in vol. 1 of the
subject index for further references.]</p>
            <p>23. Smith, Michael, with the assistance of Mary Jean DeMarr, eds. <hi rend="i">Annual
Bibliography of English Language and Literature</hi> 56 for 1981. London: Modern Humanities Research
Association, 1984. [Blake entries appear on pp. 330-33 as #5955-6033.]</p>
            <p>24. Smith, Michael, with the assistance of Mary Jean DeMarr, eds. <hi rend="i">Annual
Bibliography of English Language and Literature</hi> 57 for 1982. London: Modern Humanities Research
Association, 1985. [Blake entries appear on pp. 325-30 as #5921-6016.]</p>
            <p>25. [William Weston Gallery]. <hi rend="i">The English Vision: An Exhibition of Original Prints
by William Blake 1757-1827, Samuel Palmer 1805-1881, Edward Calvert 1799-1883.</hi> Catalogue 11 (1985) [whole
no. 195]. London: William Weston Gallery, 1985. [There are some sixty unnumbered pages in this small, but
illustrated catalogue of a sale exhibition. The forty-seven items offered included sets of Blake’s Virgil
wood-engravings, his <hi rend="i">Job</hi> prints, as well as some of the rarer Calvert engravings.]</p>
            <p>
              <hi rend="i">See also #198 below.</hi>
            </p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Critical Studies</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>26. Adkins, Camille. “In Adam’s Room: Incarnation of the Divine Image in 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
International</hi> 45 (1984): 1404A. Texas Christian U. [“. . . Blake . . . shared Milton’s interest in
the concept of incarnation. Both poets uphold the Protestant assertion which entitles each individual to
private judgment in matters of conscience. This individualism leads Milton and Blake to unique perceptions of
the myths which underlie <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>—the myth of
Genesis, the fall and redemption of the Sophia, several mystic marriages, including that of Eros and Psyche. .
. . Milton perceives a God who is all light, whereas Blake recognizes light and darkness in divinity.”]</p>
            <p>27. Adlard, John. “Blake and Wimbledon.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 31 (1984):
468.</p>
            <p>28. Adlard, John, and B. J. M. Folliot. “A Blake Poem.” <hi rend="i">Times Literary
Supplement</hi> 21 Sept. 1984: 1055. [Two letters to the editor, commenting on Geoffrey Keynes’s attribution
of “The Phoenix to Mrs Butts” to William Blake; see #119, below.]</p>
            <p>29. Anderson, Mark. “Oothoon, Failed Prophet.” <hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and
Present</hi> 8.2 (1984): 1-21.</p>
            <p>30. Anderson, Mark. “Why Is That Fairy in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>?” <hi rend="i">Colby
Library Quarterly</hi> 21 (1985): 122-33.</p>
            <p>31. Baine, Rodney M. “Blake’s Sons of Los.” <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> 63
(1984): 239-54.</p>
            <p>32. Beer, John. <hi rend="i">William Blake 1757-1827.</hi> Writers and Their Work 277. Windsor,
Berks.: Profile Books, 1982. £1.50. [A brief introduction to Blake’s work (46 pp. of text), obviously
designed to replace Miss Raine’s text of 1951 in the same series (3rd ed., 1969). The select bibliography
has been augmented and brought up to date (pp. 47-52), but retains most of the misprints of publication dates
of the earlier editions and adds a few new ones.]</p>
            <p>33. Behrendt, Stephen C. “<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> and Blake’s View of the Fall.”
<hi rend="i">Trivium</hi> 18 (1983): 39-48.</p>
            <p>34. Behrendt, Stephen C. “‘This Accursed Family:’ Blake’s <hi rend="i">America</hi> and
the American Revolution.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 27 (1986):
26-51.</p>
            <p>35. Bennett, Shelley M. “A New Blake at the Huntington.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 132-39.</p>
            <p>36. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “The Daughters of Albion and the Butts Household.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 116.</p>
            <p>37. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “The Felpham Rummer: A New Angel and ‘Immoral Drink’ Attributed
to William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 94-99.</p>
            <p>38. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “From ‘London’ to ‘Jerusalem:’ The City in William Blake’s
Poetry.” <hi rend="i">Aligarh Journal of English Studies</hi> 10 (1985): 35-48.</p>
            <p>39. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “From Sketch to Text in Blake: The Case of <hi rend="i">The Book of
Thel.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1986): 128-41.</p>
            <p>40. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Thomas Sivright and the Lost Designs for Blair’s 
<hi rend="i">Grave.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 103-06.</p>
            <p>41. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “‘The Triumph of Owen:’ William Owen Pughe and Blake’s
‘Ancient Britons.’ ” <hi rend="i">National Library of Wales Journal</hi> 24 (1985): 248-61.</p>
            <p>42. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “[‘Tyger’ and ‘Lamb:’ A Question Easy to Pose, Yet Hard to
Answer.]” <hi rend="i">Guo-wai Wenxue</hi> 15 (1984): 86-113. [An essay on Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, printed in no. 3 of the 1984 volume of this Chinese journal on the foreign
languages—not only the first of Bentley’s articles I have seen in Chinese characters, but also the first
time I have come across Chinese versions of Blake’s poems; I couldn’t read either.]</p>
            <pb id="p20-80" n="80"/>
            <p>43. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “The Way of a Papermaker with a Poet: Joshua Gilpin, William Blake,
and the Arts in 1796.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 33 (1986): 80-84. [In a “Postscript,”
which has not yet been published, the author presents additional evidence that—alas!—leaves no doubts as
to the identity of Gilpin’s Blake: he was the writing engraver William Staden Blake of Exchange Alley, not
the painter-poet as Bentley had assumed when submitting his article in 1985.]</p>
            <p>44. Berninghausen, Thomas F. “The Marriage of Contraries in ‘To Tirzah.’ ” 
<hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 20 (1984): 191-98.</p>
            <p>45. Bidney, Martin. “Faulkner’s Variations on Romantic Themes: Blake, Wordsworth, Byron,
and Shelly in <hi rend="i">Light in August.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Mississippi Quarterly</hi> 38 (1985):
277-86.</p>
            <p>46. Billigheimer, Rachel V. “The Eighth Eye: Prophetic Vision in Blake’s Poetry and
Design.” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 22 (1986): 93-110.</p>
            <p>47. Blaydes, Sophia B., and Philip Bordinat. “Blake’s ‘Jerusalem’ and Popular Culture:
<hi rend="i">The Loneliness of the Long-Distance Runner</hi> and <hi rend="i">Chariots of Fire.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Literature / Film Quarterly</hi> 11 (1983): 211-14.</p>
            <p>48. *Blondel, Jacques. “L’Eros blakien.” <hi rend="i">Romantisme anglais et Eros.</hi>
Ed. Christian La Cassagnère. Publications de la Faculté des Letters et Sciences Humaines de l’Université
de Clermont-Ferrand II 14. Clermont-Ferrand: U de Clermont-Ferrand II, 1982. 7-16.</p>
            <p>49. *Blondel, Jacques. “William Blake: De l’enfance au progrès de contraries.” 
<hi rend="i">L’Enfance et les ouvrages d’éducation.</hi> Vol. 1: “Avant 1800.” Ed. Paule M.
Pénigault-Duhet. Nantes: U de Nantes, 1983. 119-42.</p>
            <p>50. Bloom, Harold, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Modern Critical Views. New York, NY:
Chelsea House, 1985. $17.95. [“This volume gathers together a representative selection of the best criticism
devoted to William Blake from 1950 until the present.” To this purpose Bloom has selected essays by David V.
Erdman, Robert F. Gleckner, Northrop Frye, W. J. T. Mitchell, Thomas R. Frosch, Thomas Weiskel, Susan Fox,
Leslie Brisman, Leopold Damrosch, Jr., David Wagenknecht, Diana Hume George, and by himself. There are about
200 pages of text, plus a select bibliography.]</p>
            <p>51. Bracher, Mark. <hi rend="i">“Being Form’d:” Thinking Through Blake’s</hi> Milton.
Barrytown, NY: Clinamen Studies—Station Hill P, 1985. $9.95 paper.</p>
            <p>52. Bracher, Mark. “The Metaphysical Grounds of Oppression in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Visions
of the Daughters of Albion.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 20 (1984): 164-76.</p>
            <p>53. Brown, James Boyd. “The History of an Illusion: The Meaning of the Four Zoas in Blake’s
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 44 (1984):
3385-86A. York U, Canada. [Intended “to demonstrate two hypotheses. The first is that each of the Zoas has
an essential core of meaning which can be understood by ‘translating’ it into regular English words. . . .
My second hypothesis is that the poem has a referential structure: its plot presents Blake’s view of the
history of man.”]</p>
            <p>54. Butlin, Martin. “Two Blakes Reappear and Make Three.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 118-19.</p>
            <p>55. *Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Rev. ed. Salem, NH: Salem
House-Merrimack, 1985. $6.95. [According to the author, this is a revised version in a larger format of his
guide to the Tate Gallery’s Blake collection; first published in The Tate Gallery Little Book Series in
1966, reprinted in 1968, 1972, 1975, 1978, and—revised—in 1983.]</p>
            <p>56. Butter, P. H. “William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 4 Feb. 1983:
108. [A letter to the editor in reply to Enright’s review of the author’s <hi rend="i">Blake: Selected
Poems</hi>; see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 17 (1983): 72, #214.]</p>
            <p>57. Chayes, Irene H. “Blake’s Ways with Art Sources: Michelangelo’s <hi rend="i">The Last
Judgment.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 20 (1984): 60-89.</p>
            <p>58. Connolly, Thomas E. “Point of View in Interpreting ‘The Fly.’ ” 
<hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi> 22.1 (1984): 32-37.</p>
            <p>59. Cooper, Robert M. “Felpham.” <hi rend="i">The Literary Guide and Companion to Southern
England.</hi> Athens, OH: Ohio UP, 1985. 115-17. [No news in this account of Blake’s Felpham years.]</p>
            <p>60. Cramer, Patricia. “The Role of Ahania’s Lament in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Book of
Ahania</hi>: A Psychoanalytic Study.” <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi> 83 (1984):
522-33.</p>
            <p>61. Crossan, Greg. “‘Infant Sorrow’ and Robert Greene’s <hi rend="i">Menaphon.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1986): 142-43.</p>
            <p>62. Cushing, James Byers. “The Figure of the Poet: Self-Representation in Young, Blake, and
Wordsworth.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 44 (1984): 3387A. U of California,
Irvine. [Treats Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs as a critical comment on Young, and 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> as responding “to <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> in its (the poem’s) focus
on the figure of the poet, Los, and his struggle to represent himself.”]</p>
            <p>63. Deen, Leonard W. <hi rend="i">Conversing in Paradise: Poetic Genius and
Identity-as-Community in Blake’s Los.</hi> Columbia, MO: U of Missouri P, 1983. $23.</p>
            <p>64. Dörrbecker, Detlef W. “Fläche, Linie, Figur und Raum: Grundzüge der Bildform bei
William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Unijournal: Zeitschrift der Universität Trier</hi> 12.2 (1986): 6. [A
dissertation abstract; U of Trier, West Germany.]</p>
            <p>65. Dörrbecker, D. W. “Grant’s ‘Problems in Understanding:’ Some Marginalia.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 185-90. [Part of the public debate between one
of the editors of the Clarendon edition
<pb id="p20-81" n="81"/>
of the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs and some of its reviewers; see also #89, 140, and 148,
below.]</p>
            <p>66. Ellis, Helen. “Blake’s ‘Bible of Hell:’ <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
Albion</hi> and the Song of Solomon.” <hi rend="i">English Studies in Canada</hi> 12 (1986): 23-36.</p>
            <p>67. *Engelborghs, Maurits. “Het grafisch werk van William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dietsche
Warande en Belfort</hi> 128 (1982): 297-300. [Possibly not more than a review of the Dutch edition of
Bindman’s <hi rend="i">The Complete Graphic Works of William Blake.</hi>]</p>
            <p>68. Essick, Robert N. “Blake in the Marketplace, 1982-1983.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 68-93.</p>
            <p>69. Essick, Robert N. “Blake in the Marketplace, 1984.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 24-38.</p>
            <p>70. Essick, Robert N. “Blake in the Marketplace, 1985.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986): 12-31.</p>
            <p>71. Essick, Robert N. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi>: Some Unrecorded Proofs and Their
Inscriptions.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 96-102.</p>
            <p>72. Essick, Robert N. “<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: Intention and Production.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 216-220.</p>
            <p>73. Essick, Robert N. “A ‘New’ Blake Engraving?” <hi rend="i">Print Quarterly</hi> 2
(1985): 42-47. [Discusses an engraving showing the “Carfax Conduit, Oxford,” signed “Blake sc.,” and
probably to be attributed to the poet-engraver William Blake. “The graphic style and subject of 
<hi rend="i">Carfax Conduit</hi> support the attribution made possible by the signature in the plate. Although
this assemblage of evidence is far from conclusive, it is at least as convincing as the reasons for
attributing to Blake a number of book illustrations of the 1770s generally included in his canon without
hesitation.” (p. 47)]</p>
            <p>74. Essick, Robert N. “Variation, Accident, and Intention in William Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.” Studies in Bibliography</hi> 39 (1986): 230-35. [Demonstrates that a loose
impression of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> 4 originally had been intended for inclusion in Copy G, and thereby
defines the extent to which accidents in the printing process may have affected the texts of Blake’s
illuminated books—brief, but important.]</p>
            <p>75. Essick, Robert N. “William Blake, William Hamilton, and the Materials of Graphic
Meaning.” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi> 52 (1985): 833-72.</p>
            <p>76. Fenske, Siglinde, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake 1757-1827.</hi> Maler: Leben, Werk und
ihre Zeit 15. Hamburg, W. Ger.: Marshall Cavendish International, 1986. DM4.90. [An illustrated pamphlet in a
popular series; an English version has probably been published in the United Kingdom and the United
States.]</p>
            <p>77. *Ferber, Michael. <hi rend="i">The Social Vision of William Blake.</hi> Princeton, NJ:
Princeton UP, 1985. $29.50.</p>
            <p>78. *Filipova, Evgenija. “Revducionnite idei v poezijata na Uiljam Bleik [Revolutionary Ideas
in the Poetry of William Blake].” <hi rend="i">Rodna reč</hi> 26.4 (1982): 40-42.</p>
            <p>79. Finch, G. J. “Romantic Poetry and the Limits of Explication.” <hi rend="i">Ariel</hi>
16.1 (1985): 27-42. [For a discussion of these limits in the interpretation of the works of Blake see pp.
37-41.]</p>
            <p>80. Fischer, Michael. “Blake’s Quarrel with Indeterminacy.” <hi rend="i">New Orleans
Review</hi> 10 (1983): 43-49. [See <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 17 (1983): 68,
#133.]</p>
            <p>81. *Forbes, Gregory. <hi rend="i">A Companion to the New Musical Settings</hi> [for 
<hi rend="i">Selections from William Blake’s</hi> Songs of Innocence and of Experience] <hi rend="i">by Gregory
Forbes.</hi> Kingston, ON: Quarry P, 1983.</p>
            <p>82. Fuller, David. “<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, and the Development of Blake’s Thought.”
<hi rend="i">An Infinite Complexity: Essays in Romanticism.</hi> Ed. J. R. Watson. University of Durham
Commemoration Series 1. Edinburgh: Edinburgh UP, 1983. 46-94.</p>
            <p>83. Gaddy, Holly C. “The Poet as Monk.” <hi rend="i">Massachusetts Studies in English</hi>
9.4 (1984): 1-12. [The monk is Thomas Merton, and the article is devoted to Blake’s influence on him.]</p>
                      <p>84. Genet, Jacqueline. “Blake et Yeats: Deux modes d’approche d’une même tradition.”
<hi rend="i">Études Irlandaises</hi> ns 8 (1983): 21-39.</p>
            <p>85. Glausser, Wayne. “The Gates of Memory in Night VIIa of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.”
Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 196-203.</p>
            <p>86. *Gleckner, Robert F. <hi rend="i">Blake and Spenser.</hi> Baltimore, MD: Johns Hopkins UP,
1985. $29.50.</p>
            <p>87. Godard, Jerry Caris. <hi rend="i">Mental Forms Creating: William Blake Anticipates Freud,
Jung, and Rank.</hi> Lanham, MD: UP of America, 1985. $25.25 cloth / $11.25 paper.</p>
            <p>88. Grams, Paul Mueller. “Blake’s Antinomianism.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
International</hi> 45 (1985): 2110A. U of Michigan. [“This study focuses on the theological expressions in
Blake’s pre-1800 writings to demonstrate that Blake held antinomian beliefs from the start of his artistic
career.”]</p>
            <p>89. Grant, John E. “A Re-View of Some Problems in Understanding Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts.” Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 155-81. [See also #65, 140, and 148.]</p>
            <p>90. Greenberg, Mark L. “William Michael Rossetti’s Transcription and William Bell Scott’s
Tracings from Blake’s Notebook.” <hi rend="i">Library</hi> 6th ser. 6 (1984): 254-70.</p>
            <p>91. Gross, David. “Infinite Indignation: Teaching, Dialectical Vision, and Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell.” College English</hi> 48 (1986): 175-86.</p>
            <p>92. Gross, David. “ ‘Mind Forg’d Manacles:’ Hegemony and Counter-Hegemony in Blake.”
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 27 (1986): 3-25.</p>
            <pb id="p20-82" n="82"/>
            <p>93. Groves, David. “Blake, Thomas Boston, and the Fourfold Vision.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1986): 142.</p>
            <p>94. Gugelberger, Georg M. “Blake, Neruda, Ngugi wa Thiong’o: Issues in Third World
Literature.” <hi rend="i">Comparative Literature Studies</hi> 21 (1984): 463-82.</p>
            <p>95. Gully, Anthony Lacy. “Mr. B. and the Cherubim: A Critical Examination of William
Blake’s <hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalogue</hi> of 1809.” <hi rend="i">Phoebus: A Journal of Art
History</hi> 1 [1978]: 23-45.</p>
            <p>96. Hagstrum, Jean H. “Richardson and Blake.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 236-37.</p>
            <p>97. Hagstrum, Jean H. “‘What Seems to Be: Is:’ Blake’s Idea of God.” 
<hi rend="i">Johnson and His Age.</hi> Ed. James Engell. Harvard English Studies 12. Cambridge, MA: Harvard UP,
1984. 425-58. [Jean Hagstrum’s contribution to a <hi rend="i">festschrift</hi> for Walter Jackson Bate.]</p>
            <p>98. Haigwood, Laura Ellen. “Eve’s Daughters: The Subversive Feminine in Blake and
Wordsworth.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 46 (1985): 157A. U of California, Santa
Cruz. [“ . . . beginning with a comparison of Blake’s and Milton’s images of Eve and of woman, using
Blake’s illustrations to <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> as the central text (sic). . . . (followed by) a
reading of <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, arguing that Oothoon’s apparently
subversive arguments for free love are embedded in sexist assumptions about the nature of woman which
compromise her revolutionary potential and that her speeches may be an example of Blake’s skill at dramatic
irony rather than a simple enunciation of his own views on free love.”]</p>
            <p>99. Hall, Carol Louise. <hi rend="i">Blake and Fuseli: A Study in the Transmission of
Ideas.</hi> Garland Publications in Comparative Literature. New York, NY: Garland, 1985. $30.</p>
            <p>100. *Hearn, Michael Patrick. “William Blake’s Illustrations for Children’s Books.” 
<hi rend="i">American Book Collector</hi> ns 2.2 (1981): 33-43.</p>
            <p>101. *Heinzelman, Kurt. <hi rend="i">The Economics of the Imagination.</hi> Amherst, MA: U of
Massachusetts P, 1980, 110-33.[This chapter on Blake is a revision of the author’s 1978 essay on “William
Blake and the Economics of the Imagination;” see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 14
(1980): 88.]</p>
            <p>102. Heppner, Christopher. “Blake’s ‘The New Jerusalem Descending:’ A Drawing (Butlin
#92) Identified.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986): 4-11.</p>
            <p>103. Hilton, Nelson. “Blakean Zen.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 24 (1985):
183-200.</p>
            <p>104. Hilton, Nelson. “Pudendaddendum.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
18 (1985): 235-36.</p>
            <p>105. *Hilton, Nelson, and Thomas A. Vogler, eds. <hi rend="i">Unnam’d Forms: Blake and
Textuality.</hi> Berkeley CA: U of California P, 1986. $34. [A collection of studies by David Simpson, Gavin
Edwards, Paul Mann, Donald D. Ault, Stephen Leo Carr, Robert N. Essick, V. A. De Luca, Geoffrey H. Hartman,
and the editors. Most of these essays are based on papers read at the 1982 Santa Cruz Conference on “Blake
and Criticism;” see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 17 (1983): 68, #133.]</p>
            <p>106. *Himy, Armand. “Un Symbole de Blake: Le <hi rend="i">Sparagmos.” Bulletin de la
Société d’Études Anglo-Americaines des XVII<hi rend="s">e</hi> et XVIII<hi rend="s">e</hi> Siècles</hi>
16 (1983): 89-105.</p>
            <p>107. Hoagwood, Terence Allan. “‘God Blessing the Seventh Day:’ William Blake’s Visions
of God and His Biblical Watercolors.” <hi rend="i">Studia Mystica</hi> 7.2 (1984): 65-77.</p>
            <p>108. Hoagwood, Terence Allan. “Pictorial Apocalypse: Blake’s ‘Great Red Dragon and the
Woman Clothed with the Sun.’ ” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 21 (1985): 11-21.</p>
            <p>109. Hoagwood, Terence Allan. <hi rend="i">Prophecy and the Philosophy of Mind: Traditions of
Blake and Shelley.</hi> University, AL: U of Alabama P, 1985. $23.50. [The author specifies the philosophic
sources which helped to shape <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and <hi rend="i">Prometheus Unbound</hi> and
attempts to establish the philosophical impact that he believes these poetic creations can justly claim:
“Prior relations subsisted between Christian biblical commentaries and secular philosophies of mind, but the
poets’ splendid unification of these traditions is revolutionary.” (p. ix)]</p>
            <p>110. Holloway, John. <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi> The Open University Arts (A Third Level Course,
ser. A362: “Romantic Poetry,” units 2-3). Milton Keynes, Bucks.: Open UP, 1984. [Holloway’s coursebook
on Blake’s “Romantic Poetry” is concerned with his writings up to <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>,
which is reprinted in its entirety from Stevenson’s 1971 edition as “Appendix 2.” The three epics,
however, remain unstudied. The booklet is structured by a succession of introductory and interpretative
chapters on Blake’s “lyrics and <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>,” on the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> and the
“Prophetic Books” of the 1790s; these chapters are interspersed with “Questions and Problems”
addressed to the reader. There are 57, pages, complete with text extracts and a list for further reading. A
television program which was connected with the Open University course concentrated on Blake’s art and was
presented by David Bindman.]</p>
            <p>111. *Howard, John. <hi rend="i">Infernal Poetics: Poetic Structure in Blake’s Lambeth
Prophecies.</hi> East Brunswick, NJ: Fairleigh Dickinson UP-Associated UP, 1984. $34.50.</p>
            <p>112. Howard, Seymour. “Blake: Classicism, Gothicism, and Nationalism.” <hi rend="i">Colby
Library Quarterly</hi> 21 (1985): 165-87. [See <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984):
103, #64.]</p>
            <p>113. *Johnston, Arthur. “William Blake and the ‘Ancient Britons.’ ” 
<hi rend="i">National Library of Wales Journal</hi> 22 (1982): 304-20.</p>
            <p>114. Johnston, John H. “Thomson, Jago, Cowper, Blake, and Seward.” <hi rend="i">The Poet
and the City: A Study in</hi>
	<pb id="p20-83" n="83"/>
	<hi rend="i">Urban Perspectives.</hi> Athens, GA: U of Georgia P, 1984. 56-82.</p>
            <p>115. Kauvar, Elaine M. “Blake’s Interpretation of Dreams: ‘Mental Forms Creating.’ ”
<hi rend="i">American Imago</hi> 41 (1984): 19-45.</p>
            <p>116. *Kauvar, Elaine M. “The Sorrows of Thel: A Freudian Interpretation of <hi rend="i">The
Book of Thel.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Journal of Evolutionary Psychology</hi> 5 (1984): 210-22.</p>
            <p>117. Keane, Patrick J. “Time’s Ruins and the Mansions of Eternity: or, Golgonooza and
Jerusalem, Yes; Bloomusalem and Beulah, No; Ithaca, Yes and No: Another Joyce-Blake Parallel at the End of
Bloomsday.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi> 86 (1983): 33-66.</p>
            <p>118. Kemeny, Tomaso, ed. <hi rend="i">Seminario sull’opera di William Blake.</hi>
Pubblicazioni della facoltà di lettere e filosofia dell’Università di Pavia 30. Proc. of a Conference at
the Istituto di lingua e letteratura inglese. Jan. 1982. Florence, It.: Nuova Italia, 1983. Lit. 10’000.
[This volume of conference papers from Pavia presents Claudia Corti on Blake’s “poetical iconism,”
Marcella Quadri on word and image in Blake’s oeuvre, Carla Locatelli on “tautology” in the 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, Roberto Sanesi on Blake and Newton, Rossana Bossaglia on Blake and the “problem of the
predecessors of symbolism,” and the editor on Blake and Joyce. The publication of the booklet attests to how
firmly Italian Blake scholarship has been established at English Departments on the peninsula during the past
four or five years.]</p>
            <p>119. Keynes, Geoffrey. “An Unpublished Poem by William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Times Literary
Supplement</hi> 14 Sept. 1984: 1021-22. [“The Phoenix to Mrs Butts” published, attributed to Blake, and
interpreted to illuminate the poet’s personal relation with Elizabeth Butts; see also #28, above.]</p>
            <p>120. Kittel, Harald Alfred. “Perception and Reflection: The Text and Title-Page Design of
William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Poetic Knowledge: Circumference and
Centre—Papers from the Wuppertal Symposium 1978.</hi> Ed. Roland Hagenbüchle and Joseph T. Swann.
Schriftenreihe Literaturwissenschaft 18. Bonn: Bouvier, 1980. 30-41. [Should, of course, have been listed
years ago, but wasn’t.]</p>
            <p>121. LaBelle, Jenijoy. “A Pencil Sketch for Blake’s Dante Illustrations.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 73-74.</p>
            <p>122. Latané, David E., Jr. “The Door into <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and Present</hi> 7.2 (1983): 17-26.</p>
            <p>123. Latané, David Eaton, Jr. “ ‘Energetic Exertion’ —Reading and the Romantic Long
Poem: Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and Browning’s <hi rend="i">Sordello.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 45 (1985): 192A. Duke U. [“Blake’s annotations,
illustrations and poems show that he practiced an active reading that engages in dialogue with the text. In
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> his difficult rhetoric makes language itself sublime and compels the reader’s
energetic exertion in response. Blake plays on the incomprehensibility of the sublime and the morphology of
prophecy . . . to draw the reader into the poem.”]</p>
            <p>124. Lesser, Harry. “Blake and Plato.” <hi rend="i">Philosophy</hi> 56 (1981): 223-30.</p>
            <p>125. Lincoln, Andrew. “Blake and the Natural History of Creation.” <hi rend="i">Essays and
Studies</hi> 39 (1986): 94-103.</p>
            <p>126. Linkin, Harriet Kramer. “The Search for a Transcendent Language: Linguistic Strategies
in Herbert and Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 46 (1985): 989A. U of
Michigan. [“George Herbert and William Blake are two poets who devise poetic systems or metaphors that
attempt transcendence by mimetically representing the infinitude hidden within the mundane, secular, or
experientially bound universe. Though Herbert and Blake disagree on the specific nature of immanence, both
believe language provides a means of approaching their visions of sublimity.”]</p>
            <p>127. Mann, Paul. “Apocalypse and Recuperation: Blake and the Maw of Commerce.” 
<hi rend="i">ELH</hi> 52 (1985): 1-32.</p>
            <p>128. Mann, Paul. “The Final State of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake /
An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 204-15.</p>
            <p>129. Marvel, Laura. “Blake and Yeats: Visions of Apocalypse.” <hi rend="i">College
Literature</hi> 13 (1986): 95-105.</p>
            <p>130. Masterson, Donald, and Edward O’Shea. “Code Breaking and Myth Making: the Ellis-Yeats
Edition of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Works.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Yeats Annual</hi> 3 (1985): 53-80.</p>
            <p>131. Matsushima, Shōichi. <hi rend="i">Koko no Geijutsuka William Blake.</hi> Tokyo:
Hokuseido, 1984. ¥5000.</p>
            <p>132. McCord, James. “Historical Dissonance and William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Song of
Los.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 20 (1984): 22-35.</p>
            <p>133. McCord, James. “John Butler Yeats, ‘The Brotherhood,’ and William Blake.” 
<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi> 86 (1983): 10-32.</p>
            <p>134. McCord, James. “An Unrecorded Colored Copy of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 116-18.</p>
            <p>135. McHenry, Henry Davis, Jr. “I. Prolegomenon for a Complete Angler: The Social
Conditioning of Learning—II. Reference and Exuberance: Blake’s Idea of Language.” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 45 (1984): 821A. U of Virginia. [“To Blake the most
insidious danger is the use of the referential language prescribed by Locke and the scientists. . . . Blake
uses his own exuberant poetic language as an ‘adverse wheel’ to reveal the limitations of the empiricist
paradigm. . . .”]</p>
            <p>136. Meller, Horst. “Audens ‘As I Walked Out One Evening’ und Blakes ‘London:’ Zwei
Epiphanien großstädtischer Unheimlichkeit.” <hi rend="i">Anglistik und Englischunterricht</hi> 26 (1985):
107-25.</p>
            <p>137. Meller, Horst. “Gedichtstruktur und die ungelösten Antagonismen der Realität: Blakes
‘London’-Gedicht.”
<pb id="p20-84" n="84"/>
	<hi rend="i">Zum Verstehen englischer Gedichte.</hi> Literaturstudium 2 / Uni-Taschenbücher 1070. München:
UTB-Fink, 1985. 169-84.</p>
            <p>138. Miller, Dan. “Contrary Revelation: <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 24 (1985): 491-509.</p>
            <p>139. Mitchell, Orm. “Blake’s Subversive Illustrations to Wollstonecraft’s 
<hi rend="i">Stories.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Mosaic</hi> 17.4 (1984): 17-34.</p>
            <p>140. Mitchell, W. J. T. “Reply to John Grant.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 181-83. [See also #65, 89, and 148.]</p>
            <p>141. Mitchell, W. J. T. “Visible Language: Blake’s Wond’rous Art of Writing.” 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism and Contemporary Criticism.</hi> Ed. Morris Eaves and Michael Fischer. Ithaca, NY:
Cornell UP, 1986. 46-86. [This essay was first read to a group of students participating in a course on “The
Romantic Self,” 1982-83, at the Department of English, University of New Mexico. It is here printed together
with a series of questions and the author’s answers on pp. 86-95.]</p>
            <p>142. Moskal, Jeanne. “Every Word and Every Character Was Human: Blake, 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, and Literary History.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 46
(1985): 431A. U of Washington. [“This study outlines a theory of literary history based on the work of
William Blake, and in particular on his poem <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> The cornerstone of this theory is
Blake’s idea that poets construct their personal identities in the process of writing their poems.”]</p>
            <p>143. Mulhallen, Karen. “The Crying of Lot 318; or, Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
Colored Once More.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 71-72.</p>
            <p>144. *Nanavutty, Piloo. “Blake and Gnostic Imagery: A Note.” <hi rend="i">Aligarh Journal
of English Studies</hi> 9 (1984): 43-55.</p>
            <p>145. *Okuma, Akinoku. “Blake no Shiteki Gengo.” <hi rend="i">Eigo Seinen</hi> 129 (1984):
574-78.</p>
            <p>146. Ostriker, Alicia. “Reply to Hagstrum.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 238. [See also #96, above.]</p>
            <p>147. Ott, Judith Lynn. “The Illuminations of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem, The
Emanation of the Giant Albion</hi>: What Are Those Golden Builders Doing?” <hi rend="i">Dissertation
Abstracts International</hi> 45 (1985): 1897-98A. Ohio State U. [“. . . an explication of the illuminations
of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> with an emphasis on establishing the perimeters of his
multiple sources, an understanding of his working methods as an artist and an informed appreciation of the
visual themes in his symbolic system.”]</p>
            <p>148. Paley, Morton D. “Further Thoughts on <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 183-84. [See also #65, 89, and 140.]</p>
            <p>149. Paley, Morton D. “<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and the Form of History.” 
<hi rend="i">Aligarh Journal of English Studies</hi> 10 (1985): 66-80.</p>
            <p>150. *Pasquier, Pierre. “L’Infini qui naît au creux de la paume ou Edward Gordon Craig et
William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Revue d’Histoire du Théatre</hi> 36 (1984): 227-46.</p>
            <p>151. Peterfreund, Stuart. “Blake, Freemasonry and the Builder’s Task.” 
<hi rend="i">Mosaic</hi> 17.3 (1984): 35-57.</p>
            <p>152. Peterfreund, Stuart. “The Problem of Originality and Blake’s <hi rend="i">Poetical
Sketches.</hi>” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi> 52 (1985): 673-705.</p>
            <p>153. Phipps, Frances. <hi rend="i">Let Me Be Los: Codebook for</hi> Finnegans Wake. Lubbock,
TX: Toth-Maatian P, 1985. $50. [This richly illustrated study was published as “Supplement A” to the 
<hi rend="i">Toth-Maatian Review</hi> 3.5 (1985). “Convinced of Blake’s importance to Joyce, the compiler of
this codebook has put together isolated suggestions in an order which it is hoped can prove useful.” Besides
this “Stolen-Telling” (p. 9), the commentary consists of hundreds of illustrations—many of ancient
Egyptian artifacts, others taken from Blake’s prints and paintings—and diagrams. Orders and inquiries
should be sent to the publisher’s new address at 503 West Indiana Avenue, Urbana, IL 61801.]</p>
            <p>154. Piquet, François. “Blake, l’intertexte de <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> et les
tribulations d’Albion.” <hi rend="i">Romantisme</hi> 15.49 (1985): 35-45.</p>
            <p>155. *Piquet, François. “Quelques aspects de l’Eros chez Blake.” <hi rend="i">Romantisme
anglais et Eros.</hi> Ed. Christian La Cassagnère. Publications de la Faculté des Lettres et Sciences
Humaines de l’Université de Clermont-Ferrand II 14. Clermont-Ferrand: U de Clermont-Ferrand II, 1982.
17-28.</p>
            <p>156. Punter, David. “Blake/Hegel/Derrida: A Response to Nelson Hilton’s Review of 
<hi rend="i">Blake, Hegel and Dialectic.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984):
58-63. [See <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 113, #273.]</p>
            <p>157. Punter, David. “Blake, Trauma and the Female.” <hi rend="i">New Literary History</hi>
15 (1984): 475-90.</p>
            <p>158. Punter, David. “The Sign of Blake.” <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 26 (1984): 313-34.</p>
            <p>159. Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">Blake and the City.</hi> Academic Inn Discussion Papers 7.
London: privately printed for the Academic Inn, Institute of Directors, 1984. [The text of a lecture given on
20 Nov. 1984. According to the bookdealer Julian Nangle of Words etcetera, only 100 copies of this leaflet
have been printed.]</p>
            <p>160. Raine, Kathleen. “Blake and Maya.” <hi rend="i">Indian Horizons</hi> 32.3 (1983):
5-24.</p>
            <p>161. Reisner, Thomas A. “Blake and Chatterton.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 32
(1985): 328-29.</p>
            <pb id="p20-85" n="85"/>
            <p>162. *Rix, Donna S. “<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: Blake’s Reading of Second Isaiah.” 
<hi rend="i">Poetic Prophecy in Western Literature.</hi> Ed. Jan Wojcik and Raymond-Jean Frontain. Rutherford, NJ:
Fairleigh Dickinson UP; London: Associated UP, 1984. 106-18.</p>
            <p>163. Robertson, P. J. M. “Criticism and Creativity IV: Blake and Keats.” 
<hi rend="i">Queen’s Quarterly</hi> 91 (1984): 941-53.</p>
            <p>164. Rose, Edward J. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, St. Paul, and Biblical
Prophecy.” <hi rend="i">English Studies in Canada</hi> 11 (1985): 396-412.</p>
            <p>165. Rothenberg, Molly Anne. “Blake’s Higher Criticism: Rhetoric and Re-Vision in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 46 (1985): 973A. U of
California, Irvine. [“I argue that Blake wrote <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> in order to teach his readers to
recognize the rhetorical strategies by which sacred texts are constructed so that he could liberate his
readers from the institutionalized, oppressive effects of the interpretative conventions of traditional
exegesis.”]</p>
            <p>166. Ryskamp, Charles. “Paul Mellon and William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Essays in Honor of
Paul Mellon: Collector and Benefactor.</hi> Ed. John Wilmerding. Washington, DC: National Gallery of Art,
1986. 329-37. [A concise history of the growth of Mellon’s splendid Blake collection.]</p>
            <p>167. Sánchez Pérez, Aquilino. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Graphic Work and the Emblematic
Tradition.</hi> Murcia, Spain: Secretariado de Publicaciones, U de Murcia, 1982.</p>
            <p>168. Sánchez [Pérez], Aquilino. “William Blake, pintor y poeta: hacia una nueva perspectiva
en la lectura de su obra.” <hi rend="i">Departomento de Inglés: Anuario</hi> 1981: 5-23. [Published for the
Facultad de Letras at the Universidad Autònoma de Barcelona.]</p>
            <p>169. Schiff, Gert. “William Blake: Anarchist, Haeretiker und Moralist.” <hi rend="i">Forma
et subtilitas: Festschrift für Wolfgang Schöne zum 75. Geburtstag.</hi> Ed. Wilhelm Schlink and Martin
Sperlich. Berlin: de Gruyter, 1986. 229-48.</p>
            <p>170. Shabetai, Karen. “Blake’s Perception of Evil.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
International</hi> 45 (1984): 1762A. U of California, San Diego. [“ . . . examines the connection between
Blake’s idea about evil and his theory of perception. I locate contradictions in Blake’s ideas about
theodicy, which have to do with the problems he encounters when he posits the internal world as the exclusive
source of creativity, and with a system of meaning that depends on the psychological state of the perceiving
subject. . . . I concentrate on Blake’s illustrations to Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, early versions
of the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> poems, and his Job illustrations.”]</p>
            <p>171. Shaviro, Steven. “‘Striving With Systems:’ Blake and the Politics of Difference.”
<hi rend="i">Boundary 2</hi> 10.3 (1982): 229-50.</p>
            <p>172. Singh, Charu Sheel. <hi rend="i">The Chariot of Fire: A Study of William Blake in the
Light of Hindu Thought.</hi> Salzburg Studies in English Literature III: Romantic Reassessment 104. Salzburg,
Austria: Institut für Anglistik und Amerikanistik, U of Salzburg, 1981. $25. [Distributed in the United
States by Humanities P.]</p>
            <p>173. Singh, Gurbhagat. <hi rend="i">Poetry as Metaconsciousness: Readings in William
Blake.</hi> Atlantic Highlands, NJ: Humanities P, 1983. $16.</p>
            <p>174. Sosnowski, T. Ford. “Meter and Form in Blake’s ‘The Lamb’ and ‘The Tyger.’ ”
<hi rend="i">Kwartalnik Neofilologiczny</hi> 31 (1984): 407-16.</p>
            <p>175. Spector, Sheila A. “Death in Blake’s Major Prophecies.” <hi rend="i">Studia
Mystica</hi> 7.3 (1984): 3-28.</p>
            <p>176. *Staudt, Kathleen Henderson. “The Text as Material and as Sign: Poetry and Incarnation
in William Blake, Arthur Rimbaud, and David Jones.” <hi rend="i">Modern Language Studies</hi> 14 (1984):
13-30.</p>
            <p>177. Storch, Margaret. “The ‘Spectrous Fiend’ Cast Out: Blake’s Crisis at Felpham.”
<hi rend="i">Modern Language Quarterly</hi> 44 (1983): 115-35. [See <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 17 (1983): 68, #133.]</p>
            <p>178. Suzuki, Masashi. “[Confined Force and Motion: <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi>
and Newtonian Dynamics.]” <hi rend="i">Studies in English</hi> [Tokyo] 59 (1982): 29-42. [For a summary in
English see <hi rend="i">ibid.</hi> 59 (1983): 251-52.]</p>
            <p>179. Taft, Richard Tomlinson. “The Relationship between Art and Philosophy: An Examination of
Hegel, Blake, Nietzsche and Heidegger.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 45 (1985):
3367A. Duquesne U. [“In Chapter 4 the works of William Blake and Friedrich Nietzsche are discussed because
each attempts to transgress the traditionally established boundary between art and philosophy.”]</p>
            <p>180. Taylor, Dena Bain. “Emanations of the Divine: Kabbalistic Elements in the Poetry and
Designs of William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 45 (1985): 2889A. U of
Toronto. [The author “establishes the significance of the influence of the Kabbalah in Blake’s work and a
biographical context for the influence.”]</p>
            <p>181. Tidwell, Paul Alexander. “Joyce’s Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
International</hi> 44 (1984): 3075A. State U of New York, Buffalo. [“Joyce refused to adhere to his
contemporaries’ classification of Blake as a mystic . . . (he) learned contrariety, simultaneity, tenacity,
and charity from Blake.”]</p>
            <p>182. Twitchell, James B. “Blake: The Anti-Sublime.” <hi rend="i">Romantic Horizons: Aspects
of the Sublime in English Poetry and Painting 1770-1850.</hi> Columbia, MO: U of Missouri P, 1983. 40-59.</p>
            <p>183. Van Schaik, Pamela. “Blake’s Vision of the Fall and Redemption of Man: A Reading Based
on the Contrary Images of Innocence and Experience.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi>
45 (1984): 1411A. U of South Africa. [“This thesis explores Blake’s vision of the Fall of Man, and his
restoration to Eden, in terms of the poet’s
<pb id="p20-86" n="86"/>
consistent use of contrary pairs of images to denote the ‘States’ of Innocence and Experience. It attempts
to provide a matrix for Blake’s images, and to demonstrate the unity and coherence of his symbolic vision by
relating the symbols of his poetry to those of his visual art.”]</p>
            <p>184. Viscomi, Joseph. “Recreating Blake’s Illuminated Prints: The Facsimiles of the
Manchester Etching Workshop.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 4-23.</p>
            <p>185. Vogler, Thomas A. “Intertextual Signifiers and the Blake of That Already.” 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and Present</hi> 9.1 (1985): 1-33.</p>
            <p>186. Warner, Janet A. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Language of Art.</hi> Kingston, ON:
McGill-Queen’s UP; Gloucester, Glos.: Sutton, 1984. $29.95. [This study is concerned with “a kind of
visual vocabulary,” “with a set of visual forms, gestures and attitudes of the human body,” which were
repeatedly used in Blake’s designs. As in her earlier articles, the author’s “approach to Blake is from
design to poetry” and attempts “to demonstrate the variety and importance” of the artist’s “visual
shorthand.” Thus, Warner’s “central concern” is to show “to what extent Blake’s formula-figures
stand alone as symbols and to what extent their meanings are defined by the context in which they appear.”
(pp. xvii-xviii)]</p>
            <p>187. Warner, Nicholas O. “Visual Analogues to Blake’s ‘The Dog.’ ” <hi rend="i">Blake
/ An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 140-43.</p>
            <p>188. Weathers, Winston. “William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>: A
Transaction.” <hi rend="i">The Nature of Identity: Essays Presented to Donald E. Hayden by the Graduate
Faculty of Modern Letters, The University of Tulsa.</hi> Tulsa, OK: U of Tulsa, 1981. 71-91.</p>
            <p>189. Wetenhall, John. “Blake’s Sketches for ‘Hamlet.’ ” <hi rend="i">Burlington
Magazine</hi> 127 (1985): 229. [A letter to the editor, discussing the subject and date (c. 1805-06) of
Butlin’s #74 recto and verso, #75, 140, and 547(5).]</p>
            <p>190. Whitmarsh-Knight, David Edward. “Structure as a Key to Meaning in William Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 45 (1984): 1764A. U of
New Brunswick. [“This dissertation provides virtually a line by line textual analysis and critical
commentary of . . . <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> which traces the poem’s mythology and plot, helps reveal
Blake’s conscious craftsmanship, and relates the poem’s parts to the work as a whole.”]</p>
            <p>191. Wilkinson, D. R. M. “Blake’s ‘Songs:’ Taking Stock, 1984.” <hi rend="i">English
Studies</hi> 66 (1985): 227-40.</p>
            <p>192. “William Blake: Prints and Drawings.” <hi rend="i">National Galleries of Scotland
News</hi> May / June 1986: n. pag. [An anonymous announcement of a small studio exhibition of the Blake
holdings at the Department of Prints and Drawings of the National Gallery of Scotland which was to be seen at
The Mound from 3 May to 13 July 1986.]</p>
            <p>193. Wintersgill, Donald. “Museum Is Given Blakes.” <hi rend="i">Guardian</hi> 16 May 1985:
5. [Reports the acquisition of the late Sir Geoffrey Keynes’s Blake collection by the Fitzwilliam Museum,
Cambridge, Cambs.]</p>
            <p>194. *Witke, Joanne. <hi rend="i">William Blake and Human Imagination.</hi> London: Croom Helm,
1986. £19.95.</p>
            <p>195. Yoshimura, Masakazu. “[Blake and the Cycle Symbolism.]” <hi rend="i">Studies in
English Literature</hi> [Tokyo] 60 (1983): 47-59. [For a summary in English see <hi rend="i">ibid.</hi> 61
(1984): 116-17.]</p>
            <p>196. Zimmerman, Daniel John. “‘What Are Those Golden Builders Doing?:’ A Study of
Blake’s Poetics of Reception.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 44 (1984): 3075A.
State U of New York, Buffalo. [“William Blake’s poetics establishes his authority to divine and revise the
received word in two dimensions, contention and combat, each of them twofold. . . . Examined in this
framework, the dynamics of Blake’s poetic ‘moves’ suggest the need to enlarge reception theory with
imaginal ‘fit auditors’ of inspiration in poet and reader alike. . . .”]</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part II Blake’s Circle</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">General Studies</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>197. Bindman, David, ed. <hi rend="i">The Thames and Hudson Encyclopaedia of British Art.</hi>
London: Thames and Hudson, 1985. £10.50. [Contains entries on most of the artist members of Blake’s circle
(Barry, Bartolozzi, Blake himself, Calvert, Flaxman, Fuseli, Gillray, the two classicist Hamiltons, Jeffreys,
Kauffmann, Payne Knight, Linnell, Loutherbourg, the Master of the Giants, Mortimer, Opie, Palmer, Richmond,
Romney, the Runcimans, Stothard, Varley, and West), and with short articles on history painting, Boydell’s
Shakespeare Gallery, the industrial revolution, neoclassicism, the Royal Academy, Shoreham, and the sublime
will make a most useful work of reference for anybody interested in British art of Blake’s—or, in fact,
any other—period.]</p>
            <p>198. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">Great Images of British Printmaking: A Descriptive Catalogue
1789-1939.</hi> London: Garton, 1978. [Published in conjunction with an exhibition at Garton’s gallery;
prints by Blake, Richmond, Calvert, Palmer, and the British neoromantics who were influenced by them, figured
largely in the show (see #2-6, 9, 10, 18 and 19 of this catalogue).]</p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">James Barry</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>199. *Allan, D. G. C. “Barry and Johnson.” <hi rend="i">Journal of the Royal Society of
Arts</hi> 133 (1985): 628-32.</p>
              <p>200. Barrell, John. “The Functions of Art in a Commercial Society: The Writings of James
Barry.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 25 (1984): 117-40.</p>
              <pb id="p20-87" n="87"/>
              <p>201. Brown, David Blayney. “Testaments of Friendship; Two New Portraits by James Barry of
Francis Douce and Joseph Nollekens.” <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 128 (1986): 27-31.</p>
              <p>202. *Hamlyn, Robin. “James Barry: The Ideals of High Art and the Problems of Patronage.”
<hi rend="i">Antique Collector</hi> 54 (1983): 66-70. [Possibly no more than a review of Pressly’s monograph
and / or the Tate Gallery’s Barry exhibition of 1983.]</p>
              <p>203. <corr type="emend">McNamara, Ruth Ann.</corr> “The Theme of the Learned Painter in Eighteenth-Century British
Self-Portraiture.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 44 (1984): 3526A. Bryn Mawr
College. [Examines “the interpretation of the ideal of the learned painter in eighteenth-century England as
revealed in the self-portraits of Hogarth, Reynolds, West, Barry, and Fuseli. . . . In the fourth chapter, the
self-portraits of Barry and Fuseli are examined as examples of the ambivalence created by the clash between
the ideal of the learned painter and the growing strength of the concept of original genius. Finally,
Blake’s total rejection of the premises upon which the ideal of the learned painter rested is seen as
heralding the decline of the influence of the notion of the learned painter in eighteenth-century
England.”]</p>
              <p>204. *Pressly, William L. “A Chapel of Natural and Revealed Religion: James Barry’s
Series for the Society’s Great Room Reinterpreted.” <hi rend="i">Journal of the Royal Society of Arts</hi>
132 (1984): 543-46, 634-37, and 693-95.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">William Staden Blake</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>205. Warner, Janet [A.] “Trade Cards of W. S. Blake.” <hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi> 32
(1983): 105-07.</p>
              <p><hi rend="i">See also</hi> #43, <hi rend="i">above.</hi></p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Edward Calvert</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See #19, 25, and 198 above, as well as #250, below.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">William Cowper</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>206. Anderson, David R. “Landscape and Theodicy in Pope, Thomson, and Cowper.” 
<hi rend="i">Essays in Literature</hi> 13 (1986): 13-27.</p>
              <p>207. Davie, Donald. “Homage to Cowper.” <hi rend="i">PN Review</hi> 6.6 (1980):
21-24.</p>
              <p>208. Digby, Joan Owen. “Survival of the ‘Stricken Deer.’ ” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of
Research in the Humanities</hi> 85 (1982): 341-43.</p>
              <p>209. *Hartley, Lodwick. “Harlequin Intrudes: William Cowper’s Venture into the Satiric
Mode.” <hi rend="i">The Dress of Words: Essays on Restoration and Eighteenth-Century Literature in Honor of
Richmond P. Bond.</hi> Ed. Robert B. White, Jr. Lawrence, KS: U of Kansas Libraries, 1978. 127-37.</p>
              <p>210. King, James. “Some Additions and Corrections to ‘New and Corrected Cowper
Correspondence.’ ” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 30 (1983): 63. [See also #223, below.]</p>
              <p>211. *King, James. <hi rend="i">William Cowper: A Biography.</hi> Durham, NC: Duke UP, 1986.
$35.</p>
              <p>212. *Moreux, Françoise. “Identité et folie chez Cowper.” <hi rend="i">Folie, folies,
folly dans le monde anglo-américain aux XVII<hi rend="s">e</hi> et XVIII<hi rend="s">e</hi> siècles.</hi>
Aix-en-Provence: PU de Provence, for the Société d’Ètudes Anglo-Américaines des XVII<hi rend="s">e</hi>
et XVIII<hi rend="s">e</hi> Siècles, 1984. 165-75.</p>
              <p>213. *Rawson, Claude. <hi rend="i">Order from Confusion Sprung: Studies in Eighteenth-Century
Literature from Swift to Cowper.</hi> London: Allen, 1985. $31.</p>
              <p>214. Schmidt, A. V. C. “T. S. Eliot and William Cowper: A New <hi rend="i">Waste Land</hi>
Source.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 29 (1982): 347.</p>
              <p>215. Sherbo, Arthur. “Cowper’s ‘Stricken Deer’ and Literary Tradition.” 
<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi> 85 (1982): 336-40.</p>
              <p>216. Sherbo, Arthur. “Three Letters of Samuel Boyse and a Poem by Cowper(?).” 
<hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 33 (1986): 78-80.</p>
              <p>217. Sherbo, Arthur. “William Cowper and the <hi rend="i">European Magazine.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi> 34 (1981): 238-41.</p>
              <p>218. Sherbo, Arthur. “William Cowper’s Bullfinch Poem: a Minor Sub-Genre?” 
<hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 32 (1985): 243-45.</p>
              <p>219. Smith, Margaret M. “A Missing Cowper Letter Found.” <hi rend="i">Notes and
Queries</hi> ns 32 (1985): 245-46.</p>
              <p>220. Ty, Eleanor. “Cowper’s <hi rend="i">Connoisseur</hi> #138 and Samuel Johnson.” 
<hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 33 (1986): 63-64.</p>
              <p>221. Vogler, Thomas A. “The Tropology of Silence in Eighteenth-Century English Blank
Verse.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 26 (1985): 211-37. [Besides
Cowper’s <hi rend="i">Task</hi>, Vogler discusses works such as Thomson’s <hi rend="i">Seasons</hi> or
Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts.</hi>]</p>
              <p>222. Watson, J. R. “Cowper’s Olney Hymns.” <hi rend="i">Essays and Studies</hi> 38
(1985): 45-65.</p>
              <p>223. Weinglass, D[avid] H. “New and Corrected Cowper Correspondence.” <hi rend="i">Notes
and Queries</hi> ns 27 (1980): 416-18. [Includes the publication of a letter by Hayley to Mrs. Rose of 7 March
1794.]</p>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See also #114, above, and #240 and 319, below.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">George Cumberland</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>224. *Cumberland, George. <hi rend="i">The Captive of the Castle of Sennaar.</hi> Ed. G. E.
Bentley, Jr. Newcastle-upon-Tyne: Avero, 1983. £14. [This entry was lifted from the current edition of 
<hi rend="i">British Books in Print</hi>; G. E. Bentley, Jr., however, now informs me that his edition of
Cumberland’s narrative so far has <hi rend="i">not</hi> been printed at all, but may be available from a
different publisher in 1987-88.]</p>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See also #260, below.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <pb id="p20-88" n="88"/>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Erasmus Darwin</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>225. Becquemont, Daniel. “Erasmus Darwin, médecin et poète: 1731-1802.” 
<hi rend="i">Revue des Sciences Humaines</hi> 69.198 (1985): 9-29.</p>
              <p>226. Cohen, B. “Erasmus Darwin’s Observations on Rotation and Vertigo.” 
<hi rend="i">Human Neurobiology</hi> 3 (1984): 121-28.</p>
              <p>227. Colp, Ralph, Jr. “The Relationship of Charles Darwin to the Ideas of His Grandfather,
Dr. Erasmus Darwin.” <hi rend="i">Biography</hi> 9 (1986): 1-24.</p>
              <p>228. Hart, Clive. “Erasmus Darwin’s Model Goose.” <hi rend="i">Aeronautical Journal of
the Royal Aeronautical Society</hi> 89 (1985): 17-20.</p>
              <p>229. Hassler, Donald M. “New Diggings in Old Mines: Erasmus Darwin and Romantic Views on
Evolution.” <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 15 (1984): 26-28.</p>
              <p>230. *King-Hele, Desmond. <hi rend="i">Erasmus Darwin and the Romantic Poets.</hi> London:
Macmillan, 1985. [Darwin’s influence on Blake’s writings of the Lambeth period is dealt with in
detail.]</p>
              <p>231. King-Hele, Desmond. “Erasmus Darwin: Master of Interdisciplinary Science.” 
<hi rend="i">Interdisciplinary Science Reviews</hi> 10 (1985): 170-91. [An extremely useful introduction to
Darwin’s career and many-faceted scientific achievements.]</p>
              <p>232. King-Hele, Desmond. “Erasmus Darwin’s Contributions to Geophysics and Astronomy.”
<hi rend="i">Vistas in Astronomy</hi> 27 (1984): 63-75.</p>
              <p>233. Sheffield, Charles. <hi rend="i">Erasmus Magister.</hi> New York, NY: Ace Books, 1982.
[Described by Desmond King-Hele as a kind of “historical fiction.”]</p>
              <p>234. *Ullrich, David W. “Distinctions in Poetic and Intellectual Influence: Coleridge’s
Use of Erasmus Darwin.” <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 15 (1984): 74-80[?81].</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">John Flaxman</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>235. Hendriks, Ella. “The First Patron of Flaxman.” <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi>
126 (1984): 618-25.</p>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See also #10, above.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Henry Fuseli</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>236. Andrews, Keith. “Scottish Artists in the Roman Circle of Winckelmann and Fuseli.”
<hi rend="i">“Sind Briten hier?:” Relations between British and Continental Art 1680-1880.</hi> Ed.
Zentralinstitut für Kunstgeschichte in München. Proc. of a Conference at the Zentralinstitut, organized on
the occasion of the exhibition “Zwei Jahrhunderte englische Malerei.” 14-15 Jan. 1980. Munich: Fink, 1981.
83-95. [See <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 14 (1980): 86.]</p>
              <p>237. *Gizzi, Corrado, ed. <hi rend="i">Füssli e Dante.</hi> Milano, It.: Torre
de’Passeri-Pinacoteca di Brera, 1985. [An exhibition catalogue, reported to contain a series of essays on
Fuseli’s early and important “discovery” of Dante’s poetry as a subject for the visual arts.]</p>
              <p>238. Hahn, Karl-Friedrich. “‘Raffael und die Fornarina:’ eine Bilderfindung Johann
Heinrich Füsslis.” <hi rend="i">Labyrinthos</hi> 3.5-6 (1984): 37-53.</p>
              <p>239. Hammerschmidt-Hummel, Hildegard. “Johann Heinrich Füsslis Illustrationen zu
Shakespeares <hi rend="i">Macbeth</hi> unter besonderer Berücksichtigung seiner Kunsttheorie.” 
<hi rend="i">Arcadia</hi> 20 (1985): 225-38.</p>
              <p>240. King, James. “An Unlikely Alliance: Fuseli as Revisor of Cowper’s Homer.” 
<hi rend="i">Neophilologus</hi> 67 (1983): 468-79.</p>
              <p>241. Klemm, Christian. <hi rend="i">Johann Heinrich Füssli: Zeichnungen.</hi> Kunsthaus
Zürich: Sammlungsheft 12. Zurich: Kunsthaus Zürich, 1986. [Almost a catalogue raisonné of the Kunsthaus’
holdings of Fuseli drawings, published in conjunction with an exhibition of fifty of these drawings held at
the Kunsthaus from 23 May to 17 Aug. 1986.]</p>
              <p>242. Ottani Cavina, Anna. “Giani e la cerchia di Füssli a Roma.” 
<hi rend="i">Paragone</hi> 36.419/421/423 (1985): 279-85.</p>
              <p>243. *Schiff, Gert, and Paola Viotto. <hi rend="i">Tout l’oeuvre peint de Füssli.</hi>
Classiques de l’Art. Paris: Flammarion, 1980. [The French edition of vol. 91 in the Classici dell’Arte
series which was first published at Milan in 1977; see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 12
(1978): 147.]</p>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See also #99 and 203, above, as well as #280, #290, and #320, below.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">William Hayley</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>244. *Bishop, Morchard [i.e., Oliver Stoner]. “William Haley [sic] and His Last Printer.”
<hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi> 31 (1982): 187-200. [Includes the publication of almost seventy letters
exchanged between Hayley and the family of William Mason, who became Seagrave’s successor as Hayley’s
favorite printer.]</p>
              <p>245. *Whiteley, Paul. “Beattie, More, and Hayley.” <hi rend="i">The Late Augustans and
the Origins of English Romanticism.</hi> London: Croom Helm, 1985. £15.95.</p>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See also #223, above.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">John Linnell</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See #19, above.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>246. Bindman, David. “Samuel Palmer’s <hi rend="i">An Address to the Electors of West
Kent, 1832</hi> Rediscovered.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 56-59. [See
also #251, below.]</p>
              <p>247. Butlin, Martin. “Connoisseurship and the Palmer Fakes.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19
<pb id="p20-89" n="89"/>
(1986): 155. [A reply to Lister’s review of <hi rend="i">Essays on the Blake Followers</hi> that is listed
as #471.2, below.]</p>
              <p>248. *Irwin, Helen. “Samuel Palmer, Poet of Light and Shade: His Last Years at Reigate,
Surrey.” <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 114 (1981): 109-13.</p>
              <p>249. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">The Paintings of Samuel Palmer.</hi> Cambridge, Cambs.:
Cambridge UP, in association with the Pevensey P, 1985. £17.50. [This is not a catalogue raisonné; the
volume offers some 75 color plates which reproduce, besides Palmer’s oil paintings, some of his watercolors,
his gouaches, his drawings, and even his prints; all are briefly described by the author. A companion volume
on <hi rend="i">The Paintings of William Blake</hi> in the same format is to be published in fall 1986.]</p>
              <p>250. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer and ‘The Ancients.’</hi> Cambridge,
Cambs.: Cambridge UP, for the Fitzwilliam Museum, 1984. £24 cloth/£8.95 paper. [The catalogue of an
exhibition which was shown at the Fitzwilliam from 9 Oct. to 16 Dec. 1984. Represented in the exhibition were
149 items, all of which are illustrated and discussed in this catalogue; besides the Palmers they include
works by Calvert, Finch, Richmond, Sherman, Tatham, as well as a few Blakes.]</p>
              <p>251. Palmer, Samuel. “An Address to the Electors of West Kent [ . . . ] 1832.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 60-68. [A reprint of Palmer’s 
<hi rend="i">Address</hi>, edited by David Bindman. See also #246, above.]</p>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See also #10 and 19, above.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">George Romney</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>252. Burkett, Mary E., ed. <hi rend="i">George Romney 1734-1802.</hi> Kendal, Cumbria: Abbot
Hall Gallery, 1984. [The catalogue of a small exhibition, shown from 5 July to 2 Sept. 1984 in Romney’s home
county to celebrate the 250th anniversary of the artist’s birth. Besides ten oil paintings, a selection of
thirty-nine pencil, pen and ink, and wash drawings were on show. The small catalogue also contains a four-page
essay on “George Romney and His Drawings” by Gerhard Charles Rump.]</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">John Varley</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>253. Kauffmann, C. M. <hi rend="i">John Varley 1778-1842.</hi> British Watercolours. London:
Batsford, in association with the Victoria and Albert Museum, 1984. £7.95 paper.</p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part III Works of Related Interest</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Some General Studies, Mostly of Romantic Art, Poetry, and Their Historical
Context</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>254. *Albright, Daniel. <hi rend="i">Lyricality in English Literature.</hi> Lincoln, NE: U of
Nebraska P, 1985. $24.50.</p>
            <p>255. *Alford, Steven E. <hi rend="i">Irony and the Logic of the Romantic Imagination.</hi>
American University Studies, 3rd ser.: Comparative Literature 13. New York, NY: Lang, 1984. $19.45.</p>
            <p>256. *Altizer, Thomas J. J. “The Apocalyptic Identity of the Modern Imagination.” 
<hi rend="i">Journal of the American Academy of Religion: Thematic Studies</hi> 48 (1981): 19-29.</p>
            <p>257. *Baker, Carlos. <hi rend="i">The Echoing Green: Romanticism, Modernism, and the Phenomena
of Transference in Poetry.</hi> Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP, 1984. $32.50.</p>
            <p>258. Behrendt, Stephen C. “The Best Criticism: Imitation as Criticism in the Eighteenth
Century.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 24 (1983): 3-22. [Blake’s works
are cited as an <hi rend="i">exemplum.</hi>]</p>
            <p>259. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “The Freaks of Learning: Learned Pigs, Musical Hares, and the
Romantics.” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 18 (1982): 87-104. [Includes a discussion of Blake’s
learned pigs and his “Hare playing on a Tabor;” see pp. 101-03.]</p>
            <p>260. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “<hi rend="i">Rasselas</hi> and <hi rend="i">Gaudentio di Lucca</hi>
in the Mountains of the Moon.” <hi rend="i">Revista Canaria de Estudios Ingleses</hi> 9 (1984): 1-11. [In a
“Postscript” (pp. 9-10) Bentley compares Johnson’s and Berington’s novels with George Cumberland’s
<hi rend="i">Captive of the Castle of Sennaar</hi> and Blake’s <hi rend="i">Thel.</hi>]</p>
            <p>261. *Bridson, Gavin, and Geoffrey Wakeman. <hi rend="i">Printmaking and Picture Printing: A
Bibliographical Guide to Artistic and Industrial Techniques in Britain 1750-1900.</hi> Kidlington, Oxon.:
Plough P, 1984. £30.</p>
            <p>262. Bruntjen, Sven H. A. <hi rend="i">John Boydell (1719-1804): A Study of Art Patronage and
Publishing in Georgian London.</hi> Outstanding Dissertations in the Fine Arts. New York, NY: Garland, 1985.
$50. [The reprint of a 1974 Stanford U Ph.D. thesis.]</p>
            <p>263. Cantor, Paul A. <hi rend="i">Creature and Creator: Myth-Making and English
Romanticism.</hi> Cambridge, Cambs.: Cambridge UP, 1984. $34.50. [Includes a discussion of the creation myth
in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>]</p>
            <p>264. Cave, Kathryn, ed. <hi rend="i">The Diary of Joseph Farington.</hi> Vols. 13-16 (Jan. 1814
to Dec. 1821). Studies in British Art. New Haven, CT: Yale UP, for the Paul Mellon Centre for Studies in
British Art, 1984. £90. [The entire text of the diary has now been printed; despite the annoying number of
typographical as well as editorial errors that have already been detected, the sixteen volumes certainly mark
a major achievement for all future “Studies in British Art” of the times of William Blake. A detailed
editorial commentary and the much needed index are said to be forthcoming.]</p>
            <p>265. *Cook, Albert. <hi rend="i">Thresholds: Studies in the Romantic Experience.</hi> Madison,
WI: U of Wisconsin P, 1985. $37.50. [Said to treat Blake in the ‘context’ of such writers as Dickinson,
Dostoevsky, and Mallarmé.]</p>
            <pb id="p20-90" n="90"/>
            <p>266. Cooke, Michael G. “Romanticism and the Paradox of Wholeness.” <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi> 23 (1984): 435-53. [There are numerous references to the “paradox of wholeness” in the
writings of Blake.]</p>
            <p>267. Cooksey, Thomas L. “Dante’s England, 1818: The Contribution of Cary, Coleridge, and
Foscolo to the British Reception of Dante.” <hi rend="i">Papers on Language and Literature</hi> 20 (1984):
355-81.</p>
            <p>268. Dobai, Johannes. <hi rend="i">Die Kunstliteratur des Klassizismus und der Romantik in
England.</hi> Vol. 4: “Registerband.” Comp. Katharina Dobai. Berne: Benteli, n.d. [1984]. DM140. [On more
than 300 pages these indexes supply an indispensable guide to the astonishing riches of the previous three
volumes of Dobai’s monumental “Prolegomena.” It is to be regretted, however, that illness prevented the
author from contributing a list of <hi rend="i">errata et corrigenda</hi> for vols. 1-3 to the present
publication, the compilation of which he entrusted to his daughter.]</p>
            <p>269. Epstein, Julia L., and Mark L. Greenberg. “Decomposing Newton’s Rainbow.” 
<hi rend="i">Journal of the History of Ideas</hi> 45 (1984): 115-40. [On “the history of the rainbow as natural
object, as object of scientific study, and as poetic image” (p. 140); Blake’s reaction towards Newton is
briefly sketched on pp. 136-37.]</p>
            <p>270. Frye, Northrop. “The Survival of Eros in Poetry.” <hi rend="i">Romanticism and
Contemporary Criticism.</hi> Ed. Morris Eaves and Michael Fischer. Ithaca, NY: Cornell UP, 1986. 15-29.
[Frye’s essay is not directly concerned with the poetry of Blake; it was originally read to a class of
students participating in a course on “The Romantic Self,” offered by Eaves and Fischer in 1982-1983 at
the Department of English of the University of New Mexico; it is here printed together with the students’
questions and Frye’s answers, however, and there the author tells his audience how he has learned his
“views of Christianity more or less from Blake.” (p. 29)]</p>
            <p>271. Garlick, Kenneth. “Illustrations to ‘A Midsummer Night’s Dream’ Before 1920.”
<hi rend="i">Shakespeare Survey</hi> 37 (1984): 41-53.</p>
            <p>272. Gourlay, Alexander S. “Iphigenia in England: A Postscript to ‘The Melancholy
Shepherdess.’ ” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi> 86 (1983): 223-26. [See 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 103, #56.]</p>
            <p>273. McGann, Jerome J. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Ideology: A Critical Investigation.</hi>
Chicago, IL: U of Chicago P, 1983. $15. [Blake’s writings are referred to throughout. In 1985, a paperback
edition of this book was issued at $6.50.]</p>
            <p>274. Meller, Horst. “Prometheus im romantischen Heiligen-Kalender.” <hi rend="i">Antike
Tradition und Neuere Philologien: Symposium zu Ehren des 75. Geburtstages von Rudolf Sühnel.</hi> Ed.
Hans-Joachim Zimmermann. Heidelberg, W. Ger.: Winter, 1984. 151-75.</p>
            <p>275. Melot, Michel. <hi rend="i">The Art of Illustration.</hi> New York, NY: Rizzoli, 1984.
$60.</p>
            <p>276. Mitchell, W. J. T., ed. <hi rend="i">The Language of Images.</hi> Chicago, IL: U of
Chicago P, 1980. $7.95. [Most of the fourteen essays in this collection had previously appeared in print in
<hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry.</hi>]</p>
            <p>277. Rosenblum, Robert, and H. W. Janson. <hi rend="i">Art of the Nineteenth Century: Painting
and Sculpture.</hi> London: Thames and Hudson, 1984. £25. [The US edition was published under the slightly
different title of <hi rend="i">Nineteenth-Century Art</hi> (New York, NY: Abrams, 1984). For some general
accounts of artists such as Banks, Barry, Blake, Flaxman, Fuseli, Loutherbourg, Palmer, or West, refer to the
index.]</p>
            <p>278. *Schwartz, Richard B. <hi rend="i">Daily Life in Johnson’s London.</hi> Madison, WI: U
of Wisconsin P, 1984. $25 cloth / $9.95 paper.</p>
            <p>279. Stafford, Barbara Maria. “From ‘Brilliant Ideas’ to ‘Fitful Thoughts:’
Conjecturing the Unseen in Late Eighteenth-Century Art.” <hi rend="i">Zeitschrift für Kunstgeschichte</hi>
48 (1985): 329-63.</p>
            <p>280. *Starobinski, Jean. <hi rend="i">1789: The Emblems of Reason.</hi> Trans. Barbara Bray.
Charlottesville, VA: UP of Virginia, 1982. $24.95. [The American edition of Starobinski’s book of 1973 with
a chapter on Fuseli. For the original French edition and a German translation see <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 15 (1981): 88, #131; 16 (1982): 117, #147.]</p>
            <p>281. Wilson, Peter Lamborn. <hi rend="i">Angels.</hi> New York, NY: Pantheon; London: Thames
and Hudson, 1980. [A general survey of the iconography and formal history of the winged figure, with
reproductions and brief discussions of five Blakean examples.]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Some Contemporary Artists, Collectors, and Connoisseurs</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>282. Abrams, Ann Uhry. “Benjamin West’s Documentation of Colonial History: ‘William
Penn’s Treaty with the Indians.’ ” <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi> 64 (1983): 59-75.</p>
            <p>283. *Abrams, Ann Uhry. <hi rend="i">The Valiant Hero: Benjamin West and Grand-Style History
Painting.</hi> New Directions in American Art 1. Washington, DC: Smithsonian Institution P, 1985. $48 cloth /
$24.95 paper.</p>
            <p>284. Dekker, H. T. Douwes. “Angelica Kaufmann [sic] imitatrice de Madame Vigée-LeBrun?”
<hi rend="i">Gazette des Beaux-Arts</hi> 6th ser. 104 (1984): 195.</p>
            <p>285. *Erffa, Helmut von, and Allen Staley. <hi rend="i">The Paintings of Benjamin West.</hi>
New Haven, CT: Yale UP, in association with the Barra Foundation, 1986. £50. [A catalogue raisonné.]</p>
            <p>286. *Flexner, James Thomas. <hi rend="i">America’s Old Masters.</hi> New York, NY:
McGraw-Hill, 1982. [A revised edition of Flexner’s pioneering study of 1939; contains chapters on West and
Copley.]</p>
            <pb id="p20-91" n="91"/>
            <p>287. Honour, Hugh. “Benjamin West’s ‘Indian Family.’ ” <hi rend="i">Burlington
Magazine</hi> 125 (1983): 726-33.</p>
            <p>288. *Maue, Claudia. “Angelica Kauffmann invenit—Bildvorlagen für Wiener Porzellane.”
<hi rend="i">Keramos</hi> 90 (1980): 9-38. [On Vienna porcelain decorated with pictures following Angelica’s
compositions.]</p>
            <p>289. Nobs-Greter, Ruth. “Zur Rezeptionsgeschichte von Angelika Kauffmann (1741-1807):
‘Weiblichkeit’ im Urteil der deutschsprachigen Kunstgeschichtsschreibung.” <hi rend="i">Die Künstlerin
und ihr Werk in der deutschsprachigen Kunstgeschichtsschreibung.</hi> Zurich: Juris, 1984. 121-63. [Feminist
in approach, this chapter from a Zurich Ph.D. thesis traces the prejudices involved in the critical literature
on ‘Miss Angel’ from Herder to the present.]</p>
            <p>290. O’Brien, Elvy Setterqvist. “Johan Tobias Sergell (1740-1814) and Neoclassicism:
Sculpture of Sergell’s Years Abroad, 1767-1779.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 44
(1983): 5A. U of Iowa. [Treats Sergel’s artistic relationship with Fuseli and analyzes Ozias Humphrey’s
comments on Sergel’s Roman works.]</p>
            <p>291. *Ottley, William Young. <hi rend="i">The Italian School of Design.</hi> 1823. New York,
NY: Garland, 1980. $50.</p>
            <p>292. Petschauer, Peter. “Christina Dorothea Leporin (Erxleben), Sophia (Gutermann) von La
Roche, and Angelika Kauffmann: Background and Dilemmas of Independence.” <hi rend="i">Studies in
Eighteenth-Century Culture</hi> 15 (1986): 127-43.</p>
            <p>293. Roworth, Wendy Wassyng. “Angelica Kauffman’s [sic] ‘Memorandum of Paintings.’ ”
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 126 (1984): 629-30.</p>
            <p>294. Roworth, Wendy Wassyng. “The Gentle Art of Persuasion: Angelica Kaufman’s [sic]
‘Praxiteles and Phryne.’ ” <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi> 65 (1983): 488-92.</p>
            <p>295. Sund, Judy. “Benjamin West: A Scene from <hi rend="i">King Lear.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Bulletin of the Detroit Institute of Arts</hi> 58 (1980): 127-36. [Discusses the sketch for West’s
painting in the Boydell Shakespeare Gallery.]</p>
            <p>296. Sutton, Denys. “Aspects of British Collecting, Part IV, 14: From Ottley to Eastlake.”
<hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 122 (1985): 84-95.</p>
            <p>297. Walker, John. “Maria Cosway: An Undervalued Artist.” <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 123
(1986): 318-24.</p>
            <p>298. Waterhouse, Ellis K. “Reynolds, Angelica Kauffmann and Lord Boringdon.” 
<hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 122 (1985): 270-74.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Some Contemporary Authors</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>299. *Butler, Marilyn, ed. <hi rend="i">Burke, Paine, Godwin, and the Revolutionary
Controversy.</hi> Cambridge: Cambs.: Cambridge UP, 1984. $39.50 cloth / $13.95 paper.</p>
            <p>300. Butler, Marilyn. “Godwin, Burke, and <hi rend="i">Caleb Williams.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Essays in Criticism</hi> 32 (1982): 237-57.</p>
            <p>301. Canovan, Margaret. “The Un-Benthamite Utilitarianism of Joseph Priestley.” 
<hi rend="i">Journal of the History of Ideas</hi> 45 (1984): 435-50.</p>
            <p>302. DePorte, Michael. “The Consolations of Fiction: Mystery in <hi rend="i">Caleb
Williams.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Papers on Language and Literature</hi> 20 (1984): 154-64.</p>
            <p>303. Elder, Thomas Balfour. “Godwin and ‘The Great Springs of Human Passion.’ ” 
<hi rend="i">Ariel</hi> 14.1 (1983): 15-31.</p>
            <p>304. Ferguson, Moira, and Janet Todd. <hi rend="i">Mary Wollstonecraft.</hi> Twayne English
Authors Series 381. Boston, Mass.: Twayne-G. K. Hall, 1984. $17.95.</p>
            <p>305. *Fruchtman, Jack, Jr. <hi rend="i">The Apocalyptic Politics of Richard Price and Joseph
Priestley: A Study in Late Eighteenth-Century English Republican Millennialism.</hi> Transactions of the
American Philosophical Society 73.4. Philadelphia, PA: American Philosophical Society, 1983. £10.</p>
            <p>306. Fruchtman, Jack, Jr. “Joseph Priestley on Rhetoric and the Power of Political
Discourse.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Life</hi> ns 7.3 (1982): 37-47.</p>
            <p>307. Fruchtman, Jack, Jr. “The Revolutionary Millennialism of Thomas Paine.” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Eighteenth-Century Culture</hi> 13 (1984): 65-77.</p>
            <p>308. Garrett, Clarke. “Swedenborg and the Mystical Enlightenment in Late Eighteenth-Century
England.” <hi rend="i">Journal of the History of Ideas</hi> 45 (1984): 67-81.</p>
            <p>309. Graham, Kenneth W. “The Gothic Unity of Godwin’s <hi rend="i">Caleb Williams.</hi>”
<hi rend="i">Papers on Language and Literature</hi> 20 (1984): 47-59.</p>
            <p>310. *Hardt, Ulrich H., ed. <hi rend="i">A Critical Edition of Mary Wollstonecraft’s</hi> A
Vindication of the Rights of Woman: With Strictures on Politics and Moral Subjects. Troy, NY: Whitston, 1982.
$45.</p>
            <p>311. Kelly, Gary. “Convention and Criticism in William Godwin’s Early Novels.” 
<hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 33 (1984): 52-69.</p>
            <p>312. *Marshall, Peter H. <hi rend="i">William Godwin: Philosopher, Novelist,
Revolutionary.</hi> New Haven, CT: Yale UP, 1984. $30.</p>
            <p>313. *Palacio, Jean de. <hi rend="i">William Godwin et son monde intérieur.</hi> Lille: PU de
Lille, 1980.</p>
            <p>314. *Payne, Michael. “Priestley, Paine, and the Tradition of English Dissent.” 
<hi rend="i">Pennsylvania English</hi> 10 (1983): 5-13.</p>
            <p>315. Poovey, Mary. “Mary Wollstonecraft: The Gender of Genres in Late Eighteenth-Century
England.” <hi rend="i">Novel: A Forum on Fiction</hi> 15 (1982): 111-26.</p>
            <p>316. Poovey, Mary. <hi rend="i">The Proper Lady and the Woman Writer: Ideology as Style in the
Works of Mary Wollstonecraft, Mary Shelley, and Jane Austen.</hi> Women in Culture and Society. Chicago, IL: U
of Chicago P, 1984. [“Man’s Discourse, Woman’s Heart: Mary Wollstonecraft’s Two Vindications” is on
pp. 48-81; Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Letters</hi> and <hi rend="i">Maria, or the Wrongs of Woman</hi>
are
<pb id="p20-92" n="92"/>
discussed in the following chapter on pp. 82-113.]</p>
            <p>317. Scheuermann, Mona. “The Study of Mind: the Later Novels of William Godwin.” 
<hi rend="i">Forum for Modern Language Studies</hi> 19 (1983): 16-30.</p>
            <p>318. Stewart, Sally N. “Mary Wollstonecraft’s Contributions to the <hi rend="i">Analytical
Review.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Essays in Literature</hi> 11 (1984): 187-99.</p>
            <p>319. Tysdahl, B. J. <hi rend="i">William Godwin as Novelist.</hi> London: Athlone P, 1981. £15
cloth / £5.95 paper. [Discusses “links between social forces and mental disease” as interpreted by
Godwin, Cowper, and Blake; see pp. 143-45.]</p>
            <p>320. Willey, Edward P. “The Works of Alexander Chalmers, Journalist, Editor, Biographer.”
<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi> 86 (1983): 94-104. [In 1805, Chalmers edited 
<hi rend="i">The Plays of William Shakspeare</hi>, illustrated with engravings by Blake, Cromek, et al. after a
series of designs by Henry Fuseli.]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Some Blake Scholars and Collectors</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>321. Bentinck-Smith, William. “Prince of the Eye: Philip Hofer and the Harvard Library.”
<hi rend="i">Harvard Library Bulletin</hi> 32 (1984): 317-47. [A second part of this article is
forthcoming.]</p>
            <p>322. Damon, S. Foster. “<hi rend="i">Thy</hi> Hand, Great Anarch.” <hi rend="i">Michigan
Quarterly Review</hi> 24 (1985): 371. [A reprint of one of Foster Damon’s poems, first published in 
<hi rend="i">Nightmare Cemetry</hi> (1964).]</p>
            <p>323. Greenberg, Mark L. “Relentless Quest for Association Copy.” <hi rend="i">AB:
Bookman’s Weekly / Antiquarian Bookman</hi> 68.11 (1981): 1587-96. [Relates the story of the author’s
(successful) search for William Bell Scott’s transcript and tracings from Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Notebook.</hi> See also #90, above.]</p>
            <p>324. *Grigson, Geoffrey. <hi rend="i">Recollections: Chiefly of Writers and Artists.</hi>
London: Hogarth P-Chatto and Windus, 1984. £12.50. [Recalling, amongst many others, his friendship with
Ruthven Todd.]</p>
            <p>325. Grob, Alan. “The Uses of Northrop Frye: ‘Sunday Morning’ and the Romantic
Topocosm.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 22 (1983): 587-615.</p>
            <p>326. Keynes, Stephen J. “Blake Trust Chairman’s Report.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 126-27. [A complete reprint of a mimeographed text which had been
circulated by the Trust “to Members and Patrons” in Oct. 1984.]</p>
            <p>327. *Lindsay, Jack. <hi rend="i">Life Rarely Tells: Life Rarely Tells, The Roaring Twenties,
and Fanfrolico and After.</hi> Harmondsworth, Mddx.: Penguin, 1982. £5. [A new edition of the first three
volumes of Lindsay’s autobiography; the author wrote his first Blake book in the roaring twenties.]</p>
            <p>328. Luria, Maxwell, and Richard E. Brewer. “The Caliph and the Professor: A. Edward
Newton’s Correspondence with Chauncey Brewster Tinker.” <hi rend="i">Harvard Library Bulletin</hi> 33
(1985): 114-73.</p>
            <p>329. *Luria, Maxwell, and Richard E. Brewer. “‘Dear Charley:’ A. Edward Newton’s
Letters to Charles Grosvenor Osgood.” <hi rend="i">Princeton Library Chronicle</hi> 45 (1984): 230-54.</p>
            <p>330. McConnell, Frank. “Northrop Frye and <hi rend="i">Anatomy of Criticism.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Sewanee Review</hi> 92 (1984): 622-29.</p>
            <p>331. McQuail, Josephine. “An Unpublished Poem by S. Foster Damon.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 72.</p>
            <p>332. “The Mellon Centre.” Editorial. <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 126 (1984):
603.</p>
            <p>333. *Murry, Katherine Middleton. <hi rend="i">Beloved Quixote: The Unknown Life of John
Middleton Murry.</hi> London: Souvenir P, 1985. £14.95.</p>
            <p>334. Reading, Peter. “Geoffrey Grigson, 1905-1985.” <hi rend="i">Times Literary
Supplement</hi> 17 Jan. 1986: 59.</p>
            <p>335. Robertson, P. J. M. “Criticism and Creativity VI: George Orwell and Northrop Frye.”
<hi rend="i">Queen’s Quarterly</hi> 92 (1985): 374-84.</p>
            <p>336. <hi rend="i">Rosenwald and Rosenbach: Two Philadelphia Bookmen.</hi> Philadelphia, PA:
Rosenbach Museum and Library, 1983. [The catalogue of an exhibition (30 April to 31 July 1983) in honor of the
two Blake collectors. Contains introductory essays by Seymour Adelman and Kathleen T. Hunt, and includes
catalogue entries for the Rosenwald copies of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and <hi rend="i">Ahania</hi> (pp.
33-35), plus a color reproduction of “The Tyger” from Copy Z.]</p>
            <p>337. Smith, Bernard. “Jack Lindsay.” <hi rend="i">Australian Literary Studies</hi> 11
(1983): 216-26.</p>
            <p>338. Sullivan, Rosemary. “Northrop Frye: Canadian Mythographer.” <hi rend="i">Journal of
Commonwealth Literature</hi> 18.1 (1983): 1-13.</p>
            <p>339. Wilmerding, John, ed. <hi rend="i">Essays in Honor of Paul Mellon: Collector and
Benefactor.</hi> Washington, DC: National Gallery of Art, 1986. [Ryskamp’s contribution to this 
<hi rend="i">festschrift</hi>, an article on Mellon and Blake, is listed separately as #166, above.]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Blakean Echoes in the Twentieth Century</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>340. *Adams, Hazard. <hi rend="i">Joyce Cary’s Trilogies: Pursuit of the Particular.</hi>
Tallahassee, FL: Florida State UP, 1983. $20. [In the words of one reviewer, “in the theoretical discussions
(of this book) Blake overwhelms Cary” and the “Blake-allusiveness in Cary’s work” is said to be
“carefully documented;” see #346.5, below.]</p>
            <p>341. Bell, Dan. “The [First] Book of Blake: Katmandu. Typed by Gypsy 1983.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 122-23. [A parody, closely modeled on 
<hi rend="i">Urizen.</hi>]</p>
            <p>342. *Cassill, R. V. “The Folly &amp; Imagination of Wm. Blake.” <hi rend="i">R. V.
Cassill.</hi> Ed. Kay Cassill, Orin E. Cassill, and Curt Johnson. December 23. Chicago, IL: December, 1981.
49-54.</p>
            <pb id="p20-93" n="93"/>
            <p>343. *Gorsen, Peter. <hi rend="i">Alfred Hrdlicka: Blake und Füssli—47 Zeichnungen.</hi>
Frankfort on Main, W. Ger.: Galerie Timm Gierig, 1983. [An exhibition catalogue.]</p>
            <p>344. Stevenson, Warren. “On Blake’s Painting of Jesus and the Woman Taken in Adultery.”
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1986): 150. [A poem by a Blake scholar which
“supplements” Christopher Heppner’s recent essay on this painting; see <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 17 (1983): 44-60; 18 (1984): 103, #61.]</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part IV Reviews of Works Cited Above and in Previous Checklists</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>345. Abrams, Ann Uhry. <hi rend="i">The Valiant Hero: Benjamin West and Grand-Style History
Painting.</hi> Reviewed by L[ynn] R. Matteson, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 23 (1986): 1046-48.</p>
          <p>346. Adams, Hazard. <hi rend="i">Joyce Cary’s Trilogies: Pursuit of the Particular.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) Robert Bloom, <hi rend="i">Èire-Ireland</hi> 20.4 (1985): 149-52; by (2) David Bradshaw, 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 2 Nov. 1984: 1240; in (3) <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 21 (1984): 1462; by
(4) Edwin Ernest Christian, <hi rend="i">Studies in the Novel</hi> 17 (1985): 311-12; by (5) Elizabeth D.
Ermarth, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi> 84 (1985): 576-78; by (6) Michael Feehan,
<hi rend="i">Genre</hi> 17 (1984): 429-34; by (7) David E. Latané, Jr., <hi rend="i">Southern Humanities
Review</hi> 19 (1985): 382-84; by (8) Brian Murray, <hi rend="i">Modern Fiction Studies</hi> 30 (1984):
770-72; by (9) Yvon Tosser, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 38 (1985): 345-46.</p>
          <p>347. Adams, Hazard. <hi rend="i">Philosophy of the Literary Symbolic.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Michel
Cusin, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 38 (1985): 296-97; by (2) Denis Donoghue, <hi rend="i">Times
Literary Supplement</hi> 6 Apr. 1984: 370; by (3) Michael Feehan, <hi rend="i">Genre</hi> 17 (1984): 429-34;
by (4) Hans Kellner, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Notes</hi> 99 (1984): 1220-25; by (5) David E. Latané, Jr.,
<hi rend="i">Southern Humanities Review</hi> 19 (1985): 382-84; by (6) Daniel T. O’Hara, <hi rend="i">Modern
Language Quarterly</hi> 45 (1984): 311-14.</p>
          <p>348. Albright, Daniel. <hi rend="i">Lyricality in English Literature.</hi> Reviewed by (1) *Dale
K. Boyer, <hi rend="i">Rocky Mountain Review of Language and Literature</hi> 39 (1985): 277-78; by (2) Anne
Williams, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1986): 144-46.</p>
          <p>349. Alexander, David, and Richard T. Godfrey. <hi rend="i">Painters and Engraving: The
Reproductive Print from Hogarth to Wilkie.</hi> Reviewed by Morris Eaves, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 6 (1980):
251-52.</p>
          <p>350. Alford, Steven E. <hi rend="i">Irony and the Logic of the Romantic Imagination.</hi>
Reviewed by David Simpson, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 106.</p>
          <p>351. Allen, Brian. <hi rend="i">George Romney as a Painter of Children.</hi> Reviewed by E. K. W.
[Sir Ellis K. Waterhouse], <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 126 (1984): 515-16.</p>
          <p>352. Allen, Robert R., ed. <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A Current Bibliography.</hi>
Vols. 3 and 4 for 1977 and 1978 reviewed by (1) Paula R. Backscheider, <hi rend="i">Modern Language
Review</hi> 80 (1985): 681-84; by (2) P.-G. B. [Paul-Gabriel Boucé?], <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 37
(1984): 235. Vol. 5 for 1979 reviewed by (3) P.-G. B. [Paul-Gabriel Boucé?], <hi rend="i">Ètudes
Anglaises</hi> 37 (1984): 490-91; by (4) A. J. Sambrook, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi> 81 (1986):
424-26.</p>
          <p>353. Ault, Donald D. <hi rend="i">Visionary Physics: Blake’s Response to Newton.</hi> Reviewed
by *A. A. Ansari, <hi rend="i">Aligarh Journal of English Studies</hi> 7 (1982): 92-100.</p>
          <p>354. Baird, John D., and Charles Ryskamp, eds. <hi rend="i">The Poems of William Cowper.</hi>
Vol. 1 reviewed by (1) *James Fenton, <hi rend="i">Listener</hi> 106 (1981): 277-78; by (2) Frank Kermode, 
<hi rend="i">New York Review of Books</hi> 21 Oct. 1982: 39-41.</p>
          <p>355. Baker, Carlos. <hi rend="i">The Echoing Green: Romanticism, Modernism, and the Phenomena of
Transference in Poetry.</hi> Reviewed by (1) P. Brazeau, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1985): 677; by (2) Sean
French, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 17 Aug. 1984: 925; by (3) Robert [F.] Gleckner, 
<hi rend="i">American Literature</hi> 57 (1985): 158-59; by (4) Warwick Gould, <hi rend="i">Yeats Annual</hi> 4
(1986): 269-76 [for a brief commentary on Baker’s book see p. 273]; by (5) Stuart M. Sperry, 
<hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi> 23.1 (1985): 79-81.</p>
          <p>356. Beer, John. <hi rend="i">William Blake 1757-1827.</hi> Reviewed by (1) James Bogan, 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 151-52; by (2) *Grevel Lindop, 
<hi rend="i">Charles Lamb Bulletin</hi> 44 (1983): 89-90.</p>
          <p>357. Behrendt, Stephen C. <hi rend="i">The Moment of Explosion: Blake and the Illustration of
Milton.</hi> Reviewed in (1) <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 21 (1984): 1130; by (2) Stephen D. Cox, 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18 (1985): 391-405; by (3) D. V. E. [David V. Erdman], 
<hi rend="i">RMB for 1983</hi>: 74-75; by (4) Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and
Interpretation</hi> 27 (1986): 106-12; by (5) Karl Kroeber, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
19 (1985): 75; by (6) Anne K. Mellor, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 15 (1984): 110; by (7) Dennis M.
Welch, <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> 64 (1984): 424-26; by (8) Joseph Wittreich, 
<hi rend="i">Milton Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 92-94.</p>
          <p>358. Bertholf, Robert J., and Annette S. Levitt, eds. <hi rend="i">William Blake and the
Moderns.</hi> Reviewed by (1) M. T. S. [Mark T. Smith], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1982</hi>: 77-80; by (2) John
Williams, <hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi> 11 (1985): 142-43.</p>
          <p>359. Bindman, David, ed. <hi rend="i">John Flaxman, R. A.</hi> Reviewed by *Alison Kelly, 
<hi rend="i">Journal of the Royal Society of Arts</hi> 128 (1980): 532-33.</p>
          <p>360. Bindman, David, ed. <hi rend="i">The Thames and Hudson Encyclopaedia of British Art.</hi>
Reviewed in (1) <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 128 (1986): 49-50; by (2) Richard Kingzett, 
<hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 123 (1986): 292; by (3) Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 7
Feb. 1986: 144.</p>
          <p>361. Bindman, David. <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Art and Times.</hi> Reviewed by G. E.
Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">University of Toronto Quarterly</hi> 54 (1985): 297-99.</p>
          <pb id="p20-94" n="94"/>
          <p>362. Blake, William. America: A Prophecy <hi rend="i">and</hi> Europe: A Prophecy—<hi
rend="i">Facsimile Reproductions of Two Illuminated Books.</hi> Reviewed by (1) D. V. E. [David V. Erdman],
<hi rend="i">RMB for 1983</hi>: 76-77; by (2) Jenijoy La Belle, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 83-84.</p>
          <p>363. Blake, William. Songs of Experience—<hi rend="i">Facsimile Reproduction.</hi> Reviewed by
Jenijoy La Belle, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 83-84.</p>
          <p>364. Blake, William. Songs of Innocence <hi rend="i">and</hi> Songs of Experience. The Manchester
Etching Workshop prints reviewed by Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19
(1985): 39-51. [See also #184, above.]</p>
          <p>365. Blondel, Jacques, ed. and trans. <hi rend="i">Vala, ou Les Quatre vivants.</hi> Vol. 4 of
<hi rend="i">Oeuvres de William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by (1) David Fuller, <hi rend="i">Durham University
Journal</hi> ns 46 (1984): 118-19; by (2) Peter [H.] Marshall, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 38 (1985):
235-36.</p>
          <p>366. Bogan, James, and Fred Goss, eds. <hi rend="i">Sparks of Fire: Blake in a New Age.</hi>
Reviewed by Jenijoy La Belle, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 48-49.</p>
          <p>367. Borck, Jim Springer, ed. <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A Current Bibliography.</hi>
Vol. 6 for 1980 reviewed by A. J. Sambrook, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi> 81 (1986): 424-26.</p>
          <p>368. Boulger, James D. <hi rend="i">The Calvinist Temper in English Poetry.</hi> Reviewed by *A.
G. Newell, <hi rend="i">Evangelical Quarterly</hi> 56 (1984): 110-11.</p>
          <p>369. Bridson, Gavin, and Geoffrey Wakeman. <hi rend="i">Printmaking and Picture Printing: A
Bibliographical Guide to Artistic and Industrial Techniques in Britain 1750-1900.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Richard
W. Clement, <hi rend="i">Library Quarterly</hi> 55 (1985): 357-58; by (2) Antony Griffiths, 
<hi rend="i">Library</hi> 6th ser. 7 (1985): 285-87.</p>
          <p>370. Brisman, Leslie. <hi rend="i">Romantic Origins.</hi> Reviewed by Heide N. Rohloff, 
<hi rend="i">Anglia</hi> 103 (1985): 220-24.</p>
          <p>371. Brogan, T. V. F. <hi rend="i">English Versification, 1570-1980: A Reference Guide with a
Global Appendix.</hi> Reviewed by Anne Elliott, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 35 (1984):
419-20.</p>
          <p>372. Burke, Joseph. <hi rend="i">English Art 1714-1800.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Luke Herrman, 
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 120 (1978): 36; by (2) Lynn R. Matteson, <hi rend="i">Art Journal</hi> 39
(1979): 78-80.</p>
          <p>373. Burkett, Mary E., ed. <hi rend="i">George Romney 1734-1802.</hi> Reviewed by *Nicholas
Usherwood, <hi rend="i">Country Life</hi> 9 Aug. 1984: 378-79.</p>
          <p>374. Butler, Marilyn, ed. <hi rend="i">Burke, Paine, Godwin, and the Revolution Controversy.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) D. A. N. Jones, <hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi> 6-19 Sept. 1984: 18-19; by (2) Don
Locke, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 21 Sept. 1984: 1061.</p>
          <p>375. Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by
Peter Parker, <hi rend="i">New Statesman</hi> 29 Jan. 1982: 18-19.</p>
          <p>376. Butter, P. H., ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Selected Poems.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Bernard
Beatty, <hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 7 (1984): 130; by (2) F. P.
[François Piquet], <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 37 (1984): 363-64.</p>
          <p>377. [Cannon-Brookes, Peter, et al.] <hi rend="i">The British Neo-Romantics, 1935-1950.</hi>
Reviewed by John Spurling, <hi rend="i">New Statesman</hi> 5 Aug. 1983: 30-31.</p>
          <p>378. Cantor, Paul A. <hi rend="i">Creature and Creator: Myth-Making and English Romanticism.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) T[erence Allan] Hoagwood, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1984): 421-22; by (2) Iain McGilchrist,
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 3 Aug. 1984: 862; by (3) Anne K. Mellor, <hi rend="i">English
Language Notes</hi> 23.1 (1985): 77-79; by (4) Mark Roberts, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 37
(1986): 103-05; by (5) Nicholas Roe, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 32 (1985): 562-63.</p>
          <p>379. Cave, Kathryn, ed. <hi rend="i">The Diary of Joseph Farington.</hi> Vols. 7 and 8 reviewed
in (1) <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 24 (1983): 80. Vols. 7-10 reviewed by
(2) Anne Tennant, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi> 7 (1984): 375-78. Vols. 13-16 reviewed by (3) L. H. [Luke
Herrmann], <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 126 (1984): 796; by (4) Luke Herrmann, 
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 127 (1985): 814; by (5) Marcia Pointon, <hi rend="i">Times Literary
Supplement</hi> 17 May 1985: 539.</p>
          <p>380. Chan, Victor. <hi rend="i">“Leader of My Angels:” William Hayley and His Circle.</hi>
Reviewed by [Anne-Marie S. Logan], <hi rend="i">Master Drawings</hi> 22 (1984): 330-31.</p>
          <p>381. Clarke, Michael, and Nicholas Penny, eds. <hi rend="i">The Arrogant Connoisseur: Richard
Payne Knight 1751-1824.</hi> Reviewed by George B. Tatum, <hi rend="i">Journal of the Society of Architectural
Historians</hi> 44 (1985): 398-99.</p>
          <p>382. Cook, Eleanor, et al., eds. <hi rend="i">Centre and Labyrinth: Essays in Honour of Northrop
Frye.</hi> Reviewed by (1) David Scott Kastan, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 17 Feb. 1984: 163;
by (2) Dan[iel T.] O’Hara, <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 26 (1984): 91-95.</p>
          <p>383. Cooper, Robert M. <hi rend="i">The Literary Guide and Companion to Southern England.</hi>
Reviewed by Phillip Ward-Green, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 25 Oct. 1985: 1217.</p>
          <p>384. Corti, Claudia. <hi rend="i">Il primo Blake: Testo e sistema.</hi> Reviewed by Serena Cenni,
<hi rend="i">Rivista di letterature moderne e comparate</hi> 33 (1980): 313-15.</p>
          <p>385. Cox, Stephen D. <hi rend="i">“The Stranger Within Thee:” Concepts of the Self in Late
Eighteenth-Century Literature.</hi> Reviewed by (1) *James S. Grotstein, <hi rend="i">Review of Psychoanalytic
Books</hi> 2 (1983-1984): 367-73; by (2) John Sitter, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 17
(1983-1984): 189-93; by (3) David Worrall, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984):
31-32.</p>
          <p>386. Crehan, Stewart. <hi rend="i">Blake in Context.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Paul Hamilton, 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 15 June 1984: 674; by (2) T[erence Allan] Hoagwood, 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1984): 266; by (3) Stuart Peterfreund, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 113-16.</p>
          <pb id="p20-95" n="95"/>
          <p>387. Crouan, Katherine. <hi rend="i">John Linnell: A Centennial Exhibition.</hi> Reviewed by (1)
Frances Spalding, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 29 Oct. 1982: 1190; by (2) William Vaughan, 
<hi rend="i">Art History</hi> 7 (1984): 368-74.</p>
          <p>388. Damrosch, Leopold, Jr. <hi rend="i">Symbol and Truth in Blake’s Myth.</hi> Reviewed by (1)
*Stuart Curran, <hi rend="i">Review</hi> 4 (1982): 135-57; by (2) *Kevin Lewis, <hi rend="i">Religious Studies
Review</hi> 9 (1983): 370; by (3) Leland E. Warren, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 7 (1981): 393-94.</p>
          <p>389. Deen, Leonard W. <hi rend="i">Conversing in Paradise: Poetic Genius and
Identity-as-Community in Blake’s Los.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Stephen D. Cox, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century
Studies</hi> 18 (1985): 391-405; by (2) D. V. E. [David V. Erdman], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1983</hi>: 77; by (3)
Mary Lynn Johnson, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 107-10; by (4) Andrew
Lincoln, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 36 (1985): 576-77; by (5) Victoria Myers, 
<hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi> 84 (1985): 141-43; by (6) Edward J. Rose, 
<hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 15 (1984): 111-12; by (7) [Bette] Charlene Werner, <hi rend="i">Milton
Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 35-36.</p>
          <p>390. DiSalvo, Jackie. <hi rend="i">War of Titans: Blake’s Critique of Milton and the Poetics of
Religion.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Jacques Blondel, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 39 (1986): 97; by (2) Anne
Ferry, <hi rend="i">Renaissance Quarterly</hi> 37 (1984): 671-72; by (3) Robert F. Gleckner, 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1986): 146-50; by (4) Andrew Lincoln, <hi rend="i">Review
of English Studies</hi> ns 37 (1986): 105-07; by (5) M. T. S. [Mark T. Smith], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1983</hi>:
78-79.</p>
          <p>391. Doskow, Minna. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem: <hi rend="i">Structure and
Meaning in Poetry and Picture.</hi> Reviewed by (1) I. H. C. [Irene H. Chayes], <hi rend="i">RMB for
1983</hi>: 79-80; by (2) V. A. DeLuca, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 56-58; by
(3) Paul Hamilton, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 15 June 1984: 674; by (4) Donald John, 
<hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 36 (1985): 434-36.</p>
          <p>392. Dowdey, Landon, ed. The Four Zoas: The Torments of Love and Jealousy in the Death and
Judgment of Albion the Ancient Man, <hi rend="i">by William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by W. J. T. Mitchell, 
<hi rend="i">Library Quarterly</hi> 55 (1985): 115-17.</p>
          <p>393. Dunbar, Pamela. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Poetry of Milton.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) Robert F. Gleckner, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 7 (1981): 395-96; by (2) Bette Charlene Werner, 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 33-34.</p>
          <p>394. Eaves, Morris. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Theory of Art.</hi> Reviewed by (1) I. H. C.
[Irene H. Chayes], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1982</hi>: 83-84; by (2) Stephen D. Cox, 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18 (1985): 391-405; by (3) *Richard Harter Fogle, 
<hi rend="i">Clio</hi> 13 (1984): 293-95; by (4) *Raymond Lister, <hi rend="i">Journal of the Royal Society of
Arts</hi> 132 (1983): 86-87; by (5) Peter A. Taylor, <hi rend="i">Queen’s Quarterly</hi> 91 (1984): 719-22;
by (6) Thomas A. Vogler, <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 24 (1985): 289-300; by (7) Brian Wilkie, 
<hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi> 84 (1985): 138-40.</p>
          <p>395. Einem, Herbert von. <hi rend="i">Deutsche Malerei des Klassizismus und der Romantik, 1760
bis 1840.</hi> Reviewed by Jens Christian Jensen, <hi rend="i">Kunstchronik</hi> 33 (1980): 68-72.</p>
          <p>396. Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) the Santa Cruz Blake Study Group, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18
(1984): 4-31; by (2) Peter A. Taylor, <hi rend="i">Queen’s Quarterly</hi> 91 (1984): 719-22.</p>
          <p>397. Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) M. Baridon, <hi rend="i">Dix-huitième Siècle</hi> 16 (1984): 513 [very briefly!]; by (2) I.
H. C. [Irene H. Chayes], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1983</hi>: 80-81; by (3) Stephen D. Cox, 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18 (1985): 391-405.</p>
          <p>398. Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">William Blake, Printmaker.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Jim Springer
Borck, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 6 (1980): 398-99; by (2) David E. McKenty, <hi rend="i">College Literature</hi>
8 (1981): 196-97; by (3) *Mark Trevor Smith, <hi rend="i">American Book Collector</hi> ns 2.2 (1981):
75-77.</p>
          <p>399. Essick, Robert N., and Morton D. Paley, eds. <hi rend="i">Robert Blair’s</hi> The Grave,
<hi rend="i">Illustrated by William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by (1) I. H. C. [Irene H. Chayes], <hi rend="i">RMB
for 1982</hi>: 85; by (2) Claudia Corti, <hi rend="i">Rivista di letterature moderne e comparate</hi> 38
(1985): 97-100; by (3) David Fuller, <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi> ns 46 (1984): 119-23; by (4)
Andrew Wilton, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 54-56; by (5) Jonathan
Wordsworth, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 35 (1984): 547-48.</p>
          <p>400. Fairchild, B. H. <hi rend="i">Such Holy Song: Music as Idea, Form, and Image in the Poetry
of William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by Stephen Leo Carr, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 6 (1980): 399-400.</p>
          <p>401. Ferber, Michael. <hi rend="i">The Social Vision of William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by G. A.
Cevasco, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 23 (1986): 867.</p>
          <p>402. Ferguson, Moira, and Janet Todd. <hi rend="i">Mary Wollstonecraft.</hi> Reviewed in 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 21 (1984): 1605.</p>
          <p>403. Forbes, Gregory. <hi rend="i">Selections from William Blake’s</hi> Songs of Innocence and
of Experience: <hi rend="i">Musical Settings / A Companion to the New Musical Settings by Gregory Forbes.</hi>
Reviewed by Joseph Viscomi, with Margaret LaFrance, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19
(1985): 84-89.</p>
          <p>404. Fruchtman, Jack, Jr. <hi rend="i">The Apocalyptic Politics of Richard Price and Joseph
Priestley: A Study in Late Eighteenth-Century English Republican Millennialism.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Martin
Fitzpatrick, <hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 8 (1985): 236-38; by (2) A.
Thomson, <hi rend="i">Dix-huitième Siècle</hi> 17 (1985): 474.</p>
          <p>405. Frye, Northrop. <hi rend="i">The Great Code: The Bible and Literature.</hi> Reviewed by (1)
Paul-Gabriel Boucé, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 37 (1984): 449-50; by (2) J. M. Cameron, 
<hi rend="i">New York Review of Books</hi> 15 Apr. 1982: 28-31; by (3) *Robert P. Carroll, <hi rend="i">Scottish
Journal of Theology</hi> 37
<pb id="p20-96" n="96"/>
(1984): 246-50; by (4) Peter Conradi, <hi rend="i">New Statesman</hi> 18 June 1982: 20-21; by (5) S. G. K. [S.
G. Kossick], <hi rend="i">UNISA English Studies</hi> 22.2 (1984): 63; by (6) Herbert J. Levine, 
<hi rend="i">Georgia Review</hi> 36 (1982): 900-04; by (7) Gottfried Mehnert, <hi rend="i">Literatur in
Wissenschaft und Unterricht</hi> 18 (1985): 80-82; by (8) *A. G. Newell, <hi rend="i">Evangelical
Quarterly</hi> 57 (1985): 188; by (9) *Carl Ridd, <hi rend="i">Studies in Religion / Sciences Religieuses</hi>
11 (1982): 446-48; by (10) Nicholas Smith, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 36 (1985): 302-03;
by (11) Karina Williamson, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 31 (1984): 288; see also (12) “A Little
Symposium on <hi rend="i">The Great Code.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dalhousie Review</hi> 63 (1983): 400-21.</p>
          <p>406. Gallant, Christine. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Assimilation of Chaos.</hi> Reviewed in (1)
*<hi rend="i">Aligarh Journal of English Studies</hi> 6 (1981): 107-13; by (2) *Thomas J. J. Altizer, 
<hi rend="i">Journal of the American Academy of Religion</hi> Sept. 1979: 485-86; by (3) Stephen D. Cox, 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 15 (1981-1982): 205-09.</p>
          <p>407. Garlick, Kenneth, and Angus Macintyre, eds. <hi rend="i">The Diary of Joseph Farington.</hi>
Vols. 1-6 reviewed by Anne Tennant, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi> 7 (1984): 375-78.</p>
          <p>408. George, Diana Hume. <hi rend="i">Blake and Freud.</hi> Reviewed by (1) *Stuart Curran, 
<hi rend="i">Review</hi> 4 (1982): 135-57; by (2) William H. Galperin, <hi rend="i">Southern Humanities
Review</hi> 17 (1983): 79-82; by (3) L. F. M. [Leonard F. Manheim], <hi rend="i">University of Hartford
Studies in Literature</hi> 13 (1981): 201-02; by (4) *Charles E. May, <hi rend="i">Christianity and
Literature</hi> 31.1 (1981): 55-57.</p>
          <p>409. Gleckner, Robert F. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prelude:</hi> Poetical Sketches. Reviewed by (1)
I. H. C. [Irene H. Chayes], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1983</hi>: 81-83; by (2) Thomas J. Corr, <hi rend="i">College
Literature</hi> 11 (1984): 286-89; by (3) Stephen D. Cox, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18
(1985): 391-405; by (4) Paul Hamilton, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 15 June 1984: 674; by (5)
Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 23 (1984): 409-13; by (6) Donald John, 
<hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 36 (1985): 434-36; by (7) François Piquet, <hi rend="i">Ètudes
Anglaises</hi> 38 (1985): 237-38; by (8) Dennis M. Welch, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Quarterly</hi> 45
(1984): 301-02; by (9) Joseph Wittreich, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 15 (1984): 113-14.</p>
          <p>410. Glen, Heather. <hi rend="i">Vision and Disenchantment: Blake’s</hi> Songs <hi rend="i">and
Wordsworth’s</hi> Lyrical Ballads. Reviewed by (1) James R. Bennett, <hi rend="i">University of Toronto
Quarterly</hi> 54 (1985): 299-303; by (2) Avril Horner, <hi rend="i">PN Review</hi> 11.3 (1984): 54-56; by (3)
François Piquet, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 38 (1985): 465-66; by (4) David Simpson, 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 227-31; by (5) John Williams, 
<hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi> 10 (1984): 272; by (6) M. A. Williams, <hi rend="i">UNISA English
Studies</hi> 23.1 (1985): 41-42.</p>
          <p>411. Grant, John E., Edward J. Rose, and Michael J. Tolley, eds. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Designs for Edward Young’s</hi> Night Thoughts: <hi rend="i">A Complete Edition.</hi> Reviewed by Joseph
Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Fine Print</hi> 8.2 (1982): 49-50.</p>
          <p>412. Grate, Pontus, et al. <hi rend="i">PÅ klassisk mark: Malere i Rom pÅ 1780-talet.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) G. L. M. [Gian Lorenzo Mellini], <hi rend="i">Labyrinthos</hi> 2.3/4 (1983): 253; by (2) Anna
Ottani Cavina, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 125 (1983): 54-57.</p>
          <p>413. Grigson, Geoffrey. <hi rend="i">Recollections: Chiefly of Writers and Artists.</hi> Reviewed
by (1) Valentine Cunningham, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 14 Dec. 1984: 1439; by (2) Dick
Davis, <hi rend="i">PN Review</hi> 11.6 (1985): 43-46; by (3) Bernard Gutteridge, <hi rend="i">London
Magazine</hi> 24.7 (1984): 97-100.</p>
          <p>414. Hagstrum, Jean H. <hi rend="i">Sex and Sensibility: Ideal and Erotic Love from Milton to
Mozart.</hi> Reviewed by (1) *Maurice Charney, <hi rend="i">Review of Psychoanalytic Books</hi> 2 (1983-1984):
500-01; by (2) Dimiter Daphinoff, <hi rend="i">English Studies</hi> 64 (1983): 279-81; by (3) Joan F.
Gilliland, <hi rend="i">College Literature</hi> 9 (1982): 71-72; by (4) Alicia Ostriker, <hi rend="i">Blake /
An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 52-53; by (5) Peter Wagner, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Life</hi>
8.3 (1983): 108-14.</p>
          <p>415. Halsband, Robert. The Rape of the Lock <hi rend="i">and Its Illustrations 1714-1896.</hi>
Reviewed by William Vaughan, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi> 4 (1981): 485.</p>
          <p>416. Hanke, Amala M. <hi rend="i">Spatiotemporal Consciousness in English and German Romanticism:
A Comparative Study of Novalis, Blake, Wordsworth, and Eichendorff.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Dennis F. Mahoney,
<hi rend="i">Aurora: Jahrbuch der Eichendorff-Gesellschaft</hi> 42 (1982): 254-55; by (2) John D. Simons, 
<hi rend="i">German Quarterly</hi> 57 (1984): 156.</p>
          <p>417. Hardt, Ulrich H., ed. <hi rend="i">A Critical Edition of Mary Wollstonecraft’s</hi> A
Vindication of the Rights of Woman: With Strictures on Political and Moral Subjects. Reviewed by (1) J. D. F.,
<hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 31 (1984): 137-38; by (2) Sara Hudson, <hi rend="i">Southern Humanities
Review</hi> 18 (1984): 185-88; by (3) Mitzi Myers, <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 33 (1984):
231-34.</p>
          <p>418. Haskell, Francis, and Nicholas Penny. <hi rend="i">Taste and the Antique.</hi> Reviewed by
(1) Clifford W. Currie, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Life</hi> 7.1 (1981): 114-30; by (2) Leopold D.
Ettlinger, <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi> 66 (1984): 527-28; by (3) Frank Felsenstein, <hi rend="i">British
Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 5 (1982): 287-89; by (4) Seymour Howard, <hi rend="i">Journal of
Modern History</hi> 55 (1983): 300-03; by (5) Christopher Lloyd, <hi rend="i">English Historical Review</hi>
100 (1985): 415; by (6) Hugh Plommer, <hi rend="i">Classical Review</hi> ns 32 (1982): 264-65; by (7) *Francis
Russell, <hi rend="i">Journal of the Royal Society of Arts</hi> 129 (1981): 803-04.</p>
          <p>419. Hilton, Nelson. <hi rend="i">Literal Imagination: Blake’s Vision of Words.</hi> Reviewed
by (1) Stephen D. Cox, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18 (1985): 391-405; by (2) Michael Ferber,
<hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 26 (1984): 397-99; by (3) David Wagenknecht, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 117-20; by (4) Brian Wilkie, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic
Philology</hi> 83 (1984): 566-68.</p>
          <pb id="p20-97" n="97"/>
          <p>420. Hoagwood, Terence Allan. <hi rend="i">Prophecy and the Philosophy of Mind: Traditions of
Blake and Shelley.</hi> Reviewed by M. Minor, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1985): 1634.</p>
          <p>421. Hodnett, Edward. <hi rend="i">Image and Text: Studies in the Illustration of English
Literature.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Karl Kroeber, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985):
75; by (2) Joachim Möller, <hi rend="i">Germanisch-Romanische Monatsschrift</hi> ns 35 (1985): 119-21; by (3)
*Tobin A. Sparling, <hi rend="i">American Book Collector</hi> ns 5.5 (1984): 41.</p>
          <p>422. Hutchings, Bill. <hi rend="i">The Poetry of William Cowper.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Richard
Bradford, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 32 (1985): 398; by (2) Pierre Danchin, <hi rend="i">English
Studies</hi> 66 (1985): 69-72; by (3) Vincent Newey, <hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century
Studies</hi> 7 (1984): 247-48.</p>
          <p>423. Irwin, David. <hi rend="i">John Flaxman 1755-1826: Sculptor, Illustrator, Designer.</hi>
Reviewed by *Alison Kelly, <hi rend="i">Journal of the Royal Society of Arts</hi> 128 (1980): 532-33.</p>
          <p>424. James, G. Ingli, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Annotations to Richard Watson</hi>, An
Apology for the Bible in a Series of Letters Addressed to Thomas Paine, <hi rend="i">8th ed. 1797.</hi>
Reviewed by Nicholas O. Warner, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 116-17.</p>
          <p>425. Johnston, John H. <hi rend="i">The Poet and the City: A Study in Urban Perspectives.</hi>
Reviewed by D. D. Kummings, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1985): 1333.</p>
          <p>426. Kauffmann, C. M. <hi rend="i">John Varley 1778-1842.</hi> Reviewed by (1) William Joll, 
<hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 121 (1985): 359; by (2) Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 26
Apr. 1985: 465.</p>
          <p>427. Keynes, Geoffrey. <hi rend="i">The Gates of Memory.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Ralph Colp, Jr.,
<hi rend="i">Biography</hi> 9 (1986): 89-91; by (2) Sonya Rudikoff, <hi rend="i">Hudson Review</hi> 36 (1983):
199-204.</p>
          <p>428. Keynes, Geoffrey, ed. <hi rend="i">The Letters of William Blake.</hi> 3rd, rev. ed. Reviewed
by *Sheila M. Smith, <hi rend="i">British Journal of Aesthetics</hi> 22 (1982): 90-91.</p>
          <p>429. King, James. <hi rend="i">William Cowper: A Biography.</hi> Reviewed by W. B. Carnochan, 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 11 July 1986: 765.</p>
          <p>430. King, James, and Charles Ryskamp, eds. <hi rend="i">The Letters and Prose Writings of
William Cowper.</hi> Vols. 1 and 2 reviewed by (1) Frank Kermode, <hi rend="i">New York Review of Books</hi>
21 Oct. 1982: 39-41. Vol. 2 reviewed by (2) Norma Dalrymple-Champneys, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns
29 (1982): 557-58; by (3) *James Fenton, <hi rend="i">Listener</hi> 106 (1981): 277-78. Vol. 3 reviewed by (4)
Norma Dalrymple-Champneys, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 32 (1985): 134-35; by (5) W. H. [W. Bill
Hutchings?], <hi rend="i">Critical Quarterly</hi> 25.3 (1983): 90; by (6) Donald H. Reiman, <hi rend="i">Blake
/ An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 146-51; by (7) Serge Soupel, <hi rend="i">Etudes
Anglaises</hi> 37 (1984): 332. Vols. 3 and 4 reviewed by (8) Pierre Danchin, <hi rend="i">English Studies</hi>
66 (1985): 561-64; by (9) Peter J. de Voogd, <hi rend="i">Dutch Quarterly Review of Anglo-American
Letters</hi> 14 (1984): 308-19 [see p. 315]. Vol. 4 reviewed by (10) M. Baridon, <hi rend="i">Dixhuitième
Siècle</hi> 17 (1985): 432 [briefly!]; by (11) Norma Dalrymple-Champneys, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi>
ns 32 (1985): 268-69; by (12) Vincent Newey, <hi rend="i">Prose Studies</hi> 8.3 (1985): 95-96; by (13) Pat
Rogers, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 11 May 1984: 519; by (14) C. H. Sisson, 
<hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi> 2 Aug.-5 Sept. 1984: 26-27.</p>
          <p>431. King-Hele, Desmond, ed. <hi rend="i">The Letters of Erasmus Darwin.</hi> Reviewed by (1)
Clive Bush, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi> 15 (1985): 306-07; by (2) Roy Porter, 
<hi rend="i">English Historical Review</hi> 99 (1984): 444-45.</p>
          <p>432. Kroeber, Karl, and William Walling, eds. <hi rend="i">Images of Romanticism: Verbal and
Visual Affinities.</hi> Reviewed by Jeffry B. Spencer, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 6 (1980): 331-33.</p>
          <p>433. Leader, Zachary. <hi rend="i">Reading Blake’s</hi> Songs. Reviewed by (1) Robert F.
Gleckner, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 7 (1981): 397-98; by (2) Thomas A. Vogler, <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 39-47.</p>
          <p>434. LeBris, Michel. <hi rend="i">Die Romantik in Wort und Bild.</hi> Reviewed by Volkmar Stein,
<hi rend="i">Aurora: Jahrbuch der Eichendorff-Gesellschaft</hi> 44 (1984): 252-54.</p>
          <p>435. Lindsay, Jack. <hi rend="i">Life Rarely Tells: Life Rarely Tells, The Roaring Twenties, and
Fanfrolico and After.</hi> Reviewed by Andy Croft, <hi rend="i">London Magazine</hi> 24.11 (1985): 90-93.</p>
          <p>436. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">The Paintings of Samuel Palmer.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Graham
Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 123 (1986): 288; by (2) J. Riely, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 23 (1986):
1203.</p>
          <p>437. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer and ‘The Ancients.’</hi> Reviewed by R. E.
McVaugh, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1985): 1625.</p>
          <p>438. Loder, R[obert] B. <hi rend="i">William Blake to David Hockney: A Private Collection of
British Prints.</hi> Reviewed by Celina Fox, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 26 Feb. 1982:
215.</p>
          <p>439. Marshall, Peter H. <hi rend="i">William Godwin: Philosopher, Novelist, Revolutionary.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) M. B. Friedman, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1984): 558; by (2) D. A. N. Jones, 
<hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi> 6-19 Sept. 1984: 18-19; by (3) Don Locke, <hi rend="i">Times Literary
Supplement</hi> 21 Sept. 1984: 1061; by (4) B. J. Tysdahl, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 19
(1986): 435-37.</p>
          <p>440. McGann, Jerome J. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Ideology: A Critical Investigation.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) Michael Fischer, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 152-55; by
(2) Paul H. Fry, <hi rend="i">Yale Review</hi> ns 73 (1984): 603-16; by (3) William H. Galperin, 
<hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi> 84 (1985): 135-38; by (4) J. H. Haeger, 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and Present</hi> 9.2 (1985): 75-83; by (5) Beatrice Marie, <hi rend="i">Modern
Language Notes</hi> 99 (1984): 1188-92; by (6) Marlon B. Ross, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi> 83 (1985):
204-09; by (7) Frederick W. Shilstone, <hi rend="i">Southern Humanities Review</hi> 19 (1985): 176-78; by (8)
Peter L. Thorslev, Jr., <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 33 (1984): 205-08;
<pb id="p20-98" n="98"/>
see also (9) James M. Kee, “Narrative Time and Participating Consciousness: A Heideggerian Supplement to
McGann’s <hi rend="i">The Romantic Ideology.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and Present</hi> 9.2
(1985): 51-63 (with a reply by McGann on pp. 65-73).</p>
          <p>441. Melot, Michel. <hi rend="i">The Art of Illustration.</hi> Reviewed by S. Skaggs, 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1985): 1151.</p>
          <p>442. Mitchell, W. J. T. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art: A Study of the Illuminated
Poetry.</hi> Reviewed by (1) J. M. Q. Davies, <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi> ns 42 (1980):
116-17; by (2) P. M. S. D. [P. M. S. Dawson], <hi rend="i">Critical Quarterly</hi> 26.4 (1984): 93.</p>
          <p>443. Mitchell, W. J. T., ed. <hi rend="i">The Language of Images.</hi> Reviewed by Stephen Leo
Carr, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 35-38.</p>
          <p>444. Murry, Katherine Middleton. <hi rend="i">Beloved Quixote: The Unknown Life of John Middleton
Murry.</hi> Reviewed by (1) David Sexton, <hi rend="i">London Magazine</hi> 26.1 / 2 (1986): 172-76; by (2)
Hilary Spurling, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 4 Apr. 1986: 352.</p>
          <p>445. Newey, Vincent. <hi rend="i">Cowper’s Poetry: A Critical Study and Reassessment.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) Pierre Danchin, <hi rend="i">English Studies</hi> 66 (1985): 369-72; by (2) Morris Golden, 
<hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 15 (1984): 114-16; by (3) W. [Bill] Hutchings, <hi rend="i">Critical
Quarterly</hi> 25.2 (1983): 84-85; by (4) Verlyn Klinkenborg, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18
(1984): 89-92; by (5) A. J. Sambrook, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi> 16 (1986): 279-80; by (6)
Serge Soupel, <hi rend="i">Etudes Anglaises</hi> 37 (1984): 331; by (7) Peter J. de Voogd, <hi rend="i">Dutch
Quarterly Review of Anglo-American Letters</hi> 14 (1984): 308-19 [see pp. 315-16]; by (8) J. R. Watson, 
<hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 6 (1983): 213-15; by (9) Karina Williamson, 
<hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 35 (1984): 553-54.</p>
          <p>446. Nobs-Greter, Ruth. <hi rend="i">Die Künstlerin und ihr Werk in der deutschsprachigen
Kunstgeschichtsschreibung.</hi> Reviewed by Hanna M. Gagel, <hi rend="i">Kritische Berichte</hi> 13.3 (1985):
81-85.</p>
          <p>447. Palacio, Jean de. <hi rend="i">William Godwin et son monde intérieur.</hi> Reviewed by (1)
M. Baridon, <hi rend="i">Dixhuitième Siècle</hi> 15 (1983): 532 [briefly]; by (2) Alice Green Fredman, 
<hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 33 (1984): 229-31; by (3) Peter [H.] Marshall, <hi rend="i">Ètudes
Anglaises</hi> 35 (1982): 335-36.</p>
          <p>448. Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">The Continuing City: William Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem.
Reviewed by (1) Hazard Adams, <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi> 22.4 (1985): 72-74; by (2) James Bogan,
<hi rend="i">Western Humanities Review</hi> 39 (1985): 90-92; in (3) <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 21 (1984): 1608;
by (4) Stephen D. Cox, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18 (1985): 391-405; by (5) V. A. De Luca,
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 76-79; by (6) David Fuller, <hi rend="i">Review
of English Studies</hi> ns 36 (1985): 577-78; by (7) Paul Hamilton, <hi rend="i">Times Literary
Supplement</hi> 15 June 1984: 674; by (8) François Piquet, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 38 (1985):
236-37; by (9) M. T. S. [Mark T. Smith], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1983</hi>: 85-86; by (10) Frank Stack, 
<hi rend="i">Times Higher Education Supplement</hi> 6 Jan. 1984: 19.</p>
          <p>449. Paulson, Ronald. <hi rend="i">Book and Painting—Shakespeare, Milton, and the Bible:
Literary Texts and the Emergence of English Painting.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Geoffrey Ashton, 
<hi rend="i">Shakespeare Quarterly</hi> 35 (1984): 373-74; by (2) David Bindman, <hi rend="i">Times Literary
Supplement</hi> 6 Jan. 1984: 10; by (3) Roland Mushat Frye, <hi rend="i">Renaissance Quarterly</hi> 37 (1984):
488-90; by (4) Kenneth Garlick, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 36 (1985): 424-26; by (5)
Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 223-26.</p>
          <p>450. Paulson, Ronald. <hi rend="i">Literary Landscape: Turner and Constable.</hi> Reviewed by (1)
Alan Bird, <hi rend="i">Journal of European Studies</hi> 13 (1983): 223-24; by (2) Douglas Brooks-Davies, 
<hi rend="i">Critical Quarterly</hi> 25.4 (1983): 89-91; by (3) Nathan Cervo, <hi rend="i">Journal of
Pre-Raphaelite Studies</hi> 4.2 (1984): 118-23; by (4) Patricia Crown, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory
and Interpretation</hi> 26 (1985): 94-101; by (5) Roland Mushat Frye, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi> 82
(1985): 431-34; by (6) Laurence Lerner, <hi rend="i">Comparative Literature</hi> 37 (1985): 169-73; by (7)
Paul D. McGlynn, <hi rend="i">Southern Humanities Review</hi> 18 (1984): 174-75; by (8) Martin Meisel, 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 24 (1985): 267-71; by (9) Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 223-26; by (10) *Marcia Pointon, <hi rend="i">British Journal of
Aesthetics</hi> 24 (1984): 177-79; by (11) Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 118 (1983): 111-12.</p>
          <p>451. Paulson, Ronald. <hi rend="i">Representations of Revolution (1789-1820).</hi> Reviewed by
(1) Alan Bird, <hi rend="i">Journal of European Studies</hi> 14 (1984): 63; by (2) Norman Bryson, 
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 127 (1985): 102-03; by (3) W. B. Carnochan, <hi rend="i">Modern
Philology</hi> 83 (1985): 80-82; by (4) David Carrier, <hi rend="i">Journal of Aesthetics and Art
Criticism</hi> 42 (1983): 223-25; by (5) Laurence Goldstein, <hi rend="i">Michigan Quarterly Review</hi> 23
(1984): 455-58; by (6) Norman Hampson, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 4 Nov. 1983: 1225; by (7)
A. W. Heffernan, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 15 (1984): 103-05; by (8) Nelson Hilton, 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 221-23; by (9) Michel Jouve, <hi rend="i">Gazette
des Beaux-Arts</hi> 6th ser. 104 (1984): “La Chronique des Arts.” Nov. 1984: 20; by (10) Fred V. Randel,
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 268-71; by (11) William Ruddick, 
<hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi> 11 (1985): 143-44; by (12) William Walling, <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley
Journal</hi> 34 (1985): 201-03; by (13) Hugh Witemeyer, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Quarterly</hi> 45 (1984):
204-07; by (14) Jonathan Wordsworth, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 36 (1985): 581-82; by (15)
Richard Wrigley, <hi rend="i">Art Forum International</hi> Sept.-Nov. 1984: 73-75.</p>
          <p>452. Poovey, Mary. <hi rend="i">The Proper Lady and the Woman Writer: Ideology as Style in the
Works of Mary Wollstonecraft, Mary Shelley, and Jane Austen.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Nancy Armstrong, 
<hi rend="i">Modern Language Notes</hi> 99
<pb id="p20-99" n="99"/>
(1984): 1251-57; by (2) Robert A. Colby, <hi rend="i">Nineteenth-Century Fiction</hi> 39 (1984): 339-44; by
(3) Laurie A. Finke, <hi rend="i">Genre</hi> 17 (1984): 337-40; by (4) Alice Green Fredman, 
<hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 34 (1985): 190-94; by (5) Deborah Kaplan, <hi rend="i">Novel: A Forum on
Fiction</hi> 17 (1983): 81-84; by (6) April London, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 37 (1986):
270-71; by (7) Susan Morgan, <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 27 (1985): 100-03; by (8) M. Rooney, 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1984): 100; by (9) M. E. S., <hi rend="i">Prose Studies</hi> 8.3 (1985): 100-01; by
(10) James Thompson, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 27 (1986): 101-06.</p>
          <p>453. Pressly, Nancy L. <hi rend="i">Revealed Religion: Benjamin West’s Commissions for Windsor
Castle and Fonthill Abbey.</hi> Reviewed by Allen Staley, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
19 (1985-1986): 120-21.</p>
          <p>454. Pressly, William L. <hi rend="i">James Barry: The Artist as Hero.</hi> Reviewed in (1) 
<hi rend="i">Master Drawings</hi> 22 (1984): 220 [briefly!]; by (2) John Spurling, <hi rend="i">New Statesman</hi>
4 Mar. 1983: 30-31. [See also #202, above.]</p>
          <p>455. Pressly, William L. <hi rend="i">The Life and Art of James Barry.</hi> Reviewed by (1) *D.
G. C. Allan, <hi rend="i">Journal of the Royal Society of Arts</hi> 130 (1981): 60-62; in (2) 
<hi rend="i">Master Drawings</hi> 22 (1984): 220 [briefly!]; by (3) Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 7
(1981): 281-82; by (4) *Andrew Wilton, <hi rend="i">Turner Studies</hi> 2 (1982): 49-50. [See also #202,
above.]</p>
          <p>456. Priestman, Martin. <hi rend="i">Cowper’s</hi> Task<hi rend="i">: Structure and
Influence.</hi> Reviewed by (1) P. M. S. Dawson, <hi rend="i">Critical Quarterly</hi> 27.3 (1985): 84-85; by
(2) W. B[ill] Hutchings, <hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 7 (1984): 248-49; by
(3) Vincent Newey, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 36 (1985): 575-76.</p>
          <p>457. Punter, David. <hi rend="i">Blake, Hegel, and Dialectic.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Pierre Dubois,
<hi rend="i">Revue Philosophique de la France et de l’Ètranger</hi> 173 (1983): 139-40; by (2) *Kevin
Lewis, <hi rend="i">Religious Studies Review</hi> 10 (1984): 384; by (3) Stephen Prickett, <hi rend="i">Modern
Language Review</hi> 81 (1986): 159-60; by (4) John Williams, <hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi> 11
(1985): 142-43.</p>
          <p>458. Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">Blake and the New Age.</hi> Reviewed by Nelson Hilton, 
<hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 6 (1980): 401-02.</p>
          <p>459. Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">The Human Face of God: William Blake and The Book of Job.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) Glyn Hughes, <hi rend="i">New Statesman</hi> 2 Apr. 1982: 23; by (2) Bo Ossian Lindberg, 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1986): 151-55.</p>
          <p>460. Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">The Inner Journey of the Poet.</hi> Reviewed by (1) P. M. S.
D. [P. M. S. Dawson], <hi rend="i">Critical Quarterly</hi> 25.1 (1983): 93; by (2) Edna Longley, 
<hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 31 (1984): 562.</p>
          <p>461. Rawson, Claude. <hi rend="i">Order from Confusion Sprung: Studies in Eighteenth-Century
Literature from Swift to Cowper.</hi> Reviewed by David Nokes, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 8
Nov. 1985: 1261.</p>
          <p>462. Rosenblum, Robert, and H. W. Janson. <hi rend="i">Art of the Nineteenth Century: Painting
and Sculpture.</hi> Reviewed in (1) <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 21 (1984): 1457; by (2) Nicholas Penny, 
<hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi> 21 Mar. 1985: 12-14; by (3) Richard Thomson, <hi rend="i">Art
History</hi> 9 (1986): 108-15; by (4) William Vaughan, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 23 Mar.
1984: 316.</p>
          <p>463. Sánchez Pérez, Aquilino. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Graphic Work and the Emblematic
Tradition.</hi> Reviewed by Joseph S. Salemi, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984):
50-52.</p>
          <p>464. Schiff, Gert, and Paola Viotto, <hi rend="i">Tout l’oeuvre peint de Füssli.</hi> Reviewed
in *<hi rend="i">Gazette des Beaux-Arts</hi> 6th ser. 96 (1980): “La Chronique des Arts.” Dec. 1980:
16.</p>
          <p>465. Schwartz, Richard B. <hi rend="i">Daily Life in Johnson’s London.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Max
Byrd, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 110-11; in (2) 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 21 (1984): 1609; by (3) Derek Jarrett, <hi rend="i">British Journal for
Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 8 (1985): 239-40.</p>
          <p>466. Singh, Charu Sheel. <hi rend="i">The Chariot of Fire: A Study of William Blake in the Light
of Hindu Thought.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Pamela Dunbar, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi> 80 (1985): 129;
by (2) Mary V. Jackson, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 121-25.</p>
          <p>467. Stock, R. D. <hi rend="i">The Holy and the Daemonic from Sir Thomas Browne to William
Blake.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Jacques Blondel, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 37 (1984): 327; in (2) 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 24 (1983): 85; by (3) Christopher Fox, 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984-1985): 144-46; by (4) Robin Robbins, 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 24 Sept. 1982: 1046; by (5) Pat Rogers, <hi rend="i">Review of English
Studies</hi> ns 35 (1984): 377-78; by (6) Patricia Meyer Spacks, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi> 82 (1984):
206-09; by (7) L. J. Swingle, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Quarterly</hi> 44 (1983): 80-91; by (8) D. R. M.
Wilkinson, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi> 16 (1986): 286-88.</p>
          <p>468. Tannenbaum, Leslie. <hi rend="i">Biblical Tradition in Blake’s Early Prophecies: The Great
Code of Art.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Stephen C. Behrendt, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 15 (1984): 106-08;
by (2) Jerome J. McGann, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 120-21; by (3) M. T. S.
[Mark T. Smith], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1982</hi>: 90-91; by (4) Michael J. Tolley, <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi> 24 (1985): 300-07; by (5) D. R. M. Wilkinson, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi>
16 (1986): 286-88.</p>
          <p>469. Twitchell, James B. <hi rend="i">Romantic Horizons: Aspects of the Sublime in English Poetry
and Painting, 1770-1850.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Matthew C. Brennan, <hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and
Present</hi> 8.2 (1984): 45-49; by (2) Theresa M. Kelley, <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 34 (1985):
203-05; by (3) William Walling, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 15 (1984): 108-09.</p>
          <p>470. Tysdahl, B.J. <hi rend="i">William Godwin as Novelist.</hi> Reviewed by N. H. Rose, 
<hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 35 (1984): 242-43.</p>
          <pb id="p20-100" n="100"/>
          <p>471. Wark, Robert R., ed. <hi rend="i">Essays on the Blake Followers.</hi> Reviewed by (1) T. L.
A. [Thomas L. Ashton], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1983</hi>: 83-84; by (2) Raymond Lister, <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985): 80-83.</p>
          <p>472. Warner, Janet A. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Language of Art.</hi> Reviewed by (1) John Dixon
Hunt, <hi rend="i">Word and Image</hi> 1 (1985): 409-20; by (2) L[ynn] R. Matteson, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>
22 (1985): 1486; by (3) Peter A. Taylor, <hi rend="i">Queen’s Quarterly</hi> 92 (1985): 859-60.</p>
          <p>473. Webster, Brenda S. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic Psychology.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Stephen
D. Cox, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 18 (1985): 391-405; by (2) Kelvin Everest, 
<hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 8 (1985): 106-07; by (3) Paul Hamilton, 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 15 June 1984: 674; by (4) T[erence Allan] Hoagwood, 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1984): 104; in (5) “Notes on Current Books.” <hi rend="i">Virginia Quarterly
Review</hi> 60.3 (1984): 84-86; by (6) François Piquet, <hi rend="i">Ètudes Anglaises</hi> 38 (1985):
466-67.</p>
          <p>474. Weinglass, David H., ed. <hi rend="i">The Collected English Letters of Henry Fuseli.</hi>
Reviewed by G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1985): 231-34.</p>
          <p>475. Wendorf, Richard, ed. <hi rend="i">Articulate Images: The Sister Arts from Hogarth to
Tennyson.</hi> Reviewed by (1) C. L. Brooks, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 37 (1986): 128-30;
by (2) Stephen Leo Carr, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 26 (1985): 203-08; by
(3) John Dixon Hunt, <hi rend="i">Word and Image</hi> 1 (1985): 409-20; by (4) Anne K. Mellor, 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 19 (1985-1986): 112-13; by (5) Bruce Redford, 
<hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi> 83 (1986): 316-18; by (6) Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Times Literary
Supplement</hi> 25 May 1984: 578.</p>
          <p>476. Wilmerding, John, ed. <hi rend="i">Essays in Honor of Paul Mellon: Collector and
Benefactor.</hi> Reviewed by Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 123 (1986): 438-39.</p>
          <p>477. Wittreich, Joseph A., Jr. <hi rend="i">Visionary Poetics: Milton’s Tradition and His
Legacy.</hi> Reviewed by Walter Weihermann, <hi rend="i">Anglia</hi> 103 (1985): 484-88.</p>
          <p>478. Young, Howard T. <hi rend="i">The Line in the Margin: Juan Ramón Jiménez and His Readings
in Blake, Shelley, and Yeats.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Michael André Bernstein, <hi rend="i">Yeats Annual</hi> 2
(1983): 136-37; by (2) Paul R. Olson, <hi rend="i">Comparative Literature</hi> 37 (1985): 378-79.</p>
          <figure n="bb421.1.22-21.ps.detail" id="bb421.1.spb.22" work-copy="bb421.1" rend="file" width="958" height="333">
          	<figTranscr>There were not found Women fair as the Daughters of Job<lb/>
          	in all the Land &amp; their Father gave them Inheritance<lb/>
          	among their Brethren<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	If I ascend up into Heaven thou art there<lb/>
          	If I make my bed in Hell behold Thou<lb/>
          	art there<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	WBlake invenit &amp; sc</figTranscr>
          </figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
