<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>20.4.tolley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Robert F. Gleckner, Blake’s Prelude: Poetical Sketches</title>
        <author n="Tolley">Michael J. Tolley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1987</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1987</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">20.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>P.M.S. Dawson</name>
              <name>Catherine Haigney</name>
              <name>Nancy M. Ide</name>
              <name>Peter Otto</name>
              <name>Steven Goldsmith</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1987"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_20">
    <body>
	<pb id="p20-146" n="146"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-4-0009">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Robert F. Gleckner. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prelude:</hi> Poetical Sketches.
Baltimore and London: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1982. xii + 202 pp. $15.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Michael J.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Tolley</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Still the wonder grows. What Hewlett in 1876 condemned as the plagiarism of an “Imperfect
Genius,” has become, with successive refinements and extensions of the pioneering work in 1940 of Margaret
Lowery, a swelling tribute of praise to an original (not merely “untutored”) genius. Gleckner’s
researches, the most
<pb id="p20-147" n="147"/>
extensive ever undertaken into the sources of the <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>, and his critical
examination, the most thorough ever given to the book as a whole, must increase our astonishment, not only
that one young head could carry all Blake knew, but that he could have worked at such a sophisticated level,
even in the examples Gleckner finds least successful, as rightful heir to the Bible, Milton and Spenser. Could
the youthful Blake have known that he was already producing a book that is an antibook, of sketches that are
not sketchy, but “finished sketches” in the manner of Michelangelo, who “did never sketch,” according
to Blake, for “Every line of his has Meaning” (“Florentine Ingratitude”)? So, with due allowance,
Gleckner concludes (p. 152): Blake in 1783 set out to emulate the masters, even if it is doubtless “too much
to credit” him “with then regarding every line of his own poetical ‘sketches’ as imbued with
meaning.” Gleckner, thus, agrees with John Ehrstine against T.S. Eliot, that these poems are not “quite
mature and successful attempts to do something small” but are rather the sketching out of “something very
large.” We may infer that critical attention has shifted from the superficial form to the grand inferred
program: this penciled figure will be used in <hi rend="i">The School of Athens</hi>, that brief lyric in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></p>
          <p>At this point I should make two things clear. Firstly, I am aware, Gleckner perhaps
insufficiently so here, that it is dangerous to make analogies between Blake’s practice as a poet and his
work as a graphic artist. Gleckner loves striking phrases but he is sometimes seduced by them (and accordingly
we still have to try to resist his “Higher Innocence”). The idea of the “finished sketch” is
Gleckner’s, not Blake’s, because the idea of finishing was to Blake relative not absolute. Secondly,
Gleckner is very careful not to fall into the trap of supposing that Blake’s early poems should be read in
the light of his later ones; the problem he raises rather is whether we should read the early poems with the
same degree of attention as we do the later ones and with similar expectations regarding their functions or
strategies.</p>
          <p>I have great sympathy for Gleckner’s style of scholarship and for his critical approach in this
instructive book, which is far better than those of several critics to whom inexplicably he defers. That the
book is not magisterial but still exploratory in tone as in effect may be related to the more widespread
critical uncertainties of our times; it is hard to imagine that any one will soon write a better book on 
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>, and yet such a study is at once rendered obligatory by the critical problems
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Prelude</hi> engenders.</p>
          <p>The problem that looms largest to me is one of overreading. Blake is, as we all know, a highly
allusive poet, but was he always so allusive, everywhere in his work? Gleckner distinguishes persuasively
between poems (he thinks they are to be dated earlier) in which words and phrases are snatched out of context
like gems prized from a brooch and those in which there is a kind of resonant dialogue with the sources (these
are perhaps the later and better poems). Gleckner writes with authority on these matters, having conducted the
kind of thorough search we associate with Roger Lonsdale; he is also genuinely interested to discover the
truth about Blake’s relationship with his sources. Sometimes, inevitably, he has found too much;
occasionally he makes mistakes or finds too little; but he always tries to present the evidence fairly and
scrupulously and he has the great virtue of being willing to trust what at first sight may seem an unlikely
association sufficiently to press further for supporting evidence which may force a skeptical reader to
consider it equally closely. It is also good that Gleckner usually, though not everywhere, seeks to enhance
rather than diminish the reputation of particular poems. The effects vary: Gleckner is in my view wrong so to
undervalue “Fair Elenor” as to miss some of its allusions and be blind to its few virtues; he amply
confirms the satirical qualities attributed to “King Edward the Third” by Erdman and others through
finding in it ironical references to Milton; he deepens our appreciation of the celebrated seasons poems
(though not of each equally); he fails to convince me that “Samson” is such “an extraordinary
achievement” as his reading of the sources suggests because too many details in the reading are
unpersuasive.</p>
          <p>Perhaps the most instructive of such discussions is that of “To Morning,” where he brings
massive scholarship to the close analysis of a poem which, I suppose, most of us like but none of us finds
quite satisfying, the cumulative efect of which is to demonstrate just why we are unsatisfied, even if we may
not, as I do not, agree with every step in the analysis. I like the reluctance with which Gleckner concedes
that this relatively weak lyric does not work: “The final success of the resultant melange, it seems to me,
however delicately lovely the poem as a whole, must be called into question.” Gleckner’s critical
procedure here is to assume that every word, phrase or image employed by Blake in “To Morning” must be
redolent of its source, whether Spenserian epithalamic (but curiously reversed) at the opening, or ominously
Miltonic as it proceeds, or inexplicably venerian (celebratory of hunting, in the classical manner) at the
close. The effect, though impressive, makes one wonder whether one should not rather assume, in order to
rescue the poem, that Blake did not mean us to associate his lovely phrases with their highly significant
origins at all, so that it is well to remind ourselves that Blake’s “Evening Star” and “Morning”
companions have 
<pb id="p20-148" n="148"/>
a place in a homelier tradition, that of the children’s songs or hymns by such writers as Smart, Wesley and
Watts—as John Holloway points out in <hi rend="i">Blake: The Lyric Poetry</hi>, pp. 38f. (a book which
Gleckner seems, unfortunately, to have missed).</p>
          <p>Gleckner affirms that his book “is dedicated to proving” that Blake’s labors at 
<hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> were not merely an escape from the laborious tasks of an apprentice engraver
but “constituted a serious enterprise in its own right” (p. 151). I agree with him, but submit that
“serious” does not always have to mean “solemn”; it is surprising to read this ponderous judgment on
“Blind-Man’s Buff” (p. 25):
<q>
if it confutes the idyllicism of Thomson’s snug cottages, it advances an equally specious history of mankind
and “sweet society.” The ethic espoused is one of self-restraint, playing one’s part, regimentation, and
eye-for-eye justice so totally foreign to Blake even in <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> that one may be
justifiably puzzled why he saved this piece from the “hearth so red” with which it begins.
</q>
Rather than making overmuch of Thomson as a source (Holloway refers rather to <hi rend="i">A Midsummer
Night’s Dream</hi> II.i.42-57) and berating Blake for his severe ethics and false history, Gleckner might
have wondered how it was that Blake, who I am sure hated horseplay, cheating and injustice from his youth up,
could write such genial humor about them “even in <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches.</hi>” The morality of
the piece seems to me to hit off the thoughts of children on these serious issues admirably, just as Blake
enters so well into the comedy (to an outsider) of a child’s partial sense of fair play in Tilly Lally’s
song, “I say, you Joe.” No, I like “Blind-Man’s Buff” and I don’t think one should have to feel
apologetic about it.</p>
          <p>“Blind-Man’s Buff” is one of three “variously inept” poems, characterized by Gleckner
as “early” and dealt with in a chapter called “The Muses of Memory,” all lamely imitative rather than
imaginatively engaged with their sources in the true Blakean style. The other two are “An Imitation of
Spencer” and “Fair Elenor.” The Spenserian stanzas, “all different and all wrong,” need not detain
us here, but “Fair Elenor,” weak as it is, trips up its critic. Gleckner finds it comic that Elenor,
despite Spenser’s example in <hi rend="i">The Faerie Queene</hi> IV. viii. 62, shrieks “aloud”; “how
else?” he asks. Spenser and Blake meant that the shriek was loud; I understand that it is possible to shriek
faintly, too. Gleckner is so busy laughing at Blake’s silly Gothic ballad that he misses his real
achievement in the form (which is the reason why, I suppose, some people admire the Gothic mode), which is to
evoke rather skillfully the sensation of being trapped in a nightmare. Some of Blake’s startling rhythmic
effects, the staccato phrasing and dislocations of syntax, can work on us a little if we can suspend our
scornful spirit of disbelief for a moment; line 16, especially, seems magical to me. Gleckner misses the
“sublime” biblical rhythms in lines 49-51, although he castigates Blake for the inertness of his allusion
to Psalm 91.5-6 in lines 33-36 and, more interestingly, proposes a not very apt allusion to Song of Solomon 5
for lines 41-48 on the grounds, it seems, of a supposed similarity between this chapter and the plot of the
poem (pp. 18f.). He goes on to assert that “The inappropriateness of the allusion is, curiously,
instructive, for it is perhaps Blake’s first effort to make ‘use’ of a source, to bend the allusion to
his own context or to qualify his context through allusionary ‘punctuation.’ ” Although I think that the
ineptness attributed to the allusion by Gleckner is a consequence of his having picked the wrong biblical
text, passages closer to the rhetoric of Elenor’s lament for her dead lord tend to support his case that
some arbitrary “bending” of an allusion to an inappropriate context has been attempted by the poet (I
refuse to comment on the question of chronological priority). I think of such admired passages as Judges 5.27,
for the staccato incremental repetition, and of the lament for fallen Lucifer in Isaiah 14. 12: “How art
thou fallen from heaven, O Lucifer, son of the morning! how art thou cut down . . .” (compare Blake’s
“But he is darken’d; like the summer’s noon, / Clouded; fall’n like the stately tree, cut down” and
recall the account of the death of Fuzon in <hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi> 3:41-44). However, the
allusion’s failure to work here is not owing to “the excessiveness of the Gothic-balladic frame and
language,” as Gleckner would have it, because borrowing from biblical rhetoric in order to achieve a sublime
excess goes with the genre, but simply because Elenor’s lord is not related to Elenor as Lucifer is to
Isaiah or as Sisera is to Jael.</p>
          <p>I don’t think I’m ever going to be much interested in the critical problem of dating the
poems in <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>; Gleckner’s speculations on the issue are sensibly based but
cannot in the nature of things be wholly convincing. A more interesting issue is that of how and whether the
poems should be grouped; some groupings are clear, such as the seasonal and diurnal poems and the pair of
songs beginning “When early morn” and “Fresh from the dewy hill,” but the interrelationships of the
poems within these groups may be problematical. In a chapter labeled “Antithetical Structure,” Gleckner
discusses mainly the seven lyrics titled “Song” along with the “Mad Song.” He does not have
interesting things to say about all of these lyrics and sometimes he is hampered by his program. For instance,
I think it is a mistake to find an “antithetical perspective” in the fifth stanza of “Fresh from the
Dewy Hill,” signaled “by its initial ‘But’ ”: as I read the poem the “But” is intensive not
antithetical. I also think it is reaching too far to find a “marvelously apt” allusion to Spenser’s
story of Malbecco and Hellenore and then to lament that it is too weakly triggered in the third line of this
“Song.” As Gleckner more safely proposes, “it is certainly possible that Blake simply drew the
laurel-shade locution from his ample store of other stock phrases” (pp. 46f.).
<pb id="p20-149" n="149"/>
Similarly, in “Mad Song” Gleckner (p. 49) finds “a marvelous allusion if indeed it is creditable” to
the Amavia episode in <hi rend="i">The Faerie Queene</hi> II.i.46. Unfortunately, the phrase concerned in
“Mad Song,” “And my griefs unfold,” was most likely a misprint for the quite different idea of “my
griefs infold.” I suspect that Gleckner is attracted to the remote Spenserian echo partly because he
doesn’t quite understand the metaphorical force of “infold”: as I read the text, the speaker of “Mad
Song” desires Sleep to gather his griefs into a fold as the shepherd does his flock on a stormy night. This
is so much stronger a reading than the printed (but not always uncorrected) text, “unfold,” that it is
hard to believe it was not Blake’s first thought. A simpler error, the supposition that Adam and Eve turned
their backs to the East when they departed from Eden, somewhat mars Gleckner’s reading (p. 51) of the
closing lines of the poem, where also a consideration of Hewlett’s reference to <hi rend="i">2 Henry IV</hi>
II.iii.19 for Blake’s “vault / Of paved heaven” might have distracted him from depending overmuch on
Milton; the phrase was of course simply a cliché by Blake’s time (cf. also Gleckner’s note on “King
Edward the Third” 5. 19-20 on p. 182). Perhaps I should repeat here that I am not sorry that Gleckner tries
on such tentative allusions for size; he is quite right to present the case for them as fully and fairly as he
perceives it. If my final impression is that Gleckner relies too much on a search for allusions in his
readings, and particularly for allusions to Spenser and Milton, this should not weaken my awareness that we do
wrong to neglect them.</p>
          <p>Sometimes, nevertheless, it might appear that if Gleckner could not find a way to read a poem
through various perceived allusions, he would be left somewhat at a loss. Such a criticism would be unjust;
with “When Early Morn,” for instance, “one of the least allusive poems in all of the 
<hi rend="i">Sketches</hi>,” Gleckner is able to show that Blake’s establishment of “the experiential
violence of real jealousy” is achieved without “significant allusion” (p. 45). On the other hand, it is
hard not to feel that his tepid response to one of the best pieces, “How Sweet I Roam’d” (of which
nonetheless he gives largely a just account) is an effect both of his inability to find an interesting source
for it and of his failure to fit it within a larger group: he remarks indeed that “its demonstrably simple
derivativeness [from Spenserian Petrarchan love poetry] and passive relationship to other songs serve . . . to
validate Malkin’s statement about its adolescent inception” (pp. 55f.). Is this the same poem as the one I
find almost as chilling as “The Erl King”? (Teaching it as a song, I suggest to students that they try
going back to the first stanza after the final one to appreciate its formal mimicry of entrapment.) To me it
serves as a splendid introduction to the other love songs in <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>, as well as a
useful corrective to uninformed statements about the chronology of Blake’s understanding of Innocence and
Experience as contrary states; it casts a long shadow through, say, “The Chimney Sweeper” of 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi> to “The Golden Net” and “The Crystal Cabinet” and the desperate lovers in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></p>
          <p>For his chapter on the poems addressed to each of the four seasons, Gleckner seems somewhat
cramped for space in building on his valuable 1965 article. Some of the more interesting source material is
packed into a few footnotes and his presentation is blurry in places. This must be partly an effect of the
variety and quantity of possible sources that are here to be sorted; it is hard to distinguish trees from
woods. To deal adequately with these matters would require me to write a long study of Blake’s Seasons
complementary to my essay on “Blake’s Songs of Spring,” so I will content myself here with only a few
observations. The thrust of Gleckner’s chapter title, “Cycle and Anticycle,” is to propose that “To
Winter” offers a kind of “anti-myth” (Adams’s term) or “spectrous parody” of the
Spring-Summer-Autumn progression. This is a sound reading of a sequence in which the welcome seasons are
invited to “come in, sit down, put your feet up and we’ll have a song; please stay awhile,” and the bad
one to “keep out!” In “To Winter,” the iceman cometh perforce, disdaining communication with his human
victims, until heaven intercedes and drives him back to Iceland. More seriously, Gleckner shows (perhaps not
as forcefully as he might have done) that all the good seasons are associated with Christ, but Winter with
Antichrist Satan. The outline is blurred somewhat by a need to discuss the place these lyrics have in the
classical tradition initiated by Virgil, Ovid and others and regenerated by Spenser as an English topos, to
descend to Blake through Milton, Thomson, Pope, Collins and others; somewhat more by occasionally careless
handling and less than optimal integration of these sources both with each other and with the (oriental)
Christian scheme which subsumes them. Gleckner has advanced our knowledge so far in these matters that it must
seem churlish to say that we can proceed yet further and more securely at every stage, with Virgil, Spenser,
Milton, Pope, Collins, Scripture, yet it must be said nevertheless and I doubt whether Gleckner will be
surprised by it. (I have, too, to say that Gleckner has generously acknowledged in his book my own work as a
fellow toiler in this particular vineyard; all I can do in return is a little pruning and tendril-guiding.)
I’ll try to be brief here.</p>
          <p>In Virgil’s <hi rend="i">Georgics</hi> IV.62-63, Winter is put to rout by the golden sun and
chased beneath the earth. Gleckner’s association of Winter with Spenser’s wild boar will not pass; he
proposes it first on p. 63 (cf. 73f.) in connection with the vision of stasis at the end of the Mutability
Cantos, one with which I think Blake would be less comfortable than Gleckner supposes; unfortunately, he
completely mangles his quotation from Spenser’s Nature. Gleckner has demonstrated Blake’s debt 
<pb id="p20-150" n="150"/>
to the stanzas on Summer and Autumn in <hi rend="i">The Faerie Queene</hi> VII.vii.29, 30, although he makes
nothing of Blake’s pointed departure from stanza 28 in “To Spring” and does not notice that Spenser’s
Spring is recollected in the “lusty song of fruits and flowers” in “To Autumn.” (Gleckner’s
suggestion on p. 62 that Spenser’s Spring, “all dight in leaues of flowres” parallels Blake’s
“perfumed garments” is unconvincing in the light of the preferable reference to Song of Solomon 4. 11,
first noted by Miner.) Gleckner is, I think, the first to propose biblical references for “To Summer,” but
he makes an awful mess of his quotation from Psalm 84.5-6 as background for the first lines (p. 66). This is a
difficult text for translators and commentators, but one would expect that, if he had meant us to recollect
it, Blake would have brought the idea of wells or of rain in close context with it. The idea that the
Summer’s “ruddy limbs and flourishing hair” are also those of the beloved in the Song of Solomon 5.
10-11 is attractive but tenuous; if it were meant, how did Blake miss the “gold head” image?</p>
          <p>Gleckner is on stronger ground when he claims (pp. 66f.) that Blake “thoroughly Miltonizes his
[Summer] into Christ and Creation by equipping him with a ‘fervid car’ and having him ride ‘o’er the
deep of heaven,’ ” quoting <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> VII.214-25 and V.300-01 (mis-cited as to Book
X); both should be taken together, but he misses two clinching ideas, one that the voice of the car rider was
heard in both poems, the other that the noonday sun in Milton is described as, like Blake’s Summer,
“mounted.” We may notice here that when in “To Autumn” “clust’ring Summer breaks forth into
singing” it is making a classic biblical response to the redemptive initiative of God, as in Isaiah 14.7;
44.23; 49.13; 54.1 and 55.12. It is a pity that Gleckner hides in a footnote (p. 174) his proposal that the
language and details of Milton’s whole passage on the third day of Creation in <hi rend="i">Paradise
Lost</hi> “are at the center” of “To Autumn,” because the idea is clearly of some importance. Only one
word-borrowing, “clust’ring,” is adduced from the Miltonic passage, and this could have come from
elsewhere, for instance from Pope’s Autumn Pastoral, where there are several images and phrases suggestive
of “To Autumn” besides that, noted by Gleckner, which might lie behind Blake’s “golden load.”
(Gleckner has not in the past been very receptive to my suggestions that Blake was indebted to Pope; another
one is that the phrase “and rush into the stream” in “To Summer” echoes “and rush into the sea” in
Pope’s <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> IV.786.)</p>
          <p>For some reason obscure to me, Gleckner finds that what he calls the “clichéd salvation” at
the end of “To Winter” has been sabotaged, because, earlier in the last stanza, the mariner cries “in
vain.” On the contrary, I take it that the salvation is real, that the wretched mariner only cries
“till” rescue comes; Winter won’t listen to him but, in due time, heaven will. Blake’s realistic
assessment of life in a wintry world here is of a piece with that in “The Chimney Sweeper” of 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, which instructs us, not that harm will not be experienced by those doing
their duty, but that they need not fear it. You’d have to be mad, as in “Mad Song,” to turn your back on
hope and Blake nowhere allows despair to overwhelm him. In noting that Blake is portraying Winter as Satan,
Gleckner doesn’t go on to see how much he is caricaturing him as the Gothic monster Satan is (though I do
not think that he meant us to recall either Satan’s metamorphosis into a monstrous serpent or Sin’s
yelling hounds, <hi rend="i">pace</hi> Gleckner, pp. 69, 73: the “yelling” surely comes from Collins, 
<hi rend="i">Ode to Evening</hi> 46, as Hewlett proposed; Chatterton also followed Collins, <hi rend="i">pace</hi>
note 56, p. 174). I find very intriguing Gleckner’s suggestion that Winter’s pillars refer to those of
Satan’s gun-carriage in <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> VI.572-73; the suggestion is helped by the wording
in one of the sources for Winter’s “iron car,” Collins’s <corr type="emend">“Ode to Peace” 5</corr>: “To Britain bent his
iron car” (Blake has “Nor bend thy pillars with thine iron car”). Against this idea is the “more
natural” one of a demon bursting from the adamantine doors of hell across such a pillared way as that
constructed by Sin and Death in <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> X: Winter “rides heavy.”</p>
          <p>I have already encouraged the reader to profit from Gleckner’s discussion of “To Morning”
in his chapter “Mornings and Evenings.” My own reading of “To the Evening Star” would not be quite so
somber as that with which Gleckner disturbs himself (p.93) but the force one concedes to the supposed
“influence” of the star and its “sacred dew” may well vary from reader to reader. Gleckner is
over-suspicious of Blakean stars, but there is no reason to supply a negative reading here (and he should know
that Blake is not against stars as such, only against misreadings and systematic orderings of them). A
relevant text in Milton, <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> IX.106-07, missed by him here, might help Gleckner
towards a more positive response than that in note 33, pp. 177f. Also regarding this note, I should point out
that a reference to <hi rend="i">Lycidas</hi> 26-31 for “flocks covered with the dew of heaven” is
irrelevant, since Milton refers there to the sheep’s eating of dew-covered grass. This is an interesting
chapter and I’ll spare the author from more of my nitpicking.</p>
          <p>In “Worldly Wars and Mental Fight,” Gleckner focuses on “King Edward the Third” and the
three short “political” poems in a valuable discussion. His search in the play for sources from 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> is too thorough to be always convincing, but this should not mean that his general
thesis that Milton’s poem provides several ironic counterparts to Edward’s militaristic ideals may
therefore be impugned.</p>
          <p>“Prophetic Forms,” Gleckner’s last chapter before broad conclusions are drawn in the
“Epilogue,” gives the critic space to discuss in some detail the prose poems. “The Couch of Death” and
“Contemplation” are read 
<pb id="p20-151" n="151"/>
against <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> XI and “Il Penseroso” according to a program partly derived,
regrettably, from Wagenknecht. Gleckner complains of “an Ossianic flaccidness,” especially in the most
allusive passages in the poems, but they are less Ossianic in effect than one would expect and the allusions
are directly imitative of biblical rhetoric (Gleckner correctly recalls Ecclesiastes for “Contemplation”).
His reference to Milton’s Nativity Ode for the radiance and angelic visitation of the dying youth in “The
Couch of Death” seems unjustified, and his comparison of the pair’s Calvinistical self-condemnation to the
monsters of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> is unwarranted, but his account of Blake’s movement towards a definition
of sin is noteworthy. His description of the unclosed structure of “Contemplation” is yet more valuable,
suggesting a model for the confrontations of Innocence and Experience and particularly for “Introduction”
to <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> and “Earth’s Answer.” The poem-by-poem discussion is concluded
by a serious engagement with “Samson” and particularly the problems of how far the poet is critical of the
hero’s character and how the fragment is to be set within or against the narratives in Judges 13-16 and 
<hi rend="i">Samson Agonistes.</hi> As with “King Edward the Third,” “Samson” seems to me more like a
sample of what the young poet could do, given the right encouragement, than the sketch of a work that might
easily be finished; it certainly does not fulfill the promise of its beginning, even (I would submit)
ironically. Blake had a curious liking for the foiled deliverer, whose warfare, insofar as it is mental, he
rightly locates in the dialogues with Dalila. In his attempt to grapple with the puzzle of his annunciation,
Samson seems to be measuring the “truth” of the angel’s promise against his own knowledge that, in spite
of “matchless might,” wisdom and talent, he is merely human. Gleckner is a bit hard on Samson in relating
(p. 146) this “matchless might” to that of Sin and Death in <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> X. 404, but
whether the hint is to be taken or not this does not mean that the angel’s prophecy is necessarily false,
only that it remains oracular (and, perhaps, too difficult for the young Blake). Gleckner might be encouraged
to take a more positive view of the angel if, in noting that the name “wonderful” derives from Isaiah 9.6,
he were to go on to find a reference to angelic mental warfare (which he will not allow Wittreich to claim) in
Isaiah 9.5.</p>
          <p>There are errors in this book, there are misprints (not all noted here), there are stylistic
infelicities; nevertheless this is an invaluable study, containing many fine perceptions and discoveries,
which I recommend highly to all scholars and teachers of Blake.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
