<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>20.4.dawson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake and Providence: The Theodicy of The Four Zoas</title>
        <author n="Dawson">P. M. S. Dawson</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1987</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1987</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">20.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>P.M.S. Dawson</name>
              <name>Catherine Haigney</name>
              <name>Nancy M. Ide</name>
              <name>Peter Otto</name>
              <name>Steven Goldsmith</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1987"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_20">
    <body>
      <pb id="p20-134" n="134"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-20-4-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">Blake and Providence: The Theodicy of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi></hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">P.M.S.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">DAWSON</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>On the face of it, no poet could have been more hostile than was Blake to the accepted theodicies
of his age, with their facile justifications of human suffering in terms of the will of God or the greater
good. He had no belief in “the benevolent avuncular God who explains away all suffering and injustice at the
Last Judgment and proves himself to have had the best intentions all along.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">1</ref> When in annotating Bishop Watson’s <hi rend="i">Apology for
the Bible</hi> he came across the title of another of the Bishop’s works, <hi rend="i">The Wisdom and
Goodness of God, in Having Made Both Rich and Poor</hi>, he reacted vigorously and trenchantly to what he saw
could only be an attempt to justify inequitable property relations under the pretence of religion: “God made
Man happy &amp; Rich but the Subtil made the innocent Poor This must be a most wicked &amp; blasphemous
book.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">2</ref> The lament of Enion at the
end of Night the Second of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> satirizes such appeals to “The Wisdom and
Goodness of God” as the complacent response of the prosperous to the misery of others:
<q>
It is an easy thing to talk of patience to the afflicted . . .<lb/>
To see a god on every wind &amp; a blessing on every blast<lb/>
To hear sounds of love in the thunder storm that destroys our enemies house<lb/>
To rejoice in the blight that covers his field, &amp; the sickness that cuts off his children<lb/>
While our olive &amp; vine sing &amp; laugh round our door &amp; our children bring fruits &amp; flowers<lb/>
(35:18, 36:5-8, E 325)
</q>
In such hypocritical celebrations of divine providence Blake can always hear the smug accents of Job’s
comforters, or the self-satisfied moralism of the ant lecturing the grasshopper on “the laws of prudence.”
Such are the “soft mild arts” for keeping the poor in their place that Urizen recommends from his book of
brass (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 80:1-21, E 355). These arts depend on the belief in a God whose providential
decrees are both ineluctable and inscrutable. In <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> this God is Satan, the “Miller of
Eternity,” who wields “the Harrow of Shaddai / A scheme of Human conduct invisible &amp;
incomprehensible” (4:12-13, E 98). Some of Blake’s most poignant utterances are directed against the
belief in this remote and inscrutable deity:
<q>
Seek not thy heavenly father then beyond the skies:<lb/>
There Chaos dwells &amp; ancient Night &amp; Og &amp; Anak old . . .<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 20:32-33, E 114)
</q>
At the beginning of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> the Saviour calls to Albion,
<q>
I am not a God afar off, I am a brother and friend;<lb/>
Within your bosoms I reside, and you reside in me:<lb/>
Lo! we are One; forgiving all Evil; Not seeking recompense!<lb/>
Ye are my members O ye sleepers of Beulah, land of shades!<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 4:18-21, E 146)
</q>
“Is the body diseas’d when the members are healthful?” Orleans had demanded of the assembly of nobles in
<hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi> (line 182, E 294), and the converse equally applies. If all men are
“members” of the Divine Humanity (and hence, as St. Paul says, “members one of another,” Ephesians
4.25) then it is inconceivable that the good of the whole can be served by the suffering of any part. 
<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Northrop Frye, <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry: A Study of William Blake</hi>
(1947; Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1969), pp. 34-35.</note>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">2</hi><hi rend="i"> The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed.
David V. Erdman, newly revised edition (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1982), p. 612. References to
this edition will be identified by E plus page number(s); references to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> by
page and line number(s).</note></p>
        <p>Nevertheless Blake’s rejection of the concepts of theodicy and providence was not and could not
be final. For a theodicy serves not only to legitimize injustice (as Blake saw very clearly), but also to
provide a necessary explanation for the existence of evil, which continues to exist whether explained or not.
Blake was at vigorous issue with the established Christianity of his day over its definition of sin, and he
correctly identified the repressive nature of most of its ethical doctrines; but he never doubted that man as
he existed in the world was fallen, and that any attempt to reverse that fall depended on understanding
it—which implied, on justifying it. The trajectory from paradise lost to paradise regained passes through
some notion of the fall as <hi rend="i">felix culpa.</hi> As a corollary, the whole process is seen as under
the control of a superintending providence, conceived as extrahuman. Both fall and redemption are stages in a
divine plan,
<pb id="p20-135" n="135"/>
which is carried out by human agents of course, but agents who are in necessary ignorance of the nature of
what they are doing. Despite Blake’s insistent attempts to identify God with humanity, one always arrives
back at a sense that human redemption depends on the action of a saviour outside man. I wish in the present
paper to explore Blake’s treatment of the theme of providence in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, which
Kenneth Johnston has aptly called “the great battleground of Blake’s imaginative development.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">3</hi> “Blake’s Cities: Romantic Forms of Urban Renewal,” in 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman and John T. Grant (Princeton: Princeton
University Press, 1970), p. 415.</note></p>
        <p>This issue has been somewhat evaded in the central tradition of modern Blake criticism. S. Foster
Damon expresses the consensus view in describing what he terms Blake’s “heresy,” the claim that “God
is Man’s highest powers.” At the same time he hedges his bets by claiming that Blake “practically
says” this, and by noting that for Blake “Even Deity himself is only of parallel importance” to man,
which concedes that they are not simply to be identified.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48"
type="note">4</ref> As J. G. Davies has shown, Blake is often more orthodox than we are willing to allow, so
that “while emphasizing the immanence of God, he did not lose the transcendence.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">5</ref> According to Davies, Blake’s God “By His Providence . . .
directs mankind” (p. 85). In his commentary on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> Damon refers frequently to
the agency of “the Good Shepherd,” “the Council of God,” “the Lamb,” “the gods,” “the
Saviour,” “Jesus,” “the Divine Mercy,” without elucidating the question of their immanent or
transcendent status (<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, pp. 156, 157, 162, 366, 368, 375). The strong humanist
reading of Northrop Frye is more successful in eliminating awkward elements from consideration, so that even
an important concept like the Council of God does not warrant an index entry in <hi rend="i">Fearful
Symmetry.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">6</ref> David Erdman is more
willing to recognize providential elements in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, but he insists that “in a
consistently Blakean view the appearance of an external or intervening providence is really a projection or an
illusion,” and when it appears in Blake’s text he is quick to find “strong indications that this meek
resignation to God as fate goes against the grain and is not likely to endure.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">7</ref> But it is difficult to find a “consistently Blakean view”
outside the systematizations provided by his commentators. Wilkie and Johnson, in their useful commentary on
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, cannot argue away the providential elements, but they speak rather evasively
of “an elusive-to-define providence, an economy of preservation for man, that operates almost independent of
his will.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">4</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake: His Philosophy and Symbols</hi> (London:
Constable, 1924), p. 146.</note>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">5</hi><hi rend="i"> The Theology of William Blake</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press,
1948), p. 87.</note>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Frye seems to be attempting to accommodate the concept in his argument to
the effect that a “prehuman God” is meaningless, that “if always human, God must have been plural,” so
that “Our present human society . . . has evolved out of a seed of life dropped in a dead world from a
preceding eternal human society . . .” concerning whose origins we are not to enquire (<hi rend="i">Fearful
Symmetry</hi>, p. 256). Frye’s intention is to establish man firmly at the origin, and to make the Council
of God nothing but a human community (which in one sense it is, as we shall see). He says and wishes to say
nothing concerning divine providence except that “we find ourselves unable to conceive of anything
superhuman in the direction of either design or power” (p. 36).</note>
	<note id="n51"><hi rend="s">7</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake: Prophet against Empire</hi> (1954; rev. ed., New York:
Doubleday, 1969), pp. 377, 379.</note>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Brian Wilkie and Mary Lynn Johnson, <hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi> Four Zoas:
<hi rend="i">The Design of a Dream</hi> (Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1970), p. 29.</note></p>
        <p>Blake criticism does not really know what to make of these providential references, since they
suggest a transcendent conception of God which Blake is not supposed to have any truck with. The accepted
consensus has been challenged by Leopold Damrosch, in a tenaciously critical account of Blake’s myth and of
modern critical interpretations of it. Damrosch argues that
<figure n="BB209.1.72.MS" rend="file" width="780" height="1000"/>
“Blake’s system, for all its humanism, cannot get along without the divine.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53" type="note">9</ref> He points to “the increasingly soteriological nature of
Blake’s myth: through Los, and ultimately through Jesus who works in Los, we are not so much regenerated as
rescued from ourselves” (p. 155). In terms of the orthodoxy of Blake studies (a most unblakean thing, be it
said) Damrosch is advocating heresy when he claims that “everywhere in Blake’s myth the divine is invoked
because it is the only agent that can reverse the Fall” (p. 248). In this paper I shall adopt a similarly
heretical view, with particular reference to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> In the course of this work’s
composition I believe that we can see Blake being forced to shift his ground, and to invoke an extrahuman
agency of salvation to do what he no longer believes can be done by human agency in history. In particular I
shall examine the significance of Blake’s introduction of the concept of the “Council of God” in his
revisions of the poem, the providential framework within which certain actions of Urizen and later of Los and
Enitharmon are described, and finally the way in which their actions are seen as contributing to the
resolution of the poem. In the course of this examination we shall see that such things as man’s willful
self-alienation from the human community, the creation of the fallen universe, sin (and the sense of sin), and
error are not unequivocally negative; they are also essential moments in a providential scheme. 
<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">9</hi><hi rend="i"> Symbol and Truth in Blake’s Myth</hi> (Princeton: Princeton
University Press, 1980), p. 19.</note></p>
        <p>The concept of the Council of God is not to be found in the earliest surviving portion of Blake’s
manuscript, the fair copy in his copperplate and modified-copperplate hands of pp. 1-18 and 23-42, which he
probably transcribed in 1797, the date on the title-page.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54"
type="note">10</ref> Morton Paley includes it in his list of names and concepts which only appear in the last
two Nights or in additions to earlier Nights.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55"
type="note">11</ref> The most substantial of these additions is a long passage on separate leaves (pp. 21-22,
19) whose place in the text was not clearly indicated or perhaps even decided on by Blake, though his editors
have agreed in making it the Conclusion to Night the First. In doing so they greatly assist Blake in the
revision of his myth, since by allowing what may have been “the last complete pages added to the poem”
(<hi rend="i">William</hi>
	<pb id="p20-136" n="136"/>
	<hi rend="i">Blake’s Writings</hi>, 2: 1724-25) to stand so early in the text they give them considerable
authority. What then is the effect (and presumably the purpose) of the major conceptual change implied in the
introduction of the Council of God? <note id="n54"><hi rend="s">10</hi> See <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Writings</hi>, ed. G. E. Bentley, Jr. (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1978), 2: 1722-23.</note>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">11</hi><hi rend="i"> Energy and the Imagination: A Study of the Development of
Blake’s Thought</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1970), p. 143.</note></p>
        <p>At issue is a radical revisioning of the nature and status of the fallen Man. Originally he is
“Universal,” with the implication that there is nothing outside or beyond him; all the other
“characters” of the poem are produced by a continuing process of fission occurring within him. The way to
redemption lies through his reintegration, but he cannot look to any outside help in achieving this, because
outside himself there is nothing (his perception of the scattered portions of himself as external is part of
his problem). Once the concept of the Council of God has been introduced we must see the Man, not as
universal, but as one among a number of equals. While the Man has fallen, his peers in the Council have not,
and they are thus in a position to initiate redemptive action. Before we go on to consider the implications of
such providential intervention we must pause to note that the Council of God does allow Blake to develop a
number of points of increasingly crucial importance to him which could not be accommodated within the original
Zoas myth.</p>
        <p>In one sense the Council of God merely refines certain implications present in Blake’s original
conception of the Universal Man, if we see this as an attempt to reconcile an awareness of human diversity
with a conviction of human unity. The “Four Mighty Ones” who are “in every Man” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi>
3:4, E 300) are the Zoas, the primal human forces or faculties which are in constant conflict in the fallen
world, where (as with the old theory of the humors) their balance or imbalance can be used to explain
differences among individual men. But in the unfallen world these forces are in harmony and constitute “a
Perfect Unity” (3:4, E 300), a state imagined as existing before the fall and again after its divisions have
been healed. This state of harmony, Blake insists, can only exist “from the Universal Brotherhood of Eden /
The Universal Man” (3:5-6, E 300-1); so that, even as he prepares to develop his myth in terms of a single
Universal Man, he acknowledges the central importance of “Brotherhood.” Blake was impressively sensitive
to the relative status of apparently absolute values.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56"
type="note">12</ref> It could hardly have failed to occur to him that the “Brotherhood” he invokes must
remain an empty concept if there is only one true individual, the somewhat abstract Universal Man.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">13</ref> As he progressed with the poem he recognized
that he must treat man not as individual but as member of a community. In order to do this he returned to the
framework of <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> (1794), where Urizen’s fall is seen as a deliberate
cutting off of himself from the community of “Eternals,” who then put him into quarantine under the
guardianship of Los (chaps. 1-5, E 70-8).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58"
type="note">14</ref>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Cf. “Pity would be no more, / If we did not make somebody Poor: / And
Mercy no more could be, / If all were as happy as we” (“The Human Abstract,” E 27)</note>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">13</hi> John Beer points out that in the “original structure” of Blake’s
myth “the Eternal Man, as ultimate containing figure, would, on his awakening into unity, become
isolated,” appearing “as a super-Urizen, without context and therefore without possibilities of
brotherhood” (<hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Universe</hi> [Manchester: Manchester University Press,
1969], p. 158). Beer argues that it was to meet such difficulties that Blake “introduced the idea of a
council ‘of God,’ in Great Eternity, presiding over the whole scene,” and he notes that in 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> “Blake was able to learn from his experience here, and
to include the ‘Eternals’ from the beginning as an essential ordering force” (pp. 158-59). (Beer however
does not consider the problems that this conception itself presents.)</note>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Andrew Lincoln sees the Eternals of Night IX as “clearly closer to the
Eternals of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> than to the providential Council of God” (“The Revision of the
Seventh and Eighth Nights of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, 12 [summer 1978],
120). The distinction brings out the diversity of roles Blake requires his Eternals to play in 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></note></p>
        <p>In envisaging how each Immortal relates to the collective Council of God Blake is able to define
with more precision than the Zoa myth allowed his sense of positive human potential:
<q>
Then those in Great Eternity met in the Council of God<lb/>
As one Man for contracting their Exalted Senses<lb/>
They behold Multitude or Expanding they behold as one<lb/>
As One Man all the Universal family &amp; that one Man<lb/>
They call Jesus the Christ &amp; they in him &amp; he in them<lb/>
Live in Perfect harmony in Eden the land of life<lb/>
Consulting as One Man above the Mountain of Snowdon Sublime<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 21:1-7, E 310-11)
</q>
Where the Universal Man would have to be envisaged as either an abstract individual or as a clumsy aggregate
of all men, the Council of God allows Blake to suggest how man—any man—can shift between a sense of
personal individuality and one of human community.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59"
type="note">15</ref> (The Eternals apparently find it as useful to be able to contract as to expand.) The
point of what Bernard Blackstone calls Blake’s “characteristic doctrine of expansion and contraction” is
that by it “he safeguards at the same time the unity and the variety of Eternity;”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">16</ref> and also makes both at least partially available to fallen
men. As fallen beings we exist characteristically at the limit of Contraction, habitually viewing ourselves
and others as a mere crowd of atomistic individuals external to each other. If we could learn to expand our
senses, using them as human instruments rather than as passive receptors, we would see all men as one—“but
that One,” as Blackstone notes, “is a Family, not a Solitude” (p. 86). In terms of the myth of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Christ is “Man’s consciousness of his unity” while Albion is “Man unconscious
of his unity” (p. 63). Albion as he appears in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> seems to be another version of
the Universal Man, but in his willful separation from Eternity he is very like one of the Zoas, and Blackstone
actually argues that in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> the role previously assigned to Urizen is now played by
Albion.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">17</ref> It is the community of
Eternals, represented by Jesus, which is now the true Eternal Man, or original condition of human (comm)unity,
away from which Albion has fallen. By shifting his attention from the problem of division within the self to
that of alienation from the true human community Blake has sought to ensure that his solution will not be
merely some form of solipsism.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62" type="note">18</ref>
	<note id="n59"><hi rend="s">15</hi> E. B. Murray has observed to me that the passage quoted, in likening the
Council to “one Man,” “seems to put the genie back into the bottle—the Eternals into the Man.” But
the original Ancient Man is a member of the community of Eternals in a sense which goes beyond that in which
the Zoas are his members; the “one Man” formed by the Eternals is a different bottle from the one Blake
began the poem with.</note>
	<note id="n60"><hi rend="s">16</hi><hi rend="i"> English Blake</hi> (1949; Hamden, Conn.: Archon Books,
1966), p. 18.</note>
	<note id="n61"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Morton D. Paley notes that “In his divided condition, Albion takes on
many of the characteristics assigned to Urizen-figures in Blake’s earlier works” (<hi rend="i">The
Continuing City: William Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem [Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1983], p. 198).</note>
	<note id="n62"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Michael Ferber has discussed “the central importance of brotherhood”
for Blake as “a correlate or ‘contrary’ of liberty that keeps liberty from veering off into
individualistic megalomania and even tyranny or into atomistic withdrawal and solipsism” (“Blake’s Idea
of Brotherhood,” <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi>, 93 [1978], 438).</note></p>
        <p>At one level the Council of God is an image of a properly human community, as it might exist on
earth, composed of empirical human individuals. But within Blake’s myth it is also an eternal community from
which all human beings, in the form of the Man, have (or are) fallen. Now whereas the fall of any of the Zoas
is the fall of the Universal Man, the fall of the Man is not the fall of the Council of God; it is diminished
by his fall, but not ruined. It thus remains able to work for the redemption
<pb id="p20-137" n="137"/>
of the Man, offering a useful solution to the problem of how the fall is to be reversed, but constituting a
problem itself in that such a conception obliges Blake to adopt a providential reading of events in which man
is dependent at every stage on extrahuman guidance and assistance. This goes against the grain of Blake’s
humanism, and perhaps not all commentators would accept the notion that “the continued existence of an
unfallen reality is represented in the council of God” (Paley, <hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination</hi>,
p. 156). But the providential role of the eternal community is stressed along with the centrality of
brotherhood in the words spoken by “One of the Eternals” at the feast in Night the Ninth of 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>:
<q>
Man is a Worm wearied with joy he seeks the caves of sleep<lb/>
Among the Flowers of Beulah in his Selfish cold repose<lb/>
Forsaking Brotherhood &amp; Universal love in selfish clay<lb/>
Folding the pure wings of his mind seeking the places dark<lb/>
Abstracted from the roots of Science then inclosd around<lb/>
In walls of Gold we cast him like a Seed into the Earth<lb/>
Till times &amp; spaces have passed over him duly every morn<lb/>
We visit him covering with a Veil the immortal seed<lb/>
With windows from the inclement sky we cover him &amp; with walls<lb/>
And hearths protect the Selfish terror till divided all<lb/>
In families we see our shadows born. &amp; thence we know<lb/>
That Man subsists by Brotherhood &amp; Universal Love<lb/>
We fall on one anothers necks more closely we embrace<lb/>
Not for ourselves but for the Eternal family we live<lb/>
Man liveth not by Self alone but in his brothers face<lb/>
Each shall behold the Eternal Father &amp; love &amp; joy abound<lb/>
(133:10-26, E 401-02)
</q>
New Testament echoes abound here.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63" type="note">19</ref>
The most striking allusion is to St. Paul’s image of the seed to explain the resurrection of the body:
“Thou fool, that which thou sowest is not quickened except it die . . . It is sown a natural body; it is
raised a spiritual body” (1 Corinthians 15.36, 44).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64"
type="note">20</ref> Also present is an allusion to the parable of the Prodigal Son. Both allusions present a
negative (the death of the natural body, the departure and degradation of the prodigal) which is essential to
a following positive moment. If man’s sin is to close himself off “in selfish clay” (the mortal body),
the Eternals respond by helping him to persist in his folly: “we cast him like a Seed into the Earth.”
Without the original “selfish” secession of man from his fellows the true nature of community could not be
expressed or known: it is “<hi rend="i">thence</hi> we know / That Man subsists by Brotherhood &amp;
Universal Love” (emphasis added). Similarly when Blake in his later epics defines the essence of brotherhood
as the forgiveness of sins, this is to make the commission of sins an essential condition for the full
expression of brotherhood. Man’s fall is happy, since as a result “more closely we embrace” as we learn
that “Man liveth not by Self alone.” To be sure, Blake stresses that the issue is <hi rend="i">human</hi>
community; the “Eternal Father” and the Lamb of God are only present at the feast in so far as brotherhood
prevails: “in his brothers face / Each shall behold the Eternal Father,” and, perhaps, 
<hi rend="i">only</hi> there. But that is not to say that the divine as extrahuman agency working for human
redemption is not inescapably present in the body of the poem. In what follows I shall try to show that we
cannot discount the providential intervention of the Eternals, and of the “One Man . . . Jesus the Christ”
whom they compose when fully expanded. This intervention occurs both in the form of actual entry into the
world of the poem, and of the superintendence of the actions of other characters, particularly of Urizen and
of Los. <note id="n63"><hi rend="s">19</hi> A marginal reference directs us to Ephesians 3.10: “To the
intent that now unto the principalities and powers in heavenly places might be known by the church the
manifold wisdom of God,” a text whose relevance here is problematic. I would hazard that Blake means us to
note that the “wisdom of God” is here described as “manifold,” i.e., a unity formed of many, and that
it is revealed “by the church” (δια της ἐκκλησιας literally by means of the church), the
collectivity of believers who compose this manifold unity.</note>
	<note id="n64"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Blake used the last six words on the design for “To Tirzah” in 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> (E 30). The image had already been used by Enion in <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>: “As the seed waits Eagerly watching for its flower &amp; fruit . . . So Man looks out in tree
&amp; herb &amp; fish &amp; bird &amp; beast” (110:3, 6, E 385) The principle of the seed is teleological,
directed towards the end that will transcend its present being.</note></p>
        <p>As the creator of the material universe Urizen is often considered the villain of the piece. But
Blake views this creation ambivalently, or rather sees it dialectically, as part of the whole scheme of fall
and resurrection. Creation is a fall, but it also sets a limit to the fall, and hence prepares for its
reversal. To the account in Night the Second of Urizen’s creation of the Mundane Shell Blake later added a
passage to assure us that: “the Divine Lamb Even Jesus who is the Divine Vision / Permitted all lest Man
should fall into Eternal Death” (33:11-12, E 321). The later accounts of Urizen’s activities are even more
explicit in putting them within a providential framework. When at the end of Night the Fifth Urizen sets out
in search of Orc, his odyssey through his own ruined world is explicitly presented as being dependent on
divine guidance. Urizen seems half to suspect the providential irony within which he is placed: “When
Thought is closd in Caves. Then love shall shew its root in deepest Hell” (65:12, E 344). The Divine Vision
will indeed bring about man’s salvation at least partly by means of Urizen’s aggressive and destructive
quest for Orc, twisting his purposes to fulfill its own plan.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n65" type="note">21</ref> Urizen is deluded if he thinks that he acts by his own power or to his own
ends; like the heroes of another great Protestant epic, <hi rend="i">The Faerie Queene</hi>, he will find that
the true end of his quest is a discovery of his own limitations and his dependence upon the divine:
<q>
. . . now he finds in vain<lb/>
That not of his own power he bore the human form erect<lb/>
Nor of his own will gave his Laws in times of Everlasting<lb/>
(107: 12-14, E 382. Cf., e.g., <hi rend="i">The Faerie Queene</hi>, I.x.1)
</q>
The horrors he encounters as he journeys through his ruined universe constitute an appalling comment on his
attempts to impose his own will. This journey recalls Satan’s voyage through Chaos in books 2 and 3 of 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, but Urizen’s journey is not merely permitted but actually made possible only by
divine power:<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66" type="note">22</ref>
	<pb id="p20-138" n="138"/>
	<q>
The ever pitying one who seeth all things saw his fall<lb/>
And in the dark vacuity created a bosom of clay<lb/>
When wearied dead he fell his limbs reposd in the bosom of slime<lb/>
As the seed falls from the sowers hand so Urizen fell &amp; death<lb/>
Shut up his powers in oblivion.<lb/>
(71:25-29, E 348)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">23</ref></q>
As Blake stresses, “Endless had been his travel but the Divine hand him led” (72.2; E 349). Blake is
careful to point out that the Divine Hand does not <hi rend="i">compel</hi> Urizen to fulfill its purposes,
but brings them about precisely by helping him to reach what he sees as his own goal.
<q>
And now he came into the Abhorred world of Dark Urthona<lb/>
By Providence divine conducted not bent from his own will<lb/>
Least death Eternal should be the result for the Will cannot be violated<lb/>
(74:30-32, E 351)
</q>
Blake never conceives of man merely as the passive instrument of the divine, and he was to insist in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> on the inviolability of the will. There, when the friends of Albion attempt “with
kindest violence to bear him back / Against his will thro Los’s Gate to Eden,” their premature attempt
fails, “as the Will must not be bended but in the day of Divine / Power,” and “The Family Divine” does
not second it, remaining “silent calm &amp; motionless” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 39[44]:2-3, 18-20, E
186).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68" type="note">24</ref> Nevertheless it is clear that
the human will alone is ineffectual without divine aid, and that the relation between human intention and
divine purpose is characteristically an ironic one. <note id="n65"><hi rend="s">21</hi> In “The Formal Art
of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>,” Helen McNeil tries to see a rather different irony here, arguing that
“Urizen’s character has created his fate, and the Divine hand is an externalization of his impulse to
continue to create, whatever the price. . . . Even if the Divine hand were considered a separate power, it
would make a sardonic commentary on Christian determinism, since it would have led Urizen on a spiraling
descent which created, among other horrors, the ironclad world which Blake designates as our own” 
(<hi rend="i">Visionary Forms Dramatic</hi>, ed. Erdman and Grant, p. 381). McNeil’s argument ignores the fact
that Urizen’s creation was unironically providential in setting a limit to the fall (cf. p. 137
above).</note>
	<note id="n66"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Wilkie and Johnson note the similarity between Urizen’s journey and
Satan’s, which is said to be by the permission of Heaven (<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, I. 211-15), and
rightly note the difference of intention behind the permission in the two cases (p. 138).</note>
	<note id="n67"><hi rend="s">23</hi> The saviour here watches over Urizen’s sleep as earlier he had over
that of the Man (18:13-15, E 310). That the saviour’s action here parallels that of the Eternals as
described above (p. 137) suggests that Urizen has become a synecdoche for the Man, a matter which is clarified
by the Urizenic characterization of Albion in the later epics. The “seed” imagery here carries an extra
charge of irony in that in Eternity Urizen is himself the sower, who casts souls into the earth in Night the
Ninth in preparation for the universal harvest (125:3-14, E 394).</note>
	<note id="n68"><hi rend="s">24</hi> I take “bended” here as equivalent to “violated” (cf. 74:31, E
351), though some commentators seem to read it as equivalent to “exerted” (see Michael G. Cooke, 
<hi rend="i">The Romantic Will</hi> [New Haven: Yale University Press, 1976], p. 129).</note></p>
        <p>This is particularly so in the case of Urizen, whose awareness of his own dependence on divine aid
is hazy and typically retrospective. Los and Enitharmon, through whom most of the positively redemptive action
is channeled, have a more explicit awareness of the situation, though they are not exempt from error. Indeed
it is by their errors that they participate in the divine plan, errors that take a triple form: sin, the
conviction of sin, attempts to redeem sin. Now Blake’s attitude to the question of sin is complex and
possibly ambivalent, and divides his commentators.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69"
type="note">25</ref> During the early 1790s he often seems to reject the whole concept of sin as a Urizenic
mystification used by priests and kings to repress humanity. But when he later identifies the forgiveness of
sins as central to true Christianity his position is more complex. Just as brotherhood is meaningless without
some sense of a community to which the individual might belong, so the forgiveness of sins is an empty notion
if there is no such thing as sin:
<q>
. . . O Mercy O Divine Humanity!<lb/>
O Forgiveness &amp; Pity &amp; Compassion! If I were Pure I should never<lb/>
Have known thee; If I were Unpolluted I should never have<lb/>
Glorified thy Holiness, or rejoiced in thy great Salvation.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 61:43-46, E 212)
</q>
To complicate matters further, if there is no such thing as sin, then the conviction that one has sinned (or
that others have) is itself a sin, or at any rate an error that calls for forgiveness. When the Divine Voice
comforts Jerusalem by showing her Joseph forgiving Mary (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 61:1-52, E 211-12), the
whole point would seem to be lost unless we accept the idea that Mary has in fact committed adultery, and that
adultery is a sin, though, like all sins, it can be wiped out by forgiveness. The early Blake probably
followed the antinomian sects in identifying the forgiveness of sin with its abolition: “Unto the pure all
things are pure: but unto them that are defiled and unbelieving is nothing pure; but even their mind and
conscience is defiled” (Titus 1.15). But the later Blake would have appreciated the full force of Jesus’s
words to the woman taken in adultery—“go, and sin no more” (John 8.11). Blake moves in effect from the
defiant antinomian assertion that “every thing that lives is Holy”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n70" type="note">26</ref> to the more orthodox recognition that “There is none that liveth &amp;
Sinneth not!” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 61:24, E 212).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n71" type="note">27</ref> The forgiveness of sins is predicated on the awareness that man cannot
fulfill the demands of the moral law. This is certainly a point against the moral law and its creator, Urizen,
who finds to his cost, as Blake sardonically puts it, “That no flesh nor spirit could keep / His iron laws
one moment” (<hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>, 23:25-26, E 81). But Blake is not simply calling for the
abolition of the moral law, since without the realization that its impossible demands cannot be met man could
never recognize the necessity for the forgiveness of sins. These complex issues will perhaps become a little
clearer if we examine the situation of Los and Enitharmon in Night the Seventh of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas.</hi>
	<note id="n69"><hi rend="s">25</hi> Thomas J.J. Altizer argues that “A faith that recognizes itself as
existing in opposition to the state of sin must give itself both to a negation of guilt and the Law and to a
continual process of abolishing the consciousness of sin . . .” (<hi rend="i">The New Apocalypse: The
Radical Christian Vision of William Blake</hi> [East Lansing: Michigan State University Press, 1967], pp.
202-03). Blackstone on the other hand argues that in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> Blake wished to explore
“the <hi rend="i">sense of sin</hi> which is so deep within Man that we have to regard it as an integral
part of his innermost nature,” though he does stress that Blake’s concern was with 
“<hi rend="i">error</hi> that was understood as error and cast off” rather than with sin as Wesley or Whitefield
might have understood it (p. 163, 185 n.). Michael Cooke points out that “Blake’s version of the
Joseph-Mary relationship [to be considered presently] builds on the idea of the <hi rend="i">felix
culpa</hi>,” but goes on to argue that “The passage further uses Jehovah’s message to imply, beyond the
forgiveness of sins, the unreality or delusiveness of sins . . .” (pp. 137-38).</note>
	<note id="n70"><hi rend="s">26</hi><hi rend="i"> The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> 27, E 45. See also 
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> 8.10 (E 51) and <hi rend="i">America</hi> 8.13 (E 54). The
phrase is used ironically in Enitharmon’s song of triumph over Los, <hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 34.80 (E 324); see
Michael J. Tolley, “<hi rend="i">Europe</hi>: ‘to those ychain’d in sleep,’ ” in Erdman and Grant,
eds., <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic</hi>, p. 123 n. 5.</note>
	<note id="n71"><hi rend="s">27</hi> Blake’s position on the question of sin might be clearer if we take it
that he means not transgression against some absolute divine authority, but trespass or offense against other
human beings, which is inevitable since one individual cannot live by the laws appropriate to another. Such
offenses may be real infringements of their rights or simply affronts to their sense of moral values; in
either case true brotherhood consists in forgiving others their trespasses.</note></p>
        <p>When Enitharmon, like a second Eve, eats of “the fruit / Of Urizens Mysterious tree” (87:13-14,
E 369) it prompts in her an awareness of her own sinfulness. As John Sutherland points out, Blake is
deliberately parodying “the fall of man, tempted by Satanic falsehood, with an account of the fall of Los
(and himself), tempted by the doctrines of conventional Urizenic religion.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72" type="note">28</ref> Enitharmon’s real “sin,” that is, is to acquiesce in
the Urizenic (or as Blake himself would later say, Satanic) accusation that she has sinned. As if to prove how
difficult
<pb id="p20-139" n="139"/>
it is to refrain from accusation of sin, Blackstone denounces Enitharmon’s error with vigor, arguing that
“it is Enitharmon’s conviction of sin, her belief that the Son of God can only descend to condemn and not
to forgive, that postpones the resurrection into unity” (p. 294). But Enitharmon’s error is actually an
essential moment in the process that will lead to resurrection.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n73" type="note">29</ref> As Sutherland comments, “The irony of this particular ‘happy fall’ is
that Blake / Los finds that compassionate love between himself and his wife grows out of a sharing of
spectrous depressions and fears” (p. 253). Enitharmon’s first response to her conviction of sin is to
appeal to Los (as Milton’s Eve appealed to Adam) to eat also in order to redeem her.
<q>
When In the Deeps beneath I gatherd of this ruddy fruit<lb/>
It was by that I knew that I had Sinnd &amp; then I knew<lb/>
That without a ransom I could not be savd from Eternal death<lb/>
That Life lives upon Death &amp; by devouring appetite<lb/>
All things subsist on one another thenceforth in Despair<lb/>
I spend my glowing time but thou art strong &amp; mighty<lb/>
To bear this Self conviction take then Eat thou also of<lb/>
The fruit &amp; give me proof of life Eternal or I die<lb/>
(87:15-22, E 369)
</q>
The turning to Los is a positive movement, though Enitharmon’s view of the situation is still
fallen.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">30</ref> She invokes Los’s
sacrifice as the vicarious payment of a debt that she cannot meet; and the Spectre likewise talks in terms of
a “scapegoat” religion:
<q>
The Spectre of Urthona wept before Los Saying I am the cause<lb/>
That this dire state commences I began the dreadful state<lb/>
Of Separation &amp; on my dark head the curse &amp; punishment<lb/>
Must fall unless a way be found to Ransom &amp; Redeem<lb/>
(87:31-34, E 369)
</q>
The error in all this points the way to a truth. The conviction that <hi rend="i">someone</hi> must pay the
debt of sin leads to misguided demands for human sacrifice, but, as Blake was later to state with exemplary
clarity, the forgiveness of sins <hi rend="i">is</hi> a sacrifice, though of self rather than of others:
<q>
Jesus said. Wouldest thou love one who never died<lb/>
For thee or ever die for one who had not died for thee<lb/>
And if God dieth not for Man &amp; giveth not himself<lb/>
Eternally for Man Man could not exist. for Man is Love:<lb/>
As God is Love: every kindness to another is a little Death<lb/>
In the Divine Image nor can Man exist but by Brotherhood<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 96:23-28, E 256)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75"
type="note">31</ref></q>
Los understands the situation better, and he recognizes that the “ransom” must be a divine rather than a
human sacrifice, “a little Death / In the Divine Image;” while the human capacity to put off self in
repentance, in the forgiveness of sins, or in offering oneself as ransom for another, is a pledge of the
possibility of such redemption.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76" type="note">32</ref><q>
Los trembling answerd Now I feel the weight of stern repentance<lb/>
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>
Turn inwardly thine Eyes &amp; there behold the Lamb of God<lb/>
Clothed in Luvahs robes of blood descending to redeem<lb/>
O Spectre of Urthona take comfort O Enitharmon<lb/>
Couldst thou but cease from terror &amp; trembling &amp; affright<lb/>
When I appear before thee in forgiveness of ancient injuries<lb/>
Why shouldst thou remember &amp; be afraid. I surely have died in pain<lb/>
Often enough to convince thy jealousy &amp; fear &amp; terror<lb/>
Come hither be patient let us converse together because<lb/>
I also tremble at myself &amp; at all my former life<lb/>
(87:39, 43-51, E 369)
</q>
Enitharmon is not persuaded, for her “Self conviction” of sin leads her to expect the Lamb as judge rather
than redeemer; herself less forgiving than Los, she finds it hard to accept the forgiveness of sins:
<q>
Enitharmon answerd I behold the Lamb of God descending<lb/>
To Meet these Spectres of the Dead I therefore fear that he<lb/>
Will give us to Eternal Death fit punishment for such<lb/>
Hideous offenders Uttermost extinction in eternal pain<lb/>
An ever dying life of stifling &amp; obstruction shut out<lb/>
Of existence to be a sign &amp; terror to all who behold<lb/>
Lest any should in futurity do as we have done in heaven<lb/>
Such is our state nor will the Son of God redeem us but destroy<lb/>
(87:52-59, E 369-70)
</q>
This self-abasement and despair are essential moments in the account of spiritual progress offered by
Protestantism, a religion which stresses (as did Blake) man’s utter inability to fulfill the demands of the
moral law and his consequent need for divine Grace (which Blake rewrites as the forgiveness of sins). It is
particularly prominent in Calvinism, where it may prove a dead end out of which the believer cannot escape.
Blake certainly knew of the case of Cowper, who believed that he had been singled out by God as “a sign
&amp; terror to all who behold.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77" type="note">33</ref>
From this situation Enitharmon seeks escape by what any Protestant would recognize as an error—the reliance
on good works. She hopes that she and Los can escape punishment for their sins by offering the product of
their labors as “sacrificial offerings, ransoms for their sins,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n78" type="note">34</ref> and begs him to make
<q>
. . . forms sublime<lb/>
Such as the piteous spectres may assimilate themselves into<lb/>
They shall be ransoms for our Souls that we may live<lb/>
(90:22-24, E 370)
</q>
	<pb id="p20-140" n="140"/>
An error, to be sure, but a necessary one, for the work they undertake is part of the divine plan to redeem
man which they, like Urizen, are in fact working to fulfill, though they cannot recognize it until after the
event.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79" type="note">35</ref>
	<note id="n72"><hi rend="s">28</hi> “Blake and Urizen,” in Erdman and Grant, eds., <hi rend="i">Blake’s
Visionary Forms Dramatic</hi>, p. 253.</note>
	<note id="n73"><hi rend="s">29</hi> As Mary Lynn Johnson and Brian Wilkie note, the Spectre’s seeing of a
providential purpose in the Tree of Mystery is not entirely erroneous; it is “very close to the Christian
interpretation of the ‘Law,’ the old dispensation, as a divinely-appointed stopgap” (“The Spectrous
Embrace in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, VIIa,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, 12 [summer 1978], 102).</note>
	<note id="n74"><hi rend="s">30</hi> As John Beer notes, she is expounding “the Doctrine of the Atonement (a
dogma abhorrent to Blake)” (p. 135). It should be noted that while Blake opposes such dogmas he also
recuperates them by seeing them as historically necessary errors, implying a kind of theodicy of the
development of human religious conceptions.</note>
	<note id="n75"><hi rend="s">31</hi> John Kilgore claims that it is in Night VIIa of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi> “that we hear, for the very first time in all Blake’s works, of the necessity of
‘Self-Annihilation’ ” (“The Order of Nights VIIa and VIIb in Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, 12 [summer 1978], 109). The passage in question may, however, be a late
addition, posterior to parallel passages in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></note>
	<note id="n76"><hi rend="s">32</hi> It is however going too far to claim, as do Johnson and Wilkie, that
“If this husband and wife could forgive each other, they wouldn’t need a Redeemer” (“The Spectrous
Embrace,” p. 104).</note>
	<note id="n77"><hi rend="s">33</hi> It has been suggested that the Spectre of Los, who has a similar
despairing conviction of sin in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 10:37-59 (E 153-54), is at least in part a
portrait of Cowper. See Morton D. Paley, “Cowper as Blake’s Spectre,” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century
Studies</hi> 1 [1968], 236-52; and also his <hi rend="i">The Continuing City</hi>, pp. 246-50.</note>
	<note id="n78"><hi rend="s">34</hi> Johnson and Wilkie, “The Spectrous Embrace,” p. 103.</note>
	<note id="n79"><hi rend="s">35</hi> Both Erdman (<hi rend="i">Prophet against Empire</hi>, pp. 381-82) and
Paley (<hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination</hi>, pp. 159-61) are rightly skeptical of the efficacy of
these labors, and tend to see the error involved as Blake’s (encouraged by the well-known autobiographical
allusions in the passage). But in the context of the poem any human attempts to achieve salvation are seen as
inefficacious, except in ways unforeseen at the time, and Blake is well aware of his characters’
errors.</note></p>
        <p>It is the Divine Hand who directs their labors, whose full significance can only be seen from the
perspective of Eternity:
<q>
. . . Then Enitharmon erected Looms in Lubans Gate<lb/>
And calld the Looms Cathedron in these Looms She wove the Spectres<lb/>
Bodies of Vegetation Singing lulling Cadences to drive away<lb/>
Despair from the poor wandering spectres and Los loved them<lb/>
With a parental love for the Divine hand was upon him<lb/>
And upon Enitharmon &amp; the Divine Countenance shone<lb/>
In Golgonooza Looking down the Daughters of Beulah saw<lb/>
With joy the bright Light &amp; in it a Human form<lb/>
And knew he was the Saviour Even Jesus &amp; they worshipped<lb/>
(100:2-10, E 372)
</q>
From one point of view the creation of this world of Generation is, like Urizen’s creation of the material
universe, a disastrous consequence of the fall; but both are equally part of the divine plan to redeem that
fall. The labors of Los and Enitharmon provide the medium for incarnation, forming “a Vast family wondrous
in beauty &amp; love” which appears as “a Universal female form” (103:37-38, E 376):
<q>
And Enitharmon namd the Female Jerusa[le]m the holy<lb/>
Wondring she saw the Lamb of God within Jerusalems Veil<lb/>
The divine Vision seen within the inmost deep recess<lb/>
Of fair Jerusalems bosom in a gently beaming fire<lb/>
(104:1-4, E 376)
</q>
As the choric sons of Eden recognize, viewing events from the perspective of Eternity, with this incarnation
the process of redemption has begun in earnest:
<q>
We now behold the Ends of Beulah &amp; we now behold<lb/>
Where Death Eternal is put off Eternally<lb/>
Assume the dark Satanic body in the Virgins womb<lb/>
O Lamb divin[e] it cannot thee annoy O pitying one<lb/>
Thy pity is from the foundation of the World &amp; thy Redemption<lb/>
Begun already in Eternity Come then O Lamb of God<lb/>
Come Lord Jesus come quickly<lb/>
(104:11-17, E 377)
</q>
Their recognition prompts an extreme expression of submission to the workings of providence:
<q>
Now we know that life Eternal<lb/>
Depends alone upon the Universal hand &amp; not in us<lb/>
Is aught but death In individual weakness sorrow &amp; pain<lb/>
(104:8-10, E 376)
</q>
From this point on Blake is in effect retelling the Christian story of the incarnation and the passion in his
own way, having already retold the temptation and fall. For Blake, of course, the true sacrifice of Christ is
the Incarnation itself, the taking on of “the dark Satanic body;” Christ dies an eternal death for man
precisely by entering into mortal life.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80"
type="note">36</ref> But Blake also offers a version of the crucifixion, and to understand it we must consider
how the divine is able to enter the world of the Zoas. <note id="n80"><hi rend="s">36</hi> For “Eternal
Death” as Blake’s term for incarnation, see Damon, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, p. 141.</note></p>
        <p>A number of additions in the early part of the manuscript concern the role of Jesus in assuming the
garments of Luvah. The long “Council of God” passage explains that when “those in Great Eternity . . .
behold as one . . . that one Man / They call Jesus the Christ” (21:1, 3-5, E 310-11). Jesus is produced as a
historical agent when “The Family Divine” elect
<q>
the Seven Eyes of God &amp; the Seven lamps of the Almighty<lb/>
The Seven are one within the other the Seventh is named Jesus<lb/>
The Lamb of God blessed for ever<lb/>
(19:7, 9-12, E 312-13)
</q>
To redeem the Man Jesus must enter into him, and here the role of Luvah is crucial. We may reasonably
speculate that in Blake’s original scheme Urizen was the aggressor and Luvah the victim who, in the form of
Orc, was to resist and defeat Urizen. The experience of the late 1790s and 1800s could not but have called
such a resolution into question for Blake. On the political plane Urizen is England and Luvah is revolutionary
France; by 1800 Blake’s myth must have seemed all too prophetic as the revolutionary Luvah was revealed as
the Orc of Napoleon, “the child and champion of Jacobinism.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n81" type="note">37</ref> In the war between Urizen and Orc it was no longer possible to see a clear
confrontation of good and evil; instead there emerged “a Shadowy hermaphrodite black &amp; opake” (100:34,
E 374), a deadly hybrid of revolutionary energy and imperialist ambition that terrifies Urizen, though its
production is in fact his real victory over Luvah. When Blake interpolates his “standard narrative of the
Man’s first fall”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82" type="note">38</ref> at a late
stage in the composition, he presents Urizen and Luvah as jointly responsible, conspiring to usurp power from
the Man and wield it themselves, while each plans to doublecross the other (21:19-22:39, E 311-12).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83" type="note">39</ref> In this game it is Urizen rather than Luvah
who wins, in that by Night the Eighth Urizen has fixed his fallen rival in the serpent form of Orc entwined
around the Tree of Mystery, placing him firmly within his religion of sin and retribution. But actually
everyone has lost, in that having left his rightful place Luvah has effectively been destroyed. 
<note id="n81"><hi rend="s">37</hi> This phrase was used by Pitt in 1800; see S. T. Coleridge, <hi rend="i">Essays
on His Times in The Morning Post and The Courier</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman (London: Routledge &amp; Kegan
Paul, 1978), i. 185 and n. 8.</note>
	<note id="n82"><hi rend="s">38</hi><hi rend="i"> The Poems of William Blake</hi>, ed. W. H. Stevenson
(London: Longman, 1971), p. 291.</note>
	<note id="n83"><hi rend="s">39</hi> Urizen and Orc are “corporeal enemies but spiritually leagued in the
state called Satan” (Paley, <hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination</hi>, p. 166).</note></p>
        <p>Blake solves his dilemma here by recourse to the doctrine of “states,” so important in the
later prophecies. Los assures Rahab that “when Luvah in Orc became a Serpent he des[c]ended into / That
State calld Satan” (115:26-27, E 380). Luvah can only be redeemed by the
<pb id="p20-141" n="141"/>
intervention of the Lamb who acts as Luvah’s <hi rend="i">locum tenens</hi>, so to speak, preserving the
“state” of Luvah vacated by Luvah’s descent. The appearance of Luvah in two places at once causes Urizen
understandable perplexty:
<q>
When Urizen saw the Lamb of God clothed in Luvahs robes<lb/>
Perplexd &amp; terrifid he Stood tho well he knew that Orc<lb/>
Was Luvah But he now beheld a new Luvah. Or One<lb/>
Who assumd Luvahs form &amp; stood before him opposite<lb/>
But he saw Orc a Serpent form augmenting times on times<lb/>
In the fierce battle. . . .<lb/>
(101:1-6, E 373)
</q>
Having assumed Luvah’s robes of blood the Lamb must now die in Luvah’s place. There are potent ironies in
the assault on the Lamb by his enemies. Luvah’s own emanation, Vala, identifies him as Luvah’s murderer by
the evidence of the bloody robes, and the Synagogue of Satan is prepared to condemn him either for being Luvah
or for being an impostor indifferently. The Synagogue of course includes the Christian church, which Blake
regards as perpetuating the crucifixion. Urizen and his allies are quite right to recognize the Lamb as their
real enemy, however inconsistent their rationalizations, though by sacrificing him on the Tree of Mystery they
are in fact carrying out his plan and bringing about their own destruction. If mortal life is death to the
Lamb, mortal death is life eternal, and by taking on and then putting off “the dark Satanic body” the Lamb
has given that “proof of life Eternal” that Enitharmon had demanded of Los (87:22, E 369).</p>
        <p>This is not quite how Los and Jerusalem see it, for they (the Joseph of Arimathea and Mary of
Blake’s version of the passion) believe that the Lamb is dead and bury him in a sepulcher:
<q>
And Los &amp; Enitharmon took the Body of the Lamb<lb/>
Down from the Cross &amp; placd it in a Sepulcher which Los had hewn<lb/>
For himself in the Rock of Eternity trembling &amp; in despair<lb/>
Jerusalem wept over the Sepulcher two thousand Years<lb/>
(110:30-33, E 385)
</q>
The “two thousand Years” are the period of the Christian Church which has actually made the dead body of
Christ its object of worship. In so doing it has been worshipping its own death; the Lamb is buried in the
very tomb that Los had prepared for himself. The resurrection of Christ should free men from the fear of
death, but Los and the others, like the Church, fail to recognize the living saviour:
<q>
And Los &amp; Enitharmon builded Jerusalem weeping<lb/>
Over the Sepulcher &amp; over the Crucified body<lb/>
Which to their Phantom Eyes appear’d still in the Sepulcher<lb/>
But Jesus stood beside them in the Spirit Separating<lb/>
Their Spirit from their body. Terrified at Non Existence<lb/>
For such they deemd the death of the body.<lb/>
(117:1-6, E 386)
</q>
This is in fact their final redemptive error, for in his terror and panic Los seizes the sun and moon and thus
initiates the “Last Judgment” of Night the Ninth, which will lead to the restoration of all things. “Los
appears for the moment as the Angel of Death destroying the universe. . . . In his agony he tears down the
visible symbols of the Spirit and the Passions, not knowing that by destroying the symbols he is opening the
way to their eternal reality,” remarks Damon, adding: “But Jesus is the real Angel of Death” 
(<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, p. 391), the agent of a process of which Los is only the instrument.</p>
        <p>There is certainly a difficulty in seeing how Los’s actions bring about the apocalypse of Night
the Ninth. The narrative structure of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> encourages us to argue in terms of cause
and effect, no doubt one reason why Blake eschews narrative structure in his later epics. A polemical motif in
his marginalia and other writings concerns his rejection of a philosophy of cause and effect, and an
insistence on the “spiritual causes” of actions.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84"
type="note">40</ref> If we accept this, we can hardly agree with Leonard Deen’s assurance that Los and
Enitharmon “make choices that decide the history and end of this struggle in the birth of Jesus and in the
final apocalyptic renewal of heaven and earth.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n85"
type="note">41</ref> It is easier to accept Frye’s claim that “The Last Judgment . . . is not really the
work of Los, though the opening action is ascribed to him” (<hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi>, p. 308).
<note id="n84"><hi rend="s">40</hi> See annotations to Lavater (E 601), to Bacon (E 626), and to Reynolds (E
656); <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> (E 543-44); <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 26:44-46 (E 124).</note>
	<note id="n85"><hi rend="s">41</hi><hi rend="i"> Conversing in Paradise: Poetic Genius and
Identity-as-Community in Blake’s Los</hi> (Columbia: University of Missouri Press, 1983), p. 130. Wilkie and
Johnson also wish to see Los as “an agent,” though they note that he acts out of “reflex desperation,”
and concede that “His terrified struggle for life could be misunderstood as a sign that he has not absorbed
the Blakean meaning of the Crucifixion as the ultimate act of the annihilation of the self”; the most they
can finally say for Los is that “His resistance here to physical death is not an absolute error” (p. 211).
But by now we should be able to see that for Blake no error is absolute.</note></p>
        <p>When a writer like William Cowper rejects explanations in terms of second causes, it is in order to
refer all events directly to the will of God, “the genuine cause of all.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86" type="note">42</ref> Cowper’s intention is clearly to subordinate human agency
absolutely to an extrahuman providential scheme. Is this the point of Blake’s attack on causation? I have
been arguing that Blake does see human agency as dependent on the divine, but I would not go so far as to
align him with Cowper. The notion of “spiritual agency” is hard to grasp, but it may be helpful to suggest
that by it Blake is not so much asserting a divine compulsion over all events as insisting that we judge the
nature of an act rather than its (supposed) consequences. Returning to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, we
should therefore ask ourselves what it is that Los really does rather than how his act (or any comparable act
performed by anyone else) is supposed to alter the “real” world outside him. To accept an absolute
division between an agent and the “real” world outside him is to beg the question by denying
“spiritual” agency 
<pb id="p20-142" n="142"/>
from the beginning.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n87" type="note">43</ref> Los 
<hi rend="i">is</hi> his world. I would propose that we read the Last Judgment of Night the Ninth (and the same
would go for the climax of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, and possibly for that of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>) in
the light of Blake’s famous remark: “whenever any Individual Rejects Error &amp; Embraces Truth a Last
Judgment passes upon that Individual” (<hi rend="i">A Vision of the Last Judgment</hi>, 84, E 562). Like the
island of Pincher Martin, the apparently solid universe in which Los exists is his own creation, and it serves
both to preserve his existence and to lock him out of Eternity. With the death of Jesus the last hope of
salvation within that world has vanished, and although Los’s seizing of the sun and moon may be an act of
despair, it is also a recognition that that world is created and can be destroyed by his own strength whenever
he chooses to exert it, and it is thus an embracing of truth. <note id="n86"><hi rend="s">42</hi><hi rend="i">
The Task</hi> (1785), 2: 205 (<hi rend="i">Cowper: Poetical Works</hi>, ed. H. S. Milford, 4th ed., rev., ed.
Norma Russell [London: Oxford University Press, 1967], p. 150).</note>
	<note id="n87"><hi rend="s">43</hi> Cf. “True causes for Blake are spiritual, though their consequences are
to be read in the natural world. . . . Blake’s poetry . . . insists on placing the full burden of
consequence on every mental affect. . . . The whole history of consciousness seems at stake in every conscious
moment” (Leslie Brisman, <hi rend="i">Romantic Origins</hi> [Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 1978], p.
226).</note></p>
        <p>But, as we have seen, Los’s embracing of the truth is not easily to be separated from his
repeated acceptance of error: “to be an Error &amp; to be Cast out is a part of Gods Design” 
(<hi rend="i">A Vision of the Last Judgment</hi>, 84, E 562). As for the heroes of <hi rend="i">The Faerie
Queene</hi> (whose chivalric fiction plays on the root meaning of “error”), so in Blake error both
separates man from the truth and leads him to it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n88"
type="note">44</ref> It is in this sense that <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> embodies a theodicy. Critics who
resist this conclusion do so because they are reluctant to see Blake as embracing such an orthodox view of the
relationship between the human and the divine. But the shifting of gravity within the poem as it progresses
undeniably moves it in the direction of Christian (more specifically Protestant) orthodoxy, as the generous
use of Miltonic material suggests. Blake’s relation to Milton here is one of dependence more than critique,
and the result pastiche as much as parody. I have argued that the move to orthodoxy is imposed on Blake by the
need to avoid the renunciation of community exacted in his original conception. When in his next prophetic
work he turns his attention explicitly to his great predecessor and his version of the orthodox myth, he
changes the rules of the game by making Milton one of the Eternals. Thus elected as it were to the Council of
God, Milton causes as much disruption in Eternity as the incarnated Lamb did in the world of <hi rend="i">The
Four Zoas.</hi> But the question of the relation between human and divine in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is matter for another study. <note id="n88"><hi rend="s">44</hi> “The way to truth
in a fallen world is through error” (Deen, <hi rend="i">Conversing in Paradise</hi>, p. 217).</note></p>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p20-143" n="143" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
