<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>21.1.harper</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Bryan Aubrey, Watchmen of Eternity: Blake’s Debt to Jacob Boehme</title>
        <author n="Harper">George Mills Harper</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1987</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1987</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">21.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Jean H. Hagstrum</name>
              <name>George Mills Harper</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Mary V. Jackson</name>
              <name>Edward Larrissy</name>
              <name>Lousie Lippincott</name>
              <name>Catherine McClenahan</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Peter Otto</name>
              <name>George Anthoy Ross, Jr.</name>
              <name>Charu Sheel Singh</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1987"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_21">
    <body>
	<pb id="p21-25" n="25"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-21-1-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Bryan Aubrey. <hi rend="i">Watchmen of Eternity: Blake’s Debt to Jacob
Boehme.</hi> Lanham, New York, and London: University Press of America, 1986. xiii+193 pp. $27.00 cloth/$13.25
paper.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">George Mills</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Harper</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>All serious students of Blake know that he read Boehme and approved in general what he found in
the famous collection of Boehme’s <hi rend="i">Works</hi> known as the William Law Edition.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">1</ref> In his own collected writings Blake referred to
Boehme by name only twice (in 1793 and 1800), but many critics have assumed that his influence was
considerable if not great. How, we ask ourselves, can we argue with Blake’s blunt statement in 
<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>: “Any man of mechanical talents may from the writings of
Paracelsus or Jacob Behmen, produce ten thousand volumes of equal value with Swedenborgs, and from those of
Dante or Shakespear an infinite number.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
type="note">2</ref> To play the devil’s advocate, however, I will call attention to still “another plain
fact”: Blake places Boehme on the same plane as Paracelsus, far above the level of Swedenborg but far below
the level of Dante and Shakespeare. Moreover, although little can be proved precisely by Blake’s
enthusiastic distinctions, the skeptical among us remind ourselves that he annotated three of Swedenborg’s
books, one with considerable care, whereas he probably annotated none of Boehme’s. If in fact Blake owned
the Law edition, as Bentley and Nurmi cautiously suggest, the copy has not survived. Perhaps, however, the
book was too dear for the penniless Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi rend="i"> The Works of Jacob Behmen</hi>, ed., George Ward and Thomas
Langcake (London, 1764-81), 4 vols. See Aubrey’s outline and brief comment, pp. xi-xii.</note>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">2</hi> G.E. Bentley, Jr., ed., <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi>
(Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1978), 1:95. Bentley’s conjectured dates of <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> are
“(?1790-3).”</note>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">3</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., and Martin K. Nurmi, <hi rend="i">A Blake
Bibliography</hi> (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1964), p. 199. According to Bentley and Nurmi,
the Law edition was offered by Rivington in 1824 for £1.16.0. That, I suppose, was expensive for
Blake.</note></p>
          <p>But all this is beside the point in one sense: he was excited over Boehme as early as 1793 and
still excited, according to Henry Crabb Robinson, as late as 10 December 1825: “Jacob Boehme was spoken of
as a divinely inspired man. Blake praised, too, the figures in Law’s translation as being very beautiful.
Michael Angelo could not have done better.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">4</ref> That too may be beside the point: the question raised by Aubrey is how strong, pervasive,
and continuing Boehme’s influence on Blake was. For the opinions of others we may begin—as Aubrey
does—with William Butler Yeats, who was himself influenced by Boehme and who declared that <hi rend="i">The
Book of Urizen</hi> “is page by page a transformation, according to Blake’s peculiar illumination, of the
doctrines set forth in the opening chapters of the ‘Mysterium Magnum’ of Jacob Boehme.” Even so, it
should be pointed out that Yeats is trying to “convict commentators” like Garnett, Gilchrist, and
Rossetti, who “show [no] evidence of having ever given so much as a day’s study to any part of Blake’s
mystical writing.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">5</ref> Aubrey obviously
found a powerful ally in Yeats. However, one of Aubrey’s assumptions illustrates the mistakes sometimes
induced by over-enthusiastic source studies. Writing about the conflict of opposites leading to the vision of
joy in Boehme’s system, Aubrey confidently declares that “Yeats captured this vision in his play 
<hi rend="i">The Unicorn from the Stars</hi>, in which the dreamer Martin Hearne (who is based on Boehme),
discovers that the life of paradise is like ‘a battle where the sword made a sound that was like laughter’
” (39). Now the “plain fact” is that <hi rend="i">The Unicorn</hi> was inspired by Nietzsche, who
was—at one degree removed in the person of Zarathustra—the typal example for Martin Hearne. Moreover, the
source of the vision of the
<pb id="p21-26" n="26"/>
clashing swords, one of Yeats’s favorite images, was not Boehme but Mrs. Harietta Dorothea Hunter, a member
of the Hermetic Order of the Golden Dawn. Writing to Mrs. Hunter, in an unpublished letter dated 13 June
[1938], Yeats recalled the vivid impression her vision had made: “Yes, of course, I remember. . . . In a
vision you described to me the music of heaven you heard as the Clashing of Swords.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Thomas Sadler, ed., <hi rend="i">Diary, Reminiscences, and Correspondence
of Henry Crabb Robinson</hi> (London: Macmillan, 1869), 2:305.</note>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">5</hi> John P. Frayne, ed., <hi rend="i">Uncollected Prose by W. B. Yeats</hi>
(New York: Columbia University Press, 1970), 1:402. From a review in the <hi rend="i">Bookman</hi> (April
1896) of Richard Garnett’s <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Yeats’s library included six volumes of
Boehme’s works by various translators. Five were published by John M. Watkins, Madame Blavatsky’s
publisher and bookseller, and one by Joseph Richardson which contains four items from the Law edition (see
Edward O’Shea, <hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalog of W. B. Yeats’s Library</hi> [New York and London:
Garland, 1985], pp. 37-39).</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">6</hi> I quote from a xerox copy of a typescript in the library of Michael B.
Yeats.</note></p>
          <p>At one time or another, to be sure, most of us are guilty of mistaking the tail for the donkey.
Although <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> is “full of ideas and symbols” from Boehme, as
Martin K. Nurmi pointed out thirty years ago, “Blake borrows ideas from Boehme that he had not really
assimilated and that he was never to assimilate.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12"
type="note">7</ref> Extending the suggestion in an article about negative sources, Nurmi warned that “Blake
is sometimes illuminated but rarely explained by his sources. . . . It is therefore hazardous to accept prior
analogues to his ideas as sources, especially on the basis of mere conceptual analogy. . . .”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">7</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake’s Marriage of Heaven and Hell: A Critical Study</hi>
(Kent: Kent State University, 1957), p. 28. Nurmi refers to Bentley’s unpublished dissertation (Oxford,
1954) as “the only study of Blake’s connections with Boehme that approaches thoroughness.” I agree,
having read it many years ago; but much has been done since, as Aubrey points out.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">8</hi> “Negative Sources in Blake,” <hi rend="i">Essays for S. Foster
Damon</hi>, ed. Alvin H. Rosenfeld (Providence: Brown University Press, 1969), p. 303.</note></p>
          <p>Almost certainly, I suppose, Aubrey would agree in general with that cautious warning. But he
disagrees with Nurmi and numerous other critics who deny that Blake belongs in the company of mystics: “The
argument of this book, however, is that for all Blake’s idiosyncracies, the creative way in which he
transformed his sources, and his fierce independence of mind, he was nonetheless working within the broad
framework of this mystical and metaphysical tradition” (2).</p>
          <p>It is not my purpose to debate this issue,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">9</ref> but rather to consider briefly Aubrey’s method and relative success in defending his
thesis. It is true, as he writes, that “the amount of literature which deals specifically with Boehme
remains comparatively small” (ix), and he cites the most significant of these to address the
question.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">10</ref> His “aim” therefore
“is to fill the gap, to show how Boehme’s work was a major factor in Blake’s intellectual and spiritual
life, and how a knowledge of Boehme greatly enriches our understanding of Blake’s work” (ix).
Unfortunately, “the format of the book” (ix) makes Aubrey’s task difficult if not impossible. Beginning
with a brief but useful chapter on Boehme’s system, he devotes the remaining chapters to five of Blake’s
poetic works: (2) <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>; (3) <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>;
(4) <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">11</ref> Since the study of Blake’s three major poems is confined
to one chapter and since a great body of his work is considered sparingly, if at all, the reader who expects
Aubrey’s book “to fill the gap” will surely be disappointed. In fact, most of the “aspects of
Boehme’s thought” (ix) treated by <hi rend="i">Watchmen of Eternity</hi> have already been explored by
other critics, especially Kathleen Raine, to whom Aubrey “acknowledge[s] a lasting debt” (x). And well he
might: her impressive study of Blake’s sources cites the same works and traces many of the same ideas as she
presents the case of Boehme’s influence. More cautiously and from a somewhat different perspective, Paley
develops many of the same arguments in his provocative study of Blake’s thought.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">12</ref> Since the Blake-Boehme relationship represents only a part,
however significant, of Raine’s and Paley’s books, neither of them attempted to justify disregarding the
influence of “some elements” of Boehme’s thought completely, as Aubrey has (ix). 
<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">9</hi> The opposing viewpoints are most strongly supported by Kathleen Raine in <hi rend="i">Blake
and Tradition</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1968) and Helen C. White in <hi rend="i">The
Mysticism of William Blake</hi> (Madison: University of Wisconsin Studies in Language and Literature 23,
1927).</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Damon, <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Philosophy and Symbols</hi>;
Percival, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Circle of Destiny</hi>; Bentley, “William Blake and the Alchemical
Philosophers”; Raine, <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition</hi>; and Paley, <hi rend="i">Energy and the
Imagination.</hi> Aubrey’s review of the scholarship is generally sound but not comprehensive.</note>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Occasional reference is made to other poems, especially <hi rend="i">The
Book of Ahania</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> in chapter 2.</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Like Raine, Paley explores many possible sources. See especially his
chapter on “The Lambeth Books” in <hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination: A Study of the Development of
Blake’s Thought</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1970), pp. 61-88.</note></p>
          <p>Although the “element” (or subject) of numerology is not entirely disregarded by Aubrey, it
should have been expanded or rejected. Boehme had faith in the symbolic properties of numbers, explaining the
meaning of 1 to 65 in <hi rend="i">The Answers to Forty Questions Concerning the Soul</hi>,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">13</ref> and Blake was probably impressed. However, 3
and 7, the seminal numbers in Boehme’s system, were anathema to Blake. If in fact, as Aubrey suggests, Blake
learned from Boehme the value of these symbolic constructs, his borrowing may be a prime illustration of
Nurmi’s “negative sources.” We would, of course, be more certain if we had the evidence of annotations
or if we knew how long Blake continued to read Boehme after his first great burst of enthusiasm from about
1790 to 1793. Since numbers are not consistently important in Blake’s work until <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
and do not bear a heavy symbolic burden until <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, it is likely that some new or
renewed interest or source of information excited him to extend the function of the divine numbers.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">14</ref> If so, this source (Thomas Taylor, the
Cabala, or whatever) emphasized the significance of the number 4 and its extensions (especially 16, 32, and
64). By this time certainly—if not long before—Blake had concluded that 3 and its extensions (especially
6, 7, 9, 12, and 27) were pernicious if not downright evil. It is significant that Blake was not greatly
impressed by Boehme’s Seven Properties, Three Principles, Threefold Life, and so on.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">15</ref>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Law, 2: 24-31.</note>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">14</hi> See especially George Mills Harper, “The Divine Tetrad in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Essays for S. Foster Damon</hi>, pp. 235-55; see also Harper and Jane
McClellan, “Blake’s Demonic Triad,” <hi rend="i">The Wordsworth Circle</hi> 8 (spring 1977),
172-82.</note>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Vol. 1 of the Law edition contains <hi rend="i">The Three Principles of
the Divine Essence</hi>; Vol. 2 <hi rend="i">The Threefold Life of Man</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Answers to
Forty Questions Concerning the Soul.</hi> For Aubrey’s discussion of numbers, especially 7, see pp. 20-23,
and 125. Although he comments briefly on the “fourfold nature” of Freher’s designs, Aubrey concludes
that “the similar fourfold nature of Blake’s universe needs little elaboration” (102). Students of the
later Blake should keep in mind that “The Sexual is Threefold: the Human is Fourfold” 
(<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, Bentley, p. 322).</note></p>
          <p>In short, <hi rend="i">Watchmen of Eternity</hi> has not filled the gap or settled the great
argument. Although Aubrey’s brief survey of scholarship and fairly extensive quotations from the rare Law
edition are useful, the reader of his persuasion will prefer to consult Damon, Paley, Raine, and others who
study Blake’s debt to Boehme in the context of his debt to other writers of “the heterodox
tradition.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">16</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake and Tradition</hi>, I, 1. Besides Boehme, Raine has
read widely in and quotes from such esoteric sources as the Cabala, Agrippa, Hermes Trismegistus, Fludd,
Paracelsus, Swedenborg, Jacob Bryant, and Thomas Taylor the Platonist. More modest in their claims, Damon and
Paley have considered most of these.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p21-27" n="27" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
