<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>21.1.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">A Catalogue of the Lawrence Lande William Blake Collection in the Department of
Rare Books and Special Collections of the McGill University Libraries</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1987</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1987</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">21.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Jean H. Hagstrum</name>
              <name>George Mills Harper</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Mary V. Jackson</name>
              <name>Edward Larrissy</name>
              <name>Lousie Lippincott</name>
              <name>Catherine McClenahan</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Peter Otto</name>
              <name>George Anthoy Ross, Jr.</name>
              <name>Charu Sheel Singh</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1987"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_21">
    <body>
	<pb id="p21-33" n="33"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-21-1-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main"><hi rend="i">A Catalogue of the Lawrence Lande William Blake Collection in the
Department of Rare Books and Special Collections of the McGill University Libraries.</hi> Montreal: McLennan
Library, McGill University, 1983. xv + 172 pp. $50.00 Canadian.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">G. E. </hi><name><hi rend="b">Bentley</hi></name>, 
<hi rend="b">Jr.</hi></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>This is a collaborative work, with a foreword by the donor of the nucleus of the collection
Lawrence Lande, a preface by the Blake scholar Christopher Heppner, whose “role . . . has been that of
writing or verifying the annotation” (p. x), and an introduction by the Rare Books Librarian Elizabeth
Lewis, who “organized the cataloguing, most of which was done by Mrs. Rosemary Haddad” (p. x). It is a
large, handsome, oblong work<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">1</ref> in
double columns of admirable Baskerville type, generously leaded, with display pages in red and black, on Japan
paper with deckled edges, with eight sharp reproductions, twenty-four blank pages within the text, and a
“special binding” in an edition limited to five hundred copies signed by the collector, the Director of
the McGill Libraries, the cataloguer, the Rare Book Librarian, the book designer, and the annotator. The
greatest care devoted to the book seems to have been concentrated, successfully, upon the book’s
appearance<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">2</ref> rather than its function
as a work of scholarship. <note id="n23"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Well, yes, I know, all books are oblong. I mean
this one is wider than it is high.</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">2</hi> On the other hand, there is a curious variation in the length of the
columns on a page, differing by as much as six inches (e.g., p. 170).</note></p>
          <p>A few of the lacunae here are easy to identify. There is no index, which makes it surprisingly
difficult to use, nor is there a list of the reproductions, and the unnumbered reproductions themselves are so
enigmatically titled—e.g., “Venus Anadyomene 5.1. B8V4 1805”—as to leave one puzzled about the artist
(Thomas Butts), the medium (water color and ink), and where it is described in the book (p. 129). One may well
wonder who is in charge here.</p>
          <pb id="p21-34" n="34"/>
          <p>The catalogue entries are in standard Library of Congress style (repeated in their entirety for
two or more copies of the same work), without italics or reference to Blake scholarship (though the
“classification [<hi rend="i">is</hi>] based on <hi rend="i">A Blake Bibliography</hi>” of 1964 [pp.
xi-xii]) or cross-references within the text, and they are serviceable and unambitious. They serve chiefly as
a handlist of the collection.</p>
          <p>What then is in the collection? The vast majority consists of secondary works about Blake,
reprints of his writings and pictures, some of it is strikingly ephemeral, such as section 7 on
“Prospectuses, Book Jackets, Post-cards,” and some of it has nothing to do with Blake at all (see, e.g.,
pp. 47, 50-51, 60-61). It is organized as reprints of Blake’s writings (pp. 3-35), book illustrations (pp.
39-68), editions of books Blake read or owned (pp. 71-74), catalogues, biographies, criticism, and scholarship
(pp. 77-126), separate drawings and engravings (pp. 129-47), manuscripts [none by Blake] (pp. 151-53),
miscellanea (pp. 157-59), slides and microfilms (pp. 163-66), and an appendix of books with Blake
illustrations elsewhere in the McGill University Libraries (pp. 169-72).</p>
          <p>There is, of course, a great deal of Blake scholarship and ephemera here, a testimony to much
patient effort and devotion. But the books of scholarship are not very difficult to locate elsewhere, and the
ephemera will interest few besides myself.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25"
type="note">3</ref> For the Blake student, it is of course convenient to have so much gathered in one place.
<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">3</hi> See Christopher Heppner, “Notes on Some Items in the Blake Collection at
McGill,” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>, 10 (1977), 100-108.</note></p>
          <p>One of the chief values of the collection to the scholar is probably in the section of books with
Blake’s illustrations to the works of others, though even here some fifty of the works are modern reprints.
Some of the originals are in duplicate copies, such as Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> of 1808 (3 copies),
Ritson’s <hi rend="i">Select Collection of English Songs</hi> of 1783 (3 sets), Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> of 1797 (2 copies), <hi rend="i">Job</hi> of ?1874 (2 copies), and some are genuinely uncommon,
such as Mora’s <hi rend="i">Meditaciones Poeticas</hi> of 1826, one of three copies traced in 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977), and a unique set of Richardson’s <hi rend="i">Sir Charles Grandison</hi>,
originally published in <hi rend="i">The Novelist’s Magazine</hi> in 1783.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">4</ref> The section of original drawings lists four minor but
interesting Blake drawings, and the section called “Blake 6 Manuscripts” has no manuscript by Blake at all
but does have interesting contemporary manuscripts (unrelated to him) by Fuseli, Joseph Johnson, and others,
as well as some by modern scholars such as Sir Geoffrey Keynes, Foster Damon, and Martin Butlin—it must make
one feel monumental to have one’s correspondence recorded in public institutions during one’s lifetime.
The most interesting such manuscripts are those of Anne Gilchrist, the biographer’s widow. Among the loose
prints are rare and important ones of Lavater, Edmund Pitts, proofs of <hi rend="i">Job</hi> pls. 17 and
19—but the copperplates for an unidentified facsimile of <hi rend="i">Job</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">5</ref> are only referred to glancingly through the proofs pulled
from them in 1969. <note id="n26"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Vol. 1 was published for T. Kelly in 1818, vol. 2 for C.
Cooke probably about 1811. I have a set of the 1811 edition but have not seen a complete set of that of
1818.</note>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">5</hi> See “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> Copperplates,” 
<hi rend="i">Library.</hi> 5S., 26 (1976), 234-41.</note></p>
          <p>In sum, this is an extensive reference collection with a few quite unusual items in it. It is
useful to have a catalogue of the collection, but the items it records and the manner in which it records them
will rarely much concern scholars who are not actually working with the McGill Collections.</p>
          <p>But I must conclude by saying that the work of Christopher Heppner here seems to be solid and
valuable and that I have repeatedly worked in the Lande Collection with profit and gratitude. The staff is
extremely eager to help, and the environment is warm and agreeable. There are great profits to be found at
McGill if one is not led to expect too much.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
