<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>21.1.mcclenahan</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Joanne Witke, William Blake’s Epic: Imagination Unbound</title>
        <author n="McClenahan">Catherine McClenahan</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1987</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1987</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">21.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>Frances A. Carey</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Jean H. Hagstrum</name>
              <name>George Mills Harper</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Mary V. Jackson</name>
              <name>Edward Larrissy</name>
              <name>Lousie Lippincott</name>
              <name>Catherine McClenahan</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Peter Otto</name>
              <name>George Anthoy Ross, Jr.</name>
              <name>Charu Sheel Singh</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1987"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_21">
    <body>
	<pb id="p21-21" n="21"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-21-1-0007">
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Joanne Witke, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Epic: Imagination Unbound.</hi>
New York: St. Martin’s Press, 1986. ii+231 pp. $27.50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Catherine</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">McClenahan</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Joanne Witke, who has previously published articles on Blake’s connection to Bishop Berkeley
and on the synoptic Gospels as a structural model for <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> combines these approaches in her book-length reading of this
poem as Blake’s creation of a “System” designed to oppose that of Joshua Reynolds. Since Witke sees this
system as solving a philosophical problem whose “formal categories are literary,” her aim is to
demonstrate the poem’s “philosophical nucleus,” its operation as an epic, and Blake’s aesthetic
principles (prefatory note). She combines philosophical and aesthetic issues to form three arguments: first,
that Reynolds’ aesthetics are
<pb id="p21-22" n="22"/>
founded on the natural philosophy of Bacon, Newton, and, especially though tacitly, Locke; second, that
“whether or not Blake used Berkeley as a quarry,” <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s system “discloses
striking similarities to Berkeley’s critique of natural philosophy, to the principles of his system, and to
his defense of it” (217); third, that these philosophical themes structure a narrative in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (based on copy D). Hence, in Witke’s summary:
<q>
Los’s labors consist largely of exposing false principles of art based on natural philosophy and their
consequences for the nation; denouncing the fallacy of confusing morality with abstract science; liberating
human creativity from material forces; unravelling nets of abstract reasonings; opening up the narrowed
senses; and, not least, bringing to light the true principles based on the sensuous imagination. (220)
</q>
	<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> “<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>: A Synoptic Poem,” 
<hi rend="i">Comparative Literature</hi> (summer, 1970): 265-78; and “Blake’s Tree of Knowledge Grows Out of
The Enlightenment,” <hi rend="i">Enlightenment Essays</hi> 3 (1972): 71-84.</note></p>
          <p>Parts 1 and 2 of the book introduce the philosophical and aesthetic arguments. The prologue
covers Blake’s philosophical relationships to Berkeley and Plato; “Blake as Artist” examines the
influence of Plato and Locke on Reynolds, paralleling Blake’s conflict with Reynolds to Berkeley’s with
Locke. Parts 3 through 5 divide the commentary on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s first chapter into analyses
of Albion’s condition, its causes, and Los’s efforts to improve it.</p>
          <p>Part 3, “Attacks upon <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,” adds the argument that 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is a non-classical epic framed by the four-part Gospel structure: a choice that lends
the poem an “increased authenticity, sublimity and pathos but also apocalyptic significance,” befitting
its epic aim to rescue England from a state of ruin “most contributed to” by natural religion and morality
(35, 37). Specific explication covers the opening address, the narrator’s comments on Lockean principles in
plates 5 and 10, and Albion’s rejection of Jerusalem for Vala in plates 18-25. Part 4, “The Satanic
Triumvirate,” interrupts sequential explication in order to sketch the horrors of Bacon, Newton and Locke as
Coban, Hand, and Hyle. Part 5, “Defenders of Jerusalem,” returns to the poem’s first chapter to discuss
the conflict of Los and the Spectre as Blake’s argument with Reynolds, as well as the nature of Golgonooza,
and Los’s speech in plate 17. Parts 6 through 8 (“Encounters with the Enemy,” “Grim War Continues,”
and “Jerusalem Restored”), sequentially explicate the poem’s remaining three chapters, briefly noting
their links to the Gospels of Mark, Luke and John, respectively; chapter 1 is linked to Matthew. Part 9, an
epilogue, recapitulates Witke’s main arguments. The book includes black and white reproductions: 
<hi rend="i">The Meeting of a Family in Heaven</hi> and twenty plates from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></p>
          <p>Witke’s book addresses relevant questions. Although other scholars have investigated the
influence of Berkeley or Reynolds on Blake’s art, none has related them to specific works in this kind of
detail, and there are few book-length studies of this important poem. The strict parameters of her approach to
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> are a heuristic device often employed to understand something complex. In this
case, the method helps us to recognize contexts of the poem that readers may not know, and to see why Blake
might have found the ideas of Reynolds and Berkeley to be especially useful focal points. The book shows how
specific philosophical and aesthetic principles apply even where the poem’s action appears to concern
something else. Witke’s explications of how Blake also uses biblical analogies to these principles can be
clear and helpful, as in the treatment of Los’s shaping of Reuben. The philosophical analogies to
Berkeley’s thought are supported with a wealth of direct quotation. These quotations, like those from
Reynolds, Bacon, Newton, and Locke, also provide instances of terms we recognize as significant in Blake
(though without comment on possible variants in meaning): e.g., “particulars” (and “particularities,”
“minute particulars”), “energy,” “contraction and expansion,” “unfolding,” “emanation” and
“spectre.”</p>
          <p>At the same time, however, Blake’s actual practice in verbal and visual art tries to make us
aware of both the powerful allure and the dangers of such a heuristic. At times Witke’s concentration on
aesthetics leads only to more confusion about why the text says what it does; at others it may seem to work,
but in fact significantly distorts a poem whose particulars resist condensation into one system. Thus while
Witke examines legitimate contexts for the poem, the book has puzzling and even troubling aspects.</p>
          <p>For one thing, this book does less than one might expect to situate itself within existing
scholarship on Blake’s attitude toward Reynolds or the philosophers in the footnotes or the opening section;
there is no bibliography. In other cases previous work is dismissed in a casual or misleading manner.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> Such exclusionary tendencies reflect a more
fundamental conceptual problem: <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Epic</hi> exemplifies a reductive and
old-fashioned version of intellectual history, which casts Bacon, Newton, and Locke (and therefore Reynolds)
as pure mechanists, the Bad Guys, utterly opposed to the creative Good Guys. Witke acknowledges that Blake
sometimes agreed with Reynolds (e.g., 23), but she never shows how Blake’s attitude toward the philosophers
could be more than simple rejection. Bacon, Newton, and Locke are regarded exclusively from Berkeley’s point
of view. Elsewhere Witke claims that we may consult not the poem itself but Berkeley “for a straightforward
philosophical exposition” of the “essential metaphysical beliefs” (120) Blake shares with him.
Similarly, Blake is not shown to disagree with Berkeley about anything. For example, one paragraph summarizes
an indeterminate number of preceding ones with the claim that “In all of this, Blake agrees with Berkeley”
(against Plato) and promptly cites the first part of Blake’s annotation to <hi rend="i">Siris</hi>, p. 214:
“Knowledge is not by deduction but Immediate by Perception or Sense at once” (Witke, 9). But this
<pb id="p21-23" n="23"/>
very annotation registers a point of dissent. Berkeley writes:
<q>
By experiments of sense we become acquainted with the lower faculties of the soul; and from them, whether by
<hi rend="i">a gradual evolution or ascent</hi>, we arrive at the highest. These become subjects for fancy to
work upon. <hi rend="i">Reason considers and judges of the imaginations.</hi> And these acts become new
objects to the understanding. (emphasis added)
</q>
Thus Blake appears to disagree with Berkeley as well as Plato. He denies knowledge as a sequential process and
as deduction, reiterating in the following sentence, which Witke does not include: “Christ addresses himself
to the Man not to his Reason.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> For example, the brief comments on Northrop Frye (2, n. 5), or W. J. T.
Mitchell (221, n. 2).</note>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> My Blake citations are from David V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Complete
Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi> (Garden City: Anchor Press/Doubleday, 1982), 664. Leopold Damrosch,
Jr., also argues for Blake’s divergence from Berkeley in this annotation. See <hi rend="i">Symbol and Truth
in Blake’s Myth</hi> (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1980) 16, 141.</note></p>
          <p>This kind of reduction and opposition characterizes the book in other ways as well. Witke
carefully acknowledges that her study does not say “everything that needs to be said” about 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> But later statements specifically <hi rend="i">exclude</hi> the possibility of other
contexts or meanings for given speeches and actions—notably when gender and sexuality are involved. In
discussing, for example, the “seemingly absurd” metaphors of “Uncircumcision” and “Chastity,”
which “refer to corporeal substance and abstract ideas” as applied to Reynolds, Witke asserts that
“these two doctrines—generating bodies and purity of conception—<hi rend="i">account for</hi> the
remarkable persistence of sexual imagery in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>” (emphasis added). She makes this
claim, unnecessarily extreme even given the terms of her argument, in trying to highlight “Reynolds’ ideal
of ‘unadulterated’ and simple forms, which he consolidates in the phrase ‘simple chaste nature’ ”
(81). But Reynolds is not just highlighted here; he becomes the necessary and sufficient cause for everything
in the poem. Similarly, on plate 88, “the issue between Los and Enitharmon concerns power of the artist, not
power of the sexes” (196).</p>
          <p>In fact, many of the explications involving <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s females raise more
questions than they answer, but here the problem may also have another source. In theory, Witke’s approach
should allow for two kinds of conflict which the poem invites us to see: in Witke’s terms, the externalized
conflict between “the inspired artist” and critics of Reynolds’ persuasion, and the internal conflict of
the artist whose imagination has been influenced by an aesthetics based on natural philosophy and morality.
The mere conflation or intermixing of these two kinds of conflict, even within a single sentence, frequently
produces confusing accounts of the nature and actions of the Spectre and of the emanations or daughters in the
poem. For example, glossing the line, “the Feminine / Emanations Create Space. the Masculine Create Time,
&amp; plant / The Seeds of beauty in the Space” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 85:7-9), is the following account of
the act of creation (which is the same as perception, according to the argument elsewhere):
<q>
The impulse to create emanates from within the artist; the divine power of imagination perceives tangible
objects in visionary form, presenting to the poet/artist ideas which he shapes according to his genius and
artistic purpose into a work of art. The daughters here function as muses, providing Los with sensuous
material for embodying eternity in spacetime. . . . (193)
</q>
The unified character of perception/creation, as well as the unity of imagination and reality that Witke
everywhere argues for on Berkeleyan grounds, suddenly splits with an imagination that “presents” ideas to
the artist and with the daughters or emanations read as separate “muses” who “provide” Los with
material in the second sentence. (Here Los apparently refers only to the artist, not to imagination: the
scenario is only external conflict.)</p>
          <p>One extended example might better explain this kind of confusion and reductiveness in relation to
the book’s third argument, about the narrative of Los’s labors to save Albion. I agree with Witke that
there is a narrative in the poem (though not that synchronic arguments are “wrong”), but I have deep
reservations about the interpretation of Los that she provides in her account. Let me take the turning-point
of this narrative. Like Witke, I would locate it specifically at the beginning of plate 92, but also more
broadly as the section between 86:50 and 93:27—Los’s last confrontations with Enitharmon and the
Spectre.</p>
          <p>Like most readers, Witke associates the Spectre who is “the author” of Los’s and
Enitharmon’s “divisions &amp; shrinkings” (88:35) with “abstract reasoning.” This form of reason,
she adds, “has come between the artist’s inspirations and his works” (which suggests a conflict within
the artist’s imagination), “labeling them immoral, licentious, unscientific” (which suggests external
judgments on the artist’s work; 197). Likewise the divided Enitharmon is “the artist’s life-giving
substance, his faculty of creativity” (194); and she then is further described as “a disciple of Vala,”
affected by natural philosophy, and thus as having “joined Albion’s daughters” (197, 195). Now both
characterizations suggest internal division (though the second is ambiguous); the oddity, however, is that Los
remains utterly unfazed by this conflict.</p>
          <p>Los now represents only the artist in an external conflict, who holds to “spiritual
perception” and so he merely “refuses to submit,” “becomes more assertive,” and finally “smites
the Spectre until he overcomes him” (194-203, passim). In this reading, the Spectre whose senses and
“every Ratio of his reason” are altered by these blows also becomes an unambiguously external figure or
system. Given such attacks on the false system or its representative, it is creditable that “this action
signals a visible turning-point in the war” (203). For Witke, the specific signal is Los’s vision of
“the Briton Saxon Roman Norman amalgamating / . . . into One Nation the English”
<pb id="p21-24" n="24"/>
(92:1-2; only the last five words are quoted). By sticking to a scenario of divinely inspired artist at war
with a system of natural philosophy, morality, and art, Witke can read the situation here as purely positive,
“foretokening . . . resurrection, the end of warfare and a state of concord” (203) in England. As a
result, Los needs only one last “strong reproof of Reynolds’ system” (in 93:18-26) in order for
Albion/England to wake and espouse the poet’s system (204).</p>
          <p>This narrative account raises many questions. For example, if “amalgamating / . . . into One
Nation the English” is unequivocally good, what should we make of Los’s statement that “this 
<hi rend="i">sinful</hi> Nation Created in our Furnaces &amp; Looms is Albion” (92:6; emphasis added)? Could Los
be acknowledging a “sin” (aesthetic or philosophical) which at this point he also knows how to
“forgive”? Is “nation” an unquestionably positive term in the poem? Why have earlier “reproofs,”
“smitings” of the Spectre, or articulations of a counter-system not succeeded in waking Albion before? How
has an artist divided “from his creative faculty” continued to operate without making a false step
anywhere? Has the Los who spends a great deal of time uttering loud threats or smiting a Spectre really
conquered “my Pride &amp; Self-righteousness” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 8:30) or won “the war” by anything
other than successful bullying?</p>
          <p>As far as I can tell, the answers to all but the first question about the narrative argument
outlined above depend on one more contradictory aspect of this book and on Witke’s fundamental argument
about “Vision.”</p>
          <p>First, Witke notes that “the existence and nature of God are related issues” in an artistic
system predicated on “a vital creative eternal spirit”; often, and quite rightly, she stresses that
Berkeley’s <hi rend="i">spirit</hi> or Blake’s <hi rend="i">imagination</hi> is “a substance we share
with the Creator, making us one with him” (152, 119). But the relative inattention to internal conflict
evident in Witke’s reading works in conjunction with a de-emphasis of God as Imagination. Witke’s phrasing
often suggests a dualistic system of a transcendental divinity who acts on human beings: the combination of
the frequently repeated phrase “divinely inspired” (artist, poet, Los) with references to Los as “an
agent of God’s intervention in the transformation of human history” (173) or to a “revelation . . .
imparted by God to prophets” (14-15). The transcendent divinity implied by such phrasing would explain
Los’s righteous threats, his ability to avoid mistakes, and the timing of his “victory” over his
“enemies,” but it seems very much at odds with the radical Incarnationalism of “God. the Human
Imagination” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 5:20; not cited), and with Witke’s overt argument for immanence
elsewhere.</p>
          <p>Second, if I am correctly understanding a complex argument scattered through several chapters of
explication, Witke’s description of Blake’s adaptation of Berkeley’s theory of “Vision” would help
explain why words like “nation” or Blakean constructs like Beulah are interpreted in only one, positive
way—and indeed why <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Epic</hi> produces a schematic reading of the poem. This
argument is too long even to outline fully, but the key point is made in the closing summary. 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s “poetic argument proceeds almost exclusively by bare and naked ideas perceived
by imagination”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> (as opposed to
abstractions constructed by reason): that is, by “a visual quality” that “reflects the language of
determinate objects and <hi rend="i">directs</hi> the variable meanings of words” (221, emphasis added).
This recalls the earlier argument that Blake agreed with Berkeley’s idea that “the universal language is .
. . not linguistic but visionary: ‘objects of Vision constitute the Universal Language of Nature” (Witke,
123, citing Berkeley’s <hi rend="i">Theory of Vision</hi>, 147). Therefore, “for both men visual forms are
a metaphysical preference” over verbal language and so, for Blake, illustration “avoids indefiniteness”
(124). In short, Witke’s reliance on Berkeley leads her to the highly debatable positions that verbal
language cannot be both multivalent and particularized, and that the illustrations are intended to be
univalent. <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Readers can locate the details of this argument by referring to
“Bare and naked forms,” “Particulars,” and “Vision” in the index.</note></p>
          <p>In the example of plate 92, then, not only does Witke’s single positive reading of “nation”
fit the context of “Blake’s system vs. Reynolds’ system,” but such a reading also fits a Berkeleyan,
and thus supposedly Blakean, concept of <hi rend="i">particular forms.</hi> This assumption would then seem to
“direct” Witke’s own repeated description of Blake’s aim in this epic: e.g., “to ensure the
nation’s greatness and lasting fame” (219-20), presuming a nationalistic bias which some readers will
certainly question, and which, in any case, sounds remarkably like the political agenda that informs
Reynolds’ aesthetic arguments.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> In
fact, a whole discourse of division and opposition that Witke clearly associates with natural philosophy and
morality is unselfconsciously adopted in her constant reliance on words like “nation,” “enemies,”
“defenders,” and “war” to characterize the poem’s narrative, just as the approach takes on a kind of
“mechanistic” rigidity associated with Reynolds and the “Satanic Triumvirate.” 
<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> A quotation from Reynolds’ first discourse, that it is “‘necessary to the security of
society, that the mind should be elevated to the idea of general beauty . . .’ ” (38), implies the
political dimension of Reynolds’ aesthetics that becomes even more pronounced after the French Revolution.
(For this connection, I am indebted to John Barrell’s lecture on “Reynolds and the Political Theory of
Painting” at the 1986 MWASECS Conferences at Northwestern University.) However, Witke’s prefatory note
warns that it is not her aim to consider political issues, and the reliance on Berkeley restricts England’s
“crisis” to its metaphysical and aesthetic aspects only.</note></p>
          <p>Such tendencies are only reinforced by omitting to define a Gospel-based or Christian epic and
its differences from classical epic, or <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>’s difference from the Miltonic form of
Christian epic. As a result, the question of how even Christian epic could tend to legitimize concepts of
exclusion and enmity—concepts which Witke describes Blake’s system as opposing—is not overtly
considered, though relevant to arguments about his epic aims. For Blake’s “system” does more than
“forgive” vanquished enemies (209); it dismantles a system of “enemies” who strive for victory or
“dominion.” Like Los, the poet strives to persuade himself as well as others to a new kind of
seeing/creating: to a recognition that
<pb id="p21-25" n="25"/>
the work of “enemies” like Bacon, Newton, and Locke, or Milton, Shakespeare, and Chaucer, always have been
emanations of Jerusalem, however unconscious or distorted. If we do focus on narrative, it seems no accident
that when Albion “wakes,” “war” becomes a “conversation” that can begin only with a perceiver who
transforms enemies into fellow incarnations of a human form divine.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">William Blake’s Epic</hi>, then, is not the best introduction for newcomers to the
poem or to an investigation of Blake’s attitudes towards Berkeley and Reynolds. But the benefits it can
provide will be most obvious to alert readers who can, as Blake urged, both see and forgive what they do not
approve, and honor its author for the energetic exertion of her talent.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
