<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>21.2.dorrbecker</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="checklist">Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Recent Publications</title>
        <author n="Dörrbecker">Detlef W. Dörrbecker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1987</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1987</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">21.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Hazard Adams</name>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Catherine Haigney</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1987"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_21">
    <body>
    <pb id="p21-52" n="52"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-21-2-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Recent Publications</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">D.W.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">DÖRRBECKER</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>Because of my own reluctance to part with what I considered an unfinished compilation, and because
of <hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi> move to Rochester, it proved to be impossible to publish the 1984-1986
checklist in its accustomed place, viz. number two of the previous volume. When it appeared in the subsequent
winter issue, it was agreed that we would resume publication of this continuing checklist of Blake-related
scholarship in the fall issue of each volume. This left me with no more than ten weeks until the final
typescript for the present 1986-1987 compilation had to be mailed to the production office if there was to be
any chance to bring the checklist back on schedule again.</p>
        <p>Except for the decisions concerning research strategies, the bibliographer’s job is by necessity
devoid of much innovative thinking; but then, the time, the care, and the scrupulous scrutiny bestowed upon
such work will be decisive for the usefulness, i.e., the completeness and reliability, of the resulting
compilation. Now, from what I have said it should be evident that I wasn’t in a precisely ideal position to
achieve the best of what may have been possible in the 1986-1987 edition of “Blake and His Circle.” At the
time I posted my typescript, some twenty omissions were known to me which will have to wait for a listing
until next year. Therefore, I have to plead for the indulgence of authors and readers alike, who may look in
vain here for an entry for this or that 1986 publication.</p>
        <p>Shortage of time, as well as the scarcity of <hi rend="i">critical</hi> comments on what had been
published in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 20 (1986-87): 76-100, prevented me from introducing any significant
changes in the general organization of the entries in four main sections and their various subdivisions. I
have even stuck to the same few deviations from the <hi rend="i">MLA Style Manual</hi>’s citation rules and
have, e.g., quoted articles in the <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> by reference to the volume number
rather than by month, even though this journal is published twelve times a year. (In my experience this is a
more rational, at least a more convenient style, since the separate issues will eventually be bound and
shelved with the volume designation on the spine, while the information on the original month of publication
can only be determined by laboriously searching—in this particular case—as many as eight hundred pages of
the volume for the issue-titles.) However, the decision to adopt the arrangement of previous checklists as a
model is not intended to render obsolete what I have said concerning the problems inherent in this structure
in my introduction to the previous checklist. On the contrary, I would like to renew my invitation for all
sorts of critical suggestions that may help to make these annual compilations more profitable and easier to
use for the majority of their readers.</p>
        <p>The present list covers those Blake-related publications that have come to my knowledge in the
period between summer 1986 and May 1987, with—yet again, and especially so in part III—the addition of a
considerable number of earlier, hitherto unrecorded contributions. At the same time, I wish to point out that
many periodicals are a far cry from being on their official time schedule, so that a “1985” reference may
well relate to the issue of a journal which, in fact, did not appear in print until 1986 or, in a few cases,
even as late as 1987. At least in this respect, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> is a rather rare exception to the
rule.</p>
        <p>I have searched, for this year’s list, all the 1985-87 issues of more than 500 journals in the
fields of art history, bibliography, history, literary criticism and linguistics, philosophy, and political
science. This, I hope, will sound impressive enough, but I have to add that the journals actually examined did
not represent the selection I would have used if unhampered by the limitations of the holdings of those
libraries I have had to work with. For example, I had no access to journals such as the <hi rend="i">Charles
Lamb Bulletin, Christianity and Literature, Philosophy and Literature</hi>, and many others which are likely
to publish articles and reviews that are of interest for Blake studies. Here then, I was dependent either on
the generosity of authors who have kindly sent offprints, or on references I traced in the bibliographies
compiled by others. Working on what may be said to be an outer orbit of Blake scholarship has certain
advantages, but it also
<pb id="p21-53" n="53"/>
will have to account for certain shortcomings of which I am fully aware. Furthermore, I have to admit that
besides the <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi>, the <hi rend="i">London</hi> and the <hi rend="i">New
York Review of Books</hi>, and the <hi rend="i">New Statesman</hi>, biweekly and weekly periodicals or even
daily newspapers have not been systematically searched. Moreover, let me stress the fact that there is no
computerized bibliographic programming behind this list which, on the contrary, retains all the
characteristics—both positive and negative—of a fully custom-built, singlehanded product: it may be less
uniform in style, it may be less complete than, e.g., the <hi rend="i">MLA International Bibliography</hi>
which, I suppose, profits from all the technical and financial backing one can possibly imagine, but it
remains more timely and more open in its scope than such a hi-tech compilation.</p>
        <p>Despite the comparatively short period I report on in the present list, and to my own surprise, the
number of entries is an astonishingly large one. This, in part, may be due to some hype in the Related
Interest section for which I would have to assume responsibility. The inclusion, for example, of various
studies of the works of W.B. Yeats, or—even more conspicuously—of the many items concerned with the
literary rather than the critical productions of Arthur Symons is certainly problematic in a checklist that is
primarily devoted to scholarly materials for the study of Blake and his circle. If, in the end, I have decided
to be extensive rather than exclusive in coverage for the present list, this ought to be seen as an attempt to
find out whether readers think of these entries as a mere nuisance and a waste of their precious time, or
whether these listings may be considered a welcome addition to the standard curriculum of parts I, II, and
IV.</p>
        <p>Neither these introductory notes nor the following list will supply absorbing reading; I hope,
however, that even as it is the annual checklist will prove a useful research tool for following up a wide
variety of interests in the field. It would have been less complete and accurate than it actually is, had I
not enjoyed the help of a considerable number of publishing houses as well as communication with many friends
and colleagues. While the former have generously supplied inspection copies of their publications and have
thus helped to prevent misleading information from creeping into the list (such as the mistake that is
recorded in my note to #117, below), the latter freely gave of their time, their expertise, and—very
often—their stock of offprints in reply to my enquiries; I gratefully thank Bryan Aubrey, Rodney Baine,
Stephen Behrendt, G. E. Bentley, Jr., David Bindman, Ewa Borkowska, Sebastian Carter, Brendan Donnellan,
Morris Eaves, Robert Essick, Mark Greenberg, Wendy Greenhouse, Nelson Hilton, James Hogg, Seymour Howard,
Georg Kamp, Jenijoy La Belle, James McCord, Morton Paley, Henry Summerfield, Dennis Welch, and Bette Charlene
Werner. Patricia Neill, who has also been responsible for the compilation of the author index, has been
expertly supervising the production of the checklist and, moreover, has coped with my stop-press corrections
with both patience and efficiency. 
                        <p><hi rend="i">Note: Items which I have not been able to examine personally are
preceded by an asterisk.</hi></p></p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part I<lb/>
William Blake</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Editions, Translations, Facsimilies, Reproductions</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>1. *Bindman, David, ed. <hi rend="i">Colour Versions of William Blake’s Book of Job Designs
from the Circle of John Linnell: Facsimilies of the New Zealand and Collins Sets and the Fitzwilliam
Plates.</hi> London: William Blake Trust, 1987. [A limited edition of 387 copies, produced under the direction
of the late Arnold Fawcus by the Trianon Press. Contains a detailed analysis and comparison of the color
versions by Bo Ossian Lindberg. While this is entitled “The Authenticity of the New Zealand Set and of the
Coloured Engravings,” Lindberg of course argues that the colored versions of the engraved 
<hi rend="i">Job</hi> designs are “authentic” works which were executed by members of the Linnell circle and
in the actual production of which Blake had no direct participation whatsoever. The Collins and Fitzwilliam
Museum sets of the hand-tinted engravings are here reproduced in full for the first time. All the facsimile
plates have been colored by hand through stencils, employing the same processes as in earlier Blake Trust
facsimilies of the illuminated books. A full descriptive prospectus of the edition is available upon request;
see #2, the companion volume to <hi rend="i">Colour Versions</hi>, for details.]</p>
            <p>2. Bindman, David, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s</hi> Illustrations of the Book of Job:
<hi rend="i">The Engravings and Related Material with Essays, Catalogue of States and Printings, Commentary on
the Plates and Documentary Record.</hi> 2 vols. London: William Blake Trust, 1987. [This limited edition of
387 copies has been in gestation since 1969; its publication marks an important contribution to Blake
scholarship and, in an admittedly pathetic sense, is a tribute to the late Sir Geoffrey Keynes and the late
Arnold Fawcus and their commitment to the task of making Blake’s works available in highly reliable
facsimile editions. The text volume contains essays by the editor and by Keynes; Barbara Bryant contributes
“A Documentary and Bibliographic Record” on the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> designs (103-47), and Robert N.
Essick an essay on the graphic form of the engravings with a complete “Catalogue of Their States and
Printings” (35-101). The fascicules with the facsimile plates contain monochrome reproductions of the
preparatory drawings, the related
<pb id="p21-54" n="54"/>
watercolor paintings, and the engravings in proof state; these are accompanied by a plate-by-plate commentary
on “The Meaning of Blake’s Job” by Bo Lindberg. Together with its companion volume (see #1), this
edition presents a fully revised and updated version of the magnificent 1935 facsimile of 
<hi rend="i">Job</hi>, edited by Keynes and Binyon for the Pierpont Morgan Library. A full description of the
work, together with a sample of the plates which were printed by the Trianon Press under the direction of
Fawcus, is available in a prospectus; address your request to the William Blake Trust, 90 Great Russell
Street, London WC1B 3PY, England.]</p>
            <p>3. *<hi rend="i">1987 Blake Calendar.</hi> San Marino, CA: Huntington Library, [1986]. $15.95.
[Includes twelve full-color reproductions from watercolors and illuminated books by Blake in the Henry E.
Huntington Library and Art Gallery.]</p>
            <p>4. *Porter, Peter, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> The Illustrated Poets. Oxford, Oxon.:
Oxford UP, 1986. £4.95.</p>
            <p>5. *Scott, John. <hi rend="i">The Poetical Works.</hi> London, 1782. Aldershot, Hants.: Gregg
International, 1969. £35.00. [A facsimile reprint, including reproductions of the four engravings executed by
Blake from designs by Thomas Stothard. Though published long ago, this reprint has, to the best of my
knowledge, never been recorded in a Blake bibliography; see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977)
#494A, and Easson and Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake: Book Illustrator</hi> (vol. 2, 1979) #XXIII.]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Bibliographies, Bibliographical Essays, Catalogues</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>6. Auerbach, Nina. “Recent Studies in the Nineteenth Century.” <hi rend="i">Studies in
English Literature 1500-1800</hi> 24 (1984): 769-94. [Contains brief reviews of Crehan’s <hi rend="i">Blake
in Context</hi>, Hilton’s <hi rend="i">Literal Imagination</hi>, Adams’s <hi rend="i">Philosophy of the
Literary Symbolic</hi>, Deen’s <hi rend="i">Conversing in Paradise</hi>, Webster’s <hi rend="i">Blake’s
Prophetic Psychology</hi>, and Paley’s <hi rend="i">Continuing City</hi> on 773-75.]</p>
            <p>7. *Bennett, Shelley M. <hi rend="i">British Narrative Drawings and Watercolors 1660-1880:
Twenty-two Examples from the Huntington Collection.</hi> Exh. cat. San Marino, CA: Huntington Library,
1986.</p>
            <p>8. Borck, Jim Springer, ed. <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A Current Bibliography</hi> ns
8 for 1982. New York, NY: AMS P, 1986. $67.50. [For Blake entries see 384-94 and the indices. The more
extensive and signed reviews in this annotated bibliography are listed separately in part IV, where this
volume is referred to in abbreviated form as “<hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 8 (1982).”]</p>
            <p>9. Dorment, Richard. “William Blake 1757-1827.” <hi rend="i">British Painting in the
Philadelphia Museum of Art: From the Seventeenth through the Nineteenth Century.</hi> London: Weidenfeld, for
the Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1986. 28-35. [Briefly describes and catalogues the museum’s holdings of
paintings by Blake; “The Nativity” is reproduced in color. The same catalogue presents chapters on Linnell
(212-16), Opie (248-52), Romney (306-51, a fine and important collection), and William Bell Scott
(366-71).]</p>
            <p>10. Dörrbecker, D. W. “Blake and His Circle: A Checklist of Recent Publications.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 76-100. [Attempts to cover the period from summer
1984 to early summer 1986; the present compilation, however, contains a considerable number of addenda.]</p>
            <p>11. *Griffiths, Antony, and Reginald Williams. <hi rend="i">The Department of Prints and
Drawings in the British Museum: User’s Guide.</hi> London: British Museum Publications, 1986. £10.00. [A
new general introduction to the Print Room, replacing A. E. Popham’s <hi rend="i">Handbook</hi> of 1939.
This guide will be of great help to those visitors among our readers whose research interests cannot be
satisfied by simply applying to see this or that item from the “Blake cupboard.”]</p>
            <p>12. Jaffé, Michael, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake and His Contemporaries.</hi> [Cat. of] A
Loan Exhibition in Aid of the Friends of the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge at Wildenstein’s, London. 11
June-11 July 1986. Cambridge, Cambs.: Fitzwilliam Museum Enterprises, 1986. [Compiled by Craig Hartley,
Patricia Jaffé, Jane Munro, and David Scrase, this exhibition catalogue describes and illustrates 68 items by
Blake, Romney, Mortimer, Fuseli, and Flaxman from the Fitzwilliam collection. No less than 43 pages from
Blake’s illuminated books are reproduced in color, some of them chosen to contrast the coloring of the same
plate in various copies, and the rest reproducing the Fitzwilliam copies of <hi rend="i">America</hi> (O) and
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (K) in full.]</p>
            <p>13. *Jordan, Frank, ed. <hi rend="i">English Romantic Poets: A Review of Research and
Criticism.</hi> 4th rev. ed. New York, NY: Modern Language Association of America, 1985. $49.50 cloth / $22.50
paper. [Replaces the 1972 edition and includes, for the first time, a chapter on William Blake, written by
Mary Lynn Johnson.]</p>
            <p>14. Mell, Donald C., Jr. “William Blake (1757-1827).” <hi rend="i">English Poetry,
1660-1800: A Guide to Information Sources.</hi> American Literature, English Literature, and World Literatures
in English: An Information Guide Series 40. Detroit, MI: Gale Research, 1982. 106-33. [This section lists some
150 references to standard Blake literature. Other chapters are devoted to basic Cowper and Young scholarship
(161-68 and 421-25).]</p>
            <p>15. Modern Language Association of America. <hi rend="i">1985 MLA International Bibliography of
Books and Articles on the Modern Languages and Literatures: Classified Listings.</hi> Vol. 1. New York, NY:
Modern Language Association of America, 1986. 56-57. [Blake entries are listed as #2192-234; see also s.v.
“Blake” in vol. 1 of the subject index for further references.]</p>
            <pb id="p21-55" n="55"/>
            <p>16. Newey, Vincent, Bryan Burns, and Philip Dodd. “The Nineteenth Century: Romantic
Period.” <hi rend="i">The Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 64 (1983). Ed. Laurel Brake. London: Murray;
Atlantic Highlands, NJ: Humanities P; for the English Association, 1986. 326-53. [See 327-32 for Newey’s
summary review of 1983 Blake scholarship, and the index for some further references to Blake.]</p>
            <p>17. Reiman, Donald H. “Recent Studies in the Nineteenth Century.” <hi rend="i">Studies in
English Literature 1500-1800</hi> 25 (1985): 885-932. [Briefly reviews Di Salvo’s <hi rend="i">War of
Titans</hi>, John Howard’s <hi rend="i">Infernal Poetics</hi>, and Hoagwood’s <hi rend="i">Philosophy of
Mind</hi> on 892-93.]</p>
            <p>18. Smith, Margaret M. “William Blake 1757-1827.” <hi rend="i">Index of English Literary
Manuscripts.</hi> Vol. 3: “1700-1800—Part I: Addison—Fielding.” London: Mansell, 1986. 33-34.</p>
            <p>19. Smith, Michael, with the assistance of Mary Jean DeMarr, eds. <hi rend="i">Annual
Bibliography of English Language and Literature</hi> 58 for 1983. London: Modern Humanities Research
Association, 1986. [Blake entries appear on 330-35 as #5844-944.]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Critical Studies</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>20. Adams, Hazard. “The Dizziness of Freedom; or, Why I Read William Blake.” 
<hi rend="i">College English</hi> 48 (1986): 431-43.</p>
            <p>21. *Allis, U. J. L. “William Blake’s Concept of Vision.” Diss. U of Manchester,
1981.</p>
            <p>22. Aubrey, Bryan. <hi rend="i">Watchmen of Eternity: Blake’s Debt to Jacob Boehme.</hi>
Lanham, MD: UP of America, 1986. $28.50 cloth / $14.00 paper. [This book began as a Ph.D. thesis on “The
Influence of Jacob Boehme on the Work of William Blake,” which was accepted at the U of Durham in 1982.]</p>
            <p>23. Baine, Rodney M., with the assistance of Mary R. Baine. <hi rend="i">The Scattered
Portions: William Blake’s Biological Symbolism.</hi> Athens, GA: privately printed, 1986. $24.95 / special
library rate $19.95, including postage and packing. [Studies Blake’s use of biological symbols such as
animal, insect, reptilian, and of his botanical images. Distributed by the author, <hi rend="i">c/o</hi> Dept.
of English, U of Georgia, Athens, GA 30602, and by Agee Publishing, P.O. Box 526, Athens, GA 30603.]</p>
            <p>24. Balfour, Ian Grant. “The Rhetoric of Romantic Prophecy.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation
Abstracts International</hi> 47 (1986): 1313A. Yale U. [“This thesis addresses the rhetorical,
epistemological, and political issues involved in the reading and writing of prophecy in English and German
literature of the Romantic period. . . . The Blake chapter (on <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>) focuses on the
dynamics of reading and writing in a prophetic <hi rend="i">tradition</hi>, and demonstrates that prophecy
cannot be thought of as ‘unmediated vision,’ because it is shown to be an intensely citational discourse
that depends on the generality and opacity of figurative language as its driving force.”]</p>
            <p>25. *Barrell, John. <hi rend="i">The Political Theory of Painting from Reynolds to Hazlitt:
“The Body of the Public.”</hi> New Haven, CT: Yale UP, 1986. $30.00 / £16.95. [Includes a chapter on
Blake’s contribution to such a political theory of art.]</p>
            <p>26. Behrendt, Stephen C. “‘The Consequence of High Powers’: Blake, Shelley, and
Prophecy’s Public Dimension.” <hi rend="i">Papers on Language and Literature</hi> 22 (1986): 254-75.</p>
            <p>27. Bellin, Harvey F., and Darrell Ruhl, eds. <hi rend="i">Blake and Swedenborg: Opposition Is
True Friendship: The Sources of William Blake’s Arts in the Writings of Emanuel Swedenborg.</hi> New York,
N.Y.: Swedenborg Foundation, 1985. $8.95 paper. [Besides an introduction by George F. Dole, biographical notes
on Swedenborg and Blake, and three pages of “‘Correspondences’: Corresponding Ideas from Swedenborg’s
and Blake’s Writings,” this “Anthology” republishes discussions of Blake’s Swedenborgian connections
by Raymond H. Deck, Jr., Donald C. Fitzpatrick, Jr., Alexander Gilchrist, Robert Hindmarsh, Herbert N. Morris,
Morton D. Paley, and Kathleen Raine. In addition, there are three hitherto unpublished texts on “The Human
Face of God,” a lecture delivered by Raine at Paris in May 1985 (87-101), on “Opposition Is True
Friendship’: Emanuel Swedenborg and His Influences on William Blake” by Bellin (35-67), and “the text of
an address by the Reverend Peter M. Buss, delivered at the Olivet Church of the New Jerusalem in Ontario,
Canada, on 28 January 1984” which is entitled “William Blake and the Writings of Swedenborg” (147-55).
The book is illustrated, mostly with black and white reproductions of Blake’s illuminations.]</p>
            <p>28. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “A New <hi rend="i">America.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986): 37-44.</p>
            <p>29. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “The Way of a Papermaker with a Poet: Joshua Gilpin, William Blake,
and the Arts in 1796: A Postscript.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 33 (1986): 525. [Presents new
evidence which allows for an identification of Gilpin’s Blake with the writing engraver William Staden Blake
rather than with the poet-artist; see <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 80,
#43.]</p>
            <p>30. Bidney, Martin. “Solomon and Pharaoh’s Daughter: Blake’s Response to Wordsworth’s
Prospectus to <hi rend="i">The Recluse.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi> 85
(1986): 532-49.</p>
            <p>31. Billigheimer, Rachel V. “The Dance as Vision in Blake and Yeats.” <hi rend="i">UNISA
English Studies</hi> 24.2 (1986): 11-16.</p>
            <p>32. Bindman, David. “Blake und die Französische Revolution.” <hi rend="i">Bildende
Kunst</hi> 31 (1983): 594-97.</p>
            <p>33. Bindman, David. “William Blake and Popular
<pb id="p21-56" n="56"/>
religious Imagery.” <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 128 (1986): 712-18.</p>
            <p>34. Bloom, Harold. “Catastrophe Creation: Gnosis, Kabbalah and Blake.” <hi rend="i">Agon:
Towards a Theory of Revisionism.</hi> New York, NY: Oxford UP, 1982. 72-90. [Sifting through earlier editions
of this checklist, I find that this third chapter of Bloom’s by now well-known book has—for no particular
reason except the bibliographers’ negligence—never been included in our annual compilations, a fact for
which I wish to offer my apologies to both the author and our readers.]</p>
            <p>35. *Boime, Albert. “William Blake’s Graphic Imagery and the Industrial Revolution.” 
<hi rend="i">Arts Magazine</hi> 59 (1985): 107-19.</p>
            <p>36. Borkowska, Ewa. “Iconography and Iconology: A Study of William Blake’s Illuminated
Poetry.” <hi rend="i">Kwartalnik Neofilologiczny</hi> 33 (1986): 165-74.</p>
            <p>37. Brenkman, John. “The Concrete Utopia of Poetry: Blake’s ‘A Poison Tree.’ ” 
<hi rend="i">Lyric Poetry: Beyond New Criticism.</hi> Ed. Chaviva Hošek and Patricia Parker. Ithaca, NY: Cornell
UP, 1985. 182-93. $37.50 cloth / $12.95 paper. [This collection of essays as a whole will be of interest to
students of Blake’s lyric poetry; contributors include Northrop Frye, Paul de Man, John Hollander, et al.;
see also #162, below.]</p>
            <p>38. *Colmer, John. “Lawrence and Blake.” <hi rend="i">D. H. Lawrence and Tradition.</hi>
Ed. Jeffrey Meyers. Amherst, MA: U of Massachusetts P, 1985. 9-20.</p>
            <p>39. “Correction: John Clare’s ‘To a Lair at Noon’ and Blake and Chatterton.” 
<hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 33 (1986): 402. [An editorial with reference to Reisner’s 1985 note; see
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 84, #161.]</p>
            <p>40. Crehan, Stewart. “Blake, Context and Ideology.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 104-07. [A reply to Peterfreund’s unfavorable review of the author’s 
<hi rend="i">Blake in Context</hi>; see <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 94,
#386(3), and #90, below.]</p>
            <p>41. Donnellan, Brendan. “Blake and Nietzsche.” <hi rend="i">Nietzsche Studien</hi> 14
(1985): 269-80.</p>
            <p>42. Draxler, Helmut. “Der Pneumatiker als Genie: Feuer und Dynamik bei William Blake.” 
<hi rend="i">Idea: Jahrbuch der Hamburger Kunsthalle</hi> 6 (1986): 69-93. [A slightly revised version of a
chapter from the author’s Ph.D. thesis of 1986, U of Graz, Aus.; see #43, below.]</p>
            <p>43. Draxler, Helmut. “William Blake, der Pneumatiker als Genie.” <hi rend="i">Kunstforum
International</hi> 87 (1987): 80-95. [Virtually the same text as in the preceeding entry; here, however, the
author’s dissertation on “Das brennende Bild: Eine Kunstgeschichte des Feuers in der neueren Zeit” is
printed in full (though without the notes), and the illustrations are partly in color (70-228). There also is
a brief discussion of Philip James (sic) de Loutherbourg’s “fiery art” (196-97). An abstract of this
dissertation was published in <hi rend="i">Kunsthistoriker: Mitteilungen des Österreichischen
Kunsthistorikerverbandes</hi> 3.3 / 4 (1986): 44.]</p>
            <p>44. Erdman, David V. “Improving the Text of <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of
William Blake.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986): 49-52. [See also
“Errata’s Errata.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 110.]</p>
            <p>45. Essick, Robert N. “Dante Gabriel Rossetti, Frederic Shields, and the Spirit of William
Blake.” <hi rend="i">Victorian Poetry</hi> 24 (1986): 163-72. [Five versions of Shields’s “Blake’s
Work Room and Death Room” are illustrated, carefully described, and discussed in connection with
Rossetti’s sonnet on Blake’s room.]</p>
            <p>46. *Fauvet, P. “Blake, Wordsworth and Late Eighteenth-Century Radicalism.” Diss. U of
Keele, 1979.</p>
            <p>47. *Gardner, Stanley. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Innocence and Experience Retraced.</hi> New York,
NY: St. Martin’s P; London: Athlone P, 1986. $27.50 / £20.00.</p>
            <p>48. Glausser, Wayne. “A Note on the Twenty Years of Blake’s Spectre.” 
<hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi> 24.2 (1986): 43-44.</p>
            <p>49. Goldsmith, Steven Richard. “Unbuilding Jerusalem: The Romantics Against the
Apocalypse.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 47 (1987): 2594A. U of Pennsylvania.
[“This dissertation reevaluates the relationship between apocalypse and British romantic poetry, attempting
to rehistoricize a visionary tradition that has been reified by ahistorical critical approaches.” It
“demonstrates how the apocalypse functions with immediate historical purpose despite its transcendental
pretensions,” and—besides much else—examines “the varying success of Wordsworth, DeQuincey, Blake and
Shelley in counteracting apocalyptic momentum, in restoring immediate social purpose and material contingency
to visionary writing. . . . Blake and Shelley move towards socializing the apocalypse more fully, recognizing
its value as a particular social rhetoric. . . .]</p>
            <p>50. Goslee, Nancy Moore. <hi rend="i">Uriel’s Eye: Miltonic Stationing and Statuary in Blake,
Keats, and Shelley.</hi> University, AL: U of Alabama P, 1985. $27.50. [The second chapter of this book, which
takes up pages 29-67, presents a discussion of “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: From Marble Landscape to
Living Form.” The romantic transformations of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> are here interpreted with
reference to the <hi rend="i">paragone</hi> of the arts of sculpture and (landscape) painting which are seen
as related to a classical, ‘objective’ and to a romantic, ‘subjective’ expression of poetical
mythmaking.]</p>
            <p>51. Gourlay, Alexander S. “Blake’s Sisters: A Critical Edition, with Commentary, of 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> and <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 46 (1986): 2699-700A. U of Iowa. [“This edition . . .
consists of critical discussions of the texts and illustrations of both poems, an explanation of Blake’s
printing method and the editorial problems it
<pb id="p21-57" n="57"/>
presents, annotated and newly punctuated texts, pictorial notes and commentary, . . . and tables of textual
variants. . . . Wher(e)as <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> is a comic, satiric, and ultimately optimistic view of the
state of art, poetry, and religion, <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> offers a tragic appraisal of the relations
between human beings and God, men and women, blacks and whites, and rich and poor, and suggests that the root
of these evils is in organized religion and materialistic philosophy. This edition demonstrates several ways
in which the scholarly presentation of Blake’s works in illuminated printing can be improved.”]</p>
            <p>52. Greco, Norma A. “Mother Figures in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and the
Female Will.” <hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and Present</hi> 10.1 (1986): 1-15.</p>
            <p>53. Greenberg, Mark L. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>: Technology
and Artistic Form.” <hi rend="i">Annals of Scholarship</hi> 4 (1986): 69-82. [The text of a paper which was
read at the Symposium on Science and the Imagination, held at the U of California, Berkeley, 4-7 Aug.
1985.]</p>
            <p>54. Gresham, Gwendolyn Holloway Parham. “The Voice of Honest Indignation: William Blake’s
Critique of the Polity, Liturgy, Ethics, and Theology of the Church of England.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation
Abstracts International</hi> 46 (1986): 3040A. U of Arkansas. [“The 39 Articles of the Church of England
provide a statement by which to measure the religious vision of the poetry of William Blake. . . . Blake’s
response to the social and ethical teaching of the Church depends on his redefinition of the Fall and the
nature of sin, his affirmation of free will, and his rejection of Calvinistic predestination.”]</p>
            <p>55. Hagstrum, Jean H. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Body: Love and Sexuality in Keats, Wordsworth,
and Blake.</hi> Hodges Lectures. Knoxville, TN: U of Tennessee P, 1986. $14.95. [The author treats “William
Blake: ‘Arrows of Desire’ and ‘Chariots of Fire’ ” on 109-45 in the fourth of his chapters on sexual
themes and imagery in English romantic poetry.]</p>
            <p>56. *Haigwood, Laura Ellen. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>:
Revising an Interpretive Tradition.” <hi rend="i">San Jose Studies</hi> 11.2 (1985): 77-94.</p>
            <p>57. *Hales, L.-A. “The Figure of Jesus Christ in the Poetry of William Blake.” Diss. U of
Glasgow, 1980.</p>
            <p>58. Heppner, Christopher. “The New Jerusalem Defended.” <hi rend="i">Blake /An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 102-04. [Replies to Tolley’s critique (see #107, below) of his iconographical
identification of a Blake design with “The New Jerusalem Descending;” see <hi rend="i">Blake /An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 82, #102.]</p>
            <p>59. Hilton, Nelson. “Blake and the Perception of Science.” <hi rend="i">Annals of
Scholarship</hi> 4 (1986): 54-68. [The published version of a paper read at the U of California, Berkeley, on
the occasion of a Symposium on Science and the Imagination, held there 4-7 Aug. 1985.]</p>
            <p>60. Hilton, Nelson, ed. <hi rend="i">Essential Articles for the Study of William Blake,
1970-1984.</hi> Essential Articles Series. Hamden, CT: Archon Books-Shoe String P, 1986. $35.00. [As the
editor explains in his preface, it was essential for the selection of the essays that are reprinted in this
volume “to emphasize articles dealing with Blake’s verbal thought and practice” and, at the same time,
“to reflect the essential trajectory of literary-critical thought for the years it covers” (ix-x). These
editorial decisions resulted in a collection which assembles Hazard Adams’s “Blake and the Philosophy of
Literary Symbolism” of 1973 in a newly revised version, Stuart Curran’s “Blake and the Gnostic Hyle: A
Double Negative” of 1972, Florence Sandler’s “The Iconoclastic Enterprise: Blake’s Critique of
‘Milton’s Religion’ ” of 1972, Michael Riffaterre’s “The Self-sufficient Text” of 1973, Susan
Fox’s “The Female as Metaphor in William Blake’s Poetry” of 1977, Robert F. Gleckner’s “Most Holy
Forms of Thought: Some Observations on Blake and Language” of 1974, V. A. De Luca’s “Proper Names in the
Structural Design of Blake’s Myth-Making” of 1978, Donald Ault’s “Incommensurability and
Interconnection in Blake’s Anti-Newtonian Text” of 1977, Morris Eaves’s “Blake and the Artistic
Machine: An Essay in Decorum and Technology” of 1977, Alicia Ostriker’s “Desire Gratified and
Ungratified: William Blake and Sexuality” of 1982-1983, Ronald Clayton Taylor’s “Semantic Structures and
the Temporal Modes of Blake’s Prophetic Verse” of 1979, Steven Shaviro’s “ ‘Striving with
Systems’: Blake and the Politics of Difference” of 1982, and an edited and newly titled version of the
Santa Cruz Blake Study Group’s 1984 review of Erdman’s <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of
William Blake.</hi>]</p>
            <p>61. *Hjerter, Kathleen G. <hi rend="i">Doubly Gifted: The Author as Visual Artist.</hi> New
York, NY: Abrams, 1986. $29.95. [Said to contain a chapter on Blake.]</p>
            <p>62. Holmes, John R. “William Blake’s Place in the Mystical Tradition.” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 47 (1987): 188A. Kent State U. [“The aim of this
dissertation is to facilitate a proper understanding of Blake’s key religious images and ideas by showing
that they are mystic ideas, and that because they are mystic ideas they more completely unite the human, the
divine, and the worldly than poetic or religious ideas outside the mystical context do. . . . this study shows
the result in Blake’s poetry of overcoming each of the following six dualities: world and spirit (Chapter
II), subject and object (Chapter III), corporeal and spiritual senses (Chapter IV), God and Humanity (Chapter
V), Imagination and Reason (Chapter VI), and Chronology versus Hierarchy (Chapter VII).”]</p>
            <p>63. Howard, Seymour. “William Blake: The Antique, Nudity, and Nakedness: A Study in Idealism
and Regression.” <hi rend="i">Artibus et Historiae</hi> 3.6 (1982): 117-49. [An earlier version of this
study was read as a paper at the “Blake in the Art of His Time” conference at the U of
<pb id="p21-58" n="58"/>
California, Santa Barbara, in March 1976, and it ought to have been listed here years ago.]</p>
            <p>64. Imaizumi, Yoko. “Brotherhood in Blake: Psychology and Poetics.” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 46 (1986): 3359A. Yale U. [“This study explores the
concept of brotherhood in William Blake’s poems with close attention to his imagery and style,” it
examines “how the idea of brotherhood is manifest in the form of communication in his earlier works,” then
in the major prophecies, and it concludes with a study of “the labor of brotherhood on the female side in
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>”]</p>
            <p>65. *Isaksson, Folke. “William Blake (1757-1827): ‘The Chimney Sweeper.’ ” 
<hi rend="i">Gnistor under himlavalvet: tjugofem kapitel om poesi.</hi> Stockholm, Swed.: Tiden, 1982. 81-93.</p>
            <p>66. John, Donald. “Blake and Forgiveness.” <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 17 (1986):
74-80. [Read as a paper at the 1985 Wordsworth Conference in Grasmere.]</p>
            <p>67. Johnson, Mary Lynn. “Blake’s Judgment on the Book of Judges: The Watercolor Designs as
Biblical Commentary.” <hi rend="i">Reconciliations: Studies in Honor of Richard Harter Fogle.</hi> Ed. Mary
Lynn Johnson and Seraphia D. Leyda. Salzburg Studies in English Literature [III]: Romantic Reassessment 96.
Salzburg, Aus.: Institut für Anglistik und Amerikanistik, U of Salzburg, 1983. 41-71a. [Distributed in the
United States by Humanities P.]</p>
            <p>68. Johnson, Richard E. “Blake as Audience: The Designs to Gray’s ‘Ode on the Death of a
Favorite Cat.’ ” <hi rend="i">Reconciliations: Studies in Honor of Richard Harter Fogle.</hi> Ed. Mary
Lynn Johnson and Seraphia D. Leyda. Salzburg Studies in English Literature [III]: Romantic Reassessment 96.
Salzburg, Aus.: Institut für Anglistik und Amerikanistik, U of Salzburg, 1983. 72-94.</p>
            <p>69. Kamusikiri, Sandra Darlene. “‘A Building of Magnificence’: Blake’s Major Prophecies
and Eighteenth-Century Conceptions of the Human Sublime.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
International</hi> 46 (1986): 3726A. U of California. [Studies <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Milton</hi>, and
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> “in relation to Blake’s reaction to Burke’s theory of the terrible sublime,
and (his) transformation of conceptions of the human sublime developed by such eighteenth-century theorists as
Robert Lowth, Hugh Blair, John Dennis, Joseph Addison, Lord Kames, Edmund Burke and others.” Discovers and
describes “a unique type of Blakean sublimity whose two most significant features are a consistent binary
structure, and a humanizing, redemptive function. . . . Blake’s human sublimity represents not only a
rhetorical or aesthetic category, but also a civic and perceptival code—a way of thinking, acting and
seeing.”]</p>
            <p>70. *Kemeny, Tomaso. “Le parole e l’imagine nella scrittura poetica.” 
<hi rend="i">Piccolo Hans</hi> 39 (1983): 34-50. [Blake’s “parole e l’imagine” are chosen as the primary
study example.]</p>
            <p>71. Knights, L. C. “Early Blake.” <hi rend="i">Selected Essays in Criticism.</hi>
Cambridge, Cambs.: Cambridge UP, 1981. 124-36. [The reprint of an essay which was first published in 1971 in
the <hi rend="i">Sewanee Review</hi>; see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977) #B2063.]</p>
            <p>72. Kraft, Kent. “Hermetic Embodiment in Hildegard of Bingen and William Blake.” 
<hi rend="i">Proceedings of the Xth Congress of the International Comparative Literature Association / Actes du
X<hi rend="s">e</hi> congrès de l’Association internationale de littérature comparée.</hi> Vol. 2:
“Comparative Poetics / Poétiques comparées.” Ed. Claudio Guillen, with the assistance of Peggy Escher.
New York, NY: Garland, 1985. 551-57. [A paper read on the occasion of the 10th ICLA Congress at New York, NY,
22-29 Aug. 1982.]</p>
            <p>73. Kroeber, Karl. “Inventing the Unconscious.” <hi rend="i">British Romantic Art.</hi>
Berkeley, CA: U of California P, 1986. 9-33. [This chapter contains an elaborate discussion of 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> on 17-33; Blake’s works figure largely in other parts of the book as
well.]</p>
            <p>74. La Belle, Jenijoy. “William Blake’s Reputation in the 1830s: Some Unrecorded
Documents.” <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi> 84 (1987): 302-07. [Comments on eight references (six of them
previously unrecorded) to Blake in Arnold’s <hi rend="i">Library</hi> (later: <hi rend="i">Magazine</hi>)
<hi rend="i">of the Fine Arts</hi> (1831-1834), in which he was associated with such renowned artists of the
British school of history painting as Barry, Fuseli, Flaxman, and Stothard.]</p>
            <p>75. Lake, David J. “Blake’s ‘The Blossom.’ ” <hi rend="i">Explicator</hi> 45.2
(1987): 20-23.</p>
            <p>76. Larrissy, Edward. “Blake and the Hutchinsonians.” <hi rend="i">Blake /An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986): 44-47.</p>
            <p>77. Larrissy, Edward. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Rereading Literature. Oxford, Oxon.:
Blackwell, 1985. £12.50 cloth / £4.50 paper.</p>
            <p>78. *Law, Philip. “Innocence Renewed: The Divine Images of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence
and of Experience.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Theology</hi> 89 (1986): 275-82.</p>
            <p>79. Lee, Judith. “Scornful Beauty: A Note on Blake and Ariosto.” <hi rend="i">English
Language Notes</hi> 23.4 (1986): 35-38.</p>
            <p>80. Leonard, Garry Martin. “William Blake’s ‘Vegetable Existence’ and James Joyce’s
‘Moral Paralysis’: The Relationship between Blake’s Romantic Philosophy and Joyce’s Thematic Concerns
in <hi rend="i">Dubliners</hi> and <hi rend="i">A Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 47 (1986): 1319A. U of Florida. [“In my discussion, from
time to time, I argue that Blake directly influenced Joyce’s work. More often, I argue that the ideas of
Blake are analogous to Joyce’s thematic concerns and that, while direct influence cannot be proven,
comparison does illuminate Joyce’s text.”]</p>
            <p>81. Linkin, Harriet Kramer. “The Language of Speakers in <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and
of Experience.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and Present</hi> 10.2 (1986): 5-24.</p>
            <p>82. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">The Paintings of William Blake.</hi> Cambridge, Cambs.:
Cambridge UP, in association
<pb id="p21-59" n="59"/>
with the Pevensey P, 1986. £19.50. [A companion volume to the same author’s <hi rend="i">Paintings of
Samuel Palmer</hi>; see <hi rend="i">Blake /An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 89, #249. Again,
there are 75 color plates, each with a brief commentary on the facing page; and again, the author has chosen a
somewhat misleading title, since the term “painting” is here used as a synonym for “picture.”
Therefore, one ought to be prepared to encounter in this selection works in all sorts of media: tempera and
watercolor paintings alongside wash drawings, monochrome as well as hand-tinted relief-etched prints,
color-prints, miniatures, wood and line engravings on copper, a pencil and two pen drawings. However, all
these “paintings” do indeed seem to be by Blake.]</p>
            <p>83. Lyle, Janice. “Dante in British Art: 1770-1830.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
International</hi> 45 (1985): 3017A. U of California, Santa Barbara. [“The popularity of the Ugolino and
Paolo and Francesca episodes from the Inferno is directly connected to the artistic theory of the Sublime. . .
. this study examines the period beginning with Reynolds’ Ugolino and ending with Blake’s series of Dante
drawings and engravings. All known depictions of Dante’s themes done between 1770 and 1830 in Britain are
documented. Individual Dante episodes are discussed in relation to each artist’s knowledge of the poet,
involvement in the circle of British men promoting Italian art and culture, use of iconographic and stylistic
prototypes, and influence on other artists. Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Divine Comedy</hi> engravings are
emphasized. . . . Blake’s series, although incomplete and uneven in quality, is seen as an important example
of the general and pervasive impact of 18th-century ideas of the Sublime, as well as the unique instance of a
poet / artist illustrating Dante’s work.” The introductory chapters of this dissertation are devoted to
Reynolds and Fuseli as illustrators of the <hi rend="i">Divine Comedy.</hi>]</p>
            <p>84. McArthur, Murray Gilchrist. “Language and History in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
and Joyce’s <hi rend="i">Ulysses.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 46 (1986):
2689-90A. U of Western Ontario, Can. [Sees “the ground” of Joyce’s “deep debt to Blake” in the
“self-reflexive analysis within <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> of the formal and material properties of the
written text, . . . My assumption throughout is that both Blake and Joyce saw a close relation between a
writer’s formal approach to language and his historical posture. . . . <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, I maintain,
was one of Joyce’s intertextual sources for the analysis of Shakespeare’s creative and erotic life in
‘Scylla and Charybdis’, as well as for the overall borrowing and transforming of the narrative pattern of
the <hi rend="i">Odyssey.</hi>”]</p>
            <p>85. McCord, James. “Mixed Motives and Deadly Acts: Historical and Dramatic Character in
William Blake’s <hi rend="i">King Edward the Third.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 19
(1986): 480-501.</p>
            <p>86. McCord, James. “West of Atlantis: William Blake’s Unromantic View of the American
War.” <hi rend="i">Centennial Review</hi> 30 (1986): 383-99.</p>
            <p>87. McGann, Jerome J. “The Idea of an Indeterminate Text: Blake’s Bible of Hell and Dr.
Alexander Geddes.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 25 (1986): 303-24. [Identifies Geddes as “the
chief conduit for Blake’s knowledge of the new biblical scholarship” (305); from him the poet may have
learned about the distinction between the Elohist and Jahwist versions of Genesis. This distinction and its
ideological background are brought to bear upon the interpretation of the “variances to be found in and
between the texts of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>” (303), and, in general, upon the understanding of the 
“<hi rend="i">critical</hi> edge” (313) in the printer-poet’s reading of the Holy Scripture.]</p>
            <p>88. Paley, Morton D. “William Blake.” <hi rend="i">The Apocalyptic Sublime.</hi> New Haven,
CT: Yale UP, 1986. 71-100. $35.00. [This book started from a consideration of “Blake’s apocalyptic art in
relation to that of his contemporaries;” it now offers a treatment of “the entire phenomenon of art on
apocalyptic subjects in eighteenth-and nineteenth-century Britain” (v), and includes the visual argument or
more than ninety reproductions. Besides Blake’s apocalyptic designs those of West, Loutherbourg, Turner,
Martin, and Danby are discussed at length.]</p>
            <p>89. Patterson, Annabel. “Pastoral and Ideology: The Neoclassical <hi rend="i">Fête
Champêtre.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 48 (1985): 321-44. [Includes reproductions
and a discussion of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Virgil</hi> wood engravings on 334-41.]</p>
            <p>90. Peterfreund, Stuart. “Reply to Stewart Crehan.” <hi rend="i">Blake /An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 108-09. [See #40, above.]</p>
            <p>91. Piquet, François. “Blake et l’idéologie millénariste.” <hi rend="i">Idéologies
dans le monde anglo-saxon.</hi> Ed. Pierre Morere. Essais sur l’idéologie 1. Grenoble, Fr.: Centre de
Recherches d’Études Anglophones, U de Grenoble III, 1985. 189-201.</p>
            <p>92. Porée, Marc. “Pour une topique du corps ou l’image-corps en (tous) ses lieux.” 
<hi rend="i">Romantisme</hi> 15.49 (1985): 77-93. [Discusses Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Coleridge,
Shelley, and Keats.]</p>
            <p>93. *Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">L’Imagination créatrice de William Blake.</hi> Paris,
Fr.: Berg, 1983. Fr 90.00.</p>
            <p>94. Raine, Kathleen. “The Sleep of Albion.” <hi rend="i">Michigan Quarterly Review</hi> 25
(1986): 684-98. [Treats Blake on 690-98 in the context of the mythic tradition of the sleep of King
Arthur.]</p>
            <p>95. Raine, Kathleen. “Yeats’s Debt to William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Defending Ancient
Springs.</hi> 2nd ed. Ipswich, Suff.: Golgonooza P, 1985. 66-87. £5.50 paper. [This collection of Raine’s
essays was first published by Oxford UP in 1967; the reprint of her 1965 study of Blake’s influence on Yeats
has not been revised for the present
<pb id="p21-60" n="60"/>
printing; see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977) #2493.]</p>
            <p>96. *Ridge, George Ross, and Benedict Chiaka Njoku. <hi rend="i">The Christian Tragic Hero in
French and English Literature.</hi> Atlantic Highlands, NJ: Humanities P, 1983. [One out of the twelve
“Christian heroes” dealt with in this book is said to be William Blake.]</p>
            <p>97. *Riehl, Joseph. “Was Origen Urizen? Another Possible Source for the Name.” 
<hi rend="i">Publications of the Arkansas Philological Association</hi> 11.2 (1985): 65-71.</p>
            <p>98. *Robinson, D. “Joan of Orc: A Reading of Twain’s French Fantasy through Blake’s
America: A Prophesy [sic?].” <hi rend="i">American Studies in Scandinavia</hi> 18 (1986): 15-26.</p>
            <p>99. *Sanzo, Eileen. “Nature in Blake: Duality versus Comic Unity.” <hi rend="i">Nassau
Review</hi> 5 (1985): 1-7.</p>
            <p>100. Sławek, Tadeusz. <hi rend="i">The Outlined Shadow: Phenomenology, Grammatology,
Blake.</hi> Rpace Naukowe Uniwersytetu Ślaskiego w Katowicach 727. Katowice, Pol.: Uniwersytet Ślaski, 1985.
zł 224 paper. [One hundred and fifty pages of text in English on “The (pre)Face of the Text,” “Voice as
Understanding,” and “Drawing as <hi rend="i">Weltanschauung / Weltanschauung</hi> as Drawing.” Blake’s
poetry and designs are here studied in a frame of reference supplied by Heidegger’s concept of phenomenology
and some of its poststructuralist heirs.]</p>
            <p>101. Stamm, Ramona Kelley. “A Further Note on the Blakean Connection in Joyce Cary’s 
<hi rend="i">The Horse’s Mouth.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Notes on Contemporary Literature</hi> 15.4 (1985): 4-5.</p>
            <p>102. Stieg, Elizabeth Joy. “William Blake and the Prophetic Tradition.” 
<hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 47 (1986): 916A. U of Toronto, ON. [“ . . . examine(s)
Blake’s understanding of prophets and prophecy in relation to the attitudes and beliefs of contemporaries,
specifically, the theologians, enthusiasts, poets and critics. . . . two of Blake’s poems, 
<hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, are discussed at some length as early and late examples
of Blake’s explorations of the nature and purpose of prophecy and his treatment of a biblical prophetic
tradition.”]</p>
            <p>103. Summerfield, H[enry]. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi> and the
Bible.” <hi rend="i">University of Dayton Review</hi> 17.3 (1985-1986): 29-39.</p>
            <p>104. *Surbanov, Aleksandǎr. “Nebesa pod krakata.” <hi rend="i">Izbrani stihove.</hi>
Sofia, Bulg.: Narodna kultura, 1983. 5-20. [A discussion of Blake’s poems and prophecies.]</p>
            <p>105. Taylor, Dena Bain. “The Visual Context of ‘Joseph of Arimathea among The Rocks of
Albion.’ ” <hi rend="i">Blake /An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986): 47-48.</p>
            <p>106. *Tokarev, G. N. “Stikhotvorenie U. Bleǐka ‘London’ v perevodakh S. Marshaka: (o vli
i͡anii konteksta na perevode stikhotvornykh proizvedeniǐ).” <hi rend="i">Voprosy poetiki khudozhestvennogo
proizvedeii͡a.</hi> Alma-Ata, USSR: Kazakhskiǐ pedagogicheskiǐ institut, 1980. 128-40. [Discusses the
influence of the translator’s social surroundings on his work, and employs <corr type="emend">Marshak’s</corr> translation of
“London” to make the point.]</p>
            <p>107. Tolley, Michael J. “The <hi rend="i">Allegorical Female Figure</hi>: She Cometh With
Clouds.” <hi rend="i">Blake /An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 101-02. [Disputes Heppner’s
iconographical identification of a Blake drawing; see <hi rend="i">Blake /An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20
(1986-1987): 82, #102, and #58, above.]</p>
            <p>108. Watson, J. R. “Blake.” <hi rend="i">English Poetry of the Romantic Period:
1789-1830.</hi> Longman Literature in English Series. London: Longman, 1985. 78-109. £15.95 cloth / £7.50
paper.</p>
            <p>109. *Weiskel, Thomas. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Sublime: Studies in the Structure and
Psychology of Transcendence.</hi> 2nd ed. Baltimore, MD: Johns Hopkins UP, 1986. $8.95 paper. [A reimpression
of the late Thomas Weiskel’s 1976 publication, with the chapter on Blake; Harold Bloom has added a new
introduction.]</p>
            <p>110. *Welburn, A. J. “The Gnostic Imagination of William Blake: A Comparative and Typological
Investigation into the Unity and Structure of Blake’s Mythology.” Diss. U of Cambridge, Cambs., 1980.</p>
            <p>111, Welch, Dennis M. “Blake’s Critique of Election: <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and the 
<hi rend="i">Comus</hi> Illustrations.” <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> 64 (1985): 509-31. [The essay
is accompanied by a suite of sixteen reproductions from the <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> watercolor.]</p>
            <p>112. Welch, Dennis M. “‘Cloth’d with human beauty’: <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and
Blake’s Incarnational Aesthetic.” <hi rend="i">Religion and Literature</hi> 18.2 (1986): 1-15.</p>
            <p>113. Welch, Dennis M. “Imitation in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>
Illustrations.” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 22 (1986): 165-84. [Compares some of the 
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> watercolors with the allegorical representations in George Richardson’s 
<hi rend="i">Iconology</hi> of 1778-1779, and “suggests that Blake’s imitation could at times be creative and
perceptive without necessarily involving his personal symbolism or mythology” (166).]</p>
            <p>114. Werner, Bette Charlene. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Vision of the Poetry of Milton:
Illustrations to Six Poems.</hi> Lewisburg, PA: Bucknell UP; London: Associated UP, 1986. $45.00. [After
Dunbar’s and Behrendt’s, this is the third book-length study of Blake’s watercolor series for
“Comus,” <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, “Ode on the Morning of Christ’s Nativity,”
“L’Allegro,” “Il Penseroso,” and <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi> in less than a decade. There
are 79 reproductions.]</p>
            <p>115. Wilkie, Brian. “The Romantic Ideal of Unity.” <hi rend="i">Studies in the Literary
Imagination</hi> 19.2 (1986): 5-21. [Pages 15-20 of this article are entirely devoted to an interpretation of
“the ideal of unity” in the works of Blake.]</p>
            <p>116. Wind, Edgar. “Blake and Reynolds.” <hi rend="i">Hume and the Heroic Portrait: Studies
in Eighteenth-Century Imagery.</hi> Ed. Jaynie Anderson. Oxford, Oxon.: Clarendon
<pb id="p21-61" n="61"/>
P, 1986. 81-85. [Originally presented as a radio talk, this paper was afterwards published in the 
<hi rend="i">Listener</hi> in 1957; it is here reprinted, in the second volume of Wind’s collected essays, with
the notes now added for the first time from the late author’s personal papers; see Bentley, 
<hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (1977) #2985.]</p>
            <p>117. Witke, Joanne. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Epic: Imagination Unbound.</hi> London:
Croom Helm; New York, NY: St. Martin’s P, 1986. £22.50. [Concentrates on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, which
is discussed plate-by-plate; also treats Blake’s annotations to Reynolds’ <hi rend="i">Discourses.</hi>
This study was previously listed under a wrong title, quoted at a prepublication date in a publishers’
catalogue; see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 86, #194.]</p>
            <p>
              <hi rend="i">See also #140, 144, and 145, below.</hi>
            </p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part II<lb/>
Blake’s Circle</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">
                  <hi rend="i">General Studies</hi>
                </hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>118. *Fore, Byrne R. S., ed. <hi rend="i">The Best of Bell’s British Theatre: Consisting of
the Most Esteemed English Plays.</hi> 41 vols. London, 1776-1802. New York, NY: AMS P, 1977. $1,742.50 the
set/separate vols. $42.50 each. [Includes reproductions of all the original illustrations, many of which were
engraved from designs by Burney, Fuseli, and Stothard.]</p>
            <p>119. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">Prints and Printmaking: A Dictionary and Handbook of the Art
in Nineteenth-Century Britain.</hi> London: Methuen, 1984. £29.50. [As may be expected from this author,
Blake’s circle figures quite prominently in the volume. There are brief bio- and bibliographical entries for
Bartolozzi, Basire II, Blake, Calvert, Fuseli, Linnell, Linton, Muir, Ottley, Palmer, Richmond, Stothard,
West, et al. in the dictionary, and many of these printmakers are discussed in the second or fourth chapter of
the handbook section.]</p>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">James Basire</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>120. Foucart-Borville, Jacques. “Un dessinateur amateur au XVIII<hi rend="s">e</hi> s.: le
Français Joseph Basire et non l’Anglais James Basire.” <hi rend="i">Revue du Louvre et des Musées de
France</hi> 31 (1982): 15-20. [Distinguishes the oeuvre of a French amateur engraver from that of Blake’s
master.]</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">William Cowper</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>121. King, James, and Charles Ryskamp, eds. <hi rend="i">The Letters and Prose Writings of
William Cowper.</hi> Vol. 5: “Prose 1756-<hi rend="i">c</hi>. 1799 and Cumulative Index.” Oxford, Oxon.:
Clarendon P, 1986. £48.00.</p>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See also #14, above, and #153, below.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Erasmus Darwin</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>122. *McNeil, M. C. M. “A Contextual Study of Erasmus Darwin.” Diss. U of Cambridge,
Cambs., 1980.</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">John Flaxman</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>123. *Arias Anglés, E. “Influencias de John Flaxman y Gavin Hamilton en José de Madrazo y
nueva lectura de la ‘Muerte de Viriato.’ ” <hi rend="i">Archivo Español de Arte</hi> 232 (1985):
351-62.</p>
              <p>124. Gizzi, Corrado, ed. <hi rend="i">Flaxman e Dante.</hi> Exh. cat. Palazzo di Brera,
Milan. 22 Nov. 1986 – 14 Jan. 1987. Milan, It.: Mazzotta, 1986. [This catalogue has been produced in the same
large format as Gizzi’s earlier two volumes on <hi rend="i">Blake e Dante</hi> and <hi rend="i">Füssli e
Dante</hi> which accompanied similar exhibition projects realized at the Torre de’ Passeri in Pescara and
the Palazzo di Brera; see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 103, #53; 20
(1986-1987): 88, #237. The present volume in this spectacular series contains, besides ten learned essays on
various aspects of Flaxman’s classicism, his drawings and Piroli’s etchings, a suite of 73 color plates
(mostly of the sculptor’s drawings which figured largely in the exhibition), black and white reproductions
of all the Dante etchings with extracts from the <hi rend="i">Divina Commedia</hi>, and many other
illustrations throughout the text.]</p>
              <p>125. Ottani Cavina, Anna. “Neo-Primitivism and Linear Abstraction.” <hi rend="i">Paestum
and the Doric Revival 1750-1830: Essential Outlines of an Approach.</hi> Centro Di cat. 199. Florence, It.:
Centro Di, 1986. 59-62 and 89-90. [This volume, an abridged English-language version of <hi rend="i">La
fortuna di Paestum e la memoria moderna del Dorico 1750-1830</hi> (2 vols.), served as the catalogue of an
exhibition held at the National Academy of Design in New York, NY, 19 Feb.–30 Mar. 1986; included in the show
were several drawings by Flaxman, here listed as #52-59 in the catalogue section, and discussed in the essay
quoted above.]</p>
              <p>126. *<corr type="emend">Poprzęcka,</corr> Maria. “Flaxman, 1793—Picasso, 1903.” 
<hi rend="i">Polish Art Studies</hi> 5 (1984): 45-53. [Probably this is no more than a reprint of the identically
titled study by the author that was listed in <hi rend="i">Blake /An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984):
106, #134.]</p>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See also #12, 74, and 83, above.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Henry Fuseli</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>127. *Argan, Giulio Carlo. <hi rend="i">Da Hogarth a Picasso: l’arte moderna in
Europa.</hi> Milan, It.: Feltrinelli, 1983. [Said to contain a chapter devoted to Fuseli’s contribution to
the history of modern art.]</p>
              <p>128. [Behrens, Jürgen, et al.] “Freies Deutsches Hochstift: Jahresbericht.” 
<hi rend="i">Jahrbuch des Freien Deutschen Hochstifts</hi> [ns 25] (1986): 334-86. [On 362-63 Behrens reports on
the acquisition of Fuseli’s letter to DuRoveray of 2 Aug. 1799 for the Goethe-Museum in Frankfort-on-Main,
W. Ger., and gives a brief summary of its contents, based on information which had been supplied by David H.
Weinglass; the latter will publish
<pb id="p21-62" n="62"/>
the full text of this ALS in his revised and enlarged edition of <hi rend="i">The Collected English Letters of
Henry Fuseli</hi> which is in preparation.]</p>
              <p>129. Chappell, Miles L. “Fuseli and the ‘judicious adoption’ of the Antique in the
‘Nightmare.’ ” <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 128 (1986): 421-22.</p>
              <p>130. Cullen, Fintan. “Hugh Douglas Hamilton: ‘painter of the heart.’ ” 
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 125 (1983): 417-21. [Contains the ‘first’ publication of Richard St.
George Mansergh St. George’s letter of “c. 1796,” in which a commission for a portrait is offered to
Fuseli (the letter was printed slightly earlier on 66-71 of Weinglass’ 1982 edition of Fuseli’s letters);
also refers to Romney’s portrait of “Mrs. Saint George and Child.”]</p>
              <p>131. Feingold, Lawrence. “Fuseli, Another Nightmare: <hi rend="i">The Night-Hag Visiting
Lapland Witches.” Metropolitan Museum Journal</hi> 17 (1982): 49-61.</p>
              <p>132. Hammerschmidt, Hildegard. “Johann Heinrich Füsslis Illustrationen zu Shakespeares
‘Macbeth’ unter besonderer Berücksichtigung seiner Kunsttheorie.” <hi rend="i">Anglistentag 1984
Passau: Vorträge.</hi> Ed. Manfred Pfister. Tagungsberichte des Anglistentags des Verbands Deutscher
Anglisten 6. 23-26 Sept. 1984. Giessen, W. Ger.: Hoffman, 1985. 261-77. [An earlier version of an article
which has been listed in <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 88, #239.]</p>
              <p>133. Kastner, Jörg. <hi rend="i">Das Nibelungenlied: In den Augen der Künstler vom
Mittelalter bis zur Gegenwart.</hi> Exh. cat. Staatliche Bibliothek Passau, 2 May-12 June 1986. Passau, W.
Ger.: Passavia Universitätsverlag, 1986. [Five of Fuseli’s Nibelungen illustrations are discussed.]</p>
              <p>134. Lindsay, Suzanne G. “Emblematic Aspects of Fuseli’s <hi rend="i">Artist in
Despair.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi> 68 (1986): 483-84.</p>
              <p>135. Schiff, Gert. <hi rend="i">Henry Fuseli.</hi> Exh. cat. 12 Nov.-18 Dec. 1983. Tokyo,
Jap.: National Museum of Western Art, in association with the Swiss Council for the Arts (Pro Helvetia), 1983.
[The bilingual catalogue of a major exhibition: 107 of Fuseli’s drawings and paintings are documented and
illustrated, many of them in excellent full-color reproductions. Schiff’s text, however, does not, as far as
I can see, substantially revise his earlier interpretations in the 1973 oeuvre catalogue, the 1975 Tate
Gallery exhibition catalogue, or the 1977 <hi rend="i">L’opera completa di Füssli.</hi>]</p>
              <p>136. Schnyder-Seidel, Barbara. <hi rend="i">J. H. Füssli und seine schönen Zürcherinnen:
Verwirrungen um Bildnisse im Umkreis von Goethe, Füssli und Tischbein.</hi> Zurich, Switz.: Classen, 1986. DM
24.00 paper.</p>
              <p>137. *Woźniakowski, J. “Heroes of Our Times: Some Remarks on Fuseli and Adventure
Strips.” <hi rend="i">Polish Art Studies</hi> 6 (1985): 99-106.</p>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See also #12, 74, 83, 118, 119, above, as well as #143, 145, 146, 170, 173, 178,
below.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">John Linnell</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See #1, 9, 119, above.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>138. Abley, Mark, ed. <hi rend="i">The Parting Light: Selected Writings of Samuel
Palmer.</hi> Manchester, Lancs.: Carcanet P, in association with Mid Northumberland Arts Group, 1985. £8.95
cloth. [Selections from Palmer’s letters, journals, memoranda, poems, essays, and inscriptions; mostly taken
from previously published sources, with some of the writings in new transcriptions that differ here or there
from Raymond Lister’s readings. Some of the letters, poems, and memoranda, however, “are published here
for the first time from documents belonging to the Linnell Trust, the Bodleian Library, and the Victoria and
Albert Museum.” Though the editor has “omitted none of the few poems and essays by Palmer that survive”
(21) he had had no access to one of the two recently traced copies of the artist’s pamphlet containing 
<hi rend="i">An Address to the Electors of West Kent</hi>, which has been edited for the pages of this journal by
David Bindman; see <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 88-89, #246 and 251.]</p>
              <p>139. Lister, Raymond. “A Reply to Martin Butlin.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986): 52. [Once more on Keating’s Palmer fakes and the questions of connoisseurship; see
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 88, #247.]</p>
              <p>140. Schulz, Max F. <hi rend="i">Paradise Preserved: Recreations of Eden in Eighteenth- and
Nineteenth-Century England.</hi> Cambridge, Cambs.: Cambridge UP, 1985. £30.00. [The book’s second part on
“Romantic Paradisal Bowers, Valleys, and Islands” not only has a chapter on “Bewick’s, Constable’s,
and Palmer’s <hi rend="i">Locus Paradisus</hi>” (112-36), but also opens up with a section on “Blake and
the Unending Dialectic of Earth and Eden” (41-56).]</p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">George Romney</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>141. Buttery, David. “George Romney and the Second Earl of Warwick.” 
<hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 124 (1986): 104-09.</p>
              <p>142. *Rump, Gerhard Charles. “George Romney: Pictor Celeberrimus.” 
<hi rend="i">Weltkunst</hi> 54 (1984): 2653-56. [Published in commemoration of the 250th anniversary of the
artist’s birth.]</p>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See also #9, 12, and 130 above, as well as #143 and 173, below.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
            <div4>
              <head>
                <title>
                  <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard</hi>
                </title>
              </head>
              <p>
                <hi rend="i">See #5, 74, 79 (Stothard as the designer of Blake’s Ariosto engraving), 118,
and 119, above, as well as #143, below.</hi>
              </p>
            </div4>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <pb id="p21-63" n="63"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part III</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">Works of Related Interest</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Some General Studies, Mostly of Romantic Art, Poetry, and Their Historical
Context</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>143. Altick, Richard D. <hi rend="i">Painting from Books: Art and Literature in Britain,
1760-1900.</hi> Columbus, OH: Ohio State UP, 1985. £54.00. [Part 1, chapter 2 treats eighteenth-century book
illustrations, Boydell’s Shakespeare Gallery, Macklin’s Poet’s Gallery, and Fuseli’s Milton Gallery
(37-55); the whole of the book’s second part (255-331) is devoted to the study of “Images from
Shakespeare,” and there are numerous references to artists such as West, Stothard, William Bell Scott,
Alexander Runciman, Romney, Reynolds, Opie, Northcote, Mortimer, Morland, Kauffmann, Fuseli, Blake, Barry, et
al. as well as to Cowper, Gray, Hayley, and all the major British authors that were illustrated by Blake and
his contemporaries. To say the least, one would have to admit that this volume of more than 500 pages with its
356 illustrations presents a mine of information for the history of British book illustration and literary
painting; most important, perhaps, is Altick’s attempt at a reconstruction of “What happened when people
‘read’ pictures” (234) in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.]</p>
            <p>144. Altizer, Thomas J. J. <hi rend="i">History as Apocalypse.</hi> SUNY Series in Religion.
Albany, NY: State U of New York P, 1985. $36.50 cloth / $12.95 paper. [Besides being of related interest for
the study of Blake’s apocalyptic imagery in general, the book treats—in chapter 8 (175-207)—“Blake and
the French Revolution.”]</p>
            <p>145. Bate, Jonathan. <hi rend="i">Shakespeare and the English Romantic Imagination.</hi>
Oxford, Oxon.: Clarendon P, 1986. £22.50. [Had I only seen this volume earlier, its entry would have been
transferred to the Critical Studies section, part I, above. There are two entire chapters devoted to the study
of Shakespeare in Blake’s “Romantic Imagination,” tracing the “Auspices of Shakespeare” in his
poetry, 117-56. With its numerous references to the reception of the Bard’s poems and plays in the works of
Blake’s contemporaries the book as a whole, however, certainly should be of “Related Interest” to Blake
scholars, too.]</p>
            <p>146. Bate, Jonathan. “Shakespearean Allusion in English Caricature in the Age of Gillray.”
<hi rend="i">Journal of the Warburg and Courtauld Institutes</hi> 49 (1986): 196-210. [Interesting background
reading for the public reception of Boydell’s Shakespeare Gallery in general, and Fuseli’s contributions
to that project in particular.]</p>
            <p>147. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “The Bookseller as Diplomat: James Edwards, Lord Grenville, and Earl
Spencer in 1800.” <hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi> 33 (1984): 471-85. [Publishes and analyzes a long letter
written by Edwards on 12 Aug. 1800, in which he reports to Lord Grenville from Napoleonic France on the state
of affairs—both political and book wise. The essay forms the first installment of a series of studies of the
book-trade around the year 1800 in Britain, and is related to Bentley’s forthcoming book on “F. J.
DuRoveray, Henry Fuseli, and Elegant Book-Making 1798-1806.”]</p>
            <p>148. Bogel, Fredric V. <hi rend="i">Literature and Insubstantiality in Later Eighteenth-Century
England.</hi> Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP, 1984. $22.50.</p>
            <p>149. *Boime, Albert. <hi rend="i">A Social History of Modern Art.</hi> Vol. 1: “Art in an Age
of Revolution, 1750-1800.” Chicago, IL: U of Chicago P, 1987.</p>
            <p>150. Cook, Albert. “Myth and Language.” <hi rend="i">Actes du VIII<hi rend="s">e</hi>
Congrès de l’Association Internationale de Littérature Comparée / Proceedings of the 8th Congress of the
International Comparative Literature Association.</hi> Vol. 2: “Littératures de diverses cultures au
vingtième siècle [et] Littérature comparée et théorie Littéraire / Twentieth-Century Literatures
Originating in Different Cultures [and] Comparative Literature and Theory of Literature.” Ed. Béla Köpeczi
and György M. Vajda. Stuttgart, W. Ger.: Kunst und Wissen-Bieber, 1985. 721-25. [This short study, first
presented as a paper at the 8th ICLA Conference in Budapest, 12-17 Aug. 1976, discusses Blake on 725.]</p>
            <p>151. Curran, Stuart. “The Political Prometheus.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>
25 (1986): 429-55. [Includes a brief treatment of <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> in the
context provided by Shelley’s notion of imperialism on 444.]</p>
            <p>152. Endy, Melvin B., Jr. “Just War, Holy War, and Millennialism in Revolutionary America.”
<hi rend="i">William and Mary Quarterly</hi> 42 (1985): 3-25.</p>
            <p>153. Griffin, Dustin. <hi rend="i">Regaining Paradise: Milton and the Eighteenth Century.</hi>
Cambridge, Cambs.: Cambridge UP, 1986. £25.00. [An investigation into the influence of Milton’s writings on
British authors from Addison to Cowper, who is the subject of the final chapter on 217-28.]</p>
            <p>154. *Knapp, Steven. <hi rend="i">Personification and the Sublime: Milton to Coleridge.</hi>
Cambridge, MA: Harvard UP, 1985. £14.95.</p>
            <p>155. Koppenfels, Werner von. “Le Coucher du soleil romantique: Die Imagination des Weltendes
aus dem Geist der visionären Romantik,” <hi rend="i">Poetica</hi> 17 (1985): 255-98. [Discusses the
apocalyptic imagery of romantic literature in a frame of reference supplied by Baudelaire’s poem from 
<hi rend="i">Les Fleurs du Mal.</hi>]</p>
            <p>156. Levi, Peter, “Visionary Poets.” <hi rend="i">Agenda</hi> 24.3 (1986): 27-50. [Blake is
frequently referred to in this printed version of an Oxford lecture; see especially 44-46.]</p>
            <p>157. *Meehan, Michael. <hi rend="i">Liberty and Poetics in Eighteenth-Century England.</hi>
London: Croom Helm, 1985. £17.95.</p>
            <pb id="p21-64" n="64"/>
            <p>158. *Meisel, Martin. <hi rend="i">Realizations: Narrative, Pictorial, and Theatrical Arts in
Nineteenth-Century England.</hi> Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP, 1984. $55.00/£38.80.</p>
            <p>159. *Merchant, W. Moelwyn. “Shakespeare and the Painter and Illustrator.” 
<hi rend="i">William Shakespeare: His World, His Work, His Influence.</hi> Vol. 3. New York, NY: Scribner, 1985.
757-69.</p>
            <p>160. Patrides, C. A., and Joseph Wittreich, eds. <hi rend="i">The Apocalypse in English
Renaissance Thought and Literature: Patterns, Antecedents and Repercussions.</hi> Ithaca, NY: Cornell UP,
1984. $49.50.</p>
            <p>161. *Peckham, Morse. <hi rend="i">The Birth of Romanticism: Cultural Crisis, 1790-1815.</hi>
Romanticism and Its Consequences: Emergent Culture in the 19th Century 1. Greenwood, FL: Penkevill, 1986.
$32.50.</p>
            <p>162. Rajan, Tilottama. “Romanticism and the Death of Lyric Consciousness.” 
<hi rend="i">Lyric Poetry: Beyond New Criticism.</hi> Ed. Chaviva Hošek and Patricia Parker. Ithaca, NY: Cornell
UP, 1985. 194-207. [Blake (see 201), Wordsworth, and Shelley serve to make the author’s point on
“delyricized discourse.”]</p>
            <p>163. Sambrook, James. <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: The Intellectual and Cultural
Context of English Literature, 1700-1789.</hi> Longman Literature in English Series. London: Longman, 1986.
£15.95 cloth / £7.95 paper.</p>
            <p>164. Smith, Olivia. <hi rend="i">The Politics of Language 1791-1819.</hi> Oxford, Oxon.:
Clarendon P, 1984. $27.95. [A reimpression in paper covers was issued in 1986.]</p>
            <p>165. *Thorslev, Peter L., Jr. <hi rend="i">Romantic Contraries: Freedom versus Destiny.</hi>
New Haven, CT: Yale UP, 1984. $21.50.</p>
            <p>166. Webster, Sarah McKim. “Circumscription and the Female in the Early Romantics.” 
<hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> 61 (1982): 51-68. [Blake (see 64-67), Coleridge, Wollstonecraft, and
Wordsworth are treated.]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Some Contemporary Artists, Collectors, and Connoisseurs</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>167. *Abrams, Ann Uhry. “A New Light on Benjamin West’s ‘Pennsylvania Instruction.’ ”
<hi rend="i">Winterthur Portfolio</hi> 17 (1982): 243-57.</p>
            <p>168. Greenhouse, Wendy. “Benjamin West and Edward III: A Neoclassical Painter and Medieval
History.” <hi rend="i">Art History</hi> 8 (1985): 178-91.</p>
            <p>169. Hamilton-Phillips, Martha. “Benjamin West and William Beckford: Some Projects for
Fonthill.” <hi rend="i">Metropolitan Museum Journal</hi> 15 (1980): 157-74.</p>
            <p>170. Hammerschmidt, Hildegard. “Illustrationen zu Shakespeares Sommernachtstraum: Eine
Ausstellung im Marburger Schauspiel zur Erinnerung an Horst Oppel.” <hi rend="i">Alma Mater Philippina</hi>
Winter 1984-1985: 23-25. [Fuseli, Blake, and some other British illustrators of <hi rend="i">A Midsummer
Night’s Dream</hi> are briefly mentioned in this exhibition review.]</p>
            <p>171. *Mravik, L. “Angelika Kauffmann kérdéses arcképe Kitty Fisherról.” 
<hi rend="i">Múvészettörténeti Értesitó</hi> 32.1/2 (1983): 228-30. [A portrait of the actress Kitty Fisher,
which has surfaced on the Budapest art market, is here tentatively attributed to Angelica.]</p>
            <p>172. Staley, Allen. “West’s <hi rend="i">Death on the Pale Horse.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Bulletin of the Detroit Institute of Arts</hi> 58 (1980): 137-49.</p>
            <p>173. Tscherny, Nadia. “Beyond Likeness: Late Eighteenth Century British Portraiture and
Origins of Romanticism.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts International</hi> 47 (1986): 1098A. New York
U. [“ . . . the introductory chapter establishes the portraiture of the Fuseli circle as an extreme against
which the work of Reynolds, Gainsborough and Romney are measured. . . . deals with a series of intimate
portraiture by these three painters.”]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Some Contemporary Authors</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>174. Aldridge, A. Owen. <hi rend="i">Thomas Paine’s American Ideology.</hi> Newark, DE: U of
Delaware P; London: Associated UP, 1984. $38.50.</p>
            <p>175. *Andrews, Stuart. “Tom Paine in France.” <hi rend="i">History Today</hi> Aug. 1983:
5-11.</p>
            <p>176. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Copyright Documents in the George Robinson Archive: William Godwin
and Others 1713-1820.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi> 35 (1982): 67-110.</p>
            <p>177. Boerner, Peter. “Bürger’s Ballad <hi rend="i">Lenore</hi> in Germany, France and
England.” <hi rend="i">Festschrift für Henry Remak: Sensus Communis: Contemporary Trends in Comparative
Literature / Panorama de la situation actuelle en Littérature Comparée.</hi> Ed. János Riesz, Peter
Boerner, and Bernhard Scholz. Tübingen, W. Ger.: Narr, 1986. 305-11.</p>
            <p>178. Camfield, Gregg. “Joel Barlow’s Dialectic of Progress.” <hi rend="i">Early American
Literature</hi> 21 (1986): 131-43. [On the political pamphlets which were published by the author of 
<hi rend="i">The Vision of Columbus</hi> in the 1790s; may be of interest to students of both Blake and
Fuseli.]</p>
            <p>179. Carpenter, Mary Wilson. “Sibylline Apocalyptics: Mary Wollstonecraft’s 
<hi rend="i">Vindication of the Rights of Woman</hi> and Job’s Mother’s Womb.” <hi rend="i">Literature and
History</hi> 12 (1986): 215-28.</p>
            <p>180. *Cohen, Seymour S. “Two Refugee Chemists in the United States, 1794: How We See Them.”
<hi rend="i">Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society</hi> 126 (1982): 301-15. [Treats Joseph
Priestley as one of these two refugees.]</p>
            <p>181. *De Luca, V. A. “DeQuincey’s Icons of Apocalypse: Some Romantic Analogues.” 
<hi rend="i">Thomas De-Quincey: Bicentenary Studies.</hi> Ed. Robert Lance Snyder. Norman, OK: U of Oklahoma P,
1985. 20-34. [Blake’s works provide some of the “Analogues” for DeQuincey’s apocalyptic imagery in 
<hi rend="i">The English Mail-Coach.</hi>]</p>
            <p>182. *Forster, Harold. <hi rend="i">Edward Young: The Poet of</hi>
	<pb id="p21-65" n="65"/>
	<hi rend="i">the</hi> Night Thoughts, <hi rend="i">1683-1765.</hi> Alburgh, nr. Harleston, Norf.: Erskine P,
1987. £29.95.</p>
            <p>183. Harasym, S. D. “Ideology and Self: A Theoretical Discussion of the ‘Self’ in Mary
Wollstonecraft’s Fiction.” <hi rend="i">English Studies in Canada</hi> 12 (1986): 163-77.</p>
            <p>184. Kaplan, Cora. “Pandora’s Box: Subjectivity, Class and Sexuality in Socialist Feminist
Criticism.” <hi rend="i">Making a Difference: Feminist Literary Criticism.</hi> Ed. Gayle Greene and
Coppélia Kahn. New Accents. London: Methuen, 1985. 146-76. [Discusses Wollstonecraft’s 
<hi rend="i">Vindication</hi> and Rousseau to explain “a split in feminist criticism, between liberal humanists
. . . and socialist feminists” (146).]</p>
            <p>185. Klaus, H. Gustav. “William Godwins <hi rend="i">‘Things as They Are’</hi>:
Sozialgeschichte im Roman.” <hi rend="i">Germanisch-Romanische Monatsschrift</hi> ns 36 (1986): 399-413.</p>
            <p>186. *Kovács, József. <hi rend="i">Aziró és a forradalmár Thomas Paine.</hi> Budapest,
Hung.: Akadémiai kiadó, 1983. [A study of Paine as writer and revolutionary.]</p>
            <p>187. *Marshall, Peter [H.], ed. <hi rend="i">The Anarchist Writings of William Godwin.</hi>
London: Freedom P, 1986. £3.50 paper.</p>
            <p>188. McKinley, Virginia Susan Gallaher. “Rendering Up ‘The Tale of What We Are’: Gothic
Narrative Methods in Selected Novels of Godwin, Brown and Shelley.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
International</hi> 47 (1987): 2597A. Michigan State U.</p>
            <p>189. Mitchell, Stephen A. “The Path from <hi rend="i">Inferno</hi> to the Chamber Plays: 
<hi rend="i">Easter</hi> and Swedenborg.” <hi rend="i">Modern Drama</hi> 29 (1986): 157-68. [Studies
Swedenborg’s writings as an influential source for Strindberg’s <hi rend="i">Easter.</hi>]</p>
            <p>190. *Nevitt, J. “William Godwin, 1789-1796.” Diss. U of Oxford, Oxon., 1981.</p>
            <p>191. *Pénigault-Duhet, Paule. <hi rend="i">Mary Wollstonecraft-Godwin (1759-1797).</hi> Paris,
Fr.: Didier Érudition, 1984. Fr 195.00. [A book of almost 800 pages which originated in a U of Lille
dissertation.]</p>
            <p>192. *Philp, Mark. <hi rend="i">Godwin’s</hi> Political Justice. London: Duckworth, 1987.
£28.00</p>
            <p>193. *Powell, David. <hi rend="i">Tom Paine: The Greatest Exile.</hi> New York, NY: St.
Martin’s P, 1985. $22.50.</p>
            <p>194. Scheiber, Andrew J. “Falkland’s Story: <hi rend="i">Caleb Williams</hi>’ Other
Voice.” <hi rend="i">Studies in the Novel</hi> 17 (1985): 255-66. [On narrative perspective in Godwin’s
novel.]</p>
            <p>195. Shortland, Michael. “The Power of a Thousand Eyes: Johann Caspar Lavater’s Science of
Physiognomical Perception.” <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 28 (1986): 379-408.</p>
            <p>196. Watson, George. “The Reckless Disciple: Godwin’s Shelley.” <hi rend="i">Hudson
Review</hi> 39 (1986): 212-30.</p>
            <p>197. *Wollstonecraft, Mary, and William Godwin. <hi rend="i">A Short Residence in Sweden /
Memoirs of the Author of</hi> The Rights of Woman. Ed. Richard Holmes. Penguin Classics. Harmondsworth, Mddx.:
Penguin, 1987. £3.95/$6.95 paper.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Some Blake Scholars and Collectors</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>198. Atkinson. F. G. “Unpublished Letters of Laurence Binyon (I): The Years of Struggle.”
<hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 29 (1982): 335-39.</p>
            <p>199. Atkinson, F. G. “Unpublished Letters of Laurence Binyon (II): The Years of
Achievement.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 31 (1984): 72-76.</p>
            <p>200. Aubrey, Bryan. “‘Telling of Presence’: The Poetry of Kathleen Raine.” 
<hi rend="i">Studia Mystica</hi> 9.4 (1986): 14-25.</p>
            <p>201. Block, Ed, Jr. “Walter Pater, Arthur Symons, W. B. Yeats, and the Fortunes of the
Literary Portrait.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Literature 1500-1900</hi> 26 (1986): 759-76.</p>
            <p>202. Beckson, Karl. “Arthur Symons on John Millington Synge: A Previously Unpublished
Memoir.” <hi rend="i">Éire-Ireland</hi> 21.4 (1986): 77-80.</p>
            <p>203. Carter, Sebastian. “Arnold Fawcus and the Trianon Press.” <hi rend="i">Matrix</hi> 3
(1983): 77-93. [Contains much relevant information on Fawcus’s biography and professional character as well
as on Trianon Press’s publications in general and its Blake related projects in particular. Also included is
a checklist of Trianon Press publications, compiled by Julie Fawcus (91-93). The author, in 1964, designed the
version of Blake’s signature which today still serves as this journal’s official ‘trade mark.’]</p>
            <p>204. *Chaplin, Harry F. <hi rend="i">Jack Lindsay: A Catalogue of First Editions, Extensively
Annotated by the Author, Together with Letters, Manuscripts, and Association Items.</hi> Sydney, Austral.:
Wentworth P, 1983. $12.00. [The bibliography of Jack Lindsay’s fictional and critical writings, in a limited
edition of 225 copies.]</p>
            <p>205. Cook, David. <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye: A Vision of the New World.</hi> New World
Perspectives. Montréal, PQ: New World Perspectives/Perspectives Nouveau Monde, 1985. $7.95. [As is to be
expected, Frye’s understanding of the poetry and art of William Blake figures prominently in this study of
his achievements and influence as a literary critic.]</p>
            <p>206. Dunn, John J. “Darrell Figgis, a Man Nearly Anonymous.” <hi rend="i">Journal of Irish
Literature</hi> 15.1 (1986): 33-42. [On the life, the literary and political activities, and the death of the
author of <hi rend="i">The Paintings of William Blake</hi> (1925).]</p>
            <p>207. *Edwards, Ruth Dudley. <hi rend="i">Victor Gollancz: A Biography.</hi> London: Gollancz,
1987. £20.00.</p>
            <p>208. Egremont, Max. “The Third Earl of Egremont and His Friends.” <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>
122 (1985): 280-87. [See especially 284 for George O’Brien Wyndham, 3rd Earl of Egremont, as a collector of
the works of William Blake.]</p>
            <p>209. *Fite, David. <hi rend="i">Harold Bloom: The Rhetoric of Romantic Vision.</hi> Amherst,
MA: U of Massachusetts P, 1985. $25.00.</p>
            <p>210. Graff, Robert D., et. al. <hi rend="i">The Grolier Club 1884-1984: Its Library,
Exhibitions, and Publications.</hi>
	<pb id="p21-66" n="66"/>
New York, NY: Grolier Club, 1984. $125.00. [See 137, 149, 158, 160 in the list of “Publications of the
Grolier Club, 1884-1983” and the “Exhibition Handlist” for the Club’s Blake-related projects; the
edition of this <hi rend="i">festschrift</hi> is limited to 600 copies.]</p>
            <p>211. Hope, Warren, ed. “Ruthven Todd’s Memories of Norman Cameron: A Sketch Written in
1973.” <hi rend="i">Poetry Review</hi> 76.1/2 (1986): 95-97.</p>
            <p>212. Johnson, Alan, ed. “Arthur Symons’ ‘The Life and Adventures of Lucy Newcome’:
Preface and Text.” <hi rend="i">English Literature in Transition 1880-1920</hi> 28 (1985): 332-45.</p>
            <p>213. Johnson, Alan, ed. “‘An Episode in the Life of Jenny Lane.’ By Arthur Symons. With
an Afterword.” <hi rend="i">English Literature in Transition 1880-1920</hi> 29 (1986): 351-59. [The
Blake-related interest in this and the two preceding entries admittedly is of the remotest possible nature
only; since, however, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> has itself published the imaginative work of some Blake
scholars, I decided to risk annoyance rather than being reproached with bibliographical negligence.]</p>
            <p>214. Kelly, John, with the assistance of Eric Domville, eds. <hi rend="i">The Collected Letters
of W. B. Yeats.</hi> Vol. 1: “1865-1895.” Oxford, Oxon.: Clarendon P, 1986. £22.50. [There are numerous
references to both Blake and Yeats’s fellow-editor of the elder poet’s <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, Edwin J.
Ellis; see the book’s index.]</p>
            <p>215. *Leigh, John. “Arthur Symons and the Evolution of Pound’s Concepts of Absolute Rhythm
and Precision.” <hi rend="i">Paideuma</hi> 15 (1986): 55-60.</p>
            <p>216. Lister, Raymond. “William Muir.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20
(1986): 49. [Quotes information which was supplied in a 1961 letter by the late Kerrison Preston.]</p>
            <p>217. Loveday, John. “Geoffrey Grigson, 1905-1985.” <hi rend="i">Agenda</hi> 23.3/4
(1985-1986): 221-22.</p>
            <p>218. Müller, Marianne. “Northrop Frye’s ‘Secular Scripture’: Structural Principles of
Literature.” <hi rend="i">Wissenschaftliche Zeitschrift der Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin:
Gesellschaftswissenschaftliche Reihe</hi> 33 (1984): 437-39.</p>
            <p>219. O’Hara, Daniel T. <hi rend="i">The Romance of Interpretation: Visionary Criticism from
Pater to de Man.</hi> New York, NY: Columbia UP, 1985. [Presents chapters on Pater, Bloom, Hartman, Frye, and
de Man as theorists of the romantic imagination.]</p>
            <p>220. Raine, Kathleen. “Eighteen Poems.” <hi rend="i">Agenda</hi> 24.2 (1986): 3-18.</p>
            <p>221. Sena, Vinod. <hi rend="i">The Poet as Critic: W. B. Yeats on Poetry, Drama and
Tradition.</hi> Delhi, India: Macmillan, 1980. [Contains numerous references to Yeats as a critic of Blake;
see the book’s index on 222 as well as #227, 229-31, below, for studies of Blake’s influence on Yeats’s
fictional poetry and prose, and #214, above, for Blake references in Yeats’s letters.]</p>
            <p>222. *Smith, Bernard, ed. <hi rend="i">Culture and History: Essays Presented to Jack
Lindsay.</hi> Sydney, Austral.: Hale, 1984. $24.95.</p>
            <p>223. *Szladits, Lola L. <hi rend="i">Brothers: The Origins of the Henry W. and Albert A. Berg
Collection of English and American Literature of the New York Public Library.</hi> New York, NY: New York
Public Library, 1985.</p>
            <p>224. Thornton, R. K. R. “Arthur Symons.” <hi rend="i">The Decadent Dilemma.</hi> London:
Arnold, 1983. 134-64. [The “dilemma” is unrelated to Symons’ Blake monograph of 1907.]</p>
            <p>225. “Un legs important de Sir Geoffrey Keynes.” <hi rend="i">Gazette des Beaux-Arts</hi>
6th ser. 108 (1986): “La Chronique des Arts” Sept. 1986: 21. [A brief and unsigned note on the Keynes
bequest of the Blake and Gooden collections to the Fitzwilliam Museum.]</p>
            <p>226. Warner, Eric, and Graham Hough, eds. <hi rend="i">Strangeness and Beauty: An Anthology of
Aesthetic Criticism 1840-1910.</hi> Vol. 2: “Pater to Arthur Symons.” Cambridge, Cambs.: Cambridge UP,
1983. £25.00 cloth / £7.95 paper. [The section devoted to Symons’ literary criticism (see 210-72) contains
selected quotations from his study of Blake on 267-72.]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="b">
                  <hi rend="i">Blakean Echoes in the Twentieth Century</hi>
                </hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>227. Cavanaugh, Catherine. <hi rend="i">Love and Forgiveness in Yeats’s Poetry.</hi> Studies
in Modern Literature 57. Ann Arbor, MI: UMI Research P, 1986. [Yeats’s indebtedness to his reading of
Blake’s poetry is discussed by the author, especially in her chapter “Celibate and Adept” (27-52).]</p>
            <p>228. Crutchfield, Will. “Bolcom Sets Blake to Several Kinds of Music.” <hi rend="i">New
York Times</hi> 9 Jan. 1987: C15. [Announces the New York premiere of William Bolcom’s “Songs of Innocence
and of Experience: A Musical Illumination of the Poems of William Blake” at the New Wave Festival; see also
#234 and 235, below.]</p>
            <p>229. Kline, Gloria C. <hi rend="i">The Last Courtly Lover: Yeats and the Idea of Woman.</hi>
Studies in Modern Literature 6. Ann Arbor, MI: UMI Research P, 1983. [Blake’s influence on Yeats’s
concepts of “courtly love” and of woman is treated on many pages of this study.]</p>
            <p>230. Levine, Herbert J. <hi rend="i">Yeats’s Daimonic Renewal.</hi> Studies in Modern
Literature 16. Ann Arbor, MI: UMI Research P, 1983. [Numerous references to Yeats’s encounter with his
precursor Blake are listed in the index.]</p>
            <p>231. *Loizeaux, Elizabeth Bergmann. <hi rend="i">Yeats and the Visual Arts.</hi> New Brunswick,
NJ: Rutgers UP, 1986. £29.95. [“ . . . shows how Pre-Raphaelite principles—filtered through late
19th-century aestheticism and reaching back to William Blake—always underlay Yeats’s attitudes toward
art” (quoted from a publishers’ advert).]</p>
            <p>232. *Milosz, Czeslaw. <hi rend="i">The Land of Ulro.</hi> Trans. Louis Iribarne. Manchester,
Lancs.: Carcanet P, 1985.
<pb id="p21-67" n="67"/>
£12.95 / $16.95. [Comments on both Swedenborg and Blake; the first edition was published in Poland in
1978.]</p>
            <p>233. Praly, Raymonde. “A Neoplatonic Variation from the Bird’s [sic] Songs of Innocence to
Their Songs of Experience in <hi rend="i">The Waves.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Cahiers Victoriens et
Edouardiens</hi> 25 (1987): 49-61. [On Blake and Virginia Woolf.]</p>
            <p>234. Rich, Alan. “Tiger, Tiger Daring Bright: Bolcom Illumines Blake.” 
<hi rend="i">Newsweek</hi> 19 Jan. 1987: 58. [Comments on Bolcom’s choral cantata “Songs of Innocence and of
Experience: A Musical Illumination of the Poems of William Blake;” see also #228, above, and #235,
below.]</p>
            <p>235. Rockwell, John. “Music: Bolcom’s Rendering of Blake’s ‘Songs.’ ” 
<hi rend="i">New York Times</hi> 11 Jan. 1987, sec. 1: 42. [See #228 and 234, above.]</p>
            <p>236. Slotten, Ralph. “William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Studia Mystica</hi> 9.4 (1986): 13. [A
poem.]</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part IV</hi>
              <lb/>
              <hi rend="b">Reviews of Works Cited Above and in Previous Checklists</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>237. Abley, Mark, ed. <hi rend="i">The Parting Light: Selected Writings of Samuel Palmer.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 27 Feb. 1987: 216; by (2) Charles
Tomlinson, <hi rend="i">PN Review</hi> 13.2 (1986): 52-53.</p>
          <p>238. Abrams, Ann Uhry. <hi rend="i">The Valiant Hero: Benjamin West and Grand-Style History
Painting.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Henry Adams, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 128 (1986): 435-36; by (2)
Marcus Cunliffe [or a collaborator], <hi rend="i">American Studies International</hi> 24.2 (1986): 86
[briefly!].</p>
          <p>239. Adams, Hazard. <hi rend="i">Philosophy of the Literary Symbolic.</hi> Reviewed by (1)
Shyamal Bagchee, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi> 84 (1986): 239-41; by (2) William Keach, 
<hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 35 (1986): 213-18; in (3) <hi rend="i">Poetics Today</hi> 5 (1984): 212;
see also #6, above.</p>
          <p>240. Albright, Daniel. <hi rend="i">Lyricality in English Literature.</hi> Reviewed by J.
Wilkinson, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 23 (1985): 599.</p>
          <p>241. Aldridge, A. Owen. <hi rend="i">Thomas Paine’s American Ideology.</hi> Reviewed by (1)
Joyce O. Appleby, <hi rend="i">Journal of American History</hi> 72 (1985): 679-80; by (2) Roger Asselineau,
<hi rend="i">Revue de Littérature Comparée</hi> 60 (1986): 240-41; by (3) Robert A. Ferguson, 
<hi rend="i">American Literature</hi> 57 (1985): 490-91; by (4) G. L. Jones, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1985):
1221; by (5) Steven Rosswurm, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 19 (1986): 549-51.</p>
          <p>242. Altick, Richard D. <hi rend="i">Paintings from Books: Art and Literature in Britain,
1760-1900.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Peter Campbell, <hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi> 4 Dec. 1986: 20-21;
in (2) <hi rend="i">English Literature in Transition 1880-1920</hi> 29 (1986): 343 [very briefly]; by (3)
Robert Bernard Martin, <hi rend="i">New York Review of Books</hi> 12 Feb. 1987: 29-30; by (4) S. Skaggs, 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 24 (1986): 99.</p>
          <p>243. Baine, Rodney M., with the assistance of Mary R. Baine. <hi rend="i">The Scattered Portions:
William Blake’s Biological Symbolism.</hi> Reviewed by Brian Allen, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 125 (1987):
150-51.</p>
          <p>244. Baker, Carlos. <hi rend="i">The Echoing Green: Romanticism, Modernism, and the Phenomena of
Transference in Poetry.</hi> Reviewed by (1) George Bornstein, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 16 (1985):
180-82; by (2) Richard Harter Fogle, <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 35 (1986): 218-20; by (3) David
Perkins, <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 25 (1986): 295-98; by (4) Linda Wagner, 
<hi rend="i">Contemporary Literature</hi> 26 (1985): 482-86; by (5) A. K. Weatherhead, <hi rend="i">Comparative
Literature</hi> 39 (1987): 94-96.</p>
          <p>245. Barrell, John. <hi rend="i">The Political Theory of Painting from Reynolds to Hazlitt:
“The Body of the Public.”</hi> Reviewed by (1) Thomas Crow, <hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi> 19
Mar. 1987: 10-12; by (2) Graham Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 124 (1986): 568; by (3) Pat Rogers, 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 9 Jan. 1987: 44.</p>
          <p>246. Bate, Jonathan. <hi rend="i">Shakespeare and the English Romantic Imagination.</hi> Reviewed
by M. Minor, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 24 (1986): 622.</p>
          <p>247. Behrendt, Stephen C. <hi rend="i">The Moment of Explosion: Blake and the Illustration of
Milton.</hi> Reviewed by David W. Lindsay, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi> 17 (1987):
304-05.</p>
          <p>248. Bertholf, Robert J., and Annette S. Levitt, eds. <hi rend="i">William Blake and the
Moderns.</hi> Reviewed by Kurt Heinzelmann [i.e., Heinzelman], <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 8 (1982): 384-86.</p>
          <p>249. <hi rend="i">Blake:</hi> The Marriage of Heaven and Hell<hi rend="i">: Television
Docudrama.</hi> Dir. Harvey Bellin and Tom Kieffer. Swedenborg Foundation, 1984. Reviewed by Tim Hoyer, 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986): 68-70.</p>
          <p>250. Bloom, Harold. <hi rend="i">Agon: Towards a Theory of Revisionism.</hi> Reviewed by (1)
Denis Donoghue, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 30 July 1982: 811-12; by (2) Frank McCombie, 
<hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 30 (1983): 567-68; by (3) Marjorie Perloff, <hi rend="i">Modern Language
Review</hi> 81 (1986): 431-35; by (4) Ann Wordsworth, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 36
(1985): 458-61.</p>
          <p>251. Bogel, Fredric V. <hi rend="i">Literature and Insubstantiality in Later Eighteenth-Century
England.</hi> Reviewed by (1) John A. Dussinger, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi>
85 (1986): 456-59; by (2) Wallace Jackson, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986): 57-60;
by (3) François Piquet, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi> 38 (1985): 467; by (4) Bruce Redford, 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 19 (1986): 414-417; by (5) Nigel Wood, <hi rend="i">Durham University
Journal</hi> ns 48 (1986): 135-36.</p>
          <p>252. Borck, Jim Springer, ed. <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A Current Bibliography.</hi>
Vol. 7 for 1981 reviewed by Paul-Gabriel Boucé, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi> 40 (1987): 86-88.</p>
          <pb id="p21-68" n="68"/>
          <p>253. Bracher, Mark. <hi rend="i">“Being Form’d”: Thinking Through Blake’s</hi> Milton.
Reviewed by (1) Stephen C. Behrendt, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi> 86 (1987):
256-59; by (2) Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and Present</hi> 10.1 (1986): 67-70; by (3) Andrew
Lincoln, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 38 (1987): 85-87; by (4) *Joseph Wittreich, 
<hi rend="i">Religion and Literature</hi> 18.1 (1986): 79-82.</p>
          <p>254. Brantley, Richard E. <hi rend="i">Locke, Wesley, and the Method of English Romanticism.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) *James Chandler, <hi rend="i">Journal of Religion</hi> 66 (1986): 106-08; by (2) Leopold
Damrosch, Jr., <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 19 (1986): 438-41; by (3) *John Greenfield, 
<hi rend="i">South Atlantic Review</hi> 51 (1986): 140; by (4) Lisa Low, <hi rend="i">Kritikon Litterarum</hi> 13
(1984): 86-87; by (5) *D. G. Paz, <hi rend="i">Religious Studies</hi> 11 (1985): 304; by (6) John C.
Villalobos, <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 48 (1985): 313-18.</p>
          <p>255. Butler, Marilyn. <hi rend="i">Burke, Paine, Godwin, and the Revolutionary Controversy.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) C. B. Jones, <hi rend="i">Prose Studies</hi> 8.1 (1985): 82-84; by (2) I. K. [i.e., Isaac
Kramnick], <hi rend="i">Ethics</hi> 96 (1986): 687-88; by (3) Alain Morvan, <hi rend="i">Études
Anglaises</hi> 39 (1986): 224; by (4) Mark Philp, <hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century
Studies</hi> 9 (1986): 244-46; by (5) William Stafford, <hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi> 12 (1986):
255-57.</p>
          <p>256. Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by
Morris Eaves, <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 25 (1986): 147-54.</p>
          <p>257. Cantor, Paul A. <hi rend="i">Creature and Creator: Myth-Making and English Romanticism.</hi>
Reviewed by Terence German, <hi rend="i">Theological Studies</hi> 47 (1986): 196-97.</p>
          <p>258. Cook, David. <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye: A Vision of the New World.</hi> Reviewed by (1)
Ramsay Cook, <hi rend="i">University of Toronto Quarterly</hi> 56 (1986): 157-59; by (2) Lorne Ellaschuk, 
<hi rend="i">Books in Canada</hi> Mar. 1986: 20.</p>
          <p>259. Dorment, Richard. <hi rend="i">British Painting in the Philadelphia Museum of Art: From the
Seventeenth through the Nineteenth Century.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Brian Allen, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 125
(1987): 150-51; by (2) John Ingamells, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 129 (1987): 123; by (3) Graham
Reynolds, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 27 Mar. 1987: 334.</p>
          <p>260. Edwards, Ruth Dudley. <hi rend="i">Victor Gollancz: A Biography.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Robin
Blackburn, <hi rend="i">New Statesman</hi> 20 Feb. 1987: 29-30; by (2) Valentine Cunningham, 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 13 Feb. 1987: 156.</p>
          <p>261. Erdman, David V., ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi>
Reviewed by Robert F. Gleckner, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 8 (1982): 386-87; see also #44 and 60, above.</p>
          <p>262. Erffa, Helmut von, and Allen Staley. <hi rend="i">The Paintings of Benjamin West.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) Brian Allen, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 124 (1986): 455; in (2) <hi rend="i">Gazette des
Beaux-Arts</hi> 6th ser. 109 (1987): “La Chronique des Arts” Jan. 1987: 25; by (3) John Hayes, 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 24 Oct. 1986: 1179-80; by (4) R. W. Liscombe, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi>
24 (1986): 108; by (5) William L. Pressly, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 128 (1986): 752-53; by (6) L.
C. R. [i.e., Licia Collobi-Ragghianti?], <hi rend="i">Critica d’Arte</hi> 4th ser. 51.11 (1986): 77-79; by
(7) John Spurling, <hi rend="i">New Statesman</hi> 15 Aug. 1986: 28-29 [briefly noticed only].</p>
          <p>263. Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue.</hi>
Reviewed by David Scrase, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986): 64-66.</p>
          <p>264. Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">The Works of William Blake in the Huntington Collections: A
Complete Catalogue.</hi> Reviewed by Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 129 (1987):
123-24.</p>
          <p>265. Ferber, Michael. <hi rend="i">The Social Vision of William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by (1)
Jenijoy La Belle, <hi rend="i">Romanticism Past and Present</hi> 10.1 (1986): 63-66; by (2) Andrew Lincoln,
<hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 38 (1987): 85-87; by (3) Karen Shabetai, 
<hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 28 (1986): 343-46.</p>
          <p>266. Fite, David. <hi rend="i">Harold Bloom: The Rhetoric of Romantic Vision.</hi> Reviewed by W.
D. Horn, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 23 (1986): 1670.</p>
          <p>267. Forster, Harold. <hi rend="i">Edward Young: The Poet of the</hi> Night Thoughts, 
<hi rend="i">1683-1765.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Pat Rogers, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 20 Mar. 1987:
287-88; see also (2) Jonathan Bate’s letter, <hi rend="i">ibid.</hi> 3 Apr. 1987: 351.</p>
          <p>268. Fruchtman, Jack, Jr. <hi rend="i">The Apocalyptic Politics of Richard Price and Joseph
Priestley: A Study in Late Eighteenth-Century English Republican Millennialism.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Margaret
Canovan, <hi rend="i">English Historical Review</hi> 101 (1986): 512-13; by (2) *Margaret C. Jacob, 
<hi rend="i">Isis</hi> 76.281 (1985): 128; by (3) *Ernest Tuveson, <hi rend="i">Church History</hi> 53 (1984):
558.</p>
          <p>269. Frye, Northrop. <hi rend="i">The Great Code: The Bible and Literature.</hi> Reviewed by (1)
Gerald Gillespie, <hi rend="i">Comparative Literature</hi> 38 (1986): 289-97; see also (2) Alvin A. Lee,
“Towards a Language of Love and Freedom: Frye Deciphers the Great Code.” <hi rend="i">English Studies in
Canada</hi> 12 (1986): 124-37.</p>
          <p>270. Gardner, Stanley. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Innocence and Experience Retraced.</hi> Reviewed by
G. A. Cevasco, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 24 (1986): 475.</p>
          <p>271. Gizzi, Corrado, ed. <hi rend="i">Flaxman e Dante.</hi> Reviewed by Carlo Bertelli, 
<hi rend="i">Corriere della Sera</hi> 8 Oct. 1986: 18, “Arte”/4.</p>
          <p>272. Gleckner, Robert F. <hi rend="i">Blake and Spenser.</hi> Reviewed by Stephen C. Behrendt,
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 257-60.</p>
          <p>273. Gleckner, Robert F. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prelude:</hi> Poetical Sketches. Reviewed by Kurt
Heinzelman, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 8 (1982): 389-90.</p>
          <p>274. Glen, Heather. <hi rend="i">Vision and Disenchantment: Blake’s Songs and
Wordsworth’s</hi> Lyrical Ballads. Reviewed by (1) Michael H. Friedman, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi>
16 (1985): 160-63; by (2) Edward Larrissy, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi> 17 (1987):
305-06.</p>
          <p>275. Graff, Robert D., et al. <hi rend="i">The Grolier Club</hi>
	<pb id="p21-69" n="69"/>
	<hi rend="i">1884-1984: Its Library, Exhibitions, and Publications.</hi> Reviewed by (1) *R. C. Alston, 
<hi rend="i">Library</hi> 6th ser. 8 (1986): 279-81; by (2) D. F. McKenzie, <hi rend="i">Papers of the
Bibliographical Society of America</hi> 79 (1985): 579-80.</p>
          <p>276. Graham, John. <hi rend="i">Lavater’s</hi> Essays on Physiognomy: <hi rend="i">A Study in
the History of Ideas.</hi> Reviewed by E. Heier, <hi rend="i">Canadian Review of Comparative Literature /
Revue Canadienne de Littérature Comparée</hi> 13 (1986): 138-40.</p>
          <p>277. Griffin, Dustin. <hi rend="i">Regaining Paradise: Milton and the Eighteenth Century.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) D. J. Littlefield, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 24 (1986): 624; by (2) Lucy Newlyn, 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 8 Aug. 1986: 871; by (3) Ashraf H. A. Rushdy, <hi rend="i">Essays in
Criticism</hi> 37 (1987): 67-71; by (4) James Sambrook, <hi rend="i">Times Higher Education Supplement</hi> 1
Aug. 1986: 17.</p>
          <p>278. Griffiths, Antony, and Reginald Williams. <hi rend="i">The Department of Prints and Drawings
in the British Museum: User’s Guide.</hi> Reviewed by David Bindman, <hi rend="i">Times Literary
Supplement</hi> 27 Mar. 1987: 334.</p>
          <p>279. Hagstrum, Jean H. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Body: Love and Sexuality in Keats, Wordsworth,
and Blake.</hi> Reviewed by N[orman] Fruman, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 23 (1986): 1675.</p>
          <p>280. Hilton, Nelson. <hi rend="i">Literal Imagination: Blake’s Vision of Words.</hi> Reviewed
by (1) Donald Ault, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 16 (1985): 163-65; by (2) David Fuller, 
<hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 9 (1986): 269-70; see also #6, above.</p>
          <p>281. Hoagwood, Terence Allan. <hi rend="i">Prophecy and the Philosophy of Mind: Traditions of
Blake and Shelley.</hi> Reviewed by (1) *David L. Ackiss, <hi rend="i">South Atlantic Review</hi> 51 (1986):
136; by (2) Alan Robinson, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 37 (1986): 576-77; see also #17,
above.</p>
          <p>282. Hodnett, Edward. <hi rend="i">Image and Text: Studies in the Illustration of English
Literature.</hi> Reviewed by David Blewett, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 8 (1982): 344-45.</p>
          <p>283. Hošek, Chaviva, and Patricia Parker, eds. <hi rend="i">Lyric Poetry: Beyond New
Criticism.</hi> Reviewed by Michael H. Keefer, <hi rend="i">University of Toronto Quarterly</hi> 56 (1986):
127-29.</p>
          <p>284. Hutchings, Bill. <hi rend="i">The Poetry of William Cowper.</hi> Reviewed by Joan H.
Pittock, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi> 17 (1987): 303-04.</p>
          <p>285. Jaffé, Michael, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake and His Contemporaries.</hi> Reviewed by
Judy Egerton, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 128 (1986): 619-21.</p>
          <p>286. Kelly, John, with the assistance of Eric Domville, eds. <hi rend="i">The Collected Letters
of W. B. Yeats.</hi> Vol. 1 reviewed by (1) S. Barnet, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 23 (1986): 1680; by (2) Denis
Donoghue, <hi rend="i">New York Review of Books</hi> 14 Aug. 1986: 14-16; by (3) René Fréchet, 
<hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi> 39 (1986): 474-75; by (4) Roy Fuller, <hi rend="i">London Magazine</hi> ns
26.1/2 (1986): 145-48; by (5) Jacqueline Genet, <hi rend="i">Études Irlandaises</hi> ns 11 (1986): 241-44; by
(6) Maurice Harmon, <hi rend="i">Irish University Review</hi> 16 (1986): 101-02.</p>
          <p>287. King, James. <hi rend="i">William Cowper: A Biography.</hi> Reviewed by J. Wilkinson, 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 23 (1986): 1676-77.</p>
          <p>288. King, James, and Charles Ryskamp, eds. <hi rend="i">The Letters and Prose Writings of
William Cowper.</hi> Vol. 1 reviewed in (1) <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 17 (1980): 384. Vols. 2-4 reviewed by (2)
Patricia Meyer Spacks, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi> 84 (1985): 559-62. Vol. 3
reviewed by (3) Paul J. deGategno, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 8 (1982): 416-17; by (4) *Christopher Hawtree, 
<hi rend="i">Literary Review</hi> 57 (1983): 6-8.</p>
          <p>289. King-Hele, Desmond. <hi rend="i">Erasmus Darwin and the Romantic Poets.</hi> Reviewed by (1)
Gillian Beer, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 19 Sept. 1986: 1036; by (2) T[erence] A[llan]
Hoagwood, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 23 (1986): 1541.</p>
          <p>290. Knapp, Steven. <hi rend="i">Personification and the Sublime: Milton to Coleridge.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) Rosemary Ashton, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 19 Sept. 1986: 1035-36; by (2)
Keith G. Thomas, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 20 (1987): 395-98.</p>
          <p>291. Kroeber, Karl. <hi rend="i">British Romantic Art.</hi> Reviewed by D. Kolker, 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 24 (1987): 751.</p>
          <p>292. Larrissy, Edward. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Nelson Hilton, 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986): 66-68; by (2) T[erence] A[llan] Hoagwood, 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 23 (1986): 1390.</p>
          <p>293. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">The Paintings of Samuel Palmer.</hi> Reviewed by David Blayney
Brown, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 128 (1986): 436-37.</p>
          <p>294. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">The Paintings of William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by Brian Allen,
<hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 125 (1987): 150-51.</p>
          <p>295. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">Prints and Printmaking: A Dictionary and Handbook of the Art
in Nineteenth-Century Britain.</hi> Reviewed in (1) <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 126 (1984): 796; by
(2) Simon Houfe, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 121 (1985): 211.</p>
          <p>296. Marshall, Peter [H.], ed. <hi rend="i">The Anarchist Writings of William Godwin.</hi>
Reviewed by Nicolas Walter, <hi rend="i">New Statesman</hi> 14 Mar. 1986: 28.</p>
          <p>297. Marshall, Peter H. <hi rend="i">William Godwin: Philosopher, Novelist, Revolutionary.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) James K. Chandler, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi> 82 (1987): 173-76; by (2) J. R.
Dinwiddy, <hi rend="i">English Historical Review</hi> 102 (1987): 506-07; by (3) Rodney W. Kilcup, 
<hi rend="i">Review of Politics</hi> 48 (1986): 133-35; by (4) David McCracken, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi>
84 (1986): 99-101; by (5) Edward Royle, <hi rend="i">History</hi> 70 (1985): 524-25; by (6) William Stafford,
<hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi> 12 (1986): 255-57; by (7) Marion K. Stocking, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth
Circle</hi> 16 (1985): 190-92; by (8) Ralph M. Wardle, <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 35 (1986):
205-07; by (9) G. W. [i.e., George Woodcock], <hi rend="i">Ethics</hi> 96 (1986): 453.</p>
          <p>298. McGann, Jerome J. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Ideology: A Critical Investigation.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) Lilian R. Furst, <hi rend="i">Canadian Review of Comparative Literature / Revue Canadienne de
Littérature Comparée</hi> 13 (1986): 301-03;
<pb id="p21-70" n="70"/>
by (2) Marjorie Levinson, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 16 (1985): 171-75; by (3) Anne K. Mellor, 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 25 (1986): 282-86.</p>
          <p>299. Meisel, Martin. <hi rend="i">Realizations: Narrative, Pictorial, and Theatrical Arts in
Nineteenth-Century England.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Richard D. Altick, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and
Germanic Philology</hi> 84 (1985): 278-81; by (2) C. B. Cooper, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1984): 73; by (3)
George Levine, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi> 84 (1986): 233-35; by (4) *David Mayer and by *Simon
William, <hi rend="i">Theatre Survey</hi> 26 (1985): 85-88 and 246-49; by (5) G. B. Tennyson, 
<hi rend="i">Nineteenth-Century Fiction</hi> 39 (1984): 112-15; by (6) W. V. [i.e., William Vaughan?], 
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 129 (1987): 130; by (7) Martha Vicinus, <hi rend="i">Victorian Studies</hi>
28 (1985): 527-28; by (8) Joseph Viscomi, <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 25 (1986): 561-67.</p>
          <p>300. Mell, Donald C., Jr. <hi rend="i">English Poetry 1660-1800: A Guide to Information
Sources.</hi> Reviewed by (1) M[ichel] Baridon, <hi rend="i">Dix-Huitième Siècle</hi> 16 (1984): 498-99; by
(2) A. J. Sambrook, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi> 17 (1987): 289-90.</p>
          <p>301. Milosz, Czeslaw. <hi rend="i">The Land of Ulro.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Stanislaw Baranczak,
<hi rend="i">Partisan Review</hi> 52 (1985): 448-52; by (2) Roger Scruton, <hi rend="i">Times Literary
Supplement</hi> 3 Oct. 1986: 1092.</p>
          <p>302. Murry, Katherine Middleton. <hi rend="i">Beloved Quixote: The Unknown Life of John Middleton
Murry.</hi> Reviewed by Kate Kellaway, <hi rend="i">New Statesman</hi> 28 Mar. 1986: 28-29.</p>
          <p>303. Newey, Vincent. <hi rend="i">Cowper’s Poetry: A Critical Study and Reassessment.</hi>
Reviewed by Patricia Meyer Spacks, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 8 (1982): 418-19.</p>
          <p>304. O’Hara, Daniel T. <hi rend="i">The Romance of Interpretation: Visionary Criticism from
Pater to de Man.</hi> Reviewed by R. H. Sanders, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 23 (1986): 1383-84.</p>
          <p>305. Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">The Apocalyptic Sublime.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Brian Allen, 
<hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 125 (1987): 150-51; by (2) John Gage, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 27 Feb.
1987: 216; see also (3) Morton D. Paley’s reply to Gage’s review, <hi rend="i">ibid.</hi> 1 May 1987:
463.</p>
          <p>306. Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">The Continuing City: William Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem.
Reviewed by (1) Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Quarterly</hi> 45 (1984): 413-15; by (2) Mary Lynn
Johnson, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi> 85 (1986): 275-78; by (3) David W.
Lindsay, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi> 17 (1987): 304-05; by (4) *Hatsuko Niimi, 
<hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature</hi> [Tokyo, Jap.] 61 (1986): 59-64[?]; by (5) David Worrall, 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 25 (1986): 277-81; see also #6, above.</p>
          <p>307. Patrides, C. A., and Joseph Wittreich, eds. <hi rend="i">The Apocalypse in English
Renaissance Thought and Literature: Patterns, Antecedents and Repercussions.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Frank
Kermode, <hi rend="i">Renaissance Quarterly</hi> 38 (1985): 554-57; by (2) Morton D. Paley, 
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986): 53-56.</p>
          <p>308. Paulson, Ronald. <hi rend="i">Book and Painting—Shakespeare, Milton, and the Bible:
Literary Texts and the Emergence of English Painting.</hi> Reviewed by Lawrence J. Homolka, 
<hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 8 (1982): 299-300.</p>
          <p>309. Paulson, Ronald. <hi rend="i">Literary Landscape: Turner and Constable.</hi> Reviewed by (1)
Thomas J. McCormick, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 8 (1982): 300-01; by (2) Kathleen Nicholson, <hi rend="i">Art
Bulletin</hi> 68 (1986): 343-45.</p>
          <p>310. Paulson, Ronald. <hi rend="i">Representations of Revolution (1789-1820).</hi> Reviewed by
(1) Thomas Crow, <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi> 68 (1986): 497-502; by (2) David P. Jordan, 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 27 (1986): 205-08; by (3) Peter Wagner, 
<hi rend="i">Archiv für das Studium der neueren Sprachen und Literaturen</hi> 222 (1985): 477-78.</p>
          <p>311. Peckham, Morse. <hi rend="i">The Birth of Romanticism: Cultural Crisis, 1790-1815.</hi>
Reviewed by M. B. Friedman, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 24 (1987): 868.</p>
          <p>312. Pénigault-Duhet, Paule. <hi rend="i">Mary Wollstonecraft-Godwin (1759-1797).</hi> Reviewed
by (1) Michel Baridon, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi> 39 (1986): 354; by (2) J[ean] Ducrocq, 
<hi rend="i">Dix-Huitième Siècle</hi> 17 (1985): 495; by (3) Emily W. Sunstein, <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley
Journal</hi> 35 (1986): 203-05.</p>
          <p>313. Philp, Mark. <hi rend="i">Godwin’s</hi> Political Justice. Reviewed by Don Locke, 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 20 Feb. 1987: 178.</p>
          <p>314. Poovey, Mary. <hi rend="i">The Proper Lady and the Woman Writer: Ideology as Style in the
Works of Mary Wollstonecraft, Mary Shelley, and Jane Austen.</hi> Reviewed by (1) *Mary Hughes Brookhart, 
<hi rend="i">South Atlantic Review</hi> 51 (1986): 133-36 [?]; by (2) James V. Catano, <hi rend="i">Style</hi> 19
(1985): 403-10; by (3) Kathleen Fowler, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 16 (1985): 199-200; by (4) *Evelyn
L. Pugh, <hi rend="i">Clio</hi> 14 (1985); by (5) Judith Wilt, <hi rend="i">Modern Philology</hi> 83 (1986):
434-37.</p>
          <p>315. Powell, David. <hi rend="i">Tom Paine: The Greatest Exile.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Daryl E.
Jones, <hi rend="i">American Literature</hi> 58 (1986): 624-26; by (2) Brian Martin, <hi rend="i">New
Statesman</hi> 23 May 1986: 29; by (3) James Kirby Martin, <hi rend="i">Journal of American History</hi> 73
(1986): 457-58.</p>
          <p>316. Pressly, Nancy L. <hi rend="i">The Fuseli Circle in Rome: Early Romantic Art of the
1770s.</hi> Reviewed in (1) *<hi rend="i">Connaissance des Arts</hi> Sept. 1979; by (2) *Gert Schiff, 
<hi rend="i">Arts Magazine</hi> Dec. 1979; by (3) David H. Solkin, <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi> 67 (1985):
507-15; by (4) *S. Tennenbaum, <hi rend="i">Arts Canada</hi> Apr.-May 1980.</p>
          <p>317. Pressly, William L. <hi rend="i">The Life and Art of James Barry.</hi> Reviewed by David H.
Solkin, <hi rend="i">Art Bulletin</hi> 67 (1985): 507-15.</p>
          <p>318. Punter, David. <hi rend="i">Blake, Hegel, and Dialectic.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Ernest
Bernhardt-Kabisch, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 8 (1982): 392; by (2) *Michael Fischer, <hi rend="i">Philosophy and
Literature</hi> 7 (1983): 265-66.</p>
          <p>319. Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">The Human Face of God: William Blake and The Book of Job.</hi>
Reviewed by Robert F. Gleckner, <hi rend="i">ECCB</hi> 8 (1982): 393-94.</p>
          <pb id="p21-71" n="71"/>
          <p>320. Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">L’Imagination créatrice de William Blake.</hi> Reviewed by
François Piquet, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi> 39 (1986): 353-54.</p>
          <p>321. Rawson, Claude. <hi rend="i">Order from Confusion Sprung: Studies in Eighteenth-Century
Literature from Swift to Cowper.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Paul-Gabriel Boucé, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi>
40 (1987): 88-89; by (2) Frederick M. Keener, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi> 86
(1987): 116-18.</p>
          <p>322. Schulz, Max F. <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained: Recreations of Eden in Eighteenth- and
Nineteenth-Century England.</hi> Reviewed by (1) B. E. McCarthy, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 24 (1986): 310; by
(2) Serge Soupel, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi> 39 (1986): 464-65.</p>
          <p>323. Smith, Olivia. <hi rend="i">The Politics of Language 1791-1819.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Alain
Bony, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi> 39 (1986): 223; by (2) Gregory Claeys, <hi rend="i">Literature and
History</hi> 12 (1986): 257-58; by (3) M. A. Fingrutd, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1985): 1666; by (4) Alf
Louvre, <hi rend="i">Prose Studies</hi> 9.1 (1986): 78-80; by (5) Mark Philp, <hi rend="i">British Journal for
Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 9 (1986): 244-46; by (6) David Simpson, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986): 63-64.</p>
          <p>324. Stock, R. D. <hi rend="i">The Holy and the Daemonic from Sir Thomas Browne to William
Blake.</hi> Reviewed by Kent Ljungquist, <hi rend="i">University of Mississippi Studies in English</hi> ns 4
(1983): 195-96.</p>
          <p>325. Szladits, Lola L. <hi rend="i">Brothers: The Origins of the Henry W. and Albert A. Berg
Collection of English and American Literature of the New York Public Library.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Roger
Asselineau, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi> 39 (1986): 494 [briefly]; in (2) <hi rend="i">Bulletin of
Research in the Humanities</hi> 86 (1983-1985): 370-71.</p>
          <p>326. Tannenbaum, Leslie. <hi rend="i">Biblical Tradition in Blake’s Early Prophecies: The Great
Code of Art.</hi> Reviewed by (1) François Mouret, <hi rend="i">Revue de Littérature Comparée</hi> 59
(1985): 351-53; by (2) *Joseph Wittreich, <hi rend="i">Christianity and Literature</hi> 32.2 (1983):
59-62.</p>
          <p>327. Thorslev, Peter L., Jr. <hi rend="i">Romantic Contraries: Freedom versus Destiny.</hi>
Reviewed by (1) Stephen C. Behrendt, <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 27 (1985): 418-21; by (2) G. A. Cevasco, 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 22 (1984): 272; by (3) Stuart Curran, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 17 (1986):
192-94; by (4) James Engell, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Quarterly</hi> 46 (1985): 212-15; by (5) Robert F.
Gleckner, <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 34 (1985): 172-75; by (6) Nelson Hilton, 
<hi rend="i">Philosophy and Literature</hi> 9 (1985): 232-33; by (7) Rolf P. Lessenich, <hi rend="i">Anglia</hi>
105 (1987): 237-40; by (8) E. Pereira, <hi rend="i">UNISA English Studies</hi> 23.2 (1985): 48-52; by (9)
David Punter, <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986): 60-63; by (10) John R. Reed, 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 25 (1986): 156-59; by (11) Donald H. Reiman, <hi rend="i">Romanticism
Past and Present</hi> 10.2 (1986): 65-69; by (12) Alan Robinson, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi>
ns 37 (1986): 269-70.</p>
          <p>328. Twitchell, James B. <hi rend="i">Romantic Horizons: Aspects of the Sublime in English Poetry
and Painting, 1770-1850.</hi> Reviewed in (1) <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 21 (1984): 1454-55; by (2) Lucy Newlyn,
<hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 37 (1986): 430-33.</p>
          <p>329. Tysdahl, B. J. <hi rend="i">William Godwin as Novelist.</hi> Reviewed by *Wilbur S. Braden,
<hi rend="i">Philosophy and Literature</hi> 7 (1983): 130-31.</p>
          <p>330. Warner, Eric, and Graham Hough, eds. <hi rend="i">Strangers and Beauty: An Anthology of
Aesthetic Criticism 1840-1910.</hi> Reviewed by John Stokes, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi> 17
(1987): 331-32.</p>
          <p>331. Warner, Janet A. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Language of Art.</hi> Reviewed by Karen
Mulhallen, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 17 (1986): 202-04.</p>
          <p>332. Watson, J. R. <hi rend="i">English Poetry of the Romantic Period: 1789-1830.</hi> Reviewed
by (1) Jacques Blondel, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi> 39 (1986): 348-49; by (2) G. A. Cevasco, 
<hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 23 (1986): 1680; by (3) Martin Dodsworth, <hi rend="i">English</hi> 35 (1986): 102-09
[see 104 for a brief mention]; by (4) Mary Wedd, <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi> ns 48 (1986):
141-42.</p>
          <p>333. Watson, J. R., ed. <hi rend="i">An Infinite Complexity: Essays in Romanticism.</hi> Reviewed
by (1) François Piquet, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi> 39 (1986): 349-50; by (2) Nicholas Roe, 
<hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 32 (1985): 271-74; by (3) Paul D. Sheats, <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley
Journal</hi> 34 (1985): 175-77.</p>
          <p>334. Webster, Brenda S. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic Psychology.</hi> Reviewed by Christine
Gallant, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 16 (1985): 165-68; see also #6, above.</p>
          <p>335. Weiskel, Thomas. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Sublime: Studies in the Structure and Psychology
of Transcendence.</hi> The new edition reviewed in <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 21 Nov. 1986:
1327.</p>
          <p>336. Wendorf, Richard, ed. <hi rend="i">Articulate Images: The Sister Arts from Hogarth to
Tennyson.</hi> Reviewed by William Walling, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 16 (1985): 178-80.</p>
          <p>337. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s</hi> An Island in the Moon. Dir. Joseph Viscomi and Evamarii
Johnson. Department of English, U of North Carolina, 1983. Reviewed by Tim Hoyer, <hi rend="i">Blake/An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986): 68-70.</p>
          <p>338. Wind, Edgar. <hi rend="i">Hume and the Heroic Portrait: Studies in Eighteenth-Century
Imagery.</hi> Reviewed by (1) Brian Allen, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 125 (1987): 150-51; by (2) Arthur C.
Danto, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 17 Oct. 1986: 1116; by (3) John Gage, 
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 128 (1986): 906-07; by (4) Pat Rogers, <hi rend="i">London Review of
Books</hi> 6 Nov. 1986: 20-21.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="p21-72" n="72"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Index of Authors</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Abley, Mark 138, 237</p>
          <p>Abrams, Ann Uhry 167, 238</p>
          <p>Ackiss, David L. 281</p>
          <p>Adams, Hazard 6, 20, 60, 239</p>
          <p>Adams, Henry 238</p>
          <p>Albright, Daniel 240</p>
          <p>Aldridge, A. Owen 174, 241</p>
          <p>Allen, Brian 243, 259, 262, 294, 305, 338</p>
          <p>Allis, U. J. L. 21</p>
          <p>Alston, R. C. 275</p>
          <p>Altick, Richard D. 143, 242, 299</p>
          <p>Altizer, Thomas J. J. 144</p>
          <p>Andrews, Stuart 175</p>
          <p>Appleby, Joyce O. 241</p>
          <p>Argan, Giulio Carlo 127</p>
          <p>Arias Anglés, E. 123</p>
          <p>Ashton, Rosemary 290</p>
          <p>Asselineau, Roger 241, 325</p>
          <p>Atkinson, F. G. 198, 199</p>
          <p>Aubrey, Bryan 22, 200</p>
          <p>Auerbach, Nina 6</p>
          <p>Ault, Donald 60, 280</p>
          <p>Bagchee, Shyamal 239</p>
          <p>Baine, Mary R. 23, 243</p>
          <p>Baine, Rodney M. 23, 243</p>
          <p>Baker, Carlos 244</p>
          <p>Balfour, Ian Grant 24</p>
          <p>Baranczak, Stanislaw 301</p>
          <p>Baridon, Michel 300, 312</p>
          <p>Barnet, S. 286</p>
          <p>Barrell, John 25, 245</p>
          <p>Bate, Jonathan 145, 146, 246, 267</p>
          <p>Beckson, Karl 202</p>
          <p>Beer, Gillian 289</p>
          <p>Behrendt, Stephen C. 26, 247, 253, 272, 327</p>
          <p>Behrens, Jürgen 128</p>
          <p>Bellin, Harvey F. 27, 249</p>
          <p>Bennett, Shelley M. 7</p>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. 28, 29, 147, 176</p>
          <p>Bernhardt-Kabisch, Ernest 318</p>
          <p>Bertelli, Carlo 271</p>
          <p>Bertholf, Robert J. 248</p>
          <p>Bidney, Martin 30</p>
          <p>Billigheimer, Rachel V. 31</p>
          <p>Bindman, David 1, 2, 32, 33, 138, 278</p>
          <p>Blackburn, Robin 260</p>
          <p>Blewett, David 282</p>
          <p>Block, Ed, Jr. 201</p>
          <p>Blondel, Jacques 332</p>
          <p>Bloom, Harold 34, 109, 250</p>
          <p>Boerner, Peter 177</p>
          <p>Bogel, Fredric V. 148, 251</p>
          <p>Boime, Albert 35, 149</p>
          <p>Bony, Alain 323</p>
          <p>Borck, Jim Springer 8, 252</p>
          <p>Borkowska, Ewa 36</p>
          <p>Bornstein, George 244</p>
          <p>Boucé, Paul-Gabriel 252, 321</p>
          <p>Bracher, Mark 253</p>
          <p>Braden, Wilbur S. 329</p>
          <p>Brantley, Richard E. 254</p>
          <p>Brenkman, John 37</p>
          <p>Brookhart, Mary Hughes 314</p>
          <p>Brown, David Blayney 293</p>
          <p>Bryant, Barbara 2</p>
          <p>Burns, Bryan 16</p>
          <p>Buss, Peter M. 27</p>
          <p>Butler, Marilyn 255</p>
          <p>Butlin, Martin 256, 264</p>
          <p>Buttery, David 141</p>
          <p>Camfield, Gregg 178</p>
          <p>Campbell, Peter 242</p>
          <p>Canovan, Margaret 268</p>
          <p>Cantor, Paul A. 257</p>
          <p>Carpenter, Mary Wilson 179</p>
          <p>Carter, Sebastian 203</p>
          <p>Catano, James V. 314</p>
          <p>Cavanaugh, Catherine 227</p>
          <p>Cevasco, G. A. 270, 327, 332</p>
          <p>Chandler, James K. 254, 297</p>
          <p>Chaplin, Harry F. 204</p>
          <p>Chappell, Miles L. 129</p>
          <p>Claeys, Gregory 323</p>
          <p>Cohen, Seymour S. 180</p>
          <p>Collobi-Ragghianti, Licia [?] 262</p>
          <p>Colmer, John 38</p>
          <p>Cook, Albert 150</p>
          <p>Cook, David 205, 258</p>
          <p>Cook, Ramsay 258</p>
          <p>Cooper, C. B. 299</p>
          <p>Crehan, Stewart 6, 40, 90</p>
          <p>Crow, Thomas 245, 310</p>
          <p>Crutchfield, Will 228</p>
          <p>Cullen, Fintan 130</p>
          <p>Cunliffe, Marcus [?] 238</p>
          <p>Cunningham, Valentine 260</p>
          <p>Curran, Stuart 60, 151, 327</p>
          <p>Damrosch, Leopold, Jr. 254</p>
          <p>Danto, Arthur C. 338</p>
          <p>Deck, Raymond H., Jr. 27</p>
          <p>Deen, Leonard W. 6</p>
          <p>deGategno, Paul J. 288</p>
          <p>De Luca, V. A. 60, 181</p>
          <p>De Man, Paul 37</p>
          <p>DeMarr, Mary Jean 19</p>
          <p>Dinwiddy, J. R. 297</p>
          <p>Di Salvo, Jackie 17</p>
          <p>Dodd, Philip 16</p>
          <p>Dodsworth, Martin 332</p>
          <p>Dole, George F. 27</p>
          <p>Domville, Eric 214, 286</p>
          <p>Donnellan, Brendan 41</p>
          <p>Donoghue, Denis 250, 286</p>
          <p>Dorment, Richard 9, 259</p>
          <p>Dörrbecker, D. W. 10</p>
          <p>Draxler, Helmut 42, 43</p>
          <p>Ducrocq, Jean 312</p>
          <p>Dunn, John J. 206</p>
          <p>Dussinger, John A. 251</p>
          <p>Eaves, Morris 60, 256</p>
          <p>Edwards, Ruth Dudley 207, 260</p>
          <p>Egerton, Judy 285</p>
          <p>Egremont, Max 208</p>
          <p>Ellaschuk, Lorne 258</p>
          <p>Endy, Melvin B., Jr. 152</p>
          <p>Engell, James 327</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V. 44, 60, 261</p>
          <p>Erffa, Helmut von 262</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N. 2, 45, 263, 264</p>
          <p>Fauvet, P. 46</p>
          <p>Feingold, Lawrence 131</p>
          <p>Ferber, Michael 265</p>
          <p>Ferguson, Robert A. 241</p>
          <p>Fingrutd, M. A. 323</p>
          <p>Fischer, Michael 318</p>
          <p>Fite, David 209, 266</p>
          <p>Fitzpatrick, Donald C., Jr. 27</p>
          <p>Fogle, Richard Harter 244</p>
          <p>Fore, Byrne R. S. 118</p>
          <p>Forster, Harold 182, 267</p>
          <p>Foucart-Borville, Jacques 120</p>
          <p>Fowler, Kathleen 314</p>
          <p>Fox, Susan 60</p>
          <p>Fréchet, René 286</p>
          <p>Friedman, M. B. 311</p>
          <p>Friedman, Michael H. 274</p>
          <p>Fruchtman, Jack, Jr. 268</p>
          <p>Fruman, Norman 279</p>
          <p>Frye, Northrop 37, 269</p>
          <p>Fuller, David 280</p>
          <p>Fuller, Roy 286</p>
          <p>Furst, Lilian R. 298</p>
          <p>Gage, John 305, 338</p>
          <p>Gallant, Christine 334</p>
          <p>Gardner, Stanley 47, 270</p>
          <p>Genet, Jacqueline 286</p>
          <p>German, Terence 257</p>
          <p>Gilchrist, Alexander 27</p>
          <p>Gillespie, Gerald 269</p>
          <p>Gizzi, Corrado 124, 271</p>
          <p>Glausser, Wayne 48</p>
          <p>Gleckner, Robert F. 60, 261, 272, 273, 319, 327</p>
          <p>Glen, Heather 274</p>
          <p>Godwin, William 187, 197</p>
          <p>Goldsmith, Steven Richard 49</p>
          <p>Goslee, Nancy Moore 50</p>
          <p>Gourlay, Alexander S. 51</p>
          <p>Graff, Robert D. 210, 275</p>
          <p>Graham, John 276</p>
          <p>Greco, Norma A. 52</p>
          <p>Greenberg, Mark L. 53</p>
          <p>Greenfield, John 254</p>
          <p>Greenhouse, Wendy 168</p>
          <p>Gresham, Gwendolyn</p>
          <p>Holloway Parham 54</p>
          <p>Griffin, Dustin 153, 277</p>
          <p>Griffiths, Antony 11, 278</p>
          <p>Hagstrum, Jean H. 55, 279</p>
          <p>Haigwood, Laura Ellen 56</p>
          <p>Hales, L.-A. 57</p>
          <p>Hamilton-Phillips, Martha 169</p>
          <p>Hammerschmidt, Hildegard 132, 170</p>
          <p>Harasym, S. D. 183</p>
          <p>Harmon, Maurice 286</p>
          <p>Hartley, Craig 12</p>
          <p>Hawtree, Christopher 288</p>
          <p>Hayes, John 262</p>
          <p>Heier, E. 276</p>
          <p>Heinzelman, Kurt 248, 273</p>
          <p>Heppner, Christopher 58, 107</p>
          <p>Hilton, Nelson 6, 59, 60, 253, 280, 292, 306, 327</p>
          <p>Hindmarsh, Robert 27</p>
          <p>Hjerter, Kathleen G. 61</p>
          <p>Hoagwood, Terence Allan 17, 281, 289, 292</p>
          <p>Hodnett, Edward 282</p>
          <p>Hollander, John 37</p>
          <p>Holmes, John R. 62</p>
          <p>Homolka, Lawrence J. 308</p>
          <p>Hope, Warren 211</p>
          <p>Horn, W. D. 266</p>
          <p>Hošek, Chaviva 37, 162, 283</p>
          <p>Houfe, Simon 295</p>
          <p>Hough, Graham 226, 330</p>
          <p>Howard, John 17</p>
          <p>Howard, Seymour 63</p>
          <p>Hoyer, Tim 249, 337</p>
          <p>Hutchings, Bill 284</p>
          <p>Imaizumi, Yoko 64</p>
          <p>Ingamells, John 259</p>
          <p>Isaksson, Folke 65</p>
          <p>Jackson, Wallace 251</p>
          <p>Jacob, Margaret C. 268</p>
          <p>Jaffé, Michael 12, 285</p>
          <p>Jaffé, Patricia 12</p>
          <p>John, Donald 66</p>
          <p>Johnson, Alan 212, 213</p>
          <p>Johnson, Evamarii 337</p>
          <p>Johnson, Mary Lynn 13, 67, 306</p>
          <p>Johnson, Richard E. 68</p>
          <p>Jones, C. B. 255</p>
          <p>Jones, Daryl E. 315</p>
          <p>Jones, G. L. 241</p>
          <p>Jordan, David P. 310</p>
          <p>Jordan, Frank 13</p>
          <p>Kamusikiri, Sandra Darlene 69</p>
          <p>Kaplan, Cora 184</p>
          <p>Kastner, Jörg 133</p>
          <p>Keach, William 239</p>
          <p>Keefer, Michael H. 283</p>
          <p>Keener, Frederick M. 321</p>
          <p>Kellaway, Kate 302</p>
          <p>Kelly, John 214, 286</p>
          <p>Kemeny, Tomaso 70</p>
          <p>Kermode, Frank 307</p>
          <pb id="p21-73" n="73"/>
          <p>Keynes, Sir Geoffrey 2</p>
          <p>Kieffer, Tom 249</p>
          <p>Kilcup, Rodney W. 297</p>
          <p>King, James 121, 287, 288</p>
          <p>King-Hele, Desmond 289</p>
          <p>Klaus, H. Gustav 185</p>
          <p>Kline, Gloria C. 229</p>
          <p>Knapp, Steven 154, 290</p>
          <p>Knights, L. C. 71</p>
          <p>Kolker, D. 291</p>
          <p>Koppenfels, Werner von 155</p>
          <p>Kovács, József 186</p>
          <p>Kraft, Kent 72</p>
          <p>Kramnick, Isaac 255</p>
          <p>Kroeber, Karl 73, 291</p>
          <p>La Belle, Jenijoy 74, 265</p>
          <p>Lake, David J. 75</p>
          <p>Larrissy, Edward 76, 77, 274, 292</p>
          <p>Law, Philip 78</p>
          <p>Lee, Alvin A. 269</p>
          <p>Lee, Judith 79</p>
          <p>Leigh, John 215</p>
          <p>Leonard, Garry Martin 80</p>
          <p>Lessenich, Rolf P. 327</p>
          <p>Levi, Peter 156</p>
          <p>Levine, George 299</p>
          <p>Levine, Herbert J. 230</p>
          <p>Levinson, Marjorie 298</p>
          <p>Levitt, Annette S. 248</p>
          <p>Lincoln, Andrew 253, 265</p>
          <p>Lindberg, Bo Ossian 1, 2</p>
          <p>Lindsay, David W. 247, 306</p>
          <p>Lindsay, Suzanne G. 134</p>
          <p>Linkin, Harriet Kramer 81</p>
          <p>Liscombe, R. W. 262</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond 82, 119, 138, 139, 216, 293, 294, 295</p>
          <p>Littlefield, D. J. 277</p>
          <p>Ljungquist, Kent 324</p>
          <p>Locke, Don 313</p>
          <p>Loizeaux, Elizabeth Bergmann 231</p>
          <p>Louvre, Alf 323</p>
          <p>Loveday, John 217</p>
          <p>Low, Lisa 254</p>
          <p>Lyle, Janice 83</p>
          <p>Marshall, Peter H. 187, 296, 297</p>
          <p>Martin, Brian 315</p>
          <p>Martin, James Kirby 315</p>
          <p>Martin, Robert Bernard 242</p>
          <p>Mayer, David 299</p>
          <p>McArthur, Murray Gilchrist 84</p>
          <p>McCarthy, B. E. 322</p>
          <p>McCombie, Frank 250</p>
          <p>McCord, James 85, 86</p>
          <p>McCormick, Thomas J. 309</p>
          <p>McCracken, David 297</p>
          <p>McGann, Jerome J. 87, 298</p>
          <p>McKenzie, D. F. 275</p>
          <p>McKinley, Virginia Susan Gallaher 188</p>
          <p>McNeil, M. C. M. 122</p>
          <p>Meehan, Michael 157</p>
          <p>Meisel, Martin 158, 299</p>
          <p>Mell, Donald C., Jr. 14, 300</p>
          <p>Mellor, Anne K. 298</p>
          <p>Merchant, W. Moelwyn 159</p>
          <p>Milosz, Czeslaw 232, 301</p>
          <p>Minor, M. 246</p>
          <p>Mitchell, Stephen A. 189</p>
          <p>Morris, Herbert N. 27</p>
          <p>Morvan, Alain 255</p>
          <p>Mouret, François 326</p>
          <p>Mravik, L. 171</p>
          <p>Mulhallen, Karen 331</p>
          <p>Müller, Marianne 218</p>
          <p>Munro, Jane 12</p>
          <p>Murry, Katherine Middleton 302</p>
          <p>Nevitt, J. 190</p>
          <p>Newey, Vincent 16, 303</p>
          <p>Newlyn, Lucy 277, 328</p>
          <p>Nicholson, Kathleen 309</p>
          <p>Niimi, Hatsuko 306</p>
          <p>Njoku, Benedict Chiaka 96</p>
          <p>O’Hara, Daniel T. 219, 304</p>
          <p>Ostriker, Alicia 60</p>
          <p>Ottani Cavina, Anna 125</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D. 6, 27, 88, 305, 306, 307</p>
          <p>Parker, Patricia 37, 162, 283</p>
          <p>Patrides, C. A. 160, 307</p>
          <p>Patterson, Annabel 89</p>
          <p>Paulson, Ronald 308, 309, 310</p>
          <p>Paz, D. G. 254</p>
          <p>Peckham, Morse 161, 311</p>
          <p>Pénigault-Duhet, Paule 191, 312</p>
          <p>Pereira, E. 327</p>
          <p>Perkins, David 244</p>
          <p>Perloff, Marjorie 250</p>
          <p>Peterfreund, Stuart 40, 90</p>
          <p>Philp, Mark 192, 255, 313, 323</p>
          <p>Piquet, François 91, 251, 320, 333</p>
          <p>Pittock, Joan H. 284</p>
          <p>Poovey, Mary 314</p>
          <p><corr type="emend">Poprzęcka</corr>, Maria 126</p>
          <p>Porée, Marc 92</p>
          <p>Porter, Peter 4</p>
          <p>Powell, David 193, 315</p>
          <p>Praly, Raymonde 233</p>
          <p>Pressly, Nancy L. 316</p>
          <p>Pressly, William L. 262, 317</p>
          <p>Preston, Kerrison 216</p>
          <p>Pugh, Evelyn L. 314</p>
          <p>Punter, David 318, 327</p>
          <p>Raine, Kathleen 27, 93, 94, 95, 220, 319, 320</p>
          <p>Rajan, Tilottama 162</p>
          <p>Rawson, Claude 321</p>
          <p>Redford, Bruce 251</p>
          <p>Reed, John R. 327</p>
          <p>Reiman, Donald H. 17, 327</p>
          <p>Reisner, Thomas A. 39</p>
          <p>Reynolds, Graham 237, 245, 259</p>
          <p>Rich, Alan 234</p>
          <p>Ridge, George Ross 96</p>
          <p>Riehl, Joseph 97</p>
          <p>Riffaterre, Michael 60</p>
          <p>Robinson, Alan 281, 327</p>
          <p>Robinson, D. 98</p>
          <p>Rockwell, John 235</p>
          <p>Roe, Nicholas 333</p>
          <p>Rogers, Pat 245, 267, 338</p>
          <p>Rosswurm, Steven 241</p>
          <p>Royle, Edward 297</p>
          <p>Ruhl, Darrell 27</p>
          <p>Rump, Gerhard Charles 142</p>
          <p>Rushdy, Ashraf H. A. 277</p>
          <p>Ryskamp, Charles 121, 288</p>
          <p>Sambrook, A. J. 300</p>
          <p>Sambrook, James 163, 277</p>
          <p>Sanders, R. H. 304</p>
          <p>Sandler, Florence 60</p>
          <p>Sanzo, Eileen 99</p>
          <p>Scheiber, Andrew J. 194</p>
          <p>Schiff, Gert 135, 316</p>
          <p>Schnyder-Seidel, Barbara 136</p>
          <p>Schulz, Max F. 140, 322</p>
          <p>Scott, John 5</p>
          <p>Scrase, David 12, 263</p>
          <p>Scruton, Roger 301</p>
          <p>Sena, Vinod 221</p>
          <p>Shabetai, Karen 265</p>
          <p>Shaviro, Steven 60</p>
          <p>Sheats, Paul D. 333</p>
          <p>Shortland, Michael 195</p>
          <p>Simpson, David 323</p>
          <p>Skaggs, S. 242</p>
          <p>Sławek, Tadeusz 100</p>
          <p>Slotten, Ralph 236</p>
          <p>Smith, Bernard 222</p>
          <p>Smith, Margaret M. 18</p>
          <p>Smith, Michael 19</p>
          <p>Smith, Oliva 164, 323</p>
          <p>Solkin, David H. 316, 317</p>
          <p>Soupel, Serge 322</p>
          <p>Spacks, Patricia Meyer 288, 303</p>
          <p>Spurling, John 262</p>
          <p>Stafford, William 255, 297</p>
          <p>Staley, Allen 172, 262</p>
          <p>Stamm, Ramona Kelley 101</p>
          <p>Stieg, Elizabeth Joy 102</p>
          <p>Stock, R. D. 324</p>
          <p>Stocking, Marion K. 297</p>
          <p>Stokes, John 330</p>
          <p>Summerfield, Henry 103</p>
          <p>Sunstein, Emily W. 312</p>
          <p>Surbanov, Aleksandăr 104</p>
          <p>Szladits, Lola L. 223, 325</p>
          <p>Tannenbaum, Leslie 326</p>
          <p>Taylor, Dena Bain 105</p>
          <p>Taylor, Ronald Clayton 60</p>
          <p>Tennenbaum, S. 316</p>
          <p>Tennyson, G. B. 299</p>
          <p>Thomas, Keith G. 290</p>
          <p>Thornton, R. K. R. 224</p>
          <p>Thorslev, Peter L., Jr. 165, 327</p>
          <p>Tokarev, G. N. 106</p>
          <p>Tolley, Michael J. 58, 107</p>
          <p>Tomlinson, Charles 237</p>
          <p>Tscherny, Nadia 173</p>
          <p>Tuveson, Ernest 268</p>
          <p>Twitchell, James B. 328</p>
          <p>Tysdahl, B. J. 329</p>
          <p>Vaughan, William [?] 299</p>
          <p>Vicinus, Martha 299</p>
          <p>Villalobos, John C. 254</p>
          <p>Viscomi, Joseph 299, 337</p>
          <p>Wagner, Linda 244</p>
          <p>Wagner, Peter 310</p>
          <p>Walling, William 336</p>
          <p>Walter, Nicolas 296</p>
          <p>Wardle, Ralph M. 297</p>
          <p>Warner, Eric 226, 330</p>
          <p>Warner, Janet A. 331</p>
          <p>Watson, George 196</p>
          <p>Watson, J. R. 108, 332, 333</p>
          <p>Weatherhead, A. K. 244</p>
          <p>Webster, Brenda S. 6, 334</p>
          <p>Webster, Sarah McKim 166</p>
          <p>Wedd, Mary 332</p>
          <p>Weiskel, Thomas 109, 335</p>
          <p>Welburn, A. J. 110</p>
          <p>Welch, Dennis M. 111, 112, 113</p>
          <p>Wendorf, Richard 336</p>
          <p>Werner, Bette Charlene 114</p>
          <p>Wilkie, Brian 115</p>
          <p>Wilkinson, J. 240, 287</p>
          <p>William, Simon 299</p>
          <p>Williams, Reginald 11, 278</p>
          <p>Wilt, Judith 314</p>
          <p>Wind, Edgar 116, 338</p>
          <p>Witke, Joanne 117</p>
          <p>Wittreich, Joseph 160, 253, 307, 326</p>
          <p>Wollstonecraft, Mary 197</p>
          <p>Wood, Nigel 251</p>
          <p>Woodcock, George 297</p>
          <p>Wordsworth, Ann 250</p>
          <p>Worrall, David 306</p>
          <p>Woźniakowski, J. 137</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
