<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>21.3.abley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">New Blake Documents: Job, Oedipus, and the Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</title>
        <author n="Abley">Mark Abley</author>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1987/1988</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1987-88</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">21.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Mark Abley</name>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Mark Bracher</name>
              <name>Leslie Brisman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Dan Miller</name>
              <name>Michael Scrivener</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1987/1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_21">
    <body>
	<pb id="p21-104" n="104"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-21-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">New Blake Documents: <hi rend="i">Job, Oedipus</hi>, and the <hi rend="i">Songs
of Innocence and of Experience</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">1</hi> The materials exhibited here were discovered and recorded by Mark Abley in
1982 and 1983 and generously shared with G. E. Bentley, Jr., in September 1986; they have been organized and
made into the present essay by GEB.
                                <p>We should like to dedicate this essay to our friend Joan Linnell Ivimy in
thanks for her friendship to each of us over many years. The manuscripts are quoted here by her
permission.</p></note>
	</title>
          </head>
          <byline><docAuthor>Mark <name>Abley</name></docAuthor> and <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>,
Jr.</docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Contemporary documents of William Blake’s life are widely scattered, in record offices,
museums, churches, and libraries from London to San Marino and Melbourne. However, one of the richest
collections of such materials is in a cottage called Apple Thatch in Hampshire among the voluminous papers of
Blake’s last great patron, the artist John Linnell. This extraordinarily rich cache of manuscripts has
wonderful materials not only for John Linnell and William Blake but for many others as well, such as Samuel
Palmer and William Butler Yeats. Scholars with many goals have been welcomed, and often fed, housed, and
entertained, by the splendidly generous custodian of these papers, John Linnell’s great granddaughter Joan
Linnell Ivimy. The pages of <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (1969), which attempted to gather all contemporary
references to Blake, are thickly strewn with references to the Ivimy Manuscripts, particularly in the parts
recording the last ten years of Blake’s life.</p>
          <p>When I first went through the Ivimy mss. in 1959, it quickly became apparent that I could not
possibly read the majority of them without devoting more years to the undertaking than I had weeks to spare.
Consequently, I read with care everything I could find which related directly to Blake and to his known
acquaintances during his lifetime (1757-1827); I read almost equally scrupulously everything for the period
from his death in 1827 to that of his wife in 1831. For the period after 1863, I read much more casually and
rarely did more than glance at letters unless they were to or from someone important to Blake, such as Anne
Gilchrist or Samuel Palmer. I concluded my search, confident that I had found most of the Blake references
there and that more were awaiting searchers with sharper eyes and more patience and time than I could
muster.</p>
          <figure n="Linnell.EdwardDenny.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="547">
            <head>1. John Linnell’s oil portrait (dated “1821”) of Edward Denny (then age 25) in the
collection of Robyn Denny, and reproduced with permission of Robyn Denny.</head>
          </figure>
          <p>But the collection kept growing, with the discovery of here a trunk of Linnell manuscripts which
had lain unrecognized for decades in the vaults of a family lawyer and there the return of letters from other
members of the family. In the past twenty-seven years, I have returned repeatedly to Apple Thatch and to the
loving hospitality of Joan Linnell Ivimy, and I have often found more references to Blake.</p>
          <pb id="p21-105" n="105"/>
          <p>In 1982 and 1983, Mark Abley, formerly a Rhodes Scholar at Oxford and now a successful Canadian
journalist, called by arrangement at Apple Thatch in search of letters of William Butler Yeats and documents
relating to Samuel Palmer. He was welcomed with her customary generosity by Joan Linnell Ivimy, and indeed
Mark Abley stayed for some time at Apple Thatch. During his stay, he found not only manuscripts relating to
William Butler Yeats and Samuel Palmer, which were partly for the Oxford edition of Yeats’s letters and
partly for Mark Abley’s own <hi rend="i">Parting Light: Selected Writings of Samuel Palmer</hi> (1985); he
also found a number of references to William Blake which were not recorded in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>
(1969) or <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Critical Heritage</hi> (1975). A number of these references to Blake
I had myself seen in the years since <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> went to press, and, by the time I met
Mark Abley in September 1986, these were already incorporated in the <hi rend="i">Blake Records
Supplement</hi>, which is now in press. Some of them, however, were quite new to me, among them some of the
most interesting references to Blake. When <hi rend="i">The Parting Light</hi> was published, I discovered in
it some Blake references (not from the Ivimy mss.) which were new to me, and when I wrote to Mark Abley, and
subsequently met him in Toronto, he generously offered me the notes he had made of his discoveries among the
Ivimy mss. for the <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement.</hi> Because of the remarkable interest of these
Blake materials not already incorporated in the <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement</hi>, I thought it
desirable to make them into a separate article, to which Mark Abley generously agreed.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>BLAKE AND <hi rend="i">OEDIPUS</hi></title>
            </head>
            <p>John Linnell had deeply impressed a young man some four years younger than himself named Edward
Denny (b. 1796), the son of a baronet and a man of substance, and Linnell had apparently made Denny acquainted
with Blake and his works. From August through November 1821 Linnell was busy painting portraits of Edward
Denny and five other members of his family; that of Edward Denny<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n38" type="note">2</ref> shows a dreamy young man with his finger marking his place in a little
book—he looks strikingly like a Romantic poet such as Shelley (see illus. 1). On 30 October Linnell sent
some of the portraits to Denny at his home at King’s End House, Worcester, and on 2 November Denny wrote
that the pictures had arrived. In passing he remarked:
<q>
when you see Mr. Blake be so kind as to tell him to keep the drawings he is making for me, when they are
finished, till he either sees or hears from me— . . .<lb/>
and Believe me, dear Sir,<lb/>
your’s truly obliged,<lb/>
Edward Denny.—
</q>
This is the first known reference to a direct connection between Blake and Denny, but it is plain that already
Denny was an admirer of Blake. Unfortunately, we do not know what drawings Blake was making for Denny in 1821,
for Denny is not known to have owned any drawings by Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n39" type="note">3</ref> Apparently the drawings pleased Denny, for Denny purchased other Blake works
in November 1826. <note id="n38"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Linnell’s portrait of Edward Denny (1821) was exhibited
in Katharine Crouan, <hi rend="i">John Linnell:</hi> A Centennial Exhibition (Fitzwilliam Museum 5 Oct.-12
Dec. 1982; Yale Center for British Art, 26 Jan.-20 March 1983), #76.</note>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">3</hi> According to the index to Martin Butlin’s magisterial 
<hi rend="i">Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (1981). Through Linnell, Denny bought Blake’s Job
engravings and Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> with Blake’s designs (<hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>
[1969], 335-36, 593).</note></p>
            <p>John Linnell scrawled a long draft reply to Denny on the letter itself, including a fascinating
reference to a curious theatrical performance:
<q>
    Mr Varley, Mr Blake &amp; myself were much entertained Thursday Evening last by wittnessing a
representation of Oedipus at the West London Theatre—it much exceeded our expectations as to the effect of
the Play &amp; the performance of the Actors. I see it sneered at in one of the public[<hi rend="i">?</hi>]
papers but you know what [a bad(<hi rend="i">?</hi>) set <hi rend="i">del</hi>] petty motives govern all 
<hi rend="sub">^</hi> most of <hi rend="sub">^</hi> the Public criticism[.]
</q>
Linnell had taken his friends<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">4</ref> to a
box at the West London Theatre in Tottenham Street<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41"
type="note">5</ref> where they saw <hi rend="i">Oedipus</hi> by John Dryden and Nat Lee, first acted in 1678.
However, the play was advertised as being the <hi rend="i">Oedipus</hi> of Sophocles, and, not surprisingly,
at least some in the audience reacted with indignation to the imposture. The anonymous reviewer in 
<hi rend="i">The Times</hi> for Friday 2 November 1821 wrote:
<q><hi rend="u">ROYAL WEST LONDON THEATER.</hi><lb/>
A numerous audience was attracted yesterday evening to this theatre, by as barefaced an imposition as was ever
practised on a public audience since the days of the bottle-conjuror. It was ostentatiously announced in the
play-bills, and also in some of the public prints, that the <hi rend="i">Œdipus Tyrannus</hi> of Sophocles
would be acted last night at this theatre, “being its first appearance these 2440 years”. Of course many
persons, attracted by the accurate chronological knowledge of the supposed translator, went in the expectation
of seeing the ancient tragedy stalking for once on modern boards . . . . In this expectation, which the
numerous translations of the <hi rend="i">Œdipus Tyrannus</hi> into English prose and verse did not render
altogether unfounded, they were most miserable disappointed; for instead of listening to the simple yet
majestic strains of Sophocles, they were indulged with a cut-down edition of the bombastic yet powerful
tragedy of Lee and Dryden upon the same subject. That piece, which must always affect an audience very
strongly, certainly has made its appearance on the stage within the last 2440 years . . . . The tragedy, in
spite of “being its first appearance for these last 2440 years”, was given out for repetition amidst
thunders of applause, which we expect the play-bills of today will inform us proceeded from an audience,
distinguished no less for its numbers and its fashion, than for its intelligence and discrimination.
</q>
The reviewer’s dire prediction was at least partly fulfilled, for in <hi rend="i">The Times</hi> for
Wednesday 7 November appeared the following advertisement:
<q><hi rend="u">NEW ROYAL WEST LONDON THEATRE,</hi>
Tottenham-street, Charlotte-street, Fitzroy-square. Œdipus Tyrannus, by Sophocles, revived after a lapse of
2440 years, and received (as at Athens) with shouts of applause. It will be repeated till further notice. THIS
and every EVENING, ŒDIPUS. Œdipus, Mr. Huntley; Jocasta, Mrs. Glover. After which, THE WAGER LOST; in which
Mrs. Glover will perform. Boxes 4s., pit 2s., gallery 1s. Private boxes for families may be had nightly.
</q>
	<pb id="p21-106" n="106"/>
At least the date in this advertisement is two centuries less preposterous than that in the review. 
<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">4</hi> In his Journal, Linnell recorded that he went on “Th[<hi rend="i">ursday
November</hi>] 2 To see Œdipus,” but he said nothing about his companions, and in his Cash Account Book he
noted under 8 November 1821 payment of four shillings “to Dr Thornton for Box Ticket—for Œdipus[?].”
                                <p>Linnell was clearly keenly interested in Greek plays, and the impulse to
attend this production may have been his. On 8 May 1819 he paid £1.1.0 “for Greek Theatre 3 vol. 4<hi
rend="s">to</hi>,” and on 24 April 1821 he paid four shillings for “Sophocles—Greek.”</p></note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">5</hi> For details of the theatre itself, see Raymond Mander &amp; Joe
Mitchenson, <hi rend="i">The Lost Theatres of London</hi> (1976), 202. It was not a patent theatre and was not
therefore entitled to perform legitimate drama, but, “being of too humble pretensions to create jealousy,
[<hi rend="i">it</hi>] is permitted to play tragedy, comedy, or farce, in as legitimate a manner as the
company is capable of doing” (<hi rend="i">The Percy Anecdotes Original and Select</hi> [1822], 168, cited
in Allardyce Nicoll, <hi rend="i">A History of English Drama, 1660-1900</hi>, 4 [1955], 288).</note></p>
            <p>Blake was certainly familiar with Sophocles, for his “Philoctetes and Neoptolemus at
Lemnos” (1812) was made nine years before from Sophocles’ <hi rend="i">Philoctetes</hi>,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">6</ref> and his intimate friends John Flaxman and John
Linnell<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note" n="4b">4</ref> were admirers of
Sophocles, and Flaxman had made designs from his plays. It is agreeable to find that Blake was “much
entertained” by the performance, even though the play he saw was some two thousand three hundred years
younger than it was advertised to be. <note id="n42"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Butlin (1981), #676.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>BLAKE AND <hi rend="i">JOB</hi></title>
            </head>
            <p>On 9 February 1826 Linnell wrote to his father from Cheltenham about a “scrape” relating to
his painting of “The Burial of Saul,” and as an afterthought he remarked: “I shall be glad to hear from
Ed. Chance how the Job goes on &amp; what has occurred.” Edward Chance was Linnell’s nephew, who was
helping to supervise the printing of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> at just this
time. For instance, on this same day, 9 February 1826, Linnell’s wife Mary wrote to him that “Edward . . .
has been every day to Lahees &amp; to [<hi rend="i">the Linnell’s house in</hi>] Cirencester Place[<hi
rend="i">;</hi>] from all I can learn the printing is going on well by a man of the name of Freeman[.]”</p>
            <p>The landscape painter Edward Price wrote to Linnell from Trentham on Monday 3 September 1827,
three weeks after Blake’s death, about Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engravings:
<q>
Lady Stafford will not be here for a month so I have not been able to put before her Ladyship Blake’s
Etchings, and I fear I shall not be able to get subscribers as many of my friends who have seen them, have
only made the remark that they were striking but extravagant and not one has yet expressed a desire to buy,
but I will omit no opportunity of shewing it whenever I meet with the One Man in a Thousand who understands
Painting.
</q>
Elizabeth Lady Stafford, the wealthy Countess of Sutherland in her own right, was married to the even
wealthier George Grenville Leveson-Gower, Marquis of Stafford, who was famous as a politician and an improver
of their huge estates (including most of the County of Sutherland). Both Lord and Lady Stafford were keenly
interested in the arts; he was President of the British Institution, she was a painter in watercolors, and
both collected art eagerly. A purchase from the Staffords might have led to important commissions for Linnell
and perhaps to purchases of other works by Blake. However, if Lady Stafford was shown the 
<hi rend="i">Job</hi> engravings on her return to their home in Trentham, she apparently showed little interest in
them, for her name does not appear in Linnell’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> accounts.</p>
            <p>There are numerous letters from Edward Price to Linnell among the Ivimy mss., but he is not
known to have had any other connection than this one with Blake. Clearly he was simply one of many
acquaintances through whom Linnell tried to sell copies of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job.</hi></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>BLAKE AND THE <hi rend="i">SONGS OF INNOCENCE AND OF EXPERIENCE</hi></title>
            </head>
            <p>Blake sold an extraordinarily beautiful copy of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi> (copy AA) to Mrs. Charles Aders in July 1826 for £5.5.0,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">7</ref> and Linnell apparently had it bound for her—indeed,
probably the sale was made through him. Eight years later, when in somewhat narrower circumstances, Mrs. Aders
wrote to Linnell:
<q>
24 Savage Gardens June 17th [<hi rend="i">1834</hi>]<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44"
type="note">8</ref><lb/>
My dear Sir<lb/>
    I much hoped to have been able to see you before this, but as usual illness has prevented me.—The fact
is, I wish to explain to you my feelings &amp; wishes about Blakes songs of Innocence &amp; I cannot resist
the desire to have Mr Aders’ portrait [painted by you], but am not now so well able to dispose of money as I
was, (at any rate for my luxuries or fancies) and wish therefore that you would take that work in part
payment, it cost me as you know 6£ that is <table type="inline"><row>
	<cell>£</cell>
	<cell>s</cell>
	<cell>d</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>5..</cell>
	<cell>5..</cell>
	<cell>0</cell>
</row></table> to Mr Blake and <table type="inline"><row>
	<cell>s</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>16</cell>
</row></table> to you for the Book in which they are [<hi rend="i">bound?</hi>]—I have also another work of
Blakes for which I gave to Mr. Tatham 5..5..0[<hi rend="i">;</hi>] perhaps you might like to have that
also—What I have said above is in confidence to you, &amp; I feel sure your delicacy will treat it as
such—If you agree to my plan you will have the kindness to send for the Songs—and Michael Angelo’s 
[<hi rend="i">designs engraved by Linnell</hi>] whenever you please[<hi rend="i">;</hi>] perhaps some day it may
please God that I may be rich enough to purchase the latter[.]<lb/>
Yours very sincerely<lb/>
Eliza Aders 
                            </q>
Linnell evidently was not tempted by the Blake work which had come from Frederick Tatham—perhaps the
drawings of “Los Walking on the Mountains of Albion” or “Christian with the Shield of Faith, Taking
Leave of His Companions” from <hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> which Mrs. Aders kept in an album until
her death<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">9</ref>—but he did take the 
<hi rend="i">Songs.</hi> Next year he had an unfortunate misunderstanding with Mrs. Aders about the prices of
these works, and on 8 August 1835 she wrote to him that she had understood the price of Linnell’s portrait
of Mr. Aders was to have been £26.5.0; “when therefore you took Blakes Songs of Innocence &amp;c at 6G<hi
rend="s">s</hi> I of course concluded I had only 20£ to pay.” She declined to pay more but said that a
friend might do so, “in which case when you receive the money you will send us the 6 G<hi rend="s">s</hi>
for Blakes work.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">10</ref> Linnell did keep
the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, and twenty-eight years later he inscribed it: “Given to James Tho Linnell by
John Linnell sen<hi rend="s">r</hi>, April 28 1863.” <note id="n43"><hi rend="s">7</hi> The receipt of 29
July 1826 is given in <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi>, 583, the source of the other Blake references quoted
incidentally here.</note>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">8</hi> The letter is postmarked “NIGHT / JU 17 / 1834” and addressed to “J.
Linnell Esq<hi rend="s">r</hi>. / Porchester Terrace / Bayswater.”</note>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Butlin (1981), #784 and #829 (20).</note>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">10</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi>, 583, n 1, quoting the Ivimy
mss.</note></p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>BLAKE AND <hi rend="i">JOB</hi></title>
            </head>
            <p>Linnell had become a profound admirer of “the
<pb id="p21-107" n="107"/>
dear kind and accomplished Lady Torrens,” and in 1820 he painted an admirable portrait of her with her six
children.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">11</ref> In April 1826 he sold a
copy of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> to her,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48"
type="note">12</ref> and on 19 December 1832 her son A. W. Torrens, a captain in the Grenadier Guards, asked
Linnell to send “by the bearer the ‘<hi rend="i">Book of Job</hi>,’ as you kindly promised to
do.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">13</ref> He apparently admired but did
not buy Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, and three years later he wrote again to Linnell:
<q>
Windsor.<lb/>
17. <hi rend="i">April 1835.</hi><lb/>
Dear Mr. Linnell,<lb/>
I received the book of Job, &amp; return you many thanks for the present, in the name of my wife.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">14</ref>—The note you were so good as to send with
it, is no mean part of the value of the gift, containing as it does from so eminent an artist such strong
approbation of the copy which was inadvertently left in the book . . . .<lb/>
Yr. very truly obliged,<lb/>
<hi rend="i">Arthur W. Torrens.</hi></q>
Clearly the Denny and Torrens families were appreciative patrons of William Blake. If only we had records of
the rest of their dealings with and opinions of him. <note id="n47"><hi rend="s">11</hi> It is reproduced in
color in Katharine Crouan’s catalogue of <hi rend="i">John Linnell</hi> (1982), #75.</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">12</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi>, 590, 599.</note>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">13</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake: The Critical Heritage</hi> (1975),
226.</note>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Of course neither Arthur Torrens nor his wife appears in the records of
payments for <hi rend="i">Job</hi>, since the copy they received was a gift.</note></p>
            <p>These are so far the last of the records of Blake’s life and works to be discovered among the
Ivimy mss., but it seems likely that yet more will be found in that rich respository. Few discoveries,
however, are likely to be so intriguing as the view given here of Blake sitting between his friends John
Varley and John Linnell in a box in a little theatre in Westminster being “much entertained” by a
performance of <hi rend="i">Oedipus</hi> advertised as having been written in 619 BC by Sophocles (496-406 BC)
but in fact written by Dryden and Lee and first acted in 1678.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
