<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>21.3.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Robert N. Essick, The Works of William Blake in the Huntington Collections: A
Complete Catalogue</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1987/1988</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1987-88</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">21.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Mark Abley</name>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Mark Bracher</name>
              <name>Leslie Brisman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Dan Miller</name>
              <name>Michael Scrivener</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1987/1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_21">
    <body>
	<pb id="p21-114" n="114"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-21-3-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Robert N. Essick. <hi rend="i">The Works of William Blake in the Huntington
Collections: A Complete Catalogue.</hi> San Marino: The Huntington Library, Art Collections, Botanical
Gardens, 1985. xviii + 256 pp. $20.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor><hi rend="b">G. E. </hi><name><hi rend="b">Bentley</hi></name>, 
<hi rend="b">Jr.</hi></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The Huntington Library and Art Gallery has one of the great Blake collections in the world,
including seventeen of his printed books (<hi rend="i">All Religions Are One</hi>, the “Exhibition of
Paintings in Fresco,” and <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi> in the only copies known),<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">1</ref> seventeen of about ninety-six known letters,
some of his greatest series of designs including those for <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> (8), <hi rend="i">Paradise
Lost</hi> (12), “On the Morning of Christ’s Nativity” (6), Visionary Heads (6), the Illuminated Genesis
Manuscript (12), colorprints (3), and eighty-two works with his commercial engravings. Only five other
collections have anything like such Blake riches—the British Library and Museum, the Library of Congress
plus the National Gallery, Harvard, Yale, and Cambridge University—and probably none of these has been so
extensively described and exhibited as that in the Huntington. There is of course a special need 
<figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
for such exhibition and description of the Huntington collections, for they are not easily accessible to most
Blake students, and they are never loaned to other institutions. To make up for this isolation, the Huntington
is uniquely beautiful and wonderfully gracious and accommodating to students who do wend their way to the
imaginary barony of San Marino in the avocado groves in the foothills of the mountains above Los Angeles.
<note id="n51"><hi rend="s">1</hi> The most important works in illuminating printing not to be found there are
the <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></note></p>
          <p>The Huntington collection of Blakes has been repeatedly and extensively described, in the
catalogue of drawings and paintings by C. H. Collins Baker (1938), revised and extended by R. R. Wark (1957,
reprinted 1969), and in the handlist of the entire collection by R. N. Essick in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi>
(1978). There have been Huntington exhibitions focusing on Blake in 1936 (<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>
drawings), 1940 (ibid.), 1953, 1965-66 (William Blake and his Circle), 1972-73 (the followers of William
Blake), 1974, 1978 (Prints by Blake), 1981-82 (prints by the Blake Followers), 1983, and 1984. The
administration
<pb id="p21-115" n="115"/>
of the Huntington has been splendidly generous in making known its Blake riches.</p>
          <p>One might well wonder what this new catalogue can offer which has not been available before,
since the ground has been so frequently traversed. The answer is rather surprising. Most of the Huntington
exhibitions and all the catalogues before Essick’s were concerned almost exclusively with Blake’s drawings
and paintings. The scope of this work is, therefore, vastly greater than those of its predecessors. Further,
even the graphic works are described in considerably greater detail than was heretofore available. The edition
of Baker’s catalogue revised by Wark (1957) consists of only fifty-five pages, whereas the corresponding
sections of Essick’s work comprehend drawings and paintings (pp. 1-140), separate prints (pp. 193-204),
works of questionable attribution (pp. 233-38), and portraits of Blake (pp. 239-40), and to what Baker and
Wark surveyed Essick has added extensive sections on Blake’s writings (pp. 141-91) and his commercial book
illustrations (pp. 204-31).</p>
          <p>The first great virtue of this admirable catalogue, then, is its comprehensiveness.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">2</ref> For the first time we have an account of
“all original Blake materials at the Huntington” (p. xi), not just the drawings and paintings. 
<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">2</hi> No attempt is made to detail the Huntington’s extensive holdings of reprints,
criticism, and scholarship concerning Blake nor to describe the related materials such as the bill for
Blake’s funeral or drawings and manuscripts of contemporaries like Flaxman, Fuseli, Stothard, and
Palmer.</note></p>
          <p>The second great virtue of the new Huntington catalogue is its method: “[<hi rend="i">It</hi>]
is based on a new examination of them [<hi rend="i">Blake’s works</hi>] and all relevant documents I have
been able to locate. My major goal has been to provide scholars and students with basic facts about the
physical properties of the works recorded” (p. xi). With a first-class scholar such as Essick working with
the primary materials of his field, the results are bound to be impressive.</p>
          <p>With each drawing, he gives not only the physical details such as size and defects, but a
meticulous and elaborate description, and usually a reproduction as well—there are fifty plates in all,
including all those for <hi rend="i">Comus, Paradise Lost</hi>, “On the Morning of Christ’s Nativity,”
and the Illuminated Genesis Manuscript.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53"
type="note">3</ref> Further, there are careful comparisons with other versions of the same subjects, e.g., for
the <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> designs. In future, critical accounts of these Huntington designs should
begin with Essick’s descriptions of them. <note id="n53"><hi rend="s">3</hi> These reproductions are
serviceable, but they are only in black-and-white, and they are not so good as those in previous Huntington
catalogues. A major catalogue deserves better plates than these. Doubtless the motive was to keep the price to
the remarkably low level of $20.</note></p>
          <p>An incidental advantage of the 1985 catalogue is that it is more up-to-date than its
predecessors. Essick reports that the Huntington copies of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (I), 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (N), and <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> (E) were disbound in 1983 and 1984 and that rare prints
were acquired as late as August and December 1984 (pp. 146, 149, 163, 194, 203).</p>
          <p>Most of the new profits from this catalogue are for literary scholars, for the Huntington copies
of Blake’s writings and of books with his commercial engravings have only been described in detail
previously in comprehensive bibliographies such as Keynes’ great <hi rend="i">Bibliography of William
Blake</hi> (1921), the Keynes &amp; Wolf <hi rend="i">Census</hi> (1953), and <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>
(1977). One might have expected, or indeed hoped, that his predecessors had exhausted what is to be found in
the Huntington books, but this is not the case. Though Essick builds confidently on the work of his
predecessors, he has a good deal that is new to offer, and every copy has been described with a fresh eye. For
instance, he reports (as no one else has) that the edges of <hi rend="i">All Religions Are One</hi> (A), 
<hi rend="i">No Natural Religion</hi> pl. a2, <hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi> (E), and <hi rend="i">The Ghost of
Abel</hi> (C) are deckled (pp. 143, 145, 165, 175), indicating that they were the original outside edges of
the sheets from which they were cut, and he can even deduce from these facts that the <hi rend="i">All
Religions Are One</hi> plates “are quarter pieces [cut] from a sheet approx. 75.6 × 54 cm.” (p. 143). He
points out numerous small variants which Blake created in coloring his works in illuminated printing and which
have not been remarked before. In <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> pl. 13-14 (“The Little Boy Lost 
[<hi rend="i">and</hi> Found]” in <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> [I] and <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> [E]) the boy has
been given a hat (pp. 146, 157), in pl. 19 (the innocent “Holy Thursday” in <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> [E])
the man at bottom left has a book in his hands (p. 157), and in pl. 46 (“London” in 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> [N]) a serpent has been added in the bottom margin (p. 163). In <hi rend="i">Song of
Los</hi> (E) pl. 8, the etched butterfly visible beside 11. 6-8 in other copies is not apparent (p. 166), and
in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (B) pl. 4 there are “Eight stars drawn in [<hi rend="i">the</hi>] sky with pen
and ink” (p. 169). All these variants should be recorded in the standards bibliographies of Blake. Essick
has advanced our knowledge very considerably with his original observation and careful recording of these
minute details.</p>
          <p>Very occasionally the vagaries of institutional records or of proofreading have had small
unfortunate consequences. Of the history of the Huntington’s copy of Blake’s great print of Chaucer’s
Canterbury Pilgrims he can say no more than that it “has been in the Library’s collection for many
years” (p. 202); in recording the variants in Blake’s transcription of Genesis in his Illuminated Genesis
Manuscript (pp. 112-114) he corrects and supplements his predecessors very usefully but omits Blake’s
alteration in Genesis 2.4 of “the day that” to “the day when,” and he mistranscribes Blake’s 3.16
“in sorrow shalt thou” as “in sorrow shalt though”; watermarks such as J Whatman are regularly
recorded in large capitals rather than in large and small capitals, thus creating unnecessary variants. But
these eccentricities are very few and trifling.</p>
          <p>This is a scholarly work of considerable importance, constituting a real advance in knowledge,
thorough, accurate, intelligent, and illuminating. The Huntington Library and Art Gallery and the community of
Blake students are exceedingly fortunate that a scholar of Essick’s eminence should have devoted himself to
such an apparently thankless task and produced a work of such remarkable excellence. <hi rend="i">Semper honos
nomenque tuum laudesque manebunt</hi> (Aeneid 1.607).</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p21-116" n="116" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
