<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>21.3.scrivener</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">A Swedenborgian Visionary and The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</title>
        <author n="Scrivener">Michael Scrivener</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1987/1988</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1987-88</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">21.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Mark Abley</name>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Mark Bracher</name>
              <name>Leslie Brisman</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Dan Miller</name>
              <name>Michael Scrivener</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1987/1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_21">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-21-3-0006">
        <pb id="p21-102" n="102"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A Swedenborgian Visionary and <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Michael <name>Scrivener</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Near the end of “An Audience for <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>,” John
Howard writes that Blake’s revolutionary manifesto was “calculated to amuse the Johnson circle and to make
the members of the New Church turn ‘blue.’ ”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">1</ref> Howard argues that the angel/devil dichotomy expressed in Blake’s work corresponds to
the angelic Swedenborgians and the demonic Joseph Johnson circle to whom the work was principally addressed.
Howard persuasively shows the ways in which Blake satirizes and criticizes the corruption of the New Jerusalem
Church, and in a more recent article, Morton D. Paley uncovers even more relevant information on Blake and the
Swedenborgians.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">2</ref> There can be no doubt
that <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> was influenced to an important degree by Blake’s
dislike of the English Swedenborgians, their political, sexual, and religious conservatism. Moreover, the
Johnson circle clearly did attack Swedenborgianism and its eponymous founder, and the 1791 Birmingham riot,
during which the Swedenborgians placated the same Church and King mob that attacked Priestley and other
Dissenters, exemplified the differences between the new religious group and the English “Jacobins.”
Nevertheless, I cannot accept one part of Howard’s argument, that Blake’s <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> was
intended to amuse the Joseph Johnson circle of radical intellectuals and thus to constitute a skirmish in the
battle against the Swedenborgians. The Johnson circle would have found the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> as
outrageous as the New Jerusalem Church would have found it blasphemous. The <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> runs
counter in essential ways to the Rational Dissent of the Johnson circle and the dominant radicalism of the
1790s embodied in groups like the Revolution Society, the Society for Constitutional Information, and Friends
of the People, and expressed in publications like <hi rend="i">The Analytical Review</hi> and the 
<hi rend="i">Morning Chronicle.</hi> Furthermore, it seems implausible that Blake would have concentrated so much
of the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> on Swedenborgian error simply to express solidarity with Priestley and the
Johnson circle; rather, the New Jerusalem Church, with which Blake became disillusioned, was the only
ideological association with which he could (at one time at least) identify. Although Blake never joined the
Church, in 1789 he and his wife did indeed subscribe to the tenets of the Swedenborgians who ultimately and
rather rapidly disappointed him. Despite the many political ideas that Blake shared with the Johnson circle
and the radicalism of the 1790s, Rational Dissent’s hostility to all varieties of “religious enthusiasm”
would have alienated Blake to such an extent that it is unlikely he would have written a satire in which the
implied reader opposes Swedenborgian error from the assumptions of mainstream Jacobinism. Rather, the 
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> positions itself against both Swedenborg and Priestley, both the New Jerusalem Church
and English Jacobinism. <note id="n32"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Studies</hi>, 3 (fall, 1970):
51.</note>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">2</hi> “‘A New Heaven Is Begun’: William Blake and Swedenborgianism,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>, 13 (fall, 1979): 64-90.</note></p>
          <p>In the 5 September 1791 issue of the London <hi rend="i">Morning Chronicle</hi>, there is a brief
article entitled “A New Visionary” that is interesting in this context because it gives a revealing
example of how the Swedenborgians were represented in one of the most important Foxite Whig publications. The
<hi rend="i">Chronicle</hi>, of course, supported the French Revolution, defended Priestley (to whom it opened
its pages on numerous occasions), and in general sustained an influential version of English
Jacobinism.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">3</ref> If one imagines William
Blake reading this 1791 article, which is brief enough to quote in full, one can begin to understand why and
how the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> is a critique also of the mainstream radicalism:
<q>
Where will things end? There is a person now in this city, at the head of the Swedenborgians, who, besides
possessing <hi rend="i">their common faculty</hi> of seeing Angels, has the privilege of conversing with the
Jewish Prophets and Apostles, whom he frequently meets in the streets of this metropolis; but very seldom if
he is not in company with a third person. In this case, where the other cannot see any person near them, he
frequently makes a full stop; and with an air of astonishment, either falls upon one knee, or makes the
handsomest bow he can! To the natural expressions of surprise at this unaccountable conduct, he always retorts
by asking the other party if he did not see any thing? “That,” says he, “is Isaiah—this Apostle
Paul!” He had a few days ago a very favourable vision of St. Paul, in St. Paul’s Church-yard! and on that
account detained two friends who were with him a considerable time. The Apostle, according to his account, was
then listening to a song in favour of the French Revolution! He further says, that he can any time have a
sight of Moses, and the other Jewish Prophets at a boxing match, or about Rag Fair!
</q>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Lucyle Werkmeister, <hi rend="i">A Newspaper History of England
1792-1793</hi> (Lincoln: Univ. of Nebraska Press, 1967), 34.</note></p>
          <p>One striking thing about the article is the number of parallels between the Swedenborgian’s
reported activities and words, and parts of Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>: the
visionary’s conversing with Isaiah, Paul, and others is similar to the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>’s
narrator’s conversations with Isaiah and Ezekiel in plates 12 and 13; the visionary’s listening to “a
song in favour of the French Revolution” is not unlike the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>’s concluding “A
Song of Liberty”; the visionary’s seeing Moses and “the other Jewish prophets at a boxing match” could
be construed as similar in some ways to the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>’s doctrine of the contraries and
Blake’s idea of “Mental War.” Another striking thing is the way the article constructs an implied reader
who would, as a matter of course, dismiss the visionary as a religious fanatic who need not be taken seriously
but who exists entirely for comic effect. It is difficult to imagine Blake conforming to the expected
responses of condescension and ridicule for the visionary. The tone of the article is contemptuous, which is
especially apparent in sentences like the
<pb id="p21-103" n="103"/>
first one: “Where will things end?” That question assumes a shared perception of a particular kind of
social disorder that is not so much dangerous and subversive as it is absurd. The italicized words in 
“<hi rend="i">their common faculty</hi> of seeing Angels” communicate a sneer at the presumption of
Swedenborgians which is quite clearly homologous with social presumption (the word “common” has an
unmistakable snobbish resonance). The observer-writer perceives the visionary entirely as an object, and one
imagines him shaking his head, perhaps chuckling, and waiting for further evidence that the Swedenborgian is
outside the category of rational human being.</p>
          <p>It is not difficult to imagine a Blakean response to the article: “If the fool would persist in
his folly he would become wise”; “Every thing possible to be believ’d is an image of truth”; “Listen
to the fools reproach! it is a kingly title!”; “If the doors of perception were cleansed every thing would
appear to man as it is: infinite. / For man has closed himself up, till he sees all things thro’ narrow
chinks of his cavern” (E 36-37,39). In the dichotomy of the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, the 
<hi rend="i">Chronicle</hi>’s author would be angelic, and the visionary a devil. The 
<hi rend="i">Chronicle</hi>’s article does not simply criticize the visionary; rather, it represents him in such
a way that everything he says or does can be dismissed as preposterous. The article is rhetorically violent in
that the person being represented is deprived of any qualities that might make the reader take him seriously,
and for Blake the rhetorical violence would have been especially offensive because the article attacks the
notion of visionary experience, of which the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> is an extensive defense. The 
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> surely portrays Swedenborg as insufficiently visionary, but the other emphasis is on
the limitations and errors of his <hi rend="i">vision.</hi> In most Blakean respects, the 
<hi rend="i">Chronicle</hi> article is more error-ridden than Swedenborg’s writings because at least Swedenborg
does not repudiate visionary experience, the Poetic Genius.</p>
          <p>The article is interesting in another way because in 1791 the English Swedenborgians were
explicitly anti-revolutionary and dissociated themselves entirely from the French Revolution and English
political radicalism, so that it is unlikely that the “head” of the sect would imply support for the
French Revolution. It is also unlikely that a leader of the New Jerusalem Church would have behaved in public
in the ways described in the <hi rend="i">Chronicle</hi> because the Swedenborgians were anxious to achieve a
kind of respectability.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">4</ref> There are a
number of possible explanations. Given the <hi rend="i">Chronicle</hi> author’s obvious lack of sympathy for
both the Swedenborgians and the individual visionary he is writing about, one cannot assume the author is
especially reliable, so that possibly the visionary, far from being the “head” of the Swedenborgians,
might have had only the most tenuous connection with the New Jerusalem Church. If this were the case, the
visionary might have been one of the Swedenborgians who had been expelled from the Church during the
“concubinage” controversy. A candidate for the visionary’s identity would have to be Augustus
Nordenskjöld who not only found himself on the “wrong” side of the concubinage controversy but who was a
champion of the French Revolution and was in England in 1791 to plan an interracial community to be
established in Sierra Leone.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">5</ref> Of
course the visionary could have been someone else who found himself outside the Swedenborgian fold because of
his radicalism. It is worth remembering that Blake himself fits the description of the visionary—not that
Blake could have been the individual described in the article (he was never close enough to the inner circle
of Swedenborgians to be mistaken for the “head” of the sect), but that he would have identified more
closely with the visionary than with the implied reader of the <hi rend="i">Chronicle</hi> article. The 
<hi rend="i">Chronicle</hi> article quite clearly wants to dissociate itself from the “excesses” of democratic
enthusiasm and to establish a perspective within which one could distinguish easily between legitimate and
illegitimate kinds of oppositional politics. That Blake refused to accept this definition of illegitimate,
excessive radicalism is obvious. <note id="n35"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Howard, 24-32; Paley, 70-74.</note>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Paley, 83. In 1791, Joseph Proud or Robert Hindmarsh would have been
viewed as leaders of the Swedenborgians.</note></p>
          <p>Blake might very well have read the <hi rend="i">Chronicle</hi> article, or if he did not, he
would probably have known the visionary directly or indirectly (through his Swedenborgian friends). One can
take for granted that Blake realized what the reception of the visionary’s words would be in the Johnson
circle and mainstream English Jacobinism. He hardly would have been surprised or shocked by the tone and
rhetoric of the <hi rend="i">Chronicle</hi> article. Plates 12 and 13 of the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, which
represent the narrator’s conversations with Isaiah and Ezekiel, are not necessarily influenced by the
article or the visionary, but they are nevertheless an assault upon the assumptions of the 
<hi rend="i">Chronicle</hi> article which would dismiss visionary experience as absurd. The assumptions of
mainstream radicalism, which Blake would call natural religion or deism, marginalized the religious radicalism
Blake defended. One cannot find in Priestley, Paine, Thelwall, Godwin or Wollstonecraft anything even closely
reminiscent of Blake’s bold assertions of visionary experience. The Johnson circle, then, would have enjoyed
the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>’s attacks on Swedenborg, but it could not have accepted the overall logic of
the work.</p>
          <p>Blake seems to have shared a particular structure of feeling with the Swedenborgians that he did
not share with the Johnson circle, even after he repudiated Swedenborg and the conservative New Jerusalem
Church, even when he maintained a political radicalism similar to that of the Johnson circle. Blake could have
conversed with the <hi rend="i">Chronicle</hi>’s visionary on terms of real respect, even if he disagreed
with him; the Johnson circle would have perceived him as the <hi rend="i">Chronicle</hi>’s author did.
Swedenborg’s
<pb id="p21-104" n="104"/>
errors are so central to the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> not because the Johnson circle also attacked
Swedenborg but because Blake wanted to rescue a particular kind of religiously based radicalism from
Swedenborg’s limitations and Jacobinism’s rationalism. Moreover, the New Jerusalem Church seems to have
been for Blake the one institution which at one time seemed to represent his most passionate commitments. As a
way of working through his disillusionment with Swedenborgianism, <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi> would have to have Swedenborgian error as a principal point of departure.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
