<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>21.4.disalvo</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">William Bolcom, Songs of Innocence and of Experience, A Musical
Illumination of the Poems of William Blake</title>
        <author n="Di Salvo">Jackie Di Salvo</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1988</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1988</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">21.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Jackie Di Salvo</name>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>George Goyder</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Inge Jonsson</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Tadeusz Sławek</name>
              <name>Sheila A. Spector</name>
              <name>David H. Weinglass</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_21">
    <body>
      <pb id="p21-152" n="152"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-21-4-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Bolcom, composer. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience, A
Musical Illumination of the Poems of William Blake.</hi> New York premiere at the Next Wave Festival. Brooklyn
Academy of Music, 9-11 January 1987. Brooklyn Philharmonic, Lukas Foss, conductor.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Jackie <name>Di Salvo</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>After hearing the piper piping again in William Bolcom’s symphonic rendering of Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, one rereads them as what they always were: a cantata with human voices joining a chorus
of birds and beasts and all nature providing orchestration.</p>
          <p>On the “Ecchoing Green” the skylark, thrush, and “merry bells” ring in the morning; a
“Cradle Song” lulls an “infant joy,” and beetles hum through the “silent delight” of night. The
lamb trumpets in call and response to the ewe’s “tender reply,” inspiring the shepherd’s tongue to his
own psalm of praise. Correspondingly, “when voices of children are heard on the green,” the green woods,
the air, the dimpling stream, the meadows, the grasshopper, and the painted birds all add their various
strains to the cosmic “Laughing Song;” a fly dances to an intoxicated rhythm, and the nightingale, the
lark, and the crowing cock punctuate the pervasive “Infant noise.”</p>
          <figure n="Program.p1.21.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="589" height="897">
          	<figTranscr>BROOKLYN ACADEMY OF MUSIC<lb/>
          	HARVEY LICHTENSTEIN, President and Executive Producer<lb/>
          	and<lb/>
          	THE BROOKLYN PHILHARMONIC SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA<lb/>
          	LUKAS FOSS, Music Director and Conductor<lb/>
          	present<lb/>
          	The New York Premiere performances of<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	SONGS OF INNOCENCE AND OF EXPERIENCE<lb/>
          	A Musical Illumination of the Poems of William Blake (1757-1827)<lb/>
          	by<lb/>
          	WILLIAM BOLCOM<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	performed by<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	THE BROOKLYN PHILHARMONIC<lb/>
          	LUKAS FOSS, Conductor<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Sine Nomine Singers<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	The Brooklyn College Chorus<lb/>
          	Prepared by Harry Saltzman, Conductor<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	The Cathedral Choristers<lb/>
          	Prepared by Donald Barnum<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	SOLOISTS:<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	SARA ARNESON, Soprano<lb/>
          	WILLIAM BROWN, Tenor<lb/>
          	DAVID CALDWELL, Vocalist<lb/>
          	BOBBY CAVANAUGH, Boy Soprano<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	ALVIN EPSTEIN, Speaker<lb/>
          	LESLIE GUINN, Baritone<lb/>
          	DORIS MAYES, Mezzo-Soprano<lb/>
          	JOAN MORRIS, Mezzo-Soprano<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	DIANE RAGAINS, Soprano<lb/>
          	Steven J. Mercurio, Assistant Conductor<lb/>
          	Greg MacPherson, Lighting Designer<lb/>
          	Danny Kapilian, Sound Designer<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	*<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Opera House<lb/>
          	Brooklyn Academy of Music<lb/>
          	Friday, January 9, 1987, 8 p.m.<lb/>
          	Saturday, January 10, 1987, 8 p.m.<lb/>
          	Sunday, January 11, 1987, 2 p.m.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	*<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Duration: Approximately 3 hours<lb/>
          	There will be one intermission.</figTranscr>
          </figure>
          <figure n="Program.p2.21.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="593" height="902">
          	<figTranscr>SONGS OF INNOCENCE<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Part I<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	INTRODUCTION<lb/>
          	William Brown<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	THE ECCHOING GREEN<lb/>
          	Chorus<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	THE LAMB<lb/>
          	Diane Ragains<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	THE SHEPHERD<lb/>
          	Leslie Guinn<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	INFANT JOY<lb/>
          	Children’s Choir<lb/>
          	Doris Mayes<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	THE LITTLE BLACK BOY<lb/>
          	David Caldwell<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Part II<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	LAUGHING SONG<lb/>
          	Madrigal Choir<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	SPRING<lb/>
          	William Brown<lb/>
          	Chorus and Children’s Choir<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	A CRADLE SONG<lb/>
          	Sara Arneson<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	THE NURSE’S SONG<lb/>
          	Joan Morris<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	HOLY THURSDAY<lb/>
          	Madrigal Choir<lb/>
          	Chorus<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	THE BLOSSOM<lb/>
          	Diane Ragains<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	INTERLUDE (Orchestra)<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	THE CHIMNEY SWEEPER<lb/>
          	Bobby Cavanaugh<lb/>
          	Women’s Chorus<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	THE DIVINE IMAGE<lb/>
          	Joan Morris<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Part III<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	NOCTURNE (Orchestra)<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	NIGHT<lb/>
          	William Brown<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	A DREAM<lb/>
          	Sara Arneson<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	ON ANOTHER’S SORROW<lb/>
          	Chorus and Children’s Chorus<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	THE LITTLE BOY LOST<lb/>
          	Bobby Cavanaugh<lb/>
          	Chorus and Children’s Chorus<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	THE LITTLE BOY FOUND<lb/>
          	David Caldwell<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	INTERMISSION<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	SONGS OF EXPERIENCE: Volume I<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Part I<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	INTRODUCTION (Orchestra)<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	HEAR THE VOICE OF THE BARD<lb/>
          	Leslie Guinn<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	INTERLUDE (Orchestra)<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	EARTH’S ANSWER<lb/>
          	Diane Ragains<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Part II<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	NURSE’S SONG<lb/>
          	Joan Morris<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	THE FLY<lb/>
          	Children’s Chorus<lb/>
          	Women’s Chorus<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	THE TYGER<lb/>
          	Chorus<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	THE LITTLE GIRL LOST<lb/>
          	Leslie Guinn<lb/>
          	Madrigal Choir<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	THE LITTLE GIRL FOUND<lb/>
          	Madrigal Choir<lb/>
          	Chorus and Children’s Chorus</figTranscr>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p21-153" n="153"/>
          <p>In counterpoint to this joyful melody, a darker theme weaves its “notes of woe.” The
“sobbing, sobbing” of the urban robin and sorrowful wren mingle with the chimney sweeper’s “weep,
weep,” the “infant groan” and orphans’ “trembling cry.” The harlot’s bawdy taunt and the dirge
of a “Soldiers sigh” sound in the cacophony of London streets where, amid a vast moaning chorus around the
altar of industrial slavery, weeping parents deliver piteously shrieking children to the roar of furnaces and
din of clanging hammer and anvil, the drumming heartbeat of this tigerish city.</p>
          <p>Beyond both the spontaneous cries of life, of pleasure and pain, and the mechanical rhythms of
grinding mills, the Bard creates songs that reverberate with the harmonious thunder of the multitudes. The
“School-Boy,” torn from the sweet accompaniment of lark and huntsman’s horn, has been forced to “Sit
in a cage and sing,” and priests, muttering their pious rounds, have
manacled every throat and voice in a stifled squawk. But, the poet troubadour of streets and lanes continues
to call forth a vibrant ale-house chorus to raise up his hymn to the “human form divine.”</p>
          <p>We know from J. T. Smith that Blake composed tunes for his poems which “he would occasionally
sing to his friends” and that “his ear was so good, that his tunes were sometimes most singularly
beautiful and were noted down by musical professors.” Allan Cunningham informs us that when Blake created,
“As he drew the figure, he meditated the song which was to accompany it, and the music to which the verse
was to be sung, was the offspring too of the same moment,” but since he “wanted the art of noting it down,
. . . we have lost melodies of real 
value.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">1</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon
Press, 1969) 457, 482.</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s great visual art might distract us from all this music in his songs, but it is clear
why many modern composers have tried to bring aspects of his rich and varied
            <figure n="Program.p3.21.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="583" height="895">
            	<figTranscr>Part III<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	THE CLOD AND THE PEBBLE<lb/>
            	William Brown<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	THE LITTLE VAGABOND<lb/>
            	Joan Morris<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	HOLY THURSDAY<lb/>
            	Diane Ragains<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	THE POISON TREE<lb/>
            	Alvin Epstein<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	THE ANGEL<lb/>
            	Sara Arneson<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	THE SICK ROSE<lb/>
            	Doris Mayes<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	TO TIRZAH<lb/>
            	Chorus<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	SONGS OF EXPERIENCE: Volume II<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	Part IV<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	THE VOICE OF THE ANCIENT BARD<lb/>
            	Leslie Guinn<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	MY PRETTY ROSE-TREE<lb/>
            	Men’s Chorus<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	AH, SUN-FLOWER<lb/>
            	Madrigal Choir<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	THE LILLY<lb/>
            	William Brown<lb/>
            	Chorus<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	Part V<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	INTRODUCTION (Orchestra)<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	THE GARDEN OF LOVE<lb/>
            	William Brown<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	THE LITTLE BOY LOST<lb/>
            	Bobby Cavanaugh<lb/>
            	Madrigal Choir<lb/>
            	Chorus<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	A LITTLE GIRL LOST<lb/>
            	Diane Ragains<lb/>
            	Leslie Guinn<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	INFANT SORROW<lb/>
            	Madrigal Choir<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	VOCALISE<lb/>
            	Chorus<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	Part VI<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	LONDON<lb/>
            	David Caldwell<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	THE SCHOOL-BOY<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	Bobby Cavanaugh<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	THE CHIMNEY-SWEEPER<lb/>
            	Madrigal Choir<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	THE HUMAN ABSTRACT<lb/>
            	Leslie Guinn<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	VOCES CLAMANDAE<lb/>
            	(Orchestra)<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	A DIVINE IMAGE<lb/>
            	David Caldwell<lb/>
            	Ensemble of Soloists and<lb/>
            	Choruses<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	A special note of thanks to:<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	Dover Publications, Inc., New York<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	The University of Michigan at Ann Arbor<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	Wurttembergisches Staatstheater<lb/>
            	Stuttgart, West Germany<lb/>
            	<lb/>
            	for their generous contribution of William Blake’s<lb/>
            	Illustrations and Poems as produced in this Program.</figTranscr>
            </figure>
            <figure n="Program.p4.21.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="579" height="892">
            	<figTranscr>NOTES BY THE COMPOSER<lb/>
				<lb/>
				(These notes were written for the Stuttgart premiere January 8 and 9, 1984: they are slightly
				revised for this performance.)<lb/>
				<lb/>
				Ever since I was 17, when the reading of William Blake was to make a profound difference
				in my life, I have wanted to set the entire Songs of Innocence and of Experience to music.
				Several songs were actually completed in l956—the opening, revised, of the Songs of
				Innocence and The Sick Rose are survivors of that time—and the work remained in my
				mind until 1973, when I moved to Ann Arbor to teach at the University of Michigan. I felt
				that I could thus simplify my life enough to be able to realize the cycle I had dreamed of
				for so long.<lb/>
				<lb/>
				Most of the work was completed in the years 1973, 1974, 1979, 1980, l981 and 1982; the
				opening of the Songs of Experience was fully sketched in 1966 and several of the major
				songs date from the early and middle 1970s. The largest problem was the form the entire
				setting would take. It could not be a standard opera, and the stopping and starting that
				constantly bedevils the oratorio form would prove fatal for 46 poems over an evening.<lb/>
				<lb/>
				The final ordering of the Songs left by Blake, as will be seen, is quite different from the one I
				had become used to in my earliest reading. In the l880s William Muir, an artist very
				involved with the revival of interest in Blake’s engravings and paintings, actually printed
				some of Blake’s works from the original copper plates and then (as Blake and his wife
				Catherine did) hand-colored them, although not to my mind as interestingly or vividly as
				Blake himself did. In Muir’s edition of The Marriage of Heaven and Hell (1888) I found by
				chance in the appendix an ordering of the Songs of Innocence and of Experience that Blake 
				had presumably left for the use of his wife should anyone want a further printing
				of the Songs, which had been one of the few of his engraved works that had had any sale. 
				(No one evidently asked for a Catherine Blake copy.) This ordering, new to me, gave what 
				I had needed in trying to find an overall shape to the work: a series of arches, in both subject 
				and emotion, that marked off the piece into nine clear movements, each inhabiting a certain 
				spiritual climate and progressing ever further in “Shewing the Contrary States of the Human
				Soul.”<lb/>
				<lb/>
				For those who are used to the ordering of the poems in the Oxford or Modern Library editions, it
				should be mentioned that these orderings derive from only a few of the printings Blake did that
				are somewhat consistent in that respect; Blake changed the ordering of the poems in practically 
				every printing during his lifetime, even trading poems from Innocence to Experience and vice
				versa. With slight changes I have used Blake’s last ordering in my piece; I had always wanted 
				to end the evening with “A Divine Image,” which Blake had engraved and then rejected for the 
				Experience cycle, and I revised the order of the last Part to accommodate the poem.<lb/>
				<lb/>
				The Blakean principle of contraries:<lb/>
					“Without Contraries is no progression. Attraction and Repulsion, Reason and Energy.
					Love and Hate, are necessary to Human existence.” (The Marriage of Heaven and Hell)<lb/>
				would also dominate my approach to the work, particularly in matters of style. Current
				Blake research has tended to confirm what I had assumed from the first, that at every point
				Blake used his whole culture, past and present, highflown and vernacular, as sources for his
				many poetic styles. Throughout the entire Songs of Innocence and of Experience, exercises
				in elegant Drydenesque diction are placed check by jowl by ballads that could have come
				from one or the songsters of his day; it is as if many different people were speaking, from all
				walks of life, each in a different way. The apparent disharmony of each clash and juxtaposition 
				eventually produces a deeper and more universal harmony, once the whole 
				cycle is absorbed. All I did was to use the same stylistic point of departure Blake did, in my
				musical settings.<lb/>
				<lb/>
				If I could say that any one work of mine has been the chief source and progenitor of the
				others, I would have to say that this is it. My fascination with the synthesis of the most
				unlikely stylistic elements dates from my knowledge and application of Blake’s principle of
				contraries, and I have spent most of my artistic life in pursuit of this higher synthesis. In this
				work, through my settings, I have tried my best to make everything clear; I have used music
				in the same way as Blake did line and color, in order to illuminate the poems.<lb/>
				<lb/>
				William Blake is to me the most urgent of poets. What he says is as immediate as ever, but
				particularly to us. He came from an epoch of social change as total as ours, and we can learn
				from him in the time of our deepest human crisis, that of whether or not we will survive as a
				planet. With clear and unjudging vision Blake saw where the human race was heading; it
				could be argued that the Songs of Innocence and of Experience may be the clearest
				explanation we have of what forces have brought us to this frightening impasse. If there is
				any solution, it is only through acceptance and understanding of our own nature, and if I
				have caused a more careful listening of Blake’s message, then my work over a span of
				twenty-five years will not have been in vain.<lb/>
				<lb/>
				WILLIAM BOLCOM</figTranscr>
            </figure>
<pb id="p21-154" n="154"/>
symphony to our ears. Benjamin Britten, Ralph Vaughn Williams, Virgil Thomson, and Samuel Adler have all set
groups of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> to music. Ben Weber wrote a <hi rend="i">Symphony in Four Movements on
the Poems of William Blake</hi> (1950). Ellen Raskin set some of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> to guitar for
children, and Allen Ginsberg recorded his harmonium chants. <corr type="emend">Wilfrid Mellers</corr> began but never completed the
entire cycle; John Sykes (1909-62) finished thirty seven songs.</p>
          <figure n="Chorus.21.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="428">
            <head>1. The Brooklyn College Chorus, Sine Nomine Singers and the Brooklyn Philharmonic Orchestra
performing William Bolcom’s <hi rend="i">Musical Illumination of Songs of Innocence and Experience</hi> at
the Brooklyn Academy of Music, 11 January 1987.</head>
            <figDesc>(The St. James Cathedral Choristers, a children’s choir, is not visible here.) Courtesy
of T. Brazil.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>At this “Enormous Labor,” no one has been more tenacious than William Bolcom, who spent
twenty-five years setting all forty-six poems for his <hi rend="i">Musical Illumination of the Poems of
William Blake</hi>, a massive megascore requiring as many as 200 singers and 100 musicians. Running almost
three hours, this neo-Mahlerian “Symphony of a Thousand,” twice as long as Beethoven’s ninth symphony,
is a monumental montage of lyrics for an epic Blake. After previous renditions in such radically different
venues as the Stuttgart Opera, Chicago’s park concerts, and the University of Michigan where Bolcom teaches,
the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> had its successful New York premiere in January 1987 at the Brooklyn Academy of
Music’s avant garde Next Wave Festival with Lucas Foss conducting the Brooklyn Philharmonic. Although no
recording is yet planned due to the costs of assembling such forces, some further performances, probably in
Europe, are projected for 1988.</p>
          <p>Bolcom, now forty-eight, began playing the piano at three, reading music at five, and attending
university classes at eleven. He reports that, upon first encountering Blake at age seventeen in 1956, he
“felt an immediate kinship” and set to music then the “Piper’s Song” that opens the piece.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">2</ref> Throughout the 60s and 70s, while working as a
teacher, composer, and piano player, he continued orchestrating the poems in what he hoped would be, like
Blake’s illustrations, an “illumination.” <note id="n30"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Quotations from Bolcom are
drawn from his “Program Notes,” other materials made available to me by the composer and comments reported
in such media as the <hi rend="i">Village Voice, New York Times</hi>, and <hi rend="i">New
Yorker.</hi></note></p>
          <p>The composer cites Blake as precedent for his own attempt to combine the classical and the
popular. After getting a graduate degree from Stanford, becoming a Rockefeller and Guggenheim fellow, and
studying with the French composer Darius Milhaud, he wrote “serious” modern music in the prevailing
dissonant mode—a few symphonies, eight string quartets, piano etudes. Then in 1963 Bolcom dropped out to
write an off-Broadway “opera for actors,” <hi rend="i">Dynamite Tonight</hi>, with Arnold Weinstein,
discovered a gift for ragtime piano, wrote his <hi rend="i">Ghostly Rags</hi>, collaborated with Eubie Blake
and began composing his <hi rend="i">Unpopular Songs</hi>, using classical techniques in pop styles and
influencing such rock groups as Pink Floyd. After teaming up professionally and personally with mezzo-soprano,
Joan Morris, (they walked down the aisle in 1975 to a ragtime <hi rend="i">Wedding March</hi> played by
ninety-six-year-old Eubie), he became best known as her accompanist. They soon gained renown for bringing
American popular music to classical labels and concert halls with wit, charm, and artistic seriousness. After
earning a Grammy nomination for <hi rend="i">After the Ball</hi>, a collection of pre-1920s tunes (Nonesuch)
which topped the classical charts, they followed with anthologies of vaudeville songs, Civil War era ballads,
songs by Gershwin, Kern, Rodgers and Hart, and cabaret tunes, many by Bolcom, recorded on two live albums, 
<hi rend="i">Black Max</hi> and <hi rend="i">Lime Jello</hi> (RCA)—fourteen recordings in all. Bolcom never
entirely stopped writing more formal modernist music, however, and the week of the Blake premiere also saw
both a concert of popular songs with Morris and a performance of his violin concerto at Carnegie Hall. Soon
after, the St. Louis Symphony would perform his <hi rend="i">Fourth Symphony</hi>, developed around an
extended setting of Theodore Roethke’s “The Rose.” In preparation for setting poetry to music, Bolcom
had studied at the University of Washington with Roethke, whose use of old poetic forms such as the villanelle
parallels Bolcom’s own mining of traditions. Here the main musical influence was the composer Charles Ives
whose celebration of popular American idioms and emphasis on accessibility would influence such diverse other
composers as Kurt Weill, Virgil Thomson, Leonard Bernstein, Lukas Foss, George Rothberg (whose writings Bolcom
edited), David Del Tredici and Peter Schickele.</p>
          <p>However, the confidence and theory for this eclecticism, according to Bolcom, came from Blake:
“Blake
<pb id="p21-155" n="155"/>
used his whole culture, past and present, highflown and vernacular as sources for his many poetic styles”
with “elegant Drydenesque diction placed cheek by jowl by ballads that could have come from the songsters of
his day . . . as if many different people were speaking, from all walks of life.” The 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, Bolcom’s most ambitious attempt at synthesis, which he alternately calls a
symphony-oratorio or cantata and compares to song cycle, opera, glee club concert, and rock album, pushes
traditional composers’ incorporation of folk motifs to new limits. Bolcom complains that “some composers
have become so concerned with being one-pointed. You can become imprisoned that way. Bach and Mozart
constantly brought some of the pop music of their day into their music.” What differentiates Bolcom’s work
from more traditional borrowers, like Dvorak, who work classical embellishments on stolen snippets of popular
melodies, is that Bolcom eschews such classical reworking and allows each vernacular style its own character.
Instead, he explores the contrasts which result from letting rock and folk jostle alongside dissonant
twelve-tone chorales. He attributes his “fascination with the synthesis of the most unlikely stylistic
elements” to his knowledge and application of Blake’s principle that “Without Contraries is no
progression.” In his wide variety of musical settings, he seeks to mirror the scope of Blake’s work itself
so “the apparent disharmony of each clash and juxtaposition eventually produces a deeper and more universal
harmony, once the whole cycle is absorbed.”</p>
          <p>In order to achieve this range, avoid tedium and give maximum color to the lengthy work, he
employs a massive panoply of musical forces in a three ring circus
            <figure n="Foss.21.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="439">
	<head>2. Lukas Foss conducting the Brooklyn Philharmonic with boy soprano Bobby Cavanaugh performing “The
Chimney Sweeper” from <hi rend="i">Innocence.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of T. Brazil.</figDesc>
</figure>
whose spotlight shifts among a full oratorio chorus, a children’s choir, madrigal group, nine soloists (two
sopranos, a classical and a pop mezzo, tenor, baritone, boy soprano, rock singer and narrator), as well as a
huge amplified orchestra with organ, euphonium, the usual winds in triplicate, flugelhorn, electric violins, a
large percussion and brass ensemble, including two saxophones, and a rock band with electric bass and guitar.
Bolcom hopes ultimately for a multi-media presentation with Blake’s relief etchings projected during
performances, and perhaps, even costumes and dance, but this has not yet proved possible although elaborate
programs have included select plates.</p>
          <p>He has found his order for the texts in one of the last of Blake’s reorderings (indicated in a
late letter, perhaps to Butts, E 772), a version existing in only one copy. Bolcom, having discovered the plan
in the appendix to William Muir’s 1880 facsimile of <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi>, arranged the 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> into three parts, I for <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, II and III for 
<hi rend="i">Experience.</hi> Altering only the final sequence (to build to the restored “Divine Image”), he
divided each part into three groups of varying numbers of poems as “a series of arches, in both subject and
emotion, that marked off the piece into nine clear movements, each inhabiting a certain spiritual climate and
progressing ever further in “Shewing the Contrary States of the Human Soul.” While he sees “a sort of
plot in the canon,” with its three sections as a progression from childhood to adulthood to maturity, equal
musical attention is given the nine song groups as contrasting vocal-symphony movements.</p>
          <p>Within that mosaic structure attention is focused on the <corr type="emend">segueing</corr> of
one song into the next, their sometimes jolting contrasts, and the orchestrated pauses between movements.
Through these musical contrasts and developments Bolcom tries to reflect those of Blake’s poems. All the
oppositions between and within texts yield, however, to the symphony’s main contrast between the atonal
dissonant complexities of abstract modernism and the more straightforward melodies of various popular
genres.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">3</ref> Bolcom’s sequence offers
him marvelous opportunities for such progress through contrast and reveals Blake’s belated principle of
organization as truly inspired. <note id="n31"><hi rend="s">3</hi> I was assisted with the music by Daniel
Goode, a composer of New Music and professor at Rutgers University.</note></p>
          <p>The opening group provides a strong and upbeat introduction to <hi rend="i">Innocence.</hi> In a
manner typical of the piece throughout, we hear a confusing, loud, polytonal, orchestral cacophony out of
which a song eventually emerges with its own vision, as here the tenor lifts the piper’s song, a simple tune
to fluty pipe and tambourine in bright three-quarter-time swing. The chorus follows with “The Ecchoing
Green” in lilting, folksy triple-time with gorgeous choral echoes set off by country fiddle, chimes, and
gong. The shock comes when “The Lamb” completely abandons this pastoral primitivism for the
<pb id="p21-156" n="156"/>
first of what will be several atonal, operatic soprano pieces through which Bolcom tries to express the more
visionary and unearthly Blake of such angelic visitations as “A Dream” and later, 
<hi rend="i">Experience</hi>’s “An Angel.” We are, however, brought thumpingly back out of the clouds with a
kind of “Home on the Range” country-western “Shepherd” baritone solo with fiddle. The children’s
choir appropriately initiates “Infant Joy’s” chromatic duet with a maternal mezzo over orchestral
chords.</p>
          <p>The movement then culminates in a soft-rock, electric jazz “Little Black Boy,” whose drumming
beat is intended to underscore Blake’s ultimately nonassimilationist celebration of the boy’s essentially
black, sun-inflamed soul. In “Night the Ninth” of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> Blake puts the “New
Song” of apocalypse into the voice of an African slave in a remarkable musical prophecy of the Afro-American
liberation of modern popular music. Bolcom’s mild, folksy rock is performed here, however, by an
overwhelmingly white chorus and orchestra. We were listening to it in the middle of black and Caribbean
Brooklyn, whose street kids, chanting in repetitive fury from fire escapes and street corners in a Blakean
populism of their own, have merged rhythm and rhyme to make it the rap center of the universe. Sensing here a
missed opportunity, I wished the composer had ventured further beyond white popular idiom than a little
ragtime and modified reggae into more Blakean spiritual-erotical ranges of gospel, rhythm and blues, or
soul.</p>
          <p>He tends, rather, to put Blake’s wildness into orchestration and things like the fortissimo
conclusion of the madrigal sextet’s “Laughing Song” which opens the next movement. This section also
includes the melodious lullaby of “Cradle Song” and in waltz time to guitar the first of Morris’s
delightful “Nurse’s Songs,” the work’s only strictly musically paired poems. Gratified desire then
yields to the angry exuberance of a “Holy Thursday” carol with horns by madrigalists and chorus, a neat
choice for the liturgical-pop thundering of Blake’s multitude. “The Chimney Sweeper” explicates such
ferocity as that suppressed in its contrastingly pathetic recitation of the sweepers’ plight against the
whining euphonium of a sentimental music hall tune while an angelic chorus and clarinet enacts the sweeper’s
fantasy liberation. But, the set ends hopefully in F-major piety with “The Divine Image,” serenely hymned
by Morris. Part III of <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> is a mostly classical and modernist movement, far less to
my taste, though it introduces the Romantic “Night,” nicely through a meditative “Nocturne” whose
instrumental trill, pluck, and rattle bring us Blake’s birds, beetles and crickets. In the shrieking soprano
fluttering of “A Dream,” the orchestral clamor and clanging cymbals of “On Another’s Sorrow” and the
completely dissonant “Little Boy Lost,” the text is completely lost, only to be recovered in the folk tune
of “The Little Boy Found.”</p>
          <p>The opening of <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> continues the post-Schoenberg mode for “The Voice
of the Ancient Bard” and “Earth’s Answer.” The second movement is more enchanting. Beginning with a
“Nurse’s Song,” rendered less bouncy and more plaintive by the addition of wood-winds and harp, Bolcom
then places Blake’s “Tyger,” not against “The Lamb,” but the preceding “Fly,” a sad, haunting
evocation of human contingency sung to skittish rhythms by the children’s and women’s choruses. “The
Tyger” then confronts us with the harrowing forces with which such frail beings must contend in a shouted
speech-song mostly by male voices. Bolcom, who said he tried “to make everything clear,” both submits here
to the poem’s insistent beating and breaks its familiarity by putting two beats on each first syllable
“Ty-y-ger Ty-y-ger
            <figure n="MorrisBolcom.21.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="420">
	<head>3. Joan Morris and William Bolcom, courtesy of Shaw Concerts, Inc.</head>
</figure>
bur-ur-ning bright” against a wild rumbling percussion. The group then concludes with a romantic Mahlerian
rendition of “Little Girl Lost” and “Found,” its straight-forward five note melody first relayed
acappella between male and female choruses, then, by the time it has taken us to the kingly lion’s hallowed
ground, rounded out with rich harmonizing. When the “spirit arm’d in gold” appears, it is encompassed by
harmonious orchestration as well, until finally “The Tyger’s” dread is resolved with the Blakean vision
of the “sleeping child / Among tygers wild” of its rapturous conclusion.</p>
          <p>The next three movements continue these contrapuntal styles: “The Little Vagabond” ’s lusty
barroom fox trot against the soaring Fs and F sharps above high C of “The Angel” ’s frigid maid, scored
to be performed “Silvery, like a princess in an ice-palace” and “A Poison Tree” ’s grim narration
against the ominous chords of an atonal piano. The flower group moves from a pretty barbershop
<pb id="p21-157" n="157"/>
“Rose Tree,” to the sighing echoes of “Ah! Sunflower” and the complex, chromatic setting of “The
Lilly,” making in its own way the piece’s strong argument against finding an illusory simplicity in
Blake’s lyrics. The penultimate movement drowns the complaint against childhood repression of “The Garden
of Love,” “The Little Girl Lost” and “Infant Sorrow” in its disharmonies, but the 
<hi rend="i">Carmina Burana</hi>-like “A Little Boy Lost” with boy soprano and chorus drives it home with
scary rhythm to a bit of melody picked up, appropriately, from “Holy Thursday.”</p>
          <p>Finally, we move toward an apocalyptic finale through the felicitous concluding cluster. The
“mind-forg’d manacles” denounced by a rocking “London” are analyzed in “The Human Abstract.”
Such spiritual oppression is further exemplified in “The School-Boy” ’s lyric plaint against a
stultifying education and “The Chimney Sweeper” ’s denunciation of religion, its tambourines, gong and
drum brush capturing the child’s wretched gaiety in what could be either a festive Elizabethan procession or
a prison march. These contraries of human self-creation-become-self-destruction sharpen in the slow reggae
finale whose terrible vision that “Cruelty has a Human Heart” is sung in cheerful full throated vigor to a
too singable, too swingable tune passed with mounting energy from rock singer to full chorus and orchestra.
Since you can’t get the tune out of your head for days, the ironies continue to unsettle.</p>
          <p>Bolcom claims he learned such juxtaposition from Bob Marley, to whom the song is dedicated, and
that, in this dark age, he wanted to end the cycle in celebration, but one is equally reminded of our
culture’s hedonistic dance of death on the brink of every kind of economic, political, and ecological
catastrophe. Ultimately, this prophetic element is what Bolcom, who spent the 60s studying in California and
Paris, says draws him to Blake: “Blake is the most urgent of poets. He came from an epoch of social change
as total as ours, and we can learn from him in the times of our deepest crisis. Blake saw where the human race
was heading; it could be argued that the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and Experience</hi> may be the
clearest explanation of what brought us to this impasse.” The solution he hopes to promote is a greater
“acceptance and understanding of our own nature” through “a more careful listening to Blake’s
message.”</p>
          <p>I’m not sure quite how to assess his achievement. Is this the new American masterpiece that
some critics have called it? Is it Blake? Which Blake? I feel too musically inexpert to venture a judgment.
The eclecticism and the Neo-Romanticism seem right; one wants the range of heaven and earth, common and
sublime that Bolcom attempts. I loved the lyricism, and he has a way with melody that certainly gets you
singing those very different “Divine Image” songs. As a whole, however, the piece, written over
twenty-five years, may be overwhelmed by its own variety; motifs don’t return often, or, at least, I
couldn’t hear the continuity. Thus, unity seems to rest on its most repeated and pervasive style, the
post-Schoenberg, post-Berg abstractions and dissonance. I’m not sure what this angst-ridden mode brings to
Blake finally; perhaps it articulates some of the alienation, ambiguity, and indeterminacy so prominent in
recent readings of Blake. Or is it just what a serious modern composition must sound like?</p>
          <p>As for the vernacular, its effect is weakened by Bolcom’s political-aesthetic decision to use
mostly classical voices, and I felt that sometimes it was the wrong vernacular. Bolcom’s popular idiom is
mostly the milder, nostalgic kind, old folk tunes or turn of the century ballads. His rock made me want
something funkier, harder—Pink Floyd, indeed. Though it’s intriguing to imagine Blake as their bond,
there’s nothing in Bolcom so rebellious as “We don’t want no education; We don’t want no thought
control” (Pink Floyd, <hi rend="i">The Wall</hi>). And where is the Dionysian? For me, it is still Ginsberg
who captures Blake’s prophetic seriousness in his passionately committed incantations. I heard Ginsberg get
a college auditorium chanting as a fierce refrain, the “Merrily, merrily we welcome in the year” of
“Spring” ’s erotic pastoral which, he promised us, sung with sufficient conviction, could resurrect the
60s utopian dream. It has never failed to teach my students more in ten wild minutes about Blake’s
contraries than any other introduction. What Ginsberg’s chants or the Labour Party’s bellowing of
Parry’s “Jerusalem” capture is that Blake’s poetry must be sung so it can be taken into our yearning
bodies and filled with our hearts’ desires.</p>
          <p>Even so, it is not just Ginsberg’s but probably two, three, many Blakes that we are wanting and
that all these furiously composing musicians like Bolcom will continue to give us. We have been absorbing the
lesson of Blake’s “composite art” as providing, in the mutual commentary of picture and text, not a more
definitive interpretation, but more interpretive possibilities. This aesthetic, W. J. T. Mitchell has
commented, demands creative participation, almost as if we must intuit missing poems Blake could have written
to go with the pictures.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">4</ref> Well, there
is missing music to go with the engraved poems, and composers like Bolcom remind us that Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> bequeath to us an even greater freedom, leaving to the ongoing “wonders Divine of Human
Imagination” the interpretive music to which they will be sung. <note id="n32"><hi rend="s">4</hi> W. J. T.
Mitchell, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art: A Study of the Illuminated Poetry</hi> (Princeton: Princeton
UP, 1978), 8.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
