<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>21.4.jonsson</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Harvey F. Bellin and Darrell Ruhl, eds., Blake and Swedenborg: Opposition is True
Friendship</title>
        <author n="Jonsson">Inge Jonsson</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1988</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1988</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">21.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Jackie Di Salvo</name>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>George Goyder</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Inge Jonsson</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Tadeusz Sławek</name>
              <name>Sheila A. Spector</name>
              <name>David H. Weinglass</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_21">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-21-4-0007">
        <pb id="p21-158" n="158"/>
        <div2>
          <figure n="BlakeSwedenborg.bkcover.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="435"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Harvey F. Bellin and Darrell Ruhl, eds. <hi rend="i">Blake and Swedenborg:
Opposition Is True Friendship.</hi> New York: Swedenborg Foundation Inc., 1985. 157 pp. $8.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Inge</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Jonsson</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The subtitle of this anthology, “The Sources of William Blake’s Arts in the Writings of
Emanuel Swedenborg,” is more precise about its contents than its allusive title. The subtitle has the virtue
of reminding us of the demonstrated connection between Blake’s poetry and engravings and the theosophical
writings of Emanuel Swedenborg.</p>
          <p>This does not come as a surprise, and apart from some introductory surveys the anthology presents
very few articles that have not been published elsewhere. A good starting-point is Morton D. Paley’s paper
“A New Heaven Is Begun: Blake and Swedenborgianism” (15-34), which is not only the first but also the best
contribution to the book. There are in all thirteen surviving books in which Blake made notes, and among
those, three had been written by Swedenborg: <hi rend="i">Heaven and Hell, Divine Love and Wisdom</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Divine Providence.</hi>
	<pb id="p21-159" n="159"/>
The first Swedenborgian conference in London in 1789, in which Blake and his beloved Catherine registered
among the participants, was the only assembly we know him to have attended. Of similar importance are
Blake’s attacks on Swedenborg in his marginal notes in <hi rend="i">Divine Providence</hi> and the satire
<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi> When dealing with a well-informed critic like Blake a
negative reading often indicates influences as interesting as those emanating from the submissive attitude of
a follower.</p>
          <p>The conference in April 1789 unanimously accepted forty-two theological theses; they are
available in a later section of the anthology. Thus it is easy for the reader to find out what Blake could
accept at that time as a foundation for his creed. It is a matter of course that he firmly believed in man’s
free will, but Paley emphasizes that he also accepted Swedenborg’s famous <hi rend="i">Nunc licet.</hi>
“That Now it is allowable to enter intellectually into the Mysteries of Faith” (<hi rend="i">Vera
Christiana Religio</hi>, n. 185).</p>
          <p>Obviously Blake had already strained the meaning of Swedenborg’s words in a direction that did
not correspond to the intentions of the master. Paley takes one of the marginal notes in <hi rend="i">Heaven
and Hell</hi> as an example. According to Blake’s reading, hell becomes something negative, a kind of
mistake for heaven, which is of course in line with his own passionate conception of unity but not in
accordance with Swedenborg’s thinking. In a similar way Blake tried to stress the unifying elements of
Swedenborg’s doctrine of correspondence restraining everything that separates nature from the spiritual
world: i.e., an attitude toward reality which later he was to express by the wonderful metaphor of looking 
<hi rend="i">through</hi> the eye but not <hi rend="i">with</hi> it.</p>
          <p>As Paley correctly observes, Blake had no reason for attacking Swedenborg as a representative of
a doctrine of predestination “more abominable than Calvin’s.” In a number of texts Swedenborg firmly
repudiated all ideas of a divine predestination. God is omniscient, however, knowing the final destination of
all individuals, but this should not prevent man from making use of his <hi rend="i">liberum arbitrium.</hi>
From an omniscient point of view it may be impossible to divide between predestination and prediction but not
from a human one, and man’s free will is a basic element in Swedenborg’s theology.</p>
          <p>But Blake found this well-known method of dealing with the theodicy problem unacceptable, and
there were other reasons which forced Blake to dissociate himself from the New Jerusalem of the Swedenborgians
and to build his own. First Paley mentions the attitude to the French revolution. For Blake, the upheavals in
France were a cause for rejoicing, but the New Church people were anxious to condemn them completely. Some
internal conflicts made Blake indignant, e.g., the expulsion of a number of members, among them two remarkable
Swedes, Carl Bernhard Wadström and August Nordenskjöld, because of a controversy about Swedenborg’s view
of concubinage presented in <hi rend="i">De amore conjugiali</hi> (1768). The rather macabre opening of
Swedenborg’s tomb in 1790, or more precisely the motivation for it, had a similar effect on Blake. As Paley
reports, he fiercely alluded to these events in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi></p>
          <p>However, this formidable satire does not represent Blake’s last words about Swedenborg. On the
contrary, Paley shows very convincingly that there are many Swedenborgian influences to be found in Blake’s
later works, in details as well as in general evaluations. The list given in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> of
the books of the Bible, which contain the internal sense of the Word, is exactly the same as the one
Swedenborg established. Swedenborg also inspired Blake’s view of history as a series of “churches” more
or less in a state of decomposition, and gave him the fancy piece of information that the oldest Word is
preserved in Great Tartary. Swedenborg himself referred to his angelic interlocutors, but a skeptical reader
probably prefers a number of contemporary texts as possible sources for this statement, which of course cannot
be scientifically verified.</p>
          <p>Following Paley’s learned essay is a survey of a more popular kind written by one of the
editors. Bellin’s way of presenting the relations between Swedenborg and Blake indicates that the author is
a prominent TV-producer with a keen eye for what is dramatically and pictorially efficient. Blake’s art
contains many qualities of that sort and Bellin’s contribution includes a number of impulses for the
analysis of the artist’s Swedenborg inspiration. The author lays the main stress on the doctrine of
correspondence as a liberating as well as a structuring force in Blake’s attempt to visualize his ideas of a
psychic universe, and this seems generally reasonable. But when it comes to details Bellin hardly succeeds in
dealing with the wide gap between the rationalistic factors of Swedenborg’s own presentation of the doctrine
and Blake’s distinctive mythology. On the other hand, he certainly exaggerates Swedenborg’s contributions
as a scientist, which is as characteristic as understandable in most Swedenborgian contexts. The rather
unfortunate effect of this apologetic attitude is that Swedenborg will be seen as a less problematic, and
consequently less interesting, author than he becomes if one tries to understand him as representing some
esoteric trends in eighteenth-century thinking.</p>
          <p>In one of his footnotes Paley refers polemically to Kathleen Raine’s book <hi rend="i">Blake
and Tradition</hi> (1968). Her chapter on <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">Songs of
Experience</hi> is reprinted in the anthology, but Paley’s critical reference concerns a neoplatonic
interpretation in a later part of Raine’s book. However, the platonic tradition has been invoked also in
this chapter, where Swedenborg’s
<pb id="p21-160" n="160"/>
“symbolism” is presented as a variation of platonic thinking. This is certainly true of all “symbolic”
languages in European philosophy, but this very fact makes precise distinctions more important. Even if Raine
is of the same opinion, she has put almost all emphasis on Swedenborg’s rather arbitrary methods for
interpreting Holy Writ. The most fascinating elements of Swedenborg’s thinking are not given their due
attention, e.g., that the doctrine of correspondence represents a substitute for the mathematically conceived
universal language of which some of his greatest predecessors in the seventeenth century had been dreaming.
Swedenborg’s visions bear the stamp of decades of scientific work and daring speculations within the
framework of contemporary science about the hidden structure of nature. In Raine’s view “there is no
literary value in Swedenborg’s symbolism, and nothing could be less poetic than the ‘visions’ of that
sage,” but she has presented most unsatisfactory reasons for her evaluation. On the contrary, Swedenborg’s
works as a whole display deep intellectual and emotional qualities resulting in a personal combination of
enlightened rationality and romantic forebodings. Blake must have felt the intensity behind Swedenborg’s
systematic rigidity, and he reacted in the same manner as so many other artists and poets: sometimes he found
these qualities attractive and inspiring; on other occasions he was repelled by the master’s
conventionalities in concepts and style.</p>
          <p>The second contribution to the anthology by Kathleen Raine is a lecture held in Paris in 1985
called “The Human Face of God.” Her subject here is the concept of God in Swedenborg’s and Blake’s
works in comparison with Jung’s <hi rend="i">Answer to Job.</hi> From a literary point of view this lecture
is interesting as an attempt to prove that the influence of Swedenborg appears to have been stronger in
Blake’s later works than in those from the 1790’s. Since this is a hypothesis contradictory to the
mainstream of Blake scholarship it should be considered. But the argumentation here can hardly be regarded as
well founded. In order to prove the hypothesis a much more penetrating analysis of Swedenborg’s and
Blake’s use of the concept “the Divine Human” will be necessary. Still, Raine’s edifying discourse
contains many valuable impulses for future research.</p>
          <p>The second section of the anthology, “Historical contexts,” includes the report of the London
conference in 1789 mentioned above and a study by Raymond H. Deck, Jr. of Charles Augustus Tulk (originally
published in <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 1977). This is a solid historical account of one of
Blake’s nineteenth-century patrons, who probably had some importance for the artist’s later opinions of
Swedenborg. Tulk’s parents took part at the London conference in 1789, but their son preferred to remain
outside Swedenborgian sectarianism. Still, he was well read in the master’s writings, and he was also one of
the founders of a society for printing and publishing these works in 1810. As the Swedenborg Society, this
association has done great work in promoting information about them and is still doing so.</p>
          <p>Tulk was a gentleman of independent means, who devoted his time to politics and his reading of
Swedenborg. He also supported William Blake in different ways. It was probably their common friend John
Flaxman who enticed Tulk to buy some of Blake’s works around 1815. In February 1818 he lent Coleridge a copy
of the poet’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, and the learned critic immediately identified some essential
Swedenborg influences in them. On a later occasion he also arranged a meeting between Coleridge and Blake. The
author has also given convincing reasons for the attribution of an article in 1830 to Tulk, which describes
this encounter: “Blake and Coleridge, when in company, seemed like congenial beings of another sphere,
breathing for a while on our earth; which may easily be perceived from the similarity of thought pervading
their works.”</p>
          <p>The concluding section of the anthology is called “Swedenborgian Postscripts.” It consists of
two articles and one lecture by New Church men, who illustrate different attempts at explaining Blake’s
complicated relations to Swedenborg from their particular point of view. In that respect they outline a
reception history, to which this beautiful anthology itself is the latest contribution. The question marks in
its margins should not discourage anyone interested in William Blake’s art from reading this book. It
certainly deserves many readers both within and outside of the New Church tradition, where the artist has
caused many sorrows but also great pride.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
