<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>21.4.slawek</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Czeslaw Milosz, The Land of Ulro</title>
        <author n="Sławek">Tadeusz Sławek</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1988</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1988</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">21.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Jackie Di Salvo</name>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>George Goyder</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Inge Jonsson</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Tadeusz Sławek</name>
              <name>Sheila A. Spector</name>
              <name>David H. Weinglass</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_21">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-21-4-0007">
		<pb id="p21-160" n="160"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Czeslaw Milosz. <hi rend="i">The Land of Ulro.</hi> Trans. Louis Iribarne. New
York: Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, 1984. vii +287 pp. Hard cover $17.95/paper $9.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Tadeusz</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Sławek</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>This book, whose title must unfailingly attract attention of all Blakeans, opens in a series of
familiar, almost Derridean, hesitations. The reader learns from the first sentence of the preface that he is
no more than an intruder in the world of the book, and if he wishes to indulge in the act of reading it is
only at his risk: “Dear
<pb id="p21-161" n="161"/>
Reader, this book was not intended for you, and I feel you should be forewarned before you enter its bizarre
tangle” (v)—even Sterne and Derrida would have spared remarks like that till the moment when they had
already let the reader well into their mazes.</p>
          <figure n="Milosz.bkcover.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="741"/>
          <p>The speaking voice, however, which announces the book in a highly assertive manner (“My
decision to write <hi rend="i">The Land of Ulro</hi> was an act of perfect freedom . . . ,” v) is not exempt
from general indecision: what was started as a probing of personal, “maverick” pleasure turns out to be a
disquieting search for identity. The assertive tone has been only a brief romance with the tradition of the
preface where one knows, announces, and establishes relationships with past epochs and works; the mode of
Milosz’s book itself is interrogative (“Who was I? Who am I now, years later, here on Grizzly Peak, in my
study overlooking the Pacific?” 3). “Dear Reader” who will take up <hi rend="i">The Land of Ulro</hi>:
you are in an alien territory that is a labyrinth (<hi rend="i">Lasciate ogni speranza</hi>), and the voice
that leads you is that of a ventriloquist.</p>
          <p>The task of the (dear) Reader is, however, more Romantic than Dantean: it is less to study the
philosophical pattern of existence and more to penetrate the principle of one’s identity. The book then is
in part Wordsworthian in its attempt to trace the “Growth of a Poet’s Mind” so that we shall finally see
that the identity of the voice questioned in the first sentence is secured again on the last page by a
reference to a Romantic concept of memory: “By recalling that the boy and the poet—‘catastrophist’ and
the old professor in Berkeley are the same man . . .” (275). If it is true that the book is a “tangle,”
then it is equally true that it has its own “principle” (275), which saves it from chaos and which is
conterminous with a continuity of the human self. In the same way as the young boy from Lithuania and the old
professor in Berkeley are one person (despite the meanders of life defying understanding: “I do not
understand my life . . .” 4), the book is—like Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>—both “childish and
adult, both ethereal and earth-bound” (275) (despite its “chimerical kingdoms” of allusions and
digressions).</p>
          <p>The Sternian/Derridean attitude of the preface resolves in the Platonic Care which saturates the
whole book. This Care is Platonic, not Heideggerian, because unlike the Care in <hi rend="i">Sein und
Zeit</hi> it is not destined to be a mode of man’s rootedness in Being, but as in <hi rend="i">The Laws</hi>
it is animated by the sense of the moral duty which one has in the face of culture and in the name of culture.
The (dear) reader from his ostracized position of a total stranger and intruder in Milosz’s world passes
through a more sympathetic territory where the author, the reader, and humanity are purged by the waters of
understanding. “Reader, be tolerant of me. And of yourself. And of the singular aspirations of our human
race” (275). Reader (notice, how Care eliminates a formulaic “dear”), it is true, we have studied my
idiosyncratic tastes and family relations, but we have done so in order to see how our Care enables us to
participate in something larger than a mere individual self.</p>
          <p>This “something larger,” which goes beyond narcissistic introspection, Care bodies forth in
culture. In Milosz’s philosophy, which is predominantly a philosophy of culture, Nature plays the role of a
gothic villain: it is either invisible but subtly pulls the strings, or manifest and then cataclysmic and
indifferent in its destructive force (“Nature’s reckless indifference . . . ,” 37). Thus a series of
readings of particular authors that Milosz offers in his book is organized by two principles: that a human
freedom is a freedom of intellectual growth in a library, and that this library necessarily has to define
itself against the external world of Nature. We should be careful not to confound Milosz’s and Borges’s
<pb id="p21-162" n="162"/>
versions of the library: the latter is so extensive that, in effect, it offers no choice and no freedom, the
former is a library of masterpieces (“basic texts”) where the choice may seem haphazard or even absurd,
but it is never meaningless.</p>
          <p>“I insist on the freedom, on my right to browse at will among the basic texts that are the
inheritance of centuries . . .” (159). Although unlike Borges’s Library of Babel Milosz’s shelves always
shelter meaning, the path of the reader is no less labyrinthine: Gombrowicz, Dostoyevsky, Mickiewicz, Oscar
Milosz, Stanislaw Brzozowski, Swedenborg, Simon Weil, Shestov, Blake. Also unlike the Library of Babel
Milosz’s maze of books has a thread, a sparkle of hope which turns the archives of pure 
<hi rend="i">écriture</hi> into the memoirs of human mind. As Milosz confesses: “That thread is my
anthropocentrism and my bias against Nature” (159).</p>
          <p>We begin to see the first reason why Blake became a haunting presence in Milosz’s book: the
critique of Nature (spelled characteristically to emphasize, through capitalization, its Manichaean power) is
inevitably aimed at a certain version of the Romantic philosophy represented by Rousseau, one of the three
chief villains of Blake’s philosophical mythology, who “prescribed it [Nature] as the cure for a corrupted
civilization” (160). Culture, Milosz seems to be saying, will always benefit more from the drugs of
Plato’s rather than Nature’s Pharmacy. The way to a recovery from the crisis does not lead to a nostalgic
look backward towards the Golden Age but to a bold analysis of the future. A diatribe against Nature must
necessarily open a discussion of the sense of human time.</p>
          <p>There seem to exist two types of literature, one which is easier to detect and name and which,
almost diabolically corrupted, still turns out to be its own caricature when one faces the unfathomable
abysses of human history. Milosz calls this tradition “dark” and quickly defines his response to it as
“hostile” (38). No names are mentioned, but a few pages later Milosz hints at Kafka, Beckett, Sartre, and
Ionesco (42) as if unwilling to leave us in the dark. Milosz’s unfavorable response to this literature is
grounded in his disbelief and mistrust of Nature: “dark” literature probes the nature of man and pretends
to achieve shattering effects whereas its “naturalness” thus obtained is but a parody of, as Blake would
put it, “Real Existence.” To deal with Nature in this manner inescapably winds up in certain cheapness of
effect, “. . . its [dark literature’s] mockery, sarcasm, and profanations have seemed cheap to me when
compared to the power of Evil that is within every man’s experience” (38).</p>
          <p>The other type of literature is more difficult to name but can be described as
“anthropocentric,” i.e., based not so much on the idea of man as the measure of all things, but on man as
a possible hope for all things. The difference between these two statements measures the gap separating the
old version of Greek and Roman humanism (no longer possible in the light of human past), and a new mutation of
humanist lore grounded in a careful and tending attitude towards human future. This millenarian thread in the
weave of culture is what links all the diverse writers Milosz presents in <hi rend="i">The Land of Ulro.</hi>
Of Gombrowicz he says that he staked his future “on the next spin of the wheel, on mankind’s future
course” (23). The reading of Dostoyevsky hinges upon a note from his journals maintaining that “All
depends on the next century” and a powerful eschatological belief in a perfect, final harmony “after
civilization” (54). Oscar Milosz, a hermetic “French poet born a subject of the tsarist Empire,
one-quarter Italian on his grandmother’s side . . . half Jewish on his mother’s . . .” (75), shared with
Dostoyevsky and Gombrowicz a profound rebellion against the ages of “wholesale trivialization” (206) and
was right, according to his nephew writing <hi rend="i">The Land of Ulro</hi>, “not to expect anything of
his contemporaries or of their sons” (206), and to look in his cabalistic meditations, in the last decade of
his life, for the regenerated man of the future. It is this hope that is the mode of the future because the
anthropocentric vision of philosophy that pumps the blood into Milosz’s book is dominated by the
Swedenborgian principle “that Heaven, the sum of myriads of personal heaven-projections, is Man-shaped”
(145), and the evolution of man’s religious sentiments seems to coincide with that of Dostoyevsky’s: from
man-God to God-man (54).</p>
          <p>Still the adjective “Manichaean” makes its appearance far too frequently in this book to be
incidental. Man is not only a domain of hope but also of despair torn schizophrenically between his angelic
and satanic elements. It is at that moment when Nature creeps back into Milosz’s literary and philosophical
readings: his argument against the “dark” writing is founded not only upon the “cheapness” of its
effects but, first of all, upon the fact that “it comes <hi rend="i">naturally</hi>, in a way, to a part of
the human spirit I regard as inferior” (my emphasis, 244). Despair and blasphemy are then cheap, easy, and
natural while hope and future, the future of the new man, are “artificial,” difficult, and painstaking, in
a word—aesthetic. We can see now that in Milosz’s universe, as in Blake’s, there is an immediate link
between future, hope, and art on the one hand, and the chance for overcoming the crisis which started some
time in the eighteenth century on the other.</p>
          <p>What is at stake in Milosz’s interpretation of the crisis is precisely the future of man. To
the humble question of the amazed and depressed reader, “What does it all mean?” the last chapter of the
book offers this straightforward answer:
<pb id="p21-163" n="163"/>
	<q>
This much can be said: that Blake’s land of Ulro is not a fantasy if we ourselves have been there; that
since the eighteenth century something, call it by whatever name one will, has been gaining ground, gathering
force. And all who have sought exit from the ‘wasteland’ . . . have been, in my opinion, justified in
their endeavor, more, are worthy of admiration, even if their efforts ended in failure and were bought at the
price of various ‘abnormalities.’ (269)
</q></p>
          <p>This long quotation shows that, for Milosz, Blake matters less as a master of words and more as a
poet-thinker who codes in his writings some basic existential elements which must be rediscovered by those who
are in search of exit from the predicament in which humanity has been locked for two centuries. Hence Milosz
reads Blake and his longer poems as a work of the author who “engaged the ‘scientific world-view’ in a
fundamental dialogue” (158). From Newton to Jacques Monod, one of whom Milosz quotes as the founding father
and the other as a prodigy of the land of Ulro, the crisis can be defined by two processes: one, a growing gap
between religion and science; two, a reflection of this situation in the inner structure of the human being
whose ability to believe and to know splits to form two separate channels of cognition. In Milosz’s
philosophy the crisis is summarily represented as a more and more thorough invasion of culture by Nature, as
the intrusion of what is easy and cheap upon what is difficult and aesthetic, of a sudden surfacing of the
base and inferior which unexpectedly masters the language of symbols. In this diagnosis there are hidden
skirmishes with Freudianism (“how could I make pretensions to ‘sincerity,’ I who go around in a corset,
all self-discipline on the inside?” 12), Beckett (“Man has been mired in Ulro by the successes of science
. . . but the ultimate proof of the crippling power of Ulro . . . lies in the passivity of those
vegeto-animals, those pale Elysian shades that are its literary ‘figures’ ” 244-45), but the main war is
waged against Nature. Hence it is Swedenborg and Blake who determine the main front line of the battle:
“Swedenborg was well aware that Nature, perceived as a system of mathematical relations, had begun to usurp
God in the minds of the educated” (140). Similarly, Blake “did not approve of Nature” (160), working
towards the future transfiguration of man who would be in a position to save Nature from suffering. Blake fits
then the Manichaean pattern of Milosz’s philosophy in that in his own thinking Blake emphasized the
antagonisms of double nature (the Outward and the Inward Eye), and good God and the monstrous miscreator of
the universe (Urizen as Blake’s reading of the Valentinian Achamoth, the monstrous offspring who, expelled
from the pleroma, became the ultimate origin of the created world).</p>
          <p>In the first part of his diagnosis of the modern crisis of thought Milosz retraces familiar
Eliotic paths: T. S. Eliot’s “dissociation of sensibility” located in the seventeenth century is moved a
hundred years later and redressed as a conflict of science and faith. But the remedy offered by Milosz does
not come from Eliot’s Pharmacy; it is a result of his life-long studies of philosophy and literature as well
as his “leftist” sympathies. Milosz needs the tradition of Swedenborg, Blake, and Oscar Milosz to
demonstrate that the way out of the dilemma is in a reformed notion of science, in making the scientific
compatible with the poetic. It is not a coincidence that the 60s, the most promising and most ungratified of
all the decades of the twentieth century, also appear in Milosz’s book. The remedy that he prescribes for
man, the dweller of the wasteland, is first of all the cure of vision by metaphor and symbol; Milosz, the old
professor from Berkeley, knows “that the battle was decided not by discourses and disquisitions, not by
faith or heresy, but by visions of the universe . . .” (224). Thus, one may repeat after Blake that “if
the doors of perception were cleansed . . . ,” but one should not stop short of going to the next stage of
Blake’s thought and say that the way towards this cleansing must involve imagination. The science which at
one moment in his meditation Milosz ascribes to Copernicus and Newton (226), evokes a vision of a static and
immovable universe where man is a homeless being. The sense of unification Swedenborg was talking about is
achieved at the price of man’s alienation, which is measured by man’s inability to situate himself. The
drama of the wasteland is a story of space that cannot shelter and protect, in the same way as the time of
Ulro is that of the archivistic past bereft of the future. Milosz’s Ulro is the land of Newtonian space
which, as Alexandre Koyré describes it, “broke down the barriers that separated the heavens and the earth .
. . and unified the universe. . . . It did this by substituting for our world of quality . . . the world of
quantity, of reified geometry, a world in which . . . there is no place for man.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Alexandre Koyré. <hi rend="i">Newtonian Studies</hi> (Cambridge: Harvard
UP, 1965) 23.</note></p>
          <p>It is to the “visionary reformers of science, whether it be Goethe, Blake, or [Oscar] Milosz”
(240) that Milosz’s philosophy turns to in search of the exit. Characteristically enough, so that the spirit
of the 60s would never slip away from our reach, Einsteinian physics is also included among the poetic and
philosophical groping for the Way. Fritjof Capra has already shown that the Tao of physics is an important
path to get us out of the maze of the wasteland; hence Milosz is fully justified not only in reporting to us
Oscar Milosz’s enthusiasm for the physics of relativity but also in musing on how “humbly respectful” he
had been when he met Einstein
<pb id="p21-164" n="164"/>
at Princeton (226). Einstein liberates imagination, i.e., man is able again to think a meaningful topography,
a topography where the symbolic dimension gathers divers areas to form a significant image. This gathering,
itself symbolic in its etymology (<hi rend="i">symbolein</hi> means “to grow together”)—let us note
parenthetically that here we have one of very infrequent moments in Milosz’s thought where it gets close to
the philosophy of Martin Heidegger—brings about a true unification. Not the one when Nature usurps the place
of the sacred, but the unification which is actualized in response to the most basic human need: the
compulsion to situate all things. This argumentation points at two facts: first, that the land of Ulro is a
territory that cannot be mapped and where things are scattered in a chaotic way (very much like the map of the
world from Lewis Carroll’s <hi rend="i">The Hunting of the Snark</hi> which consists of “a perfect and
absolute blank”); if so, then there can be no more pressing task than organizing space, not in the static
manner of science but in the active way of imagination. Both in Oscar Milosz and in Blake, the author of 
<hi rend="i">The Land of Ulro</hi> is looking for the indications that would bring us closer to imagination, i.e.,
to reshaping and restructuring the paradigm of our thinking, since imagination is treated not “as something
incidental to sensory perception but as its prime condition” (200).</p>
          <p>We have seen so far that in the perspective of Milosz’s book Blake matters as one of a few
visionary scientists who dared to undermine the dominating image of the world, a philosopher of the future
transfiguration of man and an organizer of symbolic space. We ought not to forget, however, that Blake is not
the main figure of the book; this place having been reserved for Milosz’s uncle and Parisian mentor Oscar
Milosz. We are justified then in our asking about the role of Blake in a carefully cast drama of the two
centuries of Western intellect that Milosz sketches in <hi rend="i">The Land of Ulro.</hi> For Milosz, Blake
is one of the key figures of European culture not so much for what his poetry can offer as it calls for an
ultimate effort of interpretation and undivided attention (“. . . what sort of poet is Blake if not even a
five-hundred page glossary of his symbols . . . is adequate to elucidate the esoterica in his 
<hi rend="i">Prophetic Books</hi>, paintings and engravings?” 32), but for what Blake’s reading can contribute
to the understanding of other texts and other writers. Blake’s texts seem to be, for Milosz, one of the few
master texts of culture indispensible to anyone who wishes to respond to the primal urge to “situate
things.” Blake’s defense of “Minute Particulars” against violent assaults of the Universal comes to
Milosz’s assistance during his wrestling with Gombrowicz. The problem of Gombrowicz’s writing—to what
extent a human individual can be saved or made compatible with the ever growing pressure of the
general—seems to refer not only to this Polish émigré writer. Throughout <hi rend="i">The Land of
Ulro</hi> Milosz repeatedly asserts that he wants “to ensure that his words correspond to reality” (245),
to say “something about matters I regard as urgent” (187), thus combining the aesthetic with the
ontological bias. Common mistakes, the tyrannies of words, are as a matter of fact only failed ontologies. If
Gombrowicz overcomes the restraints of traditional humanism and philosophical subject-object division by
questioning the independence of the individual, by removing the ego to the conceptual background and placing
in the foreground the undefinable and untraceable pattern of relationships between individuals and groups, if
Gombrowicz—like so many other modern writers—was advising humanity not to say “I assume” but rather
“it is assumed by/for me” (42), if then we live—as Heidegger puts it concisely—in the epoch of the end
of humanism, it is Blake who brings back, through his defense of the “Minute Particular,” ethical security
according to which an individual can still be made responsible for his deeds.</p>
          <p>To protect “Minute Particulars” against the assaults of the Universal is to defend man who
situates things in the space of symbols. As in Gombrowicz’s space of endless reproductions of ritualistic
gestures, so in the cosmic abysses of the longer poems a complicated system of mythology is woven to make a
protective veil against the brutality of the non-symbolic mass. “First there was Homo sapiens, later Homo
faber and above all, in our time, Homo ritualis” (44)—in this somewhat Yeatsian passage Milosz reveals
another Blake who looks for the way out from the wasteland through symbols and rituals of mythology no longer
cheap and easy but difficult, dramatic, and individual.</p>
          <p>At this point there seems to lie the existentialist connection of Blake’s thought which Milosz,
however, does not pursue—a decision hardly surprising in the light of his hostility towards “dark”
literature. The paradox of faith, as described by Sören Kierkegaard in <hi rend="i">Fear and Trembling</hi>,
is anchored precisely in the act of resignation through which the individual becomes larger than the universal
but which defies even the aesthetic and expressive potential of tragedy by the power of difficulty, distress,
and dread. Blake’s taking up philosophical arms in defense of “Minute Particulars” is then an act of
viewing religion not as an institutionalized way of “saying things” but as a passion where man needs a
power larger than himself but through which man reasserts his individuality that dooms him to loneliness. What
Kierkegaard says of the man of faith can very well describe Blake’s position: “A man can become a tragic
hero by his own powers—but not a knight of faith. When a man enters upon a way . . . of the tragic
<pb id="p21-165" n="165"/>
hero, many will be able to give him counsel; to him who follows the narrow way of faith no one can give
counsel, him no one can understand. Faith is a miracle . . . for that in which all human life is unified is
passion, and religion is a passion.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34"
type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Sören Kierkegaard, <hi rend="i">Fear and Trembling and the Sickness unto
Death</hi>, trans. W. Lowrie (Garden City: Doubleday/ Anchor Books, 1954) 77.</note></p>
          <p>Through the effort towards mythological ritualization Blake becomes a particularly important
buffer zone against chaos in the time of the gradual fading of Christian symbols in the West. It is this
revitalization of Christianity that allows for a comparison between Blake and Dostoyevsky. What is at stake
here is something much more fundamental than a reading of <hi rend="i">The Brothers Karamazov</hi> through the
Blake tetrad (Fyodor—Tharmas, carnality; Dmitri—Luvah, passion; Ivan—Urizen, suffering intellect;
Alyosha—Urthona, imagination). For Milosz, <hi rend="i">The Brothers Karamazov</hi> is a part of the same
strategy with which intellect tries to replace the eighteenth-century God, Deus absconditus, the perfect
Clockmaker, by the God-man, God who is not “a mathematical diagram.” At one moment in his analysis Milosz
even risks a sociological hypothesis: the withdrawal of Christian myths leaves space for bizarre cults (“The
California of Far Eastern and satanic cults is an illustration of what happens when Christianity
‘abstains’ ” 186). The guess may be wrong, but it again opens the same “urgent” question about the
exit from the land of Ulro. If the exit is possible at all, it must be unconcealed through symbols and
imagination and not through the literalist vision of science. Through what Theodore Roszak calls the
“Rhapsodic Intellect” which is nothing else but the ability, to a large extent lost or to say the least
threatened through the withdrawal of Christian mythology, to view the world as a reflection of a higher
reality, a collection of symbols that tell us their drama which is, the sooner we realize it the better, the
drama of human condition. Blake is so precious to Milosz because nowhere else in the recent history of culture
do we find a more strenuous and heroic effort to bring home to man the truth of humanity as homo
symbolicus.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
