<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>21.4.goyder</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">The Origins of the William Blake Trust</title>
        <author n="Goyder">George Goyder</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1988</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1988</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">21.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">21</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Jackie Di Salvo</name>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>George Goyder</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Inge Jonsson</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Tadeusz Sławek</name>
              <name>Sheila A. Spector</name>
              <name>David H. Weinglass</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_21">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-21-4-0006">
        <pb id="p21-150" n="150"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">The Origins of the William Blake Trust</title>
          </head>
          <byline>by <docAuthor>George <name>Goyder</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>In Sir Geoffrey Keynes’s autobiography <hi rend="i">The Gates of Memory</hi>, the origins of
the William Blake Trust are ascribed to the year 1948 and the desire to make a worthy facsimile of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> This was not as it happens the beginning of the idea. More than two years earlier (1
November 1945) I drafted a letter to Dr. Thomas Jones asking that the Pilgrim Trust help in a project to
reproduce Blake’s engravings, paintings and prophetic books. As the text of the letter shows, our first
priority was to reproduce the <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> series of drawings, secondly the Bible illustrations in
tempera and watercolor, and thirdly, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Before mailing this letter I sent a draft to
Geoffrey which he returned with a few minor corrections. Dr. Jones replied asking for time to consider the
matter, so on 4 June 1947 I wrote again mentioning my previous letter and this time put forward 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> as our first priority as the unique copy of that book had meantime become available
for reproduction.</p>
          <p>The original objectives of the William Blake Trust were very broadly defined and at no time have
its aims been abandoned. It is more a case of the Trust using the technical expertise of Arnold Fawcus and his
Trianon Press to the best advantage. Now that the William Blake Trust has successfully completed the
long-awaited <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engravings in their several states it might be thought that the Trust has
fulfilled the task for which it was formed. This is not the case. Three of the four original aims of the Trust
remain uncompleted and some have not even been begun. There is work aplenty for the Trust still to do.</p>
        	<figure n="Goyder.letter.21.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="800" height="504">
          	<figTranscr>November 1st, 1945.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Dear Dr. Jones, <lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	You kindly sent me a copy of the Annual Report <lb/>
          	of the Pilgrim Trust. I was struck with the help you <lb/>
          	are giving to the encouragement of literature and am <lb/>
          	prompted by it to put a suggestion to you which has been <lb/>
          	in my mind for some time.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	William Blake is not only a great English poet but<lb/>
          	equally a great English painter - if not the greatest. <lb/>
          	His work is hardly known except to a small number of <lb/>
          	people. The reason is, I believe, partly that some of <lb/>
          	his best paintings are still in private hands such as <lb/>
          	those of Graham Robertson and Mrs. Stirling in this <lb/>
          	country, and Philip Hofer In America; partly because <lb/>
          	no adequate reproductions have been made. <lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	In 1935 {John Morgan} The Pierpont Morgan Library undertook the reproduction of<lb/>
          	the three known coloured copies of the Job, together with<lb/>
          	the original pencil sketches and the engravings. This <lb/>
          	magnificent production in six sections enabled the student <lb/>
          	to see Blake’s work in a form hardly distinguishable from <lb/>
          	the original works. I understand the price to the trade <lb/>
          	was 10 guineas a copy, and that the total expense of <lb/>
          	production was between £5,000. and £8,000. 300 copies <lb/>
          	were sold in America and 200 in England. By now the<lb/>
          	original outlay should have been recovered. If you have <lb/>
          	not seen the Job I would like to show you a set next time <lb/>
          	you are in London. Geoffrey Keynes, who is the leading <lb/>
          	authority on Blake, wrote the introduction, and in every <lb/>
          	way the work is superb. We owe a great deal to {Pierpont}<lb/>
          	The Morgan Library for this enterprise.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	My suggestion is that to encourage artists in this <lb/>
          	country and U.S.A. to study Blake (I believe there is no <lb/>
          	more inspiring master than Blake - he literally teems with<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	P.T.O.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	- 2 -<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	inspiration), plans should now be made for reproducing <lb/>
          	the other great Blake series in the same way as was done <lb/>
          	for the Book of Job by The Morgan Library and by the National Art<lb/>
          	Collections Fund for the Dante drawings.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	My first priority is to reproduce the Milton series<lb/>
          	Some of these are in Boston, some in the Huntington<lb/>
          	Library, and some at Cambridge. The series include<lb/>
          	Paradise Lost and Regained, L’Allegro and Il Penseroso, <lb/>
          	The Nativity, and Comus. It will be necessary to obtain <lb/>
          	the loan of the American originals and this will take <lb/>
          	time; hence the need to start now.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	The second great work cycle never hitherto reproduced <lb/>
          	is the series of Biblical temperas illustrating <lb/>
          	the Life of Our Lord. All the paintings need putting <lb/>
          	together and reproducing in fine collotype, as used for <lb/>
          	the Job. When they are seen together the world may <lb/>
          	appreciate for the first time the glorious beauty and <lb/>
          	religious creativeness of this wonderful artist. You <lb/>
          	probably know some of Blake’s paintings of Christ’s Life, <lb/>
          	such as the Infant John riding on the Lamb. No more <lb/>
          	tender presentation of the God-head - Divine Humanity and <lb/>
          	Human Divinity - can be imagined. There is nothing else <lb/>
          	I know of in Western art since the Reformation which <lb/>
          	conveys such deep religious feeling in form, colour and <lb/>
          	composition, as do these temperas, some of the finest of <lb/>
          	which are still in private collections. Ruthven Todd’s<lb/>
          	catalogue {should} will help in tracing these.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Thirdly, there is the magnificent coloured Jerusalem<lb/>
          	in the possession of Mrs. Stirling. Joseph Wickstead is <lb/>
          	still available to write the introduction for this book, <lb/>
          	but he is getting on in years and there is no young Blake <lb/>
          	scholar with the same understanding and learning. <lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Then there are the eighteen paintings illustrating <lb/>
          	Bunyan’s Pilgrim’s Progress which the late Lord Crewe sold recently to America.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	P.T.O.</figTranscr>
          </figure>
          <pb id="p21-151" n="151"/>
        	<figure n="Goyder.letter.p3.21.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="790">
          	<figTranscr>- 3 -<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	They have been poorly reproduced in the United States, <lb/>
          	but the book is unobtainable in England.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	It may be many months before Emery Walker &amp; Co.<lb/>
          	can re-assemble their expert men, but it is not too early<lb/>
          	to start planning the undertaking.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Geoffrey Keynes tells me he would give all help<lb/>
          	possible in the project. I imagine the cost would be<lb/>
          	twice or three times as great as before the war. The <lb/>
          	outlay for the Milton series might, therefore, be £10,000<lb/>
          	to £15,000. A {similar} smaller figure would cover the Biblical<lb/>
          	series. These are outside figures. As I understand<lb/>
          	{J.P.} The Morgan Library recovered the whole of the outlay for the<lb/>
          	Job, the question for the Pilgrim Trust should be one of<lb/>
          	outlay rather than of expenditure. I am very anxious to<lb/>
          	interest you in the project, for I know of nothing else<lb/>
          	better calculated to inspire the present generation of <lb/>
          	artists and to link England and U.S.A. in creative amity<lb/>
          	than a noble and really worthy presentation of Blake’s <lb/>
          	work to the public here and in America for the first time.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	I should like to talk further with you about this <lb/>
          	together with Geoffrey Keynes, and will be grateful if you <lb/>
          	will let me know when you are coming to London.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Sincerely yours,<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Dr. Tom Jones,<lb/>
          	The Pilgrim Trust,<lb/>
          	Harlech,<lb/>
          	N. Wales.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	GAG:MB</figTranscr>
          </figure>
        	<figure n="Manuscript.letter.21.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="818">
          	<figTranscr>11 ARKWRIGHT ROAD, HAMPSTEAD, LONDON N.W.3<lb/>
          	HAMPSTEAD 3923<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	2 Nov 1945<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	My dear George,<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	I return your draft with some suggested<lb/>
          	alterations. I am not sure about<lb/>
          	the “first priority.” It would be much<lb/>
          	easier to get hold of the Jerusalem<lb/>
          	than any of the others.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Yesterday I secured my sixth<lb/>
          	copy of Remember Me! It is, of course,<lb/>
          	different from the others<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	I went to an interesting sale of pictures<lb/>
          	at Christie’s today. You could have<lb/>
          	people your walls with handsom ancestors,<lb/>
          	flower pieces, bird pieces, &amp;c. (mostly from<lb/>
          	Whaddon Hall) for the price of two M.S.S.<lb/>
          	(or one)<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Your affectionate<lb/>
          	Geoffrey</figTranscr>
          </figure>
        	<figure n="PilgrimTrust.letter.21.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="848">
          	<figTranscr>THE PILGRIM TRUST<lb/>
          	FOUNDER: EDWARD S. HARKNESS<lb/>
          	1 LOWTHER GARDENS<lb/>
          	EXHIBITION ROA, LONDON, S.W. 7<lb/>
          	TELEPHONE: KENSINGTON 3665<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	CHAIRMAN: RT. HON. LORD MACMILLAN, G.C.V.O.<lb/>
          	SECRETARY: THE HON. J. F. A. BROWNE<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	8th November 1945<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Dear Goyder,<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	I have read with much interest<lb/>
          	your letter about the Blake drawings,<lb/>
          	and fully share your sense of their <lb/>
          	great importance in the art life of<lb/>
          	this country.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	The Trust is at the present<lb/>
          	moment deeply committed to the publication<lb/>
          	of several very expensive works.<lb/>
          	You may have seen the first volume of <lb/>
          	MEDIEVAL WALL PAINTING; it is only<lb/>
          	the first of several volumes. Then<lb/>
          	we have RECORDING BRITAIN on the stocks,<lb/>
          	and RECORDING SCOTLAND to follow. The<lb/>
          	range of present costs is very high,<lb/>
          	and that is another reason why we should<lb/>
          	delay for a year or two sounding the<lb/>
          	Trustees on a project of this kind.<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Yours sincerely,<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	Thomas Jones<lb/>
          	<lb/>
          	George Goyder, Esq.</figTranscr>
          </figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
