<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>22.1.bennett</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Raymond Lister, The Paintings of Samuel Palmer; 
Raymond Lister, The Paintings of William Blake</title>
        <author n="Bennett">Shelley M. Bennett</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1988</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1988</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">22.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Shelley M. Bennett</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Aethelred Eldridge</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
              <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_22">
    <body>
      <pb id="p22-20" n="20"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-22-1-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Raymond Lister. <hi rend="i">The Paintings of Samuel Palmer.</hi> Cambridge:
Cambridge University Press, 1985. 178 pp. $29.95.</title>
            <title type="main">Raymond Lister. <hi rend="i">The Paintings of William Blake.</hi> Cambridge:
Cambridge University Press, 1986. 176 pp. $29.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Shelley M. <name>Bennett</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Raymond Lister has contributed two new publications to the rich body of works on Blake and his
followers. <hi rend="i">The Paintings of Samuel Palmer</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Paintings of William
Blake</hi> are attractive picture books directed to the general public. Each comprises a short introduction on
the life of the artist, followed by seventy-five color plates arranged in a chronological sequence. The plates
are accompanied by a brief commentary. Although there are no footnotes, a selected bibliography is included
for further suggested reading.</p>
          <p>These broad surveys span the entire artistic careers of Palmer and Blake. In the case of Palmer,
this is particularly useful. By devoting more coverage than usual to his prosaic middle years, Lister corrects
an imbalance that exists in most Palmer literature. Lister also covers the wide variety of media utilized by
these two artists. Since this includes drawings and prints, in addition to paintings, the titles of both works
are misleading. Perhaps “art works” would be more indicative of the myriad material covered in each
book.</p>
          <p>The brief introductions encapsulate in a very readable manner a good deal of biographical
information. In his commentary on the color plates, Lister introduces the reader to the diverse literary,
musical, and artistic references that enrich the works of both artists. Although attuned to a general
audience, his discussion of Blake’s works also refers to various interpretations which prevail in current
scholarship. As he justly notes in his remarks on Blake’s “The Dance of Albion” (pl. 10), “Perhaps all
these readings are valid, for one of the sources of Blake’s strength is the multiplicity of meaning in much
of his work.” Without footnotes, there is, however, no way for the uninitiated to tell what is borrowed from
other sources and what is a fresh interpretation.</p>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <p>On the whole, Lister has done a fine job of presenting the richly nuanced art of both men in a
manner which will be easily accessible to the general reader. This broad approach has distorted the material
in some instances. In the introduction, for example, there is too much emphasis on biographical anecdote,
rather than the intellectual and artistic content of Blake’s and Palmer’s work.</p>
          <p>The format also has necessitated an overly simplistic explanation of some aspects of their work,
in particular the social side. Indeed, Lister’s explanation of Palmer’s scenes of labor, such as “The
Harvest Moon” (pl. 25), tell us more about his own nostalgic projections than about Palmer’s intent:
“One can imagine the constant talk, the satisfaction of working in a group, and the well-earned simple but
gratifying meal during the afternoon, washed down by cider; and at the end of it all the jollity and feasting
of harvest home.”</p>
          <p>The restricted format also results in some strange bedfellows. For example in his remarks on
Palmer’s “A Hilly Scene” (pl. 10), Lister has thrown together, willy-nilly, allusions to Gothic
architecture, illuminated manuscripts, Milton, Schubert, and Keats within a few brief sentences. The
discussion of Palmer’s “The Sleeping Shepherd” (pl. 32), piles up references to Graeco-Roman sculpture,
a play by John Fletcher, nocturnes by Chopin and John Field, and a passage by Walter Pater.</p>
          <pb id="p22-21" n="21"/>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <p>For the most part, Lister is careful to note related works (and their location), but there are
some inconsistencies in his procedure. In a few cases, he fails to cite closely allied studies. For example,
in his discussion of Blake’s “Pestilence” (pl. 2), he refers to the versions of this composition in
Steigal Fine Art at Edinburgh, the City of Bristol Museum and Art Gallery, the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston,
and an American private collection, but no mention is made of the pencil drawing of “Pestilence” in the
Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery (published in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (winter 1984-85):
132-40).</p>
          <p>Although adept, Lister’s discussion of Palmer’s and Blake’s techniques is limited by the
restrictions imposed by the audience to which it is directed. Some of the basic data necessary for a scholarly
reading is not included. For instance, he does not identify the state of the print he reproduces in Palmer’s
“The Lonely Tower” (pl. 70), although he emphasizes the difference in quality between earlier and later
impressions. He could have supplied this information by citing the entries in his own publication, 
<hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer and his Etchings.</hi> The addition of Butlin’s catalogue numbers would also make
Lister’s Blake book of greater use to the scholar.</p>
          <p>Since these are picture books, they rely primarily on the quality of the copious color
reproductions. With few exceptions, the color is good, ensuring the popular success of both publications.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
