<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>22.1.wittreich</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Morton D. Paley, The Apocalyptic Sublime</title>
        <author n="Wittreich">Joseph Wittreich</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1988</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1988</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">22.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Shelley M. Bennett</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Aethelred Eldridge</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
              <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_22">
    <body>
	<pb id="p22-21" n="21"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-22-1-0008">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Morton D. Paley. <hi rend="i">The Apocalyptic Sublime.</hi> New Haven and
London: Yale University Press, 1986. xii + 196 pp.; illus. $35.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Joseph</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Wittreich</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>“Pieces of art, in the frame of Prophecy”: thus, in the late seventeenth century Thomas
Beverley<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">1</ref> anticipates the
phenomenon—the translation of the Apocalypse into paintings—that is nominally the subject of Morton
Paley’s fine book. And I say <hi rend="i">nominally</hi> because <hi rend="i">The Apocalyptic Sublime</hi>,
like any book of first importance, has a reach that exceeds the grasp of its seven chapters and three
appendices. Indeed, encoded within the very organization of the book—its threefold structures, its septenary
design—is an ambition (perhaps too modestly expressed) to redefine romanticism, at least in England, in
terms of a preoccupation with the apocalyptic myth. Shared by poets and painters alike, this preoccupation,
when fully understood, is with history (the creation of a new history) and with poetics (the formation of a
new aesthetics). Paley’s concern, then, is with the poetry of history as it registers itself in the history
of painting. That concern, in turn, is centered in romanticism, which is a breakthrough—a revolution—in
both ideology and aesthetics but which, paradoxically, is rooted in the past. Paley’s book (appropriately
given the occasion that inspired it) is a necessary supplement to Northrop Frye’s <hi rend="i">A Study of
English Romanticism</hi> (1968) and M. H. Abrams’ <hi rend="i">Natural Supernaturalism</hi> (1971). It
extends the conclusions of both these books into another art form, another dimension of romantic culture.
<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Thomas Beverley, <hi rend="i">The Great Charter for the Interpretation of
All Prophecy of Scripture, and of the Times Defined by It</hi> (London, 1694) 34.</note></p>
          <p>The alliance of word and picture in the last of the scriptural books, together with the question
of which is to be privileged, is the subject of an exchange between Richard Haydock and Joseph Mede; and it is
an alliance foregrounded, a question centered, through the juxta-position of Haydock’s and Mede’s opinions
within the prefatory matter that accompanies most editions of Mede’s highly influential, twice translated,
and often reprinted <hi rend="i">Clavis Apocalyptica.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n10" type="note">2</ref> Mede marks a turning point in the history of apocalyptic interpretation,
making of it a science, and part of that science involves implicating the Apocalypse in the other arts:
painting, drama, architecture, and even music. Mede’s followers were legion in the eighteenth and nineteenth
centuries, and what they stressed about St. John’s apocalyptic theater (indeed, what is still stressed about
that theater today) is that this intricately designed and structured edifice, this mental theater and sacred
drama, is filled with “shifting scenes” making up the landscapes of human
<pb id="p22-22" n="22"/>
<figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
life within a panorama of human history—with “pictures on the mind,” boldly colored, “the strongest
paintings” of which any artist is capable.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">3</ref> If in our own century we read about the Apocalypse as a “great picture” or “a
gorgeous picture-book” or, more extravagantly, as “a book of spiritual cartoons,” “a magnificent
triptych,” “A Nine-Room Picture Gallery . . . Revelation through Pictures,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">4</ref> it is probably owing (at least in part) to the phenomenon
Paley describes, which itself may have taken inspiration, if not direction, from Revelation commentary
contemporaneous with it. Following the lead of William Paulet Carey, Paley cites Moses Lowman’s frequently
reprinted commentary (1737) as one possible point of reference. <note id="n10"><hi rend="s">2</hi> See Joseph
Wittreich, “The Apocalypse: A Bibliography,” in <hi rend="i">The Apocalypse in English Renaissance Thought
and Literature</hi>, ed. C. A. Patrides and Joseph Wittreich (Cornell UP: Ithaca, N.Y., 1984) 393,
#497.</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">3</hi> See, e.g., Samuel Langdon, <hi rend="i">Observations on the Revelation of
Jesus Christ to St. John</hi> (Worchester, Mass., 1791) 18, 21, 27, 29-30.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See, respectively, Henry Barclay Swete, <hi rend="i">The Apocalypse of St.
John</hi>, 2nd ed. (New York and London, 1907) cxxxii; Roy Summers, <hi rend="i">Worthy Is the Lamb: An
Interpretation of Revelation</hi> (Nashville, 1951) 60; Hanns Lilje, <hi rend="i">The Last Book of the Bible:
The Meaning of the Revelation</hi>, trans. Olive Wyon (Philadelphia, 1957) 25; Edwin A. Schick, <hi rend="i">A
Revelation: The Last Book of the Bible</hi> (Philadelphia, 1977) 9, 18.</note></p>
          <p>Equally if not more relevant are those late eighteenth and early nineteenth-century commentators
who speak repeatedly, insistently of the Book of Revelation in terms of “writing in picture” and symbol or
of “visionary scenes” emblematizing the current time of trial and revolution; of Revelation as
“Prophetical picture[s]” and “hieroglyphical prophecy.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n13" type="note">5</ref> And more pertinent still, given the inflection Paley places on “the
apocalyptic sublime,” are those like the anonymous commentator of 1790 who emphasize the “sublimity” of
the Apocalypse, both in matter and language; or like Joseph Galloway (1802) who proclaims in a series of
comparative statements that there is nothing in Homer, Virgil, or Milton “equal to it in . . . sublimity”;
or like Edward Irving (1831) who, in this book “wrought into a beautiful mosaic,” discovers the perfect
vehicle “for the embodying of sublime ideas.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">6</ref> Where the commentator Samuel Hallifax discerns “the plastic hand of the Almighty
Architect,” “a sublime geometry,” “an optical experiment,” the artist Henry Fuseli discovers the
model for the ultimate in sublime art and in that model beholds a sky split open by revelation.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">7</ref> What Revelation meant as a model is perhaps
best summarized by Robert Lowth and James Bicheno for whom, on the one hand, St. John is “endued with a
sublimer genius” than any of the other prophets and, on the other hand, his whole prophecy, imbued with that
sublimity, “may be considered as a number of scenic pictures,” one of them being “a miniature picture of
. . . history” and the others “the same picture variegated . . . on a larger scale.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">8</ref> As a picture book, then, the Apocalypse is
filled with hieroglyphics, emblems, symbols; and in its natural landscape are to be found the types and signs
of history as it was unfolding during the years of the French Revolution which eventually came to be regarded
as an objective correlative for the drama then playing itself out in the mind of mankind. And so it must have
seemed to Blake who, under the influence of Emanuel Swedenborg, probably conceived of Revelation’s heavenly
and infernal landscapes as exteriorizations of forms seated within. “The Form of Heaven is like the Form of
the Human Mind,” according to Swedenborg, a form in process, gradually perfecting itself: “the Mind is the
smallest Image of that Form.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">9</ref>
Swedenborg’s formulation affords the reminder that the Apocalypse, so often regarded as recording the
movements of history, also records movements of mind, motions of thought. <note id="n13"><hi rend="s">5</hi>
See, respectively, Richard Hurd, <hi rend="i">An Introduction to the Study of the Prophecies</hi> (London,
1772) 288; anon., <hi rend="i">A Key to the Mystery of the Revelation</hi> (London, 1785) 96; Edward King, 
<hi rend="i">A Supplement to the Remarks on the Signs of the Times</hi> (London, 1799) 27; William Ettrick, 
<hi rend="i">The Season and Time: or, An Exposition of the Prophecies</hi> (London, 1816) 321.</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">6</hi> See, respectively, anon. <hi rend="i">A Paraphrase, Notes, and
Observations, upon the Revelation of St. John</hi> (London, 1790) 89; Joseph Galloway, <hi rend="i">Brief
Commentaries upon Such Parts of the Revelation and Other Prophecies as Immediately Refer to the Present
Times</hi>, 2 vols. (1802; rpt. Trenton, 1809) 277; Edward Irving, <hi rend="i">Exposition of the Book of
Revelation, in a Series of Lectures</hi>, 4 vols. (London, 1831) 1: 52, 53.</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">7</hi> See both Samuel Hallifax, <hi rend="i">Twelve Sermons on the
Prophecies</hi> (London, 1776) 7, 227, 261, and Henry Fuseli, “Lecture II,” in <hi rend="i">The Life and
Writings of Henry Fuseli</hi>, ed. John Knowles (3 vols.; London, 1831) II: 75.</note>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">8</hi> See both Robert Lowth, <hi rend="i">Lectures on the Sacred Poetry of the
Hebrews</hi>, 2nd ed., trans. G. Gregory (Boston, 1815) 293, and James Bicheno, <hi rend="i">The Signs of the
Times; or the Dark Prophecies of Scripture Illustrated by the Application of Present Important Events</hi>
(West Springfield, Mass., 1796) 10.</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Emanuel Swedenborg, <hi rend="i">A Treatise Concerning the Last Judgment,
and the Destruction of Babylon</hi> (London, 1788) 16, 17; see also 19.</note></p>
          <p>Predictably, Blake is the subject of the keystone chapter in Paley’s book. The chapters
preceding this crucial fourth one reveal affinities, establish indebtedness; those following it acknowledge
analogies with Blake’s apocalyptic art, even sometimes measure its possible influence. The imaginary
landscapes of Benjamin West (chapter 2) and Philippe Jacques de Loutherbourg (chapter 3), the historical
landscapes of J. M. W. Turner (chapter 5) and naturalistic ones of John Martin (chapter 6), the personalizing
as well as politicizing of the Apocalypse in the paintings of Samuel Coleman and Francis Danby—all find
their counterparts in Blake’s art as do the various forms and counterforms of the apocalyptic sublime: the
terrible sublime, the material sublime, the retrograde apocalypse, and the apocalyptic grotesque. If Nicolas
Poussin (<hi rend="i">The Deluge</hi>) provides a prototype of the “sublime painting” (8) and John
Hamilton Mortimer (<hi rend="i">Death as a Pale Horse</hi>) affords “the first example of the apocalyptic
sublime” (18), Blake is the quintessential
<pb id="p22-23" n="23"/>
artist of the apocalyptic sublime. If it can be claimed for West that he establishes this category of painting
and for de Loutherbourg that he explores the subtleties of this new genre, Blake must be credited as the
artist who, no less attentive to iconographic detail and pictorial devices, to the fine particularities of the
Revelation aesthetic, in his poetry and painting alike grasps and appropriates to both the stupendous
architectural design of the Apocalypse, its dramatic and theatrical potential, its multiple planes of
activity, the synchronism and simultaneum of its structure, along with its elaborate optics, its intricate and
often illusionary perspectivism, its grammar of allusion and quotation within a syntax of typology, its system
of contextualizations, the significance of its obscurities and silences—all within a poetics of the glance
and an aesthetics of disclosure. If here Blake seems a throwback to West and de Loutherbourg, there he seems
to look ahead to Turner and Martin, Coleman and Danby.</p>
          <p>It is especially with these chapters devoted to later artists that the one on Blake can be
meaningfully, pointedly cross-referenced. Following the lead of Ronald Paulson, for example, Paley remarks of
Turner’s <hi rend="i">St. Michael’s Mount</hi> that the artist may have identified himself not with the
angel but with the visionary who sees and records the scene (121). Or later, commenting on Martin’s 
<hi rend="i">The Opening of the Seventh Seal</hi>, Paley allows that if, in one sense, “the viewer sees from
John’s perspective . . . . In another sense, the tiny, astonished observer is part of what the viewer sees,
and so a double perspective is established, one inside and the other outside the picture” (148). This double
perspectivism, the binocular vision accompanying it, the multiplying perspectives it anticipates, have an
obvious bearing on Blake’s own apocalyptic designs, very notably <hi rend="i">The Angel of Revelation</hi>
(see 86), but also on the designs arrayed around the texts of both <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>—or even around the texts of other poets (the last design in Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> series is a good example). But more, it is in these moments (<hi rend="i">The
Apocalyptic Sublime</hi> is strewn with them) that critical discourse shows painterly procedures intersecting
with hermeneutical tenets. According to Charles Daubuz, John as artist and seer assumes a role in the
apocalyptic drama (rather as Blake does in a number of the illuminations for <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>):
<q>
. . . this Practice may be illustrated by the like of the Dramatick Poets in the old Comedy, who used to mix
the Representation with the Action, and the Spectators with the <hi rend="i">Drama</hi> itself; and so might
commit Anachronisms, which would seem intolerable, were they not excused by this Reason, that no man can be
deceiv’d thereby; and that this Method heightens the Liveliness of the <hi rend="i">Drama.</hi> So St. 
<hi rend="i">John</hi> is spoken to as an Apostle, and Spectator of Vision, and also farther yet as a
Representative, and one that bears a Part in this Dramatic Vision.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n18" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Charles Daubuz, <hi rend="i">A Perpetual Commentary on the Revelation of
St. John</hi> (London, 1730) 509-10.</note></q>
St. John’s apocalyptic theater affords the apt analogy for Blake’s visionary forms dramatic; the program
notes provided by Revelation’s commentators, in turn, are the best glosses we have on Blake’s poetics of
perspectivism, not to mention his theory of the poet’s secretaryship. When Blake proclaims himself to be
none other than secretary to the great artists who dwell in eternity he apparently means to align himself with
John of Patmos who was commonly regarded as “the Secretary of Christ.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19" type="note">11</ref> It is unremarkable that the patron saint of artists should
author the book constituting a code for their art. <note id="n19"><hi rend="s">11</hi> See, e.g., Richard
Capel, <hi rend="i">Capel’s Remains</hi> (London, 1658) 25.</note></p>
          <p>Particularly (but by no means only) in the example of Blake, we find the romantic artist aligning
himself with a theory of the imagination—and a hermeneutic situated in the imagination—such as is set
forth by East Apthorp:
<q>
Critical interpretation consists, not merely in weighing the moment of words, but in seizing the genius and
spirit of composition. In <hi rend="i">sacred</hi> composition especially, a rigid adherence to the diction
and letter would prevent the discovery of truth, conveyed from and to the imagination . . . . Nothing is more
adverse to the prophetic spirit, than a cold and barren fancy, with a rigid and abstracted judgment, and a
will fixed in a contrary system. The requisites which feel and admit this evidence, are those which are most
perfective of the human mind: a memory stored with history, manners, and opinions; a fancy replete with ideal
images and poetical combinations; a judgment serene and flexible . . . .<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">12</hi> East Apthorp, <hi rend="i">Discourses on Prophecy</hi>, 2 vols. (London,
1786) I: 10-11.</note></q>
Not just large conceptions but even such particularities as coloration, to which Paley is keenly attentive,
find their counterpart in principles formulated by Revelation’s commentators. Thus Apthorp also remarks:
“When this mingled mass of poetic colours is seen unmethodized, and in its native form; its lustre is
properly Divine; that is, Prophetic. To appear such, it needs only to be distributed into its proper
arrangement, whose Lights and Shades will form a Prophetic Picture, or Succession of Pictures, comprehending
the whole history of a Character and Action.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21"
type="note">13</ref> Color contrasts and shading, light perspectives and rainbows, blacks, whites, and regions
of shadow—all are aspects of the tradition Paley describes. Moreover, for most of the artists who figure in
<hi rend="i">The Apocalyptic Sublime</hi>, the Book of Revelation led not only, and not even principally, into
isolated compositions but instead into elaborate sequences of designs: in the case of West, into a series of
designs for William Beckford as well as an intended series in which pictures with “apocalyptic content would
have appeared as the culmination of the Progress of Revealed Religion” (38); in the instance of Blake, into
“a group of powerful water colors illustrating Revelation itself” (74), as well as four designs for Thomas
Butts of which “we may assume that in Blake’s mind they constituted a series” (87). Indeed,
<pb id="p22-24" n="24"/>
as John E. Grant has proposed, perhaps all the Revelation designs by Blake may be viewed as the constituent
parts of an elaborately orchestrated whole. What is crucially significant about Paley’s book, in this
context, is that it isolates moments of intersection between painterly practices and hermeneutical theorizing
(Joseph Mede, Moses Lowman, Richard Hurd, Edward Irving), thus discovering a line of influence worth pursuing
and surely worthy of documentation. Yet Paley also comprehends that this line of connection extends beyond
aesthetics, encompassing matters of ideology as well. <note id="n21"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Apthorp,
328.</note></p>
          <p>Emerging out of, and about, a moment of crisis, the Apocalypse was now understood to be a book of
crises—private and public, inward and psychological no less than outward and historical. The Book of
Revelation was as much as sourcebook for apocalyptic glitz as for eschatological despair, as much a sponsor of
millenarian hopes as of cultural anxiety in this era of revolutions and of wars. If the apocalyptic myth is
the common property of romantic poets and painters, it is also a property often valued differently (by West
and Martin, let us say, or by Blake and Byron). In consequence, as some advance others move against the
apocalyptic myth: for every apocalypse, it seems, there is a counter-apocalypse; and for every vision of the
New Jerusalem, a parodic version of the deluge or the last man. The myth that Blake and Wordsworth in
different ways foster is one by which, again in different ways, Byron and Mary Shelley are frustrated. As some
move with others move across the grain of apocalypse. If, in one sense, the apocalypse is an aspect of the
romantic myth and a harbor for its ideology, it is, in another sense, a myth under siege, subjected to
interrogation, even inquisition—a myth in which romanticism finds its identity, but also the myth through
which romanticism eventually critiques itself. Romantic poets and painters, no less than Derrida, are able to
ask the tough questions: “What benefit? What bonus of seduction or intimidation? What social or political
advantage? Do they want to cause fear? Do they want to give pleasure? To whom and how? Do they want to
terrify? To blackmail? . . . . To lure into an outmatching in enjoyment? . . . . What effect do these noble .
. . prophets or eloquent visionaries want to produce? In view of what immediate or adjourned
benefit?”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">14</ref> Romanticism is forever
questioning the myths it seems most to court. <note id="n22"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Jacques Derrida, “Of an
Apocalyptic Tone Recently Adopted in Philosophy,” <hi rend="i">The Oxford Literary Review</hi> 6 (1984): 7,
23.</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Apocalyptic Sublime</hi> is a strong book with perhaps too strong a sense of an
ending. Apocalyptic art, “not long after 1848,” simply disappears by Paley’s account: “The apocalyptic
sublime had been a mode of central importance in its time, but that time . . . was ‘finished’ before the
end of the nineteenth century” (183). History may not repeat itself, but it does rhyme; and the history
Paley reports surely finds some rhyme, albeit slant rhyme, in the neo-romanticism of <hi rend="i">Apocalypse
Now</hi> or of Damon’s <hi rend="i">Peintures de L’Apocalypse</hi> (a gallery of nineteen apocalyptic
paintings). Indeed, the series of painterly translations that Paley reports and reproduces, represents and
documents, are, more than the beginning of something, but another instance of rhyme within history. As
Montague Rhodes James reminds us: in John’s presentation of his message “the seer has employed means
essentially pictorial; the book cannot be read without calling up to the mind’s eye a tremendous panorama of
images, and the temptation to translate these into visible forms was . . . inevitable.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">15</ref> Not the phenomenon of translation per se, but
notable, distinctive features of these romantic translations should now command our attention: the
personalizing and politicizing, the historicizing and secularizing of the apocalyptic myth, and the
inscription within apocalyptic poetry and painting of a critique of romanticism itself, its myths and
ideologies. As an affiliate of prophecy, the Apocalypse invites interpretation and is self-interpreting: it is
a system of interrogations that interrogates its own interrogations; it is a token of romantic culture—at
once a contemplation and a criticism of that culture. <note id="n23"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Montague Rhodes
James, <hi rend="i">The Trinity College Apocalypse</hi> (London, 1909) 1.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p22-25" n="25" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
