<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>22.1.mellor</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">William Blake and His Circle, A Symposium</title>
        <author n="Mellor">Anne K. Mellor</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1988</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1988</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">22.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Shelley M. Bennett</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Aethelred Eldridge</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
              <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_22">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-22-1-0008">
        <pb id="p22-29" n="29"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A Symposium on William Blake and His Circle held in conjunction with the
exhibition. William Blake and His Contemporaries and Followers: Selected Works from the Collection of Robert
N. Essick. The Huntington Library, Art Gallery, and Botanical Gardens, 29 and 30 January, 1988.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Report by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Anne K.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Mellor</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The Symposium on William Blake and His Circle was generously funded by the University of
California at Berkeley, Los Angeles, and Riverside, the California Institute of Technology, and the
Huntington. It presented five speakers, a banquet and a luncheon, and was attended by over 100 Blake
enthusiasts.</p>
          <p>Following an opening reception on Friday evening, 29 January, Martin Butlin of the Tate Gallery
spoke on “The Physicality of William Blake: the 1795 Colour Prints.” After detailing the dating problems
associated with the color prints, Butlin put forth the provocative suggestion that these prints were conceived
and executed as <hi rend="i">pairs</hi> and should be interpreted in these terms. Relying primarily on visual
similarities in compositional format, tonal harmonies, and iconographic motifs, Butlin suggested the following
pairs: <hi rend="i">The Creation of Adam</hi> and <hi rend="i">Satan Exulting over Eve</hi>; <hi rend="i">God
Judging Adam</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Good and Evil Angel Struggling for Possession of a Child</hi>; 
<hi rend="i">Newton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Nebuchadnezzar</hi>; <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Pity</hi>; <hi rend="i">Lamech</hi> and <hi rend="i">Ruth</hi>; and <hi rend="i">The House of
Death</hi> and <hi rend="i">Christ Appearing to the Apostles after the Resurrection.</hi> He concluded that
the meaning of these images may lie more in their purely visual relationships than others have thought.</p>
          <p>Aileen Ward of New York University led off the speakers on Saturday morning with a challenging
biographical account of Blake’s relationship with the Royal Academy of Art, “Blake and the Academy.”
Contesting previous beliefs, she argued that Blake’s interactions with the Academy were more positive, more
complex, and more sustained than has been thought. The outstanding student engraver of his year, Blake trained
to become a history painter and submitted entries to the annual Royal Academy exhibition for the six years
following his admission. On his deathbed, he was again preparing a history painting, the lost <hi rend="i">The
Last Judgment</hi>, for submission to the Academy. Ward effectively showed that Blake’s relationship with
the Academy was more supportive and far less hostile than previous biographers have assumed.</p>
          <p>Detlef W. Dörrbecker from the University of Trier then stunned the audience by announcing that
he has discovered four previously unrecorded copies of illuminated poems by Blake: a late “Songs of
Innocence,” a “Visions of the Daughters of Albion,” a “Song of Los”—all in the Bayerische
Staatsbibliothek in Munich—and a “Book of Urizen” in the Albertina in Vienna (see a forthcoming issue of
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> for Dörrbecker’s report on his findings). He then discussed in detail the Munich
“Song of Los,” a particularly luminous and clearly printed copy, judging from the slides presented, and
offered a fascinating interpretation of the frontispiece and final plate in the context of Herschel’s
astronomical discoveries of dead suns, sunspots, and cloud-covers over the suns in other galaxies.</p>
          <figure n="FrontispieceSongsOfExperience.22.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="545"></figure>
          <pb id="p22-30" n="30"/>
          <p>The discussion following these two insightful papers focused first on Blake’s partnership with
James Parker in their printselling (as well as engraving) shop, which Ward suggested lasted for five (rather
than one and a half) years and constituted Blake’s primary source of income for this period; and on
Blake’s personal contacts with James Barry.</p>
          <p>After lunch and a visit to the exhibition, where Robert Essick was on hand to answer numerous
questions concerning the works in his collection, Morris Eaves gave a fascinating account of
eighteenth-century art criticism, “An Inquiry into the Real and Imaginary Obstructions to the Acquisition of
the Arts in England: The Comedy of the English School.” He traced the attempts of English artists and
reviewers to establish the triumph of English art over its competition, primarily French and Italian art, and
to consummate the happy marriage of a heroic English art with the world of commerce.</p>
          <p>Morton Paley brought the symposium to a delightful conclusion with a detailed and convincing
examination of the influence of William Blake on his followers, “The Art of ‘The Ancients.’ ”
Emphasizing the elegiac elements in Blake’s illustrations to Thornton’s Virgil (actually, as Paley noted,
Blake was illustrating a poem by Ambrose Phillips), Paley then extensively and convincingly documented the
ways in which Samuel Palmer, Edward Calvert and George Richmond adapted both the pictorial vocabulary and the
media techniques of woodcut, engraving, fresco and tempera in their own later works.</p>
          <p>In the discussion that followed, Hazard Adams asked whether English artists had promoted a myth
of origins; Eaves responded that while James Barry had hailed Greek art as having discovered what he called
the “master art” (its line, color, harmony, etc.), Blake tended to see the origin of art in an eternity
variously identified with the Ancient Britons and Christianity; John Grant suggested the central role of
Blake’s image of Joseph of Arimathea in this context. Dörrbecker emphasized the ways in which Fuseli, in
his promotion of Winckelmann, one of the three demons (along with Montesquieu and Dubos) who obstructed the
triumph of English art on the European art market, somewhat qualified the plot of conspiracy successfully
thwarted that Eaves had told. Eaves then acknowledged that his account was intended to emphasize the story
that eighteenth-century English artists and art theorists told in common, rather than individual revisions and
digressions.</p>
          <p>The papers from the symposium will be published in <hi rend="i">The Huntington Library
Quarterly</hi>, where those unable to attend will have the opportunity to relish their subtlety, excitement,
and learning in greater detail. The exhibition, which continued through February 1988, was accompanied by a
superbly annotated and finely illustrated (in black and white) catalogue, <hi rend="i">William Blake and His
Contemporaries and Followers</hi>, prepared by Robert N. Essick and available from the Huntington Library
Bookstore or Publications Department for the phenomenally reasonable price of $5.95. I urge all readers of 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> to send for it immediately before the edition is sold out.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
