<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>22.1.hilton</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">“Under the Hill”</title>
        <author n="Hilton">Nelson Hilton</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1988</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1988</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">22.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Shelley M. Bennett</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Aethelred Eldridge</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Janet Warner</name>
              <name>Joseph Wittreich</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_22">
    <body>
      <pb id="p22-16" n="16"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-22-1-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">“Under the Hill”</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Nelson <name>Hilton</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Despite frequent citation of “To the Accuser who is The God of This World” as “one of
Blake’s most perfect short poems” (Bloom 435, cf. Damrosch 356), no one seems to have remarked a probable
source for the poem’s concluding reference to (or, that) “The lost Travellers Dream under the Hill.”
Alicia Ostriker writes that “The lost traveller is man, and Satan is but his dream” (1040); W. H.
Stevenson sees an “allusion to such common folktales as that of True Thomas, or Rip Van Winkle, in which a
mortal is carried into a fairy hill” (845); Damon, perhaps choosing not to be too explicit, refers to “the
mistaken ideals of those still wandering in the wilderness of life” (87).</p>
          <p>But as the “prologue” of <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi> is
preoccupied with images involving the Sinai revelation of Exodus (“Sinais heat,” “his Mercy Seat,”
“Jehovahs Finger” writing the Law), it’s not surprising to find that event in the “epilogue” as
well. Moses’ fellow travellers, Blake could read (reading white where we read black), are finally lost
“under the hill.” For in William Tyndale’s translation (does anyone imagine Blake limiting himself to
“the Authorized Version”?), “Moses brought the people out of the tētes to mete with God. and they stode
vnder the hyll” (Ex 19:17). Later, according to both Tyndale and the AV, Moses builds “an altar under the
hill” (Ex 24:4). And Tyndale’s Deuteronomist has Moses remind the people that “ye came ād stode also
vnder the hyll [AV: ‘under the mountain’] ād the hyll burnt with fire” (4:11). “Under” in these
translations of the common Hebrew preposition “tahat” (“under”) has the evident denotation of
“position at the bottom or foot of something” (s.v. <hi rend="i">OED</hi> I.7, cf. c. 1402 and 1662),
though some literalist rabbis suggested that YHWH uprooted the mountain and suspended it over the Israelites
to encourage acceptance of the Torah (Kasher 9:90). They submitted and—Blake seems to say—remained
asleep.</p>
          <p>The illustration offers another comment alongside the striking representation of psycho-sexual
fantasy (Hilton 169). For the sleeping figure (Moses and his rod might suit the context) is graphically 
<hi rend="i">under</hi> a design that suggests an image of Lucifer, “The Son of Morn”—or, in terms of the
text, “the Hill.” Here we encounter a marvellous particular instance of how powerful texts
            <figure n="ForTheSexesJPlate21.22.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="524">
	<head>Epilogue, <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Pierpont Morgan Library, New York. PML 9948.35 copy J pl. 21.</figDesc>
</figure>
are overdetermined, since Blake knows the Hebrew <hi rend="i">Hêlēl</hi> for Lucifer or the morning star (as
in Isaiah 14:12) and writes in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> that “Hillel . . . is Lucifer” (32.8). We might
further hypothesize the term *<hi rend="i">hill’el</hi> on the analogy of the Hebrew 
<hi rend="i">har’el</hi> or “mountain of god,” which, fascinatingly enough, is the AV gloss on Ezekiel’s
vision of “the altar” (43:15: “Harel, that is, The mountain of God”). In any event, the trajectory
continuing Hillel’s lowest visible right wing rib along the outline of the hill suggests we are to see both
bodies as alternate states of the same dream-work. The Sinai context also suggests that, far from a happy
“hill beyond which dawn is bursting on all sides” seen by Erdman (279), we end peering through smoke of
hill-fire and wondering, with those earlier lost dreaming travellers, what and where is real.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="p22-17" n="17"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Works Cited</title>
          </head>
          <p>Bloom, Harold. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse: A Study in Poetic Argument.</hi> 1963. Ithaca:
Cornell UP, 1970.</p>
          <p>Damon, S. Foster. <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Philosophy and Symbols.</hi> 1924. Gloucester,
MA: Peter Smith, 1958.</p>
          <p>Damrosch, Leopold, Jr. <hi rend="i">Symbol and Truth in Blake’s Myth.</hi> Princeton: Princeton
UP, 1980.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V., annot. <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake.</hi> Garden City: Anchor-Doubleday,
1974.</p>
          <p>Hilton, Nelson. “Some Sexual Connotations.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
16 (1982-83): 166-71.</p>
          <p><corr type="emend">Kasher, Menachem M., ed.</corr> <hi rend="i">Encyclopedia of Biblical Interpretation: A Millennial
Anthology.</hi> 9 vols. 1953. New York: American Biblical Encyclopedia Society, 1979.</p>
          <p>Ostriker, Alicia, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: The Complete Poems.</hi> Penguin English Poets.
Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1977.</p>
          <p>Stevenson, W. H., ed. <hi rend="i">Blake: The Complete Poems.</hi> Annotated English Poets.
London: Longman, 1971.</p>
          <p>Tyndale, William. <hi rend="i">William Tyndale’s Five Books of Moses Called The
Pentateuch.</hi> 1884, rpt. of 1530. Carbondale: Southern Illinois UP, 1967.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
