<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>22.2.david</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">Ministry Continues...</title>
        <author n="David">Prabu David</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1988</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1988</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">22.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_22">
    <body>
      <pb id="p22-74" n="74"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-22-2-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">NEWSLETTER</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="b">By</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="b">Prabu</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="b">David</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor><lb/>
          <hi rend="i">Athens NEWS Contributor</hi>
        </byline>
        <note type="unreferenced"><hi rend="i">Blake</hi> thanks John E. Grant for sending us this article.
                    Photograph and text courtesy of the Athens <hi rend="i">News.</hi></note>
        <figure n="Edridge.22.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="209">
          <head>Aethelred Eldridge operates a water pump on Sunday morning as friends and
                        students look at the remains of his fire-destroyed church near
                        Millfield.</head>
        </figure>
        <div2>
          <p>Ten people gathered yesterday outside the remains of the Church of William
                        Blake, which was destroyed by arson last week, to hold their Sunday morning
                        service.</p>
          <p>“I feel the fire is an act of vandalism and was maliciously
                        intended,” declared Aethelred Eldridge, founder of the church and
                        an associate professor of art at Ohio University.</p>
          <p>Asked about the fire, Jim Hanson, fire chief of the Chauncey-Dover Volunteer
                        Fire Department, replied, “We had problems getting to the place,
                        and the church was completely destroyed.”</p>
          <p>The church, which is located off Ohio Rt. 550, has been a place of worship
                        for more than 20 years for Eldridge and various friends, students and fellow
                        travelers. The art professor charged yesterday that people with different
                        philosophies have declared war on him and “defiled the place.</p>
          <p>“The last three years, there has been an ugly war. They have been
                        stealing art objects and utensils,” Eldridge said.</p>
          <p>On Sunday, people involved with the church and residents in the area said
                        they feared being targeted by the vandals and asked not to be quoted in The
                        NEWS.</p>
          <p>One neighbor blamed the arson on “some youths who attended a KKK 
            <figure n="AethelredEdridge.22.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="226">
          	<head>With the destruction of his church by arsonists, Eldridge preached
                                to a dozen people outside Sunday morning</head>
            <figDesc>NEWS photos/SUSAN MITCHELL</figDesc>
          </figure> 
                        rally” the same day the church was destroyed. And a
                        member of the church said it was a “group from
                        Glouster.”</p>
          <p>At the beginning of the service, Eldridge handed out a piece of clean toilet
                        paper and a black and white abstract illustration to all the people present.
                        Although he said the toilet paper was to wipe off “all
                        scuttlebutt,” he didn’t explain the abstract art.</p>
          <p>The vandals also struck a “cemetery” outside the church
                        where Eldridge and his congregation had stuck painted white broomsticks as a
                        memorial to what Eldridge described as deceased followers of the church.</p>
          <p>As Eldridge and friends gathered under a shade tree encircled by the brooms
                        Sunday, the professor opened his sermon saying, “You
                        don’t know teleology because you are not from a strange
                        background.”</p>
          <p>The unabridged Webster’s Third New International Dictionary
                        describes teleology as a metaphysical doctrine explaining phenomena and
                        events by final causes, or the use of design, purpose, or utility as an
                        explanation of any natural phenomenon.</p>
          <p>Without explaining exactly what teleology meant, the artist preached on, as
                        his followers listened with rapt attention. “I’ll
                        build a rope ladder from here to paradise...<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied>remission is when you lose
                        your heart and never get it back,” he said. Then he elaborated on
                        the beauty of circular reasoning, chaos, cosmos, bipolars and
                        “salvation through I.”</p>
          <p>Referring to those who burned the church, Eldridge continued, “We
                        have met the enemy in the dust...<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied>you have only
dust there...<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied>it was
                        lunatic on their part...<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied>Ashes to Ashes...<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied>It was God
                        ridden.”</p>
          <p>One church member explained. “He is only an eccentric artist, but
                        the local people think it is a Satanic church. Actually he is a real
                        Christian, who started the church after William Blake.”</p>
          <p>Doug Onley, who has known members of the congregation of the Church of
                        William Blake, asked, “Superstition or fear, why should someone
                        burn a place down?”</p>
          <p><hi rend="b">The Athens NEWS, June 6, 1988 /3</hi></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
