<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>22.2.dorrbecker</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="checklist">Blake and His Circle: An Annotated Checklist of Recent Publications</title>
        <author n="Dörrbecker">Detlef W. Dörrbecker</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1988</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1988</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">22.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_22">
    <body>
    <pb id="p22-36" n="36"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-22-2-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">Blake and His Circle: An Annotated Checklist of Recent
                        Publications</title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">D. W.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">DÖRRBECKER</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <p>The present edition of this continuing report on Blake-related literature records
                    the publication of some 250 books and articles, plus more than 300 reviews. The
                    number and type of journals that I have examined remain much the same (see the
                    preface to last year’s compilation), while the library resources at
                    Trier have not considerably improved in the meantime. Almost all the sections of
                    the checklist include back entries with publication dates as early as 1980,
                    however most of the items appeared in print between, approximately, May 1987 and
                    April 1988 (including, once again, some journal issues with a 1986 or even a
                    1985 date on their covers).</p>
        <p>As before, I have resisted the temptation to list references to non-print media
                    such as Tangerine Dream’s 1987 recording of “The
                    Tyger.” And I have banned from the section on Blake and the moderns
                    an entry for an exhibition entitled “Songs of Experience”
                    at the National Gallery of Ottawa in 1986. The works by contemporary Canadian
                    artists presented under that heading did, in the words of one reviewer,
                    “not invoke William Blake who [was] referenced conveniently, like a
                    postmodern embellishment tacked to the entrance of pre-existing
                    architecture” (Lorne Falk, <hi rend="i">Vie des Arts</hi> 30.124
                    [1986]: 28). Yet despite such occasional rejections, at least part III of this
                    year’s checklist appears to be haunted by the ghost of
                    “inclusiveness” and the continuing lack of a clear-cut set
                    of standards for selection—and this to such an extent that further
                    comments seem in order.</p>
        <p>To begin with, however, let me say that no major changes in arrangement or style
                    have been introduced in this year’s installment of the checklist.
                    While in matters of style I will continue to follow the guidelines laid down for
                    bibliographies in <hi rend="i">The MLA Style Manual</hi>, the arrangement of
                    entries may well have to be subjected to some considerable reshuffling in next
                    year’s compilation where I plan to merge and reorganize parts II and
                    III. Comprehensiveness, I am afraid, has been too much of an ideal in the
                    gathering of the materials for the construction of the 1985-1988 lists,
                    and—eventually—it may diminish rather than enhance their
                    usefulness as a research tool for a group of highly specialized scholars. An
                    attempt to achieve completeness may be very fine; but with respect to parts
                    II-IV of the checklists I wonder who, in fact, is being served with no less than
                    fourteen reviews listed in the past two years for a book of such peripheral
                    interest to Blake studies as the first volume of <hi rend="i">The Collected
                        Letters of W. B. Yeats</hi> (see #327, below). In a sense, such
                    inclusiveness is—though time-consuming and tiresome to both the
                    compiler and the user of a bibliography—easier to realize than
                    deliberate selectiveness.</p>
        <p>In a review of the 1981 volume of <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A Current
                        Bibliography</hi>, Thomas Lockwood suggested that “maybe it is
                    time now to think about how to shrink, not to expand, the
                    bibliography” (p. 277 in #271[1], below). The same on a miniature
                    scale can be said of the Blake checklists, and as long as there is no massive
                    protest from those who regularly consult these annual reports, I will indeed
                    shrink the scope of coverage in the future. Parts II and III—and, in
                    consequence, part IV—should again be considered as selective and
                    exclusive, rather than inclusive. Getting rid of what I think are too many
                    entries on too many aspects of the works of, for example, Cowper, Godwin, West,
                    or Wollstonecraft would allow both for some more extensive annotations in part I
                    and for the reintroduction of an early <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi>
                    feature, “work in progress.” I cannot yet say what will
                    result from these plans. Readers of these notes, however, are encouraged to send
                    both their suggestions for the organization of the checklist and notices of
                    their current research projects to Trier at the earliest date possible.</p>
        <pb id="p22-37" n="37"/>
          <figure n="BooksCircle.22.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="506"></figure>
        <p>Just as before, I have tried to keep evaluative statements in the annotations to
                    a minimum, that is, well within those boundaries which I thought legitimate in a
                    context which does not allow for an exposition of the criteria of evaluation. If
                    I have not been able to abstain completely from critical asides, I still hope to
                    meet with the indulgence of the readers and the victims of such comments alike.
                    No one is going to seriously judge the value of a study from my annotations
                    anyway. To compile these brief glosses, however, I have most often had recourse
                    to quotations from the books and articles themselves. These, it is hoped, will
                    highlight the authors’ own claims and intentions rather than my
                    estimates of their achievements. Let me add that in general I am not sure how
                    helpful or distracting these usually brief notes are. Here again I would be glad
                    to receive criticisms and suggestions from users.</p>
        <p>As in previous years, an asterisk preceding the entry indicates that as yet I
                    have not been able to examine the publication. For the first time, however, I
                    have supplied cross-references to the initial entries for books under review.
                    This seemed desirable, especially since so many of the reviews listed in part IV
                    either treat books published many years ago or are themselves recorded here only
                    three, four, or even more years after their publication. References in square
                    brackets which follow the titles of the works under review are of two sorts: for
                    a reference such as “[17#71]” simply read “see
                    the main entry that was included in the checklist for volume 17 as item
                    71”; for pre-1981 lists page references rather than item numbers are
                    supplied in much the same style (e.g., “[14p92]”).</p>
        <p>Once again, the relative completeness and reliability of this compilation owe a
                    great deal to the help I have received from various publishing houses (that
                    supplied me with inspection copies of new books in the field) as well as from a
                    number of colleagues who have generously sent offprints from their recent
                    articles and/or furnished me with references to some out-of-the-way materials. I
                    wish to thank G. E. Bentley, Jr., David Blayney Brown, Frederick Burwick, Joseph
                    Childers, Jackie DiSalvo, David Fuller, Michela Gori, the Martyn Gregory
                    Gallery, Anthony Lacy Gully, David Herrstrom, Nelson Hilton, Nancy Ide, Desmond
                    King-Hele, Kevin Lewis, Richard Martin, James McCord, David McKitterick, Dan
                    Miller, Peter Otto, and Molly Rothenberg, who have all made important
                    contributions to this year’s checklist. Earlier this year, I enjoyed
                    the unrestricted hospitality of Jenijoy La Belle and Robert Essick at Altadena
                    and was allowed to browse through the holdings of the finest private Blake
                    library I have ever met with (surpassing, to my tastes at least, even that of
                    the late Sir Geoffrey Keynes at Lammas House). This has yielded the majority of
                    entries for previously unrecorded publications from the years 1980-1984 and has
                    acquainted me with a number of new books, too. Very special thanks are also due
                    to Patricia Neill. Using just the right mixture of cheer and threat, she
                    actually managed to get hold of my typescript in time (well, almost). It was
                    then that her own work began, and her copy-editing expertise has saved me (and,
                    incidentally, the reader) from various stylistic inconsistencies and some
                    unforgivable blundering.</p>
        <p>Despite the help I have received, I still feel convinced that even in part I,
                    where comprehensiveness continues to be the guiding principle, all too many
                    omissions as well as an occasional error in the citations remain. It is
                    appropriate, then, to finish this introductory note by stating that I shall
                    include any omitted items in a future edition of this checklist and also
                    incorporate <hi rend="i">errata</hi> in an appendix to next year’s
                    issue of this annual report.</p>
        <pb id="p22-38" n="38"/>
        <div2>
            <figure n="BlakeBookPile.22.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="490"></figure>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part I William Blake</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Editions, Translations, and Facsimiles</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>1. *Blake, William. <hi rend="i">The Fly.</hi> n.p. [Gt. Brit.]: Dalin,
                            1976. [This pamphlet of only eight pages was issued in a limited edition
                            of only 55 copies; measuring no more than 54 millimeters in height, it
                            was easily overlooked and made its first appearance in the <hi rend="i">British
National Bibliography</hi> only in 1987.]</p>
            <p>2. *Blake, William. <hi rend="i">Proverbs of Hell.</hi> Harper Woods, MI:
                            Adagio P, 1982. [Not listed previously, this limited edition of 200
                            copies is now reported on the authority of a bookdealer’s
                            catalogue.]</p>
            <p>3. Borgmeier, Raimund, ed. <hi rend="i">19. Jahrhundert I: Romantik.</hi>
                            Die englische Literatur in Text und Darstellung 7. Stuttgart, W. Ger.:
                            Reclam, 1983. 40-51 and 324-27. DM 13.00 paper. [A bilingual selection
                            of a few poems by Blake and even fewer of his annotations to Reynolds
                            with a brief introduction by the editor of this anthology.]</p>
            <p>4. Kavanagh, P. J., and James Michie, eds. “William Blake
                            1757-1827.” <hi rend="i">The Oxford Book of Short Poems.</hi>
                            Oxford, Oxon.: Oxford UP, 1985. 106-09. [Eleven short poems and
                            fragments by Blake make their appearance as #243-53 of this
                            collection.]</p>
            <p>5. Kunitz, Stanley, ed. <hi rend="i">The Essential Blake.</hi> The
                            Essential Poets 4. New York, NY: Ecco P, 1987. $5.00 paper. [The editor
                            has chosen as “essential” reading in
                            Blake’s poetry the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, and
some thirty-five pages of selections from the
                                <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>, from the <hi rend="i">Gates</hi>, from
                            the letters, etc. Kunitz’s introduction takes up pages
                            3-8.]</p>
            <p>6. Luetjohann, Sylvia, ed. and trans. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Die
                                Hochzeit von Himmel und Hölle: Eine Auswahl aus den
                                prophetisch-revolutionären Schriften.</hi> Bad
                            Münstereifel, W. Ger.: Edition Tramontane, 1987. DM 34.00
                            cloth. [The only new translation of a selection from Blake’s
                            writings into German in almost thirty years; covers the <hi rend="i">Religion</hi>
tracts, <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell,
                                Visions of the Daughters of Albion, America, Europe, The Song of
                                Los</hi>, and “The Everlasting Gospel.” The
                            deliberately “free” translations are accompanied
                            by a careful introduction (7-31) to Blake’s thought and
                            poetry in general, and by commentaries on each of the works here
                            represented. Blake has never received as much attention in Germany as in
                            other non-anglophone countries such as France, Italy, or
                            Japan—this edition may change this situation a lot.]</p>
            <p>7. Mason, Michael, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> The Oxford
                            Authors. Oxford, Oxon.: Oxford UP, 1988. £17.50
                            cloth/£7.95 paper. [“This collection of William
                            Blake’s writings includes almost all his poetry and prose
                            works, and a few of his letters.” These are grouped under
                            such headings as “Blake on Religion and
                            Knowledge,” “Blake on Art and
                            Literature,” “Early Visionary and Narrative
                            Writings,” “The Lyrics,” or
                            “Late Lyrics” (which here include two Lambeth
                            prophecies). The more peculiar features of the editorial decisions
                            behind this collection are perhaps best explained by quoting from the
                            introduction: the volume “differs, deliberately, from all
                            recent editions of Blake. To start with, his very diverse output has
                            been arranged under kinds of writing . . . rather than chronologically.
                            A greater variety of his work is included here than in most (selective)
                            editions, and it seemed inappropriate to make chronology the sole
                            organizing principle of this disparate material, and thus thwart the
                            reader wanting a concentrated experience of Blake as a lyricist, or
                            insight into his views on a single important topic, such as art. . . .
                            The second unusual feature of this anthology is that it offers a single,
                            and entirely verbal, version of Blake’s writings. Deleted or
                            alternative readings are almost completely ignored, and there is no
                            attempt to describe or reproduce Blake’s illustrations to his
                            poems. . . . In recent years the doctrine has gained 
<pb id="p22-39" n="39"/>
ground that Blake’s text, where it was
                            illustrated, can only be read adequately in conjunction with the
                            illustration. This poses great problems for a modern editor . . . but,
                            more troublingly, the enhancement of our reading of Blake which was
                            expected to flow from attention to his illustrations has simply not
                            occurred. And the whole principle of the exercise may be questioned.
                            Blake himself seems to have been less tender of his text than some of
                            his editors. . . . Finally, no attempt is made in this edition to
                            summarize the content or message of individual prophetic works, nor is
                            there any explication of Blake’s mythology. I feel that both
                            enterprises are mistaken” (xiii-xiv). Brave and challenging
                            words, indeed; it is interesting to view these editorial statements in
                            the context of canon formation which has recently been discussed by
                            Morris Eaves; see #229, below. Mason’s text “may
                            be thought of as a modernized version of the transcriptions in G. E.
                            Bentley Jr.’s <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
                                Writings</hi> (1978). . . . The modernizing has been thorough, but
                            all original spellings in the verse (and in some of the prose) which
                            have metrical consequences are retained” (xxvi). To give his
                            readers “an edition which makes a single choice of text (with
                            Blake’s endorsement) and is not cluttered with indications of
                            what he rejected,” Mason after all remains indebted to one of
                            those “editors who have fallen into the habit of transcribing
                            what Blake crossed out, or improved on” (xiii); this
                            relationship between the “fallen” text and the
                            thoroughly modernized version that Mason believes his readers to be
                            “entitled to,” is not devoid of irony.]</p>
            <p>8. Phillips, Michael, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>: An Island in
                            the Moon: <hi rend="i">A Facsimile of the Manuscript.</hi> With a
                            Preface by Haven O’More. Cambridge, Cambs.: Cambridge UP, in
                            association with the Institute of Traditional Science, 1987.
                            £75.00, $125.00. [A limited edition of 775 numbered copies;
                            there are twenty-nine facsimile pages—reproducing the
                            Fitzwilliam Museum manuscript in “offset
                            litho”—which are accompanied by a new
                            transcription of the text, extensive annotation, and an introduction by
                            the editor (3-26). A second copy of the facsimile, folded and stitched
                            as a single quire, is inserted inside the back cover of the slipcased
                            volume which has been produced by the Stamperia Valdonega in Verona,
                            Italy. While the preface claims that the “manuscript (of <hi rend="i">An Island
in the Moon</hi>) had not been
                            published” at the time the project for this facsimile was
                            first discussed with Sir Geoffrey Keynes and Arnold Fawcus, and while
                            there is no mention of the only other separate edition of the 
<hi rend="i">Island</hi> manuscript, readers of this journal will recall
                            Erik Frykman’s not on Göran Malmqvist’s
                            Swedish translation of Blake’s satire which includes black
                            and white reproductions of “William Blakes
                            manuskript;” see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
                                Quarterly</hi> 14 (1981): 217-18; and 15 (1981): 84, #7. It
                            certainly would not have diminished the importance of the present
                            edition if references to Malmqvist’s introductory study as
                            well as to some other recent literature on the subject had been included
                            in the notes to Phillip’s commentary.]</p>
              <figure n="DavidPunterManuscript.22.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="493"></figure>
            <p>9. Punter, David, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Selected Poetry and
                                Prose.</hi> Routledge English Texts. London: Routledge, 1988.
                            £4.95 paper. [While acknowledging the “extraordinary
                            fidelity to Blake’s own script” of
                            Erdman’s “most <corr type="emend">authoritative</corr> edition,”
                            the editor has based his own text on Keynes’s slightly
                            modernized version and has “risked further
                            modernization” as well as “conventionalized
                            Blake’s habits of capitalization” (17). Punter
                            supplies an “Introduction” (1-19), a
                            “Critical Commentary” (223-46), as well as
                            “Notes” on the text (251-83). His selections
                            include <hi rend="i">Tiriel, Thel</hi>, the <hi rend="i">Marriage,
                                Visions, America</hi>, the <hi rend="i">Songs, The Song of Los</hi>
                            in full, and extracts from <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches, The French
                                Revolution, Urizen, Vala</hi> and other manuscript materials, 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>,
                            and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> A list for further reading with brief
                            editorial comments is supplied on pages 247-49.]</p>
            <pb id="p22-40" n="40"/>
            <p>10. Sanesi, Roberto, ed. <hi rend="i">Opere di William Blake.</hi> Trans.
                            G. Conte, R. Sanesi, and D. Villa. Parma, It.: Guanda, 1984. Lit 90000.
                            [Not yet seen, but with more than 800 pages and at such a price this is
                            very likely the first complete edition of Blake’s writings in
                            Italian or, at least, a very extensive bilingual selection.]</p>
            <p>11. Sanesi, Roberto, ed. and trans. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Libri
                                profetici.</hi> Tascabili Bompiani 400. Milan, It.: Bompiani, 1986.
                            Lit 6000. [Contains <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, the
<hi rend="i">French Revolution, Visions of the
                                Daughters of Albion, America, Europe, Urizen, Ahania</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">The Book</hi> as well as <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>;
                            the Italian translations of the Lambeth Books are printed on the rectos,
                            while Blake’s original texts appear on the versos of this
                            pocket edition. The editor has supplied both a
                            “Repertorio” (vii-xxvii), a brief biography of the
                            poet (xxix-xxxii), a select bibliography (xxxiii-xxxv), and some notes
                            on the text (215-25). It comes as a surprise to find that
                            Blake’s poetry is here quoted neither from
                            Bentley’s, nor from Erdman’s, nor
                            Keynes’s editions, but from Sampson’s 1913
                            “Oxford Edition” (see xxxv). Blake’s
                            titlepages are reproduced in poor, but legible halftones.]</p>
            <p>12. Sanesi, Roberto, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Libri
                                profetici.</hi> L’altra biblioteca 13. Milan, It.:
                            SE-Studio Editoriale, 1987. Lit 22000. [While the contents of the
                            present volume are almost identical with those of the edition listed in
                            the preceding entry (though the <hi rend="i">French Revolution</hi> and
                            “A Song of Liberty” are omitted), this printing of
                            Sanesi’s translations is on better paper, is spaced more
                            elagantly, and has all the editorial material grouped together at the
                            end of the book (155-80). However, at less than a third of the price of
                            the “Altra biblioteca” edition, the illustrated
                            Bompiani version seems to be by far the better choice to make for
                            Italian readers of Blake.]</p>
            <p>13. Taylor, Joshua C., ed. “William Blake: A Descriptive
                            Catalogue of Pictures (1809)/Marginalia to Reynolds’s 
<hi rend="i">Discourses</hi> (c. 1808).” <hi rend="i">Nineteenth-Century Theories of Art.</hi> California
Studies in the
                            History of Art 24. Berkeley, CA: University of California P, 1987.
                            139-52.</p>
            <p>14. Tramontano Magno, Cettina, and David V. Erdman, eds. The Four Zoas
                                <hi rend="i">by William Blake: A Photographic Facsimile of the
                                Manuscript with Commentary on the Illuminations.</hi> Lewisburg, PA:
                            Bucknell UP; London: Associated UP, 1987. $65.00. [A complete set of
                            reproductions from Blake’s manuscript in reduced format,
                            making use of infrared photography to improve the legibility of the
                            drawings. The “Commentary on the
                            Illuminations”—i.e., the designs which were mostly
                            executed in chalk or pencil and left uncolored—takes up pages
                            25-102 and is a page-by-page account not unlike in approach and style
                            Erdman’s earlier facsimile edition of the <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> (1973 and
1977) or his <hi rend="i">Illuminated
                                Blake</hi> (1974 and 1975).]</p>
            <p>
              <hi rend="i">Bibliographies, Bibliographical Essays, and Catalogues</hi>
            </p>
            <p>15. Dörrbecker, D.W. “Blake and His Circle: A
                            Checklist of Recent Publications.” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
                                Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987): 52-73.</p>
            <p>16. Erdman, David V., with the assistance of Brian J. Dendle, et al.,
                            eds. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Movement: A Selective and Critical
                                Bibliography for 1984.</hi> Garland Reference Library of the
                            Humanities 219. New York, NY: Garland, 1985. 95-112. [Especially where
                            concerned with studies of Blake, the more extensive of the brief reviews
                            in this annotated bibliography are also listed separately in part IV,
                            below. There, this volume is referred to in abbreviated form as
                                “<hi rend="i">RMB for 1984.</hi>”]</p>
            <p>17. Erdman, David V., with the assistance of Brian J. Dendle, et al.,
                            eds. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Movement: A Selective and Critical
                                Bibliography for 1985.</hi> Garland Reference Library of the
                            Humanities 683. New York, NY: Garland, 1986. 82-99. [Where concerned
                            with books on Blake, the more extensive of the reviews in this annotated
                            annual bibliography have also been listed separately in part IV, below.
                            This volume is there referred to in abbreviated form as “<hi rend="i">RMB for
1985.</hi>”]</p>
            <p>18. Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">William Blake and His Contemporaries
                                and Followers: Selected Works from the Collection of Robert N.
                                Essick.</hi> Exh. cat. San Marino, CA: Huntington Library, 1987.
                            $5.95 paper. [This is the catalogue for an exhibition shown at the
                            Huntington Art Gallery from Nov. 1987 through Feb. 1988. It features a
                            preface by Robert R. Wark, an introduction by the scholar-collector
                            (3-7), and his detailed descriptions of the sixty-four works on show
                            (8-75), many of which are illustrated.]</p>
            <p>19. Fitzwilliam Museum Cambridge. <hi rend="i">The Annual Reports of the
                                Syndicate and of the Friends of the Fitzwilliam: For the Year Ending
                                1985.</hi> n.p. [Cambridge, Cambs.: Fitzwilliam Museum], n.d.
                            [1986]. [The numerous acquisitions of works by Blake which are listed on
                            pages 13, 29, 34-35, and 38-40 of this “Annual Report of the
                            Fitzwilliam Museum Syndicate for the Year 1985” record the
                            bequest of the magnificent collection of the late Sir Geoffrey Keynes.
                            There are three Blake reproductions on plates VI and VII.]</p>
            <p>20. Folkenflik, Robert. “Recent Studies in the Restoration and
                            Eighteenth Century.” <hi rend="i">Studies in English
                                Literature 1500-1900</hi> 27 (1987): 503-53. [While paying little
                            attention to Blake literature, this review essay discusses many titles
                            on related subjects: Griffin’s <hi rend="i">Regaining
                                Paradise</hi>, Schulz’s <hi rend="i">Paradise
                                Preserved</hi> (520-21), Redford’s <hi rend="i">Converse
                                of the Pen</hi> (536-37), King’s <hi rend="i">Cowper</hi>
                            (538-39), Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Commerce des
                                Lumières</hi> (541), Barrell’s <hi rend="i">Political Theory</hi> (543-45),
and Wind’s <hi rend="i">Studies</hi> (545); it closes with brief notes on
                            Abram’s West monograph and Paley’s <hi rend="i">Apocalyptic Sublime</hi>
(545).]</p>
            <pb id="p22-41" n="41"/>
            <p>21. Manning, Peter J., and Sylvia Manning. “Recent Studies in
                            the Nineteenth Century.” <hi rend="i">Studies in English
                                Literature 1500-1900</hi> 27 (1987): 685-729. [Among the books
                            briefly reviewed in this report on current scholarship are 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism and Contemporary Criticism</hi>, ed. Eaves and Fischer
                            (685), Klancher’s <hi rend="i">Reading Audiences</hi>
                            (686-87), Metzger’s <hi rend="i">Modes of Pastoral</hi>
                            (692), Bate’s <hi rend="i">Shakespeare and the English
                                Romantic Imagination</hi> (700), and Kroeber’s <hi rend="i">Romantic
Art</hi> (712); again, however, none of the recent
                            Blake monographs figures in this review essay.]</p>
            <p>22. Modern Language Association of America. <hi rend="i">1986
                                International Bibliography of Books and Articles on the Modern
                                Languages and Literatures: Classified Listings.</hi> Vol. 1. New
                            York, NY: Modern Language Association of America, 1987. 55-57. [Blake
                            entries are numbered#2129-95. Though helpful with some out-of-the-way
                            citations, the MLA’s Blake listings for 1986 are surprisingly
                            incomplete.]</p>
            <p>23. Newey, Vincent, Bryan Burns, and James Michie. “The
                            Nineteenth Century: Romantic Period.” <hi rend="i">The
                                Year’s Work in English Studies</hi> 65 (1984). Ed. Laurel
                            Brake, with the assistance of Susan Brock, et al. London: Murray;
                            Atlantic Highlands, NJ: Humanities P; for the English Association, 1987.
                            387-415. [Blake criticism is scarcely mentioned in the present
                            volume—one of the reasons for this omission may well be that,
                            in Newey’s words, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
                                Quarterly</hi> was “unfortunately not available for
                            consultation this year” (390); but see the index for what
                            sporadic references to Blake-related items there are.]</p>
            <p>24. Smith, Michael, and Elizabeth Erskine, with the assistance of Mary
                            Jean DeMarr and D. Gene England, eds. <hi rend="i">Annual Bibliography
                                of English Language and Literature</hi> 59 for 1984. London: Modern
                            Humanities Research Association, 1987. 308-13. [Blake entries are listed
                            as #5478-568.]</p>
            <p>25. Taylor, Dena Bain. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Books in Print.</hi>
                            Thornhill, ON: Ben Abraham Books, n.d. [1987]. [A
                            bookdealer’s specialized sales offer which supplies a useful
                            and handy checklist of current scholarly publications and numerous
                            reprint editions; copies may be requested from Ben Abraham Books, 97
                            Donnamora Crescent, Thornhill, ON, Canada L3T 4K6.]</p>
            <p>26. Wordsworth, Jonathan, Michael C. Jaye, and Robert Woof, with the
                            assistance of Peter Funnell. <hi rend="i">William Wordsworth and the Age
                                of English Romanticism.</hi> Exh. cat. New Brunswick, NJ: Rutgers
                            UP, in association with The Wordsworth Trust, 1987. [There are numerous
                            (indexed) references to Blake’s poetry and art throughout
                            this handbook for an exhibition which was presented at the New York
                            Public Library (Oct. 1987-Jan. 1988), the Indiana University Art Museum
                            at Bloomington (Jan.-Mar. 1988), and by the Chicago Historical Society
                            (Apr.-June 1988). On show, with many other important manuscripts of the
                            period, was Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala, or The Four Zoas</hi>,
                            lent by the British Museum. Many members of Blake’s circle
                            are at least briefly mentioned in the text and catalogue, including
                            Barry, Erasmus Darwin, Godwin, Joseph Johnson, Linnell, Paine, Palmer,
                            Priestley, Crabb Robinson, Swedenborg, John Varley, and Wedgwood. Seven
                            of the color plates reproduce works by Blake.]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
              <figure n="BlakesHeroicArgument.22.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="453"></figure>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Critical Studies</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>27. Abley, Mark, and G. E. Bentley, Jr. “New Blake Documents:
                                <hi rend="i">Job, Oedipus</hi>, and the <hi rend="i">Songs of
                                Innocence and of Experience.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake /
                                An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987-1988): 104-07.</p>
            <p>28. Adams, Hazard. “Must a Poem be a Perfect
                            Unity?” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21
                            (1987): 74-77.</p>
            <pb id="p22-42" n="42"/>
            <p>29. Ault, Donald. <hi rend="i">Narrative Unbound: Re-Visioning William
                                Blake’s</hi> The Four Zoas. Clinamen Studies Series.
                            Barrytown, NY: Station Hill P, 1987. $43.00. [This book claims to
                            present “the first minutely detailed interpretation of the
                            verbal text” (xii) of Blake’s manuscript poem; it
                            runs to no less than 517 pages. For better or for worse, the author
                            wanted his study to be different from all previous Blake criticism. In
                            his “Foreword,” George Quasha says that Ault has
                            responded “to virtually every written mark on the page as
                            well as every created gap in the narrative,” accepting
                            “the challenge of the text at the level of radical
                            intentionality” (x), and Ault describes his own intentions in
                            writing <hi rend="i">Narrative Unbound</hi> by telling his readers that
                            it was his “desire to re-think the narrative foundations of
                            William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and to
                            provide the reader with a process text that plausibly retells this
                            immensely complex manuscript poem’s narrative through
                            analytical discourse,” which made him embark on the project.
                            “By turning critical attention to what has been left
                            unthought in previous accounts of the poem, I offer a description of the
                            poem’s narrative operations that is not intended to compete
                            with the existing body of Blake scholarship but rather to be
                            fundamentally incommensurable with it.” The
                            “attempt to defamiliarize the reader with Blake’s
                            poetics has involved me in a process of interpretation that requires
                            constant retroactive reconstitution of ‘facts’ or
                            reader ‘events’; . . . I have come to accept this
                            process, which takes on the quality of Blake’s own
                            interminable revising of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, as endless and
                            inevitable, one in which the final fixity of meaning is neither possible
                            nor desirable” (xi). For what I take to be an abstract of the
                            argument in this full-length study, see the author’s
                            contribution to <hi rend="i">Unnam’d Forms</hi> (ed. Hilton
                            and Vogler, 1986) which was listed in <hi rend="i">Blake / An
                                Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 82, #105. One ought to
                            remember, however, that <hi rend="i">Narrative Unbound</hi> is based on
                            the assumption “that every detail in the poem has aesthetic
                            and perceptual significance and that the most minute articulations of
                            similarity and discriminations of difference hold the keys to vast
                            narrative riches” (xi). These riches, the multiple layers of
                            meaning and the complex narrative structure of <hi rend="i">The Four
                                Zoas</hi>, which had in part been mapped in the earlier essay are
                            traced in full detail only in the present book, and it is only through
                            its careful study that all the implications of Ault’s radical
                            suggestions for a far-reaching renovation of the reading experience will
                            become fully apparent. To say the least then, this is an unusual and
                            provocative book (even in its layout), and it is bound to unbind a major
                            critical debate.]</p>
            <p>30. Baridon, Michel. “‘Copy for Ever Is My
                            Rule’: Blake lecteur de Reynolds dans le débat sur
                            mémoire et création.” <hi rend="i">Mémoire et création dans le monde
                                angloaméricain aux XVIIe et XVIIIe
                                siècles.</hi> Ed. Société
                            d’Études Anglo-Américaines des XVIIe et
                            XVIIIe Siècles. Strasbourg, Fr.: U de Strasbourg II, 1984.
                            75-87.</p>
            <p>31. Behrendt, Stephen C. “<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> 6:
                            Plundering the Treasury.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
                                Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987-1988): 85-94.</p>
            <p>32. Bentley, G. E., Jr. <hi rend="i">Blake Records Supplement: Being New
                                Materials Relating to the Life of William Blake Discovered since the
                                Publication of Blake Records (1969).</hi> Oxford, Oxon.: Clarendon
                            P, 1988. £27.50. [This important publication appeared on 16
                            June 1988. The <hi rend="i">Supplement</hi> updates the documentary
                            record of Blake’s life and work from nineteenth-century
                            sources and is bound to immediately establish itself as
                            “required reading” alongside the same
                            editor’s earlier compilations of Blake-related documents in
                            the 1969 <hi rend="i">Records</hi> and his volume in the
                            “Critical Heritage” series of 1975.]</p>
            <p>33. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “Richard Edwards, Publisher of
                            Church-and-King Pamphlets and of William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Studies in
Bibliography</hi> 41 (1988): 283-315. [While the fully
                            documented publication history of “Edward’s
                            Magnificent Edition of Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
                                Thoughts</hi>” (303) is right at the center of the
                            present study (293-311), it is the context of Edwards’ other
                            publishing activities during the 1790s which here supplies a new
                            perspective for the discussion of Blake’s watercolors and
                            engravings.]</p>
            <p>34. Bentley, G. E., Jr. “William Blake Musician.”
                                <hi rend="i">Revista Canaria de Estudios Ingleses</hi> 12 (1986):
                            147-51. [Although the author has been able to trace “a song
                            by W. Blake, complete with its music” (148), the composer
                            turns out to be a “Doctor in Divinity” who has
                            nothing whatsoever to do with the poet and artist of the same name,
                            except that the two men were contemporaries.]</p>
            <p>35. Bergevin, Gerald Walter. “The Darkening Green: Irony and
                            Revisionism in Blake’s Political Prophecies.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation
Abstracts International</hi> 48 (1987): 396A.
                            Washington State U. [“ . . . , in the political prophecies
                            written after <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> there is no synthesis or
                            progression which subsumes or contains the contradictory currents within
                            them. On the contrary much of their emotional force comes from the
                            ambiguity which seems to rest on an unresolved tension between hoped-for
                            social transformation and the realities of the social ills which the
                            poems describe. Furthermore, the affirmation of the positive social role
                            of the Poetic 
<pb id="p22-43" n="43"/>
Genius or imagination which we
                            find in <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> is revised and often undercut by
                            irony in the later political prophecies. These poems cast doubt on the
                            political efficacy of the imagination. Enthusiasm for the revolution is
                            tempered by serious doubts and concerns. . . . The political poems
                            dramatize the difficulty of presenting the truth about social problems
                            in <hi rend="i">language</hi> which is the poet’s primary
                            task. The discourse of these works refuses to encode a settled meaning.
                            However, the range of meanings available to the reader includes certain
                            identifiable social themes and the poems raise important social
                            issues.”]</p>
            <p>36. Bhattacharya, Biswanath. <hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi> Songs:
                                <hi rend="i">A Critical Study.</hi> Calcutta, India: KLM, 1980. Rs
                            40.00 cloth. [This volume only came to my notice some six or seven years
                            after its publication (which is dated “1981”
                            rather than “1980” on the dust jacket). It has not
                            just been ignored in previous issues of this annual checklist, but also
                            in all the recent studies of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> that are known
                            to me, and this despite of some extraordinary claims for the importance
                            of this critical study that are raised in the author’s
                            “Foreword: An Apology.” Here, the book is said to
                            be “the first-ever attempt to study Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> in the
light of his conceptual thinking and is
                            therefore likely to immensely enrich and expand our knowledge of the
                            subject” (iv).]</p>
            <p>37. Bidney, Martin. “A Russian Symbolist View of William
                            Blake.” <hi rend="i">Comparative Literature</hi> 39 (1987):
                            327-39. [On the Blake chapter, “Praotec sovremennykh
                            simvolisto: Vil’jam Blek, 1757-1827”
                            (“The Forefather of Contemporary Symbolists: William Blake,
                            1757-1827”), in Konstantin Bal’mont’s
                                <hi rend="i">Gornyja Vershiny</hi> (<hi rend="i">Mountain
                                Summits</hi>, Moscow, 1904).]</p>
            <p>38. Billigheimer, Rachel V. “Blake’s
                            ‘Eyes of God’: Cycles to Apocalypse and
                            Redemption.” <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> 66
                            (1987): 231-57.</p>
            <p>39. Blondel, Jacques. “Les ‘Proverbs
                            d’Enfer’ de William Blake.” <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi> 40 (1987):
448-54.</p>
            <p>40. Bloom, Harold, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s</hi> The
                            Marriage of Heaven and Hell. Modern Critical Interpretations. New York,
                            NY: Chelsea House, 1987. $19.95 cloth. [A slender collection of nine
                            articles, all published before as parts of books and judged by the
                            editor to represent “the most useful criticism available on
                            William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
                                Hell</hi>” (vii). Besides an index and two pages of
                            “Bibliography,” the less than 140 pages also
                            include an “Introduction” (1-24) which is
                            reprinted from Bloom’s 1963 monograph; the other contributors
                            are Crehan, Damrosch, Erdman, Frosch, Frye, George, Gleckner, and
                            Nurmi.]</p>
            <p>41. Bloom, Harold, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s</hi> Songs
                            of Innocence and of Experience. Modern Critical Interpretations. New
                            York, NY: Chelsea House, 1987. $19.95 cloth. [There are eight previously
                            published essays and excerpts from books by the Brismans, George,
                            Glazer, Gleckner, Frye, Paulson, and Price on the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>,
together with a list for further reading and an
                            introduction (1-24) which, again, has been “quarried from . .
                            . <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse</hi>” (vii).
                            Both of these collections in Bloom’s series of recycled
                            “Modern Critical Interpretations” seem to be
                            designed for classroom use rather than for the specialist who will be
                            familiar with most of their contents.]</p>
            <p>42. *Borges, Jorge Luis, and Gert Schiff. “Blake in Heaven and
                            Hell.” <hi rend="i">Magazine of Franco Maria Ricci</hi> 3
                            (1984): 67-94.</p>
            <p>43. Brisman, Leslie. “Blake’s Comme-bined Cherubim:
                            A Note on <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, Plate 32.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987-1988): 95-98.</p>
            <p>44. *Burwick, Frederick. “Visceral Visions, Marionettes, and
                            Monsters.” <hi rend="i">The Haunted Eye: Perception and the
                                Grotesque in English and German Romanticism.</hi> Reihe Siegen:
                            Beiträge zur Literatur-und Sprachwissenschaft 70. Heidelberg,
                            W. Ger.: Winter, 1987. 240-54. [Contains a discussion of
                            Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>]</p>
            <p>45. Butlin, Martin. “A New Blake from His Apprentice
                            Years?” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21
                            (1988): 143.</p>
            <p>46. Carr, Robert. “Divine Construct and the Individual Will:
                            Swedenborgian Theology in <hi rend="i">The Book of
                            Thel.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 23
                            (1987): 77-88.</p>
            <p>47. Cartwright, Jerome. “Blake’s ‘The
                            Little Black Boy.’ ” <hi rend="i">Explicator</hi>
                            45.3 (1987): 16-18. [The very same article reappeared in the fall 1987
                            issue of the <hi rend="i">Explicator</hi> where, however, Norma Greco
                            was credited as its author (see #69, below)—this certainly
                            calls for some future explication!]</p>
            <p>48. Cayley, David, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Prophet of the New
                                Age.</hi> Ideas 4ID7-197. Montreal, PQ: CBC Transcripts, 1987. [The
                            transcript of a Canadian Broadcasting Corporation program composed of
                            statements by Northrop Frye, Kathleen Raine, David Bindman, G. E.
                            Bentley, Jr., Michael Ferber, and George Goyder, to which are added
                            numerous quotations from the writings of Blake, Palmer, Crabb Robinson,
                            Hayley, etc. The original broadcastings were to be heard at CBC Toronto,
                            ON on 12, 19, and 26 Mar. 1987.]</p>
            <pb id="p22-44" n="44"/>
            <p>49. Chayes, Irene H. “Fallen Earth and Man in Nature: William
                            Blake in Iconographic Tradition.” <hi rend="i">Studies in
                                Iconography</hi> 10 (1984-1986): 169-95. [Traces the iconographic
                            tradition behind such motifs as the reclining female nude in
                            “The Little Girl Found” and the
                            “Introduction” page to <hi rend="i">Songs of
                                Experience</hi>, the “human quadruped in <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> 24”
(178) and some of Blake’s
                            watercolors to find that “the borrowed poses thems(el)ves and
                            the traditional meanings associated with them . . . contributed to the
                            evolution of Blake’s own meanings, supplemented or reinforced
                            by other iconographic sources. . . . he was inextricably involved with
                            and dependent upon a cumulative historical inheritance he might try to
                            renounce but could not evade” (191). Thus, the essay forms a
                            sequel to the same author’s earlier investigation into
                            “Blake’s Ways with Art Sources;” see
                                <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987):
                            80, #57.]</p>
            <p>50. Childers, Joseph. “Opposing the Paradigm: The Example of
                            Blake.” <hi rend="i">Dalhousie Review</hi> 66 (1986):
                            301-10.</p>
            <p>51. Clark, David Leonhard. “Auguries of Difference:
                            Indeterminacy and Displacement in Blake’s Prophetic
                            Texts.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
                                International</hi> 48 (1987): 1458A. U of Western Ontario.
                            [“Critical studies of William Blake have emphasized the
                            integrity of his major prophecies and their commitment to a
                            ‘grammar of the imagination’ which reconciles
                            differences in favor of the identity of the ‘human form
                            divine.’ This thesis throws these emphases into question in
                            two ways. First, a close examination of Blake’s accounts of
                            life in ‘Eden’ suggests that he could view
                            perfection as a conflictual condition which ceaselessly undoes itself,
                            creatively deferring rather than seeking the stability of final form. .
                            . . The highly purposive nature of the prophetic text is the most
                            palpable expression of the poet’s visionary will-to-order.
                            That this emphasis on containment is made at the same time that the
                            origin is celebrated for its resistance to (hierarchical; DWD) enclosure
                            produces in the case of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> what I call the
                            ‘cleft text.’ The second task of the thesis is to
                            track the articulation of this cleft or self-difference as it
                            complicates Blake’s language.” The author
                            discovers a “deconstructive indeterminacy, (which) discloses
                            an underlying complicity between terms that are arranged as origin and
                            derivation, inside and outside, and suggests . . . that each exists as
                            the other’s possibility in a circulation of mutual
                            interchange that textually mirrors Blake’s primordial
                            whole.”]</p>
            <p>52. Clark, Lorraine Joan. “Blake, Kierkegaard, and the Spectre
                            of Dialectic.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
                                International</hi> 48 (1987): 396A. U of Virginia. [Earlier
                            commentators on romantic poetry are said to “have limited
                            themselves (and the poets they seek to interpret) to two forms of
                            Romantic dialects (dialectics?; DWD): Hegelian mediation and Schlegelian
                            Romantic irony. Neither pattern illuminates the more profound concept of
                            irony underlying the Romantic enterprise of secularization. Mediation is
                            too theologically optimistic, Romantic irony too nihilistic, to do
                            justice to the passionate struggles of thought between theology and
                            nihilism which run throughout Romanticism. My thesis argues that William
                            Blake at the beginning of the age and Soren Kierkegaard at its end
                            exemplify with particularly fierce clarity this stubbornly ironic
                            vision, . . .”]</p>
            <p>53. Damon, S. Foster. <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and
                                Symbols of William Blake.</hi> Rev. ed., with a new foreword, an
                            annotated bibliography, and index by Morris Eaves. Hanover, NH: UP of
                            New England, for Brown UP, 1988. $18.00 paper. [See #229, below, for a
                            “reprint” (i.e., an advance printing) of
                            Eaves’ preface in the pages of this journal.]</p>
            <p>54. Davis, Patricia Elizabeth. “Revelation in
                            Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> 65
(1986): 451-77. [The essay is
                            preceded by four reproductions from the series of Blake’s
                            engravings.]</p>
            <p>55. Dawson, P. M. S. “Blake and Providence: The Theodicy of
                                <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake / An
                                Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1987): 134-43.</p>
            <p>56. DiSalvo, Jackie. “The Future of an Illusion and the
                            Imagining of the Future: The Analysis of Religion in Volney, Blake and
                            Freud.” <hi rend="i">The Age of Enlightenment.</hi> Ed.
                            Joseph E. Riehl. Spec. ser. of <hi rend="i">Explorations</hi> 1 (1987):
                            29-43.</p>
            <p>57. Edinger, Edward F. <hi rend="i">Encounter with the Self: A Jungian
                                Commentary on William Blake’s</hi> Illustrations of the
                            Book of Job. Studies in Jungian Psychology by Jungian Analysts 22.
                            Toronto, ON: Inner City Books, 1986. [A plate-by-plate interpretation
                            based on Jung’s distinction between the ego and the
                            “Self,” that “greater, objective
                            personality . . . the transpersonal center and totality of the
                            psyche” (7). The author demonstrates that just “as
                            with most great works of art, Blake expressed far more than he knew. In
                            these pictures (i.e., the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engravings) the
                            objective psyche speaks directly to us” (12).]</p>
            <pb id="p22-45" n="45"/>
            <p>58. Eitner, Lorenz. “British Neoclassicism and William
                            Blake.” <hi rend="i">An Outline of 19th Century European
                                Painting: From David through Cézanne.</hi> Vol. 1:
                            “Text.” New York, NY: Icon Editions-Harper, 1987.
                            75-99. [A general account of the achievement of Gavin Hamilton, Benjamin
                            West, James Barry, Henry Fuseli, John Flaxman, and William Blake and
                            their position in the history of art.]</p>
            <p>59. Ellis, Helen B. “Added and Omitted Plates in <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Colby Library
                                Quarterly</hi> 23 (1987): 99-107.</p>
            <p>60. Essick, Robert N. “Blake, Hayley, and Edward Garrard
                            Marsh: ‘An Insect of Parnassus.’ ” <hi rend="i">The Age of
Enlightenment.</hi> Ed. Joseph E. Riehl. Spec.
                            ser. of <hi rend="i">Explorations</hi> 1 (1987): 58-84. [Publishes and
                            comments on excerpts from Marsh’s letters of 1801-14 to
                            Hayley—acquired by the author in 1985—which
                            “constitute one of the largest groups of contemporary
                            references to Blake discovered in this century” (65).]</p>
            <p>61. Essick, Robert N. “Blake in the Marketplace,
                            1986.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21
                            (1987): 4-14.</p>
            <p>62. Essick, Robert N. “The Resurrection of <hi rend="i">America</hi> Copy R.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An
                                Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1988): 138-42.</p>
            <p>63. Essick, Robert N. “William Blake: Essick on the
                            Exhibition.” <hi rend="i">Huntington Calendar</hi> Nov.-Dec.
                            1987: 2. [The collector on the “principles and
                            procedures” which led to the formation of the collection
                            which was shown in an exhibition at the Huntington Art Gallery (Nov.
                            1987-Feb. 1988); for the catalogue accompanying this exhibition see #18,
                            above.]</p>
            <p>64. Everest, K. D. “Thel’s Dilemma.” <hi rend="i">Essays in Criticism</hi> 37 (1987):
193-208.</p>
            <p>65. Fuller, David. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Heroic Argument.</hi>
                            London: Croom Helm, 1988. £35.00. [On a relatively small number
                            of pages (xv + 297 in all) this study manages to address a surprising
                            range of subjects; all of Blake’s works in illuminated
                            printing as well as <hi rend="i">Tiriel, The Four Zoas</hi>, and
                            Blake’s critical writings are discussed at least briefly.
                            Special reference is made to the historical contexts of
                            Blake’s work, and to the writings of Swedenborg, Mary
                            Wollstonecraft, Burke, and Paine, whose influence on Blake’s
                            thought is critically reassessed. The final chapter (224-80) is
                            concerned with methodological problems, “the issue of the
                            proper exercise of subjectivity in criticism and (it) attempts to
                            explain . . . the individual subjectivity as well as the historical
                            viewpoint that operates in my own reading” (xii).]</p>
              <figure n="DavidFullerHeroic.22.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="380"></figure>
            <p>66. George, Diana Hume. “Reading Isaiah and Ezekiel through
                            Blake.” <hi rend="i">New Orleans Review</hi> 13.3 (1986):
                            12-21. [A contribution to a <hi rend="i">NOR</hi> spec. issue on
                            “Reading Blake, Blake Reading” (ed. Mark Lussier);
                            see also #76, 94, 97, and 110, below.]</p>
            <p>67. Gleckner, Robert F. “Blake’s ‘The
                            Tyger’ and Edward Young’s Book of Job.”
                                <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987-1988):
                            99-101.</p>
            <p>68. *Gori, Michela. “Dalla visione al mito: <hi rend="i">The
                                Four Zoas</hi> di William Blake.” Diss. U of Florence,
                            It., 1985.</p>
            <p>69. Greco, Norma A. “Blake’s ‘The Little
                            Black Boy.’ ” <hi rend="i">Explicator</hi> 46.1
                            (1987): 13-15. [Concerning the dubious authorship of this article see
                            the note to #47, above.]</p>
            <p>70. Hagstrum, Jean H. “More on <hi rend="i">The Romantic
                                Body.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
                                Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987): 16-17. [Enlarges on the argument of his
                            book—for which see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
                                Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987): 57, #55—and replies to Anne
                            Mellor’s review which is listed as #311(5), below.]</p>
            <pb id="p22-46" n="46"/>
            <p>71. Haigney, Catherine. “Reply to Andrew Lincoln.”
                                <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987): 77.
                            [See #72 and 90, below.]</p>
            <p>72. Haigney, Catherine. “Vala’s Garden in Night the
                            Ninth: Paradise Regained or Woman Bound?” <hi rend="i">Blake
                                / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1987): 116-24. [For the debate
                            provoked by the publication of this article see the preceding entry and
                            #90, below.]</p>
            <p>73. *Hampsey, John C. “Blake’s Bound
                            Children.” <hi rend="i">Forum</hi> 27.3 (1986): 20-37.
                            [Probably a condensed version of the argument in the author’s
                            dissertation, for which see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
                                Quarterly</hi> 17 (1983): 66, #78.]</p>
            <p>74. Herrstrom, David Sten. “Blake’s Redemption of
                            God in the Laocoön: Literal Incarnation and the Marriage of
                            Picture and Text.” <hi rend="i">Perspective: Art, Literature,
                                Participation.</hi> Ed. Mark Neuman and Michael Payne. Spec. issue
                            of <hi rend="i">Bucknell Review</hi> 30.1 (1986): 37-71.</p>
            <p>75. Hilton, Nelson. “Blake Rouzes the Faculties.”
                                <hi rend="i">Teaching the Eighteenth Century: Three Courses.</hi>
                            n.p. [Northfield, MN]: American Society for Eighteenth-Century Studies,
                            1987. 24-37. [The objectives of Hilton’s proposed
                            undergraduate course are to present “Blake’s work
                            as crystallization” of the eighteenth-century concerns with
                            Christianity, with “a developing consciousness of education
                            as a practice, . . . the diffusion of print culture . . . changes in
                            language consciousness . . . the rise of natural philosophy . . . the
                            rise of mass culture and decay of civic humanism . . . the development
                            of graphic, visual literacy . . . deepening contradictions in patriarchy
                            (and) some political, social, cultural chronology” (35).
                            Perhaps not a course for students of only average talents and
                            capacities, but—as the cunningly coined title will make known
                            to them—“Blake Rouzes the
                            Faculties!”]</p>
            <p>76. Hilton, Nelson. “The Heavy Metal of Blake’s
                            Language.” <hi rend="i">New Orleans Review</hi> 13.3 (1986):
                            34-39. [Part of a spec. section on “Reading Blake, Blake
                            Reading;” see also #66, 94, 97, and 110 in the present
                            list.]</p>
            <p>77. Ide, Nancy M. “Image Patterns and the Structure of William
                            Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
Quarterly</hi> 20 (1987): 125-33.
                            [To establish these “patterns” and the
                            “structure” they create, “a
                            multipurpose computer program for text analysis” (125) has
                            been employed; their interpretation, however, is left to the reader and
                            critic. See also the subsequent entry.]</p>
            <p>78. Ide, Nancy M. “Patterns of Imagery in William
                            Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Méthodes quantitatives
et informatiques dan
                                l’étude des textes/Computers in Literary and
                                Linguistic Research: En hommage à Charles Muller.</hi>
                            Ed. Étienne Brunet. Travaux de linguistique quantitative 35.
                            Geneva, Switz.: Slatkine, 1986. 495-505. [“This paper
                            describes a computer-assisted analysis of semantic patterning in . . .
                                <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and considers the way in which such
                            patterns contribute to the structure and meaning of the
                            work.” (496) See also the preceding entry.]</p>
            <p>79. Jackson, Mary V. “Reply to Charu Sheel Singh.”
                                <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987): 16. [A
                            brief reply to Singh’s rejoinder to the author’s
                            review of <hi rend="i">The Chariot of Fire</hi>; see #116, below, and
                                <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987):
                            85, #172, and 99, #466(2).]</p>
            <p>80. *Kang, Sun-Koo. “William Blake eui Archetypal Symbolism
                            Yeongu.” Diss. Joong-Ang U, Korea, 1982. [A study of
                            Blake’s symbolism, seen from the perspective supplied by
                            Jung’s theory of archetypes.]</p>
            <p>81. *Kang, Tong-Won. “[Poetry of Mammalian to Reptilian: On
                            William Blake’s Poetry.]” <hi rend="i">Jeju
                                University Journal: Humanities</hi> 16 (1983): 113-29. [In
                            Korean.]</p>
            <p>82. *Kang, Yop. “[‘The Tyger’ of William
                            Blake.]” <hi rend="i">University Journal: Humanities</hi>
                            [Busan, Korea] 22 (1982): 161-78. [In Korean.]</p>
            <p>83. *Kang, Yop. “William Blake’s Conception of God
                            and Man.” <hi rend="i">University Journal: Humanities</hi>
                            [Busan, Korea] 24 (1983): 297-320. [Just in case some readers may feel
                            puzzled about this and the three preceding entries for Korean
                            contributions to the study of Blake—or, in fact, about the
                            identity of Sun-Koo, Tong-Won, and Yop Kang—let me point out
                            at once that these citations seem rather mysterious to the compiler,
                            too. I have seen none of these articles and can do no more than to
                            identify my source: the Kang entries are listed as #5519-22 in 
<hi rend="i">ABELL</hi> 59, for which see #24, above.]</p>
            <p>84. Kaufman, Andrew Frederick. “Authority and Vision: A Study
                            of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                                Experience.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
                                International</hi> 48 (1987): 399A. U of Toronto, ON.
                            [“An overview of Blake’s understanding of
                            authority is presented and shows how it derives from his radical but
                            coherent reading of the Gospels. For Blake the point is that all forms
                            of temporal authority, regardless of intentions, are pernicious. It
                            stands in opposition to the redemptive understanding Blake identifies
                            with Jesus, which involves the imagination’s capacity to
                            perceive metaphorically, in terms that transfigure the visible world
                            into a visionary one. . . . Rather than the relatively simple opposition
                            between two states of mind that critics most often have seen the
                            collection as, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>
                            may . . . be seen as an essentially dramatic structure in which Blake
                            presents four distinct modes of understanding and treatments of
                            authority, each illuminating the limitations or possibilities of the
                            other.”]</p>
            <pb id="p22-47" n="47"/>
            <p>85. Konopacki, Adam. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Trans. Renate
                            Böning. Welt der Kunst. Berlin, E. Ger.: Henschelverlag, 1986
                            [i.e., 1987]. DM 20.90/c. $14.00. [Published simultaneously at Warsaw,
                            Pol.: Arkady; Budapest, Hung.: Corvina; and Bratislava, Czech.: Tatran.
                            This is a book for the chicory coffee-table with sixteen plates in
                            mostly faded and unreliable colors and forty murky black-and-white
                            reproductions. It is sad to imagine that anybody’s
                            understanding of Blake’s art may be dependent on
                            reproductions of such a poor quality.]</p>
            <p>86. Latané, David E., Jr. “A Blakean Reference in
                            Joyce Cary’s <hi rend="i">Except the Lord.</hi>”
                                <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi> 24.3 (1987): 57-61.</p>
            <p>87. Lemaitre, Henri. <hi rend="i">William Blake: vision et
                                poésie.</hi> Paris, Fr.: Corti, 1985. Fr 115.00 paper.
                            [There is a “Spiritual Biography of a Visionary”
                            (7-30), a chapter on the poet’s “Search and
                            Obsession” (31-76), another on “Obsession and
                            Contemplation” (77-101), and the author summarizes his
                            findings as “Une Poétique surnaturaliste de la
                            forme-figure” (103-19). He also supplies a “Petit
                            Lexique Blakien” (115-19), a bibliography, and thirty-four
                            monochrome illustrations, including all the <hi rend="i">Job</hi>
                            engravings; while the latter reproduce well enough, facsimiles have been
                            used for the reproductions from pages of the illuminated books, with the
                            result that the plates on pages 130-35 and 137 are considerably
                            blurred.]</p>
            <p>88. Lewis, Kevin. “The Impasse of Coleridge and the Way of
                            Blake.” <hi rend="i">The Interpretation of Belief: Coleridge,
                                Schleiermacher and Romanticism.</hi> Ed. David Jasper. London:
                            Macmillan; New York, NY: St. Martin’s P, 1986. 225-34.</p>
            <p>89. Lewis, Kevin. “The Use of Blake and the Recovery of
                            Fideism.” <hi rend="i">Journal of the American Academy of
                                Religion</hi> 54 (1986): 741-57.</p>
            <p>90. Lincoln, Andrew. “Vala’s Garden.”
                                <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987): 77.
                            [See also #71 and 72, above.]</p>
            <p>91. Linkin, Harriet Kramer. “The Function of Dialogue in <hi rend="i">The Book of
Thel.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Colby
                                Library Quarterly</hi> 23 (1987): 66-76.</p>
            <p>92. Lipking, Lawrence. <hi rend="i">“The Marriage of Heaven
                                and Hell.” The Life of the Poet: Beginning and Ending
                                Poetic Careers.</hi> Chicago, IL: U of Chicago P, 1981. 34-47. [This
                            is a revised version of an essay which first appeared in 1976 as
                            “Blake’s Initiation: <hi rend="i">The Marriage of
                                Heaven and Hell</hi>;” see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake /
                                An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 11 (1977-1978): 164, #B2133. There are
                            numerous other references to Blake’s poetic career throughout
                            the present volume.]</p>
            <p>93. Lundeen, Kathleen Farmer. “Ambiguous Blasphemy: Blake and
                            the Ontology of Language.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation
                                Abstracts International</hi> 47 (1987): 4089-90A. U of California,
                            Santa Barbara. [“One of the more curious features of
                            Blake’s prophetic canon is that each poem or cluster of poems
                            describes the same event. . . . Just as each poem describes the recovery
                            of the divine Word, the canon as a whole dramatizes the rise from Ulroan
                            (utilitarian) to Edenic (poetic) perception of language. . . . The
                            metaphors describe a gradual rise from the material elements to spirit .
                            . . a close examination of Blake’s apocalyptic visions of
                            language shows the eventual falling away of metaphor. . . . I shall
                            begin my analysis by showing how ‘The Tyger’
                            wrestles with the inherent ambiguity of the fallen tongue, and I shall
                            conclude with Heidegger’s solution to the problem of
                            metaphor.”]</p>
            <p>94. Lussier, Mark. “‘Vortext’ as
                            Philosopher’s Stone: Blake’s Textual Mirrors and
                            the Transmutation of Audience.” <hi rend="i">New Orleans
                                Review</hi> 13.3 (1986): 40-50. [The guest editor’s
                            contribution to this issue’s spec. section on
                            “Reading Blake, Blake Reading;” Lussier has also
                            written the “Introduction” (5) to the essays
                            listed as #66, 76, 94, 97, and 110.]</p>
            <p>95. Martin, Richard G. “Material Differences: The
                            Immaterialisms of Berkeley and Blake.” <hi rend="i">English
                                Studies in Canada</hi> 13 (1987): 391-405.</p>
            <p>96. McCord, James. “All Human Forms Identified: William
                            Blake’s Illustrations to <hi rend="i">The
                                Pilgrim’s Progress.</hi>” <hi rend="i">CEA
                                Critic</hi> 48.4/49.1 (1986): 87-100. [The essay is accompanied by
                            twelve reproductions of Blake’s watercolor designs to
                            Bunyan.]</p>
            <p>97. Miller, Dan. “Blake’s Allusions: <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 86.” <hi rend="i">New
Orleans Review</hi>
                            13.3 (1986): 22-33. [One of the five essays which constitute this
                            issue’s spec. section on “Reading Blake, Blake
                            Reading;” see also #66, 76, 94, and 110.]</p>
            <p>98. Miller, Dan, Mark Bracher, and Donald Ault, eds. <hi rend="i">Critical Paths: Blake and the
Argument of Method.</hi> Durham, NC:
                            Duke UP, 1987. $45.00 cloth/$17.95 paper. [A collection of essays;
                            besides the three editors, the contributors are Hazard Adams, David
                            Aers, Stephen D. Cox, Nelson Hilton, William Dennis Horn, Elizabeth
                            Langland, Thomas A. Vogler, David Wagenknecht, and Brenda S. Webster.
                            Their subjects range from general considerations of “Methods
                            and Limitations,” “Revisionism,”
                            “De-Formation,” and “Feminist
                            Revision” in Blake studies to new interpretations of <hi rend="i">Tiriel, The
French Revolution, Visions of the Daughters of
                                Albion</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>]</p>
            <pb id="p22-48" n="48"/>
              <figure n="BlakeMethod.22.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="373"></figure>
            <p>99. *Nanavutty, Piloo. “Blake and Medieval Christian
                            Iconography.” <hi rend="i">Aligarh Journal of English
                                Studies</hi> 10 (1985): 59-65.</p>
            <p>100. Nesfield-Cookson, Bernard. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Prophet of
                                Universal Brotherhood.</hi> n.p. [Wellingborough]: Crucible-Aquarian
                            P, 1987. £9.95 paper. [It was Rudolf Steiner who cut the
                            author’s key to a “new” understanding
                            of Blake. The foreword was written by Sir George Trevelyan.]</p>
            <p>101. *Otto, Peter. “Constructive Vision and Visionary
                            Deconstruction: Los, Eternity and the Productions of Time in the Later
                            Poetry of William Blake.” Diss. U of Adelaide, S. Austral.,
                            1985. [No abstract of this dissertation has, as yet, been published;
                            however, a large portion of Otto’s thesis will soon become
                            available in a book forthcoming from Oxford UP.]</p>
            <p>102. Otto, Peter. “Final States, Finished Forms, and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi>” 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An
                                Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1987): 144-46. [Contributes to a
                            discussion which was started by Mann and Essick in 1985; see <hi rend="i">Blake /
An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 81,
                            #72, and 83, #128.]</p>
            <p>103. Otto, Peter. “The Spectrous Embrace, the Moment of
                            Regeneration, and Those Two Seventh Nights.” <hi rend="i">Colby Library
Quarterly</hi> 23 (1987): 135-43. [In <hi rend="i">Vala, or The Four Zoas</hi> “Night the Seventh (a) and
                            Night the Seventh (b) are . . . in a relationship which can only be
                            called an embrace. At the same point in narrative place and time the
                            reader has two Nights which persist in standing alongside one another. .
                            . . if the Nights are read as parallel narratives of the flesh and the
                            spirit then the apparent discontinuity between the accounts is no longer
                            a problem which must be solved or explained” (142). What a
                            snappy and ingenious explanation!]</p>
            <p>104. Otto, Peter. “Visionary Deconstruction: The
                            Bard’s Song in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Philological
Quarterly</hi> 66
                            (1987): 207-30.</p>
            <p>105. Owens, Norah. <hi rend="i">William Blake and Felpham 1800-1803.</hi>
                            Bognor Regis, W. Sx.: Bognor Regis Local History Society, 1987.
                            £1.60.</p>
              <figure n="SelfhoodRedemption.22.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="334"></figure>
            <pb id="p22-49" n="49"/>
            <p>106. Pagliaro, Harold. <hi rend="i">Selfhood and Redemption in
                                Blake’s</hi> Songs. University Park, PA: Pennsylvania
                            State UP, 1987. $20.00. [The author, following up the argument of some
                            of his earlier essays—see, e.g., <hi rend="i">Blake / An
                                Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 16 (1982): 114,
                            #99—“intends to offer a reading of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi> as a basis for a more
                            immediate sense of Blake’s psychology of redemption than is
                            generally available in the scholarship” (ix). To do so, the
                            evidence found in the later prophecies which “gives meaning
                            to words like ‘Self-hood,’
                            ‘Self-examination,’ and
                            ‘Self-annihilation’ ” is brought to
                            bear upon an interpretation of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> that
                            considers these poems as “a consistent human
                            psychology,” good for “our psychological
                            disorientation and renewal,” rather than seeing them
                            “in a perspective defined by social criticism, by irony, or
                            by some derivative of Christian doctrine” (ix-x). The
                            book’s concluding chapter (111-30) argues that the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>
“may be regarded as the individuated
                            prelude to the prophecies” (x); while stressing
                            “some continuities,” the author treats the
                            conceptual “differences” between the shorter poems
                            and the major prophecies as well.]</p>
            <p>107. *Patterson, Annabel. <hi rend="i">Pastoral and Ideology: Virgil to
                                Valéry.</hi> Berkeley, CA: U of California P, 1988.
                            £28.15. [Though I have not yet seen a copy of this book, I
                            expect it to contain a chapter on Blake’s Virgil wood
                            engravings; see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21
                            (1987): 59, #89.]</p>
            <p>108. *Raine, Kathleen. “The City in William Blake.”
                                <hi rend="i">Aligarh Journal of English Studies</hi> 11 (1986):
                            75-92. [Probably much the same text that was previously printed in a
                            limited edition as an “Academic Inn Discussion
                            Paper;” see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
                                Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 84, #159.]</p>
            <p>109. Ricards, Philip Clayton. “Visionary Mysticism: A Study of
                            Visionary Mystical Experience as It Informs the Works of Jacob Boehme
                            and William Blake and Its Importance for the Philosophy of
                            Religion.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
                                International</hi> 48 (1987): 153-54A. Claremont Graduate School.
                            [The “meaning of the presence in Blake’s works of
                            many of Boehme’s themes, ideas, symbols, and concepts is best
                            understood as an effect of their similar mystical experiences.
                            Accordingly, this study investigates this type of mysticism as it is
                            found in Blake and Boehme and in this way seeks to clarify the nature of
                            Boehme’s presence in Blake’s thought and to access
                            the nature of visionary mystical experience from the perspective of the
                            philosophy of religion. The historical, cultural, literary, and
                            religious connections and continuities between Boehme and Blake are
                            discussed with a view to establishing the nature of the indebtedness of
                            Romantic thought in general and Blake’s thought in particular
                            to Boehme’s heritage. The nature of the language of mystical
                            vision will be shown to be similar to that of poetic
                            discourse.”]</p>
            <p>110. Riehl, Joe [i.e., Joseph E.]. “Gnosticism in
                            Blake’s ‘I saw a chapel all of gold.’
                            ” <hi rend="i">New Orleans Review</hi> 13.3 (1986): 6-11.
                            [This essay, together with the articles listed as #66, 76, 94, and 97,
                            above, makes up a spec. section on “Reading Blake, Blake
                            Reading,” edited by Mark Lussier.]</p>
            <p>111. Rothenberg, Molly Anne. “Blake Reads ‘The
                            Bard’: Contextual Displacement and Conditions of Readability
                            in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Studies in
                                English Literature 1500-1900</hi> 27 (1987): 489-502.</p>
            <p>112. Rothenberg, Molly [Anne]. “The Provisional Vision of
                            Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Word and Image</hi> 3
(1987): 305-11.</p>
            <p>113. Scrivener, Michael. “A Swedenborgian Visionary and <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven
and Hell.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987-1988):
                            102-04.</p>
            <p>114. Shabetai, Karen. “Blake’s Antifoundationalist
                            Poetics.” <hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature
                                1500-1900</hi> 27 (1987): 555-70.</p>
            <p>115. *Singer, June. <hi rend="i">The Unholy Bible: Blake, Jung and the
                                Collective Unconscious.</hi> Boston, MA: Sigo P, 1986. $24.95
                            cloth/$12.95 paper. [A new edition or a reprint of the 1970 and 1973
                            publications, then subtitled “A Psychological Interpretation
                            of William Blake.”]</p>
            <p>116. Singh, Charu Sheel. “Reply to Mary V.
                            Jackson.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
                            21 (1987): 14-15. [In defence of the argument in his <hi rend="i">Study
                                of William Blake in the Light of Hindu Thought</hi>;
                            Jackson’s review was listed in <hi rend="i">Blake / An
                                Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1986-1987): 99, #466(2); for her
                            rejoinder to Singh see #79, above.]</p>
            <p>117. Spector, Sheila A. “The Reasons for
                            ‘Urizen.’ ” <hi rend="i">Blake / An
                                Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1988): 147-49.</p>
            <p>118. Summerfield, Henry. “Beards, Disputations and Revelry:
                            Observations on Blake’s <hi rend="i">Job</hi> Engravings with
                            Special Reference to Plates 2 and 3.” <hi rend="i">Colby
                                Library Quarterly</hi> 23 (1987): 89-98.</p>
            <p>119. *Sung, Chan-Kyung. “[William Blake, with Special
                            Reference to His Imagination.]” <hi rend="i">Journal of the
                                English Language and Literature</hi> [Seoul, Korea] 28 (1982):
                            23-46. [In Korean; see also #80-83, above.]</p>
            <p>120. Tandecki, Daniela. “ ‘Mind-Forg’d
                            Manacles’: William Blake und das Moralgesetz.” <hi rend="i">English and
American Studies in German</hi> (1986): 78-79.
                            [A dissertation abstract; for the published version of this thesis see
                            the subsequent entry.]</p>
            <pb id="p22-50" n="50"/>
            <p>121. Tandecki, Daniela. <hi rend="i">Mind-Forg’d Manacles:
                                William Blake und das Moralgesetz.</hi> Diss. U of Bonn, W. Ger.,
                            1986. Studien zur englischen und amerikanischen Literatur 10. Frankfort
                            on the Main, W. Ger.: Lang, 1987. SFr 65.00 paper. [This is the first
                            full-length study of what Denis Saurat described as the
                            “rebellion of Blake against dogma and morality,”
                            his “reversal of all values” (<hi rend="i">Blake
                                and Modern Thought</hi>, London: Constable, 1929, 9). The author
                            traces the history of the concept of a moral law from Wycliff to the
                            eighteenth-century Deists (17-57), studies Blake’s critique
                            of these concepts in the entire corpus of his writings (59-252), and
                            draws attention to similar ideas in the productions of a large array of
                            nineteenth- and early twentieth-century writers (253-77). For an
                            abstract of the useful summary and explication of one of the central
                            tenets in Blake’s thinking which is presented in this thesis,
                            see the preceding entry.]</p>
              <figure n="DanielaTandeckei.22.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="343"></figure>
            <p>122. Thinès, Georges. “William Blake et Arthur
                            Rimbaud: Deux visions de l’infernal.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin de l’Académie
Royale de Langue et de
                                Littérature Françaises</hi> 44.1 (1986):
                            12-27.</p>
              <figure n="AlanTomlinson.22.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="383"></figure>
            <p>122A. Tomlinson, Alan. Songs of Innocence and of Experience <hi rend="i">by William Blake.</hi>
Macmillan Master Guides. Basingstoke,
                            Hants.: Macmillan Education, 1987. £1.95 paper. [This booklet
                            is meant to help its readers with understanding as well as enjoying
                            Blake’s poems when used as a study guide for
                            “passing an examination in literature” (vi). In a
                            series of brief chapters it offers information on the poet’s
                            “Life and Background” (1-8), on his
                            “Printing Methods” (9-13), the “Themes
                            and Issues” of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (14-24), a
                            “Commentary” on the poems (25-66), an introduction
                            to “Blake’s Style” (67-75), a
                            “Critical Analysis of a Specimen Poem” (i.e., of
                            “London,” 76-79), a note on the
                            “Critical Reception” of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> (80-82), some “Revision
                            Questions,” and a few suggestions for “Further
                            Reading” (83-86). In its general organization then,
                            Tomlinson’s “Master Guide” may be
                            compared with Handley’s and Hyland’s earlier
                            publications in the “Brodie’s Notes”
                            (1979) and “York Notes” (1982) series.]</p>
            <pb id="p22-51" n="51"/>
            <p>123. Turman, Kathryn Lee Green. “The Illumination of the
                            Paradise Within: An Iconological Analysis of <hi rend="i">Milton, a Poem
                                in 2 Books.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
                                International</hi> 48 (1987): 1213A. U of Texas. [“This
                            iconological analysis . . . tests the utility of a critical method based
                            on C. G. Jung’s theory of archetypal analysis and Owen
                            Barfield’s theory of idolatry as a hermeneutic program for
                            reading the verbal and visual text of this apocalyptic prophecy. . . .
                                <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (unlike <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>) is
                            a wholly theocentric iconological system. Not only topographic and
                            structural but also vital and pictorial configuration(s) make multiply
                            manifest Christocentric circled-cross patterns. . . . Exploring the
                            evolution of the significance of iconological configuration in 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> reveals both the conceptual coherence and the
                            representational simplicity of the poem. <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> is
                            radically Christological in that it is conceptually as well as
                            spiritually anchored in Jesus. The test is representationally simple in
                            that both verbally and visually posited configurations are ultimately
                            defined by the central point identified with Jesus. Because this point
                            is also defined as the emanative divine center of every being, 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> may be said to be mystic.” May I add
                            that to the compiler who, after all, is not a native speaker of the
                            English language, this abstract sounds like a mere bubble of words. It
                            is only fair to say, however, that for the reader of dissertation
                            abstracts Turman’s is no isolated case.]</p>
            <p>124. Watkinson, Ray. “A Meeting with Mr. Rossetti.”
                                <hi rend="i">Journal of Pre-Raphaelite Studies</hi> 4.1 (1983):
                            136-39. [Publishes material from an anonymous nineteenth-century
                            notebook. Its unidentified owner was a collector of Blake drawings who
                            had attended the 1852 Butts sale of “works of that able but
                            eccentric artist, William Blake, with many of his best
                            drawings” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>, 1977, 659,
                            #559), and had planned to write a monograph on the artist until he
                            learned of Gilchrist’s then projected <hi rend="i">Life.</hi>
                            According to this manuscript, its owner was among the informants
                            consulted by Gilchrist. The present article, however, is mostly
                            concerned with a report in this notebook about a visit to Dante Gabriel
                            Rossetti; the conversation of the two men centered on Blake, and the
                            Pre-Raphaelite painter is said to have kindly lent Blake’s
                                <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> to the anonymous collector, allowing him
                            to copy or trace from its pages whatever he may like. Since Watkinson
                            claims that the author of his notebook was in possession of a large and
                            important collection of Blake’s (watercolor?) drawings,
                            superior to that of Monckton Milnes, it is tempting to identify him with
                            some such figure as “Mr. Strange” from the
                            catalogue of works compiled by William Michael Rossetti for the second
                            volume of the 1863 <hi rend="i">Life of Blake.</hi> J. C. Strange,
                            however, mostly bought at the 1853 Foster’s rather than the
                            1852 Sotheby’s sale, and without a hint at the subject of any
                            of the works then owned by Rossetti’s visitor, all this
                            speculation lacks a sound factual basis. In any case, this manuscript
                            source—of which I had never heard before reading
                            Watkinson’s short article—seems to supply a
                            fascinating account of the feelings and motives of an early Blake
                            collector, and it is to be hoped that either the present owner of this
                            nineteenth-century notebook or some Blake scholar will comment in more
                            detail about its contents in the future.]</p>
            <p>125. “William Blake: Exhibit Opens, Enriches Huntington as the
                            Center of Blake Studies,” and “William Blake:
                            Exhibition Catalogue, Other Huntington Blake Publications . . . Events
                            Related to the Exhibition.” <hi rend="i">Huntington
                                Calendar</hi> Nov.-Dec. 1987: 1 and 3. [An unsigned announcement of
                            the exhibition from the Essick collection; see also #18 and 63,
                            above.]</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part II Blake’s Circle</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">General Studies</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>126. *Pointon, Marcia. “Romanticism in English
                            Art.” <hi rend="i">Romantics.</hi> Ed. Stephen Prickett.
                            Context of English Literature. London: Methuen; New York, NY: Holmes,
                            1981. 76-114. [Discusses, <hi rend="i">inter alia</hi>, the work of
                            Barry, Fuseli, Flaxman, and Blake.]</p>
            <p>127. Spencer, Keith. <hi rend="i">At the Sign of the Dial: Charles
                                Haslewood Shannon and His Circle.</hi> Exh. cat. Lincoln, Lincs.:
                            Usher Gallery-Lincolnshire County Council, 1987. [Shown in the
                            exhibition and catalogued as #71-75 were Blake’s Virgil wood
                            engravings and three prints by Palmer and Calvert. These works are
                            described as “an important influence on the book design and
                            illustration of The Vale Press” (40). The exhibition was
                            presented at the Usher Gallery from 9 Aug.-13 Sept. 1987 and then
                            traveled to the University of Hull Art Collection, the Nottingham
                            University Art Gallery, and the Carlisle Museum and Art Gallery until 23
                            Apr. 1988. The catalogue was designed to resemble the books produced by
                            Shannon and Ricketts in the late nineteenth century, and was printed in
                            an edition of only 750 copies.]</p>
            <p>
              <hi rend="i">See also #18, 26, and 58, above, and 165, below.</hi>
            </p>
          </div3>
          <pb id="p22-52" n="52"/>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">James Barry</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>128. Allan, D. G. C. “James Barry as a Member of the
                            Society.” <hi rend="i">Journal of the Royal Society of
                                Arts</hi> 135 (1987): 330-33. [The revised version of a paper read
                            at the 1983 James Barry Symposium, which was organized by the Royal
                            Society on the occasion of the Barry exhibition at the Tate
                            Gallery.]</p>
            <p>
              <hi rend="i">See also #160, 164, and 173, below.</hi>
            </p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">William Cowper</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>129. Marshall, W. Gerald. “The Presence of ‘the
                            Word’ in Cowper’s <hi rend="i">The
                            Task.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Studies in English Literature
                                1500-1600</hi> 27 (1987): 475-87.</p>
            <p>130. *Pache, Walter, ed. <hi rend="i">18. Jahrhundert II.</hi> Die
                            englische Literatur in Text und Darstellung 6. Stuttgart, W. Ger.:
                            Reclam, 1983. [German translations of some of Cowper’s poems
                            and prose writings, printed to face their English originals on opposite
                            pages as part of an anthology.]</p>
            <p>131. *Redford, Bruce. <hi rend="i">The Converse of the Pen: Acts of
                                Intimacy in the Eighteenth-Century Familiar Letter.</hi> Chicago,
                            IL: U of Chicago P, 1987. [Cowper’s letters are studied at
                            some length.]</p>
            <p>132. *Rhodes, Nick, ed. <hi rend="i">William Cowper: Selected Poems.</hi>
                            The Fyfield Series. Manchester, Lancs.: Carcanet P, 1984.
                            £3.95/$7.50 paper.</p>
            <p>133. Sherbo, Arthur. “More from the <hi rend="i">Gentleman’s Magazine</hi>: Graves,
Mainwaring, Wren,
                            Sterne, Pope, Bubb Dodington, Goldsmith, Hill, Herrick, Cowper,
                            Chatterton.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi> 40
                            (1987): 164-74.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Robert Hartley Cromek</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>134. Read, Dennis M. “Cromek, Cunningham, and <hi rend="i">Remains of Nithsdale and Galloway
Song</hi>: A Case of Literary
                            Duplicity.” <hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi> 40
                            (1987): 175-87.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Erasmus Darwin</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>135. Busch, Werner. “Wright, die Lunar Society und die
                            Ästhetik des Erasmus Darwin.” <hi rend="i">Joseph
                                Wright of Derby: Das Experiment mit der Luftpumpe: Eine Heilige
                                Allianz zwischen Wissenschaft und Religion.</hi>
                            Kunststück: Fischer Taschenbuch 3941. Frankfort on the Main,
                            W. Ger.: Fischer, 1986. 57-74.</p>
            <p>136. *McNeil, Maureen. “The Scientific Muse: The Poetry of
                            Erasmus Darwin.” <hi rend="i">Languages of Nature: Critical
                                Essays on Science and Literature.</hi> Ed. L. J. Jordanova. New
                            Brunswick, NJ: Rutgers UP, 1986. 159-203. [Compares Darwin’s
                            imagery with Blake’s.]</p>
              <figure n="MaureenMcNeil.22.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="351"></figure>
            <p>137. McNeil, Maureen. <hi rend="i">Under the Banner of Science: Erasmus
                                Darwin and His Age.</hi> Manchester, Lancs.: Manchester UP, 1987.
                            £27.95, $49.95. [This study, which incorporates the material of
                            the essay listed in the preceding entry, is a fully revised version of
                            the author’s dissertation of 1980, for which see <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987): 61, #122. Aiming
                            at “an exploration of one component of the cultural legacy of
                            the Industrial Revolution” and “a reconsideration
                            of the bonds between science and technology on the one hand, and culture
                            on the other” (7), and unlike previous biographical studies
                            of Erasmus Darwin, this book attempts to view Darwin in the context of
                            the history of eighteenth-century science and its interrelations with
                            the history of economic and political revolutions. “In short,
                            this book is concerned to situate Darwin in his full historical context
                            and to begin to clear the way to see the interrelations among his
                            various interests and involvements. . . . the analysis is structured
                            into four units, (which focus) on . . . the Industrial Revolution, the
                            British reaction to the French Revolution, the medical world of
                            late-eighteenth-century 
<pb id="p22-53" n="53"/>
Britain, and the
                            Agricultural Revolution. The first chapter of each of the units explores
                            Darwin’s situation in these social settings. The second
                            chapters consider the specific ways in which his writings relate to
                            these features of his setting” (6).]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">John Flaxman</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>138. *Chan, Victor. “A Note on Géricault, Flaxman,
                            and Michelangelo.” <hi rend="i">Arts Magazine</hi> 57.6
                            (1983): 88-90. [The French artist is said to have looked at Michelangelo
                            through Flaxman’s classicist eyes.]</p>
            <p>139. Morris, Barbara. “Flaxman’s Illustrations to
                            Homer as a Design Source for Glass Decoration in the 1870s.”
                                <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 129 (1987): 318-21.</p>
            <p>140. Yarrington, Alison. “Nelson the Citizen Hero: State and
                            Public Patronage of Monumental Sculpture 1805-18.” <hi rend="i">Art History</hi>
6 (1983): 315-27. [Includes a brief
                            discussion of Flaxman’s Nelson monument in St.
                            Paul’s Cathedral (318-19); also should make useful background
                            reading for anyone attempting a new interpretation of Blake’s
                            “The Spiritual Form of Nelson Guiding
                            Leviathan.”]</p>
            <p>
              <hi rend="i">See also #18, 58, 152, 154, 165, and 182 in the present
                                list.</hi>
            </p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Henry Fuseli</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>141. *Bechtold, Carmen. “‘Die
                            Nachtmahr’: Johann Heinrich Füsslis
                            Alptraumdarstellung.” M. A. thesis. U of Karlsruhe, W. Ger.,
                            1986-1987.</p>
            <p>142. “A Drawing by Fuseli.” <hi rend="i">National
                                Galleries of Scotland</hi> Apr.-May 1988: n. pag. [A brief and
                            unsigned note, commenting on the acquisition of a pen and wash drawing
                            by Fuseli, presumably a portrait of the artist’s wife Sophia,
                            for the Department of Prints and Drawings at the National Gallery in
                            Edinburgh. The female head is reproduced in poster size on the verso of
                            this issue of the Scottish National Galleries’
                            newsletter.]</p>
            <p>143. Gantner, Joseph. “Formen der Angst im Bild.”
                                <hi rend="i">Sandoz Bulletin</hi> 21.73 (1985): 20-30. [Discusses
                            the “objective representation of fear” in two of
                            Fuseli’s drawings and the “Nightmare”
                            (21-23).]</p>
            <p>144. Klein, Jürgen. “11. Vorlesung.” <hi rend="i">Anfänge der englischen Romantik
1740-1780:
                                Heidelberger Vorlesungen.</hi> Anglistische Forschungen 191.
                            Heidelberg, W. Ger.: Winter, 1986. 245-71. [The entire lecture was
                            devoted to Fuseli’s early literary career as a translator and
                            critic in London during the 1760s.]</p>
            <p>145. Weinglass, D. H. “Henry Fuseli’s Letter of
                            Enquiry to Paris on Behalf of Mary Wollstonecraft’s Sister,
                            Everina.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
                            21 (1988): 144-46.</p>
            <p>
              <hi rend="i">See also #18, 58, 159, 160, 164, 165, 173, 180, and 182 in
                                the present list.</hi>
            </p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">William Hayley</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>146. LeFaye, Deirdre. “Jane Austen and William
                            Hayley.” <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 34 (1987):
                            25-26.</p>
            <p>
              <hi rend="i">See also #60, above, and #152, below.</hi>
            </p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">John Linnell</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>147. Crouan, Katharine. <hi rend="i">John Linnell: Truth to Nature (A
                                Centennial Exhibition).</hi> Martyn Gregory Catalogue 31. Exh. cat.
                            London: Martyn Gregory Gallery, 1982. [This catalogue accompanied an
                            exhibition which was shown from 8-20 Nov. 1982 at the London gallery
                            and, later on, at Davis and Langdale’s of New York. The
                            majority of the 112 drawings, watercolors, and oils on exhibition came
                            from the collections of the artist’s descendants and are
                            still little known. The fifty pages of the catalogue are profusely
                            illustrated, including eight color plates, and effectively supplement
                            the same author’s better known catalogue for the centennial
                            exhibitions held at the Fitzwilliam Museum and the Yale Center for
                            British Art; see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 16
                            (1982): 117, #152.]</p>
            <p>
              <hi rend="i">See also #26, above.</hi>
            </p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">John Hamilton Mortimer</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>148. Wynne, Michael. “Drawings by John Hamilton Mortimer in
                            the Staatliche Graphische Sammlung, Munich, and a Stained Glass Window
                            at Brasenose College, Oxford.” <hi rend="i">Pantheon</hi> 47
                            (1987): 107-11. [Treats Mortimer’s drawings of
                            “Christ and the Four Evangelists,”
                            Blackberd’s engravings after these designs, and their
                            adoption in a stained glass window executed by James Pearson in
                            1776.]</p>
            <p>
              <hi rend="i">See also #181, below.</hi>
            </p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>149. Brown, David Blayney. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer 1805-1881:
                                Catalogue Raisonné of the Paintings and Drawings, and a
                                Selection of the Prints in the Ashmolean Museum.</hi> Oxford, Oxon.:
                            Ashmolean Museum, 1983. [This is a retitled reprint of the 1982 Palmer
                            exhibition catalogue; see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
                                Quarterly</hi> 17 (1983): 69, #159. According to the
                            “Compiler’s acknowledgements,” the
                            “text is presented as in the original” edition
                            which was published on the occasion of the exhibitions held at London
                            and Edinburgh and sold in aid of The Friends of the Ashmolean
                            Museum.]</p>
            <pb id="p22-54" n="54"/>
            <p>150. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer: His Life and Art.</hi>
                            Cambridge, Cambs.: Cambridge UP, 1987. £25.00. [Not an entirely
                            new book, but rather a revised and expanded version of the
                            author’s Palmer biography of 1974. The present edition is
                            published to team up with Lister’s forthcoming catalogue
                            raisonné of Palmer’s works. Blake’s
                            influence on Palmer is discussed on many pages scattered throughout the
                            book. There are 102 half-tone reproductions.]</p>
            <p>151. Thurin, Susan Schoenbauer. “<hi rend="i">Pictures from
                                Italy</hi>: Pickwick and Podsnap Abroad.” <hi rend="i">Dickensian</hi> 83
(1987): 67-78. [Reproduces and briefly mentions
                            Palmer’s vignette illustrations to Dicken’s
                            book.]</p>
            <p>
              <hi rend="i">See also #18 and 26, above, and 165, below.</hi>
            </p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">George Romney</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>152. Tscherny, Nadia. <hi rend="i">George Romney: “Flaxman
                                Modelling the Bust of Hayley.”</hi> n.p. [New Haven, CT]:
                            Yale Center for British Art, n.d. [1987]. [A single folding sheet which
                            served as the catalogue for a “Yale Center for British Art
                            Painting in Focus” exhibition; it contains a brief essay on
                            the painter, the two Hayleys and the sculptor depicted, and on the
                            history of the portrait painting which commemorates their friendship.
                            There also is a checklist of the thirty-five items which made up this
                            small studio exhibition, including two drawings and an engraving by
                            Blake as well as some Flaxman materials.]</p>
            <p>153. Watson, Jennifer C. <hi rend="i">George Romney in Canada.</hi> Exh.
                            cat. Waterloo, ON: Wilfrid Laurier UP, for the Kitchener-Waterloo Art
                            Gallery, 1985. [Catalogue of an exhibition which was to be seen in
                            Ontario and Alberta, at the Art Gallery of Windsor, 22 Dec. 1985-16 Feb.
                            1986, and at the Edmonton Art Gallery, 8 Mar.-20 Apr. 1986.]</p>
            <p>
              <hi rend="i">See also #159 and 164, below.</hi>
            </p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>154. Bennett, Shelley M. <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard: The Mechanisms of
                                Art Patronage in England circa 1800.</hi> Columbia, MO: U of
                            Missouri P, 1988. #29.00. [Published 82 years after Coxhead’s
                                <hi rend="i">Stothard</hi>, this is only the third and certainly
                            much needed monograph on the most industrious book illustrator of
                            Blake’s times. Bennett’s book is a fully revised
                            version of her 1977 U of California, Los Angeles, dissertation in which
                            she takes a fresh look at Stothard’s oeuvre by placing it in
                            the context of an increasingly industrialized society, which thoroughly
                            affected both the production and the marketing of art. This context
                            enables the author to explain Stothard’s success with his
                            contemporaries as well as his later relegation to a minor place in the
                            history of English art. Thus, the book examines the reverse of the medal
                            coined in Blake’s “Laocoön”
                            plate. Bennett also supplies a reassessment of Stothard’s
                            close association with both Flaxman and Blake.]</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">John Varley</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>155. Wark, Robert [R.] <hi rend="i">British Landscape Watercolors from
                                Southern California Private Collections: An Exhibition at the Henry
                                E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</hi> Exh. cat. San Marino,
                            CA: Huntington Library, 1986. 12-15. [The author refers to the special
                            attraction of the works of Blake and Rowlandson for American collectors
                            in his introduction (4); Varley was represented in this exhibition with
                            six of his landscape designs which are described in #6-11.]</p>
            <p>
              <hi rend="i">See also #26, above.</hi>
            </p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part III Works of Related Interest</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Some General Studies, Mostly of Romantic Art and
                                    Poetry, and Their Historical Context</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>156. Adams, Hazard. “Titles, Titling, and Entitlement
                            To.” <hi rend="i">Journal of Aesthetics and Art
                                Criticism</hi> 46 (1987): 7-21. [Briefly discusses
                            “Blake’s title <hi rend="i">Jerusalem the
                                Emanation of the Giant Albion</hi>” on page 17.]</p>
            <p>157. *Anderson, Ross, ed. <hi rend="i">A Brush with Shakespeare: The Bard
                                in Painting, 1780-1910.</hi> Exh. cat. Montgomery, AL: Montgomery
                            Museum of Fine Arts, 1985. $12.00. [Contributions by Lucy Oakley, et
                            al.; includes discussion of Boydell’s Shakespeare
                            Gallery.]</p>
            <p>158. Bonnell, Thomas F. “John Bell’s <hi rend="i">Poets of Great Britain</hi>: The
‘Little Trifling
                            Edition’ Revisited.” <hi rend="i">Modern Philology
                                85</hi> (1987): 128-52. [Blake engraved one of the Chaucer
                            frontispieces after a design by Stothard for Bell’s
                            collection.]</p>
            <p>159. Brosch, Renate, Joachim Möller, and Gretel Wagner. <hi rend="i">Shakespeare: Buch und
Bühne.</hi> Exh. cat.
                            Berlin, W. Ger.: Kunstbibliothek Berlin-Staatliche Museen <corr type="emend">Preußischer
                            Kulturbesitz,</corr> 1986. [Published on the occasion of the Third World
                            Shakespeare Congress on “Images of Shakespeare” to
                            accompany an exhibition at the Kunstbibliothek in Apr. 1986. Romney,
                            Fuseli, and Boydell’s Shakespeare Gallery are discussed by
                            the authors in the context of 400 years of Shakespeare
                            illustrations.]</p>
            <pb id="p22-55" n="55"/>
            <p>160. Dingley, R. J. “A Note on the Historical
                            Sublime.” <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi> ns 48
                            (1987): 249-56. [The subject of this article are the writings and/or
                            paintings of Baillie, Burke, Priestley, Winckelmann, Reynolds, Fuseli,
                            Barry, Turner, and John Martin.]</p>
            <p>161. *Erdman, David V. <hi rend="i">Commerce des Lumières:
                                John Oswald and the British in Paris, 1790-1793.</hi> Columbia, MO:
                            U of Missouri P, 1986. $39.00 [Studies the cooperation of French and
                            British intellectuals during the years following the Great
                            Revolution.]</p>
            <p>162. *Gordon, Catherine M. <hi rend="i">British Paintings of Subjects
                                from the English Novel, 1740-1870.</hi> Diss. Courtauld Institute of
                            Art (U of London), 1981. Outstanding Theses in the Fine Arts from
                            English Universities. New York, NY: Garland, 1987. $150.00. [Should have
                            something to say about Stothard and some other members of
                            Blake’s circle.]</p>
            <p>163. *Gross, Kenneth. <hi rend="i">Spenserian Poetics: Idolatry,
                                Iconoclasm, and Magic.</hi> Ithaca, NY: Cornell UP, 1985 [i.e.,
                            1986]. $24.95.</p>
            <p>164. Gully, Anthony Lacy. “John Milton’s
                            ‘Unholy Trinity’ (Satan, Sin, and
                            Death).” <hi rend="i">Phoebus</hi> 3 (1981): 19-36. [This
                            article on illustrating <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, bk. 2, ll.
                            711-26, effectively supplements the respective references in Marcia R.
                            Pointon’s <hi rend="i">Milton and English Art</hi>
                            (Manchester, Lancs.: Manchester UP, 1970), by studying
                            Romney’s, Barry’s, Fuseli’s,
                            Gillray’s, and Blake’s versions of the subject in
                            the context of the “interest in utilizing Milton’s
                            text as a vehicle for exploring political allegory or the
                            sublime” (33).]</p>
            <p>165. Hodnett, Edward. <hi rend="i">Five Centuries of English
                                <corr type="emend">Book Illustration.</corr></hi> Aldershot, Hants.: Scolar P,
1988.
                            £65.00. [The chapter on “The Eighteenth Century
                            (II): 1776-1800” of this posthumous publication contains
                            brief sections on Blake (94-97), Burney (97-98), Flaxman (99), Fuseli
                            (101-03), Loutherbourg (103), and Stothard (106) as <corr type="emend">book
illustrators.</corr>
                            Just as the texts on Palmer (135) and Shields (175) in subsequent
                            chapters, these notes add little that is new in fact or in approach to
                            the existing literature on the subject, and some of them appear to be
                            strongly condensed versions of chapters in the author’s
                            previous “studies in the illustration of English
                            literature;” see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
                                Quarterly</hi> 17 (1983): 66, #83. However, the book seems to have
                            been designed primarily for use as a reference work and a general
                            instruction; as such and on account of its illustrations it may indeed
                            serve its purpose.]</p>
            <p>166. *Hope, Ann M. <hi rend="i">The Theory and Practice of Neoclassicism
                                in English Painting: The Origins, Development and Decline of an
                                Ideal.</hi> Diss. U of Nottingham, Notts., 1968. Outstanding Theses
                            in the Fine Arts from English Universities. New York, NY: Garland,
                            1987. $125.00.</p>
            <p>166. *Hope, Ann M. <hi rend="i">The Theory and Practice of Neoclassicism
                                in English Painting: The Origins, Development and Decline of an
                                Ideal.</hi> Diss. U of Nottingham, Notts., 1968. Outstanding Theses
                            in the Fine Arts from English Universities. New York, NY: Garland, 1987.
                            $125.00.</p>
            <p>167. <hi rend="i">The Huntington Art Collections: A Handbook.</hi> [Ed.
                            Robert R. Wark]. San Marino, CA: Huntington Library, 1986. $12.95. [This
                            is a revised and enlarged edition of <hi rend="i">The Huntington Art
                                Collection</hi>, a summary catalogue compiled by the curatorial
                            staff, edited by Robert Wark, and published in 1970. While the extensive
                            Blake collection at the Huntington is covered separately and in full
                            detail in Robert Essick’s <hi rend="i">Complete
                                Catalogue</hi>, the present handbook describes in brief the
                            important collection of works by Blake’s contemporaries that
                            is housed at San Marino.]</p>
            <p>168. Isphording, Eduard, with the assistance of Manfred von Arnim. <hi rend="i">Fünf
Jahrhunderte Buchillustration: Meisterwerke
                                der Buchgraphik aus der Bibliothek Otto Schäfer.</hi>
                            Ausstellungskataloge des Germanischen Nationalmuseums ser. A/Bayerische
                            Staatsbibliothek: Ausstellungskataloge 42. Exh. cat. Nuremberg, W. Ger.:
                            Germanisches Nationalmuseum, 1987. DM 42.50. [The finely printed and
                            lavishly illustrated catalogue of an exhibition which was first shown at
                            the GNM in Nuremberg (11 Sept.-15 Nov. 1987) and then at the BSB in
                            Munich (4 Feb.-16 Apr. 1988). The exhibition handbook supplies a general
                            introduction to the history of book illustration from the fifteenth to
                            the early twentieth century, catalogues an impressive selection of
                            mostly French illustrated eighteenth-century books, and includes a copy
                            of Blake’s Blair designs as #162 (with some misunderstandings
                            of both technique and publication history in the text), probably a copy
                            of the 1813 large paper folio “proof” edition
                            rather than of the 1808 folio as stated by the authors.]</p>
            <p>169. Keener, Frederick M. “Parallelism and the
                            Poets’ Secret: Eighteenth-Century Commentary on <hi rend="i">Paradise
Lost.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Essays in
                                Criticism</hi> 37 (1987): 281-302.</p>
            <p>170. *Kernan, Alvin. <hi rend="i">Printing Technology, Letters and Samuel
                                Johnson.</hi> Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP, 1987. $29.50.</p>
            <p>171. *Klancher, Jon P. <hi rend="i">The Making of English Reading
                                Audiences, 1790-1832.</hi> Madison, WI: U of Wisconsin P, 1987.
                            $25.00. [For an exposition of the book’s central thesis, see
                            the author’s earlier article “From
                            ‘crowd’ to ‘audience’: The
                            Making of an English Mass Readership in the Nineteenth
                            Century.” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi> 50 (1983): 155-73.]</p>
            <pb id="p22-56" n="56"/>
            <p>172. Macmillan, Duncan. <hi rend="i">Painting in Scotland: The Golden
                                Age.</hi> Exh. cat. Oxford, Oxon.: Phaidon P, in association with
                            the Talbot Rice Art Centre, the University of Edinburgh, and the Tate
                            Gallery, London, 1986. £19.95 cloth/£12.95 paper.
                            [Macmillan’s book was published in conjunction with an
                            exhibition held at the Talbot Rice Art Centre in Edinburgh (8-31 Aug.
                            1986) and the Tate (15 Oct. 1986-4 Jan. 1987). It contains extensive
                            sections on Gavin Hamilton’s proto-classicism of the 1760s
                            and 1770s (31-42) and the works of the two Runciman brothers (43-62),
                            which are illustrated in eight color plates and numerous half-tone
                            reproductions.]</p>
            <p>173. Mai, Ekkehard, and Anke Repp-Eckert, eds. <hi rend="i">Triumph und
                                Tod des Helden: Europäische Historienmalerei von Rubens
                                bis Manet.</hi> Exh. cat. Milan, It.: Electa, for the Museen der
                            Stadt Köln, 1987. [The exhibition was to be seen at the
                            Wallraf-Richartz-Museum in Cologne, W. Ger. (30 Oct. 1987-10 Jan. 1988),
                            at the Kunsthaus in Zurich, Switz. (3 Mar.-24 Apr. 1988), and at the
                            Musée des Beaux-Arts in Lyon, Fr. (18 May-17 July 1988). On
                            show in the British section were paintings, drawings, and engravings by
                            and after such artists as Barry (#96), Copley (#97, 110), Fuseli
                            (#98-99, 122-24), Gillray (#131-33), Gavin Hamilton (#100, 141-43),
                            Kauffmann (#83), Trumbull (#101, 157-58), and West (#102-03, 159). The
                            massive catalogue contains essays on English history painting from 1750
                            to 1830 by David Irwin (81-90), and on West’s “The
                            Death of Nelson” by Robert Rosenblum (91-94).]</p>
            <p>174. *Metzger, Lore. <hi rend="i">One Foot in Eden: Modes of Pastoral in
                                Romantic Poetry.</hi> Chapel Hill, NC: U of North Carolina P, 1986.
                            $25.00. [Said to include a discussion of the pastoral mode in
                            Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi>]</p>
            <p>175. Ostriker, Alicia. “Dancing at the Devil’s
                            Party: Some Notes on Politics and Poetry.” <hi rend="i">Critical Inquiry</hi> 13
(1987): 579-96. [“My education
                            in political poetry begins with William Blake’s remark about
                            John Milton in <hi rend="i">The Marriage</hi> . . .”
                            (579).]</p>
            <p>176. Rajan, Tilottama. “The Supplement of Reading.”
                                <hi rend="i">New Literary History</hi> 17 (1986): 573-94. [Treats
                            Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> and
                            his <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> in a
                            theoretical context (580-82), the phenomenon described by the author as
                            “the disappearance of narrative, dramatic, or conceptual
                            actualization” (573) in romantic texts.]</p>
            <p>177. *Reiman, Donald H. <hi rend="i">Romantic Texts and Contexts.</hi>
                            Columbia, MO: U of Missouri P, 1987. $32.00. [A selection of the
                            author’s essays and reviews concerned with romantic
                            literature.]</p>
            <p>178. Rousseau, G. S. “ ‘Till we have built
                            Jerusalem’: The Berkeley Symposium and the Future of
                            Literature and Science.” <hi rend="i">Annals of
                                Scholarship</hi> 4 (1986): 1-21. [The introductory essay to a spec.
                            issue on “Science and the Imagination;” places the
                            Blakean contributions by Nelson Hilton and Mark L. Greenberg into a
                            bigger context; for the latter, see <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
                                Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987): 57, #53 and 59.]</p>
            <p>179. *Summerfield, Geoffrey. <hi rend="i">Fantasy and Reason:
                                Children’s Literature in the Eighteenth Century.</hi>
                            London: Methuen, 1984. £20.00. [Mrs. Barbauld, Godwin,
                            Wollstonecraft, and Blake are amongst the authors who are the subject of
                            Summerfield’s study.]</p>
            <p>180. Tscherny, Nadia. “Likeness in Early Romantic
                            Portraiture.” <hi rend="i">Art Journal</hi> 46 (1987):
                            193-99. [Besides Reynolds, Northcote, Opie, and Gainsborough,
                            Fuseli’s early self-portrait at the Victoria and Albert
                            Museum is briefly analyzed.]</p>
            <p>181. Westfehling, Uwe. <hi rend="i">Englische Druckgraphik des
                                späten 18. und frühen 19. Jahrhunderts.</hi>
                            Exh. cat. Cologne, W. Ger.: Wallraf-Richartz-Museum der Stadt
                            Köln, 1984. [The exhibition was to be seen at the WRM from 30
                            Nov. 1984-3 Feb. 1985; the catalogue includes entries for prints by
                            Bartolozzi, Blake (#142-43), Boydell, Gillray, Heath, Mortimer,
                            Woollett, et al.]</p>
            <p>182. Yates, Frances A. “Transformations of Dante’s
                            Ugolino.” <hi rend="i">Renaissance and Reform: The Italian
                                Contribution.</hi> Collected Essays 2. London: Routledge, 1983.
                            30-58. [A reprint of the late Dame Frances Yates’s classic
                            study in Dantesque iconography of 1951. Fuseli’s,
                            Blake’s, and Flaxman’s pictorial translations of
                            the Ugolino story are discussed on pages 53-55.]</p>
            <p>
              <hi rend="i">See also #26, above.</hi>
            </p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Some Contemporary Artists and Authors</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>183. *Ayer, A. J. <hi rend="i">Thomas Paine.</hi> London: Secker, 1988.
                            £12.95.</p>
            <p>184. “Benjamin West, 1738-1820.” <hi rend="i">National Galleries of Scotland News</hi>
Summer [1987]: n. pag. [An
                            unsigned note recording the acquisition of West’s
                            “Alexander III of Scotland Rescued from the Fury of a Stag by
                            the Intrepidity of Colin Fitzgerald,” commissioned in 1784,
                            for the National Gallery at Edinburgh; the painting is reproduced in
                            color.]</p>
            <p>185. *Bernstein, Samuel. <hi rend="i">Joel Barlow: A Connecticut Yankee
                                in an Age of Revolution.</hi> Cliff Island, ME: Ultima Thule P,
                            1985. $5.95.</p>
            <pb id="p22-57" n="57"/>
            <p>186. Brantley, Richard E. “Charles Wesley’s
                            Experiential Art.” <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Life</hi>
                            ns 11.2 (1987): 1-12. [The younger Wesley’s poems and hymns
                            seen as “a record of common feeling” (1), and his
                            view of “experience and subjectivity” interpreted
                            as an anticipation of “the Romantic apotheosis of
                            self” (2); also compares Wesley with Blake.]</p>
            <p>187. Claeys, Gregory. “William Godwin’s Critique of
                            Democracy and Republicanism and Its Sources.” <hi rend="i">History of European
Ideas</hi> 7 (1986): 253-69.</p>
            <p>188. Conger, Syndy McMillen. “The Sentimental Logic of
                            Wollstonecraft’s Prose.” <hi rend="i">Prose
                                Studies</hi> 10 (1987): 143-58.</p>
            <p>189. Cozzens, Christine Suzanne. “The Magic Circle: Elizabeth
                            Inchbald, Mary Hays, and Mary Wollstonecraft and the Politics of
                            Domestic Fiction.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
                                International</hi> 48 (1987): 1209A. U of California, Berkeley,
                            1986.</p>
            <p>190. Cronin, Richard. “Carps and <hi rend="i">Caleb
                                Williams.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Review</hi> 1
                            (1986): 35-48.</p>
            <p>191. *Denizot, Paul. “Quelques réflexions sur <hi rend="i">A Vindication of the Rights of
Woman.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Bulletin de la Société
                                d’Études Anglo-Américaines des
                                XVIIe et XVIIIe Siècles</hi> 23 (1986): 79-89.</p>
            <p>192. *Dole, George, ed. and trans. <hi rend="i">Emanuel Swedenborg:
                                Divine Love and Wisdom.</hi> New York, NY: Swedenborg Foundation,
                            1986. $6.95. [A new translation, not part of the well-known
                            “Student Edition” of Swedenborg’s
                            theological writings.]</p>
            <p>193. *Douglas, Aileen. “Anna Seward’s Annotated
                            Copy of <hi rend="i">Caleb Williams.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Princeton University
Library Chronicle</hi> 49 (1987): 74-78.</p>
            <p>194. *Duhet, Paule-Marie. “Bonheur et douleur dans <hi rend="i">Elements of Morality for the
Use of Children</hi>
                            (1790-1791) de Mary Wollstonecraft.” <hi rend="i">Le Corps et
                                l’âme en Grande-Bretagne au XVIIIe
                                siècle.</hi> Ed. Paul-Gabriel Boucé and Suzy
                            Halimi. Langues et Langages 14. Paris, Fr.: Publications de la Sorbonne,
                            1986. 167-77. [On Wollstonecraft’s translation of
                            Salzmann’s <hi rend="i">Elementarbuch</hi>, which was
                            illustrated with engravings by Blake.]</p>
            <p>195. *Duhet, Paule-Marie. “Mary Wollstonecraft, <hi rend="i">A
                                Vindication of the Rights of Woman</hi> (1792): Bibliographie
                            sélective et critique.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin de
                                la Société d’Études
                                Anglo-Américaines des XVIIe et XVIIIe
                                Siècles</hi> 23 (1986): 25-36.</p>
            <p>196. Durey, Michael. “Thomas Paine’s Apostles:
                            Radical Emigrés and the Triumph of Jeffersonian
                            Republicanism.” <hi rend="i">William and Mary Quarterly</hi>
                            3rd ser. 44 (1987): 661-88.</p>
            <p>197. Durey, Michael. “William Cobbett, Military Corruption and
                            London Radicalism in the Early 1790s.” <hi rend="i">Proceedings of the American
Philosophical Society</hi> 131 (1987):
                            348-66. [Should be of interest to those readers who would like to learn
                            more about Cobbett, Priestley, and “the hapless Soldiers
                            sigh” in Blake’s London.]</p>
            <p>198. *Dyck, Ian, ed. <hi rend="i">Citizen of the World: Essays on Thomas
                                Paine.</hi> Bromley, Greater London: Christopher Helm, 1988.
                            £14.95.</p>
            <p>199. Farr, Richard. “New Thoughts on Godwin’s
                            Mother.” <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi> ns 48
                            (1987): 269-78.</p>
            <p>200. *Feldman, Burton, and Robert R. Richardson, eds. <hi rend="i">William Godwin: The
Pantheon: or, Ancient History of the Gods of
                                Greece and Rome.</hi> Myth and Romanticism [series]. New York, NY:
                            Garland, 1984. $80.00.</p>
            <p>201. *Foot, Michael, and Isaac Kramnick, eds. <hi rend="i">The Thomas
                                Paine Reader.</hi> Harmondsworth, Mddx.: Penguin, 1987.
                            £5.95.</p>
            <p>202. *Hammer, Sabine. <hi rend="i">Angelika Kauffmann.</hi> Vaduz,
                            Liechtenstein: Staedlezo, 1987.</p>
            <p>203. *Herrick, Jim. “Thomas Paine’s 250th
                            Anniversary.” <hi rend="i">New Humanist</hi> 102.1 (1987):
                            12-13.</p>
            <p>204. Jolles, Evelyn B. <hi rend="i">G. A. Bürgers Ballade</hi>
                            Lenore <hi rend="i">in England.</hi> Sprache und Literatur: Regensburger
                            Arbeiten zur Anglistik und Amerikanistik 7. [2nd ed.] Frankfort on the
                            Main, W. Ger.: Lang, 1987. SFr 44.80. [The third part of this study,
                            which was first published in Nuremberg and Regensburg in 1974, traces
                            the history of the British reception of Bürger’s
                            ballad by analyzing the translations that were published in England
                            between 1790 and 1798. Stanley’s version of 1796, which was
                            illustrated with engravings after designs by Blake in the second and
                            considerably revised edition, is discussed at length on pages 93-116,
                            and the illustrations are at least mentioned in passing on pages
                            107-08.]</p>
            <p>205. Jones, Chris. “Godwin to Mary: The First
                            Letter.” <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Review</hi> 1 (1986):
                            61-74.</p>
            <p>206. Kramnick, Isaac. “Eighteenth-Century Science and Radical
                            Social Theory: The Case of Joseph Priestley’s Scientific
                            Liberalism.” <hi rend="i">Journal of British Studies</hi>
                            25.1 (1986): 1-30.</p>
            <p>207. Kuzniar, Alice A. “Signs of the Future: Reading (in)
                            Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Aussichten.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Seminar: A Journal of
Germanic Studies</hi> 22 (1986):
                            1-19.</p>
            <p>208. Lavater, Johann Caspar. <hi rend="i">Sämtliche kleinere
                                prosaische Schriften vom Jahr 1763-1783.</hi> Winterthur, Switz.
                            1784-1785. Hildesheim, W. Ger.: Olms, 1987.</p>
            <pb id="p22-58" n="58"/>
            <p>209. Maison, Margaret. Mary Wollstonecraft and Mr. Cresswick.”
                                <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 34 (1987): 467-68.</p>
            <p>210. *Morvan, Alain. “Passion et idéologie dans les
                            romans de Mary Wollstonecraft.” <hi rend="i">Bulletin de la
                                Société d’Études
                                Anglo-Américaines des XVIIe et XVIIIe
                                Siècles</hi> 23 (1986): 65-78.</p>
            <p>211. Mulford, Carla Jean. “Joel Barlow’s Letters,
                            1775-1788.” <hi rend="i">Dissertation Abstracts
                                International</hi> 45 (1984): 1753A. U of Delaware.</p>
            <p>212. *Myers, Mitzi. “Impeccable Governesses, Rational Dames,
                            and Moral Mothers: Mary Wollstonecraft and the Female Tradition in
                            Georgian Children’s Books.” <hi rend="i">Children’s Literature</hi> 14
(1986): 31-59.</p>
            <p>213. Obermeier, Siegfried. <hi rend="i">Die Muse von Rom: Angelika
                                Kauffmann und ihre Zeit.</hi> Frankfort on the Main, W. Ger.:
                            Oberon, 1987. DM 25.00.</p>
            <p>214. Peters, Anne. <hi rend="i">Francesco Bartolozzi: Studien zur
                                Druckgraphik nach Handzeichnungen.</hi> Diss. U of Cologne, W. Ger.,
                            1985. Duisburg, W. Ger.: privately printed, 1987. [Studies
                            Bartolozzi’s engravings after drawings by Guercino,
                            Castiglione, Holbein, Leonardo, Carracci, etc. (109-38) in the context
                            of the history of collecting (15-54) and engraving (54-108) in
                            eighteenth-century Britain. Besides a brief chapter on William Young
                            Ottley (138-40), and another on the techniques employed for printed
                            “facsimile” reproductions after old master
                            drawings (151-53), the author also supplies a catalogue of
                            Bartolozzi’s works in this genre (189-224). The 286
                            illustrations which were part of the original dissertation had to be
                            reduced to 32 plates in the published version.]</p>
            <p>215. Roth, Martin. “Tom Paine and American
                            Loneliness.” <hi rend="i">Early American Literature</hi> 22
                            (1987): 175-82.</p>
            <p>216. Schotte, Edith. “Eine frühe politische
                            Kampfschrift für die Rechte der Frau: Christian Gotthilf
                            Salzmanns Standpunkt zu den Auffassungen von Mary
                            Wollstonecraft.” <hi rend="i">Zeitschrift für
                                Geschichtswissenschaft</hi> 36 (1988): 226-31. [Wollstonecraft
                            translated Salzmann’s <hi rend="i">Elementarbuch</hi> into
                            English; Salzmann translated Wollstonecraft’s <hi rend="i">Vindication</hi> into
German. It is this German version of the <hi rend="i">Rights of Woman</hi> of 1793 which is studied in the
                            present article.]</p>
            <p>217. *Sheriton, Janet. “Reason and Romance: Mary
                            Wollstonecraft.” <hi rend="i">New Humanist</hi> 102.9 (1987):
                            8-13.</p>
            <p>218. Simms, Karl N. “‘Caleb Williams’
                            Godwin: Things as They Are Written.” <hi rend="i">Studies in
                                Romanticism</hi> 26 (1987): 343-63.</p>
            <p>219. Stafford, Barbara Maria. “‘Peculiar
                            Marks’: Lavater and the Countenance of Blemished
                            Thought.” <hi rend="i">Art Journal</hi> 46 (1987): 185-92.
                            [Includes a brief discussion of Blake’s aesthetic theory in
                            the context supplied by Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essays on
                                Physiognomy.</hi>]</p>
            <p>220. Tomory, Peter. “Angelika Kauffmann’s
                            ‘Costanza.’ ” <hi rend="i">Burlington
                                Magazine</hi> 129 (1987): 668-69.</p>
            <p>221. *Tysdahl, B. J. “A Defence of Mary
                            Wollstonecraft’s Last Novel.” <hi rend="i">Proceedings from the Second Nordic
Conference for English
                                Studies.</hi> Ed. Håkan Ringbom and Matti Rissanen.
                            Publications of the Research Institute of the Åbo Akademi
                            Foundation 92. Åbo, Finland: Åbo Akademi, 1984.
                            463-75.</p>
            <p>222. *Vincent, Bernard. <hi rend="i">Thomas Paine ou la religion de la
                                liberté.</hi> Paris, Fr.: Aubier, 1987. [A
                            translation.]</p>
            <p>223. Warren, Leland E. “<hi rend="i">Caleb Williams</hi> and
                            the ‘Fall’ into Writing.” <hi rend="i">Mosaic</hi> 20.1 (1987): 57-69.</p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Some Blake Scholars and Collectors</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>224. Ash, Beth Sharon. “Jewish Hermeneutics and Contemporary
                            Theories of Textuality: Hartman, Bloom, and Derrida.” <hi rend="i">Modern
Philology</hi> 85 (1987): 65-80.</p>
            <p>225. *Beckson, Karl. <hi rend="i">Arthur Symons: A Life.</hi> Oxford,
                            Oxon.: Clarendon P, 1987. £35.00.</p>
            <p>226. *Bradley, John Lewis, and Ian Ousby, eds. <hi rend="i">The
                                Correspondence of John Ruskin and Charles Eliot Norton.</hi>
                            Cambridge, Cambs.: Cambridge UP, 1987. $59.50. [Both correspondents are
                            to be considered as—at least—minor figures in the
                            history of nineteenth-century Blake collections and Blake
                            publications.]</p>
            <p>227. *Bronowski, Rita, et al. <hi rend="i">Jacob Bronowski: A
                                Retrospective.</hi> Spec. issue of <hi rend="i">Leonardo</hi> 18.4
                            (1987). [Other contributors include Gerald Holton, Jonas Salk, Bruce
                            Mazlish, Clifford Grobstein, and Paul Saltman.]</p>
            <p>228. Cumming, Mark. “Wagner, Verlaine, and Arthur
                            Symons’ ‘Parsifal.’ ” <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi> 25.1
(1987): 66-73.</p>
            <p>229. Eaves, Morris. “Blake as Conceived: The Endurance of S.
                            Foster Damon.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
                                Quarterly</hi> 21 (1988): 132-37. [A “reprint”
                            (i.e., an advance printing) of the preface to the new edition of
                            Damon’s <hi rend="i">Blake Dictionary</hi> (see #53, above);
                            supplies a critical assessment of Damon’s role in the
                            academic institutionalization of Blake studies and an outline of those
                            critical paradigma which essentially shaped the history of Blake
                            scholarship from c. 1875 to c. 1975.]</p>
            <pb id="p22-59" n="59"/>
            <p>230. Gonzalez, Alexander. “The Achievement of Darrell
                            Figgis’s <hi rend="i">Children of Earth</hi>: Realism and
                            Folk Custom.” <hi rend="i">Éire-Ireland</hi> 22.3
                            (1987): 129-43. [An appraisal of a novel, published in 1918, by the
                            author of <hi rend="i">The Paintings of William Blake.</hi>]</p>
            <p>231. Goyder, George. “The Origins of the William Blake
                            Trust.” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21
                            (1988): 150-51. [The author, himself a trustee of the first hour, adds
                            to and corrects the late Sir Geoffrey Keynes’s account of the
                            Trust’s early history.]</p>
            <p>232. Gutiérrez, Félix Martín.
                            “Hacia una historia literaria crítica sobre el
                            romanticismo inglés y americano 1920-1960.” <hi rend="i">Filología
Moderna</hi> 73 (1981): 77-117.
                            [Discusses Blake scholarship in general, and Frye’s <hi rend="i">Fearful
Symmetry</hi> in particular on pages 107-17.]</p>
            <p>233. Harmer, Michael, et al. <hi rend="i">Sir Geoffrey Keynes 1887-1982,
                                Surgeon and Scholar: A Tribute.</hi> Suppl. to <hi rend="i">Annals
                                of the Royal College of Surgeons of England</hi> (1983). London:
                            Royal College of Surgeons of England, n.d. [1983]. [Five commemorative
                            essays, including one on Keynes’s achievements as a
                            bibliographer by Nicolas Barker, and “A List of the Writings
                            of Sir Geoffrey Keynes,” compiled by William R. LeFanu
                            (16-20).]</p>
            <p>234. *Healey, R. M., ed. <hi rend="i">Grigson at Eighty: Tributes from
                                Friends and Admirers.</hi> Cambridge, Cambs.: Rampant Lions P, 1985.
                            [A <hi rend="i">festschrift</hi> for the poet-scholar who died in the
                            year of the publication of this limited edition of 375 copies.]</p>
            <p>235. Jeffrey, Ian. “Neo-Romanticism Against Itself: The Case
                            of Geoffrey Grigson.” <hi rend="i">A Paradise Lost: The
                                Neo-Romantic Imagination in Britain 1935-55.</hi> Ed. David Mellor.
                            Exh. cat. London: Lund Humphries, in association with the Barbican Art
                            Gallery, 1987. 129-35. [<hi rend="i">See also #246, below.</hi>]</p>
            <p>236. *Lea, F. A. <hi rend="i">Lawrence and Murry: A Twofold Vision.</hi>
                            London: Brentham P, 1985. £2.95.</p>
            <p>237. McKitterick, David. “The Young Geoffrey
                            Keynes.” <hi rend="i">Book Collector</hi> 36 (1987): 491-517.
                            [Contains a lot of background information on the compilation and the
                            reception of the 1921 <hi rend="i">Bibliography of William Blake</hi>
                            that is not to be found in its author’s own account of the
                            history of that milestone in Blake scholarship, i.e., in his
                            “Religio Bibliographici,” or elsewhere.]</p>
            <p>238. *Moynihan, Robert. <hi rend="i">A Recent Imagining: Interviews with
                                Harold Bloom, Geoffrey Hartman, J. Hillis Miller, Paul de Man.</hi>
                            Hamden, CT: Archon Books-Shoe String P, 1986. $17.50.</p>
            <p>239. Müller, Marianne. “Humanistisches
                            Literaturerbe im Dienste des Überlebens der Menschheit: Zu
                            Northrop Fryes Funktionsverständnis und
                            Traditionsauffassung.” <hi rend="i">Wissenschaftliche
                                Zeitschrift der Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin:
                                Gesellschaftswissenschaftliche Reihe</hi> 36 (1987): 313-18. [In the
                            1960s Frye provoked some of the best contributions to Marxist literary
                            theory that are known to me (see, e.g., Robert Weimann’s 
<hi rend="i">Literaturgeschichte und Mythologie: Methodologische und
                                historische Studien</hi>, 3rd ed., Berlin, E. Ger.: Aufbau, 1974);
                            it comes as some surprise then, that in the late 1980s one finds East
                            German critics attempting to pocket Frye’s myth criticism by
                            reading him in a “revisionist” way and stressing
                            the “humanitarian” basis of his theory of
                            literature.]</p>
            <p>240. *Raine, Kathleen, and K. D. Sethna. <hi rend="i">The English
                                Language and the Indian Spirit: Correspondence.</hi> Pondicherry,
                            India: [n.p. known], 1986. [Both correspondents have contributed to the
                            study of Blake whose works are likely to be one of the subjects
                            discussed in their letters.]</p>
            <p>241. Salusinsky, Imre, et al. “Special Section: Northrop
                            Frye.” <hi rend="i">AUMLA</hi> 66 (1986): 154-259. [Articles
                            by Salusinsky, K. K. Ruthven, David Lawton, Mary Dove, Catherine Runcie,
                            and Eric J. Sharpe, plus an interview with Frye.]</p>
            <p>242. *Sharma, L. R. <hi rend="i">In Defence of J. Middleton Murry.</hi>
                            Allahabad, India: Dikshit, 1986. Rs 150.00.</p>
            <p>243. Stokes, John. “Arthur Symons’s
                            ‘Romantic Movement’: Transitional Attitudes and
                            the Victorian Precedent.” <hi rend="i">English Literature in
                                Transition 1880-1920</hi> 31 (1988): 133-50.</p>
            <p>244. Watkinson, Ray. “Shields in Manchester: The Making of an
                            Artist.” <hi rend="i">Journal of Pre-Raphaelite and Aesthetic
                                Studies</hi> 1.1 (1987): 15-27. [The Manchester City Art
                            Gallery’s version of Shields’s “William
                            Blake’s Room (3 Fountain Court), Strand” appears
                            as fig. 12 and is twice mentioned as an example for the
                            artist’s “significant works” (26).
                            There are ten pages (28-37) of reproductions.]</p>
            <p>
              <hi rend="i">See also #124, above.</hi>
            </p>
          </div3>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>
                <hi rend="i">Some Blakean Echoes in the Twentieth Century</hi>
              </title>
            </head>
            <p>245. *Lima, Marcelo. <hi rend="i">Hommage à William Blake:
                                Poème-objet bilingue
                                brésilien-français en quatre lithotriptyques
                                en couleur.</hi> Grospierres, Fr.: Aux Enfants de la Balle, 1984. Fr
                            400.00. [Hitherto, I have not been able to get hold of a copy of this
                            limited edition through my French bookdealer. It may well be that this
                            suite of color lithographs is out of print by the time it gets listed in
                            “Blake and His Circle.”]</p>
            <pb id="p22-60" n="60"/>
              <figure n="AParadiseLost.22.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="302"></figure>
            <p>246. Mellor, David, ed. <hi rend="i">A Paradise Lost: The Neo-Romantic
                                Imagination in Britain 1935-55.</hi> Exh. cat. London: Lund
                            Humphries, in association with the Barbican Art Gallery, 1987.
                            £14.95. [Published on the occasion of an exhibition of works by
                            such artists as Cecil Collins, Henry Moore, Ceri Richards, John Piper,
                            David Jones, Robert Colquhoun, John Minton, Michael Ayrton, and Graham
                            Sutherland that was presented at the Barbican from 21 May-19 July 1987.
                            The catalogue is profusely illustrated with an anthology of drawings,
                            paintings, prints, and photographs, many of which refer back to the
                            example of Blake’s Virgil wood engravings and/or the prints
                            and drawings of the “Ancients.” One of the
                            catalogue essays is listed separately as #235, above.]</p>
            <p>247. *Robinson, Abby. <hi rend="i">The Dick and Jane.</hi> New York, NY:
                            Dell, 1985. $14.95 cloth/$3.50 paper. [Refer to #370, below, to learn
                            about the Blakean plot of this novel.]</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Part IV Reviews of Works Cited Above and in Previous
                                Checklists</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>248. Abrams, Ann Uhry. <hi rend="i">The Valiant Hero: Benjamin West and
                            Grand-Style History Painting</hi> [20#283]. Reviewed by James T. Callow,
                            <hi rend="i">American Historical Review</hi> 91 (1986): 727-28.</p>
          <p>249. Adams, Hazard. <hi rend="i">Philosophy of the Literary Symbolic</hi>
                        [18#23]. Reviewed by (1) Martin Bickman, <hi rend="i">Philosophy and
                            Literature</hi> 8 (1984): 143-44; by (2) Wallace Martin, 
<hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 29 (1987): 242-45.</p>
          <p>250. Albright, Daniel. <hi rend="i">Lyricality in English Literature</hi>
                        [20#254]. Reviewed by (1) Christopher Clausen, <hi rend="i">Sewanee
                            Review</hi> 95 (1987): 633-39; by (2) David E. Latané, Jr.,
                            <hi rend="i">South Atlantic Review</hi> 52 (1987): 107-09; by (3)
                        Nicholas Roe, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 34 (1987): 114-15.</p>
          <p>251. Aldridge, A. Owen. <hi rend="i">Thomas Paine’s American
                            Ideology</hi> [21#174]. Reviewed by Ralph Ketcham, <hi rend="i">American
                            Historical Review</hi> 91 (1986): 174.</p>
          <p>252. Alford, Steven E. <hi rend="i">Irony and the Logic of the Romantic
                            Imagination</hi> [20#255]. Reviewed by M. T. S. [Mark T. Smith], <hi rend="i">RMB
for 1984</hi> (1985): 96-98.</p>
          <p>253. Altick, Richard D. <hi rend="i">Paintings from Books: Art and Literature
                            in Britain, 1760-1900</hi> [21#143]. Reviewed by (1) Kenneth Garlick,
                            <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 35 (1988): 134-35; by (2) Michael
                        Hancher, <hi rend="i">Victorian Studies</hi> 30 (1987): 421-22; by (3)
                        Dianne Sachko Macleod, <hi rend="i">Victorian Poetry</hi> 25 (1987): 251-57;
                        by (4) Martin Meisel, <hi rend="i">Nineteenth-Century Literature</hi> 42
                        (1987): 97-101; by (5) Leonée Ormond, <hi rend="i">Word and
                            Image</hi> 3 (1987): 321-22; by (6) Clive Wainwright, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 126
(1987): 301-02.</p>
          <p>254. Altizer, Thomas J. J. <hi rend="i">History as Apocalypse</hi> [21#144].
                        Reviewed by (1) Richard Kenneth Emmerson, <hi rend="i">Modern Language
                            Quarterly</hi> 46 (1985): 429-39; by (2) Steven Goldsmith, <hi rend="i">Blake / An
Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1987): 154-57; by (3) Paul
                        Merkley, <hi rend="i">American Historical Review</hi> 92 (1987): 97-98; by
                        (4) Eugene Webb, <hi rend="i">Religion and Literature</hi> 19.2 (1987):
                        87-90.</p>
          <p>255. Anderson, Ross, ed. <hi rend="i">A Brush with Shakespeare: The Bard in
                            Painting, 1780-1910</hi> [22#157]. Reviewed by Peter Cummings, 
<hi rend="i">Shakespeare on Film Newsletter</hi> 11.1 (1986): 2.</p>
          <p>256. Aubrey, Bryan. <hi rend="i">Watchmen of Eternity: Blake’s
                            Debt to Jacob Boehme</hi> [21#22]. Reviewed by George Mills Harper, 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987): 25-27.</p>
          <p>257. Ayer, A. J. <hi rend="i">Thomas Paine</hi> [22#183]. Reviewed by Maurice
                        Cranston, <hi rend="i">Times Higher Education Supplement</hi> 6 May 1988:
                        24.</p>
          <pb id="p22-61" n="61"/>
          <p>258. Baine, Rodney M., with the assistance of Mary R. Baine. <hi rend="i">The
                            Scattered Portions: William Blake’s Biological Symbolism</hi>
                        [21#23]. Reviewed by (1) Andrew Lincoln, <hi rend="i">Review of English
                            Studies</hi> ns 39 (1988): 117-18; by (2) Molly Anne Rothenberg, 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 21 (1987): 127-33.</p>
          <p>259. Baker, Carlos. <hi rend="i">The Echoing Green: Romanticism, Modernism,
                            and the Phenomena of Transference in Poetry</hi> [20#257]. Reviewed by
                        (1) Philip Hobsbaum, <hi rend="i">Times Higher Education Supplement</hi> 27
                        July 1984: 16; by (2) Edward Larrissy, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English
                            Studies</hi> 18 (1988): 335-36.</p>
          <p>260. Barrell, John. <hi rend="i">The Political Theory of Painting from
                            Reynolds to Hazlitt:</hi> “<hi rend="i">The Body of the
                            Public</hi>” [21#25]. Reviewed by (1) David Carrier, <hi rend="i">Journal of
Aesthetics and Art Criticism</hi> 45 (1987): 420-21;
                        by (2) Andrew Hemingway, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi> 10 (1987): 381-95; by
                        (3) L. R. Matteson, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 24 (1987): 1205; by (4) W. J.
                        T. Mitchell, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 21 (1987): 91-95;
                        by (5) C. L. R. [Carlo L. Ragghianti], <hi rend="i">Critica
                            d’Arte</hi> 4th ser. 52.13 (1987): 6-7; by (6) David H.
                        Solkin, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 129 (1987): 460-61; (7) see
                        also #20, above.</p>
          <p>261. Bate, Jonathan. <hi rend="i">Shakespeare and the English Romantic
                            Imagination</hi> [21#145]. Reviewed by (1) Larry S. Champion, <hi rend="i">English
Studies</hi> 68 (1987): 285-88; by (2) Harriett
                        Hawkins, <hi rend="i">Essays in Criticism</hi> 37 (1987): 170-78; by (3)
                        Angela Leighton, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 31 July 1987:
                        814; by (4) Nicholas Roe, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 35 (1988):
                        128-29; by (5) *Donald Sultana, <hi rend="i">British Book News</hi> Aug.
                        1986: 483-84.</p>
          <p>262. Beckson, Karl. <hi rend="i">Arthur Symons: A Life</hi> [22#225].
                        Reviewed by (1) Isobel Murray, <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi>
                        ns 49 (1987): 152; by (2) Edmund White, <hi rend="i">Times Literary
                            Supplement</hi> 13-19 Nov. 1987: 1239-40.</p>
          <p>263. Bellin, Harvey F., and Darrell Ruhl, eds. <hi rend="i">Blake and
                            Swedenborg: Opposition Is True Friendship: The Sources of William
                            Blake’s Arts in the Writings of Emanuel Swedenborg</hi>
                        [21#27]. Reviewed by Inge Jonsson, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
                            Quarterly</hi> 21 (1988): 158-60.</p>
          <p>264. Bernstein, Samuel. <hi rend="i">Joel Barlow: A Connecticut Yankee in an
                            Age of Revolution</hi> [22#185]. Reviewed by James Kirby Martin, 
<hi rend="i">Historian</hi> 50 (1987): 99-100.</p>
          <p>265. Bindman, David, ed. <hi rend="i">Colour Versions of William
                            Blake’s Job Designs from the Circle of John Linnell:
                            Facsimiles of the New Zealand and Collins Sets and the Fitzwilliam
                            Museum Plates</hi> [21#1]; and <hi rend="i">William
                            Blake’s</hi> Illustrations of the Book of Job: <hi rend="i">The Engravings and
Related Material with Essays, Catalogue of States
                            and Printings, Commentary on the Plates and Documentary Record</hi>
                        [21#2]. Reviewed together by (1) David McKitterick, <hi rend="i">Book
                            Collector</hi> 36 (1987): 305-20; by (2) Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Burlington
Magazine</hi> 129 (1987): 747-48; by (3) Andrew Wilton, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 14 Aug.
1987: 879.</p>
          <p>266. Bloom, Harold. <hi rend="i">Agon: Towards a Theory of Revisionism</hi>
                        [21#34]. Reviewed by (1) Steven Gould Axelrod, <hi rend="i">Modern
                            Philology</hi> 81 (1984): 290-97; by (2) Thomas R. Frosch, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth
Circle</hi> 15 (1984): 87-91; by (3) Charles Molesworth, <hi rend="i">Partisan Review</hi> 51 (1984):
155-58.</p>
          <p>267. Bloom, Harold. <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> [20#50]. Reviewed by
                        Peter Otto, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987):
                        29-31.</p>
          <p>268. Bogel, Fredric V. <hi rend="i">Literature and Insubstantiality in Later
                            Eighteenth-Century England</hi> [21#148]. Reviewed by (1) *Stephen D.
                        Cox, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 27
                        (1986): 299-304; by (2) Robert Markley, <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 27
                        (1985): 211-14; by (3) Serge Soupel, <hi rend="i">Études
                            Anglaises</hi> 38 (1985): 465 [this last entry is a correction of
                        #251(3) in last year’s checklist].</p>
          <p>269. Boime, Albert. <hi rend="i">A Social History of Modern Art.</hi> Vol. 1
                        [21#149] briefly reviewed in <hi rend="i">Gazette des Beaux-Arts</hi> 6th
                        ser. 110 (1987): “La Chronique des Arts” Dec. 1987:
                        24.</p>
          <p>270. Bolcom, William. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience: A
                            Musical Illumination of the Poems of William Blake</hi> [see 21#228,
                        234-35]. Reviewed by Jackie DiSalvo, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
                            Quarterly</hi> 21 (1988): 152-57.</p>
          <p>271. Borck, Jim Springer, ed. <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: A Current
                            Bibliography.</hi> Vol. 7 for 1981 [20#9] reviewed by (1) Thomas
                        Lockwood, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi> 18 (1988): 277-78.
                        Vol. 8 for 1982 [21#8] reviewed by (2) Peter Sabor, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of
                            English Studies</hi> 18 (1988): 278-80.</p>
          <p>272. Bracher, Mark. <hi rend="i">“Being
                            Form’d”: Thinking Through Blake’s</hi>
                        Milton [20#51]. Reviewed by (1) D. V. E. [David V. Erdman], <hi rend="i">RMB
                            for 1985</hi> (1986): 83; by (2) Brian Wilkie, <hi rend="i">Blake / An
                            Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987): 43-44.</p>
          <p>273. Bradley, John Lewis, and Ian Ousby, eds. <hi rend="i">The Correspondence
                            of John Ruskin and Charles Eliot Norton</hi> [22#226]. Reviewed by (1)
                        A. R. Vogeler, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 25 (1988): 754; by (2) Raymond
                        Williams, <hi rend="i">London Review of Books</hi> 25 June 1987: 13-14.</p>
          <p>274. Brantley, Richard E. <hi rend="i">Locke, Wesley, and the Method of
                            English Romanticism</hi> [18#163]. Reviewed by (1) Richard Fadem, 
<hi rend="i">Philosophy and Literature</hi> 10 (1986): 120-21; by (2) A. J.
                        Sambrook, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi> 82 (1987): 922-23; by (3)
                        Ronald A. Sharp, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi>
                        86 (1987): 563-65; by (4) Roger Sharrock, <hi rend="i">Notes and
                            Queries</hi> ns 34 (1987): 405-06; by (5) Ernest Tuveson, <hi rend="i">Studies in
Romanticism</hi> 26 (1987): 468-71.</p>
          <pb id="p22-62" n="62"/>
          <p>275. Bridson, Gavin, and Geoffrey Wakeman. <hi rend="i">Printmaking and
                            Picture Printing: A Bibliographical Guide to Artistic and Industrial
                            Techniques in Britain 1750-1900</hi> [20#261]. Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Papers of
the Bibliographical Society of America</hi> 81 (1987):
                        381.</p>
          <p>276. Brosch, Renate, Joachim Möller, and Gretel Wagner. <hi rend="i">Shakespeare: Buch und
Bühne</hi> [22#159]. Reviewed
                        by (1) Manfred Pfister, <hi rend="i">Word and Image</hi> 3 (1987): 319-20;
                        by (2) Gretel Wagner, <hi rend="i">Deutsche Shakespeare-Gesellschaft West:
                            Jahrbuch</hi> (1987): 239-44.</p>
          <p>277. Bruntjen, Sven H. A. <hi rend="i">John Boydell (1719-1804): A Study of
                            Art Patronage and Publishing in Georgian London</hi> [20#262]. Reviewed
                        by Louise Lippincott, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21
                        (1987): 44-46.</p>
          <p>278. Busch, Werner. <hi rend="i">Joseph Wright of Derby: Das Experiment mit
                            der Luftpumpe: Eine Heilige Allianz zwischen Wissenschaft und
                            Religion</hi> [22#135]. Reviewed in <hi rend="i">Burlington
                            Magazine</hi> 129 (1987): 752.</p>
          <p>279. Butler, Marilyn, ed. <hi rend="i">Burke, Paine, Godwin, and the
                            Revolutionary Controversy</hi> [20#299]. Reviewed by Peter [H.]
                        Marshall, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi> 83 (1988): 160-61.</p>
          <p>280. Butler, Marilyn. <hi rend="i">Romantics, Rebels and Reactionaries:
                            English Literature and Its Background 1760-1830</hi> [17#174]. Reviewed
                        by (1) Richard Lehan, <hi rend="i">Nineteenth-Century Fiction</hi> 37
                        (1982): 248-49; by (2) *Raymond N. MacKenzie, <hi rend="i">Victorian
                            Periodicals Review</hi> 15 (1982): 149-51; by (3) *Susanna Roxman, 
<hi rend="i">Edda</hi> 83 (1983): 126-27.</p>
          <p>281. Cantor, Paul A. <hi rend="i">Creature and Creator: Myth-Making and
                            English Romanticism</hi> [20#263]. Reviewed by (1) *John Coulson, 
<hi rend="i">Journal of Theological Studies</hi> ns 37 (1986): 652-54; by
                        (2) Edward T. Duffy, <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 36 (1987):
                        206-07; by (3) Derek Roper, <hi rend="i">Times Higher Education
                            Supplement</hi> 28 Sept. 1984: 18.</p>
          <p>282. Cook, David. <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye: A Vision of the New World</hi>
                        [21#205]. Reviewed by (1) Michael Hurley, <hi rend="i">Queen’s
                            Quarterly</hi> 94 (1987): 219-22; by (2) Lauriat Lane, Jr., <hi rend="i">English
Studies in Canada</hi> 13 (1987): 349-52.</p>
          <p>283. Cook, Eleanor, et al., eds. <hi rend="i">Centre and Labyrinth: Essays in
                            Honour of Northrop Frye</hi> [18#167]. Reviewed by Gabriel Josipovici,
                            <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi> 82 (1987): 687-89.</p>
          <p>284. Crehan, Stewart. <hi rend="i">Blake in Context</hi> [18#39]. Reviewed by
                        (1) D. V. E. [David V. Erdman], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1984</hi> (1985): 101;
                        by (2) Ken Edward Smith, <hi rend="i">British Journal for Eighteenth-Century
                            Studies</hi> 10 (1987): 110; by (3) Frank Stack, <hi rend="i">Times
                            Higher Education Supplement</hi> 4 May 1984: 24.</p>
          <p>285. Crouan, Katharine. <hi rend="i">John Linnell: A Centennial
                            Exhibition</hi> [16#152]; and <hi rend="i">John Linnell: Truth to Nature
                            (A Centennial Exhibition)</hi> [22#147]. Reviewed together by A.-M. L.
                        [Anne-Marie S. Logan], <hi rend="i">Master Drawings</hi> 23-24 (1985-1986):
                        420-21.</p>
          <p>286. Di Salvo, Jackie. <hi rend="i">War of Titans: Blake’s
                            Critique of Milton and the Politics of Religion</hi> [18#44]. Reviewed
                        by (1) George Anthony Rosso, Jr., <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi>
                        26 (1987): 317-21; by (2) Joseph Wittreich, <hi rend="i">Milton
                            Quarterly</hi> 18 (1984): 92-94 [this review has previously been
                        recorded only s.v. Behrendt’s <hi rend="i">Moment of
                            Explosion.</hi>]</p>
          <p>287. Dorment, Richard. <hi rend="i">British Painting in the Philadelphia
                            Museum of Art: From the Seventeenth through the Nineteenth Century</hi>
                        [21#9]. Reviewed by J. Barter, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 24 (1987): 1043.</p>
          <p>288. Dowdey, Landon, ed. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas: The Torments of Love and
                            Jealousy in the Death and Judgment of Albion the Ancient Man</hi>, by
                        William Blake [18#3]. Reviewed by *Michael Patrick Hearn, <hi rend="i">American Book
Collector</hi> ns 5.3 (1984): 56.</p>
          <p>289. Dyck, Ian, ed. <hi rend="i">Citizen of the World: Essays on Thomas
                            Paine</hi> [22#198]. Reviewed by Maurice Cranston, <hi rend="i">Times
                            Higher Education Supplement</hi> 6 May 1988: 24.</p>
          <p>290. Eaves, Morris, and Michael Fischer, eds. <hi rend="i">Romanticism and
                            Contemporary Criticism</hi> [20#141/270]. Reviewed by (1) Marcel
                        Cornis-Pop, <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 29 (1987): 133-36; by (2) V. A. De
                        Luca, <hi rend="i">University of Toronto Quarterly</hi> 56 (1987): 575-87;
                        by (3) Michael Hurley, <hi rend="i">Queen’s Quarterly</hi> 94
                        (1987): 219-22; by (4) Virgil Nemoianu, <hi rend="i">MLN</hi> 102 (1987):
                        1220-22; (5) see also #21, above.</p>
          <p>291. Edwards, Ruth Dudley. <hi rend="i">Victor Gollancz: A Biography</hi>
                        [21#207]. Reviewed by Frank Bealey, <hi rend="i">Political Studies</hi> 36
                        (1988): 146-47.</p>
          <p>292. Eitner, Lorenz. <hi rend="i">An Outline of 19th Century European
                            Painting: From David through Cézanne</hi> [22#58]. Reviewed
                        by Philip Conisbee, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 25-31 Dec.
                        1987: 1426.</p>
          <p>293. Erdman, David V. <hi rend="i">Commerce des Lumières: John
                            Oswald and the British in Paris, 1790-1793</hi> [22#161]. Reviewed by
                        (1) Alan Forrest, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 11-17 Sept.
                        1987: 983; by (2) Christine Gallant and by (3) Burton R. Pollin, 
<hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 18 (1987): 168-69 and 169-71 [two
                        separate reviews]; (4) see also #20, above.</p>
          <p>294. Erffa, Helmut von, and Allen Staley. <hi rend="i">The Paintings of
                            Benjamin West</hi> [20#285]. Reviewed by (1) Mark A. Cheetham, 
<hi rend="i">Canadian Review of American Studies</hi> 18 (1987): 121-25; by
                        (2) *Jane van Norman Turano, <hi rend="i">American Art Journal</hi> 18.3
                        (1986): 74-75.</p>
          <p>295. Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">William Blake and His Contemporaries and
                            Followers: Selected Works from the Collection of Robert N. Essick</hi>
                        [22#18]. Reviewed by Suzanne Muchnic, <hi rend="i">Los Angeles Times</hi> 5
                        Jan. 1988, sec. IV: 1 and 4.</p>
          <pb id="p22-63" n="63"/>
          <p>296. Essick, Robert N. <hi rend="i">The Works of William Blake in the
                            Huntington Collections: A Complete Catalogue</hi> [20#16]. Reviewed by
                        (1) G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi>
                        21 (1987-1988): 114-16; by (2) I. H. C. [Irene H. Chayes], <hi rend="i">RMB
                            for 1985</hi> (1986): 85.</p>
          <p>297. Ferber, Michael. <hi rend="i">The Social Vision of William Blake</hi>
                        [20#77]. Reviewed by (1) D. V. E. [David V. Erdman], <hi rend="i">RMB for
                            1985</hi> (1986): 85-86; by (2) Edward Larrissy, <hi rend="i">Blake / An
                            Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987): 41-42; by (3) Morton D. Paley, 
<hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi> 86 (1987):
                        567-70; by (4) David Worrall, <hi rend="i">British Journal for
                            Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 10 (1987): 110-12.</p>
          <p>298. Fite, David. <hi rend="i">Harold Bloom: The Rhetoric of Romantic
                            Vision</hi> [21#209]. Reviewed by V. A. De Luca, <hi rend="i">University
                            of Toronto Quarterly</hi> 56 (1987): 575-87.</p>
          <p>299. Foot, Michael, and Isaac Kramnick, eds. <hi rend="i">The Thomas Paine
                            Reader</hi> [22#201]. Reviewed by Brian Lee, <hi rend="i">Times Literary
                            Supplement</hi> 11-17 Sept. 1987: 996.</p>
          <p>300. Fruchtman, Jack, Jr. <hi rend="i">The Apocalyptic Politics of Richard
                            Price and Joseph Priestley: A Study in Late Eighteenth-Century English
                            Republican Millennialism</hi> [20#305]. Reviewed by Arthur H.
                        Williamson, <hi rend="i">Journal of the History of Philosophy</hi> 24
                        (1986): 418-20.</p>
          <p>301. Gardner, Stanley. <hi rend="i">Blake’s</hi> Innocence <hi rend="i">and</hi> Experience 
<hi rend="i">Retraced</hi> [21#47].
                        Reviewed by (1) Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
                            Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987): 27-29; by (2) Molly Anne Rothenberg, 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 21 (1987): 127-33.</p>
          <p>302. Gleckner, Robert F. <hi rend="i">Blake and Spenser</hi> [20#86].
                        Reviewed by (1) J. M. Q. Davies, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi>
                        ns 39 (1988): 118-20; by (2) François Piquet, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi> 40
(1987): 355-56; by (3) George
                        Anthony Rosso, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21
                        (1987): 34-37; by (4) M. T. S. [Mark T. Smith], <hi rend="i">RMB for
                            1985</hi> (1986): 86-87; by (5) Irene Tayler, <hi rend="i">Renaissance
                            Quarterly</hi> 39 (1986): 802-03.</p>
          <p>303. Gleckner, Robert F. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prelude:</hi>
                        Poetical Sketches [17#71]. Reviewed by (1) *Pamela Dunbar, <hi rend="i">Review</hi> 6
(1984): 187-90; by (2) Edward Larissy [rect.: Larrissy],
                            <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 34 (1987): 100; by (3) Michael J.
                        Tolley, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20 (1987):
                        146-51.</p>
          <p>304. Glen, Heather. <hi rend="i">Vision and Disenchantment:
                            Blake’s</hi> Songs <hi rend="i">and
                            Wordsworth’s</hi> Lyrical Ballads [18#54]. Reviewed by (1) P.
                        M. S. Dawson, <hi rend="i">Critical Quarterly</hi> 26.1/2 (1984): 139-46
                        [part of an omnibus review, see 144-46]; by (2) M. T. S. [Mark T. Smith],
                            <hi rend="i">RMB for 1984</hi> (1985): 102.</p>
          <p>305. Godard, Jerry Caris. <hi rend="i">Mental Forms Creating: William Blake
                            Anticipates Freud, Jung, and Rank</hi> [20#87]. Reviewed by Christine
                        Gallant, <hi rend="i">RMB for 1985</hi> (1986): 87.</p>
          <p>306. Goslee, Nancy Moore. <hi rend="i">Uriel’s Eye: Miltonic
                            Stationing and Statuary in Blake, Keats, and Shelley</hi> [21#50].
                        Reviewed by Beth Lau, <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 36 (1987):
                        199-202.</p>
          <p>307. Griffin, Dustin. <hi rend="i">Regaining Paradise: Milton and the
                            Eighteenth Century</hi> [21#153]. Reviewed by (1) Balz Engler, 
<hi rend="i">English Studies</hi> 68 (1987): 468-71; by (2) David Hopkins,
                            <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 34 (1987): 388-89; by (3)
                        Frederick M. Keener, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi> 18
                        (1988): 285-86; (4) see also #20, above.</p>
          <p>308. Griffiths, Antony, and Reginald Williams. <hi rend="i">The Department of
                            Prints and Drawings in the British Museum</hi> [21#11]. Reviewed in (1)
                            <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 129 (1987): 687; by (2) Howard
                        Coutts, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 125 (1987): 459; in (3) <hi rend="i">Gazette des
Beaux-Arts</hi> 6th ser. 109 (1987): “La
                        Chronique des Arts” May-June 1987: 9.</p>
          <p>309. Gross, Kenneth. <hi rend="i">Spenserian Poetics: Idolatry, Iconoclasm,
                            and Magic</hi> [22#163]. Reviewed by (1) Robert F. Gleckner, <hi rend="i">Blake /
An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987): 19-21; by (2)
                        Jonathan Goldberg, <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 28 (1986): 341-43; by (3)
                        Michael Murrin, <hi rend="i">Renaissance Quarterly</hi> 40 (1987): 363-65;
                        by (4) Patricia Thomson, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 38
                        (1987): 545-47.</p>
          <p>310. [Haddad, Rosemary, Christopher Heppner, and Elizabeth Lewis]. <hi rend="i">A Catalogue of
the Lawrence Lande William Blake Collection in
                            the Department of Rare Books and Special Collections of the McGill
                            University Libraries</hi> [20#17]. Reviewed by G. E. Bentley, Jr., 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987): 33-34.</p>
          <p>311. Hagstrum, Jean H. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Body: Love and Sexuality in
                            Keats, Wordsworth, and Blake</hi> [21#55]. Reviewed by (1) Joan Baum,
                            <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Journal</hi> 36 (1987): 207-08; by (2)
                        Frederick L. Beaty, <hi rend="i">Nineteenth-Century Literature</hi> 42
                        (1987): 365-68; by (3) Jerome Christensen, <hi rend="i">English Language
                            Notes</hi> 24.4 (1987): 77-80; by (4) V. A. De Luca, <hi rend="i">University of
Toronto Quarterly</hi> 56 (1987): 575-87; by (5) Anne K.
                        Mellor, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987): 17-19;
                        by (6) Lucy Newlyn, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 15 May 1987:
                        525-26; by (7) Jack Stillinger, <hi rend="i">South Atlantic Quarterly</hi>
                        86 (1987): 181-83; in addition, see #70, above.</p>
          <p>312. Halsband, Robert. The Rape of the Lock <hi rend="i">and Its
                            Illustrations</hi> [18#137]. Reviewed by (1) Morris R. Brownell, 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 16 (1982): 90-93; by (2) Peter
                        Conrad, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 7 Nov. 1980: 1255-56; by
                        (3) Peter Quennell, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 112 (1980): 214; by (4) *Daniel
                        Traister, <hi rend="i">American Book Collector</hi> ns 2.2 (1981):
                        60-73.</p>
          <p>313. Hilton, Nelson, ed. <hi rend="i">Essential Articles for the Study of
                            William Blake</hi> [21#60]. Reviewed by Peter Otto, <hi rend="i">Blake /
                            An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987): 29-31.</p>
          <pb id="p22-64" n="64"/>
          <p>314. Hilton, Nelson. <hi rend="i">Literal Imagination: Blake’s
                            Vision of Words</hi> [18#62]. Reviewed by (1) Mark Bracher, 
<hi rend="i">Philosophy and Literature</hi> 8 (1984): 136-37; by (2) *Pamela Dunbar,
                            <hi rend="i">Review</hi> 6 (1984): 187-90; by (3) Aaron Fogel, 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 26 (1987): 591-98.</p>
          <p>315. Hilton, Nelson, and Thomas A. Vogler, eds. <hi rend="i">Unnam’d Forms: Blake and
Textuality</hi> [20#105]. Reviewed
                        by (1) Dan Miller, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21
                        (1987-1988): 116-24; by (2) David Punter, <hi rend="i">Studies in
                            Romanticism</hi> 26 (1987): 612-17.</p>
          <p>316. Hoagwood, Terence Allan. <hi rend="i">Prophecy and the Philosophy of
                            Mind: Traditions of Blake and Shelley</hi> [20#109]. Reviewed by Mark
                        Bracher, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987-1988):
                        108-14.</p>
          <p>317. Hodnett, Edward. <hi rend="i">Image and Text: Studies in the
                            Illustration of English Literature</hi> [17#83]. Reviewed by Valerie
                        Wainwright, <hi rend="i">Revista di Letterature Moderne e Comparate</hi> 35
                        (1982): 379-82.</p>
          <p>318. Hošek, Chaviva, and Patricia Parker, eds. <hi rend="i">Lyric
                            Poetry: Beyond New Criticism</hi> [21#37/162]. Reviewed by (1) Joseph
                        Adamson, <hi rend="i">English Studies in Canada</hi> 12 (1986): 246-54; by
                        (2) Gabriella Bedetti, <hi rend="i">Genre</hi> 20 (1987): 91-95; by (3) Hans
                        Bertens, <hi rend="i">Revue de Littérature
                            Comparée</hi> 61 (1987): 232-34.</p>
          <p>319. Howard, John. <hi rend="i">Infernal Poetics: Poetic Structure in
                            Blake’s Lambeth Prophecies</hi> [20#111]. Reviewed by M. T.
                        S. [Mark T. Smith], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1984</hi> (1985): 103.</p>
          <p>320. <hi rend="i">The Huntington Art Collections: A Handbook</hi> [22#167].
                        Reviewed by Geoffrey Ashton, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 127 (1988): 68-69.</p>
          <p>321. Isphording, Eduard, with the assistance of Manfred von Arnim. <hi rend="i">Fünf
Jahrhunderte Buchillustration: Meisterwerke der
                            Buchgraphik aus der Bibliothek Otto Schäfer</hi> [22#168].
                        Reviewed by Eduard Isphording, <hi rend="i">Monatsanzeiger: Museen und
                            Ausstellungen in Nürnberg</hi> Sept. 1987: 621-22.</p>
          <p>322. Jaffé, Michael, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake and His
                            Contemporaries</hi> [21#12]. Reviewed by David McKitterick, <hi rend="i">Book
Collector</hi> 36 (1987): 305-20 [a few passing remarks on the
                        exhibition and catalogue are included with a review essay on the Blake Trust
                            <hi rend="i">Job</hi> publications and their history.]</p>
          <p>323. James, G. Ingli, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Annotations to Richard
                            Watson</hi>, An Apology for the Bible in a Series of Letters Addressed
                        to Thomas Paine, <hi rend="i">8th ed. 1797</hi> [18#1]. Reviewed by (1) D.
                        V. E. [David V. Erdman], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1984</hi> (1985): 104; by (2)
                        Peter [H.] Marshall, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English Studies</hi> 18
                        (1988): 333-34.</p>
          <p>324. Jordan, Frank, ed. <hi rend="i">The English Romantic Poets: A Review of
                            Research and Criticism.</hi> The 4th ed. [21#13] reviewed by (1) Eric
                        Birdsall, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth Circle</hi> 18 (1987) 184-86; by (2)
                        Jacques Blondel, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi> 40 (1987):
                        220-21; by (3) Nicholas Roe, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 34
                        (1987): 554-55.</p>
          <p>325. Kauffmann, C. M. <hi rend="i">John Varley 1778-1842</hi> [20#253].
                        Reviewed by Judy Egerton, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 127 (1985):
                        244-47 [part of an exhibition review].</p>
          <p>326. Kavanagh, P. J., and James Michie, eds. <hi rend="i">The Oxford Book of
                            Short Poems</hi> [22#4]. Reviewed by D. L., <hi rend="i">UNISA English
                            Studies</hi> 25.2 (1987): 55-56.</p>
          <p>327. Kelly, John, with the assistance of Eric Domville, eds. <hi rend="i">The
                            Collected Letters of W. B. Yeats.</hi> Vol. 1 [21#214] reviewed by (1)
                        Linda Dowling, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi> 83 (1988): 174-75;
                        by (2) Ian Fletcher, <hi rend="i">English Literature in Transition
                            1880-1920</hi> 30 (1987): 475-81; by (3) John P. Frayne, <hi rend="i">Journal of
English and Germanic Philology</hi> 86 (1987): 464-66; by
                        (4) Nicholas Grene, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 34 (1987):
                        565-67; by (5) Steven Helmling, <hi rend="i">Sewanee Review</hi> 95 (1987):
                        490-94; by (6) Eberhard Kreutzer, <hi rend="i">Archiv für das
                            Studium der Neueren Sprachen und Literaturen</hi> 224 (1987): 171-75; by
                        (7) Diane Roberts, <hi rend="i">Western Humanities Review</hi> 41 (1987):
                        88-91; by (8) Alan Robinson, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns
                        38 (1987): 271-72.</p>
          <p>328. Kernan, Alvin. <hi rend="i">Printing Technology, Letters and Samuel
                            Johnson</hi> [22#170]. Reviewed by Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Blake /
                            An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1988): 165-67.</p>
          <p>329. King, James. <hi rend="i">William Cowper: A Biography</hi> [20#211].
                        Reviewed in (1) “The Editorial Miscellany,” <hi rend="i">English</hi> 36 (1987):
191-96; by (2) D. L. Macdonald, <hi rend="i">University of Toronto Quarterly</hi> 57 (1987): 115-17; by (3)
                        Donald H. Reiman, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21
                        (1988): 167-70; by (4) William Roosen, <hi rend="i">American Historical
                            Review</hi> 92 (1987): 661-62; by (5) Patricia Meyer Spacks, <hi rend="i">Journal
of English and Germanic Philology</hi> 86 (1987):
                        432-34; by (6) Geoffrey Ward, <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi> ns
                        48 (1987): 391-92; by (7) Karina Williamson, <hi rend="i">Review of English
                            Studies</hi> ns 38 (1987): 567-68; by (8) David Willis, <hi rend="i">Queen’s
Quarterly</hi> 94 (1987): 212-14; (9) see also #20,
                        above.</p>
          <p>330. King, James, and Charles Ryskamp, eds. <hi rend="i">The Letters and
                            Prose Writings of William Cowper.</hi> Vol. 4 [18#122] reviewed by (1)
                        Donald H. Reiman, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 20
                        (1987): 151-54. Vol. 5 [21#121] reviewed in (2) “The Editorial
                        Miscellany,” <hi rend="i">English</hi> 36 (1987): 191-96.</p>
          <p>331. King-Hele, Desmond. <hi rend="i">Erasmus Darwin and the Romantic
                            Poets</hi> [20#230]. Reviewed by (1) Joseph Bristow, <hi rend="i">Times
                            Higher Education Supplement</hi> 6 June 1986: 20; by (2) Richard Gravil,
                            <hi rend="i">British Book News</hi> July 1986: 428; by (3) J. C. C.
                        Mays, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi>
	<pb id="p22-65" n="65"/>
ns 38 (1987): 396-97; by (4) Peter Scupham, <hi rend="i">Poetry Review</hi> 77.2
(1987): 38-40; by (5) David Worrall,
                            <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987): 31-33.</p>
          <p>332. Klancher, Jon P. <hi rend="i">The Making of English Reading Audiences,
                            1790-1832</hi> [22#171]. Reviewed by (1) C. B. Dodson, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 24
(1987): 1693; by (2) John Kucich, <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 29 (1987): 527-32; by (3) David Simpson, 
<hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1988): 170-72.</p>
          <p>333. Knapp, Steven. <hi rend="i">Personification and the Sublime: Milton to
                            Coleridge</hi> [21#154]. Reviewed by (1) Bruce Clarke, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth
Century: Theory and Interpretation</hi> 28 (1987): 271-77;
                        by (2) Paul Hamilton, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 35 (1988):
                        130-32.</p>
          <p>334. Kroeber, Karl. <hi rend="i">British Romantic Art</hi> [21#73]. Reviewed
                        by (1) Nicola Kalinsky, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 129 (1987):
                        748-49; (2) see also #21, above.</p>
          <p>335. Larrissy, Edward. <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> [21#77]. Reviewed by
                        (1) Rikky Rooksby, <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 34 (1987): 556-57;
                        by (2) M. T. S. [Mark T. Smith], <hi rend="i">RMB for 1985</hi> (1986):
                        89-91.</p>
          <p>336. Lea, F. A. <hi rend="i">Lawrence and Murry: A Twofold Vision</hi>
                        [22#236]. Reviewed by Keith Cushman, <hi rend="i">D. H. Lawrence Review</hi>
                        19 (1987): 43-45.</p>
          <p>337. Lemaitre, Henri. <hi rend="i">William Blake: vision et
                            poésie</hi> [22#87]. Reviewed by François Piquet,
                            <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi> 40 (1987): 471-72.</p>
          <p>338. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">The Paintings of Samuel Palmer</hi>
                        [20#249]. Reviewed by Krzysztof Z. Cieszkowski, <hi rend="i">Journal of the
                            Royal Society of Arts</hi> 134 (1986): 847.</p>
          <p>339. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">The Paintings of William Blake</hi>
                        [21#82]. Reviewed by (1) J. Barter, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 24 (1987):
                        1388; by (2) David Fuller, <hi rend="i">Durham University Journal</hi> ns 48
                        (1987): 373-74.</p>
          <p>340. Lister, Raymond. <hi rend="i">Samuel Palmer: His Life and Art</hi>
                        [22#150]. Reviewed by Christopher Newall, <hi rend="i">Times Literary
                            Supplement</hi> 4-10 Mar. 1988: 250.</p>
          <p>341. Loizeaux, Elizabeth Bergmann. <hi rend="i">Yeats and the Visual
                            Arts</hi> [21#231]. Reviewed by (1) Ian Fletcher, <hi rend="i">English
                            Literature in Transition 1880-1920</hi> 30 (1987): 475-81; by (2) E. F.
                        Harden, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 24 (1987): 1398; by (3) Claude Rawson, 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 24 July 1987: 783-85 [a brief
                        mention as part of a review essay on recent Yeats literature].</p>
          <p>342. Macmillan, Duncan. <hi rend="i">Painting in Scotland: The Golden
                            Age</hi> [22#172]. Reviewed by (1) John Hayes, <hi rend="i">Burlington
                            Magazine</hi> 128 (1986): 912-14; by (2) John Spurling, <hi rend="i">New
                            Statesman</hi> 31 Oct. 1986: 21; by (3) [Denys Sutton], <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi>
124 (1986): 72-77 [a brief announcement of the exhibition
                        as part of an editorial].</p>
          <p>343. Mai, Ekkehard, and Anke Repp-Eckert, eds. <hi rend="i">Triumph und Tod
                            des Helden: Europäische Historienmalerei von Rubens bis
                            Manet</hi> [22#173]. Reviewed by Gisela Zick, <hi rend="i">Kunstchronik</hi> 41
(1988): 46-53.</p>
          <p>344. Marshall, Peter [H.], ed. <hi rend="i">The Anarchist Writings of William
                            Godwin</hi> [21#187]. Reviewed by Gregory Claeys, <hi rend="i">Historical
Journal</hi> 30 (1987): 759-64.</p>
          <p>345. Marshall, Peter H. <hi rend="i">William Godwin: Philosopher, Novelist,
                            Revolutionary</hi> [20#312]. Reviewed by (1) Gregory Claeys, 
<hi rend="i">Historical Journal</hi> 30 (1987): 759-64; by (2) John P.
                        Clark, <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi> 27 (1985): 320-24; by (3) Seamus Deane,
                            <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley Review</hi> 1 (1986): 85-90; by (4) H. T.
                        Dickinson, <hi rend="i">Times Higher Education Supplement</hi> 14 Sept.
                        1984: 18; by (5) *John Lucas, <hi rend="i">Listener</hi> 12 July 1984:
                        24-25; by (6) Serge Soupel, <hi rend="i">Études Anglaises</hi> 38
                        (1985): 468-69.</p>
          <p>346. McGann, Jerome J. <hi rend="i">The Romantic Ideology: A Critical
                            Investigation</hi> [20#273]. Reviewed by Theodore Ziolkowski, <hi rend="i">Sewanee
Review</hi> 95 (1987): 276-87.</p>
          <p>347. McNeil, Maureen. <hi rend="i">Under the Banner of Science: Erasmus
                            Darwin and His Age</hi> [22#137]. Reviewed by (1) Desmond King-Hele, 
<hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 11-17 Dec. 1987: 1370; by (2)
                        Charles Sheffield, <hi rend="i">New Scientist</hi> 7 Apr. 1988: 57.</p>
          <p>348. Meisel, Martin. <hi rend="i">Realizations: Narrative, Pictorial, and
                            Theatrical Arts in Nineteenth-Century England</hi> [21#158]. Reviewed by
                        (1) Victor Emeljanow, <hi rend="i">Queen’s Quarterly</hi> 92
                        (1985): 400-02; by (2) Stephen Wall, <hi rend="i">Times Literary
                            Supplement</hi> 10 Aug. 1984: 883-84.</p>
          <p>349. Mell, Donald C., Jr. <hi rend="i">English Poetry 1660-1800: A Guide to
                            Information Sources</hi> [21#14]. Reviewed by (1) David L. Vander 
[<hi rend="i">sic</hi>] Meulen, <hi rend="i">Literary Research
                            Newsletter</hi> 9.1 (1984): 29-31; by (2) *Alan F. Taylor, <hi rend="i">Library
Review</hi> 32 (1983): 309-11.</p>
          <p>350. Mellor, David, ed. <hi rend="i">A Paradise Lost: The Neo-Romantic
                            Imagination in Britain 1935-55</hi> [22#246]. Reviewed by (1) James
                        Burr, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 126 (1987): 58-59 [concentrates on the
                        exhibition; see #350(7), below]; by (2) Peter Fuller, <hi rend="i">Burlington
Magazine</hi> 129 (1987): 472-74; by (3) *Paddy Kitchen, <hi rend="i">Country Life</hi> 28 May 1987: 38-39; by
(4) R. E. McVaugh, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 25 (1988): 757; by (5) *Charles Pickstone, <hi rend="i">Month</hi>
July 1987: 271-74; by (6) Frances Spalding, <hi rend="i">Times Literary Supplement</hi> 5 June 1987: 607; by
(7) Angela
                        Summerfield, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 126 (1987): 120 [concentrates on the
                        catalogue; see #350(1), above]; by (8) *Marina Vaizey, <hi rend="i">Sunday
                            Times</hi> [London] 24 May 1987; by (9) *Philip Vann, <hi rend="i">Contemporary
Review</hi> Aug. 1987: 97-101.</p>
          <pb id="p22-66" n="66"/>
          <p>351. Milosz, Czeslaw. <hi rend="i">The Land of Ulro</hi> [21#232]. Reviewed
                        by Tadeusz Sławek, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated
                            Quarterly</hi> 21 (1988): 160-65.</p>
          <p>352. Moynihan, Robert. <hi rend="i">A Recent Imagining: Interviews with
                            Harold Bloom, Geoffrey Hartman, J. Hillis Miller, Paul de Man</hi>
                        [22#238]. Reviewed by <corr type="emend">K. Tölölyan,</corr> <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 24
                        (1987): 1696.</p>
          <p>353. Obermeier, Siegfried. <hi rend="i">Die Muse von Rom: Angelika Kauffmann
                            und ihre Zeit</hi> [22#213]. Reviewed by Eckart Klessmann, 
<hi rend="i">Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung</hi> 1 Feb. 1988: 26.</p>
          <p>354. O’Hara, Daniel T. <hi rend="i">The Romance of Interpretation:
                            Visionary Criticism from Pater to de Man</hi> [21#219]. Reviewed by (1)
                        Paul A. Bové, <hi rend="i">Dalhousie Review</hi> 65 (1985-1986):
                        594-97; by (2) Donald E. Pease, <hi rend="i">Journal of Aesthetics and Art
                            Criticism</hi> 46 (1987): 91-94.</p>
          <p>355. Palacio, Jean de. <hi rend="i">William Godwin et son monde
                            intérieur</hi> [20#313]. Reviewed by David McCracken, 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 17 (1984): 380-83.</p>
          <p>356. Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">The Apocalyptic Sublime</hi> [21#88].
                        Reviewed by (1) Irene H. Chayes, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century
                            Studies</hi> 21 (1987): 95-98; in (2) <hi rend="i">Gazette des
                            Beaux-Arts</hi> 6th ser. 110 (1987): “La Chronique des
                        Arts” Oct. 1987: 32; by (3) Laurence Goldstein, <hi rend="i">Michigan Quarterly
Review</hi> 26 (1987): 578-91; by (4) James
                        Heffernan, <hi rend="i">Word and Image</hi> 3 (1987): 323-25; by (5) Cecilia
                        Powell, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi> 11 (1988): 135-40; by (6) Allen
                        Staley, <hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 129 (1987): 406-07.</p>
          <p>357. Paley, Morton D. <hi rend="i">The Continuing City: William
                            Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem [18#85]. Reviewed by (1) * A. A.
                        Ansari, <hi rend="i">Aligarh Journal of English Studies</hi> 10 (1985):
                        100-08; by (2) Kevin Lewis, <hi rend="i">Religious Studies Review</hi>
                        12.3/4 (1986): 279.</p>
          <p>358. Patrides, C. A., and Joseph Wittreich, eds. <hi rend="i">The Apocalypse
                            in English Renaissance Thought and Literature: Patterns, Antecedents and
                            <corr type="emend">Repercussions</corr></hi> [21#160]. Reviewed by (1) Richard Kenneth Emmerson,
                            <hi rend="i">Modern Language Quarterly</hi> 46 (1985): 429-39; by (2)
                        John C. Meagher, <hi rend="i">Religion and Literature</hi> 19.1 (1987):
                        83-88.</p>
          <p>359. Paulson, Ronald. <hi rend="i">Literary Landscape: Turner and
                            Constable</hi> [17#189]. Reviewed by (1) Karl Kroeber, <hi rend="i">Criticism</hi>
25 (1983): 165-68; by (2) William Vaughan, <hi rend="i">Art History</hi> 7 (1984): 368-74 [part of a review
essay on British
                        landscape painting].</p>
          <p>360. Peckham, Morse. <hi rend="i">The Birth of Romanticism: Cultural Crisis,
                            1790-1815</hi> [21#161]. Reviewed by Roger Nicholls, <hi rend="i">Comparative
Literature</hi> 40 (1988): 87-89.</p>
          <p>361. Philp, Mark. <hi rend="i">Godwin’s</hi> Political Justice
                        [21#192]. Reviewed by (1) Gregory Claeys, <hi rend="i">Historical
                            Journal</hi> 30 (1987): 759-64; by (2) Iain Hampsher-Monk, 
<hi rend="i">Albion</hi> 19 (1987): 447-49; by (3) William Stafford, <hi rend="i">History of Political
Thought</hi> 8 (1987): 371-74.</p>
          <p>362. Poovey, Mary. <hi rend="i">The Proper Lady and the Woman Writer:
                            Ideology as Style in the Works of Mary Wollstonecraft, Mary Shelley, and
                            Jane Austen</hi> [20#316]. Reviewed by (1) Susan Groag Bell, <hi rend="i">History
of European Ideas</hi> 8 (1987): 611-14; by (2) *Rachel
                        Brownstein, <hi rend="i">Nation</hi> 238 (1984): 337-40; by (3) Olwen
                        Hufton, <hi rend="i">Literature and History</hi> 13 (1987): 297-99; by (4)
                        Ellen Pollak, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 21 (1987-1988):
                        260-63.</p>
          <p>363. Powell, David. <hi rend="i">Tom Paine: The Greatest Exile</hi> [21#193].
                        Reviewed by (1) *Stuart Andrews, <hi rend="i">History Today</hi> 36 (1986):
                        56; by (2) *Paul David Nelson, <hi rend="i">History: Review of New
                            Books</hi> 14 (1986): 153-54.</p>
          <p>364. Pressly, William L. <hi rend="i">James Barry: The Artist as Hero</hi>
                        [17#139]; and <hi rend="i">The Life and Art of James Barry</hi> [16#133].
                        Reviewed together by Richard Godfrey, <hi rend="i">Print Quarterly</hi> 1
                        (1984): 72-74.</p>
          <p>365. Priestman, Martin. <hi rend="i">Cowper’s</hi> Task: <hi rend="i">Structure and
Influence</hi> [18#124]. Reviewed by A. J.
                        Sambrook, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi> 82 (1987): 922-23.</p>
          <p>366. Punter, David. <hi rend="i">Blake, Hegel, and Dialectic</hi> [17#115].
                        Reviewed by Dan Dahlstrom, <hi rend="i">Journal of the History of
                            Philosophy</hi> 23 (1985): 267-69.</p>
          <p>367. Rawson, Claude. <hi rend="i">Order from Confusion Sprung: Studies in
                            Eighteenth-Century Literature from Swift to Cowper</hi> [20#213].
                        Reviewed by (1) Wilhelm Füger, <hi rend="i">Anglia</hi> 105
                        (1987): 499-502; by (2) Phillip Harth, <hi rend="i">Modern Language
                            Review</hi> 82 (1987): 706-08; by (3) Joan H. Pittock, <hi rend="i">English</hi>
36 (1987): 163-68; by (4) Peter J. de Voogd, <hi rend="i">Dutch Quarterly Review of Anglo-American
Letters</hi> 17 (1987): 129-41
                        [as part of an omnibus review]; by (5) Calhoun Winton, <hi rend="i">Sewanee
                            Review</hi> 95 (1987): xxxi-xxxvi; by (6) David Womersley, <hi rend="i">Notes and
Queries</hi> ns 34 (1987): 396-98.</p>
          <p>368. Redford, Bruce. <hi rend="i">The Converse of the Pen: Acts of Intimacy
                            in the Eighteenth-Century Familiar Letter</hi> [22#131]. Reviewed by (1)
                        T. S. Kobler, <hi rend="i">Choice</hi> 24 (1987): 1553; (2) see also #20,
                        above.</p>
          <p>369. Rhodes, Nick, ed. <hi rend="i">William Cowper: Selected Poems</hi>
                        [22#132]. Reviewed in (1) “The Editorial Miscellany,”
                            <hi rend="i">English</hi> 36 (1987): 85-94; by (2) *Joan H. Pittock, 
<hi rend="i">British Journal of Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 7 (1984):
                        249-50.</p>
          <pb id="p22-67" n="67"/>
          <p>370. Robinson, Abby. <hi rend="i">The Dick and Jane</hi> [22#247]. Reviewed
                        by Morris Eaves, <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21
                        (1987): 37-41.</p>
          <p>371. Rump, Gerhard Charles. <hi rend="i">George Romney (1734-1802): Zur
                            Bildform der Bürgerlichen Mitte in der Englischen
                            Neoklassik</hi> [12p147]. Reviewed by Renate Heidt, <hi rend="i">Zeitschrift für
Ästhetik und Allgemeine
                            Kunstwissenschaft</hi> ns 25 (1980): 74-84.</p>
          <p>372. Sambrook, James. <hi rend="i">The Eighteenth Century: The Intellectual
                            and Cultural Context of English Literature, 1700-1789</hi> [21#163].
                        Reviewed by (1) Rebecca Ferguson, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English
                            Studies</hi> 18 (1988): 282-83; by (2) Alain Morvan, <hi rend="i">Études
Anglaises</hi> 40 (1987): 352; by (3) Andrew Varney,
                            <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 35 (1988): 93-94.</p>
          <p>373. Schulz, Max F. <hi rend="i">Paradise Preserved: Recreations of Eden in
                            Eighteenth- and Nineteenth-Century England</hi> [21#140]. Reviewed by
                        (1) Chris Brooks, <hi rend="i">Review of English Studies</hi> ns 38 (1987):
                        280-81; by (2) Frederick Garber, <hi rend="i">Journal of English and
                            Germanic Philology</hi> 87 (1988): 120-21; by (3) John Dixon Hunt, 
<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> 129 (1987): 466-67; by (4) George P.
                        Landow, <hi rend="i">Victorian Studies</hi> 31 (1988): 276-78; by (5)
                        Herbert L. Sussman, <hi rend="i">American Historical Review</hi> 92 (1987):
                        953-54.</p>
          <p>374. Sharma, L. R. <hi rend="i">In Defence of J. Middleton Murry</hi>
                        [22#242]. Reviewed by Sharron Cassavant, <hi rend="i">English Literature in
                            Transition 1880-1920</hi> 31 (1988): 103-07.</p>
          <p>375. Smith, Bernard, ed. <hi rend="i">Culture and History: Essays Presented
                            to Jack Lindsay</hi> [21#222]. Reviewed by John Lucas, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of
English Studies</hi> 18 (1988): 355-57.</p>
          <p>376. Smith, Olivia. <hi rend="i">The Politics of Language 1791-1819</hi>
                        [21#164]. Reviewed by (1) Claude Fierobe, <hi rend="i">Études
                            Anglaises</hi> 40 (1987): 353-54; by (2) Neil Fraistat, <hi rend="i">Keats-Shelley
Journal</hi> 36 (1987): 208-11; by (3) Gareth Stedman
                        Jones, <hi rend="i">American Historical Review</hi> 92 (1987): 662; by (4)
                        Jon P. Klancher, <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 49 (1986):
                        409-14; by (5) Peter [H.] Marshall, <hi rend="i">Modern Language Review</hi>
                        83 (1988): 160-61; by (6) James C. McKusick, <hi rend="i">Wordsworth
                            Circle</hi> 18 (1987): 166-68.</p>
          <p>377. Summerfield, Geoffrey. <hi rend="i">Fantasy and Reason:
                            Children’s Literature in the Eighteenth Century</hi>
                        [22#179]. Reviewed by (1) Gilles Duval, <hi rend="i">Dix-huitième
                            Siècle</hi> 18 (1986): 543; by (2) Marcus Walsh, <hi rend="i">Yearbook of English
Studies</hi> 18 (1988): 289-90.</p>
          <p>378. Tysdahl, B. J. <hi rend="i">William Godwin as Novelist</hi> [20#319].
                        Reviewed by David McCracken, <hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 17
                        (1984): 380-83.</p>
          <p>379. Vaughan, William. <hi rend="i">German Romanticism and English Art</hi>
                        [14p92]. Reviewed by T. J. Edelstein, <hi rend="i">Journal of Pre-Raphaelite
                            Studies</hi> 1.1 (1980): 107-08.</p>
          <p>380. Vincent, Bernard. <hi rend="i">Thomas Paine ou la religion de la
                            liberté</hi> [22#222]. Reviewed by Marcel Dorígny,
                            <hi rend="i">Annales Historiques de la Révolution
                            Française</hi> 59 (1987): 342-43.</p>
          <p>381. Warner, Eric, and Graham Hough, eds. <hi rend="i">Strangeness and
                            Beauty: An Anthology of Aesthetic Criticism 1840-1910</hi> [21#226].
                        Reviewed by Werner Bies, <hi rend="i">Archiv für das Studium der
                            Neueren Sprachen und Literaturen</hi> 222 (1985): 187-89.</p>
          <p>382. Warner, Janet A. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Language of Art</hi>
                        [20#186]. Reviewed by I. H. C. [Irene H. Chayes], <hi rend="i">RMB for
                            1984</hi> (1985): 108-09.</p>
          <p>383. Watson, J. R. <hi rend="i">English Poetry of the Romantic Period:
                            1789-1830</hi> [21#108]. Reviewed by E. D. Mackerness, <hi rend="i">Notes and
Queries</hi> ns 34 (1987): 404-05.</p>
          <p>384. Watson, Jennifer C. <hi rend="i">George Romney in Canada</hi> [22#153].
                        Reviewed by Laurier Lacroix, <hi rend="i">Vie des Arts</hi> Dec. 1986:
                        75.</p>
          <p>385. Webster, Brenda S. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic
                            Psychology</hi> [17#134]. Reviewed by (1) I. H. C. [Irene H. Chayes],
                            <hi rend="i">RMB for 1984</hi> (1985): 109-10; by (2) Dan Miller, 
<hi rend="i">Journal of the Midwest Modern Language Association</hi> 17.2
                        (1984): 37-39; by (3) Frank Stack, <hi rend="i">Times Higher Education
                            Supplement</hi> 4 May 1984: 24.</p>
          <p>386. Wind, Edgar. <hi rend="i">Hume and the Heroic Portrait: Studies in
                            Eighteenth-Century Imagery</hi> [21#116]. Reviewed by (1) *Peter Jones,
                            <hi rend="i">British Journal of Aesthetics</hi> 27 (1987): 287-88; by
                        (2) A. M. [Alain Mérot], <hi rend="i">Revue de
                            l’Art</hi> 78 (1987): 94-95; by (3) Ronald Paulson, 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth-Century Studies</hi> 20 (1987): 472-75; (4) see also
                        #20, above.</p>
          <p>387. Witke, Joanne. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Epic: Imagination
                            Unbound</hi> [21#117]. Reviewed by (1) David Fuller, <hi rend="i">Durham
                            University Journal</hi> ns 49 (1987): 148; by (2) Catherine McClenahan,
                            <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 21 (1987): 21-25.</p>
          <p>388. Wordsworth, Jonathan, Michael C. Jaye, and Robert Woof, with the
                        assistance of Peter Funnell. <hi rend="i">William Wordsworth and the Age of
                            English Romanticism</hi> [22#26]. Reviewed in (1) *<hi rend="i">Arts
                            Magazine</hi> Nov. 1987: 104-05; by (2) David Bromwich, <hi rend="i">Times
Literary Supplement</hi> 11-17 Dec. 1987: 1379; by (3) John
                        Murdoch, <hi rend="i">Apollo</hi> 127 (1988): 199-200; by (4) Charles Rosen,
                            <hi rend="i">New York Review of Books</hi> 17 Dec. 1987: 22-31 [see also
                        the exchange of letters that was provoked by this review and was published
                        on 17 Mar. 1988: 45]; by (5) Andrew Wilton, <hi rend="i">Burlington
                            Magazine</hi> 130 (1988): 258.</p>
        </div2>
        <pb id="p22-68" n="68"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>
              <hi rend="b">Index of Authors, Editors, and Reviewers</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p>Abley, Mark 27</p>
          <p>Abrams, Ann Uhry 248</p>
          <p>Adams, Hazard 28, 98, 156, 249</p>
          <p>Adamson, Joseph 318(1)</p>
          <p>Aers, David 98</p>
          <p>Albright, Daniel 250</p>
          <p>Aldridge, A. Owen 251</p>
          <p>Alford, Steven E. 252</p>
          <p>Allan, D. G. C. 128</p>
          <p>Altick, Richard D. 253</p>
          <p>Altizer, Thomas J. J. 254</p>
          <p>Anderson, Ross 157, 255</p>
          <p>Andrews, Stuart 363(1)</p>
          <p>Ansari, A. A. 357(1)</p>
          <p>Arnim, Manfred von 168, 321</p>
          <p>Ash, Beth Sharon 224</p>
          <p>Ashton, Geoffrey 320</p>
          <p>Aubrey, Bryan 256</p>
          <p>Ault, Donald 29, 98</p>
          <p>Axelrod, Steven Gould 266(1)</p>
          <p>Ayer, A. J. 183, 257</p>
          <p>Baine, Mary R. 258</p>
          <p>Baine, Rodney M. 258</p>
          <p>Baker, Carlos 259</p>
          <p>Baridon, Michel 30</p>
          <p>Barker, Nicolas 233</p>
          <p>Barrell, John 260</p>
          <p>Barter, J. 287, 339(1)</p>
          <p>Bate, Jonathan 261</p>
          <p>Baum, Joan 311(1)</p>
          <p>Bealey, Frank 291</p>
          <p>Beaty, Frederick L. 311(2)</p>
          <p>Bechtold, Carmen 141</p>
          <p>Beckson, Karl 225, 262</p>
          <p>Bedetti, Gabriella 318(2)</p>
          <p>Behrendt, Stephen C. 31</p>
          <p>Bell, Susan Groag 362(1)</p>
          <p>Bellin, Harvey F. 263</p>
          <p>Bennett, Shelley M. 154</p>
          <p>Bentley, G. E., Jr. 27, 32, 33, 34, 48, 296(1), 310</p>
          <p>Bergevin, Gerald Walter 35</p>
          <p>Bernstein, Samuel 185, 264</p>
          <p>Bertens, Hans 318(3)</p>
          <p>Bhattacharya, Biswanath 36</p>
          <p>Bickman, Martin 249(1)</p>
          <p>Bidney, Martin 37</p>
          <p>Bies, Werner 381</p>
          <p>Billigheimer, Rachel V. 38</p>
          <p>Bindman, David 48, 265</p>
          <p>Birdsall, Eric 324(1)</p>
          <p>Blondel, Jacques 39, 324(2)</p>
          <p>Bloom, Harold 40, 41, 266, 267</p>
          <p>Bogel, Fredric V. 268</p>
          <p>Boime, Albert 269</p>
          <p>Bolcom, William 270</p>
          <p>Bonnell, Thomas F. 158</p>
          <p>Borck, Jim Springer 271</p>
          <p>Borges, Jorge Luis 42</p>
          <p>Borgmeier, Raimund 3</p>
          <p>Boucé, Paul-Gabriel 194</p>
          <p>Bové, Paul A. 354(1)</p>
          <p>Bracher, Mark 98, 272, 314(1), 316</p>
          <p>Bradley, John Lewis 226, 273</p>
          <p>Brake, Laurel 23</p>
          <p>Brantley, Richard E. 186, 274</p>
          <p>Bridson, Gavin 275</p>
          <p>Brisman, Leslie 43</p>
          <p>Bristow, Joseph 331(1)</p>
          <p>Bromwich, David 388(2)</p>
          <p>Bronowski, Rita 227</p>
          <p>Brooks, Chris 373(1)</p>
          <p>Brosch, Renate 159, 276</p>
          <p>Brown, David Blayney 149</p>
          <p>Brownell, Morris R. 312(1)</p>
          <p>Brownstein, Rachel 362(2)</p>
          <p>Brunet, Étienne 78</p>
          <p>Bruntjen, Sven H. A. 277</p>
          <p>Burns, Bryan 23</p>
          <p>Burr, James 350(1)</p>
          <p>Burwick, Frederick 44</p>
          <p>Busch, Werner 135, 278</p>
          <p>Butler, Marilyn 279, 280</p>
          <p>Butlin, Martin 45</p>
          <p>Callow, James T. 248</p>
          <p>Cantor, Paul A. 281</p>
          <p>Carr, Robert 46</p>
          <p>Carrier, David 260(1)</p>
          <p>Cartwright, Jerome 47</p>
          <p>Cassavant, Sharron 374</p>
          <p>Cayley, David 48</p>
          <p>Champion, Larry S. 261(1)</p>
          <p>Chan, Victor 138</p>
          <p>Chayes, Irene H. 49, 296(2), 356(1), 382, 385(1)</p>
          <p>Cheetham, Mark A. 294(1)</p>
          <p>Childers, Joseph 50</p>
          <p>Christensen, Jerome 311(3)</p>
          <p>Cieszkowski, Krzysztof Z. 338</p>
          <p>Claeys, Gregory 187, 344, 345(1), 361(1)</p>
          <p>Clark, David Leonhard 51</p>
          <p>Clark, John P. 345(2)</p>
          <p>Clark, Lorraine Joan 52</p>
          <p>Clarke, Bruce 333(1)</p>
          <p>Clausen, Christopher 250(1)</p>
          <p>Conger, Syndy McMillen 188</p>
          <p>Conisbee, Philip 292</p>
          <p>Conrad, Peter 312(2)</p>
          <p>Cook, David 282</p>
          <p>Cook, Eleanor 283</p>
          <p>Cornis-Pop, Marcel 290(1)</p>
          <p>Coulson, John 281(1)</p>
          <p>Coutts, Howard 308(2)</p>
          <p>Cowper, William 130, 132</p>
          <p>Cox, Stephen D. 98, 268(1)</p>
          <p>Cozzens, Christine Suzanne 189</p>
          <p>Cranston, Maurice 257, 289</p>
          <p>Crehan, Stewart 284</p>
          <p>Cronin, Richard 190</p>
          <p>Crouan, Katharine 147, 285</p>
          <p>Cumming, Mark 228</p>
          <p>Cummings, Peter 255</p>
          <p>Cushman, Keith 336</p>
          <p>Dahlstrom, Dan 366</p>
          <p>Damon, S. Foster 53</p>
          <p>Davies, J. M. Q. 302(1)</p>
          <p>Davis, Patricia Elizabeth 54</p>
          <p>Dawson, P. M. S. 55, 304(1)</p>
          <p>Deane, Seamus 345(3)</p>
          <p>De Luca, V. A. 290(2), 298, 311(4)</p>
          <p>DeMarr, Mary Jean 24</p>
          <p>Dendle, Brian J. 16, 17</p>
          <p>Denizot, Paul 191</p>
          <p>Dickinson, H. T. 345(4)</p>
          <p>Dingley, R. J. 160</p>
          <p>DiSalvo, Jackie 56, 270, 286</p>
          <p>Dodson, C. B. 332(1)</p>
          <p>Dole, George 192</p>
          <p>Domville, Eric 327</p>
          <p>Dorigny, Marcel 380</p>
          <p>Dorment, Richard 287</p>
          <p>Dörrbecker, D. W. 15</p>
          <p>Douglas, Aileen 193</p>
          <p>Dove, Mary 241</p>
          <p>Dowdey, Landon 288</p>
          <p>Dowling, Linda 327(1)</p>
          <p>Duffy, Edward T. 281(2)</p>
          <p>Duhet, Paule-Marie 194, 195</p>
          <p>Dunbar, Pamela 303(1), 314(2)</p>
          <p>Durey, Michael 196, 197</p>
          <p>Duval, Gilles 377(1)</p>
          <p>Dyck, Ian 198, 289</p>
          <p>Eaves, Morris 53, 229, 290, 370</p>
          <p>Edelstein, T. J. 379</p>
          <p>Edinger, Edward F. 57</p>
          <p>Edwards, Ruth Dudley 291</p>
          <p>Egerton, Judy 325</p>
          <p>Eitner, Lorenz 58, 292</p>
          <p>Ellis, Helen B. 59</p>
          <p>Emeljanow, Victor 348(1)</p>
          <p>Emmerson, Richard Kenneth 254(1), 358(1)</p>
          <p>England, D. Gene 24</p>
          <p>Engler, Balz 307(1)</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V. 14, 16, 17, 161, 272(1), 284(1), 293, 297(1), 323(1)</p>
          <p>Erffa, Helmut von 294</p>
          <p>Erskine, Elizabeth 24</p>
          <p>Essick, Robert N. 18, 60, 61, 62, 63, 295, 296</p>
          <p>Everest, K. D. 64</p>
          <p>Fadem, Richard 274(1)</p>
          <p>Farr, Richard 199</p>
          <p>Feldman, Burton 200</p>
          <p>Ferber, Michael 48, 297</p>
          <p>Ferguson, Rebecca 372(1)</p>
          <p>Fierobe, Claude 376(1)</p>
          <p>Fischer, Michael 290</p>
          <p>Fite, David 298</p>
          <p>Fletcher, Ian 327(2), 341(1)</p>
          <p>Fogel, Aaron 314(3)</p>
          <p>Folkenflik, Robert 20</p>
          <p>Foot, Michael 201, 299</p>
          <p>Forrest, Alan 293(1)</p>
          <p>Fraistat, Neil 376(2)</p>
          <p>Frayne, John P. 327(3)</p>
          <p>Frosch, Thomas R. 266(2)</p>
          <p>Fruchtman, Jack, Jr. 300</p>
          <p>Frye, Northrop 48, 241</p>
          <p>Füger, Wilhelm 367(1)</p>
          <p>Fuller, David 65, 339(2), 387(1)</p>
          <p>Fuller, Peter 350(2)</p>
          <p>Funnell, Peter 26, 388</p>
          <p>Gallant, Christine 293(2), 305</p>
          <p>Gantner, Joseph 143</p>
          <p>Garber, Frederick 373(2)</p>
          <p>Gardner, Stanley 301</p>
          <p>Garlick, Kenneth 253(1)</p>
          <p>George, Diana Hume 66</p>
          <p>Gleckner, Robert F. 67, 302, 303, 309(1)</p>
          <p>Glen, Heather 304</p>
          <p>Godard, Jerry Caris 305</p>
          <p>Godfrey, Richard 364</p>
          <p>Goldberg, Jonathan 309(2)</p>
          <p>Goldsmith, Steven 254(2)</p>
          <p>Goldstein, Laurence 356(3)</p>
          <pb id="p22-69" n="69"/>
          <p>Gonzalez, Alexander 230</p>
          <p>Gordon, Catherine M. 162</p>
          <p>Gori, Michela 68</p>
          <p>Goslee, Nancy Moore 306</p>
          <p>Goyder, George 48, 231</p>
          <p>Gravil, Richard 331(2)</p>
          <p>Greco, Norma A. 69</p>
          <p>Grene, Nicholas 327(4)</p>
          <p>Griffin, Dustin 307</p>
          <p>Griffiths, Antony 308</p>
          <p>Grobstein, Clifford 227</p>
          <p>Gross, Kenneth 163, 309</p>
          <p>Gully, Anthony Lacy 164</p>
          <p>Gutiérrez, Félix Martín 232</p>
          <p>Haddad, Rosemary 310</p>
          <p>Hagstrum, Jean H. 70, 311</p>
          <p>Haigney, Catherine 71, 72</p>
          <p>Halimi, Suzy 194</p>
          <p>Halsband, Robert 312</p>
          <p>Hamilton, Paul 333(2)</p>
          <p>Hammer, Sabine 202</p>
          <p>Hampsey, John C. 73</p>
          <p>Hampsher-Monk, Iain 361(2)</p>
          <p>Hancher, Michael 253(2)</p>
          <p>Harden, E. F. 341(2)</p>
          <p>Harmer, Michael 233</p>
          <p>Harper, George Mills 256</p>
          <p>Harth, Phillip 367(2)</p>
          <p>Hawkins, Harriett 261(2)</p>
          <p>Hayes, John 342(1)</p>
          <p>Healey, R. M. 234</p>
          <p>Hearn, Michael Patrick 288</p>
          <p>Heffernan, James 356(4)</p>
          <p>Heidt, Renate 371</p>
          <p>Helmling, Steven 327(5)</p>
          <p>Hemingway, Andrew 260(2)</p>
          <p>Heppner, Christopher 310</p>
          <p>Herrick, Jim 203</p>
          <p>Herrstrom, David Sten 74</p>
          <p>Hilton, Nelson 75, 76, 98, 301(1), 313, 314, 315, 328</p>
          <p>Hoagwood, Terence Allan 316</p>
          <p>Hobsbaum, Philip 259(1)</p>
          <p>Hodnett, Edward 165, 317</p>
          <p>Holton, Gerald 227</p>
          <p>Hope, Ann M. 166</p>
          <p>Hopkins, David 307(2)</p>
          <p>Horn, William Dennis 98</p>
          <p>Hošek, Chaviva 318</p>
          <p>Hough, Graham 381</p>
          <p>Howard, John 319</p>
          <p>Hufton, Olwen 362(3)</p>
          <p>Hunt, John Dixon 373(3)</p>
          <p>Hurley, Michael 282(1), 290(3)</p>
          <p>Ide, Nancy M. 77, 78</p>
          <p>Irwin, David 173</p>
          <p>Isphording, Eduard 168, 321</p>
          <p>Jackson, Mary V. 79</p>
          <p>Jaffé, Michael 322</p>
          <p>James, G. Ingli 323</p>
          <p>Jasper, David 88</p>
          <p>Jaye, Michael C. 26, 388</p>
          <p>Jeffrey, Ian 235</p>
          <p>Jolles, Evelyn B. 204</p>
          <p>Jones, Chris 205</p>
          <p>Jones, Gareth Stedman 376(3)</p>
          <p>Jones, Peter 386(1)</p>
          <p>Jonsson, Inge 263</p>
          <p>Jordan, Frank 324</p>
          <p>Jordanova, L. J. 136</p>
          <p>Josipovici, Gabriel 283</p>
          <p>Kalinsky, Nicola 334</p>
          <p>Kang, Sun-Koo 80</p>
          <p>Kang, Tong-Won 81</p>
          <p>Kang, Yop 82, 83</p>
          <p>Kauffmann, C. M. 325</p>
          <p>Kaufman, Andrew Frederick 84</p>
          <p>Kavanagh, P. J. 4, 326</p>
          <p>Keener, Frederick M. 169, 307(3)</p>
          <p>Kelly, John 327</p>
          <p>Kernan, Alvin 170, 328</p>
          <p>Ketcham, Ralph 251</p>
          <p>King, James 329, 330</p>
          <p>King-Hele, Desmond, 331, 347(1)</p>
          <p>Kitchen, Paddy 350(3)</p>
          <p>Klancher, Jon P. 171, 332, 376(4)</p>
          <p>Klein, Jürgen 144</p>
          <p>Klessmann, Eckart 353</p>
          <p>Knapp, Steven 333</p>
          <p>Kobler, T. S. 368</p>
          <p>Konopacki, Adam 85</p>
          <p>Kramnick, Isaac 201, 206, 299</p>
          <p>Kreutzer, Eberhard 327(6)</p>
          <p>Kroeber, Karl 334, 359(1)</p>
          <p>Kucich, John 332(2)</p>
          <p>Kunitz, Stanley 5</p>
          <p>Kuzniar, Alice A. 207</p>
          <p>Lacroix, Laurier 384</p>
          <p>Landow, George P. 373(4)</p>
          <p>Lane, Lauriat, Jr. 282(2)</p>
          <p>Langland, Elizabeth 98</p>
          <p>Larrissy, Edward 259(2), 297(2), 303(2), 335</p>
          <p>Latané, David E., Jr. 86, 250(2)</p>
          <p>Lau, Beth 306</p>
          <p>Lavater, Johann Caspar 208</p>
          <p>Lawton, David 241</p>
          <p>Lea, F. A. 236, 336</p>
          <p>Lee, Brian 299</p>
          <p>LeFanu, William R. 233</p>
          <p>LeFaye, Deirdre 146</p>
          <p>Lehan, Richard 280(1)</p>
          <p>Leighton, Angela 261(3)</p>
          <p>Lemaitre, Henri 87, 337</p>
          <p>Lewis, Elizabeth 310</p>
          <p>Lewis, Kevin 88, 89, 357(2)</p>
          <p>Lima, Marcelo 245</p>
          <p>Lincoln, Andrew 90, 258(1)</p>
          <p>Linkin, Harriet Kramer 91</p>
          <p>Lipking, Lawrence 92</p>
          <p>Lippincott, Louise 277</p>
          <p>Lister, Raymond 150, 338, 339, 340</p>
          <p>Lockwood, Thomas 271(1)</p>
          <p>Logan, Anne-Marie S. 285</p>
          <p>Loizeaux, Elizabeth Bergmann 341</p>
          <p>Lucas, John 345(5), 375</p>
          <p>Luetjohann, Sylvia 8</p>
          <p>Lundeen, Kathleen Farmer 93</p>
          <p>Lussier, Mark 66, 76, 94, 97, 110</p>
          <p>Macdonald, D. L. 329(2)</p>
          <p>MacKenzie, Raymond N. 280(2)</p>
          <p>Mackerness, E. D. 383</p>
          <p>Macleod, Dianne Sachko 253(3)</p>
          <p>Macmillan, Duncan 172, 342</p>
          <p>Magno, Cettina Tramontano 14</p>
          <p>Mai, Ekkehard 173, 343</p>
          <p>Maison, Margaret 209</p>
          <p>Manning, Peter J. 21</p>
          <p>Manning, Sylvia 21</p>
          <p>Markley, Robert 268(2)</p>
          <p>Marshall, Peter H. 279, 323(2), 344, 345, 376(5)</p>
          <p>Marshall, W. Gerald 129</p>
          <p>Martin, James Kirby 264</p>
          <p>Martin, Richard G. 95</p>
          <p>Martin, Wallace 249(2)</p>
          <p>Mason, Michael 7</p>
          <p>Matteson, L. R. 260(3)</p>
          <p>Mays, J. C. C. 331(3)</p>
          <p>Mazlish, Bruce 227</p>
          <p>McClenahan, Catherine 387(2)</p>
          <p>McCord, James 96</p>
          <p>McCracken, David 355, 378</p>
          <p>McGann, Jerome J. 346</p>
          <p>McKitterick, David 237, 265(1), 322</p>
          <p>McKusick, James C. 376(6)</p>
          <p>McNeil, Maureen 136, 137, 347</p>
          <p>McVaugh, R. E. 350(4)</p>
          <p>Meagher, John C. 358(2)</p>
          <p>Meisel, Martin 253(4), 348</p>
          <p>Mell, Donald C., Jr. 349</p>
          <p>Mellor, Anne K. 311(5)</p>
          <p>Mellor, David 235, 246, 350</p>
          <p>Merkley, Paul 254(3)</p>
          <p>Mérot, Alain 386(2)</p>
          <p>Metzger, Lore 174</p>
          <p>Meulen, David L. Vander 349(1)</p>
          <p>Michie, James 4, 23, 326</p>
          <p>Miller, Dan 97, 98, 315(1), 385(2)</p>
          <p>Milosz, Czeslaw 351</p>
          <p>Mitchell, W. J. T. 260(4)</p>
          <p>Molesworth, Charles 266(3)</p>
          <p>Möller, Joachim 159, 276</p>
          <p>Morris, Barbara 139</p>
          <p>Morvan, Alain 210, 372(2)</p>
          <p>Moynihan, Robert 238, 352</p>
          <p>Muchnic, Suzanne 295</p>
          <p>Mulford, Carla Jean 211</p>
          <p>Müller, Marianne 239</p>
          <p>Murdoch, John 388(3)</p>
          <p>Murray, Isobel 262(1)</p>
          <p>Murrin, Michael 309(3)</p>
          <p>Myers, Mitzi 212</p>
          <p>Nanavutty, Piloo 99</p>
          <p>Nelson, Paul David 363(2)</p>
          <p>Nemoianu, Virgil 290(4)</p>
          <p>Nesfield-Cookson, Bernard 100</p>
          <p>Neuman, Mark 74</p>
          <p>Newall, Christopher 340</p>
          <p>Newey, Vincent 23</p>
          <p>Newlyn, Lucy 311(6)</p>
          <p>Nicholls, Roger 360</p>
          <p>Norton, Charles Eliot 226, 273</p>
          <p>Oakley, Lucy 157</p>
          <p>Obermeier, Siegfried 213, 353</p>
          <p>O’Hara, Daniel T. 354</p>
          <p>O’More, Haven 8</p>
          <p>Ormond, Leonée 253(5)</p>
          <p>Ostriker, Alicia 175</p>
          <p>Otto, Peter 101, 102, 103, 104, 267, 313</p>
          <p>Ousby, Ian 226, 273</p>
          <p>Owens, Norah 105</p>
          <pb id="p22-70" n="70"/>
          <p>Pache, Walter 130</p>
          <p>Pagliaro, Harold 106</p>
          <p>Palacio, Jean de 355</p>
          <p>Paley, Morton D. 265(2), 297(3), 356, 357</p>
          <p>Parker, Patricia 318</p>
          <p>Patrides, C. A. 358</p>
          <p>Patterson, Annabel 107</p>
          <p>Paulson, Ronald 359, 386(3)</p>
          <p>Payne, Michael 74</p>
          <p>Pease, Donald E. 354(2)</p>
          <p>Peckham, Morse 360</p>
          <p>Peters, Anne 214</p>
          <p>Pfister, Manfred 276(1)</p>
          <p>Phillips, Michael 8</p>
          <p>Philp, Mark 361</p>
          <p>Pickstone, Charles 350(5)</p>
          <p>Piquet, François 302(2), 337</p>
          <p>Pittock, Joan H. 367(3), 369(2)</p>
          <p>Pointon, Marcia 126</p>
          <p>Pollak, Ellen 362(4)</p>
          <p>Pollin, Burton R. 293(3)</p>
          <p>Poovey, Mary 362</p>
          <p>Powell, Cecilia 356(5)</p>
          <p>Powell, David 363</p>
          <p>Pressly, William L. 364</p>
          <p>Priestman, Martin 365</p>
          <p>Punter, David 9, 315(2), 366</p>
          <p>Quennell, Peter 312(3)</p>
          <p>Ragghianti, Carlo L. 260(5)</p>
          <p>Raine, Kathleen 48, 108, 240</p>
          <p>Rajan, Tilottama 176</p>
          <p>Rawson, Claude 341(3), 367</p>
          <p>Read, Dennis M. 134</p>
          <p>Redford, Bruce 131, 368</p>
          <p>Reiman, Donald H. 177, 329(3), 330(1)</p>
          <p>Repp-Eckert, Anke 173, 343</p>
          <p>Rhodes, Nick 132, 369</p>
          <p>Ricards, Philip Clayton 109</p>
          <p>Richardson, Robert R. 200</p>
          <p>Riehl, Joseph E. 56, 60, 110</p>
          <p>Ringbom, Hakan 221</p>
          <p>Rissanen, Matti 221</p>
          <p>Roberts, Diane 327(7)</p>
          <p>Robinson, Abby 247, 370</p>
          <p>Robinson, Alan 327(8)</p>
          <p>Roe, Nicholas 250(3), 261(4), 324(3)</p>
          <p>Rooksby, Rikky 335(1)</p>
          <p>Roosen, William 329(4)</p>
          <p>Roper, Derek 281(3)</p>
          <p>Rosen, Charles 388(4)</p>
          <p>Rosenblum, Robert 173</p>
          <p>Rosso, George Anthony, Jr. 286(1), 302(3)</p>
          <p>Roth, Martin 215</p>
          <p>Rothenberg, Molly Anne 111, 112, 258(2), 301(2)</p>
          <p>Rousseau, G. S. 178</p>
          <p>Roxman, Susanna 280(3)</p>
          <p>Ruhl, Darrell 263</p>
          <p>Rump, Gerhard Charles 371</p>
          <p>Runcie, Catherine 241</p>
          <p>Ruskin, John 226, 273</p>
          <p>Ruthven, K. K. 241</p>
          <p>Ryskamp, Charles 330</p>
          <p>Sabor, Peter 271(2)</p>
          <p>Salk, Jonas 227</p>
          <p>Saltman, Paul 227</p>
          <p>Salusinsky, Imre 241</p>
          <p>Sambrook, A. J. 274(2), 365</p>
          <p>Sambrook, James 372</p>
          <p>Sanesi, Roberto 10, 11, 12</p>
          <p>Schiff, Gert 42</p>
          <p>Schotte, Edith 216</p>
          <p>Schulz, Max F. 373</p>
          <p>Scrivener, Michael 113</p>
          <p>Scupham, Peter 331(4)</p>
          <p>Sethna, K. D. 240</p>
          <p>Shabetai, Karen 114</p>
          <p>Sharma, L. R. 242, 374</p>
          <p>Sharp, Ronald A. 274(3)</p>
          <p>Sharpe, Eric J. 241</p>
          <p>Sharrock, Roger 274(4)</p>
          <p>Sheffield, Charles 347(2)</p>
          <p>Sherbo, Arthur 133</p>
          <p>Sheriton, Janet 217</p>
          <p>Simms, Karl N. 218</p>
          <p>Simpson, David 332(3)</p>
          <p>Singer, June 115</p>
          <p>Singh, Charu Sheel 116</p>
            <p><corr type="emend">Sławek,</corr> Tadeusz 351</p>
          <p>Smith, Bernard 375</p>
          <p>Smith, Ken Edward 284(2)</p>
          <p>Smith, Mark T. 252, 302(4), 304(2), 319, 335(2)</p>
          <p>Smith, Michael 24</p>
          <p>Smith, Olivia 376</p>
          <p>Solkin, David H. 260(6)</p>
          <p>Soupel, Serge 268(3), 345(6)</p>
          <p>Spacks, Patricia Meyer 329(5)</p>
          <p>Spalding, Frances 350(6)</p>
          <p>Spector, Sheila A. 117</p>
          <p>Spencer, Keith 127</p>
          <p>Spurling, John 342(2)</p>
          <p>Stack, Frank 284(3), 385(3)</p>
          <p>Stafford, Barbara Maria 219</p>
          <p>Stafford, William 361(3)</p>
          <p>Staley, Allen 294, 356(6)</p>
          <p>Stillinger, Jack 311(7)</p>
          <p>Stokes, John 243</p>
          <p>Sultana, Donald 261(5)</p>
          <p>Summerfield, Angela 350(7)</p>
          <p>Summerfield, Geoffrey 179, 377</p>
          <p>Summerfield, Henry 118</p>
          <p>Sung, Chan-Kyung 119</p>
          <p>Sussman, Herbert L. 373(5)</p>
          <p>Sutton, Denys 342(3)</p>
          <p>Swedenborg, Emanuel 192</p>
          <p>Tandecki, Daniela 120, 121</p>
          <p>Tayler, Irene 302(5)</p>
          <p>Taylor, Alan F. 349(2)</p>
          <p>Taylor, Dena Bain 25</p>
          <p>Taylor, Joshua C. 13</p>
          <p>Thinès, Georges 122</p>
          <p>Thomson, Patricia 309(4)</p>
          <p>Thurin, Susan Schoenbauer 151</p>
          <p>Tolley, Michael J. 303(3)</p>
          <p><corr type="emend">Tölölyan, K.</corr> 352</p>
          <p>Tomlinson, Alan 122A</p>
          <p>Tomory, Peter 220</p>
          <p>Traister, Daniel 312(4)</p>
          <p>Tramontano Magno, Cettina 14</p>
          <p>Trevelyan, George 100</p>
          <p>Tscherny, Nadia 152, 180</p>
          <p>Turano, Jane van Norman 294(2)</p>
          <p>Turman, Kathryn Lee Green 123</p>
          <p>Tuveson, Ernest 274(5)</p>
          <p>Tysdahl, B. J. 221, 378</p>
          <p>Vaizey, Marina 350(8)</p>
          <p>Vander Meulen, David L. 349(1)</p>
          <p>Vann, Philip 350(9)</p>
          <p>Varney, Andrew 372(3)</p>
          <p>Vaughan, William 359(2), 379</p>
          <p>Vincent, Bernard 222, 380</p>
          <p>Vogeler, A. R. 273(1)</p>
          <p>Vogler, Thomas A. 98, 315</p>
          <p>Voogd, Peter J. de 367(4)</p>
          <p>Wagenknecht, David 98</p>
          <p>Wagner, Gretel 159, 276</p>
          <p>Wainwright, Clive 253(6)</p>
          <p>Wainwright, Valerie 317</p>
          <p>Wakeman, Geoffrey 275</p>
          <p>Wall, Stephen 348(2)</p>
          <p>Walsh, Marcus 377(2)</p>
          <p>Ward, Geoffrey 329(6)</p>
          <p>Wark, Robert R. 18, 155, 167</p>
          <p>Warner, Eric 381</p>
          <p>Warner, Janet A. 382</p>
          <p>Warren, Leland E. 223</p>
          <p>Watkinson, Ray 124, 244</p>
          <p>Watson, J. R. 383</p>
          <p>Watson, Jennifer C. 153, 384</p>
          <p>Webb, Eugene 254(4)</p>
          <p>Webster, Brenda S. 98, 385</p>
          <p>Weinglass, D. H. 145</p>
          <p>Westfehling, Uwe 181</p>
          <p>White, Edmund 262(2)</p>
          <p>Wilkie, Brian 272(2)</p>
          <p>Williams, Raymond 273(2)</p>
          <p>Williams, Reginald 308</p>
          <p>Williamson, Arthur H. 300</p>
          <p>Williamson, Karina 329(7)</p>
          <p>Willis, David 329(8)</p>
          <p>Wilton, Andrew 265(3), 388(5)</p>
          <p>Wind, Edgar 386</p>
          <p>Winton, Calhoun 367(5)</p>
          <p>Witke, Joanne 387</p>
          <p>Wittreich, Joseph 286(2), 358</p>
          <p>Womersley, David 367(6)</p>
          <p>Woof, Robert 26, 388</p>
          <p>Wordsworth, Jonathan 26, 388</p>
          <p>Worrall, David 297(4), 331(5)</p>
          <p>Wynne, Michael 148</p>
          <p>Yarrington, Alison 140</p>
          <p>Yates, Frances A. 182</p>
          <p>Zick, Gisela 343</p>
          <p>Ziolkowski, Theodore 346</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
