<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>22.2.essick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Dating Blake’s “Enoch” Lithograph Once Again</title>
        <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1988</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1988</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">22.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_22">
    <body>
      <pb id="p22-71" n="71"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-22-2-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULAR</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Dating Blake’s “Enoch” Lithograph
                            Once Again</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Robert N. <name>Essick</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Archibald G. B. Russell was the first to suggest a date of composition and
                        execution for Blake’s only known lithograph (illus. 1). Although
                        he believed that the design represents “Job in
                        Prosperity,” Russell’s estimate of “about
                        1807” has held up surprisingly well over the years.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> In <hi rend="i">William Blake
                            Printmaker</hi>, doubts about this fairly specific date led me to
                        suggest only the period c. 1803-1820 for the print.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref> Later, in an article in this journal and in a
                        catalogue of Blake’s separate plates, I argued more confidently
                        for a date of 1806-1807 for “Enoch” because of its
                        execution on “White Lyas” stone (according to George
                        Cumberland’s inscription on the verso of the impression
                        reproduced here) and the buff and brown wove papers used for three of the
                        four extant impressions.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3"
type="note">3</ref> Both
                        characteristics associate the print with the early lithographic (or
                        “polyautographic”) printmaking in London by Georg
                        Jacob Vollweiller during the years at issue. However, in a review published
                        in 1981 of <hi rend="i">William Blake Printmaker</hi>, John Gage offered a
              different approach to dating “Enoch”: <figure n="ESXV.1.1B.SP" rend="file" width="958" height="674">
	<head>1. Blake.</head>
	<figDesc>“Enoch.” Modified lithograph, printed in
                                relief from a stone, 21.7 × 31 cm., 1806-1807. The
                                disfiguring marks above the central figure’s head are
                                fragments of George Cumberland’s verso inscription that
                                have bled through to the recto. Collection of Mrs. Edward
                                Croft-Murray, Richmond, Surrey.</figDesc>
</figure>
<q> If we recall that the first [complete English] translation of the
                            [Ethiopic] <hi rend="i">Book of Enoch</hi> appeared in 1821, and that
                            the subject of the print [i.e., “Enoch”], although
                            it bears some relation to an earlier watercolour by Blake, relates
                            rather closely to verses 1-3 of Chapter XCII of this book, we may place
                            the print, whose style and formal modelling seems to this reviewer to be
                            very close to that of the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> engravings published in
                            1825, rather later even than Essick’s bracket of 1803/20.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref></q>
This suggestion seems to have achieved some
currency, for the catalogue
                        of the 1986 exhibition of Blake’s works at Wildenstein Gallery,
                        London, accepts Gage’s “convincing date of 1821 or
                        later for [the] lithograph.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5"
type="note">5</ref>
                        Gage’s date and his rationale for it deserve a more careful
                        consideration. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Russell, <hi rend="i">The
                                Engravings of William Blake</hi> (London: Grant Richards, 1912) 91.
                            The same date is given in Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">Engravings by
                                William Blake: The Separate Plates</hi> (Dublin: Emery Walker, 1956)
                            43-44.</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake
                                Printmaker</hi> (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1980), caption to pl.
                            166.</note>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Essick, “Blake’s
                            ‘Enoch’ Lithograph,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 14
(1981): 180-84; Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A Catalogue</hi>
                            (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1983) 55-59.</note>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Gage, review of J.-C. Le Blon, <hi rend="i">Coloritto</hi>, and Essick, 
<hi rend="i">William Blake
                                Printmaker</hi>, in <hi rend="i">Art History</hi>, 14 (1981):
                            473. I was not aware of Gage’s proposal until after my
                            catalogue of Blake’s separate plates had gone to
                            press.</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi><hi rend="i"> William Blake and His
                                Contemporaries</hi>: A Loan Exhibition in Aid of the Friends of the
                            Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge. Wildenstein Gallery, London, 11 June-11
                            July, 1986. (Cambridge, Cambs.: Fitzwilliam Museum Enterprises, 1986)
                            104, No. 63. This catalogue also served for the exhibition at the
                            Fitzwilliam Museum, summer 1987.</note></p>
          <p>The passage in <hi rend="i">The Book of Enoch</hi> Gage refers to reads as
                        follows: 
						<q> 1. After this, Enoch began to speak from a book.<lb/>
 2. And
                            Enoch said; Concerning the children of righteousness, concerning the
                            elect of the world, and concerning the plant of righteousness and
                            integrity,<lb/>
 3. <hi rend="i">Concerning</hi> these things will I
                            speak, and <hi rend="i">these things</hi> will I explain to you, my
                            children: I <hi rend="i">who</hi> am Enoch. In consequence of that which
                            has been shewn to me, from my heavenly vision and from the voice of the
                            holy angels have I acquired knowledge; and from the tablet of heaven
                            have I acquired understanding.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> The Book of Enoch the
                                    Prophet: An Apocryphal Production</hi>, trans. Richard Laurence
                                (Oxford: at the University Press for the author, 1821) 134.</note></q>
The
general parallels between these verses and Blake’s print
                        are certainly worthy of notice. Enoch holds a book, the three youths on the
                        plinth may be his children, and the floating figures holding a tablet or
                        open scroll may be the “holy angels.” The radiance
                        descending from above would seem to signal the divine origin of
                        Enoch’s wisdom. Other passages in the 1821 text speak to these
                        same acts and associations, thereby underscoring their importance to
                        Enoch’s character. Enoch sees “a holy vision in the
                        heavens” at the very beginning of the book (1), he is named as a
                        “scribe” in the twelfth chapter (13), he is commanded
                        by God in the eightieth chapter to “look on the book which heaven
                        has gradually dropped down” (99), and a few sentences later told
                        to “instruct thy family, write these things, and explain them to
                        all thy children” (100).</p>
          <p>On the face of it, Gage’s textual source for Blake’s
                        “Enoch” is reasonably convincing. Yet, the parallels
                        are fairly general, with the possible exception of the
                        “angels” with a “tablet.” The
                        viability of Gage’s thesis would diminish considerably if the
                        essential features offered by the 1821 volume—Enoch’s
                        book, its divine inspiration, and the communication of its wisdom to his
                        family—were available to Blake from some other sources.</p>
          <p>One textual basis for “Enoch” is explicitly presented
                        by the print itself. Enoch holds a book inscribed with his name in Hebrew,
                        while the hovering figures on the right bear and point to a tablet or
                        manuscript inscribed with the Hebrew words that begin Genesis 5:24,
                        “And Enoch walked with God. . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n7" type="note">7</ref> Blake did not have 
<pb id="p22-72" n="72"/>
to wait
                        until 1821 to find an authoritative statement of Enoch’s direct
                        access to divinity. <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> The identification of
                            this quotation is credited to Joseph Wicksteed in Laurence Binyon and
                            Geoffrey Keynes, <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job by
                                William Blake</hi> (New York: Pierpont Morgan Library, 1936),
                            fascicle 1, 8-9; Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake: Separate Plates</hi>,
                            43-44; Keynes <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi>, 2nd ed. (Oxford:
                            Clarendon Press, 1971) 178.</note></p>
          <p>Other motifs of the lithograph accounted for by the passage in <hi rend="i">The Book of
Enoch</hi> also appear in other texts. The descriptions of
                        Enoch in the pseudepigraphic Book of Jubilees 4:17-24 are particularly
                        important. Enoch is there described as the first man to learn writing.
                        Further, he “was the first to write a testimony, and he testified
                        to the sons of men among the generations of the earth . . .”
                            (4:18).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">8</ref>
Jubilees was not translated
                        into English until 1885; but it is possible that Blake knew something of it
                        through verbal or visual allusions, much as he seems to have known about the
                        apocryphal Testament of Job.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">9</ref> Other
                        sources of information about Enoch could have come more readily to
                        Blake’s attention by 1806 or earlier. In chapter 30 of <hi rend="i">Mysterium
Magnum: or, an Explanation of the First Book of Moses
                            Called Genesis</hi>, Jacob Boehme claims that Enoch marked “a
                        Beginning of the prophetical Spirit,” a comment of the sort
                        almost designed to attract the notice of a latter-day English prophet.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> Later in the same chapter, Boehme
                        refers to that “Time when Enoch and the Children under his Voice
                        lead a <hi rend="i">divine Life</hi>, of which the first Life of 
<hi rend="i">Enoch</hi> was a Type . . .” (3:159, para. 46). In
                            <hi rend="i">The True Christian Religion</hi>, Emanuel Swedenborg refers
                        to Enoch in one of his many discussions of his key doctrine of
                        correspondences. The “men of the Most Ancient Church which
                        existed before the flood, were of a genius so celestial that they talked
                        with the angels of heaven, and were able to talk with them by means of
                        correspondences. . . . Furthermore, I have been informed that Enoch (who is
                        mentioned in <hi rend="i">Gen.</hi> v. 21-24) and those associated with him
                        collected correspondences from the lips of these men, and transmitted this
                        knowledge to their posterity . . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n11" type="note">11</ref> The possibility that Swedenborg’s
                        writings transmitted this knowledge to Blake is buttressed by
                        Blake’s reference in his <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>
                        of 1809 to Swedenborg’s “Universal
                        Theology”—the subtitle of <hi rend="i">The True
                            Christian Religion</hi>—as the basis for his painting (now
                        lost) of <hi rend="i">The Spiritual Preceptor.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> Thus, Enoch’s role as a communicator of
                        divine wisdom to his offspring—a key feature of the passage Gage
                        cites from the Ethiopic text—can also be found in a work known to
                        have influenced Blake’s pictorial works long before 1821. 
<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> R. H. Charles, ed., <hi rend="i">The
                                Apocrypha and Pseudepigrapha of the Old Testament in English</hi>
                            (Oxford: Clarendon, 1913) 2: 18.</note>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> The influence of the Testament on
                            Blake’s Job designs is discussed in Bo Lindberg, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Illustrations to the Book of Job</hi>
                            (Abo: Abo Akademi, 1973) 137-48. See Robert Watt, <hi rend="i">Bibliotheca
Britannica</hi> (Edinburgh: Constable, 1824), vol. 3,
                            “Enoch,” for a list of works published before 1806
                            that at least refer to the patriarch in their titles. I have not been
                            able to locate a copy of one particularly intriguing title, <hi rend="i">Enoch; a
Poem: Book I</hi> (London: Cadell, 1805).</note>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi><hi rend="i"> The Works of Jacob Behmen,
                                the Teutonic Theosopher</hi> [the so-called
                            “Law’s Edition”] (London: G. Robinson,
                            1772) 3: 154-55, para. 14. Boehme is an often-cited source for many of
                            Blake’s spiritual concepts. He refers to
                            “Behmen” in <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven
                                and Hell</hi> (c. 1790-1793) and in a letter to John Flaxman of 12
                            September 1800 (<hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William
                                Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman [Berkeley: Univ. of California
                            Press, 1982] 43, 707). According to Henry Crabb Robinson, in 1825 Blake
                            praised the illustrations “in Law’s transl.<hi rend="s">n</hi>”; in 1864,
Frederick Tatham wrote that
                            Blake had “a large collection of works of the mystical
                            writers. Jacob Behmen, Swedenborg, and others” (G. E.
                            Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> [Oxford: Clarendon, 1969]
                            41, n. 4, 313).</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi><hi rend="i"> The True Christian Religion
                                Containing the Universal Theology of the New Church</hi> (New York:
                            American Swedenborg Society, 1915) 1: 300, para. 202.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi><hi rend="i"> Complete Poetry and
                                Prose</hi>, 546. Blake’s knowledge of <hi rend="i">The
                                True Christian Religion</hi> is discussed in Morton D. Paley,
                            “ ‘A New Heaven is Begun’: William
                            Blake and Swedenborgianism,” <hi rend="i">Blake/An
                                Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 13 (1979): 64, 78-80, 82.</note></p>
          <p>The most intriguing dimension of the iconography of Blake’s print
                        is the association of the young folk (presumably Enoch’s
                        children) with the instruments of poetry, painting, and music.
                        Enoch’s parentage of the arts may be lurking somewhere in the
                        texts and legends surrounding his name, but I have not been able to find any
                        evidence for it.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13"
type="note">13</ref> Gage’s
                        claims for the 1821 volume would be strengthened materially if it contained
                        a reference to Enoch and the arts, but such is not the case. It is of course
                        possible that this association is Blake’s own addition to
                        Enochian lore. The arts were for Blake the necessary vehicles of that divine
                        wisdom of which Enoch was himself a channel. Keynes (<hi rend="i">Blake
                            Studies</hi>, 178) quite rightly associates the lithograph with
                        Blake’s identification, in “A Vision of the Last
                        Judgment,” of Noah and his sons Shem and Japhet as
                        representatives of “Poetry Painting &amp; Music the three
                        Powers in Man of conversing with Paradise which the flood did not Sweep
                        away” (E 559). Since Enoch was Noah’s
                        great-grandfather (see Genesis 5:22-29), the quill and book, brush and
                        palette, and lyre in “Enoch” simply place the
                        iconography of Blake’s “Vision of the Last
                        Judgment” in the hands of an earlier generation of the same
                        antediluvian family. <note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> For useful and
                            surprisingly detailed summaries, see <hi rend="i">The Jewish
                                Encyclopedia</hi>, ed. Isidore Singer (New York: Funk and Wagnalls,
                            1910) 1: 676-79, 5: 178-82.</note></p>
            <figure n="but146.1.1.wc" id="but146.1.wc.01" work-copy="biblicalwc" rend="db" width="958" height="722">
	<figTranscr/>
            <head>2. Blake.</head>
            <figDesc><hi rend="i">Enoch Walked with God(?).</hi> Pen and water color
                            over pencil and charcoal, 45.4 × 61 cm., c. 1780-1785.
                            Cincinnati Art Museum, Gift of Mr. and Mrs. John W.
                            Warrington.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <p>A subsidiary feature of Gage’s argument depends upon the pictorial
                        associations between “Enoch” and Blake’s
                        Job illustrations. But in fact these very connections speak more forcefully
                        for a date of 1806-1807 than for c. 1825. While Gage bases his opinion on a
                        sense of general parallels in “style and formal
                        modelling,” the “early watercolour” he
                        mentions in passing establishes a documentary link between
                        “Enoch” and the Job series. Martin Butlin has
                        tentatively entitled this water color <hi rend="i">Enoch Walked with
                            God</hi> (illus. 2) and dated it to c. 1780-1785 with somewhat greater
                            confidence.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">14</ref> The design 
<pb id="p22-73" n="73"/>
shares with “Enoch” a
                        patriarchal figure holding a book, several youths of both sexes who may be
                        his children, and hovering figures on the right holding a tablet or open
                        scroll bearing sketchy indications of written characters. If
                        Butlin’s title correctly indicates its subject, then this drawing
                        demonstrates Blake’s knowledge in the 1780s about
                        Enoch’s association with books, the transmundane source of his
                        wisdom, and the appropriateness of placing Enoch within a family setting.
                        But even if the subject is not Enoch, it remains clear that Blake recycled
                        motifs from this undoubtedly early drawing for both the
                        “Enoch” lithograph and the second design in his Job
                        illustrations. The latter were first created for Thomas Butts as a series of
                        water colors datable to c. 1805-1806 (Butlin #550). If the pictorial
                        parallels between “Enoch” and the Job illustrations
                        signify anything at all about the print’s date, then it seems
                        most probable that Blake borrowed from his early drawing to create
                        “Enoch” at about the same time he was reworking the
                        same drawing into a Job illustration. This reworking took place not in 1825,
                        when Blake was transforming his Job water colors into copperplate
                        engravings, but in the same period to which “Enoch”
                        has been traditionally assigned. In contrast, Blake’s series of
                        five pencil sketches based on <hi rend="i">The Book of Enoch</hi>, dated by
                        Butlin to c. 1824-1827 (#827), bear no relation in format, composition, or
                        motif to the lithograph. <note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi><hi rend="i"> The
                                Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (New Haven: Yale UP,
                            1981) No. 146 and color pl. 181. For another early drawing with similar
                            motifs and compositional format, see <hi rend="i">Moses and Aaron(?)
                                Flanked by Angels</hi> (Butlin #112 and pl. 121).</note></p>
          <p>Gage has raised some interesting issues about the dating of
                        Blake’s only known lithograph. He has not, however, demonstrated
                        that the 1821 <hi rend="i">Book of Enoch</hi> supplied any information about
                        its eponym unavailable in texts very probably known to Blake many years
                        earlier. Nor does the association with the Job designs testify to a date in
                        the 1820s. What are arguably the most specific motifs shared by the print
                        and the 1821 text—the patriarch’s book and the
                        hovering “angels” holding a
                        “tablet”—were part of Blake’s
                        repertoire of Enochian (or at least proto-Enochian) images as early as the
                        1780s (illus. 2). The circumstantial evidence summarized by Russell and
                        Keynes in their catalogues, supplemented and extended by details in mine,
                        remains the best basis for dating “Enoch.”</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
