<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
        <idno>22.3.ward</idno>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="article">Canterbury Revisited: The Blake-Cromek Controversy</title>
                <author n="Ward">Aileen Ward</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>Winter 1988/89</edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date>1988/89</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope unit="volIss">22.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
                        <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Editors</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <resp>Review Editor</resp>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                            <resp>Production Office</resp>
                            <name>Morris Eaves</name>
                            <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
                            <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
                            <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
                            <name>David Worrall</name>
                            <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
                            <name>Patricia Neill</name>
                            <resp>Contributors</resp>
                            <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
                            <name>Martin Butlin</name>
                            <name>Michael Phillips</name>
                            <name>John B. Pierce</name>
                            <name>Aileen Ward</name>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1988"/>
                        <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
                <constitution type="composite"/>
                <domain type="education"/>
            </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="volume_22">
        <body>
        <pb id="p22-80" n="80"/>
            <div1 id="BQ-22-3-0005">
                <head>
                    <title type="main">Canterbury Revisited: The Blake-Cromek Controversy</title>
                </head>
                <byline>
                    <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
                    <docAuthor>
                        <hi rend="i">AILEEN</hi>
                        <name>
                            <hi rend="i">WARD</hi>
                        </name>
                    </docAuthor>
                </byline>
                <p>If crooked roads without improvement are the ways of genius, the road Blake took
                    to Canterbury was a veritable Pilgrim’s Progress.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n0" type="note">*</ref>
	<note id="n0">This article is an expanded version of a paper
                        delivered in the symposium “William Blake: His Art and Times,” The Yale
                        Center for British Art, 11 September 1982.</note> For of all his works of
                    art, the one that cost him the most grief and stirred up the greatest
                    controversy during his lifetime was the large “fresco” painting of 
                        <hi rend="i">Sir Jeffery Chaucer and the Nine and Twenty Pilgrims on their Journey to
                        Canterbury.</hi> This painting, dated 1808, was the major work in Blake’s
                    1809 Exhibition and the first to be attacked in Robert Hunt’s scathing review in
                        <hi rend="i">The Examiner.</hi> It also caused a bitter falling-out between
                    Blake and his old friend Thomas Stothard, who in May 1807 had exhibited an
                    immensely successful oil painting of the same subject, similar in size and basic
                    design to Blake’s own. Blake’s engraving from his fresco, entitled 
                        <hi rend="i">Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>, was published in October 1810; the
                    engraving of Stothard’s painting was delayed, through a series of mishaps, till
                    1817. Stothard protested that Blake had “commenced his picture in rivalry” to
                    Stothard’s own, since, he reported, Blake had seen and admired his 
                        <hi rend="i">Procession of Chaucer’s Pilgrims to Canterbury</hi> while it was still
in
                    progress. Blake on his side claimed that he had sketched the design for his 
                        <hi rend="i">Pilgrims</hi> even earlier and had shown the drawing to Robert
                    Cromek, his erstwhile agent, who, while appearing to be delighted with it, had
                    taken the idea to Stothard and engaged him to paint it instead.</p>
                <p>Such are the outlines of the controversy as described by Blake’s earliest
                    biographers, quite evenhandedly by John Thomas Smith in 1828 and, with obvious
                    bias against Blake, by Allan Cunningham in 1830.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n1" type="note">1</ref> But since the appearance of Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life
                        of William Blake</hi> in 1863, the controversy has been regarded as settled:
                    virtually every twentieth-century biographer or critic who has discussed the
                    matter has, despite minor uncertainties over points of fact, followed Gilchrist
                    in taking sides with Blake and accusing Cromek of treachery.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
                        type="note">2</ref> Yet it must be borne in mind that the story of Blake’s
                    life as hitherto received is based in very large part on Blake’s own testimony,
                    supported by a modicum of corroboratory evidence—that is, on Blake’s
                    recollections during his sixties which he passed on to the disciples who became
                    Gilchrist’s informants some three decades later. A fresh look at the evidence in
                    the dispute over <hi rend="i">The Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> may not merely
                    suggest a different interpretation of a central episode in Blake’s life but also
                    serve as example of the need for a critical re-examination of his life as a
                    whole. In the process the critic must scrutinize the minutest particulars of
                    fact, weigh conflicting testimony, and keep constantly in mind the ambiguity of
                    interpretation and the fallibility of memory. The remembrance of things past is
                    a voyage over shifting sands. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi>As reprinted in
                        G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon,
                        1969; hereafter cited as <hi rend="i">BR</hi>) 464-67 and 491-92. On the
                        1808 date of Blake’s painting, now obscured, see W. M. Rossetti, “Annotated
                        Lists of Blake’s Paintings, Drawings, and Engravings,” in Alexander
                        Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, “<hi rend="i">Pictor
                            Ignotus</hi>” (London: Macmillan, 1906) 428, and Martin Butlin, 
                            <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (Oxford:
                        Clarendon, 1981) 1: 475; on the 1817 date of Stothard’s engraving, see
                        Alexander Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, ed. Ruthven
                        Todd (London: Everyman, 1945; hereafter cited as <hi rend="i">Life</hi>)
                        253-55 and <hi rend="i">Dictionary of National Biography</hi> (London:
                        Oxford UP, 1917, hereafter cited as <hi rend="i">DNB</hi>) 18: 1322. Duncan
                        Macmillan’s suggestion that Blake got the idea of the cavalcade from viewing
                        the Elgin Marbles (“Blake’s Exhibition and <hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi>
                        Reconsidered” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 5 [1971-72]: 205-06)
                        supports the 1808 date, since the Marbles were not unpacked and placed on
                        private view till 1807 (David Irwin, <hi rend="i">John Flaxman
                            1755-1826</hi> [London: Cassell, 1979] 174).</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi
                            rend="s">2</hi> To cite only a few: Mona Wilson, <hi rend="i">The Life
                            of William Blake</hi>, 3rd ed. rev.; Geoffrey Keynes (London: Oxford UP,
                        1971) 232-34; Ruthven Todd, <hi rend="i">William Blake, the Artist</hi>
                        (London: Studio Vista Ltd., 1971) 78; David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake:
                            Prophet Against Empire</hi> (3rd rev. ed., Princeton UP, 1977) 439;
                        David Bindman, <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist</hi> (Oxford: Phaidon, 1977)
                        155; Jack Lindsay, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (New York: Braziller,
                        1979) 193; Butlin 1: 475; and Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate
                            Plates of William Blake</hi> (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1983)
                    84.</note></p>
                <p>Gilchrist based his account largely on John Linnell’s notes on Smith’s memoir,
                    which he wrote in 1855 drawing on conversations with Blake over thirty years
                    earlier. According to Linnell, Cromek actually commissioned Blake to finish the
                    Canterbury fresco for twenty guineas with the promise that he would also receive
                    the much more lucrative fee for engraving it—the identical arrangement he had
                    made with Blake for his designs for Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> two or three
                    months earlier. But, Linnell states, Cromek secretly negotiated with William
                    Bromley to engrave Blake’s design; meanwhile Blake became suspicious and refused
                    to give Cromek his drawing when requested; whereupon Cromek took the idea and
                    the commission to Stothard without informing either painter of the other’s
                    involvement. Gilchrist like Linnell clears Stothard of complicity in Cromek’s
                    scheme; he also quotes an insulting letter that Cromek wrote to Blake in May
                    1807 which contains the only known reference to the dispute by either of the two
                    principals. The letter consists mainly of Cromek’s abusive response to Blake’s
                    “furious rage” at the success of Stothard’s <hi rend="i">Procession</hi> (then
                    being exhibited in London) by challenging Blake “to send [him] a better”:
                    whereupon, Gilchrist adds, “the indignant painter acted in executing, hereafter,
                    his 
<pb id="p22-81" n="81"/>
<figure n="CoronationEdwardVI.22.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="488">
                        <head>The coronation procession of Edward VI from the Tower to Westminster
                            by an unknown sixteenth-century painter, engraved by James Basire in
                            1787.</head>
                        <figDesc>Photo courtesy of The Society of Antiquaries of London.</figDesc>
                    </figure> projected ‘fresco’ from <hi rend="i">The Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>, and
                    exhibiting and engraving it.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3"
type="note">3</ref>	
                            <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> Life</hi> 223-25; 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi>
                        184-87, 464n1. The letter was published by Allan Cunningham’s son in 1852
                            (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 187n2), and thereby prompted Gilchrist to cast
                        Cromek as the villain of the piece. Stothard’s painting was the sensation of
                        the 1807 season in London, drawing crowds of thousands at a shilling
                        admission, and subsequently toured the provinces with similar success. The
                        engraving, despite its delayed appearance, became the best-selling print of
                        the first half of the nineteenth century (Anna E. Bray, <hi rend="i">Life of
                            Thomas Stothard</hi> [London, 1851] 140).</note></p>
                <p>Gilchrist’s suggestion, that Blake painted, exhibited, and engraved his 
                        <hi rend="i">Pilgrims</hi> only after seeing Stothard’s painting and in response
                    to Cromek’s challenge in 1807, is curiously inconsistent with his earlier
                    statement (following Linnell) that Cromek first saw a sketch of the 
                        <hi rend="i">Pilgrims</hi> by Blake and then, after negotiations between them broke
                    down, went to Stothard and “suggested the subject as a novelty.” Indeed, the
                    precise chronology of the whole affair is a puzzle. If, as it is generally
                    assumed, Blake had begun work on his fresco (or even his engraving) sometime
                    late in 1805 or early in 1806,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
type="note">4</ref> his delay in
                    meeting the threat to his own project till 1808 is inexplicable: the subject had
                    never been painted before, and priority was an important concern. It is also
                    difficult to understand why Blake, on seeing Stothard’s half-finished painting
                    in 1806, would have failed to mention his own work in progress to his friend,
                    who was surprised and angered on learning later of Blake’s rival version.<ref
                        target="n5" type="note">5</ref> Finally, it is striking that Cromek’s letter
                    of May 1807 nowhere mentions any drawing or painting of Chaucer’s 
                        <hi rend="i">Pilgrims</hi> by Blake, or replies to any charge by Blake of the theft of
                    his idea; rather it suggests that Blake’s rage was directed against the
                    extraordinary success of Stothard’s painting and what he felt was Stothard’s
                    contemptible treatment of the subject. The earliest accounts of the affair are
                    vague about dates and mutually contradictory on certain points, and it is hardly
                    surprising that recent discussions also give a confused picture of the entire
                        controversy.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref> A
survey of the
                    relationship between Blake and Cromek from the beginning may help to clarify
                    matters. <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Erdman 439; <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 179;
                        see also <hi rend="i">Life</hi> 220.</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 465-66 and n1, and see 179n3. On the
                        novelty of the subject, which—<hi rend="i">pace</hi> Gilchrist 
                            (<hi rend="i">Life</hi> 221)—greatly intensified the rivalry, see Richard D.
Altick,
                            <hi rend="i">Paintings from Books</hi> (Columbus: Ohio State UP, 1985)
                        339. Betsy Bowden in “The Artistic and Interpretive Context of Blake’s
                        ‘Canterbury Pilgrims’ ” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 13 (1980): 164-90 examines
                        in detail a number of analogues to Blake’s design in previous illustrations
                        of the <hi rend="i">Tales</hi>; but the single illustration she cites (172,
                        174-75) of the Pilgrims setting out on their journey, from Urry’s 1721
                        edition of Chaucer, barely qualifies as a source for Blake’s painting, even
                        though Blake may have known of this edition. Only 11 of the tiny figures in
                        the 7½″ × 3¾″ engraving are identifiable, much less individualized, and the
                        overall design and graphic style are completely different from Blake’s. The
                        figures of the Merchant and the Wife of Bath in the Chaucer portrait of the
                        “Heads of the Poets” (Butlin, vol. 2, pl. 440), which she cites as “faithful
                        copies” from Urry, are totally unlike their counterparts in the 
                            <hi rend="i">Pilgrims.</hi></note>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> On Linnell and
                        Smith’s inaccuracies, see note 37 below. Butlin, citing Bentley 
                            (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 220), states that Stothard’s engraving appeared before
                        Blake’s “in about November 1809” (1: 475), while Anthony Blunt 
                            (<hi rend="i">The Art of William Blake</hi> [New York: Columbia UP, 1959] 77),
                        followed by Kathleen Raine (<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> [New York:
                        Prager, 1970] 169), states that Cromek “published an engraving after
                        Stothard’s painting, with great profit to himself.” But only the preliminary
                        etching was completed by Schiavonetti in 1809, a few months before his
                        death, and the engraving did not appear till five years after Cromek’s death
                        in 1812.</note></p>
                <p>We should start by recalling the depressed state of the craft of engraving in the
                    1800’s as well as the low ebb of Blake’s fortunes at that time. Partly this was
                    a matter of economics—the decay of the crafts system in general, the low state
                    of the economy, the development of new techniques of reproduction, and the
                    collapse of the European market for English prints as a result of the war with
                    Napoleon. The bank crash of 1797, which had contributed to the failure of
                    Blake’s illustrated edition of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, had also
                    bankrupted Boydell’s ambitious <hi rend="i">Shakespeare Gallery</hi>; the
                    imperilled state of engraving in England during the 1800’s led to the founding
                    of a short-lived Society for the Encouragement of the Art of Engraving by the
                    Chaleographic Society in 1810.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7"
type="note">7</ref><pb
                        id="p22-82" n="82"/> But Blake’s precarious circumstances around 1805—when
                    he was apparently living on a guinea a week<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n8" type="note">8</ref>—must also be seen in terms of changing fashions in graphics. All during
                    his career English taste in printmaking had been shifting away from traditional
                    line engraving to the newer tonal processes of mezzotint, stipple, and aquatint.
                    For Blake, trained primarily in the linear tradition, pure line remained his
                    chosen medium; the “old Hard Stiff &amp; Dry” effects that his teachers at the
                    Royal Academy reproved him for admiring were the very qualities that turned
                    prospective buyers away from <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> and toward the
                    softer more painterly style of Bartolozzi and his disciples.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
                        type="note">9</ref> Contemporary critics found Blake’s engraving technique
                    “defective,” “completely inferior” to such rivals as Schiavonetti, and condemned
                    his designs as “deformity and extravagance.” Boydell, Macklin, and Bowyer had
                    passed him over in their ambitious publishing projects, and now even Hayley and
                    Flaxman were withdrawing their support.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n10" type="note">10</ref> By
                    the autumn of 1805, then, Blake seemed headed toward failure both as independent
                    designer and as commercial engraver. To gain any recognition from the public,
                    his work emphatically needed promotion. <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Dennis
                        M. Read, “The Context of Blake’s ‘Public Address’: Cromek and The
                        Chalcographic Society” <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> 60 (1981):
                        70-75, 80-81.</note>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Cromek’s figure,
                        disputed by Bentley: whose claim that Blake was “riding the crest of a wave
                        of prosperity” in the autumn of 1805 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 173) must,
                        however, be questioned. He estimates Blake’s income for the first ten months
                        of 1805 at £98, or £2.3 a week (186n1). But apart from payments by Flaxman
                        and Butts totalling £37.18 (571-72) there is only a very doubtful commission
                        of 10 guineas from Joseph Thomas in September (166, 606 and G. E. Bentley,
                        Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> [Oxford: Clarendon, 1977], hereafter
                        cited as <hi rend="i">BB</hi>, 420n1) beside a still more doubtful 50
                        guineas for the plates to the 1805 edition of the <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>
                        promised him by the publisher Phillips under a profit-sharing agreement.
                            (<hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed.
                        David V. Erdman [hereafter cited as E] 762-65). To prove this was actually
                        paid Bentley cites a letter of 25 April 1805 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 161,
                        186n1—actually by Phillips not Blake), but the payment is not mentioned in
                        the letter as quoted (161-62). Blake’s letters from June to December 1805 (E
                        765-67) indicate he was in constant want of cash and had heard nothing from
                        Phillips since the <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> were published in June: the
                        1805 venture was apparently as much of a financial loss as the 1802 
                            <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> had been (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 116-17). His final
                        word on the subject is the epigram on Phillips: “He loved me and for no Gain
                        at all / But to rejoice &amp; triumph in my fall” (E 505). It seems, then,
                        that Blake’s income for the ten months leading up to Cromek’s offer was
                        probably not much over £40. From Bentley’s figures for the following year
                            (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 574-75, 606, 617), his income for 1806 came to
                        about £55. Blake’s increasing poverty was an important factor in his state
                        of mind in 1807 and afterward.</note>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> On
                        the ideology of Blake’s opposition to the newer techniques, see Morris
                        Eaves, “Blake and the Artistic Machine: An Essay in Decorum and Technology”
                            <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi> 92 (1977): 907 and 915n16.</note>	
                            <note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 193-94 and n1, 197, 200,
                        54-55, 173-74. Blake was commissioned to engrave only one plate out of the
                        100 included in Boydell’s illustrated <hi rend="i">Shakespeare</hi> 
                            (<hi rend="i">BB</hi> 535-36). Between April 1805 and 1813 he received only a
                        single engraving commission—the plate for Prince Hoare’s 
                            <hi rend="i">Inquiry into the . . . Arts</hi> (1806) <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 571,
                        616-17 and n1).</note></p>
                <p>This is the point at which Robert Hartley Cromek entered the scene. A book
                    collector and moderately successful engraver, Cromek had studied under
                    Bartolozzi at the same time as Schiavonetti; he was a good friend of the
                    Flaxmans and George Cumberland and probably acquainted for some years with both
                    Blake and Stothard. Though his work had won high praise from Flaxman, Cromek
                    decided about this time to give up engraving for the more active life of
                    print-publisher and dealer.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
type="note">11</ref> With little
                    capital behind him, he conceived of a large illustrated edition of Robert
                    Blair’s popular if lugubrious poem <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> as his first
                    project, and he showed a courageous taste in choosing Blake in September 1805 to
                    do the designs. In a letter to Hayley of 27 November 1805 enclosing a copy of a
                    Prospectus for the volume, Blake spoke warmly of his friend Cromek’s
                    “liberality” in commissioning a set of drawings (for a fee of twenty guineas)
                    and of his “Spirited Exertions” in securing the recommendations of thirteen
                    Royal Academicians for the work—the high-water mark of recognition by the
                    Academy that he was to receive in his lifetime. Blake added that Cromek was so
                    pleased with the twenty designs he selected “that he with the same liberality
                    with which he set me about the drawings, has now set me to Engrave them.”<ref
                        target="n12" type="note">12</ref> However, in a second Prospectus almost
                    identical with the first and like it dated November 1805, the number of plates
                    was reduced to twelve and the name of Schiavonetti substituted for Blake’s as
                    the engraver. This action by Cromek has repeatedly been described as a betrayal
                    of Blake, on the assumption that Cromek had arbitrarily transferred the
                    commission to Schiavonetti and perfidiously issued the second Prospectus without
                    informing Blake of his decision, neither of which seems to be the case. The
                    November 1805 date of the second Prospectus, on which the charge of Cromek’s
                    perfidy rests, now appears to be incorrect; it was evidently issued a month or
                    two later, and there is no reason to think that Cromek concealed his decision
                    from Blake till after it was printed.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13"
type="note">13</ref> The
                    decision itself was his reaction to Blake’s first engraving for <hi rend="i">The
                        Grave</hi>, his design for “Death’s Door”—his first plate etched completely
                    in white line, a revolutionary inversion of traditional technique. The potential
                    subscribers who viewed the proofs at Cromek’s place of business were evidently
                    nonplussed or worse; and Cromek, realizing that Blake’s bold ruggedness of
                    treatment would doom the book to failure, hastily turned to Schiavonetti to
                    engrave the designs instead—a move that was within his rights as the originator
                    and financer of the project.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14"
type="note">14</ref> This is not
                    to deny Blake’s disappointment and humiliation, or to accept the popular
                    preference for Schiavonetti’s style over Blake’s, or to recast the “Fiends of
                    Commerce” as the heroes of the piece: only to remind ourselves that—as J. T.
                    Smith drily remarked—“it would be unreasonable to expect the booksellers to
                    embark in publications not likely to meet remuneration.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15"
                        type="note">15</ref>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> On Cromek’s
                        background, see <hi rend="i">DNB</hi> 5: 144 and the “Biographical Sketch of
                        Robert Hartley Cromek” in Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave, A Poem</hi>
                        (London, 1813) 45-54. On his friendship with the Flaxmans, see Irwin 189; on
                        his friendship with Cumberland, see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 198. Flaxman
                        thought his engravings from Stothard “in beauty far exceed any other prints
                        from that Artist’s works” (Wilson 222n)—i.e., including Blake’s; see also
                            <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 154-55.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 168. Contrary to the usual interpretation
                        of the agreement, Blake’s letter implies that in September 1805 Cromek
                        merely commissioned “a set of drawings,” and that the engraving was not
                        agreed on till November. On the other hand, a letter by Flaxman to Hayley of
                        18 October 1805 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 166-67) reports that Cromek had
                        proposed that Blake engrave 20 of his original 40 drawings, but it is not
                        clear whether Flaxman had this information from Cromek or from Blake.
                        Cromek’s fee of a guinea for each finished drawing is what Blake was
                        receiving from Butts for his tempera frescoes at this time.</note>	
                        <note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> See <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 168-71 for the second
                        prospectus; the first prospectus of November 1805, naming Blake as the
                        engraver, was not discovered and printed till G. E. Bentley, Jr.’s article
                        “Blake and Cromek: The Wheat and the Tares” <hi rend="i">Modern
                            Philology</hi> 71 (1974): 367-69. This discovery, along with a letter by
                        Cromek to James Montgomery of April 1807 speaking warmly of Blake (372-75),
                        considerably softened Bentley’s earlier criticism of Cromek 
                            (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 168-71 <hi rend="i">et passim</hi>). Butlin, who like
Bentley
                        notes that the type of the second prospectus was only partly reset (in fact
                        only three lines were altered and three added), suggests (1: 454) that it
                        was issued some time after Blake’s letter to Hayley of 11 December 1805,
                        which thanked him for his “kind Reception” of the “New Projected Work” and
                        said nothing of the commission being given to Schiavonetti (E 766-67). Since
                        the first proof of Schiavonetti’s first etching (also of “Death’s Door”) was
                        dated 12 February 1806, it appears that Schiavonetti was appointed and the
                        prospectus revised in late December or January.</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi
                            rend="s">14</hi> On Blake’s innovative technique, see Robert N. Essick,
                            <hi rend="i">William Blake Printmaker</hi> (Princeton UP, 1980) 107; on
                        Cromek’s reaction, see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 172, and Robert N. Essick and
                        Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Robert Blair’s The Grave Illustrated by
                            William Blake</hi> (London: Scolar Press, 1982) 18. Blake’s and
                        Schiavonetti’s versions of “Death’s Door” are reproduced by Todd 76-77 and
                        by Eaves 920-21. Essick also suggests that Cromek turned to Schiavonetti
                        because he found Blake’s use of perspective faulty in another drawing (“A
                        Preliminary Design for Blake’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Studies</hi> 4 [1972]: 11).</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi><hi
                            rend="i"> BR</hi> 468. Even Gilchrist, who was mainly responsible for
                        the blackening of Cromek’s character, admits that the change was “a happy
                        choice of engravers on Cromek’s part; . . . indeed, Schiavonetti’s
                        engravings introduced Blake’s designs to a wider public than himself could
                        ever have done” (<hi rend="i">Life</hi> 219). Todd 84 suggests that in
                        refusing to work in a more acceptable style Blake “may have been more
                        blameworthy than has usually been admitted.”</note></p>
                <p>However, Cromek has been depicted as an unscrupulous publisher, a “printjobber”
                    who “jockeyed Blake out of his copyright” and made windfall profits on the
                    venture. But Blake would not have retained the copyright even if he had done the
                    engravings for <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>: as with his arrangement in 1796 with
                    Richard Edwards for <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, once he sold his designs
                    the copyright passed automatically to the purchaser, who assumed the costs of
                    publication (including the engraving) in the hope of making a profit.<ref
                        target="n16" type="note">16</ref> Edwards, incidentally, paid Blake a mere
                    twenty guineas—or 9 ½d. each—for his 537 folio-size watercolor designs for 
                        <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, though probably five pounds (Blake’s usual
                    fee) for each of his forty-three engravings.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n17" type="note">17</ref> By May 1807, it is true, Cromek’s twenty-guinea fee for the twenty
                    designs to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> no longer seemed liberal to Blake, who
                    had evidently heard that Cromek had paid Stothard a hundred guineas for his
                    Chaucer painting and was making huge profits on the exhibition: hence his angry
                    demand of four guineas for the dedication page which elicited Cromek’s angry
                    reply. But Cromek’s 
<pb id="p22-83" n="83"/>
profits on <hi rend="i">The
                        Grave</hi> have been vastly exaggerated, from Kathleen Raine’s figure of
                    “about £1800” down to Bentley’s more cautious estimate of £900.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
                        type="note">18</ref> Even this latter figure needs correcting. First, it
                    underestimates Cromek’s fee to Schiavonetti by almost £300; second, it computes
                    the sales figures in terms of the postpublication price of two and a half
                    guineas instead of the subscription price of two guineas; and third, it does not
                    take into account Cromek’s travel expenses for over two years throughout England
                    and Scotland, drumming up subscriptions and then delivering the finished books,
                    which he had packed himself.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
type="note">19</ref> A revised
                    estimate of his profits for nearly three years’ work on the edition comes to
                    about £295—not including travel expenses.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n20" type="note">20</ref>
                    And Cromek’s “Spirited Exertions” did not cease after securing the
                    recommendations of the Academicians. He persuaded Fuseli to write a glowing
                    endorsement of Blake’s designs, exhibited the drawings in London and the
                    provinces, found subscribers for almost 700 copies, advertised the book
                    repeatedly, and finally arranged for the volume to be dedicated to the
                        Queen.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> On the customary copyright arrangements for engravings in
                        Blake’s time, see David Alexander and Richard T. Godfrey, 
                            <hi rend="i">Painters and Engraving: The Reproductive Print from Hogarth to
                            Wilkie</hi> (New Haven: Yale Center for British Art, 1980) 11-12. On
                        Cromek’s “jockeying” see <hi rend="i">Life</hi> 217-19.</note>	
                            <note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 52. On the “not
unusual”
                        disproportion between the designer’s and engraver’s fees and the publisher’s
                        profits, Alexander and Godfrey cite the example of the highly successful
                        print of <hi rend="i">The Destruction of the Children of Niobe</hi>, in
                        which Richard Wilson received 80 guineas for his 1761 painting, Woollett
                        £150 for the engraving, and Boydell collected £2,000 for the sale of the
                        prints (<hi rend="i">Painters and Engravers</hi> 24). As for the 537 
                            <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> watercolors, Edwards’s brother Thomas tried
                        to sell them for 50 guineas in 1826 and 1828, but without success 
                            (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 442n1).</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Raine
                        169: <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 184n3.</note>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi>
                        On Schiavonetti’s fee, see Bentley’s corrected figure in “Blake and Cromek”
                        378; on the subscription price, <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 171 and Dennis M. Read,
                        “Cromek’s Provincial Advertisements for Blake’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>” 
                            <hi rend="i">Notes and Queries</hi> ns 27 (1980) 75; on Cromek’s travels,
                        ibid. 73-75 and Bentley “Blake and Cromek” 378-79.</note>
	<note id="n20"><hi
                            rend="s">20</hi> Using Bentley’s estimates of printing, advertising, and
                        selling costs (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 184n3), plus an additional £280 for the
                        engraving fee, gives total costs for <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> of
                        £1,209.2.6. Sales of 680 subscriptions at two guiness and 20 nonsubscription
                        copies at 2½ guineas, with perhaps five proof copies at four guineas 
                            (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 191), yield a total of 1430 guineas or £1501.10, making
                        an estimated net profit of £292.7.6 (not counting travel expenses). Some
                        copies remained unsold at least five months after publication 
                            (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 213-14).</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> See G. E.
                        Bentley, Jr., “The Promotion of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> Designs” 
                            <hi rend="i">University of Toronto Quarterly</hi> 31 (1962): 34-53; Read,
                        “Advertisements” 73-75. To these efforts should be added Cromek’s persuading
                        Malkin to include an encomium of Blake’s art and poetry and a puff for 
                            <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> in the preface to his <hi rend="i">Father’s
                            Memoir of His Child</hi> (Bentley “Promotion” 348), as well as
                        commissioning Thomas Phillips R.A. to paint Blake’s portrait (engraved by
                        Schiavonetti) for a frontispiece to the volume. And in 1807 and 1808 Cromek,
                        professing admiration of his “Noble though extravagant Flights” (“Blake and
                        Cromek” 372), was apparently trying to find buyers for some of Blake’s
                        earlier books (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 191 and n1). However, as Essick and
                        Paley point out, all Cromek’s “bustling and puffing” could not produce
                        favorable reviews of <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>: only one mildly positive
                        one and two long negative ones are known (<hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> 25;
                            <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 195ff., 199ff., 201ff.).</note></p>
                <p>With this first episode of the Blake-Cromek relationship in mind we may turn back
                    to the quarrel over the <hi rend="i">Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> project. The first
                    point at issue is whether the idea for the painting originated with Blake or
                    with Cromek. Both Smith and Linnell state that it was Blake’s: but this
                    ascription is unlikely, even though it has been almost universally accepted. In
                    the first place, both Smith and Linnell erroneously credit Blake with the
                    original idea for the <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> designs, and they may be in
                    similar error about the Chaucer project. More important, it was Blake’s habit as
                    an engraver to work on “tasks happily prescribed by others,” as Gilchrist put
                    it, especially with ambitious undertakings such as <hi rend="i">Night
                        Thoughts</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi> Living largely on publishers’
                    advances, continually short of cash, Blake simply could not afford to embark on
                    a long-term independent project in 1805; in fact, with the exception of his
                    illustrations to Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>, he had not published any
                    engravings of his own design for over ten years.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n22" type="note">22</ref> Furthermore, it is striking that Blake never evinced an interest
                    in Chaucer prior to his 1808 painting and his 1809 <hi rend="i">Descriptive
                        Catalogue.</hi> Only one reference to Chaucer occurs in all his poetry, on
                    the next-to-last page of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (98:9), and his discussion
                    of Chaucer’s universality in the <hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi> is heavily indebted
                    to Dryden’s comments in his preface to the <hi rend="i">Fables.</hi><ref
                        target="n23" type="note">23</ref> Indeed, from all we know of Blake’s
                    preoccupations in 1805, a painting of Chaucer’s Pilgrims seems one of the least
                    likely projects he could have undertaken. In the absence of any expressed
                    concern with Chaucer by Blake before 1808, there seems no reason, then, to doubt
                    Cromek’s word when he congratulated himself “for thinking of such a glorious
                    Subject” in a letter to James Montgomery of April 1807.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24"
                        type="note">24</ref> Cromek’s own interest in Chaucer—like that of many
                    other readers including Coleridge—may have been kindled by William Godwin’s
                    popular biography of 1803, the first attempt at a full-length life. His account
                    of picking up a copy of the <hi rend="i">Tales</hi> in Halifax in the summer of
                    1806 while waiting for the London coach and conceiving of the idea for a
                    painting of the Pilgrims which he then took to Stothard, is at least as
                    circumstantial as Blake’s story preserved by Smith and Linnell.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25"
                        type="note">25</ref>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> See 
                            <hi rend="i">Life</hi> 95. Excepting the illuminated books and <hi rend="i">The
                            Gates of Paradise</hi>, only 17 or 18 of the more than 600 plates
                        engraved by Blake during his lifetime were done on his own initiative, not
                        on commission; and of these he published under his own copyright only five:
                        “Edward &amp; Elenor,” “Job,” “Ezekiel,” and “The Accusers” (all dated
                        1793-94), and in 1810 “Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims” (Essick 
                            <hi rend="i">Plates</hi> 3-122 <hi rend="i">passim</hi>). <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
                        and possibly <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, begun probably about this time,
                        were of course independent large-scale projects from which Blake expected no
                        financial reward proportionate to his investment of time: presumably they
                        would have occupied all the attention he had left for unremunerative
                        work.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> This single reference to
                        Chaucer outside the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, the 
                            <hi rend="i">Public Address</hi>, and the 1809-10 prospectuses for the
                        Chaucer engraving contrasts significantly with Blake’s frequent mention of
                        other poets: Milton (61, excluding references in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>),
                        Shakespeare (20), Dryden (10), Chatterton (7), Spenser (6), Pope (5), and
                        Gray (5): see <hi rend="i">A Concordance to the Writings of William
                            Blake</hi> ed. David V. Erdman, 2 vols. (Ithaca: Cornell UP, 1967) 
                            <hi rend="i">passim.</hi> It is often assumed that Blake was familiar with
                        Chaucer from his earliest years (see e.g., Michael Phillips “Blake and the
                        ‘Unincreasable Club’ ” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of the New York Public
                            Library</hi> 80 (1976): 30, and Robert Gleckner, <hi rend="i">Blake’s
                            Prelude</hi> [Baltimore: The Johns Hopkins UP, 1982] 137). But neither
                        Phillips nor Gleckner in their studies of Blake’s early poetry demonstrates
                        any Chaucerian influence; and Karl Kiralis, noting his erratic
                        transcriptions in the <hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi>, questions his later
                        knowledge of the <hi rend="i">Tales</hi> (“William Blake as an Intellectual
                        and Spiritual Guide to Chaucer’s Canterbury Pilgrims” <hi rend="i">Blake
                            Studies</hi> 1 [1969]: 171-74). It is significant that in quoting a line
                        from Dryden’s translation of “The Knight’s Tale” in <hi rend="i">For
                            Children: The Gates of Paradise</hi> Blake attributed it to Dryden
                        rather than Chaucer (see <hi rend="i">The Notebook of William Blake</hi>,
                        ed. David V. Erdman [Oxford: Clarendon, 1973] N69). Though Chaucer was
                        included among the “Heads of the Poets” which he painted for Hayley’s
                        library, these portraits clearly reflect Hayley’s choice rather than Blake’s
                        own (Butlin 1: 297; Bindman 133-34). On his debt to Dryden see S. Foster
                        Damon <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary</hi> (New York: Dutton, 1971) 78-79;
                        on his wavering admiration for Chaucer see Essick <hi rend="i">Plates</hi>
                        68-69, 87.</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Bentley “Blake and
                        Cromek” 372. Bentley’s discovery of this letter prompted both Erdman (518)
                        and Lindsay (193) to raise the possibility that the original idea for the
                            <hi rend="i">Pilgrims</hi> was indeed Cromek’s.</note>
	<note id="n25"><hi
                            rend="s">25</hi> “Biographical Sketch” in Blair (1813) xlviii. On
                        Godwin’s biography see Caroline Spurgeon. <hi rend="i">Five Hundred Years of
                            Chaucer Criticism and Allusion</hi> (Cambridge UP, 1925) 1: ciii, cxi
                        and <hi rend="i">Collected Letters of Samuel Taylor Coleridge</hi>, ed. E.
                        L. Griggs (Oxford: Clarendon, 1956) 2: 951, 1054. It is significant that the
                        minutely detailed description of the social-historical background for which
                        Godwin’s work was generally praised (Spurgeon 2: 9-19, 31-37) is the same
                        “antiquarian exactness” for which Stothard’s painting was acclaimed (see the
                        “Prospectus” for the engraving of Stothard’s <hi rend="i">Procession</hi> in
                        Blair <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> [London: 1808] [38]—to which Blake’s
                        rather Johnsonian praise of Chaucer’s universality was diametrically
                        opposed.</note></p>
                <p>The second question in dispute is whether, as Blake asserted to Linnell, Cromek
                    actually commissioned him to design the <hi rend="i">Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>,
                    with the promise of the engraving fee to follow. The issue is largely academic
                    since, if the idea was Cromek’s to begin with, he would have been within his
                    rights to take the subject to Stothard if, after first proposing it to Blake, he
                    had been dissatisfied with Blake’s initial treatment of it—as indeed he would
                    have been bewildered by the consciously archaic style Blake adopted for his
                    design. However, it is significant that J. T. Smith, whose record of the affair
                    in 1828 was based on first-hand discussion with a number of Blake’s friends,
                    made no reference to a commission; it was Allan Cunningham who first mentioned
                    it two years later, simply to record Cromek’s denial that he had ever given
                        one.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref> A third
question is whether Blake
                    in fact made a pencil sketch of the subject in 1805 or early 1806, which would
                    bolster though not clinch his claim that Cromek stole his idea. No drawing that
                    can be so dated survives, though Gilchrist recounts a curious story concerning
                        <figure n="CanterburyPilgrimsDetail.22.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="849"/>
<pb
                        id="p22-84" n="84"/> such a sketch. Blake, as he tells it, hung his original
                    design for the <hi rend="i">Pilgrims</hi> on his sitting room wall for perhaps a
                    year before the appearance of Stothard’s <hi rend="i">Procession</hi> in 1807;
                    then on taking it down to use for his own fresco “he found it nearly effaced:
                    the result of some malignant spell of Stothard’s,” as he insisted later to
                    Flaxman, who naturally pooh-poohed the suggestion.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n27" type="note">27</ref> Since neither Smith nor Linnell mentioned this incident in his
                    account of the affair, it may be another piece of the Blake apocrypha; but even
                    if Blake made the charge to Flaxman, the story itself does not prove that an
                    1805 sketch ever existed. Yet interestingly enough, a drawing of the Pilgrims
                    does survive whose appearance clearly indicates that it was hung on the wall as
                    Gilchrist describes. This is the drawing of 1809 or 1810, soiled and faded and
                    showing tack marks at top and bottom, which Blake made to reduce the design of
                    his painting to the dimensions of his plate for engraving.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28"
                        type="note">28</ref> So Gilchrist’s story may recall an actual conversation,
                    though it is misleadingly vague as to the date. Either the exchange took place,
                    as Gilchrist suggests, in 1807 or 1808, and Blake invoked Stothard’s “malignant
                    spell” to explain to Flaxman the absence of an earlier sketch of the subject
                    that would prove his priority; or possibly the incident occurred some years
                    later, when Blake could have pointed to the 1809-10 drawing as the “original
                    design” from which Stothard had stolen his theme. In either event, the drawing
                    remained as concrete evidence for Linnell or another informant to later convince
                    Gilchrist of the truth of Blake’s version of the case. One more point at issue,
                    Crabb Robinson’s vague recollection in 1852 of hearing some thirty years earlier
                    of a prospectus for Blake’s engraving circulated in 1806, proves a red herring
                    on close inspection.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29"
type="note">29</ref>
	<note id="n26"><hi
                            rend="s">26</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 464-65, 491. While Cunningham’s
                        memoir of Blake is unreliable in a number of details, it is likely to be
                        accurate in his account of Cromek, whom he knew well from his mildly
                        discreditable part in the <hi rend="i">Remains of Nithsdale and Galloway
                            Song</hi>, published by Cromek in 1809-10 (<hi rend="i">Life</hi>
                        250-52).</note>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi><hi rend="i"> Life</hi>
                        241. Wilson insists (235) that Blake was jesting when he made this remark,
                        if indeed he did: but it is in keeping with other wild accusations Blake
                        made during these years (see note 46 below).</note>
	<note id="n28"><hi
                            rend="s">28</hi> Butlin 1 no. 654, 2 pl. 880. The verso is inscribed by
                        Tatham, who inherited the drawing from Catherine Blake, “The Original
                        reduced Drawing made to reduce the Picture of the Canterbury Pilgrims to the
                        size of the Plate Blake afterwards engraved.” Linnell, who probably relayed
                        the story to Gilchrist, was evidently aware of the drawing’s existence but
                        not of its date: perhaps because Tatham wrote his note shortly before
                        offering it for sale in 1862 or, as Morton Paley has suggested in
                        correspondence, because Linnell, whose relations with Tatham were strained,
                        was given no opportunity to examine it.</note>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">29</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 538, 179 and n3.</note></p>
                <p>Beyond the unlikelihood of Blake’s conceiving of the <hi rend="i">Canterbury
                        Pilgrims</hi> in 1805, however, there are more positive reasons for linking
                    the project to 1808, the date recorded on the painting. The first is Blake’s
                    probable motive in undertaking the Chaucer painting at this time. Nothing in
                    Blake’s art of 1805—predominantly Biblical themes in a recreation of his earlier
                    neoclassic manner—provides a context for the Gothic style and realistic subject
                    matter of the <hi rend="i">Pilgrims.</hi> But in 1807, his simmering resentment
                    against Cromek and Schiavonetti over the Blair project, the success of
                    Stothard’s painting (which Schiavonetti had now been appointed to engrave), and
                    Cromek’s insolent challenge to “send me a better” evidently roused Blake to
                    indignant protest, not only against Stothard’s treatment of the subject but also
                    against the whole system that produced it. For the 
                    <figure n="CanterburyProcessionDetail.22.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="842"/>
					<hi rend="i">Pilgrims</hi> is not simply the most consciously archaic of all Blake’s
                    works: its archaism is not merely a style but a statement. The unholy alliance
                    of publisher, painter, and engraver—Cromek, Stothard, and Schiavonetti—was to
                    Blake the cause of the corruption of art in his time, in which increasingly the
                    conception of a design was isolated from both its execution and, at one more
                    remove, its reproduction, and the role of the artist increasingly subordinated
                    to that of the entrepreneur. This system of production, which Morris Eaves has
                    aptly named “the artistic machine,” Blake saw reflected in the “broken lines”
                    and mechanical techniques of Schiavonetti’s stipple and mezzotint, to which
                    Blake scornfully contrasted the integrity of his own linear style, the unbroken
                    line which is the test of true artistry. As he wrote years later, “A Line is a
                    Line in its Minutest Subdivision[s] Strait or Crooked It is Itself &amp; Not
                    Intermeasurable with or by any Thing Else” (E 783). Thus his choice of the style
                    he had learned from “Alb. Durer and the old Engravers” (E 572) was not a simple
                    quest of historical accuracy, like the “antiquarian exactness” of Stothard’s
                    painting based on patient research in the British Museum; more significantly it
                    was a return to the spirit of his uncorrupted youth, the Gothic world of
                    Westminster Abbey and the medieval master craftsmen. Integrity of style was to
                    be matched by integrity of production: Blake conceived his own vision of the 
                    <hi rend="i">Pilgrims</hi>, painted it, exhibited it, engraved it, advertised
                    and sold it all on his own. “If a man is master of his profession,” he wrote at
                    the end of the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, “and if he is not
                    employed by 
                    <pb id="p22-85" n="85"/>
                    <figure n="CanterburyCrowdDetail.22.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="849"/> 
                    those who pretend to
                    encourage art, he will employ himself and laugh in secret at the pretences of
                    the ignorant”—thus gaining “a reward for the labours of the day, such as the
                    world cannot give” (E 550). The <hi rend="i">Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> must be
                    read as Blake’s answer to Schiavonetti’s facile virtuosity, Stothard’s
                    inauthentic medievalism, and Cromek’s crass commercialism.</p>
                <p>The most concrete evidence against the received account of the controversy,
                    however, is found in Blake’s published remarks on the affair. It is striking to
                    note that nowhere in the <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> of 1809 does he
                    charge Cromek with stealing his idea for the <hi rend="i">Canterbury
                    Pilgrims.</hi> Rather, Blake tells us, his picture was painted “in
                    self-defence against the insolent and envious imputation of unfitness for
                    finished and scientific art.” Cromek’s rejection of his engraving for 
                    <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> now seemed a slander on his abilities which, he
                    hints, Cromek has “artfully and industriously endeavoured to be propagated among
                    the public by ignorant hirelings,” i.e., reviewers. He “courts comparison” with
                    his competitors (Cromek and Stothard) and accuses Cromek of having reaped
                    enormous profits from his designs for <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> by employing
                    another more docile engraver (Schiavonetti) to produce a work which has gained
                    both of them “public patronage,” while Blake’s designs “which gained them that
                    patronage are cried down as eccentricity and madness” (E 537-38). These
                    outbursts spring partly from Blake’s rage at the reviews of <hi rend="i">The
                    Grave</hi> in the latter half of 1808—first and foremost the Hunts’ 
                    <hi rend="i">Examiner</hi>—which attacked his designs as “indecent,”
                    “absurd,”
                    “the offspring of a morbid fancy” which “has totally failed” in its aim, while
                    commending “the unrivalled graver of L. Schiavonetti.” However, these were only
                    salt in the wounds Blake was still nursing over Cromek’s substitution of
                    Schiavonetti as engraver, his failure to pay Blake what he now thought he
                    deserved for his designs, his outrageous letter of May 1807, and a number of
                    other grievances—now climaxed in Blake’s imagination by Cromek’s complicity in
                    the reviewers’ 
                    attacks.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">30</ref> 
                    But to all such
                    aspersions and calumnies, he asserts, “the works now exhibited will give the
                    lie.” Following this defense with an attack, Blake links Stothard with “a class
                    of men”—Reynolds and his followers in the Royal Academy—“whose whole art and
                    science is fabricated for the purpose of destroying art,” as Blake saw it, by
                    promoting Venetian over Florentine principles, coloring over drawing; he then
                    convicts such painters of “Stupidity” by a withering analysis of Stothard’s 
                        <hi rend="i">Procession</hi> as described in his Prospectus (E 538-40). 
                        <note id="n30"><hi rend="s">30</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 195-97, 199-208, 209-10.
                        Blake’s grievances include Cromek’s insistence on re-engraving Blake’s plate
                        for the frontispiece to Malkin’s <hi rend="i">Memoir</hi> in 1806 (Dennis M.
                        Read, “A New Blake Engraving: Gilchrist and the Cromek Connection” 
                            <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 14 [1980]: 64); his failure to mention Blake by name
                        in several of the advertisements to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (Bentley,
                        “Promotion” 351); his failure to acknowledge Blake’s contribution in his
                        prefactory advertisement to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> while praising
                        Schiavonetti’s engravings (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 192-93); his omission of
                        Blake’s name from the title page (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 529); and his
                        inclusion of a glowing prospectus for the engraving of Stothard’s 
                            <hi rend="i">Procession</hi> at the end of the volume, announcing the
                        patronage of the Prince of Wales for the print (Blair [1808] 37).</note></p>
                <p>In the <hi rend="i">Public Address</hi> of 1810 Blake extends these lines of
                    attack and defense to his engraving of the <hi rend="i">Pilgrims</hi>, decrying
                    the modern style of engraving of Bartolozzi and his followers as contaminated by
                    painterly principles of tone, and upholding his own work as founded firmly on
                    line. He rails especially against “the artfully propagated pretence” that “Great
                    Inventors” such as himself “cannot Execute,” or that “A Translation or a Copy of
                    any kind” can be as good as “An Original Invention”—in short, that an engraver
                    such as Schiavonetti can do justice to Blake’s own designs (E 572, 576, 582).
                    Clearly his humiliation over the Blair illustrations is still as much on his
                    mind as his need to promote his Chaucer engraving; but even if his protest
                    against his competitors’ Calumny &amp; the Arts of Trading Combination” (E 577)
                    is read as referring to the dispute over the <hi rend="i">Pilgrims</hi> rather
                    than to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, still it attacks Cromek not for stealing
                    his original idea but for maligning his abilities and for promoting Stothard’s
                    painting far more successfully than Blake did his own.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
                        type="note">31</ref>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">31</hi> The one allusion to
                        “robbery” in the <hi rend="i">Public Address</hi> is a veiled reference to
                        alleged borrowings much earlier in his career by Stothard and Flaxman (E
                        582: see 508, 540). Other references in the <hi rend="i">Descriptive
                            Catalogue</hi> and <hi rend="i">Public Address</hi> to “imitation,”
                        “copy,” “original,” “thieves,” and “plagiarism” are not directed at
Cromek
                        or Stothard at all, nor are there any to “steal” or “cheat.”</note></p>
                <p>The failure of the 1809 Exhibition, followed by that of the Chaucer engraving (of
                    which he may have sold only seven or eight copies out of a printing of thirty or
                        so),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">32</ref> was a
staggering blow, the climax
                    of a long series of disappointments and (as he saw them) betrayals since the end
                    of 1805. In the epigrams Blake began scribbling in his Notebook at about this
                    time, Cromek is prominent among the “foes” on whom he vents his rage: but the
                    terms of his attack deserve close scrutiny. Cromek is 
                        <pb id="p22-86" n="86"/>
<figure n="CanterburySteepleDetail.22.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="841"/> denounced as
                    “a petty sneaking knave,” who loves the art only of cheating, and who in trying
                    “to please everybody” has “set to work Both ignorance and skill”—i.e., has
                    employed Schiavonetti to engrave Blake’s designs for <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>
                    rather than Blake himself. The one possible reference to the 
                        <hi rend="i">Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> affair—and a murky one at that—occurs in the
                    enigmatic poem “And his legs carried it like a long fork” (E 503-04). This poem,
                    begun late in 1810, apparently celebrates Blake’s publication of his Chaucer
                    engraving ahead of Stothard’s, thereby frustrating the schemes of Screwmuch
                    (Cromek), Stewhard (Stothard), and Assassinetti (Schiavonetti) to cheat Blake
                    out of a just reward for his talents. Though Cromek has peddled Stothard’s
                    painting the length and breadth of Great Britain, it has been to no avail. His
                    “eggs” (the profits from the exhibition of Stothard’s painting) have been
                    “addled and decayed” by Schiavonetti’s death in June 1810 before finishing the
                    engraving which would have proved still more lucrative to Cromek, while at the
                    same time he has failed to turn “the wretched soul of William Blake” into “eggs
                    of gold” for his own profit. And when Cromek, almost penniless, died of
                    tuberculosis in 1812, Blake added some lines savagely exulting over his demise
                    as well as the deaths or misfortunes of other enemies and some former friends—an
                    alarming index to his state of mind at the time.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n33" type="note">33</ref>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">32</hi> Essick 
                            (<hi rend="i">Plates</hi> 60-70) lists 29 prints made during Blake’s lifetime.
Actual
                        sales in Blake’s lifetime are recorded for only about seven copies 
                            (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 592 and 594, and Essick <hi rend="i">Plates</hi> 63,
                        64, 75, 76). The price was set at four guineas to subscribers in the 1809
                        prospectus (“to be considerably raised to Non-subscribers,” E 567), lowered
                        to three guineas in 1810, and sold for two or 2½ guineas in 1826-28 
                            (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 592, 594-95, 607). The first three obituaries of Blake
                        failed to mention the <hi rend="i">Pilgrims</hi> among his other works; the
                        fourth described it as though it were unknown (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 348-50,
                        351-53, 354-55, 357).</note>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">33</hi> The
                        “enemies” include “Billy’s Lawyer” Rose—“Sweet Rose” (E 759)—his old
friend
                        Flaxman, and his erstwhile employer Prince Hoare as well as the brothers
                        Hunt and the villainous dragoon Scholfield, who died in 1812 
                            (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 669). “Dady Jack Hemps Parson” may be the Rev. Joseph
Thomas, a
                        friend of Flaxman’s and a generous patron to Blake, who died in 1811 
                            (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 674). “Dady” or “daddy” was a current term of
contempt
                        for a prim old man (see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 53). “Cur, my Lawyer” is
                        probably Charles Ker, a barrister with whom Blake was embroiled in a lawsuit
                        in 1810, and whose father lost a famous and expensive lawsuit in 1812 (see
                            <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 227-28 and n3).</note></p>
                <p>Yet it is striking that Stothard, Flaxman, and Hayley come in for more frequent
                    and violent abuse in the Notebook poems than Cromek.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34"
                        type="note">34</ref> Stothard is compared to “The Fox, the Owl, the Beetle
                    &amp; the Bat” and is attacked as “the golden fool” who has “grown old and rich”
                    by observing “the golden rule,” the seeming “friend of all mankind” who is in
                    truth iron-hearted, wooden-headed, brazen-faced (E 508, 503). These verses
                    express Blake’s resentment of Stothard’s financial success and his coolness to
                    an old friend, however, rather than raise any charge of plagiarism. The animus
                    against Stothard seems excessive, especially in the light of Stothard’s
                    cordiality in 1806, when he is said to have promised to include a portrait of
                    Blake among his Pilgrims “as a mark of esteem for him and his works.”<ref
                        target="n35" type="note">35</ref> When his painting appeared in 1807 it
                    contained no such portrait: but this would hardly account for Blake’s anger.
                    Perhaps Stothard in an expansive moment actually promised Blake the commission
                    for engraving his work—a promise that Cromek would have forced him to withdraw.
                    Such a hypothesis would at least account for the mysterious commission of a
                    Chaucer engraving which Blake believed he had received but which Cromek denied
                    he had ever given. Blake goes on in the Notebook to link Stothard with Flaxman
                    as his two Calibans, treacherous “old acquaintance” whom he “taught to see” but
                    who now “have shewn their backsides,” and who spread the poisonous rumor that
                    “Blakified drawing spoils painter &amp; engraver” (E 508, 505). The assault on
                    Flaxman, the innocent bystander, is surprising. Like Stothard he is accused of
                    copying Blake; but a more frequent accusation is that he has refused to believe
                    Blake and demanded “a proof of what he can’t perceive,” mocking Blake as a
                    “madman”—who replies by calling him a “blockhead” (E 507, 501). Perhaps this
                    exchange of insults was precipitated by Flaxman’s refusal to believe Blake’s
                    improbable story of Stothard’s casting a “malignant spell” on his original
                    sketch of the <hi rend="i">Pilgrims</hi> when Flaxman quizzed him, as he must
                    have done, on his reason for apparently copying Stothard’s design.<ref
                        target="n36" type="note">36</ref>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">34</hi> Cromek
                        is mentioned in nine of the epigrams, Hayley in 10, and Stothard and Flaxman
                        in 11 each (under their respective aliases in “And his legs carried it like
                        a long fork,”) (Erdman <hi rend="i">Concordance</hi> s.v.)</note>	
                        <note id="n35"><hi rend="s">35</hi><hi rend="i"> Life</hi> 221.</note>	
                        <note id="n36"><hi rend="s">36</hi> Flaxman evidently had a falling-out with Blake
                        in 1808, which seems to have lasted till 1814 or 1815: see 
                            <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 190, 241-422, 235, 239 and <hi rend="i">BB</hi>
419.</note></p>
                <p>Thus we are faced like Flaxman, and later J. T. Smith, with the difficult
                    question of how far we can take Blake’s word against Cromek and Stothard’s in
                    the matter. Discounting the story of supernatural influences on the mysterious
                    pencil sketch of 1805, how much can we believe of the account Blake gave Linnell
                    that Cromek saw his drawing of the Pilgrims, commissioned him to paint it for
                    twenty guineas, promised him the engraving fee in addition while secretly
                    negotiating with another 
<pb id="p22-87" n="87"/>
engraver, then “sneaked” the
                    idea to Stothard when Blake refused to surrender his design? This account, as we
                    have seen, is backed by no external evidence and indeed conflicts with most of
                    the facts surrounding the matter. It is possible, of course, that Linnell’s
                    recollection in 1855 of his conversations with Blake around 1820 is at fault.
                    Like Smith’s memoir of 1828 his note on the affair contains some factual
                    inaccuracies, and in certain details—notably the promise of the engraving
                    commission subsequently withdrawn—it suspiciously resembles the episode of the
                        <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> illustrations, belonging also to the fall of 1805,
                    which may have fused with it in Linnell’s memory.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">37</ref> But, given Blake’s emotional state around 1809 and after,
it seems
                    more likely that this fusion or confusion had already taken place in Blake’s
                    mind when he talked with Linnell a decade or so after the event, and that this
                    is the real origin of the story. Blake’s version of the affair is thus probably
                    a gradual reconfiguration of the events during his years of obscurity after
                    1810, when he had alienated all of his old friends and was left to brood over
                    their injustices in isolation.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38"
type="note">38</ref> In either
                    case, when all the contemporary evidence is taken into account the contemporary
                    understanding of the coincidence between the two Chaucer paintings seems the
                    probable one—that Blake commenced his picture in rivalry to Stothard’s 
                        (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 492, 209, 243-44). No disinterested witness at the time
                    supports Blake’s claim to priority, and the factual evidence all points in the
                    other direction. <note id="n37"><hi rend="s">37</hi> Linnell accepts Smith’s
                        misstatement that Blake himself had the original idea for the 
                            <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> illustrations and has Blake starting work on his Chaucer
                        engraving in 1806 (<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 464 and n1), two years before
                        completing his painting and three years before he started to engrave it (E
                        567-68). The coincidences between the Blair and the Chaucer projects in
                        Linnell’s account are the commission with the 20 guinea fee for the designs;
                        the promise on which Cromek reneged that Blake would do the engraving; and
                        the negotiations behind Blake’s back with another engraver.</note>	
                        <note id="n38"><hi rend="s">38</hi> Gilchrist’s statement (<hi rend="i">Life</hi>
                        247) that “to the end of his life” Blake would abuse Stothard to strangers
                        with “unaccountable vehemence,” while keeping silent to friends and
                        sympathizers about the affair, suggests that he sensed his side of the story
                        would not bear close examination.</note></p>
                <p>The difficult question remains of how Blake arrived at his conviction that the
                    idea for the Chaucer painting was originally his; and an answer here must be
                    almost completely speculative. It must start from the premise that Blake lived
                    in an eidetic world, thronged with precise visual images having the force of
                    reality, with a visual memory developed to an unusual degree by his training in
                    art and well-stocked with years of study of the work of other artists. Many of
                    his apparently original designs have been shown to be based on (probably
                    unconscious) recollections of other works, both contemporary and ancient, from a
                    wide range of sources—which is not to deny that what he borrowed from other
                    artists he transmuted into something wholly his own.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39"
                        type="note">39</ref> Like many of his other paintings, then, the 
                        <hi rend="i">Pilgrims</hi> may well have been an amalgamation of half-conscious
                    memories of other works under the pressure of some immediate stimulus. It may
                    well be that, as has been suggested, Blake saw the Elgin Marbles not long after
                    they were placed on exhibition in 1807 and this visual experience—especially in
                    conjunction with his view of Stothard’s <hi rend="i">Procession</hi> around the
                    same time—was the seed of his own conception. The sight of the actual Marbles
                    would certainly have brought to the surface of his memory the line engravings of
                    the Panathenaic Procession reproduced in Stuart and Revett’s 
                        <hi rend="i">Antiquities of Athens</hi>, which he had studied as a young man and which
                    are closer in feeling to his own work than the sculptures themselves. But quite
                    apart from the Marbles, Stothard’s procession evidently triggered a recollection
                    of two other cavalcades—those of two outsized engravings by Basire which have
                    been claimed were the primary influences on both the scale and the archaic style
                    of his <hi rend="i">Pilgrims</hi>—“The Field of the Cloth of Gold” (1774) and
                    “The Procession of Edward VI” (1787), the latter of which was especially close
                    to Blake’s design.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
type="note">40</ref> It seems, then, that
                    from all these recollections fusing in his visual memory arose a new image of
                    the same compelling vividness as the spiritual publications he described years
                    later to Crabb Robinson, to which the existence of actual manuscripts was
                    irrelevant—one of “those wonderful Originals seen in my visions” before he ever
                    set pencil to paper.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41"
type="note">41</ref> Thus Stothard’s
                    cavalcade would have appeared to him as a copy of an idea he had long had in
                    mind, which he gradually became convinced he had sketched a year or two before
                    seeing Stothard’s painting in progress. <note id="n39"><hi rend="s">39</hi> See
                        the discussions by C. H. Collins Baker, “The Sources of Blake’s Pictorial
                        Expression” <hi rend="i">Huntington Library Quarterly</hi> 4 (1940): 359-67;
                        Blunt 33-43; and <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, ed. Robert N. Essick
                        and Donald Pearce (Bloomington: Indiana UP, 1978) <hi rend="i">passim.</hi>
                        On Blake’s eideticism see Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Energy and the
                            Imagination</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1970) 202-05, and Joseph Burke,
                        “The Eidetic and the Borrowed Image: An Interpretation of Blake’s Theory and
                        Practice of Art” in <hi rend="i">The Visionary Hand</hi>, ed. Robert N.
                        Essick (Los Angeles: Hennessy and Ingalls, 1973) 263-67, 271-77.</note>	
                        <note id="n40"><hi rend="s">40</hi> Laurence Binyon, <hi rend="i">The Engraved
                            Designs of William Blake</hi> (London: Benn, 1926) 62, and Essick 
                            <hi rend="i">Printmaker</hi> 189-90, which provides a detailed comparison of
                        Basire’s and Blake’s engraving technique. As is apparent from the
                        reproduction, the compositional similarities between Basire’s print and
                        Blake’s are far closer than those suggested to the Elgin Marbles (see note 1
                        above). In addition to the frieze-like arrangement of the figures with
                        near-isocephaly noted by Essick, Blake’s design closely parallels Basire’s
                        in the gently rolling hills and dense foliage of the trees in the
                        background; in the architectural details of diamond-paned windows, Gothic
                        spires and gateway, and pillars enclosing sculptures of ecclesiastics; and
                        most of all in the horses and their trappings, an unlikely subject for
                        Blake. The similarities to the Parthenon frieze adduced by Macmillan (see
                        note 1 above) are generalized and remote by comparison—not only the human
                        figures but especially the horses. In the Panathenaic procession the horses
                        with their bare-back riders move from right to left in a bounding canter,
                        tossing their heads, with both forefeet usually off the ground; the London
                        cavalcade moves from left to right at a dignified walk or slow trot. Blake’s
                        improbable rendition of Chaucer’s horse with both left feet off the ground
                        at the same moment may result from his amalgamation of the front and rear
                        ends of two horses at the rear of the mounted procession in Basire’s print,
                        each partly obscured by a pillar: which suggests that he may have refreshed
                        his memory by another view of the print. Its heroic dimensions (22¾ × 52½
                        inches) are only slightly larger than those of Blake’s engraving (18⅜ × 53
                        15/16 inches).</note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">41</hi> <hi rend="i">
                            BR</hi> 322; E 531. On the indebtedness of such “original” visions to
                        recollections of earlier images, see Morton D. Paley, “‘Wonderful Originals’
                        —Blake and Ancient Sculpture” in <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>
                        170-97.</note></p>
                <p>In conclusion, two points must be made. First, it appears that Cromek has been
                    “much maligned,” as William Bell Scott, a Victorian collector and editor of
                    Blake’s engravings, later opined. From Gilchrist onward he has been described as
                    “slippery,” “greedy,” “treacherous,” an opportunist who “picked the brains
of
                    his proteges and stopped the pay.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42"
type="note">42</ref> Partly
                    this may be due to the fact that the role of artistic and literary entrepreneur
                        <figure n="CanterburyTownDetail.22.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="848"/>
<pb id="p22-88"
                        n="88"/> was still relatively new and not highly regarded in Blake’s
                        time;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">43</ref> it is
also true that Cromek, who
                    seems to have operated on a very narrow margin of cash, was not generous in his
                    dealings and engaged in sharp and perhaps shady practices. Cromek was no hero:
                    he was quick-tempered, brash, disingenuous, and drove a hard bargain though to
                    no great financial return. Yet it has been claimed in the light of recent
                    evidence that he also showed “a surprising breadth of aesthetic and intellectual
                    sympathy” with Blake in the earlier stage of their relationship; moreover, that
                    he was the most reliable and conscientious of Robert Burns’s nineteenth-century
                    editors as well as an enterprising and energetic collector of unpublished
                        material.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">44</ref>
Cromek’s career as a whole
                    awaits reassessment; in his relationship with Blake he should at the very least
                    be given credit for introducing Blake’s art to the widest public he was to have
                    in his lifetime with the designs to <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, and doing
                    everything in his power to ensure the success of the work. 
                            <note id="n42"><hi rend="s">42</hi><hi rend="i"> Life</hi> 221, 250, 244, 252. See
Wilson
                        227 (“a second-rate engraver”), Bernard Blackstone, <hi rend="i">English
                            Blake</hi> (Cambridge UP, 1949) 123 (“an exploiter more unscrupulous and
                        more cunning than Hayley”), and so forth. Essick and Paley give evidence of
                        his hard dealings with other business associates (<hi rend="i">Blair’s
                            Grave</hi> 18), and Bentley even blames “the obscurity and poverty of
                        Blake’s last years” on Cromek for discouraging Blake “from appealing
                        directly to the public” (“Blake and Cromek” 375-76). Dennis M. Read, who has
                        published valuable research on Cromek’s career, has raised doubts in
                        correspondence about several of the charges leveled against him by
                        Gilchrist, such as Cromek’s stealing an autograph letter by Ben Jonson from
                        Sir Walter Scott (<hi rend="i">Life</hi> 252-53) and failing to pay Stothard
                        the extra £40 promised for his <hi rend="i">Procession</hi> (253). On
                        Cromek’s financial difficulties over the engraving of Stothard’s picture,
                        see Read, “Engraving” 60-65; on W. B. Scott see <hi rend="i">BR</hi> 193 and
                        Todd in <hi rend="i">Life</hi> 384, 386.</note>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">43</hi> The first recorded use of the term 
                            <hi rend="i">entrepreneur</hi> in the sense of “manager” occurs in 1828: “an
animal
                        whom it is supposed lawful and commendable to bleed at every vein” 
                            (<hi rend="i">OED</hi> Supplement).</note>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">44</hi>
                        Bentley “Blake and Cromek” 366, 376-77; J. DeLancey Ferguson, “In Defense of
                        R. H. Cromek” <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> 9 (1930): 239-48; and
                        Dennis M. Read, “Practicing ‘The Necessity of Purification’: Cromek, Roscoe,
                        and <hi rend="i">Reliques of Burns</hi>” <hi rend="i">Studies in
                            Bibliography</hi> 35 (1982): 306-19. Essick and Paley cite the
                        “surprisingly Blakean . . . rhetoric” of Cromek’s 1810 obituary of
                        Schiavonetti, which must have struck Blake with considerable irony 
                            (<hi rend="i">Blair’s Grave</hi> 28-29).</note></p>
                <p>Yet a more significant point emerges when we shift from looking at the quarrel
                    with Cromek through the eyes of Blake to viewing Blake through the perspective
                    of the quarrel. Blake seems to have been driven to the edge of sanity in the
                    years surrounding his exhibition. As Bentley has suggested, between 1807 and
                    1812 the visionary world seemed often to supplant rather than to supplement the
                    ordinary world of causality in Blake’s mind, or—to put it another way—“a firm
                    perswasion that a thing is so, [seemed to] make it so.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45"
                        type="note">45</ref> His relationship with Cromek is perhaps the most
                    telling example of his loosening grip on reality during those years, though few
                    of his readers have been willing to see it thus. Yet the belief which apparently
                    began to grow on him after 1810 that Cromek and Stothard had stolen his idea for
                    a painting from Chaucer is no more delusive than a number of other suspicions of
                    his friends and foes that he vented at the time.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n46" type="note">46</ref> But there is more to it than this. If Blake was in his Spectre’s
                    power in his dealings with Cromek, his Humanity was also awake and struggling,
                    like Los, to subdue it to the ends of art. It is one of the mysteries of
                    creativity that the imagination feeds on contraries, is stirred by the
                    experience of hate as well as love, by scorn and rivalry as well as admiration
                    and brotherhood, perhaps even by the petty as well as the sublime. We know what
                    the years at Felpham with Hayley contributed to the making of 
                        <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> Robert Cromek must have appeared to Blake as “the Age’s
                    Knave,” the reincarnation of Chaucer’s Pardoner, the man “sent in every age for
                    a rod and scourge,” but “suffered by Providence for wise ends.” It is then a
                    providential irony that Blake’s conviction of Cromek’s villainy prompted him to
                    paint one of his grandest “Visions of the eternal principles or characters of
                    human life [which] appear to poets, in all ages” (E 535-36). Seen thus, Cromek
                    indeed had “his great use, and his grand leading destiny.” 
                            <note id="n45"><hi rend="s">45</hi><hi rend="i"> BR</hi> 180; E 38. It is
significant that
                        the idiosyncratic word “delusion” in its several forms occurs only twice in
                        Blake’s work before <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and 54 times thereafter
                            (<hi rend="i">Concordance</hi> s.v.). It appears that Blake recognized
                        in his own experience the power of hallucinatory images to take on the force
                        of reality.</note>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">46</hi> Blake’s complaint that
                        his designs have been rejected by the Royal Academy merely because they were
                        painted in watercolor (E 527; see Erdman 455n57); his statement that Cromek
                        made over 1400 guineas profit on <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (E 537); his
                        insinuation that Cromek was responsible for the death of Schiavonetti (E
                        505); his claim that Flaxman “was blasting my character as an Artist to
                        Macklin, my <corr type="emend">Employer” in</corr> 1782-83 (E 572; see 
<hi rend="i">BR</hi> 610-11),
                        the very time at which Flaxman was finding influential patrons for Blake,
                        arranging for the printing of <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi>, assisting
                        in a plan to send Blake abroad, and generally promoting his reputation
                        (ibid. 24-27). Blake’s sneer at Hayley for “being a friend just in the nick”
                        to Cowper (E 507)—i.e., for neglecting Cowper’s needs and doubting his
                        genius while alive but capitalizing on his fame after his death by writing
                        his biography on a commission from “some book-seller”—is unfair and
                        inaccurate: see Morchard Bishop, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Hayley</hi> (London:
                        Gollancz, 1951) 152-85, 217-25, 252-53 on Hayley’s long drawn-out campaign
                        to secure a pension for Cowper, his extraordinary efforts to rescue Cowper
                        from depression, and his attempts to persuade the Rev. John Johnson and Lady
                        Hesketh to write Cowper’s biography until Lady Hesketh, Cowper’s cousin,
                        insisted that he was the proper person to do it. Blake’s accusation that
                        Hayley “when he could not act upon my wife / Hired a Villain to bereave my
                        Life” (E 506) is, in the light of Hayley’s generous assistance to Blake at
                        the time of his trial, paranoiac.</note></p>
            </div1>
	<pb id="p22-89-92" n="89-92" rend="hidden"/>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
