<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>22.3.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Michael Phillips, ed., William Blake, An Island in the Moon</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1988/89</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1988/89</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">22.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <name>John B. Pierce</name>
              <name>Aileen Ward</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_22">
    <body>
      <pb id="p22-103" n="103"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-22-3-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Blake. <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi>: A Facsimile
                            of the Manuscript Introduced, Transcribed, and Annotated by Michael
                            Phillips with a Preface by Haven O’More. Cambridge: Cambridge
                            University Press in Association with Institute of Traditional Science,
                            1987. viii+110 pp., with an extra copy of the 20-page manuscript in a
                            pocket in the back paste-down. $125.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>,
                        Jr.</docAuthor></byline>
          <p>This facsimile has been a surprising number of years in gestation, for it was
                        in effect commissioned by Sir Geoffrey Keynes (d. 1982) and Arnold Fawcus
                        (d. 1979) as a continuation of the Blake Trust series of facsimiles. For
                        unexplained reasons, “it fell to the Institute [<hi rend="i">of
                            Traditional Science</hi>] to take the work soon after its conception and
                        bring it to completion” (viii). The manuscript in the Fitzwilliam
                        Museum has never been reproduced in its entirety before;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78" type="note">1</ref> it is the longest and most important piece of
                        writing by Blake which has been thus neglected. <note id="n78"><hi rend="s">1</hi> For
that matter, it is not reproduced in its entirety now,
                            for the original consists of a booklet of 32 pages, of which the first
                            17 bear the text and the last one has a drawing on it. Only the first 17
                            pages and the last 1 are reproduced; the 12 blank pages are not
                            reproduced, and the work is therefore not, strictly speaking, a
                            facsimile. Much reduced photographs of the text-pages of the 
<hi rend="i">Island</hi> are reproduced in William Blake, <hi rend="i">En Ö På Månen</hi>, ed.
                            Göran Malmqvist (Uppsala, 1979) 133-149.</note></p>
          <p>The virtues of this edition are all conservative. The reproduction of the
                        manuscript is excellent—true size, on fine wove paper not unlike
                        Blake’s, in remarkably faithful color rather than in black and
                        white. The transcription builds carefully upon the accomplishments of its
                        predecessors and extends them a little, and the introduction (3-26) and
                        annotations (67-99) cull the best of what has been written about the 
<hi rend="i">Island in the Moon.</hi> These are great and worthy
                        virtues.</p>
          <p>Occasionally the repetitions of the discoveries of the past are somewhat
                        uncritical. Thus the character called “Aradobo, the dean of
                        Morocco” is 
						<q> conjectured [<hi rend="i">by</hi> Erdman, pp.
                            507-8] to be one of the sons of William Edwards of Halifax, famous for
                            his Morocco bindings . . . . In 1784, James, thirty, and John,
                            twenty-eight, opened their bookshop at 102 Pall Mall, evidently
                            innovating the exhibition sale room, for which ‘Descriptive
                            Catalogues’ were issued. (72) </q>
<figure n="bb74.1.14.ms" id="bb74.1.ms.14" work-copy="bb74.1" rend="db" width="610" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>while he ran out of the room. come out come out<lb/>
	we are putrified we are corrupted. our lungs are destroyd<lb/>
	with the Flogiston this will spread a plague all thro’ the<lb/>
	Island he was down stairs the very first on the back of him<lb/>
	came all the others in a heap<lb/>
	So they need not bidding go<lb/>
	<lb/>
	Chap 11<lb/>
	Another merry meeting at the house of Steelyard the Lawgiver<lb/>
	After Supper Steelyard &amp; Obtuse Angle. had pumpd Inflammable<lb/>
	Gass quite dry. they playd at forfeits &amp; tryd every method to get<lb/>
	good humour. said Miss Gittipin pray Mr Obtuse Angle sing us<lb/>
	a song then he sung<lb/>
	<lb/>
	Upon a holy thursday their innocent faces clean<lb/>
	The children walking two &amp; two in grey &amp; blue &amp; green<lb/>
	Grey headed beadles walkd before with wands as white as snow<lb/>
	Till into the high dome of Pauls they like thames waters flow<lb/>
	<lb/>
	O what a multitude they seemd, these flowers of London town<lb/>
	Seated in companies they sit with radiance all their own<lb/>
	The hum of multitudes were there but multitudes of lambs<lb/>
	Thousands of little girls &amp; boys raising their innocent hands<lb/>
	<lb/>
	Then like a mighty wind they raise to heavn the voice of song<lb/>
	Or like harmonious thunderings the seats of heavn among<lb/>
	Beneath them sit the revrend men the guardians of the poor<lb/>
	Then cherish pity lest you drive an angel from your door<lb/>
	<lb/>
	After this they all sat silent for a quarter of an hour &amp; Mrs Nannicantipot<lb/>
	said it puts me in Mind of my mothers song<lb/>
	<lb/>
	x<lb/>
	<lb/>
	When the tongues of children are heard on the green<lb/>
	And laughing is heard on the hill<lb/>
	My heart is at rest within my breast<lb/>
	And every thing else is still<lb/>
	<lb/>
	Then come home my children the sun is gone down<lb/>
	And the dews of night arise<lb/>
	Come Come leave off play &amp; let us away<lb/>
	Till the morning appears in the skies</figTranscr>
</figure> 
                        James Edwards (1756-1816) was 27 or 28 (not
                        “thirty”) when he moved to London in 1784, and his
                        brother John (23 December 1758-1793) was 25 (not
                        “twenty-eight”). From the Edwards’s
                        bookshops at 102 Pall Mall (1784-93) and 77 Pall Mall (1793-1800), shop
                        catalogues of antiquarian books were issued in January 1785, May 1787, 1789,
                        1790, 1794, and 1796, and they were called either merely <hi rend="i">A
                            Catalogue</hi> (1787, 1789, 1794, 1796) or <hi rend="i">Edwards’s Catalogue</hi>
(1785, 1790) and never
                        “Descriptive Catalogue” (like Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi> of
1809). And there seems to be no
                        evidence at all that any of the Edwardses had an “exhibition sale
                        room” in London, <pb id="p22-104" n="104"/>
as did their great
                        rivals in illustrated-book publishing John Boydell, Thomas Macklin, and
                        Robert Bowyer.</p>
          <p>More important, the branches of the firm of Edwards of Halifax were indeed
                        famous for bindings, but their fame was not based upon morocco bindings. The
                        three styles of bookcover decoration for which the Edwardses of Halifax were
                        particularly known were: (1) their patented method of painting under
                        transparent vellum on the covers; (2) “Etruscan calf,”
                        with designs stained with acid (not gilt) on the boards in imitation of
                        Etruscan vase paintings; (3) the fore-edges painted so that, when the leaves
                        are fanned, a scene appears where the closed book shows only gilt or marbled
                        edges. These three techniques were originated or renewed by the Edwardses of
                        Halifax, and these are the ones remarked by contemporaries such as Horace
                        Walpole, Mrs. Piozzi, and T. H. Horne (<hi rend="i">An Introduction to the
                            Study of Bibliography</hi> [1814], I, 309). Of course, as professional
                        bookbinders, they must have commissioned bindings in many materials, such as
                        calf, vellum, goat (morocco), and sheep, but their fame was not particularly
                        associated with morocco bindings, and today it may not be possible to
                        identify any individual examples of a morocco binding as their work.</p>
          <p>In short, if Aradobo, the dean of Morocco, is a bookbinder, there is no
                        particular reason to identify him with any of the Edwardses of Halifax
                        because of either their famous styles of binding or their known association
                        with Blake at the time his <hi rend="i">Island in the Moon</hi> was written
                        (? 1784).</p>
          <p>The “Description” of the manuscript itself is brief,
                        one paragraph on page 3, and somewhat strange. The watermark is not
                        identified (fleur de lis with a shield and GR countermark), and there is no
                        notice of the fact that the last leaf was sewn in separately, thus obscuring
                        its relationship with the rest of the leaves. (Indeed, we are told that
                        “The leaves are no longer conjugate, having at an early stage
                        been mounted on guards for binding” [3], but this is not noted in
                        Keynes’s <hi rend="i">Bibliography</hi> [1921] or in <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>
[1977], and one wonders what the evidence is for this
                        “early stage.”) There is no reference to the five
                        other leaves with which the <hi rend="i">Island</hi> was bound or to the
                        proofs of the Virgil woodcuts with them or to A. H. Palmer’s
                        statement about the provenance of the proofs. And it concludes
                        “that the extant manuscript is complete, but lacking the missing
                        sheet or sheets” after page 16 with an unknown amount of text.
                        This seems to be an odd use of “complete” when the
                        manuscript lacks an undefined amount of text. The <hi rend="i">Island</hi>
                        would have distressed Aristotle because it seems to have a beginning and an
                        end but no middle.</p>
          <p>The notes to the transcription scrupulously compare the readings of Erdman
                            (<hi rend="i">Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi> [1982])
                        and Bentley (<hi rend="i">William Blake’s Writings</hi> [1978])
                        with those given here, and, as an interested party, I have kept score as to
                        who seems to be correct: <table rows="2" cols="4"><row>
	<cell>Phillips</cell>
	<cell>Erdman</cell>
	<cell>Bentley</cell>
	<cell>None of the Former</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>34</cell>
	<cell>18</cell>
	<cell>21</cell>
	<cell>6</cell>
</row></table> In general, both Phillips and Erdman read deletions more
                        confidently than I do—and most of these uncertainties are in
                        deleted passages. Then there are half a dozen points at which the truth
                        seems to be slightly different from what any of these worthies has printed,
                        though the extent and significance of the disputed passages is generally not
                        very great. Thus in chapter 5, line 3, we find: <table rows="2" cols="2"><row>
	<cell><hi rend="i">Erdman, Bentley:</hi></cell>
	<cell>Is Chatterton a Mathematician</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell><hi rend="i">Phillips:</hi></cell>
	<cell>Is Chatterton a Mathematicum</cell>
</row></table> The disputed word does indeed look more like
                        “Mathematicum” than
                        “Mathematician”—but it looks more like
                        “Mathematicune” than either. Unfortunately, neither
                        “Mathematicum” nor
                        “Mathematicune” seems to make sense—neither
                        is in the <hi rend="i">Oxford English Dictionary.</hi> Perhaps it would be
                        best to give “Mathematicum[?]” here. In many small
                        particulars Michael Phillips has improved the readings of the 
<hi rend="i">Island</hi>, and this is useful labor.</p>
          <p>The annotations incorporate the best work of his predecessors and
                        occasionally extend it as well. I do not remember seeing the operatic
                        passage concluding: “And the Cellar goes down with a Step (Grand
                        Chorus)” (ch. 9, 1. 16) compared before to Shadwell’s
                        play <hi rend="i">The Virtuoso</hi> (1676) and Dryden’s poem <hi rend="i">Mac
Flecknoe</hi> (c. 1678) in which the protagonist-buffoon,
                        instead of being translated to heaven, “drops to the cellar
                        through a trapdoor.” I’m not sure the analogy is a
                        necessary one, but it has the virtue of making sense of a very puzzling
                        passage. And the account of Steelyard the Lawgiver sitting at his table
                        taking extracts in chapter 8 is usefully identified as “A
                        burlesque of the opening of Act V, Scene i, of Joseph Addison’s
                        tragedy <hi rend="i">Cato</hi> (1713, pp. 56-7): ‘Cato solus, 
                        <hi rend="i">sitting in a thoughtful Posture: In his Hand</hi>
                        Plato’s <hi rend="i">Book on the Immortality of the
                        Soul</hi>,’ ” for Addison’s <hi rend="i">Cato</hi> is later quoted in Blake’s
manuscript. The song of
                        innocence beginning “O father father where are you
                        going” is connected intriguingly with the fact that
                        “Blake’s father died July 1784” (74, 80),
                        for the <hi rend="i">Island</hi> is generally taken to have been written
                        about 1784 or early 
<pb id="p22-105" n="105"/>
1785. Michael Phillips argues
                        that the MS is a fair copy with revisions “composed
                        intermittently between 1782 and 1785, or perhaps even later” (6),
                        but the evidence for a date before 1784 is not very persuasive. Indeed, even
                        the conventional date of 1784 is not very firm. The claims for novel
                        conclusions here are put with appropriate caution, and, while some scholars
                        may not accept all the conclusions which Michael Phillips presents, at least
                        the evidence is laid out plainly.</p>
          <p>In sum, this is a satisfactorily faithful reproduction of the manuscript, the
                        transcription, introduction, and notes are just what they should be and what
                        they pretend to be, and the whole is a genuine contribution to Blake
                        scholarship. Anyone concerned to know the appearance and implications of
                        Blake’s puzzling manuscript of <hi rend="i">An Island in the
                            Moon</hi> can in future turn with confidence to this careful and
                        valuable edition. [See Michael Phillips’s comment, below]</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
