<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>22.3.phillips</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">An Island in the Moon</title>
        <author n="Phillips">Michael Phillips</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1988/89</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1988/89</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">22.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <name>John B. Pierce</name>
              <name>Aileen Ward</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_22">
    <body>
	<pb id="p22-110" n="110"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-22-3-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section"><hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">DISCUSSION</hi></hi>:</title>
        </head>
        <head>
          <title type="section-subtitle"><hi rend="i">with intellectual spears &amp; long winged arrows of
                        thought</hi></title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">An Island In The Moon</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Michael <name>Phillips</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>G. E. Bentley, Jr., has generously invited my comment on his review of the
                        facsimile of William Blake’s <hi rend="i">An Island in the
                            Moon.</hi> The only aspect where I feel that it may be appropriate for
                        me to do so is in answer to the questions he raises regarding the
                        “Description” of the manuscript, as these questions
                        may lead some readers to conclude that the edition may not present all of
                        the material that it should, or that what has been presented may not be
                        faithfully described.</p>
          <p>A misunderstanding appears to stem from reference to the binding of the
                        manuscript and to knowledge of its history prior to 1978. At the time of
                        Keynes’s inspection, and later that of Bentley, the manuscript
                        was bound together with leaves of later Van Gelder paper, upon which were
                        mounted a proofsheet of Blake’s woodcuts for
                        Thornton’s <hi rend="i">Pastorals of Virgil</hi> (1821) and a
                        note referring to their provenance by Samuel Palmer’s son, A. H.
                        Palmer. In 1978 it was disbound for restoration and rebinding by the late S.
                        M. Cockerell. As the old binding was removed Cockerell made the following
                        description of its condition and contents and of the processes of rebinding: 
						<q><hi
rend="i">Note by Binder</hi>; DC6477; Island in the Moon; William
                            Blake. Condition when received: Binding red hard grain, title blocked in
                            gold on front board, leaves overcast very close to the text and the book
                            sewn on five sawn cords, slips cut off. Collation—paste down
                            and three blank leaves at front, paste down and one blank leaf at the
                            back all Van Gelder paper plus six blank leaves at the back of the same
                            thin paper as the manuscript; the third blank leaf numbered 1, two A. H.
                            Palmer notes mounted on leaf 2, wood engraving mounted on leaf 3, text
                            on leaves 4 to 12, drawings on the verso of leaf 13, leaves 2 and 3
                            foxed.<lb/>
<lb/>
 Leaves disbound, overcasting removed, acidity of paper
                            checked, average reading pH 4.12, leaves deacidified with a solution of
                            Barium Hydroxide in Methanol, reading after treatment pH5.30, the Palmer
                            notes and the wood engraving remounted on handmade paper, leaves edged
                            with handmade paper using heatset tissue and mounted in handmade paper
                            frames, each mounted leaf bound separately in quarter brown morocco,
                            buckram sides, gold lettering, the blank leaves in one binding, the
                            thirteen bindings housed in three buckram covered boxes. (Solvent for
                            the adhesive of heatset tissue—I. M. S.) [Signed] SMC; D. C.
                            and Son November 1978 </q>
It was after rebinding, and while the
                        manuscript was being photographed for the color facsimile, that it was first
                        inspected for the edition.</p>
          <p>As Cockerell’s description suggests, the manuscript leaves were
                        not conjugate. It had been bound as separate folio leaves in the order
                        given, with the leaf of sketches bound out of order, before the six blank
                        leaves. The narrow inside margins of each of these leaves, of thin and quite
                        brittle paper, showed evidence of being broken, and at the time, I
                        understood this condition to indicate that each leaf had previously been
                        mounted on a guard for binding.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79"
type="note">1</ref>
                        Cockerell’s description, “leaves overcast very close
                        to the text,” indicates that in fact each leaf had only been
                            “overcast”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80"
type="note">2</ref>
                        and then sewn directly onto cords for binding. If any part of the manuscript
                        had been conjugate this would have been noted and the full sheet preserved.
                            <note id="n79"><hi rend="s">1</hi> “I saw Sandy Cockerell last
                            Thursday, and . . . asked him about the manuscript of <hi rend="i">An
                                Island in the Moon.</hi> . . . Sandy said that when they disbound
                            the volume in which the MS had been bound, they found all the pages were
                            separate, and had been joined together with guards—or so he
                            remembered. Certainly, he said, he would never have cut any bifoliate
                            leaf, though he would remove the guards, as they are often a cause of
                            damage.” Letter to the author, 23 June 1981, from Simon
                            Rendall, who was responsible for photographing the manuscript and with
                            whom I had discussed the condition of the separate leaves.</note>
	<note id="n80"><hi rend="s">2</hi> “<hi rend="i">Overcasting</hi>,
                            over-sewing the back edges of single leaves or weak
                            sections.” Douglas Cockerell, <hi rend="i">Bookbinding, and
                                the Care of Books</hi>, 5th ed. (New York: Appleton, 1901), revised
                            by Sydney M. Cockerell (London: Pitman, 1982) 336; 57-9. See especially
                            M. T. Roberts and D. Etherington, <hi rend="i">Bookbinding and the
                                Conservation of Books: A Dictionary of Descriptive Terminology</hi>
                            (Washington, 1982) 182-3 for “overcasting” and
                            “oversewing.” I am grateful to Bernard C.
                            Middleton for assistance in explaining the process; and for the
                            reference to Roberts and Etherington, and to Howard M. Nixon cited
                            below.</note></p>
          <p>The surviving sixteen leaves contain an equal number of watermarks and
                            countermarks.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81"
type="note">3</ref> In this sense the
                        extant manuscript is described as complete, in that what has survived
                        represents eight complete sheets of the original gathering, each sheet
                        containing a watermark and a countermark. However, in absolute terms, the
                        “Description” also makes plain that at least one sheet
                        is missing from the center of the gathering, indicated by the lacuna between
                        the surviving eighth and ninth leaves of an otherwise consecutive text.
                            <note id="n81"><hi rend="s">3</hi> See the diagram of watermarks and
                            countermarks given in G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>
                            (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1977) 221.</note></p>
          <p>There remains the question of the other contents of the volume, as disbound
                        by Cockerell. Understandably, Bentley associates these materials with the
                        manuscript as they were bound together at the time of his inspection, and
                        duly noted in <hi rend="i">Blake Books.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n82" type="note">4</ref> As they bear upon the subject of the facsimile, a distinction
                        was made: foremost, that no <hi rend="i">intrinsic</hi> relationship exists
                        between the manuscript and the other materials that were at one time present
                        in the same binding. A consideration was the binding itself and its history.
                        Exactly when and for whom the binding was made could not be determined at
                        the time, and remains unknown. What was clear, from the nature of the
                        binding and its contents, was that the manuscript had only been placed
                        together with the other materials some time after Blake’s death.
                            <note id="n82"><hi rend="s">4</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Books</hi>
                            223.</note></p>
          <pb id="p22-111" n="111"/>
          <p>The Fitzwilliam Museum has now been able to supply further information. The
                        binding was by the firm of Rivière &amp; Son; it contained
                        the bookplate “FROM THE LIBRARY OF / CH.FAIRFAX
                        MURRAY”; and it was in this binding that Charles Fairfax Murray
                        presented the volume to the Fitzwilliam Museum in 1905.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83" type="note">5</ref> The firm of Rivière was started in Bath
                        in 1829, changed to Rivière &amp; Son in 1881, and ceased
                        business in 1939.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84"
type="note">6</ref> By 1893 the
                        manuscript belonged to Charles Fairfax Murray, as acknowledged by Ellis and
                        Yeats in their edition of Blake published that year. Their description does
                        not make clear whether the manuscript is bound.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n85" type="note">7</ref> Nor does that of John Sampson published in 1905, which is
based
                        upon an inspection of the manuscript while it was still in Fairfax
                        Murray’s possession.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86"
type="note">8</ref> Neither
                        Ellis and Yeats, nor Sampson, make reference to the other materials. It
                        would seem likely therefore that these materials, including the manuscript,
                        were gathered together by Charles Fairfax Murray and bound for him by
                        Rivière &amp; Son, certainly not later than 1905 and
                        possibly, specifically for presentation to the Fitzwilliam Museum. 
<note id="n83"><hi rend="s">5</hi> I am grateful to Dr. Paul Woudhuysen, Keeper
                            of Manuscripts and Printed Books, Fitzwilliam Museum, for supplying this
                            information and a copy of the binder’s note by S. M.
                            Cockerell.</note>
	<note id="n84"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Howard M. Nixon, <hi rend="i">Five
                                Centuries of English Bookbinding</hi> (London: Scolar Press, 1978)
                            98.</note>
	<note id="n85"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Edwin J. Ellis and W. B. Yeats, eds. <hi rend="i">The Works of William
Blake, Poetic, Symbolic, and
                                Critical</hi>, 3 vols. (London: B. Quaritch, 1893) 1:1186-7 and
                            200-1.</note>
	<note id="n86"><hi rend="s">8</hi> John Sampson, ed. <hi rend="i">The
                                Poetical Works of William Blake</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1905)
                            50-2.</note></p>
          <p>I hope this clarifies any misunderstanding and assures those who may use the
                        edition. It should perhaps be added that it was for reasons of economy that
                        the six blank leaves which survive, and which were originally conjugate with
                        the leaves of Blake’s manuscript, were not reproduced in
                        facsimile. These leaves are clearly referred to in the
                        “Description.”</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
