<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>22.3.pierce</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The Shifting Characterization of Tharmas and Enion in Pages 3-7 of Blake’s
Vala or The Four Zoas</title>
        <author n="Pierce">John B. Pierce</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1988/89</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1988/89</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">22.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <name>John B. Pierce</name>
              <name>Aileen Ward</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_22">
    <body>
      <pb id="p22-93" n="93"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-22-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="main">The Shifting Characterization of Tharmas and Enion in Pages 3-7 of
                        Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four
                        Zoas</hi></title>
        </head>
        <byline>
          <hi rend="i">BY</hi>
          <docAuthor>
            <hi rend="i">JOHN B.</hi>
            <name>
              <hi rend="i">PIERCE</hi>
            </name>
          </docAuthor>
        </byline>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>I</title>
          </head>
          <p>The opening pages of the <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four
                            Zoas</hi> manuscript present perhaps the most difficult bibliographical
                        and interpretive cruxes in the entire manuscript. These pages have been
                        described as “one of the most heavily revised parts of the
                        poem” in which “the physical evidence in the
                        manuscript is sometimes highly confusing.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n47" type="note">1</ref> Indeed, the “thicket of erased and
                        deleted original and additional lines”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n48" type="note">2</ref> has caused one critic to remark
                        “Certainly no creation myth has ever done a better job of
                        conveying a sense of the initial chaos out of which the world
                            began.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">3</ref>
The chaotic
                        state of pages 3 through 7 has made a definitive text of the Tharmas-Enion
                        conflict difficult to establish; however, recently Andrew Lincoln and David
                        Erdman have reexamined the opening pages of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
                        and, as a result, helped our bibliographical understanding of the stages in
                        the genesis and growth of this text. Yet beyond the difficulties of
                        establishing a faithful rendering of Blake’s textual intentions,
                        the extensive erasures and rewritings which fill these pages reveal the
                        process of composition in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> The extensive
                        revisions suggest that the Tharmas character gradually evolved even as Blake
                        transcribed his manuscript and that the significance of the character
                        developed and in some cases shifted as he wrote and revised the first pages
                        of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> In
                        Tharmas’ shifting characterization we can see a specific example
                        of Blake’s poetic process as he revised the tone, symbolism, and
                        form of his narrative. Indeed, as we shall see, the development of Tharmas
                        seems tied to the stress created within <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> as
                        it moves from a linear to nonlinear narrative.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n50" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Andrew Lincoln, “<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: The Text of Pages 5,
6, &amp; 7, Night the
                            First,” <hi rend="i">Blake / An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 12
                            (1978): 91.</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">2</hi> David V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The
                                Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, newly rev. ed.
                            (Berkeley: U of California P, 1982), 821.</note>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Paul A. Cantor, <hi rend="i">Creature and
                                Creator: Myth-making and English Romanticism</hi> (Cambridge:
                            Cambridge UP, 1984) 69.</note>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">4</hi> I will return to this idea later in my
                            essay, but for a more extensive discussion of nonlinear narrative in 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> see Donald Ault,
                            “Re-Visioning <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>,”
                                <hi rend="i">Unnam’d Forms: Blake and Textuality</hi>,
                            Nelson Hilton and Thomas A. Vogler, eds. (Berkeley: U of California P,
                            1986) 105-39. For a more detailed study of Ault’s argument,
                            see his recent full-length study, <hi rend="i">Narrative Unbound:
                                Revisioning William Blake’s</hi> The Four Zoas
                            (Barrytown: Station Hill, 1987) esp. 3-58. Because his approach is
                            structural rather than developmental, it does not impinge directly on my
                            approach to the evolution of the Tharmas-Enion conflict.</note></p>
          <p>Blake seems to have invented Tharmas and Enion while writing <hi rend="i">The
                            Four Zoas</hi>, since they do not appear in his earlier works.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">5</ref> It is not altogether certain, however,
                        that Tharmas, in particular, played a significant role in Blake’s
                        plan of the poem even at the time he began to transcribe it. Pages 4-6,
                        those in which the narrative first introduces Tharmas and Enion, are a mass
                        of erasures and rewritings in which different layers of text may be seen but
                        not easily distinguished from one another. The earliest text, the
                        transcription in Blake’s “copperplate
                            hand,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">6</ref>
is almost
                        entirely obscured. Indeed, the extent of these erasures suggests a radical
                        departure by Blake from his original text on these pages. As the existence
                        of two Nights VII indicates, Blake was loath to discard any text if he
                        thought he could salvage anything from it. Thus, it seems possible that the
                        revised text differs radically in tone, image, or perhaps even character
                        from the original transcription. Such a complete change in the story could
                        help to explain why such radical revisions were brought to these opening
                        pages. Margoliouth, the only critic to speculate at length on this problem,
                        argues that 
						<q> There is evidence that Vala originally played a larger part
                            in Night I. . . . How Vala came into the lost eighty or so lines of the
                            beginning of . . . [the earliest erased text of <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>]
                            I cannot even conjecture, but somehow she must be identifiable with the
                            Woman-Serpent which Enion becomes at the moment of her mating . . . [7].
                            The Woman-Serpent in the text there, in the drawing below and in the
                            drawing on . . . [13], must be identifiable with the Woman-Serpent
                            (Woman-Dragon) of the drawing on . . . [26], which represents Vala as
                            described by Luvah.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53"
type="note">7</ref></q>
	<pb id="p22-94" n="94"/>
The exact nature of this earlier story remains and
                        may always remain in question. It does seem likely, though, that the top
                        layer of text was written considerably later than the rest of the
                        copperplate text and perhaps even later than pages 43-84 of the <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> proof sheets. The surface text contains references
                        to characters and ideas such as Jerusalem, the Daughters of Beulah, and sin
                        and atonement not present in the basic transcription of pages 43-84. This
                        text also contains passages used in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, and thus it
                        seems likely that the surface layer of pages 4-6 is a relatively late
                        addition to the manuscript. <note id="n51"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Tharmas and
                            Enion seldom appear in Blake’s later writings. The <hi rend="i">Concordance to
the Writings of William Blake</hi>, David V.
                            Erdman, ed., 2 vols. (Ithaca: Cornell UP, 1967) reveals that
                            Tharmas’ and Enion’s names do not appear in
                            Blake’s work before <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, and they only
                            appear infrequently in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>
Tharmas’ name appears 6 times in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 11 times in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>;
                            Enion’s, once in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 6 times in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> This absence may reflect Blake’s
                            later change of focus to the struggle of specific universal characters
                            such as Milton and Albion.</note>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">6</hi> The “copperplate
                            hand” is described by G. E. Bentley, Jr., ed., <hi rend="i">Vala or The Four
Zoas: A Facsimile of the Manuscript, A Transcript
                                of the Poem and A Study of Its Growth and Significance</hi> (Oxford:
                                Clarendon, 1963) 196.</note>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">7</hi> H. M. Margoliouth, ed., <hi rend="i">William Blake’s</hi> Vala: 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Numbered Text</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon, 1956)
                            xx.</note></p>
          <p>The only surviving copperplate appearances of Tharmas occur in two brief
                        instances where he is little more than a name. In Night I, Los alludes to
                        the “cold expanse where watry Tharmas mourns” (11:27),
                        and in Night II Blake writes that the windows in the “golden
                        Building” (32:10) raised by Urizen and his sons 
						<q> Lookd out
                            into the world of Tharmas, where in ceaseless torrents<lb/>
 His billows
                            roll where monsters wander in the foamy paths.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">8</ref><lb/>
 (33:6-7) <note id="n54"><hi rend="s">8</hi> All quotations from <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The
Four Zoas</hi> are taken from
                                    Bentley’s facsimile. Quotations from
                                    Blake’s other works are taken from
                                    Erdman’s <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose
                                        of William Blake.</hi> References to Erdman’s
                                    textual notes will be cited parenthetically by an E followed by
                                    the page number. Text in square brackets [thus] is that added by
                                    myself or Blake’s editors; italicized text in square
                                    brackets [<hi rend="i">thus</hi>] is that deleted by Blake; and
                                    angle brackets &lt; &gt; indicate text added by
                                    Blake. David Erdman and Cettino Tramontano Magno’s
                                    recently published edition of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas: A
                                        Photographic Facsimile of the Manuscript with Commentary on
                                        the Illuminations</hi> (Lewisburg: Bucknell UP, 1987) makes
                                    available a new photographic reproduction of the poem. While it
                                    offers a useful commentary on the designs in the poems, it does
                                    not, as the editors point out, comment extensively on the
                                    poem’s textual development: 
<q> for the present
                                        enterprise we must stress that we cannot begin to do justice
                                        to the poem’s integrity, its own
                                        completeness—so much of which is <hi rend="i">not</hi> represented
in the designs; so much of which
                                        is entangled in its own problems of interpretation and
                                        uncompleted revisions (and undeciphered cancelations). (16)
                                    </q></note></q>
Here Tharmas seems merely a ruler over a watery chaos set
in contrast
                        to Urizen’s ordered world. His world, with its
                        “ceaseless torrents” and “monsters [that]
                        wander in the foamy paths,” seems to be an imminent threat to
                        that of Urizen. Tharmas, thus, appears to be a sea god, like Poseidon, set
                        in opposition to a Zeus-like sky god.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n55" type="note">9</ref>
                        The juxtaposition of Tharmas’ chaotic world against
                        Urizen’s world of light and order seems to say more about Urizen
                        than Tharmas. It is designed to emphasize the precarious nature of
                        Urizen’s endeavors and remind the reader that Urizen has not
                        conquered the chaos of matter on which his world is built, but only
                        circumscribed a portion of it. Blake may also have intended, however, that
                        the brief appearance of Tharmas’ world of “ceaseless
                        torrents” would adumbrate the world of disorder that follows the
                        collapse of Urizen’s world of order. <note id="n55"><hi rend="s">9</hi> This
opposition is played out more fully in Night IV where
                            Tharmas enlists the help of Los to rebuild his watery world after the
                            collapse of Urizen’s golden one. It should be remembered that
                            Tharmas first appears in Night III as a product of the confusion and
                            chaos created by the separation of Urizen and Ahania, and therefore he
                            appears as a figure in symbolic opposition to them. Although the lines
                            in Night IV are physically later in the narrative of the manuscript, it
                            seems that they were likely transcribed before the revisions to the
                            early part of Night I describing Tharmas, since Night IV presents a more
                            simplified picture of him and does not define him as a
                            “Spectre.”</note></p>
          <p>In her first copperplate appearance, Enion is described as brooding
                        “oer the rocks, the rough rocks” (8:12) of the barren
                        world Los and Enitharmon are born into. Her brooding causes “the
                        rough rocks” to “vegetate” and give rise to
                        the forms of nature which protect “the bright Infants from the
                        desolating winds” (8:20) of a hostile world. Her laments
                        emphasize her role as a nurturing earth-mother figure; unfortunately, Enion
                        is forced to substitute tares for crops, pestilence and famine for
                        nourishment, hypocrisy for truth in fallen nature: 
						<q> I am made to sow
                            thistle for wheat; the nettle for a nourishing dainty<lb/>
 I have
                            planted a false oath in the earth, it has brought forth a poison
                            tree<lb/>
<lb/>
 . . .<lb/>
<lb/>
 I have taught the thief a secret path
                            into the house of the just<lb/>
 I have taught pale artifice to spread
                            his nets upon the morning<lb/>
 My heavens are brass my earth is iron my
                            moon a clod of clay<lb/>
 My sun a pestilence burning at noon &amp;
                            a vapour of death in night.<lb/>
 (35:1-2, 7-10) </q>
Her laments serve
                        mainly to punctuate the endings of Nights I and II, casting a sense of
                        desolation over the marriage feast of Night I and Urizen’s newly
                        planted “Golden World” (32:8) in Night II. Beyond
                        these laments, however, her identity in the poem seems some-what
                        limited.</p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>II</title>
          </head>
          <p>Blake appears to have begun his development, or redevelopment, of the
                        Tharmas-Enion story on pages 3-7 by transferring a portion of his text on
                        page 7 to page 5. Under a series of erasures on page 7, Erdman conjecturally
                        reconstructs the following lines, apparently describing Tharmas: 
						<q>
                            ?Weeping, then bending from his Clouds he stoopd his innocent head<lb/>
                            ?And stretching out his holy hand in the vast Deep sublime<lb/>
 ?Turnd
                            round the circle of Destiny with tears &amp; bitter sighs<lb/>
 And
                            said Return O Wanderer when the day of clouds is o’er<lb/>
 So
                            saying he . . . ?fell . . . into the restless sea<lb/>
 Round rolld ?the
                            . . . globe self balanc’d.<lb/>
 (E 821-22) </q>
He then
                        points out that “All six [lines] were apparently moved to p 5 for
                        the modified copperplate addition there of lines 9-14 and 25” (E
                        822). Andrew Lincoln has noted that the Tharmas figure described in these
                        lines is called “innocent” in contrast with the
                        jealous, malevolent figure in the chronologically later text of pages 4-6.
                        The evil tendencies of Tharmas, then, would only emerge after the
                        “innocent” Tharmas falls into the sea.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n56" type="note">10</ref> The result of Lincoln’s
                        argument is to demonstrate that Blake had two different ideas of Tharmas and
                        that much of the revision on pages 5-7 was an attempt to reconcile the two
                            figures.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">11</ref>
On one hand, we have
                        Tharmas, the 
<pb id="p22-95" n="95"/>
victim, bending his
                        “innocent head” from the clouds, turning the
                        “circle of Destiny” and falling into the sea where he
                        is woven into a spectrous form by Enion; on the other, we have the proud,
                        malicious, Spectre-like Tharmas who asserts his will over Enion and finally
                        rapes her. Though Lincoln’s argument is compelling, it rests in
                        part upon the idea that the earliest text on these opening pages always
                        referred to the union of Tharmas and Enion. While this is possible, it is by
                        no means inevitable. The text reconstructed by Erdman does not name the male
                        or female figures, and not until this passage is moved to page 5 are their
                        identities firmly established as Enion and Tharmas. Furthermore, from my own
                        examination of the manuscript in the British museum, I have found that it is
                        not always possible to tell which erased text is the earliest copperplate
                        one. <note id="n56"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Andrew Lincoln, “<hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>” 91.</note>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Kathleen Raine, <hi rend="i">Blake and
                                Tradition</hi>, 2 vols. (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1968) 1:279-82,
                            discusses the two-sided nature of Tharmas in terms of possible
                            alchemical sources.</note></p>
          <p>However, once Blake had decided to transfer his text from page 7 to page 5,
                        for whatever reason and at whatever stage of composition, he began to rework
                        the intervening pages in two fairly distinct phases. It seems that the lines
                        4:7-11, 18-16, 5:6-12, 14, 16-19, 23-28, 46-55, 57 and 6:5-27, 32-37
                        represent a single phase of rewriting, since they seem to be centered over
                        the erased text, appear in the same writing style and are consistent in
                        tone, image and narrative setting.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n58" type="note">12</ref> The
                        emphasis on fear, terror, jealousy, hatred and delusive beauty characterizes
                        these passages as much later than the copperplate transcription of Night I.
                        I suspect that this stage of revision is concurrent with or follows the
                        revision of the Los-Enitharmon and Urizen-Ahania stories in Nights I and II.
                        An almost cynical emphasis on love and jealousy as motive forces in
                        male-female relationships and a tendency to place the female in the more
                        sinister role seem characteristic of the revision in both stories.
                        References to love and jealousy are far less pronounced in the basic
                        copperplate text; for the most part, Blake’s later revisions of
                        this text tend to magnify these elements only suggested in the early
                        transcription of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> It is probable, then, that
                        the passages in the Tharmas-Enion conflict were added as a unit while Blake
                        worked on the rest of the poem, heightening “The torments of Love
                        &amp; Jealousy,” and were intended to introduce Tharmas and
                        Enion more fully earlier in the narrative in preparation for
                        Tharmas’ appearances, in particular, in the text after page 43.
                            <note id="n58"><hi rend="s">12</hi> I do have some reservations about
                            6:5-8 in this grouping. They appear to be written higher on the page
                            than the erased portion of text on page 6 and may have been added
                            slightly later than the other lines I have included here. This idea is
                            supported by the narrative connection between
                            5:57—“But standing on the Rocks her woven shadow
                            glowing bright”—and
                            6:11—“Searching for glory wishing that the heavens
                            had eyes to See.” Perhaps, then, the text on page 6 during
                            this phase of rewriting began at line 6:11; however, lines 6:5-8 have
                            little that would characterize them as distinctly later than the rest of
                            this phase of rewriting. Presumably, they were added much earlier than
                            the other obvious additions to pages 3-6.</note></p>
          <p>The structure of this text seems fairly simple. Tharmas laments the loss of
                        his Emanations and calls for Enion to “come forth”
                        (4:8). She appears and proclaims that “All love is lost Terror
                        succeeds &amp; Hatred instead of Love / And stern demands of Right
                        &amp; Duty instead of Liberty” (4:19-20). Then, in an
                        attempt to shield herself from his terrifying appearance, she begins to
                        weave a “tabernacle of delight” (5:7) for herself
                        which upon its completion becomes “the circle of
                        Destiny” (5:11). Tharmas subsequently emerges from
                        Enion’s loom in the form of a Spectre and after glorying in his
                        own beauty, terrorizes and finally rapes Enion. The relative lateness of
                        this text is suggested by the fact that specific terms such as
                        “Emanation” and “Spectre” are
                        not used in the text before revisions: “Emanation” is
                        not found in the base text of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> nor is the
                        term “Spectre” applied to Tharmas in the narrative of
                        the following Nights. Moreover, the weaving imagery used as a specifically
                        feminine evil activity only appears in arguably late portions of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi> and thus would add to the evidence that this
                        text on pages 5-6 is relatively late.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n59" type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n59"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Morton D. Paley, in “The
                            Figure of the Garment in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Milton</hi>, and
                                <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake’s Sublime Allegory:
Essays on</hi> The Four Zoas,
                            Milton <hi rend="i">and</hi> Jerusalem, eds. Stuart Curran and Joseph
                            Anthony Wittreich, Jr. (Madison: U of Wisconsin P, 1973) 119-39,
                            discusses the late occurrence of weaving imagery in Blake’s
                            poetry.</note></p>
          <p>Lines 4:12-15, 16-17, 27-41, 5:13, 15, 20-22 and 6:27-31, apparently all
                        added at the time of Blake’s work on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,
                        seem significantly later than the preceding phase of rewriting. They
                        introduce the ideas of sin and repentance common in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> but
found only in the added pages 86-90 of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> Moreover, this language of sin and
repentance is
                        further allied with feminine delusiveness and weaving
                        imagery—Enion states, “I thought to weave a Covering
                            [<hi rend="i">from</hi>] &lt;for&gt; my Sins from wrath
                        of Tharmas” (6:38)—as it is in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">14</ref> Blake also
revised specific lines in his earlier
                        text to include these new ideas of sin and repentance. “Jealous
                        Despair” becomes “Silent Contrition” in
                        4:10 and the “Seas of Trouble &amp; rocks of
                        sorrow” become “Seas of &lt;Doubt&gt;
                        &amp; rocks of &lt;Repentance&gt;” in 5:51.
                        Furthermore, Blake changed “false woven bliss” to
                        “Repentance &amp; Contrition” in 5:28. <note id="n60"><hi rend="s">14</hi><hi
rend="i"> Milton</hi> 18[20]:30;E 111, 22[24]:38;E 117. <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 21:11-12;E 166, 64:1-5;E
215, 80:62-65;E 237,
                            87:18-19;E 246, 88:19-20, 27-28;E 247.</note></p>
          <p>Throughout these two phases of revision, however, the source of Tharmas and
                        Enion’s strife shifts at least three times, and as it shifts, so
                        does the characterization of Tharmas and Enion. In the first stage, strife
                        exists solely between Tharmas and Enion with no third party involved.
                        Moreover, Tharmas is clearly the oppressor of Enion. Tharmas, in the
                        earliest surviving reading of lines 10-11 on page 4, states, “I
                        have hidden thee Enion in Jealous Despair / I will build thee a Labyrinth
                        where we 
<pb id="p22-96" n="96"/>
may remain for ever alone.”
                        These lines begin a story of Tharmas’ jealousy and possessiveness
                        that prepares for his later appearance as the domineering Spectre with Enion
                        as his victim. Enion’s response, after their initial argument, is
                        to weave “A tabernacle of delight” (5:7) which entraps
                        Tharmas, but there is no suggestion that she weaves it for Enitharmon or
                        Jerusalem, as later revisions show.</p>
          <p>While modifying the first phase of rewriting pages 4 through 7, Blake
                        complicates the Tharmas-Enion conflict by the addition of Enitharmon as a
                        source of strife. Enitharmon’s presence in the story gives an
                        external object for the story of jealousy. As a result, blame for strife in
                        the Tharmas-Enion relationship shifts over to Enion. Blake revises
                        Tharmas’ opening speech to read 
						<q> I have hidden
                            &lt;Enitharmon&gt; in Jealous Despair O Pity Me<lb/>
 I
                            will build thee a Labyrinth &lt;also O pity me O
                            Enion&gt;<lb/>
 &lt;Why hast thou taken Enitharmon from
                            my inmost Soul<lb/>
 Let her Lay secret in the Soft recess of darkness
                            &amp; silence<lb/>
 It is not Love I bear to Enitharmon It is
                            Pity<lb/>
 She hath taken refuge in my bosom &amp; I cannot cast her
                            out&gt;<lb/>
 (4:10-15) </q>
In revision Blake brings out the
                        pitying quality that Tharmas is generally noted for but that was virtually
                        nonexistent in the first stage of revision. The cry for pity, even the wrong
                        kind of pity, tends to make Tharmas a little more sympathetic; at the same
                        time, Enion’s jealousy towards Enitharmon may now qualify our
                        sympathy for her.</p>
          <p>The myth, as told here, is elaborated in one of the last additions to Night I
                        and indeed the entire poem. On page 22, thought by Bentley to be added
                        sometime after 1805 and the transcription of Night VIII (B 165), Blake tells
                        of Urthona’s experience of the fall and how 
						<q> dividing from his
                            aking bosom fled<lb/>
 A portion of his life shrieking upon the wind she
                            fled<lb/>
 And Tharmas took her in pitying Then Enion in jealous
                            fear<lb/>
 Murderd her &amp; hid her in her bosom embalming her for
                            fear<lb/>
 She should arise again to life Embalmd in Enions bosom<lb/>
                            Enitharmon remains a corse such thing was never known<lb/>
                            &lt;In Eden that one died a death never to be
                            revivd&gt;.<lb/>
 (22:20-26) </q>
Blake had used the idea of the
                        love triangle as early as <hi rend="i">The Visions of the Daughters of
                            Albion</hi>, but this mythic mode of expressing it was part of a later
                        development. In particular, the interchangeable nature of the female
                        Emanation, fleeing from one Zoa to seek refuge with another, is a later
                        development very important to <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Before the composition of <hi rend="i">The Four
                            Zoas</hi>, Blake had written of Enitharmon splitting from
                        Los’ side or of Ahania “Cast out from thy
                        [Urizen’s] lovely bosom” (<hi rend="i">Book of
                            Ahania</hi> 5:40; E 90), but he had not yet fully developed the idea
                        that Emanations could leave one male figure’s bosom and enter
                        another. Not until <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> does Blake present the most
                        highly developed explication of the Emanative function: 
						<q> When in Eternity
                            Man converses with Man they enter<lb/>
 Into each others Bosom (which are
                            Universes of delight)<lb/>
 In mutual interchange. and first their
                            Emanations meet<lb/>
 Surrounded by their Children. if they embrace
                            &amp; comingle<lb/>
 The Human Four-fold Forms mingle also in
                            thunders of Intellect<lb/>
 But if the Emanations mingle not; with storms
                            &amp; agitations<lb/>
 Of earthquakes &amp; consuming fires
                            they roll apart in fear<lb/>
 For Man cannot unite with Man but by their
                            Emanations<lb/>
 Which stand both Male &amp; Female at the Gates of
                            each Humanity.<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 88:3-11; E 246) </q>
In the
                        Lambeth books, after leaving the male source, the female Emanation either
                        becomes highly assertive over the male, as Enitharmon ultimately does or,
                        like Ahania, becomes “a faint shadow wandring / . . . / As the
                        moon anguishd circles the earth” (<hi rend="i">Book of
                            Ahania</hi> 2:38, 40; E 85). There is never any mention of one Emanation
                        fleeing into the bosom of a male figure who is not her place of origin
                        (e.g., Enitharmon entering Urizen’s bosom or Ahania fleeing to
                        Los).</p>
          <p>As Blake revises the story of Tharmas and Enion, he connects the source of
                        their strife to a breakdown in the free movement of Emanations. At the end
                        of Tharmas’ opening speech, Blake adds, “The Men have
                        received their death wounds &amp; their Emanations are fled / To me for
                        refuge &amp; I cannot turn them out for Pitys Sake”
                            (4:16-17.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61"
type="note">15</ref> Blake anticipates (or
                        repeats?) his own idea developed in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> that
                        Jerusalem herself is an Emanation comprised of the Emanations of all men
                        just as Albion is seen as the composite form of the human imagination. Thus
                        the “Emanations” which flee to Tharmas 
<pb id="p22-97" n="97"/>
for refuge are
symbolized by the figure of Jerusalem who hides
                        in Tharmas’ bosom. We see here that Tharmas has begun to take on
                        a fairly significant role as the repository of the creative emanative power
                        of humanity which survives the fall. Unfortunately, Tharmas’
                        secretive and deceptive protection of these Emanations demonstrates that his
                        attitudes to the emanative process are perverted by the fall. By hiding
                        these Emanations, he begins separating himself from his own Emanation and
                        falls further into the chaos of fallen existence. <note id="n61"><hi rend="s">15</hi>
Note that Enion’s lines at 7:3-8 appear
                            to be part of this revision.</note></p>
          <p>Yet the idea that Tharmas acts as a repository for man’s
                        redemptive Emanations suggests that Blake saw him as an increasingly
                        important figure or quality to be tapped in the process of undoing the
                        effects of the fall. The Circle of Destiny is composed, at least in part,
                        from the fibers of his being, and although it may be a constraining force of
                        destiny, it does help put a limit to the chaos existing at the beginning of
                        the poem. Moreover, when Tharmas reemerges from the chaos resulting from the
                        collapse of Urizen’s world in Night IV, he is instrumental in
                        initiating the reconstruction of the collapsed universe. Ultimately,
                        Tharmas, along with the Spectre of Urthona infuses power into Los which
                        enables him to tear down the sun and moon, bringing about the Last Judgement
                        (107:32-35). These features point to Tharmas’ potential
                        importance in the poem as the “Parent Power,” as a
                        kind of encompassing form, central to the substructure of the
                        poem’s mythology. Blake was later able to exploit these features
                        in the revisions to Night I, making Tharmas a figure containing the seeds of
                        destruction and recreation. These changes seem designed to make him an
                        increasingly more central figure.</p>
          <p>In the basic development of female-male relationships, however, many elements
                        of the Enion-Tharmas story as Blake revises it in pages 3-7 resemble the
                        interactions in the notebook poem, “My Spectre around me night
                        &amp; day,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62"
type="note">16</ref> and
                        “The Mental Traveller” of the 1800-04 period.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63" type="note">17</ref> In “My Spectre around
                        me,” the Spectre, like Tharmas, complains that his Emanation,
                        like Enion, murders his sweet Loves and seems to have the power of life or
                        death over them and him: he pleads 
						<q> When wilt thou return &amp;
                            view<lb/>
 My loves &amp; them to life renew<lb/>
 When wilt thou
                            return &amp; live<lb/>
 When wilt thou pity as I forgive.<lb/>
                            (29-32; E 476) </q>
The note of lament for the absent loved one who
                        causes such pain is also typical of Tharmas’ complaints. Further,
                        the counter accusations of sin by Tharmas (6:29-31) and Enion (4:27-41) are
                        paralleled in what appears to be a postscript to “My Spectre
                        around me”: 
						<q> Oer my Sins Thou sit &amp; moan<lb/>
 Hast
                            thou no Sins of thy own<lb/>
 Oer my Sins thou sit &amp; weep<lb/>
                            And lull thy own Sins fast asleep.<lb/>
 (1-4; E 477) </q>
	<note id="n62"><hi rend="s">16</hi> This poem is difficult to date
                            precisely. Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon,
                            1977) 322, dates “My Spectre” in period 1801-03,
                            while Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Notebook of William Blake: A Photographic
                                and Typographic Facsimile</hi>, rev. ed. (New York: Readex, 1977)
                            55, dates it after August 1803. Despite this disagreement between
                            Bentley and Erdman, it seems safe to assume that based on similarities
                            in symbolism, character, and tone, this poem was written during roughly
                            the same period when Blake was reworking the opening of 
<hi rend="i">Vala.</hi></note>
	<note id="n63"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi>
                            342, notes that the earliest this poem could have been written in its
                            present form is 1802, since it is written on blank leaves from
                            Hayley’s <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi> of that year. However,
                            Bentley qualifies this late date by noting that “The dates of
                            original composition may well be 1800-4 for the Ballads Manuscript
                            poems.” A date of soon after 1800 would correspond roughly
                            with the time Blake was working on the Tharmas-Enion
                        material.</note></p>
          <p>In addition, Enion resembles the “Woman Old” of
                        “The Mental Traveller”—a poem written in
                        the same period as “My Spectre” and which describes a
                        similar relationship—who binds her love and 
						<q> Her fingers
                            number every Nerve<lb/>
 Just as a Miser counts his gold<lb/>
 She lives
                            upon his shrieks &amp; cries<lb/>
 And She grows young as he grows
                            old.<lb/>
 (17-20; E 484) </q>
Enion torments Tharmas in similar terms:
						<q> In [<hi rend="i">dismal</hi>] &lt;gnawing&gt; pain
                            drawn out by her lovd fingers every nerve<lb/>
 She counted. every vein
                            &amp; lacteal threading them among<lb/>
 Her woof of terror.
                            Terrified &amp; drinking tears of woe<lb/>
 Shuddring she wove nine
                            days &amp; nights Sleepless her food was tears<lb/>
 . . .<lb/>
 A
                            Frowning Continent appeard Where Enion in the desart<lb/>
 Terrified in
                            her own Creation viewing her woven shadow<lb/>
 Sat in a sweet
                            intoxication of false woven bliss.<lb/>
 (5:16-19, 26-28) </q>
Only the
                        added note of terror differentiates the picture of Enion from that of the
                        “Woman Old”; yet the “sweet
                        intoxication” of her actions seems to mitigate Enion’s
                        terror. Thus, it appears that the changing face of the Tharmas-Enion story
                        is linked to a widespread development in Blake’s presentation of
                        the male-female conflict in terms of what he would ultimately depict between
                        the Spectre and Female Will. Although his latest revisions were not
                        thoroughly consistent, Blake eventually replaced
                        “Enitharmon” with “Jerusalem” in
                        Tharmas’ opening speech. It seems probable that Blake made this
                        change around the time he added the ideas of language of Sin and Repentance
                        to his text. The concurrence of these additions is by no means certain;
                        however, their thematic congruency could not be overlooked by Blake. 
<pb id="p22-98" n="98"/>
As a scene of love and jealousy expanded to include
                        the language of sin and repentance, it seems logical that Blake might decide
                        to locate the source of controversy in Jerusalem, a victimized biblical
                        figure of increasing importance his later writings. Moreover, both elements
                        share a common relative lateness in the manuscript.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64" type="note">18</ref> Basically, the emotional conflict between Tharmas
                        and Enion remains the same in this love triangle except that Tharmas has
                        “Hidden &lt;Jerusalem [instead of Enitharmon] in Silent
                        Contrition&gt;” (4:10), and he now asks Enion,
                        “&lt;Why hast thou taken sweet Jerusalem from my inmost
                        Soul&gt; (4:12). Blake did not, however, carry out these revisions
                        in Tharmas’ plea, “It is not Love I bear to Enitharmon
                        It is Pity” (4:14) or in the story told by the messengers from
                        Beulah on page 22, and this fact leads me to assume either that the change
                        was only very tentative or that Blake “accidentally neglected
                        making the same change here as in lines 9 and 11, and 5:7” (E
                        819). Moreover, Blake’s incomplete revision of the
                        Enion-Tharmas-Jerusalem triangle may have signalled his temporary
                        abandonment of the text of pages 5-7. <note id="n64"><hi rend="s">18</hi> If
                            the addition of Enitharmon to the Tharmas-Enion conflict is concurrent
                            with the addition of pages 20-22 to the manuscript, as I suggested
                            earlier, then the addition of Jerusalem to the conflict (and also the
                            language of Sin and Repentance) would be very late indeed, perhaps the
                            latest addition to the entire poem.</note></p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>III</title>
          </head>
          <p>In the process of developing and later deleting the text of pages 4-6, Blake
                        put his characters through a series of interesting changes.
                        Blake’s tampering with this text is quite revealing in terms of
                        his development of the relationship between Tharmas and Enion and their
                        characterization. In lines 9-15 on page 6 Tharmas is described in
                        “self admiring raptures” (6:13) 
						<q> wishing that the
                            heavens had eyes to See<lb/>
 And courting that the Earth would ope her
                            Eyelids &amp; behold<lb/>
 Such wondrous beauty repining in the
                            midst of all his glory<lb/>
 That nought but Enion could be forced to
                            praise adore &amp; love.<lb/>
 (6:9-12) </q>
In a subsequent passage
                        (6:26-35) Tharmas finds that Enion does not admire him half as much as he
                        himself does, rebukes her accusations of sin (26-28), asserts his own moral
                        purity against her supposed sins (29-31) and proclaims himself god over her
                        tortured soul (32-35). Finally, he accuses her of being a false temptress
                        (7:12-17) who first wants him to “hide thee with my power and
                        delight thee with my beauty” (13) but then “darknest
                        in my presence” (14) when he does appear. Thus, he decides
                        “In my jealous wings / I evermore will hold thee when thou goest
                        out or comest in” (15-16). Throughout these lines, we see Blake
                        developing the most negative aspects of the Spectre which he later called
                        the “Selfhood.” The net effect of these passages is to
                        polarize the innocent and evil sides of Tharmas into two distinct
                        characters. On the one hand, we have the innocent Tharmas, a victim of the
                        fall caused by the war between Luvah and Urizen; on the other, we find the
                        malevolent Spectre of Tharmas, the perversion of the victimized Tharmus,
                        bent on dominating and destroying Enion. It is not surprising to find that
                        as Tharmas grows more evil, Enion becomes a more sympathetic (or simply
                        pathetic) victim.</p>
          <p>In her first speech in this section (5:46-55, 57), Enion repents of weaving
                        Tharmas into a Spectre, an act in which “Love is changed to
                        deadly Hate” (48) and laments the feeling that her
                        “Soul has lost its splendor &amp; a brooding Fear / Shadows
                        me oer &amp; drives me outward to a world of woe” (53-54).
                        Following the description of Tharmas’ “self admiring
                        raptures,” Enion laments her solitude and calls out for Tharmas
                        whom she does not recognize in his Spectre form (6:16-25). And finally, she
                        repents for slaying Tharmas’ Emanations and defies the
                        Spectre’s perceived temptation that she “murder my own
                        soul &amp; wipe my tears &amp; smile” (6:36-7:11). In
                        Blake’s rather patchy narrative here, it appears that the
                        victimized Tharmas sinks beneath the waves of Enion’s
                        “filmy Woof” (5:14) after turning “round
                        the circle of Destiny” (5:11). This
                        “innocent” Tharmas does not reappear until pages 43-44
                        where he arises from the watery ruin of Urizen’s world. Enion,
                        through her weaving, draws out the Spectre of Tharmas from the nerves and
                        veins of the innocent Tharmas.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65"
type="note">19</ref> The
                        narrative then follows the Spectre’s rape of Enion, after which
                        he seems to disappear from the narrative. Blake leaves some clues suggesting
                        that, in mingling with Enion, the Spectre becomes one with her in a perverse
                        attempt to dominate and at the same time unify with her. His influence
                        continues in the birth of Los and Enitharmon and the “Spectrous
                        Life” (9:4) they draw from Enion. Ultimately, this spectrous
                        quality would seem to emerge in the Spectre of Urthona. In a sense, this
                        chronicle reinforces the connection between Tharmas and Urthona as brothers
                        in Eternity and allies in the war against Urizen while trapped in the fallen
                        world. Again, the revisions of these opening pages make Tharmas a more
                        central figure. In his Spectre form, he stands as the starting point for the
                        spectrous qualities which enter the fallen world. <note id="n65"><hi rend="s">19</hi>
Blake also mentions the “World of
                            Tharmas” at 33:6. This passage, as part of the early
                            copperplate text, does not contain enough information to state clearly
                            which Tharmas Blake meant here; however, the later narrative context
                            created after the revisions to Night I suggests a logical connection
                            with the innocent Tharmas trapped beneath the waves until he arises in
                            Night III.</note></p>
          <p>Blake seems uncertain, however, about the degree of malevolence to attribute
                        to the Spectre of Tharmas. Like the Spectre of Urthona—perhaps
                        the first use of the idea of a Spectre—the Spectre of Tharmas
                        arises as the product of sexual dissension and division, a perverted 
<hi rend="i">dopplegänger</hi> for an eternal identity,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66"
type="note">20</ref> and represents a 
<pb id="p22-99" n="99"/>
spirit of despair and self-destruction. In
particular, the
                        Spectre of Tharmas seems an inversion of Tharmas’ unanswered
                        desire for pity into a tyrannical attempt instill terror and dominate or
                        destroy the appearance of weakness in others, especially Enion. This
                        entirely negative presentation of the Spectre seems more in keeping with the
                        bat-winged, devouring figure in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and lacks the
                        potentially redemptive memory of eternity that we see in the Spectre of
                        Urthona in Night VIIa.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67"
type="note">21</ref> Thus at some
                        point, Blake sought to moderate this confrontation of extremes and deleted
                        all of the above passages with grey wash, diagonal ink strokes or both. The
                        result of this deletion was to neutralize the characterization of Tharmas
                        somewhat and to confine his violent nature to the union with Enion
                        (7:21-26). But another problem arises as a result of such extensive
                        deletions. Enion has now lost much of the sympathetic quality that her
                        laments gave her, and the keynote of her repentance is entirely lost. She is
                        now merely a character acting out of sorrow and terror, weaving her lover
                        into a terrible Spectre. Therefore, Blake may have decided to circle certain
                        passages to be readmitted to the final version of Night I. 
<note id="n66"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Literal
                                Imagination: Blake’s Vision of Words</hi> (Berkeley: U of
                            California P, 1983) 151.</note>
	<note id="n67"><hi rend="s">21</hi> This factor suggests that Blake did not
                            develop the story of the Spectre of Tharmas until after much of 
<hi rend="i">Vala</hi> was transcribed, and he was well into work on <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></note></p>
          <p>At one time the ink circles around certain passages on pages 5, 6 and 7 were
                        seen as part of Blake’s process of deletion, but Andrew Lincoln
                        has demonstrated that these circles were actually used by Blake to set off
                        material that was to be saved from the mass of deletions on the page and
                        that Blake had added to these passages after they were struck out and
                            circled.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68" type="note">22</ref>
Blake leaves the passage
                        concerning Tharmas’ “self admiring
                        raptures” deleted, possibly because the line preceding
                        it—“Glorying in his own eyes Exalted in terrific
                        Pride” (6:8)—carries the essential significance of the
                        7 deleted lines (6:9-15). Blake also leaves out the previously deleted
                        passage in which Tharmas condemns Enion as a temptress (7:12-17). This
                        passage is useful in offering a clear explanation for Tharmas’
                        violent attack, but perhaps Blake felt that the venom in the one passage he
                        returned to the text was strong enough to get his point across. Thus,
                        Tharmas’ rebuke of Enion and his proclamation of himself as a god
                        of moral purity over her tortured soul (6:26-35) is circled in order to be
                        retained for a later version of the poem. The modified version of these
                        lines (6:26-27, 29-35)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69"
type="note">23</ref> expands
                        Tharmas’ accusation that Enion is a “sinful
                        Woman” (the deleted line 7:12), and perhaps this is another
                        partial explanation for leaving 7:12-17 deleted. Further, Blake probably
                        retained these lines because they present an essential expression of the
                        Spectrous aspect of Tharmas’ character and also because they
                        establish an aspiration to godhood and moral purity that is characteristic
                        of Tharmas and the rest of the Zoas and increasingly becomes a central
                        concern for Blake. In these respects, this passage seems to supersede the
                        characterization developed in the passages which Blake did not circle to
                        retain for later use.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70"
type="note">24</ref>
	<note id="n68"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Lincoln, “<hi rend="i">The
                                Four Zoas</hi>” 94. The passages discussed here are as
                            follows (the undeleted form of these lines is based on
                            Lincoln’s arguments): <table rows="8" cols="4"><row>
	<cell>Stage 1—passages marked for deletion</cell>
	<cell/>
	<cell>Stage 2—passages circled for return to final
                                        draft</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>Tharmas</cell>
	<cell>Enion</cell>
	<cell>Tharmas</cell>
	<cell>Enion</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell/>
	<cell>5:46-57</cell>
	<cell/>
	<cell>5:46-55</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>6:9-15</cell>
	<cell/><cell/><cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell/>
	<cell>6:16-25</cell>
	<cell/><cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>6:26-35</cell>
	<cell/>
	<cell>6:26-27, 29-35</cell>
	<cell/>
</row>
<row>
	<cell/>
	<cell>6:36-7:11</cell>
	<cell/>
	<cell>6:36,38,-7:3-8,11</cell>
</row>
<row>
	<cell>7:12-17</cell>
	<cell/><cell/><cell/>
</row></table></note>
	<note id="n69"><hi rend="s">23</hi> Lincoln, “<hi rend="i">The
                                    Four Zoas</hi>” 94-95, notes that in
                                Blake’s revision, “The end of the first line
                                [6:26] and all of the second line (‘Art thou not my slave
                                &amp; shall thou dare / To smite me with thy tongue beware lest
                                I sting thee also’) were deleted and replaced by an
                                addition of one-and-a-half lines (the full line subsequently
                                deleted): 
<q> Who art thou Diminutive husk &amp; shell [<hi rend="i">Broke
from my bonds I scorn my prison I scorn
                                        &amp; yet I love</hi>].” </q>
Erdman,
                                following Lincoln’s reconstruction, prints this modified
                                version at 6:8-16 in his new edition.
                        </note>
	<note id="n70"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Brian Wilkie and Mary Lynn Johnson, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Four Zoas: The
Design of a Dream</hi>
                            (Cambridge: Harvard UP, 1978) 74, point out that in Night III,
                            “Urizen’s insistence that Ahania is
                            ‘diminutive’ repeats the pattern of
                            Tharmas’s rejection of Enion in Night I; in both instances a
                            domineering character projects his own smallness or sense of it onto his
                            more passive partner.” In a note to this discussion, Wilkie
                            and Johnson (268) suggest that 6:27 (and the remaining portion of this
                            deleted passage), in particular, may have been reinstated to strengthen
                            the parallels between the Tharmas-Enion and Urizen-Ahania
                            stories.</note></p>
          <p>Of the three Enion passages, Blake circled two and left the other one
                        deleted. He retains most of Enion’s first lament,
                        “What have I done . . . accursed wretch! What deed . .
                        .” (5:46-57), but drops the last two lines. This passage is of
                        importance in returning the sympathetic and lamenting quality to Enion. It
                        establishes her realization of error that drives her “outward to
                        a world of woe” (5:54) where she wanders throughout the course of
                        the poem. Also, a modified form of the passage at the top of page 7 is
                        retained in part as a continuation of the circled passage at the bottom of
                        page 6 (Tharmas’ assertion of godhood over Enion).
                        “The final text at the top of page 7,” argues Lincoln,
                        “. . . should probably include lines 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, &amp;
                            11.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71" type="note">25</ref>
This passage
                        expands on the sense of realization within Enion about the murder of
                        Tharmas’ Emanations and adds a heightened pathos to her character
                        with her realization “now I find that all those Emanations were
                        my Childrens Souls / And I have murderd them with cruelty above
                        atonement” (7.5-6). The depth of pathos here puts her
                        characterization quite in line with that of her other laments at 17:2-18:7
                        and 35:1-36:13, and her sense of murder without atonement gives an added
                        explanation for the fact that she never answers to Tharmas’ call
                        as she wanders in the “dark deep” (34:98). <note id="n71"><hi rend="s">25</hi>
Lincoln, “<hi rend="i">The Four
                                Zoas</hi>” 95.</note></p>
          <p>This passage also strengthens Enion’s connection with her
                        mythological antecedent, Demeter, who wanders the earth in search of her
                        child Persephone.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72"
type="note">26</ref> Enion’s
                        laments show her wandering through a spiritual wasteland, lamenting for her
                        surviving children who flee from her “cruelty into the desarts /
                        Among wild beasts to roam” (7:7-8). Yet Blake goes beyond his
                        Greek sources to depict a mother who drives all love from her life and
                        thereby exiles her creative potential as represented by her offspring.
                        Indeed, her own self-absorption creates children who draw away her own life
                        and vitality. Blake, however, remains unwilling to condemn Enion
                        whole-heartedly. The one passage Blake did not circle to be reclaimed
                        (6:16-25) does not evoke the same degree of pathos as the two circled
                        passages nor does it contain any statement of self-realization or
                        repentance. Indeed, Enion seems to show less awareness in this than in the
                            <pb id="p22-100" n="100"/>
previous speech. This deleted passage is
                        merely a lament in solitude and a call for Tharmas that does not really fill
                        out the narrative. In fact, some confusion seems to re-main in the setting,
                        since Enion first stands “on the Rocks” before
                        “her woven shadow glowing bright” (5:57), then hides
                        “in the darksom Cave” (6:15) and then sits
                        “among the Rocks” (6:22) and finally sleeps
                        “in a Chasm of the Valley” (6:24). I may perhaps be
                        seeking a greater degree of consistency here than Blake saw necessary;
                        however, because of the deletion of the material around this passage, it
                        does not seem that it could be easily refitted into the narrative at this
                        point. Yet just as importantly, Blake could not logically undermine
                        Enion’s laments at the ends of Nights I and II; she makes a
                        central statement about the actual effect of the fall in these laments that
                        is true not only for the world of the poem but also the failings in
                        contemporary British life that Blake attacked throughout his career. The
                        pathos in her laments represents the spirit of pathos shut out from the
                        sublime at the fall.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73"
type="note">27</ref>
	<note id="n72"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Northrop Frye, <hi rend="i">Fearful
                                Symmetry: A Study of William Blake</hi> (Princeton: Princeton UP,
                            1969) 279, notes this correspondence between Demeter and Enion. See also
                            Judith Lee, “Ways of Their Own: The Emanations of
                            Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> or <hi rend="i">The Four
                                Zoas</hi>,” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi>, 50 (1983): 134, for a
                            more detailed discussion of this correspondence. Note that Blake
                            strengthened these associations in additions to the poem which show that
                            Enion’s lament, at least in part, may be traced to her
                            children, Los and Enitharmon, who draw life and vitality from their
                            parent “And then they wanderd far away she sought for them in
                            vain / In weeping blindness stumbling she followd them oer rocks
                            &amp; mountains” (9:1-2).</note>
	<note id="n73"><hi rend="s">27</hi> In a unique version of the
                                frontispiece to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (see Geoffrey Keynes,
                                “New Lines from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,”
                                    <hi rend="i">Blake Studies: Essays on His Life and Work</hi>,
                                2nd ed. (Oxford: Clarendon, 1971) 115-17, Blake wrote of the sublime
                                and the pathos at the fall: 
<q> His [Albion’s] Sublime
                                    &amp; Pathos become Two Rocks fixd in the Earth<lb/>
 His
                                    Reason his Spectrous Power, covers them above<lb/>
 Jerusalem his
                                    Emanation is a Stone laying beneath<lb/>
 O [<hi rend="i">Albion
                                        behold Pitying</hi>] behold the Vision of Albion.<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 1:4-7;E 144) </q>
Possibly, Blake began to
                                see Tharmas and Enion’s relationship as an icon of the
                                situation represented by these lines and continued to revise it
                                accordingly in late stages of revising pages 4-7. Tharmas and Enion,
                                as the Sublime and the Pathos, are fixed and separated by virtue of
                                the Spectrous power emerging from mutual distrust and jealousy over
                                Tharmas’ relationship with Jerusalem.
                        </note></p>
          <p>Throughout this process of revision, however, we can see a tendency in
                        Blake’s writing, first, to fill out the symbolic and conceptual
                        elements in his character and then revise these elements to fit the
                        character they apply to. Thus, he works out the Spectre-like aspect of
                        Tharmas to its fullest and then attempts to revise it in this case to limit
                        the singular evil that the Tharmas character seems to take on. With Enion,
                        Blake shifts the degree and expression of her pathos in relation to the
                        ferocity of Tharmas. The result of such a process of revision seems to bring
                        a balance between the two characters. Of course, the fact that Blake revised
                        the opening of Night I long after he had already written most of the poem
                        also means that he had to consider whether he should accommodate his
                        revisions to make later appearances of Tharmas consistent. It is not clear
                        whether he was wholly committed to abandoning the consistency necessary to
                        the relatively linear narrative of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> in favor
                        of a more nonlinear form such as that used in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></p>
        </div2>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>IV</title>
          </head>
          <p>Although Blake worked extensively with the Tharmas-Enion story in Night I, I
                        suspect that this painstaking work eventually contributed to his abandonment
                        of the manuscript. It seems that Tharmas’ significance began to
                        outstrip his role as one of the Four Zoas. Even as Blake elaborates on the
                        identity of Tharmas, he develops him beyond the immediate needs of the
                        narrative. In the poem’s narrative, he stands at the nodal point
                        of the fall into the chaotic sea of time and space and acts as a source for
                        the conditions of fallen existence. Enion’s weaving of Tharmas
                        into the Circle of Destiny and the form of the Spectre suggests that
                        Tharmas’ fall introduces fate and error. The weaving imagery also
                        suggests Tharmas’ incarnation into the limitations of the
                        physical body, while the notion that he holds the Emanation Jerusalem within
                        suggests the potential for redemption of the body when it contains the City
                        of God. These associations suggest that Tharmas is analogous to the
                        universal human form of the One Man, Jesus Christ. Such associations give
                        Tharmas a symbolic equivalence with Albion. Indeed, as he developed the
                        Tharmas character more fully, while, at the same time, working on 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, Blake may have begun to transfer some of his
                        characteristics to Albion. In the design on plate 25 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,
Albion’s fibers, like Tharmas’,
                        are drawn out by female figures to create the vegetated world. Also,
                        Albion’s Spectre, like Tharmas’, emerges at the
                        opening of the poem and moves to the west—Tharmas’
                        dark domain (4:6)—where he remains “a black
                        Horror” (J. 5:68; E 148). The influence of these Spectres
                        symbolically overshadows events in their respective poems. Moreover, the
                        action of Tharmas’ hiding Jerusalem “in the Soft
                        recess of darkness &amp; silence” (4:13) from Enion may be
                        compared to Albion’s hiding of Jerusalem “in jealous
                        fears” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 4:33; E 147) “From the
                        vision and fruition of the Holy-one” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 4:17; E
                        146). In addition, lines addressed by Enion to Tharmas in <hi rend="i">The
                            Four Zoas</hi> (4:18-21) are transferred to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
                        where they are spoken by Vala to Albion (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 22:1, 10-12; E
                            167).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">28</ref> Of
these lines, Paley
                        remarks that “Although it cannot be proved that the traffic goes
                        from <hi rend="i">FZ</hi> to <hi rend="i">J</hi> here, it seems as if Blake
                        were quarrying material from his nearly abandoned Zoas myth for the later
                        myth of Jerusalem and Albion.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75"
type="note">29</ref> The suggestion that Tharmas became a model for
                        Blake’s development of Albion thus seems quite possible; the
                        outcome of such revision would render Tharmas a redundant character in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and explain his relative absence from that poem.
                            <note id="n74"><hi rend="s">28</hi> Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">The
                                Continuing City: William Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem (Oxford:
                            Clarendon, 1983) 79-80. compares the use of these lines in <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>
and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> See also 35-6.</note>
	<note id="n75"><hi rend="s">29</hi> Paley, <hi rend="i">The Continuing
                                City</hi> 80.</note></p>
          <p>Yet the shifting portrayal of Tharmas, in particular, suggests that Blake
                        conceived of his characters’ significances as more fluid than
                        many critics have yet suggested. He seems more than willing to experiment
                        freely with a character in a particular episode. Indeed, in the case of
                        Tharmas, Blake seems to become obsessed with the scene before him, giving it
                        a greater immediacy by straining certain attributes to their limits. Under
                        this obsession, Blake relaxes concerns with narrative consistency 
<pb id="p22-101" n="101"/> (whatever value that term may have to a poet who
                        often undermines consistency) for the immediacy of effect. Yet with <hi rend="i">The
Four Zoas</hi>, Blake seems again to modify the immediacy
                        of a scene to fit with the consistency of the thematic whole. Blake perhaps
                        felt uncertain about how to resolve the tension emerging in the revisions to
                            <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> between a sequentially coherent and
                        consistent narrative structure—what Donald Ault has called the
                        “Newtonian” narrative—and a subversively
                        disjunctive and disruptive
                        narrative—“anti-Newtonian,” in
                        Ault’s terms.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76"
type="note">30</ref> The Newtonian
                        narrative is necessary in conveying a fixity of events which may be
                        understood and interpreted by the reader. Interpretation of such narrative,
                        however, involves a rational assemblage and comparison of events along a
                        temporally and spatially limited schema, but the anti-Newtonian narrative
                        offers expanded possibilities in educating the reader. The anti-Newtonian
                        narrative, with its lack of explicitness and interpretive closure,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77" type="note">31</ref> exerts pressure on the reader, forcing
                        him to use his own imaginative vision to unify rather than assemble
                        potential meaning in the text. Blake found his answer to this tension in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> In reading <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, we find
                        that Blake seems to demonstrate that immediacy of scene is all; overall
                        effect seems derived from the imaginative unification of disparate parts.
                        Thus, meaning derives from an accretion of disjunctive parts rather than
                        from a linear narrative imposed by the consistencies of time and space. In
                            <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Blake still seems to feel a certain
                        stress between sequential and disjunctive narratives and does yet not fully
                        abandon one for the other. Perhaps the stress between these two forces
                        caused additional delays in Blake’s work on the poem, and created
                        fractures in the framework of his epic that he found he could never
                        completely or satisfactorily repair. <note id="n76"><hi rend="s">30</hi>
                            Ault, “Re-Visioning <hi rend="i">The Four
                            Zoas</hi>” 105-09.</note>
	<note id="n77"><hi rend="s">31</hi> Ault, “Re-Visioning <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>” 108, sees an
                            “open narrative field in which the past is not closed and
                            complete but open—unfinished and revisable” as one
                            of the prime elements of the anti-Newtonian narrative.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p22-102" n="102" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
