<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>22.3.butlin</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">David Bindman, ed., William Blake’s Illustrations to the Book of Job; 
David Bindman, ed., Colour Versions of William Blake’s Book of Job Designs from the Circle of John Linnell</title>
        <author n="Butlin">Martin Butlin</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1988/89</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1988/89</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">22.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G. E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>Michael Phillips</name>
              <name>John B. Pierce</name>
              <name>Aileen Ward</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_22">
    <body>
	<pb id="p22-105" n="105"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-22-3-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">David Bindman, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations of the
                Book of Job</hi>, London: The William Blake Trust, 1987. 172 pp., 53 pp.
              reproductions, 22 plates.</title>
            <title type="main">David Bindman, ed. <hi rend="i">Colour versions of William
                Blake’s Book of Job designs from the circle of John Linnell</hi>, London: The
              William Blake Trust, 1987. 28 pp., 48 color facsimiles.</title>
            <title type="main">Deluxe edition with stencils,
              proofs, and an extra set of plates, 22 copies at £1,600 for both publications.
              Standard edition, 250 copies at £580 for both publications. Standard edition, 50
              copies, £260 and £360 respectively for each publication.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Martin <name>Butlin</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>It is a long time since I have received one of these wonderful William Blake Trust
            publications. The excitement of unwrapping a package large enough to enclose a complete
            set of hi-fi equipment, the characteristic smell of glue and leather, the sumptuous
            effect of gold tooling on brown leather with carefully attuned cloth and marbled papers,
            beautifully clear and legible typeface—I had feared that these were a thing of the past.
            And of course, in many ways this publication is a product of the past. The “onlie
            begetters,” Sir Geoffrey Keynes and Arnold Fawcus, died in 1982 and 1979 respectively,
            leaving the work unfinished, and a new team, David Bindman, Barbara Bryant, Robert
            Essick and Bo Lindberg, some already involved in the project, have brought the work to
            completion. The result is something rather different from, and rather more ambitious
            than, what was originally envisaged. The long list of color facsimiles produced by the
            Trianon Press under Arnold Fawcus for the William Blake Trust were above all objects of
            beauty, recreating as near to perfection as possible Blake’s original achievements. The
            accompanying text, though fully adequate, was deliberately kept as short as possible.
            Only in a few of the later publications, such as <hi rend="i">Blake’s Laocoön, a Last
              Testament</hi>, published in 1976, and <hi rend="i">The Complete Portraiture of
              William and Catherine Blake</hi>, of 1977, was the accompanying matter of necessity
            fuller and more scholarly. Now, as the preface by David Bindman 
          <pb id="p22-106" n="106"/>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <figure n="bb421.1.2-1.ps" id="bb421.1.spb.02" work-copy="bb421.1" rend="db" width="774" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>ספר איוב<lb/>
	ILLUSTRATIONS of<lb/>
	The<lb/>
	BOOK<lb/>
	of<lb/>
	JOB<lb/>
	Invented &amp; Engraved<lb/>
	by William Blake<lb/>
	1825<lb/>
	London Published as the Act directs March 8: 1825. by William Blake No3 Fountain Court Strand</figTranscr>
</figure>
            and John Commander states, “a more
            extensive range of discussion, analysis and documentation” has been included. From the
            simplicity of the original idea this publication has become a multipart, complex
            production including not only the visual evidence, but also a profusion of analysis and
            description. For the scholar this has obvious advantages, but it also has two major
            disadvantages, particularly for the primary market for this publication, the Blake
            enthusiast.</p>
          <p>First, there is no consistency of opinion throughout the publication; different
            theories as to order of execution and so on are put forward by the different authors.
            The preface somewhat disingenuously suggests that “this partly reflects the many-layered
            complexity of Blake’s involvement with the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> theme and is also an
            acknowledgement that the range and depth of Blake studies can no longer be embraced by
            one scholar.” The problem is at its greatest in connection with Keynes’s introductory
            text on “The Development of the Job Designs.” This was written some years before
            Keynes’s death and indeed the main substance dates back to the great five-part
            publication of <hi rend="i">Illustrations to the Book of Job
              by William Blake</hi> edited by Keynes and Laurence Binyon in 1935, and subsequently
            republished with emendments in <hi rend="i">Blake Studies</hi> in 1971. The editors were
            faced with a difficult decision and in the end, “It was decided not to attempt to bring
            the text up to date but to leave it essentially unchanged. A few minor editorial
            alterations have been made . . . .” However, this has left not only contradictions
            between Keynes’s text and what is written elsewhere in the publication but even
            contradictions within Keynes’s text itself. On page 18, the date of the first, Thomas
            Butts set of watercolors, is brought back from the 1820s to the first decade of the
            nineteenth century but the subsequent text is left largely unaltered, leaving Keynes to
            suggest at the head of page 19 that, after a few early isolated depictions of subjects
            from the Book of Job, Blake did not set about “telling the story in his own way . . . .
            in the series of ‘Inventions’ until after his second spiritual rebirth following the
            dark days of 1810-18.” On the other hand, it is not just for sentimental and nostalgic
            reasons that one is glad that Keynes’s piece has been retained. There is a
            characteristic lightness of touch and sense of humor largely lacking from the writings
            of later writers on Blake, as in the juxtaposition 
<pb id="p22-107" n="107"/>
of the
            transcription of the entries recording the sale of proofs to the King and to Josiah
            Taylor, the latter having been “sent to the House of Correction by F. Tatham, Taylor
            being S<hi rend="s">t</hi> [sent] H. of C. for swindling.”</p>
          <p>Much the most crucial result of the decision to submit the whole question of Blake’s
            illustrations to the Book of Job to a thorough scholarly review is that it has proved
            impossible to suppress the doubts concerning the genuineness of the works that had
            already been printed in expensive color facsimile by the Trianon Press before Fawcus’s
            death, the so-called New Zealand set, the Collins hand colored engravings, and the four
            hand colored plates in the Fitzwilliam Museum. By the time he died, Keynes must have
            been the only reputable Blake scholar still to insist on the authenticity of the New
            Zealand set; even Fawcus, who had previously been persuaded that they were genuine, had
            begun to have his doubts, which were later reinforced by his widow’s researches. Other
            scholars had doubted them long before. The result is that this fine but expensive
            publication is largely taken up with what at the best can only be regarded as peripheral
            material, together with a scholarly apparatus that demonstrates just how peripheral it
            is. In fact the scholarly apparatus is perhaps almost too damning in its judgement on at
            least one group of the works.</p>
          <p>To make things easier for the impecunious the Blake Trust has made 50 copies of the two
            main parts of this publication (each in its own box) available separately; however, the
            22 deluxe copies and 250 of the standard copies can only be acquired both parts
            together. Nevertheless it will perhaps be helpful if this review continues with a
            discussion of the contents of the publication section by section so that people wanting
            to buy only one part will know what is involved.</p>
          <p>The first box, devoted to <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Book of
              Job</hi>, contains two sections, one a book of most of the introductory texts, the
            other a box filled with a series of 22 fascicules each devoted to the various treatments
            of one composition in the series. The text volume starts with a select bibliography
            which also serves as a list of abbreviations, a page of acknowledgements written by
            Stephen Keynes, and a foreword, discussing the activities of the William Blake Trust, by
            Charles Ryskamp. This is followed by the preface by Bindman and Commander, already
            mentioned, which discusses and explains the complicated evolution of the publication.
            Then follows Keynes’s essay on “The Development of the Job Designs.”</p>
          <p>The rest of this introductory text volume is required reading for the Blake scholar. It
            begins with an essay on “The Book of Job Designs from Butts series to final engravings”
            by Bindman, which discusses the evolution of the various series of illustrations and
            relates them to the evolution of Blake’s thought. He starts by establishing the present
            view that the first set of watercolor illustrations for the Book of Job, those executed
            for Thomas Butts, were mainly done in the first decade of the nineteenth century rather
            than at the beginning of the 1820s, and that two of the series are later additions. One
            small addition can be made to his account of the stages by which this new dating was
            reached: in the 1971 second edition of my 1957 catalogue of the works by Blake in the
            Tate Gallery I had already suggested (see page 63) a dating of c. 1810. More important
            than the question of precedence however is the fact that Bindman makes sense of the
            redating in the context of Blake’s changing opinions as between the first decade of the
            century and the Indian summer of Blake’s last years. He also throws in the interesting
            speculation that the watercolor illustrations to the Bible, which seem to have
            immediately preceded the first series of illustrations to the Book of Job, were designed
            for an extra-illustrated volume. However, my own view is that the Bible watercolors,
            with their large inscriptions in a copperplate hand, were designed for display; the
            badly faded condition of many of these shows that they were so displayed and suffered
            from the ruinous effect of daylight.</p>
          <p>Bindman’s essay is followed by Essick’s on “Blake’s Engravings to the Book of Job: An
            Essay of their Graphic Form with a Catalogue of their States and Printings.” This is as
            detailed and exhaustive as one would expect and includes a lot of new material
            including, for instance, the fact that glue spots on the reduced size drawings in the
            Fitzwilliam Museum show that they were actually stuck to the copperplates as an aid to
            their engraving. Again the factual examination of the evidence, in this case Blake’s
            actual technique, is related to the wider issue of his artistic philosophy. Reading
            Essick’s analysis of the difference between the various states of the engravings is
            laborious, but well worthwhile in that it gives an insight into Blake’s working methods
            and attention to “minute particulars.” One slight disadvantage is that the various sets
            of pre-publication proofs are not discussed in chronological order but by location,
            which makes it difficult to follow the progression through from one series of proofs to
            the next. However a hitherto unknown set of proofs in the University of Texas library is
            included and, most fascinating of all, there is an analysis, as full as the
            circumstances allow, of a set of proofs that was last recorded when sold in 1936 (this
            has already formed the subject of an article in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 19 (1985-6):
            96-102). These last include evidence, not fully taken into account elsewhere in this
            publication, that even at this late stage Blake did not regard Job’s act of worship in
            the first design as merely an act of uninspired conformity, an inscription in the margin
            at the 
<pb id="p22-108" n="108"/>
foot of the altar reading “Prayer to God is the Study
            of Imaginative Art.” Only the fact that this set of proofs has now disappeared can
            account for the relative calm that has followed the publication of this revolutionary
            piece of information.</p>
          <p>The final section of this first volume of text is that on “The Job designs; a
            Documentary and Bibliographical Record,” compiled by Bryant with introductory notes by
            Bindman. This sets out all the Linnell accounts that relate to the publication of Job
            illustrations and includes fascinating short biographical notes on nearly every figure
            mentioned. These are especially full on lesser known figures and are made readily
            accessible through an index at the end. Only in amazingly few cases have the authors had
            to admit total failure in discovering anything about their subject. One small correction
            must be made: at the top of page 104 it is stated that three watercolors from the John
            Linnell set are not in the Fogg Art Museum; in fact one is in the National Gallery of
            Art, Washington, one is in a private collection in Paris, but the third, although parted
            at one stage from the rest of the Fogg Museum set when it passed through the collection
            of A. E. Newton, has now rejoined that set (Butlin no. 551 <hi rend="i">14</hi>).</p>
          <p>In addition to the introductory volume of text, the first of these two joint
            publications contains a box of fascicules each containing monochrome reproductions of
            the various stages in the evolution of each composition in the series: the Butts
            watercolor, the John Linnell watercolor, the reduced-size Fitzwilliam Museum drawings
            and the final engraving, together with some of the related tempera paintings,
            watercolors or drawings, some proof engravings including all those with marginal
            sketches, and the corresponding composition from the New Zealand set of watercolors.
            There is an introductory folder containing “The Meaning of Blake’s Job” by Lindberg, and
            each fascicule bears on the front of each folder a plate by plate commentary together
            with notes on previous interpretations by such writers as Wicksteed and S. Foster Damon.
            This commentary does not, perhaps thankfully, go into great interpretive detail but is
            more of a basic introduction of the kind found in earlier Blake Trust publications.</p>
          <p>However, the long evolution of this publication has led to certain problems. In the
            first place Essick’s researches have produced rather more states for some of the prints
            than were known when these fascicules were printed in the 1970s. The new information is
            available, but only in Essick’s catalogue. The short list of contents on the inside of
            the enclosing page of each fascicule, printed at the same time as the rest, gives the
            earlier, incorrect information. Certain additional reproductions have been made since
            the first printing, and these are listed on the back of the introductory folder, but
            again not at the front of the appropriate fascicule.</p>
          <p>More seriously, certain related works are omitted both from this collection of
            reproductions and indeed, so far as I can discover, from the text as a whole. The
            tempera painting related to plate 20, <hi rend="i">Job and his Daughters</hi> in the
            National Gallery of Art, Washington, is reproduced and mentioned in the text with the
            correct date of c. 1799-1800 (thus correcting the dating in the 1820s of William
            Rossetti and of Lindberg in his pioneering book on <hi rend="i">The Illustrations for
              the Book of Job</hi>, 1973). However, there is no mention at all, let alone a
            reproduction, of the Tate Gallery’s tempera on panel of <hi rend="i">Satan smiting Job
              with sore Boils</hi>, surely the final summation of that composition. Similarly, of
            the three pencil and watercolor sketches that play an important part in the evolution of
            certain of the later versions of the composition (Butlin nos. 552, 553 and 556), that
            showing <hi rend="i">Job’s Sacrifice</hi> in the City Art Gallery, Leeds, is mentioned
            but not reproduced (though there is an acknowledgement for permission to reproduce to
            the Leeds City Art Gallery). Only the recto of <hi rend="i">Every Man also gave him a
              piece of Money</hi>, a version of the upright variant of the composition, and now in
            the Tate Gallery, is reproduced, but not the recently discovered drawing on the reverse.
            This means that this collection of reproductions, in some ways the most useful part of
            the whole publication, is maddeningly incomplete; one still has to refer to other
            publications for certain works essential to the evolution of Blake’s designs.</p>
          <p>The second of these two joint publications, devoted to <hi rend="i">Colour versions of
              William Blake’s Book of Job designs from the circle of John Linnell</hi>, consists of
            a large box containing a seventeen-page introduction by Lindberg on “The Authenticity of
            the New Zealand Set and of the Colour Engravings; Comparisons between the sets,”
            together with the three sets of color facsimiles that were the original 
              <hi rend="i">raison d’etre</hi> of this publication: the socalled New Zealand set of
watercolors,
            the size of the engravings though without the margins, including all the compositions
            together with the title page; the so-called Collins set of hand colored engravings, the
            complete set with title page; and the four hand colored engravings, of compositions 11,
            15, 18 and 20, in the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge. These facsimiles are of the highest
            quality, hand colored through stencils by the pochoir process.</p>
          <p>Lindberg’s introduction is, to put it bluntly, a detailed and, in all but one case
            perhaps, a convincing demolition job on the authenticity of all three sets of works. In
            the case of the New Zealand set some of his arguments have been given before, as in his
            own 1973 publication on the Job illustrations; some are new and include observations
            made independently by Fawcus’s widow Julie. Lindberg kindly acknowledges my
            contribution, which I can confirm was also arrived at independently. 
              <pb id="p22-109" n="109"/>
Once again, to put the record straight, I should perhaps point out
that my
            suspicions were voiced, if only by omission, in the second edition of my catalogue of
            the works by Blake in the Tate Gallery: in the first edition I had mentioned the New
            Zealand set among the authentic works of Blake, while in the second I omitted all
            reference to it. To sum up the arguments, in every case the New Zealand watercolors
            depend either upon the final state of engravings where these have been altered or, where
            they differ from the final state of the engravings, upon the John Linnell set of
            watercolors. There is no way in which they can be regarded as independent works by Blake
            himself, whereas Lindberg convincingly places them within the circle of John Linnell and
            his sons and pupils whom Linnell is known to have instructed by having them copy works
            by Blake.</p>
          <p>For the two sets of hand colored engravings the arguments are less technical and more
            based on the judgement of the eye. The coloring of both sets is closely related to that
            of the New Zealand set, as is convincingly demonstrated by Lindberg. Moreover, the hand
            colored engravings and the New Zealand set are closer to each other than they are to the
            Linnell set of watercolors. One technical argument against the authenticity of the hand
            colored engravings, like that of the New Zealand set, is that the coloring of Job’s
            three friends is wrong in compositions 15 and 18, but this argument is somewhat vitiated
            by the fact that Blake himself seems to have made a similar mistake in composition
            16.</p>
          <p>The very quality of the color facsimiles makes this reviewer doubt the almost
            overwhelming evidence produced by Lindberg, at least in the case of the four Fitzwilliam
            Museum prints. It is not really correct to say, as Lindberg does, that the coloring in
            plate 11 is paler because the work has faded, though this argument does perhaps apply in
            the case of plate 18. In each case, to my eye, the coloring of the Fitzwilliam Museum
            version is more sensitive than that in either the Collins set or the New Zealand series
            of watercolors. Given that it is at least arguable that in other cases of hand colored
            engravings of Blake compositions, for instance the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>,
            there is at least one prime original hand colored by Blake himself, from which his wife
            or whoever made subsequent hand colored copies, it strikes me that the Fitzwilliam
            Museum prints could represent either the compositions surviving from a complete set or
            an incomplete set begun by Blake himself.</p>
          <p>Unfortunately there is no provenance for the Fitzwilliam Museum engravings prior to
            1935. That of the Collins engravings can be traced back to the middle of the nineteenth
            century and Lindberg has been able to supply new information about the history of the
            New Zealand set, two watercolors from which, it has been discovered, were exhibited at
            the Auckland Society of Arts in 1881 as being by William Blake. This attribution is
            clearly not enough in itself to authenticate the works. Lindberg dismisses another
            argument for the authenticity of the Collins set of hand colored engravings, that the
            monochrome engraving itself was deliberately printed paler to make the coloring more
            effective: as Linnell seems to have been responsible for much of the early printing, it
            could have been his intention that the works should be colored, or indeed, if I am
            correct in assuming that Blake himself was responsible for the Fitzwilliam Museum
            coloring, Blake himself could have intended the coloring but not actually executed
            it.</p>
          <p>Only in one further, minor point would I wish to disagree with Lindberg’s most thorough
            analysis of the various problems connected with Blake’s illustrations to the Book of
            Job. Lindberg suggests that the two compositions added to the Thomas Butts set of
            watercolors, clearly in the 1820s, were done before the corresponding compositions in
            the John Linnell set; Bindman and myself hold that they were executed subsequent to the
            Linnell watercolors. In the case of composition 17, <hi rend="i">The Vision of
              Christ</hi>, Lindberg argues that the position of the three friends, facing the vision
            of Christ in the Butts watercolor, is reversed in all the other versions and that this
            reversal is subtler in effect, particularly in the final engraving. However it could
            well be that Blake, or perhaps his widow who may have finished at least the coloring of
            this watercolor, wanted to give Butts, an old patron, something rather different from
            what had been done for the much younger patron John Linnell. In the case of 
              <hi rend="i">Job and his Daughters</hi>, composition 20, the two preliminary sketches (and
            significantly there are more such sketches for this composition than for most of the
            others) and the Linnell watercolor show Blake undecided as between setting his figures
            in a landscape or in an interior. In the final engraving he reverted to the solution of
            some 25 years earlier, the composition of the biblical tempera painting now in the
            National Gallery of Art, Washington. Rather than see the Butts watercolor as a stage in
            the evolution from a landscape setting towards an interior setting, I would suggest that
            the landscape solution of the Butts watercolor could again be a deliberate effort to
            distinguish his watercolor from the composition as evolved for John Linnell.</p>
          <p>It is because of the excellence of the reproductions and the thoroughness of the
            scholarship, that one can argue over such detailed points. Access to the Collins set of
            hand colored engravings is not easy but I have been fortunate enough to see them in the
            past (and even more fortunate in being able to examine the Fitzwilliam Museum prints
            laid out on my own grand piano!). But the quality of the facsimiles, even unaided by
            memories of the originals, is so high that value judgments can be made to supplement the
            detailed arguments of the text. Whether the effort and expense is worth it one must
            leave to the customer. For the scholar of Blake’s work in 
<pb id="p22-110" n="110"/>
the
            visual arts, both publications will be essential. For somebody willing to be satisfied
            with the main core of Blake’s achievement perhaps the first of the two publications will
            be sufficient, particularly if one has access to the 1935 Pierpont Morgan Library
            publication, which contains color facsimiles of the Butts and Linnell set of watercolors
            (only reproduced here in monochrome), and indeed of the New Zealand set, together with
            reproductions of the Fitzwilliam Museum drawings, many of the related sketches, and the
            final engravings.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
