<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>22.4.lincoln</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Cettina Tramontano Magno and David V. Erdman, The Four Zoas by William
          Blake: A Photographic Facsimile of the Manuscript with Commentary on the
          Illuminations</title>
        <author n="Lincoln">Andrew Lincoln</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1989</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1989</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">22.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>John A. Hodgson</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>David W. Lindsay</name>
              <name>M. A. L. Locherbie-Cameron</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Peter Otto</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_22">
    <body>
    <pb id="p22-116" n="116"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-22-4-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Cettina Tramontano Magno and David V. Erdman. <hi rend="i">The Four
                Zoas by William Blake: A Photographic Facsimile of the Manuscript with Commentary on
                the Illuminations.</hi> Lewisburg: Bucknell University Press; London and Toronto:
              Associated University Presses, 1987. 258 pp. $65/£45.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Andrew <name>Lincoln</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>This is the second facsimile of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> manuscript. The first,
            edited by G. E. Bentley, Jr. (1963), helped to clarify the textual problems in Blake’s
            poem by including a detailed transcription of Blake’s revisions.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1"
              type="note">1</ref> This new facsimile complements the first: there is no
            transcription of the text as the editors’ primary concern is to define and interpret the
            visual designs. In the manuscript there are more than 80 pages of drawings and several
            dozen specimens of Blake’s engraving. The new facsimile provides the first truly
            comprehensive examination of these illustrations, and makes an important contribution to
            our understanding of Blake’s technique of “illumination.” 
            <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> G.E. Bentley, Jr., ed., <hi rend="i">William Blake, “Vala or
The Four Zoas”:
                A Facsimile of the Manuscript, A Transcript of the Poem, and a Study of Its Growth
                and Significance</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1963).</note></p>
          <p>The manuscript is reproduced in monochrome, and four pages are also reproduced in
            color. The prints in this facsimile are smaller than the manuscript leaves, as the
            editors explain: “Photographs we have seen in full size [i.e., about 12¾ × 16½ inches]
            show less detail in faint places than do the 8 × 10 inch prints, many in infrared
            photography, obtained for this work, and we were advised to print from them without
            enlargement, to retain their sharpness of detail.” Comparison with the Bentley facsimile
            shows the wisdom of this decision. Many features that are invisible or barely detectable
            in Bentley become clearly visible here, including a fullpage design (the figure beneath
            the text on page 16), several individual figures (e.g., the figure rising in the
            left-hand margin of the title page) and a number of small details (such as the female
            breasts on the standing figure on page 31). At other points details that were visible in
            Bentley achieve a new clarity (the reclining figure on page 6; the design at the foot of
            page 12; the erased areas of the marginal figures on page 26; figures beneath the text
            of page 132). Sometimes the price of the increased definition is a murky page tone that
            makes 
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
            the text difficult to read (presumably the result of infrared), but the
            price is worth paying. There are a few places where the reduction leads to a slight (but
            not significant) loss of detail: drawings on pages 92, 108, 118, 134 and 144 seem, to my
            eye at least, clearer in Bentley. A hair seems to have got onto the camera lens in the
            plate of page 75.</p>
          <p>The four color plates are disappointing. The manuscript leaves have weathered into a
            lemon ocher, which becomes darker and more orange in the color prints. As a result color
            contrasts are flattened: the delicate pink on the shoulder and legs of the figure at the
            foot of page 5 becomes more difficult to see. I doubt whether any of these plates really
            justify their cost.</p>
          <p>Some photographic prints are supplemented with tracings, and even “enhanced” tracings
            of problematic details (there are 23 tracings in all). This difficult work has generally
            been executed with great care. It helps to clarify both large-scale drawings (on pages
            16 and 126) and local details (such as the three distinct faces disentangled from a
            revised sketch on page 17). Some tracings are colored by the editors’ guesswork. A
            tracing of page 22 (previously page 20) isolates loops and curves which in the original
            appear to be part of a larger sketch, 
            <pb id="p22-117" n="117"/>
            <figure n="jester.22.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="225">
            	<figTranscr/>
            </figure> 
            very faint, that continues under the text and
            into the left hand margin. The editors construe the isolated portion as “a large
            grinning figure,” but the evidence scarcely supports this construction. A small,
            indeterminate detail from page 64 has been transformed in tracing, and appears in the
            commentary over the title <hi rend="i">Jester with cap and bells.</hi> The tracing adds
            dark shading which makes the figure look more definite than it is, and substitutes a dot
            for a loop, thus creating an “eye.” Presumably the tracings were taken from photographic
            prints; these two might have been checked more carefully against the manuscript.</p>
          <p>As the editors explain in their introduction, the arrangement of the leaves in the
            present binding of the manuscript is the result of editorial judgment, primarily that of
            the poem’s first editors, W. B. Yeats and—especially—Edwin J. Ellis. In this facsimile
            24 leaves have been relocated. The changes affect three areas of the manuscript. First,
            the leaf containing pages 21-22 has been inserted between pages 18 and 19. Second, the
            two Nights VII have been conflated to follow the narrative sequence given in Erdman’s
            <hi rend="i">Complete Poetry and 
            Prose.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref>
            Third, two leaves, pages 113-16, bound at the end of Night VIII have now been inserted
            between pages 104-05. 
            <note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> David V. Erdman, ed., 
            	<hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, 
            	rev. ed. (New York: Anchor Press/Doubleday, 1982).</note></p>
          <p>There are problems here which don’t afflict the editor of a printed text. In more than
            one instance Blake has divided a page of text into portions, and assigned each portion
            to a different location. In a printed text such rearrangements can be accommodated with
            ease. But a manuscript page—and the design that appears on it—can have only one
            location. In such cases <hi rend="i">any</hi> arrangement of the leaves will involve
            some disruption of the text. One answer to this problem is to reproduce the manuscript
            in its existing order, as Bentley does, and note the errors and complications in the
            commentary. But in this facsimile the editors have a special interest in the appearance
            of the manuscript, and in the relationship among the designs.</p>
          <p>Their rearrangement of leaves in Night VIII seems fully justified. The new sequence
            makes good sense of Blake’s instructions on page 104 (calling for the interpolation of
            text from page 113). And it makes equally good sense of the instruction on page 106
            (asking the reader to “turn back 3 leaves” in order to interpolate the second portion of
            text on page 113). There is some disruption for the reader here, but Blake’s
            instructions clearly authorize such disruption, and signal the point of dislocation (the
            two portions of text on page 113 are clearly separated by a line). The arrangement
            places the fascinating visual sequence of three images of Christ (resurrected, page 114;
            crucified, page 115; walking on earth, page 116) at the climax of the Night.</p>
          <p>The other changes involve textual difficulties that seem less easy to resolve. Pages
            19-22 are two added leaves which apparently contain additional material for the end of
            Night I. From the evidence of the narrative sequence the leaves were almost certainly
            bound in reverse order, and by placing 21-22 before 19-20 the editors have rectified the
            error. They assume that these pages follow on from the original ending of Night I on
            page 18, and that Night II begins on page 23. Those readers who (like me) accept Blake’s
            marginal note indicating that Night II begins on page 9, and who think the text on pages
            19-22 may follow 9:33, will still have doubts about the appropriate place of these two
              leaves.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> But few could
doubt that the new
            arrangement is an improvement, and that it produces a readable text. 
                <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> See the textual arrangement of Nights I and II in Stevenson,
W. H.,
              ed., text by David V. Erdman. <hi rend="i">The Poems of William Blake</hi> (London:
              Longman, 1977).</note></p>
          <p>Inevitably, the arrangement of the Night(s) now known as VIIa (pages 77-90) and VIIb
            (pages 91-98) is the most problematic. Blake left clear instructions for the
            transposition of two parts of the <hi rend="i">text</hi> of VIIb, but the instructions
            (unlike those in Night VIII) appear to assume that the reader will encounter the
            manuscript <hi rend="i">leaves</hi> in their untransposed order.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
              type="note">4</ref> If the leaves are transposed, page 95 becomes a problem as it
            contains both the new beginning and the new ending of the Night. Should it appear at the
            beginning or the end? In either position it will contain an isolated fragment of text.
            The editors put it at the beginning of VIIb, thus isolating the new ending. The other
            aspect of the revision, the interpolation of the transposed pages of VIIb between pages
            86 and 87 of VIIa, seems even more problematic. The editors’ justification is the
            assumption that Blake’s narrative is least disrupted if the transposed VIIb is inserted
            into VIIa after 85:22. But the textual evidence on which this assumption rests is
              ambiguous.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> And here
again, the movement of pages
            splinters the text, putting lines 85:23-86:14 before VIIb, whereas in the desired
            textual sequence they follow on from VIIb. The editors claim that “The pictorial
            suitability of this sequence seems clearly to justify” the arrangement. But in their
            detailed comments on the visual designs they offer surprisingly little to substantiate
            the claim. As Blake left no instructions to authorize this interpolation, it may have
            been wiser to reproduce the existing order of the manuscript (VIIa followed by
            untransposed VIIb), and to outline the alternative sequence in the commentary. Perhaps
            one day we shall have a facsimile with loose leaves, <pb id="p22-118" n="118"/>
that
            will allow each reader to make his or her own arrangement of the two Nights VII. 
              <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> A note under the Night heading on page 91 reads “This
              Night begins at line 15 the following comes in at the End.”</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi
                rend="s">5</hi> See the discussion of the textual evidence in 
                <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 12 (1978): 107-39.</note></p>
          <p>The major effort in this facsimile is directed to the interpretation of the
            illustrations. Here the authors have wrestled with a formidable task, for the most
            finished illustrations in the manuscript are the engravings originally designed to
            illuminate a quite different text, Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, while the
            illustrations drawn for Blake’s own poem are often no more than tentative sketches. The
            authors bring to their task an undaunted optimism, an intimate knowledge of the text,
            and a keen sense of the relationships that appear among different elements of Blake’s
            art. They show very clearly that even those drawings that appear to offer simple and
            direct illustration of the narrative can be related subtly to the interplay of dramatic
            perspectives created in the poem. For example, in considering the figure sketched at the
            foot of page 7, which accompanies the description of the “Mingling” of Enion and the
            Spectre of Tharmas, they say: “Insofar as we see this ‘monster’ as a female body, half
            serpent rather than half fish, we attribute the traditional guile and treachery of the
            serpent to Eve herself, as a stage of exorcism. Visibly opposed to the sleeping but
            human spectre on the opposite page, Enion appears to embody the loathed part of himself
            which Tharmas scorns.” The relationship between text and drawings is often far from
            simple or direct, and in such cases the authors’ keen awareness of parallels and
            patterns within the work as a whole can be very helpful. In the text on page 82, for
            example, Los laments his inability to enjoy Enitharmon, while his Spectre woos the
            Shadow of Enitharmon beneath the Tree of Mystery. This is an intensification of error
            that paradoxically results, as the authors note, in a “progression of the imagination.”
            At the foot of the page Blake drew a female figure who holds or turns a circle in which
            eight stars are visible. The design doesn’t provide a direct illustration of the text.
            But the authors relate the wheel to other images within the poem—the Circle of Destiny,
            the “starry wheels” that feel the divine hand in Night IV, the dismal squadrons or
            Urthona that “o’erwheel” at Urizen’s command, the eight eyes of God—and thus tentatively
            suggest its relationship to the idea that forms of error can serve the scheme of divine
            providence.</p>
          <p>The same awareness of relationships that appear between different aspects of Blake’s
            work informs the discussion of the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> proofs used in the
            manuscript. The authors argue that the effect of the proofs on Blake’s text and drawings
            “is usually noticeable, sometimes striking”: 
			<q> Often the design drawn on the page
              facing an engraved scene mirrors or balances it. A body lying with slightly raised
              head is matched by a different body in the same position. A spear or dart in the
              engraving is matched by some weapon in the adjacent drawing. And the text too has its
              reverberations both ways. </q>
The detailed commentary amply justifies this claim, and
            gives a vivid sense of Blake’s working methods. The authors usually consider with
            admirable deftness both the original context in Young’s poem, and the new context in
            Blake’s. On page 45, for example, in which the resurrected Tharmas laments the loss of
            his emanation Enion, Blake uses an engraving of Jesus raising Lazarus. The authors note
            that the design originally illustrated, and transformed, “Young’s argument for the
            unique efficacy of ‘the cross.’ ” Blake changes Young’s “symbolic touching to a direct
            human eye-and-body communication between the despairing Zoa of touch, Tharmas, and an
            instantly ready Saviour.” The inclusion of the engraving here, they suggest, is far from
            arbitrary. Indeed, as the gesture of Lazarus mirrors the drawing of Tharmas on the
            facing page (page 44) Blake “must have planned to use this <hi rend="i">Night
              Thoughts</hi> design” when he made the drawing. Moreover the design hints at the
            conclusion of Blake’s poem: “The text gives no hint of the Saviour’s presence, but both
            lovers take steps that could bring him near. Enion repents, forgetting her ‘sin’ and
            rebellion; Tharmas recoils from his ‘fierce rage’ . . . .” The authors note that the
            same print was used again in Night VII (page 97), in which Tharmas again recalls his
            separation from Enion: “Blake rescues his worthy demon by holding forth the silent
            promise of Christ’s hand.” Such comments throw much light on Blake’s practice in the
            poem, and exemplify the kind of attentiveness demanded by this work.</p>
          <figure n="angel.22.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="276"></figure>
          <p>The authors’ commitment to the close “reading” of Blake’s designs entails a minute
            attention to detail that is consistently revealing. Their clear descriptions repeatedly
            point to the presence of features that might be missed even on close scrutiny, and
            clarify potentially misleading impressions. On page 24, for example, a figure in the
            left-hand margin looks at first (and second) sight to be a phallus. With the aid of the
            commentary 
<pb id="p22-119" n="119"/>
we can see that it is in fact “the torso of a
            female with legs apart but with neither head nor feet.” Such difficulties abound in the
            manuscript, and the authors, building on the work of earlier scholars and frequently
            surpassing it, have clarified many cloudy areas.</p>
          <p>But there are limits to what can be achieved here. It is often extremely difficult, and
            sometimes impossible, to define the image with certainty (is the figure male, female,
            young, old, rising, falling—does the vague configuration constitute a figure at all?).
            The slightest detail <hi rend="i">can</hi> have significance, or might be merely
            incidental, or might even be an illusion created by the unfinished state of the sketch.
            Is the standing figure at the foot of page 12, for example, “sheathed in protective
            clothing from head to foot” with “a round helmet resembling a fencing mask” (as the
            authors suggest), or is the clothing an illusion—simply alternative postures 
<figure n="FencingMan.22.4.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="476"></figure>
            sketched in? The authors argue that the strongest evidence to resolve such uncertainties
            may be in the text. But deciding which part of the text (if any) is relevant is not
            always easy. For example, the authors interpret the drawing at the foot of page 14 in
            the light of an added passage, the song of war sung at the feast of Los and Enitharmon.
            Accordingly the three-headed female is seen as “a united committee of outrage.” The
            authors explain: “All seem agreed on the combat demanded by the outstretched right arm
            with upraised palm.” But if the design is seen in the light of the original copperplate
            text that survives at the top of the page, in which bright souls of vegetative life
            “Stretch their immortal hands to smite the gold &amp; silver Wires,” the female heads
            become singers “soft warbling,” the outstretched hand reaching to “Wires” visible in the
            left hand margin. Similarly, at the foot of page 56 an aged seated man holds by the
            hands or wrists a kneeling youth who stretches towards him. If we interpret this in the
            light of the last passage inscribed on the page (in which “Limit Was put to Eternal
            Death”) we may, like the authors, see the youth as “cheerful.” The commentary explains:
            “Setting a Limit, he balances his energy against the gripe of one who chooses not to
            die, transforming mummy into man.” But conversely, if we see the drawing in the light of
            the lines marked to come in at the end of the inscribed text (lines in which Los “became
            what he beheld”) we may see the youth being pulled reluctantly into the power of Urizen.
            Even where the text appears to offer one clear theme, the visual image may be ambiguous.
            If we agree that the male and female figures at the foot of page 27 in some sense
            illuminate the “bondage of the Human form” referred to in the text, should we see, as
            the authors do, “The body of man . . . dependant on the womb of woman” or should we see
            woman emerging from the rib of man as a captivating presence?</p>
          <p>Faced with such possibilities, definite interpretations and identifications can seem
            oddly reductive, or merely arbitrary. A willingness to remain in uncertainties and
            doubts often seems an appropriate response. The reader who is capable of remaining
            content with half knowledge will at least not confuse definiteness with accuracy. The
            most significant limitation of the commentary is, paradoxically, the authors’
            irrepressible reaching after fact and certainty in the grey areas of the manuscript:
            their attempt to determine the indeterminate. They define the head sketched on pages
            21-22 as that of an <hi rend="i">old</hi> man, but it could be that of a middle-aged man
            or even a young man. They claim that in the “social cluster of naked bodies” sketched
            and partly erased on page 38, Blake is offering an undressed version of the elegantly
            clothed bodies in an illustration (by Thomas Stothard and Anker Smith) of Pope’s 
              <hi rend="i">The Rape of the Lock.</hi> I admire their ingenuity here, but find the
            evidence frail and quite unconvincing. When they say of the cupid on page 112 “He looks
            old; his hair must be a wig,” I feel they must be joking.</p>
          <p>The same readiness to offer boldly decisive judgments in areas where the evidence is
            ambiguous or slight also mars some of the comments on the <hi rend="i">Night
              Thoughts</hi> proofs. The most startling example appears in the comments on page 121,
            whose uncolored design is reproduced in one of the four color plates. The engraving is
            marked by a spotted line of stains. In the commentary 
<pb id="p22-120" n="120"/>
the
            line is related to Blake’s reference on the previous page to “That line of blood that
            stretchd across the windows of the morning.” The authors comment: 
			<q> the bloody line on
              the engraved proof can be seen to mark exactly the moment when one sees or does not
              see the “windows of the morning.” If the line was present in the proof, by accident,
              before Blake wrote on this leaf, it may have inspired his writing. It seems only
              remotely possible that he put it in to illustrate his text. Either way, he was
              redeeming the plate “from Error’s power.” </q>
The caption of the color plate states
            “streak across chest of reclining figure, dull red.” The authors quote in support of
            their interpretation my own description of the stain as “very dark brown dried
            blood/rust colour.” The word “blood” seems to have encouraged a slide from “very dark
            brown” to “bloody” and “dull red.” If the authors had looked carefully at the manuscript
            they would presumably have seen that the stains are not red. There are comparable stains
            on page 117, but these are not mentioned in the commentary. We have no way of knowing
            how the stains appeared—they might conceivably have arrived after the manuscript had
            left Blake’s possession. The authors’ determination to miss no significant detail is
            admirable, but it does not always redeem them “from Error’s power.”</p>
          <p>The commentary does much to dispel the traditional view that the poem evolved through a
            chaotic and arbitrary process of composition. It is therefore regrettable that the
            introduction should lead back to this view by offering a brief history of the manuscript
            based on untested assumptions rather than on a study of particular revisions. In order
            to account for the composite nature of the manuscript the authors imagine Blake “working
            over the text year after year, with increasing doubt that a perfected volume would ever
            be called for.” Accordingly, “as the margins filled up” Blake “resorted to making fair
            copies on fresh sheets,” and “As time passed . . . Blake made revisions with less and
            less attention to any finished appearance.” At this stage “the easiest way to borrow
            designs from the published <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> (and to save paper) was to
            coopt the proofs that survived from that labor.” This account seems to imply that the
            text on the proof pages evolved from a continuous process of revision that overran one,
            or possibly two, previous fair drafts. The surviving evidence makes this seem highly
            unlikely. Where there are marginal revisions in the manuscript the texture of the
            revised narrative is relatively fragmented—more fragmented, for example, than the basic
            text of pages 43-85 (on proof pages), which seems as homogeneous as any part of the
            poem. The authors’ own commentary suggests that Blake was sufficiently concerned about
            the appearance of the manuscript to choose the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> proofs
            with care. The transition from copperplate text to proof text coincides with a major
            transition within the narrative: the breaking of the bounds of destiny, the fall from
            the teleological vision embodied in Urizen’s Golden World into the blind materialism of
            the Caverns of the Grave. Any account of the poem’s development should at least take
            such evidence into consideration. But here the authors do not engage significantly with
            the manuscript evidence at all.</p>
          <p>A project of this complexity will inevitably have weaknesses. But they should be seen
            in the light of the authors’ overall achievement. The writing is crisp and lively, and
            communicates an infectious excitement. When the commentary grapples with the minute
            details of Blake’s drawings, with alternative interpretations, and with the complex
            relationships that appear among the constituent parts of Blake’s work, it provides a
            challenging example of the kind of interpretative exercise that Blake’s illuminated
            writings were surely intended to stimulate. In its attempts to determine the
            indeterminate, to authorize particular readings where the evidence is ambiguous, it will
            inevitably leave many readers dissenting. But the book provides sufficient detail in its
            reproductions, descriptions, and comments to allow readers to form their own judgments.
            It is well indexed, compact enough to be used easily, and—given the quality of its
            reproduction, and the price of other facsimiles—relatively inexpensive. This is a book
            that every library should own, and that every reader of Blake will want to have.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
