<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>22.4.mann</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">Finishing Blake</title>
        <author n="Mann">Paul Mann</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1989</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1989</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">22.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>John A. Hodgson</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>David W. Lindsay</name>
              <name>M. A. L. Locherbie-Cameron</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Peter Otto</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_22">
    <body>
	<pb id="p22-139" n="139"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-22-4-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">DISCUSSIONS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Finishing Blake</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Paul <name>Mann</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Since Peter Otto’s response to the tandem articles written by Robert Essick and myself about
Blake’s possible production plans for <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is not precisely an attack, this will
not be precisely a defense.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">1</ref> I had
proposed that at some stage of his work on <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, Blake toyed more or less seriously
with the idea of publishing the poem in letterpress, in a format rather like the <hi rend="i">Night
Thoughts</hi> edition he did with Edwards. Essick nicely modified this hypothesis by proposing that at some
earlier stage Blake seems to have experimented with producing the entire work in intaglio, then directed the
project toward letterpress with intaglio etched and/or engraved illustrations, then finally suspended
publication plans, though without abandoning work on the
<pb id="p22-140" n="140"/>
manuscript for some time. Otto has no objection to the first two hypothetical working stages; indeed, they
seem hardly to interest him. It is our rather plain and hardly more than descriptive claim that 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> became for Blake “a working manuscript unrelated to any specific production
intentions” (Essick 18:219; see also Mann 18:208) that inspires Otto’s response, or rather his 
<hi rend="i">swerve</hi>, his shift of the discussion to an entirely different level. The course of this swerve
seems to me to exemplify one of the most characteristic moves in Blake studies: the dematerialization of
Blake’s work. <note id="n35"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Paul Mann, “The Final State of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 18 (1985): Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>: Intention
and Method,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 18 (1985): 204-200; Peter Otto, “Final States, Finished Forms, and
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 20 (1987): 144-47.</note></p>
          <p>I should not speak for Essick here, but I will suggest that his extensive studies of Blake’s
production methods and the conditions of Blake’s works provide us with a wealth of materials for a kind of
interpretation that still remains largely unexplored, perhaps even by Essick himself: an interpretation in
which Blake is no longer primarily a poet(-prophet) or inspired illustrator, nor even precisely a composite
artist, as the current compromise has it, but first and foremost someone as committed to working 
<hi rend="i">in</hi> his materials as any sculptor or painter, someone whose work was absolutely identified with
his <hi rend="i">work.</hi> (The analogy here would be with Rodin, were it not otherwise so imprecise.) For
me, the process of seeing <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> as a manuscript in which Blake was not only
investigating poetic and graphic possibilities but also his commitments to different material forms and modes
of publication, was a process of learning to see the work in the work. I have elsewhere called this double
work, this work whose first goal is to manifest and epitomize a kind of work, Blake’s
“production-aesthetic,” a rather clumsy phrase meant to do nothing more than mark his deliberate
insistence on the in-sistence of imaginative labor in concrete materials and methods.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">2</ref> But one need hardly take any of this into consideration to
see the point of our articles: they are quite straightforward attempts to examine the manuscript’s material
conditions and to explore the possibilities for publication that those conditions imply; that is, to grasp the
manuscript precisely <hi rend="i">as</hi> manuscript, as I emphasized at the end of my article. 
<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">2</hi> It is easy to dislike writers who use footnotes to advertise their other works,
but I promised to be brief here and can only do so by glossing this article thus: See my “Apocalypse and
Recuperation: Blake and the Maw of Commerce,” <hi rend="i">ELH</hi> (Spring 1985):1-32; and my “Editing
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Pacific Coast Philology</hi> XVI.1 (1981), which may in fact
anticipate Otto’s argument.</note></p>
          <p>But the situation of the manuscript, of any manuscript, is a loaded critical issue. We inhabit an
age when theories of displacement and supplementarity, for instance, lend a certain cachet to the romantic
fragment or unfinished work. They need no longer be dismissed as failures, as an earlier (by implication:
benighted) age would have done. Our notions of poetic unity are less rigorous, more liberal, if they survive
at all: now we tend to grant a strange integrity to the fragment and distrust the unity of the masterpiece. It
is in this discursive environment that Otto’s defense of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> takes place. His
task is to rescue the manuscript from those mechanistic critics (he rounds up the usual suspects, Frye and
Bentley) for whom the manuscript was the mark of a magnificent, even a tragic failure. So much the better that
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is a work <hi rend="i">about</hi> unfinishedness, that there is a nice analogy
or perhaps even homology between unfinished work and unfinished world. The work’s unfinished state is—what
other word is more fitting than this piece of romantic tradecraft?—<hi rend="i">organic</hi> to its matter,
its theme, its narrative order, its purpose. Otto suspends this argument from a distinction borrowed from
Balachandra Rajan:
<q>
Incomplete poems are poems which ought to be completed. Unfinished poems are poems which ask not to be
finished, which carry within themselves the reasons for arresting or effacing themselves as they do. If an
unfinished poem were to be finished it would ideally erase its own significance.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Otto 144, citing Rajan, <hi rend="i">The Form of the Unfinished: English
Poetics from Spenser to Pound</hi> (Princeton NJ: Princeton UP, 1985) 14.</note></q>
This, for Otto, is the key to the scriptures. <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is no longer a failure, an
unsightly blemish on the beautiful body of Blake’s <hi rend="i">oeuvre</hi>; it is no longer unfinished but,
so to speak (here writing begins to generate properly Janus-like neologisms:) un/finished. “. . . Blake left
his creation myth in an unfinished condition because this was the only form which is appropriate for the
effort of a fallen self to recount the origins, history, and regeneration of the world” (146).</p>
          <p>We are now in a position to chart the swerve. It tends to occur in the spaces between Otto’s
paragraphs. Here he is just finishing his surveillance of Essick’s three-phase hypothesis:
<q>
. . . It is with the status that we ascribe to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> in the third and final stage of
its development that I am concerned.<lb/>
Discussion of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> has been dominated by a strong desire to retrieve the outlines
of a poem (<hi rend="i">Vala</hi>), or potential poem, that lies somewhere behind its pages. This approach
assumes that the present poem represents a “major cultural disaster,” “a tantalizing and tragic
failure,” and that it would be irresponsible to suggest “a reversion to ‘the poem itself.’ ” This
position is supported by the belief that poems should be unified, coherent, and formally complete. It also
draws on the trope that couples incompletion in the present with completion in some other realm. As a result,
the wealth of hypotheses about the possible form of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> in the “first” and
“second” stages of the poem’s development is coupled with a relative unanimity of response to the
third.<lb/>
It seems to me that there are cogent thematic and contextual reasons to entertain the possibility at least
that when Blake finally stopped working on the manuscript he believed that the form taken by the work was the
only one that the subject matter could assume. Or, to phrase this in a less intentionalist idiom: the
(unfinished) form of the work embodies the poem’s insights about the nature of the fallen world and of
fallen perceptions (144).
</q>
And he then goes on to explain why it must stay that way.</p>
          <p>The swerve is actually rather subtle, at least partly because it is entirely tacit. A metaphysics
or poetics of unfinishedness may seem appropriate (in the case of <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> criticism, it is
certainly an improvement), but it also marks an appropriation of the work as “text.” In Otto’s argument
the movement from work to text, from
<pb id="p22-141" n="141"/>
material manuscript to dematerialized “poem” is plotted something like this: consideration of the
manuscript’s material conditions and production “intentions”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n38" type="note">4</ref> are dangerous: they can lead one to confound the unfinished with the failed.
(We did nothing of the kind.) Hence these material considerations must be marginalized or left behind: the
unfinishedness of the manuscript must become the sign of some greater purpose, some deeper (non-)structure,
some truer meaning that can be grasped interpretively. Or rather, first of all, theoretically. Issues of
production must always be read into this theory of unfinishedness; <hi rend="i">any</hi> attention to the
material condition of the manuscript must be contained by the poetics of the unfinished. Now it is
unfinishedness that is the “end of the art”; now the manuscript is complete in its incompleteness. Its
material chaos is rendered quite literally <hi rend="i">ideal.</hi> The urgency with which Otto frames
descriptions and speculations about the material work is exemplary of the persistently text-centered
orientation of Blake studies. <note id="n38"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Essick defines this word more precisely than
Otto: “Given the practical exigencies of image production, as well as Blake’s insistence on the radical
unity of conception and execution, it is reasonable to assume that the preliminary stages in the development
of an image <hi rend="i">may</hi> reveal the medium in which Blake intended to produce the final form of that
image” (216).</note></p>
          <p>What this swerve really entails is a movement from the production of a finally unfinished
manuscript to the production of a <hi rend="i">finished discourse</hi> of unfinishedness. In Otto’s argument
completion must occur <hi rend="i">at some level</hi>—“in some other realm,” as he puts it: a realm that
turns out to be that of criticism. The critical recounting, the representation of unfinishedness as ideal is
meant to rescue the poem-cum-text from its insufficiency, its embarrassing failure. We witness a movement from
interpretation to interpretation, from a narrative of failure to a narrative of success, all taking place
strictly at the level of discourse <hi rend="i">about</hi> the “poem.” What is more, the movement from
failed manuscript to ideally unfinished text must pass through the dematerialization of the manuscript because
there is, in fact, <hi rend="i">no inherent reason</hi> why, if the poem was <hi rend="i">essentially</hi>
unfinished, Blake could not have devised a form for its publication as such. We are faced here with the
crudest instance of the fallacy of imitative form—the sort of instance that makes it a fallacy. There is no
<hi rend="i">necessary</hi> relation, no true marriage between the unfinished text and the unfinished world in
the text: for Otto, the condition of the manuscript is merely an image, an ornament, a suggestion, a formal
hint for a reading that is, at bottom, in no way dependent upon it. In the end, then, the discourse of
unfinishedness <hi rend="i">replaces</hi> the unfinished work: it becomes the ideal form of the poem’s
publication, a solid critical framework on which to hang the manuscript’s rags.</p>
          <p>The transubstantiation of work into text is most evident in the movement from a notion of Blake
working on the manuscript to what Otto calls the “curious fact that the <hi rend="i">narrator</hi> is
himself an ‘effect’ of the <hi rend="i">story</hi> that he recounts” (144, my emphases). Once Otto
replaces artist with narrator and manuscript with story his work is in a sense complete (so is Blake’s); and
the machinery of interpretation can take over. Now “the narrator is . . . contained within his own
[unfinished] poem,” which is contained within a finished and finishing reading of the poem. Otto’s point
is, in one sense, well taken. In order to complete the narration of the fallen world the fallen narrator would
have had to stand outside it, and that is impossible. But what we must mark here is that the “real”
narrator of this ideally unfinished text is the critic. Not Blake but Otto. The issue is one of mediation: in
order for the poem to enter discourse, for there to be any commentary on it at all, <hi rend="i">someone</hi>
must stand “outside” it; an outside must somehow be established, an archimedean fulcrum for levering the
manuscript into Blake studies must be found. There must be some (tacit; or not so tacit: editorial) means for
reproducing the manuscript as text, and critical structures for determining a discourse of unfinishedness.
Someone, in short, must finish it. If the “narrator” cannot ethically or logically or epistemologically
stand outside then the critic will (tacitly) do it for him. Otto’s narrative is generated precisely outside
the fallen textual world which, he argues, one cannot rightly stand outside, in relations that must be the
products of critical discourse itself but must always conceal this mediating agency behind a rhetoric of
unmediated internalization.</p>
          <p>So the “story” of unfinishedness is also the story of dematerialization, which is also the
story of the manuscript’s rematerialization as a narrated narration, a completely unmediated internal world
completely mediated by an external observer. We have read this story before: Blake himself tells it in the
parable of the Ancient Poets, which today we must come to read as one of many Blakean parables of Blake
criticism:
<q>
The ancient Poets animated all sensible objects with Gods or Geniuses, calling them by the names and adorning
them with the properties of woods, rivers, mountains, lakes, cities, nations, and whatever their enlarged
&amp; numerous senses could percieve.<lb/>
And particularly they studied the genius of each city &amp; country, placing it under its mental deity.<lb/>
Till a system was formed, which some took advantage of &amp; enslav’d the vulgar by attempting to realize or
abstract the mental deities from their objects: thus began Priesthood.<lb/>
Choosing forms of worship from poetic tales.<lb/>
And at length they pronouncd that the Gods had ordered such things.<lb/>
Thus men forgot that All deities reside in the human breast<lb/>
(E 38)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">5</hi><hi rend="i"> The Complete Poetry &amp; Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed.
David V. Erdman, newly revised edition (Garden City NY: Anchor Books, 1982).</note></q>
Like Goliath championing David against Goliath.</p>
          <p>It is certainly true that calling <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> a failure was once a trope of
dismissal, but the trope of un/finishedness is hardly a solution to the strange and irreducible
inaccessibility of the manuscript. Indeed, it amounts to about the same thing. Just as earlier readers of 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> tried “to retrieve a . . . potential poem
<pb id="p22-142" n="142"/>
that lies somewhere behind its pages,” so Otto tries to retrieve an ideally unfinished poem from somewhere
behind the manuscript; the difference is that the unfinishedness of earlier critics was “bad” while his is
“good.” There is a certain identity between these earlier critics and Otto: in either case we end up
without the manuscript. But it is precisely the manuscript that is at issue, precisely the manuscript that is
least recuperable by either a metaphysics of unity or a metaphysics of incompletion; it is precisely the
manuscript that <hi rend="i">has never been read.</hi> If the only way to get rid of the notion of failure is
by abandoning the manuscript or recuperating it into some ideal state, then perhaps we must learn to live with
the idea of failure. In fact, at the level of (the) work itself, the failure of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi> might be a lot less troubling than it is out here in critical discourse. Perhaps, for Blake, failure
might not have been so unthinkable a judgment on a work that at one or more stages of development was clearly
intended for publication but never published. What’s so terrible about failure? It might be less of a
problem for a working artist, for whom in a sense nothing can ever be wasted, than it is for a discourse whose
responsibility is always in some part the determination and maintenance of canons. What we have in Otto is one
instance of the general attempt to recuperate that failure so that the poem can exhibit a distinctly literary
<hi rend="i">value.</hi> What we do not yet have is a way to read <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi></p>
          <p>But whose will be the final state-ment?</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
