<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>22.4.grant</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Morris Eaves and Michael Fischer, eds., Romanticism and Contemporary Criticism;
Arden Reed, ed., Romanticism and Language</title>
        <author n="Grant">John E. Grant</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1989</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1989</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">22.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>John A. Hodgson</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>David W. Lindsay</name>
              <name>M. A. L. Locherbie-Cameron</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Peter Otto</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_22">
    <body>
	<pb id="p22-124" n="124"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-22-4-0005">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Morris Eaves and Michael Fischer, eds. <hi rend="i">Romanticism and
Contemporary Criticism.</hi> Ithaca: Cornell University Press, 1986. 246 pp. $29.96 cloth/paper $8.95.</title>
            <title type="main">Arden Reed, ed. <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Language.</hi> Ithaca: Cornell
University Press, 1984. $38.50 cloth/paper $12.95.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">John E.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Grant</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>These two collections of essays often show how the deconstructionist movement in criticism, with
its program of dissipating poetry into “language,” effects a rollback of revolutionary romanticism.
Despite the revolutionary ambitions of individual theoreticians, the movement they have generated, like many
other successful sociological or ideological movements, produces effects opposite from those intended. In
overturning “the authority of the text,” the deconstructive machine has given us the monopoly of the
indefinite. Since some of the ideas held up in these volumes as being particularly illuminating derive from
errors of earlier critics, it is evident that would-be devils are only angels of the most recent heaven.
Critics of the “language” school wander into crucial misconstruals, intermingled with valuable new
perceptions, because they are preoccupied with <hi rend="i">words</hi> rather than poems, and thus have no
structure of reference for distinguishing among endlessly proliferating meanings.</p>
          <p>Moreover, any sense of the work conveyed by the text, if ascertainable at all, is assumed to be
less important than what it may signify for a modern reader who usually has some point of view very different
from that of the author. Maureen Quilligan has accounted for this mind-set as follows:
<q>
In Marxist theory, as well as in all strong modern theories of interpretation, the assumption necessarily is
that the text does not, at the surface level, want said what the critic finds in it to say. The critic, by his
or her interpretation, brings to light what was repressed from the text’s surface.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi rend="i"> Milton’s Spenser: The Politics of Reading</hi> (Ithaca:
Cornell UP, 1983) 29.</note></q>
<pb id="p22-125" n="125"/>
<figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
<figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
In an interesting elaboration of this point, Edward Pechter finds the motive for this critical strategy in the
will to power.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">2</ref> It has often been
remarked that Humpty Dumpty expressed this mentality in his credo: “the question is . . . which is to be
master—that’s all.” <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">2</hi> “The New Historicism and its Discontents:
Politicizing Renaissance Drama,” <hi rend="i">PMLA</hi> 102 (1987): 299.</note></p>
          <p>But even readers not so zealous to keep ahead of the text have been indoctrinated to expect that
the surface meaning is superficial or more or less duplicitous, not to be believed, and in any case not
something the author understood well enough to bind the modern reader to the ancient author’s delights or
despairs. What seems to count is whatever can be attributed to the psychological or (more currently) the
political unconsciousness of the author. It is a dimension of significance of which the author was necessarily
unaware. Even the unaggressive reader will become preoccupied with something the author failed to say.
Proponents of “weak” theories are hardly less affected by such assumptions than proponents of “strong”
theories. Many good citizens in the teaching profession now feel that they are morally obligated to expound
what the text does not say. If all or even most texts are indeterminate, and if all students deserve
warm encouragement in their interpretations, then randomness in one’s own exposition, together with a
receptivity to any forceful comment (except that of the poet), is the mark of having the right attitude of
openness. Believers in either “strong” theories or “weak” theories can thus hardly concede any
interest to “strong” <hi rend="i">poems</hi> that exhibit determinate form as an essential part of their
mode of existence. While some aspects of a strong poem may be held up for display purposes, the things that
are said about such poems often grow out of some frame of reference having little to do with that in which the
poem was written. On the other hand, libertarians among post-structuralists object that any specifically
acknowledged “frame of reference” is arbitrary if not authoritarian. They do not consider that, as in the
display of pictures, a frame may serve to feature and focus, not constrict.</p>
          <p>Out of the fifteen essays in the two volumes, the only piece primarily concerned with Blake’s
work occurs in <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Contemporary Criticism</hi>: “Visible Language: Blake’s
Wond’rous Art of Writing,” an attempt of the brilliant and resourceful W. J. T. Mitchell
<pb id="p22-126" n="126"/>
to correlate Blake and Derrida. Although Mitchell suggests that “one could think of this as an essay written
about and ‘for’ Blake and ‘against’ Derrida (48), the reader is often presented with an uncriticized
Derridean kind of mischief that goes dead against what Blake was aiming to say or show, as will be pointed out
later in this review.</p>
          <p>The essays in Arden Reed’s collection, <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Language</hi>, attempt
deconstructive applications of the generalities of the title to well-known romantic poems. But because such
generalities offer amorphous vantage points, most of these essays are peppered with random observations or
reflections indicating that the authors have little conception of or interest in poems as poems. They tend to
read words of poems in ways that slip in and out of focus because they have no consistent awareness of the
identity the words take on as parts of particular poems. These authors defer repeatedly to de Man, one of
whose ponderous pronouncements about the indeterminability of “language” is used as one of two epigraphs
for the volume. The other epigraph, from the opening of Frye’s energetic 1963 English Institute essay, on
the vanity of romanticizing, expresses a preference for “actual literary experience,” such as can seldom
motivate critics, however gifted, who have joined the entourage of de Man. They operate under the
presupposition that a poem is a formless construct, a notion that had considerable currency long before
deconstruction was named. As Olson and later Hirsch pointed out, on the first page of <hi rend="i">Seven Types
of Ambiguity</hi> Empson identifies his concern as being the ambiguities in “a piece of language.” Empson
made free to remark on anything that interested him, but such maneuverings within the ill-delineated area of
“language” cannot be revealing about actual poems unless a critic possesses a rare Empsonian ingenuity and
resilience that makes him or her entertaining even when wrong. Critics with more limited resources are unable
to recoup the losses sure to be experienced when cavorting somewhere between “the great dictionary,”
tenuous etymologies, and great poems. Lest it be supposed that Empson’s way with “language” has no
bearing on deconstructionism, it should be noticed that J. Hillis Miller, in <hi rend="i">Romanticism and
Contemporary Criticism</hi>, declares Empson to be at least one of the “great uncles” of the movement.</p>
          <p>Though not all the essays in <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Language</hi> are opaque, anyone who
sits down to read several of them through will experience the same response Rosemary Ashton reported in 
<hi rend="i">TLS</hi>, 5 July 1985: “I felt distinctly dizzy as I temporarily inhabited the Babel which this
collection of essays seems to celebrate.” Part of the cause of this vertigo may be that even those
contributors who can write well often lack a sense of the varied occasions that prompted words which, in
themselves, have similar purport. The first essay, Susan Wolfson’s “The Language of Interpretation in
Romantic Poetry: ‘A Strong Working of the Mind,’ ” for instance, fails to distinguish the boundaries of
particular poems. Wolfson gets off the mark by eliding a passage in Blake’s letter to Trusler on “what is
not too Explicit” with Keats’s words about “uncertainties, Mysteries, doubts,” (22) as though Keats
had sought to advocate such troubles. Later, as part of a nine-page discussion of the gloss of the 
<hi rend="i">The Rime of the Ancient Mariner</hi>, she quotes from Mellor’s <hi rend="i">English Romantic
Irony</hi> a comment on the fact that the gloss (when added) “ ‘is printed in the outside margin and would
thus normally be read before the text of left-hand pages, after the text of right-hand pages,’ yielding ‘a
visual emblem’ of Coleridge’s ambivalence.” Such factors are alleged by Wolfson to present “an
explicit figure for the ultimate uncertainty of interpretation” (31). Each layer of these comments contains
nothing more significant than the mystification of a convention—as if one were to argue that we are given
access to the Spanish soul because the question marks are upside down. Thus students who don’t understand
eighteenth-century conventions of capitalization are led to discover Jesus and Mary in the “Youth” and
“Virgin” in Blake’s “Ah! Sun-Flower.” So far as Coleridge’s “ambivalence” is concerned, the
text-and-gloss simply constitutes a talking point for what is abundantly obvious on other grounds, rather than
being an unconscious betrayal of Coleridge’s divided consciousness.</p>
          <p>Wolfson also fails to recognize the closure of Coleridge’s poem, stating that the “poem
leaves open to question whether the newly haunted listener might himself become a haunted purveyor of the
Rime’s repetitive life . . .” (30), and designating the poem, from the point of view of Coleridge as
author, an intolerably “inconclusive tale” (31). But in Coleridge’s favorite play, 
<hi rend="i">Hamlet</hi>, when Horatio is exhorted by the dying prince to tell his tale through this harsh world,
no one worries overmuch about whether he did as he was bid. Even if some sequel were punctuated with
retellings of the tragedy of Hamlet, and that of the Ancient Mariner too, the tale would not be
Shakespeare’s or Coleridge’s complete but open-ended stories, but the reader’s, or Tom Stoppard’s.
Both <hi rend="i">Hamlet</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Rime</hi> have a form, which means that they are not
interminable, nor did Coleridge fail to give the reader a sufficient conclusion when the Wedding Guest arises
“a sadder and a wiser man.”</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Romanticism and Language</hi> contains another extended essay on “The Rime of the
Ancient Mariner,” a reprinted piece by the editor, Arden Reed. Reed makes a wide sweep through Coleridge’s
use of the word “rime,” usually in the sense of frost, and manages to relate most occurrences to the
primary sense of “Rime.”
<pb id="p22-127" n="127"/>
But Reed’s credibility is much diminished by his insistence that the Ancient Mariner sees himself among, and
blesses himself along with, the water snakes (190). Reed’s concluding declaration that the 
<hi rend="i">Rime</hi> counters “the current of Romantic literature” to “privilege speech,” thereby
somehow “Subvert[ing] the ideology of the very movement it is always taken to exemplify—which may be what
makes it a genuine Romantic poem” also depends on Derridean prestigitation to say everything and nothing at
the same time. Such a maneuver seems particularly unfortunate since Reed can be very acute. He has a rare
ability to see through ingrained interpretive errors, such as the assertions of Warren, Beer, Chayes, and
others that the crew condemned the shooting of the albatross at a time when the ship was becalmed, although
Coleridge plainly states that “the good south wind still blew behind.”</p>
          <p>Six of the other essays in <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Language</hi>, those on Wordsworth or
Coleridge by Chase, Bahti, Parker, and Christensen, on Shelley by Ferguson, and on romantic prose by Jacobus,
all become entangled in their own exposition. Despite the subtle critical intelligence that Ferguson brings to
bear on “Mont Blanc,” she utterly mistakes the tone: “although <hi rend="i">Mont Blanc</hi> is a sublime
poem upon a sublime subject, it projects an air of sociability” (208). And she is bound down by the
implications of an inapposite and mistaken allusion: “just as Milton’s Eve was once ‘stupidly good,’
so matter is, in Shelley’s account, ‘stupidly powerful,’ and powerful more because of its stupidity than
in spite of it” (211-12). But it is Satan in prospect of Eve, of course, who is “stupidly good” 
(<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> 9.465)—imagined so because he had previously been so resourceful. This phrase
has no bearing on Mont Blanc, whose powerful and abiding identity is unchanging. From a human point of
view—Shelley’s—the wonder inspired by the mountain has nothing to do with its having any quasi-human
capacity to be either clever or stupid. Ferguson certainly knows this, but she became ensnared in the web of
language and thus fell into comments that have no validity.</p>
          <p>The last two pieces in <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Language</hi> are more successful: Brisman on
“Swinburne and the Language of Shelleyan Love” and Macksey on Keats’s “To Autumn.” Brisman adroitly
expounds a passage of Swinburnean lesbian sadism, and Macksey, despite some local errors, keeps Keats’s poem
clearly in view. Unlike most recent commentators, Macksey does not maintain that the foreshadowing of winter
and death at the end of the poem is the main point. Under the influence of de Man, Macksey does wander from
the spirit of Keats in representing the poet as a self-declared “child,” quoting the letter of 14-31
October 1818: “I give in to their feelings as though I were refraining from irritating a little child”
(275). It is disappointing to have to point out that Keats is representing his friends, not himself, as an
irritable child.</p>
          <p>Most of the essays in <hi rend="i">Romanticism and Contemporary Criticism</hi> were delivered as
papers in 1984-85, at the last moment in American literary studies when an acknowledgement of the New
Historicism could have been avoided. One essay, J. Hillis Miller’s “On Edge: The Crossways of Contemporary
Criticism,” which first appeared in 1979, contains a classic deconstructive exposition of “A Slumber Did
My Spirit Seal” and is reissued in this volume because it provoked M. H. Abrams’s “Construing and
Deconstructing,” which contains a fuller discussion of the poem and a critique of the premises of Miller’s
procedures. In response, Miller offers “Postscript: 1984,” in which he holds out for his 1979
interpretation, with perhaps slight modifications, against many pages of reasoned critique by Abrams; then, on
the basis of a deconstructive maneuver, he declares either that he has triumphed or that he is sure to, at
least among judicious readers. There is no hint of the shift expressed in his 1986 MLA presidential address,
entitled “The Triumph of Theory, the Resistance to Reading, and the Question of the Material
Base,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8" type="note">3</ref> in which he attempted to
persuade the audience that Derrida and de Man have always been Marxist at heart, while at the same time
constructing an invisible bridge that can carry him over to the latest concern. One of the best features of
the volume is its preservation of the lively question-and-answer sessions following the presentations by
Miller, Abrams, and the other symposiasts, Frye, Mitchell, and Cavell. In them the essayists—challenged by
an acute and well-informed audience—refined their positions and often achieved greater clarity than in the
papers themselves. <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">3</hi><hi rend="i"> PMLA</hi> 102 (1987): 281-91.</note></p>
          <p>Although Mitchell does not claim to have done historicist work in his essay, a paper that
exhibits a style of thinking common in advanced writing of the 1980s, he takes in some historicist
considerations in discussing Blake’s relation to printing. And in the discussion session, he alludes to
Burke, Said, and Williams, concluding with a paragraph in which he appears to say that he may soon go into
serious Marxism, while, however, continuing in the playful Derridean manner.</p>
          <p>Mitchell’s main interests are apparent in his extensive discussion of Blake’s scene of
writing, in connection with an interpretation of the tailpiece design for the “Proverbs of Hell” 
(<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, plate 10). Here the Devil acts as an interpreter for a writer
while another person who holds a poised writing implement looks over toward the other two figures. In his
professedly Derridean manner, but with no sign of ironic reservation, Mitchell argues that what we should see
in this design is a new kind of imposition in which witless scribes (the one at left being less alert than the
<pb id="p22-128" n="128"/>
one at right) are accepting the Devil’s dubious dictation of infernal graffiti, which are either stale in
themselves, because they are unoriginal and ubiquitous down there, or are rendered ineffectual by the
Devil’s commentary. In a more involuted argument Mitchell further declares that the figures in Blake’s
picture are blasphemously derived from the Prophets, Sybils, and Nudes (“angels”) in Michelangelo’s
Sistine Ceiling—as expounded by the late Edgar Wind. This Michelangelesque standard is supposed to show
Blake’s viewer that an unreliable encounter with texts is going on. In the end, according to Mitchell, the
infernal way of reading and transmitting texts delivers nothing that is really better than the orthodox way.
Ironically, though unobserved by Mitchell, such a view turns out to be quite compatible with major
pre-deconstructionist interpretations of Erdman and Keynes: that some things in the picture are indeed
supposed to be wrong, and that they reflect discredit on the foregoing “Proverbs of Hell.” Evidently this
history “has been adopted by both parties.” But Blake for one does not agree.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> is the first work of English literature written
consciously and deliberately from the point of view of the Devil’s Party. It is a satire, not merely a
polemic, and thus contains features that complicate or qualify its words and pictures. But this illuminated
book contains no invitation to the reader to adopt an adversarial point of view, angelic or other (if that is
possible), toward the scenes, sayings, or stories in it. Blake undoubtedly expected that readers would
initially resist the infernal point of view, but he indicates that angelic temperaments, be they as involuted
as Swedenborg’s, can only invent mountains, never remove them. A heaven, so long as it is new, is built on
“what was stolen from the abyss”: energy. The imposture that makes a heaven old is a priestly, angelic
fabrication, not the Devil’s doing—as the Devil is envisioned by the narrator of the 
<hi rend="i">Marriage.</hi> Plate 3 announces that “the Eternal Hell revives.” Any reader who immediately
thereafter seeks for signs that hell is expiring even before things get heated up must be of the Angels’
party without knowing it.</p>
          <p>The crucial considerations in plate 10 are these: Since the design comes immediately after the
Proverbs, the scribe at the viewer’s left must represent the narrator who collected the Proverbs, and the
figure at the viewer’s right must represent the illustrator. The scroll that must contain the Proverbs of
Hell appears to issue (in almost all copies) from under the robe of the narrator-scribe and then to receive
appropriate reinforcement from the revolutionary Devil, who has descended from his seat of authority in his
eager commitment to point out a text, such as the penultimate proverb: “Truth can never be told so as to be
understood and not be believ’d.” Skeptics who find solace in Blake’s doctrine of contraries, which can
be enlisted to support the rational premise that any extreme formulation should be counterbalanced by some
moderate alternative, would have to search hard to discover a Proverb of Heaven to counteract that piece of
infernal wisdom.</p>
          <p>The figure at the viewer’s right, probably female, shows by her familiar cross-legged position,
with drawing sheet spread across her lap, that she must be an artist rather than another scribe. She eagerly
awaits the space on the scroll after the end of the proverbs where the tailpiece to the Proverbs of Hell
should appear, at the conclusion of the second main section of the <hi rend="i">Marriage.</hi> Indeed, the
picture we see on the page of the codex book before us is the design she will have created. This figure can
hardly be construed (despite the arguments of Erdman, Keynes, and Mitchell) as a second “scribe,” one who
is quicker than her dull-witted counterpart on the left, for then she would have no function except as a
producer of extra copy. The seventy Proverbs of Hell, as a text, are completed and concluded with “Enough!
or Too much,” a final flourish that calls for no revisions or afterthoughts, especially those of the sort
produced by “mechanical talents” so heavily ridiculed by the narrator on plate 22. But the addition of a
pictorial tailpiece is an appropriate conclusion for the words of revolutionary art, involving no pointless
supererogation.</p>
          <p>The pictorial contrary of the design on plate 10 of the <hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> is the title
page of <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>, which is also discussed by Mitchell, though not in relationship
to the <hi rend="i">Marriage.</hi> The title page of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, like plate 10 of 
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, depicts a scribe and both writing and artistic implements—but all misused. This
scene of priestly imposition and obfuscation deserves all the opprobrium it has received from commentators,
not least because Urizen tries to practice all the arts himself, and bungles them. They are beyond his powers
because he also aspires to statecraft and moral authority and lacks the energy of imagination. Although Blake
himself did have the necessary energy to excel in both verbal and visual arts, he chose in the 
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi>, plate 10, to represent the liberty of creation and interpretation as a collective
achievement, dependent upon the energetic guidance of the only infernal being actually depicted in the major
pictures of the <hi rend="i">Marriage.</hi></p>
          <p>As part of his general exposition of the concept of “visible language,” with particular
reference to Blake’s position in the eighteenth-century debate between the conservative-oral tradition of
Burke and the democratic-textual innovations of Paine, Mitchell discusses images of writing in two familiar
works by Blake. First he maintains that an alleged “sinister” nuance in the “Introduction” to 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> is a commonplace; then he argues, possibly whimsically, that Urizen is supposed to be
an ideologue of the left rather than the right.</p>
          <pb id="p22-129" n="129"/>
          <p>Mitchell declares that “Blake’s encomia on writing are frequently ‘stained’ by irony,”
(55) but, while admitting the obvious celebratory view of writing in “Introduction” to 
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, he judges that “no critical reader of this poem . . . has been able to avoid the
ironic undertones.” The moment of writing is also the moment when the inspired child vanishes:
<q>
the hollow reed and the stained water suggest that a kind of emptiness, darkness and loss of innocence
accompanies the very attempt to spread the message of innocence. What makes this a song of 
<hi rend="i">innocence</hi>, then, is the speaker’s unawareness of these sinister connotations. Indeed, we might
say that the most literal version of this innocence is the speaker’s blithe assumption that the mere act of
writing is equivalent to publication and a universally appreciative readership, a bit of wish-fullfillment
that every writer will recognize. The piper . . . is unaware of both the problems and the possibilities of
print culture. . . . (55-56)
</q></p>
          <p>In fact, despite Mitchell’s pronouncement about the “ironic undertones” and “sinister
connotations” of staining the water that must occur to any “critical reader,” very few who have written
well on Blake have thought to express such misgivings. Those hinted at by Gleckner and Hirsch, and expounded
by one or two others, were disposed of by Adams in 1963 and Holloway in 1968. Such suspicions were revived by
Edward Said in 1975, who proposed the curious argument that the piper is so inept as to try to use the water
as paper.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9" type="note">4</ref> This unfortunate
misconstrual was eventually identified and neutralized by Lawrence Lipking.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">5</ref> The only “critical reader” who seems to have reached
conclusions about “stain’d” similar to those of Mitchell and who has gone unanswered is Heather Glen in
1983.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">6</ref> Her brand of politicized
iron-izing may well have seemed plausible to Mitchell, though he does not mention her work. 
<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">4</hi><hi rend="i"> Beginnings: Intention and Method.</hi> (New York: Basic Books, 1975) 227; the
passage occurs on pages 205-6 of the Columbia UP, 1985 reprint.</note>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">5</hi> “Life, Death, and Other Theories,” <hi rend="i">Historical Studies and
Literary Criticism</hi>, ed. Jerome J. McGann (U of Wisconsin P, 1985) 190-91.</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> Vision and Disenchantment: Blake’s Songs &amp;
Wordsworth’s Lyrical Ballads</hi> (Cambridge UP, 1983) 66-99.</note></p>
          <p>So far as Mitchell’s own attempts to identify something “sinister” in “Introduction” to
<hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> are concerned, the source of his difficulties appear to be with the word
“stain’d.” Why the senses of this word sometimes connected elsewhere by Blake with “sin” should
distract the reader of this poem would be hard to explain except on the basis of loose deconstructionist
“language” theories. As Adams pointed out, Blake’s use of “stained” in the first line of his “To
Autumn” ought to be enough to vindicate it; Keats’s use of the word in the second stanza of “Ode to a
Nightingale” offers further reassurance for those not determined to be bloodyminded. As most commentators
remind us, “stained” refers to the making of ink and perhaps to watercolors. Had the verse permitted,
Blake might have written “tinted” or “colour’d” without appreciable change in meaning.</p>
          <p>What, then, shall the “sinister” residue alleged in “stain’d” be called? A smidgen? A
trace? For the reader of Blake’s poem it is insignificant: nothing worth theorizing about.</p>
          <p>Mitchell’s criticism has often been animated by a streak of antitheticalism and a Derridean
alacrity in discovering some deep counter-signification that underlies or subverts the ostensible sense of a
picture or poem. Not entirely unexpected then is his project in this essay to show how often Blake and Derrida
are compatible. Despite my misgivings about this project, suspecting that Blake is at most as compatible with
Derrida as he is with Voltaire and Rousseau, I attempted to suspend disbelief because I believe that Mitchell
is a learned Blakean and has a powerful imagination. But the argument Mitchell puts up about the 
<hi rend="i">Book of Urizen</hi> (56-59), including a full-page reproduction of Morgan Copy B of the title page,
is demonstrably wrong.</p>
          <p>The old bearded often-blind scribe squatting among books on the title page of 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> is conjectured by Mitchell to represent either “a self-portrait of the artist as a
solitary reader” (58) or “a utopian revolutionary reformer” (59) like Rousseau or Condorcet. Since
Urizen is shown deploying implements of artistic production, one might say that Urizen prompts the reader to
think of Blake the artist, who unquestionably “printed” the illuminated book. If Blake were known to have
affected a Whitmanian beard when he lived in Lambeth, one might think there could be more to the notion. The
best evidence that Mitchell can offer for his thesis that Urizen is “a utopian revolutionary reformer,” is
to argue that Blake had a distaste for rationalism of any stripe, left or right, and that the notorious
rationalists of the time were on the left. This, together with his activities as a mover and shaker is
supposed to identify Urizen as a revolutionist! Mitchell does concede that “Urizen is no doubt sometimes
employed as a figure of English reaction in the late 1790s” (58).</p>
          <p>It is not easy to see how this solecism in defense of a paradoxical argument could have gone
uncorrected, but a review of the facts will, of course, remind us that Urizen was not employed on 
<hi rend="i">any</hi> newly published projects “in the late 1790s” and his <hi rend="i">entire</hi> career
prior to the appearance of <hi rend="i">The First Book of Urizen</hi> in 1794 <hi rend="i">was</hi> as “a
figure of English reaction”: Urizen was first named in <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>
and was again named and first appeared in <hi rend="i">America</hi>, both dated 1793, and in those works
unmistakably functions as the patron of reaction.</p>
          <p>Such considerations would suggest that Mitchell simply made several careless mistakes though it
is always conceivable that a critic in a Derridean manner assumed by Mitchell might still attempt to salvage
some new adventures for Urizen in “the late 1790s.” There is, to be sure, the manuscript of 
<hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, on which Blake may have been working, and even “Death” in the designs for Young’s
<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, who looks like Urizen—though he is never called “Urizen” and is not
consistently
<pb id="p22-130" n="130"/>
political on one side of the question or the other. The last expedient for discovering Urizen in “the late
1790s” (apart, that is, from <corr type="emend">cummings’</corr> “mr u”) would be to appeal to 
<hi rend="i">A Small Book of Designs</hi>, a copy of which contained a color print of the title page of 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> redated “1796” (Butlin Cat 261.1). Perhaps Blake’s inscription, added to this
print, can stand as the last word on the matter: “Which is the Way / The Right or the Left.”</p>
          <p>The interaction between J. Hillis Miller and M. H. Abrams during their rematch anent
Wordsworth’s “A Slumber Did My Spirit Seal” is probably the most interesting feature in 
<hi rend="i">Romanticism and Contemporary Criticism</hi> even though these old antagonists did not actually
confront one another in Albuquerque. A 1979 essay by Miller, “On Edge: The Crossways of Contemporary
Criticism” evidently led Abrams to respond with an essay entitled “Construing and Deconstructing.” Of
Miller’s original fifteen pages, well over half are primarily addressed to perceived problems in and about
Wordsworth’s eight-line poem. In Abrams’s response some fifteen pages are focused on the poem and what
Miller made of it. In “Postscript: 1984” Miller responds unrepentantly in seven pages to Abrams’s
critique and Abrams added a few pages to his previous comments in his question and answer session. Anyone who
had imagined that most of the issues concerning “A Slumber” must have been at least sighted by Bateson and
Brooks in their venerable disagreement about the poem, which was so notably reported by Hirsch, is likely to
be amazed that Miller and Abrams found so much more to say. Yet once one gets thinking about it, various other
reflections arise that none of these champions chose to discuss. I doubt whether, however prompted, anyone
else would ever have come up with the hypothetical dilemma proposed by Knapp and Michaels in their well-known
1982 piece entitled “Against Theory”: the problem of interpreting the poem if it had somehow been written
by waves on the seashore.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">7</ref> Meanwhile
Miller had gone farther out and got in deeper. <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Steven Knapp and Walter Benn
Michaels, “Against Theory,” <hi rend="i">Against Theory</hi>, ed. W. J. T. Mitchell (Chicago: Chicago UP,
1985): 15-16. My point here is that these authors deliberately conceived of a far-fetched set of circumstances
in which Wordsworth’s poem might conceivably appear in order to illustrate a theoretical point about how it
would be transformed thereby. There is nothing wrong with entertaining thoughts about such an hypothetical
situation even though it would never occur to any reader trying to construe the poem. In thus employing the
term “construe” to express a basic aim of interpretation I am following Abrams, who argues persuasively
for the rehabilitation of this venerable standard for criticism. The Knapp-Michaels discussion about
Wordsworth’s poem, on the other hand, does not pretend to be a construal and thus differs from erroneous or
preposterous interpretations, which do.</note></p>
          <p>What Miller presents is an exercise in unbounded association round about the language used in
Wordsworth’s poem. Like most readers, Miller mentions “Lucy” (though of course she is not named in this
poem) but unlike any previous reader, he particularly associates the dead person with Wordsworth’s
parents—not only his mother, who died in 1778, but also his father, who died in 1783—as well as with more
familiar figures such as Dorothy (106). Soon this biographical association leads Miller into such assertions
as:
<q>
“The speaker of the poem rather than being the opposite of Lucy, male to her female, adult knowledge to her
prepubertal innocence, is the displaced representative of both the penetrated and the penetrator, of both Lucy
herself and of her unravishing ravisher, nature or death. The speaker was ‘sealed,’ as she was. Now he
knows. . . . Lucy is both the virgin child and the missing mother, that mother earth that gave birth to the
speaker and has abandoned him. . . . The poet himself somehow caused Lucy’s death by thinking about it.
Thinking recapitulates in reverse mirror image the action of the earthly years in touching, penetrating,
possessing, killing, encompassing, turning the other into oneself and therefore being left only with a corpse,
an empty sign. . . .” (108)
</q>
Miller goes on to archetypal analogies (not described as such, of course): the parents are the sun and moon as
somehow (with the aid of a phrase from Stevens) implied in the name “Lucy,” that is, “light” (109).
There is even anagogy: Lucy is the Logos. Presumably the only reason for excluding the Lucys of Dante and
Donne is that their colorations were not markedly Freudian.</p>
          <p>Abrams offers a summary, but doesn’t attempt to reason with the author. Earlier Miller had gone
into the metaphysics of the word “thing”, not (of course) as an English word, but as a topic to be
elucidated by references to Heidegger and Plato (104-5). Abrams did remind us that the girl in the English
folksong “Charming Billy” is also repeatedly referred to as “a young thing” and indicates that this
might bring us closer to the poem as written (152-53). It is true that the word “thing,” especially as
applied to women or children, has a rich presence in nineteenth century writing; I have recently noted cases
in Blake, Austen, Keats, Dickens, Eliot, and Gilbert, any of which might seem more interesting in relation to
Wordsworth than Heidegger’s usage. Perhaps we could get a more useful grip on “thing” by noticing how
Coleridge used it—of himself—in “Work Without Hope.”</p>
          <p>But as Abrams points out, Miller and his school take as their purview “the Western tradition
generally” and thus “cut themselves free from the limitations of construing the poem as a specific lyric
<hi rend="i">parole.</hi>” (153) Thus, though you can find places where Miller seems to have paid attention
to such basic structural features of the poem as the relation between before and after in the two stanzas, in
the long run he doesn’t care at all for them. He proposes as a paradox that a poem may not have “organic
form at all”; but he means that if he discusses a poem at any length it will be to show that it doesn’t.
Thus he can probably in good conscience declare that those parts of his discourse which Abrams could commend
as making some sense as the observations of a good reader were ironically intended, modest
proposals—something, indeed, like the bone of sense T. S. Eliot’s poetical burglar throws to the watchdog.
I think this is a sincere rather than honest account of what prompted Miller’s 1979 expatiation round
Wordsworth’s poem, for his notions of a wirey bounding line are so indefinite that he could not rule out any
comments, even commonsensical or plausible ones.</p>
          <p>Such a strategy of excess overwhelms any poem, particularly a little one, that has a distinct
formal structure but the consolation is that one may, unlike “the
<pb id="p22-131" n="131"/>
fond maniac” in <hi rend="i">The Prelude</hi>, regard such a work as a shell that will not be damaged by the
deluge, however formidable and glittering it appears. The poem will eventually surface again, insufficiently
elucidated, after the flood of “language” has receded. At that point readers will again see the point that
Wordsworth’s long-dead parents could have left no ascertainable mark on “A Slumber Did My Spirit Seal”
even if William Wordsworth never got over his bereavement—<corr type="emend">conjecturally,</corr> that is,
since there is no evidence to support this theory or that it was ever mixed up in the Lucy complex.</p>
          <p>At times Miller hints at underlying scenarios according to which the male speaker in “A
Slumber” is expressing or betraying sexist attitudes toward the dead woman in the poem. Those interested in
the poem as a determinant form must object that nothing in the words of the poem requires that the speaker be
male; the poem could as well be articulated by a woman who had, recently, been bereft of another woman. It is
necessary to maintain the specification <hi rend="i">recently</hi>, however, because, though some people have
been known to have mourned longer than Queen Victoria, the word “now” in the poem insists that the special
facts or qualities in question, whatever they may be, have finally (and recently) sunk into the consciousness
of the bereft speaker.</p>
          <p>Though I would maintain that Miller’s persistent appellation of Wordsworth’s poem as a
“piece of language” and even as a linguistic “emergency” (e.g., 116) to justify his desperate critical
measures is more likely to lose the patient-poem than to save it, there are peculiar verbal factors within
Wordsworth’s eight lines that may not have been encompassed either by his maneuvers or by Abrams’s (see
115). It is indeed odd that Wordsworth should write of the slumber of a spirit, which is moreover, sealed. For
Miller this is just an obvious case of the ultimate incomprehensibility of all poetry; for Abrams a special
case quite different from most poetry. Interestingly, however, Miller paid no attention to the proposal as
regards “spirit,” which Abrams reports from Hugh Sykes Davies, to the effect that “ ‘she’ in the
third line refers back to ‘spirit’ in the first” (145), thus producing a poem “about a trance-state of
the speaker’s own spirit.” This line of inference, which was first proposed in print (I believe) by Robin
Skelton a decade before Davies’s better-reasoned discussion, is adjudged by Abrams as “not impossible, but
extremely unlikely.” It is, however, quite different in kind from Miller’s expatiations in a verbal
universe and probably more worthy of critical regard. In a way Davies was even more concerned with poetic
integrity than Abrams or any expounder of “organic form,” which Miller so deeply distrusts. One
unconsidered reason that the Skelton-Davies theory that “she” is “my spirit” has considerable
plausibility is that it makes most sense when “A Slumber” is read apart from the (other) “Lucy” poems,
as it often is represented in selections of just a few of Wordsworth’s poems—and as it was in all the
poetry collections published in Wordsworth’s own lifetime. Thus it is that good students, who have heard
nothing of the Skelton-Davies theory (why should they?) will sometimes spontaneously discover the spirit-she
correlation that the poem itself certainly permits.</p>
          <p>The critical performance of Stanley Cavell entitled “In Quest of the Ordinary: Texts of
Recovery” is stylistically the most peculiar in either volume. It seems as though Cavell’s aim as a
thinker is to carry on past Kant and provide a critique of skepticism:
<q>
“My thought is that if, as I take it, skepticism is a place, perhaps the central secular intellectual place,
in which the drive to deny the conditions of human existence is enacted; then so long as that 
<hi rend="i">denial</hi> of the human is essential to what we think of <hi rend="i">as</hi> the human, skepticism
cannot, or what I call the threat of skepticism must not, be denied. You might even take it as the mission of
philosophy now to preserve rather than to turn aside the scandal of skepticism—as if this preservation is
our access to the memory that we are, or meant to be, human, to live with stumbling.” (184)
</q></p>
          <p>So Cavell stumbles on and on, mixing up all the pronouns so ineptly that it is almost impossible
to tell who is supposed to think what. That the author of such hedging prose should have been responsible for
no less than eight books, and that these have attracted a following, is astonishing. Yet if the reader
perseveres to the end of Cavell’s piece he or she may be reassured that Cavell’s heart is in the right
place: he is on the side of the romantics, especially the American romantics, and against those skeptics. But
having been subjected to such an ordeal of language without style I am brought to the verge of saying, “Damn
his romantics!” and of drawing my Hume.</p>
          <p>Eventually Cavell devotes ten pages to talk about “The Rime of the Ancient Mariner” (193-203)
but, though here the style is not quite so bad, anyone would rather read Wolfson or Reed in spite of what I
“take to be” their errors. A mark of Cavell’s rhetorical disorientation is that he keeps talking about
“the line” in Coleridge’s poem as though it referred to a “line” that Kant either discusses or
implies. Unless you happen to pick up a casual reference on page 199 or to read another of Cavell’s
discussions of the poem elsewhere (not specifically identified in the footnotes), you cannot be sure that he
knew that “the line” in Coleridge’s poem means the equator. The fact that “the line” was in place in
the 1798 version of the poem, before Coleridge knew anything of Kant, ought to have been sufficient to have
aborted Cavell’s thesis. But Cavell is irrepressible. He does not even have recourse to deconstructive
whimsicality in arguing that the mariner shot the albatross because he wanted to get to know the bird
better.</p>
          <pb id="p22-132" n="132"/>
          <p>What a surprise, then, to hear Cavell perform spontaneously through fourteen pages of question
and answer! Suddenly he drops the hedging manner (which is suited only for obfuscation) and speaks quite
simply and forthrightly about his purposes in combatting skepticism. The sincerity of his final statement is
even quite moving, but there remains the pathos in the demonstrated fact that he will not write in a way that
would encourage anyone to give up a debilitating skepticism. The two voices of Stanley Cavell are the opposite
of the two that J. K. Stephen detected in Wordsworth’s language: neither comes close to sublimity, but the
personal one is engaging.</p>
          <p>Finally, the contribution of Northrop Frye. When I first read <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi>
in 1949 on the advice of the late Richard Ellmann I had the immediate sense that great criticism was being
written in my time. As with <hi rend="i">Lord Weary’s Castle</hi> (of the same vintage) Frye seemed certain
to prove as readable as Arnold and as interesting as Coleridge a century hence. Not everyone saw Frye that
way: often those who felt themselves equal to Ransom or Blackmur or Burke were unable to cope with “The
Burden of the Valley of Vision.” It wasn’t for almost a decade thereafter that it became obligatory to
understand Frye. Then, after another decade opinion-makers began to declare that Frye was a Christian, and no
better than Arnold, and therefore outmoded, though due some respect as an elder statesman. Under questioning,
Miller confessed in 1984 that Frye seemed to him some kind of Jungian, for whom “archetypes tend to be
thought of as preceding or exceeding any of their embodiments” (123). Or a structural anthropologist who,
after gathering a hundred different examples of myth, tries to discern “some original myth of which they are
all representative.” He declares that this is an “anaclastic illusion” to which Frye “sometimes seems
to yield.”</p>
          <p>Though Frye has often denied that he is in any way a Jungian and imagines instead that all myths
are culturally transmitted, Miller’s impression that Frye believes in ur-myths is hardly without foundation.
In “The Survival of Eros in Poetry” Frye begins with what must be his hundredth retelling of the four main
levels of the mental cosmos. Frye would maintain that he had to do so because there were certain to be
students and others in the audience who were not conscious of ever having heard of such an organizing scheme.
Just as a person cannot get oriented in the physical world without reference to the points of the compass, so
a reader cannot find bearings in the literary universe without reference to an hierarchal scheme that starts
with the gods at the top. This breeds uneasiness for advanced critical thinkers who believe that literary
studies would be better off if they were immediately divested of all the illusions of Coleridge and the
compromises of Arnold. The aura of Christianity that still surrounds the figure of Frye, together with his
sometime lack of responsiveness to gender distinctions, have had much to do with his rapid descent from
critical eminence during the last generation.</p>
          <p>Certainly Frye is not going to ride back into office with the next movement currently assuming
power in criticism. New Historicists have decided that Frye has no interest in historical criticism and will
thus continue to overlook the fact that the first chapter in <hi rend="i">Anatomy of Criticism</hi> is
entitled “Historical Criticism,” and that it is, at bottom, hardly more schematic than the Marxism of the
New Historicism. But Frye’s kind of historicism deals with literature as an imaginative product, while that
of the New Historicist deals with literature as a class product. Thus when Frye, in “The Survival of Eros in
Poetry,” writes as follows, he in effect admits that he has not taken out any insurance in his own
popularity for the next decade: “Society is much less willing to grant literature or the other arts any
degree of inner authority . . . Certain Marxist regimes, such as Stalinist Russia with its ‘social
realism’ and the so-called Gang-of-Four group in China, deny such authority as a matter of dogma. . . .”
(24)</p>
          <p>The mark that this is no better than newspaper historicizing is not the general point, or even
the clichéd, if true, identification of the adversary, but the solecism “social realism.” The Stalinist
standard was, of course, <hi rend="i">socialist</hi> realism, a very different matter of projecting the
correct role models and working to show devotion to the state. It is hard not to feel that this elementary
mistake occurred in the writing of this brilliant critic because of what he does, from time to time,
acknowledge as comparative dissympathy with “realism” of any stripe. In the pleasantly vigorous give and
take of the long question and answer period at Albuquerque Frye acquitted himself better and more genially
than he has often done in the past. Anyone who has the impression that Frye is only interested in classifying,
pigeonholing, and categorizing literature will be surprised to discover that he can be as good-natured and
appreciative as Charles Lamb. You could not tell it from most of his essay, except for some shrewd and (I
believe) new observations about De Quincey, but for all his generalizing and synthetic power, Frye is at
bottom a great reader of literary works as they are, from their own point of view. The reason that most of his
Blake is still with us is that Frye was not struck dumb by the wonder of “Introduction” to 
<hi rend="i">Experience, Milton</hi>, or even by Blake’s books as illuminated.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p22-133" n="133" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
