<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>22.4.lindsay</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">“Malden” in Blake’s Jerusalem</title>
        <author n="Lindsay">David W. Lindsay</author>
        <author n="Locherbie-Cameron">M. A. L. Locherbie-Cameron</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1989</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1989</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">22.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>John A. Hodgson</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>David W. Lindsay</name>
              <name>M. A. L. Locherbie-Cameron</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Peter Otto</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_22">
    <body>
      <pb id="p22-136" n="136"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-22-4-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">MINUTE PARTICULAR</title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">“Malden” in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>David W. <name>Lindsay</name></docAuthor>
            <docAuthor>M. A. L. <name>Locherbie-Cameron</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The role of the druids in the symbolic terminology of Blake’s later work has been frequently
discussed, and its general significance is now well understood.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n13" type="note">1</ref> Northrop Frye and others have shown how the sacrificial rituals of druidism
were linked with London Stone and the Tree of Mystery, and have exposed the druidical origins of political
tyranny and Newtonian science. Though we are still unclear about Blake’s London-Welsh contacts, pictorial
and verbal sources for his serpent-temple imagery have been found in antiquarian literature. His presentation
of druidism, however, contains many details which remain puzzling, and one of these is the prominence of the
name “Malden.” <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry</hi> has nothing to say about Malden and much to say about
Stonehenge, but the text of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> names Stonehenge on five occasions and Malden on
eight. The connections between Malden and druidism seem worth exploring. <note id="n13"><hi rend="s">1</hi>
Ruthven Todd, “William Blake and the Eighteenth-Century Mythologists,” in <hi rend="i">Tracks in the Snow:
Studies in English Science and Art</hi> (London: Grey Walls Press, 1946); Northrop Frye, <hi rend="i">Fearful
Symmetry: A Study of William Blake</hi> (Princeton NJ: Princeton UP, 1947) 129-32, 397-99; David V. Erdman,
<hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet against Empire</hi> (Princeton NJ: Princeton UP, 1954) 196-97; Peter F. Fisher,
“Blake and the Druids,” <hi rend="i">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</hi> 58 (1959): 589-612; A.
L. Owen, <hi rend="i">The Famous Druids</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1962) 224-36; S. Foster Damon, 
<hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols of William Blake</hi> (Providence RI: Brown UP, 1965)
108-10; Glenda Carr, <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">William Owen Pughe</hi></corr> (Caerdydd: Gwasg Prifysgol Cymru, 1983) 183-91;
Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">The Continuing City: William Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem (Oxford: Clarendon Press,
1983) 160-61, 196-97; Dena Taylor, “A Note on William Blake and the Druids of Primrose Hill,” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 17 (1983-84): 104-05.</note></p>
          <p>On plate 21, when Albion is lamenting his children’s sufferings under the Babylonian tyranny of
Hand and Hyle, Malden and Colchester are linked with five British mountains which “Reason in Cruelty” and
“Demonstrate in Unbelief,” thus tormenting Liverpool and Manchester and causing four London districts to
“mourn” and “sicken” for four of Albion’s daughters. On plate 27, in the lyrical section of the
preface to chapter 2, an eastward movement from Lambeth through Malden to the Euphrates is connected with
Albion’s sleep, Jerusalem’s fall, and the triumph of Satan’s druidical religion of human sacrifice. On
plate 41[37], Malden and Canterbury are associated with “the delights of cruelty” in another account of
Jerusalem’s fall and division as an eastward movement. On plate 57, in a passage about the symbolic conflict
between “the Fires of the Druid” and the “deep black rethundering Waters / Of the Atlantic,” Malden
and Colchester are envisaged as the sites of “Druid Altars” and connected with other places where humanity
has been sacrificed to a jealous sky-god. On plate 65, when Albion’s “Spectre Sons” are tormenting Luvah
on the “Stone of Trial,” the phrases “over Malden” and “of Canterbury” are awkwardly added to
lines from <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> 7 in order to link those towns with the worship of Vala as
war-goddess. On plate 68, within the framework of another sadistic war-song, “Maldens cove” is related to
Stonehenge in a further account of Jerusalem’s eastward fall. On plate 90, a passage about the response of
Albion’s “Giants” to the vehement words of Los connects Malden with the Great Glen and the island of
Jura, appearing to suggest that all three possessed stone circles of the type erected by druids and deists. On
plate 94, the lament of the newly-awakened England or Britannia envisages Malden as a place whose “Oak
Groves,” like Stonehenge and London Stone, served as settings for a druidical sacrifice of the Eternal Man
to prohibitive morality.</p>
          <p>Scholars have agreed in identifying Blake’s “Malden” not with Malden in Surrey but with
Maldon in Essex, which is referred to as Malden in Cooke’s <hi rend="i">Topographical and Statistical
Description of Essex</hi> (c. 1806-10). Although the phrase “Maldens cove” need not mean that Malden is a
coastal town, because Blake elsewhere uses “cove” in archaic and dialectal senses unrelated to the
sea,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">2</ref> nonetheless the allusions to
“Malden” on plates 21 and 57 connect it with Colchester, and those on plates 27, 41[37] and 68 place it
east of London. It is equally clear that Maldon is to be connected in the cosmology of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> with a druidical religion of oak-groves and stone circles, human sacrifice and rational
demonstration. Maldon emerges from these texts as a British analogue to Calvary, a place where the values of
liberty and the imagination are cruelly subordinated to those of jealousy and war. Many commentators have
found it hard to explain, however, why this minor port on the Essex coast should be envisaged as a major
center of sacrificial religion. Foster Damon correctly observes that it has “some prehistoric remains” but
“no rocking stones or druidic circle.” He also claims that Maldon and Colchester were “connected in
Blake’s mind with naval or military disturbances,” but this is an implausible conjecture based on a
misinterpretation of the word “demonstrate.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15"
type="note">3</ref> W. H. Stevenson usefully reminds us that Maldon was “supposed (by Camden and others) to
be the site of the Roman Camulodunum”; but in explanation of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 90:58-66 he can
only repeat Damon’s statement that the town has “prehistoric remains, but no stone circles.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16" type="note">4</ref> One might add that it has not in modern times
been conspicuously rich in oak forests. <note id="n14"><hi rend="s">2</hi> See plate <hi rend="i">c</hi> of
<hi rend="i">America</hi>, line 1, and plate 66 of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, lines 13 and 57.</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Damon 260.</note>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">4</hi> William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Poems</hi>, ed. W. H. Stevenson (London:
Longman, 1971) 679, 826-27.</note></p>
          <p>Maldon is best known among modern students of literature as the site of a battle which was
celebrated in and Old English heroic poem, and Morton D. Paley has sought to explain Blake’s use of the name
by reference to this text. He connects the bloody fight on the Blackwater estuary with Blake’s pharse about
the accumulation of a “black water”; and he asserts that “the heroic Byrhtnoth was killed with a
poisoned spear,” and that the victorious Vikings “went on to sack London.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">5</ref> Though Blake’s anti-militarist ethos is far removed from
that of the Old English poem, he might well have interpreted this annihilation
<pb id="p22-137" n="137"/>
of Christian Saxons by pagan Danes as a druidical sacrifice, and readers familiar with <hi rend="i">Fearful
Symmetry</hi> will have no difficulty in seeing Byrhtnoth as an Anglo-Saxon analogue of Balder, Odin, Absalom,
Fuzon, and Christ. Such a connection between <hi rend="i">The Battle of Maldon</hi> and Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is more aesthetically satisfying than historically probable, however, for the Old
English poem was scarcely known at the relevant date. When Thomas Hearne produced the first printed text in
1726 in the appendix to a Latin chronicle, he called it “Fragmentum quoddam historicum de Eadrico etc.”
and made no reference to Maldon; J. J. Conybeare’s translation did not appear until 1826, by which time the
whole text of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> had been engraved.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n18" type="note">6</ref> Even the battle commemorated in the Old English poem was not a conspicuous
event in Blake’s main sources for early British history. Milton’s <hi rend="i">History of Britain</hi>,
for example, dismisses it in a single sentence:
<q>
The third year following, under the conduct of <hi rend="i">Justin</hi> and <hi rend="i">Guthmund</hi> the Son
of <hi rend="i">Steytan</hi>, they landed and spoiled <hi rend="i">Ipswich</hi>, fought with 
<hi rend="i">Britnoth</hi> Duke of the <hi rend="i">East Angles</hi> about <hi rend="i">Maldon</hi>, where they
slew him; the slaughter else had bin equal on both sides.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
type="note">7</ref></q>
Rapin’s <hi rend="i">History of England</hi>, which Blake knew at least by reputation, is no more
illuminating. It too reports the battle in one sentence, and although it names “Brithnoth” it does not at
this point name Maldon.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">8</ref> For the
historians whose work was available to Blake, this routine encounter between Anglo-Saxon and Danish forces
could not compete in dramatic interest with the British rebellion which sacked Camulodunum. References to it
might catch the attention of readers already interested in Maldon, but there was nothing in the
chronicle-derived accounts of the battle that would of itself make the event seem either historically or
symbolically important. <note id="n17"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Paley 76, 198.</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Thomas Hearne, <hi rend="i">Johannis Confratris et Monachi Glastoniensis
Chronica sive Historia de Rebus Glastoniensibus</hi>, 2 vols. (Oxonii: e Theatro Sheldoniano, 1726) 2: 570-77;
J. J. Conybeare, <hi rend="i">Illustrations of Anglo-Saxon Poetry</hi> (London: Harding and Lepard, 1826)
lxxvii-xcvi.</note>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">7</hi> John Milton, <hi rend="i">Complete Prose Works</hi>, vol. 5, part 1 (New
Haven and London: Yale UP, 1971) 334-35.</note>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Paul de Rapin-Thoyras, <hi rend="i">The History of England</hi>, trans.
and continued to the accession of George II, by N. Tindal, with the reign of George II by T. Smollett, 5 vols.
(London: John Harrison, 1789) 1: 104.</note></p>
          <p>A better pointer to the main significance of Maldon for antiquarians of Blake’s time is
Stevenson’s observation that some writers identified it as the site of Camulodunum; and some of the
implications of this fact have been explored in a learned and informative article by David Worrall.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">9</ref> Taking up a suggestion made by John
Beer,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">10</ref> Worrall shows that Blake’s
interpretation of early British history was significantly influenced by the text and engravings of Aylett
Sammes’ <hi rend="i">Britannia Antiqua Illustrata.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23"
type="note">11</ref> He connects Blake’s description of Hand with Sammes’ account of four Saxon gods, one
of whom was “worshipped as Mars”; and he suggests that the overthrow of a false god on plate 94 of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> may recall not only Milton’s <hi rend="i">Nativity Ode</hi> but also Sammes’
report that a Roman statue of Victory was overthrown in Camulodunum at the time of Boadicea’s rebellion.
Worrall points out that Sammes represents Malden as a “British religious centre” whose chief dieties were
Heus and Adraste; and he quotes Sammes’ conjectures that “Heus, Mars or Camulus . . . was not only
worshipped as a God of War but of Peace also,” that “this Camulus” gave his name to “Camulodunum, or
Mars-hill, near Malden in Essex,” and that the name of Heus was also “given to Bacchus.” Sammes further
identified Adraste with Venus, thus giving added significance to the ceremonies at her temple in Maldon, where
the Britons “sacrificed Prisoners alive” and spent their time “in Feasts and Banquets.” This system of
multiple identifications would have obvious attractions for Blake, since it allowed him to unite a druidical
sacrifice with a Bacchic orgy and to interpret the result as an act of homage to a Urizenlike war-god and a
Vala-like love-goddess. Worrall’s arguments leave one in no doubt that Blake was familiar with Sammes’
work, and that his image of Maldon as a religious center was substantially determined by it. 
<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">9</hi> David Worrall, “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and the Visionary History
of Britain,” <hi rend="i">Studies in Romanticism</hi> 16 (1977): 189-216.</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">10</hi> John Beer, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Humanism</hi> (Manchester: Manchester
UP, 1968) 255.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Aylett Sammes, <hi rend="i">Britannia Antiqua Illustrata: or, the
Antiquities of Ancient Britain</hi> (London: Tho. Rycroft, 1676).</note></p>
          <p>Sammes’ account of Maldon’s distinctive place in religious history can be supplemented,
however, by reference to works published in Blake’s lifetime; among these the writings of Philip Morant
(1700-1770) are of particular significance, especially for the connection between Maldon and Colchester.
Morant was born in Jersey, but spent most of his life as a clergyman in Essex. In 1738 he became Rector of
St.-Mary’s-at-the-Walls in Colchester, and in 1748 he published <hi rend="i">The History and Antiquities of
Colchester.</hi> He was elected a Fellow of the Society of Antiquaries in 1755, and between 1763 and 1768 he
produced a richly-illustrated work in two volumes entitled <hi rend="i">The History and Antiquities of the
County of Essex.</hi> After his wife’s death in 1767 he went to live in Battersea with his son-in-law Thomas
Astle, the eccentric lawyer whom Erdman in 1954 identified as the “Etruscan Column” of <hi rend="i">An
Island in the Moon.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">12</ref> Although
Morant died two years before Blake began his apprenticeship, he may well have known Blake’s master James
Basire, who was engraver to the Society of Antiquaries. <hi rend="i">The History and Antiquities of
Colchester</hi>, which had been revised and incorporated in the larger work, appeared in octavo and duodecimo
versions in 1789 and 1810; <hi rend="i">The History and Antiquities of the County of Essex</hi> was itself
reprinted in 1816.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Erdman 30.</note>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Philip Morant, <hi rend="i">The History and Antiquities of the County of
Essex</hi>, 2 vols. (London: J. Osborne and others, 1768), rpt. with an introduction by G. H. Martin
(Wakefield, West Yorkshire: E. P. Publishing, 1978) 1: v-xviii.</note></p>
          <p>In the introduction to <hi rend="i">The History and Antiquities of the County of Essex</hi>,
Morant quotes at length from a dissertation on the county’s Roman roads by “the late Smart Lethieullier,
Esq.” Lethieullier argues that Essex was “fully inhabited in the British times,” and that its “vast
Forest” was a “proper Habitation” for the Druids; but he explains that the “want of Quarries of
Stone” made it impossible for the Britons of this area to “leave such Monuments of themselves here, as . .
. at Stonehenge, Rollright, and elswhere.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26"
type="note">14</ref> In his discussion of Colchester, Morant offers a similar picture in support of his claim
that there was a town on this site “even in the earliest times.” He asserts that the area was “covered
<pb id="p22-138" n="138"/>
with woods,” and points out that “according to J. Caesar, the Strong Towns or fortified Places, of the
Britans were only thick Woods, fenced with a ditch and a rampart.” He argues that “the Woodiness of this
place” was “quite suited and agreeable to the Religion of the ancient Britans,” and reminds us that
“Woods, especially of Oaks, were the Habitations of the Druids, and their places of religious worship.” It
was in such woods that “all their Mysteries were transacted, and their Sacrifices offered,” and it was
there that “their much admired and celebrated Mistletoe grew.” As “the Instructors of Youth” they had
schools “situated in the midst of pleasant groves,” and they also had “little arch’d, round
stone-buildings,” in one of which a “retir’d and contemplative Druid” might sit “when his Oak would
not shelter him from the Weather.” Morant acknowledges that the Colchester area has “no remains of
Druidical Temples or Altars,” but argues that the monuments which once existed “have been demolish’d to
make room for other Edifices, or even for the sake of Stones to be employed in building.” That the district
is now “thinly wooded” does not disturb him, because “great Alterations must have happened in the
surface of the Earth in the course of above 2,000 years.” <note id="n26"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Morant 1, 1978
intro, ii.</note></p>
          <p>These arguments provide the excuse for a learned footnote about “Druidical Temples and
Altars.” Morant explains that these are “stupendous and massy stones, either standing single or in
circles, or in rows, with others of enormous bulk, set up horizontally.” He reports that such monuments
exist “at Stoneheng, and Abury, in Wiltshire,” and at other sites in Cornwall, Wales, Scotland, Ireland
and Jersey; and he asserts that the “true use of them was first discovered by John Aubrey, Esq.” For
further information he refers “the curious reader” to
<q>
the Right Reverend the Lord Bishop of London’s last edition of Camden’s Britannia, the Rev. H. Rowland’s
Mona antiqua restaurata, J. Toland’s Postumous Works, Vol.I, M. Martin’s Description of the Western
Islands of Scotland. The Rev. Ph. Falle’s Account of Jersey; and especially the learned Dr. W. Stukeley’s
most curious Works on that Subject.
</q>
He does not mention Sammes, however, and he does not suggest that any of these books records druidical
monuments on the Essex coast.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">15</ref>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Morant 1, History and Antiquities of Colchester, 11-12.</note></p>
          <p>Morant’s description of druidical Essex is immediately followed by his account of the Roman
conquest. He rejects Camden’s suggestion that Mars was worshipped at Camulodunum under the name of Camulus;
but he reports that a temple was erected there in honor of the Emperor Claudius, and that the priests of that
temple “behaved with intolerable Insolence towards the natives.” Opposing Camden’s suggestion that
Camulodunum was at Maldon, he argues that Tacitus’ praise of the town’s site “agrees very well with
Colchester,” but “doth not by any means agree with Maldon, seated in one of the most unhealthy corners of
the kingdom”; and he cites archaeological evidence to prove that Colchester was the site of “a very
considerable Roman Town.” On this basis, he proceeds to demolish Camden’s etymological arguments:
<q>
After all, there is not so great a Necessity of fetching the name of Maldon from Cama- or Camu-lodunum, as Mr.
Camden and others have imagined; upon a kind of presumption that it could not so well admit of any other
derivation. For it is plainly a Saxon name formed from the two words Mæl a cross, or boundary, and dun a
hill. As if you should say Cross-Hill: The occasion of which name, as of many others, is at present
unknown.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">16</ref>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Morant 1, History and Antiquities of Colchester, 13-15.</note></q>
Morant also records the tradition that Helena and her son Constantine were born in Colchester; and he claims
that her discovery of the True Cross is commemorated in the arms of Colchester, which show “<hi rend="i">a
Cross</hi> between three crowns, or coronets.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29"
type="note">17</ref> Morant’s long account of the history of Colchester includes a brief reference to the
Battle of Maldon, which tells us that the Danes overthrew “Byrhtnoth the King’s ealdorman” and
“remained masters of the field of battle”;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30"
type="note">18</ref> and the same statements appear in the section about Maldon in his description of the
Hundred of Dengey. This section also reports that Maldon “is one of the two ancientest Towns in the County
of Essex,” that it “stands on an eminence, or side of a hill, south of the river Idumanum, or
Black-water-bay,” and that its bay “makes a convenient harbour” from which “the merchants carry on a
considerable trade.” Here again Morant rejects the notion that Maldon “was the 
<hi rend="i">Colonia-Camulodunum</hi> mentioned in Antonine’s Itinerary,” and offers an etymology more
plausible than Camden’s: “The name of it is derived from the two Saxon words Mæl, a cross, and dun, a
hill; qu. Cross-hill.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">19</ref>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Morant 1, History and Antiquities of Colchester, 28, 34.</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Morant 1, History and Antiquities of Colchester, 44.</note>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Morant 1, The Hundred of Dengey, 327-28.</note></p>
          <p>In the writings of Philip Morant, then, Blake could have found the name of Maldon associated with
druidism, oak forests, stone circles, imperial tyranny, the Roman war-god, a busy harbour, the death of
Byrthnoth, and a cross on a hill. Most of that material, including the crucial etymology, was available both
in <hi rend="i">The History and Antiquities of Colchester</hi>, versions of which appeared in 1748, 1789 and
1810, and in <hi rend="i">The History and Antiquities of Essex</hi>, which appeared in 1768 and was reprinted
in 1816. The chronology of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is a complex and controversial
problem,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">20</ref> but it is obvious that
Blake could have encountered Morant’s comments on Maldon before he engraved those plates in which the town
is mentioned. The large-scale replacement of biblical with British place-names came at a late stage in the
development of Blake’s mythology, and might still have been in process when the 1810 version of 
<hi rend="i">The History and Antiquities of Colchester</hi> was published; but in any case this material could
have reached Blake through an earlier version, or even through the
<pb id="p22-139" n="139"/>
conversation of antiquaries, booksellers, and engravers. What can hardly be doubted is that Blake’s
identification of Maldon as a center of sacrificial religion was encouraged by a report that the name of this
ancient town alluded to a cross on a hill. Blake had found many passages in the Old Testament which allowed
him to equate other biblical mountains with Calvary, and Blake scholarship is familiar with the many variants
of that hilltop crucifixion in which Orc howls “time after time” on Mount Atlas. As he moved from biblical
to British names, Blake saw analogues to Calvary in the Tyburn execution-place and the Snowdon of Gray’s
“The Bard”; and he enlisted other British mountains, from Penmaenmawr to “the Rocky Peak of
Derbyshire,” as equivalents for such places as the mountain-top of Genesis 22 and the Ebal of Deuteronomy
27. It was altogether natural, in this context, that he should attach some importance to a town with druidical
and Roman connections whose name was translated by one authority as “Marshill” and by another as
“Crosshill.” When one adds to this the fact that Sammes gave “Hesus” as an alternative name for the
war-god to whom sacrifices were made at Maldon,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33"
type="note">21</ref> it becomes clear that the little port on the Essex coast would have for Blake a range of
associations which made it a symbol of manifold significance. Maldon took its place, therefore, in Blake’s
apocalyptic vision of that primeval catastrophe which divided Jerusalem from Albion and released Satan “in
all the pomp of War.” In the age which “began to turn allegoric and mental signification into corporeal
command,” the “Oak Groves of Maldon” had been “the Habitations of the Druids, and their places of
religious worship.” Although the “reasoning historian” might doubt their existence, the stone circles
beside “Maldens Cove” had been the “Temples and Altars” where “the Druids golden Knife / Rioted in
human gore.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">22</ref>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Paley 1-7.</note>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Worrall 207.</note>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">22</hi> William Blake, <hi rend="i">Complete Writings</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes
(London: Oxford UP, 1966) 246, 279, 281, 484, 578-79, 650, 689, 706, 742; Morant 1: 12.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
