<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>22.4.otto</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">Is There a Poem in This Manuscript?</title>
        <author n="Otto">Peter Otto</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1989</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1989</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">22.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Production Office</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>John A. Hodgson</name>
              <name>Andrew Lincoln</name>
              <name>David W. Lindsay</name>
              <name>M. A. L. Locherbie-Cameron</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Peter Otto</name>
              <name>Warren Stevenson</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1988"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textDesc n="Scholarly journal">
        <constitution type="composite"/>
        <domain type="education"/>
      </textDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_22">
    <body>
	<pb id="p22-142" n="142"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-22-4-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Is There A Poem in This Manuscript?</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Peter <name>Otto</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>As I happen to agree with the devils that “Opposition is True Friendship,” it was with some
pleasure that I sat down to read Paul Mann’s response to my own response to articles by himself and Robert
Essick. One of the pleasures of argument is the transformative force that can sometimes transform devils into
angels, Leviathans into Pipers and what is down into what is up. I was fascinated by my own transformation
from an Antipodean Blake scholar (one who comes from “down under,” as popular geography would have it) to
a figure who had somehow attained a prominence from which he was able to keep the “key to the scriptures,”
undertake the “surveillance” of Essick’s hypothesis, assert that what is “must stay that way,” and
at the same time represent “the central movement of Blake criticism.” A metamorphosis indeed!</p>
          <p>As these preliminary remarks might suggest, the terms of Mann’s response are broadly homologous
with those used by Blake in the <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell.</hi> The high ground of authority
and the dematerialized world of the spirit are claimed by the angels, while the nether world, the world of
fact and action, is claimed by the devils. Mann believes that he occupies the world of material fact (he deals
with the physical manuscript), while I along with Blake criticism as a whole have imposed my “phantasy” on
the poem. It is, however, not the “phantasy,” at least not in the first instance, that Mann is concerned
about. (In fact, he is ready to affirm that my hypothesis is “in the case of <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi>
criticism . . . certainly an improvement.”) What bothers Mann is the swerve that he detects in my reply and
in Blake studies as a whole away from the physical material manuscript towards some form of “ideal” text.
His later and contradictory assertion that my hypothesis regarding the form of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
does not assist with the reading of the poem is a conclusion derived from his analysis of that swerve.</p>
          <p>In responding to Mann and Essick’s illuminating hypothesis regarding Blake’s production
intentions for <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, I proposed that we consider <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> in
its final state as an unfinished rather than an incomplete poem. In contradistinction to views of the poem
that maintain, for example, that Blake abandoned the manuscript because he did not foresee the Peace of Amiens
(Erdman) or because of some personal failing (Bentley), I argued that the poem is arrested by forces which are
intrinsic to its subject matter. Mann begins his critique of this position by detailing a logical paradox or
conundrum.</p>
          <pb id="p22-143" n="143"/>
          <p>To produce a “<hi rend="i">finished discourse</hi> of unfinishedness” is, for Mann, to
complete the poem on the level of “critical recounting.” If this is done, then, he argues, “there is . .
. <hi rend="i">no inherent reason</hi> why, if the poem was <hi rend="i">essentially</hi> unfinished, Blake
could not have devised a form for its publication as such.” He concludes that “the condition of the
manuscript is merely an image, an ornament, a suggestion, a formal hint for a reading that is, at bottom, in
no way dependent upon it.” It is difficult to see the logic in this sequence.</p>
          <p>To claim that the fabrication of a “<hi rend="i">finished discourse</hi> of unfinishedness”
completes the poem and becomes “the ideal form of the poem’s publication” is surely to confuse levels.
To explain why a mechanic was unable to build a car because of problems with the way in which that car was
first imagined does not (in any sense evident to me) produce a workable car. To discourse about why one has
failed to complete a project is not in my experience at least to complete that project.</p>
          <p>The recognition of the problems intrinsic to a particular work may, of course, lead one to
attempt a very different kind of project. This is a response to the “failure” of <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi> which Blake seems to have adopted when he wrote <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Yet it would clearly be absurd to say that either of these poems was a complete
version of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas.</hi> Of course, in elaborating a “<hi rend="i">finished
discourse</hi> of unfinishedness” one sets up a contrast between the unfinished poem and the finished
discourse, but what is involved here is a difference in object. To attempt to narrate a history of the world,
from Fall to Apocalypse, is very different from the attempt to explain why for Blake that narrative could not
be completed.</p>
          <p>I should hasten to add, however, that if one accepts that there is a broad homology between
unfinished poem and fallen world, then Mann is right to point out that in elaborating a 
“<hi rend="i">finished discourse</hi> of unfinishedness” one is adopting a position outside of the “chaos” of
the text that the narrator and the poem’s characters are unable to attain. As Mann observes:
<q>
The issue is one of mediation: in order for the poem to enter discourse, for there to be any commentary on it
at all, <hi rend="i">someone</hi> must stand “outside” it; an outside must somehow be established, an
archimedean fulcrum for levering the manuscript into Blake studies must be found.
</q>
Levering <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> into Blake criticism may not on all occasions be a reprehensible act;
yet even putting this equivocation aside, the issue is not as straightforward as Mann suggests.</p>
          <p>A poem that attempts to recount the history of the fallen world (from Fall to Apocalypse) must
enclose narrator, author, and critic within its spaces. The forces that ensure that the poem’s narrator is
unable to oversee a history of which he is an effect also ensure that the critic is unable to attain a vantage
point from which to survey the whole. This puts readers of the poem in a curious position, for to claim to
have attained a position from which we are able to “view all things beneath [our] feet” is to assert that
we have reached the position denied to Urizen. We must stand outside of the poem to comment on it; but each
claim to have reached an outside from which we can see the poem in its entirety is proof that we remain inside
the dream. The poem undoes the authority of the reading that at the same time it seems to invite. Even on the
level of critical appropriation the poem is therefore unfinished (an observation which is itself subject to
the same vicissitudes). Rather than offering “a solid critical framework on which to hang the manuscript’s
rags,” the notion of an “unfinished poem” is itself unstable. This relentless undoing of the reader’s
position is clearly appropriate for a poem that attempts to wake its readers from the sleep of the fallen
world, an observation which has implications for our understanding of Blake’s production intentions and even
his “production-aesthetic.”</p>
          <p>At times Mann’s concerns about “mediation,” and some of the implications of the argument
that unfolds from his critique of the critic’s position outside of the text, seem to imply rather remarkable
conclusions. All reading assumes an ability to adopt (at least provisionally) a position with regard to the
text. Insofar as reading is the yoking of the reader’s discourse to that of the text<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">1</ref> it would seem to involve some form of mediation. Does this
mean that <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> cannot or should not be read? This possibility is certainly
suggested by Mann’s reference to “the strange and irreducible inaccessibility of the manuscript.” But
surely the manuscript is not <hi rend="i">that</hi> inaccessible. If this is the price on must pay to keep the
manuscript safe from the iniquities of dematerialization, then it is too high. 
<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Paul Ricoeur, “What is a Text? Explanation and Interpretation,” in 
<hi rend="i">Mythic-Symbolic Language and Philosophical Anthropology</hi>, by David M. Rasmussen (The Hague:
Martinus Nijhoff, 1971) 135-50; 144.</note></p>
          <p>Mann is, of course, not really opposed to reading the poem; instead he is championing a
particular kind of reading. This is to be based on a study of Blake’s “production-aesthetic.” For Mann,
“. . . Blake[’s] . . . commitment to different material forms and modes of publication was a process of
learning to see the work in the work.” Although I have no quarrel with this project (I think it is one of
the more interesting of the approaches to <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>), I do find it surprising that this
kind of reading should be seen in competition with other ways of reading Blake (Mann mentions
“poet(-prophet), inspired illustrator . . . [and] composite artist”). I am also skeptical as to whether
such an approach is able to avoid a swerve similar to that which Mann traces in Blake criticism. Seeing the
work in the work is closely allied to religious metaphors that would seem to bring with them the very swerve
that Mann condemns.
<pb id="p22-144" n="144"/>
It is perhaps not fortuitous that the swerve that is the subject of Mann’s reply is located in those most
spiritual and disembodied of realms, “the spaces between [my] paragraphs” and the gap between Mann’s
article and my reply.</p>
          <p>These observations are not meant as criticism of a reading that aims to delineate Blake’s
“productionaesthetic.” For me at least, the reading of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is only just
beginning and at this stage of the process it would in my view be unfortunate to put too rigid a line between
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> as manuscript and as poem, as work and as text. As I suggested in my first
response, what is striking about <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> is that it suggests both “. . . a drive
towards clarity and completion (telling the <hi rend="i">whole</hi> story) and a residue or excess which must
leave this drive short of its goal.” Or to phrase this in a more parabolic style: the manuscript implies a
poem which in turn implies a manuscript. To drive a wedge between these two dimensions is likely to result in
a view of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> which is less complete than others. This point is well made by the
passage that Mann quotes from the <hi rend="i">Marriage.</hi></p>
          <p>The parable of the Ancient Poets begins with a description of a world in which there is an
interaction between the material and the spiritual, the “natural” and the human worlds. On the one hand
the Ancient Poets animate all sensible objects with Gods or Geniuses and so impose their phantasies on the
world; but on the other hand these Gods are called by the names and adorned with the properties of things that
lie outside the Poets’ world. They are adorned with “whatever their enlarged &amp; numerous senses could
perceive.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">2</ref> As a parable of Blake
criticism, this suggests that in its prelapsarian state there was an interaction between the critics’
phantasies (their animation of the inert manuscript) and the force exerted by the manuscript on the critic.
Mann argues that in the time that has elapsed since those halcyon days, Blake criticism has drawn apart from
the manuscript and has been used to form a system to enslave the vulgar. One could, however, argue that Blake
criticism might just as easily be precipitated into this parlous condition if critics were to attempt to
quarantine the manuscript from the improprieties of reading. A division of this kind would just as surely
involve forgetting that “All deities reside in the human breast.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n42" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">2</hi> David V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of
William Blake</hi>, newly rev. ed. (Garden City: Anchor Press, 1982) 38.</note>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Erdman 38.</note></p>
          <p>In a poem/manuscript such as this—where there is both a drive towards completion and an excess
which continually makes that drive fall short of its goal—the dematerialization of the manuscript that
occurs in reading is not a problem so long as it is followed by a movement back towards the manuscript. This
does not imply that I believe that consideration of the “manuscript’s material conditions and production
‘intentions’ are dangerous.” In fact my article was a response that began from Mann’s and Essick’s
reflections on the manuscript and provided what still seems to me to be a plausible conclusion to their own
narrative. At the same time, however, I believe that in certain cases reflection on a manuscript can sometimes
be corroborated or extended by a reading of the words contained by that manuscript. At this stage I will
persist in thinking that to call <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> an unfinished rather than an incomplete poem
does in some small way illuminate the <hi rend="i">manuscript.</hi> It may even provide a fulcrum for levering
Blake studies some small distance towards that endlessly fascinating poem/manuscript, <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas.</hi></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
