<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>23.1.schuchard</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake’s Healing Trio: Magnetism, Medicine, and Mania</title>
        <author n="Schuchard">Marsha Keith Schuchard</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1989</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1989</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">23.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Terence Allan Hoagwood</name>
              <name>Marsha Keith Schuchard</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1989"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_23">
    <body>
      <pb id="p23-20" n="20"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-23-1-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="main">Blake’s Healing Trio: Magnetism, Medicine, and Mania</title>
        </head>
        <byline>BY <docAuthor>MARSHA KEITH <name>SCHUCHARD</name></docAuthor></byline>
        <p>When William Blake returned to London from his “three years Slumber” at Felpham, he initially
found sympathetic friends as he pursued his “visionary studies.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n1" type="note">1</ref> Blake participated throughout the 1780s and 90s in an eclectic network of 
<hi rend="i">illuminés</hi>, which included Swedenborgians, Freemasons, and Cabalists who shared his interest in
animal magnetism spirit-communication, and erotic trances.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref> In 1804 he apparently renewed his acquaintance with several theosophers, who continued
their secret meetings and occult studies over the next decade. Unfortunately, the fragmentary evidence for
this collaboration comes from an embittered notebook poem (c. 1808-11), when Blake accuses his friends of
cowardly withdrawal from their mutual studies. Compressed into eight hostile lines, Blake’s mental distress
and spiritual commitment reveal the radical daring of his visionary enterprise:
<q>
Cosway, Frazer &amp; Baldwin of Egypts Lake<lb/>
Fear to Associate with Blake<lb/>
This Life is a Warfare against Evils<lb/>
They heal the sick he casts out Devils<lb/>
Hayley Flaxman &amp; Stothard are also in doubt<lb/>
Lest their Virtue should be put to the rout<lb/>
One grins tother spits &amp; in corner hides<lb/>
And all the Virtuous have shewn their backsides<lb/>
(E 505)
</q>
	<note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> David V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">Complete Poetry</hi> &amp; 
<hi rend="i">Prose of William Blake</hi>, newly rev. ed. (New York: Doubleday/Anchor, 1982) 728-29. Hereafter
cited as E.</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Marsha Keith Schuchard, <hi rend="i">Freemasonry, Secret Societies, and the
Continuity of the Occult Traditions in English Literature</hi> (Ph.D. dissertation, Univ. of Texas at Austin,
1975); <hi rend="i">The Men of Desire: Swedenborg, Blake, and Illuminist Freemasonry</hi>
(forthcoming).</note></p>
        <p>The first three friends—Cosway, Frazer, and Baldwin—were drawn together by shared interest in
animal magnetism, the bizarre pseudoscience that played a role in its day equivalent to Freudian and Jungian
Psychology in our own.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> Animal
magnetism was a “modern” version of ancient Cabalistic meditation techniques, merged with Hermetic,
Paracelsan, and astrological theories of man as microcosm. Seventeenth-century speculation on the universal
magnetic fluid was updated with new theories of electricity. Developed by Dr. Franz Anton Mesmer into a
methodical science of hypnosis, trance, and nervous catharsis, magnetism became a kind of countercultural
therapy and religion to the restless, millenarian spirits of the revolutionary decades. Despite its
“holistic” claims, the new magnetic religion split into rival schools which accused each other,
respectively, of materialistic atheism and occultist fanaticism. Blake and his three friends were not immune
to these bitter though often comical quarrels. 
                    <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Robert Darnton, <hi rend="i">Mesmerism and the End of
the Enlightenment in France</hi> (Harvard UP, 1968); Clarke Garrett, <hi rend="i">Respectable Folly:
Millenarians and the French Revolution in France and England</hi> (Johns Hopkins UP, 1975).</note></p>
        <p>Richard Cosway (1740-1821), the fashionable miniature painter, was one of Blake’s oldest friends.
Fascinated by magic, alchemy, and Cabala, Cosway was intimately acquainted with radical Freemasons and
millenarian <hi rend="i">illuminés</hi> in Europe as well as England.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n4" type="note">4</ref> Cosway joined the Swedenborg society in 1783-84, at a period when it was
dominated by French and Swedish Freemasons who believed that Swedenborg himself was a Cabalist, alchemist, and
Mason.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> Working closely with the London
society were Dr. Benedict Chastanier and the Marquis de Thomé, who founded the Masonic rite of 
<hi rend="i">Illuminés Théosophes</hi> in London and Paris.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref> They believed that Mesmer took his theories from Swedenborg and then perverted them into a
materialistic science.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> Cosway and the
London group agreed, and John Flaxman still believed this in 1823<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n8" type="note">8</ref>. 
                    <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> George Williamson, <hi rend="i">Richard Cosway</hi>,
rev. ed. (London: G. Bell, 1905); Frederick Daniell, <hi rend="i">A Catalogue Raisonée of the Engraved Works
of Richard Cosway, R. A.</hi> (London: F. B. Daniell, 1890).</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> “Mr. Cosway, Painter in History,” is listed by C. F. Nordenskjöld as a
member of the group in 1783-84. Unpublished list in Academy Collection of Swedenborg Documents, Academy of the
New Church, Bryn Athyn, PA. On Freemasonry and early Swedenborgianism, see Martin Lamm, 
<hi rend="i">Upplysningstiden Romantik</hi>, 2 vols. (Stockholm: Hugo Gebers, 1918) 1: 63; R. L. Tafel,
“Swedenborg and Freemasonry,” <hi rend="i">New Jerusalem Messenger</hi> (1869): 266-67.</note>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Karl-Erik Sjoden, “Swedenborg en France,” <hi rend="i">Stockholm
Studies in the History of Literature</hi>, 27 (1985): 10-40.</note>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi><hi rend="i"> Intellectual Repository</hi>, 2 (1874-75): 191-98; 
<hi rend="i">Journal Encyclopédique</hi>, 6 (1 Sept. 1785): 310-20.</note>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Henry Crabb Robinson, <hi rend="i">Diary, Reminiscences, and
Correspondence</hi>, ed. Thomas Sadler, 2 vols. (Boston: J. R. Osgood, 1871) 1: 494-96.</note></p>
        <p>In 1784 a French governmental commission exposed animal magnetism as a fraud, which only drove its
disciples into more radical defenses of the new science.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">9</ref> A disgusted Mesmer traveled to England in August 1785, hoping to establish a Mesmeric
Masonic lodge.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10" type="note">10</ref> But he found his
rivals already dominating the popular magnetic stage. Mesmer faded from the English scene, while his apostate
pupil, Dr. John Bonniot de Mainaduc, instituted a decade-long reign.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n11" type="note">11</ref> Cosway and his Swedenborgian friends became Mainaduc’s earliest and, for a
while, most ardent disciples. Born in Ireland to a French Protestant family, Mainaduc studied medicine in
London in the 1770s under Drs. William and John Hunter, George Fordyce, and other eminent physicians. In
1782-84, he studied in France where he was caught up in the Mesmeric enthusiasm. When he offered Mesmer 200
guineas for his secret, the German doctor haughtily refused.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n12" type="note">12</ref> Mortified, Mainaduc turned to Dr. Charles Deslon, an early champion of
Mesmer, who developed a different technique. Mainaduc claimed that Deslon raised the science beyond Mesmer’s
“crude state.” <note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Darnton 62-66.</note>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> See W. R. Dawson, ed., <hi rend="i">The Banks Letters</hi> (London:
British Museum, 1958) 66, as a corrective to Vincent Buranelli, <hi rend="i">The Wizard from Vienna</hi> (New
York, 1975) 182.</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi><hi rend="i"> The Lectures of J. B. de Mainaduc, M.D.</hi> (London:
printed for the Executrix, 1798). Copy in Royal College of Surgeons, London. Includes list of paying students.
I am grateful to Jonathon Miller, M.D., for informing me of this copy.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> John Martin, <hi rend="i">Animal Magnetism Examined</hi> (London, 1790)
5-6.</note></p>
        <pb id="p23-21" n="21"/>
        <p>Returning to London in 1785, Mainaduc introduced magnetism into his medical treatment, drawing a
clientele initially from his large midwifery practice. He soon deviated from the materialistic gadgetry of
Deslon’s style (tubs, tubes, rods, etc.), and declared a purely spiritual form of magnetism. A Freemason
himself, Mainaduc attracted the interest of Swedenborgian Freemasons who appreciated his spiritualistic
approach in which “divine influx” aided the cures. On 12 December 1785, he initiated Chastanier into
“this Modern Magical Science.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref>
For the next ten months, Chastanier served as Mainaduc’s chief assistant at his lavish clinic in Bloomsbury
Square. Attacked by a Mesmeric rival, Dr. John Bell, as superstitious and unscientific apostates, Mainaduc and
Chastanier defended themselves by claiming to perform the same kind of spiritual cures as Christ and his
disciples.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> The two 
<hi rend="i">illuminés</hi> then invited “twenty gentlemen of distinction” to hear their lectures, in which
Paracelsus, Fludd, Kircher, and Swedenborg were presented as precursors of Mesmer.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> Mainaduc also recruited twenty women to form a “Hygeian
Society,” which was incorporated with a sister lodge in France. To demonstrate their Masonic notions of
equality, Mainaduc instructed Chastanier to round up twenty poor patients for free treatment at Bloomsbury.
Over the next decade, Mainaduc instructed over 270 paying customers in the secret science. Among the dozen
identifiable Swedenborgians were four artistic peers of Blake—Maria and Richard Cosway, P. J. de
Loutherbourg, and William Sharp. <note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Benedict Chastanier, <hi rend="i">A Word
of Advice to a Benighted World</hi> (London, 1795) 30-31.</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> Daniel Lysons, <hi rend="i">Collectanea</hi>, A Scrapbook of
Eighteenth-Century Newspaper Clippings in the British Museum, 1: 156-63 on animal magnetism. Also, John Bell,
<hi rend="i">A New System of the World</hi> (London, 1788).</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi><hi rend="i"> Morning Herald</hi> 15 Feb. 1786.</note></p>
        <p>In Mainaduc’s lectures, printed posthumously in 1798 with his portrait by Cosway, there are many
striking similarities to terms and themes in Blake’s work. In April 1786, Mainaduc revealed to an eager
assembly that men and women “possess a power in themselves of which they are ignorant, and want but little
instruction to do more than they are aware of; I open to you an astonishing field, if you dare to cultivate
it, a field which must redouble the religionist’s devotion, confirm the deist in the existence of his God,
and fill the atheist with astonishment.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16"
type="note">16</ref> His first lecture covered “Atmospheres and Emanations of the Form,” which proved that
“emanating atoms continually fly from the earth, and from all its productions; and that, as the earth, so
all its forms are surrounded by atmospheres, and passed through by emanations peculiar to
themselves.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> The “atmospherical
part of the human body” may, by the magnetizer’s effort, “be attracted from, or distended to, any
unlimited distance”; it may then “penetrate any other form in nature.” The healing occurs when through
“the influence of Volition (or Spirit)” the Emanations are “forced out of their natural course” or
“attracted into the Pores of the Operator.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">18</ref> The magnetizer is effective according to the Intention and Energy of his or her
“spiritual Volition.” Mainaduc then gave detailed instructions, such as:
<q>
The Examiner should fix on some particular part of the Patient’s external or internal Form; then, turning
the backs of his hands, with the fingers a little bent, he must vigorously and steadily command the Emanations
and Atmospheres, which derive from that part, to strike his Hands, and must closely attend to whatever
Impressions are produced on them.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
type="note">19</ref></q>
Maria Cosway possessed great “spiritual Volition” and was easily magnetized. As she wrote her lover,
Thomas Jefferson, “I am susceptible and everything that surrounds me has great power to magnetise
me.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Mainaduc xi.</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Mainaduc 28-29.</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Mainaduc 81-83.</note>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Mainaduc 97.</note>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Julian Boyd, ed., <hi rend="i">The Papers of Thomas Jefferson</hi>, 22
vols. (Princeton UP, 1950) 4: 3-4; F. M. Brodie, <hi rend="i">Thomas Jefferson</hi> (New York, 1974)
204-24.</note></p>
        <p>Mainaduc and Chastanier soon faced stiff competition as new rivals entered the field. In France the
Puysegur brothers rediscovered “induced hypnosis” or “magnetic sleep,” in which the entranced patient
spoke with spirits and displayed clairvoyance. In a derivation of the Cabalistic “revolution of
perspective,” the somnambulists saw the inner organs of their patients in externalized visions.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref> Mainaduc complained that this “new food”
of somnambulism is “grasped at with avidity by impostors” and many “entertain their acquaintances with
the wonder of their last comatose dream.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22"
type="note">22</ref> Even worse, “a most scientific lass, wishing me to believe she saw my brain,” said it
“resembled an oyster.” Cosway and Sharp magnetized Henry Tresham (another friend of Blake) and told him he
had a hole in his liver, “the form of which Cosway drew.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n23" type="note">23</ref> Blake probably refers to this magnetic effect when he proclaims: “Their
eyes their ears nostrils &amp; tongues roll outward they behold / What is within now seen without” (E 314).
Moreover, Blake’s strange descriptions of Bowlahoola and Allamanda seem to draw on the magnetizers’
concept of the Archaeus, the ganglion of sympathetic nerves in the abdominal region. 
<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> Gershom Scholem, <hi rend="i">Major Trends in Jewish Mysticism</hi> (New York: Schocken
Books, 1954) 217.</note>
	<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Mainaduc 196.</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> K. Garlick and A. Macintyre, eds., <hi rend="i">The Diary of Joseph
Farington</hi>, 16 vols. (New Haven: Yale UP, 1978) 3: 710.</note></p>
        <p>Paracelsus and Van Helmont believed the Archaeus to be “a sort of demon presiding over the
stomach, acting constantly by means of vital spirits, performing the most important offices in the animal
economy, producing all the organic changes which take place within the corporeal frame.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref> Van Helmont further claimed that by virtue of
the Archaeus, man could be approximated to the realm of spirits. In somnambulistic trance, the “exalted
sensibility” of the epigastric region transferred perception from the brain to the abdomen (including the
erotically susceptible “loins”). The modern magnetizer manipulated the transfer of sensibility from one
organ to another, in order to clear the flow of lucidity (health) from obstruction (disease). Mainaduc taught
that “in Man is comprised in miniature, the entire vegetating system in its greatest perfection.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref> His form is composed of pipes and particles,
“between which the
<pb id="p23-22" n="22"/>
most extensive and minute porosity admits . . . the passage of atoms and fluids.” Similarly, though with
vivid mythic overtones, Blake describes “the Four States of Humanity in its Repose”:
<q>
The First State is in the Head, the Second is in the Heart:<lb/>
The Third in the Loins &amp; Seminal Vessels &amp; the Fourth<lb/>
In the Stomach &amp; Intestines terrible, deadly, unutterable<lb/>
And he whose Gates are opend in those Regions of his Body<lb/>
Can from those Gates view all these wondrous Imaginations<lb/>
(E 134)
</q>
Blake’s principal regions of vision are Bowlahoola, “the Stomach in every individual man,” and
Allamanda, “the Loins &amp; Seminal Vessels” (E 121, 134). His strange physiology was entirely consistent
with that of animal magnetism, especially in its Swedenborgian forms. <note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi> J.
C. Colquhoun, trans., <hi rend="i">Report of the Experiments on Animal Magnetism</hi> (Edinburgh: Robert
Cadell, 1833) 101-03.</note>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi> Mainaduc 31.</note></p>
        <p>Where Mainaduc and his more radical disciples got into trouble was in their technique of stroking
the Archaeus:
<q>
The fluids are to be conducted upward, slowly, softly, and gently . . . [in order to] carry up the fluids from
the stomach to the brain . . . the operation is to commence at the pit of the stomach, and the first intention
must be to separate the plexus, or heap of nerves, situated in that part . . . The nerves must then be
pursued, through the diaphragm up the pleura, and into the skull to the Brain.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">26</ref>
	<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Mainaduc 207.</note></q>
Critics charged them with sexual designs on the women; in fact, this accusation was the real motive for the
French Commission’s hostile report. In an unpublished appendix, sent secretly to the French king, the
commissioners revealed:
<q>
. . . the greater number of women who are magnetised are not really ill . . . their senses are not impaired,
their youth has all its sensibility. Continued proximity, contact, the communication of bodily warmth, and the
mingling of glances . . . effect a communication of sensations and affections. The man who magnetises had
generally the knees of his female patient enclosed between his own . . . the hand is applied to the
hypochondriac region, and sometimes over the ovaries. Touch is exercised over a large extent of surface, and
in the neighborhood of the most sensitive parts of the body . . . the reciprocal attraction of the sexes acts,
of course, with all its force. . . . When this state of crisis approaches, the visage fires by degrees, and
the eyes light up with desire . . . the eyelids now become moist; the breathing hurried and irregular; the
bosom heaves violently and rapidly, and convulsions and sudden twitchings take place in particular limbs, and
sometimes all over the body. In lively and sensitive women, the last stage, the most agreeable termination of
their emotions, is often a convulsion.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27"
type="note">27</ref>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> “Animal Magnetism,” <hi rend="i">British and Foreign Medical
Review</hi> 14 (1839): 9.</note></q>
One critic saw “a woman thrown by a magnetic process into a <hi rend="i">furor uterinus</hi>,” and London
wits ridiculed Maria Cosway and the high-born women who flocked to Mainaduc as Princesses of the “House of
Libidinowsky.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">28</ref>
	<note id="n28"><hi rend="s">28</hi> “Animal Magnetism” 19; <hi rend="i">A Letter to a Physician in the
Country on Animal Magnetism</hi> (London: J. Debrett, 1786) 32.</note></p>
        <p>Undeterred by such criticism and inspired by visions into their patients’ Bowlahoola and
Allamanda, Cosway, Sharp, and Loutherbourg enthusiastically practiced magnetic medicine. At Loutherbourg’s
house in Hammersmith, thousands of patients sought the miracle cure. As Anthony Pasquin wickedly remarked,
“The blind followed the whoopings of the lame” to the “liberal chymists” of the clinic.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">29</ref> Initially with Mainaduc’s approval,
Chastanier opened a magnetic clinic in his residence at 62 Tottenham Court Road, where the Swedenborgian
Freemasons also gathered.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">30</ref> But
Chastanier eventually broke with Mainaduc, charging that he “made the art instrumental to horrid
enormities.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">31</ref> Apparently worried by
the competition of his own pupils, Mainaduc began to require a Masonic-style oath of secrecy from his
clients.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">32</ref> For paying “Brothers,”
he would draw aside the veil of the sacred mysteries: “Here we shall find the <hi rend="i">grand
arcanum</hi>, the steady <hi rend="i">point d’appui</hi>, the <hi rend="i">philosopher’s stone</hi>, and
<hi rend="i">omnium uno</hi>”—all under the Masonic “all-seeing Eye of the Creator.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">33</ref>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">29</hi> Anthony Pasquin [John Williams], <hi rend="i">Memoirs of the Royal
Academicians</hi> (London: H. D. Symonds, 1796) 80-81.</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">30</hi><hi rend="i"> Morning Post</hi> 16 June 1786.</note>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">31</hi><hi rend="i"> Monthly Observer and New Church Record</hi> 1 (Jan.-Dec.
1857): 420.</note>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">32</hi> Mainaduc xi.</note>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">33</hi> Mainaduc 226-28.</note></p>
        <p>Blake probably could not have afforded Mainaduc’s deluxe course, but he may have benefited from
Chastanier’s inexpensive instruction. Blake may also have attended the spin-off lectures of Thomas Holloway,
the engraver, with whom he worked on Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essay on Physiognomy.</hi> (Lavater himself was
an enthusiastic magnetist.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34" type="note">34</ref>)
Following the lead of his brother John, Thomas Holloway gave lectures on animal magnetism which attracted
hundreds of artisans as well as professional people.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35"
type="note">35</ref> The Holloways’ magnetic therapy was so successful that John Newton tried to persuade
the poet William Cowper to accept their offer of treatment. However, a wary Cowper replied:
<q>
With respect to my own initiation into the Secret of Animal Magnetism, I have a thousand doubts. Twice, as you
know, I have been overwhelmed with the blackest despair, and at those times every thing in which I have been
at any period of my life concerned has afforded to the Enemy a handle against me. I tremble therefore almost
at every step I take, lest on some future similar occasion, it should yield him opportunity and furnish him
with means to torment me. Decide for me, if you can. And, in the mean time, . . . best thanks to Mr. Holloway
for his most obliging offer. I am perhaps the only man living who would hesitate a moment whether on such easy
terms he should, or should not accept it. But if he finds another like me, he will make a greater discovery
than even that which he has already made of the principles of this wonderful art.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">36</ref></q>
Cowper’s worry was later echoed by Blake, who resented those magnetic healers who tried to bind “all
Mental Powers by Diseases,” rather than allowing the artist to “spend his soul in Prophecy.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">37</ref>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">34</hi><hi rend="i"> Analytical Review</hi> 6 (1790): 155-56.</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">35</hi><hi rend="i"> World</hi> 2 Oct. 1791; Thomas Holloway, 
<hi rend="i">Memoir</hi> (London, 1827) 29-32.</note>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">36</hi> J. King and C. Ryskamp, eds., <hi rend="i">The Letters and Prose Writings
of William Cowper</hi>, 5 vols. (Oxford: Clarendon, 1979-82) 3: 404-05.</note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">37</hi> David V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Notebook of William Blake</hi> (Oxford:
Clarendon, 1973) N50-51.</note></p>
        <p>As part of their sympathy for the French Revolution and the new egalitarian trends, the Holloways
developed a simplified, democratic form of magnetism.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38"
type="note">38</ref> Though they were both Freemasons and enjoined secrecy on their pupils, they required
neither oath nor bond.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">39</ref> Teaching a
short, simplified form of hypnosis and making no supernatural claims, the Holloways avoided the illuminist
controversies that eventually placed animal magnetism on dangerous political grounds. John Holloway was still
advertising his lectures in 1805, opposite the Shakespeare Gallery. <note id="n38"><hi rend="s">38</hi>
Holloway, <hi rend="i">Memoir</hi> 24-25; Maria, <hi rend="i">The Secret Revealed: or, Animal Magnetism
Displayed</hi> (London: T. Hawkins, 1790) 5-11.</note>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">39</hi> Grand Lodge, London: Atholl Register F., vol. 6, f.487; Index to Moderns,
F series, vol. 14.</note></p>
        <pb id="p23-23" n="23"/>
        <figure n="DoigtMagique.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="729">
          <head>“Le Doigt Magique.”</head>
          <figDesc>Courtesy of Robert Darnton.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p23-24" n="24"/>
        <p>For many of Mainaduc’s students, however, magnetism became increasingly a vehicle for political
radicalism. Darnton points out that as the French Revolution developed, “mesmerists tended increasingly to
neglect the sick in order to decipher hieroglyphics, manipulate magic numbers, communicate with spirits, and
listen to speeches on Egyptian religion.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40"
type="note">40</ref> This development stemmed from the somnambulists’ refined techniques of
vision-inducement as well as a revival of Cabalistic meditation on Hebrew letters and talismans. The
magnetizing Swedenborgians in London were soon linked with Cabalistic developments in France, for they were
visited by three celebrated <hi rend="i">gurus</hi> of Cabalistic Freemasonry—Count Grabianka of the Avignon
<hi rend="i">Illuminés</hi>, “Count” Cagliostro of the Egyptian Rite, and Louis Claude de Saint-Martin of
the <hi rend="i">Elus Coens.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">41</ref>
Their colorful personalities and visionary claims made a lasting impression on the London group, while at the
same time accelerating the turbulent schisms over political and sexual controversies. 
<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">40</hi> Darnton 70.</note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">41</hi> Garrett, <hi rend="i">Respectable</hi> 100-20; Constantin Photiades, 
<hi rend="i">Count Cagliostro</hi> (London: William Rider, 1932); M. Matter, <hi rend="i">Saint-Martin</hi>
(Paris, 1862).</note></p>
        <p>As the English government geared up for a counterrevolutionary crackdown on secret societies,
followers of Swedenborg and Mainaduc were considered fair game for official spies and police. On 4 March 1795,
the <hi rend="i">London Times</hi> charged that Swedenborg was “the Chief of the Somnambulists,” whose
influence on the “revolutionarily exalted” prophets prepared the public mind for “great political
convulsions.” In 1797 the Abbé Barruel (a former Freemason, now an emigré priest) proclaimed in London:
<q>
The brethren of Avignon recognized the <hi rend="i">Illuminés</hi> of Swedenborg as their parent Sect;
neither were they unmindful of the embassy sent them by the Lodge of Hampstead. Under the auspices of 
<hi rend="i">De Mainaduc</hi>, the have seen their disciples thirsting after that <hi rend="i">celestial
Jerusalem</hi>, that <hi rend="i">purifying fire</hi> (for these are the expressions I have heard them make
use of) that was to kindle into general conflagration throughout the earth by means of the French
Revolution—and thus Jacobin Equality and Liberty was to be universally triumphant in the streets of
London.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">42</ref>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">42</hi> Augustin Barruel, <hi rend="i">Memoirs, Illustrating the History of
Jacobinism</hi>, 4 vols. (London: T. Burton, 1797-98) 4: 546.</note></q></p>
        <p>Unintimidated by the crackdown and encouraged by his Swedenborgian readers, the flamboyant William
Belcher published <hi rend="i">Intellectual Electricity, Novum Organum of Vision, and Grand Mystic System . .
. the Connection between the Material and Spiritual World Elucidated, the Medium of Thought Rendered Visible,
Instinct Seems Advancing to Intuition, Politics Assume a Form of Magical Intimation</hi> (London, 1798).
Boldly interpreting mystical vision and sexual passion in electromagnetic terms, Belcher praised the 
<hi rend="i">illuminati</hi> as the only society still practcing “this field of science.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">43</ref> To political radicals like Cosway, who
acquired Belcher’s work, his assertion that “mysticism carried Buonaparte into Egypt, its original
school,” must have rung with millenarial implications.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44"
type="note">44</ref> Among the Swedenborgian and Masonic acquaintances of Cosway and Blake, political charge
and countercharge proliferated, as increasingly polarized radicals and conservatives split into rival
factions. However, the lines were not always clearly drawn, and radical devotées of animal magnetism were
sometimes odd bedfellows of political conservatives. <note id="n43"><hi rend="s">43</hi> William Belcher, 
<hi rend="i">Intellectual Electricity</hi> (London, 1798) i, 27.</note>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">44</hi> Belcher (i); handlist of half the books in Cosway’s library, compiled
by the late Diana Wilson and now at the Huntington Library. I am grateful to Morton D. Paley for informing me
about this list.</note></p>
        <p>Into this complex milieu in 1793-94 walked George Baldwin, who eagerly plunged into magnetic
experiments regardless of their political ramifications.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45"
type="note">45</ref> Home on leave from his post as British Consul in Egypt, Baldwin renewed his acquaintance
with various artists and Swedenborgians. Blake may already have known Baldwin in the period 1781-86, when the
exotic traveler and his beautiful Greek wife, Jane, attracted much attention in London’s social scene.
Cosway and Bartolozzi painted portraits of Mrs. Baldwin, and Joshua Reynolds exhibited “The Fair Greek,”
in full Turkish costume, at the Royal Academy in 1782.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46"
type="note">46</ref> Baldwin also shared Blake’s interest in Druid lore, Ossian, Boehme, Law, and
Paracelsus.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">47</ref> During his adventures in
the Middle East, Baldwin had investigated the contacts between Egypt and India, which he applied to the study
of hieroglyphics.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">48</ref> These inquiries
also fueled his interest in native medicines, with their heavy component of magic and trance. While in London,
he read in <hi rend="i">The Gazeteer and New Daily Advertiser</hi> (6 October 1783) an article on Quinquet’s
“new discoveries in the electric arcana.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49"
type="note">49</ref> He studied the French Commission Report on magnetism in 1784 and interpreted its hostile
criticism as testimony to “the stupendous power” of magnetism.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n50" type="note">50</ref>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">45</hi> “George Baldwin,” <hi rend="i">Dictionary of National
Biography.</hi></note>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">46</hi> Freeman O’Donoghue, <hi rend="i">Catalogue of Engraved British
Portraits . . . in the British Museum</hi> (London, 1910) 1: 107; J. T. H. Baily, <hi rend="i">Francesco
Bartolozzi</hi> (London, 1907).</note>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">47</hi> George Baldwin, <hi rend="i">Mr. Baldwin’s Legacy to His Daughter</hi>
(London: William Bulmer, 1811) 4: 40-45.</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">48</hi> British Museum Additional Manuscripts. 29,198.f.379.</note>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">49</hi> George Baldwin, <hi rend="i">An Investigation into Principles</hi>
(London: George Bulmer, 1801) 31.</note>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">50</hi> Baldwin, <hi rend="i">Legacy</hi> iv.</note></p>
        <p>Fired with enthusiasm for electric and magnetic therapy, Baldwin returned to Egypt in December
1786, where he ordered a continuing stream of literature on animal magnetism. One of these may have been
Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> (London, 1789), with engravings by Blake and Holloway, for
a “Captain Baldwin” subscribed to the first volume. As noted earlier, Lavater was widely viewed as a
fanatic for animal magnetism, and his system of physiognomy was assimilated into the grab-bag of magnetic
literature.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">51</ref> By 1789 Baldwin was
tirelessly experimenting with magnetic therapy and even boasted of finding an effective preventative for the
plague. Believing the disease traveled by “electric sparks,” he advocated the coating of the body with
sweet oils to prevent penetration of the pores.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52"
type="note">52</ref>
	<note id="n51"><hi rend="s">51</hi> Darnton <hi rend="i">passim.</hi></note>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">52</hi> George Baldwin, <hi rend="i">Political Recollections Relative to
Egypt</hi>, 2nd. rev. ed. (London: W. Bulmer, 1802) 127.</note></p>
        <p>In 1793-94 Baldwin returned to London, where he showed off his collection of drawings of Eastern
scenes.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53" type="note">53</ref> He probably revisited Cosway
and his artistic friends, as well as those Swedenborgians who still experimented with magnetic and electric
cures. Baldwin subscribed to George Adams’ <hi rend="i">Lectures on Natural and Experimental Philosophy</hi>
(London, 1794), which combined Swedenborgianism and Freemasonry with advanced magnetic and electric theory.
Blake almost certainly knew Adams, who was also the mentor of Blake’s friend, Dr. John Birch. (Blake would
later praise “Mr. Birch’s Electrical
<pb id="p23-25" n="25"/>
Magic” for relieving his wife’s rheumatism [E 759].) George Adams embodied the contradictory strains among
the Swedenborgians, for he was fascinated by occult and magnetic phenomenon but repelled by the radical
politics which often accompanied its practice. Baldwin shared these polarized opinions but, like Adams in the
1790s, he was willing to keep his feet in both camps in the interest of the “new science.” 
<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">53</hi> Dawson 672.</note></p>
        <p>While he was in London, Baldwin apparently added somnambulistic techniques to his magnetic
repertoire, for on his return to Egypt in late 1794, he plunged into experiments in spirit-communication,
automatic writing, and dream analysis. Could he have learned these from Blake, Cosway, Loutherbourg, Sharp,
and their Swedenborgian friends? In 1794 Blake described his own involvement in spirit-dictation:
<q>
Eternals I hear your call gladly,<lb/>
Dictate swift winged words, &amp; fear not<lb/>
To unfold your dark visions of torment.<lb/>
(E 70)
</q>
In <hi rend="i">Vala</hi>, which he began in 1795, Blake describes various magnetic phenomenon: “ . . . they
behold / What is within now seen without”; Los has “sparks issuing from his hair”; emanations produce
“sweet rapturd trance” (E 314, 332, 371). Most suggestive, though, of Blake’s probable collaboration
with Baldwin is the drawing in Night Nine of a woman dressed in Turkish costume, holding a tambourine, lying
in a trance state on Oriental pillows.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54"
type="note">54</ref> In the earlier portraits of Mrs. Baldwin by Cosway and Reynolds, she holds a tambourine
and sits on a divan, respectively. George Baldwin also dressed in Oriental garb in London and discoursed on
magnetism while lolling on pillows.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">55</ref>
The accompanying speech by Vala seems to echo Baldwin’s new enthusiasm for the “magnetic sleep” which
led to spirit-communication:
<q>
Vala awoke. “When in the pleasant gates of sleep I enter’d,<lb/>
“I saw my Luvah like a spirit stand in the bright air.<lb/>
“Round him stood spirits like me . . .<lb/>
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
he laid his hand on my head,<lb/>
“And when he laid his hand upon me, from the gates of sleep I came.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">56</ref></q>
	<note id="n54"><hi rend="s">54</hi> C. T. Magno and D. V. Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> by William
Blake (Bucknell UP, 1987) 242.</note>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">55</hi> Thomas Wright, <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi>, 2 vols. (London:
Olney, Bucks, 1929) 2: 31.</note>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">56</hi> Magno and Erdman 242.</note></p>
        <p>In Egypt from 1794 to 1798, Baldwin continued his experiments with the “magnetic sleep,” which
he explained as “the discovery of a spiritual influence on the physical temperature of man.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">57</ref> As he witnessed many “elevations of the
soul,” Baldwin became convinced that “no earthly bound could bound this spirit.” Then, in January 1795,
his life changed dramatically when a wandering Italian poet, Casare Avena de Valdieri, arrived in Alexandria
and joined in Baldwin’s sessions. Through the poet’s magnetic trance, Baldwin achieved communication with
the spirit of a young girl, his first love in the 1760s. He rapturously affirmed:
          <figure n="Page128.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="620">
	<head>Page 128 in C. T. Magno and David V. Erdman, The Four Zoas <hi rend="i">by William Blake</hi> (Bucknell
UP, 1987).</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the British Museum.</figDesc>
</figure>
<q>
It is in common tradition over the world, that spirits will come and converse with men; mankind, in general,
hath an involuntary dread of these spirits; why?—for my part I see nothing to dread; or something of the
kind must exist to justify our fears.—I say indeed that these spirits do exist;—must of necessity exist .
. . <ref target="n58" type="note">58</ref></q>
Baldwin and Valdieri magnetized an Arab servant, whose clairvoyant descriptions were verified by witnesses.
But the most astounding of their feats was the massive output of poetry and operas produced by Valdieri from
spirit-dictation. In a trance state, Valdieri claimed to travel through the celestial world, speak with
spirits, and experience a state of ecstatic beatitude. The poetic works, produced by automatic writing,
revealed “amid the most eccentric flights of fancy, an order, an intricacy of arrangement, a regular
confusion, a wilderness of beauties, an harmony of verse, a reach of discovery that shall satisfy his (the
reader’s) mind about the real author of it.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59"
type="note">59</ref> Like Blake in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, Baldwin identified this dictating spirit as the
same Muse who illumined Milton in <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, 1.25. For Baldwin, Blake’s description of
automatic writing would seem precisely accurate:
<pb id="p23-26" n="26"/>
	<q>
. . . Muses who inspire the Poet’s Song,<lb/>
Record the journey of immortal Milton thro’ your Realms<lb/>
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
. . . Come into my hand<lb/>
By your mild power; descending down the Nerves of my right arm<lb/>
From out the Portals of my Brain . . .<lb/>
(E 96)
</q>
	<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">57</hi> Baldwin, <hi rend="i">Investigations</hi> 88.</note>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">58</hi> Baldwin, <hi rend="i">Investigations</hi> 120.</note>
	<note id="n59"><hi rend="s">59</hi> Baldwin, <hi rend="i">Investigations</hi> 93.</note></p>
        <p>To provide a haven for the writing bouts, Baldwin built a special temple within the British
consulary mansion in Alexandria. Baldwin’s artistic friends may have heard about these psychic adventures
from Thomas Hope, the art patron, who returned to London after visiting Baldwin in 1797.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">60</ref> Hope was also interested in the Cabala,
Swedenborgianism, and magnetism; moreover, his brother Henry was a student of Mainaduc.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61" type="note">61</ref> When Napoleon moved into Egypt, Baldwin
opposed the French in a series of complex intrigues. He had to flee Egypt, losing all his property, but
returned with British forces in 1801, where he played a significant role in the defeat of the French. Arriving
back in London in late 1801, Baldwin was treated as a political hero by conservatives and as a psychic hero by
magnetizers. Blake’s allusion to Baldwin suggests his familiarity with both roles. 
<note id="n60"><hi rend="s">60</hi> Dawson 427.</note>
	<note id="n61"><hi rend="s">61</hi> Sandor Baumgarten, <hi rend="i">Le Crépuscule Neo-Classique: Thomas
Hope</hi> (Paris: Didier, 1958) 218-24, 254; also Mainaduc xii.</note></p>
        <p>Immediately upon his arrival, Baldwin arranged for the private printing of <hi rend="i">An
Investigation into Principles</hi> (1801). It was not for sale but was distributed by the author to his
friends. The work traced the history of animal magnetism and told the romantic story of his contact with the
spirit of his lost love. Evidently encouraged by his friends, he next printed privately <hi rend="i">La Prima
Musa Clio</hi> (1802), which included his explanation of automatic writing and the Italian poems of Valdieri.
Though Blake was in Felpham, he may have heard of these works from London friends or from Hayley, who was an
inveterate student of electric and magnetic medicine.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62"
type="note">62</ref> When Blake returned to London in autumn 1803, he evidently joined the magnetic sessions
of Baldwin, Cosway, and their friends. Baldwin soon gained a devoted following. As Thomas Wright observed,
Baldwin was “in respect to the healing art, the Aloysius Horn of his day; he was now famous and lolled on
Oriental cushions amid strange hangings.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63"
type="note">63</ref>
	<note id="n62"><hi rend="s">62</hi> Morchard Bishop, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Hayley</hi> (London: Gollancz,
1951) 95-96.</note>
	<note id="n63"><hi rend="s">63</hi> Wright, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 2: 31.</note></p>
        <p>Baldwin’s courageous commitment to his visionary studies would surely have appealed to Blake. In
<hi rend="i">Mr. Baldwin’s Legacy to His Daughter, or the Divinity of Truth</hi> (1811), he revealed his
enthusiastic philosophy which merged Paracelsus, Van Helmont, Swedenborg, and Druidism into a therapeutic,
visionary science. He had delayed publication of this work because “I have been told, that I shall be called
a <hi rend="i">Visionary</hi>”; however, “I am told by Scripture that where there is no vision the people
perish.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64" type="note">64</ref> In <hi rend="i">B.
A.</hi>’<hi rend="i">s Book of Dreams</hi> (London, 1813), he described his treatment of an extremely
deformed young lady (B. A.), who not only saw visions but greatly improved physically. Blake seems to refer
directly to this case in his <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi>, emblem 19, when he sketches a sick girl on a pallet,
approached by a turbaned, cloaked man. Blake’s odd lines may reflect his ambivalent feelings towards
Baldwin: “The Cripple every step Drudges &amp; labours / And says come learn to walk of me Good
Neighbours.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65" type="note">65</ref> The next lines
scratched out and confused, either condemn the single vision (“doubt”) of Newton, Bacon, and Reynolds, or
possibly scorn the medical treatment of Baldwin: “He is all Experiments from last to first.” On the same
page where Blake criticizes “Cosway, Frazer, and Baldwin,” for merely healing the sick, he shows five
figures grouped in pyramidal form (suggestive of Egypt), who watch over the sickbed of a girl who holds a book
(possibly <hi rend="i">B. A.</hi>’<hi rend="i">s Book of Dreams</hi>).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66" type="note">66</ref>
	<note id="n64"><hi rend="s">64</hi> Baldwin, <hi rend="i">Legacy</hi> iii.</note>
	<note id="n65"><hi rend="s">65</hi> Erdman, <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> N39.</note>
	<note id="n66"><hi rend="s">66</hi> Erdman, <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> N39.</note></p>
        <figure n="N39.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="623">
          <head>N39, emblem 19, from <hi rend="i">The Notebook of William Blake</hi> by David V. Erdman
(Oxford: Clarendon, 1973).</head>
          <figDesc>Courtesy of the British Museum.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p23-27" n="27"/>
        <p>Blake’s identification of Baldwin with “Egypt’s Lake” may point to one reason for their
broken friendship. Blake, whose acquittal of treason charges did not mean he gave up his radicalism, was
possibly put off by Baldwin’s contribution to Napoleon’s defeat in Egypt. In 1802 Baldwin published 
<hi rend="i">Political Recollections Relative to Egypt</hi>, in which he revealed that it was his idea to cut the
canal of Alexandria and let sea water into the dry bed of Lake Mareotis. When carried out by Sir Sydney Smith
on 13 April 1801, the French were cut off from all communication with the interior of Egypt. This led to the
English victory over Napoleon in August. Baldwin carried home “the famous Standard of the Invincible Legion
of Bonaparte,” and he was caught up in the out-burst of patriotic enthusiasm.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">67</ref> Thus, Blake’s phrase, “Baldwin of Egypt’s Lake,” had
definite political connotations. Cosway, on the other hand, seemed to forgive Baldwin his political stance
while benefitting from his magnetic expertise. Still as radical as Blake, Cosway could blithely boast of
witnessing the King’s birthday dinner (while invisible and “in a spiritual capacity”) and then rejoice
exceedingly at the victories of Bonaparte.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68"
type="note">68</ref>
	<note id="n67"><hi rend="s">67</hi> Baldwin, <hi rend="i">Political Recollections</hi> 145.</note>
	<note id="n68"><hi rend="s">68</hi> Garlick and Macintyre, <hi rend="i">Diary</hi> 7: 3096.</note></p>
        <p>The last four lines of Blake’s poem suggest another possible reason for Baldwin’s withdrawal
from Blake. Blake accuses Hayley, Flaxman, and Stothard of prudish concern over his works. Certainly, if
Baldwin saw Blake’s <hi rend="i">Vala</hi> and believed that Mrs. Baldwin was portrayed in Oriental costume,
he may have been offended. Through her diaphanous Turkish veil, her vulva is clearly revealed. For the
Swedenborgian magnetizers of the 1790s, the mystical significance of the female genitals to the visionary
process was considered the highest of “coelestial arcana.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n69" type="note">69</ref> William Belcher proclaimed, “As well almost might Paracelsus make a man,
without female aid, as can be acquired mystic knowledge without woman, the centre of magnetic
attraction.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70" type="note">70</ref> Ebenezer Sibly, a
Swedenborgian Freemason and magnetizer, made a series of Rosicrucian drawings which depicted the vulva as the
center of the Cabalistic universe.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71" type="note">71</ref>
	<note id="n69"><hi rend="s">69</hi> Based on Swedenborg’s descriptions in his <hi rend="i">Journal of
Dreams, Spiritual Diary</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Conjugial Love</hi> (especially #103, 146). See also Magno and
Erdman 158.</note>
	<note id="n70"><hi rend="s">70</hi> Belcher, <hi rend="i">Intellectual</hi> 109.</note>
	<note id="n71"><hi rend="s">71</hi> Ebenezer Sibly, <hi rend="i">The Dumb Made to Speak . . . or the Grand
Arcanum of Adepts.</hi> Manuscript #4594 in Wellcome Institute of History of Medicine.</note></p>
        <p>The radical Swedenborgians among the magnetizers struggled to publish Swedenborg’s more explicit
writings on the methodology of the Cabalistic erotic trance, but their efforts were frustrated by a wave of
counter-revolutionary prudery which developed at the turn of the century. By 1805, Fuseli complained about
prudish objections to naked figures in art, and Thomas Hope feared that nude sculpture might have to be draped
for exhibition.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72" type="note">72</ref> In this new
pre-Victorian climate, the radical magnetizers went underground. The explicit Cabalistic drawings of Sibly and
manuscripts of erotic rituals were never published; rather, they became the provenance of a secretive
Rosicrucian network that gathered at occult bookstores and clandestine lodges in the early decades of the
century.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n73" type="note">73</ref> Cosway and Blake
participated in this network, whose members stimulated a revival of Hebrew and Cabalistic studies, especially
among a new generation of magnetizers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74"
type="note">74</ref>
	<note id="n72"><hi rend="s">72</hi> Garlick and Macintyre, <hi rend="i">Diary</hi> 7: 2518-19.</note>
	<note id="n73"><hi rend="s">73</hi> Sibly, <hi rend="i">Dumb; A Catalogue of Books and Manuscripts . . . on
Astrology, Magic, and Alchymy, etc. . . . the Stock of John Denley</hi> (London, 1820).</note>
	<note id="n74"><hi rend="s">74</hi> Schuchard, <hi rend="i">Freemasonry</hi> 476-505; and more extensively in
<hi rend="i">Men of Desire.</hi></note></p>
        <p>Bindman observes that on his return to London, “Blake’s rejection of the Classics is in the
name of the Hebraic sublime.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75" type="note">75</ref>n his
renewed devotion to Hebrew studies, there may be a clue to the puzzling identity of “Frazer,” the third
member of Blake’s healing trio. A “J” or “I” Frazer appears on Mainaduc’s list of pupils. He may
be the artist, G. Fraser, who painted a striking portrait of Solomon Bennett, a talented Jewish
engraver.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76" type="note">76</ref> Though nothing more is
currently known of G. Fraser, the fact that Cosway was a patron of Bennett makes the possible linkage of Blake
to Bennett (via Frazer and Cosway) worth pursuing. The question of Blake’s access to Hebrew and Cabalistic
instruction, through published sources or personal contacts, continues to perplex scholars.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77" type="note">77</ref> Though the full context of Swedenborgian and
Masonic connections with Jews in London needs extensive investigation, the immediate context of magnetism in
1804-11 makes Solomon Bennett a plausible candidate for a role in Blake’s biography. Besides being an
admirable artist and erudite man of letters, Bennett was the most accomplished Hebrew teacher in London.
Moreover, the connection between magnetic healers and Jewish instructors is consistent with the experiences of
Cosway and Baldwin among the Swedenborgians and students of Mainaduc. Dr. Isaac Benamore, a Jewish physician,
was Mainaduc’s most successful disciple.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n78"
type="note">78</ref> Benamore was still practicing magnetic medicine, in collaboration with various
Swedenborgians, in 1807. Curiously, though William Cowper turned down the Holloway’s offer of magnetic
therapy, he had only praise for Benamore’s treatment of a friend.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n79" type="note">79</ref>
	<note id="n75"><hi rend="s">75</hi> David Bindman, <hi rend="i">Blake as an Artist</hi> (Oxford: Phaidon,
1977) 141.</note>
	<note id="n76"><hi rend="s">76</hi> Alfred Rubens, “Early Anglo-Jewish Artists,” 
<hi rend="i">Transactions of Jewish Historical Society of England</hi> 14 (1935-39): 112-17. The initials to names
on Mainaduc’s list are often inaccurate. Keynes speculated that Blake referred to Alexander Fraser, a minor
painter (<hi rend="i">Blake: Complete Writings</hi>, ed. Geoffrey Keynes [Oxford UP, 1985] 911). But Fraser
lived in Edinburgh until 1813, when he moved to London. Earlier, I speculated that Blake referred to Alexander
Fraser, a Freemason and shorthand writer, who was also a friend of Bennett (Schuchard, 
<hi rend="i">Freemasonry</hi> 478-80). The question remains open.</note>
	<note id="n77"><hi rend="s">77</hi> Sheila Spector, “Kabbalistic Sources—Blake’s and his Critics’,”
<hi rend="i">Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</hi> 17 (1983-84): 84-99.</note>
	<note id="n78"><hi rend="s">78</hi> Rainsford Papers, British Museum Add. Mss. 23,670,f.71; 
<hi rend="i">Monthly Observer and New Church Record</hi> 3 (Jan.-Dec. 1859): 281. Benamore’s son was also a
physician and student of Mainaduc.</note>
	<note id="n79"><hi rend="s">79</hi> Cowper, <hi rend="i">Letters</hi> 3: 404.</note></p>
        <p><hi rend="i">If</hi> Blake knew Solomon Bennett, through the medium of Cosway, Frazer, and their
magnetizing friends, the two would have had much in common, as well as critical differences of religious
opinion. Bennett (1761-1831) came from a Polish family in White Russia and seemed to have absorbed the
peculiar, paradoxical mentality of the Sabbatian Jews of the period.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n80" type="note">80</ref> In his home area, many Jews became Freemasons and aspired to assimilation
with Christians. Bennett recorded “the unbounded veneration I feel for our present Nazarenes . . . from my
infancy I was their admirer, and exerted myself to be their imitator.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81" type="note">81</ref> In 1792 Bennett set out for Copenhagen, determined to pursue
a career in the arts that was impossible at home. He evidently had some contact with the alchemical circle
headed by Prince Charles of Hesse-Cassel, who attempted to unite Christians and Jews in a new Masonic rite of
“Asiatic Brethren,” which synthesized Sabbatian Cabalism and Christian mysticism.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82" type="note">82</ref> It was in this Danish lodge that Blake’s idol Lavater, a
veteran
<pb id="p23-28" n="28"/>
magnetizer, achieved the visionary spirit-communication that made him a convinced Rosicrucian.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83" type="note">83</ref>
	<note id="n80"><hi rend="s">80</hi> Arthur Barnett, “Solomon Bennett, 1761-1838: Artist, Hebraist, and
Controversialist,” <hi rend="i">Transactions of Jewish Historical Society of England</hi> 17 (1951-52):
91-111.</note>
	<note id="n81"><hi rend="s">81</hi> Solomon Bennett, <hi rend="i">The Constancy of Israel</hi>, 2nd. ed.
(London: printed for the author and sold by him at No. 475, Strand, 1812) iv-v.</note>
	<note id="n82"><hi rend="s">82</hi> Jacob Katz, <hi rend="i">Jews and Freemasons in Europe</hi> (Harvard UP,
1970) 27-53.</note>
	<note id="n83"><hi rend="s">83</hi> Antoine Faivre, <hi rend="i">Mystiques, Théosophes et Illuminés au
Siècle des Lumières</hi> (New York: Georg Olms, 1976) 175-90. Fuseli owned Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Reise
nach Copenhagen</hi> and was working on a biography of his friend in the early 1800s.</note></p>
        <p>As Scholem observes, the “Asiatic Brethren” occupied a “no man’s land” between extreme
tendencies of rationalism and mysticism, which it aspired to synthesize in a Christian-Cabalistic
equilibrium.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84" type="note">84</ref> Bennett exemplified
this paradoxical mentality, for he was a skeptical, scientific rationalist, who also studied Cabala and
alchemy. His strikingly engraved portrait of Lorenz Werskoss, a seventeenth-century alchemist, was said to
reflect “his own mystic nature.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n85" type="note">85</ref>
Bennett was elected to the Danish Royal Academy of Art, a singular honor for a Jew at the time. Moving to
Berlin in 1795, Bennett achieved acclaim as a portraitist and evidently mixed in high Jewish-Masonic
circles.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86" type="note">86</ref> However, he chafed under
Prussian anti-Semitism and, seeking a freer climate, he emigrated to London in November 1799. 
<note id="n84"><hi rend="s">84</hi> Gershom Scholem, <hi rend="i">Du frankisme au jacobinisme</hi> (Paris:
Gallimard, 1981) 28.</note>
	<note id="n85"><hi rend="s">85</hi> S. Kirchstein, <hi rend="i">Juedische Graphiker</hi> (Berlin, 1918)
20.</note>
	<note id="n86"><hi rend="s">86</hi> Katz 27-53; Bennett, <hi rend="i">Constancy</hi> 224-25.</note></p>
        <p>Relishing English liberties, Bennett boldly expressed his eclectic and colorful views, compounded
of radical free-thinking and ardent spirituality. Soon rejected as a heretic by orthodox rabbis, whom he
scorned as “insignificant reptiles,” he found supporters among gentile artists, literary men, and
Freemasons.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n87" type="note">87</ref> While studying
voraciously, he eked out a living by engraving and giving Hebrew lessons. William Beechey, who helped Blake in
1805, also helped Bennett that year, by allowing the poverty-stricken Jew to engrave his portrait of the
Prince of Wales (Grand Master of the Freemasons).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n88"
type="note">88</ref> Bennett’s portrait of Shakespeare was used as the frontispiece to the 1807 Stockdale
edition of <hi rend="i">Shakespeare’s Dramatic Works</hi> (the edition used by Coleridge for his
marginalia).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n89" type="note">89</ref> In 1808 Bennett boldly
exhibited his own portrait of his hero, Napoleon, whom he praised in millenarial terms for emancipating the
Jews and spreading tolerance throughout Europe.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n90"
type="note">90</ref>
	<note id="n87"><hi rend="s">87</hi> Bennett, <hi rend="i">Constancy</hi> 216.</note>
	<note id="n88"><hi rend="s">88</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon,
1969) 165; Rubens, “Anglo-Jewish” 114.</note>
	<note id="n89"><hi rend="s">89</hi> Bentley 17; British Museum Catalogue entry for Stockdale edition.</note>
	<note id="n90"><hi rend="s">90</hi> Barnett 96; Bennett, <hi rend="i">Constancy</hi> 5, 228.</note></p>
        <p>Bennett may have met Cosway and Frazer by this time, for they evidently supported his effort to
publish <hi rend="i">The Constancy of Israel</hi> (1809), by “a native of Poland . . . professing the Arts
in London.” Bennett stressed his appreciation for the artists who helped him publish, and Cosway owned the
extremely rare first edition of the work.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n91"
type="note">91</ref> The frontispiece was Bennett’s engraving of his portrait by Fraser. As Kirchstein
observes, Fraser’s portrayal reveals the whole history of Bennett: “In the eyes are a penetrating
spirituality and a quiet pensive melancholy. You can read from his face all his wanderings and striving, all
his intellectual and artistic powers, all his lone battle with life.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n92" type="note">92</ref> Bennett’s book was a learned defense of Judaism in the
face of aggressive propaganda by the newly formed London Society for the Conversion of the Jews. Bennett heard
in some chapels, “a crow from the pulpit, with a human voice,” who ignorantly attacked Jewish beliefs, and
he scorned the “religious barterers” who “spy among the poor, illiterate, and distressed” Jews of
Petticoat-lane and Frying-pan Alley.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n93" type="note">93</ref>
Cosway, who had long been a champion of the Jews, followed the conversionist controversy with interest and
collected many of the treatises put forth by both radical and reactionary “philo-Semites.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n94" type="note">94</ref>
	<note id="n91"><hi rend="s">91</hi> Handlist of Cosway’s library.</note>
	<note id="n92"><hi rend="s">92</hi> Barnett 94.</note>
	<note id="n93"><hi rend="s">93</hi> Bennett, <hi rend="i">Constancy</hi> 34, 206.</note>
	<note id="n94"><hi rend="s">94</hi> Handlist of Cosway’s library.</note></p>
        <p>Though Bennett welcomed Christian students and enjoyed debating with sincere readers of the Hebrew
Bible, he resented those conversionist efforts that were based on ignorant linguistic analysis and
anachronistic Christological interpretations. It may have been Cosway who was the “friend” who showed
Bennett <hi rend="i">An Address to the Jews</hi> (1710), by John Xeres.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n95" type="note">95</ref> Cosway owned a rare copy of the little known work, which
described Xeres’ reasons for abandoning Judaism and embracing Christianity. Bennett then refuted Xeres’
argument that the Cabalists’ notion of a plurality within God was the same as the Christians’
Trinity.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n96" type="note">96</ref> Blake, who was immersed in
Hebrew studies and mystical illustrations of the Old Testament, made his own contribution to the conversionist
controversy with his address “To the Jews” in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> As Bogan notes, in Blake’s
solution, “Hebrew Adam / English Albion joins the two seemingly disparate nations of England and Israel in a
common patriarchal religion.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n97" type="note">97</ref> Even
more suggestive of Blake’s conversionist preoccupation with the Jewish visionary tradition is the
frontispiece to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, in which the illuminator, Los, is dressed like a Hasidic rabbi or
Polish Jew.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n98" type="note">98</ref>
	<note id="n95"><hi rend="s">95</hi> Bennett, <hi rend="i">Constancy</hi> 34, 206.</note>
	<note id="n96"><hi rend="s">96</hi> Bennett, <hi rend="i">Constancy</hi> 105-06.</note>
	<note id="n97"><hi rend="s">97</hi> E 171; J. M. Bogan, “Apocalypse Now: William Blake and the Conversion
of the Jews,” <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi> 19 (1981): 117.</note>
	<note id="n98"><hi rend="s">98</hi> See entry on “William Blake” in <hi rend="i">Encyclopedia
Judaica.</hi></note></p>
        <p>Cosway, Frazer, and their magnetizing friends may have sought out Bennett because of his expertise
in Cabala, for the Jewish mystical traditions of the microcosmic Grand Man underlay the psychic physiology of
animal magnetism. Bennett described his studies in published and manuscript works on “Kabala or Magic, which
are merely extracts from the Hebrew.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n99"
type="note">99</ref> He discusses the Cabalists’ seven names for <hi rend="i">Alohim</hi>, but then urges
that we must “proceed to a more sublime idea of this noble creation of the Microcosm,” for Man’s
“qualities material and spiritual” are the “sublime of all Creations.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n100" type="note">100</ref> In Blake’s address “To the Jews,” he stresses this
Cabalistic concept: “You have a tradition, that Man anciently containd in his mighty limbs all things in
Heaven &amp; Earth” (E 171). Unlike Blake, Cosway, and Baldwin, however, Bennett was determined to maintain
a scientific and rational view of the Cabalistic microcosm. He scorned the revivers of occult notions of
spirits:
<q>
The prophane doctrines of invisible beings who act on mankind, faith in sorcerers, visionaries, dreamers, etc.
which had been but too successful on the human mind are now exploded, except in the brains of some chimerical
individuals, or hypocrites, to dazzle the lowest class of humanity.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n101" type="note">101</ref></q>
	<note id="n99"><hi rend="s">99</hi> Bennett, <hi rend="i">Constancy</hi> 200.</note>
	<note id="n100"><hi rend="s">100</hi> Bennett, <hi rend="i">Constancy</hi> 106-09.</note>
	<note id="n101"><hi rend="s">101</hi> Bennett, <hi rend="i">Constancy</hi> 77.</note></p>
        <p>For Blake, who was enthusiastically describing in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> his celestial journeys
among the Rosicrucian-style “Fairies, Nymphs, Gnomes, and Genii of the Four Elements,” Bennett’s scorn
would have stung. Moreover,
<pb id="p23-29" n="29"/>
Blake’s defense of a “Professor of Sidereal Science” (an astrologer), who was arrested and “the
cabalistical chattels of his profession” confiscated, would undoubtedly have been ridiculed by Bennett as
the product of a low-class, chimerical brain.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n102"
type="note">102</ref> Cosway, however, may have understood Bennett’s desire to distance himself in print
from spirit-communicators and magnetizers. Cosway acquired <hi rend="i">The Supernatural Magazine</hi>
(Dublin, 1809), in which a critic charged that animal magnetism was a diabolical, anti-Christian practice,
imported from France, which had insidious links with the naturalization of the Jews and the
Revolution.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n103" type="note">103</ref> The same magazine
noted that a recent book described the current revival of Rosicrucianism in London, out of the ashes of
Egyptian Masonry, Illuminism, and the New Jerusalem Church.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n104" type="note">104</ref> Bennett may have become disillusioned with those of his Masonic friends
whose interest in Cabalism led them into Rosicrucianism, for, as the radical republican Richard Carlile later
charged, “the drift . . . of these Rosicrucian degrees, is to make Masonry begin in Judaism and end in
Christianity.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n105" type="note">105</ref> Certainly, Blake
seemed to share that “drift,” for he challenged the Jews that “If your tradition that Man contained in
his Limbs, all Animals, is True,” then you should “Take up the Cross O Israel, &amp; follow Jesus” (E
174). <note id="n102"><hi rend="s">102</hi> E 769; “Police . . . Astrology,” <hi rend="i">Oracle and True
Briton</hi> (13 Oct. 1807).</note>
	<note id="n103"><hi rend="s">103</hi><hi rend="i"> The Supernatural Magazine</hi> (Dublin, 1809) 7-9.</note>
	<note id="n104"><hi rend="s">104</hi><hi rend="i"> The Supernatural Magazine</hi> 67-71.</note>
	<note id="n105"><hi rend="s">105</hi> Richard Carlile, ed., <hi rend="i">The Republican</hi>, 12 (1825): 469.
Bennett became the close friend of the Duke of Sussex, who, as Grand Master from 1813 on, struggled to
maintain Jewish rights within Freemasonry and to suppress the exclusively Christian Rosicrucian
degrees.</note></p>
        <p>Frustrated that Cabalism was being turned into “ill digested opinions” by conversionists and
Rosicrucians, Bennett determined to reclaim the Temple of Ezekiel from the Christian visionaries and dreamers
and to root it solidly in actual Jewish history. In February 1811, he announced a new work on the rebuilding
of the Temple of Ezekiel, with an explanation of the Jews’ “newly reformed <hi rend="i">democratical</hi>
or rather theocratical government”:
<q>
Although the explanation of the visionary Temple of Ezekiel upon scientific principles may be objectionable to
some orthodox Jews or Christians, who prefer the mystical to the rational, especially in scriptural matters,
yet I think . . . the prophets (independently of their divine inspiration) were able politicians and men of
science.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n106" type="note">106</ref>
	<note id="n106"><hi rend="s">106</hi> Solomon Bennett, <hi rend="i">The Temple of Ezekiel</hi> (London, 1824)
151.</note></q>
Bennett had prepared for the work a large, fold-out engraving of the Temple of Ezekiel which was considered a
“masterpiece of imagination and technique,” showing his “sound knowledge of architectural
draftsmanship.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n107" type="note">107</ref> It is possible
that Blake’s preoccupation with the architectural design of Ezekiel’s Temple in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> was stimulated by conversations or arguments with Bennett.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n108" type="note">108</ref> Told by a Christian printer that “It is our duty to
suppress everything relating to Hebrew literature,” Bennett turned to his artistic and Masonic friends for
help.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n109" type="note">109</ref> Three current friends or
patrons of Blake—William Frend, Prince Hoare, and Earl Spencer—subscribed to the project.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n110" type="note">110</ref> Another subscriber, the sculptor John
Henning, utilized Bennett’s Hebrew instruction to further his own investigations into alchemy, astrology,
and geomancy (studies Henning shared with John Varley, soon to become Blake’s intimate friend).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n111" type="note">111</ref> Unfortunately, orthodox opposition (both
Jewish and Christian) delayed publication of <hi rend="i">The Temple of Ezekiel</hi> until 1824. As Blake
became more vociferous in his British Israelism, Bennett became more vehement in his Jewish Israelism. Both
men became isolated in their own communities. <note id="n107"><hi rend="s">107</hi> Barnett 96.</note>
	<note id="n108"><hi rend="s">108</hi> See Morton D. Paley, “‘Wonderful Originals’—Blake and Ancient
Sculpture,” in <hi rend="i">Blake in His Time</hi>, eds. R. N. Essick and D. Pearce (Indiana UP, 1978)
183-92.</note>
	<note id="n109"><hi rend="s">109</hi> Bennett, <hi rend="i">Temple</hi> 5.</note>
	<note id="n110"><hi rend="s">110</hi> Bentley 273, 136, 232.</note>
	<note id="n111"><hi rend="s">111</hi> William Bell Scott, <hi rend="i">Autobiographical Notes</hi>, 2 vols.
(New York: Harper’s, 1892) 1:115-20.</note></p>
        <p>Though the withdrawal of Cosway, Baldwin, and Frazer from Blake may have also signaled the
withdrawal of Bennett from their circle, Blake’s break with his magnetizing friends may have been temporary.
In fact, his suspicious and hostile reaction was possibly caused by overindulgence in Cabalistic-magnetic
experiments. Cabalistic texts and Swedenborg’s writings are full of warnings about the dangers of mental
derangement that threaten the intense meditator upon magical arcana.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n112" type="note">112</ref> Podmore discusses the paranoia that often accompanied excessive attempts
at magnetic trances.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n113" type="note">113</ref> The
conviction of persecution by distant enemies, operating by Mesmerism or telepathy, occurred frequently among
the magnetizers of the nineteenth century. Though such paranoia is one of “the commonest delusions of
incipient insanity,” many sane persons who dabble in psychic trances “have not escaped the contagion of
this panic fear.” In 1806 Blake accused Stothard of effacing his drawing of the Canterbury Pilgrims by means
of a “malignant spell.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n114" type="note">114</ref> He
railed against the plots of his steady supporters Hayley and Flaxman. The tolerant George Cumberland noted
that he seemed “crack’d” and “dimm’d with superstition,” while Robert Southey pitied his obvious
madness.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n115" type="note">115</ref> Curiously, Seymour Kirkup
also diagnosed Blake as insane, a verdict Kirkup later retracted when he became an animal magnetizer.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n116" type="note">116</ref> Bentley points out that between 1807 and
1812, Blake seemed to lose his firm grasp of the nature and limits of reality:
<q>
He sometimes seems to have thought of the spiritual world as supplanting rather than supplementing the
ordinary world of causality. More and more frequently the spirits seem to have been controlling Blake rather
than merely advising him.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n117" type="note">117</ref></q>
	<note id="n112"><hi rend="s">112</hi> Sheila Spector, <hi rend="i">Jewish Mysticism</hi> (New York: Garland,
1984) xi; Swedenborg’s <hi rend="i">Journal of Dreams</hi> and <hi rend="i">Spiritual Diary
passim.</hi></note>
	<note id="n113"><hi rend="s">113</hi> Frank Podmore, <hi rend="i">From Mesmer to Christian Science</hi> (New
York: University Books, 1963) 258.</note>
	<note id="n114"><hi rend="s">114</hi> Bentley 180.</note>
	<note id="n115"><hi rend="s">115</hi> Bentley 229, 236.</note>
	<note id="n116"><hi rend="s">116</hi> W. M. Rossetti, <hi rend="i">Rossetti Papers</hi> (London, 1903)
171-72.</note>
	<note id="n117"><hi rend="s">117</hi> Bentley 180.</note></p>
        <p>Blake’s insistence that animal magnetism include exorcism—“he casts out devils”—may have
smacked of magical megalomania to his friends. However, his plight would have been well understood by Benedict
Chastanier, the former “powerful assistant” to Mainaduc. After playing a lead role in disseminating animal
magnetism, Chastanier “at last found out its evil tendency, and like an honest man first abandoned the
practice and next exposed it.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n118" type="note">118</ref>
Still friendly with Cosway in the early 1800s, Chastanier may have influenced Cosway’s withdrawal from
Blake’s essentially magical practice.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n119"
type="note">119</ref> As Chastanier explained in 1795, animal magnetism was
<pb id="p23-30" n="30"/>
          <figure n="Temple.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="428">
	<head>“The Temple of Ezekiel.”</head>
	<figDesc>Engraving, 26½ × 20½ inches. Designed by Bennett in the 1790s, engraved c. 1809-10, and published
in 1824 in Bennett’s book of the same title.</figDesc>
</figure>
certainly a real and powerful science, which only increased its spiritual dangers:
<q>
. . . the very great danger there is for a man to meddle with any Science that openeth to them a freer
communication with the world of Spirits, than that they naturally are to have; for as every man is by nature
attached to his own peculiar evil, (and there is no Man, nor even any Angel, also free from evil,) the Spirits
with whom he may thus communicate, can but confirm him more and more into that evil, peculiarly annexed to his
own nature, and thus become an insur-mountable bar to his Regeneration.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n120" type="note">120</ref></q>
	<note id="n118"><hi rend="s">118</hi> William Spence, <hi rend="i">Essays in Divinity and Physic</hi>
(London: Robert Hindmarsh, 1792) 58.</note>
	<note id="n119"><hi rend="s">119</hi> Rainsford Papers, British Museum Add. Mss. 23, 670, vol.
2.f.275.</note>
	<note id="n120"><hi rend="s">120</hi> Chastanier 31.</note></p>
        <p>Despite the timidity or genuine worry of his magnetizing friends, Blake was committed to his
“perilous adventure,” regardless of political, erotic, or psychic dangers. Though he would be driven to
note, “Jan<hi rend="s">ry</hi>. 20. 1807 between Two &amp; Seven in the Evening—Despair,” he could also
boast in happier times, “excuse my enthusiasm or rather madness, for I am really drunk with intellectual
vision” (E 733, 694, 757).</p>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p23-31-32" n="31-32" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
