<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>23.2.gourlay</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Greg Brown, Songs of Innocence and of Experience</title>
        <author n="Gourlay">Alexander S. Gourlay</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1989</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1989</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">23.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Manging Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>Martin Bidney</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Michael Grenfell</name>
              <name>Desmond King-Hele</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Dena Bain Taylor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1989"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_23">
    <body>
	<pb id="p23-96" n="96"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-23-2-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Greg Brown, <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience.</hi> Red House
Records, RHR14, 1986. Cassette, $9.00, LP $9.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Alexander S.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Gourlay</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Greg Brown’s contributions to the growing number of musical arrangements for Blake’s 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> will be of interest not only to students and teachers of Blake, but also to everyone who
thinks about the relationship between lyric poems and popular songs. Brown is most familiar to national
audiences from Garrison Keillor’s <hi rend="i">Prairie Home Companion</hi>, where he appeared as a musical
celebrator of small-town midwestern life. He is a singer and guitarist, and writes exceedingly diverse songs
on a variety of subjects other than small-town life. These range from jazz ballads to spare country songs in
the manner of Jimmie Rodgers to imitations of traditional songs so authentic-sounding that they are sometimes
taken by folk purists to be as old as the hills. His biggest commercial hit so far was recorded by Carlos
Santana and Willie Nelson in an improbable duet.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53"
type="note">1</ref>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">1</hi> The song, “They All Went to Mexico,” was released as a single (and
made the Top Ten in the Netherlands); it appears on Nelson’s <hi rend="i">Half Nelson</hi> LP on Columbia
and on Santana’s <hi rend="i">Havana Moon</hi>, also on Columbia.</note></p>
          <p>On this recording of sixteen arrangements of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> Brown is very ably
accompanied by Angus Foster on bass, Michael Doucet on violin, Peter Ostroushko on violin and mandolin, and
Dave Moore on button accordion, harmonica, and pan pipes; the last two musicians, both regulars on 
<hi rend="i">Prairie Home Companion</hi>, are also songwriters and solo artists with their own followings. These
performances have been arranged only loosely; Brown’s singing and guitar are backed up by accompaniments
that sound largely improvised. If Brown followed his usual practice, he and the sidemen settled on ad hoc
arrangements in rehearsal, probably in the studio, and then recorded the bulk of the parts together in a
single take. This procedure gives the recordings an entirely appropriate feeling of spontaneity and
informality, even if it results as well in occasional moments of aimless noodling; these performers are all
experts at improvisation, and some of them have worked with Brown for years.</p>
          <p>Brown’s settings are extraordinary in several respects. For one thing, this seems to me to be
by far the most successful attempt ever to put the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> to something like traditional
popular melodies (I don’t recognize any wholesale borrowings, but the songs incorporate jazz, blues, Irish
fiddle tunes and many other things here and there). Brown’s background as a popular songwriter is evident in
the dexterous weighing of the rhythm, stress, meter, and melody in his phrasing; the results will startle
those accustomed to art-song arrangements of these and similar lyric poems, which tend to work against the
grain of the spoken word. Although Brown was aware of the work of Ralph Vaughan Williams and others, he
reports in conversation that he paid no attention to previous settings; nor did he attempt to be authentic in
any historical sense. Most listeners will agree that these performances are not only extraordinarily sensitive
to Blake’s complexities and ironies, and that some work as popular songs in their own right, but also that
they are authentic in spirit, reflecting music in the air today (and relatively modern instrumentation) as
well as melodies that were around in eighteenth-century London.</p>
          <p>Brown’s bass-baritone voice might appear to present a difficulty in that it obviously can’t
cover all the personae called for by the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, but this is not as serious a problem as it
might seem. For example, “The Lamb” must be understood as having an innocent speaker, presumably the boy
shown in the illustration. But Brown’s performance in deep, rolling tones interposes an inconsequential
additional distance, and the effect is successful—far more successful than, say, a formal performance of the
song by even the most accomplished child. At the same time, the melody is simple enough that we can imagine a
boy singing it to himself, or to a lamb.</p>
          <p>This is a consistently thoughtful and sensitive treatment of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, even if
it was undertaken in a spirit of genial distaste for most Blake criticism and is never merely reverent. Brown
sometimes makes minor changes and additions in the individual songs in order to create verses and choruses,
but he is mostly careful with Blake’s words and the work in general evinces a subtle reader’s appreciation
of his ironies. Certainly the
<pb id="p23-97" n="97"/>
<figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
choice of songs reflects a better understanding of the contrary states than the typical selection in poetry
anthologies. One side of the record is devoted to “Innocence” (“Introduction,” “The Lamb,”
“Infant Joy,” “The Chimney Sweeper,” “The Ecchoing Green,” “Night,” “On Anothers Sorrow”),
and the other to “Experience” (“The Tyger,” “The Angel,” “The Garden of Love,” “Infant
Sorrow,” “Holy Thursday,” “Ah! Sunflower,” “The Little Vagabond,” “The Poison Tree,”
“London”).</p>
          <p>At one point in writing this review I contemplated adapting Coleridge’s graphic grading system
for the original <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>—“Night,” for instance, doesn’t do much for me, whereas the
rollicking “Little Vagabond” seems just right—but listeners can surely make judgments about individual
performances for themselves. Not all
<pb id="p23-98" n="98"/>
the ensemble performances are equally satisfactory, and I sometimes found myself preferring some sparer
arrangements that Brown recorded informally a few years ago. But even the songs that don’t quite work are
illuminating, especially because Brown finds so many ways to complement and complicate the metrical
stresses—as I listened to this record, I couldn’t help feeling that I didn’t know the poems as well as I
thought I did.</p>
          <p>This should also be a useful tool in teaching. W. J. T. Mitchell reports that he sings the songs
himself to his own arrangements when teaching them, and for those with his talents that is probably the best
approach. But Brown’s performances (and perhaps his arrangements) may help many of the rest of us who teach
the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> to students who are not yet comfortable with poetry on the page, especially
because these versions are so unintimidating and their idiom is so familiar to students. One runs the risk, of
course, of fixing their imaginations upon one interpretation of the poems, but one also gains from having them
hear them as songs, and catchy songs at that.</p>
          <p>The record is on a minor label, Red House Records, but it is distributed by Rounder Records on
the East Coast and can be obtained through record stores almost anywhere. Or, write to Red House Records at P.
O. Box 4044, St. Paul, MN 55104.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
