<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>23.2.butlin</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Six New Early Drawings by William Blake and a Reattribution</title>
        <author n="Butlin">Martin Butlin</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1989</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1989</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">23.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Manging Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>Martin Bidney</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Michael Grenfell</name>
              <name>Desmond King-Hele</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Dena Bain Taylor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1989"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_23">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-23-2-0008">
        <pb id="p23-107" n="107"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Six New Early Drawings by William Blake and a Reattribution</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Martin <name>Butlin</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>No fewer than four early drawings by Blake turned up in Bond Street in the summer of 1988; in
fact I first saw all of them within the space of ten days or so in June. Two belong to dealers, while the
other two belong to clients of these dealers from whom I learned of their existence. Seeing these early works,
and relating them to other works of the same kind by Blake, finally convinced me of the authenticity of a
large drawing in the Fogg Museum of Art that I had previously rejected as being by Blake and omitted from my
catalogue.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72" type="note">1</ref> Four of these drawings are
in pen and wash, usually over a slight pencil underdrawing, while the fifth is in pencil alone. The four pen
and wash drawings have all previously been attributed to John Flaxman, an understandable attribution but one
that does not bear comparison with works in the same technique and general neoclassical manner that can
definitely be attributed to him. On the other hand they fall naturally into place among the large group of
“Miscellaneous Early Works, Mainly in Pen and Wash” dating from c. 1775 to c. 1790, included in my
catalogue as nos. 71-183. This group was based around certain key works
            <figure n="angels.23.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="568">
	<head>1. William Blake, “Angels Gathered Around a Book,” c. 1785.</head>
	<figDesc>Pen and wash over pencil, 32.5 × 40.5 cm. Colnaghi, London.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p23-108" n="108"/>
            <figure n="moses.23.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="556">
	<head>2. William Blake, “Moses with the Tablets of the Law,” c. 1780-85.</head>
	<figDesc>Pencil, 20.8 × 14.6 cm. Private collection, Great Britain.</figDesc>
</figure>
that related directly to well-documented works by Blake, such as the two sketches (B 159 recto and verso) for
“Joseph Making Himself Known to his Brethren,” exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1785 (B 157). 
<note id="n72"><hi rend="s">1</hi> I am indebted to Andrew Wyld of Thos. Agnew &amp; Sons Ltd. and Mark Fisher
formerly of Colnaghi for helping with the works belonging to their galleries and in private collections. I was
able to see the drawings in the Fogg Museum of Art during a recent visit, thanks to the helpfulness of the
staff there; I had first seen the drawing in 1966 when I failed to recognize its authorship.
                            <p>The drawing at Agnew’s (illus. 3) was included in <hi rend="i">Agnew’s
116th Exhibition of Watercolours and Drawings</hi>, February-March 1989 (22 illus.); it now belongs to a
British private collection.</p>
	<p>My catalogue, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>, was published in 1981. The
abbreviations “B 159,” etc. in my text refer to the catalogue numbers in this publication, where all the
works referred to are illustrated.</p></note></p>
          <p>The first of these newly discovered drawings (illus. 1) shows a group of haloed figures standing
around a table bearing a book with a Hebrew inscription; rays of light emanate from the book. Allowing for the
difficulties most people find in describing works of art accurately, it is just possible that this drawing is
that described by the daughter of Charles Augustus Tulk, the Swedenborgian friend of Flaxman and patron of
Blake, as one of a group of drawings for Swedenborg’s “Memorable Relations”: “A Female Angel
Instructing a Number of Children in the Spiritual World” (B128). A similar book appears in the drawing in
pen and watercolor in the Tate
            <figure n="children.23.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="392">
	<head>3. William Blake, “Three Naked Children Crouching Around a Source of Light,” c. 1785.</head>
	<figDesc>Pen and wash over pencil, 14.3 × 19.2 cm. Thos. Agnew &amp; Sons Ltd., London.</figDesc>
</figure>
            <figure n="seated.23.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="464">
	<head>4. William Blake, “A Young Man Seated Behind a Stone Slab,” c.1785.</head>
	<figDesc>Pen and wash over pencil, 14.3 × 14.5 cm. Private collection, London.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p23-109" n="109"/>
            <figure n="sight.23.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="617">
	<head>5. William Blake, called “The First Sight of the Spiritual World,” c. 1785.</head>
	<figDesc>Pen and wash over pencil, irregular, 48.5 × 56 cm. Courtesy of the Harvard University Art Museums
(Fogg Art Museum; bequest of Grenville L. Winthrop).</figDesc>
</figure>
Gallery, at present called “An Allegory of the Bible” (B 127). This drawing is fairly exceptional among
Blake’s early works in showing a good feeling for the solidity of the body beneath the flowing draperies,
and the sense of graceful contraposto, particularly in the foremost angel on the right, is particularly
striking; it can be compared with that of the figure of Christ in the version of “The Good Farmer” in the
collection of Robert N. Essick (B 122 recto) or the left-hand fairy in “Oberon, Titania and Puck with
Fairies Dancing” in the Tate Gallery (B 161). What is particularly noticeable is the sense of movement in
the figures on the right (how many angels exactly are there?), produced by the pentimenti by which Blake has
changed the position of the angel’s leg.</p>
          <p>Something of the same effect is seen in the pencil drawing of “Moses and the Tablets of the
Law” (illus. 2), another of the newly discovered drawings. Pencil drawings of this type are exceptionally
difficult to date but this one would seem to relate to the series of pen and wash drawings dealing with the
story of Moses, dated by me to the first half of the 1780s (B 111-15). The forcefulness of this drawing,
linked with a certain stiffness and angularity of line, is found in such pencil drawings as that of a “Man
with Arms Upraised, Perhaps the Resurrection” in the National Gallery of Art (B 78 verso) and “The
Resurrection of the Dead” in an American private collection (B 79), both dated by me to the early 1780s.</p>
          <p>Another of the newly discovered drawings in pen and wash (illus. 3) shows three naked children
crouched round a bowl-like source of light by which they are illuminated. As in the case of the drawing of
“Angels Gathered Around a Book” the precise subject is difficult to ascertain, but again one senses a
reference to Swedenborg. The relatively heavy outlines are, allowing for the difference in scale, relatively
close to the drawings for the Job and Ezekiel engravings already mentioned.</p>
          <p>Very similar in style is the drawing (illus. 4) of a young man shown seated behind a slab of
stone on which he rests his arms, though this is carried slightly further in that the muscles of the arms and
legs are suggested by lines within the general outlines. Mark Fisher has suggested that this might be a design
for a bookplate.</p>
          <p>In the large drawing in the Fogg Museum (illus. 5)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n73" type="note">2</ref> the internal modeling of the foremost figure goes further, and is executed in
a much more delicate way with a pen or the point of a brush, the same fine line being found in the figures and
horses rushing across from right to left in the background. The old man holding his arms outstretched above
the kneeling youth is of the type found in the pen and ink drawings of Moses already mentioned, while a
parallel for the head of the young man can also be found in one of these, “The Children of Israel Receiving
the Ten Commandments from Moses” in the Israel Museum, Jerusalem (B 114). The use of fine line to define
internal forms is similar to that in the drawing, apparently after the antique, of “Charon” in the Tate
Gallery (B 178 recto) and in the copies after
            <figure n="brethren.23.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="507">
	<head>6. William Blake, sketch for “Joseph’s Brethren Bowing Before Him,” c. 1785.</head>
	<figDesc>Pen and wash over pencil, 33.5 × 47.4 cm. Courtesy of Sammlung der Zeichnungen, National-Galerie,
Staatliche Museum, Berlin, DDR.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p23-110" n="110"/>
            <figure n="job.23.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="700" height="513">
	<head>7. William Blake, “The Complaint of Job,” c. 1785.</head>
	<figDesc>Pen and Indian ink, 33.2 × 47.1 cm. Thomas Gibson Fine Art Ltd.</figDesc>
</figure>
d’Hancarville in the British Museum (B 174 and 175). The helmet of the figure on the right in the background
also suggests a classical subject though it is difficult to see what this might be. 
<note id="n73"><hi rend="s">2</hi> No. 9 in the catalogue, with the title “The First Sight of the Spiritual World,” no size
or medium given.</note></p>
          <p>Little if anything is known of the history of these drawings. The one in the Fogg Museum was
purchased by Grenville L. Winthrop from A. J. Finberg at the Cotswold Gallery in London in 1923 and was
displayed in the exhibition of <hi rend="i">Drawings by J. M. W. Turner, William Blake, Samuel Palmer and
Others</hi> held there in July 1923. On the back has been written the number “504” and, more
interestingly, “This belongs to JLG/by Blake.” However, the only JLG that I can trace is Mrs. John L.
Gardner who, with George N. Black, presented the Thomas Butts set of illustrations of Milton’s 
<hi rend="i">Comus</hi> to the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston in 1890. If the drawing did belong to John L. Gardner
it would have to have returned to London by 1923. The other drawings have no history before they turned up,
separately, in the art trade recently. The drawing of “Angels Gathered Around a Book” turned up, perhaps
significantly, in Germany, the others in Britain.</p>
          <p>Since the appearance of the four new drawings discussed above, my friend David Bindman has kindly
drawn my attention to another of the early group of pen and wash drawings, found by him in the
National-Galerie in East Berlin. This is in fact an additional key work in dating the whole group, being a
preliminary sketch for “Joseph’s Brethren Bowing Before Him” (illus. 6), one of the three watercolors of
Joseph subjects exhibited at the Royal Academy in 1785 and now in the Fitzwilliam Museum, Cambridge (B 155).
This new discovery
<pb id="p23-111" n="111"/>
means that we now have sketches for all three of the group, one of which is the sketch with a certain amount
of color for “Joseph Ordering Simeon to be Bound” now in a private collection, Milan (B 158); the two
others, in pen and ink, the recto and verso of a sheet, are in the Royal Collection at Windsor Castle (B 159).
What is interesting about the new sketch is that it differs considerably from the final watercolor—Joseph is
placed on the opposite side of the composition, though in the same pose deriving from the antique—with the
prominent figure, also from the antique, of a girl holding a large dish on her head again filling the space
between Joseph and his brethren.</p>
          <p>It never rains but it pours! No sooner had I posted off the preceding paragraph to the ever
compliant editors of <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> than yet another of the early pen and wash drawings appeared,
this time one included in my catalogue as “Untraced since 1928” (B 163; illus. 7)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">3</ref>. This is the intermediate sketch of “The Complaint of
Job” of about 1785, falling, as Geoffrey Keynes said it did, between the verso of the drawing in the Tate
Gallery (on which Blake takes the figure of Job’s wife from the recto and redraws it in the pose that he was
to retain through the subsequent sketches until it appeared in the engraving “Job. What is Man That Thou
Shouldest Try Him Every Moment?”) and the more finished pen and wash drawing formerly in the collection of
T. E. Hanley and now in the Fine Art Museums of San Francisco (B 164). It bears exactly the same relationship
to the drawing in San Francisco as does the Homans drawing of “The Death of Ezekiel’s Wife” to the more
finished version in the Philadelphia Museum of Art (B 165 and 166). <note id="n74"><hi rend="s">3</hi> This
work has been brought to my attention through the good offices of Mrs. Gottesman at Thomas Gibson Fine Art
Ltd. It measures 13 1/16 × 18½ in. (33.2 × 47.1 cm) and is on laid paper. The recto is in pen and wash, the
verso, which is an upright, in pencil. It has apparently remained in a single British private collection since
the sale of 1928.</note></p>
          <p>The drawing on the reverse also fits with what was known about the formerly untraced drawing,
showing a full-length figure, fully draped, with wild locks and beard as described in the Sotheby’s sale
catalogue for 17-21 December 1928 (illus. 8). The appearance of this drawing on the reverse was the more
exciting because of its close resemblance to the two drawings labeled “Ossian” in the newly rediscovered
larger Blake-Varley sketchbook, sold at Sotheby’s on 21 March 1989<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n75" type="note">4</ref>. It resembles both the double-page spread showing the figure full length
holding his harp on the edge of a cliff with a landscape to the left, and the page devoted to his head alone.
Moreover at first glance the drawing looked to be later in style than that on the recto. However, two factors
suggest that it is more likely to date from about the same time as the recto or slightly earlier. First, the
figure fits uneasily on the page as it now stands, cramped at the top and with plenty of space below. Indeed
there are signs that the page was cut and the paper trimmed all round. The composition of “The Complaint of
Job” on the recto however fits the page very nicely, with slightly more space around the figures,
particularly on the left (which is the top of the verso), than in the more finished pen and wash drawing in
San Francisco. This implies that the drawing on the verso was probably done first, the paper then cut,
particularly at the top, and then used for the recto. Moreover the subject of the drawing on the verso, though
prefiguring the Ossian of the larger Blake-Varley sketchbook, could equally well be the Bard; the drawing
seems most likely to have been a preliminary sketch for the lost work, almost certainly a watercolor,
exhibited by Blake at the Royal Academy in 1785 as “The Bard, from Gray” (B 160). The composition lacks
the figures of the royal train and deceased bards that appear in the tempera included by Blake in his
exhibition in 1809 and now in the Tate Gallery (B 655), but the other evidence suggests that we now have, in
this newly discovered drawing, at least an idea of the appearance of the 1785 exhibit. It was this work of his
youth to which Blake returned when asked by John Varley to see Ossian in a vision. 
<note id="n75"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Lot 184. The sketchbook is fully illustrated in a separate catalogue devoted to this one item.
The double spread of Ossian occurs on pages 33 verso and 34 recto, and the single head on the following page,
34 verso.</note></p>
          <figure n="bard.23.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="556">
            <head>8. Sketch for “The Bard, from Gray,” c. 1785.</head>
            <figDesc>Pencil, 47.1 × 33.2 cm. Verso of “The Complaint of Job.” Thomas Gibson Fine Art
Ltd.</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p23-112" n="112" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
