<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>23.2.baine</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Robert D. Denham, Northrop Frye: An Annotated Bibliography of Primary and
Secondary Sources</title>
        <author n="Baine">Rodney M. Baine</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1989</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1989</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">23.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Manging Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>Martin Bidney</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Michael Grenfell</name>
              <name>Desmond King-Hele</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Dena Bain Taylor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1989"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_23">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-23-2-0007">
        <pb id="p23-88" n="88"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Robert D. Denham, <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye: An Annotated Bibliography of
Primary and Secondary Sources.</hi> Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1987. xviii + 449 pp.
$50.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Rodney M. <name>Baine</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Robert Denham’s <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye: An Annotated Bibliography of Primary and Secondary
Sources</hi> updates and replaces his earlier <hi rend="i">Northrop Frye: An Enumerative Bibliography</hi>
(1974) and its four supplements and addenda. It is divided into two sections: Frye’s own writings (the
primary sources) and criticism thereof (the secondary sources). It has two indexes: a name and subject index
and a title index.</p>
          <p>Although arranged chronologically in the earlier bibliography, Frye’s writings are here broken
up into ten divisions: books; books edited; monographs; essays, interviews and dialogues; audio and visual
recordings; manuscripts; unpublished correspondence; and a catchall division which lists Frye’s
undergraduate writings, his university reports, his letters to periodicals, and even his replies to
questionnaires. Within each section Frye’s writings appear chronologically except for the manuscripts and
unpublished correspondence, where several thousand items are listed according to the special collections or
archives where they are held. All editions, reprints, and translations are listed (up to June 1987) along with
the main entry; and a system of cross-reference and a comprehensive index of titles insure that a reader will
find any item (except book reviews). All these entries are followed by a descriptive statement, varying in
length according to the importance, length, and complexity of Frye’s original.</p>
          <p>The secondary sources appear in six divisions: books and collections of essays; essays and parts
of books; reviews, where each of Frye’s twenty-two books receives separate treatment; dissertations and
theses; bibliographies; and a miscellaneous section which includes news stories, biographical notices,
letters, and anecdotes. In the earlier bibliography Denham included summaries for “Writings about Frye’s
Criticism,” which reappear here virtually unchanged, but he now includes expositions for almost all the
secondary materials, with a “brief notice” for short and unimportant entries. All are arranged by author;
but for those who wish to trace changes of attitude toward Frye’s work, Denham has
<figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
added an appendix, “A Chronological Listing of Entry Numbers for Books and Essays about Frye’s
Criticism.”</p>
          <p>Denham’s new bibliography is a welcome tool for researchers into the work of an author whose
writings have established him as probably the most influential humanistic critic living, an author who is
still productive. His writings on Blake have established him as surely the most seminal influence in Blake
studies. Although the analytical arrangement makes the new bibliography somewhat difficult to use, this
reviewer has only two other, relatively minor complaints to register. In the earlier book Denham made some
attempt to winnow the wheat from the chaff. Here he has excised all his praise and denigration. Moreover, in
the earlier bibliography Denham informed his readers that the reviews were not listed in the title index.
However, on page 430 of the <hi rend="i">Annotated Bibliography</hi> the opening statement leads a reader to
expect to find them in the title index. He does not.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
