<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>23.2.worrall</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Geoff Bennington and Ian McLeod, trans., Jacques Derrida, The Truth in Painting</title>
        <author n="Worrall">David Worrall</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1989</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1989</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">23.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Manging Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>Martin Bidney</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Michael Grenfell</name>
              <name>Desmond King-Hele</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Dena Bain Taylor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1989"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_23">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-23-2-0007">
        <pb id="p23-89" n="89"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Jacques Derrida. <hi rend="i">The Truth in Painting.</hi> Trans. by Geoff
Bennington and Ian McLeod. Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press, 1987. xiv + 386 pp. $49.95
cloth/$19.95 paper.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">David</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Worrall</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>“I owe you the truth in painting and I will tell it to you” (Paul Cézanne to Emile Bernard,
23 October 1905). Derrida’s book first appeared in France in 1978 and is largely a compilation of writings
from the mid 1970s. What is “the truth in painting” and does Derrida tell it to you? Do you need to know
what deconstruction means to the visual arts? The answer to the former is partially explained by this review
but it could actually be the latter question which proves to be of immediate and wider interest.</p>
          <p>At the end of March 1988 London’s Tate Gallery played host to “the world’s first symposium
on art, architecture and Deconstruction.” Derrida was to have appeared at this packed conference but it
turned out he was absent except in the reproductive (what else?) medium of a video interview specially
recorded for the event. The Tate symposium was breezily covered by most of the quality newspapers but there
was one substantial report by David Lodge (<hi rend="i">The Guardian</hi> 8 April 1988, London ed.: 25)
However, a more lasting testament to deconstructive movements in art and architecture is the publication of
two special issues from the Academy Group. The issue of <hi rend="i">Art</hi> &amp; <hi rend="i">Design</hi>
is devoted to “The New Modernism: Deconstructionist Tendencies in Art” (4[1988]), while 
<hi rend="i">Architectural Design</hi> covers “Deconstruction in Architecture” (58 [1988]). Of the two, the
<hi rend="i">Architectural Design</hi> issue is probably the more substantial and scholarly although the 
<hi rend="i">Art</hi> &amp; <hi rend="i">Design</hi> number has excellent color reproductions of work by Adami
(discussed below) as well as a spicy set of aphorisms by the translator of <hi rend="i">The Truth in
Painting</hi>, Geoff Bennington (“Deconstruction is Not What You Think” 6-7). <hi rend="i">The Truth in
Painting</hi> is also excerpted in the magazine.</p>
          <p>There are several reasons why deconstructive architecture will probably be of future note (or
notoriety). Deconstructive buildings have already been built and deconstructive architects seem already to
have identified their own high-priests and coteries grouped around Bernard Tschumi, Peter Eisenman, Frank
Gehry, and Zaha Hadid. It is also the case that Derrida has been recently thinking (or has been asked to
think) about architecture
<figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
especially in connection with his contributions and dialogues with Peter Eisenman and Bernard Tschumi. There
is a spiky interview in <hi rend="i">Architectural Design</hi> between Charles Jencks and Eisenman (“that is
silly of you . . . there’s no need to get on your high-horse and dichotomise. . . .”) with lots of talk of
<hi rend="i">différance</hi>, intertextuality, and the dislocation of the center. Derrida has contributed
“an unfinished text that he was working on from Plato’s <hi rend="i">Timaeus</hi>” for a Choral or Chora
work of Eisenman’s: “We finally forced Jacques to draw something. He then drew the lyre which became both
the figure and the frame for the site” (or <hi rend="i">liar</hi>, Eisenman concedes). Derrida has also
written on Bernard Tschumi’s “Parc de la Villette” which is now well under construction and whose sets
of gardens have a collaborative contribution from Jean-Francois Lyotard. Perhaps it is in these ways that
deconstruction will become a genuinely popular, or populist, idea. Charles Jencks has ventured to bet that a
multinational corporation is likely to build
<pb id="p23-90" n="90"/>
a major deconstructivist building in two years time and a major headquarters in probably four years time.</p>
          <p>Meanwhile, although reports of its demise appear daily, deconstruction still seems to be only
narrowly, or even mistakenly, understood. It is easy enough to detect in some of the writings and interviews
with architects and art historians in these issues some rather willful readings of Derrida’s work (although
the essays by Andrew Benjamin are notable exceptions). Nevertheless, precisely because artistic practice may
be running ahead of academic theory and practice, it is invigorating to have such a seminal book as
Derrida’s translated into English.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Truth in Painting</hi> is an exciting book. Why read Culler, Eagleton, or Norris
when Derrida’s methodology is visible in all its rigor at every turn? Begin anywhere. Although Derrida has
slotted disparate writings together (journal articles, prefaces to exhibition catalogues), the argument is
consistent throughout and each stage can be treated discretely. In <hi rend="i">The Truth in Painting</hi> as
well as in painting there is no frame, no passe-partout of a necessary introduction or conclusion which is not
already a part of “the work.” The “work of art” (and Derrida’s <hi rend="i">The Truth in
Painting</hi> can stand in its place) has no outside which is not already inside and no inside which is not
already outside: “These prolegomena of <hi rend="i">The Truth in Painting</hi>, themselves the 
<hi rend="i">parergon</hi> of this book, are ringed together by a circle” (9). Begin anywhere and lace it
together.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Of Grammatology</hi> (trans. Gayatri Chakravorty Spivak [Baltimore: Johns Hopkins
UP, 1974]) is now over twenty years old and its discoveries, and its author’s subsequent discoveries, should
no longer be considered optional. <hi rend="i">Différance</hi> is not “free-play” or “anything-goes”
or “lack-of-referentiality” brings “any-referentiality.” Still less is it “nihilism.” Rather, 
<hi rend="i">différance</hi> is process, an economy of presence and absence (and anything else structured like
language: e.g., psyche, painting) which is like the rattle of a machine. This is worth saying at the outset
because of the frequent misreadings of Derrida which occur in print and in the conference hall from people who
seem to have read nothing but “Structure, Sign, and Play in the Discourse of the Human Sciences” (cf. 
<hi rend="i">Writing and Difference</hi>, trans. Alan Bass [London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1978] 196-231).
Their position is as ideological as any they think they are “deconstructing.” “Free-for-all” free-play
is as good a demonstration of the workings of the supplement as could be hoped for as any careful reading of
“Structure, Sign, and Play” will reveal.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Truth in Painting</hi> has all the rigor of Derrida’s other books and, of the
principal works to date, can be neatly placed chronologically between <hi rend="i">Glas</hi> (1974) and 
<hi rend="i">The Post Card</hi> (1980). Much of the book is directed at a re-reading of Hegel’s, Heidegger’s
and Kant’s aesthetics with a concentration on textual examples rather at the expense of the visual. Derrida
quotes Kant to the effect that “Examples are thus the wheelchairs of the faculty of judging” but, in his
own view, “If things run as though on wheels, this is perhaps because things aren’t going so well. . .
.” (78-79). Perhaps examples are to logic what metaphor is to language. Anemic: white logic.</p>
          <p>In many ways the arguments of <hi rend="i">The Truth in Painting</hi> are an elaboration from the
revelation of the workings of <hi rend="i">différance.</hi> It is seldom recognized that Derrida shares with
Saussure an urge to keep things simple. This is perhaps the only way in which it is fair to say that he is
reductive. The book has a simple formal structure: a large section (half the book) called “Parergon”
discusses the frame in art. This has further subsections on “The <hi rend="i">Sans</hi> of the Pure Cut”
(the beautiful) and “The Colossal” (the sublime). The book then moves into the exciting chapters “+ R
(Into the Bargain),” “Cartouches” and “Restitutions” which deal with the way Derrida looks at
pictures and where there is a usually a transition from the more didactic format of “Parergon.”</p>
          <p>In “Parergon” Derrida asks what is not <hi rend="i">of</hi> the work of art? Does it have an
end and a beginning? What is a frame? Is ornament <hi rend="i">of</hi> the work or outside it? Derrida
provides an illuminating example: Lucas Cranach’s <hi rend="i">Lucretia</hi>, 1533 (Staatliche Museen
Preussische Kulturbesitz, Gemäldegalerie, Berlin) which is reproduced in a (barely adequate) black and white
photograph. Cranach’s Lucretia holds the point of a dagger to her chest while, with the other hand, she
positions a diaphanous veil over her upper thighs. She wears a necklace but is otherwise unclothed. Derrida
asks “. . . where is the <hi rend="i">parergon</hi>? Should one regard as a <hi rend="i">parergon</hi> the
dagger which is not part of her naked and natural body and whose point she holds turned toward herself,
touching her skin (in that case only the point of the <hi rend="i">parergon</hi> would touch her body, in the
middle of a triangle formed by her two breasts and her navel)? A <hi rend="i">parergon</hi>, the necklace that
she wears around her neck?” (57). The
<pb id="p23-91" n="91"/>
lack of plenitude in the “content” of the painting produces its meaning as a supplement. But which is the
supplement? Lucretia, the dagger, the veil, the necklace, the picture frame, other works by Cranach, other
paintings of his epoch, the title and its supplements? The <hi rend="i">parergon</hi> is “lacking 
<hi rend="i">in</hi> something and it is lacking <hi rend="i">from itself</hi>” (56). What works, what labors is
the frame: “The frame labors [<hi rend="i">travaille</hi>] indeed. Place of labor, structurally bordered
origin of surplus value, i.e., overflowed [<hi rend="i">débordée</hi>] on these two borders by what it
overflows, it gives [<hi rend="i">travaille</hi>] indeed” (75). In other words, the production of meaning is
absent from what one might call “pictorial content” and is deferred to the frame which is the site of the
picture’s placement in the process of <hi rend="i">différance.</hi> Whereas “the whole analytic of
aesthetic judgment forever assumes that one can distinguish rigorously between the intrinsic and the
extrinsic” (63) at the place of the frame, which is the site of the production of supplement,
“Deconstruction must neither reframe nor dream of the pure absence of the frame. These two apparently
contradictory gestures are the very ones—and they are systematically indissociable—of 
<hi rend="i">what</hi> is here deconstructed” (73).</p>
          <p>The Derridean frame has already been discussed by Edward Larrissy in <hi rend="i">Re-Reading . .
. William Blake</hi> (Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 1985) but rather than discuss passe-partout and 
<hi rend="i">parergon</hi> further, I would like to come back to an earlier, more immediately recognizably
Blakean, example from <hi rend="i">The Truth in Painting</hi> in order to lead on to Derrida’s discussions,
in the earlier parts of the book, on the limits of the representational in art. Derrida reproduces a
printer’s emblem showing the ubiquitous Renaissance device of
hands-in-clouds-holding-dividers-inscribing-a-circle, a device which has long been held to be generic with
Blake’s “The Ancient of Days” and the Urizenic attempt to contain the abyss. Derrida abruptly begins
“Parergon” with the words “it’s enough to say: abyss and satire of the abyss” (17). Admittedly this
is Derrida at his most apparently gnomic but the phrase gets worked through reassuringly and systematically.
In a brilliant piece of deconstruction Derrida argues that the “abyss,” which is forced between being
presented and yet remaining unpresentable, “saturates,” fills up and yet “hollows out” (33-34) the
content of its meaning: this is why the abyss is “satire, farce on the edge of excess” (17). Any idea of
the “abyss” is forced into representationality which is narrativity (parody, satire, farce) or, to put it
more simply, supplement. This, it seems to me, was exactly Blake’s problem: how to present the
unpresentable?</p>
          <p>Derrida’s discussions of the sublime (in “The Colossal”) are highly relevant to Blake’s
arguments with his contemporaries about the presentation and content of his pictures and poems. What looms
perilously close is the satire of the abyss, a presenting of the unpresentable as a lack of presentation.
Blake’s way, and he has no other, was “Sublime Allegory,” a satire of the abyss. It is worth pursuing a
deconstructive reading of Blake’s important statements on this in his letter to Thomas Butts: “Allegory
addressed to the Intellectual powers while it is altogether hidden from the Corporeal Understanding is My
Definition of the Most Sublime Poetry” (to Butts, 6 July 1803, E 730). Blake’s position is a fairly
standard phenomenological one (dilute Husserl) where the “Intellectual powers” are capable of being
remotely “addressed” across the abyss from “Corporeal Understanding.” In other words, Blake bridges
the gulf between the corporeal and the intellectual in an analogy or allegoric narrative while maintaining the
discretion of these two faculties: “The abyss calls for analogy . . . but analogy plunges endlessly into the
abyss as soon as a certain art is needed to describe analogically the play of the analogy” (36). There is
nothing “wrong” with Blake’s allegoric innovation: there is, quite simply, no other way.</p>
          <p>The colossal, like the abyss, like Blake’s “Sublime Allegory,” is appeased into
presentation by a lack in presentation: “Colossal <hi rend="i">Fort: Da.</hi> What comes-in-front 
[<hi rend="i">devant</hi>]-of-it-to-erect-itself. Having to [<hi rend="i">Devant</hi>] erect itself in the
excessive movement of its own disappearance, of its unpresentable presentation” (145). This is why
“Singular &amp; Particular Detail is the Foundation of the Sublime” (Annotations to Reynolds, E 647) and
why “Obscurity is Neither the Source of the Sublime nor of any Thing Else” (E 658). Blake’s position on
the sublime is, in fact, postmodernist. It is worth comparing Jean-Francois Lyotard’s definition, which is
more succinct, if less rigorous, than Derrida’s: “The postmodern would be that which, in the modern, puts
forward the unpresentable in presentation itself; that which denies itself the solace of good forms, the
consensus of a taste which would make it possible to share collectively the nostalgia for the unattainable;
that which searches for new presentations, not in order to enjoy them but in order to impart a stronger sense
of the unpresentable” (“What is Postmodernism?” [1982] printed as the appendix to <hi rend="i">The
Postmodern Condition</hi> [1979], Manchester: Manchester UP, 1984, 81; also in 
<hi rend="i">Innovation/Renovation</hi>, ed. Ihab Hassan and Sally Hassan, Madison: U of Wisconsin P, 1983). The
essentialism of Blake’s ideas may be rather at variance with his artistic practice.
<pb id="p23-92" n="92"/>
The télos of this journey, from essentialist reaction against eighteenth-century mimesis to postmodernism,
has already been hinted at in an account of art history from the perspective of postmodernism (see Simon
Morley, “A Differance,” <hi rend="i">Art</hi> &amp; <hi rend="i">Design</hi> 4 [1988]: 26-32).</p>
          <p>To come back to Blake’s letter to Butts once again: Derrida helps us to see very clearly the
aporia in Blake’s statement. This is not, structurally, the corporeal/intellectual opposition but, rather,
the supposition that the two powers can be “addressd.” The fully located address from addressor to
addressee is Blake’s bridge plunging into the abyss as intention tries to deposit itself into absolutely
referenced meaning: “both potent and impotent, potent in its very impotence, all potential in its
unequalness to itself. Everything here resounds and echoes in the dynamic sublime” (146). This echo or
resonance is the rattle of the frame or passe-partout and is denotative of “The <hi rend="i">Sans</hi> of
the Pure Cut.”</p>
          <p>“The <hi rend="i">Sans</hi> of the Pure Cut” is a fascinating section on the beautiful
facilitated by the use of the work “cise” by Derrida’s translators: “an obsolete spelling of
‘size’ . . . and suggestive of cutting (cf. incision)” (120n32). The <hi rend="i">sans</hi> of the pure
cut is rather like reformulating Derrida’s “<hi rend="i">il n’y a pas de hors-texte</hi>” 
(<hi rend="i">Of Grammatology</hi> 158). This phrase seems to have been the subject of repeated, ideologically
positioned, misreadings: it is not just that “there is nothing outside of the text” but also that “there
is no outside-text.” In order to understand the <hi rend="i">sans</hi> of the pure cut (Derrida’s example
is a ubiquitous print of a single cut tulip), it is necessary to take the object of beauty and notice that
“This tulip is complete from the first because a concept cannot fill it up” (94). The tulip or tulip-print
is installed within an economy of <hi rend="i">différance</hi> because the single tulip is the 
<hi rend="i">parole</hi> within the <hi rend="i">langue</hi> of the tulips of the field, the tulips of Nature. As
such, the cise of the single tulip has no meaning fully unto itself. Its only completion is that it signifies,
which is to say that it fixes no referent: “A beautiful flower is in this sense an absolutely 
<hi rend="i">coupable</hi> [guilty, cuttable] flower that is absolutely absolved, innocent. Without debt. Not
without law, but of a law without concept” (94). In other words, the concept of the beautiful tulip is
another labor at the frame. The cise is what samples this tulip from millions of others, makes it into a
small-sized sample, but also cuts it off from signification: “The <hi rend="i">without-goal</hi>, the 
<hi rend="i">without-why</hi> of the tulip is not significant, is not a signifier, not even a signifier of a lack.
At least insofar as the tulip is beautiful, <hi rend="i">this</hi> tulip. As such, a signifier, even a
signifier without signified, can do anything except be beautiful” (95). This is the double-bind of the work
of art: a Blake <hi rend="i">Song of Innocence</hi>, say, is a snap-shot, a photographic print (both unique
<hi rend="i">and</hi> reproducible) which is the cise of “Innocence”: both the size of “Innocence” and
cut-off/cut-into it. This cise, this “<hi rend="i">sans</hi>” of the pure cut (there is nothing outside
the cut/there is no outside cut, we might say) is the economy of <hi rend="i">différance</hi> in
pictures.</p>
          <p>The without/absence of the pure cut is an important contribution to the philosophy of art. It is,
substantially, a philosophy based on a grammatological method (not that grammatology is exclusively, or even
strictly, an epistemology). As such, it is analogous to Lévi-Strauss’s application of the method of
Saussurian linguistics to anthropology. What Derrida has put forward is rather more than a 
<hi rend="i">simple</hi> intertextuality of pictures; rather, what is discovered is the 
<hi rend="i">différance</hi> of pictures. To repeat Derrida’s words: “What comes-in-front 
[<hi rend="i">devant</hi>]-of-it-to-erect-itself. Having to [Devant] erect itself is the excessive movement of its
own disappearance, of its unpresentable presentation.” Pictures present themselves, yet they do not present
themselves completely: in the presence of presentation is the absence of presentation. Perhaps the easiest way
of putting across Derrida’s point about a presentation of the unpresentable is to look at his discussion of
the deconstructionist painter Valerio Adami and at one picture in particular. Adami’s pencil drawing 
<hi rend="i">Disegno par un ritratto di W. Benjamin</hi> (1973, private collection) has a reasonably good
illustration in <hi rend="i">The Truth in Painting.</hi></p>
          <p>Derrida’s discussion is, essentially, a simple one. Adami uses a familiar, fairly ubiquitous,
photograph of Walter Benjamin as the basis for his picture. Benjamin was the author of the important “The
Work of Art in the Age of Mechanical Reproduction” (1936). What, then, is the relationship of Adami’s
drawing to Benjamin’s photograph “reproduced,” off-center, by Adami’s pencil?</p>
          <p>Derrida notes that Adami has captured Benjamin in an economy of <hi rend="i">différance</hi>:
<q>
Benjamin had a theory of the portrait, which, according to him, played a transition role, on the fronter
between “ritual religious art” and “technical reproducibility.” The photographic representation of the
face is the remainder, the last resistance of ritual. When the face begins to disappear or, as here, no longer
to occupy the top or the center, the legend [<hi rend="i">Beschriftung</hi>] becomes necessary. “Its
character is quite different from the title of a picture.” <hi rend="i">Ritratto di Walter Benjamin</hi> is
of a type as legendary as the name “Benjamin.” Just about in the middle land on the subject’s forehead
[<hi rend="i">front</hi>], the name is also at the bottom of a frame. Title of one absent (picture): of one no
more [<hi rend="i">disparu</hi>]. <hi rend="i">Disappeared</hi> [<hi rend="i">disparu</hi>] is the subject.
What has disappeared <hi rend="i">appears</hi>, absent in the very place of the commemorative monument,
returning to the empty place marked by his name. (178)
</q>
	<pb id="p23-93" n="93"/>
This is a brilliant commentary: concise, witty, and flawless.</p>
          <p>But there is something of further, perhaps of greater, importance here. Reproduction is a 
<hi rend="i">condition</hi> of painting: there are no “originals.” This case can be proven with regard to
Blake’s life and art. Blake’s deconstructive economies (this is not an anachronism: deconstructive
economies are consistently latent and have never waited on Derrida’s writings) can be identified by the
paradoxes of his positions with regard to drawing and engraving which may be conveniently discussed in
relation to Blake’s <hi rend="i">Canterbury Pilgrims.</hi> To follow the usual formula of deconstructive
styles of argument: <hi rend="i">on the one hand</hi>, Blake protests that Stothard and Cromek stole the
essence of his conception of <hi rend="i">Chaucer’s Canterbury Pilgrims</hi> while, <hi rend="i">on the
other hand</hi>, Blake offers his own multiplication of that essence as an engraving.</p>
          <p>Blake’s status as an artist offering a supplement at the origin can easily be seen from
Blake’s first prospectus on <hi rend="i">The Canterbury Pilgrims</hi>: “no other Artist can reach the
original Spirit so well as the Painter himself, especially as Mr. B. is an old well-known and acknowledged
Engraver” (E 567). In other words, the “original Spirit” which “the Painter himself” offers to
“reach” in painting is simultaneously offered as a reproduction deferring the “original Spirit,” just
as writing signs the absence of the author. In a revealing passage from the Notebook “Public Address”
Blake seems to specify that the reproductive supplement is already there at the origin of drawing: “I
request the Society to inspect my Print, of which Drawing is the Foundation &amp; indeed the Superstructure it
is Drawing on Copper as Painting ought to be Drawing on Canvas or any other [<hi rend="i">table</hi>]
&lt;surface&gt; &amp; nothing Else” (E 572). In saying that drawing is both “the Foundation &amp; . . .
Superstructure” it seems that drawing must operate as <hi rend="i">both</hi> an original 
<hi rend="i">and</hi> a reproduction. Blake’s intensifier, “indeed,” is a signifying aporia which attempts
to bridge the “Foundation” and “Superstructure” of “my Print” but which only reveals the
inevitable break into allegory. Drawing is both the original “Foundation” <hi rend="i">below</hi> the
“Print” (embodying “the original Spirit”) which might offer the artist’s invention as presence (his
“reach”), but at the same time, drawing is also the reproductive “Superstructure” 
<hi rend="i">above</hi> drawing, mystifyingly close to “Print” yet retaining the trace of the origin (the
“drawing”). Blake’s architectural metaphor notifies the chiasmus operative at the ground level between
foundation and superstructure: precisely the “ground” of the copper plate which has to act as two and yet
one. Drawing operates as Blake’s version of Freud’s Mystic Writing Pad (cf. <hi rend="i">Writing and
Difference</hi> 196-231): it must be both breachable <hi rend="i">hyle</hi> (i.e., a “Print” made by “an
old well-known and acknowledged Engraver” “on copper”) and yet also remain (for it precisely 
<hi rend="i">is</hi> a <hi rend="i">remainder</hi> or supplement) an “original Spirit.” Blake’s art was
never elsewhere but in The Age of [Mechanical] Reproduction.</p>
          <p>I have tried, so far, to sketch out some of the theory of Derrida’s book and how it might apply
to Blake’s works. But, <hi rend="i">how does Derrida look at pictures</hi>? The final part of 
<hi rend="i">The Truth in Painting</hi>, called “Restitutions,” is a long meditative argument about those
            series of paintings by Van Gogh on the subject of shoes which prompted Meyer <corr type="emend">Schapiro’s</corr> criticism of
Heidegger’s discussion of them in <hi rend="i">The Origin of the Work of Art.</hi> To give Derrida’s long
and careful critique a rather violent and injurious summary, Derrida puts forward the view that shoes, like
paintings, cannot be located determinately with their peasant owners or their painters. To do so would be to
give not <hi rend="i">The Truth</hi> [<hi rend="i">in Painting</hi>] but “hallucination in painting”
(366), the spectres of painting as he calls them elsewhere (374). Yet, at the same time Derrida does not
simply end up with the position that nothing can be said about Van Gogh’s shoes; 
<hi rend="i">différance</hi> may be in process but so is representationality and the viewing subject. The viewing
subject is constantly modified by pictures acting like texts, like post cards: picture post cards.</p>
          <p>I emphasize picture post cards by way of alluding to Derrida’s <hi rend="i">The Post Card.</hi>
If Derrida’s datings of his missives are to be believed, the early parts of <hi rend="i">The Post Card</hi>
were being written at the same time as <hi rend="i">The Truth in Painting</hi>’s “Cartouches,” that is,
in approximately the last few months of 1977 (a few specific days in November 1977 do appear to coincide
between the two works). “Cartouches” was published at the time of the exhibition of Gerard
Titus-Carmel’s <hi rend="i">The Pocket Size Tlingit Coffin and the 61 Ensuing Drawings</hi> (National Museum
of Modern Art, Pompidou Center, Paris, 1 March-10 April 1978). <hi rend="i">OED</hi>: 
“<hi rend="b">Cartouche</hi>: in architecture, scroll ornament e.g. volute of Ionic capital; tablet imitating, or
drawing of, scroll with rolled-up ends, used ornamentally or bearing inscription; ornate frame . . . F, =
cartridge.” “<hi rend="b">Cartridge</hi>: . . . spool of film, magnetic tape, etc., in container . . .
ink-container for insertion in pen. 2. <corr type="emend"><hi rend="b">~ paper</hi></corr> thick and rough,
used for cartridges, for drawing and strong envelopes.” That there are no “strong envelopes” for
pictures might be implicit from Derrida’s remarks on painting, but “Cartouches” is also a discussion of
the concept of what constitutes a series. Of a series of 127, why were only 61 drawings exhibited (plus
<pb id="p23-94" n="94"/>
the extraordinary <hi rend="i">Pocket Size Tlingit Coffin</hi> which is hand-sized and made of wood, glass,
fur, and brass with lacings hanging from it, cf. 187)? At least two drawings are said by Derrida to have been
destroyed or else there would have been 129 (209). Answers to me on a post card, please, which, no matter how
clearly addressed, will be sure to go astray. Which is exactly the point about the other 66 drawings: they
never arrived.</p>
          <p>Derrida’s meditations on Titus-Carmel’s series of productions is a matter of concern for
anyone thinking about what constitutes a series. Despite the oddness of Titus-Carmel’s titles, his naming is
no more performative than, say, Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> or 
<hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi> What Derrida discusses is the relationship, or lack of it,
between the producer, performances, and readers or viewers. The Tlingit Coffin is a fascinating device that
may very well work like, say, one of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> in that
each is a pocketable cise (a size) of Innocence and Experience yet each cise is interlaced to something beyond
itself. The relationship of one <hi rend="i">Song</hi> to another is like the Tlingit Coffin: it is both
self-contained and yet interlaced beyond itself, like a post card and its unforeseen readers. The squared
margins of Blake’s plate at once defines and falls short of defining his <hi rend="i">Song.</hi> Derrida
seems to modify his earlier concept or condition of <hi rend="i">brisure</hi> to accept this lacing effect
(<hi rend="i">Of Grammatology</hi> 65-73). Instead of texts being both hinged/broken, the lacing allows us to
see that while <hi rend="i">brisure</hi> might be a condition of text, lacing is a condition of the
relationship between reader and text (or viewer and picture). “A parallelepiped (OED: “solid bounded by
parallelograms”) like the coffin . . . the matchbox has the peculiarity that it does not open, like so many
other caskets, along the articulation of a hing . . . Here, for once, <hi rend="i">one</hi> box opens or shuts
by sliding <hi rend="i">into another</hi>, which is none other than itself . . . The hermetic closure composes
the two openings, is composed by them both” (226). Or, a <hi rend="i">Song of Innocence</hi>, like the brief
hermetic closure of a post card, closes on itself yet opens out into <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> (which is its
cise) and opens out to the play of reading. The post card, or <hi rend="i">Song</hi>, never arrives at its
destination because the specificity of its communication is readable by everyone. Theoretically it may have
its own conditions (William Blake, 1757-1827, may well have <hi rend="i">intended</hi> to say something with
it) but it is always laced to something else, to another <hi rend="i">Song</hi> or another ideology:
<q>
There are remains of cartridge, because the dissemination of the cartridges or cartouches (in all
sense/directions, in all genres/genders) never exhausts a <hi rend="i">total.</hi> There is no total of
meanings and genders (masculine/feminine). Always a box <hi rend="i">in</hi> the box, some supplementary
cartridge, a <hi rend="i">parergon</hi>, that’s what the coffin’s mutism <hi rend="i">says</hi> to us,
and, in it, the couple of beakless fledglings. Always a box <hi rend="i">outside</hi> the box. (231)
</q>
This is Derrida at his most creatively rigorous (the silent fledglings are the fur deposited in the Tlingit
Coffin): cartridge is to <hi rend="i">Song</hi> as cartridge is to can(n)on (229)! “The play of the
supplement, the repetition of the deviation can go on <hi rend="i">ad infinitum</hi>, or 
<hi rend="i">almost</hi>, unless, with a ‘that’s sufficient’ you let the series stop one fine day” (237).
In other words, the <hi rend="i">Song</hi> cartridge is already in the can(n)on: the can(n)on bears the trace
of other <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>/cartridges.</p>
          <p>Pictures act like Van Gogh’s shoes: their laces offer to lace themselves to an hallucinatory
Van Gogh yet they also unlace themselves because Van Gogh can never fill the shoes shown in his pictures. The
paintings of shoes by Van Gogh and Derrida’s discussion of them is the culmination of an “interlacing”
effect he has hinted at throughout <hi rend="i">The Truth in Painting.</hi> The lacing of the picture to the
viewer passes towards the viewer but also behind the picture. Valerio Adami’s <hi rend="i">Study for a
Drawing after Glas</hi> (reproduced on consecutive pages, 153-54) makes this point by having one side of the
picture have a penciled-in frame across which words transgress (Marcel Duchamp’s <hi rend="i">The Bride
Stripped Bare by her Bachelors, Even</hi> [1915-23] would be an early deconstructive piece of art working in
the same way). On the other side, a sketched scaffolding of ladders and thongs keeps the picture moving in,
out, near, far, there, gone.</p>
          <p>The logic of lacing, of stricture and destricture, is one I want to finally turn to, coming back
to my earlier comments about “play” in Derrida. Derrida says quite clearly that “Any stricture is 
<hi rend="i">simultaneously</hi> stricturation and destricturation” (340). To emphasize: stricturing is a
necessary alternation of destricturing. “The loosening of the laces is not absolute, it does not absolve,
unbind, cut. It keeps an organized stricture. Not a more or less of stricture but a determined (structured)
form of stricture: of the outside and the inside, the underneath and the top . . . Deferring: it never
sutures” (340). In other words, this is not “play” (except in the sense of the play of loose machinery)
but, rather, <hi rend="i">fort/da</hi>: “lacing across the line in both directions, making come back, making
go away, making come back again, inside, outside, down
<pb id="p23-95" n="95"/>
there, here, <hi rend="i">fort/da</hi>” (357). Certainly the picture goes away from us, destricturing,
deferring itself in “the logic of stricture, in the interlacing of <hi rend="i">différance</hi> of (or as)
stricture” (340) but it also comes back, stricturing itself into the would-be fullness of representation:
“What we know is that every step (discursive or pictural in particular) implies a <hi rend="i">fort/da.</hi>
Every relation to a pictural text implies this double movement doubly interlaced to itself. It is a kind of
<hi rend="i">fort/da</hi> that is <hi rend="i">described by</hi> the circuit of the lace” (357).</p>
          <p>This seems to be a little different from the emphasis Derrida’s works are sometimes,
mistakenly, given. If, simultaneously, with destricturing there is a “determined (structured) form of
stricture” then it is clearly one to which attention must be paid and to which “the whole path of thought,
for Heidegger, leads back, by a dis-tancing, to a <hi rend="i">Da</hi> (thus the <hi rend="i">Da</hi> of 
<hi rend="i">Sein</hi>) which is not merely close, but whose proximity lets the distance of the 
<hi rend="i">fort</hi> play within it” (357). The word “proximity” is important and Derrida isolates this
word as something wanting in Heidegger’s discussion: “No doubt he misrecognized the necessity of the
argumentation, the lacing movement of its coming and going and the abyss of its <hi rend="i">fort/da</hi>”
(358). After these discussions (and one now sees that the truth in painting is something I cannot give you) we
are left with (remaindered with) logic and strictured play: “<hi rend="i">There is</hi> painting, writing,
            restitutions, that’s all. Who among you knows Van Gogh? Does anyone here know Heidegger? Goldstein? <corr type="emend">Schapiro?</corr>
This square—” (371). When we look at a picture all we can bet on is that we <hi rend="i">are</hi> going to
bet on it:
<q>
All these shoes remain there, in a sale, so you can compare them, pair them up, unpair them, bet or not bet on
the pair. The trap is the inevitability of betting. The logic of the disparate. You can also try to buy the
trap and take it home, as a tribute, or the way you think you’re taking something away on the soles of the
painted shoes. All these shoes remain there—for he painted so many. . . . (381)
</q>
Pocket up Blake how we may, something will remain: “It gives to be rendered. To be put back on/put
off.—It’s just gone.—It’s coming round again.—It’s just gone again” (382). 
<hi rend="i">Fort/da.</hi></p>
          <p>In deconstruction there is no <hi rend="i">lack</hi> of referentiality but, rather, an 
<hi rend="i">excess</hi>: “Enough! or Too much” (<hi rend="i">MHH</hi> 10; E 38). It will be interesting to
see the emergence of deconstructive analyses of painting for which <hi rend="i">The Truth in Painting</hi>
will be to art historians what <hi rend="i">Of Grammatology</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Post Cart</hi> have been
to literary critics.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
