<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>23.2.kinghele</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">A Twist in the Tale of “The Tyger”</title>
        <author n="King-Hele">Desmond King-Hele</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1989</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1989</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">23.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Manging Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>Martin Bidney</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Michael Grenfell</name>
              <name>Desmond King-Hele</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Dena Bain Taylor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1989"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_23">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-23-2-0008">
        <pb id="p23-104" n="104"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A Twist in the Tale of “The Tyger”</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Desmond <name>King-Hele</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Most readers of “The Tyger” have their own ideas of its meaning: I shall not be adding my own
interpretation, but merely offering a factual record of minute particulars, by pointing to a number of verbal
parallels with Erasmus Darwin’s <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden.</hi> A few of these were given in my book
<hi rend="i">Erasmus Darwin and the Romantic Poets</hi>; the others I have come across more recently.</p>
          <p>Darwin’s poem <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi> was published in two parts, with Part 2, 
<hi rend="i">The Loves of the Plants</hi>, appearing first in 1789, and Part 1, <hi rend="i">The Economy of
Vegetation</hi>, nominally in 1791, though it did not actually appear until about June 1792, probably because
of delay in printing Blake’s superb engravings of the Portland Vase.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n66" type="note">1</ref> After my quotations I give the canto and line numbers from the third edition
of <hi rend="i">The Loves of the Plants</hi> (1791) and the first edition of <hi rend="i">The Economy of
Vegetation.</hi>
	<note id="n66"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Desmond King-Hele, ed. <hi rend="i">The Letters of Erasmus Darwin</hi>
(Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1981) 215.</note></p>
          <p>One of the best-known passages in Darwin’s poem was his vivid description of a nightmare, based
on Fuseli’s painting (illus. 1), which features the half-visible head of a large animal with unnaturally
bright eyes, enveloped in black night. Obviously the head is intended as that of a horse, but the word
“nightmare” has no etymological connection with horses, male or female.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">2</ref> (The nightmare is produced by the incubus, or “squab
fiend” as Darwin calls him.) Could Fuseli’s monstrous animal, with eyes burning bright in the blackness of
the night, have given Blake the cue for his Tyger? Such a speculation is encouraged by a verbal parallel
between “The Tyger” and Darwin’s verses about the sleeping girl. The nightmare induces in her an
“interrupted heartpulse” and “suffocative breath”, as frightful thoughts
<q>
In dread succession agonize her mind.<lb/>
O’er her fair limbs convulsive tremors fleet,<lb/>
Start in her hands, and struggle in her feet.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">Lov. Pl.</hi> 3: 68-70)
</q>
This is not quite “What dread hand? and what dread feet?,” but dread is powerfully present, “in her
hands, and . . . in her feet”; and “dread” was a favorite adjective with Darwin, used twenty times in
<hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden.</hi>
	<note id="n67"><hi rend="s">2</hi> N. Powell, <hi rend="i">Fuseli: The Nightmare</hi> (London: Allen Lane,
1973).</note></p>
          <p>The burning brightness of the first two stanzas of “The Tyger” has some resemblances to
Darwin’s picture of Nebuchadnezzar ordering “a vast pyre . . . of sulphurous coal and pitch-exuding
pine” with “huge bellows” to fan the roaring flames:
<pb id="p23-105" n="105"/>
<figure n="nightmare.23.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="757">
	<head>Henry Fuseli, <hi rend="i">The Nightmare</hi>, oil on canvas, 40 × 50 inches, 1781.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of The Detroit Institute of Arts.</figDesc>
</figure>
<q>
Bright and more bright the blazing deluge flows,<lb/>
And white with sevenfold heat the furnace glows.<lb/>
And now the Monarch fix’d with dread surprize<lb/>
Deep in the burning valut his dazzled eyes.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">Lov. Pl.</hi> 4: 61-64)
</q>
Nebuchadnezzar was so dreadfully surprised because Shadrec, Meshec, and Abednego were enduring the heat of the
furnace unscathed: “Fierce flames innocuous, as they step, retire; / And calm they move amid a world of
fire!” (<hi rend="i">Lov. Pl.</hi> 4: 69-70). In these two quotations we have <hi rend="i">burning</hi> once
and <hi rend="i">bright</hi> twice, as well as <hi rend="i">dread</hi> and four other obvious words from
“The Tyger”—<hi rend="i">furnace, deep, eyes</hi> and <hi rend="i">fire.</hi> Also Darwin has a complete
answer to Blake’s question “What the hand dare seize the fire?”</p>
          <p>There is another curious parallel in Darwin’s picture of the night-flowering Cerea, who lifts
her brows “to the skies” at midnight, “Eyes the white zenith; counts the suns, that roll / Their distant
fires, and blaze around the Pole” (<hi rend="i">Lov. Pl.</hi> 4: 21-22). Blake sets “the fire of thine
eyes” deep in “distant . . . skies”: the image is similar,
<pb id="p23-106" n="106"/>
though the Tyger is very different from the strange plant that flowers unseen.</p>
          <p>In an earlier canto of <hi rend="i">The Loves of the Plants</hi> there is a correctly-ordered
preview of Blake’s word-sequence “deeps . . . on . . . wings . . . aspire . . . fire”: Darwin
<q>
Calls up with magic voice the shapes that sleep<lb/>
In Earth’s dark bosom, or unfathom’d deep;<lb/>
That shrin’d in air on viewless wings aspire,<lb/>
Or blazing bathe in elemental fire.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">Lov. Pl.</hi> 2: 297-300)
</q>
Darwin likes the “aspire/fire” rhyme and uses it in <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi> on three other
occasions (<hi rend="i">Lov. Pl.</hi> 1: 281-82; <hi rend="i">Ec. Veg.</hi> 1: 225-26 and 1: 255-56).</p>
          <p>After all these parallels you may think it is easy to find a parallel for anything. But that is
not so: unlike conventional literary criticism, which can sweep unwanted facts under the carpet,
source-hunting is sharp and scientific—failures cannot be hidden. Thus there is no “fearful symmetry” to
be found anywhere in the verse of <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden.</hi> Also Darwin never mentions a Tyger
specifically in his poem. The nearest he comes to it is with his fierce-eyed “Monster of the Nile”:
“With Tyger-paw He prints the brineless strand . . . / Rolls his fierce eye-balls, clasps his iron claws”
(<hi rend="i">Ec. Veg.</hi> 4: 434, 437). Nor does Darwin offer a “forest of the night”: his closest
approach is when Hercules “drives the Lion to his dusky cave” in “Nemea’s howling forests” 
(<hi rend="i">Ec. Veg.</hi> 1: 313).</p>
          <p>No labor of Hercules is needed, however, to find parallels in canto 1 of <hi rend="i">The Economy
of Vegetation</hi>, because its subject is Fire. Darwin tells us how Vulcan and Cyclops “forged immortal
arms” on “thundering anvils”; when Venus came to watch them she “Admired their sinewy arms, and
shoulders bare, / And ponderous hammers lifted high in air” (<hi rend="i">Ec. Veg.</hi> 1: 169-70). Blake
has <hi rend="i">shoulder, sinews, hammer</hi> and <hi rend="i">anvil</hi>, though his immortal artificer is
forging not fearsome weapons but a fearsome Tyger. Darwin is equally creative at times, for example in
bringing to birth the Tyger-pawed Monster of the Nile:
<q>
First in translucent lymph with cobweb-threads<lb/>
The Brain’s fine floating tissue swells, and spreads;<lb/>
Nerve after nerve the glistening spine descends,<lb/>
The red Heart dances, the Aorta bends.<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">Ec. Veg.</hi> 4: 425-28)
</q>
The first two lines answer Blake’s “In what furnace was thy brain?” In the last line Darwin’s phrase
“The red Heart dances” is too pretty for Blake, who soberly states “thy heart began to beat”; in 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, however, closer links with Darwin’s picture can be found.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n68"><hi rend="s">3</hi> See D. C. Leonard, “Erasmus Darwin and William Blake,” 
<hi rend="i">Eighteenth Century Life</hi> 4 (1978): 79-81.</note></p>
          <p>There are many other parallels from canto 1 of <hi rend="i">The Economy of Vegetation.</hi> For
example, lines 216-22 have “dread Destroyer . . . bright . . . dread snakes . . . immortal . . . Terror.”
The noun <hi rend="i">chain</hi> appears thirteen times in <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi>, notably in
the picture of a shackled “Giant-form” bursting his chains to bring about the French Revolution, an image
that may have links with Blake’s <hi rend="i">French Revolution.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n69" type="note">4</ref> However, the phrase “what the chain?” does not appear in
<hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden.</hi> Nor do Blake’s “deadly terrors”: the best Darwin can offer is
“twisted terror” (<hi rend="i">Ec. Veg.</hi> 3: 502), with “sinewy shoulders” in the previous line, to
parallel “shoulder . . . twist . . . sinews . . . terrors” in the third and fourth stanzas of “The
Tyger.” <note id="n69"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See D. Worrall, “William Blake and Erasmus Darwin’s 
<hi rend="i">Botanic Garden</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Bulletin of New York Public Library</hi>, 78 (1975):
397-417.</note></p>
          <p>That brings me to the fifth stanza of “The Tyger,” which I have already discussed at some
length in my book,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70" type="note">5</ref> where I quoted
from Darwin’s long note on the aurora, to show that it might be a source for “the stars threw down their
spears.” I also gave a quotation from Darwin’s <hi rend="i">Zoonomia</hi>, with his evolutionary
explanation—now sanctioned by modern science—of how the tyger was created from the same original “living
filament” as the lamb. Thus he answers Blake’s question in stanza 5, and the query in stanza 1 about the
framer of the Tyger’s fearful symmetry. Darwin’s answer was timely too, for volume 1 of 
<hi rend="i">Zoonomia</hi> was published in 1794, the same year as <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience.</hi>
	<note id="n70"><hi rend="s">5</hi> See Desmond King-Hele, <hi rend="i">Erasmus Darwin and the Romantic
Poets</hi> (London: Macmillan Press, 1986) 49-50.</note></p>
          <p>Perhaps I have been twisting the tail of the Tyger too sadistically; but a full scholarly
appreciation of Blake’s poem should take account of all such verbal parallels. There is much
evidence<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71" type="note">6</ref> that Blake was influenced by
Darwin between 1789 and 1795, so the parallels may well be significant. <note id="n71"><hi rend="s">6</hi>
Worrall 397-417; N. Hilton, “The Spectre of Darwin,” rev. of <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi>, by
Erasmus Darwin, <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 15 (1981) 36-48; King-Hele, <hi rend="i">Romantic Poets</hi>, chap.
2.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
