<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>23.2.mellor</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Dan Miller, Mark Bracher, and Donald Ault, eds., Critical Paths: Blake and the
Argument of Method</title>
        <author n="Mellor">Anne K. Mellor</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1989</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1989</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">23.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Manging Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>Martin Bidney</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Michael Grenfell</name>
              <name>Desmond King-Hele</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Dena Bain Taylor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1989"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_23">
    <body>
	<pb id="p23-98" n="98"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-23-2-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Dan Miller, Mark Bracher, and Donald Ault, eds. <hi rend="i">Critical Paths:
Blake and the Argument of Method</hi> (Durham, NC: Duke UP, 1987). $45.00 cloth/$17.95 paper.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Anne K.</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Mellor</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>It is the argument of this uneven collection of essays that modern critical theory provides us
with new and necessary ways to interpret Blake’s poetry and art. While no one would argue with that in
principle, too many of these essays take this occasion to summarize at length by now familiar critical
methods, from the Chicago School of Aristotelian formalism and Derridean deconstruction through Lacanian
psychoanalysis to Marxism and feminism, for their own sakes, rather than using them with subtlety and
originality to produce understanding and interpretations of Blake’s work that enhance our reading or viewing
experience. There are some notable exceptions—fine essays by Hazard Adams, Nelson Hilton, Elizabeth
Langland, and David Aers—to which I shall return.</p>
          <p>The general tone of the volume is set by Dan Miller in his introduction, a rather florid,
impressionistic meditation on methods and divergent paths which says little more than that the criticism of
Blake reflects the critical variety present everywhere in the discipline and that all readings of Blake, as of
any author, are inherently theoretical and therefore biased. Stephen Cox’s “Methods and Limitations”
strenuously recovers much of this same ground by insisting that critics must be aware of the ways in which
their own theoretical assumptions and
<figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
<pb id="p23-99" n="99"/>
critical failures define the limits of their interpretive results. Unfortunately his own analysis of the
criticism of plate 23 of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> ends up, as does his essay, “like
poor, tiresome Swedenborg, . . . writing ‘all the old fals[e]hoods’ but not ‘one new truth’ ” (40).
William Dennis Horn, in “Blake’s Revisionism: Gnostic Interpretation and Critical Methodology,” offers a
persuasive (albeit hardly original) critique of the limitations of Harold Bloom’s revisionary theory, and
rightly insists on the affinity of Blake’s thought to gnostic texts—a claim that will surprise no reader
of Blake, Kathleen Raine, or Elaine Pagels. However, he fails to identify any particular gnostic texts which
Blake could have read or known and proceeds at such a level of oversimplified generality that, again, he
provides no “new truth.”</p>
          <p>The essays by the three editors elaborate with varying degrees of success the ways we might use
highly sophisticated critical methods to approach Blake. Donald Ault’s “Blake’s De-Formation of
Neo-Aristotelianism” demonstrates convincingly, if perhaps unintentionally, that neither a mathematical
approach—his, own 14-year-old attempt to provide a “calculus of perspectives” on <hi rend="i">The Book
of Urizen</hi>—nor the Chicago School of neo-Aristotelian criticism helps us to understand the subversive
complexity of Blake’s thought. After a particularly sensitive visual/visceral response to the titlepage of
<hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, Mark Bracher invokes Lacanian psychoanalytic techniques
both to elucidate his own responses and to show how Blake’s visual and verbal texts force the reader to
experience “interpellation” (in Althusser’s sense) or intellectual repositioning. Arguing that Blake’s
language becomes “a force capable of promoting change in the reader,” Bracher offers somewhat tendentious,
heavily phallic/Oedipal, readings of the Proverbs to show how Blake first evokes desire, then elicits
interpretation, and finally constructs a new linguistic code.</p>
          <p>Dan Miller provides a needlessly long, if lucid, explication of deconstructive methodology (a
useful primer if you haven’t already read your Derrida) before moving to an analysis of the logical
inconsistencies in Blake’s attempts to define the distinction between nature and vision, allegory and
imagination, in <hi rend="i">The Vision of the Last Judgment</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell.</hi> His final comments on the way the chariot at the end of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> functions as an
allegory that both blocks final revelation (by sending us to other texts for elucidation) and at the same time
effects an apocalyptic climax is a telling example of deconstructive reading. The utility and continuing
appeal of a Derridean approach is stressed again by David Wagenknecht in his “Afterword.” However, his
chosen exaple, an interpretation of why the central soldier in Blake’s “The Soldiers Casting Lots for
Christ’s Garments” raises his left hand in blessing, is seriously flawed, to my mind, by his failure to
consider other alternatives, for example, whether it matters that it is the left rather than the right hand,
whether this is unequivocally “a gesture that resembles benediction” (to my eyes it also resembles
gestures of surprise, protest, throwing the dice overhand, mere hovering, etc.). A third Derridean
“unreading” is provided by Thomas Vogler’s “ ‘In vain the Eloquent Tongue’: An Un-Reading of 
<hi rend="i">VISIONS of the Daughters of Albion</hi>,” an illuminating discussion of the ways in which the poem
is about seeing and knowing, about its own interpretation, which places the semiotics of the text in the
context of eighteenth-century political and sexual discourse.</p>
          <p>Vogler reaches an insight via de Sade which also informs Brenda Webster’s feminist and
psychoanalytic discussion of “Blake, Sexuality and Women,” that Blake’s vision of a liberated female
sexuality is designed to gratify only male fantasies. Hence Oothoon offers to spread “silken nets and traps
of adamant” to catch for Theotormon “girls of mild silver, or of furious gold,” (<hi rend="i">VDA</hi>
7:23-24), but no male in the poem offers to provide Oothoon with a corresponding orgy of male lovers.
Webster’s essay condenses the argument already available in her <hi rend="i">Blake’s Prophetic
Psychology</hi>—that Blake never resolved his Oedipal fixation with killing the father and possessing the
mother and hence that the sexually liberated woman is also the sexually available mother. But she is
particularly shrewd here in seeing the ways in which Blake’s fantasies have gratified his male readers, who
have persistently ignored or denied his misogynistic attitudes to women.</p>
          <p>A more sophisticated feminism informs Elizabeth Langland’s formal-thematic interpretation of
Blake’s “The Sick Rose.” Not only does Langland provide an excellent overview of the possibilities and
problems of contemporary feminist theory, but she tracks through a careful reading of the poem, its design,
and its Notebook contexts the difference that gender makes, both to our understanding of the Rose (which could
be male as well as female) and the speaker (who could be female as well as male). The essay is flawed only by
the failure to include an illustration of the poem, an odd omission since less useful illustrations are
provided for other essays. Her close reading of the myriad contexts of the poem gives added force to her
conclusion, that “ideology” (she should probably specify gender as a crucial
<pb id="p23-100" n="100"/>
dimension of ideology here) determines the “nature of critical knowledge itself.”</p>
          <p>A similarly powerful argument for Blake’s ideological blind spots is made by David Aers in his
Marxist essay, “Representations of Revolution: From <hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi> to 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>,” in which he analyzes the way in which Blake’s failure to envision particular
differences and a meaningful plurality among the classes of the oppressed enables Blake to posit a polarized,
two-class society, and then to celebrate a “salvific violence” where by the sons of Los trample down the
sons of Urizen in Night IX of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, a violence that modern readers ought to find
extremely troubling. Aers’s essay, which invokes both Bakhtin and Carol Gilligan’s concept of a female
ethic of care to good effect, is flawed only by its failure to incorporate into its argument an analysis of
what should be Aers’ primary text, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi></p>
          <p>Nelson Hilton and Hazard Adams both pay close attention to Blake’s use of particular words and
rhetorical methods to generate convincing readings of specific texts. In “Literal/<hi
rend="i">Tiriel</hi>/Material,” Hilton offers another demonstration of what he has called Blake’s literal
imagination, the way allusion and wordplay function in Blake’s texts. In this case, he turns to the
Concordance to show how <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> becomes a calculated meditation on the death of old myths,
the curse of inherited language and metrics, and the ways Blake attempts to lift off the burden of the rubbish
heap of the past. In “Synecdoche and Method,” Hazard Adams describes the peculiarly radical and
progressive nature of Blake’s use of synecdoche, which he illustrates with a brilliant analysis of the way
both intrinsic and historical clues enable us to understand the way Blake’s mind worked in composing plate
10 of <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi></p>
          <p>These essays provide a compelling illustration of how contemporary critical theory both impedes
and enables our understanding and appreciation of literary texts. When theory becomes the focus of critical
attention, as it does in the essays by the editors, Stephen Cox and David Wagenknecht, it can lead to little
more than a self-indulgent hermeneutic exercise, resulting in reductive, predictable (or unconvincing)
readings. Typically, for all that these exercises claim to take into account the necessary self-reflexivity of
both language and ideology, they are usually carried out with no recognition, as is the case here, of the
individual critic’s personal psychological profile, gender, ethnicity, religion, or other ideological
commitments and interests. But when theory enables the critic to uncover the blind spots or fault lines of
both the author’s and previous critics’ ideological limitations and thus opens the way to more
encompassing and genuinely critical understandings, as the essays by Langland and Aers do most effectively in
this volume, it must be welcome. Perhaps, in the context of the deconstructive and self-critical methods
advocated so pervasively in this volume, I should add, “to me.” And end with a personal credo that grows
out of my experience of gender oppression and teaching of feminist theory: I believe that the time has come
for contemporary literary criticism to move beyond deconstructive theory (whose intellectual insights have by
now been absorbed, even exhausted) in an effort to recuperate more politically engaged, less elitist,
practices of reading and teaching.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
