<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>23.2.grenfell</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">William Blake, The Marriage of Heaven and Hell, performed by DIY Theatre</title>
        <author n="Grenfell">Michael Grenfell</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1989</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1989</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">23.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Manging Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>Martin Bidney</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Michael Grenfell</name>
              <name>Desmond King-Hele</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Dena Bain Taylor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1989"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_23">
    <body>
	<pb id="p23-95" n="95"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-23-2-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">William Blake, <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi><lb/>
DIY Theatre,<lb/>
Rosemary Branch Theatre Club, London, July 1988</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <hi rend="b">Reviewed by</hi>
            <docAuthor>
              <hi rend="b">Michael</hi>
              <name>
                <hi rend="b">Grenfell</hi>
              </name>
            </docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Is Blake entertaining? One step inside this tiny café theatre and the average member of the
public might well regard any encounter with him as a pretty hellish experience: strange subterranean voices
cry out like lost souls in an auditorium covered in shroudlike drops. From the ceiling hang various luminous
objects with no apparent sense or meaning. Striding through the audience onto the stage, the three actors (two
men and a woman) continue in the same vein— “Energy, Genius, Infinite, One Law,” they hiss in witch-like
tones before stating “The Argument.” I say stating, but really it was chanted using various vocal
styles—unison, staccato, and syncopation. This made quite a sound, but what was gained in energy and sheer
dynamics was lost in clarity and finally in comprehension of the text. Happily this was not the case
elsewhere, and, often following Blake’s original “color-coding” (Copy H), the swapping of lines between
the actors injected a terrific pace and direction into the words. At key points, as in “A Song of
Liberty,” the players set the text to music, but this was less successful, the natural rhymes and rhythms of
the words seeming to fight with the imposed melody.</p>
          <p>The biggest laughs of the evening came from the “Proverbs of Hell”—whether out of excess
sorrow, nervousness, or at the audacity and wit of the man. With so many no offer it was inevitable that some
were passed over rapidly, while others were given a more lingering treatment. Intended interpretation, too,
was often heavily hinted at by the use of appropriate intonation. For the most part this was acceptable, but,
less forgivable in the interrogative, puzzled tone adopted for “Enough! or Too much”—surely more
didactic and imperative in the text?</p>
          <pb id="p23-96" n="96"/>
          <p>But this was mostly a dramatic presentation, the three actors flinging themselves about the stage
in the kind of ecstatic postures of “William” and “Robert” depicted in <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi>
Things settled down, though, for the Memorable Fancies which gave them stronger character and more
conventional narrative to follow. Isaiah was played as pompous and illusory to the Blakean protagonist, whilst
Ezekiel became lying and pretentious. Debatable as these interpretations may be, it did make good theatre.
Indeed, considering the drama of much of Blake’s work, I wonder how more has not found its way onto the
stage.</p>
          <p>“Energy,” they finally cried, “is eternal delight,” tearing away the shrouds to reveal
painted fire over all the walls. A powerful and visual performance, then, of Blake’s Hell with all its
heavenly delights. Corrosive stuff!</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
