<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>23.2.deluca</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake and Burke in Astonishment!</title>
        <author n="De Luca">V. A. De Luca</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1989</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1989</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">23.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Manging Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>Martin Bidney</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Michael Grenfell</name>
              <name>Desmond King-Hele</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Dena Bain Taylor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1989"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_23">
    <body>
	<pb id="p23-100" n="100"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-23-2-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake and Burke in Astonishment!</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>V. A. <name>De Luca</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>On those occasions when Blake discloses his most important views on art and poetry—say, in the
<hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, or in the Annotations to Reynolds’s <hi rend="i">Discourses</hi>,
or in the letter to Butts of 6 July 1803—the sublime never seems far from his mind. We do not know the
extent of his acquaintance with formal eighteenth-century theories of the sublime but we can be certain that
he read the most famous treatise on the subject—Burke’s <hi rend="i">Philosophical Enquiry into . . . the
Sublime and the Beautiful</hi>: “Burke’s Treatise on the Sublime &amp; Beautiful,” he tells us in the
annotations to Reynolds, “is founded on the Opinions of Newton &amp; Locke on this Treatise Reynolds has
grounded many of his assertions.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">1</ref>
Blake tells us that he read it when “very young,” and what he read when “very young” usually struck,
held in a strong clasp of love or hate. The avowed hatred in this case has tended to mask a rich overlay of
tastes and assumptions. A few critics have recognized the link between the two men,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">2</ref> but our sense of the complexity of the relation may still
need some refining—such as how much even Blake’s departures from Burke issue from a Burkean ground. 
<note id="n54"><hi rend="s">1</hi> David V. Erdman, ed. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William
Blake</hi>, newly rev. ed. (Garden City: Anchor P/Doubleday, 1982) 660; hereafter referred to as E.</note>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">2</hi> See, for example, Josephine Miles, <hi rend="i">Eras and Modes in English
Poetry</hi> (Berkeley and Los Angeles: U of California P, 1957) 78-99; Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Energy
and the Imagination: A Study of the Development of Blake’s Thought</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1970) 18-24;
and especially Paley, <hi rend="i">The Continuing City: William Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem (Oxford: Clarendon P,
1983) 57ff.</note></p>
          <p>One handy and efficient way of approaching a complicated relation between two writers is to focus
on key terms that are shared in their vocabularies. Blake and Burke share “astonishment,” one of the
central terms in
<pb id="p23-101" n="101"/>
the idiom of the eighteenth-century sublime, and an examination of their use of the term sheds light on the
parallels and divergencies of their aesthetics. In the discourse of sublimity “astonishment” comes laden
with ambiguity: it names a human psychological state, yet resonates with the powers of external nature, from
the airy might of thunder (from which it derives etymologically) to the solidity of stone (which it resembles
in sound). Burke begins the second part of his <hi rend="i">Philosophical Enquiry</hi>, an analysis of the
sublime proper, with a definition of “astonishment”:
<q>
The passion caused by the great and sublime in <hi rend="i">nature</hi>, when those causes operate most
powerfully, is Astonishment; and astonishment is that state of the soul, in which all its motions are
suspended, with some degree of horror. In this case the mind is so entirely filled with its object, that it
cannot entertain any other, nor by consequence reason on that object which employs it. Hence arises the great
power of the sublime, that far from being produced by them, it anticipates our reasonings, and hurries us on
by an irresistible force.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n56"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Edmund Burke, <hi rend="i">A Philosophical Enquiry into the Origin of Our
Ideas of the Sublime and the Beautiful</hi>, ed. J. T. Boulton (London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1958)
57.</note></q>
Writers throughout the century refer to astonishment in similar terms.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n57" type="note">4</ref> But however much these formulas are repeated, perplexities abound. The
psychological state itself seems curiously resistant to straightforward discursive explanation, as Burke’s
own highly figurative language demonstrates. There is a marked ambiguity in the play of these figures. At the
moment of astonishment, when the power of the sublime manifests itself, the mind becomes utterly open to the
influx of what it beholds (“filled with its object”), and yet this flood of power into the mind produces
no kinetic transfer of energy to the mind’s faculties but rather the reverse, a suspension of internal
motion, a total arrest. At first appearing entirely permeable, the mind in an instant becomes impenetrable,
like a container packed to the bursting point (“so entirely filled with its object, that it cannot entertain
any other”). The mind is quite stopped (“suspended”), only to be “hurried”; its internal density
becomes crushing and yet finally it is easily carried along. “Astonishment,” then, cannot be so much
described as circumscribed by a ring of mutually canceling figures such as action/arrest,
penetration/resistance, inertial mass/momentum. The figures are drawn from physical mechanics, but they
compose no mechanics that Newton would recognize. Here the continuum of cause and effect breaks down; outward
forces have unpredictable inward consequences. As Burke presents it, “astonishment” marks the intervention
of sharp discontinuities in the spheres of both nature and mind: nature suddenly manifests itself in so
overwhelming a fashion that normal relations of subject and object are abolished; at the same time the mind
loses its consistency of operation and becomes a thing of paradox, of self-contradictory extremes. 
<note id="n57"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Addison, for example, tells us that “our imagination loves to be filled with an
object, or to grasp at anything that is too big for its capacity. We are flung into a pleasing astonishment at
such unbounded views. . . .” According to Johnson, “[The sublime is] that comprehension and expanse of
thought which at once fills the whole mind, and of which the first effect is sudden astonishment, and the
second rational admiration.” Here is a sampling of similar contemporary opinions: “The sublime . . . takes
possession of our attention, and of all our faculties, and absorbs them in astonishment”; “[the sublime]
imports such ideas presented to the mind, as raise it to an uncommon degree of elevation, and fill it with
admiration and astonishment”; “objects exciting terror are . . . in general sublime; for terror always
implies astonishment, occupies the whole soul, and suspends all its motions.” See, respectively, 
<hi rend="i">Works of Joseph Addison</hi>, 6 vols. (London: T. Cadell and W. Davies, 1811) 4: 340; Samuel Johnson,
“The Life of Cowley,” <hi rend="i">Lives of the English Poets</hi>, ed. George Birkbeck Hill, 3 vols.
(1905; Oxford: Clarendon P; New York: Octagon Books, 1967) 1: 20-21; James Usher, <hi rend="i">Clio: Or, a
Discourse on Taste</hi>, 2nd ed. (London: T. Davies, 1769) 102; Hugh Blair, “A Critical Dissertation on the
Poems of Ossian,” in <hi rend="i">The Poems of Ossian</hi>, trans. James Macpherson, 2 vols. (London: W.
Strahan and T. Cadell, 1773) 2: 422; Alexander Girard, <hi rend="i">An Essay on Taste</hi> (London: A Millar,
1759) 19.</note></p>
          <p>It is easy to comprehend the part that astonishment plays in the dynamics of a Burkean
“terrific” sublime. Terror and astonishment are kindred states, as Burke makes clear in an etymological
aside:
<q>
The Romans used the verb <hi rend="i">stupeo</hi>, a term which strongly marks the state of an astonished
mind, to express the effect either of simple fear, or of astonishment; the word <hi rend="i">attonitus</hi>,
(thunderstruck) is equally expressive of the alliance of these ideas; and do not the french 
<hi rend="i">étonnement</hi> and the english <hi rend="i">astonishment</hi> and <hi rend="i">amazement</hi>,
point out as clearly the kindred emotions which attend fear and wonder?<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n58"><hi rend="s">5</hi><hi rend="i"> Philosophical Enquiry</hi> 58.</note></q>
To be struck by lightning is literally a form of astonishment, for etymologically the word means
“thunderstruck.” Perhaps the prestige of the term “astonishment” in eighteenth-century aesthetics
derives ultimately from Longinus, who tells us that “the Sublime, when seasonably addressed, with the rapid
force of Lightning has born down all before it, and shewn at one stroke the compacted Might of
Genius.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n59" type="note">6</ref> The two metaphors that
Longinus employs here for the onset of the sublime, the stroke of natural lightning and the blow of
intellectual power, imply a hidden and prior third, one that connects the forces of nature to the forces of
mind. This mediating figure is of course that of a divine being, like the Jove and Jehovah of myth and
scripture, at once the author of natural thunder and of human inspiration. Hence the word 
<hi rend="i">astonishment</hi> incorporates within itself two contradictory aspects of the sublime; it immobilizes
or releases, destroys or raises up. One is either struck by the divine power and “hurried” on to
participate in its glories, or one is struck dead as a stone. <note id="n59"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Dionysius
Longinus, <hi rend="i">Essay on the Sublime</hi>, trans. William Smith (London, 1756) 3.</note></p>
          <p>Blake shows a surprisingly persistent allegiance to Burkean settings and diction, giving us
imagery and narrative scenarios that are full of sensory deprivations—darkness, cloudiness, and the host of
disquieting sensations that gather under the general term “terror”.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60" type="note">7</ref> He also uses the term “astonishment” more frequently than
any other major poet in the period 1660-1830,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61"
type="note">8</ref> and always with careful discrimination. Extraordinarily sensitive to the possibilities of
word play,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62" type="note">9</ref> he is quick to hear the
thunder and to see the “stone” in astonishment.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n63"
type="note">10</ref> The word thus could easily encompass the whole program of Urizen, armed with “his ten
thousands of thunders” (<hi rend="i">BU</hi> 3.28), to bring about a “solid without fluctuation,” “a
wide world of solid obstruction” (<hi rend="i">BU</hi> 4.11,23). Hence to experience astonishment means in
one sense to turn to stone, to be “filled,” as Burke would say, with the inducing power and filled solid.
Thus in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, “Wonder, awe, fear, astonishment, / Petrify the eternal myriads” 
(<hi rend="i">BU</hi> 18.13-14). As it is the fate of overweening deities in Blake to be struck by their own
thunder, as soon as Urizen manifests himself in all his pride, he is struck down and stunned (from 
<hi rend="i">étonnement</hi>) into “<hi rend="i">a</hi>
	<pb id="p23-102" n="102"/>
stony sleep” (<hi rend="i">BU</hi> 6.7) or, elsewhere, into “<hi rend="i">a stoned</hi> stupor” 
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 52.20). The moment of astonishment, then, is <hi rend="i">par excellence</hi>, the moment
when, in Blake’s famous formula, one becomes what one beholds. Beholding Urizen’s stony sleep, mentioned
above, Los is “smitten with astonishment” (<hi rend="i">BU</hi> 8.1). But whose astonishment is meant
here? Los’s own or that of Urizen whom he beholds lying stunned? There is no meaningful way of sorting out
distinctions of this nature. Astonishment astonishes, the petrified petrifies. Thus in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, seeking for the Minute Particulars, Los is again “astonished he beheld only the
petrified surfaces” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 46.5); two lines earlier we read “Los was all astonishment &amp;
terror: he trembled sitting on the Stone.” Los is now filled with his stony object and is 
<hi rend="i">all</hi> astonishment; we see <hi rend="i">all as stone</hi> in these regions. From becoming all
astonishment it is easy to become a thing that causes astonishment, as in Los’s statement, “I now am what
I am: a horror and an astonishment” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 8.18). The abstract noun becomes a stony
particular, substituting itself for an individuality now petrified and soon to petrify others. 
<note id="n60"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Just as Burke’s sublime rides on an aesthetics of darkness, deprivation, pain,
and “whatever is in any sort terrible” (<hi rend="i">Philosophical Enquiry</hi> 39) so in Blake’s
vocabulary <hi rend="i">dark</hi> prevails numerically over <hi rend="i">light</hi>, night over 
<hi rend="i">day, death</hi> over <hi rend="i">life.</hi> More notably, the word <hi rend="i">terror(s)</hi> and
its co-derivatives <hi rend="i">terrible, terrific, terrified</hi>, taken as a collectivity, would rank in the
dozen most frequently used words in his concorded vocabulary (David V. Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Blake
Concordance</hi> [Ithaca: Cornell UP, 1967] reveals a total of 393 uses of these terms). Despite his stated
aversion to Burke, Blake so closely associates the sublime with the terrific that the terminology of the
latter often acquires an honorific lustre in his work. Thus we have such phrases as “Terrified at the
Sublime Wonder” (a reference to the beneficent Spaces of Erin—see <hi rend="i">J</hi> 11.8-15),
“terrible Blake in his pride” (When Klopstock England defied,” line 2), an uncharacteristically
affectionate Enitharmon’s “Lovely terrible Los wonder of Eternity” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 90.160), the
“terrors of friendship” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 45.5), and the “terrific Lions &amp; Tygers” that
“sport and play” before the Great Harvest at the end of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> (<hi rend="i">M</hi>
42.38). In these instances <hi rend="i">terror</hi> loses most of its terrors, and one gets the sense that in
such cases Blake is not paying tribute so much to the signified <hi rend="i">feeling</hi> of terror but rather
to the signifier, a vocabulary of the sublime fondly preserved from the fashions of his youth.</note>
	<note id="n61"><hi rend="s">8</hi> There are 51 uses of the terms from the collectivity 
<hi rend="i">(astonish(ed)(es)(ing)(ment)</hi> in Blake’s poetry. Among poets of comparable stature, range, and
sublime interests, Milton’s poetry yields only 6 instances, Wordworth’s, 17, and Shelley’s, 11. Pope
draws upon this cluster of terms 16 times, almost entirely for his translations of Homer, and Dryden, 11
times, mostly for the <hi rend="i">Aeneid.</hi></note>
	<note id="n62"><hi rend="s">9</hi> See Nelson Hilton, <hi rend="i">Literal Imagination: Blake’s Vision of
Words</hi> (Berkeley: U of California P, 1983) 16-17, and especially 239-57.</note>
	<note id="n63"><hi rend="s">10</hi> This connection is reinforced by the older sense of 
<hi rend="i">astonished</hi> (or its variant <hi rend="i">astonied</hi>) to connote death-like paralysis and
insensibility; thus the <hi rend="i">OED</hi> on <hi rend="i">astonied</hi>: “Stunned; made insensible,
benumbed, paralyzed (1611)”; cf. also Milton on Satan’s legions, who “lie thus astonisht on
th’oblivious Pool” (<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> 1.266).</note></p>
          <p>But as there is a thunder that immobilizes and petrifies, there is also a thunder that cracks
open the stones, releasing our buried powers to freedom, a “crack of doom” for a sullen old dispensation.
In contrast to the “inarticulate thunder” that Urizen booms at his misshapen children in 
<hi rend="i">Vala</hi> (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 70:39), we have the articulare thunder of that true God who “To Man
the wond’rous art of writing gave” and who “speaks in thunder and in fire! / Thunder of Thought, &amp;
flames of fierce desire” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 3.4,5-6). There is also the awakened Albion, “Loud
thundring, with broad flashes of flaming lightning &amp; pillars / Of fire, speaking the Words of Eternity in
Human Forms” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 95.8-9). And there are the at last fraternal Zoas who “conversed
together in Visionary forms dramatic which bright / Redounded from their Tongues in thunderous majesty” 
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 98.28-29). In contrast to the obliterating power of the Urizenic thunder, the power of this
thunder resides in its incisive capacity to clarify and reveal. It does not stun with an avalanche of sound
but cleaves through darkness and obstruction, employing as its cutting tools those instruments that inscribe
the definite lines of Blake’s “writing,” “Words,” and “Forms.”</p>
          <p>It follows that the “astonishment” produced by this clarifying thunder encompasses the moment
when surfaces and opacities are burst to reveal an infinite potential within. Thus when Eno in the 
<hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> “took an atom of space &amp; opend its center / Into Infinitude &amp; ornamented it
with wondrous art / Astonishd sat her Sisters of Beulah to see her soft affections” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi>
9.12-14) A similar response to visionary revelation appears in Blake’s ecstatic report of his first days at
Felpham:
<q>
In particles bright<lb/>
The jewels of Light<lb/>
Distinct shone &amp; clear<lb/>
Amazd &amp; in fear<lb/>
I each particle gazed<lb/>
Astonishd Amazed<lb/>
For each was a Man<lb/>
Human formd.<lb/>
(Letter to Butts, 2 Oct. 1800, lines 15-22, E 712)
</q>
If visions of nature humanized bring astonishment, so too do the recognition and recovery of unfallen portions
of humanity within the self: “Los embracd the Spectre first as a brother / Then as another Self; astonishd
humanizing &amp; in tears” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 85.29-30). Images of barriers broken, of visions glimpsed
through sudden openings, of obdurate forms melting down and flowing together, attend this form of
astonishment:
<q>
Then Los said I behold the Divine Vision thro the broken Gates<lb/>
Of thy poor broken heart astonishd melted into Compassion &amp; Love<lb/>
(<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 99.15-16)
</q>
Finally, in the single instance in Blake’s poetry where astonishment is modified by the adjective 
<hi rend="i">sublime</hi>, Jerusalem recalls ancient days before Albion’s dreadful separation: “I taught the
ships of the sea to sing the songs of Zion. / Italy saw me, in sublime astonishment: France was wholly mine”
(<hi rend="i">J</hi> 79.38-39). The response of the nations embraces the full paradox of the sublime moment;
arrest is freedom here, for to be filled with the object in this case is to be filled with a being who is
“called Liberty among the Children of Albion” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 54.5).</p>
          <p>Blake’s wide-ranging use of the term <hi rend="i">astonishment</hi> provides a good index of
his understanding of the problematic dynamics of the eighteenth-century sublime. Not only does astonishment
occupy a gap between polarized states of experience but it also unfolds within itself alternate destinies of
the sublime moment. Two possible sublimes quiver in the indeterminacy of the moment of astonishment: one, the
sublime of terror and deprivation most closely associated with Burke, and the other, a sublime of desire and
plenitude. Blake’s imagination is repeatedly drawn to the Burkean sublime, as our examination of his
vocabulary and imagery indicates, but nowhere does this evidence suggest that he finds in Burkean
“astonishment” any genuine access for the mind to an expansive and liberating power. Burke would have us
believe that psychic disequilibrium, suspension of faculties, and immobilization of will are sure indications
of the presence of an overwhelming external power or magnitude. Blake reads such scenes otherwise:
encountering “terrific” objects his protagonists reel not at a magnitude of power made present but at the
magnitude of power lost, at the degree of petrifaction revealed
<pb id="p23-103" n="103"/>
in so-called powers by the time they present themselves as natural “terrors.”</p>
          <p>Blake seeks a less melancholy sublime, and if as a poet he is to gratify desire and recover
plenitude, he must attempt some sort of redemption of astonishment. When Reynolds repeats the Burkean saw that
“obscurity . . . is one source of the sublime,” Blake retorts that it is “Neither the Source of the
Sublime nor of any Thing Else” (E 658). Yet in a famous letter to Thomas Butts where he proclaims the
sublimity of his own poetry (he calls it a “Sublime Allegory”), Blake ventures an important clarification:
“Allegory addressed to the Intellectual powers <hi rend="i">while it is altogether hidden</hi> from the
Corporeal Understanding is <hi rend="i">My Definition</hi> of the Most Sublime Poetry” (E 730; emphases
mine). To obscure originally meant to veil, cover, or conceal, and nothing can be more thoroughly obscured
than that which is altogether hidden. Thus a sublime object (in this case the poetical text) becomes “most
sublime” when it is altogether obscure to our mundane faculties. There is no apparent conflict with Burke
here. Indeed, it is not immediately easy to see how this bafflement of the “Corporeal Understanding”
differs much from Burke’s own opinion in the <hi rend="i">Philosophical Enquiry</hi>: “It is our ignorance
of things that causes all our admiration, and chiefly excites our passions.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n64" type="note">11</ref> Blake apparently has no intention of abandoning the drama,
the clash of oppositions, and the suspense inherent in Burke’s account of the sublime. He is willing to
exploit Burke’s evocations of giddiness and irresistible rush since they so easily consort with Blake’s
own imagery of centers opening up, gates broken down, and forms melting. There is a need, however, to relocate
the scene of this drama, away from a point of humiliating encounter between the experiencing mind and some
thunderous externality. As Blake’s own notions of the sublime become fully articulated, the encounter is
seen to take place between a lesser and a greater faculty of the mind, made manifest through the mediation of
the poetic text. Blake not only represents scenes of astonishment in his work but also seeks to create fresh
moments of astonishment in the encounter of poem and reader, offering a petrific text to stony understandings
and a field of openings for the receptive. <note id="n64"><hi rend="s">11</hi><hi rend="i"> Philosophical
Enquiry</hi> 61.</note></p>
          <p>It becomes increasingly clear that we should attach the term “astonishment” to that moment
when the reader’s mind divides into a stunned Corporeal Understanding and privileged intellectual powers.
Astonishment is thus a liminal or threshold state, dividing the complacent mind from the stunned understanding
and the latter from exalted powers of intuitive reception. The function of liminal states is to mark
boundaries and hence to provide bounding outlines for what lies beyond them. Blake’s sublime allegory serves
to isolate the intellectual powers from the other components of the mind, for the essence of Blake’s sublime
resides in intellect becoming present to itself as a wholly determinate form (see the <hi rend="i">Descriptive
Catalogue</hi>: “The Beauty proper for sublime art, is lineaments, or forms and features that are capable of
being the receptacles of intellect” [E 544]). The analogy to this process in Burke’s system would be the
recoil of delight that floods the consciousness when it realizes its safe distance from the contingent pain or
deprivation that provoked the sublime experience in the first place.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n65" type="note">12</ref> Blake and Burke do not differ in their understanding of the structure or the
dynamics of the sublime experience. Blake’s quarrel is with Burke’s choice of sublime objects (ratios of
the five senses rather than glimpses of Eternal Death or of Divine Vision) and Burke’s apparatus of
transformation (nerves and muscles rather than passion and imagination). But both writers place discontinuity
of consciousness at the center of their ideas of the sublime. <note id="n65"><hi rend="s">12</hi> See 
<hi rend="i">Philosophical Enquiry</hi> 37, 40.</note></p>
          <p>If anything, in stressing the determinate, the particular, and the distinct as necessary
qualities of sublime objects, as he does in the Reynolds annotations and elsewhere, Blake provides for a more
radical discontinuity and deprivation of the ordinary senses than anything that Burke can supply from his
storehouse of the corporeally vast and terrific. The Blakean visionary symbol, the reflexive emblem of the
Intellectual Powers—determinate, particular, and distinct in itself—must be radically discontinuous with
everything that is beyond its bounding outline. Here Blake occupies a sphere of conception that would be
“altogether hidden” to Edmund Burke, but we would be wrong to ignore the elements of a Burkean sensibility
that lick about the borders of this sphere like a darkness to its radiance, enhancing its outline. Blake
always assimilates his enemies’ strength before he discards their excrementitious husk.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p23-104" n="104" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
