<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>23.2.mann</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Donald Ault, Narrative Unbound: Re-Visioning William Blake’s The Four
          Zoas</title>
        <author n="Mann">Paul Mann</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1989</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1989</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">23.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Manging Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Rodney M. Baine</name>
              <name>Martin Bidney</name>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>V.A. De Luca</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>Michael Grenfell</name>
              <name>Desmond King-Hele</name>
              <name>Paul Mann</name>
              <name>Anne K. Mellor</name>
              <name>Dena Bain Taylor</name>
              <name>Joseph Viscomi</name>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1989"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_23">
    <body>
	<pb id="p23-80" n="80"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-23-2-0007">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Donald Ault, <hi rend="i">Narrative Unbound: Re-Visioning William
                Blake’s</hi> The Four Zoas. Barrytown, NY: Station Hill Press, 1987. xxvi + 518 pp.
              $37.50 cloth/$14.95 paper.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Paul <name>Mann</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>An enormous, astonishing, monumental book; a quantum leap in the reading of 
              <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>; etc. (It is difficult, at one level, to avoid the
            rhetoric of dust-jacket superlatives in appraising the scale and importance of Ault’s
            accomplishment; but so too the puny scale of a review will inevitably belittle his book
            even in singing its praises.) For more than fifteen years, patiently, obsessively, Ault
            has labored over <hi rend="i">FZ</hi>, his “master text,” reading and rereading,
            revising and revising and revising (“revisioning”). The phrase “master text” (xviii) is
            in fact exemplary. But Blake sought no disciples and Ault is no false-humble acolyte.
            What we are given are the results not only of scholarly study but of a sustained attempt
            to rise to <hi rend="i">FZ</hi>’s occasion, to answer to its demands. In fact, 
              <hi rend="i">Narrative Unbound</hi> is nearly as demanding as <hi rend="i">FZ</hi> itself.
            One imagines readers so severely tested by the demands <hi rend="i">NU</hi> transfers to
            them—outrageous demands, for a patience and obsessiveness approaching Ault’s own—that
            they resort to the stock charge of self-indulgence. Here, they will say, is still one
            more critic who thinks he deserves as much attention as the poet he interprets, who
            doesn’t read and explicate but usurps, who overwhelms us with an excess that some Blake
            slogan or other calls for but no one really wants to witness. Just who is the master of
            this master text, Blake or Ault? But in reading Ault’s vast book one might also come to
            the conclusion that the only way really to appreciate <hi rend="i">FZ</hi>, to be
            faithful to it, is to exceed it, or rather to <hi rend="i">keep it</hi> excessive, to
            refuse reduction at all costs.</p>
          <p>What sort of mastery does this master text require? For Ault, reading must see itself
            in the light of Blake’s radical insistence on the primacy of perception. It is no longer
            a matter of choosing between a hypostatic Poem Itself that pretends to bracket off every
            “extrinsic” relation and one immersed in some “concrete” historical context, nor between
            authorial intention and readerly affect. Ault’s proper reader is neither usurper nor
            servant, neither before nor after meaning: in <hi rend="i">FZ</hi>, Ault discovers,
            “text and reader come into existence simultaneously to constitute and alter one another
            at each point 
          <pb id="p23-81" n="81"/>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/> 
            in the poem” (6). It is a revolutionary
            notion, if taken seriously, and announces what might be the most Blakean project that
            Blake criticism could take upon itself, one in which ontology recapitulates
            phenomenology: being as an act of perception, an act of minds in relation, with no
            actuality outside of relation. Becoming and beholding and being beheld are simultaneous,
            interconstitutive, a single nexus: “perspective ontology,” in Ault’s phrase. We have
            seen this sort of claim before—Frye, of course, begins his own study with an analysis of
            Blake’s radical epistemology—but in Ault it is not just a claim, it is a 
            <hi rend="i">modus operandi.</hi> Ault’s <hi rend="i">FZ</hi> is an attempt to generate in its
            reader an <hi rend="i">actual</hi> awareness of the primacy of perception, and 
              <hi rend="i">NU</hi> is an attempt to respond to that awareness in kind. But to respond in
            this manner is necessarily to produce something excessive, outrageous, monstrous, no
            longer simply a book on a poem: indeed, it will be difficult henceforth to separate
            study-title from poem-title. Perhaps they should be rewritten thus: 
            <hi rend="i">NU/FZ.</hi></p>
          <p>So the massive bound object that Ault names <hi rend="i">Narrative Unbound</hi> is a
            monument to the inter-exorbitance of text and reading. It is a monument constructed by
            the relentless disclosure and intercalation of what became, in practice, endlessly
            resonant, mutually interfering <hi rend="i">details.</hi> So much detail that Ault can
            provide no index: “categories that would make sense for an index . . . would generate
            [one] competitive in length with the book itself” (xxii). The very detailedness of
            Ault’s study is its first gift and one of its foremost theses about 
            <hi rend="i">FZ.</hi> “The physical bulk of this book is integral to its program: the
accumulation
            of details does not <hi rend="i">exemplify</hi> but actually 
            <hi rend="i">constitutes</hi> its argument” (xxiv; Ault’s emphases). Ault’s project is
Blakean not
            only in its epic scale but in its microscopic attentiveness. Not a single verbal blur or
            mark is permitted to admit of insignificance. Minute particularity is not just a “theme”
            here, it is an operational principle, a way of enacting or embodying a specificity that
            remains, for others, only a general idea. We must imagine a reading that has so
            thoroughly appropriated the poem that it knows immediately if some instance of food or
            circles or the sun or sitting or mildness or armour recurs similarly or differently at
            some distant elsewhere in the poem, and if that <hi rend="i">kind</hi> of recurrence
            recurrence or difference resonates with narrative strategies at yet other junctures; for
            Ault the poem is a complex web (an image that may already mark a reservation about 
              <hi rend="i">NU</hi>) whose slightest vibration is transmitted throughout the entire
            network. We must imagine him coming to know the poem virtually by heart and still,
            daily, uncovering new details, new relations between cruxes he had once thought settled,
            with each discovery having to alter his sense of the whole until the constant flux of
            this alteration finally unsettles every hope for a wholeness dependent upon
            closure—until alteration becomes the poem. That is the sort of monument we encounter
            here: <hi rend="i">NU/FZ</hi> is an altar to alteration. The key is once again in
            epistemology.” The Eye altering alters all”: to mark well some hitherto unmarked detail
            is fundamentally, substantively, to transform the whole. Nor can such revision ever end.
            The potential and perhaps virtual endlessness of Ault’s reading is epitomized in 
              <hi rend="i">NU</hi>’s extraordinary marginalia, where he not only frames, summarizes,
            annotates and glosses but also interrupts, extends, departs from his own text, reaches
            toward still other “possible” readings. For Ault, the perpetual perceptual motion of
            this reading <hi rend="i">is</hi> the meaning of <hi rend="i">FZ.</hi></p>
          <p>Let me try to summarize <hi rend="i">NU</hi>’s argument without displacing either the
            primacy of its detail or its radical phenomenological embeddedness.</p>
          <p>Assume that, faced with a text of <hi rend="i">FZ</hi>’s density, the Common Reader
            would try to organize the experience of the poem into some unitary and coherent sense,
            some interpretation that would, in effect, be simpler than the poem itself. The task
            would be to resolve difficulties into 
<pb id="p23-82" n="82"/>
singular meanings—however
            complex, however admittedly partial. For Ault, such resolutions, such closures, are
            profoundly anti-Blakean; perhaps the very concern with establishing the poem’s meaning
            is anti-Blakean. Every attempt to define some “character” as an autonomous allegorical
            identity; every attempt to read through the poem’s incredible flux to the presumed core
            of some more or less coherent plot; every attempt to locate in the poem a single
            narrative agent finally capable of resurrecting its fall into division into a unity that
            has anything in common with classical aesthetic categories: every normative critical
            project toward <hi rend="i">FZ</hi> is classed as single vision, as 
            <hi rend="i">Newtonian.</hi> (We might remark here that Ault has a particularly single vision of
            the common reader’s commitment to single vision; Ault’s invocation of this normative
            reading as a basic plot in any actual encounter with the text might very well
            overdetermine it, rendering it at times little more than a strawman against which to
            measure his super-anti-methodology.) The poem’s chief task is to resist and supercede
            both Newtonian narrative structures and their counterparts in the reader’s mental
            operations. Instances of such Newtonian projects are not difficult to locate, even prior
            to what Ault apparently takes as “reading.” The persistent editorial attempt to
            normalize the text of <hi rend="i">FZ</hi> and of Blake’s work in general is one
            instance of the sort of attitude against which Ault militates; the ongoing debate about
            whether Blake—as primary creative agent—has succeeded or failed, finished or abandoned
            this poem is another. In what is one of its most radical gestures, <hi rend="i">NU</hi>
            simply hypostatizes the manuscript text, takes it as is, sets aside all questions of
            whether “Blake” finished the poem as irrelevant to its true purposes. What once seemed
            editorial “discrepancies”—accidents of the poem’s incompletion—are neither resolved nor
            dismissed but “taken to be significant <hi rend="i">as such</hi>” (xvii; Ault’s
            emphasis). Along lines like these, <hi rend="i">FZ</hi> is constituted as a 
              <hi rend="i">process</hi> by which the propensity toward Newtonian single vision that dominates
            normative reading, that dominates most normative mental activity, is continuously and at
            times brutally “subverted.” The poem becomes a School for Epistemologists in which we
            are retrained for Fourfold, or at least Non-Newtonian, Vision.</p>
          <p>This subversive education is carried out not only through the poem’s corrosive flood of
            detail but, at the same time, in <hi rend="i">NU/FZ</hi>’s deployment of these details
            in a range of extremely complex and “incommensurable” narrative strategies. 
              <hi rend="i">NU/FZ</hi> gives us an unprecedented look into the poem’s flux. Indeed, one
suspects,
            it is in the enumeration of these strategies, as much as in the quantity of detail that
            he raises, for the first time, into critical attention, that Ault’s influence is most
            likely to be felt. Tumultuous shiftings, transformations, disruptions, multiple
            intersections, fractured mirrorings, mutual containments, eclipses and feedback loops
            are the order of this world. Everything is a version, an inversion, a revision of
            something else, an aspect or analysis of something else, “embedded” in or a suppression
            of something else, overlapping or reemerging from something else. An event might be seen
            primarily as a “perspective analysis” of one or more prior events and at the same time
            embedded in or bracketed by them. Nights VIIa and VIIb are treated, at one moment, as
            alternative narrative perspectives (328, 333); later, VIIb is embedded in VIIa (475-76).
            Distant events are conterminous and consecutive events are simultaneous; an established
            sequence of events might turn out to be simultaneous from another perspective and in
            reverse order from yet another. “Event-clusters overlap but are by no means
            unequivocally identical” (268). An outcome can create “preconditions” for a prior event
            that seems to be its origin: “The Lamb [of God] and Satan are . . . preconditions for
            each other’s entrance into the narrative proper” (275; also 327, 336, etc.). What is at
            one juncture seen as a cause will later appear as an effect of what it appeared to have
            caused. Transformations can as easily be “retroactive” (300) as successive: new
            information might substantially change not only our understanding of what has preceded
            but <hi rend="i">therefore</hi>—and this is precisely the causal link these
            transformations underscore—the character of the event-complex itself, and of the chains
            of events that depend from it. “[R]e-enactments <hi rend="i">alter</hi> those earlier
            relationships through a complex process of feedback” (329; Ault’s emphasis). Competing
            versions of events (e.g., the two versions of the “war plot” concluding Night I) cause
            the reader either to suppress differences, to invent overviews that circumvent
            incommensurability—both Newtonian responses—or to embrace narrative undecidability and a
            radically perspectual sense of the real. As Ault remarks, in one of his provisional
            summaries of the onto-epistemo-narrative strategies of <hi rend="i">NU/FZ</hi>: 
              <pb id="p23-83" n="83"/><q> Among the comprehensive textual models or patterns for
              perspective transformation which Blake invokes throughout the poem, the following are
              most prevalent: 1) perspective analysis and linearly embedded structures; 2)
              hierarchical displacement; 3) fictions of causal sequence; 4) overlapping of “events”
              by repetition; 5) involution of events by causal circularity and information loops; 6)
              disjunctive jumps (within a nexus of events) between discrete information bits; and 7)
              continuous re-orientation of perspective. (16) </q>
The strategies, in other words, of
            the dreamwork itself. This is, after all, a Dream of Nine Nights, and for Ault the
            engine driving these narrative condensations and displacements is essentially
            psychosexual. Nonetheless he insists that it is the least of Blake’s concerns to 
              <hi rend="i">represent</hi> dreaming. Rather, Blake uses dreamwork strategies to disorient
            the reader’s habitual relation to the nightmare of single-vision reality itself. So that
            readers might read themselves awake.</p>
          <p>The same flux that organizes the narrative defines its characterology. It is in fact
            difficult to discuss characters and narrative structures in separate terms: events are
            displacements of characters and characters are condensations—“crystallizations,” in
            Ault’s recurrent phrase—of events that are perspectives on them. Ault’s radical
            treatment of Tharmas, Enion, Urizen and so on surely constitutes another way in which
            this book should mark future studies. None of these names any longer represents an entry
            in some Blake Dictionary. Now characters overlap each other, are projections or returned
            repressions of each other, arise into the “narrative proper” only through
            event-contexts. Everything here is context-dependent, but contexts are no more fixed or
            absolute than what they contain: a context out of which some character arises might
            later be shown to be a projection by the character it seemed to create. Urizen is not an
            identity who steps from <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> into this poem, nearly if
            perhaps not fully realized: he is sung into it by Enitharmon in a response to Los.
            Urizen “begins” not as a character but as a name attached by Enitharmon to an aspect of
            her own reactive vision. But he does not rest within the fictive frame of her song:
            Enitharmon “calls Urizen into the narrative proper out of his function as a dialogical
            operator in her interpolated vision” (69). She invents him as a fiction of her needs,
              <hi rend="i">ergo</hi> he exists. But when he is “wrenched out of his interpolated
            status,” forced into “the narrative proper,” it is <hi rend="i">as</hi> an agent,
            equipped with a history and identity that influence events not only after he appears but
            retroactively, as if he had always been there. And Enitharmon is “herself,”
            “originally,” a projection of Enion, without prior existence but with retrospective
            force.</p>
          <p>Everything in <hi rend="i">NU/FZ</hi> is generated out of the repression or absence
            that demands it; everything is desired, imagined, projected, sung before it can exist,
            and then exists as if it had always been there, until in some other context it
            disappears into the never-was. Just as characters arise, so they dissolve back into
            event-clusters, or are repressed in the “psyches” of other figures, or end up exerting
            force only as absent or displaced, or function subliminally as “primary aspect[s] of all
            the characters” (175). Their names are like linguistic shifters, words without inherent
            referents that attach themselves to various entities and forces, and that can be
            determined only relationally within a given utterance. As Ault describes it, characters
            are “substitutions for, or analyses of, previously narrated relationships” (120),
            “aspects of one another syntactically and semantically” (234). The flux of characters—an
            “interchangeability of roles in a field of difference” (175), a “crisis of relational
            versus individual identity” (241)—and the flux of events are linked versions of each
            other. In other words, the Zoas and their various Emanations, Spectres, children and so
            on interconstitute one another in the same “perspective ontology” by which, Ault’s Blake
            proposes, we are ourselves interconstituted with the text, and with the world we might
            regenerate out of it.</p>
          <p>Let me cite as evidence at least one passage in which these various concerns
            emphatically converge: 
			<q> Blake forces us to experience the Lamb of God and Satan
              totally from the outside: they appear and disappear enigmatically throughout Night
              VIII. Though they are in some ways the most important “characters” in Night VIII, we
              have no sense of their motives: they seem, even more than other characters, to be
              complexes of relationships, with no real interiors. Although Blake relentlessly forces
              the reader to experience characters as interlocking sets of transforming relationships
              rather than static identities, Blake can lure the reader into accepting the alternate
              fiction that his characters have desires and feel that they are acting causally. The
              Lamb and Satan, however, in Night VIII act exactly as if they are characters totally
                <hi rend="i">constituted by situations</hi> in a way that, for example, Los is not.
              It is impossible to imagine an interior, in this sense, of the Lamb and Satan: they
              remain as completely enigmatic to the characters in the poem as they do to the reader.
              They perform functions, create situations, make conditions possible, and act as
              consolidations of conditions and relationships. But they remain fundamentally
              indeterminate, successfully evading all attempts at scrutiny because, if Blake’s
              perspective ontology holds, there is nothing there to scrutinize. . . . This enigma is
              central to Blake’s establishing the reader’s expectations for entrance into Night IX.
              The reader’s need to seek out motivation, <hi rend="i">internal</hi> cause, within and
              behind these images, is a corollary of the reader’s urgent need for an 
                <hi rend="i">external</hi> redemption in the text. (280-81; Ault’s emphases) </q></p>
          <pb id="p23-84" n="84"/>
          <p>It is a dense passage and could be unraveled along several lines, but what we need most
            to mark here are the various implicit and explicit relations between writer, poem and
            reader. What Ault has produced, in the anti-Newtonian epistemological school of Blake’s
            text, is a version of reader-response criticism—a fact underscored by one of Ault’s few
            overt references to other critics, a late reference to the influence of Stanley Fish
            (511). In <hi rend="i">Surprised By Sin</hi>, we recall, Fish reconsidered the perennial
            problem of the attractiveness of Satan and decided that Milton’s Satan is so designed in
            order to lure the reader as well as Adam and Eve into choosing badly, so that the reader
            can experience and hence better understand the Fall. Ault’s version of Blake’s reader
            also falls. The reader is tempted by the radically disjunctive experience of Blake’s
            poem to choose not Satanic rhetoric but Newtonian order—a bad choice that, as the poem’s
            characters and events themselves demonstrate, leads only to further chaos. Like
            Milton’s, Blake’s reader must be driven toward a paradise within, happier far, a
            difficult paradise of radical indeterminacy and perspective ontology. Hence it is hardly
            surprising to find, in Ault’s text, the familiar Fishian melodrama of author as
            omnipotent manipulator, punishing the reader for his or her own good. In the passage
            cited above, Blake relentlessly forces the reader, lures the reader; again and again in
            Ault’s critical narrative, Blake’s reader is tempted, dazzled, seduced, overwhelmed,
            frustrated. Possibilities of establishing solid origins or closures, of grounding the
            experience of the text in some external order, some non-visionary truth, are continually
            held out to the reader only to be immediately withdrawn. Every discontinuity and
            discrepancy, every blur and mark is recruited into the service of this (dis)abusive
            project. What used to seem accidents of the manuscript’s incompletion now become holes
            purposely left for the reader to fall through in a bizarre, almost sado-masochistic form
            of visionary therapy.</p>
          <p>But the situation is even more complicated than this. For the traditional
            administrative order of readerresponse criticism would be incoherent in the perspective
            ontology Ault’s Blake seeks to reveal. Blake’s perceiver cannot be merely manipulated by
            the perceived: reader-response must be recast within the terms of the profoundly
            relational ontological orders of <hi rend="i">NU/FZ.</hi> As we have seen, text and
            reader are “interconstituted,” in effect operate as writers and readers of one another;
            or rather—for it is still more complicated—“narrative, text, and reader come into
            existence and alter one another at each point in the poem” (6). The reader is not merely
            a screen on which the text’s operations are projected—their teleological alibi, as it
            were, and as they are in so much so-called reader-response criticism; here the reader is
            in some sense the text’s proper agent, its producer. But its blurs and marks are no
            Rorschach either: the matter is more complicated yet: 
			<q> Though the actual individual
              reader is absolutely indispensable to the existence of the <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi>
              narrative and text, it is not the reader but the narrative itself that is the primary
              agent of transformation, while the text participates equally with the reader in their
              acts of mutual constitution and revision. . . . [T]he <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi>
              narrative is a purely relational process that has no existence (cannot be pointed to)
              in any form except through the act of reading. But instead of simply coming into
              existence as a dialectical product of the interaction between reader and text, the 
                <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> narrative actually brings the reader and text into mutual
              existence. This radical relational narrative process undermines Newtonian narrative
              ontology (through retroactive transformation, aspectual interconnection, and so on). .
              . . The <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi> narrative can come into existence only if reader
              and text are freed from existing independent of reading, but this liberation can be
              performed only by the narrative itself: reader, text, and narrative are thus mutually
              preconditions for one another’s existence. (22) </q>
The distinction between
            “narrative” and “text” in passages like this is especially, and perhaps purposefully,
            difficult to determine. Narrative is not simply the order of the poem’s events but the
            non-Newtonian order that those events generate in the reading—which is here to say the
            text’s production—itself; text is not simply manuscript or printed words on the page but
            some order of verbal/authorial agency that is finally indistinguishable from the
            indistinguishability of narrative and reader. There is no reader or text or narrative
            prior to the unfolding of reading, no identity or truth to fall back on; before reading
            animates it, the poem has no ontological priority. (This explains, at least in part,
            Ault’s bracketing-out of all but a few references to prior literary theory, or Blake
            criticism, or influences on Blake; though this is not to say that such references are
            not everywhere implicit.) Like the Zoas themselves, in <hi rend="i">NU/FZ</hi>’s own
            elaborate characterology, nothing and no one has any being except 
            <pb id="p23-85" n="85"/>
through context, through relation, through manifold interenactments.</p>
          <p>Within the narrative of <hi rend="i">NU</hi> itself, however, this gordian knot of
            interconstitutions is laid out in more familiar and, I would argue, regressive terms. In
            the syntax of the typical Aultian sentence, the threefold ontology of text, narrative
            and reader becomes “Blake,” “narrator” and “reader.” “Blake” is the familiar
omnipotent
            poetgod, in unerring command of his words, marshaling them for heroic battle with
            Newtonian demons; the “reader,” as we have seen, is the standard victim of
            reader-response manipulations, lured, tempted, forced, frustrated, etc. The third
            figure, the “narrator,” is a quasi-authorial personage distinct from the all-seeing,
            all-knowing “Blake”—something like the “dramatic speaker” or “poet” of New Critical
            analyses, that ineradicable, functional voice left over once the intentional author is
            eliminated. In the hands of Ault’s Blake, this narrator is in effect an internalization
            of the same sorts of Newtonian attempts to resolve the poem’s purposive indeterminacies
            that, Ault maintains, the Newtonian reader undertakes; hence “narrator” and “reader” are
            paired functions, mirror-dupes of the poem’s subversive strategies. The narrator
            operates more or less as a character in the poem, not on the event-level of the Zoic
            drama but perceiving, responding, mistaking, retelling from his own skewed, partial and
            usually single-vision perspective. Witness this characteristic passage, dealing with the
            feast of Night IX: 
			<q> We learn, as we did with Luvah, that Luvah’s sons populate the
              feast only as they arise to gather the vintage in golden baskets. At this point Blake
              shows how easily the narrator can lapse into language that instantly allows the reader
              to seize on a hope of redemption on the page and thus forget the chain of past
              unfulfilled expectations. (433) </q>
Or this: 
			<q> The narrator’s explicit demarcation
              of embedded structures at this point is the most obvious in the entire poem and calls
              attention to how extensively we ourselves have been lured into the dream. We too have
              suppressed the wracking confusion; our own senses have become orbed; and we too have
              been “entertaind” by these perverse visions, which Blake will now proceed to eradicate
              just as totally as Vala’s world succeeded in repressing its immediate narrative
              context, the harvest. Blake accomplishes this feat by turning his narrative inside
              out. (411) </q>
There appears to be some sort of contradiction between the radical
            interconstitution of narrative-text-reader and the more conventional reader-response
            hierarchy of Blake, narrator and reader. Perhaps this hierarchy is simply a critical
            convenience, as when Ault lays out events in a linear form while assuring us that they
            are not in fact linearly arranged. But reader-response conventions cannot adequately
            represent what Ault seems to mean by perspective ontology. According to those
            conventions, “Blake” knows all and exerts total control; “the narrator” knows a little,
            understands less and fails again and again as a visionary writer; and “the reader” is
            subjected to a thousand tricks to get him or her to identify falsely with the narrator
            in order someday to see how stupid the choice was in the first place. The narrator also
            serves, in effect, as an alibi for any “failures” one might perceive in the text—a bad
            writer, but certainly not Blake, the master of the master text, who planned all this in
            advance and whose reputation must still be protected at all costs. There is something
            quite Newtonian about this sort of Blake, and while one recognizes that the
            readerresponse syntax might have helped Ault sort out various local relationships, it is
            a lot less interesting than his notion of a purely situational and relational
            ontology.</p>
          <p>But where there is threefold one expects a fourth. Not just Blake, narrator and reader,
            then, but also Reader, <hi rend="i">Ault.</hi> If the “narrator” is a duped and fallen
            “Blake,” so perhaps the “reader” is a duped and fallen “Ault.” Blake and Ault pair off
            opposite narrator and reader as the properly interconstituted, implicitly resurrected
            writer-reader of <hi rend="i">NU/FZ.</hi> But none of this ever rises to the surface of
            Ault’s text; he continues to observe the decorum of the self-effacing explicator even as
            everything in his book demonstrates how false this is. One cannot dismiss Ault’s study
            as subjectivist or impressionistic or a mere reading-into; one cannot say that what he
            discovers in <hi rend="i">FZ</hi> is not “there,” in the senses of thereness that 
              <hi rend="i">NU/FZ</hi> allows; but there is something more than casually personal driving
            this reading. It is hardly accidental that this particular reader—with his background in
            mathematics and engineering, and longstanding interest in the history and philosophy of
            science—produced an anti-Newtonian reading. What is being mastered in this master text
            is not just a text. <hi rend="i">NU/FZ</hi> is the narrative of a struggle with Newton
            not only in but through Blake’s work: the narrative of Ault’s struggle with the Newton
            in himself. It is a struggle—an event-cluster, if you will—out of which Ault as Reader
            is born, and Newton is the Zoic name he sings out of this struggle into the narrative
            proper of <hi rend="i">NU/FZ.</hi> This Newton-Within partly explains the complex
            Urizenism 
<pb id="p23-86" n="86"/>
<figure n="AultNUChart.23.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="641"/> of
            Ault’s obsession with structure, witnessed spectacularly in <hi rend="i">NU</hi>’s
            incredible charts. The elaboration of narrative structure is presented as a discursive
            convenience, but it is clearly a great deal more than that; it is evidence of a reader
            striving with systems in order to deliver himself from them. Perhaps then we might
            re-vise the Blakean motto Ault takes for his own: in <hi rend="i">NU</hi>, the manifold
            I of <hi rend="i">FZ</hi> aulters all.</p>
          <p>The reader-response paradigm thus serves, ironically, as a cover for the agency of the
            “real” reader. We should also observe that the question of reader-response criticism in
              <hi rend="i">NU</hi> is linked to the question of what claims on the rader can be made
            by a text that remains essentially an unpublished manuscript. Ault’s “reader” is a
            familiar fiction that extends the interrupted trajectory of the manuscript’s journey
            through a publication it never had, just as his “Blake” extends the realities of the
            poet’s relation to the manuscript into an ideal of authorial control. Perhaps the most
            serious problem with <hi rend="i">NU/FZ</hi> lies precisely in the manner in which
            work-in-progress is hypostatized into “finished” work—or rather, into a work that is
            neither finished nor unfinished but hyperfinished. Forms of completion and control
            proposed along one line of Ault’s argument are belied both by the manuscript itself and
            by the forces in Ault’s own reading that militate against Newtonian closure. In a sense,
            then, what is most conspicuously absent in this study is a more serious interest in the
            poem’s manuscript status. At times Ault can be especially subtle about the vagaries of
            punctuation and orthography in the manuscript, and when it suits him he may make a
            marginal comment about layers of revision; but for the most part he treats the
            manuscript as a Poem, overtextualizes it, relegates any specific attention to it as a
            “visual text” to a few appendix pages. The powerful author and the mastered and
            masterful text of Ault’s critical allegory usurp the possibility of fully exploring the
            manuscript-poem’s openness. Such an exploration might have shown us the poem’s “radical
            optionality” at the most material levels; and it might have allowed Ault to articulate
            even more clearly his own (and any reader’s) actual and <hi rend="i">proper</hi> agency
            in the interconstituted universe of this work. It is, <pb id="p23-87" n="87"/>
<figure n="AultChart2.23.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="958" height="638"/> after all, “Ault” who finishes 
              <hi rend="i">FZ</hi>; he is the reader liberated by reading from Newtonian bondage; but he binds
            that liberation into the fiction of dutiful critical service to master poet and master
            text. But I must also apologize to him for, in effect, demanding another five hundred
            pages of close study. I am being greedy, and foolish: this sort of exploration could
            have kept <hi rend="i">NU</hi> out of our hands for another decade.</p>
          <p>There is, finally, the question of this study’s place in Blake criticism. It is
            interesting to speculate on whether Ault has opened a door only to close it behind him,
            whether his monument is the end of a golden string or a wide world of solid obstruction.
            I have suggested a few ways in which Ault should someday be seen to have made a
            contribution to Blake scholarship: in unearthing a wealth of detail, in the elaboration
            of narrative and characterological strategies. But the very nature of his project—the
            mode in which these discoveries have been carried out, which <hi rend="i">is NU</hi>’s
            interpretation of <hi rend="i">FZ</hi>—is more likely to be passed over. In a Blakean
            economy, the book’s excesses make perfect sense: the more that is done, the more there
            is to do; the more exhaustive the reading, the more inexhaustible the poem. But in the
            economy of Blake criticism, the book is an aberration, a transgression. In being so
            radically exemplary, it becomes eccentric. Perhaps it is for this reason that Ault
            self-consciously remarks that his analysis “is not intended to compete with the existing
            body of Blake scholarship but rather to be fundamentally incommensurable with it” (xi).
              <hi rend="i">NU/FZ</hi> is more than incommensurable with existing Blake scholarship,
            it is a condemnation of it. If it is “not a <hi rend="i">necessary</hi> reading” but “a
              <hi rend="i">possible</hi> reading” (xxiii; Ault’s emphases), it also presents itself
            as precisely the sort of possibility the Blake industry has to marginalize. Nothing will
            permit the vast majority of Blake’s readers to devote this much or this kind of
            attention to his work. <hi rend="i">NU/FZ</hi> is an indictment of a critical economy in
            which such a book cannot really be useful, perhaps cannot even be exemplary except as
            the sign of a project that most readers will find neither the time, the patience, the
            energy, the courage, nor the professional latitude to pursue.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
