<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>23.4.pierce</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">Bunyan at the Gates of Paradise</title>
        <author n="Pierce">John B. Pierce</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1990</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1990</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">23.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Bidney</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Harriet Kramer Linkin</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>John B. Pierce</name>
              <name>Sheila A. Spector</name>
              <name>Michael Tolley</name>
              <name>Gunnel Tottie</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1990"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_23">
    <body>
	  <pb id="p23-198" n="198"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-23-4-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section"><hi rend="b"><hi rend="i">DISCUSSION</hi></hi></title>
        </head>
        <head>
          <title type="section-subtitle"><hi rend="i">with intellectual spears &amp; long winged arrows of
thought</hi></title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="b">Bunyan at the Gates of Paradise</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>John B. <name>Pierce</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>In a recent issue of 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66" type="note">1</ref> 
Nelson Hilton offers some useful insights into possible sources for Blake’s
“The lost Travellers Dream under the Hill,” the last line of “To The Accuser who is The God of This
World.” In particular, he remarks on the possible biblical antecedents for this concluding line from the
epilogue to <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi>, focusing especially on the last half as a reference to
“the Sinai revelation of Exodus.” Hilton’s equation of the “Hill” with Sinai is supported not only
by references to the Law in the prologue, as he points out, but also by the implications of the ten coils
(corresponding to the decalogue) of the snake depicted below the title of the 
epilogue.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67" type="note">2</ref> 
Yet while his discussion of “under the Hill” seems satisfactory, his identification of the “lost 
Travellers Dream” as a reference to Moses seems more tenuous. I believe Blake’s commentary on Mosaic 
law is filtered through an intermediate source—John Bunyan’s <hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress.</hi> 
A reading of the episode in which Christian meets Mr. Worldly-Wiseman and passes by the burning hill in 
conjunction with the epilogue to <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi> will strengthen the connections 
among Sinai, the traveler’s dream, and the illustration in “To The Accuser Who is The God of this World.” 
	<note id="n66"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Nelson Hilton, “Under the Hill,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 22 (1988): 
16-17.</note>
	<note id="n67"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Geoffrey Keynes, ed. <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise: For Children, For
the Sexes</hi>, 3 vols. (London: Trianon P, 1968) 22. Keynes points out that “The heading is separated from
the poem by a coiling serpent, emblem of priesthood and organized religion. This interpretation is supported
by the fact that the coils are numbered from 1 to 10, these being evidently a reference to the Decalogue. The
numbers were faintly engraved and can be best seen through a magnifying glass.”</note></p>
          <p>Blake’s approbation of Bunyan’s work is evident in his comments on “A Vision of the Last
Judgment,” While distinguishing between the “Fable” as “a totally distinct &amp; inferior kind of
<pb id="p23-199" n="199"/>
poetry” and “Vision . . . as a Representation of what Eternally Exists, Really &amp; Unchangeably,”
Blake remarks that “Fable or Allegory is seldom without some Vision. Pilgrim’s Progress is full of it”
(E 544).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68" type="note">3</ref> He also adopted ideas such
as “Beulah” from <hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n69" type="note">4</ref> and late in his career Blake made 29 water color illustrations and several
sketches for <hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n70"
type="note">5</ref> Thus, it should not be surprising that in addition to these direct references to
Bunyan’s work, Blake includes an indirect allusion to <hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> in his
epilogue to <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise.</hi>
	<note id="n68"><hi rend="s">3</hi> All references to Blake’s works are taken from David V. Erdman, ed. 
<hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, newly rev. ed. (Berkeley: U of California P,
1982), hereafter referred to as E followed by a page number.</note>
	<note id="n69"><hi rend="s">4</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., ed., Vala <hi rend="i">or</hi> The Four Zoas: 
<hi rend="i">A Facsimile of the Manuscript, A Transcript of the Poem and a Study of Its Growth and
Significance</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1963) 174. Bentley discusses the derivation of Beulah from 
<hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress.</hi></note>
	<note id="n70"><hi rend="s">5</hi> See Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William
Blake</hi>, 2 vols. (New Haven: Yale UP, 1981) 1093-1125.</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>, as its title page announces, is “Delivered under
the Similitude of a Dream,” following in the tradition of the medieval dream vision.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n71" type="note">6</ref> While traveling through “the wilderness of this world”
(<hi rend="i">PP</hi> 8), the narrator stops to rest and dreams the story of Christian’s journey to the city
of heaven. <hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> is this “lost Travellers Dream” in which Christian
acts as a surrogate for the narrator’s quest for spiritual enlightenment while in the physical world. The
final line in Blake’s epilogue to <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi> pinpoints a special moment of
Vision in the dream. <note id="n71"><hi rend="s">6</hi> All references to John Bunyan’s <hi rend="i">The
Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> are taken from the edition by N. H. Keeble (New York: Oxford UP, 1984) and are cited
in the text as <hi rend="i">PP</hi> followed by a page number.</note></p>
          <p>Within the dream vision, Christian encounters Mr. Worldly-Wiseman, who persuades him to go to the
Village of Morality where Mr. Legality will free him of his burden of sin. The road to Mr. Legality’s house
leads directly by a “high Hill” which the marginal gloss identifies as Mount Sinai in Bunyan’s allegory
(<hi rend="i">PP</hi> 16). The description of Christian’s journey by this hill may have been the source for
Blake’s “lost Travellers Dream under the Hill”:
<q>
So <hi rend="i">Christian</hi> turned out of his way to go to Mr. <hi rend="i">Legality’s</hi> house for
help: but behold, when he was got now hard by the <hi rend="i">Hill</hi>, it seemed so high, and also that
side of it that was next the way side, did hang so much over, that Christian was afraid to venture further,
lest the <hi rend="i">Hill</hi> should fall on his head: wherefore there he stood still, and wotted not what
to do. Also his burden, <hi rend="i">now</hi>, seemed heavier to him, than while he was in his way. There came
also flashes of fire out of the Hill, that made <hi rend="i">Christian</hi> afraid that he should be burned. .
. . (<hi rend="i">PP</hi> 17)
</q>
Bunyan’s commentary here on religion, morality, and the law bears comparison with central ideas in Blake’s
work. The pilgrim’s passage under the hill represents the threat of life lived under Old Testament law.
Bunyan argues (and Blake would be quick to agree) that the direction of the Christian soul by Morality leads
only to death under the Law. The Evangelist who saves Christian from this threat points out that “by the
deeds of the Law no man living can be rid of his burden” (<hi rend="i">PP</hi> 19-20). The fearful spectacle
of Mount Sinai fails to offer redemption for the Christian soul in Bunyan’s and Blake’s theologies.</p>
          <p>Yet the connections between Blake’s and Bunyan’s texts do not stop here. The encounter
between Christian and Mr. Worldly-Wiseman seems to have represented a visionary moment in the work for Blake
since it records a moment of division in the soul between spiritual and corporeal paths. At this crossroad,
Christian is torn between the advice of Evangelist and Mr. Worldly-Wiseman from the town of “Carnal
Policy” (<hi rend="i">PP</hi> 14). The powerful impact of this conflict emerges in Blake’s illustration
for “To The Accuser” which externalizes and dramatizes the moment of worldly temptation and places it
within the context of an artistic crisis. The design accompanying the text depicts a bat-winged figure
hovering over a reclining figure at the foot of a hill radiating light. In the light of Blake’s reading of
Bunyan, this image seems to represent Bunyan dreaming <hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> at the moment
when Christian encounters Mr. Worldly-Wiseman and the vision of Mount Sinai. The reclining figure holds a
pilgrim’s staff, connecting him with Christian and by synecdoche with Bunyan; the bat-winged Spectre acts as
a counterpart for Mr. Worldly-Wiseman, another of the many names Satan is known by. Blake’s water color
illustration of “John Bunyan Dreams a Dream,” possibly conceived as a frontispiece to <hi rend="i">The
Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>, depicts a recumbent figure in a posture similar to that of the sleeping figure in
“To The Accuser . . . of this World” and helps reinforce the connection between the two reclining male
figures. The bat-winged figure is similar to Blake’s other depictions of the spectrous life of man which
attempts to direct him away from his true spiritual path. Both Satan and Mr. Worldly-Wiseman are Gods of this
World tempting man from a spiritual path by advocating an adherence to law, morality, and a corporeal
spirituality. Both confuse the fleshly garment with the spiritual man. And, as a result, both Satan and Mr.
Worldly-Wiseman are dunces: the former through delusions of godhood; the latter through the complacent
certainty of his own moral sanctity. In both Blake and Bunyan these events take place in the shadow of Sinai.
Blake’s illustration includes Sinai in the background, not hiding “dawn . . . bursting on all sides” as
Erdman suggests,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n72" type="note">7</ref> but bursting forth
with “flashes of fire out of the Hill, that made Christian afraid that he should be burned” (PP 17). 
<note id="n72"><hi rend="s">7</hi><hi rend="i"> The Illuminated Blake</hi>, annotated by David V. Erdman (Garden
City: Anchor Books, 1974) 279.</note></p>
          <p>The fact that Blake ultimately centers his text and design on the artist and his internal
conflict reflects his reappraisal of Bunyan’s puritan text in terms of romantic aesthetics. Bunyan becomes
an Albion figure, experiencing the temptation to turn away from his spiritual quest for the gates of heaven
through his dream of Christian’s encounter with Mr. Worldly-Wiseman.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n73" type="note">8</ref> To give up on the quest would be to abandon the artistic impulse that drove
Bunyan to create a work like <hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress.</hi> In a sense the encounter is not
unlike that in Albion’s dream of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> in which Los is tempted by his Spectre to
give in to worldly concerns and abandon his quest to create (and recreate) the city of Golgonooza while
awaiting the Last Judgment.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n74" type="note">9</ref> In
reworking Bunyan’s allegorical tale, Blake transforms
<pb id="p23-200" n="200"/>
it into a moment of Vision and redeems Bunyan’s work from the same moral reductivism that Milton’s work
became subject to. As with the Bible and as with Milton, Blake approaches Bunyan reading black where most read
white and liberating the visionary aspects of art. Thus Christian’s journey becomes a Sublime Allegory
addressed to the Intellectual powers about the conflict between physical and spiritual, rational and
imaginative, aspects of the life of man. Such a Sublime Allegory equates the life of man with the world of
art. The text of <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi> ends on this union of art and life leaving the reader
with the Keys to the Gates which open the world of Vision. <note id="n73"><hi rend="s">8</hi> The illumination
to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 33[37] bears comparison with the illustration for “To The Accuser.” It
depicts a recumbent Albion lying underneath a less anthropomorphic bat-winged spectre.</note>
	<note id="n74"><hi rend="s">9</hi> The illustration to <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 6 depicts this dialogue
between self and spectre in a fashion similar to that used in “To The Accuser.” In 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> the illustration shows Los sitting at his forge, looking up at the bat-winged,
hovering Spectre of Urthona as he attempts to compel his spectre to help the sleeping Albion.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
