<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>23.4.linkin</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Revisioning Blake’s Oothoon</title>
        <author n="Linkin">Harriet Kramer Linkin</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1990</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1990</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">23.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Bidney</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Harriet Kramer Linkin</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>John B. Pierce</name>
              <name>Sheila A. Spector</name>
              <name>Michael Tolley</name>
              <name>Gunnel Tottie</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1990"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_23">
    <body>
      <pb id="p23-184" n="184"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-23-4-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="main">Revisioning Blake’s Oothoon</title>
        </head>
        <byline>by <docAuthor>Harriet Kramer <name>Linkin</name></docAuthor></byline>
        <p>In applying feminist perspectives to Blake studies critics continue to explore the disparity
between Blake’s larger advocacy of human liberation and his more limited representation of the female in his
poetry. Arguing for a Blake who is alternately feminist, sexist, engendered, beyond gender or struggling
towards a truly androgynous vision, most implicitly accept Fox’s general categories for Blake’s portrayal
of the female: positive/passive, pernicious/active, and, in the rarest of instances, active/good.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">1</ref> Disagreements occur in slotting specific
figures into those categories, perhaps none quite as frustrating as Oothoon in <hi rend="i">Visions of the
Daughters of Albion.</hi> Early modern critics hailed Oothoon as the perfect vehicle for Blake’s
psychosexual beliefs, hearing the poet’s voice resound in her cries for “Love! Love! Love! happy happy
Love! free as the mountain wind!” (7:16, E 50).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32"
type="note">2</ref> Although critics celebrated her imaginative awakening as active and good, they still
placed the poem within the cycle of Experience because Oothoon remained unable to share her newly organized
desires with Theotormon.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">3</ref> In 1973
Peterson broke with standard readings of <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> by positing imperfections in Oothoon
herself as the source of her lack of fulfillment.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34"
type="note">4</ref> Since then, more and more critics fault Oothoon rather than her situation for the seeming
paralysis and prophetic failure that ends her story, suggesting she adopts the strategies of her oppressors to
become pernicious or passive or, for some, both.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35"
type="note">5</ref> This shifting characterization of Oothoon foregrounds recent sociocultural history in that
the liberated Oothoon of the decades culminating in the 1960s is revisioned as the co-opted
    <figure n="vda.i.p11" id="vda.i.illbk.11" work-copy="vda.i" rend="db" width="715" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>Where the cold miser spreads his gold? or does the bright cloud drop<lb/>
	On his stone threshold? does his eye behold the beam that brings<lb/>
	Expansion to the eye of pity? or will he bind himself<lb/>
	Beside the ox to thy hard furrow? does not that mild beam blot<lb/>
	The bat, the owl, the glowing tyger, and the king of night.<lb/>
	The sea fowl takes the wintry blast. for a cov’ring to her limbs:<lb/>
	And the wild snake, the pestilence to adorn him with gems &amp; gold.<lb/>
	And trees. &amp; birds. &amp; beasts, &amp; men. behold their eternal joy.<lb/>
	Arise you little glancing wings. and sing your infant joy!<lb/>
	Arise and drink your bliss. for every thing that lives is holy!<lb/>
	Thus every morning wails Oothoon. but Theotormon sits<lb/>
	Upon the margind ocean conversing with shadows dire,<lb/>
	The Daughters of Albion hear her woes, &amp; eccho back her sighs.<lb/>
	The End</figTranscr>
	<head>1. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, 1793, plate 8.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
Oothoon of the 70s and 80s. Because I believe Oothoon stands for something uniquely positive throughout
Blake’s poetic career—in <hi rend="i">Visions, Europe, Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>—I
hope to challenge current negative
<pb id="p23-185" n="185"/>
estimations of her by questioning whether <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> ends in stasis as well as in her
complicity. Instead, I argue (1) that Blake concludes <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> with two strategic
disjunctions to prompt double vision: the emotive power of Oothoon’s language counters the narrator’s
assertion of paralysis, which is subsequently undermined by the illuminator’s image of Oothoon in flight,
and (2) that Oothoon’s experience is ultimately progressive rather than degenerative. 
<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Susan Fox, “The Female as Metaphor in William Blake’s Poetry,” <hi rend="i">Critical
Inquiry</hi> 3 (1977): 507-19. Along with Fox, key articles discussing Blake’s representation of the female
include Irene Taylor, “The Woman Scaly,” <hi rend="i">Blake’s Poetry and Designs</hi>, ed. Mary Lynn
Johnson and John Grant (1973; New York: Norton, 1979) 539-53; Anne K. Mellor, “Blake’s Portrayal of
Women,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 16 (1982-83): 148-55; Alicia Ostriker, “Desire Gratified and Ungratified:
William Blake and Sexuality,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 16 (1982-83): 156-65; and Brenda S. Webster, “Blake,
Women, and Sexuality,” <hi rend="i">Critical Paths: Blake and the Argument of Method</hi>, ed. Dan Miller,
Mark Bracher, and Donald Ault (Durham: Duke UP, 1987) 204-24.</note>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">2</hi> All quotations of Blake’s poetry are from <hi rend="i">The Complete
Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman (Berkeley: U of California P, 1982), hereafter
cited as E followed by the page number.</note>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">3</hi> S. Foster Damon identifies <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> as a poem of
Experience in his <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Philosophy and Symbols</hi> (Boston: Houghton-Mifflin, 1924)
107 and <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and Symbols of William Blake</hi> (1965; rpt. Shambhala P,
1979) 437, Northrop Frye considers it part of the doomed Orc cycle in <hi rend="i">Fearful Symmetry: A Study
of William Blake</hi> (1947; rpt. New Jersey: Princeton UP, 1969) 245, and Harold Bloom notes that Oothoon
achieves Organized Innocence but Theotormon never receives her message in <hi rend="i">Blake’s Apocalypse: A
Study in Poetic Argument</hi> (New York: Cornell UP, 1963) 113-16.</note>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Jane E. Peterson, “<hi rend="i">The Visions of the Daughters of
Albion</hi>: A Problem in Perception,” <hi rend="i">Philological Quarterly</hi> 52 (1973): 252-64.</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Though the following critics condone aspects of Oothoon’s imaginative
awakening, they find fault as well; the listing is not meant to be exhaustive but to reflect recent critical
trends: Michael G. Cooke, <hi rend="i">Acts of Inclusion</hi> (New Haven: Yale UP, 1979); Vernon E. Lattin,
“Blake’s Thel and Oothoon: Sexual Awakening in the Eighteenth Century,” <hi rend="i">The Literary
Criterion</hi> 16 (1981): 11-24; Mark Anderson, “Oothoon: Failed Prophet,” <hi rend="i">Romanticism Past
and Present</hi> 8 (1984): 1-21; Laura Ellen Haigwood, “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
Albion</hi>: Revising an Interpretive Tradition,” <hi rend="i">San Jose Studies</hi> 11 (1985): 77-94; and
Nelson Hilton, “An Original Story,” <hi rend="i">Unnam’d Forms: Blake and Textuality</hi>, ed. Nelson
Hilton and Thomas A. Vogler (Berkeley: U of California P, 1986) 69-104.</note></p>
        <p>Assessments of Oothoon’s general failure derive from a negative reading of the ending, where the
darker visions of the narrator follow Oothoon’s last joyous exhortations:
<q>
Arise you little glancing wings, and sing your infant joy!<lb/>
Arise and drink your bliss, for every thing that lives is holy!<lb/>
<lb/>
Thus every morning wails Oothoon. But Theotormon sits<lb/>
Upon the margind ocean conversing with shadows dire.<lb/>
<lb/>
The Daughters of Albion hear her woes, &amp; eccho back her sighs.<lb/>
(8:6-13, E 51)
</q>
By dramatically shifting both the temporal and emotional planes of the text, these concluding lines replace
conventional narrative past tense with a continuing present and move from exultation to resignation. Just as
Oothoon reaches the apex of her awakening, the narrative reduces her culminating vision to daily activity; her
resounding proclamations of liberty turn into the narrator’s “wails,” “sighs,” and “woes.” Given
the narrator’s disconcerting summary view of Oothoon’s orations, many readers believe her prophetic
insights conclude with failure, since she does not appear to free Theotormon or her sisters.</p>
        <p>Although the illumination that follows the last three lines depicts Oothoon in flight (pl. 8,
illus. 1),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36" type="note">6</ref> supplanting the Urizenic
pursuer illustrated on the title page (pl. ii, illus. 2), and possibly bearing the word to her sisters, most
critics envision her at tale’s end locked in the static tableau Blake illustrates in his frontispiece (pl.
i, illus. 3). Even the more optimistic Johnson and Grant believe the bound tableau scene eclipses the final
visual impression of hard-won freedom:
<q>
Oothoon never actually escapes from the two warped lovers she is bound to. The three appear locked in their
situation in the full-page frontispiece (or tailpiece in one copy), plate i, in a sort of “No Exit”
triangle, even though Oothoon has achieved psychological liberation and brings her
    <figure n="vda.i.p2" id="vda.i.illbk.02" work-copy="vda.i" rend="db" width="802" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>VISIONS<lb/>
	of<lb/>
	the Daughters of<lb/>
	Albion<lb/>
	The Eye sees more than the Heart knows.<lb/>
	Printed by Will:m Blake : 1793.</figTranscr>
	<head>2. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, 1793, plate ii, title
page.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
message to the Daughters of Albion in the final design.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37"
type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">6</hi> All illustrations of Blake’s illuminations are from <hi rend="i">The
Illuminated Blake</hi>, annot. by David V. Erdman (New York: Anchor P, 1974), and follow Erdman’s plate
numbers.</note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Mary Lynn Johnson and John E. Grant, eds., <hi rend="i">Blake’s Poetry
and Designs</hi> (New York: W. W. Norton, 1979) 69.</note></q>
As Johnson and Grant indicate, Blake used the frontispiece as a tailpiece in the early (if not original) copy
A of <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>, but then consistently positioned it as frontispiece in every other
copy;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">8</ref> while shifting plates is the
easiest mode of revision for a poet who loves to play with textual orderings, I believe Blake deliberately
presented the tableau scene as frontispiece to avoid leaving viewers with a closing image of paralysis.
Nevertheless,
<pb id="p23-186" n="186"/>
readers find the frontispiece an apt illustration of the poem’s ending, accepting verbatim the narrator’s
vision of Oothoon. 
                    <note id="n38"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Erdman (<hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake</hi> 125) argues
that copy C is the first because of the angel sitting on the female rider’s lap; even so, only one of the
earliest copies of <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> used the frontispiece as tailpiece until Blake changed his
mind.</note></p>
        <p>Imaging that bound Oothoon, critics track back through the tale to uncover the character faults
that account for her defeat. To some extent doing so reenacts Bromion’s labeling of Oothoon as harlot after
he rapes her; the narrator tells us Oothoon wails daily, and rather than question how this is true, we return
to her story for the reasons why. Why, however, do we so readily take the narrator’s final despairing
description at face value? A work that impugns the validity of individual perceptions and perspectives, notes
their dependence on the identity of the perceiver, refrains from identifying the narrator (unlike many other
Blake books),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">9</ref> and repeatedly points
to the imaginative necessity of double vision requires us to question the authority of the narrative
conclusion. <note id="n39"><hi rend="s">9</hi> While the issue of who actually narrates what in Blake’s
works is a complex one, Blake often provides an ostensible narrator, such as the piper of the 
<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, the bards of <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">America</hi>, or the Blakean personae of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and Hell, Europe, The
Book of Urizen, Milton</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem. Visions</hi> contains no comparable figure or
persona.</note></p>
        <p>Rather than support or even describe the ending, the frontispiece establishes how individuals shape
or frame what is seen. Circumscribing the primary image—Oothoon and Bromion bound back to back while
Theotormon covers his head—is a cave whose outline forms a human skull while the sun above Bromion’s head
doubles as an eye (in many copies). As mere illustration of the text, the image might refer to two specific
passages: the narrator’s description of how Theotormon “folded his black jealous waters round the
adulterate pair / Bound back to back in Bromions caves terror &amp; meekness dwell” (2:4-5, E 46) and
Oothoon’s glance at the sun through Theotormon’s eyes, where “Instead of morn arises a bright shadow,
like an eye” (2:35, E 47). As illumination, Blake’s sun-eye and cave-skull indicate how perspective
influences perception; both the eye and I of the perceiver (narrator <hi rend="i">and</hi> reader) determine
what is seen. We look through our own eyes and skull to see the mirroring eyes and skull of the narrator
peering back at us. And the frontispiece’s primary image of the trio recedes into these reflecting mirrors,
frustrating efforts to “converge upon a critical center; Oothoon wails on just at the margin of our
comprehension.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">10</ref> Instead of
revealing the way Oothoon’s story ends, the frontispiece diagrams how visions accrue through individual
perspective. <note id="n40"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Mary Lynn Johnson, “William Blake,” <hi rend="i">The
English Romantic Poets</hi>, ed. Frank Jordan, 4th ed. (New York: MLA, 1985) 218.</note></p>
        <p>The title page that follows similarly comments on the nature of perception through its illumination
and language. The title emphasizes plural vision with a grammatical ambiguity that calls attention to the
identity of the perceiver-narrator
    <figure n="vda.i.p1" id="vda.i.illbk.01" work-copy="vda.i" rend="db" width="710" height="1000">
	<figTranscr/>
	<head>3. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, 1793, plate i,
frontispiece.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
by making us wonder whose visions constitute <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion.</hi> Does Blake
use “of” as a possessive indicating the Daughters who see these visions or as a preposition pointing
toward an external narrator who envisions the Daughters? Why are the visions multiple? The plurality of vision
could refer to the three participants in the tale, or the three days over which the tale ensues, but these
plurals still occur within a single overall narrative vision.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n41" type="note">11</ref> Are they “visions” because textual narration differs from visual
narration? Is the narrator also the illuminator, as Blake’s title page to <hi rend="i">The Book of
Urizen</hi> suggests (where Urizen writes with one hand and illustrates with the other, pl. 1, illus. 4), or
do narrator and illuminator offer separate and equally unreliable visions? Perhaps the visions are plural
because internal evidence offers the viewer more than one way of seeing Oothoon’s experience, overriding any
single reading of the conclusion. The motto warns, “The Eye sees more than the Heart knows” (pl. ii, E
45): beyond its obvious application to Theotormon, Bromion, Oothoon, and her sisters, the motto speaks
directly to readers whose eyes see more of Blake’s composite intent than either the verbal or visual text
establishes.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">12</ref>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">11</hi> John Middleton Murry suggests there were to be other 
<hi rend="i">Visions</hi>, perhaps as there were to be books beyond <hi rend="i">The [First] Book of Urizen</hi>,
in “A Note on William Blake’s Visions of the Daughters of Albion,” <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters
of Albion</hi>, reproduced in facsimile (London and Toronto: J. M. Dent and Sons, 1932) 11.</note>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">12</hi> W. J. T. Mitchell writes “For Blake, writing does not move in a
straight line toward a single version (or vision) of the story. It traces the clash of contraries and subverts
the tendency to settle into the fixed oppositions he calls ‘Negations,’ whether these are the moral
antitheses of law and prophecy, the sensory divide between eye and ear, or the aesthetic gulf between word and
image” in his “Visible Language: Blake’s Wond’rous Art of Writing,” <hi rend="i">Romanticism and
Contemporary Criticism</hi>, ed. Morris Eaves and Michael Fischer (Ithaca: Cornell UP, 1986) 80.</note></p>
        <p>Among the visual cues of the title page, the vertically and horizontally centered “i” of
“Albion” is augmented by a figure crouching over the “bi”; reminiscent of the bowed (unseeing) head of
Theotormon (pl. i) and anticipating the bowed (unseeing) Daughters depicted later (pl. 7), the figure
implicates the unitary perspective of a seeing eye/I. Plate 1 (illus. 5) similarly attacks the seeing eye/I
through the annotated “i”s of “Visions”: the first is dotted with a dreamy female figure on a cloud
while an archer aims his arrow through the second. Other figures on the top of plate 1 slyly undermine the
closure of narrative vision: the illuminator frames the printed word “Visions” with a curved “V” on
the left and a sinuously robed figure on the right—just as the narrator frames Oothoon’s story with
introductory and concluding present tense statements. That same “V” sets off the text’s enlarged first
word—“Enslav’d”—when paired with the comma that follows. A robed figure also appears to drip paint
or tears over the word “weep,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">13</ref>
hinting, perhaps, at a narrative inability to see beyond enslavement. As the illuminator suggests, the
<pb id="p23-187" n="187"/>
<figure n="urizen.c.p1" id="urizen.c.illbk.01" work-copy="urizen.c" rend="db" width="703" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>THE<lb/>
	FIRST BOOK<lb/>
	of<lb/>
	URIZEN<lb/>
	LAMBETH. Printed by Will Blake 1794.</figTranscr>
	<head>4. William Blake, <hi rend="i">First Book of Urizen</hi>, 1794, plate 1.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
narrator may well be locked in a vision of slavery precluding other visions; the illuminator’s efforts to
undermine the narrator’s vision here, however, dangerously minimize the morally irreducible fact of slavery.
Both visions invite serious scrutiny. <note id="n43"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Erdman (<hi rend="i">Illuminated
Blake</hi> 130) likens the figure to an “apocalyptic angel [who] pours liquid from a thin vial to drip
beside ‘weep,’” while Johnson and Grant see “a draped figure [who] holds out what appears to be a
dripping paintbrush” (71).</note></p>
        <p>While the frontispiece, title page, and annotating figures above the text on plate 1 incriminate
unitary perspective, the third preliminary plate illuminates double vision. Almost evenly divided into text
and image, plate iii (illus. 6) provides another instance of the discrepancy between various views.
Oothoon’s first-person account in “The Argument” summarizes the opening actions of 
<hi rend="i">Visions</hi> from a fairly physical perspective (in what critics identify as a flat, repressed
voice<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">14</ref>): she loves Theotormon, hides
in a vale, plucks a flower, rises to meet him, and is raped by Bromion. Probably for Theotormon and Bromion,
Oothoon’s plot summary accurately describes her story; even the Daughters—and some critics—might accept
her eight lines as the shell of what happens to Oothoon, since she never seems to move beyond the rape in her
relationship with Theotormon. <note id="n44"><hi rend="s">14</hi> See Harold Bloom, “Commentary,” 
<hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman, Berkeley: U of California
P, 1982) 901 and Peterson 255.</note></p>
        <p>The illumination below the text provides a counter-image by depicting the glorious imaginative
awakening “The Argument” omits: Oothoon not only reveals and revels in double vision by seeing the
Marygold as flower and nymph (as do we), but also demonstrates her prophetic response in kissing “the joy as
it flies.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">15</ref> When we view the entire
page in context, “The Argument” shows Oothoon’s enslavement and enlightenment as well as the need to
connect emotional truths with physical experience. Most important, it offers a holistic way of reading the
conclusion: just as “The Argument” requires text and image for cohesion, the final plate of 
<hi rend="i">Visions</hi> achieves balance when we conflate the illumination with the narration. Like Oothoon and
the Marygold, we could welcome Oothoon as she flies. <note id="n45"><hi rend="s">15</hi> D. G. Gillham points
to Blake’s Notebook entry on “Eternity” to gloss Oothoon’s response to the Marygold in his 
<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1973) 210: “He who binds to himself a joy / Does the
winged life destroy / But he who kisses the joy as it flies / Lives in eternity’s sun rise” (E
470).</note></p>
        <p>To credit the illuminator with a true vision, and castigate the narrator for a limited one,
however, abrogates the larger implication of double vision. Just as the narrator’s perspective determines
perception, so too the illuminator’s. Oothoon’s story contains more than rape, as “The Argument”’s
illumination shows; at the same time, nothing mitigates the painful horror of rape or victimization or
slavery, despite the illuminator’s optimistic efforts here. And the illuminator is not always an optimist.
When Oothoon asserts she is “Open to joy and to delight where ever beauty appears” (6:22, E 50), she goes
on to describe how she would “in evening mild. wearied with work; / Sit on a bank and draw the pleasures of
this free born joy” (7:12, E 50); directly above her words the illuminator ironically juxtaposes an image of
the weary Daughters sitting on such a bank (pl. 7, illus. 7), bringing to mind the hard truth of the
Daughters’ enslavement. Earlier the illuminator undercuts Theotormon’s anguished “and in what rivers
swim the sorrows? and upon what mountains / Wave shadows of discontent?” (3:25-4:1, E 47-48) by presenting
Oothoon chained in a shadowy wave that not only hovers over Theotormon’s bowed head but also ironically
rises out of his very words “Wave shadows of discontent” (pl. 4, illus. 8). In viewing the conclusion’s
disjunctive components, we should not reject the narrator’s vision for the illuminator’s image or
Oothoon’s words, but see how these visions oppose one another to effect plural understanding: “Without
Contraries is no progression” (<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> 3:6, E 34).</p>
        <p>The preliminary plates establish hermeneutic principles that condition our reading of the narrative
plates, where narration and illumination often present competing perspectives on how to interpret the physical
and emotional events in <hi rend="i">Visions.</hi> Rather than repeat the excellent critical accounts of what
happens in <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>, the symbolic identities of the main participants, and the nature of
Oothoon’s prophetic awakening,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">16</ref> I
turn now to a brief summary of the criticism that tends to blame Oothoon’s ostensible failure on her own
imperfections. One group sees Oothoon as flawed because (1) she depends so much on Theotormon for her identity
that she becomes no more than a reflection (Peterson, Lattin, Anderson, Hilton), (2) she decries the virgins
and priests who use nets and snares, is “snared” by Bromion, but offers to trap girls for Theotormon
(Peterson, Cooke, Anderson, Haigwood, Hilton), (3) she is inactive despite her prophetic stance on action,
neither forcing a relationship with Theotormon (Peterson) nor leaving him (Peterson, Anderson), and (4) she
reveals Urizenic traits through her manipulative use of language (Haigwood). A second group looks to Blake
himself for Oothoon’s shortcomings: too engendered by his times to conceive of a truly liberated woman, he
does not make Oothoon powerful enough to change her situation (Fox,
<pb id="p23-188" n="188"/>
Mellor, Ostriker). Although I share the critical bias of this second group, I disagree that Oothoon ultimately
fails. While her progress towards prophecy is not constant or direct, she undergoes what I outline below as a
developmental process that results in her acquiring prophetic stature by the conclusion of the poem; whatever
discrepancies remain stem from Blake’s historical inability to see beyond fundamental inequities in his
system. <note id="n46"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Excellent accounts abound; readers might turn to Anderson,
Gillham, or Peterson for a start.</note></p>
        <p>On the first day her reactions to the rape demonstrate real psychological complexity: some
instances seem to suggest she accepts the guilt thrust upon her by Bromion and Theotormon while others hint at
the beginnings of a visionary response. Unlike the weeping, paralyzed Theotormon, Oothoon does not weep; the
narrator’s characterization of her writhing limbs and “howl incessant” may point to active, Rintrah-like
rage.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">17</ref> Although she seeks to purify
herself of someone else’s pollution (despite the Marygold’s assertion that “the soul of sweet delight /
Can never pass away” 1:9-10, E 46), she wants to cleanse the bosom bathed in the Marygold’s glow and not
her rent loins: “Rend away this defiled bosom that I may reflect. / The image of Theotormon on my pure
transparent breast” (2:15-16, E46). Defining Oothoon’s desire to reflect Theotormon as limiting ignores
its affirming dimension: rather than replace Bromion’s signet with Theotormon’s eagle-inscribed insignia,
she hopes to revive the Marygold’s glow through Theotormon’s image (although her call for a Urizenic,
self-lacerating method of purification indicates feelings of culpability). The narrator’s summary statement
sheds more light on narrative perspective than the consequences of Oothoon’s demand; calling Theotormon’s
responding smile severe, the narrator declares “her soul reflects the smile; / As the clear spring mudded
with feet of beasts grows pure &amp; smiles” (2:18-19, E 46), but it is impossible for us to ascertain much
less
    <figure n="vda.i.p4" id="vda.i.illbk.04" work-copy="vda.i" rend="db" width="691" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>Visions<lb/>
	Enslav’d, the Daughters of Albion weep: a trembling lamentation<lb/>
	Upon their mountains; in their valleys, sighs toward America.<lb/>
	For the soft soul of America, Oothoon wanderd in woe,<lb/>
	Along the vales of Leutha seeking flowers to comfort her;<lb/>
	And. thus she spoke to the bright Marygold of Leutha’s vale<lb/>
	Art thou a flower! art thou a nymph! I see thee now a flower;<lb/>
	Now a nymph! I dare not pluck thee from thy dewy bed!<lb/>
	The Golden nymph replied; pluck thou my flower Oothoon the mild<lb/>
	Another flower shall spring. because the soul of sweet delight<lb/>
	Can never pass away, she ceas’d &amp; closd her golden shrine.<lb/>
	Then Oothoon pluck’d the flower saying, I pluck thee from thy bed<lb/>
	Sweet flower. and put thee here to glow between my breasts<lb/>
	And thus I turn my face to where my whole soul seeks.<lb/>
	Over the waves she went in wing’d exulting swift delight;<lb/>
	And over Theotormons reign, took her impetuous course.<lb/>
	Bromion rent her with his thunders, on his stormy bed<lb/>
	Lay the faint maid, and soon her woes appalld his thunders hoarse<lb/>
	Bromion spoke. behold this harlot here on Bromions bed,<lb/>
	And let the jealous dolphins sport around the lovely maid;<lb/>
	Thy soft American plains are mine, and mine thy north &amp; south;<lb/>
	Stampt with my signet are the swarthy children of the sun:<lb/>
	They are obedient, they resist not, they obey the scourge:<lb/>
	Their daughters worship terrors and obey the violent:</figTranscr>
	<head>5. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, 1793, plate 1.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
accept the validity of the narrator’s judgment: can the narrator see her soul? It is the narrator, and not
Oothoon, who concludes the first day with a simile that represents her as no more than a reflecting spring.
<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">17</hi> While we cannot blindly accept the narrator’s interpretive statements
(does she “howl” or “scream” or “cry”?), we must, at some point, work with the basic physical
outline of events (that, for instance, Bromion intercepts her flight towards Theotormon). Like Haigwood (81) I
disagree with Bloom’s view that Oothoon’s writhing limbs indicate her need for sexual fulfillment from
Theotormon (“Commentary,” 901).</note></p>
        <p>On the second day she surges beyong the limitations of the first by asserting her essential purity
and rejecting Urizen’s definition of the five senses, explaining how former teachings falsely restrained her
vision: “They told me that I had five senses to inclose me up. / And they inclos’d my infinite brain into
a narrow circle” (2:31-32, E 47). Moving beyond personal understanding, she offers the first of the several
glorious, image-specific orations that decimate Urizen’s law of the senses:
<pb id="p23-189" n="189"/>
	<q>
With what sense is it that the chicken shuns the ravenous hawk?<lb/>
With what sense does the tame pigeon measure out the expanse?<lb/>
With what sense does the bee form cells? have not the mouse &amp; frog<lb/>
Eyes and ears and sense of touch? yet are their habitations.<lb/>
And their pursuits, as different as their forms and as their joys:<lb/>
(3:2-6, E 47)
</q>
Through language that evolves from the innocent, revelatory query Oothoon asks of the Marygold—“Art thou a
flower! art thou a nymph!” (1:6, E 46)—to the powerful, rhetorical questions offered to Theotormon and
Bromion, Oothoon’s expanded sensory awareness moves her further and further towards prophecy.</p>
        <p>While they acknowledge Oothoon’s increasing awareness, critics also note two instances of
regression on this second day. After Oothoon rejects the limited schooling of the five senses, she turns to
Theotormon to celebrate the new morning; because he fails to share or confirm her perceptions, his eyes take
in a very different landscape, uniformly colored by his despair: “Instead of morn arises a bright shadow,
like an eye / In the eastern cloud: instead of night a sickly charnel house / That Theotormon hears me not! to
him the night and morn / Are both alike” (2:35-38, E 47). Worried by her apparent dependency on
Theotormon’s perception, some cite this moment to show how Oothoon’s vision fails.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">18</ref> Instead, we might see Oothoon’s desire for visual
intercourse with Theotormon as confirmation of her double vision: her ability to see the world through his
eyes indicates a strength, rather than a weakness. What she sees saddens her, but does not destroy her
progress towards prophecy, her sense of her own identity or her independent vision of the landscape; it is
after she looks through Theotormon’s shadowy perception that she offers her powerful assertion of multiple
sensory experience for different creatures. <note id="n48"><hi rend="s">18</hi> See Hilton 100 and Peterson
259.</note></p>
        <p>The second instance of regression is problematic, for Oothoon appears to bribe Theotormon with
silence and uses images of defilement to establish her purity:
<q>
Silent I hover all the night, and all day could be silent.<lb/>
If Theotormon once would turn his loved eyes upon me;<lb/>
How can I be defild when I reflect thy image pure?<lb/>
Sweetest the fruit that the worm feeds on. &amp; the soul prey’d on by woe<lb/>
The new wash’d lamb ting’d with the village smoke &amp; the bright swan<lb/>
By the red earth of our immortal river: I bathe my wings.<lb/>
And I am white and pure to hover round Theotormons breast.<lb/>
(3:14-19, E 47)
</q>
Like the dissembling virgin she attacks the very next day, Oothoon extends a promise of silence in exchange
for one look from Theotormon. Not yet a hypocrite, Oothoon actually might learn to condemn the virgin’s
silence because she keeps her promise when Theotormon finally responds.</p>
        <p>More disturbing than her promise, she seems to go back on her prophetic declaration of essential
purity in asking how she can be defiled when she reflects Theotormon’s “image pure.” Given the
linguistic ambiguity we do not know whether she means Theotormon himself or his image of purity; in either
case Anderson considers her metaphors for purity defiled through external forces revelatory of how Oothoon
continues to see herself in Theotormon’s terms (5). I believe Oothoon consciously adopts Theotormon’s
terms to focus her message for his level of awareness. Just as Oothoon’s address on sensory differentiation
speaks directly to Bromion, her semantic choices here disclose immense sensitivity in trying to lead
Theotormon to her own position with images culled from his perceptual system. Because the responses of
Theotormon and Bromion echo the words Oothoon offers, they show how well she reads them. That her speech
    <figure n="vda.i.p3" id="vda.i.illbk.03" work-copy="vda.i" rend="db" width="834" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>The Argument<lb/>
	I loved Theotormon<lb/>
	And I was not ashamed<lb/>
	I trembled in my virgin fears<lb/>
	And I hid in Leutha’s vale!<lb/>
	I plucked Leutha’s flower,<lb/>
	And I rose up from the vale;<lb/>
	But the terrible thunders tore<lb/>
	My virgin mantle in twain.</figTranscr>
	<head>6. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, 1793, plate iii.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
does provoke a response from the nearly paralyzed Theotormon demonstrates the efficacy of her language. When
Theotormon finally “turns his loved eyes upon her” through his reply, she keeps her word and maintains
silence.</p>
        <p>As the third day begins, Oothoon concludes her vow of silence with an exponential leap of
awareness, turning her attention from Theotormon to Urizen with a lamentation so sweeping and long it
constitutes roughly half of the text.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49"
type="note">19</ref> Extending her basic denial of Bromion’s “one law for both the lion and the ox”
(4:22, E 48) to human systems, Oothoon attacks Urizen through a brilliant series of prophetic utterances that
connect economics, agriculture, religion, education, and marriage:
<q>
How can the giver of gifts experience the delights of the merchant?<lb/>
How the industrious citizen the pains of the husbandman.<lb/>
<pb id="p23-190" n="190"/>
How different far the fat fed hireling with hollow drum;<lb/>
Who buys whole cornfields into wastes, and sings upon the heath:<lb/>
How different their eye and ear! how different the world to them!<lb/>
With what sense does the parson claim the labour of the farmer?<lb/>
What are his nets &amp; gins &amp; traps.<lb/>
(5:12-18, E 48-49)
</q>
Just as the forms, habitations, and pursuits of animals point toward multivalent experience, human systems
demonstrate such vast differences we cannot impose one code of interpretation. The giver of gifts and the
merchant may perform the same basic function—transferring an item to a new owner—and even require one
another to perform that function, but any effort to evaluate their actions demands completely separate scales.
<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">19</hi><hi rend="i"> Visions</hi> comes to two hundred twenty-two lines if we
include “The Argument” and the motto; Oothoon’s final lamentation goes for one hundred two of those
lines.</note></p>
        <p>No one disputes the depth and range of Oothoon’s prophetic statements on human systems; some
become uneasy when Oothoon moves from her broad analysis of limited Urizenic morality to refocus attention on
her own situation. Describing how the child’s natural sexuality is further and further repressed until that
child grows up to be a virgin hypocrite, Oothoon expresses her frustration through a direct attack on
Theotormon:
<q>
Then com’st thou forth a modest virgin knowing to dissemble<lb/>
With nets found under thy night pillow, to catch virgin joy,<lb/>
And brand it with the name of whore; &amp; sell it in the night,<lb/>
In silence. ev’n without a whisper, and in seeming sleep:<lb/>
. . . And does my Theotormon seek this hypocrite modesty!<lb/>
This knowing, artful, secret, fearful, cautious, trembling hypocrite.<lb/>
Then is Oothoon a whore indeed! and all the virgin joys<lb/>
Of life are harlots: and Theotormon is a sick mans dream<lb/>
And Oothoon is the crafty slave of selfish holiness.<lb/>
(6:10-20, E 49-50)
</q>
As Haigwood points out, Oothoon’s language limits rather than invites Theotormon’s response through her
does/then construction, which “doesn’t ask Theotormon what he thinks and feels; she tells him,
‘enslaving’ his experience to her own ‘system’” (88).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n50" type="note">20</ref> Haigwood’s point is well-taken: Oothoon not only exhibits Urizenic
behavior through syntax, but also adopts Bromion’s reductive name-calling by conditionally branding herself
a whore and Theotormon a “sick mans dream.” <note id="n50"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Earlier Haigwood
identifies how Oothoon’s “either/or construction slams shut the door of dialogue at the same time that it
seems to open it: that is, the possible responses are limited in such a way that if the answer doesn’t fit
the asker’s prescribed categories, the person addressed can only be mute” (88).</note></p>
        <p>In Oothoon’s defense, however, let us consider her self-righteous wrath. Oothoon lashes out in
justified anger after her description of the virgin hypocrite’s decorous silence; perhaps Oothoon 
<hi rend="i">has</hi> been made into “a whore indeed” if it is her silence rather than her great verbal
sensitivity which finally prompts Theotormon’s longed-for response. That the two lines describing how the
hypocrite virgin brands sexuality with “the name of whore” and keeps silent constitute the exact center of
Oothoon’s one hundred and two line oration on the third day highlights their importance to her experience.
Potentially co-opted by Urizen’s system, Oothoon recoils from her similarity to the virgin with rage.
Although she quickly retracts the names she calls herself—“But Oothoon is not so” (6:21, E 50)—she
never corrects her nomination of Theotormon as a “sick mans dream.” In fact, she perpetuates the image
later on by describing someone who closely resembles Theotormon as sickened with self-love (7:17-22, E
50).</p>
        <p>What critics cite most frequently as proof of Oothoon’s downfall is her offer to catch girls for
Theotormon:
<q>
But silken nets and traps of adamant will Oothoon spread,<lb/>
And catch for thee girls of mild silver, or of furious gold;<lb/>
I’ll lie beside thee on a bank &amp; view their wanton play<lb/>
In lovely copulation bliss on bliss with Theotormon:<lb/>
Red as the rosy morning, lustful as the first born beam,<lb/>
Oothoon shall view his dear delight, nor e’er with jealous cloud<lb/>
Come in the heaven of generous love; nor selfish blightings bring.<lb/>
(7:24-29, E 50)
</q>
Although her “silken nets and traps of adamant” are meant to contrast with the web of age spun by the
jealous, weeping lover in the section above, “grey and hoary! dark!” (7:19, E 50), Oothoon’s apparent
willingness to use these Urizenic tools awakens suspicions, given her denunciation of both the parson and the
virgin for their nets and traps. Despite the negative connotations nets and traps generally bear, they may not
be innately tainted in <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>: in measuring the parson’s labor against the farmer’s,
Oothoon suggests a legitimate use for nets and traps: “With what sense does the parson claim the labour of
the farmer? / What are his nets &amp; gins &amp; traps?” (5:17-18, E 49). At the same time 
<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> insists that “All wholesom food is caught without a net or a trap” (7:13, E
36).</p>
        <p>Even more troubling than her means, the offer itself alerts many critics to a weakness in Oothoon.
Most wonder why Oothoon intimates she would be content to watch Theotormon copulate with other girls, as it
exemplifies the voyeuristic sexuality Oothoon condemns in attacking “The self enjoyings of self denial”
(7:9, E 50). Several points bear consideration: first, Blake’s lines are sufficiently equivocal to suggest
that Oothoon lies beside Theotormon “in lovely copulation” while the pair watch the wanton play of the
girls; second, Oothoon never says she will only and always watch. Third, the entire episode sets up an
antimony to the kind of looking the jealous lover performs in the section above, whose “lamplike eyes
watching around the frozen marriage bed” (7:22, E 50) lock lovers into fruitless relationships. Fourth, and
most important, she clearly follows the path Blake demarcates for enlightened Emanations by advocating a form
of polygyny;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51" type="note">21</ref> as Damon writes, “To
save the marriage, 
<pb id="p23-191" n="191"/>
the Emanation must renounce her thirst for dominion and sacrifice her selfishness” 
(<hi rend="i">Dictionary</hi> 122). Oothoon’s offer to trap girls for Theotormon justifiably distresses recent
critics, but perhaps we should be troubled by Blake himself. <note id="n51"><hi rend="s">21</hi> In 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, for instance, several of Blake’s figures promote polygyny, such as the Divine Voice:
<q>
She shall begin to give<lb/>
Her maidens to her husband: delighting in his delight<lb/>
And then &amp; then alone begins the happy Female joy<lb/>
As it is done in Beulah, &amp; thou O Virgin Babylon Mother of Whoredoms<lb/>
Shalt bring Jerusalem in thine arms in the night watches; and<lb/>
No longer turning her a wandering Harlot in the streets<lb/>
Shalt give her into the arms of God your Lord &amp; Husband.<lb/>
(33:17-23, E 133)
</q></note></p>
        <p>Oothoon goes on to end the third day’s lamentation with a rousing finale that validates her
tremendous progress towards prophetic stature. Rather than seize upon the negative aspects of her experience,
I propose we consider that progress is not always swift and direct. Like the Los of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
who succumbs to Satan’s pleas only to recall that pity divides the soul, or who first joins Urizen to block
Milton’s journey before he remembers the prophecy of Eden, Oothoon must work through the obstacles in her
path towards prophecy. Not at all static, Oothoon’s language and experiences reveal increasing visionary
awareness through leaps and surges. Although at first she addresses Theotormon alone (after the rape), she
soon includes Bromion and then moves outward to Urizen, expanding the range of her commentary from sensory
differentiation to human systems. She begins the second day with a call inviting Theotormon to “Arise,”
but by the end of the third, she broadens her scope immeasurably: “Arise you little glancing wings, and sing
your infant joy! / Arise and drink your bliss, for every thing that lives is holy!” (8:9-10, E 51).</p>
        <p>The narrator’s conclusion not only undermines the emotional affect of Oothoon’s visionary
exhortations but also reverses any sense of progress: “Thus every morning wails Oothoon. but Theotormon sits
/ Upon the margind ocean conversing with shadows dire” (8:11-12, E 51). Because Oothoon imagines turning
into such a shadow through Theotormon’s continued rejection, “Till beauty fades from off my shoulders
darken’d and cast out, / A solitary shadow wailing on the margin of non-entity” (7:14-15, E 50), Hilton
wonders if Theotormon’s dire shadows might be Oothoon herself (102-
    <figure n="vda.i.p10" id="vda.i.illbk.10" work-copy="vda.i" rend="db" width="722" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>7<lb/>
	In happy copulation; if in evening mild. wearied with work;<lb/>
	Sit on a bank and draw the pleasures of this free born joy.<lb/>
	The moment of desire! the moment of desire! The virgin<lb/>
	That pines for man; shall awaken her womb to enormous joys<lb/>
	In the secret shadows of her chamber; the youth shut up from<lb/>
	The lustful joy, shall forget to generate, &amp; create an amorous image<lb/>
	In the shadows of his curtains and in the folds of his silent pillow.<lb/>
	Are not these the places of religion? the rewards of continence!<lb/>
	The self enjoyings of self denial? Why dost thou seek religion?<lb/>
	Is it because acts are not lovely, that thou seekest solitude,<lb/>
	Where the horrible darkness is impressed with reflections of desire.<lb/>
	Father of Jealousy. be thou accursed from the earth!<lb/>
	Why hast thou taught my Theotormon this accursed thing?<lb/>
	Till beauty fades from off my shoulders darken’d and cast out,<lb/>
	A solitary shadow wailing on the margin of non-entity.<lb/>
	I cry, Love! Love! Love! happy happy Love! free as the mountain wind!<lb/>
	Can that be Love, that drinks another as a sponge drinks water?<lb/>
	That clouds with jealousy his nights, with weepings all the day:<lb/>
	To spin a web of age around him, grey and hoary! dark!<lb/>
	Till his eyes sicken at the fruit that hangs before his sight.<lb/>
	Such is self-love that envies all! a creeping skeleton<lb/>
	With lamplike eyes watching around the frozen marriage bed.<lb/>
	But silken nets and traps of adamant will Oothoon spread,<lb/>
	And catch for thee girls of mild silver, or of furious gold:<lb/>
	I’ll lie beside thee on a bank &amp; view their wanton play<lb/>
	In lovely copulation bliss on bliss with Theotormon;<lb/>
	Red as the rosy morning, lustful as the first born beam,<lb/>
	Oothoon shall view his dear delight, nor e’er with jealous cloud<lb/>
	Come in the heaven of generous love; nor selfish blightings bring.<lb/>
	Does the sun walk in glorious raiment, on the secret floor</figTranscr>
	<head>7. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, 1793, plate 7.</head>
	<figDesc>Courtesy of the Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
03). Does the narrator merely echo Oothoon’s despairing possibility? Like Bromion, whose second speech
initially supports Oothoon’s vision—“knowest thou that trees and fruits flourish upon the earth / To
gratify senses unknown” (3:14-15, E 48)—and then abruptly rejects it in asserting “eternal fire, and
eternal chains” (3:23, E 48), the narrator tells Oothoon’s story sympathetically but finally denies the
larger truth of her progress through time: “the true meaning of time lies in its identity with the spirit of
prophecy, for by speaking out, the prophet can reverse the cycles of history and make time an agent of mercy,
rather than of destruction.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">22</ref>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Mollyanne Marks, “Time as Hero in Blake’s Major Prophecies,” 
<hi rend="i">Studies in Eighteenth-Century Culture</hi>, vol. 5, ed. Ronald C. Rosbottom (Wisconsin: U of
Wisconsin P, 1976) 59.</note></p>
        <pb id="p23-192" n="192"/>
        <p>Much more than a shadowy reflection of Theotormon, Oothoon actually presents a model that
Theotormon shadows; not only rent by Bromion after Oothoon is rent, Theotormon also mimes Oothoon’s
rhetoric, as the following call by Oothoon and response (albeit reductive) from Theotormon reveals:
<q>
They told me that the night &amp; day were all that I could see;<lb/>
They told me that I had five senses to inclose me up;<lb/>
And they inclos’d my infinite brain into a narrow circle.<lb/>
<lb/>
. . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
<lb/>
And then tell me the thoughts of man, that have been hid of old.<lb/>
(2:30-3:13, E 47)<lb/>
<lb/>
. . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
<lb/>
Tell me what is the night or day to one o’erflowed with woe?<lb/>
Tell me what is a thought? &amp; of what substance is it made?<lb/>
Tell me what is a joy? &amp; in what gardens do joys grow?<lb/>
. . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
Tell me where dwell the thoughts forgotten till thou call them forth<lb/>
Tell me where dwell the joys of old! &amp; where the ancient loves?<lb/>
(3:22-4:4, E 47-48)
</q>
Already a shade when we meet him, Theotormon’s past grace and glory exist, like Ahania’s Urizen or
Ophelia’s Hamlet, in the memories of those who loved him. The text’s final image of Theotormon suggests he
becomes a shadow conversing with shadows, fulfilling the dictum of Blake’s prophecy on restrained desire:
“being restrained it by degrees becomes passive till it is only the shadow of desire” 
(<hi rend="i">Marriage</hi> 5:4-5, E 34). Despite the narrator’s grim summary view of Theotormon, Oothoon’s
insistent questioning effects some small but real progress. On the first day he stops weeping to smile
(severely); on the second day Oothoon elicits a verbal response from him. By the end he no longer weeps in
front of his cave but engages in conversation.</p>
        <p>Given Theotormon’s corresponding fall, does Oothoon err in her efforts to awaken him? Those who
see Oothoon’s failure in her inability to free herself from dependence on Theotormon neglect to consider
Oothoon’s real options and prophetic commitments. As Theotormon’s Emanation, she must effect reintegration
with him; choosing another partner unleashes devastating consequences for other pairs in <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas</hi> or <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Nor does Blake present Oothoon with any options: in order to fulfill
her desire she can only turn to Theotormon or Bromion the rapist (who Gillham argues is Theotormon).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53" type="note">23</ref> If anything binds Oothoon, it is Blake’s
system of Emanations. Beyond the constraints imposed by that larger, later system, however, lies the
compelling responsibility of the true prophet. Oothoon’s daily lamentation signifies her wonderful
determination to awaken those around her, providing an early version of the persistent visionary Blake clearly
endorses in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>:
<q>
Of the Sleep of Ulro! and of the passage through<lb/>
Eternal Death! and of the wakening to Eternal Life.<lb/>
<lb/>
This theme calls me in sleep night after night, &amp; ev’ry morn<lb/>
Awakes me at sun-rise, then I see the Saviour over me<lb/>
Spreading his beams of love, &amp; dictating the words of this mild song.<lb/>
<lb/>
Awake! awake O sleeper of the land of shadows, wake! expand!<lb/>
<lb/>
I am in you and you in me, mutual in love divine:<lb/>
<lb/>
. . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
<lb/>
Trembling I sit day and night, my friends are astonish’d at me.<lb/>
<lb/>
Yet they forgive my wanderings, I rest not from my great task!<lb/>
To open the Eternal Worlds, to open the immortal Eyes<lb/>
(4:1-7, 5:16-18, E 146-47)
</q>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">23</hi> Unlike the heroines of numerous 1960s and 70s novels, Oothoon cannot walk
out on Theotormon to find a more enlightened man.</note></p>
        <p>Rather than castigate Oothoon’s seeming dependence on Theotormon, let us recognize the depth of
her resolution. Just as Los must work with his Spectre to build Golgonooza, Oothoon must bring Theotormon to a
new level of awareness. And just as Los “built the stubborn structure of the Language, acting against /
Albions melancholy, who must else have been a Dumb despair” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 36:59-60, E 183),
Oothoon moves beyond dumb despair—beyond embracing her own silence and Theotormon’s—to use the stubborn
structure of language for enlightenment. Taking action through words, Oothoon never surrenders; although
Theotormon, Bromion, and Urizen fail to comprehend her prophecy by the end of <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>, she
embodies the healing mercy of time: in describing an Oothoon who continues to wail, the narrator provides
evidence to support the possibility of change. While the narrator does not yet understand, as Oothoon does,
how “they inclos’d my infinite brain into a narrow circle” (2:32, E 47), narrative disjunction enables
readers to go into and out of the circle Blake’s Notebook taunts God with: “If you have formed a Circle to
go into / Go into yourself &amp; see how you would do” (“To God,” E 516). By framing the narrator’s
despair with two positive instances in the text—Oothoon’s triumphant calls for freedom and the
illumination depicting her in flight—Blake enables alternate viewings of the conclusion. Jumping back and
forth between the image of Oothoon called up through the narrator’s words<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">24</ref> and the illuminated Oothoon in flight<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">25</ref> effects the double vision Oothoon possesses
when she first sees the Marygold: “I see thee now a flower! now a nymph!” Although I believe we should
follow Oothoon’s prophetic response and kiss “the joy as it flies” (“Eternity,” E 470), the
illuminator’s final image does not correct the narrator’s version so much as balance it. Eyes may see more
than hearts know, but hearts
<pb id="p23-193" n="193"/>
know that at the end of <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>, Oothoon remains without Theotormon. The determined
expression on Oothoon’s face warns us not to condone her lack of fulfillment; at the same time we should
heed her words—“Arise and drink your bliss, for every thing that lives is holy!”—to joy in her
progress towards prophecy. <note id="n54"><hi rend="s">24</hi> Gillham sees the three figures on the bank in
the final plate as Oothoon, Theotormon, and Bromion (195).</note>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">25</hi> See Janet Warner, <hi rend="i">Blake and the Language of Art</hi>
(Kingston and Montreal: McGill-Queen’s UP, 1984) 94-95 and E. B. Murray, “A Pictorial Guide to Two-Fold
Vision: Copy ‘O’ of <hi rend="i">VDA</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Sparks of Fire: Blake in a New Age</hi>, ed.
James Bogan and Fred Goss (California: North Atlantic Books, 1982) 165, among others for very different
discussions of how to view the final image of Oothoon in flight.</note></p>
        <p>While Oothoon does not and cannot approximate a contemporary feminist ideal, she comes closest to
bridging the curious gap between Blake’s belief in human liberation and his poetic representation of the
female. As the best (and perhaps only) active, good female figure, Oothoon occupies a special place in
Blake’s canon; unlike his more conventional portrayal of females as positive through self-sacrifice (Ololon,
<hi rend="i">Thel</hi>s Lilly) or perniciously manipulative (Enitharmon, Vala), Oothoon acts through prophetic
speeches that render the philosophical principles generally stated by male figures. After Visions Blake offers
limiting images of women; the feminist possibilities Oothoon embodies seem to disappear. Oothoon herself,
however, periodically resurfaces as if Blake means to hold on to the fleeting possibilities she embodies; the
rebellious daughter who goes against Enitharmon’s reign of sexual delusion in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, the
guard who enables the fulfillment of Leutha’s desires after Elynittria brings Leutha to Palamabron’s bed
in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">26</ref> she is,
finally, a way into Beulah in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>:
<q>
There is a Grain of Sand in Lambeth that Satan cannot find<lb/>
Nor can his Watch Fiends find it: tis translucent &amp; has many Angles<lb/>
But he who finds it will find Oothoons palace, for within<lb/>
Opening into Beulah every angle is a lovely heaven<lb/>
(37:15-18, E 183)
</q>
In our current revisioning of Oothoon, I propose we view her through that translucent angle of vision that
opens into Beulah. <note id="n56"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Oothoon also hovers with Leutha over Orc “Opening
interiorly into Jerusalem &amp; Babylon shining glorious / Into the Shadowy Females bosom” (18:41-42, E 112)
to suggest the kind of female form Orc would have the Shadowy Female wear. Although many read her appearance
as negative, I believe she initially represents the possibility of a polygynous marriage that the Shadowy
Female rejects; that rejection accounts for the turn towards perversity. Oothoon appears again in the poem’s
concluding movement toward apocalypse: “soft Oothoon / Pants in the Vales of Lambeth weeping oer her Human
Harvest” (42:32-33, E 144).</note></p>
        <figure n="vda.i.p7" id="vda.i.illbk.07" work-copy="vda.i" rend="db" width="675" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>Wave shadows of discontent! and in what houses dwell the wretched<lb/>
	Drunken with woe forgotten. and shut up from cold despair,<lb/>
	Tell me where dwell the thoughts forgotten till thou call them forth<lb/>
	Tell me where dwell the joys of old! &amp; where the ancient loves?<lb/>
	And when will they renew again &amp; the night of oblivion past?<lb/>
	That I might traverse times &amp; spaces far remote and bring<lb/>
	Comforts into a present sorrow and a night of pain<lb/>
	Where goest thou O thought! to what remote land is thy flight?<lb/>
	If thou returnest to the present moment of affliction<lb/>
	Wilt thou bring comforts on thy wings, and dews and honey and balm;<lb/>
	Or poison from the desart wilds, from the eyes of the envier.<lb/>
	Then Bromion said; and shook the cavern with his lamentation<lb/>
	Thou knowest that the ancient trees seen by thine eyes have fruit;<lb/>
	But knowest thou that trees and fruits flourish upon the earth<lb/>
	To gratify senses unknown? trees beasts and birds unknown:<lb/>
	Unknown, not unpercievd, spread in the infinite microscope,<lb/>
	In places yet unvisited by the voyager. and in worlds<lb/>
	Over another kind of seas, and in atmospheres unknown.<lb/>
	Ah! are there other wars, beside the wars of sword and fire!<lb/>
	And are there other sorrows, beside the sorrows of poverty?<lb/>
	And are there other joys, beside the joys of riches and ease?<lb/>
	And is there not one law for both the lion and the ox?<lb/>
	And is there not eternal fire, and eternal chains?<lb/>
	To bind the phantoms of existence from eternal life?<lb/>
	Then Oothoon waited silent all the day, and all the night,</figTranscr>
          <head>8. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, 1793, plate 4.</head>
          <figDesc>Courtesy of the Yale Center for British Art, Paul Mellon Collection.</figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p23-194" n="194" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
