<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>23.4.heppner</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">“Under the Hill”: Tyndale or Bunyan?</title>
        <author n="Heppner">Christopher Heppner</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1990</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1990</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">23.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Bidney</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Harriet Kramer Linkin</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>John B. Pierce</name>
              <name>Sheila A. Spector</name>
              <name>Michael Tolley</name>
              <name>Gunnel Tottie</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1990"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_23">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-23-4-0008">
        <pb id="p23-200" n="200"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">“Under the Hill”: Tyndale or Bunyan?</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Christopher <name>Heppner</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>In a recent note,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n75" type="note">1</ref> Nelson
Hilton has suggested William Tyndale’s translation of the Pentateuch as a context for the last line of the
epilogue of Blake’s <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise.</hi> That poem, addressed “To The
Accuser who is The God of This World,” calls him, in its last line, “The lost Travellers Dream under the
Hill.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76" type="note">2</ref> Tyndale’s translation uses
the phrase “vnder the hyll” in Exodus 19:17, and the term “the hyll” elsewhere, in referring to Sinai,
and Hilton argues that Blake knew and made use of that phrase. The argument is put rather
challengingly—“does anyone imagine Blake limiting himself to ‘the Authorized Version’?” I wish to
gently answer that challenge, and then continue by suggesting what I consider a more likely context for
Blake’s phrase, and the design that illuminates the poem. <note id="n75"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Nelson Hilton,
“Under the Hill,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 22 (1988): 16-17.</note>
	<note id="n76"><hi rend="s">2</hi> David V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of
William Blake</hi>, rev. ed. (Berkeley and Los Angeles: U of California P, 1982) 269; hereafter referred to as
E followed by a page number. I have also used the reproductions in <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi>,
annotated by David V. Erdman (Garden City: Anchor Books, 1974).</note></p>
          <p>There is no evidence that Blake ever used other translations of the Bible,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77" type="note">3</ref> and he does once, though a little playfully,
make great claims for the Authorized Version: “astonishing indeed is the English Translation [of the Greek
New Testament] it is almost word for word &amp; if the Hebrew Bible is as well translated which I do not doubt
it is we need not doubt of its having been translated as well as written by the Holy Ghost” (E 727). The
Authorized Version is here simply “the English Translation,” as if there were no other. Like many of
Blake’s statements, it might be a mistake to understand this one too literally. But it is also true that
Tyndale’s <hi rend="i">Five Books of Moses Called The Pentateuch</hi>, first published in 1530 and reprinted
in a second edition in 1534, was not reprinted thereafter until the edition of 1884 which Hilton cites. The
<hi rend="i">Short Title Catalogue</hi> makes it clear that both early editions are now rare, and they cannot
have been much more common in Blake’s time. Much of Tyndale’s version was absorbed into the so-called
Matthew’s Bible, editions of which appeared in 1537, 1549, and 1551,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n78" type="note">4</ref> but these too were not common books. It is at least possible that Blake had
seen a copy of Tyndale’s translation, but extremely improbable that he had one at hand to consult. 
<note id="n77"><hi rend="s">3</hi> If he did, my bet would be on Robert Lowth’s <hi rend="i">Isaiah. A New
Translation</hi> (1778, with many subsequent editions to 1835) rather than on Tyndale. Blake did play the game
himself, on a small scale, in the <hi rend="i">Job</hi> inscriptions.</note>
	<note id="n78"><hi rend="s">4</hi> T. H. Darlow and H. F. Moule, revised A. S. Herbert, 
<hi rend="i">Historical Catalogue of the English Bible 1525-1961</hi> (New York: American Bible Society, 1968)
Nos. 34, 74, 92.</note></p>
          <p>An altogether likelier conjecture is that Blake was thinking of Bunyan’s <hi rend="i">The
Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>, a book that he described as “full” of “Vision” (E 554). In one letter he
identifies himself with “Poor Pilgrim” (E 758), and of course he made a series of illustrations to the
work, and the separate plate of <hi rend="i">The Man Sweeping the Interpreter’s Parlour.</hi> In a broader
context, E. P. Thompson has written well of the centrality of Bunyan’s allegory to dissenting culture during
the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79"
type="note">5</ref> It was clearly a work that had deep roots in Blake’s consciousness. 
<note id="n79"><hi rend="s">5</hi> E. P. Thompson, <hi rend="i">The Making of the English Working Class</hi> (Harmondsworth:
Penguin Books, 1968) 28-58.</note></p>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi> is a kind of pilgrimage, whose title, with the emblem of
“Death’s Door,” remind us that Christian’s whole progress is towards a Gate. The recurring motif of
the pilgrim’s staff, present in the illumination
<pb id="p23-201" n="201"/>
of the epilogue to the <hi rend="i">Gates</hi>, strengthens the pilgrim association of the work as a
whole.</p>
          <p>In <hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>, Mt. Sinai is repeatedly called a hill, and
Christian, when misled by Mr. Worldly-Wiseman, loses his way and finds himself, in effect, under that hill:
<q>
when he was got now hard by the <hi rend="i">Hill</hi>, it seemed so high, and also that side of it that was
next the way side, did hang so much over, that Christian was afraid to venture further, lest the Hill should
fall on his head. . . .<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n80"><hi rend="s">6</hi> John Bunyan, <hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>, ed. J. B. Wharey,
revised R. Sharrock (Oxford, Clarendon P, 1960) 20; hereafter referred to as <hi rend="i">PP</hi> followed by
a page number.</note></q>
Here, I suggest, is a likelier context for Blake’s “The lost Travellers Dream under the Hill” than
Tyndale’s rare translation.</p>
          <p>In addition, <hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> gives us a context for Blake’s
illumination of the epilogue. Later in his journey, Christian is met by Apollyon: “now the Monster was
hidious to behold, he was cloathed with scales like a Fish . . . he had Wings like a Dragon, feet like a Bear,
and out of his belly came Fire and Smoak, and his mouth was as the mouth of a Lion” (<hi rend="i">PP</hi>
56). At the end of a fierce battle, Christian emerges victor, and “<hi rend="i">Apollyon</hi> spread forth
his Dragons wings, and sped him away, that <hi rend="i">Christian</hi> saw him no more” 
(<hi rend="i">PP</hi> 60). Stripped of some of the grotesque animal imagery, this is fairly close to the situation
represented in the illumination of the epilogue, which shows a dragon-winged Satan flying away from the
dreaming traveler. The appellation “The God of This World” is a repeated biblical phrase, but it also
finds its echo in the conversation that opens Apollyon’s challenge to Christian:
<q>
Apol. <hi rend="i">Whence come you, and whither are you bound?</hi><lb/>
<hi rend="i">Chr.</hi> I come from the City of <hi rend="i">Destruction</hi>, which is the place of all evil,
and am going to the City of <hi rend="i">Zion.</hi><lb/>
Apol. <hi rend="i">By this I perceive thou art one of my Subjects, for all that Countrey is mine; and I am the
Prince and God of it.</hi> (<hi rend="i">PP</hi> 56)
</q>
Bunyan’s work thus functions as a directly relevant context for both the structure of the 
<hi rend="i">Gates</hi> as a whole and the epilogue—both poem and illumination—in particular.</p>
          <p>Hilton refers to Tyndale’s translation of Exodus as “a probable source” for Blake’s
reference to “The lost Travellers Dream under the Hill.” I would prefer to think that Blake has
deliberately shaped his phrases, and his illumination, to conjure up the reader/viewer’s memories both of
the Bible—“The God of This World”—and of Bunyan. In Blake’s imagination the two would seem to have
been almost as intertextually entwined as the Bible and <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, and doubtless 
<hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise</hi> was designed to take its place in that constellation. Maybe
Tyndale is also in there somewhere, but I am not convinced that we can separate out that weak possible echo
from the stronger surrounding voices.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
