<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>23.4.hilton</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="discussion">Fellow Travelers . . .</title>
        <author n="Hilton">Nelson Hilton</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1990</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1990</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">23.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Martin Bidney</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Harriet Kramer Linkin</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>John B. Pierce</name>
              <name>Sheila A. Spector</name>
              <name>Michael Tolley</name>
              <name>Gunnel Tottie</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1990"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_23">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-23-4-0008">
        <pb id="p23-204" n="204"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Fellow Travelers . . .</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Nelson <name>Hilton</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>First, apologies to anyone who felt bullied, intimidated, browbeaten, threatened, or insulted by
my rhetorical aside. <hi rend="i">Mea culpa.</hi> As for Tyndale’s translation, I pushed it in order to add
to the single “under the hill” reference of AV Exodus 24:4 the two other specific instances of that
formulation in Tyndale. Obviously they didn’t make the case any more convincing, and Christopher Heppner’s
neglect of even the AV occurrence shows how turning to Tyndale cost me points for my point. But one minute
particular can suffice to ground what, following Robert Gleckner (<hi rend="i">Blake’s Prelude</hi>, 1982),
we might term a Blakean “significant allusion”—and for all that can be said about the passage from 
<hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> quoted by each of the respondents to “Under the Hill,” Bunyan does not
use the telling phrase.</p>
          <p>Michael Tolley’s effort “to pull together the idea of an erotic dream with that of the
rampant Spectre” seems a useful furthering of the discussion, and I agree that we should “think first of
the dream as one of erotic desire.” In this connection we might turn from “under the hill” to “the
lost Traveller,” and Thomas Carew’s memorably licentious poem, “A Rapture.” The speaker of Carew’s
poem flies with “Celia” past “Honour” to graphically imaged delights of “Love’s Elysium.” In
this “Elysian ground. / All things are lawful”—Lucrece reads Aretine, for example, and
<q>
The Grecian Dame,<lb/>
That in her endlesse webb, toyl’d for a name<lb/>
As fruitlesse as her worke, doth there display<lb/>
Her selfe before the Youth of <hi rend="i">Ithaca</hi>,<lb/>
And th’ amorous sport of gamesome nights prefer,<lb/>
Before dull dreames of the lost Traveller.<lb/>
(125-30)
</q>
In the context of this allusion, Blake’s “pilgrim” becomes a type of Ulysses we are to write off if we
would embrace Carew’s revisionary Penelope. Such a possibility is perhaps no less scandalous than the
realization that the “Satan” intimately addressed by Blake’s speaker is “Worshipd by the Names Divine
/ Of Jesus &amp; Jehovah.” The presence of “Satan” or what Blake calls “The Accuser who is The God of
This World” and elsewhere “the Accuser of Sin” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 98.49) in the vicinity of “Every
Harlot” can facilitate the accommodation Tolley proposes between Mount Sinai and the “dream . . . of
erotic desire.” The “sin” of mounting (or being under) a Fanny Hill—“that sweet golden clime [hear
also ‘climb’] / Where the travellers journey is done”—can be summarized as having been insinuated into
culture at Mount Sinai (e.g., Ex. 21:17, “thou shalt not covet thy neighbor’s wife”). The Bible’s
other name for the site of moral revelation is Mount Horeb, opening the possibility that in some weary
night’s decline a conflicted son of mourning might ponder the schizoid equation of “mount whore” with
“mount sin” (ai!).</p>
          <p>But most would want, I think, more sympathy for “the lost Traveller.” He, after all, seems
the final avatar of the protagonist of <hi rend="i">For the Sexes</hi>: the speaking “I” specifically
labeled in plate 14 as “The Traveller [who] hasteth in the Evening.” Such a sympathetic identification,
contra Carew, would no doubt duly approve Ulysses’ dream of a faithful wife, even if supposing its twenty
years’ duration to border on wish-fulfillment. A dream of fidelity would have particular resonance for an
author well versed in “the torments of Love &amp; Jealousy” and might serve to gloss the curious possible
inference of “To the Accuser . . . ” lines 3 and 4 regarding Blake’s wife, Catherine, and the wife of
his sometimes best friend John Flaxman, Ann (also Anna and Nancy in Blake’s writing):
<q>
Harlot : Virgin :: Kate : Nan
</q>
It was for Mrs. Flaxman that Blake, commissioned by her husband, had prepared his “Illustrations to Gray’s
<hi rend="i">Poems</hi>”—including the epigraph to “Ode on the Spring.” This seemingly added comment
or clue can be seen as presenting (to “Nancy F—” most of all) the designer self-reflexively addressing
his “wild root” (phallus / sexuality / inspiration) as a “Traveller” which is now to dream among the
“leaves”—each of which in its materialization represents a leave-taking or parting from his seminal
desire:
<q>
Around the Springs of Gray my wild root weaves<lb/>
Traveller repose &amp; dream among my leaves.
</q>
In “The Keys of the Gates” the root has become “the Worm Weaving in the Ground” which, with the
wo[r]m-en in the speaker’s existence (Mother, Sister, Wife [Daughter?—as per S. Foster Damon’s
speculation about <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>], Catherine), ends “Weaving to Dreams the Sexual strife.”</p>
          <p>The speaker of Carew’s “The Rapture” also worries about sexual strife—not only the toll
of hypocritic chastity which Honor demands for women, but even more the unChristian bloody revenges and
consequent potential damnation Honor expects of jealous men. He ends the poem with this question:
<q>
Then <hi rend="i">tell me why</hi><lb/>
This Goblin Honour which the world adores,<lb/>
Should make men Atheists, and not women Whores?
</q>
The prologue to <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: THE GATES of PARADISE</hi> echoes Carew’s satiric stance in its
uncomprehending conclusion: “O Christians Christians! <hi rend="i">tell me Why</hi> / You rear it on your
Altars high” (emphases added here and above).</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
