<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
	<teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
		<idno>24.1.essick</idno>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="article">Blake in the Marketplace, 1989, Including a Report on the Recently Discovered
Blake-Varley Sketchbook</title>
				<author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<editionStmt>
				<edition>Summer 1990</edition>
			</editionStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<date>1990</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblFull>
					<titleStmt>
						<title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
						<biblScope unit="volIss">24.1</biblScope>
						<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
						<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
						<respStmt>
							<resp>Editors</resp>
							<name>Morris Eaves</name>
							<name>Morton D. Paley</name>
							<resp>Managing Editor</resp>
							<name>Patricia Neill</name>
							<resp>Bibliographer</resp>
							<name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
							<resp>Review Editor</resp>
							<name>Nelson Hilton</name>
							<resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
							<name>David Worrall</name>
							<resp>Contributors</resp>
							<name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
							<name>Robert N. Essick</name>
							<name>Michael Ferber</name>
							<name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
							<name>John E. Grant</name>
							<name>David Groves</name>
							<name>Colin Pedley</name>
							<name>Marcus Wood</name>
						</respStmt>
					</titleStmt>
					<publicationStmt>
						<publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
						<pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
						<date value="1990"/>
						<authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
					</publicationStmt>
				</biblFull>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage> 
				<language id="eng">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text id="volume_24">
		<body>
			<pb id="p24-220" n="220"/>
			<div1 id="BQ-24-1-0005">
			<head>
			<title type="main">Blake in the Marketplace, 1989, Including a Report on the Recently Discovered
Blake-Varley Sketchbook</title>
			</head>
			<byline>by <docAuthor>Robert N.
			<name>Essick</name></docAuthor></byline>
			<p>The Blake market roared
			ahead at a high level of activity throughout 1989. More illuminated
			books were sold than in any year since 1958, some stratospheric price
			records were set, and an important notebook of drawings was discovered.
			Three auctions and one private sale deserve particular attention.</p>
			<p>The long-awaited sale of Blakes from the Edward Laurence Doheny
			Memorial Library finally arrived in Christie’s New York rooms on 21
			February. The first Blake to be offered, copy N of <hi rend="i">Songs of
			Innocence</hi> (illus. 3-6), was quickly pushed by several bidders well
			beyond the estimate range of $80,000-100,000 printed in the catalogue.
			Action slowed in the neighborhood of $225,000, and then battle resumed
			between just two combatants, the New York (formerly London) dealer
			Donald A. Heald and the London dealer Libby Howie (acting for an
			American private collector). The latter made the winning bid of $300,000
			(not including the 10% purchaser’s premium). This is about the same
			amount fetched by the entire Graham Robertson collection of Blake’s
			drawings and water colors sold in 90 lots in 1949.</p>
			<p>Stephen
			Massey, head of Christie’s Book Department and the auctioneer for this
			sale, proceeded through five unspectacular Blake lots to reach a
			remarkable set of the Dante engravings, printed directly on laid paper
			rather than the usual India paper backed by wove. Heald bought these
			foxed but very fine impressions at $55,000 “hammer price” (i.e., the
			actual amount bid, not including the buyer’s premium), thereby setting a
			new 
			<figure n="BookOfThelATitlePage.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="368">
				<head>1. Blake.</head>
				<figDesc><hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, copy A, title
			page. Relief etching, 16.1 × 10.1 cm. on sheet 26.4 × 18.2 cm., printed
			in golden-brown ink and hand colored in blue, rose, pale green, and pale
			yellow. Photo courtesy of Sotheby’s New York.</figDesc>
			</figure> 
			record
			for any Dante suite. Two insignificant lots followed, leading the
			audience of about 100 to Blake’s letter to John Linnell of 2 July 1826
			(illus. 16). An auctioneer’s rule of thumb is to offer the most
			important lots by a single author or artist first so that unsuccessful
			bidders on the big-ticket items can assuage their frustrations by paying
			too much for lesser materials. Christie’s violated this custom by
			offering the letter before a splendid water color. As a result, the
			letter brought a $20,000 hammer price, only 33% above the high estimate.
			The lot would have been bid up by at least another $5000 if sold after
			the drawing.</p>
			<p>The last Blake lot was <hi rend="i">Infant Jesus
			Saying His Prayers</hi> (illus. 15), estimated at $50,000-100,000.
			Although somewhat faded in the yellows and blues, and with pigment
			(lead?) decay in the darker colors at the top, this was still the finest
			Blake water color to be offered for sale since 1973, when Paul Mellon
			bought <hi rend="i">The Magdalene at the Sepulchre</hi> at Christie’s in
			London for £23,100. Bidding was exceptionally spirited, with
			participation from several art dealers as well as booksellers. As the
			price zoomed above $200,000 and the audience murmured in surprise, it
			became difficult to determine who was still in the hunt. The final two
			bids seemed to be either on the telephone or “at the desk” (i.e.,
			handled by Christie’s for a client), but the water color fell at
			$320,000 to the same American collector who had purchased the 
			<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> a few minutes earlier. Both works join
			<hi rend="i">America</hi> copy R (see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 21 [1988]:
			138-42), a hand-colored copy of <hi rend="i">Little Tom the Sailor</hi>,
			and several leaves from illuminated books in what is now arguably one of
			the two finest (although certainly not the largest) Blake collections in
			private hands. The collector insists on anonymity.</p>
			<p>The price
			realized by <hi rend="i">Infant Jesus</hi> set a new record for a Blake
			water color and for any work by him sold at auction. Of more
			significance is the fact that this water color fetched more than the 
			<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> in the same sale. Clearly, the art
			world is waking up to Blake. Proceeds from the sale of the Doheny
			Library will be used by the Catholic Archdiocese of Los Angeles for the
			recruitment and training of priests.</p>
			<pb id="p24-221" n="221"/>
			<p>At a time unknown to me, late in 1988 or early in 1989, a gentleman
			brought to the Drawings Department at Christie’s in London a shabby
			notebook of 68 leaves, 25.4 × 20.3 cm., some with an 1804 watermark. The
			first 18 leaves bear landscape and architectural drawings by John
			Varley. But suddenly, beginning with the verso of a leaf numbered 18,
			Christie’s drawing expert came upon a series of stunning Visionary Heads
			by Blake (illus. 10-14). There are 52 leaves of drawings by Blake, a few
			with more than one portrait, plus 4 counterproofs of other Visionary
			Heads. (A counterproof of a pencil drawing is made by placing it face
			down against a dampened sheet of paper and rubbing or applying pressure
			to the back of the drawing. Graphite is transferred to the dampened
			sheet to create a reversed copy of the original.) All the drawings are
			in pencil, with the larger portraits worked up in considerable
			physiognomic detail, some heightened with black chalk. Most of the
			drawings bear brief inscriptions, apparently by Varley, identifying the
			characters. Varley foliated all the leaves consecutively on the top
			right corner of their rectos and used the book for his own drawings on a
			sketching tour in 1808, as the date inscribed on the first leaf
			indicates. In October 1819, the date inscribed on leaves 83 and 89,
			Varley lent the sketchbook to Blake, who turned it upside down and began
			to fill the leaves with his own drawings, working back to front, mostly
			on versos.</p>
			<p>Christie’s, believing they had been brought a
			considerable treasure for sale, devoted an entire catalogue to the
			sketchbook, with reproductions of all but one of Blake’s drawings (leaf
			25 recto—see the list below). No estimate was printed in the catalogue,
			but upon inquiry one was told that the auction house expected the book
			to fetch half a million pounds. At the sale on 21 March, there was not a
			single bid in the room. As is customary in such situations, the house
			ran up the asking bids to a respectable buy-in price—a practice often
			called “bouncing it off the wall.” At some time after the sale, a
			consortium of three dealers, including two Americans, made a substantial
			offer, eagerly accepted by Christie’s and the sketchbook’s owner. Upon
			application for an export license, the government put a 4 month hold on
			the sale. During that time, any British institution could acquire the
			sketchbook by meeting the selling price. The British Museum had
			expressed interest, but it could not raise sufficient funds, and the
			consortium fell asunder in January 1990. The sketchbook remains on
			deposit at Christie’s, but will be in the Blake Exhibition at the
			National Museum of Western Art, Tokyo, in September 1990. The fact that
			several leaves bearing Blake’s drawings were removed from the sketchbook
			early in its history might provide an excuse for breaking it up and
			selling each leaf individually. This was the fate of the previously
			known 
			<figure n="europe.c-proof.P4a" rend="file" width="729" height="1000">
				<head>2. Blake.</head>
				<figDesc><hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, copy c, pl. 4. Relief
			etching and white-line engraving, third state of three, 23.6 × 17.1 cm.
			on sheet 25 × 18.5 cm. mounted to a backing sheet within pen and ink
			framing lines. Printed in brick red ink, probably by Frederick Tatham,
			c. 1830-32. Essick collection.</figDesc>
			</figure> 
			Blake-Varley
			sketchbook (Butlin #692), sold leaf by leaf at Christie’s in 1971.</p>
			<p>Although I have not seen this new and “larger” Blake-Varley
			sketchbook (the smaller book has leaves measuring 15.5 × 20.5 cm.), the
			very thorough auction catalogue and information supplied by David
			Bindman allow me to make this preliminary report. I list below, in the
			probable order of their execution, all of Blake’s drawings. The leaf
			numbers follow Varley’s enumeration, and thus run in reverse. All
			quotations are of Varley’s inscriptions in the sketchbook unless noted
			otherwise. Drawings that were once in this sketchbook and other
			Visionary Heads of the same or related characters are referred to by
			Butlin numbers.</p>
			<p>89 recto. A draft of Varley’s list of Visionary
			Heads (see 85 verso) with a slight sketch of a head, “possibly Varley by
			Blake” (according to the auction catalogue). This portrait is not part
			of the main sequence. Not the same head as Butlin #689.</p>
			<p>88-86.
			Missing. Perhaps with portraits, removed for counterproofing.</p>
			<p>85
			verso. “List of Portraits Drawn by W<hi rend="s">m</hi> Blake from
			visions / which appeard to him &amp; Remain<hi rend="s">d</hi>. while he
			completed them / Some of which are in other Books[.]” In Varley’s hand.
			The “other Books” would presumably include the smaller Blake-Varley
			sketchbook, but could also include the “large book filled with drawings”
			of Visionary Heads that Allan Cunningham was shown by Varley
			(Cunningham, <hi rend="i">The Lives of the Most Eminent British
			Painters, Sculptors, and Architects</hi>, 2nd ed. [London: Murray, 1830]
			172). This group, perhaps of loose drawings inserted in a folder,
			included Pindar, Lais, and the “task-master whom Moses slew,” and thus
			cannot be identified with either extant sketchbook.</p>
			<p>84. Missing.
			Perhaps this leaf bore a portrait, like others removed for
			counterproofing.</p>
			<p>83 recto. “Cassibelane the British Chief,” cut
			out and pasted to the stub of leaf 82. Same images as Butlin #716 (a
			strengthened counterproof from this drawing?). Cassivellanus, chief of
			the Catuvellani, resisted Julius Caesar’s invasion of Britain in 54
			B.C.</p>
			<p>82. Missing; possibly Butlin #716 (see 83 recto).</p>
			<pb
			id="p24-222" n="222"/>
			<p>81 verso. Counterproof of Cassibelane from 83
			recto, strengthened by another hand (Varley?).</p>
			<p>80 verso.
			Blank—see 69.</p>
			<p>80 recto. “Merlin,” counterproof of Butlin #757
			(therein provisionally identified as “A Welsh Bard, Job or Moses?”).</p>
			<p>79-72. Missing. These leaves included Butlin #722 (“Canute,” a
			strengthened counterproof, still bearing Varley’s leaf number “77”
			upside down on the reverse), probably its untraced original, and perhaps
			Butlin #731-33 (King John, 1167-1216, and two counterproofs).</p>
			<p>71.
			Blank.</p>
			<p>70. Removed. The counterproof (Butlin #725) of 69, still
			bearing Varley’s leaf number upside down on the reverse.</p>
			<p>69.
			“Empress Maud,” also known as Matilda (1102-67), daughter of Henry I and
			wife of Emperor Henry V. Removed and attached to leaf 80 verso. Three
			full-length drawings in the smaller sketchbook show Maud standing in a
			gothic apse, in bed, and without surrounding motifs (Butlin #692.23, 25,
			27).</p>
			<p>68. Removed. Counterproof (Butlin #741) of 67, still bearing
			Varley’s leaf number upside down on the reverse.</p>
			<p>67 verso, loose
			but present. “Wat Tylers Daughter / Striving to get loose from the Tax
			gatherer.” Face and shoulders of the daughter only; see also 65.</p>
			<p>66. Removed. Counterproof (Butlin #737) of 65, still bearing Varley’s
			leaf number upside down on the reverse.</p>
			<p>65. “Wat Tyler / in the
			act of striking the Tax Gatherer.” Tyler’s grimacing face only, with two
			details of his mouth. Removed and attached to the stub of leaf 70. The
			subjects of this and 67 verso may have been influenced by Fuseli’s
			design, showing Wat Tyler, his fleeing daughter, and the fallen
			tax-gatherer, engraved by Blake for Charles Allen, <hi rend="i">A New
			and Improved History of England</hi>, 1798. This legendary incident
			resulted from a confusion between Wat Tyler, who with Jack Straw
			rebelled against Richard II, and John Tyler, a blacksmith who killed a
			tax-gatherer for attacking his daughter.</p>
			<p>64 and 63. Removed.</p>
			<p>62. Removed. Counterproof (Butlin #730) of 61, still bearing Varley’s
			leaf number upside down on the reverse.</p>
			<p>61 verso. “The Bastard
			Faulconberg”—either the illegitimate son of Richard I, or the Earl of
			Kent, natural son of Sir William Neville. There are two profiles and a
			standing figure of Faulconberg in the smaller sketchbook (Butlin
			#692.38, 57).</p>
			<p>60 verso. “Hotspur” (Sir Henry Percy, 1364-1403).
			Butlin #745 is probably a strengthened counterproof of this original.
			Varley inscribed “Hotspur . . .” on a page in the smaller sketchbook
			(Butlin #692.53), but this does not seem to be related to the two
			figures (one winged, one with a halo) roughly sketched above. Hotspur is
			also mentioned in Varley’s notes near the end of the smaller book
			(Butlin #692.131).</p>
			<p>59 verso. “[Al, <hi rend="i">deleted</hi>]
			Owen Glendower” (1359?-1416?), leader of the Welsh rebellion against
			Henry IV. Butlin #743-44 are probably counterproofs of this original.
			The fragmentary “Al” may be the beginning of “Alexander”—see 58
			verso.</p>
			<p>58 verso. “Alexander the Great.” Butlin #698 may be a
			counterproof, inscribed (by John Linnell?) “David.” See also 21
			verso.</p>
			<p>57 verso (illus. 10). “Henry the 5<hi rend="s">th</hi>”
			(1387-1422).</p>
			<p>56 verso. “the Black Prince” (Edward, Prince of
			Wales, 1330-76). For an earlier portrayal, c. 1793, see 
			<hi rend="i">Edward III Presenting the Black Prince to the Barons</hi>
			(Butlin #66).</p>
			<p>55 verso. “Robin Hood.”</p>
			<p>54 verso. “Pharoah
			who knew Joseph.” For Blake’s designs based on the story of Joseph,
			exhibited in 1785, see Butlin #155-57.</p>
			<p>53 verso. “Josephs
			Mistress.” This profile is similar to the wife’s in Blake’s water color
			of c. 1803-05, <hi rend="i">Joseph and Potiphar’s Wife</hi> (Butlin
			#439).</p>
			<p>52 verso. “Perkin Warbeck” (1474-99, pretender to the
			throne of Henry VII).</p>
			<p>51 verso. “Vortigern” (betrayer of the
			British cause, c. 450, out of love for Rowena—see 49-50 verso).</p>
			<p>50 verso (illus. 11). “Rowenna” (see 51 verso).</p>
			<p>49 verso.
			“Rowenna” (basically the same portrait as 50 verso, but showing the
			woman’s breasts).</p>
			<p>48 verso. “Felton the <corr type="emend">assassinator</corr> / of the Duke
			of Buckingham” (John Felton, 1595?-1628).</p>
			<p>47 verso. “Milton when
			a Boy” (John Milton, 1608-74). Probably influenced by Cornelius 
			<figure n="SINNDivineImageN.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="390">
				<head>3. Blake.</head>
				<figDesc>“The Divine Image” from <hi rend="i">Songs of
			Innocence</hi>, copy N. Relief etching and white-line engraving, 11.2 ×
			7 cm. on sheet 19.8 × 12.8 cm., printed in brown ink, hand colored.
			Photo courtesy of Christie’s New York.</figDesc>
			</figure> 
			Johnson’s portrait, engraved by John Baptist Cipriani in 1760 and published in 
			<hi rend="i">Memoirs of Thomas Hollis</hi> (1780). For Blake’s comments to
			Henry Crabb Robinson and Samuel Palmer about the Milton portraits in
			Hollis, see G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford:
			Clarendon Press, 1969) 317n1, 543, and Bentley, “A Portrait of Milton
			Engraved by William Blake ‘When Three Years of Age’? A Speculation by
			Samuel Palmer,” <hi rend="i">University of Toronto Quarterly</hi> 51
			(1981): 28-35.</p>
			<p>46 verso. “Milton when young.” A much fuller face
			than Cipriani’s engraving in Hollis (see 47 verso) showing Milton at
			about the same age. For an older, blind Milton, see Blake’s tempera in
			his “Heads of the Poets” series of c. 1800-03 (Butlin #343.11). There is
			a portrait of Milton’s first wife in the smaller Blake-Varley sketchbook
			(Butlin #692.96), sold 14 Nov. 1989 to Christopher Powney.</p>
			<p>45
			verso (illus. 12). “Charlemagne” (first Holy Roman Emperor).</p>
			<p>44
			verso. “Miltons youngest daughter.”</p>
			<p>43 verso. “Miltons elder
			[inserted above] daughter.”</p>
			<pb id="p24-223" n="223"/>
			<figure n="SINNInfantJoyN.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="400">
				<head>4. Blake.</head>
				<figDesc>“Infant Joy” from <hi rend="i">Songs of
			Innocence</hi>, copy N. Relief etching, 11.1 × 6.8 cm., printed in brown
			ink, hand colored. Photo courtesy of Christie’s New York.</figDesc>
			</figure>
			<p>42 verso. “Bertand de Gourdon who wounded / Richard Coeur
			de Lion with an Arrow.”</p>
			<p>41 verso. “The Captain to Richard the
			first / who Flayd Bertand de Gourdon alive.” For the Visionary Head of
			Richard I, see Butlin #729.</p>
			<p>40 verso. “Jack Shepherd / under the
			Gallows.” The gallows are not pictured. John Shepherd (1702-24) escaped
			hanging twice but was not so lucky the third time.</p>
			<p>39 verso.
			“Colonel Blood who attempted / to Steal the Crown.” Thomas Blood
			(1618?-80) was pardoned by Charles II for his crime.</p>
			<p>38 verso
			(illus. 13). “The Great Earl of Warwick / Brother to Ed<hi
			rend="s">wd</hi>. the 4<hi rend="s">th</hi> / Drawn by W<hi
			rend="s">m</hi> Blake.” Richard Neville, “The Kingmaker,” 1428-71.</p>
			<p>37 verso. “Queen Isabella wife to Ed<hi rend="s">wd</hi> the 2<hi
			rend="s">d</hi>. &amp; mother to Ed<hi rend="s">wd</hi> the 3<hi
			rend="s">d</hi>.” Queen Isabella of France (1292-1358) married Edward II
			in 1308 and deposed him in favor of her son in 1327.</p>
			<p>36 verso.
			“Robert Bruce King of Scotland.” Bruce (1274-1329) was crowned King of
			the Scots in 1306.</p>
			<p>35 verso. “Geofrey of Monmouth” (1100-54,
			author of the <hi rend="i">Historia Britonum</hi>).</p>
			<p>34 verso.
			“Ossian” (the legendary Gaelic bard made famous by James Macpherson’s
			“translations”). Blake comments approvingly on Macpherson and Ossian in
			his 1826 annotations to Wordsworth’s <hi rend="i">Poems</hi> (see 
			<hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David
			V. Erdman, rev. ed. [Berkeley: U of California Press, 1982] 665-66).</p>
			<p>34 recto. A continuation of the landscape on 33 verso.</p>
			<p>33
			verso. “Ossian” (see 34 verso), full length, with his harp and standing
			on a hill before an enormous tree, mountains in the background.</p>
			<p>32 verso. Sketches of 7 heads, inscribed “Mother / Brownrigg”
			(murderess, hanged 1767), “Miss Blandy / who poisoned / her father”
			(hanged 1752), “Pope Joan” (the mythical female Pope of the 9th
			century), “Cornelius Agrippa” (occult philosopher, 1486-1535), “Eloisa”
			(Abelard’s beloved, died 1164), “Abelard” (theologian, 1079-1142),
			“Countess of Essex who / Poisoned Overbury” (Sir Thomas Overbury the
			poet, 1581-1613). A face very similar to Brownrigg’s appears in the
			smaller sketchbook (Butlin #692.72, “perhaps by Blake”); Mary Blandy’s
			features resemble Queen Isabella’s (37 verso).</p>
			<p>31 verso.
			“Catherine Hayes / Burnt for the Murder / of her Husband” in 1736.</p>
			<p>31 recto. A bishop’s mitre, no doubt linked to the bare-headed bishop
			on 30 verso.</p>
			<p>30 verso (illus. 14). An archbishop, possibly Thomas
			à Becket, murdered in 1170 (see 29 verso).</p>
			<p>29 verso. “a Becket
			Preaching,” full length with mitre and crozier standing on a gothic
			pulpit. With another standing figure, holding a book; a baby’s head;
			three fragments of gothic ornament (details for the archbishop’s costume
			or pulpit); head of an old man; 2 heads of women; and a figure standing
			in a gothic niche, perhaps a detail for one of the 5 (carved?) figures
			in niches on the pulpit.</p>
			<p>28 verso. “Mary Queen of Scots”
			(1542-87).</p>
			<p>28 recto. A continuation of the battlements on 27
			verso.</p>
			<p>27 verso. “Bothwell” (James Hepburn, 4th Earl of Bothwell,
			1536-78, and Queen Mary’s husband—see 28 verso). Behind this bust are
			some battlements.</p>
			<p>26 verso. “Tom Nixon the Idiot / the author of
			several Prophecies.” Robert (or “Tom”) Nixon, the seventeenth-century
			prophet of Cheshire.</p>
			<p>25 verso. “Pisistratus” (561-27 B.C.), the
			tyrant of Athens.</p>
			<p>25 recto. Sketches for the throne of
			Pisistratus on 24 verso.</p>
			<p>24 verso. “Pisistratus” (see 25 verso)
			seated on a monumental throne, apparently constructed of stone
			blocks.</p>
			<p>24 recto. A prisoner in profile, with a chain descending
			from his right wrist, standing between two guards in classical garb and
			holding spears. Perhaps related to the Pisistratus drawings, leaves
			24-25.</p>
			<p>23 verso. “a daughter of Shakespeare” (either Susanna,
			born 1583, or Judith, 1585-1662). See also 20 verso.</p>
			<p>22 verso.
			“Xantippe / wife of Socrates.” Blake sketched two visionary heads of
			Xanthippe’s husband, Butlin #713-14.</p>
			<p>21 verso. “Olympia.” Perhaps
			Olympias, mother of Alexander the Great (see 58 verso).</p>
			<p>20 verso.
			“Shakespeare’s Wife” (Anne Hathaway, 1556-1623). See also 23 verso.</p>
			<p>19 verso. “Savage the Poet” (Richard Savage, died 1743, was found
			guilty of murder in 1727 but was pardoned), and two counterproofs of a
			young man in profile (the original untraced).</p>
			<p>18 verso. “Sir
			Robert Lucy. Shakespeares Persecutor.” Lucy (1532-1600), who may have
			prosecuted Shakespeare for poaching c. 1585, has been suggested as the
			model for Justice Shallow in <hi rend="i">Henry IV, Part II.</hi></p>
			<p>Even this bare list of subjects encourages a little speculation. The
			principle of order lurking behind the potpourri of sketches is taxonomic
			and categorical, not chronological, as one would expect on the basis of
			Varley’s physiognomic predilections (and perhaps Blake’s). Several
			clusters of character types emerge, although none runs as an
			uninterrupted sequence. For the student of Blake’s poetry, perhaps the
			most interesting group is the poets and other visionaries: Merlin,
			Ossian, Cornelius 
			<pb id="p24-224" n="224"/>
			<figure n="SINNTheLambN.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="390">
				<head>5. Blake.</head>
				<figDesc>“The Lamb” from <hi rend="i">Songs of
			Innocence</hi>, copy N. Relief etching, 11.9 × 7.7 cm., printed in brown
			ink, hand colored. Photo courtesy of Christie’s New
			York.</figDesc>
			</figure> 
			Agrippa, Milton, Tom Nixon, and even Savage
			(whose longest poem, “The Wanderer,” is sub-titled “A Vision”). The last
			figure supplies a transition to a larger group of murderers and, more
			surprisingly, murderesses. Varley may have been seeking for the
			physiognomic traces of criminal personality of the sort Blake apparently
			tried to express in the visages of his would-be assassins in 
			<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> pl. 4 (illus. 2) and the 
			<hi rend="i">Malevolence</hi> water color of 1799 (Butlin #341). Victims
			seem under-represented in the sketchbook, although one of the
			ecclesiastics portrayed, Thomas à Becket, was a famous martyr. Some of
			these characters resist any attempt to place them in rigid, moralistic
			categories: Mary Queen of Scots was both criminal and victim, while
			Robin Hood and Jack Shepherd are remembered as folk heroes more than
			criminals.</p>
			<p>The small-scale killers, generally executed for their
			efforts, lead us to military leaders (large-scale killers honored for
			their efforts), and then to a class of paired opposites: assassins,
			traitors, and rebels vs. monarchs of church and state. Were Blake and
			Varley searching for connections between victim and victimizer, rebel
			and tyrant, signified in their visages? Physiognomy must have played a
			major role in leading the two artists to the mothers, wives, and
			children of famous men—the daughters of Milton and Shakespeare, the
			latter’s wife, the mother of Alexander the Great. But some of these
			family pairs can also remind us of Blake’s Zoas and their Emanations, a
			system of union and differentiation not incompatible with physiognomic
			paradigms. Similarly, the murderesses and characters such as Pope Joan
			and Isabella of France recall Blake’s declarations against the Female
			Will. For other thoughts on the contents of the sketchbook, see David
			Bindman’s essay in <hi rend="i">Christie’s International Magazine</hi> 6
			(March-April 1989): 2-4.</p>
			<p>The relationship between the new
			sketchbook and other Visionary Heads bears consideration. The unsigned
			introductory essay in Christie’s March 1989 auction catalogue suggests
			that drawings sketched during seance-like sessions at night in the
			smaller book were transferred to the larger for finishing, but I can
			find no convincing evidence for this as a regular practice. The only
			character who appears as a facial portrait in both sketchbooks,
			Faulconberg, is recognizably the same person, but he is pictured in
			profile in the smaller book and in three-quarter perspective in the
			larger. The smaller book is certainly in a lesser state of finish, but
			its larger companion seems also to have been used for primary sketches.
			Many of these were subsequently worked up with pencil and black chalk,
			while the latter was never used in the smaller sketchbook. The next
			stage was to remove leaves for counterproofing, but this progressed in
			the larger book only through the first twenty or so leaves used by
			Blake. It must be remembered that the entire project was a corporate
			activity involving three professional artists of considerable
			ability—Blake, Varley, and John Linnell (at least in later stages of
			production). The second and third may have had a hand in the black-chalk
			additions on some sketches.</p>
			<p>The discovery of the larger
			sketchbook allows us to disentangle the provenance of the smaller. The
			artist William Mulready, a close friend of both Varley and Linnell, sold
			at Christie’s on 28 April 1864, lot 86, “a volume containing 49 heads in
			pencil, from visions which appeared to Blake . . .; at the other end of
			the book are 16 landscapes by Varley” (£5.5s. to “Kempton”). In a note
			to Frederic George Stephens, c. 1872, Samuel Palmer refers to the sale
			of this “volume containing fortynine heads in pencil from visions which
			appeared to Blake” (untraced, but printed in Stephens, 
			<hi rend="i">Memorials of William Mulready</hi> [London: Sampson Low, 1890]
			41). Having no other candidates to fit these descriptions, Butlin took
			them to be rather inaccurate references to the smaller sketchbook, even
			though it contains more than 16 sketches by Varley. As presently
			constituted, the smaller book includes only 21 “heads” by Blake, and it
			is difficult to conceive how the missing leaves could contain another
			28. We can now identify Mulready’s volume as the larger sketchbook, for
			it has 16 drawings by Varley and 49 by Blake (if we count only the major
			“heads”). This second number is doubly significant, for it supports the
			supposition that all the missing leaves were removed prior to 1864 for
			counterproofing. The smaller book apparently passed from Varley to his
			friend William Christian Selle, then to Selle’s daughter who married H.
			Buxton Forman, who gave the sketchbook to William Bell Scott in 1870.
			After its sale in 1864, the larger volume passed by inheritance to the
			man who still owns it, in spite of Christie’s best efforts.</p>
			<pb
			id="p24-225" n="225"/>
			<p>Who would have thought that the records set at
			the Doheny sale would last only eight months? On 9 and 10 November,
			Sotheby’s New York sold in 308 lots a collection of fine books and
			manuscripts, the property of “The Garden Ltd.” This collection had been
			formed in recent years by Haven O’More, an admirer of Blake and of Sir
			Geoffrey Keynes, and for a brief spell an Associate Trustee of the Blake
			Trust. The catalogue will itself become a collector’s item, both for its
			many fine illustrations and for O’More’s literary contributions—a
			prefatory essay “On the Mystery of the Book” and an autobiographical
			note couched in the third person. Both are glorious compounds of ersatz
			mysticism and soaring egotism. The catalogue ends with a modest note
			that someone named “Michael Davis” provided “the funding for The
			Garden’s Collection” and was its sole owner.</p>
			<p>Copy D of 
			<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (illus. 7-9) was the
			first 
			<figure n="SINNSpringN.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="377">
				<head>6. Blake.</head>
				<figDesc>“Spring,” first plate, from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, copy N. Relief etching,
perhaps with touches of white-line engraving, 11.6 × 7.7 cm., printed in brown ink, hand colored. Photo
courtesy of Christie’s New York.</figDesc>
			</figure> 
			Blake lot offered from the Garden/O’More/Davis
			collection. A splendid copy in every way, it commanded an estimate of
			$300,000-400,000. Spirited bidding from several quarters brushed by
			these figures quickly. One of three remaining bidders dropped out at
			$800,000, leaving the field to the New York dealer Martin Breslauer and
			an agent acting for a private collector. The latter won his or her prize
			at $1.2 million ($1.32 million with the buyer’s premium)—a new record
			for any work by Blake, and I believe a record for any single work of
			English literature. The book’s new owner has not responded to my letter
			passed on to him or her by Sotheby’s.</p>
			<p>The room, suffering from
			sticker-shock, paid little attention to the next lot, copy A of 
			<hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> (illus. 1), one of only two remaining in
			private hands. The book fell to Donald Heald, acting for a private
			client, at a mere $130,000 on an estimate of $70,000-100,000. At that
			point, a Sotheby’s employee claimed that she had been distracted by the
			hubbub over the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and had failed to bid, as
			instructed, for a client. In spite of Heald’s protests, bidding was
			resumed, and the lot fell at $145,000 to Sotheby’s client. I have not
			yet been able to discover this collector’s identity. As a minor-league
			epilogue, the Blake lots ended with two posthumouslyprinted plates from
			<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (to Heald for Essick—see illus. 2) and a set of
			the Dante engravings (also to Heald).</p>
			<p>Edwin Wolf 2nd is known to
			Blake enthusiasts principally as the coauthor, with Geoffrey Keynes, of
			the <hi rend="i">Census</hi> of Blake’s illuminated books published by
			the Grolier Club in 1953. But Wolf is also a discriminating collector
			who built a fine working library of Blake editions, criticism, and books
			containing Blake’s commercial engravings. This last category included
			copies of the 1825 and 1826 issues of <hi rend="i">Remember Me!</hi>,
			both considerable rarities. Wolf sold his collection of some 350 books
			and offprints to an American dealer early in 1989. In June 1990 the
			collection was available from James Burmester and another British dealer
			acting in partnership.</p>
			<p>The year of all sales and catalogues in
			the following lists is 1989 unless indicated otherwise. The auction
			houses add their purchaser’s surcharge to the hammer price in their
			price lists. These net amounts are given here, following the official
			price lists. Late 1989 sales will be covered in the 1990 review. Copy
			designations and plate numbers for the illuminated books follow G. E.
			Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon Press,
			1977). I am grateful for help in compiling this review to David Bindman,
			Martin Butlin, Scot Campbell of Hindman Auctioneers, Chris Coover and
			Stephen Massey of Christie’s, William Dailey, Jay Dillon of Sotheby’s,
			Detlef Dörrbecker, Paul Grinke of Quaritch, Donald Heald, Justin
			Schiller, David Weinglass, and especially Thomas V. Lange.</p>
			<div2>
			<head>
			<title>
			<hi rend="i">ABBREVIATIONS</hi>
			</title>
			</head>
			<table
			rows="12" cols="2">
			<row>
			<cell>BBA</cell>
			<cell>Bloomsbury Book
			Auctions, London</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
			<cell>Butlin</cell>
			<cell>Martin
			Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>, 2
			vols. (New Haven: Yale UP, 1981)</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
			<cell>cat.</cell>
			<cell>catalogue or sales list issued by a dealer (usually followed by a
			number or letter designation) or auction house (followed by the day and
			month of sale)</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
			<cell>CL</cell>
			<cell>Christie’s,
			London</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
			<cell>CNY</cell>
			<cell>Christie’s, New
			York</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
			<cell>illus.</cell>
			<cell>the item or part
			thereof is reproduced in the catalogue</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
			<cell>pl(s).</cell>
			<cell>plate(s)</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
			<cell>SL</cell>
			<cell>Sotheby’s, London</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
			<cell>SNY</cell>
			<cell>Sotheby’s, New York</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
			<cell>st.</cell>
			<cell>state of an engraving, etching, or lithograph</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
			<cell>Swann</cell>
			<cell>Swann Galleries, auctioneers, New York</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
			<cell>#</cell>
			<cell>auction lot or catalogue item
			number</cell>
			</row>
			</table>
			<pb id="p24-226" n="226"/>
			<figure n="SONGSIEDTitlePage.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="417">
				<head>7. Blake.</head>
				<figDesc><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
			Experience</hi>, copy D, general title page. Relief etching with touches
			of white-line engraving, 11.2 × 7 cm., printed in golden-brown ink,
			color printed in rust brown and black, hand tinted in black, light blue,
			pink, and red. Photo courtesy of Sotheby’s New York.</figDesc>
			</figure>
			<div3>
			<head>
			<title>
			<hi rend="i">ILLUMINATED BOOKS</hi>
			</title>
			</head>
			<p><hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, copy A. 8 pls. on 8
			leaves, printed in golden-brown, 6 pls. delicately hand colored.
			Unbound, matted, in a modern morocco folding case. SNY, 10 Nov., #166,
			title page illus. color ($159,500 to a Sotheby’s employee acting for a
			client). See illus. 1.</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, pls. 4 and 5
			only on 2 leaves from posthumous copy c. SNY, 10 Nov., #167, both pls.
			illus. color ($17,600 to D. Heald for R. Essick on an estimate of
			$5000-8000). See illus. 2.</p>
			<p>“Night,” pl. 1, from 
			<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence.</hi> Clipping of the final 9 lines of text
			and lower design only, 3.1 × 6.4 cm., printed in brown and hand colored
			in blue, green, and rose, with outlining and shading in dark brown.
			Verso, lower design only from “Night” pl. 2, hand colored and outlined
			as on the recto. Acquired April from David Bindman by R. Essick. Both
			sides illus. color, Lott &amp; Gerrish, June 1986 cat., p. 2.</p>
			<p><hi
			rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, copy N. 27 pls. on 27 leaves, printed
			in dark brown and hand colored. CNY, 21 Feb., #1706, title page and “The
			Lamb” illus. color ($330,000 to the London dealer Libby Howie acting for
			an American private collector). See illus. 3-6.</p>
			<p><hi
			rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, copy BB. 55 pls. on
			55 leaves, printed in black and hand tinted in black and gray washes.
			Now (June 1990) the property of Randolph Schlegl, Ltd., but available
			for sale.</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>,
			copy D. 54 pls. on 30 leaves, printed in 2 shades of brown, touches of
			color printing, hand colored. Bound in contemporary morocco with two
			flyleaves watermarked 1796. SNY, 10 Nov., #165, general title page,
			frontispiece to <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, and “The Tyger” illus.
			color ($1,320,000). The cat. description incorrectly claims that this
			copy contains “A Divine Image,” apparently as a result of confusing that
			pl. <pb id="p24-227" n="227"/>
with the tailpiece to the 
			<hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, which is present. See illus. 7-9.</p>
			</div3>
			<div3>
			<head>
			<title>
			<hi rend="i">DRAWINGS AND PAINTINGS</hi>
			</title>
			</head>
			<p>The larger Blake-Varley sketchbook of 1819. CL, 21 March,
			only lot (numbered 184), 62 leaves illus. (not sold). See the
			introductory list of contents, discussion, and illus. 10-14.</p>
			<p><hi
			rend="i">Complaint of Job</hi> (recto), <hi rend="i">Standing Figure</hi>
			 (verso). Pen and India ink, c. 1785, recto 33.2 × 47.1 cm. Butlin #163.
			This drawing, untraced since 1928, came into the possession of Thomas
			Gibson Fine Art Ltd., summer 1989, which sold it to a California private
			collector (not I, alas). Recto and verso illus. and described in Martin
			Butlin, “Six New Early Drawings by William Blake and a Reattribution,”
			<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 23 (1989): 107-12.</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Head of a
			King in Profile.</hi> Pencil, 8 × 6 ½ in., from the smaller Blake-Varley
			sketchbook. Butlin #692.88. CL, 14 Nov., #154, illus. (£1210 to
			Christopher Powney). Butlin suggests that this drawing may represent
			“King John,” but the auction cat. notes that it is indistinctly
			inscribed by Varley, “Robert” or “Richard.”</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Infant
			Jesus Saying His Prayers.</hi> Water color, Butlin #473. CNY, 21 Feb.,
			#1716, illus. color ($352,000 on an estimate of $50,000-100,000 to a
			dealer bidding on behalf of an American private collector). See illus.
			15.</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Milton’s First Wife.</hi> Pencil, 8 × 6 ⅛ in.,
			from the smaller Blake-Varley sketchbook. Butlin #692.96. CL, 14 Nov.,
			#153, illus. (£1650 to Christopher Powney).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Moses
			with the Tablets of the Law.</hi> Pencil, 20.8 × 14.6 cm., c. 1780-85.
			Not in Butlin. Agnew’s, Sept. private offer (£11,000). For illus., see
			Martin Butlin, “Six New Early Drawings by William Blake and a
			Reattribution,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 23 (1989): 107-12.</p>
			<p><hi
			rend="i">Queen Constance and Her Son.</hi> Pen and ink with wash, 20.9 ×
			24.9 cm., c. 1785, pencil sketch of a foot on verso. Butlin #151.
			Spencer A. Samuels &amp; Co., Feb. private offer ($45,000). Previously
			sold CL, 10 July 1984, #85, illus. (Spink &amp; Son, £3780). For illus.
			of recto and verso, see <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 19 (1985): 29.</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">A Richly Attired Prince, Perhaps Edward VI.</hi> Pencil,
			8 × 6 ⅛ in., from the smaller Blake-Varley sketchbook. Butlin #692.108.
			CL, 14 Nov., #151, illus. (£11,000 to an anonymous bidder on the
			telephone).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">A Royal Couple</hi> (verso) and 
			<hi rend="i">Detailed Drawings</hi> (by Blake and Varley?) <hi rend="i">for
			the Man Who Built the Pyramids</hi> (recto). Pencil, 8 × 6 ⅛ in., from
			the smaller Blake-Varley sketchbook. Butlin #692.103-04. CL, 14 Nov.,
			#152, verso illus. (£6050 to Christopher Powney).</p>
			<p><hi
			rend="i">St. Paul Shaking Off the Viper.</hi> Water color, 39 × 30 cm.,
			Butlin #509. Sold c. 1987 by Barry Friedman, Ltd., to another New York
			dealer, who sold it c. 1988 to a private New York collector.</p>
			<p><hi
			rend="i">A Vision: The Inspiration of the Poet.</hi> Grey washes over
			pencil, 17.1 × 17.8 cm., c. 1819-20(?). Butlin #756. Acquired late 1989
			by the Tate Gallery, London, from David C. Preston. For illus., see 
			<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 23 (spring 1990): cover and p. 213.</p>
			</div3>
			<div3>
			<head>
			<title>
			<hi rend="i">MANUSCRIPTS</hi>
			</title>
			</head>
			<p>Letter by Blake to John Linnell, Postmarked 2 July 1826. 1 p., tear
			on right side. CNY, 21 Feb., #1715, illus. ($22,000 to an American
			private collector). See illus. 16.</p>
			</div3>
			<div3>
			<head>
			<title>	
			<hi rend="i">SEPARATE PLATES &amp; PLATES IN SERIES, INCLUDING PLATES
			EXTRACTED FROM LETTERPRESS BOOKS</hi>
			</title>
			</head>
			<p>“Beggar’s
			Opera, Act III,” after Hogarth. Christopher Mendez, Sept. private offer,
			4th st., cut to platemark, washed, lower right corner repaired (£300).
			Sanders, Sept. private offer, 7th st. (£50). This plate is usually
			described as existing in 4 or 5 states, but there are at least 9.</p>
			<figure n="SONGSIEDFrontispiece.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="400">
				<head>8. Blake.</head>
				<figDesc><hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence
			and of Experience</hi>, copy D, frontispiece to 
			<hi rend="i">Experience.</hi> Relief etching, first state of two, 11 × 7
			cm., printed in golden-brown ink perhaps with touches of color printing
			in black, hand colored. Photo courtesy of Sotheby’s New York.</figDesc>
			</figure>
			<p>“Chaucers Canterbury Pilgrims.” Leslie Hindman auction,
			Chicago, 14 May, #302, illus. ($5500 to a California collector/dealer
			who gave it to the National Museum of Western Art, Tokyo).</p>
			<p>Dante
			engravings. CNY, 21 Feb., #1713, 7 pls. complete, very fine impressions
			on laid paper, probably pulled before the first recorded printing on
			India of 1838, foxed, 1 pl. illus. (D. Heald, $60,500). Jeremy Norman
			&amp; Co., May cat. 19, #110, the deluxe issue of the Blake Trust Dante
			facsimile, 1978, with a modern restrike of pl. 5 ($1500). SL, 27 June,
			#226, complete set on laid India, 1 support sheet with a “J. Whatman
			Turkey Mill watermark,” pl. 2 foxed, “otherwise in excellent fresh and
			unhandled condition,” 2 pls. illus., sold the “Property of a Member of
			the Linnell Family” (£38,500). CL, 29 June, #13, pls. 1-3, 5-7 only, pl.
			1 on laid India, the remainder printed directly 
			<pb id="p24-228" n="228"/>
			<figure n="SONGSIEDTheTyger.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="450">
				<head>9. Blake.</head>
				<figDesc>“The Tyger” from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>, copy D. Relief
			etching, 11 × 6.3 cm., printed in golden-brown ink perhaps with touches
			of color printing in black, hand colored in blue, brown, gray, olive
			green, and brick red. Photo courtesy of Sotheby’s New
			York.</figDesc>
			</figure> 
			on “thickish laid paper” (see first Dante entry
			above), pls. 6-7 “with part of a watermark A &amp; D,” all but pl. 1
			“very fine, rich impressions,” some foxing, 1 pl. illus. (Weston
			Gallery, £24,200); impressions on laid paper cleaned and offered by
			Weston, Dec. London Print Fair, £9000 each. SNY, 10 Nov., #168, complete
			set on laid India, traces of illegible watermark (letters?) on 2 pls.,
			with letterpress label, morocco folding case, from the collection of
			Moncure Biddle (D. Heald, $41,250). An essay on the printings of the
			Dante plates is forthcoming in <hi rend="i">Blake.</hi></p>
			<p>“Fertilization of Egypt” after Fuseli, from Darwin, 
			<hi rend="i">Botanic Garden</hi>, 1791. C. &amp; J. Goodfriend, Aug. private
			offer ($450).</p>
			<p>“George Cumberland’s Card.” Jeremy Norman &amp;
			Co., May cat. 19, #7, illus. ($300). This impression in black on laid
			paper, from the collection of K. Garth Huston and now in the private
			collection of Paul Grinke, London, is described in 
			<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 17 (1984): 142.</p>
			<p>Job engravings. CNY, 21 Feb.,
			complete set, 1874 printing on India laid on heavy wove, pl. 4 illus.
			($16,500). Weston Gallery, April cat. 2, #115, pl. 6 only, “Proof” on
			“French” wove paper, full margins; #116, pl. 7 only, published “Proof”
			on laid India, full margins, both illus. ($1925 each). CL, 12 April,
			#37, pl. 9 only, published “Proof” on laid India, illus. (£715). SNY, 11
			May, #7, “complete set of twenty [sic?] plus title plate,” 1874
			printing, foxed, pls. 3 and 5 illus. ($13,750). SL, 27 June, #227,
			complete set, 1874 printing on laid India, some foxing, pls. 15 and 20
			illus. (not sold; estimate £15,000-20,000); #228, pl. 4 only, published
			“Proof” on laid India (not sold); #229, pl. 19 only, 1874 printing on
			laid India (£880); #230, pl. 2 only, published “Proof” on wove (not
			sold). Simon Finch, Nov. cat. 7, #115, regular issue of 1826 on Whatman
			paper, original wrappers bound in, pl. 3 illus. (£25,000)—the Thomas
			Gaisford/S. H. Pease copy, previously sold SL, 23 April 1890, #194
			(Galway, £19.10s.), and CL, 7 Dec. 1988, #122 (Finch, £15,400). In
			comparison to Blake’s other late intaglio masterpiece, the Dante
			engravings, the Job illustrations are considerably undervalued.</p>
			<p>“John Caspar Lavater,” 3rd st. CL, 29 June, #11, with “Wilson Lowry”
			(Blake and Linnell after Linnell), 4th st., and “Romeo and Juliet” after
			Opie for Boydell’s Shakespeare ed. (not sold).</p>
			<p>Virgil wood
			engravings. CNY, 21 Feb., #1710, 10 cuts only, Linnell reprints bound in
			a modern album, heavily inked and printed, 4 cuts illus. ($3850).
			Angew’s, July print cat., #30, all 17 cuts from the 1821 ed., 1st cut (a
			very fine impression) illus. ($10,500).</p>
			</div3>
			<div3>
			<head>
			<title>
			<hi rend="i">LETTERPRESS BOOKS WITH ENGRAVINGS BY &amp; AFTER
			BLAKE</hi>
			</title>
			</head>
			<p>Ariosto, <hi rend="i">Orlando
			Furioso.</hi> Robert Clark, Nov. 1988 cat. 14, #140, 1791 ed. (£75).
			Jeff Weber Books, Jan. cat. 2, #150, 1799 ed., 5 vols., some foxing
			($250). Jeffrey Stern, April cat. 7, #169, 1783 ed., 5 vols., fancy
			binding (£300). James Burmester, April cat. 9, #214, 1791 ed. (£60).
			Ximenes, Aug. cat. 85, #15, 1791 ed. ($250). Hartfield, Oct. cat. 37,
			#A-1, 1799 ed., “very tall” ($795).</p>
			<p>Blair, 
			<hi rend="i">Grave.</hi> Heritage Book Shop, Jan. cat. 173, #16, 1813
			quarto, contemporary morocco rebacked, pls. “lightly foxed” ($750).
			Robert Clark, Feb. cat. 15, #193, 1813 quarto, later reissue in blue
			blind-stamped cloth, ownership inscription dated Jan. 1864, foxed
			(£280). CNY, 21 Feb., #1709, 1808 quarto, rebound but original cover
			label preserved, top edge gilt, others uncut ($1320). Bertram Rota, May
			cat. 250, #25, 1808 quarto, lacking advert. for Stothard’s “Canterbury
			Pilgrims,” ownership signature of the sculptor Francis Chantrey
			(1781-1842), who purchased a set of Blake’s Job engravings and,
			according to Gilchrist, a copy of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
			Experience</hi> (£400). CNY, 17 May, #21, 1808 quarto ($1100). Ben
			Abraham Books, June cat. 10, #20, 1808 quarto, some foxing ($1500). BBA,
			8 June, #91, pls. loose in cloth portfolio as issued 1870, with a
			Rowlandson vol. (S. Heneage, £99). Ursus Books, Aug. cat. 134, #89, 1808
			quarto, fancy binding, engraved title page illus. ($2500). Rota, Sept.
			private offer, 1808 quarto (£350). Traylen, Sept. cat. 105, #762, 1808
			quarto (£475). Wm. Reese Co., Oct. cat. 79, #171, 1808 quarto, original
			boards rebacked, cover label, uncut, some foxing ($1400).</p>
			<p>Bryant,
			<hi rend="i">New System</hi>, 2nd ed., 1775-76. Bickersteth, Nov. cat.
			108, #12, 3 vols., “an exceptionally fine, clean, large-margined copy”
			(£385).</p>
			<p>Chaucer, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi>, in Bell’s
			British Poets, 1777-82. Kraus, June cat. <pb id="p24-229" n="229"/>
181,
			#13, complete set of Bell’s <hi rend="i">Poets</hi> in 109 vols. in 2
			fine leather boxes, no indication as to whether or not Blake’s pl. is
			present ($15,000).</p>
			<p>Cumberland, <hi rend="i">Outlines from the
			Antients</hi>, 1829. Quaritch, Sept. private offer, folio issue, from
			the library of Lord Clark of Saltwood ($450). The existence of a
			large-paper (36.6 × 26 cm. in this copy) folio issue has been previously
			noted only in Quaritch’s May 1988 cat. 1087, #25 (where I overlooked
			it). This copy is on paper, with an 1825 watermark, thicker than the
			stock used for the quarto issue.</p>
			<p>Darwin, <hi rend="i">Botanic
			Garden.</hi> Sims, Reed, March 1988 cat. 91, #221, 1791 ed. (£260).
			Walford, Sept. 1988 cat. H/153, #227, 1794-95 ed., with the “Tornado”
			pl. (£300). Marlborough, Jan. cat. 39, #22, 1st ed. of Pt. 1, 2nd of Pt.
			2, “with one extra plate” (but apparently not by Blake), worn, foxed
			(£350). Traylen, April cat. 104, #525, 1st ed. of Pt. 1, 3rd of Pt. 2,
			fancy binding (£420). BBA, 27 July, #265, 3rd ed., worn (Ginnan, £198);
			28 Sept., #370, 1st ed. of Pt. 1, 
			<figure n="versohenryV.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="307">
				<head>10. Blake.</head>
				<figDesc>“Henry V,” leaf 57 verso
			from the larger Blake-Varley sketchbook, 1819. Pencil heightened with
			black chalk on leaf 25.4 × 20.3 cm., inscribed “Henry the 5<hi
			rend="s">th</hi>” by Varley below the framing line. Photo courtesy of
			Christie’s London.</figDesc>
			</figure> 
			2nd of Pt. 2, foxed, trimmed,
			shabby (Kunkler, £104).</p>
			<p>Enfield, <hi rend="i">Speaker</hi>, 1797.
			SL, 13 July, #1097, “1793” ed. (but this turned out to be the 1797 ed.
			with the final st. of Blake’s pl.), with 8 unrelated works (Maggs,
			£88).</p>
			<p>Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Hesiod</hi>, 1817. H. D. Lyon, Sept.
			private offer, early printing with pl. 20 misnumbered “37” (£300). See
			also illus. 18-19 for Hesiod drawings.</p>
			<p>Flaxman, 
			<hi rend="i">Iliad</hi>, 1805. James Cummins, Dec. cat. 25, #20, with
			Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi>, 1805 ($225).</p>
			<p>Fuseli, 
			<hi rend="i">Lectures on Painting</hi>, 1801. Quaritch, May cat. 1105, #40,
			rebacked ($350).</p>
			<p>Gay, <hi rend="i">Fables</hi>, 1793. Edward
			Nudelman, Jan. cat. 13, #84, worn ($350); same copy?, Sept. cat. 14,
			#208, described as having “12 woodcut [sic!] engravings” by Blake (same
			price). Wm. Reese, May cat. 77, #82, contemporary calf, some foxing,
			“first printing” ($275). Argonaut Book Shop, May cat. 104, #420,
			contemporary calf, some foxing, “large and thick paper copy” with “all
			tissue guards,” good impressions ($425). Robert Clark, May cat. 16,
			#121, 2 vols. bound in 1, some foxing (£100). Phillip Pirages, June
			cat., #20, 1st ed. ($600). In Our Time, Aug. cat. 238, #40, 1st ed.
			($750). Shapiro, Sept. private offer, 1st ed. (£170). Hobbyhorse Books,
			Sept. cat. 14, #88, ed. not identified, some browning ($350). BBA, 28
			Sept., #372, foxed, some tears, trimmed (Baker, £104); 23 Nov., #277,
			cropped, rubbed (Tamura-Shoten, £132).</p>
			<p>Hartley, 
			<hi rend="i">Observations on Man</hi>, 1791. Thoemmes Books, March cat. 35,
			#55, modern binding (£475).</p>
			<p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Ballads</hi>,
			1805. CNY, 21 Feb., #1708, with comma after Blake on title page, second
			st. of pls. 1-3, fancy binding rebacked ($1210); same copy, Ursus Books,
			Aug. cat. 134, #90 ($2250). A record auction price, and a record asking
			price from a dealer.</p>
			<p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Life of Cowper</hi>,
			1803-04. Blackwell’s, summer 1988 cat. “Edgar,” #10, 2nd ed. (£175).
			Shapiro, Sept. private offer, 1st ed. (£185). Heritage, Nov. cat. 176,
			#113, 1st ed. ($450).</p>
			<p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Life of Romney</hi>,
			1809. Rainsford, Dec. 1988 cat. A47/Pt. 2, #874 (£175).</p>
			<p>Hayley,
			<hi rend="i">Triumphs of Temper</hi>, 1803. Lawson, Dec. cat. 243, #26,
			small paper issue (£210).</p>
			<p>Hogarth, <hi rend="i">Works.</hi>
			Zisska, 3-5 May 1988 auction, #1189, “ca. 1835” (DM 1500). Swann, 2
			March, #131, Baldwin and Cradock ed., “c. 1835-37” ($1430); 19 Oct.,
			#119, Baldwin and Cradock ed., “c. 1835” ($2860).</p>
			<p>Hunter, 
			<hi rend="i">Historical Journal</hi>, 1793. Traylen, April cat. 104, #358,
			quarto (£3300). SL, 14 April, #521, quarto, slight staining, rebacked
			(Shapero, £770). Maggs, July cat. 1097, #411, quarto, new binding in old
			full leather (£2200).</p>
			<p>Josephus, <hi rend="i">Whole Genuine and
			Complete Works</hi>, c. 1787-88? BBA, 20 Oct., #134, worn (Heath,
			£134).</p>
			<p>Lavater, <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy.</hi> SL, 6
			Feb., #616, 1789-98 ed., 3 vols. in 5, spotted (Hannas, £715); #617,
			1810 ed., 3 vols. in 5, worn (Russell, £132). Charles Wood, March cat.
			67, #133, 1789-98 ed., 3 vols. in 5, with Luffman, 
			<hi rend="i">Physiognomical Sketches</hi>, c. 1802 ($750). BBA, 13 April,
			#439, 1789-98 ed., 3 vols. in 5, spotted, covers detached (Axe, £280).
			Hartung &amp; Karl auction, 27 April, #2276, 1810 ed., 3 vols. in 5
			(estimate DM 1000). Jeffrey Stern, April cat. 7, #185, 1792 issue, 3
			vols. in 5, fancy binding rebacked (£675). CL, 24 May, #127, 1789-98
			ed., 3 vols. in 5, light spotting, rebacked (Traylen, £198). Traylen,
			Sept. cat. 105, #806, 1792 ed., 3 vols. in 5, rebacked (£350).</p>
			<p>Malkin, <hi rend="i">Father’s Memoirs Of His Child</hi>, 1806.
			Chelsea Rare Books, Sept. private offer, copy once owned by Edward
			Fitzgerald (poet and translator, <pb id="p24-230" n="230"/>
1809-83), a
			student of Malkin’s (£600).</p>
			<p>Rees, <hi rend="i">Cyclopaedia</hi>,
			1820. Sotheran’s, summer 1988 cat. 1003, #112, “46” (i.e., 45?) vols.,
			rebacked, some joints split (£2400). BBA, 26 Oct., #141, 26 vols. of
			text only, vol. 1 of pls. only, worn (B. Bailey, £44).</p>
			<p>Ritson,
			<hi rend="i">Select Collection of English Songs</hi>, 1783. Pickering
			&amp; Chatto, Jan. cat., #44, 3 vols., lacking a fly-title in vol. 2
			($750); Feb. cat. 101, #11, same copy and price. James Burmester, April
			cat. 9, #386, 3 vols. bound in 2 (£250).</p>
			<p>Salzmann, 
			<hi rend="i">Elements of Morality</hi>, 1792. Robert Clark, Feb. cat. 15,
			#110, lacking a few text pages at the end but with all pls. (£85). I
			have seen several copies with the last few pages missing, probably
			excised by Victorian adults unwilling to allow children in their charge
			to read about the death of the mother in Salzmann’s story.</p>
			<figure n="rowena.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="325">
				<head>11. Blake.</head>
				<figDesc>“Rowena,” the Saxon beauty for whom Vortigern betrayed the
			British cause, according to Geoffrey of Monmouth’s <hi rend="i">Historia
			Britonum.</hi> Leaf 50 verso from the larger Blake-Varley Sketchbook,
			1819. Pencil on leaf 25.4 × 20.3 cm., inscribed lower right by Varley,
			“Rowenna.” Another version of the portrait is on leaf 49 verso. Photo
			courtesy of Christie’s London.</figDesc>
			</figure>
			<p>Scott, <hi rend="i">Poetical Works</hi>, 1782. Brick Row Book Shop, April cat. 17,
			#11, hinges cracked ($250).</p>
			<p>Shakespeare, <hi rend="i">Dramatic
			Works</hi>, 9 vols., 1802. Walford, Feb. 1988 cat. A/326, #198, with
			Blake’s pl. (£500). Blackwell’s, March 1988 cat. A90, perhaps the copy
			earlier in their stock lacking Blake’s pl. (£2700). Pickering &amp;
			Chatto, April cat. 102, #44, lacking 3 pls. (including Blake’s), fancy
			binding ($10,000). Clearly, this work increases in value as the number
			of pls. diminishes.</p>
			<p>Stedman, <hi rend="i">Narrative</hi>, 1813.
			Walford, May 1988 cat. H/152, #321, pls. hand colored (£975); same copy
			and price, Aug. 1988 cat. A/328, #83.</p>
			<p>Stuart and Revett, 
			<hi rend="i">Antiquities of Athens.</hi> Charles Wood, June cat. 68, #407, 5
			vols., 1762-1830, “light blind-stamp in blank margin of each plate”
			($7500). Marlborough, Sept. cat. 135, #33, 4 vols., 1762-1816,
			internally very clean (£4000).</p>
			<p>Varley, <hi rend="i">Treatise on
			Zodiacal Physiognomy</hi>, 1828. Quaritch, May cat. 1104, #12, stitched
			without binding, uncut, washed, some margins repaired, top half of pl. 3
			(“Ghost of a Flea”) illus. ($4500).</p>
			<p>Young, <hi rend="i">Night
			Thoughts</hi>, 1797, uncolored. CNY, 21 Feb., #1707, top edge gilt,
			others uncut, few stains, lacking the explanation leaf, p. 24 illus.
			($4950). Traylen, April cat. 104, #591, with the explanation leaf, edges
			trimmed and gilt (with some loss of imprints and design margins?), fancy
			binding (£4500). CNY, 17 May, #20, top edge gilt, others uncut, some
			foxing, p. 55 with repaired tear, with the explanation leaf ($5280 on an
			estimate of $1500-2000); same copy, Bromer Booksellers, July cat. 55,
			#8, p. 80 illus. ($8500). Chelsea Rare Books, Sept. private offer,
			lacking the explanation leaf, rare 1st published st. of the title page
			to Night the First (£2000).</p>
			<p>Young, <hi rend="i">Night
			Thoughts</hi>, 1797, colored. SL, 1 June, #208, lacking the explanation
			<figure n="charlemagne.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="311">
				<head>12. Blake.</head>
				<figDesc>“Charlemagne” (so inscribed at the top by Varley),
			leaf 45 verso from the larger Blake-Varley sketchbook, 1819. Pencil
			heightened with black chalk on leaf 25.4 × 20.3 cm. Photo courtesy of
			Christie’s London.</figDesc>
			</figure> 
			leaf, portrait of Blake from
			Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> (1808) bound as a frontispiece, some
			short tears at foot of 8 leaves, “contemporary marbled calf, gilt
			borders, worn, rebacked, covers loose, uncut,” fly-title to Night the
			Third illus. color on front cover of cat., fly-title to Night the Fourth
			illus. (£33,000 to Gall of Victoria for The National Gallery of
			Victoria, Melbourne). Provenance: inscribed in the nineteenth century by
			Benjamin(?) Hines to William à Beckett (appointed solicitor general of
			New South Wales 1841, returned to England 1863). Pencil notes suggest
			that the vol. was acquired in 1904 from the Felton collection; bookplate
			of Robert Carl and Marion Oak Sticht date 1909. The book was acquired by
			the National Gallery of Victoria with the assistance of the Felton
			Bequest. For a complete(!) color reproduction of the pls., see Martin
			Butlin and Ted Gott, <hi rend="i">William Blake in the Collection of the
			National Gallery of Victoria</hi> (Melbourne: National Gallery of
			Victoria, 1989). The title page to Night the Second is in the rare 1st
			published st.</p>
			</div3>
			<pb id="p24-231" n="231"/>
			<div3>
			<head>
			<title>
			<hi rend="i">INTERESTING BLAKEANA</hi>
			</title>
			</head>
			<p>Chaucer, <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, ed. Speght, 1687. Heritage Book
			Shop, Nov. private offer, rebacked ($1250). For a cogent argument that
			this was the ed. used by Blake, see A. S. Gourlay, “What Was Blake’s
			Chaucer?” <hi rend="i">Studies in Bibliography</hi> 42 (1989):
			272-83.</p>
			<p>Chapman, trans., <hi rend="i">Iliads</hi>, c. 1611, and
			<hi rend="i">Odysses</hi>, c. 1614, of Homer. CL, 24 May, #163 (Maggs
			for Essick, £1430). See illus. 17 and its caption for an explanation of
			why this book is listed here.</p>
			<p>Gilchrist, <hi rend="i">Life of
			Blake</hi>, 2 vols., 1880. Pickering and Chatto, Nov. cat. 678, #164,
			with light blue-green dust wrappers bearing Frederic Shields’s
			adaptation of Robert Blake’s design also gilt stamped on the cloth
			covers ($850). This is the first notice I can recall indicating that the
			1880 Gilchrist was issued with pictorial dust wrappers. For the Shields
			design, see <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 8 (summer-fall 1974):
			front and back covers.</p>
			<p>Hayley, auction cat. of his library,
			Evans, 13 Feb. 1821 and 12 following days. BBA, 2 Feb., #389 (Burmester,
			£374 on an estimate of £50-75); same copy, Ximenes, Aug. cat. 85, #21
			($1250); acquired Sept. by J. La Belle. Apparently the only known copy
			fully annotated with prices and purchasers.</p>
			<p>Keynes, autograph
			notebook, 2 vols., 152 pp., c. 1945-50, including comments on Blake’s
			illuminated books and the founding of the Blake Trust. Jeremy Norman,
			May cat. 19, #273, 1 p. illus. ($1250). This Norman cat. of materials
			from the collection of K. Garth Huston offered a considerable amount of
			Keynesiana, including a bronze head of Sir Geoffrey by Nigel Booham
			(#307, illus., with a smaller bronze bust, $14,500).</p>
			<p>Yeats,
			autograph manuscript journal, 11 July 1898-31 March 1902, including a
			brief entry describing a dream about a book that “contained lost poems
			by Blake” (from the journal, as quoted in the auction catalogue). CNY,
			10 Nov., #201, 2 pp. illus. (not sold).</p>
			<figure n="warwick.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="291">
				<head>13. Blake.</head>
				<figDesc>“The Earl of Warwick,” leaf 38 verso from the larger
			Blake-Varley sketchbook, 1819. Pencil on leaf 25.4 × 20.3 cm. Inscribed
			lower right by Varley, “The Great Earl of Warwick / Brother to Ed<hi
			rend="s">wd</hi>. the 4<hi rend="s">th</hi> / Drawn by W<hi
			rend="s">m</hi> Blake.” Photo courtesy of Christie’s London.</figDesc>
			</figure>
			</div3>
			<div3>
			<head>
			<title>
			<hi rend="i">BLAKE’S CIRCLE
			&amp; FOLLOWERS</hi>
			</title>
			</head>
			<p><hi rend="i">Works are listed
			under artists’ names in the following order: untitled paintings and
			drawings sold in groups, single paintings and drawings, letters and
			manuscripts, separate plates, books by (or with plates by or after) the
			artist.</hi></p>
			<div4>
			<head>
			<title>
			<hi rend="b">BARRY, JAMES</hi>
			</title>
			</head>
			<p>“King Lear,” lithograph, 1803. Garton European
			Prints, Sept. cat., #6, with the aquatint border, illus. (£7500).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">A Letter to the Dilettanti Society</hi>, 1799. Sanders,
			Feb. cat. 114, #25, extra-illus. with 3 pls., rebacked (£150).</p>
			</div4>
			<div4>
			<head>
			<title>
			<hi rend="b">BASIRE, JAMES</hi>
			</title>
			</head>
			<p><hi rend="i">Archaeologia.</hi> BBA, 26 Oct., #251, vols.
			1-107, 1770-1982, a complete run, worn (Princeton Rare Books,
			£1540).</p>
			</div4>
			<div4>
			<head>
			<title>
			<hi rend="b">CALVERT,
			EDWARD</hi>
			</title>
			</head>
			<p>“The Brook,” wood engraving. Weston
			Gallery, April cat. 2, #127, from the <hi rend="i">Memoir</hi>, illus.
			($745).</p>
			<p>“Cyder Feast,” wood engraving. Weston Gallery, April cat.
			2, #126, from the <hi rend="i">Memoir</hi>, illus. ($1180).</p>
			<p>“The
			Ploughman,” wood engraving. Weston Gallery, April cat. 2, #125, from 
			<pb id="p24-232" n="232"/>
			<figure n="archbishop.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="317">
				<head>14. Blake.</head>
				<figDesc>An archbishop, possibly
			Thomas à Becket, leaf 30 verso from the larger Blake-Varley sketchbook,
			1819. Pencil heightened with black chalk on leaf 25.4 × 20.3 cm. Photo
			courtesy of Christie’s London.</figDesc>
			</figure> 
			the <hi rend="i">Memoir</hi>, illus. ($1180).</p>
			<p>“Return Home,” wood
			engraving. Weston Gallery, April cat. 2, #128, from the 
			<hi rend="i">Memoir</hi>, illus. ($745). SL, 20 April, #111, trimmed to
			image, from the <hi rend="i">Memoir</hi> (not sold).</p>
			</div4>
			<div4>
			<head>
			<title>
			<hi rend="b">CUMBERLAND, GEORGE</hi>
			</title>
			</head>
			<p>A large collection of his drawings and water colors, CL, 11 July,
			#22-48, 18 illus., 2 in color (£396-2200, several lots not sold). All
			are landscapes without Blakean qualities in design or execution.</p>
			</div4>
			<div4>
			<head>
			<title>
			<hi rend="b">FLAXMAN, JOHN</hi>
			</title>
			</head>
			<p>See also Flaxman under Letterpress Books, above.</p>
			<p><hi
			rend="i">Angels Gathered around a Book.</hi> Pen and gray wash over
			pencil, 32.5 × 40.5 cm. Acquired in recent years as a Flaxman drawing
			from a German collection by Heim Gallery and Christopher Powney; sold by
			Powney as a Flaxman to Colnaghi’s London; offered Feb. by Colnaghi’s New
			York as a Blake drawing ($50,000). Illus., attributed to Blake, and
			dated c. 1785 in Martin Butlin, “Six New Early Drawings by William Blake
			and a Reattribution,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 23 (1989): 107-12. I
			believe that this drawing is by Flaxman. It is too accomplished, in its
			sweet and delicate evocation of Renaissance face and figure types, to be
			by Blake. Detlef Dörrbecker has suggested that William Young Ottley
			might be the author of this or some of the other “Blake” drawings listed
			here under Flaxman.</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Cypress Trees on Monte
			Mario</hi>, attributed to Flaxman. Pen and ink, 17.5 × 10.8 cm. Agnew’s,
			Feb.-March cat. of water colors, #27 (£550).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Design
			for a Monument: A Seated Youth Clasping a Tablet.</hi> Pen and wash over
			pencil, 13.6 × 14.5 cm. Sold as a Flaxman, CL, 17 Nov. 1987, #2, with
			<hi rend="i">Three Children round a Fire</hi> (see below), also
			attributed to Flaxman (Christopher Powney, £220). Sold as a Flaxman in
			1988 by Powney to a British private collector. Illus., attributed to
			Blake, and dated c. 1785 in Martin Butlin, “Six New Early Drawings by
			William Blake and a Reattribution,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 23 (1989):
			107-12. This drawing seems to me altogether typical of Flaxman’s
			work.</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Hesiod</hi> designs, pl. 32, a drawing for.
			Acquired March by R. Essick from Christopher Powney. See illus. 18.</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Pleiades.</hi> CL, 11 July, #16 (Christopher Powney,
			£176). Acquired Sept. from Powney by R. Essick, who gave it to J. La
			Belle in Nov. See illus. 19.</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Roman Family.</hi> Pen
			and gray ink, gray wash, 23.5 × 14.8 cm. Acquired March by R. Essick
			from Christopher Powney.</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Study for a Monument to a
			Judge.</hi> Pencil, pen and gray ink, gray wash, 8 ½ × 5 ¾ in. CL, 11
			July, #97 (£418).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Study of a Man Seated, Embracing
			Children</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Study of a Woman Holding a Baby.</hi>
			Pencil, pen and gray ink, wash, 7 ⅜ × 5 ⅞ in. and 6 ¼ × 3 ⅛ in. CL, 11
			July, #17 (£550).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Three Children round a Fire.</hi>
			Ink and gray wash over pencil, 14.4 × 19.1 cm. From the collection of
			Maria Denman, Flaxman’s sister-in-law, acquired 1987 by Christopher
			Powney (see <hi rend="i">Design for a Monument</hi>, above) and sold by
			him to Agnew’s as a Flaxman drawing. Offered Agnew’s, Feb.-March cat. of
			water colors, #22, attributed to Blake, illus. (£16,000). Acquired Feb.
			by an English lord. Illus., and again attributed to Blake and dated c.
			1785, in Martin Butlin, “Six New Early Drawings by William Blake and a
			Reattribution,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 23 (1989): 107-12. Nothing in
			this loose drawing suggests Blake’s hand to me. The face of the central
			boy is particularly uncharacteristic. I believe that this drawing is
			probably, but not certainly, by Flaxman.</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Wilson
			Lowry.</hi> Portrait sketch, pencil, 6 ½ × 5 ¾ in. Christopher Powney,
			Oct. private offer ($1300).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Aeschylus</hi>
			illustrations, 1795. Book Press, Dec. cat. 48, #240, original wrappers
			($300).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Anatomical Studies</hi>, 1833. Walford, Dec.
			1988 cat. A/330, #189 (£110). Swann, 2 Feb., #112, foxed, worn ($110).
			Michael Phelps, Feb. cat. 33, #68, original cloth worn (£195).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Dante</hi> illustrations. Zisska, 3-5 May 1988 auction,
			#1660, Rome 1802 ed. (DM 460). Robert Clark, Feb. cat. 15, #224, London
			1807 ed., some browning (£90).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Hesiod</hi>
			illustrations. Erasmushaus, April cat. 858, #81, with the 
			<hi rend="i">Aeschylus</hi> designs, both pub. del Vecchio, n.d. (SwF
			650).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> illustrations, Rome, 1793.
			Erasmushaus, April cat. 858, #80 (SwF 380).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Lectures
			on Sculpture.</hi> Dawson, Feb. cat. 28, #489, 1838 ed., contemporary
			calf (£140); same copy and price, Oct. cat. 29, #152. Swann, 2 Feb.,
			#114, 1829 ed., foxed ($77). Robert Clark, May cat. 16, #203, 1838 ed.,
			original cloth (£60). BBA, 8 June, #333, 1829 ed., pls. spotted (Galton,
			£22). Philadelphia Rare Books, Nov. cat. 5, #90, 1829 ed., modern
			binding, lacking 
<pb id="p24-233" n="233"/>
frontispiece ($200—rather
			dear for an incomplete copy).</p>
			<p>Milton, <hi rend="i">Latin and
			Italian Poems.</hi> Blackwell’s, summer 1988 cat. “Edgar,” #31, 1808 ed.
			(£135). BBA, 23 Nov., #181, 1801 ed., with 3 unrelated works (Axe,
			£38).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi> illustrations. Swann, Feb. 2,
			#113, with the <hi rend="i">Aeschylus</hi> illustrations, both with
			Italian text, n.d. ($77).</p>
			</div4>
			<div4>
			<head>
			<title>	
			<hi rend="b">FUSELI, HENRY</hi>
			</title>
			</head>
			<p><hi rend="i">Agave, Ino
			and Autonoe Emerge from their Dionysian Rapture and Are Informed</hi>
			<figure n="but473.1.1.wc" id="but473.1.wc.01" work-copy="biblicalwc" rend="db" width="958" height="899">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
				<head>15. Blake.</head>
				<figDesc><hi rend="i">Infant Jesus Saying His
			Prayers.</hi> Water color over pencil, 31.6 × 34 cm., signed with
			Blake’s monogram lower right, c. 1805.<gap type="emend"/></figDesc>
			</figure>
			<hi rend="i">of the Slaughter of Pentheus.</hi> Pen, pencil,
			and gray washes, inscribed “Roma [17]74. May,” 26 × 22 cm. SL, 13 July,
			#30, illus. color (£8250). Advertised by Cummings Fine Arts, 
			<hi rend="i">Burlington Magazine</hi> (Nov. 1989): xxxii, illus. (not
			priced).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Birth of Sin.</hi> Oil, 142 × 117.2 cm. A
			recently rediscovered painting from Fuseli’s Milton Gallery of 1799. CL,
			14 April, #90, illus. color (not sold on a brave estimate of
			£100,000-120,000).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Prince Arthur’s Vision</hi>,
			drawing after Fuseli by Peltro William Tomkins in preparation for his
			engraving. Pencil with red chalk, 43.5 × 34.5 cm. SL, 13 July, #26 (not
			sold).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Study of a Nude Male.</hi> Pen and ink, 19 ×
			13 cm., c. 1795. SL, 9 March, #32, illus. (not sold; estimate
			£6000-8000).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Study of Mrs. Fuseli Wearing an
			Elaborate Hat.</hi> Pen, pencil, gray wash, 21.5 × 13.5 cm. SL, 13 July,
			#85, illus. (£7700).</p>
			<p>A collection of c. 100 autograph letters by
			artists, including Fuseli, Flaxman, Linnell, Richmond, Boydell about his
			Shakespeare Gallery, and Opie on Barry’s lectures. SL, 20 July, #454
			(Rye, £3410). <pb id="p24-234" n="234"/>
Receipt signed, 20 April 1805,
			part payment for his illustrations to Sotheby’s 
			<hi rend="i">Oberon</hi>, pub. by Cadell and Davies, 1805. BBA, 22 June,
			#300 (Weinglass, £187).</p>
			<p>20 engravings after Fuseli, C. &amp; J.
			Goodfriend, Aug. private offer. Prices ranged from $3000 for the pair of
			<hi rend="i">Midsummer Night’s Dream</hi> illustrations from Boydell’s
			Shakespeare Gallery to $75 for book illustrations. The group included a
			fine impression of J. R. Smith’s mezzotint of “Lear and Cordelia” ($950)
			and several separate pls. engraved by Moses Haughton: “Nursery of
			Shakespeare” ($400), “Dismission of Adam and Eve from Paradise” ($850),
			“Adam Resolved to Share the Fate of Eve” ($850), and “Sin Pursued by
			Death,” marginal tear and stains ($500).</p>
			<p>“O Evening thou Bringest
			All,” lithograph, 1802. Garton European Prints, Sept. cat., #5, 1st st.
			with the aquatint border, illus. (£12,500—a record asking price).</p>
			<p>“Sleeping Woman with a Cupid,” drypoint, c. 1780-90. Christopher
			Mendez, Sept. private offer, printed in brown, scuffed and laid down,
			with the collection stamp of Sir Thomas Lawrence (£500).</p>
			<p>Boothby,
			<hi rend="i">Sorrows</hi>, 1796. Swann, 25 May, #60 ($154).</p>
			<p>Boydell, <hi rend="i">Collection of Prints . . . Illustrating . . .
			Shakspeare</hi>, 1803. CL, 16 May, #128, 2 Fuseli pls. only,
			illustrating <hi rend="i">Midsummer Night’s Dream</hi>, marginal repairs
			(£308); #129, 4 Fuseli pls. only (<hi rend="i">Macbeth, King Lear, Henry
			V, Tempest</hi>), minor repairs (£418).</p>
			<p>Cowper, 
			<hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, 1808. Phillip Pirages, June cat. 15, #442, fancy
			binding ($300).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Lectures on Painting.</hi> Quaritch,
			May cat. 1105, #39, second series, 1830 ($200); #41, 1820 ed.
			($200).</p>
			<p>Gray, <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, 1801. Simon Finch, March
			cat. 5, #118, uncut in original boards, soiled (£45).</p>
			<p>Homer, 
			<hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> and <hi rend="i">Odyssey.</hi> Claude Cox, Jan. cat.
			70, #20, <hi rend="i">Iliad</hi> only, 1813, 3 vols., some pls. browned,
			fancy binding (£35). Ursus Books, Nov. cat., #55, 
			<hi rend="i">Iliad</hi>, 1813, with <hi rend="i">Odyssey</hi>, a mixed set
			of the 1806 small paper issue and 1813, all with the pls. in the 2nd
			st., 12 vols., contemporary red morocco ($1500).</p>
			<p>Milton, 
			<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, 2 vols., 1802. W. &amp; V. Dailey, Nov.
			private offer, damaged, spines broken and covered with decayed
			cellotape, 2 covers loose, cellotape repairs of a few pages, pls. badly
			foxed and ink-stained in the margins, otherwise fine ($50).</p>
			<p>Pope,
			<hi rend="i">Rape of the Lock</hi>, 1801. James Burmester, April cat. 9,
			#382, lacking half-title (£38).</p>
			<p>Winkelmann, 
			<hi rend="i">Reflections</hi>, trans. Fuseli, 1765. Quaritch, May cat. 1105,
			#115 ($650). Marlborough, July cat. 41, #218, worn, some foxing
			(£175).</p>
			<p>Young, <hi rend="i">Catalogue of the Celebrated
			Collection of. . .Angerstein</hi>, 1829. BBA, 11 May, #315, with Young,
			<hi rend="i">Catalogue of the Pictures. . .in the Possession of. .
			.Leicester</hi>, 1825, and 3 unrelated vols. (Barker, £88).</p>
				<figure n="lt2july1826.1.1.LT.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="228" height="283">
				<head>16. Blake.</head>
				<figDesc>Letter to John Linnell, postmarked 2 July 1826. Photo courtesy of Christie’s New
York.</figDesc>
			</figure>
			</div4>
			<div4>
			<head>
			<title>
			<hi rend="b">LINNELL, JOHN</hi>
			</title>
			</head>
			<p>See illus. 17.</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Changing Pastures.</hi>
			Water color, 12.5 × 19 cm., signed. SL, 9 March, #112, illus.
			(£1045).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Country Road.</hi> Oil, 70 × 99 cm., signed
			and dated 1864. CL, 14 April, #50, illus. color (not sold on an
			optimistic estimate of £20,000-25,000).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">David and
			the Lion.</hi> Oil, 139.7 × 218.4 cm., signed and dated 1850. CL, 17
			Nov., #126, illus. color (not sold; estimate £6000-8000).</p>
			<p><hi
			rend="i">Figures by a River Bank.</hi> Pen and brown ink, 16.5 × 20.5
			cm., initialed. SL, 25 Jan., #107, illus. (£550).</p>
			<p><hi
			rend="i">Portrait of Frederick Tatham.</hi> Pencil, size not recorded.
			Acquired 1987 by the Fitzwilliam Museum, gift of R. M. M. Pryor. Illus.
			in <hi rend="i">Annual Report of the Syndicate and Friends of the
			Fitzwilliam</hi> (1987), pl. 7.</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Portrait of John
			Davies Gilbert.</hi> Oil, 44.5 × 35.5 cm., signed and dated 1834. SL, 15
			Feb., #297, illus. (£2200).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Shepherd’s Love
			Song.</hi> Oil, 76 × 102 cm., signed and dated 1827. SL, 22 March, #160,
			illus. (£2750).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Sketch of Sunset.</hi> Water color,
			6 ¼ × 9 ¼ in., signed. Martyn Gregory, Oct. cat. 54, #80, illus.
			(£1600).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Study of Sky and Clouds.</hi> Water color,
			9 × 11 ¼ in., signed and dated “Augt 29/[18]63.” Martyn Gregory, Oct.
			cat. 54, #79, illus. (£1450).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Wooded Landscape with
			Windmill.</hi> Oil, 17.6 × 28.5 cm. CL, 26 May, #54 (£1100).</p>
			<p>“Sheep at Noon,” etching. SL, 27 June, #231, on thin Japan, illus.
			(not sold on an estimate of £800-1200).</p>
			</div4>
			<div4>
			<head>
			<title>
			<hi rend="b">MORTIMER, JOHN HAMILTON</hi>
			</title>
			</head>
			<p><hi rend="i">Group Portrait of Sargeant-at-Arms Bonfoy, His Son, and
			J. Clemenston.</hi> Oil, 101.6 × 127 cm. CL, 17 Nov., #17, 
			<pb id="p24-235" n="235"/>
illus. color (£55,000—a record for a work by
			Mortimer?).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Studies of Architectural
			Decorations.</hi> Pencil, pen, gray ink and gray wash, sheet 6 ½ × 4 ⅜
			in. CL, 11 July, #18, illus. (£1100).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Study for the
			Presentation of the Magna Carta to King John.</hi> Pen and ink, gray
			washes, 20.5 × 26 cm. SL, 13 July, #21 (not sold).</p>
			<p><hi
			rend="i">Etchings Dedicated to Reynolds</hi>, 1778-80. Weston Gallery,
			April cat. 2, #30, “Musical Monster,” #31, “Enraged Monster,” #32,
			“Revengeful Monster,” #33, “Sleeping Monster,” all 1816 printings, all
			illus. ($220 each).</p>
			<p>Shakespeare Characters, etchings. Weston
			Gallery, April cat. 2, #27, 1st (1775) series of 6 pls., 1816 printing,
			all illus. ($1750); #28, “Cassandra,” and #29, “Shylock,” from the 2nd
			(1776) series, both illus. ($265 each).</p>
			<p>Camoens, 
			<hi rend="i">Luciad</hi>, 1778 (frontispiece by Mortimer). Christopher
			Mendez, Sept. private offer (£50).</p>
			</div4>
			<div4>
			<head>
			<title>	
			<hi rend="b">PALMER, SAMUEL</hi>
			</title>
			</head>
			<p><hi rend="i">The
			Brothers, Guided by the Attendant Spirit, Discover the Palace and Bowers
			of Comus.</hi> Water color, 53 × 75 cm., exhibited 1856. Leslie Hindman
			auction, Chicago, 14 Oct., #10, from the William J. Stoecker collection,
			illus. color (Donald Heald, $170,000). Previously sold SL, 19 Nov. 1987,
			#144 (£55,000).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Florence and the Val d’Arno from the
			Cypress Grove of San Miniato.</hi> Water color, 12 ⅝ × 21 ⅜ in., signed.
			CL, 14 Nov., #150, illus. color (not sold on an estimate of
			£25,000-35,000). A previously untraced work first exhibited in 1845.</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Landscape with Sheep in Kent.</hi> Oil, 19.2 × 41.6 cm.
			CL, 17 Nov., #24, illus. color (£77,000).</p>
			<p>“Bellman,” etching. CL,
			12 April, #357, 7th st., illus. (£1540).</p>
			<p>“Cypress Grove,”
			etching. Weston Gallery, April cat. 2, #122, final st., illus.
			($315).</p>
			<figure n="chapman.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="319">
			<head>17. John
			Linnell.</head>
			<figDesc>Portrait of George Chapman based on the
			engraving published in <hi rend="i">The Whole Works of Homer</hi>,
			trans. Chapman, c. 1616. Pen and gray ink on sheet 17 × 13.3 cm. pasted
			to the inside front cover of Chapman’s translation of the 
			<hi rend="i">Iliads</hi>, c. 1611, bound with his <hi rend="i">Odysses</hi>,
			c. 1614. Above the drawing, written on the gray endpaper of the volume,
			is a presentation inscription in pencil: “Given to John Linnell Jun<hi
			rend="s">r</hi> / September 1840 / by me [possibly “Mr”] John Linnell.”
			The inscription above Linnell’s—“(This drawing of Chapman’s head
			was)”—added by a later hand. Linnell purchased Blake’s copy of Chapman’s
			Homer from Mrs. Blake in 1829. Might this be the same copy? An article
			addressing this question appears in <hi rend="i">English Language
			Notes</hi> 27 (1990): 27-30. Essick collection.</figDesc>
			</figure>
			<p>“Early Ploughman,” etching. Weston Gallery, April cat. 2, #121, 5th
			st., illus. ($1050). CL, 12 April, #356, 4th st., with 3 pls. by other
			artists (£275).</p>
			<p>“Herdsman’s Cottage,” etching. Weston Gallery,
			April cat. 2, #118, 2nd st., illus. ($875).</p>
			<p>“Moeris and Galatea,”
			etching. Weston Gallery, April cat. 2, #124, final st., illus.
			($220).</p>
			<p>“Opening the Fold,” etching. SL, 27 June, #249, between
			4th and 5th st., pencil signature, illus. (£1210).</p>
			<pb id="p24-236"
			n="236"/>
			<p>“Rising Moon,” etching. Weston Gallery, April cat. 2, #120,
			7th st., illus. ($1485).</p>
			<p>“Sepulchre,” etching. Weston Gallery,
			April cat. 2, #123, final st., illus. ($200).</p>
			<p>“Skylark,” etching.
			Weston Gallery, April cat. 2, #117, 7th st., illus. ($1750).</p>
			<p>“Sleeping Shepherd,” etching. Garton &amp; Co., April cat. 46, #24,
			4th st., good impression, illus. (£1100). Weston Gallery, April cat. 2,
			#119, 4th st., illus. ($1925).</p>
			<p>Dickens, <hi rend="i">Pictures
			from Italy</hi>, 1846. Traylen, Sept. cat. 105, #785, original cloth
			(£120).</p>
			<p>Hamerton, <hi rend="i">Etching &amp; Etchers</hi>, 1868.
			Swann, 14 Sept. #142, lacking 3 pls., but apparently with Palmer’s
			etching, “Early Ploughman,” 4th st. ($468).</p>
			<p>Milton, 
			<hi rend="i">Shorter Poems</hi>, 1889. Maggs, Jan. cat. 1091, #561, small
			paper, original cloth, pls. foxed in margins (£200). Phillip Pirages,
			June cat. 15, #724, small paper, original cloth ($300); same copy and
			price, Nov. cat. 16, #368.</p>
			<p>Virgil, <hi rend="i">Eclogues</hi>,
			trans. Palmer. Chaucer Head Books, June cat. 10, #526, 1884 ed.,
			“contemporary—probably publisher’s presentation—vellum” (£550). Phillip
			Pirages, June cat. 15, #725, 1883 small paper ed., original cloth, foxed
			($1400).</p>
			</div4>
			<div4>
			<head>
			<title><hi rend="b">ROMNEY,
			GEORGE</hi> (excluding most portrait paintings)</title>
			</head>
			<p><hi
			rend="i">Anger, Envy and Fear</hi> personified. Pen and brown ink, 7 ½ ×
			11 in. CL, 14 Nov., #61, illus. (£550).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Portrait of
			Emma Hamilton as Sensibility.</hi> Oil, 150 × 121.5 cm., painted c. 1786
			and acquired by William Hayley (see his <hi rend="i">Life of Romney</hi>
			[1809] 120-21). SL, 8 March, #50, illus. color (£30,800).</p>
			<p><hi
			rend="i">Studies for Sisters Contemplating on Mortality.</hi> 6
			drawings, pencil and/or pen and brown ink, 6 × 8 ⅛ in. and smaller. CL,
			11 July, #11 (not sold).</p>
			<figure n="jupiter.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="278">
			<head>18. John Flaxman.</head>
			<figDesc>Variant design for
			Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Hesiod</hi> illustrations, pl. 32, “Infant
			Jupiter” (his mother, Rhea, giving him to her mother, Gaea, to hide him
			from Saturn). Pencil, pen and ink, gray wash, 9.5 × 11.8 cm., on laid
			paper. Sold in lot 376 from the collection of Maria Denman, Flaxman’s
			sister-in-law, Christie’s, 10 April 1862. Since Blake engraved the 
			<hi rend="i">Hesiod</hi> illustrations in line and stippled line, there
			would have been no reason for Flaxman to add washes to preliminary
			drawings for the series. Apparently this example, as well as three other
			<hi rend="i">Hesiod</hi> drawings with washes, was produced with the
			expectation of publication in some medium capable of reproducing
			continuous tones, such as aquatint, used for Flaxman’s <hi rend="i">Acts
			of Mercy</hi>, 1831. Essick collection.</figDesc>
			</figure>
			<p><hi
			rend="i">Studies for Tancred and Erminia.</hi> 6 pen and brown ink
			drawings, 7 ¾ × 6 ¼ in. CL, 11 July, #9 (£220).</p>
			<p><hi
			rend="i">Woman Kneeling at a Fountain, a Child Standing Beside Her.</hi>
			Pencil, pen and ink, brown wash 12 ⅝ × 9 ⅞ in. CL, 14 Nov., #60, illus.
			(£3850).</p>
			</div4>
			<div4>
			<head>
			<title>
			<hi rend="b">SHERMAN,
			WELBY</hi>
			</title>
			</head>
			<p>“Shepherd,” engraving after Palmer, 1828.
			CL, 12 April, #395, on laid India, slightly foxed, surface dirt, but
			only the 4th known impression, illus. (£2860 on an estimate of
			£800-1200). Same impression, Garton European Prints, Sept. cat., #9,
			illus. (“Sold”).</p>
			</div4>
			<div4>
			<head>
			<title>	
			<hi rend="b">STOTHARD, THOMAS</hi>
			</title>
			</head>
			<p><hi rend="i">Alfred
			Disguised as a Harper</hi> and 11 other drawings, including studies for
			<hi rend="i">Pilgrim’s Progress.</hi> Pencil or pen and ink, 4 with
			wash, 7 ¼ × 9 ⅞ in. and smaller. CL, 11 July, #15 (£286).</p>
			<p>“The
			Lost Apple,” lithograph, 1803. Garton European Prints, Sept. cat., #2,
			2nd st.?, with aquatint border, illus. (£2000).</p>
			<p>Aesop, 
			<hi rend="i">Fables</hi>, 1793. Sotheran’s, summer 1988 cat. 1003, #2, 2
			vols. (£425).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Bijou</hi>, 1828. Claude Cox, Nov.
			cat. 75, #182a, original boards, rubbed (£30); #182b, another copy,
			lacking 1 (non-Stothard) pl. (£15).</p>
			<pb id="p24-237" n="237"/>
			<p>Bray, <hi rend="i">Life of Stothard</hi>, 1851, extra-illus. copies
			only. SL, 13 July, #845, with 97 added pls., 2 vols. (Montague,
			£198).</p>
			<p>Byron, <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, 2 vols., 1815. Simon
			Finch, May cat. 6, #83, 10 (of 12) pls., fancy binding illus.
			(£475).</p>
			<p>Catullus, <hi rend="i">Tibullus et Propertius</hi>, 1801.
			Sanders, Jan. 1988 cat. 113, #467 (£25).</p>
			<p>Cervantes, 
			<hi rend="i">Don Quixote</hi>, 1801. Claude Cox, Jan. cat. 70, #68, 4 vols.,
			fancy binding (£120).</p>
			<p>Cowper, <hi rend="i">Poems</hi>, 1800.
			Deighton, Bell, Sept. private offer, large paper, contemporary calf
			(£175).</p>
			<p>Defoe, <hi rend="i">Robinson Crusoe</hi>, 1790. Heritage
			Book Shop, Jan. cat. 173, #33, the 
			<figure n="pleiades.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="350" height="350">
	<head>19. John Flaxman.</head>
	<figDesc><hi rend="i">The
			Pleiades</hi>, a preliminary drawing for the <hi rend="i">Hesiod</hi>
			illustrations, pl. 18. Pencil, pen and gray ink, 14.4 × 17.4 cm. on a
			wove sheet with an 1809 watermark. Probably in lot 13 of the Denman sale
			(see illus. 18). The drawing varies slightly from the published
			engraving in the positions of the women’s heads at the top. Collection
			of Jenijoy La Belle.</figDesc>
</figure> 14 pls. of 1790 inserted in a
			1785 ed. ($450).</p>
			<p>Dryden, <hi rend="i">Fables</hi>, 1806. W. &amp;
			V. Dailey, Oct. private offer ($75).</p>
			<p>Fenelon, 
			<hi rend="i">Adventures of Telemachus</hi>, 1795. Ann Creed Books, Feb. cat.
			1, #319, 2 vols., rubbed, some foxing (£125). Vanbrugh Books, Sept.
			private offer, clean copy (£75).</p>
			<p>Gessner, 
			<hi rend="i">Works</hi>, 1802. Jarndyce, April cat. 62, #84, 3 vols.
			(£48).</p>
			<p>Hayley, <hi rend="i">Triumphs of Temper</hi>, 1788. James
			Burmester, April cat. 9, #365 (£38). Blackwell’s, Oct. English
			Literature cat., #30 (£30).</p>
			<p><hi rend="i">Literary Souvenir</hi>,
			1828. Rota, Sept. private offer (£30).</p>
			<p>Pinkerton, 
			<hi rend="i">Rimes</hi>, 1782. Ximenes, Aug. cat. 85, #325 ($150).</p>
			<p>Rogers, <hi rend="i">Italy.</hi> Phillip Pirages, June cat. 15, #449,
			1859 ed., fancy binding ($150). Quaritch, Sept. private offer, eds. of
			1824 (pt. 1) and 1828 (pt. 2) in 1 vol., presentation inscription by
			Rogers, with a letter by Rogers and a portrait sketch of him inserted
			($250)—the presence of 6 of Luke Clennell’s wood engravings after
			Stothard in these 2 eds. has not been previously noted. Sanders, Sept.
			private offer, 1830 ed., original boards, cloth folding case (£85).
			Bickersteth, Nov. cat. 108, #217, 1830 ed. (£35).</p>
			<p>Rogers, 
			<hi rend="i">Pleasures of Memory</hi>, 1801. Rota, Sept. private offer
			(£25).</p>
			<p>Rogers, <hi rend="i">Poems.</hi> BBA, 22 June, #388, 1834
			ed. (not sold); 13 July, #145, 1814 ed. (Whetman, £22). Sanders, Sept.
			private offers, 1827 ed. (with Clennell’s wood engravings), original
			boards (£8.50); 1834 ed., original boards, cloth folding case (£85).
			Claude Cox, Nov. cat. 75, #13, 1812 ed. (£28). Bickersteth, Nov. cat.
			108, #216, 1834 ed. (£35).</p>
			<p>Sterne, <hi rend="i">Works</hi>, 10
			vols., 1798. Walford, Nov. cat. H/159, #85 (£195).</p>
			<p>Tasso, 
			<hi rend="i">Jerusalem Delivered</hi>, 1797. Chelsea Rare Books, Sept.
			private offer, 2 vols., contemporary calf (£70).</p>
			<p>Thomson, 
			<hi rend="i">Seasons</hi>, 1793. Claude Cox, Jan. cat. 70, #34, fancy
			binding (£165).</p>
			<p>Walton, <hi rend="i">Complete Angler</hi>, 1836.
			Sanders, Jan. 1988 cat. 113, #477, 478 (£48 each). Claude Cox, March
			cat. 71, #138, 2 vols. large paper (£110).</p>
			<p>Walton, 
			<hi rend="i">Lives of Donne</hi>, et al, 1827. Sanders, Jan. 1988 cat. 113,
			#475 (£30); #476, hinge repaired (£18).</p>
			<p>Young, <hi rend="i">Night
			Thoughts</hi>, 1798. Claude Cox, Jan. cat. 70, #278, marginal browning
			(£40). Phillip Pirages, June cat. 15, #406, fancy binding ($450).
			Chelsea Rare Books, Sept. private offer (£95).</p>
			</div4>
			</div3>
			</div2>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
