<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>24.1.gourlay</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">The Franklin Library Reproduction of Songs U</title>
        <author n="Gourlay">Alexander S. Gourlay</author>
        <author n="Grant">John E. Grant</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1990</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1990</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">24.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Colin Pedley</name>
              <name>Marcus Wood</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1990"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_24">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-24-1-0008">
        <pb id="p24-260" n="260"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">The Franklin Library <hi rend="i">Reproduction of Songs</hi> U, Princeton
University Library: <hi rend="i">Songs Of Innocence and Of Experience.</hi> Franklin Center, PA: Franklin
Library, 1980.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Alexander S. <name>Gourlay</name></docAuthor> and <docAuthor>John E.
<name>Grant</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Although it will probably be difficult to find, this very good reproduction of one of the great
copies of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> may occasionally appear in used-book stores; because it was
marketed as a collectible object rather than published as an ordinary book, it has so far escaped the
attention of Blake’s bibliographers. Superficially, the volume manages to be pretentious but not
prepossessing. It is bound in brown leather and features yellow watered-silk endpapers, a marking ribbon, a
hubbed spine, gilt edges all around, a frontispiece of the Linnell portrait of Blake from the Fitzwilliam, and
ungraceful gilt stamping on the cover and spine. The leaves—of appropriately heavy (but not avowedly
acid-free) matte paper—are practically the same size as those of the original (21.5 × 14 cm.).<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n113" type="note">1</ref> Issued in April 1980, it was the sixty-eighth
of a variously sized and bound series of collectible editions of “The Hundred Greatest Books of All Time”
from the Franklin Library (an affiliate of the Franklin Mint, purveyers of such collectibles as Elvis
commemorative plates). When telephoned, the Franklin Library was at first reluctant to answer inquiries about
itself, the scope of its offerings, or this volume, but eventually revealed that the reproduction of 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> was never available except as part of the complete set of one hundred
<figure n="SONGSIEUTitlePage.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="412">
	<head><hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, copy U, general title page.</head>
	<figDesc>Franklin Library reproduction.</figDesc>
</figure>
books, which cost about $4000, and that it is long out of print. <note id="n113"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi
rend="i"> Notes from the Editors</hi>, a somewhat dizzy 22-page promotional pamphlet for this volume that was
discovered and brought to our attention by Robert N. Essick, describes the paper as “70-pound Franklin
Library Vellum White” (22).</note></p>
          <p>In spite of such unpromising auspices, and the general inferiority of the other volumes in this
series, this reproduction of <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy U is of high quality—someone (the Franklin
Library’s representative suggested that the person departed long ago) lavished considerable thoughtful
attention upon its production. Scholars, libraries, and collectors of Blakeana should all wish to acquire it.
Most readers of this journal are familiar with the various reproductions of the Rosenwald-Library of Congress
copy of <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> copy Z, which range in quality from the magnificent Blake Trust collotype and
stencil facsimile (1955) to the Orion/Oxford six- and eight-color offset reproduction (1967/1970) to the
blurry but inexpensive Dover edition (<hi rend="i">Experience</hi> only, 1984). In contrast, copy U of 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> has been reproduced as a whole only once before, not very well, by Quaritch in 1893, and
since then only single pages from it have appeared in print: in Erdman’s <hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake</hi>
(general titlepage and “Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>), Johnson and Grant (general
titlepage, in color), and accompanying Grant (“The Tyger,” in color).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n114" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n114"><hi rend="s">2</hi> For more complete information on reproductions of the 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> see Grant and Johnson, and Wilkie.</note></p>
          <p>Copy U itself is a beautiful copy, comparable in degree and quality of finishing to the
better-known, probably later, beautifully colored copies Z and AA (at the Fitzwilliam). Most pages bear
extensive delicate outlining in ink, and its general titlepage contains unique variants; some of these are
discussed by Erdman (42, 386). The arrival of the book at Princeton in 1967 was heralded by Morton D. Paley in
this journal, and its general character has been well described by Ryskamp, following Keynes and Wolf: “54
plates on 54 leaves. Watermark [RUSE &amp; TURNERS] 1815. Printed in red-brown; ‘elaborately and brilliantly
painted with water-colours and opaque pigments, heightened with silver and gold; each plate within a single
framing line. Foliated by Blake 1-54’” (38).</p>
          <p>The Franklin Library edition is not a scholarly reproduction, and it has some characteristics
that might mislead one expecting it to be exactly like copy U.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n115" type="note">3</ref> The color quality, of course, varies, and the register is sometimes
appreciably off, especially in those plates that use black ink: for example, plates 1, 2, 20, 29, 40, and 44
are all too dark, and 40 is seriously out of register in the copy we have examined. Grant’s notes on the
original indicate other discrepancies as well, but it would not be useful to report these until the
reproductions and the original have been compared side-by-side. What is more notable is that the plate sizes
in the reproduction vary from the originals by as much as a centimeter (vertically). More deliberately,
Blake’s foliation, written at the upper right hand corner of each design (within the framing line), has been
silently removed, even though the numbers accurately indicate the page sequence and would not really compete
with the alternative pagination in conventional printing. The
<pb id="p24-261" n="261"/>
edition also provides a transcription of the text on the verso facing each plate page; the punctuation has
been normalized more or less as Keynes did in the Orion/Oxford facsimile (e.g., line 16 of “The Tyger” has
a question mark rather than Blake’s printed exclamation point). <note id="n115"><hi rend="s">3</hi> See
Tanselle for a review of some problems presented even by serious scholarly facsimiles.</note></p>
          <p>As offset reproductions of illuminated books go, however, this is a decided success. On the
average it is somewhat less muddy in color and sharper than the Orion/Oxford facsimile of copy Z, partly
because Blake’s delicate outlining of details comes off well. It is not possible to reproduce Blake’s most
elaborately colored pages (such as these) by offset lithography without some murkiness and flatness in the
colors, and this edition has its share of dead spots and infelicities. Yet all the images are at least
plausible, even though no more than four ink colors were used in printing, and most of these reproductions are
about as good a job as ordinary offset can manage. The printing inks themselves are transparent, but the
presence of “opaque pigments” mentioned by
<figure n="SONGSIEUInnocenceTitle.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="402">
	<head><hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, copy U, <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> title page.</head>
	<figDesc>Franklin Library reproduction.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="SONGSIEUDivineImage.24.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="250" height="167">
	<head>Detail, <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, copy U, “The Divine Image.”</head>
	<figDesc>Franklin Library reproduction.</figDesc>
</figure>
Keynes and Wolf is sometimes easily discernible, as on plates 13 and 18, where a pale blue-white suspension
has been used to create halo effects; the metallic silver and gold they also mention are, of course, not in
evidence.</p>
          <p>Finding a copy of this edition will require haunting rare book stores, though for now one will
probably do best at the least pretentious places. Several other large series have been offered by the Franklin
Library in similar bindings, but a book dealer who has one volume from this set may have more or know where to
get them. Some purchasers of “The Hundred Greatest Books of All Time” are selling individual volumes (or
the whole set) for a fraction of their cost, and used-book dealers in the Midwest are asking twenty to thirty
dollars apiece. On the other hand, the very impressiveness of this particular book might make a collector who
was otherwise disenchanted with Western Civilization according to the Franklin Library more likely to hold on
to it alone.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Works Cited</title>
            </head>
            <p>Erdman, David V. <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake.</hi> New York: Doubleday, 1974.</p>
            <p>Grant, John E. “This Is Not Blake’s ‘The Tyger.’” <hi rend="i">The Iowa Review</hi>
19 (1989): 112-55.</p>
            <p>Grant, John E., and Mary Lynn Johnson. “Visual Resources for Teaching 
<hi rend="i">Songs.</hi>” In Robert F. Gleckner and Mark L. Greenberg, eds. <hi rend="i">Approaches to Teaching
Blake’s</hi> Songs of Innocence and of Experience. New York: Modern Language Association, 1989.</p>
            <p>Johnson, Mary Lynn, and John E. Grant. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Poetry and Designs.</hi>
New York: Norton, 1979.</p>
            <p><hi rend="i">Notes from the Editors: Songs of Innocence and of Experience by William
Blake.</hi> Franklin Center, PA: Franklin Library, 1980.</p>
            <p>Paley, Morton D. “Blake at Princeton.” <hi rend="i">Blake Newsletter</hi> 1:3 (1967):
6-7.</p>
            <p>Ryskamp, Charles. <hi rend="i">William Blake Engraver: A Descriptive Catalogue of an
Exhibition.</hi> Princeton: Princeton U Library, 1969.</p>
            <p>Tanselle, G. Thomas. “Reproductions and Scholarship.” <hi rend="i">Studies in
Bibliography</hi> 42 (1989): 25-54.</p>
            <p>Wilkie, Brian. “Blake on Microfiche.” In Robert F. Gleckner and Mark L. Greenberg, eds. 
<hi rend="i">Approaches to Teaching Blake’s</hi> Songs of Innocence and of Experience. New York: Modern Language
Association, 1989.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
