<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>24.1.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake and Wedgwood</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1990</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1990</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">24.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Michael Ferber</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>John E. Grant</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Colin Pedley</name>
              <name>Marcus Wood</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1990"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_24">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-24-1-0007">
        <pb id="p24-249" n="249"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake and Wedgwood</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>William Blake is known to have made engravings for Wedgwood’s catalogue of earthenware and
porcelain in 1815-16,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n76" type="note">1</ref> but he is not
known to have had an earlier contact with the firm or the man, though he did engrave the Wedgwood copy of the
Portland vase in illustration of Erasmus Darwin’s <hi rend="i">The Botanic Garden</hi> in 1791. Indeed, it
is commonly believed that “William Blake did not begin his connections with the Wedgwood firm until late in
his career, probably from 1815 to 1816.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n77"
type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n76"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Books</hi> (1977) 631-32.</note>
	<note id="n77"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Shelley Bennett, <hi rend="i">Thomas Stothard: The Mechanisms of Art
Patronage in England circa 1800</hi> (Columbia: U of Missouri P, 1988) 6.</note></p>
          <p>However, Blake must have known of Wedgwood from very early in his career, not only because of his
work on the Wedgwood copy of the Portland vase and the growing fame of the firm, but because his friend John
Flaxman did a great deal of work for Wedgwood in the 1780s.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n78" type="note">3</ref> Flaxman not only designed pottery for Wedgwood but also decorated his very
ambitious house called Etruria Hall in Staffordshire. And it seems likely that Flaxman managed to get Blake to
assist him in this work. <note id="n78"><hi rend="s">3</hi> “Flaxman principally subsisted through his
employment for the firm of Wedgwood &amp; Company” in 1775-87, according to Samuel Smiles, 
<hi rend="i">Josiah Wedgwood, F. R. S.: His Personal History</hi> (New York, 1895) 224.</note></p>
          <p>The account book for Etruria Hall, shows that Wedgwood paid Flaxman in itemized amounts for his
work (see box).</p>
          <table rows="7" cols="5">
            <row>
              <cell>1785</cell>
              <cell/>
              <cell>[£]</cell>
              <cell>[<hi rend="i">s</hi>]</cell>
              <cell>[<hi rend="i">d</hi>]</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Dec.<hi rend="s">r</hi> 10 . . .<lb/>
To John Flaxman Acc<hi rend="s">t</hi> for Mantles in 1781 &amp; Jaumbs of Marble—&amp; designs</cell>
              <cell>44</cell>
              <cell>19..</cell>
              <cell>12..</cell>
              <cell>3½</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>To—D°—Drawings for Saloon in 1782</cell>
              <cell>44</cell>
              <cell>1..</cell>
              <cell>8..</cell>
              <cell>—</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>To—D°—Drawings for Ceiling &amp;c</cell>
              <cell>67—</cell>
              <cell>4..</cell>
              <cell>6..</cell>
              <cell>6</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>To—D°—Chimney piece in Saloon</cell>
              <cell>67—</cell>
              <cell>29..</cell>
              <cell>4..</cell>
              <cell>4</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>To—D°—Blake for painting on Ceiling pictures</cell>
              <cell>67</cell>
              <cell>3..</cell>
              <cell>17..</cell>
              <cell>—</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>To—D°—his own work</cell>
              <cell>67</cell>
              <cell>5..</cell>
              <cell>5..</cell>
              <cell>—<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n79" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n79"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Quoted from a reproduction of Wedgwood Ledger D (1779-87) 69, in Keel
University Library (on deposit from the Wedgwood Museum Trust). Christine Fyfe, Keel University Library
Archivist, tells me that the figures “44” and “67” (before the sums paid) are apparently
cross-references to other ledgers which do not survive with the Wedgwood materials in Keel University Library.
                                    <p>The role of “Mr Blake” in this commission is mentioned without
connecting him to the poet in Bruce Tattersall, “Flaxman and Wedgwood,” <hi rend="i">John Flaxman</hi>
[catalogue of the Flaxman exhibition at the Royal Academy 26 Oct.-9 Dec. 1979], ed. David Bindman (London:
Thames and Hudson, 1979) 47.</p></note>
	</cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <p>The fact that this “Blake” is a painter suggests that he is Flaxman’s friend the painter
William Blake. That the payment came through Flaxman rather than to Blake directly and that there is no
expense money for travel to Staffordshire, etc., suggests that Blake’s work was done in London—perhaps he
was painting on canvas or on an early version of his own fresco invention which was shipped to Staffordshire
and affixed to the ceiling. The facts that he was “painting on Ceiling pictures” and that Flaxman had
already been paid for “Drawings for Ceiling” suggest that Blake was carrying out Flaxman’s designs,
perhaps transferring sketches to the surface to be put up on the ceiling—Blake was particularly skillful at
transferring designs from paper to copper, and, years later, the master-engraver John Linnell employed Blake to
help him by laying in the outlines of designs.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n80"
type="note">5</ref> The context, at any rate, suggests that the designs are Flaxman’s and that Blake is
primarily concerned with transferring Flaxman’s “Drawings” into “painting[s] on Ceiling.” 
<note id="n80"><hi rend="s">5</hi><hi rend="i"> Blake Records</hi> (1969) 256.</note></p>
          <p>The design is described in Flaxman’s letter to Wedgwood of 5 February 1784:
<q>
I was last night honored by Mr. Byerley with your enquiry concerning the pictures you employed me to paint for
the drawing-room ceiling. The four divinities heads for the corners have been nearly finished, and the
allegory for the centre has had the effect roughly laid in some time since, but that I waited for your opinion
on them, as you were expected in town almost daily for some time since. However, I have now sent two of the
corners and the centre, accompanied with the difficulties I am under, for your contemplation and decision. I
think, when you have fastened them with pins in their places and considered the effect, you will find either
the heads are too large for the centre, or that the figures in the centre are disproportionately small for the
heads. If you think the heads have a proper effect, and are not too large when seen in their proper places, I
must reduce the number of figures in the centre and replace them upright in the long way of the oval,
retaining the allegory, or make them genii children telling the same story; by which means also the whole will
have a better proportion. If you think the figures in the centre of a proper height and the heads too large
and heavy, I will alter the corner to whole figures of children (genii) sitting with the same attitude the
heads have now; and in this case I shall reduce the number of figures in the centre to show the outlines more
distinctly, like paintings on the Etruscan vases, as this manner has the best effect. When you have determined
these matters and sent back the paintings, they shall be finished with all possible despatch.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n81"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Smiles 229-30.</note></q>
In his reply of 20 February, Wedgwood said of “the paintings for my drawing-room ceiling,” that “The two
heads of divinities and a sketch of the allegory for the centre came to my hands last night. I have hastily
looked them over, but am obliged to put them by for the present. . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82" type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n82"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Smiles 232.</note></p>
          <p>The date of Blake’s work must be between February 1784 and 10 December 1785, when Flaxman was
paid, or at least when this account was entered in the ledger.</p>
          <pb id="p24-250" n="250"/>
          <p>The paintings for the ceiling are now not in Etruria Hall, and no other record of them is
known.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83" type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n83"><hi rend="s">8</hi> They are not mentioned in Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and
Drawings of William Blake</hi> (New Haven: Yale UP, 1981).
                            <p>According to Smiles (222n), the “ceilings were ornamented by drawings in oil
by Angelica Kauffman. They were removed by the agents of the Duchy of Lancaster, to whom the place belongs, to
one of their offices in the north, probably in Yorkshire.” (Such easily removable drawings were probably
painted elsewhere and affixed to the ceilings.) If this is so, there were evidently ceiling paintings in
Etruria Hall by both Angelica Kauffman and by Flaxman-Blake. Perhaps the Flaxman-Blake paintings suffered the
same fate as Angelica Kauffman’s.</p>
	<p>The Duchy of Lancaster acquired Etruria Hall in the late nineteenth century, but the printed
“Particulars” of the sale (generously provided to me by the agents of the Duchy of Lancaster) under Lot 1
detailed merely “A handsome, convenient, and well-built <hi rend="i">MANSION</hi>, called ‘ETRURIA
HALL,’ in good repair, comprising 34 Rooms, besides Entrance . . . ,” plus 44 acres with cottages, crofts,
outbuildings, and a pool, with no reference to ceiling paintings at all. There appears to be no record with
the Duchy of Lancaster of what became of the ceiling paintings.</p></note></p>
          <p>Blake thus worked for two generations of the Wedgwoods. Blake’s disciple Frederick Tatham noted
that “Mr Flaxman introduced Blake to Mr Wedgwood” in the context of “The Designs of the Pottery,” and
the introduction has therefore been dated to 1815.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n84"
type="note">9</ref> But these new records of work by Blake for Etruria Hall make it virtually certain that the
elder Josiah Wedgwood knew Blake’s work and saw it as early as 1785. <note id="n84"><hi rend="s">9</hi><hi
rend="i"> Blake Records</hi> 239.</note></p>
          <p>But note that in each case Blake is employed not as an original artist, making or copying his own
designs, but as a reproductive craftsman, transferring the genius of other men to copper or canvas. There is
no evidence that either Wedgwood knew of Blake as an original artist.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n85" type="note">10</ref> Considering that the younger Josiah Wedgwood later provided an annuity to
Coleridge, so that his genius would not need to waste itself in mundane tasks, the lost opportunity to
Blake—and to posterity—for such potential patronage is indeed striking. 
<note id="n85"><hi rend="s">10</hi> I presume that the last entry in the Wedgwood letter quoted here (£5.5.0 “To—D°—his
own work”) refers to original work by Flaxman, not by Blake, for the money is paid to Flaxman with no
indication that the work for which it paid was performed by anyone else than the payee.</note></p>
          <p>Flaxman’s sponsorship of Blake is quite in keeping with what is known already. He frequently
introduced Blake to potential patrons, and he solicited commissions for Blake widely. Naturally he endeavored
to get Blake commissions first for modest and inexpensive work, such as drawings and engravings, rather than
for finished tempera paintings or Blake’s own books in illuminated printing. Blake’s own style was so
unusual, not to say eccentric, that patrons had to be introduced to it gradually.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86" type="note">11</ref> In most cases, such as this with Josiah Wedgwood, the
commission was either not repeated at all or was succeeded only by requests for more journeyman labor. Blake
was a superb craftsman, intensely proud of his craft. He did not repine at such reproductive labor. But what
he wished for most dearly was commissions for large paintings, for suites of paintings such as Thomas Butts
gave him, even for suites of large frescoes to decorate churches. But most of his patrons, like Josiah
Wedgwood, were content to employ him—once—as a reproductive craftsman. It is not so much that they did not
appreciate his genius as that it probably never occurred to them to consider him in the light of a genius at
all. <note id="n86"><hi rend="s">11</hi> For the explosive results when a conventional patron was introduced
too abruptly to Blake’s idiosyncratic style, see the correspondence between Blake and the Rev. Dr. Trusler
in August 1799.</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
