<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>24.2.gleckner</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Janet A. Warner, Blake and the Language of Art</title>
        <author n="Gleckner">Robert F. Gleckner</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1990</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1990</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">24.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Gary Harrison</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Sandra Kamusikiri</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1990"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_24">
    <body>
      <pb id="p24-65" n="65"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-24-2-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Janet A. Warner. <hi rend="i">Blake and the Language of Art.</hi> Kingston and
Montreal: McGill-Queen’s University Press, 1984; Gloucester: Alan Sutton, 1984. xx + 211 pp. $32.50.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Robert F. <name>Gleckner</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>As she indicates in her preface, Janet Warner has been studying for a number of years what she
calls variously Blake’s visual vocabulary, pictorial language, visual shorthand, visionary clichés—in
short the language of art of her title. From 1970 through 1977 she published several essays that have become
the heart of this book, most notably “Blake and the Language of Art” in the <hi rend="i">Colby Library
Quarterly</hi> (1977). There she more firmly articulated, and elaborated, the thesis first eassayed in her
contributions to David Erdman and John Grant’s 1970 <hi rend="i">Blake’s Visionary Forms Dramatic</hi> and
to Morton Paley and Michael Phillips’s 1973 festschrift <hi rend="i">William Blake: Essays in Honour of Sir
Geoffrey Keynes</hi> (chapters 3 and 6, respectively, of the present book). We have learned much from her
about Blake’s “formula-figures” as she calls them, their poses, postures, and gestural configurations
which “carry a nucleus of meaning” that “often work[s] in conjunction with his verbal text” (but not
always), that constitute a language “sometimes. . .complementary to the poetry” (sometimes not), but that
always extend our understanding of “the important concepts of Humanity, Form, and Energy which all Blake
readers must strive” to know if we are to know what Blake is all about (xviii)—not to say how, as we have
learned to say, his composite art is to be experienced.</p>
          <p>I shall come back to my two parenthetical remarks later on, for they raise important hermeneutic
issues that are insufficiently addressed by Warner but are faced by all Blake interpreters. But first I go
back to my opening sentence and its phrase “the heart of this book”—a generous phrase, in one sense,
since the previously published articles actually constitute the bulk of the book’s pages. If we exclude for
a moment full-page illustrations, about 34 pages of text represent work previously published. Of the 186 pages
of the book (excluding the preface, notes, and index), 71 are either full-page illustrations (53) or
near-full-page illustrations (18), seven are blank, and one contains three brief paragraphs introducing part 2
of the volume. There remain the equivalent (counting the part-text part-illustration pages as well) of 73
pages of previously unpublished discussion. Needless to say, my arithmetic is not intended to suggest an
oversupply of illustrations, especially for a book devoted to Blake’s designs; indeed, while they are
generally well chosen and of good quality, Warner refers us to a number of other books as well, Butlin’s 
<hi rend="i">Paintings and Drawings</hi>, the Erdman et al. <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, Roe’s 
<hi rend="i">Divine Comedy</hi>, and Bentley’s <hi rend="i">Four Zoas</hi>, occasioning thereby some awkward
logistical reading problems (unavoidable in many cases, but annoying nevertheless). In any case, a book that
has 106 illustrations, even one in which each illustration does not require major discussion, a little over
one page of text per illustration in what purports to be more than a compendium or taxonomy simply cannot
raise it much beyond that status. Yet Warner’s claim is that she demonstrates how Blake’s designs “can
be the key which unlocks the treasure chest” of meanings (xvii), how they “underline” (and even help to
define) major ideas and concepts in the work (xviii), how they often derive from an extraordinary array of
artistic repositories of images, symbols, allegorical figures, emblems, and the like not only in the history
of art but also in the theory and history of acting, pantomime, dance, oratory, commercial textile design, and
physiognomy. The thoroughness and assiduousness of her research, then, paradoxically lead to a disappointing
cursoriness of critical discussion, the impact of which is further diminished by an odd mixture of firm and
shrewd interpretations, guesses (both provocative and unilluminating), and the non-disentangling of the
obvious or commonplace from the learned or derivative.</p>
          <p>What we have, then, is a book that is at best informative with respect to Blake’s possible,
sometimes probable, sources of a visual, gestural language that had been codified in a variety of ways, at
least since Aristotle, Plutarch, Suetonius, Horace, <corr type="emend">Quintilian,</corr> and nearer Blake’s own time, Charles
Le-Brun (<hi rend="i">Expression des Passions</hi>, 1698; translated into English in 1701), Gerard de Lairesse
(<hi rend="i">The Art of Painting in All Its Branches</hi>, 1738 English translation of 1707 original),
Lavater’s <hi rend="i">Essays on Physiognomy</hi> (English edition 1789, to which Blake contributed 4
plates), John Bulwer (<hi rend="i">Chirologia: or the Natural Language of the Hand and Chironomia: or the Art
of Manual Rhetoric</hi>, 1644), Gilbert Austin (<hi rend="i">Chironomia</hi>, 1806), and John Weaver 
(<hi rend="i">The History of the Mimes and Pantomimes</hi> 1728)—among others, of course. It is an interesting
history in its own right, a rather remarkable reflection, as Warner notes, of the eighteenth century’s
“obsession” with “the naming and categorizing of gesture and attitude in the arts,” an encoding of
meanings that had become “the general lore” understood by performing and graphic artists of Blake’s time
(68), and clearly familiar to Blake himself if only through his early training in Pars’s drawing school,
where “Copy Forever” was not only the rule he enunciated for himself in his Annotations to Reynolds but
the standard school rule as well. Along with what Blunt, Hagstrum,
<pb id="p24-66" n="66"/>
<figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
Bindman, and a host of others have taught us about Blake’s borrowings and thefts from classical artists
through an amazing variety of others right up to his own day, and with what Bo Lindberg has revealed about
Blake’s use of pathos formulae in his Job designs, Warner’s history obviously adds to our fund of visual
linguistic lore, without which we could not appreciate what Stephen Behrendt in <hi rend="i">The Moment of
Explosion</hi> calls the iconographical “flexibility and adaptability” of Blake’s visual imagery. As he
argues in careful detail with respect to Blake’s Milton illustrations, those qualities force us out of the
“intellectual automatism” of culturally conditioned responses to certain icons, gestures, postures, even
colors, “into the sort of informed analysis and interpretation governed not by convention” (certainly not
by convention alone) but by our entering into active engagement with living forms, at once unique and
universal (Lincoln: Nebraska UP, 1983 [182-83]).</p>
          <p>Part 2 of Warner’s book, entitled “Blake’s Visionary Forms,” is intended to do precisely
what Behrendt says we should do. And there are moments when Warner does it very well indeed. Yet overall, upon
completing the four essays, I came away with a sense of something like déjà vu, of knowing much of this
already, certainly in part from Warner’s previous publications, but also from our own (however acquired)
visual-linguistic lore. The three brief paragraphs introducing the essays give away the burden of the mystery,
if indeed there was one:
<q>
figures with outstretched arms stand for creativity or, in their fallen state, power perverted to tyranny;
huddled and headclutching figures signify psychic energy; and dancing figures appear to be symbols of energy
of the body, mortal impulses.
</q>
This hardly reassures us that she will pursue in detail her announced “central concern,” the discovery of
“to what extent their meanings are defined by the context in which they appear” (xviii)—presumably both
graphic and verbal contexts. More often than not we get something like the odd sequencing of chapter 3 on the
gesture of outstretched arms. The opening pages remind us of much that we know about cruciform positions,
followed by a brief account of Blake’s variations on the basic, standing form in hovering and
“knee-raised” figures with arms outstretched. The latter position, we are told, “<hi rend="i">can
perhaps be said to suggest</hi> at best God-as-Man, The Poetic Genius, and at worst, fallen man’s idea of
God as authority” (92, my emphasis). “At worst” and “at best” are hardly clear, but presumably they
refer to the flat declarations that immediately follow: “Poetic genius is implied by the figure of an old
man with raised knee in <hi rend="i">All Religions Are One. . .</hi>; the similar figure of 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> 8 represents Urizen, man’s perversion of this poetic genius into authority.” C’est
ça. We are back to the introductory paragraph quoted above. No comment on hand positions, despite all the
pages spent on hands in part 1 of the book; nothing on faces despite similar analytic preparation; no real
contextualization. Only a list of other figures in similar poses elsewhere in Blake which “appear to have
similar connotations”—followed by the conclusion, (solidified somehow beyond the tentativeness of “can
perhaps be said to suggest,” “appear,” and “similar”), that “we have seen already that this 
<hi rend="i">is</hi> the stance of the Poetic Genius” (my emphasis). It is not, alas, an isolated instance.</p>
          <p>Four pages later (96) we are reminded that “there are details . . . which help to contextualize
the forms so that the variations or additional facets of meaning become clear.” Hand positions, for example,
though “subtly differing . . . can modify the meanings of the outstretched arms like signals helping us to
experience the designs with greater delicacy.” There follows a descriptive list of different hand
positions—up-ward, palms out; forward; downward; “sloping.” No further comment—until page 102 where we
are told what these several hand positions mean, more or less regardless of context. Again on page 120, in
Warner’s dealing with hunched-up figures of despair, Blake’s variations on this basic form are described
as “always subtle—a head bowed or unbowed, a gesture of arm or hand, knees open or ankles crossed—and
yet they are always important clues to meaning.” Fine; but it is precisely the elucidation, interpretation,
and argument about this subtlety that Warner all too often sacrifices in favor of declarative namings, a kind
of visual allegoresis that undercuts rather than highlights the very delicacy that she obviously sees (and
that we see at her prompting) but for whatever reason all too rarely explores.</p>
          <p>In her <corr type="emend">conclusion,</corr> Warner returns to her “central concerns” about
context in two rather odd (at least to me) ways. Her first sentence of the “Conclusion” (185) asserts that
her “principle concern” has been twofold: “to demonstrate that a visual language exists in Blake’s
designs” and that language can “reinforce our understanding” of the designs, “often” illuminating
“the ideas of the texts they illustrate.” As I indicated earlier, by now there are few of us who haven’t
discovered that visual language one way or the other—including our reading of Warner’s own earlier work.
Moreover “reinforce our understanding”
<pb id="p24-67" n="67"/>
suggests, distressingly, that somehow we have an understanding of the designs before we employ the
interpretive tools of a codified “language of art” to reinforce it—an understanding perhaps derived via
the “intuition” she cites in her preface as “one’s greatest aid in interpreting Blake, even when one
is a seasoned scholar” (xvii). But if it is “often” that this visual language illuminates the ideas of
the text, how can we know when it doesn’t, or why it doesn’t, or, if it does, how it does? Presumably by
“context,” for Warner herself now argues that “the issue <hi rend="i">always</hi> comes down to . . .
what the context [does] to the form in question” (my emphasis). What it does, she says, is “point us in
the direction of meaning”; but at the same time the “kernel of meaning” that the visual vocabulary has
in and of itself is the meaning that “this context will elaborate for us”—a sort of hermeneutic
reciprocity that at least teeters on the brink of indeterminate oscillation of meaning, if not arguing the
power of the text to determine, in some general way, the meaning.</p>
          <p>I guess this is where intuition comes in, but to my mind that is a tenuous, gossamer-like, not to
mention anarchically subjective guide out of what she herself calls “the mysterious labyrinths of the
interactions between word and image” in Blake (185). While one might well argue that by way of the first
half of this book we have been given the end of a golden string, manifestly an appropriate “mental
pursuit,” the fine piece of book-making that McGill-Queens has produced warranted a more rigorous, detailed,
and extensive (not to say subtle and delicate) commentary than Warner, I regret to say, has given us. For all
her extended study of the problem, she has not been able to do much more than “lead us in at [the] gate”
to the treasure of Blake’s intellect.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
