<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>24.2.bentley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">A Swedenborgian Bible</title>
        <author n="Bentley">G. E. Bentley, Jr.</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1990</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1990</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">24.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Gary Harrison</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Sandra Kamusikiri</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1990"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_24">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-24-2-0006">
		<pb id="p24-63" n="63"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A Swedenborgian Bible</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>G. E. <name>Bentley</name>, Jr.</docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Among the articles of faith of the New Jerusalem Church was that “the Books of the Word are all
those which have the internal Sense” as defined by Emanuel Swedenborg.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">1</ref> The list of exclusions from the Swedenborgian Bible is
formidable: Thirty-two books, about a fourth of the bulk of the Protestant canon, including Job, Proverbs, the
Song of Solomon, Acts, and all the New Testament Epistles. <note id="n30"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi rend="i">
Minutes of a General Conference of the Members of the New Church Signified by the New Jerusalem in the
Revelation</hi> (London, 1789) 1. The articles were signed by W. and C. Blake, almost certainly the engraver
and his wife.</note></p>
          <p>Presumably the followers of the New Jerusalem Church, such as William Blake, his friend John
Flaxman, the New Church printer Robert Hindmarsh, and Blake’s friend C. A. Tulk acted on the basis of the
Swedenborgian canon. We know that Blake did, for in his <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (1804-?20) the Divine Lord
builds a tomb for the dead Albion ornamented “with emblems &amp; written verse, Spiritual Verse, order’d
&amp; measur’d” (48.6-7) which contains exactly the canon of the Bible established by Swedenborg and
endorsed by Blake and others at the 1789 New Church meeting.</p>
          <p>Since the canon of the New Church Bible is so different from that of all other Protestants, one
might have expected Robert Hindmarsh, the Society’s printer, to print a Bible for their use. However, the
only Bible text for Swedenborgians recorded in the standard bibliography of the Bible in English is for
Genesis only, and it did not appear until 1912.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31"
type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">2</hi> T. H. Darlow and H. F. Moule, <hi rend="i">Historical Catalogue of Printed
Editions of the English Bible 1525-1961</hi>, rev. A. S. Herbert (1968) #2176.</note></p>
          <p>However, there <hi rend="i">was</hi> a Swedenborgian Bible issued in Blake’s time, and it was
available just when he was issuing his <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and working on his 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> It is a bibliographically curious work entitled
<pb id="p24-64" n="64"/>
<q>
THE WORD OF GOD: BEING<lb/>
DIVINE TRUTH ITSELF,
PROCEEDING FROM The Lord’s Divine Love;<lb/>
AND CONTAINING<lb/>
<lb/>
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .<lb/>
<lb/>
DIVINE WISDOM AND DIVINE LIFE, / AS REVEALED TO MAN IN THE / OLD AND NEW TESTAMENTS, / AND RECEIVED AND /
ACKNOWLEDGED BY THE NEW CHURCH, / SIGNIFIED BY / <hi rend="i">THE NEW JERUSALEM</hi>, / IN THE REVELATIONS. /
= / LONDON: / PRINTED, FOR THE SOCIETY OF IMMANUELITES, / OR THE WORSHIPPERS OF THE LORD JESUS CHRIST, AS THE
ONLY GOD OF HEAVEN AND EARTH, / BY GEORGE HAZARD, BEECH-STREET, BARBICAN. // 1809.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n32"><hi rend="s">3</hi> The only copy of which I have record is in the Glasgow University Library.
Volume 2 is dated 1813.</note></q>
A section on “The Books of the Word” explains that “The Books of the Word are all they which have the
internal Sense,” and it lists the Books of the Word exactly as in the 1789 meeting, with cross-references to
Swedenborg’s <hi rend="i">Arcana Coelestia</hi> No. 10325 and <hi rend="i">Heavenly Doctrine</hi> No.
266.</p>
          <p>However, only a small fragment of the work was actually printed by George Hazard whose name
appears on the title page. A note to “The Books of the Word” explains:
<q>
N.B. The Title page, with the contents of this leaf—a page of the end of JUDGES—end of II.
KINGS—beginning of PSALMS—end of PSALMS—and at the end of ST. JOHN only, were <hi rend="i">Printed
by</hi> GEORGE HAZARD, <hi rend="i">Beech-street, Barbican</hi>, 1809. But the BIBLE itself was PRINTED FOR
GEORGE EYRE AND ANDREW STRAHAN, PRINTERS TO THE KING’S MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTY, 1806.
</q>
The passages printed by Hazard were bridges to replace gatherings removed when those parts of the Bible which
“have not the internal Sense” were removed. The work is therefore the Bible as printed for Eyre &amp;
Strahan in 1806 as abridged by George Hazard in 1809 and 1813 to make it conform to the Swedenborgian canon of
the New Jerusalem Church.</p>
          <p>It seems likely that those deeply interested in Swedenborg, such as William Blake and John
Flaxman, would have known of such a publication and might even have consulted or purchased it. At any rate,
this Bible as abridged by George Hazard in 1809 and 1813, demonstrates that the Swedenborgian conception of
the true Bible was actually printed twenty-some years after it was publicly affirmed at the meeting to
establish the New Jerusalem Church in 1789.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
