<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>24.2.kamusikiri</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake and the Tradition of Lamentation</title>
        <author n="Kamusikiri">Sandra Kamusikiri</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1990</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1990</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">24.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Gary Harrison</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Sandra Kamusikiri</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1990"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_24">
    <body>
      <pb id="p24-59" n="59"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-24-2-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake and the Tradition of Lamentation</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Sandra <name>Kamusikiri</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Recent scholarship has demonstrated without a doubt the multiplicity and importance of the
biblical allusions in Blake’s <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n23" type="note">1</ref> Scholars have also shown that Blake’s assumptions about sublimity have much
in common with the ideas of such eighteenth-century poets and literary theorists as John Dennis, Edmund Burke,
Edward Young, and Robert Lowth.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">2</ref> These
lines of scholarly investigation up to this point have yielded a wealth of insights into Blake’s thought and
artistry, yet for the most part they remain separate areas of study. By linking the two, however, we can
enrich our understanding of Blake’s prophecy. <note id="n23"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See for example Morton
Paley, <hi rend="i">The Continuing City: William Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1983); Murray
Roston, <hi rend="i">Prophet and Poet: The Bible and the Growth of Romanticism</hi> (Illinois: Northwestern
UP, 1965); Leslie Tannenbaum, <hi rend="i">Biblical Tradition in Blake’s Early Prophecies: The Great Code of
Art</hi> (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1962).</note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">2</hi> See Anne Mellor, <hi rend="i">Blake’s Human Form Divine</hi> (Berkeley:
U of California P, 1974); David B. Morris, <hi rend="i">The Religious Sublime</hi> (Kentucky: UP of Kentucky,
1972); Paley, <hi rend="i">The Continuing City</hi> (1983) and <hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination</hi>
(Oxford: Clarendon P, 1970); Roston, <hi rend="i">Prophet and Poet</hi> (1965); Thomas Weiskel, 
<hi rend="i">The Romantic Sublime</hi> (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins UP, 1976).</note></p>
          <p>One unnoticed outgrowth of this association is the comparison between Blake’s and the Bible’s
version of Jerusalem’s lament and its relationship to eighteenth-century commentary on the sublimity of the
Bible. Specifically we can compare Jerusalem’s lament in chapter four (pls. 78-80) of Blake’s prophecy
with Jerusalem’s lament in the Lamentations of Jeremiah. Robert Lowth serves as a late eighteenth-century
guide to how Blake’s contemporaries understood this biblical passage and its sublimity. The thematic,
imagistic, structural, and rhetorical parallels between Blake’s poetry and its biblical counterpart, and
their correspondence with Lowth’s commentary on the sublimity of the lament reveal not only Blake’s skill
as a visionary aesthetician who both adopts and transmutes the prophetic style of sublime Hebrew poetry, but
suggest also the manifold meanings of his term “the Sublime of the Bible” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
1).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">3</ref>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">3</hi> David V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of
William Blake</hi>, rev. ed., with a Commentary by Harold Bloom (New York: Doubleday/Anchor, 1982). 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> are cited by plate and line number. All unetched works
and Bloom’s Commentary are cited as E, followed by the page number.</note></p>
          <p>Robert Lowth’s <hi rend="i">Lectures on the Sacred Poetry of the Hebrews</hi>,<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">4</ref> written during his tenure as Professor of
Poetry at Oxford, was heralded by his contemporaries as a milestone in the literary understanding of the
Bible. In the <hi rend="i">Lectures</hi> Lowth “put aside the literary assumptions of his age,” and
approached the Bible “without preconceived notions.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27"
type="note">5</ref> Lowth presented the biblical poets as visionaries and seers, a fact which attracted poets
turning from the strictures of eighteenthcentury poetry to new models. Among these may have been William
Blake, who could have known about Lowth’s <hi rend="i">Lectures</hi>, given their immense popularity, his
interest in the Bible, and struggle to create what he calls unfettered poetry (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 3).
<note id="n26"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Robert Lowth, <hi rend="i">Lectures on the Sacred Poetry of the
Hebrews</hi>, 2 vols. (Latin ed. 1753; English trans. 1787; Germany: Georg Olms Verlag, Hildersheim, 1969).
All subsequent references appear in the text.</note>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Roston 21.</note></p>
          <p>Lowth attributes a significant portion of the sublime effect of the Lamentations of Jeremiah to
the personification of the Holy City as a woman wracked by sorrow. Personification, in Lowth’s view, is
“by far the boldest and most daring” of the various types of figures; it has “uncommon force and
expression [and] in no hands whatever is more successful in this respect than in those of the Hebrew
writers” (1: 281). Personification achieves its most powerfully sublime effect when objects are denominated
as female, or more specifically when “nations, regions, peoples, are brought upon the stage as it were in a
female character” (1: 285, 287). The greatest example of this can be found in the Lamentations of Jeremiah,
believed by Lowth to be an “extraordinary production” and “the most remarkable [elegy] extant” (2:
130-31). What can be more sublime, he argues, than “the description of that once flourishing city, lately
chief among the nations, sitting in the character of a female, solitary, afflicted, in a state of widowhood,
deserted by her friends, deserted by her dearest connections, imploring relief, and seeking consolation in
vain” (2: 138)? The effect of Jeremiah’s presentation of Jerusalem as a suffering widow is “excessive,
and predominates in the mind” (2: 138), and characteristic of the affective power of the sublime, the mind
“becomes heated to fury and madness” (1: 381), until finally it is carried away “with irresistible
violence” (2: 86).</p>
          <p>What strikes us most immediately, perhaps, as the clearest and most obvious indications of an
affinity between the Lamentations of Jeremiah and Blake’s poetry are the personification of the City of God
as a woman cast into the depths of suffering, and the focus on her destruction. In the Lamentations the
comparison is explicit: “How lonely sits the city that was full of people! How like a widow has she
become” (1.1). Blake’s personification of Jerusalem is far less literal than that in the Bible and depends
on the aggregate of our understanding of Blake’s prophecy, his mythopoeic symbols and the Bible as a
pretext. The focus of the Lamentations of Jeremiah, according to Lowth, is “the destruction of the holy city
and temple, the overthrow of the state, [and] the extermination of the people” (2: 137). Blake asserts a
similar focus in the opening lines of Jerusalem’s lament:
<q>
Naked Jerusalem lay before the Gates upon Mount Zion<lb/>
The Hill of Giants, all her foundations levelld with dust!<lb/>
<lb/>
Her Twelve Gates thrown down: her children carried into captivity<lb/>
Herself in chains (78.21-24)
</q>
In the biblical lament Jerusalem declares that her “children are desolate for the enemy has prevailed”
(1.16). Blake’s Jerusalem also laments the destruction of her children who have been “dashd / Upon Egypts
iron floors, &amp; the marble pavements of Assyria” (79.1-2, 78.31).</p>
          <p>Although Jerusalem’s destruction evokes sublimity because it is horrifying and sad, this effect
is heightened by the prophet’s description of the ruin of the Holy City “as actually accomplished, and not
in the style of prediction merely” (Lowth 2: 137). In this way Jeremiah intensifies her misfortunes
<pb id="p24-60" n="60"/>
and adds to the prevailing mood of solemnity and sorrow. This is also true of Blake’s Jerusalem. He presents
her destruction not as portent, but as a completed fact. While this in and of itself suggests sublime sadness
and horror, its narrative context heightens these feelings to an even greater degree in that the Holy City’s
destruction marks the culmination of the triumph of evil, a time when the natural world seems to have fallen
to the deepest point in Ulro and a return to Eternity seems impossible. Jerusalem’s destruction follows
Albion’s descent into a death-like sleep, Rahab’s ascent to “power over the Earth” (78.16), and her
conspiracy with her sons to destroy Jesus and “usurp the Throne of God” (78.19).</p>
          <p>There are also a number of other striking parallels between the two laments. Besides parallels in
subject matter, we can also identify similarities in imagery. Blake’s descriptions of the suffering and
torments experienced by Jerusalem echo those in the Lamentations of Jeremiah. In the Lamentations, Jerusalem
states that the Lord “spread a net for [her] feet” (1.13). Blake, employing similar images of entrapment,
describes Jerusalem as “Encompassed by the frozen Net” (80.1), a phenomenon of the fallen world in
Blake’s mythology, suggesting coldness, death, and fixity, in contrast to the warmth, flexibility, and
energy associated with Eden.</p>
          <p>Parallel images in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and the Lamentations of Jeremiah suggest also the
obfuscation of Jerusalem’s form, the loss of divine light, and her separation from the Lord. Jeremiah
describes Jerusalem as having been “set . . . under a cloud” by the Lord, who in his anger “has cast
down from heaven to earth the splendour of Israel” (2.1). Likewise, Blake’s imagery suggests the eclipsing
of Jerusalem’s form and her separation from heaven. She appears “Disorganizd; an evanescent shade, scarce
seen or heard” (78.28). Lost in darkness, she “seeks for light / In vain” (79.11-12), is closed “into
a dark land of pitch and bitumen” (79.61), and lost in an “eternal night of pain” (80.5). And like her
counterpart in the Lamentations, she finds that God has forsaken her and she has become “an outcast from the
Divine Presence” (78.31, 33).</p>
          <p>Finally, Blake, like Jeremiah, presents Jerusalem as having been separated from all that can
provide her comfort and security. In the Lamentations, Jerusalem mourns that “among all her lovers she has
none to comfort her; all her friends have dealt treacherously with her, / they have become her enemies”
(1.2). She grieves about the loss of her comforters:
<q>
my eyes flow with tears; for a comforter is far from me, one to revive my courage;<lb/>
<lb/>
........................................<lb/>
<lb/>
I called to my lovers but they deceived me; My priests and elders perished in the city (1.16, 19)
</q>
Blake’s Jerusalem also seeks for allies and finds that all have fled from her or have been destroyed:
<q>
I walk to Ephraim. I seek for Shiloh: I walk like a lost sheep<lb/>
Among precipices of despair: in Goshen I seek for light<lb/>
In vain: and in Gilead for a physician and a comforter.<lb/>
Goshen hath followd Philistea: Gilead hath joind with Og!<lb/>
They are become narrow places in a little and dark land (79.10-14)
</q></p>
          <p>Whereas the biblical passage is literal in its description of Jerusalem’s isolation—her
comforters, priests, and elders have abandoned her—Blake’s poetry resonates with multiple meanings. By
imaging Jerusalem’s comforters as biblical locales, Blake intensifies her isolation, for she is cut off from
not only individual people, but also from entire cities and lands. She is separated from Ephraim and Shiloh,
which are associated with the sacred first site of the Tabernacle,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n28" type="note">6</ref> divided from Goshen, the area inhabited by the Israelites and known as the
“best of the land” in Egypt (Damon 166), and closed off from Gilead, known for its healing balm (Jeremiah
8.22). All of these locales, associated with comfort, priestliness, and healing have become lost, shrunken,
and darkened. Moreover, they have become spiritually corrupted in that Goshen and Gilead join with Og and
Philistea, places associated with unholiness, Satan, and the Covering Cherub in Blake’s mythology (Damon
306, 326). <note id="n28"><hi rend="s">6</hi> S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary: The Ideas and
Symbols of William Blake</hi>, rev. ed. (Hanover, NH: UP of New England, 1988) 127.</note></p>
          <p>As is typical of Blake’s adaptation of traditional sources to fit the thematic demands of his
prophecy, this corruption of the holy lands suggests that the distancing of Jerusalem and the natural world
from the Divine Vision may be, in the context of Blake’s myth, an even greater cause for a feeling of
sublimity than the image of Jerusalem as an isolated, grieving person. To put it another way, Jerusalem’s
destruction necessarily affects the entire natural world, and in this respect the Blakean sublime is evoked
not merely by a single object, but by the realization of the meta-connection of all things. As Paley rightly
observes, Blake’s “appropriation of the language of the Bible in parts of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> goes
far beyond mere imitation; it is the product of a remarkable <corr type="emend">assimilation</corr> of
biblical texts that can then be recast into new forms of utterance” (<hi rend="i">Continuing City</hi>
50).</p>
          <p>The structural parallels between the two laments can best be seen by discussing them in the
context of Robert Lowth’s analysis of the design of the Lamentations of Jeremiah. Lowth sees in it a
tripartite structure consisting of its outward appearance, internal blocks of ideas (or what he calls the
“grand divisions”), and the sentence arrangement (2. 131, 134, 32). In its outward appearance the biblical
passage seems spontaneous and unstructured. Bemoaning the destruction of his country, Jeremiah, in the
character of a mourner, “pours forth in a kind of spontaneous effusion . . . whatever presented itself to
his mind in the midst of desolation and
<pb id="p24-61" n="61"/>
misery, whatever struck him as particularly wretched and calamitous, whatever the instant sentiment of sorrow
dictated” (2: 131-32). Similarly, Blake pours forth details about not only Jerusalem’s destruction—“my
tents are fall’n! my pillars are in ruins,” she states—but also the annihilation of the world. The hills
of Judea have fallen into the deepest hell, Mount Zion has become a desolate rock, Albion’s hills and
valleys are “no more,” the fifty-two counties of England cast Jerusalem out, the Euphrates is red with
blood, and Druid Temples “overspread all the Earth in patriarchal pomp and cruel pride” (79.15, 20-21,
66-67). Jerusalem’s lament resembles a catalogue of destruction.</p>
          <p>In his grief Jeremiah “frequently pauses and . . . ruminates upon the same object; frequently
varies and illustrates the same thought with different imagery, and a different choice of languages; so that
the whole bears rather the appearance of an accumulation of corresponding sentiments (2: 132). In a way that
suggests the influence of biblical poetry on his work, Blake repeatedly describes <corr type="emend">Jerusalem’s</corr> exiled state
in corresponding images: she walks “like a lost sheep / Among precipices of despair” (79.10-11) and
wanders “in the narrow passages / Of the valleys of destruction” (79.60-61); she is “an outcast from the
Divine Presence” (78.33) and is closed out from the four-fold world (79.58-60); she “seek[s] for light”
(79.11), and is “raisd up in a night / To an eternal night of pain, lost! lost! lost! for ever!”
(80.4-5).</p>
          <p>Typical of his transformation of traditional sources, Blake produces the effusive quality of his
lament by including in it a profusion of place names and rapid shifts from one place and time to the next, all
packed tightly onto a single plate of illuminated text. Blake names biblical places (Shiloh, Philistea, Gad,
and Goshen), modern countries such as Germany, Poland, Spain, and Italy, and counties and rivers in England,
thus creating a continual movement from near to far and ancient to modern. Most of the lament appears on a
plate containing very little illustration, so that it seems to be filled with script from top to bottom and
margin to margin. In addition, the lettering on this plate differs from that on other plates filled with text,
such as 48, 80 and 86, in that the script is smaller and more densely packed and contains none of the spacing
between paragraphs that is typical of some of the other full text plates in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> This
textual density is reminiscent of what V. A. DeLuca calls Blake’s “wall of words,” a plate which
contains “bristling ranks of capital letters, verse without syntax, nouns without predication, names without
context,” all of which combines to create in the reader a feeling something like Kant’s sublime of
magnitude.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">7</ref> In Jerusalem’s lament,
the temporal and spatial motility, combined with the crowding of the text and the lack of paragraph spacing,
contribute to the sense of unrelieved destruction and grief—the sublimity—conveyed by the lament. 
<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">7</hi> V. A. DeLuca, “A Wall of Words: The Sublime as Text,” <hi rend="i">Unnam’d
Forms: Blake and Textuality</hi>, ed. Nelson Hilton and Thomas A. Vogler (Berkeley: U of California P, 1986)
231-34.</note></p>
          <p>Although on one level the Lamentations of Jeremiah appears to be “an accumulation of
corresponding sentiments,” Lowth identifies in it also an ordered arrangement. It consists of five parts or
grand divisions, each of which is in turn divided into twenty-two periods or stanzas, with the exception of
part three which consists of sixty-six periods. While on one level Blake’s version of Jerusalem’s lament,
like its biblical counterpart, appears to consist of an unstructured profusion of images that dramatize the
depth and intensity of her sorrow, we can also identify in it some “grand divisions.” Blake has organized
the lament into three units, consisting of approximately thirty lines in each. The beginning and end sections
feature the torment of the woman and the destruction of the Holy City (78.21-79.21 and 79.53-80.5,
respectively), and the middle section offers a portrait of the ideal Jerusalem before her destruction
(79.22-52).</p>
          <p>The detailed portrait of the Holy City before its ruin marks Blake’s divergence from the
Lamentations of Jeremiah. His description of the unfallen Jerusalem contrasts sharply with Jeremiah’s brief
description. The biblical prophet’s only references to the ideal Jerusalem are the allusion to her as a
princess (1.1) and a single question: “‘Is this the city which was called the perfection of beauty, the
joy of all the earth?’” (2.15). In contrast, Blake describes Jerusalem in a way that particularizes and
makes concrete the vision of her “perfection of beauty.” In the center section of the lament, Blake
presents a clearer, more determinate vision of Jerusalem’s human form, while in the other two sections
images of the ruined city predominate. Whereas Jerusalem appears in the fallen world as a “Disorganizd . . .
evanescent shade” (78.28), in eternity all the world “discernd [her] countenance with joy!” (79.28). She
is not isolated, but involved instead in joyous, loving, human activities: she “pour[s] Joy upon every
mountain . . . teach[es] songs to the shepherd &amp; plowman,” and embraces the little children (79.37,
25-26). In her Edenic state Jerusalem’s world is expansive, not shrunken. Her pillars “reachd from sea to
sea” (79.24), and Spain, with its golden hills, served as her “heavenly couch” (79.40). Germany and
Poland “found / My gates in all their mountains &amp; my curtains in all their vales,” she declares
(79.45-46).</p>
          <p>This detailed portrait of the ideal Jerusalem suggests Blake’s skillful revision of biblical
sources to fit the narrative and thematic demands of his prophecy. It functions as a momentary opening of the
center, a kind of visionary “stay” against the deepening of the Fall, and serves as a prelude to the
apocalyptic vision of regeneration at the end of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> It signals the end of what
Erdman calls the “night of death” (E 357), and heralds the “building up of Jerusalem,” the thematic
focus of chapter four. Blake’s vision of the ideal Jerusalem forms a cohesive core
<pb id="p24-62" n="62"/>
which seems to bind together the parts of the lament and acts as a preview of the extended, minutely detailed
portrait that Blake presents in Los’ Song (85.14-86.32) later in chapter four. Consistent with Blake’s
mythology, the description of the unfallen Jerusalem is placed in the center of the lament—as Eden occupies
the center (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 28.38)—and is associated with images of expansiveness and
determinateness.</p>
          <p>Lowth analyzes the form of the Lamentations according to three criteria: its outward form, the
grand divisions, and the sentence arrangement. As we have seen, the first two criteria indicate clear
parallels between the Lamentations and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> An application of the third criterion to
Blake’s poetry demonstrates even more vividly his adoption of traditional sources and his complex treatment
of them.</p>
          <p>Parallelism is the name that Lowth gives to the particular arrangement of sentences which he
believes is unique to biblical poetry. He defines parallelism, which depends not on meter, but on the
correspondence and balance of sense units, as “the correspondence of one verse, or line, with another. . . .
When a proposition is delivered, and a second is subjoined to it, or drawn under it, equivalent, or contrasted
with it, in sense, or similar to it in the form of grammatical construction” (2: 32n10). He classifies
parallelism according to three types: synonymous, antithetic, and constructive parallelism. The following
lines from Jeremiah’s lament contain parallelism and remind us of the thematic concerns of Blake’s poetry.
For example, Jeremiah’s descriptions of Jerusalem’s sorrow contain synonymous and constructive
parallelism:
<q>
Behold, O Lord, for I am in distress, my soul is in tumult,<lb/>
my heart is wrung within me (1.20)<lb/>
<lb/>
My eyes are spent with weeping; my soul is in tumult;<lb/>
my heart is poured out in grief (2.11)
</q>
In six statements containing equivalent images, Jeremiah describes the suffering of Jerusalem. Constructive
parallelism, the grouping of sentences with similar grammatical construction is evidenced by the repetition in
each statement of the word “my” and verb structure “to be.” A similar correspondence of sense units is
clearly evident in Blake’s description of Jerusalem’s suffering and his repetition of the subject-verb
structure “I walk” in the lines,
<q>
I walk weeping in pangs of a Mothers torment for her Children:<lb/>
I walk in affliction (80.2-3)
</q>
Blake imbues the entirety of Jerusalem’s lament with prosodic cadences reminiscent of those in biblical
poetry. Several scholars such as Paley in <hi rend="i">The Continuing City</hi>, Tannenbaum in 
<hi rend="i">Biblical Tradition in Blake’s Early Prophecies</hi>, and Roston in <hi rend="i">Prophet and
Poet</hi> have discussed the connection between Blake’s poetry, Hebrew verse, and Lowth’s commentary on
biblical poetry. However, no one, as yet, has analyzed Jerusalem’s lament in the context of either Lowth’s
concept of parallelism or the sentence arrangement in the Lamentations. The following lines, in which
Blake’s Jerusalem describes her destruction, echo the thematic content of the Lamentations and suggest the
influence of biblical parallelism (I have divided these and subsequent lines from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
to highlight the parallelism):
<q>
My tents are fall’n!<lb/>
my pillars are in ruins! (79.1)<lb/>
<lb/>
My fires are corrupt! my incense is a cloudy pestilence of seven <corr type="emend">diseases!</corr>
(79.56-57)
</q>
In statements containing parallel images and grammmatical structures, Jerusalem mourns her separation from the
Divine Vision:
<q>
Once a continual cloud of salvation rose from all my myriads;<lb/>
once the Four-fold World rejoicd among/The pillars of Jerusalem<lb/>
(79.57-59)
</q>
Blake describes Jerusalem’s isolation in a longer unit of parallelism:
<q>
[Albion’s] hills &amp; his valleys no more<lb/>
Receive the feet of Jerusalem: they have cast me quite away:<lb/>
And Albion is himself shrunk to a narrow rock in the midst of the sea!<lb/>
The plains of Sussex &amp; Surrey, their hills of flocks &amp; herds/No more seek to Jerusalem nor to the
sound of my Holy-ones.<lb/>
The Fifty-two Counties of England are hardened against me/As if I was not their Mother,<lb/>
they despise me &amp; cast me out<lb/>
(79.15-21)
</q>
In this passage, the repeated images of division and contraction which are central to Blake’s myth of the
Fall underscore the fragmentation of the natural world, and the distancing of it and Jerusalem from the Divine
Vision. Isolated, Jerusalem is hated, cast out, and no longer sought. The various spiritual locales shrink and
harden against her.</p>
          <p>In contrast, in the middle section of the poem containing Blake’s portrait of the ideal
Jerusalem, the parallel sentences emphasize expansiveness and loving, cooperative human activities rather than
contraction and isolation. For example, whereas in the fallen world Albion “is shrunk to a narrow rock in
the midst of the sea!” (79.17), in eternity Albion and his emanation, Jerusalem, overspread the earth:
<q>
London covered the whole Earth.<lb/>
England encompassd the Nations:<lb/>
And all the Nations of the Earth were seen in the Cities of Albion:<lb/>
My pillars reachd from sea to sea:<lb/>
London beheld me come/From my east &amp; from my west (79.22-25)
</q>
Blake presents images of cooperative human <corr type="emend">activities</corr> in a series of parallel images
and grammatical structures:
<pb id="p24-63" n="63"/>
	<q>
Turkey &amp; Grecia saw my instr[u]ments of music, they arose<lb/>
They seizd the harp: the flute: the mellow horn of Jerusalems joy<lb/>
They sounded thanksgiving in my courts<lb/>
(79.48-50)
</q>
Places that were divided by the fall are connected in Eternity:
<q>
Thames poured his waters into my basons and baths:<lb/>
Medway mingled with Kishon: Thames recievd the heavenly Jordan<lb/>
(79.34-35)
</q>
By means of these parallel images, Blake is able to dramatize in the middle section of the lament the
humanization and restoration of the universal society of nations, events which remind us of the grand vision
of regeneration which takes place at the end of the prophecy.</p>
          <p>Clearly then, the profusion of parallel lines in Jerusalem’s lament suggests an affinity with
the Lamentations and highlights Blake’s rejection of eighteenthcentury metrical patterns, the
manifestations, he believed, of “the modern bondage of Rhyming” (<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 3). Whether
or not Jerusalem’s lament is the result of his knowledge of Lowth’s ideas or simply his deep familiarity
with the Bible and belief that the “Old &amp; New Testaments are the Great Code of Art” (Laocoon, E 273),
it is clear that the subject matter, structure, and cadences of the Lamentations of Jeremiah are present in
Blake’s version of lament. As Roston explains in his study of the impact of the Bible on the romantic
movement, “the Bible, including the Old Testament, was the noblest and most inspired literature in the
world, and the spirit of Hebrew prophecy permeated not merely Blake’s verse but even his daily life”
(160). Blake was able to transmute his understanding of biblical poetry into the uniquely Blakean thematic,
imagistic, structural, and rhetorical features of his prophecy. And this, combined with his rejection of
eighteenth-century aesthetics and his search for alternative poetics, enabled him to effect in Jerusalem’s
lament the prophetic resonances of Hebrew poetry and the “sublime of the Bible” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>
1).</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
