<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>24.2.hilton</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Robert N. Essick, William Blake and the Language of Adam</title>
        <author n="Hilton">Nelson Hilton</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1990</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1990</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">24.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Gary Harrison</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Sandra Kamusikiri</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1990"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_24">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-24-2-0007">
		<pb id="p24-67" n="67"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Robert N. Essick. <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Language of Adam.</hi>
Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1989. x + 272 pp. 8 illus. Index. $55.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Nelson <name>Hilton</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Robert N. Essick needs no introduction to readers of this journal, who, more than any other
audience, best fulfill his vision of the “something very like a hermeneutic community generated by Blake’s
works” (224) and who have already embraced Essick’s catalogues and his studies of Blake’s “materials
and methods of production, the ways they determine the images they convey, and the historical and quotidian
engagements their use entails” (1). This latest contribution sets out “to situate Blake within the history
of language theory and to generate a hermeneutic on the basis of that history” (2). The result is vaguely
reminiscent of Morton Paley’s <hi rend="i">Energy and the Imagination</hi> (Oxford, 1970) as Essick presents
in Blake’s works a kind of paradigm shift from structuralism (and post-) to phenomenology; that is, from
“dyadic signification (signifier/signified) to triadic interchanges among author, text, and reader” (223);
or again (subsuming Paley), from signs to Logos and “power” (235, 5). All of this makes for provocative
reading, and the seventy-five pages that selectively epitomize—with special regard to Blake’s
interests—seventeenth and eighteenth-century speculations on the origin and nature of language will, in
particular, prove useful and rewarding.</p>
          <p>But where Paley could point into the text and the inverse fates of his chosen terms dramatized in
pre- and post-Felpham word-counts, Essick’s argument depends on our acceding to a host of words he brings to
the feast. “Logos” is
<figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
one, and a bit more than a minute particular, given that the book culminates in “The Return to Logos”
(chapter 5). The index suggests that this Big Word (it’s always capitalized here) relates to “language,
God’s”; one context identifies it as “God’s Word, which brings the universe into being” (11), others
as an “ideal” form of semiosis with “the co-presence of conception and execution” (85) and “the
power” to “create . . . objects or give them organic life” (26). Blake never uses the word, though he
certainly knew the Greek of John 1:1, and perhaps the accusative form (<hi rend="i">logon</hi>) together with
<hi rend="i">zooas</hi>, “living,” oozes in his good news of Golgonooza (that un-ideal place of semiosis).
Some accounts derive the noun <hi rend="i">logos</hi> “from the Greek verb <hi rend="i">lego</hi>, ‘to
pick out, to gather,’ as seeds were gathered by the early food gatherers,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">1</ref> an etymology pertinent to Jesus’ gloss that “the seed is
the word” (Luke 8:11). The spore, or sperm, or semen, is logos. <note id="n33"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Theodore
Thass-Thienemann, <hi rend="i">The Interpretation of Language</hi>, vol. 1 (New York: Aronson, 1973)
44.</note></p>
          <p>Essick’s book begins by bringing some words to an untitled painting of Blake’s, which, he
agrees with Rossetti, should be called “<hi rend="i">Adam Naming the Beasts</hi>” and labels “a painting
about language” (10). He proceeds to educe two “readings” of the design, one of which evokes “the
dream of the motivated sign” and the “companionship”
<pb id="p24-68" n="68"/>
of phenomenologists like Humboldt and Heidegger, while the other, focusing on the serpent, privileges
“absence and difference” and the evidently less congenial “company” of more structural thinkers like
“Nietzsche, Sartre, and Derrida” (16). The picture thus becomes a signifier for “the double perspective
on language” (27, 208) that the book proposes. Although he reports that he “can see no easy way of
eliminating one of the two opposing interpretations” and does not “feel any great compulsion to do so”
(16), an inherent logocentrism emerges in subsequent descriptions of the second reading as “my negative or
ironic interpretation,” “my negative or Derridean interpretation” (41, 135-36). But returning to the
design (see dust-cover, reproduced above), one wonders if there isn’t at least a third position, like the
one triangulated by—and “shewing”—“the two contrary states of the human soul.” This position would
incorporate the seed Adam’s finger points to, a curiously emphasized acorn which seems rather precisely to
mirror the outline of Adam’s own head indicated by his thumb (one might fill in the curve joining the outer
halves of Adam’s eyebrows to see, like a beginning artist, the seed for the sketch). Seed, head, and
thumb-index joint are thus the corners of a triangle or triadic relationship which is itself “the seed of
Contemplative Thought” by which “the Imaginative Image returns.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n34" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">2</hi> David V. Erdman, ed., <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of
William Blake</hi>, rev. ed. (Berkley, U of California P, 1982) 555. Hereafter cited as E followed by the page
number.</note></p>
          <p>“<hi rend="i">Adam Naming the Beasts</hi>,” as the history of that title illustrates, offers
an example of Blakean dissemination: seeds—words, texts, designs—are planted “To spring up for
Jerusalem” which “IS NAMED LIBERTY” (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 85.29; 26). “Blake’s way of producing
texts,” writes Essick, “leads us to view language performance as the liberation of an inherently limited
self” (190). But the liberation comes not in performance <hi rend="i">per se</hi>, but rather “in a book
[<hi rend="i">liber</hi>, Lt.] that all may read,” and the irrecoverable, scattering dissemination of
writing-being read/reaped. For Essick, however, there is no loss in this process since we still have
“[r]eading aloud from books—a literal return of the written back into speech” (172): the ideal is not
dissemination in writing or “producing texts,” but in spoken conversation. “[S]poken language, more than
any other semiotic medium, generates and almost seems to achieve that illusive and perhaps illusory ideal, the
Adamic sign” (185), that is to say, “the ideal union of word and world, represented by the Adamic or
motivated sign” (84). Union, communion, conversation, community, all figure as ways of circumventing those
“negatives,” absence and difference, and establishing identity or self-presence. The difficulty of the
task appears as Essick contends that “[i]n rapid or ecstatic speech, we enter unself-consciously into the
medium” and don’t sense “a gap” between thoughts and the words that seem “in a fully motivated union
with out thoughts” (185) only to note, rushing on, that “[i]n rapid conversation, we all say things we
don’t mean” (191).</p>
          <p>The book’s “double perspective” on language can be correlated with the division between
semiology and semiotics, Saussure and Peirce. Simplistically put, Saussure sees the sign as 
<hi rend="i">signifier</hi> and <hi rend="i">signified</hi> existing in synchronic and diachronic dimensions. The
exponentiation of these (and other) pairs to deal with change is easily forgotten, and Saussure’s binary
predilections make him seem the epitome of “rationalist linguistics” (135). C. S. Peirce, by contrast,
“gives us a definition of a sign that adds to the sign/object, signifier/signified relationship the
interpretant, a sign in the mind, and he argues that his triadic relation is irreducible.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">3</ref> A crucial point—for it is where time and
change enter—is that for Peirce the individual “interpretant” is, as he puts it, “nothing but another
representation to which the torch of truth is handed along; and <hi rend="i">as a representation</hi>, it has
its interpretant again. Lo, another infinite series” (Sheriff 119). Both of these sign-systems are
“open” in that they do not posit an ontology or teleology and accompanying value system—in every
communication there is some slippage, some lurking quantum differential, some possibility of mutation. Since
Saussurian semiology is to be discarded as negative and “fallen” (53), its openness poses no threat, but
in order to save the alternative, Peirce’s semiotic must somehow be closed. This closure, with all that it
entails, looms as a memorable and distinguishing mark of Essick’s book. <note id="n35"><hi rend="s">3</hi>
John K. Sheriff, <hi rend="i">The Fate of Meaning: Charles Peirce, Structuralism and Literature</hi>
(Princeton: Princeton UP, 1989) 57.</note></p>
          <p>Discussing the painting, untitled by Blake, “<hi rend="i">Christ Blessing</hi>” (why not
“<hi rend="i">Jesus Blessing</hi>”?), Essick focuses on the blessing hand as a “kerygmatic or
‘performative’ gesture” which “does what it signifies.” “The structure of this sign,” he
explains, “is not dyadic (signifier/signified) but triadic, requiring for its completion the signifier
(physical gesture or sound), the signified (blessing), and the recipient believer whose condition is changed
by his inclusion within the signifying process” (25-26). And here a footnote explains, “My sense of the
triadic nature of performative signification is based in part on C.S. Peirce’s analysis of all signs as
triadic. His concept of the ‘interpretant’ fulfills the same function within signification as my
‘recipient,’ but the two cannot be equated in other respects. Peirce’s interpretant is another sign,
whereas my recipient is a human response necessarily included within the performative sign to complete it as
such” (25n). The ideal sign is to be completed: the message delivered: presence assured: no loss. For
Essick’s Blake, “the chain of signs, arbitrary or motivated, must begin and end somewhere,” and “this
point of origin and ultimate reference is the immutable truths of religious conviction” (99). Like Blake’s
works and the “hermeneutic community” they have generated (224), “Christ’s kerygmatic signs avoid the
solipsism of pure self-referentiality by extending incarnation to the community of faithful recipients”
(26)—“[t]he process is circular,” in other words, “and avoids solipsism only
<pb id="p24-69" n="69"/>
for those who have faith in a transcendental power” (54-55).</p>
          <p>“The sublimity of Blake’s allegory,” then, “depends ultimately on what is signified
(transcendental truths) and who is addressed (true believers)” and posits “a triadic structure (sign,
referent, recipient) based in turn on the community of speaker, audience, and the medium joining them” (97).
This medium is language (“[t]he mediatory action of language” [234]), that is to say, Christ (with his
“traditional mediatory role” [200]), or, finally, “Logos.” Hence, in the “trajectory of linguistic
recovery shaping the language of the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>” (112), “[i]ndividual words 
(<hi rend="i">child, lamb, meek, tender, voice, He, I, thou</hi>, and <hi rend="i">name</hi>) achieve their full
meaning only [!] in relation to Christ, conceived either as a shared origin and referent or as a universalized
form of C. S. Peirce’s ‘interpretant,’ the companion sign providing the necessary context” (113). But
for Peirce there cannot be any such “universalized form” since “a sign is a dynamic, triadic relation of
representamen, object, and interpretant within a certain ground” or, (Wittgenstein’s term) “language
game” (Sheriff 92, 94).</p>
          <p>What are Essick’s grounds? He quotes with approval Schleiermacher’s opinion that “‘[i]n
interpretation it is essential that one be able to step out of one’s own frame of mind into that of the
author’” (222) and states in the afterword that “[i]n the spirit of Schleiermacher’s hermeneutic, I
have frequently identified my interpretative orientation with what I take to be Blake’s own linguistic
suppositions” (238). What, then, is one to make of the capitalized pronominal references to God and Christ,
not to mention the preference for “Christ” over “Jesus”? One of Blake’s “models for language,”
argues Essick, is “Christ’s body, the signifier with a motivated relationship to a spiritual—not a
fallen or utterly natural—signified. As Blake writes at the conclusion of <hi rend="i">There is No Natural
Religion</hi>, ‘Therefore God becomes as we are, that we may be as he is’” (115). Yet seven pages on, we
read that “the belief that God becomes as we are so that we may be as He is, so clearly enunciated on the
concluding plate of <hi rend="i">There is No Natural Religion</hi>, offers . . . more than stylistic
implications” (122). Indeed: the <hi rend="i">h</hi> altering altars all—as, in a quite different way,
does Blake’s lower case <hi rend="i">c</hi> for “christ” (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 105.28).</p>
          <p>Discussing “The Lamb”’s “language of innocence,” Essick argues that
<q>
The reflected symmetry of “He is called by thy name” and “We are called by his name” indicates the
common derivation and interchangeability of “child,” “Lamb,” and Christ, immanent through the 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> whenever these names for Him are spoken. “Shepherd,” “father,” and all their
attendant adjectives and named qualities also gather about, and derive their meanings from, this central point
of origin. (113)
</q>
But perhaps this “reflected symmetry” is a bit more fearful than Essick’s frame allows: Jesus in point
of fact never “calls himself a lamb,” which stresses for us the question of who <hi rend="i">is</hi>
active behind the passive “He is called,” “We are called.” As this unspeaking voice of “The Lamb”
makes clear, one cannot talk about naming without entering into power, the imposition of form, Althusser’s
“interpellation” (our being “called” by a discourse and in responding, acquiescing to its authority),
Lacan’s “Name/No [Nom/Non]-of-the-Father,” and everything else that helps us understand the language
instruction that is “education.” In his <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi>, Essick accepts Christ “as the sign
of the father/ origin” (113), but I suggest that Blake knows as well as Lewis Carroll that the question in
naming is “who is to be master,” who is to say what’s “immanent” or “innocent”; and what Essick
sees as the “extra-linguistic, even ontological, origins” (113) of relationships among words in “The
Lamb” can be located more materially in the child’s verbatim repetition of snippets from Sunday-school
catechism and hymnsinging (cf. James’ lesson in <hi rend="i">The Pilgrim’s Progress</hi>, part 2, which
begins, “Canst thou tell who made thee?” and Charles Wesley’s “Gentle Jesus, meek and mild” in his
<hi rend="i">Hymns for Children</hi>). This is merely to acknowledge, as Essick does elsewhere, “the simple
yet necessary event of . . . hearing the word . . . before naming. . . .” (236). Given such implicit
recognition that “‘By the act of speech the external world becomes converted into an internal one’”
(232), one regrets the absence of any psychological model for considering the interconstitutive relations
between language and imagination, or kinds of motivation in a “motivated sign” (the Lacanian Symbolic and
Imaginary would seem particularly apposite to such considerations). The child is, to be sure, naturally (i.e.,
genetically) motivated to exercise its limited degree of semiotic mastery, but that exercise is thoroughly
coded and channelled by culture—as evident, for instance, in the different ostensibly onomatopoetic
(“motivated”) representations of animal sounds in different languages.</p>
          <p>The “double perspective” of <hi rend="i">William Blake and the Language of Adam</hi> emerges
in contrasting discussions of <hi rend="i">The [First] Book of Urizen</hi> and of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,
which contrast works to highlight the shift Essick sees in Blake’s “ideas about language’s essential
character” (238). The contrasts between “the grammatical and the phenomenological, the differential and
the constitutive” (239), not to mention (same difference?) the “rationalist and theological” (27) are of
course not absolute but serve to illustrate “the different ways texts respond to different conceptions of
language” (238). <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> here thematizes “the problem of difference and its presence in
semiosis” (128), in keeping with Urizen’s “fall” into “the language described by the rationalist
tradition of sign theory from the seventeenth-century grammarians to Derrida” (149-50). 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> directs us to “[t]he kind of semiosis, if any, Urizen falls away from” and,
according with its grounding in the different linguistic tradition “nascent in Boehme, emergent in Humboldt,
and continued by Heidegger” (149, 238) offers
<pb id="p24-70" n="70"/>
as “an alternative to the self-defeating structuralisms of Urizen” the “three key semiotic concepts”
of “articulation, conversation, and community” (203). The language presented in <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>
“constructed out of differential signs will, in its very attempts to bridge difference with reference, carry
with itself the void, the absence, from which it sprung” (150—the possible analogy here with another
“miraculous birth to a sign” [24] goes unremarked). But “[t]he desire of language to win existence in
reality” carries <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> “to a vision of language reclaiming its power as the Logos”
(235). In the world of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, the identification “‘It is Urizen,’” “[t]his
simplest of all copular structures, asserting the unity of ‘it’ and ‘Urizen,’ presupposes their
difference” and “unavoidably replicates” it (150), while in the universe of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>,
“the medium <hi rend="i">is</hi> the origin” (161) and “Jesus <hi rend="i">is</hi> the ‘Divine
Revelation’” (202).</p>
          <p>While <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> suggests “<hi rend="i">difference</hi> as the fundamental
ontological category” (149), the Blake Essick favors is primarily committed “to the shared ontological
source of all form in spirit” (115). But “are they Two &amp; not One”? (<hi rend="i">J</hi> 57.9). Does
not Urizen “as origin of difference/dispersion” (151) [dissemination] ground “the possibilities for
continual (re)conception Blake dispersed throughout the process of production” (192)? Consider the crucial
moment Essick three times returns to, “when Urizen directly utters ‘Words articulate’” (151; 153,
204). The passage, never cited, reads:
<q>
3. Shrill the trumpet: &amp; myriads of Eternity,<lb/>
Muster around the bleak desarts<lb/>
Now fill’d with clouds, darkness &amp; waters<lb/>
That roll’d perplex’d labring &amp; utter’d<lb/>
Words articulate, bursting in thunders<lb/>
That roll’d on the tops of his mountains<lb/>
<lb/>
4: From the depths of dark solitude . . . etc. (3.44-4.6)
</q>
It’s not Urizen ostensibly speaking here, but “clouds, darkness &amp; waters.” In his usual thorough
way, however, Essick supplies the key in reminding us, earlier on, that “[a]s Alexander Geddes pointed out
in 1790, ‘in the language which Moses spake, the word rendered <hi rend="i">voice</hi>, signifies, in
general, every kind of sound, and . . . particularly the awful sound of thunder’ ” (105). The point, in
view of “the primeval Priests assum’d power,” isn’t “the emergence of articulate speech out of
natural utterance” (204), but the attribution, the projection of speech into nature (forgetting where All
deities reside): in the imagined beginning was the word, which was what the thunder was heard to say
(“no!” in thunder, no doubt). For this jump to occur there had to have been a complex interpretative and
psychological structure “always already” in place. Urizen’s “Words articulate” do not “lie at the
heart of his taxonomic matrix” (204) so much as at the horizon of Blake’s psycho-cultural vision.</p>
          <p>“Words articulate, bursting in thunders” can exemplify what Essick very usefully discusses as
Blake’s “literalization of figuration.” By this term he denotes how Blake “grants substantial being to
what we would usually take to be only a figure of speech” (224). So, for instance, “Blake asks us to
believe in the literal existence of his trope of the Last Judgment and to refuse its conversion into a
trope” (99). In this case this means, I should think, that we must reconceive our notion of the Last
Judgment (if “whenever any Individual Rejects Error &amp; Embraces Truth a Last Judgment passes upon that
Individual” [E 562—though the comedy shouldn’t be overlooked: “a Last (act of) Judgment (until the
next)”]). Such reconceptions would affect “Him” as well. For Essick, <hi rend="i">The Book of
Urizen</hi> particularly evidences the “sinister uses of literalization” (225) and shows “a foolish mind
reifying itself into a world” (229). Perhaps. But it strikes me that a great deal depends on how we take the
speaking “I” of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>’s “Preludium.” If we hear him or her as other than Urizen
(returning, with Essick, the written “primeval Priests” into a spoken singular possessive meaning
“Urizen’s” [155]), then the “objectivist, grammatical, and spatial” scene Essick constructs is
convincing enough. But if, as in “The Argument” to <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>,
this speaking “I” is the protagonist <hi rend="i">in propria persona</hi>, a sadder and a wiser man, then
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, as much as <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, “asks its readers to abandon synchronic
reductions and follow an apocalyptic quest through the diachronic activities of the linguistic mind”
(238-39) and into Blake’s yoU-aRe-I-zen of our rise in reason and vision.</p>
          <p>Robert Essick has long established himself as a leading authority on Blake’s material
production; with this volume he marshals exemplary scholarship to suggest how, in the terms of older
linguistic theories, Blake in effect finds his way from structuralism to phenomenology; and he breathes new
life into “the full ontological potency” and “the conversational dynamic of language in eternity,” as
well as “divine Logos” (233).</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
