<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>24.2.labelle</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">Blake’s Bald Nudes</title>
        <author n="La Belle">Jenijoy La Belle</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1990</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1990</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">24.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Gary Harrison</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Sandra Kamusikiri</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1990"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_24">
    <body>
      <pb id="p24-52" n="52"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-24-2-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">Blake’s Bald Nudes</title>
        </head>
        <byline>by <docAuthor>Jenijoy <name>La Belle</name></docAuthor></byline>
        <figure n="europe.c.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="506">
          <head>1. Blake, <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, posthumous copy c, plate 2.</head>
          <figDesc>Relief and white-line etching, 23.6 × 17.3 cm. Courtesy of the Rosenwald Collection,
Library of Congress.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <p>Among William Blake’s illuminated books, <hi rend="i">Europe a Prophecy</hi> draws particular
attention because of the power of its designs. Plate 2, for example, is enlivened with three bald and naked
combatants, plus a fourth figure grasping his hair or wig with both hands (illus. 1). Perhaps we are to
imagine that he is escaping from the melee below. The central wrestler is having the best of it, for he has a
headlock on one victim and is choking the other. The scene itself gives no clear clue as to why one man is
treating his companions so nastily. The background suggests clouds, and thus the group would appear to be
suspended in, or falling through, the sky. The text offers little help. Nothing in the poem clearly presents
itself as a description of these wrestlers, although they may be among the “howling terrors” mentioned in
line 4 of the plate, and the headlock and choke hold may be a cryptic answer to the question in line 13:
“And who shall bind the infinite with an eternal band?”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n1" type="note">1</ref> In copy D of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> (British Museum), George Cumberland
added to plate 2 verses from Richard Blackmore’s <hi rend="i">Prince Arthur: An Heroick Poem</hi> (1695),
hinting that the three men are personifications of Horror, Amazement, and Despair:
<q>
This orb’s wide frame with the convulsion shakes,<lb/>
Oft opens in the storm and often cracks.<lb/>
<hi rend="i">Horror, Amazement</hi>, and <hi rend="i">Despair</hi> appear<lb/>
In all the hideous forms that Mortals fear.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref></q>
	<pb id="p24-53" n="53"/>
These apocalyptic suggestions, clearly in harmony with the general tone of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, are given
a contemporary context in David V. Erdman’s political interpretation of the design: “Pitt [the middle
figure] is stifling expressions of Horror and Amazement at his catastrophic policy but is unable to suppress
the silent figure of Despair, which is ascending” top right.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n3" type="note">3</ref> Erdman modifies this reading in <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> (the
“strangler” may be Henry Dundas rather than Pitt; the escapee at the top may be Lord Chancellor Thurlow)
and adds that “the [lower] scene recalls young Hercules strangling serpents in his cradle.” He further
suggests that the baldness and nakedness of the lower figures might be explained as an indication of
Hercules’ infancy (but that could account only for the strangler’s appearance) or as a pictorial
literalization of Thurlow’s loss of his “judicial gown and wig” when “expelled from Pitt’s
cabinet.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref> This last point does not
easily accommodate the identification of Thurlow as the figure top right since he retains his hair or wig.
Indeed, Erdman’s specific identifications of these figures seem farfetched, although the general thesis that
the iconography has a political dimension is sound. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See also “the terrors
of strugling times” on plate 9. Plate numbers and quotations from Blake’s works are taken from 
<hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake</hi>, ed. David V. Erdman, rev. ed. (Berkeley: U of
California P, 1982). Edward Young’s “<hi rend="i">Chaos</hi>, and the Realms / Of hideous 
<hi rend="i">Night</hi>” are illustrated by Blake with two bald and nude wrestlers similar to those in 
<hi rend="i">Europe.</hi> See <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Designs to Edward Young’s Night Thoughts</hi>, ed.
John E. Grant, Edward J. Rose, and Michael J. Tolley (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1980), NT 496 (Night IX, page
78).</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> All the lines Cumberland added in his copy of <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> are
quoted, and their sources identified, in S. Foster Damon, <hi rend="i">William Blake: His Philosophy and
Symbols</hi> (London: Constable, 1924) 348-51. The substitution of “the convulsion” for “this
convulsion” in the lines from Blackmore’s poem indicates to Damon that Cumberland was quoting from the
excerpt in Edward Bysshe’s <hi rend="i">The Art of English Poetry</hi> (415 in the London 1708 ed., under
the subject-heading “Storm”). It is possible, but far from certain, that Blake suggested or approved of
these additions by his friend, but at the very least Cumberland seems to be working within the iconography of
bald nudes discussed here.</note>
	<note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire</hi>, rev. ed. (Garden
City: Anchor Books, 1969) 220. Erdman’s assumption that only two of the personifications in Blackmore’s
poem refer to the struggling group may be correct. However, since Cumberland wrote the lines from 
<hi rend="i">Prince Arthur</hi> below the plate and added a passage from Samuel Garth’s <hi rend="i">The
Dispensary</hi>(1699) above it, the identification of Blackmore’s three personifications with the three
figures in the lower part of the plate seems more likely on the face of it.</note>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Erdman, <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake</hi> (Garden City: Anchor Books,
1974) 160.</note></p>
        <p>A few precedents for bald and naked figures in the pictorial arts can enrich our understanding of
these motifs in Blake’s work. Perhaps the most famous example in European painting is Michelangelo’s 
<hi rend="i">Last Judgment</hi> fresco, completed in 1541. At least one of the damned, a prominent figure in
Charon’s boat, lower right, clutching his head in despair, is bald and nearly nude (illus. 2). Blake’s
knowledge of Michelangelo’s painting through reproductive engravings is virtually certain.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> Blake’s own Last Judgment design illustrating
Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> includes one such figure just above the lower margin of the image
(illus. 3). Michelangelo’s figure, although completely dissimilar in posture, may have provided a precedent
for Blake’s doomed soul who, much like the
<figure n="Michelangelo.24.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="550" height="339">
	<head>2. Michelangelo, <hi rend="i">The Last Judgment</hi>, detail of a figure in Charon’s boat.</head>
	<figDesc>Fresco, Sistine Chapel.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="DayofJudgment.24.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="550" height="310">
	<head>3. Blake, “The Day of Judgment,” detail.</head>
	<figDesc>Engraved by Louis Schiavonetti for Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (1808). Whole design
27.7 × 22.3 cm., detail approx. 4.5 × 10 cm. Author’s collection.</figDesc>
</figure>
central wrestler in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> 2, holds down two companions. <note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi>
The specific engravings Blake saw have never been identified. Possible candidates include the ten detail
plates by Giorgio Ghisi (mid-1540s), the nine plates by Nicolas Beatrizet (1562), and the single engravings of
the entire fresco by Guilio Bonasone (c. 1546), Giovanni Baptista de’ Cavalieri (1567), and Martinus Rota
(1569). George Cumberland owned an impression of Bonasone’s print—see his <hi rend="i">Some Anecdotes of
the Life of Julio Bonasone</hi> (London: Robinson, 1793) 61, and <hi rend="i">An Essay on the Utility of
Collecting the Best Works of the Ancient Engravers of the Italian School</hi> (London: Payne and Foss et al.
1827) 310-11. For reproductions of the engravings by Cavalieri, Rota, and Bonasone, see Charles De Tolnay, 
<hi rend="i">Michelangelo: The Final Period</hi> (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1971) figs. 258, 259, 260b. For essays
that center on Blake’s borrowings of figure types from Michelangelo’s <hi rend="i">Last Judgment</hi>, see
Leslie W. Tannenbaum, “Transformations of Michelangelo in William Blake’s <hi rend="i">The Book of
Urizen</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Colby Library Quarterly</hi> 16 (1980): 19-50, and Irene H. Chayes, “Blake’s
Ways with Art Sources: Michelangelo’s <hi rend="i">The Last Judgment</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Colby Library
Quarterly</hi> 20 (1984): 60-89.</note></p>
        <p>Michelangelo’s bald nudes are not the first such Renaissance portrayals of the damned. Luca
Signorelli’s frescoes of the Last Judgment, painted 1499-1504
<pb id="p24-54" n="54"/>
<figure n="signorelli.24.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="499">
	<head>4. Signorelli, fresco roundel in the Cappella della Madonna di S. Brizio, Orvieto Cathedral.</head>
</figure>
<figure n="Flaxman.24.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="550" height="356">
	<head>5. John Flaxman, <hi rend="i">Know Ye Not to Whom Ye Yield Yourselves.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>Pen and brown wash over pencil, 15.3 × 18.4 cm. Courtesy of the Huntington Library and Art
Gallery.</figDesc>
</figure>
in the Cappella della Madonna di S. Brizio of Orvieto Cathedral, include supplementary roundels of naked and
bald men (illus. 4). Unlike Michelangelo’s figure but like Blake’s group in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>,
Signorelli’s nudes are fighting or torturing each other. In the context of the whole fresco program, these
scenes are visions of hell, as well as the sort of worldly behavior imitating and leading to a state of
damnation. Blake might have known Signorelli’s work through engravings, although I have not been able to
locate any prints of these specific roundels. There is, however, another avenue for Blake to have gained
access to Signorelli’s designs. During his extended stay in Italy, 1787-94, Blake’s friend John Flaxman
visited Orvieto and sketched one of the roundels.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6"
type="note">6</ref> Flaxman later integrated these figure types into his own artistic idiom and sketched at
least a few designs featuring bald and naked combatants. He retained, even intensified, Signorelli’s
identification of such figures with damnation, as for example in a sketch illustrating Romans 6:16 (illus.
5).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> The sinner in the center of the
composition retains a few locks, although far fewer than the well-thatched or bewigged figure in 
<hi rend="i">Europe.</hi>
	<note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> For reproductions of Flaxman’s pencil drawing (15.2 × 36.2 cm., Victoria
and Albert Museum, London) and Signorelli’s grisaille, which it copies, see David Irwin, <hi rend="i">John
Flaxman 1755-1826</hi>(London: Studio Vista, 1979) 41. Blake and Flaxman were close friends from no later than
the early 1780s—see G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1969)
18-19.</note>
	<note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> See Robert R. Wark, <hi rend="i">Drawings by John Flaxman in the Huntington
Collection</hi> (San Marino: Huntington Library, 1970) 49: “The motif of tumbling figures, pulled downward,
is common in Flaxman’s art, especially the funerary monuments, where it becomes a symbol of the damned in
opposition to the blessed.” See for example <hi rend="i">But Deliver us from Evil</hi>, a wash drawing
illustrating “The Lord’s Prayer” (reproduced in David Bindman, ed., <hi rend="i">John Flaxman</hi>
[London: Thames and Hudson, 1979] 123), and Inferno plate 32 (two wrestlers) and Purgatorio plate 16 (falling
figures) among Flaxman’s Dante illustrations (first engraved 1793). Bald heads in some preliminary sketches
may simply reflect the unfinished state of the compositions, but this is unlikely in the finished wash
drawings and published engravings cited here.</note></p>
        <p>The unknown date of Flaxman’s designs and his absence from London until the year Blake etched on
the title page to <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> make direct influence less than certain. But no such difficulty,
nor the distance from London to Orvieto, attends upon a more public precedent for Blake’s bald nudes. From
1676 until 1814, Bethlehem (or “Bethlem” or “Bedlam”) Hospital for the insane stood in Moorfields,
along the north side of London Wall Street (the present cite of Finsbury Circus). Over its main gate reigned
two near life-size figures sculpted in Portland stone, the one on the left representing melancholy madness,
and his chained companion on the right raving madness (illus. 6).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n8" type="note">8</ref> These statues, the work of Caius Gabriel Cibber (or “Cibert,” 1630-1700),
were placed above the gate c. 1680
<pb id="p24-55" n="55"/>
and were not removed until the hospital moved its quarters to Lambeth.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n9" type="note">9</ref> In recent years they have been kept at the Bethlem Royal Hospital, Beckenham,
and the Museum of London. Both figures are bald and, although draped with small loincloths, are basically
conceived as nudes. <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> The identification of each figure is apparently
traditional. The first printed description I have found is Colley Cibber, <hi rend="i">An Apology for the Life
of Mr. Colley Cibber</hi> (London: for the author, 1740) 5 (quoted in Bowen’s pamphlet [5 note] discussed
below). For photo reproductions of the statues removed from their pediment, see Howard Roberts, ed., 
<hi rend="i">Survey of London</hi> (London: London County Council, 1955) 25: plate 41.</note>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Samuel Redgrave, <hi rend="i">A Dictionary of Artists of the English
School</hi> (London: Longmans, Green, and Co., 1874) 80.</note></p>
        <p>Cibber’s madmen were among eighteenth-century London’s most famous public statues. In his
attack on the sculptor’s son, Colley Cibber, in <hi rend="i">The Dunciad</hi>, Pope makes reference to
“those walls where Folly holds her throne” and “Great Cibber’s brazen, brainless brothers”—that
is, his father’s sculptural offspring.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n10"
type="note">10</ref> The description of the statues by Blake’s acquaintance Allan Cunningham gives some
indication of their fame and impact: “Those who see them for the first time are fixed to the spot with
terror and awe; an impression is made on the heart never to be removed; nor is the impression of a vulgar
kind. . . I remember some eighteen or twenty years ago, when an utter stranger in London, I found myself,
after much wandering, in the presence of those statues, then occupying the entrance to Moorfields.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref> It would have been difficult for Blake, an
inveterate walker and, like Cunningham and the speaker of “London” in <hi rend="i">Songs of
Experience</hi>, a fellow wanderer in London’s streets, not to have known Cibber’s statues. Blake was
certainly aware of the building these statues decorated, or its successor in Lambeth, for on plate 45 [31] of
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, he refers simultaneously to the biblical town and to London’s hospital for the
insane: “Bethlehem where was builded / Dens of despair in the house of bread” (E 194). A further and
earlier connection with Blake’s circle of friends is established by the engraving reproduced here (illus.
6), for it is based on a drawing by Thomas Stothard of the statues and their pediment.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref> The plate was published as the frontispiece to a
sixteen-page pamphlet of 1783 by Thomas Bowen, <hi rend="i">An Historical Account of the Origin, Progress, and
Present State of Bethlem Hospital.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13"
type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Alexander Pope, <hi rend="i">The Dunciad</hi>, ed. James Sutherland, 3rd
ed. (London: Methuen, 1963) 271. “Brazen” is a comment on Colley Cibber, but also appropriate for his
“brothers” since the stone statues were stained to simulate patinated bronze.</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi><hi rend="i"> The Lives of the Most Eminent British Painters, Sculptors,
and Architects</hi> (London: John Murray, 1830) 3: 26-27. Flaxman makes passing reference to “the mad
figures on the piers of Bedlam gates” in his Royal Academy lecture on “English Sculpture”—see his 
<hi rend="i">Lectures on Sculpture</hi>(London: John Murray, 1829) 30.</note>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Blake knew Stothard well by no later than late in 1780—see Bentley
19.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> The last line of the inscribed verses is bound into the spine of the
Huntington copy, reproduced here, but is fully revealed in a copy of the pamphlet offered by the London
bookdealer C. R. Johnson, January 1990, catalogue 29, item 126, with the frontispiece reproduced. I am
indebted to my colleague George Pigman for the following rough translation: “A double column raises itself
at the gates of Bethlem; the stone on the outside has an image of the people within. On the right [from the
perspective of the figures] a man leans his bald head with a sad face; on the left, iron chains hardly hold
another man. The madness in the statues differs, but each madness praises each work and the genius of the
sculptor.” These lines are quoted from <hi rend="i">Lusus Westmonasterienses</hi> [(Westminster: A.
Campbell, 1730) 78], a collection of Latin verses and epigrams.</note></p>
        <figure n="Sharp.24.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="550" height="341">
          <head>6. William Sharp after Thomas Stothard’s drawing of Caius Cibber’s statues of melancholy
and raving madness.</head>
          <figDesc>Line engraving, 13.2 × 20.7 cm., 1783. Courtesy of the Huntington Library. This engraving
is an accurate representation of the statues as they exist today, except that the figures have their mouths
open, and hence express more anguish, in the original sculptures.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <figure n="Hogarth.24.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="550" height="446">
          <head>7. William Hogarth, “The Rake’s Progress,” plate 8.</head>
          <figDesc>Line engraving, 31.4 × 38.7 cm., 2nd state. Courtesy of the Huntington Library and Art
Gallery.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p24-56" n="56"/>
        <p>Blake’s figures in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> do not repeat the postures of Cibber’s, but their
nakedness and baldness would have united suggestions of madness to the iconography of damnation for a London
artist and his London audience. The caricature-like faces of Blake’s three wrestlers add to the implications
of insanity. Although Cibber’s figures are heavily indebted to Michelangelo’s Medici Tombs in posture,
architectural placement, and musculature, it was widely believed that they were based on actual inmates of
Bedlam. According to Horace Walpole, “one of the statues was the portrait of Oliver Cromwell’s porter,
then in Bedlam.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> Recent arrivals
at the hospital may have already had their heads shaven, and their wigs taken from them, but patients may have
been kept bald to control head lice and other pests. William Hogarth’s final plate in “The Rake’s
Progress” series of 1735 (illus. 7) shows Tom Rakewell in Bedlam—bald (like several other inmates),
wearing only breeches, insane, and being placed (like Cibber’s raving madness) in irons. The rake, and the
half-naked religious fanatic on the left, may have been influenced by Cibber’s statues as much as by real
patients;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> but Hogarth’s engraving
indicates the extent to which a paucity of clothing (the would-be monarch in the central cell is stark naked)
and a bald pate undecorated by a wig were identified with madness in popular imagery. 
<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi><hi rend="i"> Anecdotes of Painting in England</hi>, 3rd ed. (London: J. Dodsley, 1782) 3:
146. Bowen notes that this “tradition” identified the porter with the “melancholy lunatic” on the left
(5 note). Margaret Whinney, <hi rend="i">Sculpture in Britain 1530 to 1830</hi> (Harmondsworth: Penguin,
1964), reproduces the melancholic (pl. 36B) and comments that Cibber’s “two powerful nudes, horrifying in
their realism, must surely have been studied from the life . . .” (49).</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Georg Chistoph Lichtenberg, in his commentaries on Hogarth’s engravings
first published in German, 1784-96, notes that “it is said that Hogarth took the idea for that remarkable
head [the baldheaded man far right] and for the one opposite in No. 54 [the religious fanatic far left] from
the excellent statues above the portal leading into the courtyard of Bedlam” (quoted from 
<hi rend="i">Lichtenberg’s Commentaries on Hogarth’s Engravings</hi>, trans. Innes and Gustav Herdan [London:
Cresset P, 1966] 268n1).</note></p>
        <p>The legend that Cibber’s melancholic was modeled on Cromwell’s porter carries us back to
Erdman’s political interpretation of the scene in <hi rend="i">Europe.</hi> Perhaps the fate of the servant
signifies something about the politics of the master—or even the fate of all regicides. Yet if Erdman is
correct about the pictorial allusion to Pitt and his circle, the <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> 2 shifts the butt of
criticism from the revolutionary to the establishment: England’s policies are not only damnable, but insane.
Further political implications arise if we take the similarities between Blake’s figures and Cibber’s to
be a reference
          <figure n="but320.1.1.cpd" id="but320.1.cprint.01" work-copy="cpd" rend="db" width="958" height="767">
	<figTranscr>WB 1795</figTranscr>
            <head>8. Blake, <hi rend="i">The House of Death.</hi></head>
              <figDesc>Color print, 48.5 × 61 cm., designed 1795 but perhaps not executed until 1805.
Courtesy of the Tate Gallery, London/Art Resource, NY.</figDesc>
          </figure>
by the later work to the earlier, and from this extrapolate an allusion to the whole edifice of Bedlam. The
building, over 500 feet in length, had an impressive façade “adorned with Corinthian pilasters,
entablatures, foliage, &amp;c.” and a “balustrade of stone.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n16" type="note">16</ref> According to Bowen’s pamphlet (5 note), “the design of the building was
taken from the Chateau de Tuilleries [sic], at Versailles” (corrected by hand in ink to “in Paris” in
the Huntington copy), and this borrowing was taken as an insult by Louis XIV. A link is thereby established
between the palatial hospital and actual palaces, with the further implication that housing madmen in such a
structure could be taken as a comment on the residents of similarly constructed buildings. By Blake’s time,
it was known that the foundation of Bedlam was weak and the building was slowly sinking—hence the move to
new quarters in 1814.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17" type="note">17</ref> In 1794, the
“foundations” of other palaces—their authority, their dignity, and the ethos they represented—were
also crumbling—most spectacularly in France, but also in England in the eyes of many liberal artisans and
intellectuals. The intertextual reflections between Blake’s bald nudes and Bedlam supplement and deepen the
political iconography explored by Erdman. <note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> B. Lambert, <hi rend="i">The
History and Survey of London and Its Environs</hi> (London: T. Hughes and M. Jones, 1806) 2: 540. Lambert’s
book includes (2: facing 539) an engraving by “Birrell” of Cibber’s gate statues, probably copied after
the plate by Stothard and Sharp. For an engraving of 1676 showing the entire building, its wall and gate, see
the reproduction in John D. Thompson and Grace Goldin, <hi rend="i">The Hospital: A Social and Architectural
History</hi> (New Haven: Yale UP, 1975) 68.</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> The building’s limitations may have been one of the motivations for
Bowen’s pamphlet. The problems with the weak foundation are described by Roberts 25: 76 and by Thompson and
Goldin 68.</note></p>
        <p>The appearance of bald nudes in two of Blake’s later designs continues the implications of
insanity. In the year after <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, Blake designed and first executed a group of color
prints, including <hi rend="i">The House of Death</hi> based on <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>, bk. 11, lines
477-93 (illus. 8). Blake’s interest in Milton’s description of “A Lazar-house” may have been
stimulated by the reformist efforts of John Howard, whose <hi rend="i">Account of the Principal Lazarettos in
Europe</hi> appeared in 1789, with a second edition in 1791. Bedlam was among the hospitals Howard visited.
Although he found some conditions to commend, he notes in passing that “there is no separation of the calm
and quiet [inmates] from the noisy and turbulent, except those who are chained in their cells.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18" type="note">18</ref> Blake
<pb id="p24-57" n="57"/>
<figure n="jerusalem.A.P51" rend="file" width="958" height="700">
	<head>9. Blake, <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, copy A, plate 51.</head>
	<figDesc>White-line etching, 22.5 × 16.1 cm. Courtesy of the British Museum, Dept. of Prints and
Drawings.</figDesc>
</figure>
may have also known George Romney’s series of drawings based on Howard’s more horrifying descriptions of
prisons and hospitals elsewhere in Europe.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
type="note">19</ref> Two figures in Blake’s <hi rend="i">House of Death</hi> embody the iconography of
nakedness (or near nakedness) and baldness. Like the distinction between melancholy and raving madness in
Cibber’s statues, Blake’s print would seem to include a personification of melancholy standing along the
right margin contrasted with the more animated and anguished visage near the left margin. Martin Butlin
identifies the figure on the right margin of the color print as “despair,” who “tended the sick” in
Milton’s lazar house.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> His
grimacing face supports this association, but both Bedlamites recall other inmates of Milton’s house of
death: “Daemoniac Frenzy, moping Melancholy / And Moonstruck madness.” Like the patch on Rakewell’s
chest in Hogarth’s print (illus. 7),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21"
type="note">21</ref> the dagger held by Blake’s despairing madman suggests the contemplation of suicide more
than murder. <note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Howard, <hi rend="i">An Account of the Principal Lazarettos
in Europe</hi> (London: J. Johnson, C. Dilly, T. Cadell, 1791) 139.</note>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> See the examples reproduced in <hi rend="i">Drawings by George
Romney</hi>, an exhibition selected and catalogued by Patricia Jaffé (Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1977) pls.
43-46. Jean H. Hagstrum, “Romney and Blake: Gifts of Grace and Terror,” <hi rend="i">Blake in His
Time</hi>, ed. Robert N. Essick and Donald Pearce (Bloomington: Indiana UP, 1978) 201-12, makes a case for
Blake’s having seen Romney’s private drawings in the late 1780s and early 1790s.</note>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi><hi rend="i"> The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (New Haven:
Yale UP, 1981) 1: 173. All quotations from <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> are taken from John Milton, 
<hi rend="i">Complete Poems and Major Prose</hi>, ed. Merritt Y. Hughes (New York: Odyssey P, 1957) 444. See also
Cumberland’s inscription on <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> 2, quoted earlier, suggesting that one of its mad
wrestlers personifies Despair. Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">William Blake</hi> (Oxford: Phaidon, 1978) 38,
notes that “the figure at the right” in <hi rend="i">The House of Death</hi> “is despair, his head
shaved like a lunatic’s.”</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> See Sean Shesgreen, <hi rend="i">Engravings by Hogarth</hi> (New York:
Dover, 1973) plate 35: “The patch under [the rake’s] breast suggests he may have knifed
himself.”</note></p>
        <p>Blake’s final rendering of a Cibberian madman slouches near the right margin of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> plate 51 (illus. 9). Although this figure is clearly developed from his predecessor in
the color print (illus. 8), the absence of the knife and the addition of chains make his relationship to
Cibber’s raving madness (illus. 6) more prominent. In a separate impression of plate 51 (Keynes Collection,
Fitzwilliam Museum), Blake cut the word “Skofeld” in white line beneath the man on the right, thereby
identifying him with the character in Blake’s late poetry based on John Scolfield, the soldier who charged
Blake with sedition in 1803.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref>
“Scofield” (the spelling changes frequently) first appears in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, where he is
introduced as “bound in iron armour before Reubens Gate” (19.59; see also <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>
11.21-22). This location makes the characteristics Skofeld’s portrait shares with Cibber’s statues above
Bedlam’s gates all the more appropriate. To portray his accuser and the powers he represented as insane,
Blake once again used the bald and naked imagery linked to Bedlam’s inhabitants, both sculptural and human.
<note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Paley, <hi rend="i">The Continuing City: William Blake’s</hi> Jerusalem
(Oxford: Clarendon P, 1983) 217, comments that “Skofield is represented [in <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> pl.
51] as either a madman (cf. Hogarth’s dying Rake) or a convict, which is what he had wanted to make
Blake.”</note></p>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p24-58" n="58" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
