<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>24.2.ferber</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="news">The Limit of Opakeness</title>
        <author n="Ferber">Michael Ferber</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1990</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1990</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">24.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>G.E. Bentley, Jr.</name>
              <name>Robert F. Gleckner</name>
              <name>Gary Harrison</name>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <name>Sandra Kamusikiri</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1990"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_24">
    <body>
      <pb id="p24-75" n="75"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-24-2-0008">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">
              <hi rend="i">THE LIMIT OF OPAKENESS</hi>
            </title>
          </head>
          <p><hi rend="i">Blake</hi> announces a regular feature to be called “The Limit of Opakeness.” It
will consist of one or more brief articles that attempt to solve a Blakean crux.</p>
          <p>With each issue we shall propose one or two difficult short passages and invite essays of no more
than 750 words on one of them. What is a crux for one person, of course, may seem easy to another, and some of
our passages will strike some readers as poor choices. For that reason we will welcome suggestions. We may
even print a consensus list of opaque passages.</p>
          <p>Many of us Blake scholars remember first reading some of the magisterial critics and wondering
how they came to know everything so confidently (and why they passed over in silence just those passages that
were bothering us); they were as intimidating as they were inspiring. Some of us still hate to admit we
can’t figure certain passages out. “The Limit of Opakeness” will encourage candor and collaboration, and
it ought to be rewarding to diminish Satan’s domain bit by bit, issue by issue.</p>
          <p>We welcome any and all approaches and will judge them all by the same rough standard: do they
seem to clear up the difficulty to any appreciable extent? We recognize that some schools of criticism might
find this a retrograde enterprise, and offer to deconstruct the opposition between crux and “easy”
passage. Let them do so, and if in the process they actually throw light on what we call a crux, we’ll
publish their essays, too. We ask only that the writing be clear and succinct: there is no Limit of
Translucence.</p>
          <p>This feature will run on a trial basis, and will last as long as good articles are submitted. We
might set design cruxes as well (and welcome suggestions for them), but at first we will confine ourselves to
the words.</p>
          <p>For the first round, we invite essays on either of two passages from the “Bard’s Song” of
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>: 5:39-41 (on Charles, Milton, Cromwell, and James) and 8:11-12 (Los puts his left
sandal on his head).</p>
          <p>Please send essays to Michael Ferber, Department of English, University of New Hampshire, Durham,
NH 03824, USA. He will give them a first reading and then confer with the editors over which of them will be
published.</p>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Michael <name>Ferber</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
