<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>24.3.atkins</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Martin Bidney, Blake and Goethe: Psychology, Ontology, Imagination</title>
        <author n="Atkins">Stuart Atkins</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1990/1991</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1990/91</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">24.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stuart Atkins</name>
              <name>Lisa Plummer Crafton</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Bruce E. Graver</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Edward Larrissy</name>
              <name>John Mee</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1990/1991"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_24">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-24-3-0007">
		<pb id="p24-99" n="99"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Martin Bidney. <hi rend="i">Blake and Goethe: Psychology, Ontology,
Imagination.</hi> Columbia: University of Missouri Press, 1988. xvi + 184 pp. $24.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Stuart <name>Atkins</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <p>Concisely formulated and meticulously documented, this comparative study should be of equal
interest to students of romanticism and of German literature in the Age of Goethe. It is, moreover, an
impressive work of scholarship that does credit both to its author and to its publisher at a time when books
by university scholars treating foreign language materials and appearing under the auspices of university
presses are often painful to read because of inaccurate citations, inexact quotations, frequent
mistranslations, and obviously insouciant editing.</p>
          <p>As critical analysis in the Jungian tradition of Maud Bodkin’s <hi rend="i">Archetypal Patterns
in Poetry</hi>, Bidney’s monograph persuasively demonstrates—to some extent by definition, since it treats
the archetypical—strikingly similar elements of thought and form in selected texts of Blake and Goethe.
Because a “spiritual kinship” (xii) can be discerned in the shared interest of both writers in
neo-Platonic and later hermetic materials, Bidney is persuaded that they are very similar “Romantic
poet-thinkers” (xi). In Goethe’s and Blake’s writings it is indeed possible to find “Shared Ideas and
Myths” (title of Bidney’s first chapter), some of which—like the pairs “Selving” and “Unselving”
or “negation” and “contrariety”—are constants, while others are to be found in Goethe only in early
works or in ones using motifs typical of his early writing but without their original positive value or
importance. The most obvious example of “re-use” would be the anacreontic motifs in 
<hi rend="i">West-östlicher Divan</hi>, his last large poem-cycle, and of “changed value,” the
folkloristic-supernatural elements in <hi rend="i">Faust.</hi> Beginning with Goethe’s conversion to
classicism, as the writing of the drama progressed these supernatural elements were used with ever greater
irony and ever more directly satiric, often anti-romantic, intention (e.g., in “Witch’s Kitchen,”
usually dated 1788—with its mocking of superstition—and in many later scenes through act 4 of 
<hi rend="i">Part II</hi>, written in 1831, with its jibes at the cult of medievalism). Although Bidney’s
premise of a basically romantic Goethe is in no way idiosyncratic, having been promulgated for some decades
even by self-proclaimed Goethe specialists, it means limiting Goethe’s classical period—Bidney does not,
like some who take his position, suppress the fact that there was such a period for Goethe—to “the decade
of his friendship with Schiller” (xii) and ignoring the fact that Goethe expressed stronger disapproval of
romanticism in the decades after Schiller’s death than in the one before it and was still criticizing
romanticism in his last years (e.g., in the concluding volume of his account of his Italian sojourn, published
1829, and in <hi rend="i">Faust II</hi>, chiefly written 1825-31).</p>
          <p>The extent to which Goethe in some periods and works is a romantic poetthinker comparable with
Blake is economically but adequately demonstrated by Bidney with reference to a limited corpus of materials,
namely, representative lyrics and a few prose passages by each writer, and major
<pb id="p24-100" n="100"/>
sections of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and <hi rend="i">Faust.</hi> His second chapter, “Between
Selving and Unselving: ‘The Authentic Pulse of Life,’” compares successive pairs of lyrics (from
adolescence, early adulthood, and later years) to show how “Blake and Goethe express their psychological and
mythopoeic affinities” in what indeed are “strikingly similar formal patterns” (23). Slightly less
satisfactory is his third chapter, “Overcoming Negations: Problematics of Reason and Desire,” which
examines how “the selving-unselving balance” operates for each poet in the area of psychology, although
this may be because some of the texts by Goethe used for purposes of illustration are less aptly chosen than
in the two preceding chapters. For example, an occasional four-hexameter epigram (mislabeled “elegantly
satiric distichs” [60]), that a genuinely appreciative Goethe wrote to thank Herder (court-preacher as well
as scholar, and hence “priest and wise man” in Bidney’s correct translation) for his essay “Nemesis”
is interpreted to mean that “Goethe’s priest is a well-intentioned but impertinent mediator” like the
“Disguiser of the Female Form” in Blake’s verses beginning “A fairy skipd upon my knee.”</p>
          <p>In his fourth chapter, “Overcoming Negations: Problematics of Imaginative Becoming,” which
has as its theme ontology, Bidney convincingly demonstrates basic similarities in the two poets’ concepts of
time and space with lyric examples all well chosen except for “Do You Know That Land,” said to represent
Goethe “in his classical decade” (it was written a full ten years earlier) and interpreted—without
regard for the fact that in <hi rend="i">Wilhelm Meister’s Apprenticeship</hi> it is a narratively
functional expression of Mignon’s longing for Italy and the home from which she was abducted as a young
child—as presenting “an Italian journey whose projected goal is a classical Eden, a comforting shelter for
the nostalgic self” (87).</p>
          <p>Chapters 5 through 7 (and a very brief conclusory 8) identify many features common to 
<hi rend="i">Faust</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, but their central concern is the two poets’
“broader vision of self-transcendence” and how the “emerging form of this vision is dictated by each
poet’s need to try to solve, in a more comprehensive way than was possible in the lyrical utterances we have
studied, the ever-growing problem posed by the power of psychological and ontological negation” (98). On 
<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> Bidney speaks with authoritative conviction; on <hi rend="i">Faust</hi> he is
generally convincing, although at times what might be regarded as the adduction of forced parallels between
these two texts seems to weaken an already well-made point. Thus Faust, Mephistopheles, Homunculus, and the
Eternal Feminine are said to be the counterparts of Luvah, Urizen, Tharmas, and Urthona and, “as the four
major characters in the respective poems,” to “have at their command innumerable attendant (or rebellious)
spirits” (99). But the Eternal Feminine—unlike Margarete and Helen of Troy—is not a character in 
<hi rend="i">Faust</hi>, and Homunculus, however important the ideas he embodies or symbolizes, merely appears as
an episodic figure in it, and neither he (himself a spirit) nor the Eternal Feminine (or even Margarete or
Helen) nor—normally—Faust ever deal with attendant spirits.</p>
          <p>Bidney is more persuasive when, as in chapter 6, “The Spirit of Negation: Selving and
Stasis,” instead of forcing an exact equation, he distinguishes between the kinds of negation represented by
Mephistopheles and Urizen, although even here he pre-dates the composition of <hi rend="i">Faust</hi>, vv.
1349-58, by over 20 years (123) to bolster (again unnecessarily) his point. Later in this same chapter his
forcing of parallels between “Mephistopheles-Faust and Urizen-Orc conflicts” similarly permits him to
assert that Faust dies racked by the problem of Worry and fear of the future—“in his fear of Becoming, he
mirrors the Devil”—although most readers of <hi rend="i">Faust</hi> agree that Faust courageously rejects
Worry (at the price of blindness) and dies confident (perhaps mistakenly) that he has at last achieved
something significant. (Bidney has anticipated this objection by observing that what is described in Faust’s
last words as a “daily battle for the right to live, fought against the daily threat of chaotic inundation
hardly sounds like paradise” and actually “resembles R. D. Laing’s portrait of the schizoid
individual” (134), and by claiming that the dying Faust “reveals . . . his obsession with permanence and
his fear of invasive flux, the twofold worry of his teacher Mephistopheles” (135). Faust has not, however,
bidden the Moment tarry, which <hi rend="i">would</hi> be a renunciation of flux and change and growth, nor
has Mephisto had any teacher-role for Faust after his Helen experience, having become at the drama’s end
hardly more than the mere servant of an ever more imperious Faust.)</p>
          <p>Bidney uses Night 7a of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and the Classical Walpurgisnight of 
<hi rend="i">Faust</hi> as the texts best showing how Blake and Goethe similarly indicate that if “Humanity is
to regain the authentic pulse of life, a Spirit of Mediation must counterbalance the Spirit of Negation”
(138). He correlates the “three distinct types of insight” attained by Urthona-Los with those experienced
in their quests by Faust, Mephisto, and Homunculus, the last of these exemplifying “the kind of
self-surrender”—here Bidney as it were corrects his Laingian interpretation of Faust as schizoid—“that
Faust will begin to show only in the final scene of the play.” He persuasively concludes that for Los and
Faust “the key to an imaginative ontology, to life in the eternal present, is finally revealed as loving
creativity, or creative love” (150). But then he weakens what seems to me a effective conclusion by
moralistically interpreting the tragic fate of Faust’s and Helen’s son Euphorion (act 3 of 
<hi rend="i">Faust II</hi>) as “an ironic reminder that in
<pb id="p24-101" n="101"/>
courting Helen, Faust was moving backward in time as misguidedly as his son later tried to move forward.” To
observe that “Rebellious Euphorion, overcompensating both ontologically and psychologically, seeks to
violate others and succeeds in killing himself” (155) is to state only a partial truth, since Euphorion’s
“killing himself” serves what, as the threnody on his Byronic death makes clear, we are to recognize as a
noble-humane cause, Greek Independence (the historical equivalent in <hi rend="i">Faust</hi> of the more
general good of mankind that as he dies Faust will believe he has furthered).</p>
          <p>To the extent that Goethe was a romantic thinker, as in his Storm and Stress years, or that his
ideas coincided with those of romantic contemporaries, Bidney’s observations in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> and
Goethe persuade one of their validity, especially since they are offered with scrupulous documentation and
scholarly accuracy. Exceptions to this last generalization are so few that in no way do they diminish his
book’s merits: (6.15 himself [<hi rend="i">for</hi> itself], 41.24 and 119.7 dumb [<hi rend="i">for</hi>
stupid, <hi rend="i">Ger.</hi> dumm], 43.30 sullen [<hi rend="i">for, probably</hi>, unenlightened, 
<hi rend="i">Ger.</hi> trübe], 60.33 un [<hi rend="i">for the Eng. article</hi> an], 95.39 the heart 
[<hi rend="i">for</hi> our heart], 96.29 enjoy [<hi rend="i">not the imperative</hi> Laßt, <hi rend="i">but</hi>
Läßt, can be enjoyed], 104.5 O to sink down [<hi rend="i">for</hi> O had I but sunk down], 104.21 Faust’s
relief [<hi rend="i">none at given point in Goethe’s text</hi>], 127.18 jealous [<hi rend="i">for</hi>
inconstant], 157.28 the good Lord [<hi rend="i">for</hi> a great—<hi rend="i">or</hi> fine—gentleman], and
158.27 Lusty Person [<hi rend="i">for</hi> Clown]). It might now be rewarding to compare Blake and Goethe as
artists as well as thinkers, although Goethe’s fondness for idealized realism and for the classics (in
contrast to Blake’s “it is the Classics . . . that Desolate Europe with Wars”), his limited respect for
Flaxman, and his lifelong love of landscape and landscape painting suggest that here might prove to be less
“spiritual kinship” between them in this area than in the areas that Bidney has so thoughtfully
examined.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
