<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>24.3.graver</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">New Voice on Blake</title>
        <author n="Graver">Bruce E. Graver</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1990/1991</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1990/91</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">24.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stuart Atkins</name>
              <name>Lisa Plummer Crafton</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Bruce E. Graver</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Edward Larrissy</name>
              <name>John Mee</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1990/1991"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_24">
    <body>
      <pb id="p24-91" n="91"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-24-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">New Voice on Blake</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Bruce E. <name>Graver</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>In editing Wordsworth’s Chaucer modernizations for the Cornell Wordsworth, I came across a
manuscript containing a significant piece of Blake criticism.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n63" type="note">*</ref>
	<note id="n63">Research for this paper was made possible by grants from the American Council of Learned
Societies and the National Endowment for the Humanities. I am grateful to both for their assistance. I am also
grateful to Jonathan Wordsworth and the Trustees of the Wordsworth Trust for permission to quote from the Dove
Cottage Papers. Finally, I wish to thank Alexander Gourlay, Mark L. Reed, and Joseph Viscomi for their
generous advice, without which the paper could not have been written.</note> The manuscript is a fair copy
review of <hi rend="i">Chaucer Modernized</hi>, 20 pages long, clearly ready for publication but apparently
never published; it is preserved in the Wordsworth Library, boxed with Wordsworth’s other papers having to
do with Thomas Powell and the <hi rend="i">Chaucer Modernized</hi> volume. <hi rend="i">Chaucer
Modernized</hi> itself, published late in 1840, was a volume of modernizations of Chaucer’s verse organized
and edited by Powell and R. H. Horne, and containing contributions from such authors as Leigh Hunt and
Elizabeth Barrett. It included two works of Wordsworth: his version of the pseudoChaucerian “Cuckoo and the
Nightingale,” and his extract from <hi rend="i">Troilus and Criseyde.</hi></p>
          <p>The author of the manuscript review is a person of sound literary judgment, who possesses a
thorough knowledge of Middle English and has read carefully the commentary in Tyrrwhitt’s edition of
Chaucer’s poems. We can surmise that he is a lawyer, for besides references to Blackstone’s 
<hi rend="i">Commentaries</hi> and trade and tariff regulations, he draws on an extensive knowledge of English law
and the organization of the Inns of Court to illuminate several passages of Chaucer’s verse. It is also
significant that he claims to know Wordsworth personally. He disapproves of the <hi rend="i">Chaucer
Modernized</hi> project, but directs his opprobrium at the contributions of Horne and Powell, not at
Wordsworth himself. Horne, the reviewer writes, “cannot even construe old poetry, still less paraphrase
it.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n26" type="note">1</ref> And he considers Powell even
less competent. For Wordsworth’s contributions, he has the highest praise. He urges him to complete his
version of <hi rend="i">Troilus</hi>: “It will be an amusement to his honored age, feeble only in eyesight,
to dictate his translation to his amiable lady.” And of “The Cuckoo and the Nightingale,” he writes:
“We bow to the Master! We only wish he had reserved it for his own next volume of Poems, and not buried it
in this dunghill.” <note id="n26"><hi rend="s">1</hi> An amusing account of Horne’s difficulties in
translating Chaucer may be found in Ann Blainey, <hi rend="i">The Farthing Poet: A Biography of Richard
Hengist Horne, 1802-1884, A Lesser Literary Lion</hi> (London: Longman’s, 1968) 115.</note></p>
          <p>At the very end of the review, after discussing each contributor’s efforts, the reviewer turns,
as if out of the blue, to the subject of William Blake.
<q>
Have any of our readers ever seen the print of the Canterbury pilgrims by William Blake, the mad artist, whose
biography may be read in Mr. Allan Cunningham’s Lives? He painted it, he says, before Mr. Stothard’s
picture on the same subject, and nearly thirty years ago he exhibited it publicly, in opposition to that
elegant composition. Mr. Stothard’s picture is <hi rend="i">Chaucer Modernized</hi>—the horses all barbs,
from the Elgin Marbles, and the riders, refined and softened, in stage-dresses. Mr. Blake’s picture is
Chaucer in the old rough verse—“in his habit as he lived”—bad in drawing, but true and vivid in
expression. His horses are wooden toys, and his dogs pigs; but the individual character is in every human
face, and look and dress. Mr. Blake understood Chaucer, like Mr. Wordsworth, profoundly. Mr. Stothard read him
like Mr. Horne, superficially. Together with his Exhibition, Mr. Blake gave you, for your shilling, a printed
description of his Picture, in contrast with Mr. Stothard’s. This contained a little madness about painting,
and a great deal of abuse of Mr. Stothard; but it was prefaced by some Observations on Chaucer’s Poem, of so
striking and original a kind, that, as the pamphlet is now as good as MS. (few people being in the habit of
preserving their Exhibition Catalogues) we shall conclude this article by quoting them:
</q>
At this point, the reviewer indicates, by writing “the characters—happy”, that he wishes to include a
lengthy quotation from Blake’s <hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>—the entire description of the
Canterbury Pilgrims, beginning on page 9 of the catalogue and ending on page 25. The review ends with this
remark: “Poor William Blake! He was certainly a man of a genius kindred to that of Chaucer.”</p>
          <p>This passage is remarkable not so much for the information it conveys—most of that is derived
from Allan Cunningham’s biography of Blake—as for the reviewer’s lively interest in Blake and rare
appreciation of his critical acumen. Although he accepts the usual characterization of Blake as a “mad
artist,” he is not interested in perpetuating what Bentley calls “titillating rumors of the mad
painter’s visions,” as was the rule among contemporary literary journalists.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">2</ref> Rather, he expresses admiration for Blake’s understanding
and champions his interpretation of Chaucer. In quoting at tremendous length from the <hi rend="i">Descriptive
Catalogue</hi> (which, along with a copy of Blake’s “Canterbury Pilgrims,” he apparently owned), he
effectively sets Blake up as the interpreter of Chaucer that Horne was not. Also noteworthy is the analogy he
draws between the roughness of Blake’s drawing and the roughness of Wordsworth’s deliberately archaic
modernizations. He considers their rough crudeness truer to the genius of Chaucer than the “softened stage
dresses” of Stothard on the one hand, and Horne on the other. Because of these remarkable opinions, the
identity of this reviewer should be of interest to scholars of Blake and Wordsworth alike. 
<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">2</hi> G.E. Bentley, ed., <hi rend="i">Blake: The Critical Heritage</hi> (London: Routledge &amp;
Kegan Paul, 1975) 220.</note></p>
          <p>The candidate that comes first to mind is Henry Crabb Robinson. Robinson, of course, knew both
Blake and Wordsworth, attended and wrote about Blake’s 1809-10 exhibition, owned four copies of the 
<hi rend="i">Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, one of which he gave to Charles Lamb, and purchased two copies of the
“Canterbury Pilgrims.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n28" type="note">3</ref> He was
also a lawyer. But the arguments against his authorship are substantial. First, the reviewer speaks of the
admission price to the 1809 exhibition as being one shilling. This is both inaccurate—the price was half a
crown (2s.6d)—and does not square with what Robinson himself wrote in his <hi rend="i">Reminiscences</hi>
ten years
<pb id="p24-92" n="92"/>
later: “a half crown was demanded of the Visitor for which he had also a Catalogue. . . .”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29" type="note">4</ref> Second, there is a problem with the spelling
of the name of Blake’s rival, Stothard. In his <hi rend="i">Reminiscences</hi>, Robinson spelled this name
inconsistently, either as Stodart or Stoddart. The reviewer, however, spells it correctly all five times.
Third, whereas the reviewer depends on Cunningham for his account of the Stothard incident, Robinson gives a
different version that is more sympathetic to Stothard, whom he calls “an amiable and excellent
man.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30" type="note">5</ref> Finally, and most
convincingly, the handwriting in the manuscript is not Robinson’s. The review itself may have been the work
of a copyist, but traces of the author’s handwriting survive; they are found on clippings from the 
<hi rend="i">Chaucer Modernized</hi> volume that have been pasted into the review. On these clippings, the author
has written pencil corrections of Horne and Powell’s translations. These corrections do not match
Robinson’s hand at all. <note id="n28"><hi rend="s">3</hi> See Robinson’s <hi rend="i">Reminiscence</hi>
of Blake in G.E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1969) 537-38.</note>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 537.</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 537-38.</note></p>
          <p>Crabb Robinson’s diaries help to reveal the reviewer’s identity. On 8 January 1828, Robinson
records a visit he made to Blake’s widow in the company of Barron Field, a lawyer and a correspondent of
Wordsworth.
<q>
Walked with Field to M<hi rend="s">rs</hi> Blake The poor old lady was more affected than I exp<hi
rend="s">d</hi> yet she spoke of her husband as dying like an angel. She is the housekeeper of Linnell the
painter &amp; engraver—And at present her Services must well pay for her board—A few of her husbands works
are all her property—We found that Job is Linnells property and the print of Chaucers pilgrimage
hers—Therefore Field bought a proof and I two prints—@ 2- guas each—I mean one for Lamb<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 362.</note></q>
This means that Field, like Robinson and Lamb, owned a copy of Blake’s “Canterbury Pilgrims,” which
makes him the only other person among Wordsworth’s acquaintance whom we know to have possessed one. And it
would have been natural for Robinson to give him a copy of the catalogue too, to go with the proof.</p>
          <p>Barron Field’s character and circle of acquaintance are in accord with the profile I have
suggested for the author. Field, a lawyer, had published an analysis of Blackstone’s 
<hi rend="i">Commentaries</hi> in 1811, and as Chief Justice of Gibraltar until 1841, would have been familiar
with the kinds of trade and tariff regulations discussed in the review. Moreover, Field had long been
associated with major literary figures. He was a schoolmate of Leigh Hunt at Christ’s Church Hospital, and
as a young man wrote reviews for Hunt’s <hi rend="i">Reflector</hi> and published poems in the 
<hi rend="i">Examiner.</hi> Field met Wordsworth as early as 1812, and Robinson and Lamb were lifelong
<figure n="letter.WordsworthTrust.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="708">
	<head>Courtesy of the Wordsworth Trust, Dove Cottage, Grasmere.</head>
</figure>
friends.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">7</ref> In fact, he is mentioned in
two of the Elia essays, including “Distant Correspondents,” which is addressed entirely to Field, who was
then living in Australia. His friendship with Lamb is especially significant because he echoes Lamb’s
opinion about Blake’s Chaucer criticism: “Lamb,” recalled Robinson, “. . . declared that Blake’s
description [of the Canterbury pilgrims] was the finest criticism he had ever read of Chaucer’s
poem.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">8</ref> Wordsworthians know Field
primarily as the author of a memoir of the poet, completed in 1840 but not published because of Wordsworth’s
objections, and there survives a series of letters between the two, in which
<pb id="p24-93" n="93"/>
Field criticized the ways Wordsworth had revised his poems and urged him (often successfully) to change them
back. Field, in fact, kept an annotated copy of Wordsworth’s collected poems, in which he recorded all of
the poet’s alterations in the published versions of his poetry,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n34" type="note">9</ref> and he joked with Wordsworth about having “the honour to be your Editor.
‘The <hi rend="i">fifteenth</hi> Edition, with Notes by Barron Field.’”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">10</ref> Furthermore, a comparison of handwritings confirms Field’s
authorship. <note id="n32"><hi rend="s">7</hi> See Geoffrey Little’s biographical introduction to his
edition of Field’s <hi rend="i">Memoirs of Wordsworth</hi> (Sydney: Sydney UP, 1975) 7-17.</note>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 538.</note>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">9</hi> This copy can be found in the Wordsworth Library in Grasmere.</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Barron Field to Wordsworth, 10 April 1828, published in Little 133. The
manuscript is in the Wordsworth Library.</note></p>
          <p>Fortunately, we can trace Field’s interest in the <hi rend="i">Chaucer Modernized</hi> volume
with some exactness. In the early months of 1840, shortly after completing his memoir of Wordsworth, Field
visited England and called at Rydal Mount. No doubt the main subject discussed during the visit was the
memoir, whose publication Wordsworth had resisted. But Wordsworth was also preparing to publish his
modernizations of Chaucer in Horne and Powell’s volume and had a long discussion with Field about doing so.
In a paragraph added to the memoir after 1841, Field tells how
<q>
the Poet . . . read to me . . . his Lines of hearing the Cuckoo at the Monastery of San Francisco d’Assisi,
and his modernization of Chaucer’s Cuckow &amp; Nightingale. . . . [I]n illustration of the latter he
referred to the part the Crow plays in the Manciple’s Tale, and praised the father-poet’s dramatic skill
and courage, in making the Manciple, whose only object in life was to be a trusty domestic, draw this moral
alone from the story:—<lb/>
<lb/>
My sone, beware, and be non auctour newe<lb/>
Of tidings, whether they ben false or trewe:<lb/>
Wher so thou come, amonges high or lowe,<lb/>
Kepe well thy tonge, and thinke upon the Crowe<lb/>
<lb/>
He wished that the delicacy of modern ears would allow him to translate the whole of this Tale, and dwelt with
rapture upon the remorse of Phoebus for having slain his adulterous wife. . . .
</q>
Field then tells how Wordsworth “threw his Cuckow and Nightingale into a bad collection of pieces entitled
‘<hi rend="i">Chaucer Modernized.</hi>’”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n36"
type="note">11</ref> These remarks correspond closely to two passages in the review. In the first paragraph,
Field writes that “Mr. Wordsworth . . . is so warm an admirer of [“The Manciple’s Tale”], that we have
heard him lament the impossibility of translating the whole.” Then, at the end of his discussion of Leigh
Hunt’s “emasculated” version of the tale, we find the following:
<q>
[T]he Tale is well done, with a proper sense of what we once heard Mr. Wordsworth call the great poet’s
dramatic skill and courage, in making the Manciple, whose only object in life was to be a trusty domestic,
draw this moral alone from the Tale, passing by all the crime, rashness &amp; misery of the tragedy, as if
they were things that would happen in the best-regulated families, and that servants should see all and say
nothing.
</q>
What Field seems not to have known, or perhaps to have suppressed, is that Wordsworth <hi rend="i">had</hi>
modernized “The Manciple’s Tale,” and had originally offered it to Thomas Powell for publication in 
<hi rend="i">Chaucer Modernized.</hi> He withdrew the offer, however, after family and friends complained about
the tale’s bawdiness.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n37" type="note">12</ref> In any case,
it is clear that Field was interested in this project, and in Wordsworth’s questionable alliance with Horne
and Powell, well before the volume was published. His review may even have been written as a kind of public
reminder to Wordsworth to be more selective in his literary associations.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n38" type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Little 49.</note>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Wordsworth initially offered “The Manciple’s Tale” to Powell in a
letter dated “[late 1839]” by Alan Hill. Objections were raised by Edward Quillinan and, perhaps, Isabella
Fenwick, and in a letter of 1 May 1840, Wordsworth withdrew his offer. See <hi rend="i">The Letters of William
and Dorothy Wordsworth</hi>, ed. Alan Hill, 7 vols. (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1982) 6: 755-56, 7: 35, 39,
71.</note>
	<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Field’s suspicions of Powell were later borne out in ways he could not
have predicted. Powell was discovered to have supported himself by embezzlement and forgery; he faked insanity
to avoid prison, and spent the rest of his days in New York. See Blainey 114.</note></p>
          <p>Two problems remain. First, why was the review never published? Second, why was Field so
interested in promoting Blake’s reputation that he would drag him by the heels into a review like this? And
about both problems we can only speculate. <hi rend="i">Chaucer Modernized</hi> appeared in time for the
Christmas trade in 1840 and was reviewed in three periodicals: <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi>, on 5
January, <hi rend="i">The Athaenum</hi>, on 6 February, and <hi rend="i">Church of England Quarterly
Review</hi> in April.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">14</ref> The first and
third of these reviews were favorable, although J. A. Grimes in <hi rend="i">Monthly Magazine</hi> points out
several errors in Horne’s translation of the “General Prologue.” But Henry Chorley in the 
<hi rend="i">Athaenum</hi>, although kind to Wordsworth and Hunt, called Horne’s efforts a “counterfeit
presentment,” called attention to several of the same faulty passages that Field did, and complained that
“Father Chaucer [has been] reduced to sickly weakness and effeminacy.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n40" type="note">15</ref> Field himself was not in England at this time: he was in
Gibraltar until autumn, then returned to England to take up permanent residence for the first time in over a
decade.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41" type="note">16</ref> He may have written the
review abroad, but probably wrote it after his return, and it is likely that publishers considered it somewhat
repetitive and rather old news. Deprived of a public forum, Field may then have given the review to
Wordsworth, as both a token of appreciation and as a quiet reminder about 
<corr type="emend">associating</corr> himself with dubious literary enterprises.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n42" type="note">17</ref> But since the manuscript, which is still in its original
blue cover, lacks a presentation autograph, it seems unlikely that Wordsworth ever saw it. Probably the review
found its way into the Dove Cottage Papers sometime after Field’s death in 1846.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43" type="note">18</ref>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">14</hi> These reviews are all listed in N. S. Bauer, <hi rend="i">William
Wordsworth: A Reference Guide to British Criticism, 1793-1899</hi> (Boston: G. K. Hall, 1978) 133-35.</note>
	<note id="n40"><hi rend="s">15</hi><hi rend="i"> The Athaenum</hi> (6 February 1841): 107-08. Blainey 105,
115, notes that Chorley was a perennial enemy of Horne.</note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Little 51.</note>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">17</hi> Field had the opportunity to give Wordsworth the review (providing he had
finished it by then) in September 1841 when he spent time in the Lake District (Little 51). Field also tells
of helping Wordsworth write an article on Talfourd’s copyright bill at this time.</note>
	<note id="n43"><hi rend="s">18</hi> Shortly after Wordsworth’s death, as materials for Christopher
Wordsworth, Jr.’s memoir of the poet were being collected, there was correspondence between Robinson and
Edward Quillinan about Barron Field’s papers. It seems possible that Robinson or Edward Quillinan may have
had access to them, so perhaps at that time the review passed into the hands of the Wordsworth family. See 
<hi rend="i">The Correspondence of Henry Crabb Robinson with the Wordsworth Circle</hi>, ed. Edith Morley, 2 vols.
(Oxford: Clarendon P, 1927) 2: 738-39.</note></p>
          <p>Why Field should go so far out of his way to call our attention to Blake is an even more
intriguing question. Field did not attend the 1809 Blake exhibition—he apparently had never heard of Blake
before 1813—so unlike Crabb Robinson he would not have seen the original painting of the Canterbury
Pilgrims, nor any of the other impressive artworks on display.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n44" type="note">19</ref> Nor did Field, to our knowledge, ever meet Blake; his only direct contact
seems to have been with Catherine Blake in 1828. Yet the print and catalogue he owned, his reading of
Cunningham’s biography, and his conversations about Blake with Robinson and Lamb impressed him
<pb id="p24-94" n="94"/>
deeply. Field’s review thus serves to underscore how often Blake was a subject of discussion among members
of the Wordsworth circle, and how much we owe to figures like Charles Lamb and Henry Crabb Robinson for
helping to preserve the reputation of William Blake. 
                        <note id="n44"><hi rend="s">19</hi> According to Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake
Records</hi> 231, “Crabb Robinson wrote in his Diary for Tuesday, January 12th, 1813: ‘In the Eveng at
Coleridge’s lecture. And then at home. Mrs. Kenny[,] Barnes &amp; Barron Field there—The usual gossiping
chat—F &amp; B. both interested by Blake’s poems of whom they knew nothing before[.]—’”</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
