<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>24.3.groves</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">John Clerk, Esq.</title>
        <author n="Groves">David Groves</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1990/1991</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1990/91</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">24.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stuart Atkins</name>
              <name>Lisa Plummer Crafton</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Bruce E. Graver</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Edward Larrissy</name>
              <name>John Mee</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1990/1991"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_24">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-24-3-0006">
		<pb id="p24-94" n="94"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">John Clerk, Esq.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>David <name>Groves</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>In Robert Cromek’s 1808 edition of Robert Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>, with designs by
Blake, the name of “John Clerk, Esq.” appears in the list of sixteen Edinburgh subscribers to the
volume.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">1</ref> No Blake scholar has yet
identified this intriguing figure, or discussed his wide influence in artistic, literary, and social circles.
Perhaps none of Blake’s first readers were as paradoxical, irascible, immoral, or influential as John Clerk.
Clerk (1757-1832) is now such a forgotten figure, however, that few if any modern readers will know of
him.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">2</ref> In his time, Clerk was famous as
an Edinburgh lawyer and judge, and an art collector. <note id="n45"><hi rend="s">1</hi> See Robert N. Essick
and Morton D. Paley, <hi rend="i">Robert Blair’s</hi> The Grave, <hi rend="i">Illustrated by William Blake;
A Study with Facsimile</hi> (London: Scolar, 1982). The list of subscribers is unpaginated.</note>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Clerk receives a brief mention in the <hi rend="i">Dictionary of National
Biography</hi>; his name does not seem to appear in any other twentieth-century work.</note></p>
          <p>It was almost certainly Blake’s designs, rather than Blair’s poem, which led the 50-year-old
lawyer to subscribe to <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi> Clerk had studied as an artist in his youth. He had little
interest in poetry, but for many years he continued to paint and draw in his spare moments. Several of his
drawings appeared in the <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine</hi>, and elsewhere.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">3</ref> Presumably Clerk found pleasure in Blake’s designs to 
<hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>; in any event, the book was still in his library when he died.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">3</hi> The last of Clerk’s drawings for the <hi rend="i">Scots Magazine.</hi>
“Craig Crook Castle,” was “Engraved by R[obert] Scott,” and appeared as the frontispiece in April 1810
[n.p.]); for information on Robert Scott, the engraver with a “mania for Blake,” who considered the 1808
<hi rend="i">Grave</hi> to be one of the “two greatest books” in his library, see 
<hi rend="i">Autobiographical Notes of the Life of William Bell Scott</hi>, ed. W. Minto, 2 vols. (London: Osgood,
McIlvaine, 1892) 1: 68, and my note on “Blake, <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, and Edinburgh Literary
Society” in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 24 (1990): 35-36. A satirical sketch by John Clerk, “The Three Legal
Devotees,” may be found in John Kay, <hi rend="i">A Series of Original Portraits and Caricature
Etchings</hi>, ed. H. Paton, 2 vols. (Edinburgh: Black, 1877) 1: plate 119 (attributed to Clerk in the text,
2: 439-40). In suggesting that Clerk “had little interest in poetry,” I have relied on the evidence of the
<hi rend="i">Catalogue</hi> of his library, cited in note 4 below.</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">4</hi> See anon., <hi rend="i">Catalogue of the Library of the Late John Clerk of
Eldin . . . which will be sold by Auction, by Mr C. B. Tait, . . . On Monday, January 21 1833, and Nine
following Days</hi> (Edinburgh: Tait, 1833) 56. Item 1382 in the catalogue is described as “Blake’s
Illustration [sic] of Blair’s Grave, 13 <hi rend="i">plates, engraved by Schiavonetti.</hi>” In addition
to listing the books in Clerk’s library, this catalogue shows that he possessed many original paintings and
drawings attributed to Rembrandt, Holbein, Van Dyck, Rubens, Correggio, Salvator Rosa, Breughel, Titian,
Tintoretto, Raeburn, and others. It is not known who purchased Clerk’s copy of <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>,
or what price it fetched.</note></p>
          <p>With a personality like “crystallised vinegar,” Clerk was notorious for his atheism,
self-righteousness, and “drollery”: “It was impossible that he could be wrong because he acknowledged no
judge in heaven or earth but John Clerk.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49"
type="note">5</ref> Something of his legendary abrasiveness may be gauged from an episode involving his friend
Henry Raeburn the painter, when they were both students:
<pb id="p24-95" n="95"/>
<q>
One day John [Clerk] asked [Raeburn] to go and dine with him in his garret [above Parliament Square in
Edinburgh]; On going into his room the landlady came in and put on the table John’s ordinary dinner—four
herrings and three potatoes—John got up in a terrible rage and chucked the two plates out of the window and
turned about to the astonished landlady and said What for ye bitch did ye no bring aucht herrings and sax
tawties . . .<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">5</hi> John Heiton, <hi rend="i">The Castes of Edinburgh</hi>, 3rd. ed.
(Edinburgh: Nimmo, 1861) 56. 57, 57n. Only the third edition of Heiton’s book contains these (and many
other) stories about Clerk.</note>
	<note id="n50"><hi rend="s">6</hi> James White, citing his conversation with Raeburn, in a letter to Allan
Cunningham, 29 March 1831, National Library of Scotland MS 832, ff 28-29; cited by permission of the Trustees
of the NLS. “Aucht” and “sax” are Scots terms for “eight” and “six.” This excerpt has not
previously appeared in print; Cunningham gives a drastically bowdlerized version in his <hi rend="i">Lives of
the Most Eminent British Painters</hi> (5: 210). I have included this quotation partly to show that Clerk
adhered to Scottish ways and the Scots language; he was not Anglicized. Clerk’s lodgings above Parliament
Square would have placed him near the center of Edinburgh’s legal and literary establishment.</note></q>
In later years, Clerk was wealthy and titled; he became “Lord Eldin,” and a judge, in 1823. Although a
bachelor, he had several children by different women. Once, accosted by two laborers who demanded money on the
grounds that he was their father, Clerk “grinningly drew out his purse” and said, “Weel, there’s five
pounds’ and never let me see your ugly mugs again.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n51"
type="note">7</ref>
	<note id="n51"><hi rend="s">7</hi> The two men’s mothers were sisters; “The reader has only to count the
kin,” comments Heiton, “to understand the morality of [Clerk], who was received into the best society”
(Heiton 57n).</note></p>
          <p>Despite his arrogance towards women, children, and the lower classes, Clerk was a prominent
reform politician. He was a friend of the critic and politician Francis Jeffrey, and sometimes joined Jeffrey
in public demonstrations.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52" type="note">8</ref> But he was
far removed from the sober rationalism of Jeffrey and his circle. All reports agree that Clerk’s temper and
emotionality rendered him “not qualified for the duties of a judge.” Even after his promotion to the
bench, Clerk led a scandalous, “Rabelaisian” existence, sometimes “riding down openly in his carriage to
his mistress . . . or sitting carousing with the thief Maccoul.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n53" type="note">9</ref>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">8</hi> For information on Clerk’s political and literary connections, see Henry
Cockburn, <hi rend="i">Memorials of his Time</hi> (Edinburgh: Black, 1856) 407-08, and John Gibson Lockhart,
<hi rend="i">Peter’s Letters to his Kinsfolk</hi>, 3 vols. (Edinburgh: Blackwood, 1819) 2: 43-52. For an
account of a Reform meeting at which Francis Jeffrey and John Clerk shared the stage, see anon.,
“Celebration of Mr Fox’s Birth Day,” <hi rend="i">The Scotsman</hi> 15 Jan. 1823: 33-36.</note>
	<note id="n53"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Heiton 57-58, <hi rend="i">passim.</hi> I have not been able to identify
“the thief Maccoul.”</note></p>
          <p>Clerk’s judgments in court became increasingly erratic, until public outrage forced his
resignation in 1828. His final years were shrouded by some unnamed disease. He became “ungovernably
insane”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n54" type="note">10</ref> and “quite
imbecile.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n55" type="note">11</ref> Perhaps, in his last
lucid moments, John Clerk reflected on the theme of Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>, and its accompanying
designs by Blake. <note id="n54"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Robert P. Gillies, <hi rend="i">Recollections of Sir
Walter Scott, Bart.</hi> (London: Fraser, 1837) 284. Gillies is citing his conversation with Scott at
Abbotsford in 1829.</note>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">11</hi> George Thomson, letter to the painter Thomas Stothard, 7 July 1832,
National Library of Scotland MS 685, f 88; cited by permission.</note></p>
          <p>Admittedly these details tell us nothing about William Blake. But they may help readers to
appreciate the diversity of Blake’s original audience, and to perceive more fully the social context in
which Blake sold his work. They may also counteract slightly the common assumption that Blake’s work
received little attention in contemporary Scotland.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
