<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>24.3.larrissy</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">David W. Lindsay, ed., Blake: Songs of Innocence and [of] Experience; Robert F. 
Gleckner and Mark L. Greenberg, eds., Approaches to Teaching Blake’s Songs of Innocence and of Experience</title>
        <author n="Larrissy">Edward Larrissy</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1990/1991</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1990/91</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">24.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stuart Atkins</name>
              <name>Lisa Plummer Crafton</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Bruce E. Graver</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Michael Fischer</name>
              <name>Edward Larrissy</name>
              <name>John Mee</name>
              <name>Brian Wilkie</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1990/1991"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_24">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-24-3-0007">
		<pb id="p24-101" n="101"/>
        <div2>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">David W. Lindsay, ed. <hi rend="i">Blake: Songs of Innocence and
Experience.</hi> The Critics Debate Series. General editor, Michael Scott. Basingstoke: Macmillan and Atlantic
Highlands, NJ: Humanities, 1989. 92 pp. £18.50 cloth/ £4.95 paper; $29.95/ $8.50.</title>
          </head>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Robert F. Gleckner and Mark L. Greenberg, eds. <hi rend="i">Approaches to
Teaching Blake’s</hi> Songs of Innocence and of Experience. Approaches to Teaching World Literature 21.
Series editor Joseph Gibaldi. New York: Modern Language Association of America, 1989. $32.00 cloth/ $17.50
paper.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Edward <name>Larrissy</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>David Lindsay’s book is part of a series the aim of which is to introduce students to “a
variety of critical approaches to specific texts.” He pursues that aim with lucidity, impartiality,
and method. The book is divided into two halves: the first is a survey of critical approaches; the second,
called “Appraisal,” in fact “traces the evolution of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and Experience</hi>
[sic] in the context of Blake’s other writings and gives closer attention to eight poems.”</p>
          <p>The survey first defines the text, discussing the different editions. It goes
<pb id="p24-102" n="102"/>
on to look at literary and artistic antecedents of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, bringing in (according to the
brief) the ways in which knowledge of these has modified critics’ responses. The fact of the 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi> being an illuminated text is then broached, and we encounter important interpretations of
visual motifs, including some from such critics as Keynes, Erdman, and Mitchell. The ideas of the dramatic
lyric, and of an occasionally ironic use of the represented speaker, are introduced, and then Lindsay adopts
the useful ruse of using “The Chimney Sweeper” as a peg on which to hang typical reactions to Blake,
because it exemplifies so many of the complexities of the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, both in its strategies and
in its allusions. The discussion then moves on to the relationship between the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> and
Blake’s “system,” glancing at the opposed implications of Frye and Hirsch. It also looks at paired poems
(“Counterparts”), at speakers in <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>, and at the symbolism of flowers.</p>
          <p>The second part, “Appraisal,” has much less to do with “the critics”: hardly anything, in
fact. It is Lindsay’s learned and astute introduction to the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>, looking at eight poems
chiefly in the light of Blake’s other work. The readings are tactful, and responsive to many different
contexts, although the allusions to Blake’s prophetic books suffer from a brevity imposed by the format of
the series. In this respect they share their suffering with some previous sections of the book. There are
occasions when one wonders if a student will be able easily to digest the various buffet of critical
approaches so briskly served up. But this is not always a problem, chiefly because of Lindsay’s wise
decision to be selective in his choice of songs. This will be a useful book to students who do not succumb to
the temptation to make it a substitute for wider reading, not least because it suggests the value of many
different approaches to so subtle and rich an author. It may, however, be a pity that the approaches of Hazard
Adams and David Wagenknecht do not receive a mention here.</p>
          <p>Gleckner and Greenberg’s book is aimed at teachers rather than students, and this aim does
control most of the essays in it. As well as providing instances of approaches to Blake, then, they are very
much the records of instructors on how they go about teaching the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> in the class. I
found this emphasis of the book fascinating and helpful. W. J. T. Mitchell is useful on ways of talking about
the “composite text,” as one would expect. David Simpson, in “Teaching Ideology in 
<hi rend="i">Songs</hi>” follows almost precisely my own way of raising questions about “The Chimney
Sweeper,” referring to Erdman, “false consciousness,” Glen, Raine, and the “corporeal” soot from
Swedenborg. Joseph Viscomi recounts a most interesting method he uses of asking classes to copy designs from
Blake plates. This has at least the merit of focusing attention on the facts of a given design (an important
consideration in itself) as well as on the materiality of Blake’s production methods. But most of the
approaches treated here could yield something of value to most teachers. The editors have included an
extraordinarily full reasoned bibliography to the essays.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
