<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>24.4.murray</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Stanley Kunitz, ed., The Essential Blake; Michael Mason, ed., William Blake; 
David Punter, ed., William Blake: Selected Poetry and Prose</title>
        <author n="Murray">E. B. Murray</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Spring 1991</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1991</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">24.4</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert D. Denham</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Wallace Jackson</name>
              <name>E.B. Murray</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Paulette Roeske</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1991"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_24">
    <body>
      <pb id="p24-145" n="145"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-24-4-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Stanley Kunitz, ed. <hi rend="i">The Essential Blake.</hi> New York: The Ecco
Press, 1987. 92 pp. $5.00 paper; Michael Mason, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> Oxford: Oxford University
Press, 1988. xxvi + 601 pp. $45.00 cloth/$15.95 paper; David Punter, ed. <hi rend="i">William Blake: Selected
Poetry and Prose.</hi> London/New York: Routledge, 1988. ix + 283 pp. $9.95 paper.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>E. B. <name>Murray</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>Volume 4 of Ecco Press’s <hi rend="i">The Essential Poets</hi> series, <hi rend="i">The
Essential Blake</hi>, may be conveniently slipped into your hip-pocket, brought to the pub, read on the
subway, or on the toilet and may as well be flushed down the drain afterwards if a trace of scholarly
substance is what you demand in the Blake texts you keep around. Its unannotated contents, so far as they go,
are something less than those you’d find in a survey course anthology—<hi rend="i">The Songs of Innocence,
The Songs of Experience, Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, “Auguries of Innocence,”—but no 
<hi rend="i">Thel, Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, or <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>,—whose space is perhaps
taken up by a “Miscellany” of gnomic verses, epigrams, and letter excerpts. A most unpretentious booklet,
meant for the literate among <hi rend="i">hoi polloi</hi>, with a poet to provide an essential biographical
sketch and a few uninspired generalities by way of essential evaluation. All in all, a harmless little
pot-boiler.</p>
          <p>Not so the Oxford Authors and Routledge Blakes. They do have some pretensions and they may not be
altogether harmless. Michael Mason is initially concerned with telling us what he does not do in his edition.
He does not include <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon, The Book of Ahania</hi>, or <hi rend="i">The Four
Zoas.</hi> He does not follow a chronological order in presenting Blake’s texts; he does not provide deleted
or alternative readings; he does not provide the illuminations or describe them; he does not summarize the
content of Blake’s works nor does he explicate Blake’s mythology. Most of the rest of this part of his
introduction is concerned with justifying what he has not done. For example, he does not provide the
illuminations because “the enhancement of our reading of Blake which was expected to flow from attention to
his illustrations has simply not occurred.” So much for the majority of the present generation of Blake
scholars and teachers who have in fact spent much time and trouble trying to enhance their readings of Blake
by attending to his illuminations and who have subsequently beguiled themselves into believing they’ve had
some solid success in their attempts. But Mason knows how to put these bemused and errant souls in their
place. They are implicitly aligned with the “[e]ditors [who] have fallen into the habit of transcribing what
Blake crossed out,” who are either “protective Blake experts” insisting, as Blake did not, that the
illuminations are an integral part of the text they accompany or “[s]tudents of Blake . . . too ready to
assume that his mythology is a well-formed system,” and who therefore work up “drab paraphrases” to fit
Blake into the Procrustean limitations of their own inferably drab understandings. Mason, a veritable Daniel
come to judgment or an editorial David defiant against these overspecialized “giant forms,” will let Blake
speak for himself—sans illuminations and alternative readings of course.</p>
          <p>As we know, and contrary to Mason’s implications, Blake felt his illuminations an integral part
of his composite art, going so far as to applaud himself (in the third person) for having invented “a method
of Printing which combines the Painter and Poet” and, in an earlier self-evaluation, he bluntly asserts,
through a persona, that those (<hi rend="i">pace</hi> Mason) who will not accept and pay highly for the
illuminated writings he projected “will be ignorant fools and will not deserve to live.” <hi rend="i">Ipse
dixit.</hi> The poet/artist is typically seconded by his twentieth-century editors, who, even when obliged to
omit the illuminations, argue for their necessary relevance. Max Plowman, in his 1927 
<hi rend="i">Everyman’s Library</hi> edition, has the humilty and good sense to note the “insuperable
difficulty in the way of a transcript version” when “there is alternation between words that expand the
meaning of a design, and designs that give to the words their complete significance” (xxv). Vivian de Sola
Pinto (<hi rend="i">William Blake</hi>, 1965) states that the “text and illustrations form a single
integrated whole,” that part of the effect of the lyrics in <hi rend="i">The Songs of Innocence and of
Experience</hi> “is lost when they are read in ordinary print without the designs,” and that in 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> “the
<figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
<pb id="p24-146" n="146"/>
pictures are not ‘illustrations’ but essential and organic parts of the structure” (17, 52). As Thomas
Frosch noted in reviewing the most discriminating work on the subject, W. J. T Mitchell’s 
<hi rend="i">Blake’s Composite Art: A Study of the Illuminated Poetry</hi>, the author not only contends that
“each illuminated poem is an organic unit and develops its own particular relationship of text and design”
but in specific instances “indisputably shows that text and design together create signification that
can’t be gained from either by itself” (<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 13 [1979]: 40, 41). But readers tempted to
accept Mason’s assertion at face value need only riffle through the pages of this quarterly and check out
its annual bibliography to infer a consensus refutation <hi rend="i">passim.</hi></p>
          <p>While Mason is justified in singling out for our special praise his most helpful “Index of
Names and Motifs” (not so original as he seems to think, though, since a roughly comparable and more
detailed precedent appeared in the 1926 OUP Sloss/Wallis edition), the most striking feature of his edition
will surely be his mixed chronological/generic/thematic division of Blake’s works under headings such as
“Blake on Religion and Knowledge,” “Blake on Art and Literature,” “Septenary Verse of the French
Revolutionary Period,” “The Lyrics,” and “The Los Poems.” He thus reorganizes the canon for the
benefit of readers who will be less “intimidated” by Blake’s mythological writings if they find them
mixed and matched with the lyrics according to arrangements which, Mason feels, will remind them “that the
Prophetic Books are by no means all of a piece.” Assuming the epics and the Lambeth poems are together
defined as Prophetic Books, we can see how this piecemeal arrangement is effected. “The Los Poems”
contains <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen, The Book of Los, Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi>
However, lyrics from these latter poems are taken out of their epic context to form a subgenre of their own
called, not surprisingly, “Lyrics from the Epic Poems.” For reasons both chronological and nominal, 
<hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> does not appear under that title at all but is rather divided into “Africa”
and “Asia” to so flank <hi rend="i">America</hi> and <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> under the “Septentary
Verse” heading (which also subsumes <hi rend="i">Tiriel, Thel, Visions</hi>, and of course <hi rend="i">The
French Revolution</hi>). Both genre and chronology are disrupted for thematic considerations which, for
example, place under the head of “Blake on Religion and Knowledge” many of Blake’s annotations, the 
<hi rend="i">Natural Religion</hi> propositions, <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, “Auguries of
Innocence,” <hi rend="i">The Everlasting Gospel</hi>, and the prefaces to chapters 2, 3, and 4 of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> The preface to chapter 1 appears with the preface to <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> under
the “Blake on Art and Literature” rubric, along with a few other annotations, eight letters, some of 
<hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalogue of Pictures</hi> and the comments on Homer and Virgil. <hi rend="i">The
Poetical Sketches</hi> also lose their integral identity and title when they move into the margins of
nonentity variously defined by “Early Visionary and Narrative Writings,” which contains most of them, and
“The Lyrics,” which contains nearly all of the poems with “Song” in their titles. Even given Mason’s
general disregard for chronology, there seems no reason why these two divisions should be separated as they
are by the “Septenary” inclusions, all of which are dated later than any of “The Lyrics” which follow
them.</p>
          <p>One may infer that Mason’s decision to refashion the canon so led him to omit <hi rend="i">The
Book of Ahania</hi> partly because it obviously follows on <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> but could not
be put into the “Los” poems because Los barely appears in it, and partly because Mason prefers to suppose
that the real sequel to <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> is <hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> Conversely, it’s reasonable to
suppose that <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi> could not be allowed its Blakean title, lest it seem to lay at
least a nominal claim for inclusion among the Los poems. A lesser but still bothersome effect of Mason’s
categorizing nomenclature is that the running heads, instead of advising the reader that he’s confronting a
page of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> or <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> or <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, keeps him
guessing what work it is he’s opened to at some indefinite point among “The Los Poems.” For the student
who reads as he runs, Blake’s titles are likely to be replaced in his memory by Mason’s categorical name
for them. Besides the prose already noted, the edition includes excerpts from <hi rend="i">Public Address, A
Vision of the Last Judgment</hi>, and the prose from <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches.</hi> Given what Mason
provides, his claim to have provided the prose with fuller annotation than other editors seems fairly made,
since others have tended to slight it.</p>
          <p>David Punter’s text follows the traditional chronological orderings. Its selections and
annotations are presumably geared to the Routledge English Texts’ stated purpose—“to meet the needs of
readers for whom the study of literature involves the study of its historical and critical contexts.” The
usual anthology pieces, along with <hi rend="i">Tiriel, America</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Song of Los</hi>,
are presented complete; but <hi rend="i">The French Revolution, Urizen</hi>, and “Auguries of Innocence,”
as well as the longer poems, appear only in extracts. <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> is omitted, as are 
<hi rend="i">The Book of Ahania</hi>, and <hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi>, prose selections include the 
<hi rend="i">Natural Religion</hi> propositions, excerpts from <hi rend="i">A Vision of the Last Judgment, A
Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, “On Homer’s Poetry,” and “On Virgil”; there are no letters.</p>
          <p>Assuming the historical bias of the edition, it might have seemed appropriate for 
<hi rend="i">The French Revolution</hi>, probably the most history-laden of Blake’s works, to have appeared
complete; and for the potential it might have provided for historical commentary, perhaps 
<hi rend="i">Europe</hi> is likewise a desideratum. The text is bookended by an introductory essay which seems
relatively forced into a style and content expressive of innocence for the innocent reader yet to
<pb id="p24-147" n="147"/>
engage the text, as it fulfills in a generalized and superficial fashion the editorial policy of providing
historical and literary contexts; and by a freeflowing epilogue essay on a higher and more organized plane
which apparently assumes that a world of experience has been gained by a reader who has gone through the
preceding text. Unfortunately, the essay assumes a knowledge of Blake which simply cannot be gained by the
selections as presented and abstracted from in this text. There is a refreshing honesty and due humility
(particularly refreshing to a reader who has just been through the first few pages of Mason’s introduction)
in Punter’s admission that the abstracting task which he is constricted to is a “near-impossible” one
because “nothing can give the flavor of [<hi rend="i">The Four Zoas, Milton</hi>, and 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>] but a full reading of at least one of them” and because they are “interwoven”
and because we must “build up some familiarity with the ‘characters’ before we can properly understand
what is happening.” Unlike Mason, Punter also notes that the relevant works should be consulted in their
illuminated form because “there are many cases where our notions of a specific poem’s meaning can be
radically altered by looking at the visual materials which not only accompany but frequently twine around and
thread through the written text.”</p>
          <p>While the two texts seem meant for different audiences, the practical fact is that they will
probably be in <corr type="emend">competition,</corr> along with other editions, for a good part of the same
audience, particularly since most, perhaps the great majority, of Blake readers will be in college classrooms.
To find out which of the two may be better as a teaching and reading text is therefore well worth doing,
though to do only that is to do less than enough. The best presently available text for teaching and reading
is, with a qualification or two, undoubtedly the Norton Critical Edition (<hi rend="i">Blake’s Poetry and
Designs</hi>, 1979) edited by Mary Lynn Johnson and John Grant. For those who require a complete text of 
<hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> (or miss <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi>), then David Erdman’s generally diplomatic edition
or Geoffrey Keynes’ perennially reprinted Oxford Standard Authors edition will be best.</p>
          <p>Having asserted my preferences, I’d like to back them by comparing the Mason (M) and Punter (P)
editions with each other and with Johnson/Grant (J/G), both in their respective treatments of the accidental
features of Blake’s illuminated works and in the quantity and quality of their annotations. As a kind of
“control” in accidental matters I’ll use Erdman’s latest edition of <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry
&amp; Prose of William Blake</hi> (E), which, along with G. E. Bentley, Jr.’s <hi rend="i">William Blake’s
Writings</hi>, does about as good a job as can reasonably be done of reproducing in print the pointing of the
illuminated works. As the traditional reading text since its first appearance, Keynes’s 
<hi rend="i">Complete Writings</hi>(K) may also serve as a standard of modernization in a reading text, since,
along with J/G, it comes closest to observing what should probably be an editor’s golden rule of thumb: if
it works, don’t fix it.</p>
          <p>A few collations from and comment on variant pointing in <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> and 
<hi rend="i">Visions</hi> may serve as an expedient if not sufficient index to differing policies of
modernizations, insofar as a policy can be inferred from practice. The “shriek mark” is of all points the
one which should be shunned if there is no clear authority for it, either in the original or in the texts and
apparatuses of those like Erdman and Bentley who have devoted their eyesight to Blake’s ambiguous pointing.
M’s decision to provide an exclamation after “joys” in <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> 
3:6<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> is therefore dubious, given E’s colon,
Bentley’s semicolon, and the relatively neutral modernization into a period preferred by K and P. Since M
states that on occasion he returned to facsimiles (not originals) to confirm or qualify what he felt was
“problematical,” his unique reading here and elsewhere has no preferential claim to authority and must be
presumed a product of his modernizing prerogative. (One may parenthetically wonder why he didn’t go down the
road from London University, where he teaches, to the British Museum Print Room and check the
originals—though discrepant readings of the same points by Erdman and Bentley abundantly illustrate that
even that reiterated appeal may be in many instances “problematical.”) But after “maid” in 
<hi rend="i">Visions</hi> line 19 it’s M who more chastely converts the original’s ambiguous colon/semicolon
to a period, while K and P supply the emphatic but unauthorized exclamation. At this point the vacillating
subjectivity involved in this kind of nitpicking, which makes the aforementioned rule of thumb always subject
to a reader’s or editor’s clinamen towards formal or rhetorical pointing, surfaces, as I find myself
wishing that M, like K and P, had added rather than subtracted an exclamation in <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> 5:3
(which in E reads “Creator of men! mistaken Demon of heaven:”), though recognizing as well the
plausibility of M’s editorial decision. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> I use the traditional plate/line
number references, as in E. M prefers consecutive line numbers to plate divisions throughout his
edition—thereby seriously detracting from its usefulness to students and scholars who will therefore be
unable to use it with the <hi rend="i">Blake Concordance</hi> or with secondary materials using plate/number
references.</note></p>
          <p>The fact that only M removes the interruptive but rhetorically effective exclamation after
“spring” in <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 1:6 may suggest a preference for a formal syntax (see also the comma
used by K, P, and M for the original question mark after “spring” in the next line), though it is not
clear that M consistently abides by that preference. In <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>’s “Motto,” only M among
modernizers chooses to change line 3’s “rod?” to “rod,” a change which seems particularly anomalous
if one infers that the only justification for his (and K’s and P’s) changing line 4’s “Mole:” to
“mole?” is that the four clauses of the “Motto” are best formalized into a modern syntax when each of
them is followed by a question mark. If one is going to change the question mark to a comma in the first
instance, then why not keep the colon (along with the semicolon, a rhetorically prevalent surrogate for the
interrogative in a series of clausal questions in Blake’s
<pb id="p24-148" n="148"/>
time which may still be appropriately used); or else replace the question mark after line 1’s “pit” with
a comma? The assumption is that modernization helps the modern reader better understand the sense of the words
by a late twentieth-century pointing which joins them together in a formally consistent syntax. If the
modernizer is simply going to groom Blake’s inferably inconsistent pointing into his own, the would-be step
forward is really a step backward, on the grounds that in such cases Blake’s version is preferable. It is
nonetheless and also the case that no one is likely to argue against normalizing to suit modern sensitivities
such patently whimsical punctuation as that represented by the half dozen pointing variations which Blake
worked into the several repetitions of “Mark well my words, they are of your eternal salvation” in 
<hi rend="i">Milton.</hi> At the level of pure theorizing, one may care to applaud the ideal surmise of Max
Plowman, who felt that even the “vagaries” of Blake’s pointing “would eventually prove explicable”
(<hi rend="i">Blake’s Poems and Prophecies</hi>, xi). But in eagle-eyed confrontations with the originals
one very soon discovers the futility of attempting to provide the context for that eventuality by trying to
reproduce the poet’s intended punctuation when it is impossible to be sure whether a given point is a comma
or a period, a semicolon or a colon.</p>
          <p>At times modernization means disrupting Blake’s emphatic caesura (“light,” 
<hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, 1:23 in E becomes “light” in M; “cow,” 2:10 in E, becomes “cow” in M) or his
enjambment (“springs” 1:24 in E becomes “springs,” in M). Only M provides an emphatic caesura Blake
did not provide by adding a comma after “not,” (3:2 in E). But only M among modernizers follows Blake in
<hi rend="i">not</hi> providing the comma caesura in 3:9 after “thou”—perhaps indicating that random
chance rather than organizing intelligence rules the modernizer’s syntactical universe. Accepting that
indication, a reader sensitive to rhetorical pointing may further infer that even though all modernizers agree
to drop a given point, a Blakean effect worth preserving—typically an emphasis on a word before the
point—could thereby be lost (e. g., “Har,” 2:1 in E, “Har” in K, M, P). Extrapolating from that
inference, and all of the above, the reader’s ultimate (and charitable) conclusion may be that the
modernizer’s lot, in theory and in practice, is not a happy one.</p>
          <p>There’s some implicit disagreement between M and P on the “metrical consequences” of the
terminal “-ed.” While Mason states that he retains Blake’s elliptical “’d” only when he feels it
might have such consequences, P insists that any poem which contains both the “-ed” and the “’d”
participles should have them discriminated. <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> is among these poems (we have
“o’ertired”— or is it “o’erfired”?—in 2:4, “naked” in 4:5). But for M, 
<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 2:2 “ceasd &amp; smild” in E becomes “ceased” and “smiled” (P, following K,
merely provides an apostrophe). In fact, M seems seldom if ever to find the foreshortened participle of any
consequence: my own random sampling of his text has failed to turn up any example of his retaining it. While P
perhaps protests his point too much—he spends half his “Note on the Texts” minutely arguing this
particular—it’s probably best to observe Blake’s distinction, so that in those poems where it may seem
to matter the reader will discriminate appropriately. Certain words seem to prescribe a pronounced “-ed,”
at least in poetry—e.g., <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 3:31, where M’s “sailed” (for “saild”) will tend
to become a disyllable in the pronunciations of some readers.</p>
          <p>The great majority of Blake’s rhetorical (or <corr type="emend">idiosyncratic)</corr>
capitalizations are modernized away in both M and P, though both K and J/G retain most if not all of them.
Hyphenations are added <hi rend="i">passim</hi> in M, with mixed warrant and effect: <hi rend="i">Visions</hi>
2:33, “hot-burning” seems to me an unnecessary coalescence of Blake’s words, though “charnel-house,”
3:36 is unobjectionable. M’s “new-washed” (3:18) perhaps rightly avoids a possible ambiguity in the
original, since Blake could hardly have intended “new” to imply, as unmodified it might, “new born.”
M’s “fat-fed” seems to aid in understanding the rather obscure allusion of 5:14. Both M and P change
such obsolete or variant spellings as “subtil,” <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> 6:7. While a few of M’s
modernizations, such as “tyger” to “tiger,” will bother the Blakean, others, such as “may’st”
for “maist,” <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> 2:1, should seem well-warranted, since they avoid a momentary
ambiguity some readers would otherwise hesitate over. J/G continue to represent their relatively strict
adherence to Blake’s text by retaining spellings such as “hipocrisy” (“Africa” 3:13). Where this
kind of retention stops being a virtue in a reading text is a nice question. While “eccho,” 
<hi rend="i">Visions</hi> 2:20, 5:11, presents no problem, is retained in as popular an edition as 
<hi rend="i">The Norton Anthology of English Literature</hi>, and patently “works,” there seems no objection
to “echo” it in a reading text (like M’s) very much given to modernizing; likewise with
“perswading,” 2:22—K and J/G prefer Blake’s spelling; M and P do not. P, apparently following Bentley,
prints “towards” rather than “toward” in <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> 1:2; he also prints “is this”
for “this is” in <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 5:5 (his line 91—he does not use plate numbers in 
<hi rend="i">Thel</hi>). Only J/G among reading texts consulted preserve and try to justify the perhaps misread or
more probably misetched “o’erfired” in <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 2:4. (E accepts, most dubiously to my
eyes, that Blake really did etch “o’ertired,” which nonetheless seems to be what he meant to etch.)
Since I came across it, I should perhaps record for someone’s future purposes that M’s reference to
Proverbs 9:17 in his note to <hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, line 6 (iii: 6), is right, J/G’s 8:17 wrong.</p>
          <p>While the Oxford jacket-cover claims the text is “fully annotated,” compared to J/G, M
provides us with a mere thimbleful, a good portion of which
<pb id="p24-149" n="149"/>
contains bare references to the Bible and to <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> or provides dictionary definitions.
Since the Routledge series more modestly emphasizes the historical contexts of its authors, the fact that
Punter’s notes are comparably sparse and a bit disproportionate in coverage may be accepted as a built-in
limitation of general editorial policy. It will once again be most illuminating to let the two editions face
off against each other, refereed again by the generally preferable 
J/G.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2" type="note">2</ref>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> The recently revised and reissued W. H. Stevenson/David Erdman edition of
<hi rend="i">The Complete Poems of Blake</hi> (Longman/Norton) is also full of annotation and could serve
nearly as well as J/G (who seem to have critically appreciated Stevenson’s notes) in relevant contrast to
the editions reviewed here.</note></p>
          <p>Since M does not treat the <hi rend="i">Poetical Sketches</hi> as a unit, he fails to provide it
with even the perfunctory headnote which he generally supplies elsewhere. J/G have an excellently informative
headnote on composition, publication, and content, including as well a reference to the standard work on the
poems, Margaret Lowery’s <hi rend="i">Windows of the Morning.</hi> P provides only two of the poems, with
comparably minimal annotation. M’s deficiencies as annotator relative to J/G begin early and stay late. Of
“To Spring” he tells us that its metre anticipates that of the “septenaries” and prophetic writings
and that lines 2-3 could be glossed by Dan. 11:18—an utterly irrelevant reference. J/G point out that the
seasonal cycle instituted with this poem parallels comparable sets of poems by Pope and Thompson, noting as
well that general anticipations of the Biblical and Miltonic allusions of the later works appear in these
early poems, with “To Spring” echoing the “Song of Solomon,” “Lycidas,” 163 (which lines 2-3 
<hi rend="i">do</hi> echo and which perhaps M meant to note), <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, 744 [752?], 
<hi rend="i">Samson Agonistes</hi>, 119, and Horace, <hi rend="i">Odes</hi>, 1, v, 3-5 [iv might seem a more
appropriate analogue]. In the “Love and Harmony” lyric, M simply reprints without comment the obviously
incorrect “her” of line 17. Even if he had not cared to accept the handwritten “his”—the diplomatic
rigors of the Bentley and Erdman editions keep them from accepting it—he should have at least noted it,
since other less modernized texts (K, P, and J/G) accept it as Blake’s intention, which is also the common
sense of the context—Blake is hardly a feminist deconstructionist trying to rattle our pronominal
preconceptions in the interests of gender ideology.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3"
type="note">3</ref> Likewise, while M provides extraneous 1910 commentary from Saintsbury for “Mad Song,”
he fails to note, as E does, that in several copies line 4’s “unfold” was changed by hand to
“infold” and that line 7’s “birds” was so changed from “beds.” Both changes should have been
accepted (as they are by K, P, and J/G) in a reading text. <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> While Blake did
later put the case for a female cupid (in the <hi rend="i">Notebook</hi> poem “Why was Cupid a Boy”), his
grammatical context here obviates a possible argument-from-prolepsis.</note></p>
          <p>Both M and P follow an editorial tradition, perhaps enforced by the texts, of minimal annotation
for the <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> and <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, though on balance M
seems more helpful, at least in the <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> notes. P occasionally illustrates his
historical concerns—by, for example, noting that the introduction to <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> implies
Blake’s view of the poet as one “in whom the threads of human history are drawn together,” which leads
him to further infer that prophecy in Blake meant “focusing” not futurizing. When he says that in
“London” “mind-forged manacles” means that “we contribute to our plight by accepting and
internalizing various constraints on our freedom” he will allow the teacher to point out to the student that
what Blake more probably means and what the context better supports is the reading providing by J/G, who note
that they refer “primarily [to] the authorities of church and state,” though allowing the subordinate
possibility that P exclusively advances. The differing annotative policies of the editors under review and J/G
are obvious in such contrasts, with both P and M generally providing only one (perhaps unduly subjective)
reading, thereby avoiding alternative, or even consensus, readings in order to impose their restrictive
glosses. J/G will generally indicate their preference but allow for alternatives. One kind of editor goes
through the text objectively asking himself “How may this be most helpfully annotated?”; the other kind
subjectively asks “Do I have in mind an annotation I’d care to provide?”</p>
          <figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
          <p>There may be nothing particularly objectionable in M’s telling us that, in the Cynic’s first
song in <hi rend="i">An Island in the Moon</hi>, “vest” is used as in modern American and probably
signifies a dandy but not when so telling us that bit of relative inconsequence may eliminate a reading of
“Old Corruption” as a radical term for the political establishment, a much more substantive piece of
information which a majority of M’s readers will not know—unless they read J/G. In general, it’s really
not so much a matter of what M does tell us but what he does not which will make his claim to “full
annotation” a subliminal self-mockery in the mind of the reader as he recurrently ponders the relative value
of the notes, what they contain and what they do not. It is correspondingly the case that M’s implicit claim
to have provided a host of recent secondary commentary is unwarranted. J/G, in one note to “The Mental
Traveller,” a poem to which M does provide a helpfully suggestive general commentary, provide more such
references than M does through the course of his annotations for all the Blake he prints.</p>
          <pb id="p24-150" n="150"/>
          <p>Both P and M typically provide brief headnotes to each work. For example, for 
<hi rend="i">America</hi> P has about 60 words, M about 160, both therein providing the barest sense of the poem
and its historical and symbolic relations (half of M’s note is concerned with defining “prophecy” as M
construes it). J/G have over 1100 words, which enlarge on the historical context (beyond P), relate it in some
detail to other works, and devote some time to the designs. P generally uses his fewer words to better
purposes than M. M’s <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> headnote is mainly taken up with what the reader could infer
from the poem without M’s help: That it is dramatic, that its speakers are engaged in moral (sexual),
philosophical, and political dialogue. Even after allowing editorial prerogative its exegetal due, a reader
may balk at M’s feeling that Blake himself does not arbitrate among the ideologies he presents and that,
Oothoon to the contrary, there is nothing to choose between Bromion and Theotormon. M’s penchant for
irrelevant tidbits surfaces in his longest note, a disproportionate attempt at relating the “jealous
dolphins” with the story of the sea-nymph Galatea and a jealous suitor. He later tells us, to no helpful or
cogent purpose, that “wake her womb” refers to a contemporary sexual physiology. A quick read through the
fully annotated J/G <hi rend="i">Visions</hi> redundantly demonstrates how much better M might have used his
time and space. M continues to illustrate his penchant for the arbitrary: <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> “must
have been a formation from ‘horizon,’ and perhaps Greek <hi rend="i">horizein</hi> to limit. The name is
stressed on the first syllable.” J/G allow for the problematic and alternative by noting that while
“probably” deriving from the Greek word, it may also be a Blakean pun on “Your Reason”; they further
note that, while metrically Urizen accented on the first syllable seems best, pronunciation, as well as the
etymology, of such words must remain speculative. P here avoids dealing with the name but does define in a
traditional way what Urizen stands for. Both J/G and P note “God tormented” as a justifiable meaning for
“Theotormon”; M simply notes the word as Blake’s coinage.</p>
          <p>In his de facto headnote to <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi> M expends most of his space
pointing out how Blake followed the Bible in using the word “Book” to describe this and a few other of his
works. He then points out to no one’s surprise who had looked at the Table of Contents that Blake “does
not achieve anything remotely like a Bible-sized text, or even a Pentateuch-sized one”—and he then flies
off on an associative tangent to tell us such would be the case “even if the imitations of Exodus, Numbers,
Joshua, and Revelation in <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> and <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> are counted into the
project.” Is this what the reader needs to know? Instead of straightforward expository prose, we too often
get this kind of magisterial gobbledegook, usually, as here, following from and further developing a
relatively private thesis the editor believes in to the exclusion of all others: “[Urizen] modulates from a
complex reworking of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> into a strange psychomachia that is combined with an
imitation of Genesis.” Irrelevance, disproportion, and tortured prose work in concert to produce the
following note to the <hi rend="i">Preludium</hi> to <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>: “The traditional word-order
of the opening to an epic (starting with the subject of the poem, which is also the object of the first main
verb) is preserved, as is the Miltonic genitive grammatical aspect, even though there is no main verb in
Blake’s opening, let alone one that takes a genitive.” Compare J/G commenting on the same context: “The
text of the <hi rend="i">Preludium</hi>, in one formulation, summarizes the theme of the work and then invokes
the ‘Eternals’ to dictate stories ‘of torment.’ This mood is somewhat alleviated by the design . . .
of a flying woman guiding a child, which B once printed separately with the caption, ‘Teach these souls to
fly.’” Since M does not believe in the relevance of the designs, he of course can’t help his readers to
these latter associations and qualifications, though he could have emulated the clarity and relevance of the
preceding reading and application of the <hi rend="i">Preludium.</hi></p>
          <p>Having dismembered and variously distributed the “Song of Los,” M is free to make his
annotations fit his crime—the “four harps” are taken to represent the “sequence of four texts which
commences with ‘Africa.’” While the inference is plausible, it’s still the case that if Blake intended
to sell what he’d written as written, two of the four would not make up the sequence as M prints it. Only
J/G point out that “Africa” has little to do with Africa. They also note that Blake’s tendency to repeat
lines in different poems is illustrated by the first line of plate 3 of <hi rend="i">America</hi> and the last
line of “Africa” but they do not further take advantage of that kind of repetition, as M does, to separate
what Blake has integrated so that they can integrate what he has separated. The fact that 
<hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell, Visions</hi>, and <hi rend="i">America</hi> contain the line “For
every thing that lives is holy” is an argument for a seminal thought connecting these poems but nothing more
than that. M reads the problematical “loose Bible” as a reference to the “considerable overlap in events
and persons between the Koran and the Bible” which makes the former an approximation of the latter. J/G
simply supply the etymological suggestion derived by S. Foster Damon from George Sale that Koran means “a
collection of loose leaves.” (Since Antamon and Leutha, sexual sorts, give the Bible to Mahomet, Damon’s
further suggestion that moral or sexual looseness is implied may seem a more contextually helpful
interpretation.) Perhaps envisaging a more popular audience than either M or J/G, P tends towards strictly
informative notes that will seem redundant to scholars and most students—he glosses Ararat in “Africa,”
provides dates for Newton and Locke, and, it may be with his historical charge
<pb id="p24-151" n="151"/>
in mind, tells us the needful about Rousseau and Voltaire, noting as well their urizenic parallels. His
historical bent is more obviously at work when he relates Blake’s critique of the Kings of Asia to the
European <hi rend="i">ancien regime.</hi> Occasionally P indicates that he is not as much up on his American
history as he should be—or he would have singled out, as J/G do, “Light-horse Harry Lee” instead of
letting the reader do what he can with Blake’s <hi rend="i">America</hi> allusion by sorting out the “many
possible Lees” in the <hi rend="i">Dictionary of American Biography.</hi> Nor does P seem to have the
background to suggest, as J/G do, that the scribe of Pennsylvania is probably Franklin and the builder of
Virginia probably Thomas Jefferson.</p>
          <p>Blake’s tendency to foist names at his reader with an implicit challenge to make what he/she
will of them can lead to a superfoetation of predication as one moves from commentator to commentator. Both P
and M note that a historical Ariston stole his best friend’s wife. But P discounts the reference, supposing
that Blake is “using the image for his own purposes, because of the double connotation of grandeur and
hiddenness,” while M feels that the contextual association of Ariston with Atlantis may indicate that Blake
was “thinking of Plato’s story that Poseidon lord of Atlantis captured a mortal bride.” J/G, following
Damon, note both references, historical and platonic, though Damon himself feels the historical reference
(from Herodotus) “is probably a coincidence.” Readers may legitimately infer that the real significance of
this and other inextricable allusions is that they remind us of the <corr type="emend">inferable</corr>
holographs that based the plates we have, as well as of lost drafts never transcribed into copper, that might
have helped solve the referential puzzles the extant canon sometimes presents both editors and readers.</p>
          <p>Examples of differences in annotative style may be as serendipitously picked up as Indian arrow
heads were for Thoreau at Walden. For M, Orc “clearly derives from the Latin word Orcus for the underworld
and his god.” P does not try to derive the name, merely identifying the character with revolution, desire,
etc. J/G let the reader take his choice from among the vagaries of an indefinite consensus which derives the
word from “Orc” (sea monster), or “Orcus” (hell, also a giant in Spenser), or “cor” (heart), or
“orchis” (testicle), concluding that whatever you choose from the above, the word represented for Blake a
figure who struggles against political oppression, sexual repression, and restrictions on energy. M’s
“clear” if tunnel-visioned identification is in keeping with his general assurance that whatever he happens
to know is both right and exclusively so. Actually, Orc’s later association with Luvah makes it fairly clear
that among other meanings “heart” has a good deal of Blakean potential in it, with “testicle” perhaps
warranted because at last Luvah is relegated to the place of seed in one version of the Blakean millennium.
The hellish reference M is so certain of has no comparable justification in Blake or, for that matter, in
classical associations.</p>
          <p>P says of the “Atlantean hills” that Blake “was interested in myths of Atlantis; and they
become useful here as he sets up a symbolic site for debate and battle between America and Britain.” This
last would perhaps lead into a helpful association if P would further tell us what those myths were and how he
thinks Blake is usefully using them. Since he feels he should remind us that George Washington was the
President of the United States, why not more on these myths? M is even less helpful—he tells us
“Atlantean” means “as mighty as Atlas.” J/G suggest a relevance for the association when they note
that the mythical Atlantis, referred to by Plato, “is the land of the Golden Age (cf. 10:7) which is now
sunk beneath the Atlantic, breaking the continental link between England and America.” To further strengthen
this reading, they also point out a consequential parallel in the “Song of Liberty” to “those infinite
mountains of light, now barr’d out by the atlantic sea.” In this instance, the best note after all might
have been a reference to Damon’s rundown of variants under “Atlantic” or merely to “Atlantic” in the
<hi rend="i">Concordance.</hi></p>
          <p>In his notes to <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> the reference to the “secret child” (line 59, 3:2)
is simply the birth of Christ in M; in J/G it is not only a reminder of the “Nativity Hymn” (M’s
Miltonic associations seem to have failed him here) but also and consequently contains the implication that
His birth should have brought about an overthrow of Old Testament values it did not bring about: Orc’s
birth, correlated with the French Revolution, is thereby substantively kindred.</p>
          <p>Because excerpts make up most of the rest of P’s text, annotation is comparably selective,
though the editor often provides a brief gloss, mainly concerned with their symbolic purposes, of the works he
selects from. M’s annotation of the remaining works, when compared to J/G, continues minimal,
disproportionate, arbitrary, and relatively irrelevant. He correspondingly continues to suffer from a
misguided tendency to originality, perhaps traceable to an insufficient knowledge of secondary materials,
while failing to provide what’s really needed and helpful. The truly full annotation of J/G’s 
<hi rend="i">Book of Urizen</hi> indexes what we need and miss in M. No objective reader could accept M’s
reductive assessment of the integral relation between illumination and text after reading through J/G’s
commentary on the title page or, for that matter, after following up the references to the designs which they
make <hi rend="i">passim.</hi> As usual, M’s commentary suggests that all his reader needs are bare
references to the Bible and <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi> M characteristically fails to demonstrate the
validity of his parallels to either work, with most of the notes simplistically tangential analogues (e. g.,
“<hi rend="i">Dictate</hi>: Milton’s well-known
<pb id="p24-152" n="152"/>
<figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
word for the activity of his muse”; “<hi rend="i">cities</hi>: The appearance of cities at this point
reflects their similar prominance in Gen. 11-14 and 18-19”). Here as elsewhere M pretends to a knowing
superiority to his predecessors which he fails to demonstrate: “[Urizen] is a much more ambiguous figure
than many critics recognize,” a portentous utterance which delivers the usual Miltonic mouse as its
ambiguously superficial inconsequence. At about this juncture, one may strongly suspect that given a
half-day’s research for the project, a competent graduate student would have made up a more helpful set of
notes for <hi rend="i">The Book of Urizen</hi>, and, in a proportional period of time, for at least a majority
of the other works M so “fully” annotates. P has ten notes to his selections from 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, proportionally more than M provides, and they are more helpful. M’s annotations for
<hi rend="i">The Book of Los</hi> are comparably sparse, unhelpful, mere deadwood—he tells us what a polybus
is, how “pliant” and “redounding” should be defined, and of course that chapter 2 is “full of
memories of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost.</hi>” Again, the continuing point is not so much what M does give
us, but rather what he doesn’t. Dictionary definitions and references to “Gen. 2:2” would be
unobjectionable in an edition that was in fact fully annotated. M simply does not make discriminating use of
the space he has.</p>
          <p>At times, M’s annotative tendency to let what he happens to know loom disproportionately large
relative to need or merit verges on the speciously inconsequential—for example, his reminding us that
“lovely woman” (<hi rend="i">Europe</hi>, line 92, 5:3) is an echo of Goldsmith; or on the
inconsequentially ludicrous—for example, the “doors of marriage are open” (<hi rend="i">America</hi>,
line 233, 14:19) is somehow supposed to be glossed by the fact that “Blake married Catherine Boucher in
1782,” a biographical fact there is no reason to believe Blake would have felt important enough to intrude
into this 1793 prophecy. As J/G indicate, the context could better suggest Blake’s and the general liberal
hope that the Marriage Act of 1753 would by then have been repealed or modified—it was being agitated in
Parliament around this time. Blake would have regarded it as a triumph for Orc, as well as for “the females
naked and glowing with the lusts of youth.” The fact that P does not note this may encourage an occasional
impression that his historical bent is often as perfunctory as it is sometimes superficial, even when compared
to J/G, who have no special historical pretensions to live up to. Their respective notes on “caverned” man
suggest the relative awareness M and J/G have of their author’s associations. M’s reference to Plato’s
allegory of the cave is generic, shop-worn, nothing much to any <hi rend="i">ad hoc</hi> point. J/G’s
reference to Locke’s epistemology reminds the reader of the <hi rend="i">Natural Religion</hi> propositions,
of <hi rend="i">Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi>, of a particular <hi rend="i">bête noire</hi> in the Blakean
pandemonium.</p>
          <p>It’s more their quality and character than their number and length that make J/G’s 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> annotations vastly superior to M’s, though J/G have about twenty percent more notes
than M, including nearly three times as many to Milton and his works, though one would have expected that
M’s persistent use of that poet elsewhere would have been appropriately compounded in a work specifically
concerned with him. As usual, M’s annotations are typically the briefest of one liners—“Cf. Ps. 120:
3”—while J/G’s typically tell the student who needs annotation what will actually help him rather than
uselessly cf. him into what may as well be a deadend. Both M and J/G refer us to the <hi rend="i">Paradise
Lost</hi> source of “To Justify the Ways of God to Man,” Blake’s first Miltonic allusion, but J/G goes
beyond the obvious to proleptically point up to the reader its irony (“Blake makes Milton’s purpose . . .
his own, but he rejects Milton’s theology”). M’s notes fail to alert the reader to the fact that he has
placed the preface to <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> elsewhere in his edition, though even if he had so advised him,
a trip to its place in “Blake on Art and Literature” would have provided nothing of annotative value,
though it would have required yet another excursion into “Lyrics from the Epic Poems” in order for the
reader to discover the rest of what Blake had meant to preface his poem with. And even then all he would get
for his troubles is misinformation (of the preface’s “stolen and perverted writings” M vaguely supposes
Blake believed they derived “from more ancient sources,” whereas J/G, arrogating to themselves some of
M’s usual thunder, most helpfully and relevantly note that “the idea that the classics were plagiarized
from the Bible . . . had been articulated by Milton’s Christ” in <hi rend="i">Paradise Regained</hi>) or
non-information (that “delight is in destroying” is “not a specific allusion”). In fully annotating
“atonement” (<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 2:13) J/G suggest a way M might have gone, had he really got below
the surface with his Miltonic (and biblical) references: “Although much of Milton’s theology was radical .
. . his view of the atonement was the orthodox one that God demands man’s death
<pb id="p24-153" n="153"/>
as punishment for sin, but accepts Jesus’ sacrificial death as a substitute payment of man’s debt 
(<hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> 3, 203-12, 236-41). To Blake, this view of the crucifixion was no different from
‘Druidical’ sacrifice.” The note is then supplemented by references to confirming and explicatory
commentary on the subject of Blake and atonement.</p>
          <p>As noted, P realizes that excerpting from <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi>, as well as from 
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi>, is a “near[ly] impossible task,” though one he must attempt. M in his annotation of
his complete text of <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi></corr> continues as above, though he
abrogates his introductory policy and qualifies his general criticism of interpretive summaries by providing
an intelligent and perceptive account of the poem (as he had of <hi rend="i">Milton</hi>). He is of course
certain that his rendering of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> is the “best,” but we’ve come by now to smile
indulgently at M’s naive assurance of his overall superiority to whatever in the world of Blake has had the
blinkered misfortune to predate his original inferences about it.</p>
          <p>Mason’s bibliography is perfunctory at best, merely an outdated list of books containing
nothing later than 1978 (only three listings later than 1970) and would not be acceptable appended to a
graduate seminar paper on Blake. Punter’s coverage is even sparser than Mason’s, perhaps justifiable
because of the narrower focus of his editorial policy, but he does provide a brief critical note for each
entry, a few of which update the bibliography through 1985. J/G provide an ideal example of what a scholarly
bibliography can and should be, particularly in an edition which is meant primarily for the student: A
compendious headnote referring the reader to major Blake collections, bibliographies, journals etc., is
followed by a listing of over one hundred titles divided into major editions, art collections and
commentaries, reference tools, biographies, books of criticism, collected and selected essays. Not only is the
bibliography up-to-date in itself but it was later supplemented by the editors in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 16
(1982): 107-110.</p>
          <p>Finally, a format matter which will matter to some prospective buyers: Mason and Punter save the
typesetter a bit of time by numbering every tenth line; the Norton edition provides the more traditional and
helpful five-line numerations.</p>
          <p>As noted at the outset, the fact that the Oxford and Routledge texts may be primarily geared to
somewhat different audiences does not eliminate the probability that they will both vie for their major
readership in the university classroom. Which of the two is then preferable for that readership? For most
thorough-going purposes, and in spite of deficiencies in format and annotation, the Mason text is preferable
to Punter’s simply because it includes <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> and <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> whole. The
given instructor can set his students right about the illuminations, further apologize as needed for Mason’s
introductory remarks, caution them about the notes, and/or perhaps simply follow the implications of Mason’s
negating introduction and the paucity or irrelevance of his notes by telling them to indeed let Blake speak
altogether for himself. The Oxford text is a handsome and invitingly legible one, with generous margins and
interlinear spacings, a credit in this respect to the publishers. On the other hand, if a given instructor or
set of students is satisfied with selections from Blake’s major works, then Punter should be their choice
because his notes, if skimpy, are typically more helpful and to the point both in their facts and in their
interpretations than Mason’s.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4" type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> P. H. Butter’s Everyman paperback (<hi rend="i">William Blake: Selected
Poems</hi>, 1982) is preferable to Punter’s both for inclusiveness and annotation. In fact, Butter’s
occasionally arbitrary annotation is nonetheless, where comparable, superior both in quantity and quality to
Mason’s. (He is besides trenchantly helpful in explaining the problems of pointing in Blake which
modernizers tent to assume without so explaining.) The complete Stevenson poetry text noted earlier will be
overpriced (at $74.95) for most college classrooms unless or until a paperback significantly reduces its
cost.</note></p>
          <p>But, as indicated, the choice is not so limited. The Oxford Standard Authors (Keynes) Blake is
still the preferred choice for those who need all of Blake in a relatively modernized form; only Erdman’s
text will suit the scholars in a form most of them can readily afford. Even as it stands the Norton text,
which reproduces many of the illuminations in color and most of them in monochrome, is much superior to any
other selected edition. If it were reedited with a <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> complete (and 
<hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> added), and with the first edition’s errors and oversights corrected, it would on
balance be not only the best reading text available but also the most helpful for nearly all scholarly
purposes that could still do without most of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> and did not require attempts at
reproducing Blake’s accidentals such as Erdman and Bentley variously make.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
