<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>25.2.shabetai</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">David V. Erdman, ed., Blake and His Bibles</title>
        <author n="Shabetai">Karen Shabetai</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1991</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1991</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">25.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Walter S. Minot</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Karen Shabetai</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
              <name>Jules Van Lieshout</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1991"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_25">
    <body>
	<pb id="p25-92" n="92"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-25-2-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="b">
              <hi rend="i">REVIEWS</hi>
            </hi>
          </title>
        </head>
      </div1>
      <div1 id="BQ-25-2-0009">
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">David Erdman, ed. <hi rend="i">Blake and His Bibles.</hi> West Cornwall: Locust
Hill Press, 1990. xvii + 237 pp. $30.00.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Karen <name>Shabetai</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The oddities and disappointments of this collection begin on its title page, which includes the
single appearance of its distinguished editor, David Erdman, who has contributed neither a preface,
introduction, nor essay. The title is the second problem—it raises expectations that the collection’s
individual essays do not fulfill. One would expect <hi rend="i">Blake and His Bibles</hi> to have
contributions from such Blakeans as Northrop Frye and Leslie Tannenbaum, who have written so wisely on this
book’s subject—the former shaping decades of Blake studies with the biblical orientation of his approach,
the latter for his careful placement of Blake’s early prophecies in the context of biblical traditions.
Because of the collection’s title, I also expected to find an essay by Jerome McGann, who has recently
offered an historical account of Blake’s bibles (the Geddes translation) in <hi rend="i">The Book of
Urizen.</hi> The collection might have been enlivened had there been a contribution from Harold Bloom, who has
caused such a stir with his depiction of a very Blakean sounding God, by the earliest author(ess) of the
Hebrew Bible, called “J” by followers of the “documentary hypothesis.”</p>
          <p>Still, most of the collection’s authors, if they aren’t as lively as Bloom might have been,
are well worth reading, especially for their careful historical and textual analysis. If one wonders how the
critical fashions of the last decade could have passed the contributors by seemingly without notice, one must
enjoy the clarity of expression in almost all of the essays. Certainly refreshing in a book appearing in 1990
(though there is nothing to indicate that any of the essays were written after 1987) is the absence of a
politically correct agenda as well as the authors’ clear respect for Blake.</p>
          <p>Mark Trevor Smith, who provides both the introduction and an essay, takes as his subject
Blake’s enigmatic attitude towards systems. He concludes with the paradoxical position that Blake was
simultaneously a system-builder and a system-smasher. When Florence Sandler takes up the compelling annotations
to Watson’s <hi rend="i">Apology for the Bible</hi>, she reveals, among other things, a nuanced attitude to
deism, which is often ignored in the face of Blake’s own less subtle articulations on the subject. The
essays by J. M. Q. Davies, John Grant, and Mary Lynn Johnson are, characteristically, thoughtful and
illuminating. With close attention to the rich subtlety of Blake’s illustrations to Milton’s “Nativity
Ode,” Davies’ “Apollo’s Naked Human Form Divine’: The Dynamics of Meaning in Blake’s Nativity Ode
Designs” contrasts the two sets of illustrations (the Whitworth and Huntington versions) to reveal Blake’s
“post-enlightenment perspective” on Milton’s theme. Grant takes up the question of Blake’s
Christianity by examining the representations of Jesus in the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> illustrations.
These illustrations show the “wide range of sympathies and dis-sympathies to Young’s text” (73) as well
as to Young himself. Grant describes “the antitheticalism of Blake’s vision of Jesus,” which he locates
in several works by Blake, as early as, he cautiously suggests, <hi rend="i">All Religions Are One.</hi> In an
essay examining Blake’s illustrations for the Book of Psalms, Johnson discovers “Blake’s interpolation
of Jesus into Psalms 18, 85, and 93” to be at once compatible with Christian and Jewish biblical traditions,
and part of Blake’s “lively, if subdued critical commentary on the Scriptures” (146). Her notes are
especially complete and informative.</p>
          <pb id="p25-93" n="93"/>
          <p>Perhaps the most valuable essay of the collection is Sheila A. Spector’s “Blake as an
Eighteenth-Century Hebraist,” not so much for its conclusions as for its documentation of biblical
traditions and the interesting questions her investigation implicitly invoke. Scholars who have claimed that
Blake was not competent to participate in debates that require knowledge of the Hebrew language have typically
based their arguments on the accuracy in Blake’s use of the language in his works. But such arguments are
anachronistic, because, says Spector, Hebrew was in a “state of linguistic anarchy” in the eighteenth
century. While she illustrates the chaotic state of the Hebrew language during the eighteenth century in order
to show the freedom with which Blake could use the language, she doesn’t evaluate to what extent Blake was a
critic of the specific set of beliefs and attitudes that she uncovers in her sources. While Spector
convincingly refutes arguments that Blake knew little or no Hebrew and, by thoughtful historical analysis, she
shows that in fact Blake participated, though perhaps surreptitiously, in eighteenth-century debates about
Hebrew and the Jews in relation to Christianity, she never really addresses Blake’s attitudes toward Jews.
When examining Blake’s use of eighteenth-century Christian Hebraism, Spector is content to stick to
linguistic issues, though she herself demonstrates that in the eighteenth century “religion was not a study
distinct from linguistics” (180).</p>
          <p>But what Spector does do, she does to great effect. She examines four historical topics in order
to characterize eighteenth-century Hebraism: “Anti-Semitism, Linguistics, Mythology, and Mysticism.” The
first of these, she claims, is the most important because linguistics was put in the service of religious
arguments; it was the consensus of the time, oddly, that Jews were ignorant and that the text of their Bible
was full of errors, “the only difference
<figure type="reviewed-cover"/>
of opinion being whether or not they deliberately mutilated the text” (181). “Anti-Semitism seems to be a
means of questioning the authority upon which more orthodox interpretations of the Bible are predicated while,
at the same time, providing a ready scapegoat for Christian misinterpretations of the Bible” (182).</p>
          <p>Spector examines Blake’s knowledge of Hebrew in the context of eighteenth-century Christian
Hebraism. She rules out the supposition that Blake’s mistakes in Hebrew came from carelessness or error
because the poet was “an extremely careful artist”: “Every word and every letter is studied and put into
its fit place” (“To the Public”). She offers examples of Blake’s accurate use of Hebrew words and
phrases in the marginalia of his illustrations to demonstrate that “when he so desired, Blake could provide
us with correct Hebrew lettering” (199). Spector attributes inaccuracies to technical errors, such as those
that may occur in the etching process, and to deliberate and meaningful deviation. For example, she challenges
Cheskin’s conclusions in the pages of this journal (<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 12 [1978-79]: 178-83) that
Blake’s errors in lettering were due to ignorance. When Blake reverses an aleph when transcribing the
seventh commandment—“Thou shalt not commit adultery”—it is, significantly, only the aleph in the
negation that he gets wrong. Spector suggests that he wishes to render the commandment ambiguous, which would
be consistent with his attitude toward chastity expressed elsewhere in his works. She offers several examples
using similar logic to make sense of Blake’s seeming errors in his Hebrew.</p>
          <p>Spector is always cautious, more suggestive than certain in her conclusions. As she says, she
wishes to facilitate further inquiry, a fertile approach missing in the closing off of further discussion with
Cheskin’s claim that “Blake knew little or no Hebrew.” Her admirable caution, though, regrettably limits
the conclusions she is willing to draw. Although she makes an invaluable contribution to our understanding of
Blake’s Hebrew, Spector could do more with the fascinating historical data she offers. She might, for
instance, have speculated about Blake’s position on anti-semitism. In reviewing the fascinating, if
shocking, virulence of the anti-semitic sources she uncovers to document the importance of anti-semitism to
biblical commentaries in Blake’s day, one cannot help but wonder how Blake would have responded to this
material. Did he passively accept the views of his contemporaries? What can we make of blatant anti-semitic
statements that seem to be so much at odds with the egalitarian spirit of his entire project? (In his
annotations to Watson’s <hi rend="i">Apology</hi>, he refers to “Jewish Scriptures” as “only an
Example of the wickedness &amp; deceit of the Jews,” whom he two pages later calls liars, “Murderers &amp;
Revengers.”) Taking up these kinds of issues would have provided a currency as well as a vivacity that the
collection of essays as a whole lack.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
