<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>25.2.heppner</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">The Good (In Spite of What You May Have Heard) Samaritan</title>
        <author n="Heppner">Christopher Heppner</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1991</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1991</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">25.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Walter S. Minot</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Karen Shabetai</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
              <name>Jules Van Lieshout</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1991"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_25">
    <body>
      <pb id="p25-64" n="64"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-25-2-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">The Good (In Spite of What You May Have Heard) Samaritan</title>
        </head>
        <byline>by <docAuthor>Christopher <name>Heppner</name></docAuthor></byline>
        <p>Commentators on Blake’s illustrations insist that through them Blake modifies and
          criticizes the poets he illustrates, and it is often clear that they are right. But
          sometimes the expectation of finding such criticism can be a cause of error—the
          antithetical meaning is given a premature welcome before an adequate search has been made
          for a more fully articulated reading of the design. I think I have such a fuller reading
          of one of Blake’s illustrations for Young’s <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, which has
          recently received renewed critical attention. In this essay, I shall maintain that the
          design is indeed critical of Young, but in a way quite different from that described by
          previous commentary. My interpretation of the relationship between Blake’s design and
          Young’s text is based first on a close reading of the design itself in relation to the
          biblical text from which it originates, and then on a consideration of the relationship
          between the completed design and the particular portion of the text of Young’s poem which
          it illustrates.</p>
        <p>In their very useful edition of <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>, Robert Essick and
          Jenijoy La Belle give both the “Explanation of the Engravings” bound into some copies of
          Edward’s edition and a commentary of their own. The “Explanation” of the design on p. 37
          (illus. 1) reads as follows: “The story of the good Samaritan, introduced by the artist as
          an illustration of the poet’s sentiment, that love alone and kind offices can purchase
            love.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1" type="note">1</ref> The explicator,
whom Gilchrist identified as
          Fuseli, though that attribution has often been questioned, reads the design as
          illustrating the text quite straightforwardly, paraphrasing the very line starred by Blake
          in the text that he used for his original water color drawing, which reads: “Love, and
          love only, is the loan for love.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n2"
type="note">2</ref> The star was
          retained in the etched version, as is the case in most of the designs, so we cannot draw
          any conclusions about the identity of the explicator from that fact—he may or may not have
          had access to Blake’s original water color design. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi>
            Robert Essick and Jenijoy La Belle, eds., <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts or The Complaint
              and The Consolation</hi>, illustrated by William Blake (New York: Dover, 1975)
            xi.</note>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Essick and La Belle, <hi rend="i">Night
              Thoughts</hi> 37.</note></p>
        <p>The editorial commentary by Essick and La Belle that follows focuses on the difficulty of
          interpreting the cup offered by the Samaritan, which bears a serpent motif on its side.
          The editors write: 
		<q> Not only does the serpent represent mortality throughout Blake’s
              <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> designs, but the cup and serpent motif is also a
            traditional emblem for St. John the Evangelist. The Emperor Domitian once tried to kill
            St. John with a cup of poisoned wine, but a serpent sprang from the cup as a miraculous
            warning to the intended victim. Thus the prone figure in this illustration would be
            quite justified in shunning, as he seems to do with his hand gesture, the offer of an
            ostensibly poisonous gift. The difficulties in reconciling the disparate allusions in
            the design are almost as great as recognizing true friendship. </q>
This offers an
          explanation, but with a full recognition of the interpretive difficulties. It also
          identifies two key images of uncertain meaning, the serpent on the vessel, and the
          victim’s gesture of apparent rejection.</p>
        <p>Discussion of this image resumes with the recent publication of John E. Grant’s essay
          “Jesus and the Powers That Be in Blake’s Designs for Young’s <hi rend="i">Night
            Thoughts.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3" type="note">3</ref> His
comments are framed within an
          argument about Blake’s overall response to Young’s text, which he sees—and I am in full
          agreement here—as including “a wide range of sympathies and dissympathies” (73). Grant
          holds that Blake refocuses Young’s God the father as Jesus the brother of man, and that
          Blake, in the course of “ingeniously” (77) finding ways of introducing the figure of Jesus
          where it is not explicitly demanded by Young’s text, shows Jesus as a figure who gathers
          power as the illustrations to the poem progress (83-84). <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi>
            John E. Grant, “Jesus and the Powers That Be in Blake’s Designs for Young’s 
              <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>” in <hi rend="i">Blake and His Bibles</hi>, ed. David V.
Erdman
            (West Cornwall, CT.: Locust Hill Press, 1990) 77-79. The numbers in Grant’s text and my
            own refer to the numbers assigned to the water color designs in <hi rend="i">William
              Blake’s Designs for Edward Young’s</hi> “<hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi>,” ed. John
            E. Grant, Edward J. Rose, and Michael Tolley, with the assistance of David V. Erdman
            (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1980), 2 vols.</note></p>
        <p>After the frontispiece to Volume One, which does not illustrate any specific text, the
          first “indubitable depiction of Jesus” (77) is as the Good Samaritan of 
            <hi rend="i">NT</hi> 68, which was then etched as p. 37 of Edward’s edition. Grant notes that
          traditional interpretation allowed for an identification of the Good Samaritan as a form
          or image of Jesus himself, which can be confirmed by turning to a variety of commentators.
          Matthew Henry, for instance, the most popular of English commentators,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
            type="note">4</ref> writes: “We were like this poor distressed traveller. The law of
          Moses <hi rend="i">passes by on the other side</hi>, as having neither pity nor power to
          help us; but then comes the blessed Jesus, that good Samaritan; he has compassion on
            us.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n5" type="note">5</ref> John Gill, in
referring to the Samaritan, says
          succinctly “By whom Christ may be meant. . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n6" type="note">6</ref> The
          interpretation was evidently commonplace, though one should note that the identification
          of the Good Samaritan as Jesus adds to it without in any way undoing his continuing
          identity as the Good Samaritan. <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> T. H. Darlow and H. F.
            Moule, revised A. S. Herbert, <hi rend="i">Historical Catalogue of The English Bible
              1525-1961</hi> (London: British and Foreign Bible Society, 1968) 241. Henry’s work
            went through many editions.</note>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Matthew Henry, 
              <hi rend="i">Commentary on the Whole Bible</hi>, ed. Rev. Leslie F. Church (Grand Rapids,
            Mich.: Zondervan Publishing House, 1971) 1449 (commentary on Luke 10.25-37).</note>	
            <note id="n6"><hi rend="s">6</hi> John Gill, <hi rend="i">An Exposition of the New
              Testament</hi>, new ed., 5 vols. (London, 1774) 2: 143. Gill is not recorded by Darlow
            and Moule, presumably because he does not provide a complete text to accompany his
            commentary, but <hi rend="i">DNB</hi> records that the first edition was published in
            1746-48, so the work was evidently popular enough to justify the new edition, and adds
            that he used “his extensive rabbinical learning,” as will appear in later references to
            his commentary. I confess an arbitrary element in my choice of commentators—I have made
            no attempt to canvas the whole vast field. But both Henry and Gill are interesting, both
            were evidently quite widely read, the two argue from somewhat different positions, and
            so separately and together they provide useful evidence about widely received
            interpretation at the time.</note></p>
        <p>In spite of his acceptance of this identification, however, Grant goes on to build a case
          for a rather negative view of the action depicted in the design, pointing to some of the
          features that troubled Essick and La Belle, and questioning whether the scene can
          represent “an unmixed blessing.” <pb id="p25-65" n="65"/>
He refers to the disturbing
          snake, and also to the horse on which the Samaritan has arrived, suggesting that the
          latter is derived from the “donkey included among the ominous familiars of the
          subterranean goddess ‘Hecate’ . . .” (77). Grant then looks at the interaction between the
          two human figures in the drama, and finds disturbing implications there too: 
		<q> The
            startled appearance of Jesus in the watercolor version constitutes a clear sign that he
            had been unprepared for rejection by the Jewish victim. . . . Such details indicate that
            Blake wished to introduce doubts as to whether this Good Samaritan could have succeeded
            as a benefactor or <corr type="emend">‘Friend of All Mankind.’ (E 524)</corr> </q></p>
        <p>Grant’s comments on the etched version modify this view just a little, suggesting that
          the signs of consternation have been removed from the face of Jesus: “now Jesus is
          represented as being masterfully composed and earnest as he proffers his cure” (79). But
          his view of the general sense of the scene is unchanged, and is still focused on the
          serpent, “the ominous but still perfectly apparent presence depicted on the cup” (79).<ref
            target="n7" type="note">7</ref> Grant’s overall view is summed up in this passage: 
          “ . . . the posture of Jesus crouched beneath the text panel, holding unopened the sinister
          decorated cup, repelled by the victim he wishes to help, marks (at this stage) his
          inability to accomplish his mission” (83-84). <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Because
            Grant’s view of the basic thrust of the design does not change when he turns to the
            etched version, I have illustrated only the etched version, which reproduces better than
            the water color. The differences are very small, and neither Grant’s overall
            interpretation of the design nor my own depends on an exact reading of the expression on
            the face of Jesus.</note></p>
        <p>Grant has taken the doubts expressed by Essick and La Belle and has turned them into
          assertions that aim to show Blake separating his perspective from Young’s by a progressive
          revelation of the power of Jesus, which at this early stage of Blake’s visual commentary
          has not yet achieved a full statement. Grant’s point would seem to be that this version of
          the Good Samaritan shows a kind of embryonic Jesus, not yet capable of powerful action
          against resistance, and offering possibly poisonous gifts (the contents of the chalice are
          called “a dubious potion” in the text below his Figure 1).</p>
        <figure n="bb515.1.21.com" id="bb515.1.comb.21" work-copy="bb515.1" rend="db" width="793" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>inv: &amp; sc<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
          <head>1. <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> 37.</head>
          <figDesc>Courtesy of the Department of Rare Books and Special Collections, McGill
            University Libraries.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <p>The interpretive strategies proposed by Essick and La Belle, and developed by Grant, are
          based initially on a negative reading of the image of the serpent. But any reading of the
          serpent must first consider the nature of the representation of that serpent; the negative
          interpretations of it seem based on assumptions about what would be appropriate responses
          to the representation of a real, living animal. Terror and horror are therefore read as
          the responses of the victim. But we are actually dealing with the representation of a
          representation of a serpent; in both the original drawing and the etching there is a
          clearly visible line separating the body of the flask or chalice from what appears to be
          the cover, which has a different texture. The serpent is incised or enamelled on the main
          body of the vessel. Terror and horror would be merely misplaced superstition; we, and the
          victim, are dealing with an image, not an animal, and that image must therefore be
          interpreted symbolically, as the representation of a meaning.</p>
        <pb id="p25-66" n="66"/>
        <p>The point deserves elaboration. Essick and La Belle refer to the story of St. John the
          Evangelist. This is without much doubt the foundation of the description of Fidelia in the
          house of Holiness in Book 1 of Spenser’s <hi rend="i">The Faerie Queene</hi>, which at
          first sight might appear to offer a good analogy with the design under consideration: 
		<q>
            She was araied all in lilly white,<lb/>
 And in her right hand bore a cup of gold,<lb/>
            With wine and water fild vp to the hight,<lb/>
 In which a Serpent did himselfe
            enfold,<lb/>
 That horrour made to all, that did behold. . . .<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
              type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> Edmund Spenser, <hi rend="i">The
                Faerie Queene</hi>, ed. A. C. Hamilton (London: Longman, 1977) 1.10.13.</note></q>
          Hamilton’s note on this passage tells us that “St. John the Evangelist is usually
          represented with a chalice out of which issues a serpent. . . . The <hi rend="i">Golden
            Legend</hi> records the familiar story of how John drank a cup of poison to prove his
          faith.” That story only makes sense, however, if we understand this serpent to be alive
          and capable of a mortal bite, so that to overcome the fear of such a death is a true
          indication of faith. The reflexive “did himselfe enfold” makes clear that Spenser’s
          serpent is very much alive. The apparent analogy between the story of St. John and Blake’s
          design is not in fact substantial or useful.</p>
        <p>There is another traditional interpretation of the image of the serpent, however, of
          which Hamilton reminds us. His note identifies it as also “the emblem of Aesculapius, the
          symbol of healing; also of the crucified Christ, the symbol of redemption. The serpent
          lifted up by Moses (Num. 21.9) is interpreted typologically as Christ lifted up on the
          cross (John 3.14).” This can be put more forcefully by suggesting that the story of
          Aesculapius can easily be read as a type of the story of Jesus, as is strongly suggested
          by Sandy’s version of Ocyroë’s prophecy over the infant Aesculapius:
<q> Health-giver to
            the World, grow infant, grow;<lb/>
 To whom mortalitie so much shall owe.<lb/>
 Fled
            Soules thou shalt restore to their aboads:<lb/>
 And once again the pleasure of the
            Gods.<lb/>
 To doe the like, thy Grand-sires [Jupiter] flames denie:<lb/>
 And thou,
            begotten by a God, must die.<lb/>
 Thou, of a bloodless corps, a God shalt be:<lb/>
 And
            Nature twice shall be renew’d in thee.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">9</ref>	
                <note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> George Sandys, <corr type="emend"><hi rend="i">Ovid’s Metamorphosis</hi>,</corr> ed.
Karl
              K. Hulley and Stanley T. Vandersall (Lincoln: U of Nebraska P, 1970) 97.</note></q>
          For some reason, Sandys misses this opportunity in his commentary, but he redeems himself
          in his comment on the long account of the removal of Aesculapius to Rome in the fifteenth
          book: “For the Serpent was sacred unto him; not onely . . . for the quicknesse of his
          sight. . . . But because so restorative and soveraigne in Physicke; and therefore
          deservedly the Character of health. So the Brasen Serpent, the type of our aeternall
          health, erected by Moses, cured those who beheld it” (714). In a more straightforward
          vein, Lemprière writes of Aesculapius that “Serpents are more particularly sacred to him,
          not only as the ancient physicians used them in their prescriptions; but because they were
          the symbols of prudence and foresight, so necessary in the medical profession.”<ref
            target="n10" type="note">10</ref> These mythographical comments, from sources that Blake
          almost certainly knew,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11" type="note">11</ref>
provide us with a reading of
          the serpent image on the chalice offered by the Samaritan which is much more relevant and
          appropriate to the present context, and lead us to consider further the implications of
          identifying the Samaritan as both Jesus and Aesculapius. 
              <note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Lemprière, <hi rend="i">Classical Dictionary</hi>, 3rd ed.
[1797] ed. F. A.
            Wright (London: Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, 1984) 19.</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi> It is evident that Blake knew his Ovid, but I do not remember seeing it
            remarked before that his spelling “Ovids Metamorphosis” (E 556) points, though not
            definitively, to Sandys, who seems to have been the last to spell the title in that way.
            It seems that Keats was not the only major romantic poet to appreciate Sandys. Many
            other sources comment on the serpent as the attribute of Aesculapius—e.g. Joseph Spence,
              <hi rend="i">Polymetis</hi> (London 1747) 132.</note></p>
        <p>The explicitly medical nature of the Samaritan’s intervention is sometimes overlooked,
          but not by eighteenth-century commentators. Henry notes that the Samaritan “did the
          surgeon’s part, for want of a better.” Gill gives a more heavily allegorized
          interpretation: the wounds of the victim represent “the morbid and diseased condition that
          sin has brought man into,” which are “incurable by any, but the great physician of souls,
          the Lord Jesus Christ.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n12" type="note">12</ref>
In the context of this
          offering of medical help by a figure whose face is clearly modeled on that of Jesus, it
          would seem reasonable to interpret the serpent-decorated chalice as an emblem of both
          Aesculapius, the god of healing and medicine whose conventional attribute was the serpent
          or the caduceus, and of Jesus, the true healer whom Blake has made visible within the body
          of the Samaritan, who is also associated with the symbol of the serpent, and with a
          chalice filled with healing liquids. Blake is implying that any act of helping and healing
          would be the act of a true Christian. Aesculapius is, in effect, one of the incarnations
          of Jesus, as is the Good Samaritan himself, or, to put it a little differently, the Good
          Samaritan is an incarnation of Jesus as Aesculapius, the power to heal. 
              <note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Henry, <hi rend="i">Commentary</hi> 1448; Gill, 
              <hi rend="i">Exposition</hi> 2: 142.</note></p>
        <p>There is evidence in Blake’s writing to support this reading of the figure. In 
            <hi rend="i">A Descriptive Catalogue</hi>, Blake describes the Doctor of Physic as “the
          first of his profession; perfect, learned, completely Master and Doctor in his art,” and
          then identifies him as “the Esculapius,” one of the “eternal Principles that exist in all
          ages” (E 536). One might remember also that “Jesus &amp; his Apostles &amp; Disciples were
          all Artists,” and that “A Poet a Painter a Musician an Architect: the Man / Or Woman who
          is not one of these is not a Christian” (“The Laocoön,” E 274). As 
            <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> explains, these archetypal arts become “apparent in Time &amp; Space,
in
          the Three Professions / Poetry in Religion: Music, Law: Painting, in Physic &amp; Surgery”
            (<hi rend="i">M</hi> 27: 59-60, E 125). The true physician is both artist and Christian.
          I wish to emphasize, however, that Blake is not directly illustrating his own myth, but
          rather that his myth and the basis of the design under consideration are both derived by a
          process of transformation from public materials, and that any interpretation of the design
          must proceed by working through those materials in the forms in which they were available
          to Blake.</p>
        <p>We need now to consider further the contents that we are to assume fill the flask or
          chalice. The right hand of the 
<pb id="p25-67" n="67"/>
Samaritan appears to be about to
          lift the lid of the vessel; presumably it contains the “oil and wine” referred to in the
          Gospel account, which the Samaritan poured in as he “bound up his [the victim’s] wounds.”
          The two liquids were conventionally understood as antiseptic (wine) and healing balm
            (oil),<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> which, as John
Wesley explains, “when well
          beaten together, are one of the best balsams that can be applied to a fresh wound.”<ref
            target="n14" type="note">14</ref> Gill gives more detailed evidence from Jewish
          commentary, together with a more typologically oriented explanation that bridges the gap
          between Aesculapius and Jesus: “by <hi rend="i">oil</hi> may be meant, the grace of the
          Spirit of God . . .: and by <hi rend="i">wine</hi>, the doctrines of the Gospel. . .
            .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref> The invisible but
strongly implied contents of
          the vessel in Blake’s design can thus be read as a conventional healing mixture, which in
          its literal form is as appropriate to Aesculapius as it is appropriate to Jesus when
          typologically understood. Both the serpent and the oil and wine presumed to fill the flask
          function to identify the Samaritan as simultaneously Jesus and Aesculapius. 
              <note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Henry, <hi rend="i">Commentary</hi> 1448. The distinction of
            functions is based on the text of the Bible: Cruden notes the frequency with which wine
            is used as a metaphor for the anger of God, and the ways in which oil is associated with
            “comfort and refreshment.”</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi rend="s">14</hi> John Wesley, 
              <hi rend="i">Explanatory Notes upon The New Testament</hi> (London: Charles H. Kelly,
            n.d.) 241.</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Gill, <hi rend="i">Exposition</hi>
            2: 144.</note></p>
        <p>The expression on the victim’s face, and the gesture performed by his hands, can now be
          more easily interpreted. Henry’s commentary is again useful in focusing for us a sometimes
          neglected aspect of the story: the victim “was <hi rend="i">succoured</hi> and 
            <hi rend="i">relieved</hi> by a <hi rend="i">stranger</hi>, a <hi rend="i">certain
            Samaritan</hi>, of that nation which of all others the Jews most despised and detested
          and would have no dealings with.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16"
type="note">16</ref> Henry’s statement
          is based on such texts as Matthew 10.5, which has Jesus instructing his disciples “Go not
          into the way of the Gentiles, and into any city of the Samaritans enter ye not” and John
          8.48, which has the Jews say to Jesus “Say we not well that thou art a Samaritan, and hast
          a devil?” The victim is presumably a Jew, since he is described as on a journey from
          “Jerusalem to Jericho,” and the story registers disappointment if not surprise that he
            <figure n="blakerobinsoncrusoe.25.2.67.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="348">
            <head>2. William Blake, <hi rend="i">Robinson Crusoe.</hi></head>
            <figDesc>Courtesy of the Birmingham Museums and Art Gallery.</figDesc>
          </figure> is ignored by “a certain priest” and a “Levite” (Luke 10.30-32). The victim
          feels and shows astonishment and dismay because help is coming from a despised and most
          unlikely source, after two likely sources have failed him. He is not rejecting that aid.
            <note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Henry, <hi rend="i">Commentary</hi> 1448. Gill makes
            a very similar statement, <hi rend="i">Exposition</hi> 2: 143.</note></p>
        <p>The gesture made by the victim needs more detailed consideration in the light of this
          understanding of its context. The manual gesture is essentially identical with that made
          by Robinson Crusoe as he discovers the footprints in the sand (illus. 2).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n17"
            type="note">17</ref> Here is the text which Blake was illustrating on that occasion: “It
          happen’d one Day about Noon going towards my Boat, I was exceedingly surpriz’d with the
          Print of a Man’s naked Foot on the Shore, which was very plain to be seen in the Sand: I
          stood like one Thunder-struck, or as if I had seen an Apparition. . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
            type="note">18</ref> Defoe’s text makes plainer than could my own words that Crusoe’s
          gesture is understood by Blake as a sign for surprise. This gesture in turn corresponds
          closely to, and was doubtless derived from, Le Brun’s description of “Admiration”: “this
          first and principal Emotion or Passion may be expressed by a person standing bolt upright,
          with both Hands open and lifted up, his Arms drawn near his Body, and his Feet standing
          together in the same situation.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n19"
type="note">19</ref>
	<note id="n17"><hi
              rend="s">17</hi> See Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William
              Blake</hi>, 2 vols. (New Haven: Yale UP, 1981) #140r.</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi
              rend="s">18</hi> Daniel Defoe, <hi rend="i">Robinson Crusoe</hi>, ed. M. Shinagel (New
            York: Norton, 1975) 121. The drawing actually shows the time as either sunset or dawn,
            contrary to the indication of the text, but the visible footprint before Crusoe makes
            the moment illustrated quite definite. Rodney M. Baine is probably correct in suggesting
            that Blake chose a setting sun “To heighten Crusoe’s isolation and terror. . . . For
            that night the fearful Crusoe slept not at all . . .”; “Blake and Defoe” 
              <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 6 (1972): 52.</note>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi> Charles Le Brun,
            <hi rend="i">A Method To learn to Design the Passions</hi>, trans. John Williams,
            intro. Alan T. McKenzie (Los Angeles: William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, 1980)
            47.</note></p>
        <p>The fact that the victim in Blake’s portrayal of the Good Samaritan is lying down and not
          standing makes a difference, but not a crucial one, for Bulwer’s 
          <hi rend="i">Chirologia</hi> contains a plate, reproduced by Janet Warner, which represents simply
          two hands raised from the wrist with the identification 
          “Admiror.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> 
          Bulwer’s commentary on this gesture is as follows: “To throw up the
          Hands to heaven is an expression of <hi rend="i">admiration, amazement</hi>, and
          <hi rend="i">astonishment</hi>, used also by those who <hi rend="i">flatter</hi> and 
          <hi rend="i">wonderfully praise</hi>; and <hi rend="i">have others in high regard</hi>, or
          <hi rend="i">extoll</hi> anothers speech or 
          action.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref> 
          Bulwer’s text appears to describe a gesture involving arms raised above the
          head, but the fact that his illustration shows only the hands suggests that the core
          signifying element in the gesture is the upraising of the hands at the wrist, as is clear
          in Le Brun. <note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> Janet Warner, <hi rend="i">Blake and the
          Language of Art</hi> (Kingston: McGill-Queen’s Press, 1984) 51. Warner’s book received
          a rather ungenerous review recently in <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> (24 [1990]: 65-67), but
          it would seem that some of the important things that she has to tell us have not yet
          been absorbed by Blake scholars.</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> [John
            Bulwer], <hi rend="i">Chirologia: or the Naturall Language of the Hand</hi> (London,
            1644) 29.</note></p>
        <pb id="p25-68" n="68"/>
        <p>A gesture which has been read as if it were a natural sign easily interpreted intuitively
          as meaning rejection, is in fact a highly conventional, explicitly coded sign meaning
          surprise and wonder. As in the case of the serpent, the semiotic status of a sign must be
          determined before it can be usefully interpreted. As the concept of the hermeneutic circle
          suggests, detail and general context can work together to produce a persuasive
          reading.</p>
        <p>Having now focused this gesture, we can see that it is in fact very common in Blake’s
          work, and occurs frequently in the <hi rend="i">Night Thoughts</hi> illustrations. Its
          meaning there seems to range from joyful surprise at the resurrection 
            (<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 318), through awed shock at apocalypse (<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 429), to
fearful
          recognition of guilt, condemnation, and disaster (<hi rend="i">NT</hi> 18, 53). But through
          all these changes there remains the root sense of surprise, astonishment. The gesture
          seems never to mean simply rejection, though obviously there can be an element of
          rejection in the shocked recognition of unwelcome news.</p>
        <p>This interpretation of the victim’s gesture as representing not rejection but profound
          surprise at the unexpected source of the offered help can be confirmed from another
          perspective. The victim’s eyes fix not the allegedly threatening serpent but the
          Samaritan’s eyes; it is the human source of the help that is the focus of the victim’s
          response, and not the medical apparatus involved. The victim’s response is not to be read
          as a rejection; he is simply very, very surprised. And the look on the face of the
          Samaritan is one of concern and compassion; nothing more complex or questionable than
          that.</p>
        <p>The horse seems equally innocent of ethical ambiguity or menace. Grant’s attempt to
          blacken him by association with the allegedly sinister donkey that is “included among the
          ominous familiars” of Hecate in the color print of that name is an unnecessary hypothesis.
          I have in a previous essay made a tentative case for regarding the donkey in Hecate as
          merely a beast of burden;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref>
I can add here that it is
          distinguished from the “ominous familiars” by the fact that it is harmlessly and
          realistically grazing. Satan’s familiars are usually provided for in less mundane ways;
          traditionally, a witch’s familiar drank from the third teat which was one of the defining
          features of witches in the post-classical era. In addition, the donkey is the only animal
          in the print that is not depicted as gazing at something or somebody; it is simply minding
          its own business in a most unthreatening fashion. As C. H. Collins Baker noted, the basic
          design of this ass was taken by Blake from an engraving of the <hi rend="i">Repose</hi> in
          Browne’s <hi rend="i">Ars Pictoria</hi>, and was used again in a painting of 
            <hi rend="i">The Repose of the Holy Family in Egypt.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n23" type="note">23</ref> All
          of the other associations of this animal are innocent and even benign; I see no reason to
          assume any change in Blake’s version of it in the Good Samaritan. 
              <note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Christopher Heppner, “Reading Blake’s Designs: 
<hi rend="i">Pity</hi>
            and <hi rend="i">Hecate</hi>” <hi rend="i">BRH</hi> 84 (1981) 363.</note>	
              <note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> C. H.Collins Baker, “The Sources of Blake’s Pictorial
            Expression” reprinted in Robert N. Essick, ed., <hi rend="i">The Visionary Hand</hi>
            (Los Angeles: Hennessey &amp; Ingalls, 1973) 116-19.</note></p>
        <p>The difficulties encountered up to now in interpreting this design stem from the initial
          critical decision on how to approach it. Let us look at the design again in its full
          context. As the asterisk beside the text in both the original water color and the later
          engraving indicates, Blake began with the line “Love, and love only, is the loan for
          love.” This line is set in the broader context of a musing on the theme of friendship,
          which blooms “abroad” for those “who cherish it at home,” but resists the blandishments of
          power and money: “Can gold gain friendship?” Blake, looking for a story with which to
          illustrate the subject, decided upon the story of the Good Samaritan.</p>
        <p>But the story does not exactly illustrate Young’s point. The parable of the Good
          Samaritan is an illustration of the problem of defining just who is my neighbor, a problem
          opened by the lawyer’s trick question to Jesus: “Master, what shall I do to inherit
          eternal life?” (Luke 10.25). In response to Jesus’s question about the status of the law
          on this point, the lawyer interprets it as saying: “Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with
          all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy strength, and with all thy mind;
          and thy neighbour as thyself.” In response to Jesus’s approbation, the lawyer then asks
          “And who is my neighbour?” It is at this point that Jesus tells the story, which he
          concludes by asking: “Which now of these three [priest, Levite, Samaritan], thinkest thou,
          was neighbour unto him that fell among thieves?” and the obvious answer comes “He that
          showed mercy on him.” To which Jesus replies “Go, and do thou likewise.”</p>
        <p>True neighborly love does not consist in simply returning love for love, or even in
          buying love by lending or giving love, but in freely giving love to those most culturally
          remote from us when they are in need, even if they have shown nothing but scorn towards us
          in the past, and are not likely to change in the future, or ever have occasion to return
          that love. The critique of Young, in other words, takes place at the level of the choice
          of the illustrative story; Young has been implicitly corrected for the legalistic and
          monetary mere equivalence of his “Love . . . is the loan for love.” As Young goes on to
          say, “nor hope to find / A friend, but what has found a friend in three.” The story of the
          Good Samaritan is a rejection of that impoverished doctrine; the victim has just found a
          true friend in one towards whom he had always expressed contempt. Jesus as the Samaritan
          represents precisely the possibility of advancing beyond the position outlined by
          Young.</p>
        <p>The critical problems with this design have been rooted in a reluctance to spend enough
          time and thought on the relationship between the text of the story being illustrated (that
          of the Good Samaritan) and Blake’s design, and on the details of that design in relation
          to the traditions of pictorial meaning as Blake knew and understood them. In the place of
          that process of working through to the meaning of 
<pb id="p25-69" n="69"/>
Blake’s design
          there has been premature haste to move to a consideration of the relationship between
          Blake and the poet he is commenting on, a consideration largely controlled by an
          understanding of Blake’s overall position as laid out in his major poetic texts. As I have
          tried to show, Blake’s designs can bear Blakean meanings without being in any way direct
          illustrations of his own poetic texts. The commentators have been right to feel a critical
          space between Blake’s design and Young’s text, but have looked in the wrong place for the
          evidence. It does not lie in Blake’s version of the story of the Good Samaritan, which he
          has handled with his usual close attention to the details of the biblical story, assisted
          by the addition of some traditionally based iconographic details. It lies rather in his
          choice of that particular story with which to illustrate this portion of Young’s text, a
          story whose relevance is by no means immediately obvious, and which holds a powerful
          critique of Young’s economy of love as exposed at this moment of the poem.</p>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
