<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>25.2.minot</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake’s “Infant Joy”: An Explanation of Age</title>
        <author n="Minot">Walter S. Minot</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1991</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1991</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">25.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Walter S. Minot</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Karen Shabetai</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
              <name>Jules Van Lieshout</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1991"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_25">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-25-2-0006">
        <pb id="p25-78" n="78"/>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake’s “Infant Joy”: An Explanation of Age</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Walter S. <name>Minot</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>Blake’s “Infant Joy,” in <hi rend="i">The Songs of Innocence</hi>, is not a major poem in
the collection, but it has been a troublesome poem to interpret for a number of reasons, among them the
significance of the infant’s age as “two days old” rather than as some other specific number. The
crucial lines in the poem are the first stanza:
<q>
I have no name<lb/>
I am but two days old.—<lb/>
What shall I call thee?<lb/>
I happy am<lb/>
Joy is my name,—Sweet joy befall thee. (E 16)
</q>
The first and second lines and the fourth and fifth lines seem to belong to the infant speaker, while the
third and sixth lines (as well as the whole second stanza) belong to another voice, a respondent. Since babies
of two days old are realistically too young to speak, various critics have offered a number of interpretations
of these lines. Wicksteed is the one critic who specifically explains why the infant is “two days old.” He
identifies the infant’s joy with God’s creation of heaven as described in Genesis on the second day (123).
Wicksteed suggests that the infant may be only two days past conception rather than birth, thus making the joy
the joy of generation (123; 124n). Margoliouth finds Wicksteed’s explanation of the second day
“far-fetched,” but he suggests that the two days may be two days of joy for the parents since the
pregnancy has been established (55).</p>
          <p>I propose a simpler reading. When the first speaker in “Infant Joy” says it is “but two
days old,” there is no reason not to take that literally to mean that the child was born two days ago. The
fact that “I have no name” can be explained by the ancient custom of baptising (or christening) children
on the third day after birth. For example, the birthdate of William Shakespeare has been accepted (not without
some doubts) as April 23rd because he was baptised on April 26th and, according to Sidney Lee, “it was a
common practice to baptise a child three days after birth” (8), a point that is also confirmed by Adams
(21n1). Thus, the child is happy because it is completely innocent (in the Blakean sense) since it is free
from all experience—all human institutions and limitations. Nor should line five, “Joy is my name,” be
taken to mean that the child is a girl with the actual given name “Joy,” for as F. W. Bateson reminds us
in his note on the poem in his edition of Blake’s works, “in the eighteenth century, girls were not often,
in fact, called Joy then” (115).</p>
          <p>In sum, the infant at “two days old” is completely innocent, free, and joyful for probably
the last time in its life, for after that (according to Blake’s view of the world) the infant will be
christened, or named, thus limited by repressive human institutions such as the church. Certainly the
companion piece to this poem, “Infant Sorrow” in <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> (E 28), shows the
restraint of an infant “Striving against my swadling bands,” or the repressions of society. But a look at
the longer manuscript of “Infant Sorrow” suggests the connection with baptism even more strongly, for the
speaker in the poem says (lines 19-21): “But a Priest with holy look In his hand a holy book / Pronounced
curses on his head” (E 797). If we accept the manuscript emendation of “my” for “his” (E 799), then
the speaker in “Infant Sorrow” may be saying that baptism was an occasion on which the priest
“Pronounced curses on my head,” an ironic Blakean view of the Christian rite of baptism.</p>
          <p>My reading of the opening stanza of “Infant Joy” seems to make ordinary sense of the opening
two lines of the poem, and, while it may not identify the respondent to the speaker—who could be the mother,
the piper mentioned in the “Introduction” to <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (as suggested by
Gleckner, 298-99n1) or some unnamed speaker—it seems to simplify the context as well.</p>
          <div3>
            <head>
              <title>Works Cited</title>
            </head>
            <p>Adams, Joseph Quincy. <hi rend="i">A Life of William Shakespeare.</hi> Student’s ed. Boston:
Houghton Mifflin, 1923.</p>
            <p>Bateson, F. W., ed. <hi rend="i">Selected Poems of William Blake.</hi> New York: Macmillan,
1957.</p>
            <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> Newly rev.
ed. David V. Erdman, ed. Commentary by Harold Bloom. New York: Anchor, 1988.</p>
            <p>Gleckner, Robert F. <hi rend="i">The Piper &amp; The Bard.</hi> Detroit: Wayne State UP,
1959.</p>
            <p>Lee, Sidney. <hi rend="i">A Life of William Shakespeare.</hi> New ed. London: Smith, Elder,
1915.</p>
            <p>Margoliouth, H. M. <hi rend="i">William Blake.</hi> London: Oxford UP, 1951.</p>
            <p>Wicksteed, Joseph H. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Innocence and Experience.</hi> London: J. M. Dent,
1928.</p>
          </div3>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
