<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>25.2.paley</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake and Thomas Burnet’s Sacred Theory of the Earth</title>
        <author n="Paley">Morton D. Paley</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1991</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1991</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">25.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Walter S. Minot</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Karen Shabetai</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
              <name>Jules Van Lieshout</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1991"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_25">
    <body>
      <div1 id="BQ-25-2-0006">
        <pb id="p25-75" n="75"/>
        <div2>
          <figure n="36chaos.25.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="379">
            <head>1. Engraving showing the earth in Chaos.</head>
            <figDesc>Thomas Burnet, <hi rend="i">The [Sacred] Theory of the Earth.</hi> 1: 36. Courtesy of the
Royal Library, Stockholm.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <figure n="s-los.e.p1" id="s-los.e.illbk.01" work-copy="s-los.e" rend="db" width="765" height="1000">
	<figTranscr/>
            <head>2. William Blake.</head>
            <figDesc><hi rend="i">The Song of Los.</hi> Copy E. Frontispiece (plate 1). Reproduced with the
permission of the Huntington Library. RB 54043.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake And Thomas Burnet’s <hi rend="i">Sacred Theory Of The
Earth</hi></title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Morton D. <name>Paley</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The importance of Thomas Burnet to some of William Blake’s contemporaries is well recognized.
One of Coleridge’s unrealized projects was “Burnet’s <hi rend="i">theoria telluris</hi> translated into
blank verse, the originals at the bottom of the page.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n43"
type="note">1</ref> Wordsworth wrote parts of Burnet’s theory into <hi rend="i">The Ruined Cottage</hi> and
<hi rend="i">The Prelude.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44" type="note">2</ref> The
young Shelley may have been introduced by his millennialist friend John Frank Newton to Burnet’s
ideas.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n45" type="note">3</ref> There is much in Burnet that
Blake too would have found of interest. In his recent major study of Blake and the sublime, Vincent Arthur De
Luca convincingly suggests that Blake was influenced by Burnet in constructing his own myth of the origins of
the present state of the earth, including the creation of Urizen’s world in <hi rend="i">The [First] Book of
Urizen</hi> and the third Night of Vala, and the situation of the Mundane Egg in 
<hi rend="i">Milton.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n46" type="note">4</ref> De Luca’s
fine exposition is limited to the first two Books of Burnet’s work, comprising his accounts of the Creation,
the Deluge, and the original Paradise. The relevance to Blake of the third and fourth Books, concerning the
Conflagration and the New Heavens and New Earth, remains to be discussed, as does another aspect of Burnet’s
book—its illustrations. <note id="n43"><hi rend="s">1</hi><hi rend="i"> The Notebooks of Samuel Taylor
Coleridge</hi>, ed. Kathleen Coburn (New York: Pantheon Books, 1957) 1: no. 61.</note>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">2</hi> See M. H. Abrams, <hi rend="i">Natural Supernaturalism: Tradition and
Revolution in Romantic Literature</hi> (New York: W. W. Norton, 1973 [1971]) 99-106.</note>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">3</hi> See Kenneth Neill Cameron, <hi rend="i">The Young Shelley: Genesis of A
Radical</hi> (New York: Collier Books, 1962 [1950]) 428n54.</note>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">4</hi><hi rend="i"> Words of Eternity: Blake and the Poetics of the Sublime</hi>
(Princeton: Princeton UP, 1991) 155-56, 157, 158, 162-63, 191.</note></p>
          <p>Early editions of <hi rend="i">The [Sacred] Theory of the Earth</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47" type="note">5</ref> were illustrated with anonymous but well executed engravings
that are likely to have interested Blake the engraver as well as Blake the cosmogonist. (A comparison of the
first three editions in English shows no significant differences among the designs.) The first is a striking
frontispiece depicting Jesus standing above seven disks that, counting clockwise, appear as follows:
<pb id="p25-76" n="76"/>
<figure n="68deluge.25.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="383">
	<head>3a. Engraving showing the earth after the Deluge, with the Ark and angels.</head>
	<figDesc>Thomas Burnet, <hi rend="i">The [Sacred] Theory of the Earth.</hi> 1: 68. Courtesy of the Royal
Library, Stockholm.</figDesc>
</figure>
<figure n="68detail.25.2.bqscan" rend="file" width="400" height="298">
	<head>3b. Detail.</head>
</figure>
<list type="ordered">
	<item><p>1. A dark circle filled with jumbled marks, similar to the illustration of the earth in its chaos on
page 34.</p></item>
	<item><p>2. A light disk matching the representation of the “first earth” before its dissolution on page
67.</p></item>
	<item><p>3. The earth under water with Noah’s ark, accompanied by angels, floating on the waves, as
engraved on page 101.</p></item>
	<item><p>4. The earth with its continents formed, as in the foldout engraving following page 150.</p></item>
	<item><p>5. The earth in flames. This is the subject matter of the third Book, “Concerning the
Conflagration,” in volume 2.</p></item>
	<item><p>6. The restored first earth, virtually identical with the second disk, upon which the millennial
world will be created.</p></item>
	<item><p>7. A sun, illustrating Burnet’s conviction “that the Earth, after the last day of Judgment, will
be changed into the nature of a Sun, or of a fixt Star. . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n48" type="note">6</ref></p></item>
</list>
	<note id="n47"><hi rend="s">5</hi> What I refer to as Burnet’s “book” was originally published in Latin
in two parts, each of which was Englished by Burnet himself, as follows: Part I in Latin, 1681, in English
1684; Part II in Latin 1689, in English 1690. See M. C. Jacob and W. A. Lockwood, “Political Millennialism
and Burnet’s <hi rend="i">Sacred Theory,” Science Studies</hi> 2 (1972): 265-79. The printed title pages
of the first three editions omit the word “Sacred,” which does, however, appear in the engraved
frontispieces.</note>
	<note id="n48"><hi rend="s">6</hi><hi rend="i"> The Theory of the Earth Containing an Account of the Original
of the Earth and of all the General Changes Which it bath already undergone, or is to undergo Till the
Consummation of all Things.</hi> 3rd. ed. 2 vols. (London, 1697). Subsequent references are to this edition,
cited by volume and page numbers.</note></p>
          <p>The first and third disks are of special interest to us here. “There is a particular pleasure
to see things in their Origins,” writes Burnet, “and by what degrees and successive changes they ran into
that order and state we see them afterwards, when completed” (1: 35). According to the <hi rend="i">Sacred
Theory</hi>, the beginning of the earth was as a Chaos in which the elements of earth, air, and water were
intermixed before their separation. This is pictured as the first disk of the frontispiece and, in larger
scale, on page 36 as a mass of jumbled particles (illus.1). This disk bears a striking resemblance to the one
in the frontispiece of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Song of Los</hi> (illus. 2), where the sun is either eclipsed by
another heavenly body forming in front of it or is itself in the process of formation. In either case, Blake
has seemingly borrowed his visual conception from Burnet’s book.</p>
          <p>Another such borrowing occurs with respect to the Deluge scene of the third disk in the
frontispiece. After the formation of a perfectly smooth, egg-like earth, pictured as consisting of four
concrete, flattened-out circles (illustrated on page 44), the waters were contained in the Abyss. When the
crust of the earth dried, however, it cracked. “The whole fabrick brake, and the frame of the Earth was torn
in pieces, as by an Earthquake” (1: 50). Portions of the crust fell into the Abyss and forced out the water,
which then covered the land. On page 68 an engraving enlarges the third disk of the frontispiece, showing the
earth covered by water and a houseboat-like Ark accompanied by two angels (illus. 3). If we compare this part
of the illustration in Burnet to Blake’s design in the upper part of <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> 39[44]
(illus. 4), the resemblance is remarkable. Although other sources for Blake’s arks have been
suggested,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49" type="note">7</ref> none is as close to this
particular <hi rend="i">Jerusalem</hi> design as the one pictured in the <hi rend="i">Sacred Theory.</hi>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">7</hi> See Nicolas O. Warner. “Blake’s MoonArk Symbolism.” 
<hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 14 (1980-81): 44-59.</note></p>
          <p>Our discussion so far has been about Burnet’s first volume, comprising Books I and II, which
concern the creation of the earth, the original Paradise, and the Deluge. Books III and IV, which treat of the
end of the world and the millennium, also deserve some attention. A short sketch of Burnet’s chief ideas
about these events will suggest why Blake would have found them of interest, especially as regards the
structure of time, the Conflagration that will end the earth as we know it, and the regeneration of all things
in the Millennium.</p>
          <p>Burnet cites the Jews’ belief that the world will last 6,000 years, a tradition that he says
derives from “<hi rend="i">Elias</hi> the Rabbin, or <hi rend="i">Cabbalist</hi>” (2: 23). In 
<hi rend="i">M</hi> 24 (E 121), “Los is by mortals nam’d Time”
<pb id="p25-77" n="77"/>
(67); “He is the Spirit of Prophecy the ever apparent Elias” (71). In 22: 15-7 (E 117) Los says:
<q>
I am that Shadowy Prophet who Six Thousand Years ago<lb/>
Fell from my station in the Eternal Bosom. Six Thousand Years<lb/>
Are finishd. I return!
</q>
According to the <hi rend="i">Sacred Theory</hi>, the six days of the world-week would be followed by the
sabbath of the Millennium on the model of Moses’ septenaries: six days of creation, then a sabbath, after
six years a sabbath year, and after a sabbath of years a year of Jubilee. “All these lesser revolutions,”
writes Burnet, “seem to me to point at the grand Revolution, the great <hi rend="i">Sabbath</hi> or 
<hi rend="i">Jubilee</hi>, after six Millenaries . . .” (2: 102). Compare <hi rend="i">Milton</hi> 23: 55 (E
119):
<q>
Six Thousand years are passd away the end approaches fast[.]
</q>
Before the advent of this great Sabbath or Millennium, however, the world as we know it must be destroyed by
fire.</p>
          <p>Burnet places great emphasis on a physical description of what the final Conflagration will be
like (2: 73-74), citing 2 Thess. 7-9 and the “one general Fire” of Lucan’s <hi rend="i">Pharsalia.</hi>
Such a conflagration occupies much of pages 118-20 of Night the Ninth of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, and
<hi rend="i">Milton</hi> Los tells his sons:
<q>
Wait till the Judgment is past, till the Creation is consumed<lb/>
And then rush forward with me into the glorious spiritual<lb/>
Vegetation; the Supper of the Lamb &amp; his Bride; and the<lb/>
Awakening of Albion our friend and ancient companion. [25: 59-62]
</q>
After the burning of the earth there will occur “the <hi rend="i">Regeneration</hi> or 
<hi rend="i">Renovation</hi>” of the world prophesied in Isaiah 65 and referred to by Jesus in Matt. 19.28
(Burnet 2: 112-13). Christ will return to usher in a millennial state in which humankind will live in
“Indolency and Plenty” (2: 126) but will nevertheless enjoy the extension of knowledge, especially of the
sun (2: 142). The millennial state will be characterized by universal peace, righteousness, and the absence of
pain (2: 126). The position of the axis of the earth will be set parallel to the axis of the Ecliptic, as it
was in antediluvian Eden, creating a perpetual spring, Similarly, in Blake’s regained paradise of Night the
Ninth of <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>, where justice is executed upon the tyrants and warriors (123), the
Regenerate Man presides over the feast of Eternals (132-33), and “the fresh Earth beams forth ten thousand
thousand springs of
life” (139: 3). For both authors, the seeds of such a vision lie in a tradition of Christian eschatology
that emphasized the concrete, physical aspects of the millennium, and it is not possible to say precisely
where Blake is indebted to Burnet and where it is a matter of a common tradition. Nevertheless, the many
similarities between their scenarios for the future of the earth, as well as the visual correspondences
discussed earlier, strongly suggest that Blake was familiar with <hi rend="i">The Sacred Theory of the
Earth.</hi></p>
<figure n="jerusalem.F.P44" rend="file" width="712" height="1000">
	<head>4. William Blake</head>
	<figDesc><hi rend="i">Jerusalem.</hi> Plate 39 [44]. Courtesy of the Pierpont Morgan Library. PML
953.</figDesc>
</figure>
<pb id="p25-78" n="78" rend="hidden"/>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
