<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>25.2.vanderwaa</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="review">Huib Emmer and Ken Hollings, Bethlehem Hospital: William Blake in Hell, an opera</title>
        <author n="van der Waa">Frits van der Waa</author>
        <author n="van Lieshout">Jules van Lieshout</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Fall 1991</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1991</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">25.2</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Stephen C. Behrendt</name>
              <name>David V. Erdman</name>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Walter S. Minot</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Dennis M. Read</name>
              <name>Donald H. Reiman</name>
              <name>Karen Shabetai</name>
              <name>David Simpson</name>
              <name>Michael J. Tolley</name>
              <name>Jules Van Lieshout</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1991"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_25">
    <body>
<pb id="p25-90" n="90"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-25-2-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="main" rend="main">
            <hi rend="i">Opera on William Blake Destroyed by Its Own Radicalism</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title><hi rend="i">Bethlehem Hospital: William Blake in Hell</hi>, Opera by Huib Emmer and Ken
Hollings, performed by Theatre Group ‘Hollandia,’ under the supervision of Johan Simons and Lucas Vis.
Psychiatric Centre ‘Vogelenzang’ Bennebroek. Performances through 25th of October.</title>
          </head>
          <byline>Reviewed by <docAuthor>Frits <name>van der Waa</name>,</docAuthor> trans. by
<docAuthor>Jules <name>van Lieshout</name></docAuthor></byline>
          <p>The task that Huib Emmer and Ken Hollings have set themselves in their opera 
<hi rend="i">Bethlehem Hospital</hi> is not a small one. The starting-point was the work and character of the
English visionary poet and graphic artist William Blake. The problem raised is ethical, and deals with the
human soul as an intersection of lofty and crude instincts. The events take place in the madhouse where Blake,
according to a fictitious story, is supposed to have spent the last thirty years of his life.</p>
          <p>It was predictable that the result would stick in the throat. That it has turned so unpalatable
is a disappointment, nevertheless.</p>
          <p>The nicest thing one can say about <hi rend="i">Bethlehem Hospital</hi> is that the piece is
destroyed by its own radicalism. The granite-like idiom of composer Emmer, the juxtaposition of speech and
song, the decision to put the performance into the hands of a theatre group, and even the choice to perform
the opera “on location”—in the chapel
<pb id="p25-91" n="91"/>
of the Psychiatric Centre Vogelenzang—all this bespeaks a dislike of halfheartedness.</p>
          <p><hi rend="i">Bethlehem Hospital</hi> has little in common with a traditional opera, but for one
thing. The piece ends with a death scene. That takes up the entire third act and is deadly in all respects.
Until that moment Emmer’s music is still fairly captivating. To be sure, this is due more to abstract
variables like a diverse lay-out and delicately balanced sound contrasts, than to a profusion of ideas or
theatrical drive. His two-part counterpoint is masterful, but that alone does not make an opera. In the final
act—which, as opposed to the other two, has been entirely through-composed—his rigid, modular treatment of
chords, rhythms, and tones runs aground completely.</p>
          <p>It goes without saying that the librettist Hollings shares the guilt in this. It is asking a
little too much to fill an entire act with internal memories, images, and reflections that are taken from
Blake and embedded in the text. Wagner could handle that, but Emmer cannot.</p>
          <p>The players and musicians are not to blame. Charles van Tassel and David Barron, initially
playing an insane surgeon and a pyromaniac, then the prophets Ezekiel and Isaiah, and finally a split Blake,
heroically work their way through their interminable lyrics. Anne Haenen, cast as Blake’s wife, comes a
little less into her own. And, conducted by Lucas Vis, the orchestra, an ensemble for the occasion, realize
the percussionary building block score with iron consistency.</p>
          <p>It is a pity that director Johan Simons, stuck with this forbidding work, has not been able to
capture its uncompromising spirit and has resorted to vehement movements and effects that are sometimes
inventive but just as often ludicrous. Actors box each other’s ears with bouquets, the two prophets have
false beards that reach the ground, and there is even a head that explodes. The performance would not have
been saved by a drastic stylization, but it would have been made a lot more enjoyable.</p>
          <p>The designers, on the other hand, have understood: they have put up a set dominated by straight
lines, made from glass, metal, and stone. In front is a transparent square column with a half-naked man, a
prisoner condemned to death, inside. He is the only figure with a personality, as appears when he opens his
mouth halfway through the piece. This may be a slightly painful judgment for an opera that lasts over two
hours, but its essence lies in that one oppressive scene—the only one, a ten-minute soliloquy.</p>
          <p>(Originally published in <hi rend="i">De Volkskrant.</hi>)</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
