<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>25.3.groves</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">Blake and the Edinburgh Literary Gazette—with a Note on Thomas De
Quincey</title>
        <author n="Groves">David Groves</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1991/1992</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1991/92</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">25.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Eugenie R. Freed</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1986"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_25">
    <body>
      <pb id="p25-133" n="133"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-25-3-0008">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">Blake and the <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Gazette</hi>—with a Note on
Thomas De Quincey</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>David <name>Groves</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>The <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Gazette</hi> of 1829-30 was “edited by the Rev. Andrew
Crichton: and the literary department . . . principally entrusted to Mr [Thomas] De Quincey and myself,”
wrote the poet David Moir in 1838.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n112"
type="note">*</ref><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n81" type="note">1</ref> This weekly
periodical has received virtually no attention from scholars. One cause of its neglect is probably the 
<hi rend="i">Gazette</hi>’s policy of withholding the names of the authors of its articles. Some of its
better-known contributors, including De Quincey (the “English Opium-Eater”), the Scottish novelist John
Galt, and the poets Thomas Hood and Allan Cunningham, probably feared that they might jeopardize their
positions with more lucrative journals such as <hi rend="i">Blackwood’s Magazine</hi>, if their pieces in
the fledgling <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi> appeared with their names attached.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n82" type="note">2</ref> Many of the <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi>’s regular
contributors may have read the remarks about William Blake in that journal in 1830. Although the authorship of
this review remains a mystery, some evidence seems to suggest that Thomas De Quincey may have played a role in
its publication. In any event, the article is interesting for its discussion of Blake as both poet and
painter, and for bringing Blake’s work to the attention of readers outside England. 
                        <note id="n112">A grant from the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council of
Canada, for the purpose of researching Scottish periodicals, allowed me to live in Scotland while writing the
present article.</note>
	<note id="n81"><hi rend="s">1</hi> David M. Moir, “Life of Dr Macnish,” in his edition of 
<hi rend="i">The Modern Pythagorean: a Series of Tales, Essays and Sketches, by the late Robert Macnish,
LL.D.</hi>, 2 vols. (Edinburgh: Blackwood, 1838) 1: 153. Moir (1798-1851) was a popular Scottish poet, known
to readers of <hi rend="i">Blackwood’s Edinburgh Magazine</hi> through his pseudonym “Delta” (or,
“Δ”); he is mainly remembered today as the friend and biographer of John Galt.</note>
	<note id="n82"><hi rend="s">2</hi> The <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi> promised to identify the contributors of its
various articles, but was prevented from doing so by the sudden bankruptcy of its owner David Blackie in 1830,
followed by his sudden death from cholera in 1832 (see Moir, “Life of Dr Macnish,” [153n]). The 
<hi rend="i">Gazette</hi>’s four “valued correspondents” in London were “Miss Landon” (known to readers
as the poetess “L. E. L.”), and “Messrs. T. Hood, Alaric Watts, and Allan Cunningham” (anon., “To
Correspondents,” <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Gazette</hi>, 1 [1829]: 192). By 1830, contributors
included the poets Maria Jewsbury, William Howitt, and Thomas Pringle, and miscellaneous Scottish writers
Andrew Laing, William MacGillivray, John Malcolm, Andrew Picken, Leitch Ritchie, and David Vedder (all of whom
are named in the two special Anniversary Numbers of 15 May and 22 May 1830). Others who were said to
contribute included William Jerdan and James Fraser (the editors, respectively, of London’s 
<hi rend="i">Literary Gazette</hi> and <hi rend="i">Fraser’s Magazine</hi>). John Parker Lawson, and the
Edinburgh drama critic Christopher Torrop (see anon., “Literature: <hi rend="i">The Edinburgh Literary
Gazette</hi>,” <hi rend="i">Glasgow Courier</hi> [newspaper] 5 Nov 1829 [21]). Robert Macnish (known to
readers of <hi rend="i">Blackwood’s Magazine</hi> as “The Modern Pythagorean”) was also advertised as a
contributor (see <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Evening Post</hi> [newspaper] 16 Jan. 1830 [23]). For further
information on the <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi>, please see my articles “Thomas Hood, London, and the 
<hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Gazette</hi>” in <hi rend="i">English Language Notes</hi>, 27 (March 1990):
34-39, and “John Galt, the <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Gazette</hi>, and ‘The Black Ferry’” in 
<hi rend="i">Scotia: American-Canadian Journal of Scottish Studies</hi> 12 (1988): 44-54.</note></p>
          <p>The occasion of these remarks about William Blake was the publication of the second volume of
Allan Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives of the Most Eminent British Painters</hi>, in London. Cunningham’s
work attracted much interest in Edinburgh, partly as a result of Cunningham’s fame as a Scottish poet and
essayist. The first volume of the <hi rend="i">Lives</hi> had received an anonymous critique (almost certainly
written by Reverend Crichton) in the <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi> of July 1829.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n83" type="note">3</ref> Crichton quit the <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi> in anger in early
December: he cannot have written the two succeeding reviews of Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives</hi>, which
appeared in the <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi> in the following year.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n84" type="note">4</ref> Unlike the first notice of Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives</hi> (which had
contained Scottish words, phrases, and place-names), the second review is almost entirely English (rather than
Scottish), with its references to William Hazlitt, Henry Fuseli, and several other literary or artistic
figures in contemporary London. The second review has never been reprinted, or mentioned in print, since it
first appeared on 13 February 1830:
<q>
FAMILY LIBRARY, NO. X—CUNNINGHAM’S LIVES OF BRITISH PAINTERS.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n85" type="note">5</ref><lb/>
<lb/>
<hi rend="i">The Family Library, No. X. The Lives of the most eminent British Painters, Sculptors, and
Architects.</hi> By Allan Cunningham. Vol. II. London: J. Murray. 1830. 
						</q>
	<note id="n83"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Anon. rev., “Cunningham’s Lives of British Painters,” 
<hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Gazette: Devoted Exclusively to Literature, Criticism, Science, and the Arts.</hi>
1 (1829): 169-70. This initial review of Cunningham’s work may reasonably be attributed to Andrew Crichton.
(Crichton was born in Kirkmahoe, Scotland, where he knew Cunningham slightly as a youth: the reviewer claims
Cunningham as “an early acquaintance,” and refers fondly to “Kirkmahoe” [169]. For information on
Crichton, see the <hi rend="i">Dictionary of National Biography.</hi>)</note>
	<note id="n84"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Crichton “resigned the editorship” on 12 December 1829, and
subsequently had “no further connexion” with the <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi> (see anon., “Literary
Chit-Chat and Varieties,” <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Journal</hi> 3 [1830]: 28).</note>
	<note id="n85"><hi rend="s">5</hi> Anon. rev. in <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Gazette</hi> 2 (1830):
103-04. The only other mention of Blake was a brief announcement, in the “Literary Intelligence” column of
28 Nov. 1829, that “The next number of the Family Library” would be “the second volume of the Lives of
British Painters, including West, Fuseli, Barry, Blake, Opie, and Morland” (<hi rend="i">Gazette</hi> 1
[1829]: 463).</note></p>
          <p>ALTHOUGH sufficiently alive to the merits of Lockhart’s Napoleon, and Milman’s Jewish
History,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n86" type="note">6</ref> we are free to confess that
none of the volumes of the Family Library have hitherto delighted us more than the Lives of the Painters and
Sculptors by Allan Cunningham. <note id="n86"><hi rend="s">6</hi> John Gibson Lockhart’s 
<hi rend="i">History of Napoleon Buonaparte</hi>, and Henry H. Milman’s <hi rend="i">History of the Jews</hi>,
were both published in 1829, in the same “Family Library” series (published by the firm of John Murray) in
which Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives</hi> appeared.</note></p>
          <p>At first we had doubts as to whether Allan was exactly the best calculated person for the task,
and we thought that a formidable competitor might be found in Hazlitt,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n87" type="note">7</ref> by any other periodical caterer, in monthly volumes, to the public taste. We
have, however, been most agreeably disappointed. In the collection of facts and materials, the imagination of
the poet has been kept in subjection. His biographies are well digested, and are written with that feeling
which never fails to raise a corresponding interest in the heart of the reader. 
<note id="n87"><hi rend="s">7</hi> The reference is perhaps to William Hazlitt’s conversational portrait of the painter James
Northcote, entitled <hi rend="i">Boswell Redivivus</hi> (1827).</note></p>
          <p>In the former volume we were particularly pleased with the life of Gainsborough: although in
Hogarth he had an ampler fund of materials to draw from. The volume before us takes in West, Opie, Bird,
Morland, Fuseli, and Blake.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n88" type="note">8</ref> Of the
latter, we confess, we were comparatively ignorant: but from Mr. Cunningham’s account it is evident that his
mind was characterised as much by singularity as originality. It is a dangerous thing for a man in this
matter-of-fact age of the world, “to see visions and dream dreams:”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n89" type="note">9</ref> especially as (if we take the case of Haydon for an instance)
the public taste seems scarcely yet to have arisen from portrait to historical painting.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n90" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n88"><hi rend="s">8</hi> The quotation is from the New Testament: “Your sons and your daughters
shall prophesy, and your young men shall see visions and your old men shall dream dreams” (Acts
2.17).</note>
	<note id="n89"><hi rend="s">9</hi> The artists mentioned by the reviewer are Thomas Gainsborough (1727-88),
William Hogarth (1697-1764), Benjamin West (1738-1820), John Opie (1761-1807), Edward Bird (1772-1819), George
Morland (1763-1804), Henry Fuseli (1741-1825), and Blake. The reviewer has neglected to mention James Barry
(1741-1806), who also merits a chapter in Cunningham’s second volume.</note>
	<note id="n90"><hi rend="s">10</hi> The historical painter Benjamin Robert Haydon (1786-1846) was imprisoned
for debt during 1822-23.</note></p>
          <p>We are thus induced to make a few extracts from the biography of Blake, not only as we regard it
as the most singular in the volume, but as it is likely to be the newest to our readers. He appears to have
been a poet as well as a painter.</p>
		<q>
Though Blake lost himself a little in the enchanted region of song, he seems not to have neglected to make
himself master of the graver, or to have forgotten his love of designs and sketches . . . .<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n91" type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n91"><hi rend="s">11</hi> The review quotes three paragraphs (beginning with this sentence),
dealing with Blake’s “intertwin[ing] of poetry and painting,” and his relationship with his wife
Catherine, from Cunningham’s volume (147-49). The three paragraphs are printed as a single paragraph, and
contain numerous other minor alterations, in the review.</note></q>
          <p>The account of his drawing portraits from imagination, under the impression that they stood
meantime visibly revealed, is very strange, and somewhat unaccountable: as also of his holding converse with
the spirits of the departed great on the sea-shore at twilight.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n92" type="note">12</ref> There is something wildly impressive in this enthusiasm, awakening at once
our pity and our admiration. As was to have been expected, this waywardness of disposition led to an old age
of poverty and neglect, sweetened alone by the companionship of his admirable wife. We have given their
courtship: let us conclude with Blake’s death-bed:—
<q>
He had now reached his seventy-first year, and the strength of nature was fast yielding. . . .<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n93" type="note">13</ref>
	<note id="n92"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Cunningham describes Blake’s “friendships with Homer and Moses: with
Pindar and Virgil: with Dante and Milton,” during his three years at Felpham, beginning in 1800: “These
great men, [Blake] asserted, appeared to him in visions, and even entered into conversation” 
(<hi rend="i">Lives</hi> 2: 159).</note>
	<note id="n93"><hi rend="s">13</hi> The review quotes three paragraphs (beginning with this sentence),
dealing with Blake’s last days and death, from Cunningham’s volume (179-80). As with the preceding
quotation, the three paragraphs appear as one, and contain several minor alterations, in the
review.</note></q></p>
          <p>It is delightful to trace to progress of a man of true genius. No earthly impediments can resist
his progress: on he goes, conquering and to conquer:<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n94"
type="note">14</ref> soaring and ascending over the clouds that at first hid him from sight, or obstructed his
early aspirations. Such is Allan Cunningham, to whom we shortly intend dedicating a leading article.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n95" type="note">15</ref> He has written a multitude of good things:
but, excepting his inimitable imitations of the old ballad,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n96" type="note">16</ref> his “Lives of the Painters, Sculptors, and Architects,” is his best.
<note id="n94"><hi rend="s">14</hi> The reviewer alludes to the New Testament: “And I saw, and behold a
white horse: and he that sat on him had a bow: and a crown was given unto him: and he went forth conquering,
and to conquer” (Revelation 6.2).</note>
	<note id="n95"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Although the <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi> carried many notices and reviews
concerning Cunningham, the promised “leading article” never materialized.</note>
	<note id="n96"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Cunningham wrote many “imitations of the old ballad” for R. H.
Cromek’s <hi rend="i">Remains of Nithsdale and Galloway Song</hi> (1810). Cromek (who also published the
1808 edition of Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave</hi>, with designs by Blake) would perhaps have been the
best-known link between Cunningham and Blake, in Scotland in 1830, where Cromek was still renowned for his 
<hi rend="i">Reliques of Burns</hi> (1808). For further information on Cunningham’s association with Cromek, see
David Hogg, <hi rend="i">The Life of Allan Cunningham</hi> (London: Hodder and Stoughton, 1875), and De
Quincey, “London Reminiscences” (1840: rpt. <hi rend="i">Collected Writtings of Thomas De Quincey</hi>,
ed. D. Masson, 14 vols. [Edinburgh: Black, 1889-90] 3: 146).</note></p>
          <p>The reference to Cunningham by his first name alone, in the second sentence of this review, is
very striking. Of all the known regular contributors to
<pb id="p25-134" n="134"/>
the <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Gazette</hi> in 1830, only Thomas De Quincey and Thomas Hood knew Allan
Cunningham: all three men had worked extensively for the <hi rend="i">London Magazine</hi> during 1821-23. On
the surface, an article in the 1830 <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi> which refers to Cunningham simply as “Allan”
might be suspected as having been written by either De Quincey or Hood. Yet the statements about Blake seem
too matter-of-fact to be plausibly attributed to either of those authors. The article also contains more
biblical allusions than would perhaps be expected in a short piece by Hood or De Quincey. Since the same
review also refers to “Mr. Cunningham,” it may have been the product of more than one pen. David Moir, who
was the most frequent reviewer for the 1830 <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi>, makes no mention of the three notices
of Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives</hi>, in his voluminous surviving papers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n97" type="note">17</ref>
	<note id="n97"><hi rend="s">17</hi> None of the three reviews was mentioned by Moir, either in the formal
list of his own contributions to the <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi> (which he left at the time of his death in his
private papers), or in his almost weekly letters to William Blackwood (in which he regularly informed
Blackwood of his latest publications). Moir’s correspondence and private papers survive at the National
Library of Scotland (see the Blackwood collection, and Accession 9856) and the Thomas Fisher Rare Book Room
(University of Toronto Library).</note></p>
          <p>A third review, concerning the third volume of Cunningham’s <hi rend="i">Lives</hi>, appeared
in the <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi> of 12 June 1830. Although this final piece does not mention Blake, it seems
to have been written by the same critic who wrote the second review.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n98" type="note">18</ref> The third review refers to Cunningham by his first name, and even as “our
friend Allan.” The evidence of a possible connection with De Quincey comes in the form of a private letter,
from the owner of the <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi> to David Moir, dated five days before the publication of the
third review: the letter simply states enigmatically (after discussing Moir’s own work for the 
<hi rend="i">Gazette</hi>), “De Quincey is in town &amp; at Wilson’s as you will see from the
inclosed.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n99" type="note">19</ref> Whether “the
inclosed” was an article of De Quincey’s, an article by someone else which De Quincey was merely conveying
to the <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi>, a book intended for review, or something quite different, is unclear. Since
De Quincey undoubtedly knew about William Blake,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n100"
type="note">20</ref> and had a high opinion of Allan Cunningham,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n101" type="note">21</ref> it is conceivable that the two reviews of Cunningham’s 
<hi rend="i">Lives</hi> in the 1830 <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi> might have been among the rapid pieces of journalism
which De Quincey was obliged to produce, for economic reasons, at about that time.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n102" type="note">22</ref> But in the absence of external evidence, the most that can
safely be claimed is that De Quincey probably saw the article about Blake in the <hi rend="i">Gazette.</hi>
	<note id="n98"><hi rend="s">18</hi> The reviewer displays a familiarity with the previous volumes, and
recalls “[h]aving in our former notices had occasion to dwell on our friend Allan’s qualifications for the
office of an historian” (anon. rev., “Family Library,” <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Gazette</hi> 2
[1830]: 374-76). The second and third reviews are similar in style and in their “English” perspective: but
both are extremely unlike the initial review of the <hi rend="i">Lives</hi>, in spite of this reference to
“our former notices,” the second and third reviews were almost certainly written by someone other than the
author of the first review.</note>
	<note id="n99"><hi rend="s">19</hi> David Blackie, letter to Moir, 7 June 1830 (National Library of Scotland
MS Acc. 9856, no. 37). By “Wilson’s, Blackie refers to John Wilson, the editor of 
<hi rend="i">Blackwood’s Edinburgh Magazine</hi>, who was a close friend of De Quincey. Manuscripts in the
National Library of Scotland are quoted with the permission of its Trustees.</note>
	<note id="n100"><hi rend="s">20</hi> De Quincey mentions “that fine mystic, Blake the artist,” before
quoting from Blake’s poetic dedication to the 1808 edition of <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi>, in his “Society
of the Lakes” (1840; rpt. <hi rend="i">Collected Writtings</hi> 2: 400). Although this is the sole reference
to Blake in De Quincey’s known writings, it suggests a fair degree of interest and familiarity with some of
Blake’s work.</note>
	<note id="n101"><hi rend="s">21</hi> De Quincey describes Cunningham as “a man of so much original
genius” in his “London Reminiscences” (1840; rpt. <hi rend="i">Collected Writings</hi> 3: 146). It is
perhaps significant that, in a letter of 7 July 1829, Cunningham wrote to an unknown correspondent, concerning
De Quincey and the <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Gazette.</hi> “I see you are united with my friend Mr De
Quincey in this Critical undertaking of yours. . . . I beg you will name my name to him” (National Library
of Scotland MS Acc. 15973, f. 32).</note>
	<note id="n102"><hi rend="s">22</hi> For a listing of many of De Quincey’s anonymous articles, “written
with the left hand” from 1829 to 1846, see R. H. Byrns, “Some Unrepublished Articles of De Quincey in 
<hi rend="i">Blackwood’s Magazine</hi>” (<hi rend="i">Bulletin of Research in the Humanities</hi> 85 [1982]:
344-51).</note></p>
          <p>Whoever wrote the remarks on Blake in the <hi rend="i">Edinburgh Literary Gazette</hi>, it seems
likely that the piece attracted some interest, not only among readers in Scotland, but more especially among
those contributors to the <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi> who had been acquainted with Allan Cunningham. The 
<hi rend="i">Gazette</hi> enjoyed a relatively high reputation during its fourteen months of existence, with an
appeal that was mainly “confined to the sound reasoner, and philosophical enquirer.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n103" type="note">23</ref> Although the <hi rend="i">Gazette</hi>
seemed “eminently fitted to succeed,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n104"
type="note">24</ref> its circulation unfortunately never exceeded 300.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n105" type="note">25</ref>
	<note id="n103"><hi rend="s">23</hi> H., “Edinburgh Chit-Chat,” <hi rend="i">Kelso Mail</hi> (newspaper),
15 Oct. 1829 (1).</note>
	<note id="n104"><hi rend="s">24</hi> “Literature: <hi rend="i">The Edinburgh Literary Gazette</hi>,” 
<hi rend="i">Glasgow Courier</hi> (cited in n2, above).</note>
	<note id="n105"><hi rend="s">25</hi> David Blackie, letter to Moir, 14 July 1830 (NLS MS Acc 9856, no.
37).</note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p25-135" n="135" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
