<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>25.3.freed</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">“Sun-Clad Chastity” and Blake’s “Maiden Queens”: Comus, Thel, and
“The Angel”</title>
        <author n="Freed">Eugenie R. Freed</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1991/1992</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1991/92</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">25.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Eugenie R. Freed</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1986"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_25">
    <body>
      <pb id="p25-104" n="104"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-25-3-0005">
        <head>
          <title type="main">
            <hi rend="b">“Sun-Clad Chastity” and Blake’s “Maiden Queens”: <hi rend="i">Comus,
                Thel</hi>, and “The Angel”</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <byline>by <docAuthor>Eugenie R. <name>Freed</name></docAuthor></byline>
		<q> . . . To him that dares<lb/>
 Arm his profane tongue with contemptuous words<lb/>
 Against
          the sun-clad power of chastity;<lb/>
 Fain would I something say, yet to what end?<lb/>
          (Milton, <hi rend="i">A Masque Presented at Ludlow Castle, 1634</hi> 
            [<hi rend="i">Comus</hi>] 779-82) </q>
        <p>In her discussion of Blake’s illustrations to Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, Pamela
          Dunbar comments:</p>
        <p>Blake was a tireless critic of the “double standard” of sexual morality and of the
          repression of “natural desire.” It is therefore not surprising that he should have
          transformed Milton’s “sage/ And serious doctrine of virginity” (785-86) into a sterile and
          destructive dogma, and his virtuous Lady into a coy, deluded and self-denying miss. . .
          .(10)</p>
        <p>The work in which this “sage / And serious doctrine” was mounted was the subject of the
          earliest of Blake’s commissioned series of Milton illustrations. Blake executed them for
          the Reverend Joseph Thomas in c. 1801;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n1"
type="note">1</ref> but he had long
          reflected on the theme of Milton’s masque, with wit and subtlety arming his “profane
          [read: ‘iconoclastic’] tongue with contemptuous words” against it in the poems I discuss
          in this essay (to mention only two), years before he made <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> the
          subject of a series of paintings. <note id="n1"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Butlin 1: 373-74. The
            “Thomas” set of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> illustrations is now in the collection of the
            Huntington Library in San Marino, CA. Blake executed a second set for Thomas Butts c.
            1815; this series is in the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston, MA.</note></p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Comus</hi> was demonstrably one of the works on Blake’s mind while he was
          sketching motifs for <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi> in his Notebook during
          1790-93, for he jotted down quotations from it on pages 30 and 36 of the Notebook.<ref
            target="n2" type="note">2</ref> Characteristically, it was Milton’s virtuous Lady who
          came contrarily into his mind when, while copying and drafting poems into the Notebook at
          some time during this period,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n3"
type="note">3</ref> Blake opened it at page
          102, and paused to. contemplate a sketch of his own (illus. 1) which had been suggested by
          a passage from Book 4 of <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost:</hi><q> . . . into their inmost
            bower<lb/>
 Handed they went; and eased the putting off<lb/>
 These troublesome disguises
            which we wear,<lb/>
 Straight side by side were laid, nor turned I ween<lb/>
 Adam from
            his fair spouse, nor Eve the rites<lb/>
 Mysterious of connubial love refused. . . .<lb/>
              (<hi rend="i">PL</hi> 4.738-43) </q>
<figure n="BB122.1.104.MS" rend="file" width="958" height="759">
            <head>1. “Adam and Eve,” from Blake’s Notebook, page 102.</head>
            <figDesc>By permission of the British Library.</figDesc>
          </figure> The pencil sketch shows two nude figures, seen full-frontal, walking hand in
          hand toward, and looking directly at, the viewer: a long-haired Eve, and a curly-haired
          Adam, much as they appear in Blake’s earliest extant Milton illustrations.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n4"
            type="note">4</ref>
	<note id="n2"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Butlin 1: 90-91.</note>	
            <note id="n3"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Erdman suggests “a beginning date of 1791 or later, for the
            inscribing of the Songs” and a terminal date of late October 1792. (<hi rend="i">The
              Notebook of William Blake</hi>, page 7 of the editorial preface).</note>	
              <note id="n4"><hi rend="s">4</hi> The sketch on page 102 of the Notebook was not used by Blake
in
            this form in any other extant composition. It is part of a series of illustrations of
              <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> interspersed among designs for the emblem book 
              <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise.</hi> Blake’s so-called “Milton Gallery” is dated by F.
            W. Bateson (105) c. 1790-91. See Erdman, <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire</hi>
            (437-39). (Butlin 1: 104; compare with the earliest representation of Adam and Eve, 2:
            pl. 111, 1: 40). The drawing in the Notebook is reproduced as no. 14 in Keynes
            (1970).</note></p>
        <p>Blake covered the page facing this drawing (Notebook 103) with drafts of poems (illus.
          2). Three poems that appear here were to be etched as <hi rend="i">Songs of
            Experience</hi>: “The Chimney Sweeper,” “Holy Thursday,” and “The Angel.” 
            <pb id="p25-105" n="105"/>
The first two of these arise from “Songs of Innocence” having the
          same titles. The third, “The Angel,” was inspired in part by the design that presented
          itself to his eye on the opposite page of the Notebook. Blake obviously recalled the
          context in <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> of the lines he had illustrated, and affirmed
          for himself Milton’s indignant condemnation there of “hypocrites” who “austerely talk / Of
          purity . . . and innocence, / Defaming as impure what God declares / Pure . . .” 
            (<hi rend="i">PL</hi> 4.744-47). However, in the spirit of his own dictum 
            <figure n="BB122.1.105.MS" rend="file" width="793" height="1000">
            <head>2. Page of draft poems facing “Adam and Eve,” from Blake’s Notebook, page
              103.</head>
            <figDesc>By permission of the British Library.</figDesc>
          </figure> that “Opposition is true Friendship,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n5" type="note">5</ref> the
          principal Miltonic influence in this poem emanates not so much from the 
            <hi rend="i">vindication</hi>—with which Blake concurred—of sexual love in 
<hi rend="i">Paradise
            Lost</hi>, as from the defence in <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> of chastity, which he opposed.
          Having deliberately enrolled himself in the Devil’s party, Blake in effect seconds the
          urging of Comus: “List Lady be not coy, and be not cozened / With that same vaunted name
          virginity . . .” (<hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 736-37), and in “The Angel” ironically
          dramatizes such “cozening”: 
		<q> I dreamt a dream what can it mean<lb/>
 And that I was a
            maiden queen<lb/>
 Guarded by an angel mild<lb/>
 Witless woe was ne’er beguiled<lb/>
<lb/>
            And I wept both night &amp; day<lb/>
 And he wiped my tears away<lb/>
 And I wept both day
            &amp; night<lb/>
 And hid from him my hearts delight<lb/>
<lb/>
 So he took his wings &amp;
            fled<lb/>
 Then the morn blushd rosy red<lb/>
 I dried my tears &amp; armd my fears<lb/>
            With ten thousand shields and spears<lb/>
<lb/>
 Soon my angel came again<lb/>
 I was armd
            he came in vain<lb/>
 [But <hi rend="i">del.</hi>] For the time of youth was fled<lb/>
            And grey hairs were on my head<lb/>
<lb/>
 (Notebook 103. The version engraved for the 
              <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> differs only in punctuation.) </q>
The speaker of
          “The Angel,” in her dream-life a “maiden queen,” rebuffs her angel-lover because of her
          own fears and inhibitions, keeping him in a state of tantalized frustration both in her
          subconscious and her waking life. Soon it is too late to recant: 
		<q> I was arm’d, he came
            in vain,<lb/>
 For the time of youth was fled,<lb/>
 And grey hairs were on my head.<lb/>
            (14-16, E 24)<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n6" type="note">6</ref>
	<note id="n5"><hi rend="s">5</hi><hi
                rend="i"> The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> 20, E 42.</note>
	<note id="n6"><hi
                rend="s">6</hi> The last two lines of “The Angel” were taken up by Blake from the
              ending he had devised to the long first draft of “Infant Sorrow,” already written into
              the Notebook some pages earlier (E 794, 797-99). They there conclude a poem, intended
              to encompass human life from birth to old age, which also emphasizes the
              self-defeating consequences of society’s hypocritically repressive attitudes towards
              sexuality.</note></q>
This petrified virgin inhabits a fallen and time-bound world in
          which her imagination, corrupted by the “defamation” of sexuality perpetrated by those
          Milton calls “hypocrites,” creates a “horrible darkness . . . impressed with reflections
          of desire.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n7" type="note">7</ref> An engraving
of 1790 attributed to Blake
          (illus. 3) shows a nude woman, revealingly draped, asleep in a sitting position on a
          couch. A winged Cupid aims an arrow at her <hi rend="i">mons veneris</hi>, while from
          beneath the couch emerges a small, terrifyingly monstrous creature with the body of a man
          and the head of a bull elephant, complete with sharp upcurved tusks and phallic proboscis.
          (Blake placed a similarly elephant-headed figure, less sinister but obviously having the
          same symbolic intention, among the monsters at the banqueting table in his second version
          of the banquet of Comus [illus. 4].<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n8"
type="note">8</ref>) The engraving
          casts an interesting light on Blake’s speculations 
<pb id="p25-106" n="106"/>
<figure n="falsa.25.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="500" height="316">
            <head>3. <hi rend="i">Falsa ad Coelum Mittunt Insomnia Manes</hi>, engraving attributed
              to Blake (after Fuseli), 1790.</head>
            <figDesc>By permission of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
          </figure> on the subject of female erotic fantasies and fears around the time of his
          composition of “The Angel” and <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>, as
          well as, possibly, <hi rend="i">Thel.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n9"
type="note">9</ref>	
            <note id="n7"><hi rend="s">7</hi><hi rend="i"> Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> 7.11, E
            50. Sketches for the designs finally etched with the text of this work appear in various
            parts of Blake’s Notebook, suggesting that this illuminated book (dated 1793 on its
            title page) was in the making during the same period as the <hi rend="i">Songs of
              Experience.</hi> (See page 49 of Erdman’s preface to the facsimile.)</note>	
            <note id="n8"><hi rend="s">8</hi> This engraving, executed after Fuseli’s design entitled 
              <hi rend="i">Falsa ad Coelum mittunt Insomnia Manes</hi>, is reproduced as pl. XXXV in
            Keynes [1956]; and in Bindman as pl. 80. The banquet scene in the later 
              <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> series is reproduced by Butlin in 2: pl. 628. (My reading of the
            significance of the elephant-headed figure in the <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> series does
            not preclude Pamela Dunbar’s suggestion [24] that it represents the vice of
            Gluttony.)</note>
	<note id="n9"><hi rend="s">9</hi> See note 16 below regarding the
            dating of <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel.</hi></note></p>
        <p>The “maiden queen” of “The Angel” is evidently derived from the classical virgin goddess
          of the moon, Diana. Blake may have been influenced by Milton’s description of the
          nocturnal scence as Adam and Eve enter their nuptial bower, when the moon “rising in
          clouded majesty, at length / Apparent queen unveiled her peerless light” 
            (<hi rend="i">PL</hi> 4.607-08). But his image owes more to “Dian the huntress . . . fair
          silver-shafted Queen forever chaste” (440-41) from Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus.</hi><ref
            target="n10" type="note">10</ref> The angel of Blake’s poem also emerges, in an
          ironically modified form, from passages of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n11"
            type="note">11</ref> together with the maiden’s dream:
<q> So dear to heaven is saintly
            chastity,<lb/>
 That when a soul is found sincerely so,<lb/>
 A thousand liveried angels
            lackey her,<lb/>
 Driving far off each thing of sin and guilt,<lb/>
 And in clear dream
            and solemn vision<lb/>
 Tell her of things that no gross ear can hear. . . . (452-57)
			</q>
	<note id="n10"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Bette Charlotte Werner explains the presence of
            a mysterious female driving a team of serpents in the sky in Blake’s fourth 
              <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> illustration (in both series, the Attendant Spirit addressing the
            Brothers) by identifying her with the moon-goddess Diana, “represented as a severe and
            uncompromising guardian of chastity” (31).</note>
	<note id="n11"><hi rend="s">11</hi>
            Compare as well the Lady’s soliloquy: 
			<q> O welcome pure-eyed Faith, white-handed
              Hope,<lb/>
 Thou hovering angel girt with golden wings,<lb/>
 And thou unblemished form
              of Chastity . . .<lb/>
 . . . [I] now believe<lb/>
 That he, the Supreme Good . . .<lb/>
              Would send a glistering guardian if need were<lb/>
 To keep my life and honour
              unassailed.<lb/>
 Comus 212-18 </q>
See my discussion below of the Cloud in 
              <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel.</hi></note></p>
        <p>The plate of “The Angel” in the <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi><ref target="n12"
            type="note">12</ref> shows the recumbent maiden, clothed in a long gown, leaning her
          face on one hand while with the other, in an absurd gesture of repulsion, she pushes away
          the angel, who seems to be trying to impart to her “things that no gross ear can hear”
          (illus. 5-7). Her expression betrays “witless woe” and preoccupation with her inner
          conflict; his reflects distress at the rejection, while his arms reach out to her,
          attempting vainly to persuade her to 
          “turn away no more.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n13" type="note">13</ref> 
          In the line “Then the morn blush’d rosy red. . . <corr type="emend">”</corr> Blake recollects
          Adam’s description of the maiden modesty of Eve on the first night of their marriage: 
          <corr type="emend">“</corr> . . . To the nuptial bower / I led her blushing like the morn . . .”
          (<hi rend="i">PL</hi> 8. 510-11). But, Blake implies, in the fallen world, Eve’s “sweet 
          reluctant amorous <corr type="emend">delay” (<hi rend="i">PL</hi></corr> 4.311) is perverted 
          to a “hypocrite modesty,” such that “When thou awakest . . . Then com’st thou forth a modest 
          virgin, knowing to dissemble. . . .”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n14" type="note">14</ref> 
          The hysterical defence of her chastity with “ten thousand shields and spears” by the protagonist 
          of “The Angel” is a parody of the simile in Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, in which the 
          chaste virgin is compared to “a quivered nymph with arrows keen,” whose “virgin purity” 
          encases her in “complete steel,” proof against “savage fierce, bandit, or mountaineer” 
          <figure n="but528.1.5.wc" id="but528.1.wc.05" work-copy="but528.1" rend="db" width="788" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>WBlake</figTranscr>
            <head>4. Blake, illustration to Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>: “The Magic Banquet
              with the Lady Spellbound,” c. 1815.</head>
            <figDesc>Gift of Mrs. John L. Gardner and George N. Black. Courtesy of the Museum of
              Fine Arts, Boston.</figDesc>
          </figure> 
          (420-21, 425-26). Blake had turned to the same passage for the image of female
          scorn that terrifies Thel, of “. . . eyelids stord with arrows ready drawn, / Where a
          thousand fighting men in ambush lie . . .” (<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 6.13-14, E 6), perhaps
          intermingled in both poems with his satirical response to Edmund Burk’s exclamation of
          horror at the fate of the beautiful Queen of France, Marie Antoinette: 
		<q> Little did I
            dream that I should have lived to see disasters fallen upon her in a nation of gallant
            men. . . I thought ten thousand swords must have leaped from their scabbards to avenge
            even a look that threatened her with insult. (76)<ref target="n15" type="note">15</ref></q>
	<note id="n12"><hi rend="s">12</hi> Blake first sketched this design as one
            of his “Emblem” series, numbering it 42, on page 65 of the Notebook (illus. 7). In the
            original the “angel” has no wings and is obviously an importunate infant, possibly the
            same who is being lifted up by the hair from what looks like a cabbage-patch in the
            emblem-design on an earlier page of the Notebook (illus. 6). The latter eventually
            became pl. 1 of the 1793 series <hi rend="i">For Children: The Gates of Paradise</hi>,
            entitled “I found him beneath a Tree” (E 32). Blake evidently perceived a different
            application for “Emblem 42,” although the themes of the two Notebook designs are
            related. “I found him beneath a Tree” refers to the prudish fiction that mothers found
            their babies in cabbage-patches, an answer supplied to children in the eighteenth and
            nineteenth centuries when they asked where babies came from. The “witless woe,”
            frigidity and fear of the “maiden queen” of “The Angel” seem a likely development from
            an upbringing of this kind.</note>
	<note id="n13"><hi rend="s">13</hi> “Introduction.”
              <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> l.16, E 18. (The plate of “The Angel” is
            reproduced in Erdman, <hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake</hi> 83.)</note>
	<note id="n14"><hi
              rend="s">14</hi><hi rend="i"> Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> 6.8-10, 16, E
            49.</note>
	<note id="n15"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Edmund Burke, <hi rend="i">Reflections on
              the Revolution in France</hi> (1790). Erdman points out that Blake’s poem “Let the
            Brothels of Paris be opened . . .,” started on page 99 of his Notebook, satirizes the
            same passage (<hi rend="i">Prophet Against Empire</hi> 184).</note></p>
        <p>The charming <hi rend="i">Book of Thel</hi>, Blake’s earliest prophetic book, probably
          composed some time before “The Angel,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n16"
type="note">16</ref> is also both
          inspired by Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and opposed in principle to it.<ref
            target="n17" type="note">17</ref> The virgin Thel, whose name means “wish” or “will”
          (from the Greek verb meaning “to desire”), is the only one of Blake’s personages who is
          given the option of accepting or rejecting the fallen condition of mortality. Thel avails
          herself of this privilege, choosing, when she has previewed this “land 
            <pb id="p25-107" n="107"/>
of sorrows &amp; of tears” (<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 6.5, E 6), to flee
“back .
          . . into the vales of Har” (6.22, E 6).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n18"
type="note">18</ref> The poem
          makes it clear that the “daughter of beauty” will indeed, as she foresees, “fade away”
            (<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 1.3, 3.21 and 5.12, E 3, 5, and 6). As Spenser put it in a
          passage that Blake certainly had in mind, “. . . that faire flowre of beauty fades away, /
          As doth the lilly fresh before the sunny ray.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n19" type="note">19</ref> She
          will leave behind no trace or useful legacy of her existence—“And all shall say, ‘Without
          a use this shining woman liv’d . . .’” (<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 3.22, E 5)—because she
          refuses to commit herself to earthly generation, fearing the pains of Experience that
          inevitably accompany sexuality in the fallen world. <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>
          affirms that sexuality, and the giving of oneself in love to procreation, is good, and a
          necessary commitment to life on earth. For the most part it does so within a gentle,
          almost childlike ambience that sets this poem apart from the intensity of the 
          <hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi> and the later 
          prophecies,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n20" type="note">20</ref> 
          and places it between “Innocence” and “Experience,” into which latter condition 
<figure n="songsie.b.p49-41" id="songsie.b.illbk.49" work-copy="songsie.b" rend="db" width="637" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>The Angel<lb/>
	I Dreamt a Dream! what can it mean?<lb/>
	And that I was a maiden Queen;<lb/>
	Guarded by an Angel mild;<lb/>
	Witless woe, was ne’er beguil’d!<lb/>
	And I wept both night and day<lb/>
	And he wip’d my tears away<lb/>
	And I wept both day and night<lb/>
	And hid from him my hearts delight<lb/>
	So he took his wings and fled:<lb/>
	Then the morn blush’d rosy red;<lb/>
	I dried my tears &amp; arm’d my fears,<lb/>
	With ten thousand shields and spears<lb/>
	Soon my Angel came again;<lb/>
	I was arm’d, he came in vain;<lb/>
	For the time of youth was fled<lb/>
	And grey hairs were on my head</figTranscr>
	<head>5. “The Angel,” from Blake’s <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and
	  Experience.</hi></head>
	<figDesc>By permission of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
</figure> 
          Thel enters only hesitantly, fearfully, and 
          briefly.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n21" type="note">21</ref>
	<note id="n16"><hi rend="s">16</hi> Blake began to etch 
              <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, the earliest of his “prophetic books,” in 1789
(according to
            the title page). Erdman notes that pl. 6, carrying the final section of the poem, and
            the plate bearing “Thel’s Motto,” “are later than other plates of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>
            in style of lettering . . . Hence [plate 6] may be a revised version of the poem’s
            conclusion” (<hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake</hi> 40). Kathleen Raine (72-75) believes
            that there are “unmistakeable allusions” in <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> to
            Porphyry’s Neoplatonic symbolism in his treatise on Homer’s <hi rend="i">Cave of the
              Nymphs</hi>, which Blake may have derived from Thomas Taylor’s translation published
            in 1788; and also that Blake drew in the final section of the poem on Taylor’s 
              <hi rend="i">A Dissertation on the Eleusinian and Bacchic Mysteries</hi>, published in
            1790.</note>
	<note id="n17"><hi rend="s">17</hi> S. Foster Damon was the first modern
            critic to recognize the link between <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book
              of Thel</hi>, in his 1957 article “Blake and Milton.” Rodger L. Tarr perceives Thel as
            a kind of “negation” of Milton’s doctrine concerning the wisdom of
            virginity.</note>
	<note id="n18"><hi rend="s">18</hi> “The vales of Har” (from Blake’s
            earlier poem <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> 2.4, E 277) offer scenes of pastoral serenity.
            Though apparently associated with primal innocence, they prove ultimately to be a
            setting for the condition of senility, or a form of arrested emotional development.
            However, see note 52 for a different critical view.</note>
	<note id="n19"><hi rend="s">19</hi><hi rend="i"> The Faerie Queene</hi> 3.4.38.8-9. See the discussion below
of
            the significance of the “sunny” flocks tended by Thel’s sisters. Although my own reading
            of the poem takes a somewhat different line from hers, I do agree with Kathleen Raine’s
            emphasis (1: 106) on this and other parallels between Blake’s poem and Spenser’s “Garden
            of Adonis,” and with her assertion that “Mutability is <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>’s theme,
            as it was Spenser’s” (1: 100). <p>Further Spenserian sources for <hi rend="i">The Book
                of Thel</hi>, employed by Blake in a “contrary” spirit, are explored by Robert F.
              Gleckner (31-45 and 287-302). Gleckner <corr type="emend">demonstrates</corr> persuasively that
in 
                <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> Blake parodies Spenserian and Petrarchan “sublimations of the senses
and
              desire” (32), both in the <hi rend="i">Amoretti</hi> and in the figure of Alma in Book
              2 of <hi rend="i">The Faerie Queene.</hi> Gleckner also relates Thel’s wish “to die
              because she is of no ‘use’” (293) especially to the encounter between Spenser’s
              Redcrosse Knight and Despaire in Book 1, showing that “<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> is a
              severe attack upon the underpinnings of Spenser’s Book I and the language in which it
              is couched” (288).</p></note>
	<note id="n20"><hi rend="s">20</hi> S. Foster Damon
            (1965), noting that Thel does not reappear in any other of Blake’s writings, commented
            disarmingly that she is “far too nice a girl to fit in amongst Blake’s furious
            elementals” (401). Damon speculated that Blake’s account of Thel may have been an
            allegorized narrative woven about a miscarriage, or the premature birth and death of an
            infant, perhaps Blake’s own child.</note>
	<note id="n21"><hi rend="s">21</hi> David
            Wagenknecht comments on Thel’s flight back “unhinderd till she came into the vales of
            Har” that “of course this last line of the poem represents a failure,” but adds that
            Blake may mean by it “that Thel can return, at will, to however uninspired a condition .
            . . in short, that she is still a virgin ([though there are] indications that she will
            not remain one forever), but a wiser one than when she began” (162).</note></p>
        <p><hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> shares its pastoral setting with both 
          <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and the <hi rend="i">Songs of 
          Innocence.</hi><ref target="n22" type="note">22</ref> 
          “The secret air” Thel seeks out “down by the river of Adona” (1.2, 4, E 3) was
          inspired by the “regions mild of calm and serene air” (<hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 4) from
          which the Attendant Spirit descends, the “broad fields of the sky” (978) to which he
          returns again in the closing lines of <hi rend="i">Comus.</hi> Here Adonis 
          appears:<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n23" type="note">23</ref>
		<q>
          	Iris there with humid bow,<lb/>
          	Waters the odorous banks that blow<lb/>
          	Flowers of more mingled hue<lb/>
          	Than her purfled scarf can shew,<lb/>
          	And drenches with Elysian dew . . .<lb/>
          	Beds of hyacinth and roses,<lb/>
            Where young Adonis oft reposes,<lb/>
            Waxing well of his deep wound<lb/>
            In slumber soft, and on the ground<lb/>
            Sadly sits the Assyrian queen. . . .<lb/>
            (<hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 991-1001)
		</q>
          Milton’s rainbow “drenches” and nourishes “beds of hyacinth
          and roses,” symbolic of regeneration and love, where the youth Adonis, beloved of “the
          Assyrian queen” Venus, lies 
          <figure n="BB122.1.65.MS" rend="file" width="793" height="1000">
            <head>6. Draft sketch of emblem, “I found him beneath a Tree,” Blake’s Notebook, page
              63.</head>
            <figDesc>By permission of the British Library.</figDesc>
          </figure> 
          recovering from the wound given him by a boar. Milton’s passage—and the opening
          lines of <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi> as well—stem at least partially from Spenser’s
          account of Venus lovingly sustaining Adonis in the “Garden of Adonis” in <hi rend="i">The
          Faerie Queene.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n24" type="note">24</ref> 
          Both Spenser and Milton
          associate Adonis with fertility in the fallen 
          world<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n25" type="note">25</ref>—the 
          combating of death and decay by means of earthly generation. Time, in
          Spenser’s Garden, “beats down both leaves and buds without regard” (<hi rend="i">FQ</hi>
          3.6.39.8). Though Venus weeps for their loss, she has no remedy, for “All things decay in
          time, and to their end do draw” (40.9). Adonis embodies the principle of plenitude, which
          continually redresses the ravages of Time: 
		<q> All be he subiect to mortalitie<lb/>
 Yet is
            eterne in mutabilitie<lb/>
 And by succession made perpetuall. . . .<lb/>
 (47.4-6) </q>
          Thel, lamenting by the river of Adona, compares herself to a “watry bow” 
            (<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 1.8)—Milton’s “humid bow.” Through a series of parallel similes
(“shadows in
          the water,” “a smile upon an infants <figure n="BB122.1.67.MS" rend="file" width="793" height="1000">
            <head>7. Draft sketch of “The Angel,” Blake’s Notebook, page 65.</head>
            <figDesc>By permission of the British Library.</figDesc>
          </figure>
<pb id="p25-108" n="108"/>
<figure n="thel.d.p4" id="thel.d.illbk.04" work-copy="thel.d" rend="db" width="725" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>2<lb/>
	Why should the mistress of the vales of Har, utter a sigh.<lb/>
	She ceasd &amp; smild in tears, then sat down in her silver shrine.<lb/>
	Thel answerd, O thou little virgin of the peaceful valley.<lb/>
	Giving to those that cannot crave, the voiceless, the o’erfired.<lb/>
	Thy breath doth nourish the innocent lamb, he smells thy milky garments,<lb/>
	He crops thy flowers. while thou sittest smiling in his face,<lb/>
	Wiping his mild and meekin mouth from all contagious taints.<lb/>
	Thy wine doth purify the golden honey, thy perfume,<lb/>
	Which thou dost scatter on every little blade of grass that springs.<lb/>
	Revives the milked cow, &amp; tames the fire-breathing steed.<lb/>
	But Thel is like a faint cloud kindled at the rising sun;<lb/>
	I vanish from my pearly throne, and who shall find my place.<lb/>
	Queen of the vales the Lilly answerd, ask the tender cloud,<lb/>
	And it shall tell thee why it glitters in the morning sky.<lb/>
	And why it scatters its bright beauty thro’ the humid air.<lb/>
	Descend O little cloud &amp; hover before the eyes of Thel,<lb/>
	The Cloud descended. and the Lilly bowd her modest head:<lb/>
	And went to mind her numerous charge among the verdant grass.</figTranscr>
            <head>8. <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, plate 2.</head>
            <figDesc>By permission of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
          </figure> face,” “transient day” [1.9-11, E 3]) Thel emphasizes the 
            <hi rend="i">evanescence</hi> of the rainbow, where Milton’s passage stresses its functional 
            <hi rend="i">continuity</hi> within the cycle of regeneration. 
              <note id="n22"><hi rend="s">22</hi> Concerning Blake’s “idea of pastoral,” Wagenknecht
writes that “in terms of
            the <hi rend="i">Songs</hi> [of <hi rend="i">Innocence and Experience</hi>] the idea of
            the pastoral had emerged as the vehicle for conveying Blake’s ambiguous and agonized
            approach to the problem of ‘Generation’” (5). This view is congenial to my own approach
            to <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, about which Wagenknecht adds that its nature is
            best appreciated “via the pastoral ironies and ambiguities of the 
              <hi rend="i">Songs</hi>” (148).</note>
	<note id="n23"><hi rend="s">23</hi> Wagenknecht describes
            the story of Venus and Adonis as “a primary myth for pastoralists” (2). Raine points out
            an allusion to Adonis concealed in the title page emblem of <hi rend="i">The Book of
              Thel</hi>:
			<q> The flowers, from whose centers spring little lovers in amorous pursuit
              and flight, are pasqueflowers, <hi rend="i">anemone pulsatilla</hi> . . . The anemone
              is the flower of Adonis, into which he was, according to tradition, metamorphosed. . .
              . (1: 105)</q>
            <p>She describes these flowers on the title page as an allusion to
              the theme of Shakespeare’s <hi rend="i">Venus and Adonis</hi>, adding that “the
              association of the flower with Easter (<hi rend="i">pasque</hi>) is itself
              significant” (1: 105).</p></note>
	<note id="n24"><hi rend="s">24</hi><hi rend="i"> The
              Faerie Queene</hi> 3.6.43-49.</note>
	<note id="n25"><hi rend="s">25</hi> In 
              <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi> 1.446-52, a river called “Adonis” is named with reference
            to the annual rites of the fertility god Thammuz. In a gesture appropriate to his
            conception of Thel, Blake has feminized the name to “Adona.”</note></p>
        <p>Thel encounters four symbolic figures. The first, the “Lilly of the valley,” is a “gentle
          maid of silent valleys and of modest brooks” (1.16, 22) who retires after speaking with
          Thel to a “silver shrine” (2.2) (illus. 8). Blake’s “Lilly” is primarily Spenser’s
“faire
          flowre of beauty [that] fades away,” but this appealing little “watry weed” is also
          related—through the “twisted braids of lilies” knitted into the “loose train of [her]
          amber-dropping hair” (861-62)—to Milton’s Sabrina, “a gentle nymph . . . that with moist
          curb sways the smooth Severn stream” (<hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 823-24). Sabrina, sitting
          “under the glassy cool translucent wave” (860), is “Goddess of the silver lake” (864) and
          a patron of maidenhood. She is invoked by the Attendant Spirit to free the Lady held fast
          by Comus’s magic spell. Blake’s “Lilly,” a self-effacing “little virgin of the peaceful
          valley” (<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 2.3), contrasts with the regal Sabrina, whose narcissistic
          adorning of herself suggests an immature self-involvement rather like Thel’s own.<ref
            target="n26" type="note">26</ref> The life of the 
<figure n="thel.d.p6" id="thel.d.illbk.06" work-copy="thel.d" rend="db" width="714" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>4<lb/>
            <lb/>
            III<lb/>
            <lb/>
            Then Thel astonish’d view’d the Worm upon its dewy bed.<lb/>
            <lb/>
            Art thou a Worm? image of weakness. art thou but a Worm?<lb/>
            I see thee like an infant wrapped in the Lillys leaf:<lb/>
            Ah weep not little voice, thou can’st not speak. but thou can’st weep;<lb/>
            Is this a Worm? I see thee lay helpless &amp; naked: weeping,<lb/>
            And none to answer, none to cherish thee with mothers smiles.<lb/>
            <lb/>
            The Clod of Clay heard the Worms voice, &amp; raisd her pitying head;<lb/>
            She bowd over the weeping infant. and her life exhal’d<lb/>
            In milky fondness, then on Thel she fix’d her humble eyes.<lb/>
            <lb/>
            O beauty of the vales of Har, we live not for ourselves.<lb/>
            Thou seest me the meanest thing, and so I am indeed;<lb/>
            My bosom of itself is cold. and of itself is dark,<lb/>
            <lb/>
            But</figTranscr>
            <head>9. <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, plate 4.</head>
            <figDesc>By permission of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
          </figure> “Lilly” is one of self-sacrifice and selfless caring for other living creatures;
          she gives of her own material being to “nourish the innocent lamb” and “revive the milked
          cow” (2.5, 10), scatters her perfume “on every little blade of grass” (2.9) and goes,
          after speaking with Thel, “to mind her numerous charge among the verdant grass” (2.18).
            <note id="n26"><hi rend="s">26</hi> Irene Tayler notes Blake’s emphasis on the theme of
              “<corr type="emend">narcissism</corr>” in his first series of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> illustrations. See
            especially 71-78 of her essay. Bette Charlotte Werner differentiates between Milton’s
            perception of Sabrina as an agent of grace, and Blake’s reading of Milton’s imagery in
              <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 837-39. Blake, Werner says, perceives that “Sabrina’s
            restoration, her sea-change, to immortality has been accomplished, not through the
            paralysis of virginity but through the opening of her senses” (35).</note></p>
        <p>Thel’s second dialogue is with a Cloud (illus. 9) which “shewd his golden head . . . /
          Hovering and glittering on the air . . .” (<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 3.5-6, E 4). Blake’s
          Cloud takes his “bright form” from the “hovering angel girt with golden wings” 
            (<hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 213) who accompanies Faith, Hope, and Chastity in the Lady’s
          soliloquy in <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> (and is there perhaps to be identified with Hope). He
          also resembles the “glistering guardian” whom the Lady trusts to keep her “life and honour
          unassailed” (218-19) (and whose semblance Blake was to borrow for the equivocal guardian
          of maidenhood in “The Angel”). The Cloud declares to Thel: “O virgin, know’st thou not.
          our steeds drink of the golden springs / Where Luvah doth renew his horses?” (3.7-8). “Our
          steeds,” those upon which clouds are mounted in moving about the sky, “renew” their
          vitality at the same source as the “horses 
<figure n="songsie.b.p8-9" id="songsie.b.illbk.08" work-copy="songsie.b" rend="db" width="642" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>The Little Black Boy<lb/>
	My mother bore me in the southern wild,<lb/>
	And I am black, but O! my soul is white.<lb/>
	White as an angel is the English child:<lb/>
	But I am black as if bereav’d of light.<lb/>
	My mother taught me underneath a tree<lb/>
	And sitting down before the heat of day.<lb/>
	She took me on her lap and kissed me,<lb/>
	And pointing to the east began to say.<lb/>
	Look on the rising sun! there God does live<lb/>
	And gives his light. and gives his heat away.<lb/>
	And flowers and trees and beasts and men recieve<lb/>
	Comfort in morning joy in the noon day.<lb/>
	And we are put on earth a little space..<lb/>
	That we may learn to bear the beams of love,<lb/>
	And these black bodies and this sun-burnt face<lb/>
	Is but a cloud, and like a shady grove.<lb/>
	For</figTranscr>
            <head>10. “The Little Black Boy” (1) from <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and
                Experience.</hi></head>
            <figDesc>By permission of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
          </figure> of Luvah,” here virtually identified with the fiery horses of the classical
          sun-god Phoebus Apollo.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n27" type="note">27</ref>
Luvah is a symbol of
          sexuality, wherever he appears in Blake’s later work,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n28" type="note">28</ref> and the Cloud is likewise portrayed, both visually and in the text, as a
          figure of young and virile sexuality.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n29"
type="note">29</ref> Blake may have
          associated the “golden springs / Where Luvah doth renew his horses” with the “orient
          liquor” which Comus, descendant of the Sun,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n30"
type="note">30</ref> offers
          to weary travelers “to quench the drought of Phoebus” (<hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 64-66).
          That magic potion “flames, and dances in his crystal bounds” (672) as Comus presses it
          upon the obdurate Lady, urging 
		<q> . . . see, here be all the pleasures<lb/>
 That fancy
            can beget on youthful thoughts,<lb/>
 When the fresh blood grows lively, and returns<lb/>
            Brisk as the April buds in primrose season. . . .<lb/>
 (667-70) </q>
These wonderful
          images of the fires of lust, spring, morning, and regeneration are tinged in the Miltonic
          context 
<pb id="p25-109" n="109"/>
with the evil of Comus’s nature, but Blake was
          obviously determined that the devil should not have the best tunes or the finest poetry.
          Blake chose to associate Milton’s phrase from <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, “the sun-clad power
          of chastity” (<hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 781), with the lines from <hi rend="i">Paradise
            Lost</hi> describing the “apostate” Satan “exalted as a god . . . in his sun-bright
          chariot . . . Idol of majesty divine” (<hi rend="i">PL</hi> 6.99-101). In Blake’s reading
          of <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, Chastity is the “apostate,” the “idol of majesty divine,” for
          the divinity Blake delineates in the <hi rend="i">Book of Thel</hi> is one who blesses
          earthly plenitude and sustains and encourages its increase: and <hi rend="i">he</hi> is
          embodied in the sun<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n31" type="note">31</ref>
(illus. 10). The Lady in 
            <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> is transfixed by magic to Comus’s enchanted chair, “as Daphne was /
          Root-bound, that fled Apollo” (660-61). Blake was sufficiently struck by this image to
          illustrate it in an emblem in his Notebook, inscribing beneath it “As Daphne was
            root-bound”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n32" type="note">32</ref> (illus.
11-12). Thel may be seen as an
          insubstantial analogue of the “Vegetated body” of Daphne,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n33" type="note">33</ref> for she too has “fled Apollo.” In the opening lines of
the poem she shuns the
          company of sisters who “led round their <hi rend="i">sunny</hi> flocks” 
            (<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 1.1, my emphasis).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n34"
type="note">34</ref> Instead she has
          “sought the secret air, / To fade away like morning beauty from her mortal day . . .”
          (1.2-3), becoming “like a faint cloud kindled at the rising sun” (2.11). The Cloud, with
          his “golden head and . . . bright form” is indeed “kindled at the rising sun”—in common
          with all living beings—but he has <hi rend="i">followed</hi>, not fled, its beams. He
          rejoices not only in his materialization, “glitter[ing] in the morning sky,” but also in
          his dissolution, “scatter[ing] [his] bright beauty thro’ the humid air” (2.14-15). In his
          vaporous state he returns to water his “steeds” at the “golden springs / Where Luvah doth
          renew his horses” (3.7-8), a generative source where his life is renewed and he comes
          again into visible being.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n35" type="note">35</ref>
	<note id="n27"><hi rend="s">27</hi> This is the first appearance in Blake’s writings of the Zoa of the
passions
            called “Luvah” (the name is a version of “lover”); probably the earliest mention of any
            of the Zoas. Blake seems here to attribute to Luvah the properties of a sun-god,
            although in <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi> Luvah’s appropriation to himself of the
            “Steeds of Light” is treated as a usurpation of the rights of Urizen, Zoa of the Reason,
            who has charge of them in the Eternal condition of Man (<hi rend="i">FZ</hi> 5.65, 5-8, E
            344). Kathleen Raine derives this passage of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> from the “aubade” of
            Act II of Shakespeare’s <hi rend="i">Cymbeline</hi>:
<q> Hark, hark! the lark at
              heaven’s gate sings<lb/>
 And Phoebus ’gins arise<lb/>
 His steeds to water at those
              springs<lb/>
 On chalic’d flow’rs that lies . . .<lb/>
 (Raine, 1: 169) </q></note>	
            <note id="n28"><hi rend="s">28</hi> See, for instance, <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
            7.83.12-16, E 358.</note>
	<note id="n29"><hi rend="s">29</hi> In Blake’s illumination on
            pl. 4, the Cloud has the form of a young man, almost naked but with floating drapery
            flying from his body (Erdman, <hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake</hi> 38). Blake’s figure of
            Antamon in <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> 14.15-20 (E 65-66) seems to be a development of
            Thel’s Cloud.</note>
	<note id="n30"><hi rend="s">30</hi> The mother of Comus is Circe,
            “daughter of the Sun” (<hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 46-57).</note>
	<note id="n31"><hi rend="s">31</hi> Compare the teaching of the Mother in “The Little Black Boy” 9-12:
<q> Look
              on the rising sun: there God does live,<lb/>
 And gives his light and gives his heat
              away;<lb/>
 And flowers and trees and beasts and men recieve<lb/>
 Comfort in morning,
              joy in the noonday . . . (<hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi>, E 9) </q></note>	
            <note id="n32"><hi rend="s">32</hi> Blake inscribed and illustrated these lines on page 36 of
            the Notebook, and experimented with another version of the same emblem on page 12. His
            water color illustrations to <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> actually show the Lady
            “root-bound,” seated in the knotty root of an oak-tree, both at the time when Comus
            finds her (illus. 12) and after the incursion of her two brothers has set Comus and his
            train to flight. Butlin reproduces the relevant paintings in 2: pls. 616, 622, 624, 626,
            and 630. Tayler comments on the Lady’s “rooty chair” on page 53 of her
            essay.</note>
	<note id="n33"><hi rend="s">33</hi> “This world of Imagination is the world
            of Eternity; it is the divine bosom into which we shall all go after the death of the
            Vegetated body” (<hi rend="i">A Vision of the Last Judgment</hi>, c. 1810, E
            555).</note>
	<note id="n34"><hi rend="s">34</hi> See note 19 above for this reference to
            Spenser’s “Garden of Adonis.”</note>
	<note id="n35"><hi rend="s">35</hi> Raine’s
            interpretation of the theme of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> as “a debate between the
            Neoplatonic and alchemical philosophies” (1: 99), of Plotinus and Porphyry on the one
            hand and Paracelsus on the other, dwells especially upon its “watry” imagery, which is
            “appropriate to the ‘watery’ would of generation of the naiads and their everflowing
            streams, to the ‘moist’ souls who attract to themselves the hylic envelope” (1: 108) (“.
            . . the moist envelope of the soul, the generated body, [which is] called a ‘grave’
            because in it the soul is dead from eternity, or a ‘bed,’ as the place of the soul’s
            sleep” [1: 109]).</note></p>
        <figure n="BB122.1.38.MS" rend="file" width="793" height="1000">
          <head>11. Draft sketch of emblem, “As Daphne was root-bound,” from Blake’s Notebook, page
            36.</head>
          <figDesc>By permission of the British Library.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <figure n="but527.1.1.wc" id="but527.1.wc.01" work-copy="but527.1" rend="db" width="838" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>inv<lb/>
	WB</figTranscr>
          <head>12. Blake, illustration to Milton’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, “Comus with his
            Revellers,” c. 1801.</head>
          <figDesc>Courtesy of the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p25-110" n="110"/>
        <figure n="gates-child.d.p1" id="gates-child.d.illbk.01" work-copy="gates-child.d" rend="db" width="683" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>Frontispiece<lb/>
	What is Man!<lb/>
	Publishd by WBlake 17 May 1793</figTranscr>
          <head>13. “What is Man!” frontispiece of <hi rend="i">For Children: The Gates of
              Paradise</hi> (1793).</head>
          <figDesc>By permission of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <figure n="BB122.1.70.MS" rend="file" width="793" height="1000">
          <head>14. Draft sketch of emblem, “What is Man . . .”</head>
          <figDesc>from Blake’s Notebook, page 68. By permission of the British Library.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <figure n="thel.d.p7" id="thel.d.illbk.07" work-copy="thel.d" rend="db" width="696" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>But he that loves the lowly, pours his oil upon my head.<lb/>
	And kisses me, and binds his nuptial bands around my breast.<lb/>
	And says; Thou mother of my children, I have loved thee.<lb/>
	And I have given thee a crown that none can take away<lb/>
	But how this is sweet maid, I know not, and I cannot know,<lb/>
	I ponder, and I cannot ponder; yet I live and love.<lb/>
	The daughter of beauty wip’d her pitying tears with her white veil,<lb/>
	And said. Alas! I knew not this, and therefore did I weep:<lb/>
	That God would love a Worm I knew, and punish the evil foot<lb/>
	That wilful, bruis’d its helpless form; but that he cherish’d it<lb/>
	With milk and oil, I never knew; and therefore did I weep.<lb/>
	And I complaind in the mild air, because I fade away.<lb/>
	And lay me down in thy cold bed, and leave my shining lot.<lb/>
	Queen of the vales, the matron Clay answerd; I heard thy sighs.<lb/>
	And all thy moans flew o’er my roof. but I have call’d them down:<lb/>
	Wilt thou O Queen enter my house, 'tis given thee to enter.<lb/>
	And to return; fear nothing. enter with thy virgin feet.<lb/>
	IV</figTranscr>
          <head>15. <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, plate 5.</head>
          <figDesc>By permission of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <figure n="BB122.1.60.MS" rend="file" width="793" height="1000">
          <head>16. Detail.</head>
          <figDesc>Sketch in Blake’s Notebook, upper left corner of page 58. By permission of the
            British Library.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <pb id="p25-111" n="111"/>
        <p>Like the “humid bow” of Milton’s Iris, the Cloud is a vital link in the cycle of earthly
          generation. Comus describes to the Lady his first sight of her two young brothers as 
		<q> .
            . . a faery vision,<lb/>
 Of some gay creatures of the element<lb/>
 That in the colours
            of the rainbow live<lb/>
 And play i’ the plighted clouds. . . .<lb/>
 (297-300)<ref
              target="n36" type="note">36</ref>
	<note id="n36"><hi rend="s">36</hi> Blake wrote out
              the first three lines of this passage beneath a sketch of an emblem on page 30 of the
              Notebook. See Butlin 1: 90 (“Emblem 12”). (The design was used in a slightly modified
              form on the title page of his <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of
              Albion.</hi>)</note></q>
Blake’s Cloud is, like those of Milton in this passage,
          “plighted”—but with a shift of semantic emphasis.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n37" type="note">37</ref>
          The Cloud of the <hi rend="i">Book of Thel</hi> is “plighted” in being betrothed to his
          “partner in the vale” (3.31, E 5), whom he goes to join when he takes leave of Thel. The
          Cloud’s “partner” is “the fair-eyed dew,”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n38" type="note">38</ref> who
          “kneels before the risen sun” (3.14), surrendering herself—like Spenser’s “Morning dew”
            Chrysogone<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n39" type="note">39</ref>—to that
divine source of life just as
          obviously as Thel hides away from it when she seeks out “the <hi rend="i">secret</hi> air”
          (1.2, my emphasis). The “plighted” couple are “link’d in a golden band and never part, /
          But walk united bearing food to all our tender flowers”(3.12-16, E 5). Like the “Lilly of
          the valley,” they give selflessly of themselves, both to one another and to others in the
          fullfilment of social responsibilities. Like her, also, they have an oblique, complex, and
          significant, relationship with Milton’s argument and imagery in 
            <hi rend="i">Comus.</hi>
	<note id="n37"><hi rend="s">37</hi> Milton’s primary sense was “folded,”
            which gives the current English word “pleated.” He also offers the undercurrent of
            meaning that relates the rainbow to the “plighting” of God’s covenant with
            Noah.</note>
	<note id="n38"><hi rend="s">38</hi> The “Antamon” of 
              <hi rend="i">Europe</hi> is likewise “prince of the pearly dew” (<hi rend="i">Europe</hi>
14.15, E
            65).</note>
	<note id="n39"><hi rend="s">39</hi> Chrysogone (in <hi rend="i">The Faerie
              Queene</hi> 3.6.3ff) was the mother of Belphoebe and Amoret, twin daughters born “of
            the wombe of Morning dew” (3.6.3.1), miraculously begotten “through influence of
            th’heauens fruitfull ray” (6.2). Chrysogone is said to have conceived them while
            sleeping in the sun: 
			<q> The sunne-beames bright vpon her body playd,<lb/>
 Being through
              former bathing mollifide,<lb/>
 And pierst into her wombe, where they embayd<lb/>
 With
              so sweet sence and secret power vnspide,<lb/>
 That in her pregnant flesh they shortly
              fructifide. (3.6.7.5-9) </q></note></p>
        <p>The Cloud brings to Thel the Worm, one of the “numerous charge” (2.18) of the “Lilly.”
          The visual image of the Worm on plate 4 of the <hi rend="i">Book of Thel</hi><ref
            target="n40" type="note">40</ref> (illus. 9) confirms that Blake either had in mind, or
          had already sketched, “What is Man!” the emblem-design he chose to place first in 
            <hi rend="i">The Gates of Paradise</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n41"
type="note">41</ref> (illus. 13).
          Blake’s introduction of the Worm confirms an association stemming from the caption he
          wrote in the Notebook beneath his rough sketch of the emblem (illus. 14)—the passage from
          the Book of Job from which he took its title, 
		<q> What is Man that thou shouldst magnify
            him &amp; that thou shouldst set thine heart upon him. (Job 7.17)<ref target="n42"
              type="note">42</ref></q>
Three of Thel’s four visitants—the Cloud, the Worm, and the
          Clod of Clay—emerge from the context of this verse of Job: 
		<q> My flesh is clothed with
            worms and clods of dust. . . . As the cloud is consumed and vanisheth away; so he that
            goeth down to the grave shall come up no more. (Job 7.5, 9) </q>
Thel knows that she too
          will be “consumed,” to become “at death the food of worms” (3.23, 25). The Cloud offers
          Thel the wise counsel of acceptance. Though he will “vanish and [be] seen no more” he
          assures her that when he passes away he goes “to tenfold life.” If worms should consume
          her flesh, the Cloud exclaims, “How great thy use, how great thy blessing!” (3.26). For,
          he tells her, “Every thing that lives / Lives not alone nor for itself” (3.26-27). The
          emblem “What is Man!” shows two worms (illus. 13): one realistic, crawling in an arc down
          an oak-leaf, the other with the face of a sleeping child, lying face upwards on an
          adjoining leaf, chrysalis-like in swaddling bands. In the <hi rend="i">Book of Thel</hi>
          the helpless Worm appears to Thel “like an infant wrapped in the Lilly’s leaf” (4.3), and
          is shown in just this way on plate 4. It cannot speak, but cries like a baby. Thel
          expresses compassion at its helplessness—“[There is] none to cherish thee with mother’s
          smiles” (4.6)—and indeed the cries of the infant do raise the “pitying head” of the
          motherly Clod of Clay (illus. 15). <note id="n40"><hi rend="s">40</hi> Erdman, 
              <hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake</hi> 38.</note>
	<note id="n41"><hi rend="s">41</hi> Erdman,
              <hi rend="i">Illuminated Blake</hi> 268.</note>
	<note id="n42"><hi rend="s">42</hi>
            This sketch appears on page 68 of the Notebook; see Butlin 1: 97.</note></p>
        <p>The Clod of Clay “bow’d over the weeping infant and her life exhal’d / In milky fondness
          . . .” (4.8-9). This last personage of the poem attains the ultimate degree of
          selflessness, willingly giving her life as well as her substance for the Worm.<ref
            target="n43" type="note">43</ref> She echoes the Cloud’s teaching : “O beauty of the
          vales of Har! we live not for ourselves” (4.10, E 5). In response to Thel’s “pitying
          tears” (5.7) the “matron Clay” invites Thel to survey her subterraneous “house,” assuring
          her “’Tis given thee to enter / And to return: fear nothing . . .” (5.16-17). And Thel
          accepts the invitation. <note id="n43"><hi rend="s">43</hi> Compare “The Clod and the
            Pebble”: “Love seeketh not Itself to please, / Nor for itself hath any care, / But for
            another gives its ease . . . So sang a little Clod of Clay / Trodden with the cattle’s
            feet . . .” (<hi rend="i">Songs of Experience</hi>, E 19).</note></p>
        <p>What does she find in the underground realm of Clay? “Couches of the dead” (6.3); tombs
          such as the grand monuments Blake had sketched fifteen years earlier, as a young
          apprentice, in Westminster Abbey.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n44"
type="note">44</ref> In this “land of
          sorrows &amp; of tears” Thel sees “Vegetated bodies” like that of Daphne, for there “the
          fibrous roots / Of every heart on earth infixes deep its restless twists” (6.3-5). Like
          the Lady in <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, who finds no shelter “from the chill dew, amongst
          rude burs and thistles” (<hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 351), Thel strays, unprotected and
          unguided, about the thorny undergrowth of the fallen world<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n45" type="note">45</ref> (illus. 16). She enters a region (described by the Elder Brother in 
            <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>) where “thick and gloomy shadows damp” are “oft seen in
          charnel-vaults, and sepulchres / Lingering, and sitting by a new-made grave, / As loth to
          leave the body that it loved . . .” (<hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 469-72). Blake depicts Thel
          wandering 
		<q> . . . in the land of clouds thro’ valleys dark, list’ning<lb/>
 Dolours and
            lamentations; waiting oft beside a dewy grave<lb/>
 She stood in silence, list’ning to
            the voices of the ground. . . .<lb/>
 (<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 6.6-8, E 6) </q>
At last
          she comes to her own grave-plot, where a “voice of sorrow breathed from the hollow pit”
          (6.10). The voice Thel hears is potentially her own, moaning from the depths of the grave
          after the ending of a life-in-possibility to which the maiden has not yet committed
          herself. This potential self laments the painful intensity of the experiences of each of
          the senses in earthly life: 
		<q> Why are Eyelids stord with arrows ready drawn,<lb/>
 Where
            a thousand fighting men in ambush lie? . . .<lb/>
 Why a Tongue impress’d with honey from
            every wind?<lb/>
 Why an Ear, a whirlpool fierce to draw creations in?<lb/>
 Why a Nostril
            wide inhaling terror trembling &amp; affright? (<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 6.13-18) </q><pb
            id="p25-112" n="112"/> At its climax the agonized murmur articulates the anguish of the
          sexual sense of touch: the pangs of desire frustrated, the greater torment of desire
          satisfied—the agony of self-realization in earthly life that awaits the virgin whose name
          means “desire”: 
		<q> Why a tender curb upon the youthful burning boy!<lb/>
 Why a little
            curtain of flesh on the bed of our desire? (<hi rend="i">Thel</hi> 6.19-20) </q>
At
          this, Thel rushes “with a shriek” back to the “vales of Har.” She flees the precepts of
          teachers who affirm that commitment to earthly life demands a continual sacrifice of
          selfhood. Experiential existence in the fallen world is a course to inevitable
          destruction, marked by the fierce suffering and terror her own disembodied voice
          describes. Rather than face that, Thel —who prayed that she might live in
          “gentleness”—chooses not to enter into it at all.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n46" type="note">46</ref>
	<note id="n44"><hi rend="s">44</hi> The sketches of royal tombs done in
            Westminster Abbey during the period 1774-77 are among Blake’s earliest extant drawings.
            Butlin 1: 1-14, 2: pls. 1-47.</note>
	<note id="n45"><hi rend="s">45</hi> On page 58 of
            the Notebook, Blake made a sketch which may be an illustration to 
              <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> 350-54.</note>
	<note id="n46"><hi rend="s">46</hi> Wagenknecht relates
            Thel’s concern about transiency to her “sexual anxiety,” commenting that “She wants to
            sleep ‘the sleep of death’ (so long as it comes gently), and her sexual misgivings are
            deflected into concern for the fading of other innocents and into the imagery of God
            walking in his Garden in the evening time” (155).</note></p>
        <p>Thel’s “Motto,” in most copies a kind of postscript to the poem, suggests that Thel might
          have learned more from her brief sojourn in the “house of Clay” than she allowed herself
          to do: 
		<q> Does the Eagle know what is in the pit?<lb/>
 Or wilt thou go ask the Mole?<lb/>
            Can Wisdom be put in a silver rod?<lb/>
 Or Love in a golden bowl? (i.1-4, E 3) </q>
The
          Mole, the earth-dweller, knows “what is in the pit,” and may also be a symbol of the
          regenerative potential within experience.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n47"
type="note">47</ref> The Eagle,
          inhabiting the sky and aspiring always in Blake’s work to the visionary realm, knows
          nothing of the realm of Clay. The “rod” and “bowl” may at one level be reminders of the
          charming-rod and the cup of Comus (illus. 4); a rod may be a symbol of authority or of the
          phallus, a bowl may represent the Holy Grail or be a symbol of the womb. Blake obviously
          intends no simple answers to the four rhetorical questions in “Thel’s Motto.” All Thel can
          do is look in the direction these questions point. They direct her (and the reader) to the
          indisputable value of such experience of the skies and the earth as may be gained
          respectively by the Eagle and the Mole from their diametrically opposed perspectives and
          “contrary” ways of life. And they question the <hi rend="i">validity</hi> of a distinction
          between Love and Wisdom: “. . . love indeed is Esse and wisdom is Existere for love has
          nothing except in wisdom, nor has wisdom anything except from love. Therefore when love is
          in wisdom, then it <hi rend="i">exists.</hi>”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n48"
type="note">48</ref>	
            <note id="n47"><hi rend="s">47</hi> Rodger L. Tarr proposes this view (193).</note>	
            <note id="n48"><hi rend="s">48</hi> Swedenborg, <hi rend="i">Divine Love and Wisdom</hi> 14:
            7.</note></p>
        <p>Blake commented on this passage of Swedenborg’s <hi rend="i">Divine Love and Wisdom</hi>:
          “Thought without affection makes a distinction between Love &amp; Wisdom, as it does
          between body &amp; Spirit” (E 603). His annotation indicates that he regards the division
          between Love and Wisdom in the same light as he does that “between body &amp; Spirit”—as a
          notion “to be expunged.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n49"
type="note">49</ref>
	<note id="n49"><hi rend="s">49</hi><hi rend="i"> The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> 14, E 49.</note></p>
        <p>The illumination with which Blake concludes the <hi rend="i">Book of Thel</hi> depicts
          Thel’s choice quite clearly, and incidentally suggests the source of his inspiration in
          Milton’s work. Plate 6 shows three children—a girl and two younger boys—riding a
          dragon-headed serpent who coils across the width of the page over the legend “The End”
          (illus. 17). They cannot be identified from the text of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> (or from
          that of <hi rend="i">America</hi>, where Blake was to use the same motif again [illus.
          18]); and indeed, in their first appearance, on the final plate of <hi rend="i">The Book
            of Thel</hi>, they may represent the Lady and the Elder and Younger Brothers of Milton’s
            <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, shown almost in babyhood. Perhaps, in one of the several
          possible meanings of the configuration, these figures embody the desire of both Thel and
          Milton’s Lady to retreat towards the security of infancy—reversing the natural process of
          growth through adolescent sexuality into maturity. With the girl astride and holding the
          reins, the three children ride the seemingly tractable serpent—symbol of man’s
          fall—without fear.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n50" type="note">50</ref> Back
they gallop, in a leftward
          or “sinister” direction, to “the vales of Har,” where the phallic serpent has no 
            <hi rend="i">visible</hi> sting, in a paradise <hi rend="i">apparently</hi>
<figure n="thel.d.p8" id="thel.d.illbk.08" work-copy="thel.d" rend="db" width="812" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>IV.<lb/>
	The eternal gates terrific porter lifted the northern bar:<lb/>
	Thel enter’d in &amp; saw the secrets of the land unknown:<lb/>
	She saw the couches of the dead, &amp; where the fibrous roots<lb/>
	Of every heart on earth infixes deep its restless twists:<lb/>
	A land of sorrows &amp; of tears where never smile was seen.<lb/>
	She wanderd in the land of clouds thro’ valleys dark, listning<lb/>
	Dolours &amp; lamentations: waiting oft beside a dewy grave<lb/>
	She stood in silence. listning to the voices of the ground,<lb/>
	Till to her own grave plot she came, &amp; there she sat down.<lb/>
	And heard this voice of sorrow breathed from the hollow pit - <lb/>
	Why cannot the Ear be closed to its own destruction?<lb/>
	Or the glistning Eye to the poison of a smile!<lb/>
	Why are Eyelids stord with arrows ready drawn,<lb/>
	Where a thousand fighting men in ambush lie?<lb/>
	Or an Eye of gifts &amp; graces. show’ring fruits &amp; coined<lb/>
	gold!<lb/>
	Why a Tongue impress’d with honey from every wind?<lb/>
	Why an Ear, a whirlpool fierce to draw creations in?<lb/>
	Why a Nostril wide inhaling terror trembling &amp; affright<lb/>
	Why a tender curb upon the youthful burning boy!<lb/>
	Why a little curtain of flesh on the bed of our desire?<lb/>
	The Virgin started from her seat, &amp; with a shriek.<lb/>
	Fled back unhinderd till she came into the vales of<lb/>
	Har<lb/>
	The End</figTranscr>
            <head>17. <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel</hi>, plate 6.</head>
            <figDesc>By permission of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
          </figure> not yet lost—but only apparently, for the pastoral landscape of that country is
          a false Paradise of arrested development. As Blake clearly shows, the consequences of the
          fall of man are ineluctable. <note id="n50"><hi rend="s">50</hi> Wagenknecht (121)
            discusses this motif as it appears in both the last plate of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi> and
            in pl. 11 of <hi rend="i">America</hi>, relating it to similar motifs in the “Lyca”
            poems of the <hi rend="i">Songs.</hi> He restates the questions it raises (158-59), but
            finds no final answers.</note></p>
        <p>In a fallen Paradise continually laid waste by the depredations of Time, Thel laments
          that she and every form of living beauty about her must yield to this “Great enimy.”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
            target="n51" type="note">51</ref> She longs to hear “the voice / Of him that walketh in
          the garden in the evening time” (1.13-14), not in wrath, but “gentl[y].”<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n52"
            type="note">52</ref> The “Lilly of the valley,” herself a “gentle maid,” assures Thel
          that, little and weak and ephemeral though she is, “Yet am I visited from heaven, and he
          that smiles on all. / Walks in the valley and each morn over me spreads his hand . .
          .”(1.19-20). <note id="n51"><hi rend="s">51</hi><hi rend="i"> The Faerie Queene</hi>
            3.6.39.1.</note>
	<note id="n52"><hi rend="s">52</hi> Cf. <hi rend="i">Paradise Lost</hi>
            10.92-99: 
			<q> Now was the sun in western cadence low<lb/>
 From noon, and gentle airs due
              at their hour<lb/>
 To fan the earth now waked, and usher in<lb/>
 The evening cool when
              he from wrath more cool<lb/>
 Came the mild judge and intercessor both<lb/>
 To sentence
              man: the voice of God they heard<lb/>
 Now walking in the garden, by soft winds<lb/>
              Brought to their ears, while day declined. . . . </q>
Wagenknecht, while citing the
            evidence from <hi rend="i">Tiriel</hi> for “the usual view that Thel unambiguously
            retreats from life at the end of her poem” (151), argues that “Thel’s return to the
            ‘vales of Har’ from the grave which the matron Clay has shown her in a moment of vision
            cannot be construed as a return to an unreal Beulah, but only as a return to ordinary
            fallen existence, an ambiguous retreat, perhaps, from both the horror of the grave and
            from the passionate intensity of her response to that horror” (150). Wagenknecht’s
            suggestion, which is consonant with his reading of <hi rend="i">Thel</hi>, implies that
            Thel’s longing for “gentle” experience (1.12-14, E 3) may be a rejection of the
            commitment to romantic “intensity” urged, for instance, in Blake’s poem “Day,” in which
            the sun of creativity arises with “wrath increast . . . Crownd with warlike fires &amp;
            raging desires” (3-5, E 473)—an obvious “contrary” to the “judge and intercessor” who
            comes as the sun sets, without wrath “to sentence man” to a life depleted of visionary
            experience in a fallen world. </note></p>
        <p>When her brief life in time is over the “Lilly” is blessed with the certainty that she
          will “flourish in eternal vales.” The Cloud directly addresses Thel’s fear that “like a
          faint cloud kindled at the rising sun / I vanish from my pearly throne . . .” (2.11-12).
          Although, he says, “I vanish and am seen no more,” yet “when I pass away / It is to
          tenfold life, to love, to peace and raptures holy . . .” (3.10-11). Thel knows that the
          Worm 
<pb id="p25-113" n="113"/>
          <figure n="america.f.p13" id="america.f.illbk.13" work-copy="america.f" rend="db" width="729" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>Fiery the Angels rose, &amp; as they rose deep thunder roll’d<lb/>
	Around their shores; indignant burning with the fires of Orc<lb/>
	And Bostons Angel cried aloud as they flew thro’ the dark <lb/>
	night,<lb/>
	He cried; Why trembles honesty and like a murderer,<lb/>
	Why seeks he refuge from the frowns of his immortal station,<lb/>
	Must the generous tremble &amp; leave his joy, to the idle: to<lb/>
	the pestilence!<lb/>
	That mock him? who commanded this, what God! what Angel!<lb/>
	To keep the gen’rous from experience till the ungenerous<lb/>
	Are unrestraind performers of the energies of nature;<lb/>
	Till pity is become a trade, and generosity a science, <lb/>
	That men get rich by, &amp; the sandy desart is giv’n to the strong<lb/>
	What God is he, writes laws of peace, &amp; clothes him in a tempest<lb/>
	What pitying Angel lusts for tears, and fans himself with sighs<lb/>
	What crawling villain preaches abstinence &amp; wraps himself<lb/>
	In fat of lambs? no more I follow, no more obedience pay,</figTranscr>
            <head>18. <hi rend="i">America, a Prophecy</hi>, plate 11.</head>
            <figDesc>By permission of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
          </figure> 
          is loved by God, and that whoever injures it will be punished; but more than
          that, she learns, the Worm is “cherish’d . . . with milk and oil” (5.9-10)—for, as Blake
          repeatedly declares, “every thing that lives is 
          Holy.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n53" type="note">53</ref> 
          And the “matron Clay” assures Thel that though she herself is “the meanest
          thing,” and though her bosom is cold and dark, “he, that loves the lowly, pours his oil
          upon my head, / And kisses me, and binds his nuptial bands around my breast . . .”
          (4.11-12). The divine visitant who “spreads his hand” in benediction over the humble Lilly
          and “binds his nuptial bands” about the breast of the “matron Clay” is also the force who
          charges with life the “golden springs” where the Cloud’s existence is renewed. Blake
          typically makes the female personages passive and acquiescent, and the male personage, the
          Cloud, an active agent—an inseminator, while the Lilly and the “matron Clay” are
          receptacles for seed. Yet all are vehicles for the divine force of life emanating from
          “[him] that smiles on all” and “loves the lowly,” who has linked them all, together with
          the Worm, in a “golden band” of earthly generation. Thel, inspired by Blake’s complex
          response to Milton’s treatment of obdurate chastity in <hi rend="i">Comus</hi>, deplores
          the loss of Paradise. And she rejects the only alternative offered to man: coming to terms
          with experience, which includes procreation and generation, in the fallen world.
          Thel—“desire”—is Blake’s first embodiment of the “female Will,” and Milton’s 
            <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> one of his primary sources for the concept. 
              <note id="n53"><hi rend="s">53</hi><hi rend="i"> The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</hi> 27, E 45; 
              <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi> 8.10, E 51; <hi rend="i">The Four Zoas</hi>
            2.34.80, E 324.</note></p>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title>Works Cited</title>
          </head>
          <p>Bateson, F. W., ed. <hi rend="i">Selected Poems of William Blake.</hi> London:
            1957.</p>
          <p>Bindman, David, comp. and annot. <hi rend="i">The Complete Graphic Works of William
              Blake.</hi> London: Thames and Hudson, 1978.</p>
          <p>Blake, William. <hi rend="i">The Complete Poetry and Prose of William Blake.</hi> Ed.
            David V. Erdman. New rev. ed. Garden City: Anchor-Doubleday, 1982. (Cited throughout as
            E, followed by the page numbers.)</p>
          <p>—. <hi rend="i">The Notebook of William Blake: A Photographic and Typographic
              Facsimile.</hi> Ed. David V. Erdman with the assistance of Donald K. Moore. Oxford:
            Clarendon, 1973.</p>
          <p>—. <hi rend="i">Complete Writings.</hi> Ed. Geoffrey Keynes. Oxford: Oxford UP,
            1966.</p>
          <p>Burke, Edmund. <hi rend="i">Reflections on the Revolution in France.</hi> Cambridge:
            Cambridge UP, 1929.</p>
          <p>Butlin, Martin. <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of William Blake.</hi> 2 vols.,
            New Haven: Yale UP, 1981.</p>
          <p>Damon, S. Foster. “Blake and Milton.” <hi rend="i">The Divine Vision: Studies in the
              Poetry and Art of William Blake.</hi> Ed. Vivian de Sola Pinto. London: Victor
            Gollancz, 1957.</p>
          <p>—. <hi rend="i">A Blake Dictionary.</hi> London: Thames and Hudson, 1965.</p>
          <p>Dunbar, Pamela. <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Illustrations to the Poetry of
              Milton.</hi> Oxford: Clarendon, 1980.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V. <hi rend="i">Blake: Prophet Against Empire.</hi> 3rd ed. Princeton:
            Princeton UP, 1977.</p>
          <p>Erdman, David V., annot. <hi rend="i">The Illuminated Blake.</hi> London: Oxford UP,
            1975.</p>
          <p>Gleckner, Robert F. <hi rend="i">Blake and Spenser.</hi> Baltimore: Johns Hopkins UP,
            1985.</p>
          <pb id="p25-114" n="114"/>
          <p><hi rend="i">The Holy Bible</hi>, Authorized Version (1611). New York, American Bible
            Society, 1967.</p>
          <p>Keynes, Geoffrey, comp. and annot. <hi rend="i">Engravings by William Blake: The
              Separate Plates.</hi> Dublin: 1956.</p>
          <p>—. <hi rend="i">Drawings of William Blake.</hi> New York: Dover, 1970.</p>
          <p>Milton, John. <hi rend="i">The Poems of John Milton.</hi> Ed. John Carey and Alistair
            Fowler. London: Longmans, Green, 1968.</p>
          <p>Pinto, Vivian de Sola, ed. <hi rend="i">Studies in the Poetry and Art of William
              Blake.</hi> London: Victor Gollancz, 1957.</p>
          <p>Raine, Kathleen. <hi rend="i">Blake and Tradition.</hi> 2 vols. Bollingen Series
            Princeton: Princeton UP, 1968.</p>
          <p>Shakespeare, William. <hi rend="i">The Complete Works.</hi> Ed. Peter Alexander.
            London: Collins, 1951.</p>
          <p>Spenser, Edmund. <hi rend="i">The Faerie Queene.</hi> Ed. A. C. Hamilton. London:
            Longman Group, 1977.</p>
          <p>Swedenborg, Emmanuel. <hi rend="i">Angelic Wisdom concerning the Divine Love and
              Wisdom.</hi> Trans. Clifford and Doris H. Harley. London: Swedenborg Society,
            1987.</p>
          <p>Tarr, Rodger L. “‘The Eagle’ versus ‘The Mole’: The Wisdom of Virginity in 
              <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> and <hi rend="i">The Book of Thel.</hi>” <hi rend="i">Blake
Studies</hi> 3
            (1971): 187-94.</p>
          <p>Tayler, Irene. “Blake’s <hi rend="i">Comus</hi> Designs.” <hi rend="i">Blake
              Studies</hi> 4 (1972): 45-80.</p>
          <p>Wagenknecht, David. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Night.</hi> Cambridge, Mass.: Belknap Press of
            Harvard UP, 1973.</p>
          <p>Werner, Bette Charlotte. <hi rend="i">Blake’s Vision of the Poetry of Milton.</hi>
            Lewisburg, PA: Bucknell UP, 1986.</p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p25-115-116" n="115-116" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
