<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>25.3.essick</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article">A Relief Etching of Blake’s Virgil Illustrations</title>
        <author n="Essick">Robert N. Essick</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Winter 1991/1992</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1991/92</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">25.3</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>Detlef W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Robert N. Essick</name>
              <name>Eugenie R. Freed</name>
              <name>Alexander S. Gourlay</name>
              <name>David Groves</name>
              <name>Christopher Heppner</name>
              <name>Jenijoy La Belle</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date when="1986"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_25">
    <body>
      <pb id="p25-117" n="117"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-25-3-0006">
        <head>
          <title type="main">A Relief Etching of Blake’s Virgil Illustrations</title>
        </head>
        <byline>by <docAuthor>Robert N. <name>Essick</name></docAuthor></byline>
        <p>The discovery of what purports to be a previously unknown work by a major poet or artist
          provides a variety of pleasures.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n0"
type="note">*</ref>
	<note id="n0">I am
            grateful to Nancy Bialler, Martin Butlin, Thomas V. Lange, and Joseph Viscomi for their
            assistance with this essay.</note> Something akin to the sublime can strike the devotee
          on first hearing or seeing—surprise, wonder, fascination. Pronouncements based on
          instinctual connoisseurship soon follow. Doubters take equal relish in a dismissive sneer
          and a Shakespearean comment on those taken in (“What fools these mortals be”). If the now
          controversial object is on the market—and particularly if it enters that last refuge of
          unabashed capitalism, the auction room—the true believers are challenged to put their
          money where their poinions are. Next the scholars, if allowed access, take command. Those
          who think they have convincing arguments for an attribution proceed rapidly into print,
          ever fearful that the debunkers will respond with even more compelling arguments. A
          recently discovered print (illus. 1), immediately identifiable as a version of four of
          Blake’s illustrations to Ambrose Philips’ “Imitation of Eclogue I” in Robert John
          Thornton’s school Virgil of 1821, has already proceeded through much of the process
          outlined above. What follows is an attempt to carry the print into the penultimate stage
          and argue for its authenticity as a work designed, executed, printed, and hand-corrected
          by William Blake.</p>
        <p>In the late summer or early fall of 1990, a member of a Venezuelan family brought to
          Sotheby’s New York a copy of Alexander Gilchrist’s <hi rend="i">Life of William
          Blake</hi>, 1863. Although still in the original publisher’s binding, the copy was
          extra-illustrated with the Virgil print and several of Blake’s rarest graphic works, “The
          Chaining of Orc,” “The Man Sweeping the Interpreter’s Parlour,” and well-printed
          impressions 
          <figure n="bb504.essick-reliefetching.6-9" id="relbb504.1.rm.02" work-copy="relbb504.1" rend="db" width="629" height="1000">
            <figTranscr/>
            <head>1. Illustrations to Thornton’s Virgil, designs 2-5, executed as a relief
              etching.</head>
            <figDesc>Image 14.3 × 8.5 cm., plate mark 14.6 × 9 cm., printed on unwatermarked wove
              sheet 15.9 × 9.9 cm. Size of each vignette, top to bottom: 3.6 × 8.1 cm., 2.9 × 8.3
              cm., 3.4 × 8.5 cm., 3.8 × 8.5 cm. Printed in black ink with hand tinting in black.
              Essick collection.</figDesc>
          </figure>
<pb id="p25-118" n="118"/>
          <figure n="bb504.2.6-9.com" id="bb504.2.comb.06" work-copy="bb504.2" rend="db" width="482" height="1000">
			<figTranscr>To face page 14.<lb/>
			ILLUSTRATIONS OF IMITATION OF ECLOGUE I.<lb/>
			COLINET.<lb/>
			THENOT.<lb/>
			COLINET and THENOT.<lb/>
			COLINET.</figTranscr>
            <head>2. Illustrations to Thornton’s Virgil, designs 2-5, as published in the 1821
              edition.</head>
            <figDesc>Wood engravings printed in black. Size of each vignette, top to bottom: 3.7 ×
              7.5 cm., 3.2 × 7.5 cm., 3.2 × 7.4 cm., 3.5 × 7.5 cm. Essick Collection.</figDesc>
          </figure> 
          of ten plates from <hi rend="i">For the Sexes: The Gates of Paradise.</hi><ref
            target="n54" type="note">1</ref> The vendor indicated that the volumes had been acquired
          in their extra-illustrated state from a British diplomat after World War II, but the
          presence of “The Chaining of Orc” hints at an American origin. Previous to this recent
          discovery, there were only two recorded impressions of the “Orc” print, one now in the
          Lessing J. Rosenwald Collection of the National Gallery of Art, Washington, and an
          untraced impression exhibited at the Boston Museum of Fine Arts in 1880 (np. 84 in the
          catalogue, from the collection of Mrs. Alexander Gilchrist) and again at the same
          institution in 1891 (no. 10 in the catalogue, from the collection of E. W. Hooper).<ref
            target="n55" type="note">2</ref> The suspicion that the new impression might be the same
          as the one exhibited in Boston is buttressed by the presence, in volume two of the
          extra-illustrated Gilchrist, of Horace E. Scudder’s essay, “William Blake Painter and
          Poet,” clipped from the New York magazine, <hi rend="i">Scribner’s Monthly</hi> 20 (1880):
          225-40. The article begins with a reference to the 1880 Boston exhibition and was
          apparently prompted by it. Yet even if these speculations on provenance are wrong, the
          very fact that the Virgil print was accompanied by genuine Blake prints of great rarity
          places it in good company. Whoever had access to what is now only the second extant
          impression of “The Chaining of Orc” to add to his copy of Gilchrist is more likely to have
          also acquired a unique work by Blake than someone without such demonstrated abilities as a
          collector. If the Virgil print had arrived singly, it would be a slightly more suspicious
          object. <note id="n54"><hi rend="s">1</hi> For details on these works and their sale, see
            Robert N. Essick, “Blake in the Marketplace, 1991,” forthcoming in this
            journal.</note>
	<note id="n55"><hi rend="s">2</hi> For descriptions of these impressions,
            see Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The Separate Plates of William Blake: A
              Catalogue</hi> (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1983) 90-92.</note></p>
        <p>Nancy Bialler of Sotheby’s Print Department, an expert in the graphic arts in her own
          right, immediately sought out professional opinions concerning the authenticity of the
          Virgil print. One British Blake expert was sent a photograph of the work and quickly
          pronounced it a fake. Several others, including G. E. Bentley, Jr., Donald 
            <pb id="p25-119" n="119"/>
Heald, Justin G. Schiller, Jenijoy La Belle, Thomas V. Lange, and
          myself, all tended to believe in the print’s authenticity upon first inspection of the
          object itself. In her essay on the extra-illustrated Gilchrist, “William Blake
          Discoveries,” <hi rend="i">Sotheby’s Preview</hi> (April/May 1991): 16-17, Bialler
          reproduced the Virgil print, noted that “expert opinion is divided” as to its attribution,
          that “it is difficult to fit the . . . print into the sequence of other works related to
          the Virgil project,” but that its “innovative technique [on which more later] strongly
          suggests the hand of Blake.” To sell the prints, Sotheby’s disbound all but the 
            <hi rend="i">Gates of Paradise</hi> plates (plus an inconsequential impression of Blake’s
          plate after Thomas Stothard illustrating Ariosto’s <hi rend="i">Orlando Furioso</hi>,
          1783) and offered them in four lots in their 9-11 May 1991 sale of “Old Master, 19th and
          20th Century and Contemporary Prints.” The Virgil appeared as lot 9, accompanied by a
          reproduction in the catalogue. Because of the differing views about the print’s
          authenticity, Sotheby’s found it prudent to describe the work as “Attributed to William
          Blake” and noted that, “although expert opinion is divided, we believe this print should
          be attributed to Blake.” Fortunately, the “Attributed” label held down the bidding that
          sent its companions to record levels and I was able to acquire the print through the
          agency of Donald Heald.</p>
        <p>By comparing the newly-discovered print to the well-known wood engravings of the same
          basic Virgil illustrations (illus. 2), one can quickly perceive many small, and several
          large, differences in design. All the new vignettes show more image on their sides, much
          as in proofs of the wood blocks before they were cut down for publication in Thornton’s
          volumes (illus. 3). Yet, the new print does not follow the proofs in every respect, for
          the latter show a bit more image on the left sides of all four vignettes and a bit less on
          the right side of the bottom vignette. Similarly, the width of each vignette in the new
            <figure n="virgilbm.25.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="488" height="819">
            <head>3. Illustrations to Thornton’s Virgil, designs 2-5, proof of the wood engravings
              before separation and trimming for publication.</head>
            <figDesc>Size of each vignette, top to bottom: 4.1 × 8.6 cm., 3.5 × 8.6 cm., 3.5 × 8.6
              cm., 3.8 × 8.6 cm. Reproduced by permission of the Trustees of the British
              Museum.</figDesc>
            </figure>
<pb id="p25-120" n="120"/>
<figure n="s-inn.b.p1-2" id="s-inn.b.illbk.01" work-copy="s-inn.b" rend="db" width="649" height="1000">
	<figTranscr/>
            <head>4. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (1789), copy B, frontispiece.</head>
            <figDesc>Relief etching with hand coloring, 11 × 7 cm. Rosenwald Collection, Library of
              Congress.</figDesc>
          </figure>
<figure n="bbshepherd.25.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="456">
            <head>5. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (1794), copy BB, “The
              Shepherd.”</head>
            <figDesc>Relief etching, hand tinting in black and gray wash, 11.1 × 6.9 cm. European
              private collection; photo courtesy of Christie’s New York.</figDesc>
          </figure>
<figure n="songsie.z.p28" id="songsie.z.illbk.28" work-copy="songsie.z" rend="db" width="652" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>28</figTranscr>
            <head>6. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi> (1794), copy Z,
              frontispiece to <hi rend="i">Experience.</hi></head>
            <figDesc>Relief etching with hand coloring, 11 × 7 cm. Rosenwald Collection, Library of
              Congress.</figDesc>
          </figure>
<figure n="s-inn.b.p29-8" id="s-inn.b.illbk.29" work-copy="s-inn.b" rend="db" width="653" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>The Lamb<lb/>
	Little Lamb who made thee<lb/>
	Dost thou know who made thee<lb/>
	Gave thee life &amp; bid thee feed.<lb/>
	By the stream &amp; o’er the mead;<lb/>
	Gave thee clothing of delight,<lb/>
	Softest clothing wooly bright;<lb/>
	Gave thee such a tender voice,<lb/>
	Making all the vales rejoice:<lb/>
	Little Lamb who made thee<lb/>
	Dost thou know who made thee<lb/>
	Little Lamb I’ll tell thee,<lb/>
	Little Lamb Ill tell thee:<lb/>
	He is called by thy name,<lb/>
	For he calls himself a Lamb:<lb/>
	He is meek &amp; he is mild,<lb/>
	He became a little child:<lb/>
	I a child &amp; thou a lamb,<lb/>
	We are called by his name.<lb/>
	Little Lamb God bless thee.<lb/>
	Little Lamb God bless thee.</figTranscr>
            <head>7. <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (1789), copy B, “The Lamb.”</head>
            <figDesc>Relief etching with hand coloring, 11.9 × 7.7 cm. Rosenwald Collection, Library
              of Congress.</figDesc>
          </figure> print lies between those of published and proof impressions of the wood
          engravings (see measurements in captions for illus. 1-3). Other design variations are
          listed for each vignette below:</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Top vignette.</hi> Left arm and hand position of the figure on the left (the
          older shepherd, Thenot) differs from the wood engraving. The younger shepherd, Colinet,
          wears a transparent body stocking, not the high waisted, knee-length gown of the wood
          engraving. Indeed, we might think him nude except for the lines indicating mid-calf cuffs
          and a sleeve on his left arm. There are a great many more rays of sunlight and more
          foliage on the tree in the new print; a vine (ivy?) wraps itself about the lower reaches
          of the tree trunk (no vine in the wood engraving). A wedge-shaped cloud extends from behind
          Colinet’s head toward Thenot only in the new version. The left-most sheep is more clearly
          a ram in the new print, but the single sheep clearly pictured between Colinet and the tree
          in the wood engraving is not present, or at most only hinted at, in the new print. The
          background landscape is divided into two hills in both versions, but the right hill is
          forward of the left in the wood engraving and just the reverse in the new print. As in the
          other three vignettes, Thenot’s gown is more diaphanous than in the wood engravings and we
          consequently see more of his lineaments.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Second vignette from top.</hi> The new print lacks the cottage roof in the
          background, center right, of the wood engraving. The lines that could be easily mistaken
          for part of the earthen bank, lower right in the wood engraving, clearly delineate a dog,
          curled up and apparently sleeping, as in the preliminary drawing (illus. 13, middle).
          Branches of the tree on the left extend over the sun in the new print, which again shows
          many minor differences in vegetation and the outline of the distant hills. Colinet wears
          his body stocking, as in the top design, but the most dramatic difference in the entire
            <pb id="p25-121" n="121"/>
group is in the posture of Thenot. In the wood engraving, we
          see the lower half of his body from the side; in the new print, his whole body is turned
          toward us with right knee raised to his waist and his unnaturally elongated left leg
          extended far to the right. His right hand is lower than in the wood engraving and his left
          arm reaches to the right rather than bending upward at the elbow. The sheep closest to
          Thenot has her head turned to the right (to the left in the wood engraving); the sheep
          seen in profile above Colinet’s right leg is not present, or only hinted at, in the wood
          engraving. Both tree trunks are of much larger diameter in the new print (compare to the
          proof of the wood engraving, illus. 3).</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Second vignette from bottom.</hi> Colinet again wears his body stocking and
          his crook rests against his left side and shoulder (more vertical, and separated from his
          body, in the wood engraving). The few, easily overlooked, lines below his left hand in the
          wood engraving clearly delineate his Panpipe in the new print. The sheep nearest Colinet
          holds his head higher and is more intently looking at the man than in the wood engraving.
          Thenot holds no crook and the tree against which he leans is more dramatically twisted in
          the new print. The sheep on the hill are less organized than the group marching along in
          almost military order in the wood engraving.</p>
        <p><hi rend="i">Bottom vignette.</hi> The outlines of clouds and diagonal dotted lines
          around the tree, perhaps representing rain, appear only in the new print. Both may be
          responses to the “low’ring sky” and “storms” mentioned in the passage illustrated.
          Colinet’s jump-suit now sports a V neckline with a rolled collar, a fashion touch perhaps
          hinted at by a few lines in the previous design. He lacks the shepherd’s crook, so
          prominently displayed in the wood engraving, thereby freeing his left hand for a pointing
          gesture with index finger extended. The blasted tree to which he points lacks the fissure
          (“thunder-scar” 
          <figure n="bb421.1.3-2.ps" id="bb421.1.spb.03" work-copy="bb421.1" rend="db" width="846" height="1000">
			<figTranscr>1<lb/>
			Our Father which art in Heaven hallowed be thy Name<lb/>
			Thus did Job continually<lb/>
			There was a Man in the<lb/>
			Land of Uz whose Name<lb/>
			was Job. &amp; that Man<lb/>
			was perfect &amp; upright<lb/>
			The Letter Killeth<lb/>
			The Spirit giveth Life<lb/>
			It is Spiritually Discerned<lb/>
			&amp; one that feared God<lb/>
			&amp; eschewed Evil. &amp; there<lb/>
			was born unto him Seven<lb/>
			Sons &amp; Three Daughters<lb/>
			WBlake inv &amp; sculp<lb/>
			London. Published as the Act directs. March 8: 1828. by Willm Blake N3 Fountain Court Strand<lb/>
			Proof</figTranscr>
            <head>8. <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the Book of Job</hi> (1826), pl. 1.</head>
            <figDesc>Line engraving, 18.3 × 15 cm., pre-publication proof state 5. Essick
              collection.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <figure n="isaiah.25.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="300" height="437">
            <head>10. <hi rend="i">The Prophet Isaiah Foretelling the Crucifixion and the
                Ascension.</hi></head>
            <figDesc>Verso pencil sketch, approx. 12.5 × 7.5 cm., c. 1821. Reproduced by permission
              of the Trustees of the British Museum.</figDesc>
          </figure>
          <figure n="america.i.p10" id="america.I.illbk.10" work-copy="america.I" rend="db" width="735" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>The terror answerd; I am Orc, wreath’d round the accursed tree:<lb/>
	The times are ended; shadows pass the morning gins to break;<lb/>
	The fiery joy, that Urizen perverted to ten commands,<lb/>
	What night he led the starry hosts thro’ the wide wilderness:<lb/>
	That stony law I stamp to dust: and scatter religion abroad<lb/>
	To the four winds as a torn book, &amp; none shall gather the leaves;<lb/>
	But they shall rot on desart sands, &amp; consume in bottomless deeps,<lb/>
	To make the desarts blossom, &amp; the deeps shrink to their fountains,<lb/>
	And to renew, the fiery joy, and burst the stony roof.<lb/>
	That pale religious letchery, seeking Virginity,<lb/>
	May find it in a harlot, and in coarse-clad honesty<lb/>
	The undefil’d tho’ ravish’d in her cradle night and morn:<lb/>
	For every thing that lives is holy, life delights in life;<lb/>
	Because the soul of sweet delight can never be defil’d.<lb/>
	Fires inwrap the earthly globe, yet man is not consumd;<lb/>
	Amidst the lustful fires he walks; his feet become like brass,<lb/>
	His knees and thighs like silver, &amp; his breast and head like gold.</figTranscr>
            <head>9. <hi rend="i">America</hi> (1793), copy I, pl. 10.</head>
            <figDesc>Relief and white-line etching, detail of top design, approx. 12 × 16 cm.
              Huntington Library, San Marino, California.</figDesc>
          </figure>
<pb id="p25-122" n="122"/>
          <figure n="esxiii.1.1.sp" id="esxiii.1.spb.01" work-copy="esxiii.1" rend="db" width="653" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>DEATHS<lb/>
              DOOR</figTranscr>
            <head>11. “Deaths Door.”</head>
            <figDesc>White-line etching with hand-tinting in black and gray washes, 18.6 × 11.7 cm.
              Etched in 1805 as an illustration to Robert Blair, <hi rend="i">The Grave.</hi> Essick
              collection.</figDesc>
          </figure> 
          in the text) of the wood engraving. The sheep sit rather than stand, with a ram
          on the right. In the text illustrated by the previous vignette, the lambs “require their
          absent dams.” In the bottom wood engraving, they are rejoined, with one lamb on its knees
          to suckle from its mother. The new print lacks this sentimental motif, not called for by
          Colinet’s speech illustrated by the bottom vignette.</p>
        <p>The major design variants all have precedents in Blake’s work of the same and earlier
          periods. Colinet’s see-through body stocking was first worn by his fellow shepherd in the
            <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (illus. 4-5). In the <hi rend="i">Experience</hi>
          frontispiece (illus. 6), we find the V neckline and rolled collar of the bottom vignette,
          as well as an ivy-like vine similar to the one also climbing a tree trunk in the top
          vignette. Colinet’s pointing arm and finger remind one of the same gesture used by the
          adult male in the second plate of “The Ecchoing Green.” The sheep looking so attentively
          at Colinet in the second vignette from the bottom is very similar to his predecessor
          responding to the child in “The Lamb” of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> (illus. 7).
          The variant disposition of the sheep in the bottom vignette resembles the flocks in the
          first (illus. 8) and last of the Job engravings, first executed as water colors c.
            1805-06<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n56" type="note">3</ref> The powerful
figure of Thenot in the second
          Virgil vignette from the top has a long and distinguished history in Blake’s works. The
          basic arrangement of his legs, and in particular the prominent right knee, first appears
          in a small and crude form on pl. 3 of <hi rend="i">All Religions are One</hi> (c.
            1788).<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n57" type="note">4</ref> In 1793, this
figure became the threatening
          but majestic Urizen on pl. 10 of <hi rend="i">America</hi> (illus. 9). The closest
          parallel with Thenot is contemporary with the Virgil illustrations, <hi rend="i">The
            Prophet Isaiah Foretelling the Destruction of Jerusalem</hi> (Butlin 773), designed for
          a wood engraving never executed. In a variant preliminary pencil sketch (Butlin 772,
          illus. 10), Blake presents virtually the same leg posture as in the newly discovered
          Virgil illustration. Although the arm and hand gestures differ, both figures express a
          sense of patriarchal wisdom and visionary capabilities barely suggested by the much weaker
          figure of Thenot in the wood-engraved Virgil design (illus. 2-3). The major design variants
          in the new Virgil print—Thenot in the second vignette from the top, the sheep in the
          bottom vignette, and the clothing of Colinet in all four designs—are more typically
          Blakean than their very different renderings in the wood engravings. 
              <note id="n56"><hi rend="s">3</hi> See Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The Paintings and Drawings of
William
              Blake</hi> (New Haven: Yale UP, 1981) #550.1 and 550.21 (pls. 697 and 717). Hereafter
            referred to as “Butlin” followed by catalogue entry number.</note>
	<note id="n57"><hi
              rend="s">4</hi> Plate numbers and copy designations for Blake’s illuminated books
            follow G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P,
            1977).</note></p>
        <p>A skeptic might argue that the variants in the new print are the sign of a pastiche
          manufactured by a clever forger who has produced designs that look more like some of
          Blake’s best known work than do the wood engravings. Yet I do not think that such an
          argument is persuasive. When given the commission to design illustrations for an
          “imitation” of Virgil’s pastorals, Blake is likely to have returned to the pictorial
          repertoire developed years earlier for the illustration of his own pastoral poems. Blake
          was probably printing copy V of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence</hi> for James Vine in
          1820, and <hi rend="i">America</hi> copy O for John Linnell in this same period, and thus
          the precursor designs for the Virgil illustrations would have been recently before Blake’s
          attention. We see much the same sort of borrowings—for instance, the old man entering a
          tomb from <hi rend="i">America</hi> pl. 14—in Blake’s illustrations for Robert Blair’s 
            <hi rend="i">The Grave</hi> (illus. 11), executed quickly for a commercial project in 1805.
          None of the variant motifs in the Virgil print are copied mechanically from known Blake
          designs; rather, they show an evolution within basic compositional paradigms of the sort
          produced by an original artist. The many minor variants without clear iconographic
          significance also evince the spontaneous proliferation of difference within the work of an
          artist for whom every act of execution was a chance for re-conceptualization. It would
          take a very clever forger indeed to capture not only Blake’s style, but also his
          sensibility and typical working habits, with such success.</p>
        <p>The analysis of design variants leaves at least some lingering doubts. For me, these are
          stilled by a consideration of the newly-discovered print’s material and technical
          features. Blank sheets of early nineteenth-century paper are still to be had, particularly
          if one is willing to cut the flyleaves from old books, but at least we should expect the
          right sort of paper in any impression from Blake’s own hand. He very rarely used anything
          other than wove paper for his prints. As Sotheby’s auction catalogue points out, the new
          Virgil print is on a “‘Whatman-type’ wove paper” very similar, perhaps even identical, to
          several of Blake’s works of the early 1820s. Its texture—smooth and fairly hard—and
          thickness of 0.19 mm. match what we find in <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi>, both copy
          C in the Huntington Library and the impression of pl. 1 in my collection, and the first
          title page to the Genesis illuminated manuscript, showing a 
<pb id="p25-123" n="123"/>
          Whatman 1821 watermark, also in the Huntington. In contrast, Whatman papers of 1825 (the
          Job engravings), 1826 (the second Genesis title page), 1831, and 1832 (posthumous copy h
          of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of Experience</hi>) are all slightly thicker, at
          0.21 mm.</p>
        <p>The technique used to create the new Virgil print is the most convincing single piece of
          evidence for its attribution to Blake. It is unmistakably a relief etching, executed with
          great skill.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n58" type="note">5</ref> Some of the
smaller relief plateaus,
          when viewed under low-power magnification, are indented slightly into the paper—a sure
          sign of relief printing. The slight platemark, a shadow line of the outer edge of the
          relief etching border, wiped almost clean of ink in this impression, is typical of Blake’s
          technique and also reveals that all four vignettes were etched on a single piece of
          metal—very probably copper, since a softer metal such as pewter would not be suitable for
          such delicate work. The necessity for this border in relief etching, created by the wall
          of wax containing the acid, may have forced the vignettes to present less image on their
          left sides than what we see in proofs of the wood engravings (illus. 3). The plate shows
          no evidence of white-line etching or engraving, for even the stipple-like effects on the
          sheep and landscape background were created through the positive, black-line process of
          relief etching alone. We see a similar refinement on Blake’s basic technique in the
          concluding vignette to <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi> (illus. 12)—compare, for
          example, the stippling on the lower figure’s back with the sheep in the top vignette. This
          technique, combined with what are for a relief etching extremely thin lines, permitted the
          artist to create a work more delicate than the wood engravings and give to faces and
          gestures more detailed expressiveness. I know of no forgeries or facsimiles of Blake’s
          relief etchings that even approach the artistry of this work. One can still prefer the
          wood engravings for their brooding intensity, but it is hard to conceive of anyone other
          than the inventor of relief etching handling the process with such consummate skill. If
          the new Virgil print is the work of a forger, he has surpassed all but a few of Blake’s
          own relief etchings in technical excellence. <note id="n58"><hi rend="s">5</hi> “Relief
            etching” is the term generally used to name the graphic medium Blake used for most of
            his illuminated books. For descriptions of the basic process and the characteristics of
            the prints it produces, see Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake Printmaker</hi>
            (Princeton: Princeton UP, 1980) 85-120, and Joseph Viscomi, <hi rend="i">The Art of
              William Blake’s Illuminated Prints</hi> ([Manchester]: Manchester Etching Workshop,
            1983).</note></p>
        <p>The characteristics of the specific impression at issue indicate that Blake was its
          printer. The thick and somewhat grainy ink with reticulated patches is typical of his work
          and distinguishes this print from Frederick Tatham’s posthumous impressions of Blake’s
          relief plates. Lithographs and zincographs, used to facsimile Blake’s illuminated books in
          the nineteenth century, are more thinly inked and have smoother surfaces. Their slight
          reticulations visible under magnification are much more evenly distributed and consistent
          than what we find in the Virgil relief etching. The wiped etching border also suggests
          Blake’s hand, for Tatham inked and printed the borders. But it is the subtle handwork on
          the new Virgil print that speaks most eloquently for an attribution to Blake. Several
          areas in the print have been touched with a black wash almost indistinguishable from the
          printed image and perhaps executed in the same pigment, suspended in diluted glue, used
          for the ink. All six trees bear slight touches, with a large patch just above Thenot’s
          raised right hand in the second vignette from the top which might even be visible in the
          accompanying reproduction. We can find a similar use of hand-tinting in black to improve
          on the relief etchings in copy BB of <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
            Experience</hi> (see illus. 5) and on the unique impression of the white-line etching of
          “Deaths Door” (illus. 11). In the latter case, the handwork may have been added to
          compensate for slight weaknesses in the printed image and make it more acceptable to a
          commercial publisher. A similar motive may lie behind the tinting on the Virgil relief
          etching, so typical of Blake’s own hand and not to be found in either posthumous
          impressions of the illuminated books or forgeries of them.</p>
        <figure n="abel.a.p2" id="abel.a.illbk.02" work-copy="abel.a" rend="db" width="751" height="1000">
	<figTranscr>Alive &amp; not Dead: were it not better to believe Vision<lb/>
	With all our might &amp; strength tho we are fallen &amp; lost<lb/>
	Adam _ Eve thou hast spoken truly. let us kneel before his feet.<lb/>
	They Kneel before Jehovah<lb/>
	Abel  Are these the Sacrifices of Eternity O Jehovah, a Broken Spirit<lb/>
	And a Contrite Heart. O I cannot Forgive! the Accuser hath<lb/>
	Enterd into Me as into his House &amp; I loathe thy Tabernacles<lb/>
	As thou hast said so is it come to pass; My desire is unto Cain<lb/>
	And He doth rule over Me: therefore My Soul in fumes of Blood<lb/>
	Cries for Vengeance: Sacrifice on Sacrifice Blood on Blood<lb/>
	Jehovah Lo I have given you a Lamb for an Atonement instead<lb/>
	Of the Transgresor. or no Flesh or Spirit could ever Live<lb/>
	Abel__ Compelled I cry O Earth cover not the Blood of Abel<lb/>
	Abel sinks down into the Grave. from which arises Satan<lb/>
	Armed in glittering scales with a Crown &amp; a Spear<lb/>
	Satan I will have Human Blood &amp; not the blood of Bulls or Goats<lb/>
	And no Atonement O Jehovah the Elohim live on Sacrifice<lb/>
	Of Men; hence I am God of Men: Thou Human O Jehovah.<lb/>
	By the Rock &amp; Oak of the Druid creeping Misletoe &amp; Thorn<lb/>
	Cains City built with Human Blood. not Blood of Bulls &amp; Goats<lb/>
	Thou shalt Thyself be Sacrificed to Me thy God on Calvary<lb/>
	Jehovah Such is My Will: Thunders<lb/>
	that Thou Thyself go to Eternal Death<lb/>
	In Self Annihilation even till Satan Self-subdud Put off Satan<lb/>
	Into the Bottomless Abyss whose torment arises for ever &amp; ever.<lb/>
	On each side a Chorus of Angels entering Sing the following<lb/>
	The Elohim of the Heathen Swore Vengeance for Sin! Then Thou stoodst<lb/>
	Forth O Elohim Jehovah! in the midst of the darkness of the Oath! All Clothed<lb/>
	In Thy Covenant of the Forgiveness of Sins: Death O Holy! Is this Brotherhood<lb/>
	The Elohim saw their Oath Eternal Fire; they rolled apart trembling over The<lb/>
	Mercy Seat: each in his station fixt in the Firmament by Peace Brotherhood and<lb/>
	Love.<lb/>
	The Curtain falls<lb/>
	The Voice of Abels<lb/>
	Blood<lb/>
	1822 W Blakes Original Stereotype was 1788</figTranscr>
          <head>12. <hi rend="i">The Ghost of Abel</hi> (1822), copy A, pl. 2.</head>
          <figDesc>Relief etching, 16.7 × 12.4 cm. Rosenwald Collection, Library of
            Congress.</figDesc>
        </figure>
        <p>A necessary step in a successful argument for attribution is to fit the new discovery
          into the compositional sequence of the project to which it supposedly belongs. As Bialler
          points out, this would seem a difficult task in the case of the Virgil relief etching. The
          major stumbling block is that Blake’s preliminary drawings (Butlin 769) for the series
          generally accord with the wood engravings, not the relief etching (see illus. 13).<ref
            target="n59" type="note">6</ref> There is no vine in the drawing for the top vignette
          and Colinet holds his crook away from his body in the drawing for the vignette second from
          the bottom. Colinet wears his knee-length gown, and Thenot his less revealing costume, in
          all three drawings. The older shepherd and the sheep in the drawing for the second
          vignette from the top are arranged as in the wood engraving (illus. 2-3). Two lines in the
          drawing hint at the cottage roof in the middle distance, as in the wood engraving.
          However, the position of Thenot’s left arm and hand in the drawing for the top vignette is
          midway between the relief etching and the wood engraving, while the absence of Thenot’s
          crook in the drawing for the second vignette from the bottom 
          <pb id="p25-124" n="124"/>
<figure n="but769.1.1.wd" id="but769.1.wd.01" work-copy="but769.1" rend="db" width="958" height="430">
	<figTranscr/>
</figure>
<figure n="but769.1.2.wd" id="but769.1.wd.02" work-copy="but769.1" rend="db" width="958" height="380">
	<figTranscr/>
</figure>
<figure n="but769.1.3.wd" rend="file" width="958" height="385">
            <head>13. Virgil preliminary drawings (Butlin 769. 1-3).</head>
            <figDesc>Top: <hi rend="i">Thenot Remonstrates with Colinet.</hi> Pencil, pen, and gray
              wash, 4 × 9 cm., for the second cut (top vignette in the relief etching). Keynes
              Collection, Fitzwilliam Museum. Middle: <hi rend="i">Thenot and Colinet Converse
                Seated Beneath Two Trees.</hi> Pencil, pen, and sepia wash, 3.5 × 9.5 cm., for the
              third cut (vignette second from the top in the relief etching). Untraced since 1939.
              Bottom: <hi rend="i">Colinet and Thenot, with Shepherds’ Crooks, Leaning against
                Trees.</hi> Pencil, pen, and sepia wash, 3.6 × 9.3 cm., for the fourth cut (vignette
              second from the bottom in the relief etching). Collection of Arthur
              Vershbow.</figDesc>
          </figure> matches the relief-etched version. A basic assumption in determining design
          sequences is that drawings precede all etched or engraved versions. Yet the extant Virgil
          drawings would appear to be transitional between the relief etching and the wood
          engravings, and in major design variants closer to the latter. How could the relief
          etching be the first composition in the series? The special properties of relief etching
          offer an explanation. <note id="n59"><hi rend="s">6</hi> The drawing for the fifth cut
            (bottom vignette in the group at issue) is untraced and unrecorded.</note></p>
        <p>Conventional intaglio etching and engraving require the preparation of the design in a
          different medium, usually a drawing on paper. The image is then transferred, often by
          mechanical or semi-mechanical means such as counterproofing or caulking, to the metal
          plate. Blake’s method of relief etching allows for—indeed, promotes—initial composition
          directly on the metal. The drawing surface and the printing surface are one. All that is
          required is a loose pencil sketch like those for some of Blake’s illuminated books in his
          Notebook (Butlin 201) or the alternative drawing for two pages from <hi rend="i">The Book
            of Thel</hi>(Butlin 218, now in the British Museum). The present absence of detailed
          preliminary drawings or mock-ups for the illuminated books cannot prove that Blake never
          made any, but surely he realized that one of the great advantages of relief etching was
          its direct and autographic nature, one that unites the early stages of composition and the
          final stages of graphic execution.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n60"
type="note">7</ref> Thus, as odd as it
          may seem from the perspective of conventional graphics, the Virgil relief etching may very
          well be the first extant composition in the series, preceding both the carefully executed
          pen and wash drawings as well as the wood engravings. Blake probably did some pencil
          sketching on paper before turning to the relief etching, but no evidence of such
          first-steps has survived. This absence of rough preliminaries is also true of the vast
          majority of the relief-etched designs in the illuminated books. 
              <note id="n60"><hi rend="s">7</hi> For more on the autographic nature of relief etching, see
Viscomi, 
              <hi rend="i">The Art of William Blake’s Illuminated Prints</hi> 4-8.</note></p>
        <p>Once one accepts the new Virgil print as authentic and places it first in the sequence of
          Virgil designs, other stages in the composing process and early accounts of responses to
          the designs can be seen in a new light. What follows is a retelling of the history of
          Blake’s Virgil compositions that takes into account the existence of the relief
          etching.</p>
        <p>Robert John Thornton was the physician to the family of John Linnell, Blake’s great
          patron for his graphic works in the final nine years of his life. According to Linnell’s
          journal, Thornton and Blake called at his home on the same day, 19 Sept. 1818, and the two
          men may have met on that occasion.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n61"
type="note">8</ref> We do not know
          when Thornton commissioned Blake to illustrate the 1821 edition of his Virgil, but Blake
          must have been well along on the project by 15 Sept. 1820 since on that day Thornton sent
          Linnell a proof of “Blake’s Augustus” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 266), one
          of the intaglio prints of portrait busts Blake executed for the Virgil volumes. Whenever
          Blake was given the task of composing some new illustrations for Philips’ version of the
          first eclogue, he was in a position to know the required format of his designs. The 1821
          Virgil is the “Third Edition,” as its title page announces. The first edition of 1812 was
          published without illustrations, but two years later Thornton produced a companion volume
          of designs, <hi rend="i">Illustrations of the School-Virgil, in Copper-Plates, and
            Wood-cuts</hi> (London: Rivington et al., 1814). These illustrations were repeated in
          the second edition of 1819. For the third edition, some of the earlier blocks were
          reprinted, including a group of four cuts (vol. 1, facing p. 55, in the third edition)
          arranged one above the other just as in Blake’s relief etching and wood engravings. The
          overall size of these four designs, 12.7 × 7.9 cm., is only a little smaller than Blake’s
          relief etching. A group of five cuts in the 1814 volume, with an overall height of 15 cm.,
          is slightly larger than Blake’s work. Those involved in the production of the third
          edition probably knew well in advance its intended leaf size, for at 17.6 × 10.3 cm. the
          1821 leaves are the same width as, and only half a centimeter taller than, the 1814 volume
          of illustrations.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n62" type="note">9</ref> Thus,
Blake could easily have known
          the size and unusual format required of his illustrations well in advance of any
          composition and could have produced the relief etching straight away without prior use of
          a more conventional arrangement of his vignettes. <note id="n61"><hi rend="s">8</hi> See
            G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1969)
            258.</note>
	<note id="n62"><hi rend="s">9</hi> The size given here for the 1821 leaves is
            based on three copies in original sheep, the binding in which the volumes appear to have
            been issued. I have never seen an uncut copy.</note></p>
        <p>Blake may have thought that Thornton’s commission offered a good opportunity to
          incorporate his innovative graphics into a commercial project, much as he had tried to do
          in 1805 with the white-line etching of “Deaths 
<pb id="p25-125" n="125"/>
Door” (illus.
          11) for R. H. Cromek’s letterpress edition of Blair’s <hi rend="i">Grave.</hi> Like wood
          engravings, Blake’s relief etchings were printed from their raised surfaces with pressure
          much lighter than that required of intaglio plates. It is technically possible—and Blake
          may have believed it was commercially viable—to lock a relief etching into a chase with
          type for letterpress printing, just as with a wood engraving. Blake may have also believed
          that Thornton was amenable to the use of innovative graphics in his book. Thornton
          experimented with lithography, still a new medium for book illustration in England, for
          some of the designs and included in volume 1 two maps “On Stone by J. Wyld” printed at
          “The Lithographic Press 6 Dartmouth St. West.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n63" type="note">10</ref> The
          title page of the 1821 Virgil indicates that it is a “Stereotyped” edition. If Blake had
          known this in advance, he may have thought it a likely context for his own “Stereotype,”
          the word he uses to refer to his relief etchings on the second plate of <hi rend="i">The
            Ghost of Abel</hi> (illus. 12, lower right corner). <note id="n63"><hi rend="s">10</hi>
            For the documentary records indicating that Thornton planned to convert Blake’s portrait
            busts into lithographs, see Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Records</hi> 266-67, and Robert
            N. Essick, <hi rend="i">William Blake’s Commercial Book Illustrations</hi> (Oxford:
            Clarendon P, 1991) 112-13.</note></p>
        <p>When Blake presented the whiteline “Deaths Door” to Cromek, it was almost immediately
          rejected and the publisher turned to Louis Schiavonetti to execute Blake’s designs as
          conventional intaglio etchings/engravings. The relief etching of the four Virgil
          vignettes—perhaps executed (again, like “Deaths Door”) as a sample of Blake’s intentions
          for the entire series of twenty designs—was probably met with a similar initial response
          from their intended publisher. According to Alexander Gilchrist, when the “publishers” saw
          Blake’s prints they declared that “this man [Blake] must do no more” and that all the
          designs should be “recut by one of their regular hands. The very engravers received them
          with derision, crying out in the words of the critic, ‘This will never do.’”<ref
            target="n64" type="note">11</ref> Gilchrist indicates that these opinions refer to the
          wood engravings, but he did not know of the existence of the relief etching and thus may
          have taken responses to it as statements about the later cuts or conflated a sequence of
          two separate events into a single tale.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n65"
type="note">12</ref> As was the
          case with Cromek, Thornton, his “agent” William Harrison,<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n66" type="note">13</ref> or his publishers may have proclaimed that the relief
etching “will never do.”
          This was not literally and finally the case with the wood engravings, for they were indeed
          printed in the 1821 volume. <note id="n64"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Gilchrist, 
              <hi rend="i">Life of William Blake</hi> (London: Macmillan, 1863) 1: 273. At least parts of
            Gilchrist’s account of the Virgil project may have been based on information supplied by
            Henry Cole, who wrote about Blake’s wood engravings in a review of an edition of
            Goldsmith’s <hi rend="i">The Vicar of Wakefield, The Athenæum</hi> (21 Jan. 1843): 65.
            Cole quotes “this will never do,” also cited by Gilchrist.</note>
	<note id="n65"><hi
              rend="s">12</hi> Mrs. Gilchrist’s possible ownership of the Virgil relief etching (see
            earlier speculations on provenance) is not inconsistent with her husband not knowing of
            the print. She continued to collect Blake after her husband’s death in 1861.</note>	
            <note id="n66"><hi rend="s">13</hi> Harrison (active 1821-26) is named as Thornton’s agent on
            the 1821 Virgil title page. The book was registered at Stationer’s Hall on 12 Feb. 1821,
            the “Property of Wilm. Harrison” (Bentley, <hi rend="i">Blake Books</hi> 628). Harrison
            may have played an important, but completely unrecorded, role in the initial rejection
            and eventual acceptance of Blake’s Virgil illustrations.</note></p>
        <p>There were probably both technical and aesthetic reasons for the evident rejection of the
          Virgil relief etching. The copperplate would have to be cut into its four sections to
          accommodate the letterpress text printed below each wood-engraved vignette (illus. 2), a
          format established by the 1814 volume of designs. The resulting four plates would have to
          be mounted type-high for printing in a typographic press. Blake’s shallow etching would
          have been difficult to ink rapidly without fouling the whites, a problem that may have
          motivated the conversion of some of Blake’s <hi rend="i">Innocence</hi> and 
            <hi rend="i">Experience</hi> copperplates into electrotypes with higher relief for printing in
          Gilchrist’s 1863 <hi rend="i">Life of Blake.</hi> None of this would have been impossible,
          perhaps with the exception of acceptable printing quality, but it would have required
          journeymen printers to wrestle with an <figure n="virgilthird.25.3.bqscan" rend="file" width="600" height="253">
            <head>14. Blake’s Virgil illustrations, third vignette, re-cut by an anonymous
              journeyman.</head>
            <figDesc>Wood engraving, 2.9 × 7.4 cm., executed c. 1820 and published by Henry Cole in
                <hi rend="i">The Athenæum</hi> (21 Jan. 1843): 65. Essick collection. Cole does not
              mention any other such re-engravings; but a woodblock of the second vignette, probably
              cut by the same hand that executed the example reproduced here, is in the Huntington
              Library.</figDesc>
          </figure> unfamiliar medium. The aesthetic objections one can readily imagine—too crude,
          too unconventional—may have been accompanied by moral qualms centering on Colinet’s
          near-nudity in all four vignettes and Thenot’s buttocks in the top design. Such views are
          likely to have arisen since the book was intended for use by “Youtm [sic]” in “Schools”
          (title page). The re-costuming in the drawings and wood engravings may not have been
          Blake’s decision, but Thornton’s or his publishers’.</p>
        <p>Unlike his precursor, Cromek, Thornton did not immediately turn to another craftsman to
          execute Blake’s designs. One vignette present in the relief etching was re-cut in reverse
          on wood by a journeyman (illus. 14), but it follows Blake’s drawing (illus. 13, middle)
          and wood engraving in the position of the sheep and the presence of the cottage while
          adding its own unique variants (e.g., the positions of Colinet’s head and Thenot’s arms).
          This anonymous cut was probably copied after Blake’s own wood engraving, for the
          journeyman has left out the dog, clearly visible in the drawing but easily overlooked in
          Blake’s cut. Blake was evidently given a second chance to participate in the project,
          probably after firm orders that he execute wood engravings 
<pb id="p25-126" n="126"/>
to
          match the medium of most of the other illustrations and clothe his characters in a more
          decorous fashion.</p>
        <p>In contrast to relief etchings, wood engravings require reasonably detailed preliminary
          drawings, either on paper for subsequent transfer to the blocks or drawn directly on them.
          For the Virgil designs, Blake followed the first alternative, a decision that may have
          been prompted by the desire—or a request from Thornton—to have the drawings approved
          before investing all the time and labor required of wood engraving. The drawings are far
          less challenging to conventional sensibilities than either the relief etching or the wood
          engravings. One can well imagine a journeyman wood engraver turning these drawings into
          cuts not very different from others planned for the Virgil volumes, as was indeed the case
          with the re-cut design reproduced here (illus. 14) and three vignettes published in the
          book. As Geoffrey Keynes has pointed out, Blake’s “preliminary designs gave no hint of
          what the final result would be.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n67"
type="note">14</ref>
	<note id="n67"><hi
              rend="s">14</hi> Keynes, introduction to <hi rend="i">The Illustrations of William
              Blake for Thornton’s Virgil with the First Eclogue and the Imitation by Ambrose
              Philips</hi> (London: Nonesuch P, 1937) 9, rpt. in Keynes, <hi rend="i">Blake
              Studies</hi>, 2nd ed. (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1971) 137.</note></p>
        <p>Blake’s next step was to transfer the drawings to the wood. This he probably accomplished
          by making pencil tracings of the pen and wash drawings and counterproofing or caulking
          them from the back onto the face of the wood blocks. Both these processes will reverse the
          images so that impressions from the blocks will have right and left as in the drawings.
          Except for the first and largest design, given its own block, the vignettes were
          transferred four to a block, as we can see in proof impressions (illus. 3). If Thornton,
          his agent or publishers, had approved of the drawings, they were no doubt disappointed,
          perhaps even angered, by the engravings. Unlike the Virgil relief etching, in which the
          image is defined by black lines alone, the wood engravings are combinations of white and
          black lines. Other illustrations in Thornton’s volumes are technically similar, but
          Blake’s way of handling the medium is highly unconventional. The journeymen wood engravers
          were following in the tradition of Thomas Bewick, whereas Blake’s integrations of black
          and white lines grew from his own deployment of white lines in relief etchings and the
          technique of “Woodcut on Copper” Blake described in his Notebook and used for plates such
          as “Deaths Door” (illus. 11). Thornton must have found himself even worse off than he
          began, for Blake had presented him with prints even darker and more primitive than the
          relief etching. It must have been at this point that he turned to journeymen to re-cut
          Blake’s designs, but was finally persuaded, according to Gilchrist’s familiar story, by
          several distinguished artists to use seventeen of Blake’s wood engravings. The vignettes
          were cut down on their sides so that they would fit the width of the book’s leaves and cut
          apart so that letterpress text could be placed below each. Either Blake or someone else
          may have taken these final steps, but in either case the work was very probably done as a
          requirement of the publishers or printers.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n68"
type="note">15</ref>	
            <note id="n68"><hi rend="s">15</hi> Michael J. Tolley has recently argued that Thornton
            welcomed Blake’s wood engravings and included them in his book quite willingly; see
            Tolley, “Thornton’s Blake Edition,” <hi rend="i">University of Adelaide Library
              News</hi> 10 (1988): 4-11. Following Tolley’s lead, Ted Gott has claimed that Blake
            trimmed the cuts himself to achieve their “further rusticizing” and make some of the
            vignettes “tighter and more dramatically charged.” See Gott, “‘Eternity in an Hour’: The
            Prints of William Blake,” in Martin Butlin and Gott, <hi rend="i">William Blake in the
              Collection of the National Gallery of Victoria</hi> (Melbourne: National Gallery of
            Victoria, 1989) 136. These are challenging and interesting views, but I do not find them
            convincing. As Joseph Viscomi has pointed out to me in correspondence, cutting an
            end-grain wood block is exacting work requiring a special saw. It is unlikely that a
            publisher would allow an amateur, such as Blake, to tackle the job since the blocks
            could be damaged by a single false move.</note></p>
        <p>In spite of apparent impediments, the newly-discovered relief etching can be situated
          into the production process of the Virgil illustrations in a way that complicates, but
          does not contradict, the previously known record. This compatibility, combined with the
          design variants and the medium itself, comprises an excellent case for ascribing the work,
          including its printing and hand tinting, to Blake. This attribution forces some
          readjustments in our sense of the role of innovative graphics in Blake’s career. The 
            <hi rend="i">Grave</hi> project had heretofore been considered as Blake’s last attempt to
          use his relief processes for a commercial project. We now know that Blake persisted in
          such efforts into the last decade of his life. Sadly, the publisher’s evident reaction was
          much the same. Fortunately, Blake was given the chance to try his hand at wood engraving.
          Thanks to the remarkable survival of the relief etching, we can now enjoy four of the
          Virgil designs in two graphic media in which Blake’s genius excelled. </p>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p25-127" n="127" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
