<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="BQ_Documents, vols. 1-43" status="new">
    <idno>26.1.designs</idno>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="minute">A New Color Print from the Small Book of Designs</title>
        <author n="Butlin">Martin Butlin</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Summer 1992</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <date>1992</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblFull>
          <titleStmt>
            <title>Blake/An Illustrated Quarterly</title>
            <biblScope unit="volIss">26.1</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="volume">26</biblScope>
            <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
            <respStmt>
              <resp>Editors</resp>
              <name>Morris Eaves</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <resp>Managing Editor</resp>
              <name>Patricia Neill</name>
              <resp>Bibliographer</resp>
              <name>D.W. Dörrbecker</name>
              <resp>Review Editor</resp>
              <name>Nelson Hilton</name>
              <resp>Associate Editor for Great Britain</resp>
              <name>David Worrall</name>
              <resp>Contributors</resp>
              <name>Martin Butlin</name>
              <name>E.B. Bentley</name>
              <name>Morton D. Paley</name>
              <name>Michael Srigley</name>
              <name>Joan K. Stemmler</name>
              <name>Julia M. Wright</name>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Department of English, University of Rochester</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Rochester, NY, USA</pubPlace>
            <date value="1992"/>
            <authority>William Blake Archive</authority>
          </publicationStmt>
        </biblFull>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language id="eng">English</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text id="volume_26">
    <body>
      <pb id="p26-19" n="19"/>
      <div1 id="BQ-26-1-0007">
        <head>
          <title type="section">
            <hi rend="i">MINUTE PARTICULARS</hi>
          </title>
        </head>
        <div2>
          <head>
            <title type="main">A New Color Print from the Small Book of Designs</title>
          </head>
          <byline>
            <docAuthor>Martin <name>Butlin</name></docAuthor>
          </byline>
          <p>A hitherto unrecorded color-printed copy of the design on plate 20 of <hi rend="i">The Marriage
of Heaven and Hell</hi> has turned up in a British
                        private collection.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n189"
type="note">1</ref> The new discovery
                        can be shown to have come from the second copy of the socalled “Small
                        Book of Designs” and confirms recent discoveries made about the
                        color-printed designs by Robert Essick and Joseph Viscomi. It will perhaps
                        be helpful to draw these discoveries together and examine their
                        implications. <note id="n189"><hi rend="s">1</hi> Henry Wemyss of
                            Sotheby’s, London, kindly informed me about this work, allowed me
                            to inspect it, and supplied the photograph.</note></p>
          <p>In the first place it is clear that the new print is a second pull of the
                        parallel design in the first copy of the Small Book of Designs in the
                        British Museum.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n190"
type="note">2</ref> The coloring is
                        identical though somewhat thinner, with the tone of the uncovered paper
                        showing through in places. Essick has shown that, in the case of the Large
                        Book of Designs, three of the duplicates are second pulls from the first
                        copy in the British Museum, B262: <hi rend="i">Albion Rose, The Accusers of
                            Theft, Adultery, Murder</hi> and <hi rend="i">Joseph of Arimathea
                            Preaching to the Inhabitants of Britain</hi>, B284, 285, and 286.<supplied
type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n191" type="note">3</ref> To these Viscomi has added <hi rend="i">A
Dream of Thiralatha</hi>, B267, and the frontispiece to <hi rend="i">Visions of the Daughters of Albion</hi>,
B264, and Ted Gott has
                        added <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> plate 21, B281.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n192" type="note">4</ref> It is not always easy to make such assertions; at best most
                        comparisons have to be made between a good color reproduction and an
                        original. However, in the case of the Large Book of Designs it seems that,
                        in fact, every case in which there is a duplicate, in other words every
                        design except for plate 14 from <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi>, is a repeated pull
                        from the same coloring.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n193"
type="note">5</ref>
	<note id="n190"><hi rend="s">2</hi> Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">The
                                Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi> (New Haven, CT: Yale
                            UP, 1981) 134, no. 260 <hi rend="i">6.</hi> References to this catalogue
                            in the rest of this article will be given in the form “B260 
<hi rend="i">6.</hi>”</note>
	<note id="n191"><hi rend="s">3</hi> Robert N. Essick, <hi rend="i">The
                                Separate Plates of William Blake</hi> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP,
                            1983) 25 no. 1B, 32 no. 2E, and 44 no. 1B, respectively.</note>
	<note id="n192"><hi rend="s">4</hi> Joseph Viscomi, “The Myth of
                            Commissioned Illuminated Books: George Romney, Isaac D’Israeli,
                            and ‘ONE HUNDRED AND SIXTY designs . . . of
                            Blake’s,’” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 23 (1989):
                            72n38; Martin Butlin and Ted Gott, <hi rend="i">William Blake in the
                                Collection of the National Gallery of Victoria</hi> (National
                            Gallery of Victoria, 1989) 110-11, both works reproduced in
                            color.</note>
	<note id="n193"><hi rend="s">5</hi> There is an old color reproduction of
                            262 <hi rend="i">4</hi> in Laurence Binyon, <hi rend="i">The Engraved
                                Designs of William Blake</hi> (London and New York: Benn Press,
                            1926) pl. 49, which can be compared with B265 in the Tate Gallery, or
                            the color reproduction of B265 (pl. 338) can be compared with B262 
<hi rend="i">4</hi> in the British Museum.</note></p>
          <p>Viscomi has also demonstrated that the design from plate 5 of <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> in the
second copy of the Small Book of Designs was from
                        the same printings as that in the first. To this can be added the new
                        discovery and, almost certainly, the second pull of plate 3 of 
<hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> (c.f., B260 <hi rend="i">9</hi> and B261 <hi rend="i">4</hi>). As Viscomi (72n38) also
points out, even a partial 
            <figure n="MHH.plate20.26.1.bqscan" rend="file" width="450" height="239">
            	<head>1. “‘O Revolving Serpent,’ Plate 20 of <hi rend="i">The Marriage of Heaven and
Hell</hi>,”
                                1796.</head>
                <figDesc>Color-printed relief etching finished in pen and water color,
                                5.6 × 10.3 cm. Private collection, Great Britain.</figDesc>
            </figure> 
            			duplication in the color printing means that both copies of the
                        Large Book of Designs and of the Small Book of Designs must have been
                        basically prepared at the same time, whenever the final finishing in pen and
                        water color may have been done.</p>
          <p>This conclusion, so obvious once made, makes my suggestion that the two Small
                        Books of Designs were printed in 1794 and 1796 respectively invalid.
                        Moreover, if one can accept the date 1796 for the second copy of the Small
                        Book of Designs, this invalidates my suggestion that the books of designs
                        were intermediary between the use of color printing in Blake’s
                        illuminated books and the totally independent large color-printed designs of
                            “1795.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n194"
type="note">6</ref> This theory
                        made some sense in the conceptual and technical development of
                        Blake’s use of color printing but is certainly not essential for
                        Blake’s development; indeed, the experiments in the books would have
                        been sufficient to produce the independent large prints. Whether one can
                        rely on Blake’s dates with regard to his color prints is another
                        question. It has already been shown that a number of the
                        “1795” prints were actually executed in 1804 or 1805.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n195" type="note">7</ref> Moreover, Viscomi suggests that the
                        1796 date, created by altering the “1794” on the title page of
                            <hi rend="i">Urizen</hi> (B260 <hi rend="i">1</hi> and B261 <hi rend="i">1</hi>)
was done late in Blake’s career, when he added the
                        framing lines and verses characteristic of the second copy of the Small Book
                        of Designs. By this time Blake could well have wished to establish an
                        “ideal” date for the separate designs. <note id="n194"><hi rend="s">6</hi> Martin
Bultin, “The Evolution of
                            Blake’s Large Color Prints of 1795,” in Alvin H.
                            Rosenfeld, ed., <hi rend="i">William Blake; Essays for S. Foster
                                Damon</hi> (Providence, RI: Brown UP, 1969) 114-15.</note>
	<note id="n195"><hi rend="s">7</hi> Martin Butlin, “A Newly
                            Discovered Watermark and a Visionary’s Way with his
                            Dates,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 15 (1982): 101-03; Martin Butlin,
                                “<hi rend="i">Paintings and Drawings of William Blake</hi>:
                            Some Minor Additions,” <hi rend="i">Blake</hi> 17 (1984): 159;
                            Martin Butlin, <hi rend="i">Tate Gallery Collections: Volume Five:
                                William Blake 1757-1827</hi> (London: Tate Gallery, 1990) 83, 90 no.
                            28, and 92 no. 29.</note></p>
          <p>The framing lines and verses characteristic of the second copy of the Small
                        Book of Designs are also a feature of the newly discovered print. The design
                        has been cut out of the original sheet of paper, leaving no margins, but by
                        good fortune much of the original sheet remains, cut up but stuck to the
                        sheet of cardboard onto which the design is also stuck. From these fragments
                        it can be seen that, like most of the other designs identified as coming
                        from the second copy of the Small Books of Designs, there were two pen-drawn
                        framing lines and a text, similarly inscribed with double inverted commas at
                        the beginning and end of each line as follows:</p>
		<q> “O revolving serpent”<lb/>
 “O the Ocean of Time and
                        Space” </q>
          <p>I leave it to other scholars to explain the significance of the second line
                        and its relevance, if appropriate, to the 
<pb id="p26-20" n="20"/>
Arlington
                        Court picture, B803. It is generally assumed that Blake himself added these
                        inscriptions when he issued the second copy of the Small Book of Designs.
                        They seem to be in the same ink as the framing lines, which, as Viscomi
                        points out, are very close to those added to <hi rend="i">All Religions are
                            One</hi> Copy A, and <hi rend="i">Songs of Innocence and of
                            Experience</hi> Copy R, presumably at the time that they were sold to
                        John Linnell.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n196"
type="note">8</ref>
	<note id="n196"><hi rend="s">8</hi> G. E. Bentley, Jr., <hi rend="i">Blake
                                Books</hi> (Oxford: Clarendon P, 1977) 85-86 and 420. In addition,
                            Viscomi has kindly let me know of his conclusions concerning these,
                            copies, to be set out in his forthcoming book. Incidentally, the two
                            designs from the second copy of the Large Book of Designs in the Tate
                            Gallery, B264 and 265, also have framing lines similar to those that
                            characterize the second copy of the Small Book of Designs.</note></p>
          <p>Another characteristic of some of the designs from the second copy of the
                        Small Book of Designs is a small page number in the top right-hand corner.
                        These are found on B261 <hi rend="i">3, 6, 7</hi>, and <hi rend="i">9.</hi>
                        A similar number, in this case “16,” is found on the newly
                        discovered design. The other numbers so far discovered are
                        “9,” “13,” “20” and
                        “22.” This suggests that there may be ten more designs still
                        awaiting rediscovery, a very exciting prospect. There are, of course, 23
                        designs in the first copy of the Small Book of Designs but the two books
                        cannot have been identical: three designs from the second copy, B261 <hi rend="i">9,
10</hi>, and <hi rend="i">11</hi>, are of subjects not found
                        in the first copy.</p>
          <p>The possibility of missing designs is reinforced by the fact that four of the
                        designs from the second copy show stab holes from a former binding, B261 
<hi rend="i">2, 5, 6</hi> and <hi rend="i">8</hi>;<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n197"
type="note">9</ref> the absence of such stab holes on other designs can
                        be accounted for by the trimming of the paper. This binding must have been
                        done before the second copy was dispersed. The early history of some of the
                        designs is not known but B261 <hi rend="i">1</hi> was given by Mrs. Blake
                        (who died in 1831) to Frederick Tatham, B261 <hi rend="i">5</hi> belonged to
                        Samuel Palmer’s cousin John Giles, while B261 <hi rend="i">3</hi>
                        seems to have belonged to John Varley who, as will be shown, also owned the
                        newly discovered design. <note id="n197"><hi rend="s">9</hi> Bentley
                            357.</note></p>
          <p>Other inscriptions, not by Blake, give the early provenance of this work.
                        There are two references, apparently in the same hand, reading
                        “Drawing of Blake’s given to A White by M<hi rend="s">rs</hi>
                        Varley March 31 1856” and “Original Drawing by Blake/See
                        Rossettis “Life and Works of Blake” (the inscription lacks the
                        closing quotation mark for “Life and Works of Blake”). After
                        the first of these two inscriptions but in a different hand are the words
                        “evidently printed in oil and touched with colour afterwards.”
                        There is also the number “8623.”</p>
          <p>A. White is presumably the Adam White who, according to inscriptions on the
                        back of a counterproof of the Visionary Head of <hi rend="i">Wat Tyler</hi>
                        (B740), was given that drawing by J. W. Lowry; the drawing had originally
                        “belonged to Varley the artist whose wife was Miss Lowry.”
                        White also owned a number of other Visionary Heads (B711, 712, 718, 736, and
                        760), one of which, <hi rend="i">Pindar and Lais the Courtesan</hi>, now in
                        the Harris Museum and Art Gallery, Preston (B711) is inscribed, in similar
                        fashion to the new color print, “Adam White from M<hi rend="s">r</hi>
                        [or more likely “M<hi rend="s">rs</hi>”] Varley.” In
                        addition one copy of the fourth state of the engraving by Blake and John
                        Linnell after Linnell’s portrait drawing of Wilson Lowry is inscribed
                        “To Adam White with J.W. Lowry’s regards 1854.”<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n198" type="note">10</ref>
	<note id="n198"><hi rend="s">10</hi> Essick 204, no. 4M.</note></p>
          <p>The Miss Lowry who married Varley was his second wife, Delvalle (born c.
                        1797-1800), the daughter of Varley’s friend Wilson Lowry (1762-1824)
                        and his second wife Rebecca Delvalle (1761-1848) whom he married in 1796.
                        Delvalle married Varley in 1825. The Blake connection was strengthened by
                        the fact that Wilson Lowry had engraved a number of the plates for Abraham
                        Rees’ <hi rend="i">The Cyclopaedia</hi>, 1820, for which Blake also
                        executed seven plates, one page being made up of engravings by both
                            artists.<supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref target="n199"
type="note">11</ref>
	<note id="n199"><hi rend="s">11</hi> Essick 207-08. For help in unravelling
                            the family relationships of the Varleys and the Lowrys I am indebted to
                            my former colleague Anne Lyles; see also C. M. Kauffman, <hi rend="i">John Varley
(1778-1842)</hi> (London: Batsford and Victoria and
                            Albert Museum, 1984) 58 and 132.</note></p>
          <p>The mid nineteenth-century owner of this design was Sir Joseph Nöel
                        Paton, RSA (1821-1901); it was probably he who added the inscription about
                        the technique of the print. Through his father he became an admirer of
                        Blake’s work, both his poetry and his designs, at an early age, and
                        some of this influence remained with him throughout his life. As he said,
                        his father taught him to “put the <hi rend="i">thought before the
                            thing</hi>, and encouraged me in perpetual scribblings at 
<hi rend="i">subjects</hi>, instead of obliging me to copy <hi rend="i">objects.</hi>” Even a late work like 
<hi rend="i">Ezekiel</hi>
                        of 1889-91 still reflects the influence of Blake both in the pose, close to
                        that of the <hi rend="i">Dance of Albion</hi>, and in the bearded old man
                        type used for <hi rend="i">Ezekiel.</hi><supplied type="spacer"> </supplied><ref
target="n200" type="note">12</ref> In 1845 Paton won a premium for the competition for the
                        decoration of the new Houses of Parliament and in 1847 and 1849 came his two
                        large pictures of fairy subjects, the works for which he is probably best
                        known, <hi rend="i">The Reconciliation of Oberon and Titania</hi> and <hi rend="i">The
Quarrel of Oberon and Titania</hi>, both now in the
                        National Gallery of Scotland. He also painted such subjects as <hi rend="i">The Spirit
of Religion</hi> (for the Houses of Parliament) and the <hi rend="i">Pursuit of Pleasure</hi> of 1855. He
became an Associate of the
                        Royal Scottish Academy in 1847 and a full member in 1850. He was appointed
                        Her Majesty’s Limner for Scotland in 1865 and was knighted in 1867.
                        He also published two volumes of verse. He knew Millais (an associate of the
                        Rossettis in Preraphaelite days), Ruskin and the brothers David and William
                        Bell Scott, these being further links with the circle of Blake admirers in
                        the middle of the nineteenth century. It is nice to be able to identify at
                        least one work by Blake that he owned. <note id="n200"><hi rend="s">12</hi>
                            For this particular work, and Sir Nöel Paton in general, see
                            David and Francina Irwin, <hi rend="i">Scottish Painting at Home and
                                Abroad 1700-1900</hi> (London: Faber, 1975) 288-95; see also the 
<hi rend="i">Dictionary of National Bibliography.</hi></note></p>
        </div2>
      </div1>
	<pb id="p26-21" n="21" rend="hidden"/>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
